<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>十三詣り</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jusan-mairi (visit to pray by the thirteen year old children to pray for knowledge, happiness and health to become adults)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jusan-mairi (thirteen year old children pray for knowledge, happiness and health to become adults)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jusan-mairi (thirteen year old children pray for knowledge, happiness and health to become adults)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>十三参り（じゅうさん まいり）は、旧暦の3月13日（現在では月遅れで新暦の4月13日)の間、数え年13歳に成った少年少女が元服を迎え大人と成った事に感謝して、これから先の万物の福徳と英知を授かるために、虚空蔵菩薩に参詣する行事。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jusan-mairi is a ritual taken place on March 13 of lunar calendar date (today, it is held on one month later of April 13) that boys and girls who are 13th calendar year visit Kokuzo Bosatsu (Akasagarbha Bodhisattva) to thank that they come of an age and pray for future knowledge, happiness and health.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jusan-mairi is a ritual that takes place on March 13 of the lunar calendar date (today, it is held one month later on April 13) where 13 year old boys and girls visit Kokuzo Bosatsu (Akasagarbha Bodhisattva) to give thanks that they have come of age and pray for future knowledge, happiness, and health.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jusan-mairi is a ritual that takes place on March 13 of the lunar calendar date (today, it is held one month later on April 13) where 13 year old boys and girls visit Kokuzo Bosatsu (Akasagarbha Bodhisattva) to give thanks that they have come of age and pray for future knowledge, happiness, and health.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>それで一名、知恵詣り、または、智恵もらいとも云う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus it is also called as &quot;Chie-mairi (a prayer for the wisdom.)&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus it is also called as &quot;Chie-mairi&quot; (a prayer forwisdom).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus it is also called as &quot;Ichimei&quot; (one name), &quot;Chie-mairi&quot; (a prayer for wisdom) or &quot;Chie-morai&quot; (being blessed with wisdom).</e>
<cmt>訳を補いました。一名の解釈がこれで正しいかは不明です。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>参拝の最初に半紙に自分が大切にしている漢字一文字を毛筆でしたためる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before the prayer, children describe one letter they cherish on hanshi (standard-size Japanese writing paper) by mohitsu (writing, painting) brush.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。例外的に5分割しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before praying, the children describe one letter they cherish on hanshi (standard-size Japanese writing paper) using a mohitsu (writing, painting) brush.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before praying, the children describe one letter they cherish on hanshi (standard-size Japanese writing paper) using a mohitsu (writing, painting) brush.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>例えば命・心</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, &quot;命 (Life)&quot; or &quot;心 (Heart).&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, &quot;命 (Life)&quot; or &quot;心 (Heart).&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, &quot;命 (Life)&quot; or &quot;心 (Heart).&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>女子では美・雅といった文字を虚空蔵菩薩に供えご祈祷を受けて帰りにはお守り・お供物を頂いて帰り親に感謝を述べる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In case of girls for example, they devote letter like &quot;美 (Beauty)&quot; or &quot;雅 (Elegance)&quot; to Kokuzo Bosatsu and be blessed, then they receive amulets and offerings when they return, and they say words of thanks to their parents at home.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In case of girls for example, they present letters like &quot;美 (Beauty)&quot; or &quot;雅 (Elegance)&quot; to Kokuzo Bosatsu to be blessed, then they receive amulets and offerings when they return, and they say words of thanks to their parents at home.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In case of girls for example, they present letters like &quot;美 (Beauty)&quot; or &quot;雅 (Elegance)&quot; to Kokuzo Bosatsu to be blessed, then they receive amulets and offerings when they return, and they say words of thanks to their parents at home.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>お箸はこの日最初に頂く食事の時から使いはじめる、お守りは勉強机に一つと毎日の通学用の鞄に一つをつける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They keep using the chopsticks they used at the first meal on the day, and attach one amulet to their study desk and another to school bag.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They continue using the chopsticks they used at the first meal on that day, and attach one amulet to their study desk and another to their school bag.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They continue using the chopsticks they used at the first meal on that day, and attach one amulet to their study desk and another to their school bag.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>家族でお供物を頂き子の成長をお祝いする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">All the family members eat the offerings they brought back and celebrate the children&apos;s happy growth.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">All family members eat the offerings they bring back and celebrate the children&apos;s happy growth.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">All family members eat the offerings they bring back and celebrate the children&apos;s happy growth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>参詣の帰路、本殿を出たあと後を振り返ると、せっかく授かった智恵を返さなければならないという伝承があって狭い長い石段を降リ切った鳥居をくぐるまでは、又は渡月橋を渡り終るまでは周囲の誘いにも動じず後ろを振り向かないで貫き通す【お参りの前に子に教えておく事をすすめる】</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As there is a tradition that they have to return the wisdom they received if they look back after they walked out of the main hall on the way home, the children have not to look back up until they passed through a torii (an archway to a Shinto shrine) beyond long and narrow stone steps, or until they crossed the Togetsu-kyo Bridge even if they were told so (It is recommended to tell it to the children before the visiting.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As there is a tradition to return the wisdom they receive if they look back after they walk out of the main hall on the way home, the children do not look back until they pass through the torii (an archway to a Shinto shrine) beyond the long and narrow stone steps, or until they cross the Togetsu-kyo Bridge even if they were told so (It is recommended to tell the children before they make the visit)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As there is a tradition to return the wisdom they receive if they look back after they walk out of the main hall on the way home, the children do not look back until they pass through the torii (an archway to a Shinto shrine) beyond the long and narrow stone steps, or until they cross the Togetsu-kyo Bridge even if they were told so (It is recommended to tell the children before they make the visit)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>空海がそれによって飛躍的に記憶力を増大させたと言われる虚空蔵求聞持法に由来する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This custom is said to be derived from Kokuzo gumonjiho (Ritual of Praying to Akasagarbha for Increasing Memory) with which Kukai increased memory drastically.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This custom is said to be derived from Kokuzo gumonjiho (Ritual of Praying to Akasagarbha to Increase Memory) with which Kukai greatly increased his memory.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This custom is said to be derived from Kokuzo gumonjiho (Ritual of Praying to Akasagarbha to Increase Memory) with which Kukai greatly increased his memory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>また、13歳という年齢が元服の時期と合致するため、一種の通過儀礼として伝承された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the age of 13 met the time of coming of age at the time, this ritual became a tradition as a sort of rite of passage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As 13 is the time of coming of age, this ritual became a tradition as a sort of rite of passage.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As 13 is the time of coming of age, this ritual became a tradition as a sort of rite of passage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>関西では七五三よりも、こちらのほうが盛んで、中でも、京都嵐山の法輪寺 (京都市西京区)が有名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kansai region, Jusan-mairi is more poplar than Shichi-go-san (a day of prayer for the healthy growth of children of 7, 5 and 3), and especially that of Horin-ji Temple (Nishigyo Ward, Kyoto City) at Mt. Arashi-yama, Kyoto is famous.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Kansai region, Jusan-mairi is more popular than Shichi-go-san (a day of prayer for the healthy growth of children of 7, 5, and 3), and especially that of Horin-ji Temple (Nishigyo Ward, Kyoto City) at Mt. Arashi-yama, Kyoto is famous.</e>
<cmt>grammar, spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Kansai region, Jusan-mairi is more popular than Shichi-go-san (a day of prayer for the healthy growth of children of 7, 5, and 3), and especially that of Horin-ji Temple (Nishigyo Ward, Kyoto City) at Mt. Arashi-yama, Kyoto is famous.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="12">
<j>最近では関東でも徐々に盛んになりつつあり、浅草寺では3～5月にかけて上記と同様の参拝客が目に付くようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Recently, this ritual gradually became popular also in Kanto region, and the visitors participated in it are often seen at Senso-ji Temple from March to May.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This ritual has gradually became popular also in the Kanto region, and visitors participating in it are often seen at Senso-ji Temple from March to May.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This ritual has gradually became popular also in the Kanto region, and visitors participating in it are often seen at Senso-ji Temple from March to May.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="13">
<j>服装は少年は羽織袴、少女は成人式と同じ振袖を、肩上げをして着るのが原則だが、結婚しても着られる留袖、訪問着、小紋、袴の場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In principle, the costume clad by boys are haori and hakama (Japanese male formal attire) and by girls are furisode (a long sleeved type of kimono usually clad on the coming of the age day) with a shoulder tuck, however, there are cases of &quot;tomesode (formal dress patterned only below the waistline worn by a married woman)&quot;, &quot;homongi (semi-formal kimono for women)&quot;, &quot;komon (fine patterned kimono)&quot; or hakama which can be clad when they married.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In principle, the costume worn by boys are haori and hakama (Japanese male formal attire) and by girls is furisode (a long sleeved type of kimono usually worn on the coming of the age day) with a shoulder tuck, however, there are cases of &quot;tomesode&quot; (formal dress patterned only below the waistline worn by a married woman),&quot; &quot;homongi&quot; (semi-formal kimono for women), &quot;komon&quot; (fine patterned kimono) or hakama which can be worn when they married.</e>
<cmt>punctuation, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In principle, the costume worn by boys are haori and hakama (Japanese male formal attire) and by girls is furisode (a long sleeved type of kimono usually worn on the coming of the age day) with a shoulder tuck, however, there are cases of &quot;tomesode&quot; (formal dress patterned only below the waistline worn by a married woman),&quot; &quot;homongi&quot; (semi-formal kimono for women), &quot;komon&quot; (fine patterned kimono) or hakama which can be worn when they married.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>又、少女は、この時に初めて化粧（厚化粧の場合も多い）をして貰う場合が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Girls often do the first makeup (in many cases, it is heavy makeup) on this day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Girls often put on their first makeup (in many cases, it is heavy makeup) on this day.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Girls often put on their first makeup (in many cases, it is heavy makeup) on this day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>京都では、極稀に舞妓変身して参拝する場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although it is very rare, ssome girls wear and do makeup like maiko (Japanese dancing girl in and around Kyoto or apprentice geigi or geiko) on this day in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although it is very rare, some girls wear and makeup like maiko (Japanese dancing girl in and around Kyoto or apprentice geigi or geiko) on this day in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it is very rare, some girls wear and makeup like maiko (Japanese dancing girl in and around Kyoto or apprentice geigi or geiko) on this day in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 SnowBot(id:206320), Toutefoi(id:199897), Esistdas(id:59219), Nighthawks(id:36125), あお(id:33504), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>