<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>送り雀</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Okuri-suzume</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Okurisuzume</e>
<cmt>ハイフンを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Okurisuzume</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>送り雀（おくりすずめ）は、和歌山県や奈良県吉野郡東吉野村に伝わる妖怪。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Okuri-suzume (literally, accompanying sparrow) is a monster handed down in Wakayama Prefecture and Higashi-yoshino Village in Yoshino County in Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The okurisuzume (sparrow that sends off) is a specter handed down in Wakayama Prefecture and Higashi-yoshino Village, Yoshino County, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The okurisuzume (sparrow that sends off) is a specter handed down in Wakayama Prefecture and Higashi-yoshino Village, Yoshino County, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>和歌山では雀送り（すずめおくり）ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Wakayama Prefecture, this is also called suzume-okuri.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Wakayama Prefecture, it is also called suzumeokuri.</e>
<cmt>this を it に修正しました。suzume-okuri のハイフンを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Wakayama Prefecture, it is also called suzumeokuri.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>その鳴き声を実在の鳥のアオジにたとえ、蒿雀（あおじ）とも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The chirping of okuri-suzume is compared with the chirping of a real bird, black-faced bunting, okuri-suzume is also called aoji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the chirping sound of okurisuzume is compared with that of a real bird aoji (black-faced bunting), okurisuzume is also called aoji.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the chirping sound of okurisuzume is compared with that of a real bird aoji (black-faced bunting), okurisuzume is also called aoji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>夜、人が山道を歩いていると「チチチチ......」と鳴きながら飛んでくる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the nighttime, when a person is walking along a road in a mountain, okuri-suzume comes to the person flying chirping &apos;chi, chi, chi, …&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When a person is walking along a mountain road at night, there comes an okurisuzume chirping &apos;chi, chi, chi, ….&apos;</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When a person is walking along a mountain road at night, there comes an okurisuzume chirping &apos;chi, chi, chi,...&apos;</e>
<cmt>中黒をピリオドに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>和歌山では那智山 (山)によく現れたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Wakayama Prefecture, okuri-suzume often appears in Mt. Nachi (mountain).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Wakayama Prefecture, it is said that okurisuzume used to appear in Mt. Nachi (mountain).</e>
<cmt>「という」訳漏れのためit is said that を補って対応しました。okuri-suzume often appears を okurisuzume used to appear に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Wakayama Prefecture, it is said that okurisuzume used to appear in Mt. Nachi (mountain).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>この鳴き声の後にはオオカミもしくは妖怪・送り犬が現れるといい、道で転倒するとすぐにそれらに襲撃されてしまうため、送り雀の鳴き声を聞いた者は、転ばないよう足元に注意を払いつつ歩いたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that a wolf or a monster, okuri-inu (literally, accompanying dog) appears after that chirping and, if the person stumbles, the person will immediately attacked by such animal or monster and, therefore, any person who hears the chirping of okuri-suzume walks taking care not to stumble.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that a wolf or a specter, okuri-inu (dog that sends off) appears after the chirping sound, and once the person stumbles, he or she will be immediately attacked by such animal or monster, thus those who heard the chirping of okurisuzume used to walk watching their steps not to fall.</e>
<cmt>「足元に注意を払いつつ」訳漏れのため、watching their steps を追記した上で、全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that a wolf or a specter, okuri-inu (dog that sends off) appears after the chirping sound, and once the person stumbles, he or she will be immediately attacked by such animal or monster, thus those who heard the chirping of okurisuzume used to walk watching their steps not to fall.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>スズメの名の通り、鳥の姿だとされるが、その姿を見た者は誰もいない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though it is said that okuri-suzume has an appearance of a bird as its name represents, no person has seen the appearance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though it is said that okurisuzume has an appearance of a bird as its name represents, no one has seen its appearance.</e>
<cmt>person を one に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though it is said that okurisuzume has an appearance of a bird as its name represents, no one has seen its appearance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 逃亡者(id:14864), 踏蹟(id:51201), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>