<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>石州流</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sekishu school</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sekishu-ryu School</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;-ryu&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sekishu-ryu School</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>石州流 （せきしゅうりゅう）は、片桐貞昌（貞昌）を流祖と仰ぐ茶道の流派の総称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sekishu school is a general term of the various tea ceremony schools that regard Sadamasa (Sekishu) KATAGIRI as an original founder.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sekishu-ryu is a general term for the various tea ceremony schools that regard Sadamasa (Sekishu) KATAGIRI as an original founder.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;-ryu&quot;Preposition</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sekishu-ryu is a general term for the various tea ceremony schools that regard Sadamasa (Sekishu) KATAGIRI as an original founder.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>一口に石州流と言っても様々であり、初期の伝承系譜によって大きくいくつかの派に分けられるほか、地域ごとに様々なグループを形成している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are various groups in Sekishu school, divided in several schools by the traditional lineages in early period and formed several groups by areas.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are various groups within the Sekishu-ryu, divided into several schools according to the original traditional geneaology, or by area.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are various groups within the Sekishu-ryu, divided into several schools according to the original traditional geneaology, or by area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>さらにこれらのグループには、片桐家を宗家として仰ぐもの、慈光院を宗元として緩やかに糾合したもの、引き続き独立しているものとがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some groups respect the Katagiri family as a grand master, some groups get together centering on Jiko-in Temple, and others continue on their own independent ways.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some groups respect the Katagiri family as grand master, some groups meet at Jiko-in Temple, and others continue independently.</e>
<cmt>Revised to make less wordy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some groups respect the Katagiri family as grand master, some groups regard Jiko-in Temple as the origin of the school, and others continue independently.</e>
<cmt>meet at Jiko-in Temple→regard Jiko-in Temple as the origin of the school</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>また片桐家の菩提寺高林庵（芳春院内）を宗元として諸派の糾合グループもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, some groups get together centering on Korinan (in Hoshun-in Temple) which was a family temple of the Katagiri family as grand master.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, some groups use the Korinan in Hoshun-in Temple, which was the Katagiri family temple as their head school.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, some groups regard the Korinan in Hoshun-in Temple, which is the Katagiri family temple, as their origin.</e>
<cmt>was→ishead school→originuse→regardtemple の後にカンマ</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>片桐貞昌（石州）は大和小泉藩1万3000石余りを知行する大名で、普請奉行をしていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sadamasa KATAGIRI (Sekishu) was a feudal lord of the Yamato-Koizumi Domain with 13,000 koku (2345.08 cubic meters), working as Fushin bugyo (shogunate administrator of activities by a community such as cleaning or fixing stone walls).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処, それにともない日本語を一部変更。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sadamasa KATAGIRI (Sekishu) was the lord of the Yamato-Koizumi Domain worth 13,000 koku, and also held the post of Fushin-bugyo (shogunate official responsible for public works).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarityDeleted metric equvalent of &apos;koku&apos;Changed explanation of &quot;普請奉行&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sadamasa KATAGIRI (Sekishu) was the lord of the Yamato-Koizumi Domain worth 13,000 koku, and also held the post of Fushin-bugyo (shogunate official responsible for public works).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>知恩院の修復をはじめとして、作事・普請の才を認められた人であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was well known as a talented lord such as repairing Chion-in Temple.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処, それにともない日本語を一部変更。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the time of his restoration of Chion-in Temple, his construction skills were highly regarded.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the time of his restoration of Chion-in Temple, his construction skills were highly regarded.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>茶の湯は千道安の門人であった桑山貞晴に師事していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He learned tea ceremony from Sadaharu KUWAYAMA who was a disciple of SEN no Doan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He learned tea ceremony from Sadaharu KUWAYAMA, who was a disciple of SEN no Doan.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He learned tea ceremony from Sadaharu KUWAYAMA, who was a disciple of SEN no Doan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>門下に3代将軍徳川家光の異母弟にあたる保科正之がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of Sekishu&apos;s students was Masayuki HOSHINA who was a younger half-brother to the third Shogun Iemitsu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of Sekishu&apos;s students was Masayuki HOSHINA, who was a younger half-brother to the third Shogun, Iemitsu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of Sekishu&apos;s students was Masayuki HOSHINA, who was a younger half-brother to the third Shogun, Iemitsu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>その推挙により徳川幕府4代将軍徳川家綱の茶道指南役となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By recommendation of Masayuki, Sekishu became a coach of tea ceremony for the fourth Shogun Ietsuna TOKUGAWA in the Tokugawa Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On Masayuki&apos;s recommendation, Sekishu became the tea ceremony instructor to the fourth Shogun, Ietsuna TOKUGAWA and</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarityRejoined to cell G15</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On Masayuki&apos;s recommendation, Sekishu became the tea ceremony instructor to the fourth Shogun, Ietsuna TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>「なったことで、」→「なった。」and 削除してピリオド</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>以後江戸時代を通じて石州流が幕府の茶道として広がっていくことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since then, Sekishu school had spread as a tea ceremony school which got an endorsement from the shogunate during Edo era.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">the Sekishu-ryu, as the tea ceremony of the shogunate, continue to grow throughout the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarityRejoined to cell G14</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sekishu-ryu, as the tea ceremony of the shogunate, continued to grow throughout the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>the→Thecontinue→continued その前のスペース短縮。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>片桐家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Katagiri family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Katagiri Family</e>
<cmt>Capital letter</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Katagiri Family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>大和小泉藩は石州の3男の片桐貞房が継いだが、茶湯指南の職を継いだ訳ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sadafusa KATAGIRI who was the third son of Sekishu took over the Yamato-Koizumi Domain, but he didn&apos;t succeed the post of the tea ceremony coach for the shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sadafusa KATAGIRI, the third son of Sekishu, inherited the Yamato-Koizumi Domain but not the post of tea ceremony instructor for the shogunate.</e>
<cmt>Revised to make less wordy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sadafusa KATAGIRI, the third son of Sekishu, inherited the Yamato-Koizumi Domain but not the post of tea ceremony instructor for the shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>藤林宗源の系譜が片桐家中を出て本庄家に移ったこと（後述）も合わせると、おそらく片桐家では茶湯の伝承に関心がなかった時期があると考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Given that the family line of Sogen FUJIBAYASHI moved from the Katagiri family to the Honjo family, it is considered that the Katagiri family had been lack of interest in tradition of tea ceremony in certain period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the fact that Sogen FUJIBAYASHI&apos;s descendants moved from the Katagiri family to the Honjo family, it is believed that the Katagiri family for a time lost interest in the tradition of tea ceremony.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarityGrammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the fact that Sogen FUJIBAYASHI&apos;s descendants moved from the Katagiri family to the Honjo family (see below), it is believed that the Katagiri family for a time lost interest in the tradition of tea ceremony.</e>
<cmt>（後述）を追記</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>歴代の中で8代藩主片桐貞信は茶人として知られており、江戸千家の茶風を加味して新石州流と称したと伝えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the Katagiri family, Sadanobu KATAGIRI who was the eighth lord of domain was known as a master of ceremonial tea and he was said to start the Shin-Sekishu school which Sadanobu added the Edo Senke (school of tea ceremony) style to Sekishu school.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The eighth lord, Sadanobu KATAGIRI, was known as a master of the tea ceremony and is said to have founded the Shin-Sekishu-ryu (New Sekishu-ryu School), which included elements from the Edo Senke School.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The eighth lord, Sadanobu KATAGIRI, was known as a master of the tea ceremony and is said to have founded the Shin-Sekishu-ryu (New Sekishu-ryu School), which included elements from the Edo Senke School.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>しかし、これもその後伝承された痕跡は残っていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it seems like the Shin-Sekishu school was not handed down to the next generations.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it appears the Shin-Sekishu School was not handed down to future generations.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it appears the Shin-Sekishu School was not handed down to future generations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="17">
<j>昭和初期に小泉の屋敷の主人だった水田秀光が中心となって、当時の当主である片桐貞央子爵を軸に石州流の大同団結が図られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In early Showa era, Hidemitsu MIZUTA (水田秀光) who was the owner of the residence of Koizumi made effort to unite various Sekishu schools centering around the Lord Sadao KATAGIRI (片桐貞央) who was the head of the Katagiri family.</e>
<cmt>水田秀光→Hidemitsu MIZUTA (水田秀光)[定訳不明,読み方が見つからず、仮訳です。]片桐貞央子爵→Lord Sadao KATAGIRI (片桐貞央)[定訳不明,読み方が見つからず、仮訳です。]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the early Showa period, Hidemitsu MIZUTA (水田秀光), the owner of the Koizumi mansion, attempted to unite the various Sekishu schools, centering on Viscount Sadao KATAGIRI (片桐貞央), the head of the Katagiri family.</e>
<cmt>ArticleRevised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the early Showa period, Hidemitsu MIZUTA, the owner of the Koizumi mansion, attempted to unite the various Sekishu schools, centering on Viscount Sadao KATAGIRI, the head of the Katagiri family.</e>
<cmt>漢字の読み方削除。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>その結果として、戦後に財団法人高林庵（こうりんあん）が発足し、片桐家を宗家とする一種の家元制度が成立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, Korinan Foundation made a start after the war and established the grand master system regarding the Katagiri family as grand master.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, after the war, the Korin&apos;an Foundation and a grand master system with the Katagiri family as grand masters were established.</e>
<cmt>Changed word orderRevised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, after the war, the Korinan Foundation and a grand master system with the Katagiri family as Soke (the head family or house) were established.</e>
<cmt>Korin&apos;an→Korinan 宗家の定訳</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>15代片桐貞泰は井沢宗達に伝授を受けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fifteenth head of the Katagiri family, Sadayasu KATAGIRI received instruction from Sotatsu ISAWA (井沢宗達).</e>
<cmt>井沢宗達→Sotatsu ISAWA (井沢宗達)[定訳不明,読み方が見つからず、仮訳です。]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fifteenth head of the Katagiri family, Sadayasu KATAGIRI, received instruction from Sotatsu ISAWA (井沢宗達).</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The 15th head of the Katagiri family, Sadayasu KATAGIRI, received instruction from Sotatsu ISAWA.</e>
<cmt>漢字の読み方削除。fiteenth→15th</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="20">
<j>一方、長男の下條信隆（1624年～1716年）は石州の庶子で1000石の旗本として取り立てられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first son of Sekishu, Nobutaka SHIMOJO (1624 - 1716) who was a child born out of wedlock became Hatamoto (direct retainer of the shogun) with 1,000 koku (180.39 cubic meters).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first son of Sekishu, Nobutaka SHIMOJO (1624 - 1716), who was born out of wedlock, was made a hatamoto (direct retainer of the shogun) with 1,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>PunctuationArticleDeleted metric equvalent of &apos;koku&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first son of Sekishu, Nobutaka SHIMOJO (1624 - 1716), who was born out of wedlock, was made a hatamoto (direct retainer of the shogun) with 1,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>代々父子相伝で伝えられてきたが、石州から数えて7代目の片桐宗猿（1774年～1864年）の時に梶宗龍に伝授される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sekishu school had been handed down from father to son till the sixth generation, but Soen KATAGIRI (1774 - 1864) who was the seventh generation of the Katagiri family imparted the tradition to Soryu KAJI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sekishu-ryu School had been handed down from father to son, but Soen KATAGIRI (1774 - 1864), the seventh head since Sekishu, imparted the tradition to Soryu KAJI.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sekishu-ryu School had been handed down from father to son, but Soen KATAGIRI (1774 - 1864), the seventh head since Sekishu, imparted the tradition to Soryu KAJI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>宗猿までは茶道の他に、華道と盆石も伝わっていたが分流した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Not only tea ceremony but also Kado flower arrangement and bonseki (tray-landscape foundation stone) had been handed down till the period of Soen, but they were divided.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Not only the tea ceremony, but also kado flower arranging and bonseki (miniature landscapes on black lacquer trays created using white sand) had been handed down till Soen&apos;s time, but were then divided.</e>
<cmt>PunctuationChanged explanation of &quot;bonseki&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Not only the tea ceremony, but also kado flower arranging and bonseki (stones arranged on a tray, which express a natural view) had been handed down till Soen&apos;s time, but were then divided.</e>
<cmt>盆石の定訳</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>梶宗龍より維新後に磯貝宗和（1854年～1940年）に茶道が伝えられて東京で広められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soryu KAJI imparted Sekishu school to Sowa ISOGAI (1854 - 1940) after the Meiji Restoration and that spread in Tokyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soryu KAJI imparted the Sekishu-ryu School to Sowa ISOGAI (1854 - 1940) after the Meiji Restoration, and it spread throughout Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soryu KAJI imparted the Sekishu-ryu School to Sowa ISOGAI (1854 - 1940) after the Meiji Restoration, and it spread throughout Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>この流れを石州流宗猿系と称する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This lineage is called Soen-kei group of Sekishu school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This style is called the Sekishu-ryu Soen-kei-ha branch.</e>
<cmt>ArticleRevised for clarity - as &quot;石州流宗猿系&quot; is the name of the style, I think it should be transliterated rather than translated</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This style is called the Sekishu-ryu Soen-kei-ha branch.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>さらに分派がすすみ石州流片桐宗猿派と称する２派に伝えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, the Soen-kei group of Sekishu school split into two groups as Soen-kei group and Soen KATAGIRI&apos;s group.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This branch then split into two, the Soen-kei-ha and the Sekishu-ryu Katagiri Soen-ha.</e>
<cmt>PunctuationArticleRevised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This branch then split into two, the Sekishu-ryu Soen-kei-ha and the Sekishu-ryu Katagiri Soen-ha.</e>
<cmt>原文の「２派」については、石州流宗猿系と石州流片桐宗猿派の二派と解釈しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="26">
<j>石州の弟片桐貞晴は3000石の旗本として取り立てられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sekishu&apos;s younger brother, Sadaharu KATAGIRI became Hatamoto with 3,000 koku (541.17 cubic meters.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sekishu&apos;s younger brother, Sadaharu KATAGIRI, was made a hatamoto with 3,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>PunctuationRevised verbArticle</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sekishu&apos;s younger brother, Sadaharu KATAGIRI, was made a hatamoto with 3,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>子孫の片桐宗幽が茶人として名を残すがその後は茶系譜は伝えられていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His descendent Soyu KATAGIRI was known as master of ceremonial tea, however, there was no pedigree record of tea school after him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His descendent, Soyu KATAGIRI, was known as a master of the tea ceremony; however, there is no pedigree record of a tea school after him.</e>
<cmt>PunctuationArticles&quot;ceremonial tea&quot;→&quot;tea ceremony&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His descendent, Soyu KATAGIRI, was known as a master of the tea ceremony; however, there is no pedigree record of a tea school after him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="28">
<j>藤林宗源の流れ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Lineage of Sogen FUJIBAYASHI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Lineage of Sogen FUJIBAYASHI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Lineage of Sogen FUJIBAYASHI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>藤林宗源（1608年～1695年）は石州の側近で後に小泉藩の家老となった人である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sogen FUJIBAYASHI (1608 - 1695) was a close adviser of Sekishu and became a chief retainer of the Koizumi Domain.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sogen FUJIBAYASHI (1608 - 1695) was a close adviser of Sekishu and became a chief retainer of the Koizumi Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sogen FUJIBAYASHI (1608 - 1695) was a close adviser of Sekishu and became a chief retainer of the Koizumi Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>石州とともに桑山宗仙に師事していた弟弟子にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sogen became a disciple of Sosen KUWAYAMA after Sekishu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He studied with Sekishu under Sosen KUWAYAMA</e>
<cmt>Revised for accuracy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He studied with Sekishu under Sosen KUWAYAMA</e>
<cmt>「弟弟子」が訳されていませんが、ＯＫと考えます。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>石州とほぼ同世代ではあるが、石州没後も20年以上長生きして石州流の初期伝播に大きな功績がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even though Sogen was the same generation of Sekishu, he lived 20 years more after Sekishu&apos;s death and served to spread the Sekishu school at an early stage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even though Sogen was the same generation as Sekishu, he lived 20 years longer than Sekishu and served to spread the Sekishu-ryu School at an early stage.</e>
<cmt>PrepositionRevised for clarityCapital letter</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even though Sogen was the same generation as Sekishu, he lived 20 years longer than Sekishu and served to spread the Sekishu-ryu School at an early stage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>藤林流あるいは宗源派とも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His lineage was called Fujibayashi school or the Sogen-ha group.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His style was called the Fujibayashi-ryu school or the Sogen-ha branch.</e>
<cmt>&quot;lineage&quot;→&quot;style&quot;&quot;group&quot;→&quot;branch&quot;ArticleCapital letter</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His style is called the Fujibayashi-ryu school or the Sogen-ha branch.</e>
<cmt>was→is</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="33">
<j>藤林宗源の系譜は片桐家の家臣で伝承され、江戸中期に大坂鉄砲組与力の本庄宗敬に伝授された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The lineage of Sogen FUJIBAYASHI was handed down among the retainers of the Katagiri family and in the mid Edo era, it was handed down to Sokei HONJO who was Osaka Teppogumi Yoriki (feudal era police rank of the Osaka gun team).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The style of Sogen FUJIBAYASHI was handed down among the retainers of the Katagiri family and in the mi-Edo era, it was passed to Sokei HONJO, an assistant to the Osaka Commissioner of Guns.</e>
<cmt>&quot;lineage&quot;→&quot;style&quot;Revised for accuracy - I presume &quot;大坂鉄砲組与力&quot; means he was a &quot;与力&quot; of the &quot;大坂鉄砲奉行&quot;Hyphen</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The style of Sogen FUJIBAYASHI was handed down among the retainers of the Katagiri family and in the mi-Edo period, it was passed to Sokei HONJO, yoriki (a police sergeant) to the Osaka Commissioner of Guns.</e>
<cmt>与力の定訳era→period</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>以来本庄家を家元として現在に至っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since then, it has been handed down up to present centering on the Honjo family as the grand master.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since then, it has been handed down to the present with the Honjo family as grand masters.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since then, it has been handed down to the present with the Honjo family as grand masters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>この流れは特に古石州流ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This lineage is specially called &quot;Ko-sekishu school (old Sekishu school)&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This lineage in particular is called the &quot;Ko-sekishu-ryu&quot; or Old Sekishu School.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This lineage in particular is called the &quot;Ko-sekishu-ryu&quot; or Old Sekishu School.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>これは片桐本家の8代小泉藩主片桐貞信が江戸千家の茶風を取り入れて「新石州流」を名乗ったことに対抗したものと伝えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This name was said to come from the rivalry against &quot;Shin-Sekishu school (new Sekishu school),&quot;which was started by the eighth lord of the Koizumi Domain Sadanobu KATAGIRI who added the Edo Senke (school of tea ceremony) style to Sekishu school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This name was said to come from the rivalry with the &quot;Shin-Sekishu-ryu School,&quot;which had been founded by the eighth lord of Koizumi Domain, Sadanobu KATAGIRI, by adding elements of the Edo Senke School to the Sekishu-ryu School.</e>
<cmt>PrepositionArticleRevised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This name is said to have come from the rivalry with the &apos;Shin-Sekishu-ryu School,&apos; which had been founded by the eighth lord of Koizumi Domain, Sadanobu KATAGIRI, by adding elements of the Edo Senke School to the Sekishu-ryu School.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;was→iscome→have come</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="37">
<j>藤林宗源の門人に片桐家の家臣で大西閑斎という人があり、石州の没後に大坂で茶湯指南をしていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kansai ONISHI who was a student of Sogen FUJIBAYASHI and a retainer of the Katagiri family became a coach of tea ceremony in Osaka after Sekishu died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kansai ONISHI, who was a student of Sogen FUJIBAYASHI and a retainer of the Katagiri family, became a teacher of the tea ceremony in Osaka after Sekishu died.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation&quot;coach&quot;→&quot;teacher&quot;Ａｒｔｉｃｌｅ</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kansai ONISHI, who was a student of Sogen FUJIBAYASHI and a retainer of the Katagiri family, became a teacher of the tea ceremony in Osaka after Sekishu died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>大口樵翁（1689年～1764年）は閑斎の門下に入って婿となったのだが、破門されて独立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sho OGUCHI (1689 - 1764) became a student of Kansai and married into the Onishi family, however he was expelled and became on his own.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sho OGUCHI (1689 - 1764) became a student of Kansai and married into the Onishi family but was expelled and started his own branch.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoo OGUCHI (1689 - 1764) became a student of Kansai and married into the Onishi family but was expelled and started his own branch.</e>
<cmt>Sho→Shoo 「しょうおう」ですのでこうしました。Sho で良いならご訂正願います。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>この流れを大口派と称する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His lineage is called Oguchi-ha group.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His style is called the Oguchi-ha branch.</e>
<cmt>Article&quot;lineage&quot;→&quot;style&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His style is called the Oguchi-ha branch.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="40">
<j>大口樵翁門下の林津南が鳥取藩茶道方となって以来、林家が代々この地で大口派を伝えてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Tsunami HAYASHI (林津南) who was a student of Sho OGUCHI became Sadokata (person in charge of tea ceremony) of the Tottori Domain, the Hayashi family has handed down the Oguchi-ha group in Tottori.</e>
<cmt>林津南→Tsunami HAYASHI (林津南)[定訳不明,読み方が見つからず、仮訳です。]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the appointment of Sho OGUCHI&apos;s student, Tsunami HAYASHI (林津南), as the Sadokata (tea master) of Tottori Domain, the Hayashi family has taught the Oguchi-ha style in Tottori.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the appointment of Sho OGUCHI&apos;s student, Tsunan HAYASHI (林津南), as the Sadokata (tea master) of Tottori Domain, the Hayashi family has taught the Oguchi-ha style in Tottori.</e>
<cmt>林津南の定訳不明ですが、Tsunan の可能性が高いと考え訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>幕末に林常甫が小川幸逸（不詳～1910年）に伝授したのが現在の大口派の源である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The origin of current Oguchi-ha group was what Tsuneho HAYASHI (林常甫) gave instructions to Koitsu OGAWA (小川幸逸) (date of birth unknown - 1910) at the end of Edo era.</e>
<cmt>林常甫→Tsuneho HAYASHI (林常甫)[定訳不明,読み方が見つからず、仮訳です。]小川幸逸→Koitsu OGAWA (小川幸逸)[定訳不明,読み方が見つからず、仮訳です。]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The current Oguchi-ha dates from the end of Edo period, when Tsuneho HAYASHI (林常甫) gave instructions to Koitsu OGAWA (小川幸逸) (date of birth unknown - 1910).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The current Oguchi-ha dates from the end of Edo period, when Tsuneho HAYASHI gave instructions to Koitsu OGAWA(date of birth unknown - 1910).</e>
<cmt>漢字削除。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>鳥取では維新後に小川幸逸の門下の古田貞が鳥取技芸女学校（現・鳥取敬愛高等学校）を設立し教科として教えたことにより広まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Tottori, Oguchi-ha group spread because Sada FURUTA who was a student of Koitsu OGAWA founded Tottori Gigei Jogakko (Tottori girls&apos; school of practical art, now Tottori Keiai High School) and taught tea ceremony as a subject.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Tottori, the Oguchi-ha spread because Sada FURUTA, who was a student of Koitsu OGAWA, founded Tottori Gigei Jogakko (Tottori girls&apos; school of practical art, now Tottori Keiai High School) and taught tea ceremony as a subject.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Tottori, the Oguchi-ha spread because Sada FURUTA, who was a student of Koitsu OGAWA, founded Tottori Gigei Jogakko (Tottori girls&apos; school of practical art, now Tottori Keiai High School) and taught tea ceremony as a subject.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>また同じく幸逸門下の戸田宗掬は京都に大口派を伝え、これが次いで大阪に伝わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sogiku TODA (戸田宗掬) who was also a student of Koitsu taught Oguchi-ha group in Kyoto, and that spread to Osaka.</e>
<cmt>戸田宗掬→Sogiku TODA (戸田宗掬)[定訳不明,読み方が見つからず、仮訳です。]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sogiku TODA (戸田宗掬), who was also a student of Koitsu, taught Oguchi-ha group in Kyoto, from where it spread to Osaka.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation&quot;and that&quot;→&quot;from where it&quot;&quot;group&quot;→&quot;branch&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sogiku TODA, who was also a student of Koitsu, taught Oguchi-ha group in Kyoto, from where it spread to Osaka.</e>
<cmt>漢字削除。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>さらに幸逸門下の前田良太郎の系譜が東京や関西に伝わっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another Koitsu&apos;s student Ryotaro MAEDA&apos;s (前田良太郎) lineage has spread in Tokyo and Kansai.</e>
<cmt>前田良太郎→Ryotaro MAEDA (前田良太郎)[定訳不明,読み方が見つからず、仮訳です。]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The teaching of Ryotaro MAEDA (前田良太郎), another of Koitsu&apos;s students, is popular in Tokyo and Kansai.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The teaching of Ryotaro MAEDA, another of Koitsu&apos;s students, is popular in Tokyo and Kansai.</e>
<cmt>漢字削除。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>秋田にも関西から大口派が伝わっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oguchi-ha group has spread up to Akita from Kansai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Oguchi-ha branch has spread from Kansai to Akita.</e>
<cmt>ArticleChanged word order&quot;group&quot;→&quot;branch&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Oguchi-ha branch has spread from Kansai to Akita.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>現在は芳春院の住職が家元として継承されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Currently, the chief priest of Hoshun-in Temple handed down the Oguchi-ha group as a grand master.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Currently, the chief priest of Hoshun-in Temple, as Grand Master, teaches the Oguchi-ha.</e>
<cmt>Changed word orderRevised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Currently, the chief priest of Hoshun-in Temple, as Grand Master, teaches the Oguchi-ha.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="47">
<j>清水動閑の流れ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Lineage of Dokan SHIMIZU</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Style of Dokan SHIMIZU</e>
<cmt>&quot;lineage&quot;→&quot;style&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Style of Dokan SHIMIZU</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>清水動閑（1614年～1691年）は仙台藩伊達政宗の茶道頭をつとめた清水道閑の孫にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dokan SHIMIZU 清水動閑 (1614 - 1691) was a grandson of Dokan SHIMIZU 清水道閑 who served for the lord of the Sendai Domain Masamune DATE as a chief of tea ceremony.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dokan SHIMIZU (清水動閑, 1614 - 1691) was a grandson of Dokan SHIMIZU (清水道閑), master of the tea ceremony for the Lord of Sendai Domain, Masamune DATE.</e>
<cmt>PunctuationPrepositionArticleRevised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dokan SHIMIZU (清水動閑, 1614 - 1691) was a grandson of Dokan SHIMIZU (清水道閑), master of the tea ceremony for the Lord of Sendai Domain, Masamune DATE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>茶道頭を世襲して道閑・道漢と名乗ったあと、仙台藩4代藩主伊達綱村より動閑と名付けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also became a chief of tea ceremony by succession and changed his name letters such as 道閑, 道漢.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After inheriting the position of master of the tea ceremony and taking the name Dokan (written 道閑, 道漢),</e>
<cmt>Revised to rejoin to cell G62</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After inheriting the position of master of the tea ceremony and taking the name Dokan (written as 道閑, 道漢), the fourth Lord of Sendai Domain, Tsunamura DATE, named him Dokan (written as 動閑).</e>
<cmt>NCも次のセルに繋がるように訳しているので、ここは分けずに一文としたほうが良いと考えます。原文も一文に戻しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>動閑は綱村の命により石州に入門し、相伝を受けて仙台に戻った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He entered Sekishu school by Tsunamura&apos;s order and after receiving the secret art of instructions, he went back to Sendai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On Tsunamura&apos;s orders, he entered the Sekishu-ryu School and, after receiving instruction in the secret art, he returned to Sendai.</e>
<cmt>Changed word orderArticle</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On Tsunamura&apos;s orders, he entered the Sekishu-ryu School and, after receiving instruction in the secret art, he returned to Sendai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>この流れを汲む流派を一般に清水派と称する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His lineage was generally called Shimizu-ha group.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His style is generally called the Shimizu-ha branch.</e>
<cmt>TenseArticle&quot;lineage&quot;→&quot;style&quot;&quot;group&quot;→&quot;branch&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His style is generally called the Shimizu-ha branch.</e>
<cmt>「清水派」を Shimizu-ha branch としているので、後に何度も出てくる「清水派」もこの訳で統一しています。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="52">
<j>動閑は弟子の馬場道斎（1662年～1737年）を改姓させ3世清水道竿として茶道頭を継がせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dokan made Dosai BABA (馬場道斎) (1662 - 1737) who was his disciple change his name as Dokan SHIMIZU the third and made Dosai succeed a chief of tea ceremony.</e>
<cmt>馬場道斎→Dose BABA (馬場道斎)[定訳不明,読み方が見つからず、仮訳です。]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dokan gave his student, Dosai BABA (馬場道斎, 1662 - 1737), the name Dokan SHIMIZU the third and had him take over as master of the tea ceremony.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dokan gave his student, Dosai BABA (1662 - 1737), the name Dokan SHIMIZU the third and had him take over as master of the tea ceremony.</e>
<cmt>漢字削除。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>道竿は綱村の命により石州の高弟でもあった松浦鎮信 (天祥)や藤林宗源にも伝授を受けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By order of Tsunamura, Dokan the third received instructions of Sekishu school from Shigenobu (Tensho) MATSURA and Sogen FUJIBAYASHI who were Sekishu&apos;s high-caliber disciples.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On Tsunamura&apos;s orders, Dokan the third received instruction from Shigenobu (Tensho) MATSURA and Sogen FUJIBAYASHI, who were Sekishu&apos;s best students.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On Tsunamura&apos;s orders, Dokan the third received instruction from Shigenobu (Tensho) MATSURA and Sogen FUJIBAYASHI, who were Sekishu&apos;s best students.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>以来代々茶道頭として仙台藩に仕え、維新後も伝承されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since then, the Shimizu family had served for the Sendai Domain as a chief of tea ceremony and handed down the Shimizu-ha group after the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From then on, the Shimizu family served Sendai Domain as masters of the tea ceremony and continued passing it down after the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarityArticle</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From then on, the Shimizu family served Sendai Domain as masters of the tea ceremony and continued passing it down after the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>一方で動閑の実子である清水快閑（1651～1716年）は医業を生業としていたが、その後代々伊達家奥向きの茶道を務めて現在は石州清水流として伝承されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dokan&apos;s real son, Kaikan SHIMIZU (1651 - 1716) was a medical doctor, but also he taught tea ceremony in the inner part of the house of the Date family and his family had handed down Sekishu Shimizu school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dokan&apos;s real son, Kaikan SHIMIZU (1651 - 1716), was a medical doctor, but he also taught tea ceremony in the inner part of the house of the Date family and his family handed down the Sekishu Shimizu School.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation- I don&apos;t know if it needs some explanation of &quot;the inner part&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dokan&apos;s real son, Kaikan SHIMIZU (1651 - 1716), was a medical doctor, but he also taught the tea ceremony on private occasions at the home of the Date family and his family handed down the Sekishu Shimizu School.</e>
<cmt>ＮＣも触れていますが、「奥向きの茶道」の表現を変更しました。これは伊達家の中だけで、という意味ですが、private occasions でよいのでしょうか？NR: I&apos;m still not really sure of the nuance behind 奥向 here, but grammatically the sentence works now.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>すなわち藩の公式な茶湯については道竿家が務め、快閑家の代々は道竿家より伝授を受けたうえで奥向きの茶湯を勤めてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While the Dokan family worked for the official tea ceremony of the domain, the Kaikan family worked for the inner part of the house of the domain lord receiving the instructions from the Dokan family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While the Dokan family performed the official tea ceremony of the domain, the Kaikan family performed it for the inner part of the house of the domain lord, receiving instruction from the Dokan family.</e>
<cmt>Revised for claritycomma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While the Dokan family performed the official tea ceremony of the domain, the Kaikan family performed it on private occasions, receiving instruction from the Dokan family.</e>
<cmt>the inner part of the house of the domain lord→private occasions上記回答に応じて、こちらも変更すること！</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="57">
<j>清水道竿家は仙台藩茶道頭として参勤交代の折には江戸詰めになり、そのため旗本や諸藩にも清水派が伝播することになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Dokan SHIMIZU family went to Edo (now Tokyo) because of Sankin-kotai (daimyo&apos;s alternate-year residence in Edo) and worked in Edo, therefore, Sekishu Shimizu school spread among Hatamoto (retainers of a shogun) and other domains.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The system of sankin-kotai, where daimyo had to spend alternate years in Edo (now Tokyo), meant the Dokan SHIMIZU family began practicing in Edo, leading to the spread of the Shimizu-ryu among the hatamoto, as well as to other domains.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sankinkotai (a system under which feudal lords in the Edo period were required to spend every other year in residence in Edo) meant the Dokan SHIMIZU family began practicing in Edo, leading to the spread of the Shimizu-ha branch among the hatamoto, as well as to other domains.</e>
<cmt>参勤交代の定訳を入れたので、そこで説明されている内容の文を削っています。Shimizu-ryu→Shimizu-ha branch</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>3世清水道竿門下の斎藤頼母（1670年～1716年）は5000石の旗本で、現在各地の清水派に連なる要の人物である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tanomo SAITO (1670 - 1716), who was a Hatamoto with 5000 koku (901.95 cubic meters) and a student of Dokan SHIMIZU the third, was a key person of the current Sekishu Shimizu school in various regions around the country.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tanomo SAITO (1670 - 1716), who was a hatamoto with 5000 koku and a student of Dokan SHIMIZU the third, is a key person for the Sekishu Shimizu School in various regions around the country.</e>
<cmt>Capital letter Deleted metric equivalent of &apos;koku&apos;Tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tanomo SAITO (1670 - 1716), who was a hatamoto with 5000 koku and a student of Dokan SHIMIZU the third, is a key person for the Shimizu-ha branch in various regions around the country.</e>
<cmt>Sekishu Shimizu School→Shimizu-ha branch</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>高松藩では5代藩主松平頼恭の頃に、斎藤頼母に学んだ片山五左衛門によって清水派がもたらされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the reign of Yoritaka MATSUDAIRA who was the fifth lord of the Takamatsu Domain, Gozaemon KATAYAMA (片山五左衛門) learned tea ceremony of Sekishu Shimizu school from Tanomo SAITO and introduced it in the Takamatsu Domain.</e>
<cmt>片山五左衛門→Gozaemon KATAYAMA (片山五左衛門)[定訳不明,読み方が見つからず、仮訳です。] 一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the reign of Yoritaka MATSUDAIRA, who was the fifth Lord of Takamatsu Domain, Gozaemon KATAYAMA (片山五左衛門) learned the tea ceremony of the Sekishu Shimizu School from Tanomo SAITO and introduced it to Takamatsu Domain.</e>
<cmt>PunctuationArticlePreposition</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the reign of Yoritaka MATSUDAIRA, who was the fifth Lord of Takamatsu Domain, Gozaemon KATAYAMA (片山五左衛門) learned the tea ceremony from Tanomo SAITO and introduced the Shimizu-ha branch to Takamatsu Domain.</e>
<cmt>「れ、」→「れた。」of the Sekishu Shimizu School→削除it→the Shimizu-ha branch</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>明治期になってさらに群馬に伝わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Meiji era, it was spread to Gunma.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Meiji era, it was spread to Gunma.</e>
<cmt>Article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Meiji period, it was spread to Gunma.</e>
<cmt>era→period</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>土佐藩では、高畠小平次によってもたらされた流れと、上村為山による二つの流れが合流して現代に伝わっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Tosa Domain, two lineages, which were from Koheiji TAKAHATA and Izan UEMURA, mixed together and had been handed down to present.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処, それにともない日本語を一部変更。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Tosa Domain, the styles of Koheiji TAKAHATA and Izan UEMURA were mixed together and have been handed down to the present.</e>
<cmt>ArticlePunctuationTenseArticle&quot;lineages&quot;→&quot;styles&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Tosa Domain, the styles of Koheiji TAKAHATA and Izan UEMURA were mixed together and have been handed down to the present.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>高畠小平次は、8代藩主山内豊敷の時期に斎藤頼母に学び、それをもたらした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koheiji TAKAHATA learned tea ceremony from Tanomo SAITO and introduced it during the reign of Toyonobu YAMAUCHI who was the eighth lord of the Tosa Domain.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処, それにともない日本語を一部変更。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koheiji TAKAHATA learned the tea ceremony from Tanomo SAITO and introduced it during the reign of Toyonobu YAMAUCHI, the eighth Lord of Tosa Domain.</e>
<cmt>PunctuationArticlePreposition</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koheiji TAKAHATA learned the tea ceremony from Tanomo SAITO and introduced it during the reign of Toyonobu YAMAUCHI, the eighth Lord of Tosa Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>茶堂の上村為山は、6世清水道看門下の中川道茂に学び、流れをもたらした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Izan UEMURA who was a sado (tea master served to person of exalted rank) learned tea ceremony from Michishige NAKAGAWA who was a student of Dokan SHIMIZU the sixth.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処, それにともない日本語を一部変更。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The tea master Izan UEMURA learned the tea ceremony from Michishige NAKAGAWA, who was a student of Dokan SHIMIZU the sixth.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarityArticlePunctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The tea master Izan UEMURA learned the tea ceremony from Michishige NAKAGAWA, who was a student of Dokan SHIMIZU the sixth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>これはさらに明治期になって広島、次いで東京や熊本に伝わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The lineage in the Tosa Domain spread to Hiroshima, then Tokyo and Kumamoto in Meiji period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Meiji period, it spread to Hiroshima, then to Tokyo and Kumamoto.</e>
<cmt>Changed word orderArticle</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Meiji period, it spread to Hiroshima, then to Tokyo and Kumamoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>一方水戸藩では、6代藩主徳川治保の時期に4世清水道簡に学んだ田中素白によって清水派がもたらされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Mito Domain, Sekishu Shimizu school was introduced by Sohaku TANAKA who learned it from Dokan SHIMIZU the fourth during the reign of Harumori TOKUGAWA who was the sixth lord of Mito Domain.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Mito Domain, the Sekishu Shimizu School was introduced by Sohaku TANAKA, who had learned it from Dokan SHIMIZU the fourth during the reign of Harumori TOKUGAWA, the sixth Lord of Mito Domain.</e>
<cmt>ArticlePunctuationＴｅｎｓｅDeleted &quot;who was&quot;Capital letter</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Mito Domain, the Shimizu-ha branch was introduced by Sohaku TANAKA, who had learned it from Dokan SHIMIZU the fourth during the reign of Harumori TOKUGAWA, the sixth Lord of Mito Domain.</e>
<cmt>Sekishu Shimizu School→Shimizu-ha branch</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>鎮信流が流入しながら現代に伝わっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then it has been handed down to present bringing together with Chinshin school.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has been handed down to the present day, while becoming mixed with the Chinshin-ryu School.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;then&quot;Articlerevised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has been handed down to the present day, while becoming mixed with the Chinshin-ryu School.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="67">
<j>他に東京に谷村家で伝承された石州流嘉順派が伝わっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As other Sekishu Shimizu schools there is Kajun-ha group of Sekishu school in Tokyo and it is handed down in Tanimura family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処、それに伴い日本語を変更</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other branches of the Sekishu Shimizu School include the Kajun-ha in Tokyo, which has been handed down in the Tanimura family.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other branches of the Sekishu Shimizu School include the Kajun-ha in Tokyo, which has been handed down in the Tanimura family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>その初代は、谷村三育で3世清水道竿門下である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its first grand master was Saniku TANIMURA who learned Sekishu Shimizu school from Dokan SHIMIZU the third.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処、それに伴い日本語を変更</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its first grand master was Saniku TANIMURA, who learned the Sekishu Shimizu School from Dokan SHIMIZU the third.</e>
<cmt>PunctuationArticleCapital letter</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its first grand master was Saniku TANIMURA, who studied under Dokan SHIMIZU the third.</e>
<cmt>learned the Sekishu Shimizu School from→studied under</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>特異なものとしては、はじめ古石州流、その後清水派の野崎兎園に学んだ朝田宗恭の流れや、その門人で井澤宗達（1891年～1972年）の流れなども清水派から派生したものと言える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As unique groups of Sekishu Shimizu school, there are the lineage of Sokyo ASADA who learned Ko-Sekishu school first and then learned Sekishu Shimizu school from Toen NOZAKI, and the lineage of Sotatsu IZAWA (1891 - 1972) who was Sokyo&apos;s student.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Two unique styles, that of Sokyo ASADA, who first learned the Ko-Sekishu School first and then the Sekishu Shimizu School from Toen NOZAKI, and the style of Sotatsu IZAWA (1891 - 1972), who was Sokyo&apos;s student, are both descended from the Shimizu School</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Two unique styles, that of Sokyo ASADA, who learned the Ko-Sekishu School first and then the Shimizu-ha branch from Toen NOZAKI, and the style of Sotatsu IZAWA (1891 - 1972), who was Sokyo&apos;s student, are both descended from the Shimizu-ha branch.</e>
<cmt>who first→whoSekishu Shimizu School→Shimizu-ha branchShimizu School→Shimizu-ha branch</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>特に井澤宗達の流れは片桐宗家に伝えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially, the lineage of Sotatsu IZAWA has been handed down in the Katagiri family which is the grand master family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sotatsu IZAWA&apos;s style, especially, has been handed down in the Katagiri grand master family.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sotatsu IZAWA&apos;s style, especially, has been handed down in the Katagiri grand master family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="71">
<j>野村休盛の流れ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Lineage of Yasumori NOMURA (野村休盛)</e>
<cmt>野村休盛→Yasumori NOMURA (野村休盛)[定訳不明,読み方が見つからず、仮訳です。]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Style of Yasumori NOMURA (野村休盛)</e>
<cmt>&quot;lineage&quot;→&quot;style&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Style of Yasumori NOMURA</e>
<cmt>漢字の定訳不明</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>野村休盛（1642年～1711年）は代々徳川将軍家の茶道組頭を務める家の出身である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasumori NOMURA (野村休盛) (1642 - 1711) was born in the family which had served as the head of the tea ceremony group for the Tokugawa Shogunate family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasumori NOMURA (野村休盛) (1642 - 1711) was born into a family which served as the head of the tea ceremony group for the Tokugawa Shogunate family.</e>
<cmt>PrepositionArticleTense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasumori NOMURA (野村休盛) (1642 - 1711) was born into a family which served as the head of the tea ceremony group for the Tokugawa Shogunate family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>将軍家の茶道が遠州流から石州流に変わったことから石州に入門したと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that he became a disciple of Sekishu because the Shogunate family changed tea ceremony school from Enshu school to Sekishu school.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that he became Sekishu&apos;s pupil because the Shogunate family changed from the Enshu School to Sekishu School.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarityArticles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that he became Sekishu&apos;s pupil because the Shogunate family changed from the Enshu School to Sekishu School.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>江戸後期になって野村家にも清水派が取り入れられたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the end of Edo era, Sekishu Shimizu school was taken in the Nomura family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Towards the end of Edo era, the Shimizu-ha was taken over by the Nomura family.</e>
<cmt>PrepositionsArticles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Towards the end of Edo period, the Shimizu-ha was taken over by the Nomura family.</e>
<cmt>era→period</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>この流れを汲む流派が石州流野村派である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This lineage is called Nomura-ha group of Sekishu school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This style is called the Sekishu-ryu Nomura-ha.</e>
<cmt>&quot;lineage&quot;→&quot;style&quot;Article&quot;group&quot;→&quot;branch&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This style is called the Sekishu-ryu Nomura-ha branch.</e>
<cmt>Nomura-ha→Nomura-ha branch</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>御数寄屋頭の伊佐家により広く伝えられた怡渓派（後述）と異なり、茶道組頭の野村家による伝播は多くない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ikei-ha school (later explained) was spread widely by the Isa family who was Osukiya Gashira (a head of tea ceremony for the Tokugawa Shogunate family), however, Nomura-ha group of Sekishu school was not spread well by the Nomura family who was the head of the tea ceremony group.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unlike the Ikei-ha (see below), which was spread extensively by the Isa family, who held the positon Osukiya Gashira in charge of the Shogun&apos;s tea rooms, the Nomura-ha was not spread so widely by the Nomura family, who were heads of the tea ceremony.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unlike the Ikei-ha (see below), which was spread extensively by the Isa family, who held the positon Osukiya Gashira in charge of the Shogun&apos;s tea rooms, the Nomura-ha was not spread so widely by the Nomura family, who were heads of the tea ceremony.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="77">
<j>秋田藩では5代藩主佐竹義峯が野村休盛英勝に伝授を受けてから野村派が行われるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nomura-ha group of Sekishu school started spreading in Akita Domain since Yoshimine SATAKE who was the fifth lord of Akita Domain received instruction from Hidekatsu Yasumori NOMURA (野村休盛英勝).</e>
<cmt>野村休盛英勝→Hidekatsu Yasumori NOMURA (野村休盛英勝)[定訳不明,読み方が見つからず、仮訳です。]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Nomura-ha began to be practiced in Akita Domain after the fifth lord of the domain, Yoshimine SATAKE, received instruction from Hidekatsu Yasumori NOMURA (野村休盛英勝).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Nomura-ha began to be practiced in Akita Domain after the fifth lord of the domain, Yoshimine SATAKE, received instruction from Hidekatsu Yasumori NOMURA.</e>
<cmt>漢字の定訳不明</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>維新後、佐竹家御用商人だった菅原新五郎の高弟の成瀬峯雲が東京で伝授したことにより、石州流成瀬派、石州流林泉寺派、石州流古閑堂派などに分派した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Meiji Restoration, Houn NARUSE (成瀬峯雲), who was a high-caliber disciple of Shingoro SUGAWARA (菅原新五郎) who was a government contractor of the Satake family, gave instructions in Tokyo, and that split into Naruse-ha group of Sekishu school, Rinsenji-ha group of Sekishu school and Kokando-ha group of Sekishu school.</e>
<cmt>菅原新五郎→Shingoro SUGAWARA (菅原新五郎)[定訳不明,読み方が見つからず、仮訳です。]成瀬峯雲→Houn NARUSE (成瀬峯雲)[定訳不明,読み方が見つからず、仮訳です。]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Meiji Restoration, Houn NARUSE (成瀬峯雲), a top student of Shingoro SUGAWARA (菅原新五郎), who was an imperial purveyor of the Satake family, taught the Nomura-ha in Tokyo, where it split into the Sekishu-ryu Naruse-ha, the Sekishu-ryu Rinsenji-ha and the Sekishu-ryu Kokando-ha branches.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarityChanged translation of &quot;御用商人&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Meiji Restoration, Houn NARUSE, a top student of Shingoro SUGAWARA, who was a purveyor of the Satake family, taught the Nomura-ha in Tokyo, where it split into the Sekishu-ryu Naruse-ha, the Sekishu-ryu Rinsenji-ha and the Sekishu-ryu Kokando-ha branches.</e>
<cmt>漢字の定訳不明「御用商人」が imperial pureyor とＮＣによって訳されていますが、「imperial」ではないので削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>これ以外に野村派は新潟にも伝わっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, Nomura-ha group of Sekishu school also spread in Niigata.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Nomura-ha is also taught in Niigata.</e>
<cmt>Revised to make more natural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Nomura-ha is also taught in Niigata.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="80">
<j>怡渓宗悦の流れ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Lineage of Soetsu IKEI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Style of Soetsu IKEI</e>
<cmt>&quot;lineage&quot;→&quot;style&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Style of Soetsu IKEI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>怡渓宗悦（1644年～1714年）は大徳寺253世に就いたあと江戸に帰って広尾祥雲寺や東海寺 (東京都品川区)にあった高僧である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soetsu IKEI (1644 - 1714) was a high priest, who served as Daitoku-ji Temple the 253rd and then returned to Tokyo and served for Shoun-ji Temple, Hiro and Tokai-ji Temple (Shinagawa Ward, Tokyo Metropolitan government).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soetsu IKEI (1644 - 1714) was a high priest, who served as the 253rd head priest of Daitoku-ji Temple before returning to Tokyo and serving at Shoun-ji Temple in Hiro and Tokai-ji Temple (Shinagawa Ward, Tokyo Metropolitan Area).</e>
<cmt>ArticlesRevised for clarity, accuracy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soetsu IKEI (1644 - 1714) was a high priest, who served as the 253rd head priest of Daitoku-ji Temple before returning to Tokyo and serving at Shoun-ji Temple in Hiro and Tokai-ji Temple (Shinagawa Ward, Tokyo Metropolitan Area).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>藤林宗源の没後、江戸において『石州流三百ヶ条註解』を著して石州流を諸国へ伝播する中心的な役割を果たした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Sogen FUJIBAYASHI died, Soetsu wrote &quot;Sekishu-ryu Sanbyakukajo Chukai (300 articles of Sekishu school&apos;s annotation)&quot; and played a key role propagating Sekishu school across the country.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Sogen FUJIBAYASHI died, Soetsu wrote &quot;Sekishu-ryu Sanbyakukajo Chukai (Notes on the 300 articles of the Sekishu-ryu School)&quot; and played a key role in propagating Sekishu school across the country.</e>
<cmt>Changed translation of &quot;石州流三百ヶ条註解&quot;Preposition</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Sogen FUJIBAYASHI died, Soetsu wrote &quot;Sekishu-ryu Sanbyakukajo Chukai (Notes on the 300 articles of the Sekishu-ryu School)&quot; and played a key role in propagating Sekishu school across the country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>この流れを汲む流派を一般に怡渓派と称する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His lineage is generally called Ikei-ha group.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His style is generally called the Ikei-ha branch.</e>
<cmt>&quot;lineage&quot;→&quot;style&quot;Article&quot;group&quot;→&quot;branch&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His style is generally called the Ikei-ha branch.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>初代伊佐幸琢（1684年～1745年）は怡渓宗悦より皆伝を受けた高弟である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kotaku ISA the first (1684 - 1745) was a high-caliber disciple of Soetsu IKEI and was conferred full-mastership.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kotaku ISA the first (1684 - 1745) was a top student of Soetsu IKEI and was conferred full-mastership.</e>
<cmt>&quot;high-caliber disciple&quot;→&quot;top student&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kotaku ISA the first (1684 - 1745) was a top student of Soetsu IKEI and was conferred full-mastership.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>以後5代に渡って江戸幕府の御数寄屋頭となり怡渓派を伝える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He and the next four generations had handed down the Ikei-ha group as Osukiya Gashira (a head of tea ceremony for the Tokugawa Shogunate family).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He and the next four generations, as Osukiya Gashira, taught the Ikei-ha.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity - since explanation of &quot;御数寄屋頭&quot; is in cell F94, I deleted here</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He and the next four generations, as Osukiya Gashira of the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) taught the Ikei-ha.</e>
<cmt>「江戸幕府の」追記</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="86">
<j>越後新発田藩では4代藩主溝口重雄が怡渓宗悦に茶の湯を学んで以来怡渓派で、8代藩主溝口直養の頃からは伊佐家の代々から伝授を受けた「御茶道」がいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Echigo-Shibata Domain had supported Ikei-ha group since Shigekatsu MIZOGUCHI who was the fourth lord of the domain received instruction from Soetsu IKEI.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Echigo-Shibata Domain had supported the Ikei-ha since Shigekatsu MIZOGUCHI, the fourth lord of the domain, received instruction from Soetsu IKEI</e>
<cmt>ArticlePunctuationRejoined to cell G108</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Echigo-Shibata Domain had supported the Ikei-ha since Shigekatsu MIZOGUCHI, the fourth lord of the domain, received instruction from Soetsu IKEI and from the time of the eighth lord, Naoyasu MIZOGUCHI, the domain had an &apos;osado&apos; (tea master) who received instruction from the Isa family.</e>
<cmt>ＮＣが一文で訳しているので、一文に戻しました。&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>特に10代藩主溝口直諒は茶道に傾倒し、奥伝を受けて自ら越後怡渓派を名乗るほどであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially, the tenth lord of the domain Naoaki MIZOGUCHI was absorbed in tea ceremony and received esoteric, calling himself Echigo-Ikei-ha group.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The tenth lord of the domain, Naoaki MIZOGUCHI, in particular, was fascinated by the tea ceremony, receiving esoteric instruction and taking the name Echigo-Ikei-ha.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, accuracy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The tenth lord of the domain, Naoaki MIZOGUCHI, in particular, was fascinated by the tea ceremony, receiving esoteric instruction and taking the name Echigo-Ikei-ha.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>このとき奥伝を伝えたのが阿部休巴（1748年～1853年）で、この系譜にあるのが現在の茶道石州流怡渓会となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The person who initiated Naoaki into the secrets of Sekishu school was Kyuha ABE (1748 - 1853) and his lineage became current Ikeikai of Sekishu school of tea ceremony.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The person who initiated Naoaki into the secrets of the Sekishu-ryu school was Kyuha ABE (1748 - 1853) and his style became the present-day Sekishu-ryu Ikeikai tea ceremony.</e>
<cmt>ArticleRevised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The person who initiated Naoaki into the secrets of the Sekishu-ryu school was Kyuha ABE (1748 - 1853) and his style became the present-day Sekishu-ryu Ikeikai tea ceremony.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="89">
<j>会津藩は寛永20年（1643年）に保科正之が入封してから石州流である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Aizu Domain had supported Sekishu school since 1643, when Masayuki HOSHINA was in power in the domain.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Aizu Domain had supported the Sekishu-ryu School since 1643, when Masayuki HOSHINA was the lord.</e>
<cmt>ArticleCapital letterChanged end of sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Aizu Domain had supported the Sekishu-ryu School since 1643, when Masayuki HOSHINA was the lord.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>孫の3代藩主松平正容が家臣の飯束林清（1677年～1751年）を怡渓宗悦に入門させ伝授を得て会津怡渓派と称するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His grandson Masakata MATSUDAIRA who was the third lord of the Aizu Domain made his retainer Rinsei ISOKU study under Soetsu IKEI and receive instructions, thus this lineage was called as Aizu-Ikei-ha school.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His grandson, Masakata MATSUDAIRA, who was the third lord of the Aizu Domain, made his retainer, Rinsei ISOKU, study under Soetsu IKEI; thus this lineage was called the Aizu-Ikei-ha branch.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation&quot;study and &quot;receive instruction&quot; are more or less the same, so deleted &quot;and receive instructions&quot;Article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His grandson, Masakata MATSUDAIRA, who was the third lord of the Aizu Domain, made his retainer, Rinsei IIZUKA (1677 - 1751), study under Soetsu IKEI; thus this lineage was called the Aizu-Ikei-ha branch.</e>
<cmt>（1677年～1751年）追記飯束林清→「定訳不明」ですが、ISOKU より IIZUKA の可能性が高いと思い、変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>幕末以降は武家出身で薬種商を営んでいた森川家が民間への伝承の中心となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the end of Edo era, the Morikawa family, who used to be samurai family and run the second-class drug seller, got a key roll of handing down Aizu-Ikei-ha school to citizens.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the end of Edo period, the Morikawa family, an old samurai family who had turned to selling medicines, became the main teachers of the Aizu-Ikei-ha to citizens.</e>
<cmt>Reworded for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the end of Edo period, the Morikawa family, an old samurai family who had turned to selling medicines, became the main teachers of the Aizu-Ikei-ha to citizens.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>千少庵によると伝えられる茶室「麟閣」を移築して兵火から免れさせるなどしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Morikawa family moved &quot;Rinkaku&quot; which was the tea room built by SEN no Shoan to prevent from being burntand and rebuilt it.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Morikawa family moved &quot;Rinkaku,&quot; the tea room built by SEN no Shoan, to prevent it from being burnt down in fighting.</e>
<cmt>PunctuationPronounDeleted &quot;and rebuilt it&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Morikawa family moved &apos;Rinkaku,&apos; the tea room built by SEN no Shoan, to prevent it from being burnt down in fighting.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>会津怡渓派は現在は片桐宗家の門に加わっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Aizu-Ikei-ha school joins in the group of the Katagiri family which is the grand master family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At present, the Aizu-Ikei-ha is part of the Katagiri Grand Master family group.</e>
<cmt>ArticleReworded for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At present, the Aizu-Ikei-ha is part of the Katagiri Grand Master family group.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="94">
<j>幕末期、4代伊佐幸琢は5代幸琢が若いうちに他界したため、5代幸琢は阿部休巴の門人であった山本宗雄（1818年～1880年）から皆伝を受けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the end of Edo era, Kotaku ISA the fourth died when Kotaku ISA the fifth was young, therefore, Kotaku the fifth received instructions from Muneo YAMAMOTO (1818 - 1880) who was a disciple of Kyuha ABE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the end of the Edo period, Kotaku ISA the fourth died while Kotaku ISA the fifth was young, therefore Kotaku the fifth received instruction from Muneo YAMAMOTO (1818 - 1880), a disciple of Kyuha ABE.</e>
<cmt>Article&quot;era&quot;→&quot;period&quot;PunctuationGrammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the end of the Edo period, Kotaku ISA the fourth died while Kotaku ISA the fifth was young, therefore Kotaku the fifth received instruction from Muneo YAMAMOTO (1818 - 1880), a disciple of Kyuha ABE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>その山本宗雄は維新後に怡渓流を名乗って茶湯教授を始めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Muneo YAMAMOTO started the professor of tea ceremony calling himself Aizu-Ikei-ha school after the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Meiji Restoration, Muneo YAMAMOTO started teaching the tea ceremony using the Ikei-ha name.</e>
<cmt>Changed word orderRevised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Meiji Restoration, Muneo YAMAMOTO started teaching the tea ceremony using the Ikei-ha name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>また維新後伊佐家が5代限りで茶道と無縁になった際に、門人だった袖山宗脩（1853年～1932年）によって継承され石州流伊佐派と称している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the fifth generation of Isa family stopped tea ceremony after the Meiji Restoration, its disciple Munenaga SODEYAMA (袖山宗脩) (1853 - 1932) succeeded it and handed it down as Isa-ha group of Sekishu school.</e>
<cmt>袖山宗脩→Munenaga SODEYAMA (袖山宗脩)[定訳不明,読み方が見つからず、仮訳です。]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the fifth generation of the Isa family stopped its involvement in the tea ceremony after the Meiji Restoration, Munenaga SODEYAMA (袖山宗脩) (1853 - 1932), a former student of theirs, took over and taught it as the Sekishu-ryu Isa-ha.</e>
<cmt>ArticleRevised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the fifth generation of the Isa family stopped its involvement in the tea ceremony after the Meiji Restoration, Munenaga SODEYAMA (1853 - 1932), a former student of theirs, took over and taught it as the Sekishu-ryu Isa-ha.</e>
<cmt>漢字削除。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="97">
<j>その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other</e>
<cmt>Deleted &apos;s&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>堯然法親王（1602年～1661年）は後陽成天皇の第6皇子であり、妙法院門跡で天台座主となった人だが、茶道にも造詣が深く石州から「一畳半の伝授」を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cloistered Imperial Prince Gyonen (1602 - 1661), who was the sixth son of Emperor Goyozei and became the monzeki (temple formerly led by founder) of Myoho-in Temple and Tendai-zasu (chief priest of Enryaku-ji Temple in Mt. Hiei), was well versed in tea ceremony and received the instruction of &quot;Ichijo han no Denju (initiation of one and half mats)&quot; from Sekishu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cloistered Imperial Prince Gyonen (1602 - 1661), the sixth son of Emperor Goyozei, became the head priest of Myoho-in Temple and Tendai-zasu (chief priest of the Tendai sect), was well versed in the tea ceremony and received instruction in &quot;Ichijo han no Denju (initiation of one and half tatami mats)&quot; from Sekishu.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, grammarChanged explanation of &quot;Tendai-zasu&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cloistered Imperial Prince Gyonen (1602 - 1661), the sixth son of Emperor Goyozei, became the head priest of Myoho-in Temple and Tendai-zasu (chief priest of the Tendai sect), was well versed in the tea ceremony and received instruction in &apos;Ichijo han no Denju (initiation of one and half tatami mats)&apos; from Sekishu.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>妙法院の執事高屋堯忠の子孫が代々その茶湯を受け継いでおり、石州庵ないし大内派と称されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takatada TAKAYA (高屋堯忠) who was the butler of Myoho-in Temple and his descendents handed down the tea ceremony and its style was called Sekishuan group or Ouchi-ha group.</e>
<cmt>高屋堯忠→Takatada TAKAYA (高屋堯忠)[定訳不明,読み方が見つからず、仮訳です。]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takatada TAKAYA (高屋堯忠), the steward of Myoho-in Temple, and his descendents handed down the tea ceremony, which was called the Sekishuan or Ouchi-ha branch.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takatada TAKAYA, the steward of Myoho-in Temple, and his descendents handed down the tea ceremony, which is called the Sekishuan or Ouchi-ha branch.</e>
<cmt>漢字削除was→is ご確認願います。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="100">
<j>松浦鎮信 (天祥)（1622年～1703年）は平戸藩の4代藩主で、石州に学んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigenobu (Tensho) MATSURA (1622 - 1703) was the fourth lord of the Hirado Domain and learned tea ceremony from Sekishu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigenobu (Tensho) MATSURA (1622 - 1703) was the fourth Lord of Hirado Domain and learned the tea ceremony from Sekishu.</e>
<cmt>Capital letterArticles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigenobu (Tensho) MATSURA (1622 - 1703) was the fourth Lord of Hirado Domain and learned the tea ceremony from Sekishu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>また家臣に金森宗和から伝授を受けさせ、一尾流や古市流も研究して独自の茶風に達した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigenobu also made his retainers learn tea ceremony from Shigechika KANAMORI, and arrived his own tea ceremony style studying Ichio school and Furuichi school.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigenobu also made his retainers learn the tea ceremony from Shigechika KANAMORI, and arrived his own tea ceremony style studying Ichio school and Furuichi school.</e>
<cmt>Article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigenobu also made his retainers learn the tea ceremony from Sowa KANAMORI, and arrived at his own tea ceremony style studying Ichio school and Furuichi school.</e>
<cmt>宗和→そうわ。重近のことですが、これはSowa です。arrived→arrived at</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>豊田家に代々伝承、伝授させて幕末に至り、再び松浦家が家元となって鎮信流と称している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His style had been handed down in the Toyota family till the end of Edo era and then the Matsura family became the master of Chinshin school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His style was handed down in the Toyota family till the end of Edo era when the Matsura family became the master family and the name was changed to the Chinshin-ryu School.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His style was handed down in the Toyota family till the end of Edo period when the Matsura family became the master family again and the name was changed to the Chinshin-ryu School.</e>
<cmt>era→periodfamily の前のスペース短縮「再び」again 追記</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="103">
<j>宝井其角（1661年～1707年）は松尾芭蕉の門人で、俳諧に秀で能書家でも知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kikaku TAKARAI (1661 - 1707) was a disciple of Basho MATSUO and was well-known as poet of seventeen-syllable verse and calligrapher.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kikaku TAKARAI (1661 - 1707) was a disciple of Basho MATSUO and was well-known as a poet of seventeen-syllable verse and a calligrapher.</e>
<cmt>Articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kikaku TAKARAI (1661 - 1707) was a disciple of Basho MATSUO and was well-known as a poet of seventeen-syllable verse and a calligrapher.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>茶湯も嗜んでいたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also well versed in tea ceremony.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also well versed in the tea ceremony.</e>
<cmt>Article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also well versed in the tea ceremony.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>現在宗洋派を称する一派が栃木に伝わっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soyo-ha group is handed down in Tochigi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Soyo-ha is practiced in Tochigi.</e>
<cmt>ArticleRevisd for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Soyo-ha is practiced in Tochigi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>其角堂派は群馬県を中心に伝わっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kikakudo-ha group is handed down centering on Gunma Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kikakudo-ha is practiced centering on Gunma Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>ArticleRevisd for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kikakudo-ha is practiced centering on Gunma Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="107">
<j>松平不昧（1751年～1818年）は松江藩の7代藩主で、始めは一尾流を学び、次いで3代伊佐幸琢から怡渓派の伝授を受けて、独特の茶風に達した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fumai MATSUDAIRA (1751 - 1818), who was the seventh lord of the Matsue Domain, learned Icho school first and then received instructions of Ikei-ha group from Kotaku ISA the third and arrived his own tea ceremony style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fumai MATSUDAIRA (1751 - 1818), who was the seventh Lord of Matsue Domain, learned the Icho-ryu first and then received instruction in the Ikei-ha from Kotaku ISA the third and developed his own tea ceremony style.</e>
<cmt>Capital letterArticlesPreposition</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fumai MATSUDAIRA (1751 - 1818), who was the seventh Lord of Matsue Domain, learned the Icho-ryu first and then received instruction in the Ikei-ha from Kotaku ISA the third and developed his own tea ceremony style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>これが松江藩家老の有沢家で受け継がれたものを不昧流、松江藩茶堂の藤井長古家で受け継がれ、支藩の母里藩につたわった茶系を石州流不昧派と称している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His style handed down in the Arisawa family which was the chief retainer of the Matsue Domain is called Fumai school, and the other handed down from the Choko FUJII&apos;s family which was the sado (tea master served to person of exalted rank) of the Matsue Domain to the Mori Domain which was the branch domain is called Fumai-ha group of Sekishu school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This style was handed down in the Arisawa family, chief retainers of the Matsue Domain, is called the Fumai-ryu School, while the version passed on in the sub-demain of Mori by Choko FUJII&apos;s family, who were tea masters of Matsue Domain, is called the Sekishu-ryu Fumai-ha branch.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This style was handed down in the Arisawa family, chief retainers of the Matsue Domain, is called the Fumai-ryu School, while the version passed on in the sub-domain of Mori by Choko FUJII&apos;s family, who were tea masters of Matsue Domain, is called the Sekishu-ryu Fumai-ha branch.</e>
<cmt>sub-demain→sub-domain</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="109">
<j>また松江藩主の子孫の茶系も伝わっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, there is another lineage which was handed down in descendents of the lord of the Matsue Domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is also another style which was handed down by descendents of the lord of Matsue Domain.</e>
<cmt>Changed word orderPreppositionArticle</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is also another style which was handed down by descendents of the lord of Matsue Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="25">
<sen id="110">
<j>井伊直弼（1815年～1860年）は彦根藩の15代藩主で大老を務めた人である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naosuke II (1815 - 1860) was the fifteenth lord of the Hikone Domain and served as Tairo (chief minister) of Tokugawa Shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naosuke II (1815 - 1860) was the fifteenth Lord of Hikone Domain and served as Tairo (chief minister) to the Tokugawa Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>ArticleCapital letterPrepisotiojn</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naosuke II (1815 - 1860) was the 15th Lord of Hikone Domain and served as Tairo (chief minister) to the Tokugawa Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処と考え、原文も分けました。fifteenth→15th</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>元来は300俵扶持の部屋住みで、この頃からおそらく石州流の茶湯を学んでいたと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally he was a Heyazumi (son who was not an heir) with 300 bales of salary, and he was said to start learning Sekishu school when he was a Heyazumi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A youinger son with an income of 300 bales, he was not expected to become lord and it is believed this is when he started the Sekishu-ryu.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A youinger son with an income of 300 bales, he was not expected to become lord and it is believed this is when he started the Sekishu-ryu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>片桐宗猿に事細かな質問をしており、その他の著書などから当代一流の茶人であったと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He asked detailed questions to Soen KATAGIRI and he was known as a first rank tea master according to other documents.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He asked detailed questions to Soen KATAGIRI and documents show he was considered a first class tea master.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He asked detailed questions to Soen KATAGIRI and documents show he was considered a first class tea master.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="113">
<j>家臣に宇津木左近があり、維新後に茶道教授をはじめており、この系譜が復元されて一会流と称している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sakon UTSUGI who was Naosuke&apos;s retainer started teaching tea ceremony after the Meiji Restoration and his restored lineage was called Ichie school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sakon UTSUGI, who was Naosuke&apos;s retainer, started teaching the tea ceremony after the Meiji Restoration and his restored style was called the Ichie-ryu School.</e>
<cmt>PunctuationArticle</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sakon UTSUGI, who was Naosuke&apos;s retainer, started teaching the tea ceremony after the Meiji Restoration and his restored style is called the Ichie-ryu School.</e>
<cmt>was→is ご確認願います。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="26">
<sen id="114">
<j>石州流真澄（慈光院石州流）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masumi (真澄) of Sekishu school (Jiko-in Sekishu school)</e>
<cmt>石州流真澄→Masumi (真澄) of Sekishu school[定訳不明,読み方が見つからず、仮訳です。]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sekishu-ryu Masumi School (Jiko-in Sekishu-ryu school)</e>
<cmt>Changed style of names of school</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sekishu-ryu Masumi School (Jiko-in Sekishu-ryu school)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="27">
<sen id="115">
<j>歴代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Historical lineage</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Genealogy</e>
<cmt>&quot;Historical lineage&quot;→&quot;Genealogy&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genealogy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="116">
<j>片桐宗家歴代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Lineage of Katagiri Grand master family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Lineage of the Katagiri Grand Master family</e>
<cmt>ArticleCapital letter</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Lineage of the Katagiri Grand Master family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 ５１６(id:45205), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), Mzaki(id:61977), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>