<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>珠光流</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Juko School (Tea Ceremony)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Juko School</e>
<cmt>(Tea Ceremony)は後列にあるので削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Juko School (Tea Ceremony)</e>
<cmt>新規統一リストに従って補足を戻しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>珠光流（じゅこうりゅう）は茶道流派の一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Juko school is one of the schools of tea ceremony.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Juko school is one of the schools of tea ceremony.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Juko school is one of the schools of tea ceremony.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>侘び茶の創始者とされる村田珠光を祖と仰ぎ古式を伝えるが、日本統治時代ソウル特別市の妙心寺京城別院にて行われるという独特の来歴を持つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Juko school counts Juko MURATA, who was a founder of wabi-cha, as its founder and passes on the ancient style of the tea ceremony, with a unique history that the practices of the tea ceremony were held at Myoshin-ji Temple Keijo Branch Temple in Seoul Special City during the period of Japan&apos;s rule.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Juko school counts Juko MURATA, who was a founder of wabi-cha, as its founder and passes on the ancient style of the tea ceremony, with a unique history that the practices of the tea ceremony were held at Myoshin-ji Temple Keijo Branch Temple in Seoul Special City during the period of Japan&apos;s rule.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Juko school counts Juko MURATA, who was a founder of wabi-cha, as its founder and passes on the ancient style of the tea ceremony, with a unique history that the practices of the tea ceremony were held at Myoshin-ji Temple Keijo Branch Temple in Seoul Special City during the period of Japan&apos;s rule.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>家元は鈴鹿市の天沢山龍光寺にあり、庵号は摩尼庵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The school is based at Tentakuzan Ryoko-ji Temple in Suzuka City and the ango (name of hermitage) is Manian.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The school is based at Tentakuzan Ryoko-ji Temple in Suzuka City and the ango (name of hermitage) is Manian.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The school is based at Tentakuzan Ryoko-ji Temple in Suzuka City and the ango (name of hermitage) is Manian.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>中興と称せられる7代備長庵道義は元禄期の人で、伝書などを多く残しているが、大火により京都を離れ尾張に移っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Living during the Genroku period, Dogi Bichoan, who was the seventh-generation tea master called as the restorer of the school, left many records of oral teaching; he moved from Kyoto to Owari because of a great fire.</e>
<cmt>Web の用語集で人名の読み方不明のものを、家元の龍光寺に問い合わせました。備長庵道義→Dogi Bichoan</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Living during the Genroku era, Dogi Bichoan, who was the seventh-generation tea master called as the restorer of the school, left many records of oral teaching; he moved from Kyoto to Owari because of a great fire.</e>
<cmt>period → era</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Living during the Genroku era, Dogi Bichoan, who was the seventh-generation tea master called as the restorer of the school, left many records of oral teaching; he moved from Kyoto to Owari because of a great fire.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>9代珠翫宗光は座禅への造詣が深く、見性宗般より庵号「摩尼庵」を受ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soko Shukan, the ninth master of the school, had a profound knowledge of zazen (Zen sitting meditation) and received the ango &apos;Manian&apos; from Sohan Kensho.</e>
<cmt>珠翫宗光→Soko Shukan /見性宗般→Sohan Kensho</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soko Shukan, the ninth master of the school, had a profound knowledge of zazen (Zen sitting meditation) and received the ango &apos;Manian&apos; from Sohan Kensho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soko Shukan, the ninth master of the school, had a profound knowledge of zazen (Zen sitting meditation) and received the ango &apos;Manian&apos; from Sohan Kensho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>珠翫宗光の没後まもなく、珠光流は師範代の梅笑庵宗雹に預けられ、京城（ソウル特別市）に移る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soon after the death of Soko Shukan, the Juko school was passed on to Sohaku Bishoan,a shihandai (assistant instructor), and moved to Keijo (Seoul Special City) with her.</e>
<cmt>梅笑庵宗雹→Sohaku Bishoan</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soon after the death of Soko Shukan, the Juko school was passed on to Sohaku Bishoan,a shihandai (assistant instructor), and moved to Keijo (Seoul Special City) with her.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soon after the death of Soko Shukan, the Juko school was passed on to Sohaku Bishoan,a shihandai (assistant instructor), and moved to Keijo (Seoul Special City) with her.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>宗匠位は妙心寺管長代理の真浄宗詮、のちに仁峰令譲へと引き継がれて伊勢へ移るが、引き続き京城にて盛んに行われ終戦により引き揚げとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the position of the tea master was passed to Sosen Shinjo, a deputy of the chief abbot of Myoshin-ji Temple, and then to Reijo Jinpo, subsequently moving to Ise City with her; however, the practices of the tea ceremony of the school were frequently performed in Keijo, and because of the end of the World War II, the school was evacuated from Keijo.</e>
<cmt>真浄宗詮→Sosen Shinjo　/仁峰令嬢→Reijo Jinpo</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the position of the tea master was passed to Sosen Shinjo, a deputy of the chief abbot of Myoshin-ji Temple, and then to Reijo Jinpo, subsequently moving to Ise City with her; however, the practices of the tea ceremony of the school were frequently performed in Keijo, and because of the end of the World War II, the school was evacuated from Keijo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the position of the tea master was passed to Sosen Shinjo, a deputy of the chief abbot of Myoshin-ji Temple, and then to Reijo Jinpo, subsequently moving to Ise City with her; however, the practices of the tea ceremony of the school were frequently performed in Keijo, and because of the end of the World War II, the school was evacuated from Keijo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>特徴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Characteristics</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Characteristics</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Characteristics</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>珠光流の現在の流儀のうち、文献に照らして古式と判断される点を挙げる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the context of the literature, some ancient styles would be listed among the present-day styles of the Juko school of tea ceremony.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the context of the literature, some ancient styles would be listed among the present-day styles of the Juko school of tea ceremony.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the context of the literature, some ancient styles would be listed among the present-day styles of the Juko school of tea ceremony.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>柄杓・蓋置・建水を運び出す時に、全てを建水に仕組むのが一般的である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While it is a general preparation for tea ceremony that water utensils are arranged in the way the host would bring them into the tearoom; thus a hishaku (a ladle) rests in a kensui (a waste-water container (for tea ceremony)) and inside is a hutaoki (a rest for the lid of a tea kettle), it is the preparation of the Juko school&apos;s style that the host enters the tearoom, bringing in a hishaku and a hutaoki with his right hand and only kensui with his left hand in the same way to take these utensils from the tearoom after the tea ceremony is over.</e>
<cmt>仕組む→準備する→全てを建水に仕組む→具体的に、&quot;a hishaku rests on a kensui and inside is a hutaoki&quot;と訳出し/ 仕舞い→かたずける→&quot;to take these utensils from the tea room after the tea ceremony is over&quot;と訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While it is a general preparation for tea ceremony that water utensils are arranged in the way the host would bring them into the tearoom; thus a hishaku (a ladle) rests in a kensui (a waste-water container [for tea ceremony]) and inside is a hutaoki (a rest for the lid of a tea kettle), it is the preparation of the Juko school&apos;s style that the host enters the tearoom, bringing in a hishaku and a hutaoki with his right hand and only kensui with his left hand in the same way to take these utensils from the tearoom after the tea ceremony is over.</e>
<cmt>カッコを整理しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While it is a general preparation for tea ceremony that water utensils are arranged in the way the host would bring them into the tearoom; thus a hishaku (a ladle) and a hutaoki (a rest for the lid of a tea kettle) rest in a kensui (a waste-water container [for tea ceremony]).</e>
<cmt>内容を変更しました。一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>しかし仕舞いと同様右手で柄杓・蓋置を持ち左手は建水のみを持って運び出す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is the preparation of the Juko school&apos;s style that the host enters the tearoom, bringing in a hishaku and a hutaoki with his right hand and only kensui with his left hand in the same way to put these utensils away after the tea ceremony is over.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="13">
<j>居前について後、帛紗を捌いて茶器・茶杓を清めるが、その後さらに柄杓を清める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After sitting the imae position (the correct seating position for the host when performing tea ceremony), the host purifies chaki (tea utensils) and a chashaku (bamboo of tea spoon for making Japanese tea) with folded fukusa (small cloth for wiping tea utensils) and after that, additionally purifies a hishaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After sitting the imae position (the correct seating position for the host when performing tea ceremony), the host purifies chaki (tea utensils) and a chashaku (bamboo tea spoon for making Japanese tea) deftly with fukusa (small cloth for wiping tea utensils) and after that, additionally purifies a hishaku.</e>
<cmt>bamboo of tea → bamboo teafoldを削除、deftlyを追加しました。(捌くはたたむではなく、巧みに使うという意味のようです--広辞苑)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After sitting the imae position (the correct seating position for the host when performing tea ceremony), the host purifies chaki (tea utensils) and a chashaku (bamboo tea spoon for making Japanese tea) deftly with fukusa (small cloth for wiping tea utensils) and after that, additionally purifies a hishaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="14">
<j>濃茶の廻し飲みをしない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While koicha (thick tea) is usually prepared by the host in a single bowl from which all guests drink and after savoring it, each wipes the rim of the bowl before passing it to the next guest, a bowl of koicha is individually served to guests in the style of the Juko school.</e>
<cmt>濃茶がどのようなものか分かるように、一般的な飲み方を補足しました</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While koicha (thick tea) is usually prepared by the host in a single bowl from which all guests drink and after savoring it, each wipes the rim of the bowl before passing it to the next guest, a bowl of koicha is individually served to guests in the style of the Juko school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While koicha (thick tea) is usually prepared by the host in a single bowl from which all guests drink and after savoring it, each wipes the rim of the bowl before passing it to the next guest, a bowl of koicha is individually served to guests in the style of the Juko school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="15">
<j>その他、茶巾を毎度たたみ直すことがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another style is that everytime the tea bowl of koicha is drunk and returned by each guest to the host, the host folds the chakin (tea cloth, a bleached white linen cloth used to dry a tea bowl) to dry the emptied bowl, and that hot water is used in the tea bowl to rinse the used chasen (tea whisk) before taking the utensils from the tearoom when the tea ceremony is over.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other characteristic styles include that everytime the tea bowl of koicha is drunk and returned by each guest to the host, the host folds the chakin (tea cloth, a bleached white linen cloth used to dry a tea bowl) to dry the emptied bowl, and that hot water is used in the tea bowl to rinse the used chasen (tea whisk) before taking the utensils from the tearoom when the tea ceremony is over.</e>
<cmt>NC_CheckAnother style is → Other characteristic styles include</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another style includes that everytime the tea bowl of koicha is drunk and returned to the host, the host refolds the chakin (tea cloth, a bleached white linen cloth used to dry a tea bowl).</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>また仕舞いの茶筅通しに湯を用いることなどがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also hot water is used in the tea bowl to rinse the used chasen (tea whisk) before putting the utensils away when the tea ceremony is over.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="17">
<j>歴代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>元禄期津軽藩の茶道役野本道玄の「珠光流聞書」には珠光の弟子である一樹庵光玉を流祖とする系図が示されているが、ほぼ同時期の宗匠である鈴木備長庵による「茶道珠光流系譜」によれば流祖は村田珠光であり備長庵は7代にあたるとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although &quot;Juko-ryu kikigaki (dictation of oral narrative, or interview report about the Juko school)&quot; shows the family tree whose founder was Kogyoku Ichijuan, one of the disciples of Juko, written by Dogen NOMOTO, who was a chabozu of the Tugaru domain (a tea-server sustaining Japanese tea ceremony of bakufu and domains) during the Genroku period, &quot;Sado Juko-ryu Keifu (family tree of the Juko school of tea ceremony)&quot; written by Bichoan SUZUKI, the tea master of almost the same period as Dogen NOMOTO, reads that the founder of the Juko school was Juko MURATA and the seventh-generation head of the school was Bichoan SUZUKI.</e>
<cmt>一樹庵光玉→Kogyoku Ichijuan / 鈴木備長庵→Bichoan SUZUKI</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although &apos;Juko-ryu kikigaki (dictation of oral narrative, or interview report about the Juko school)&apos; shows the family tree whose founder was Kogyoku Ichijuan, one of the disciples of Juko, written by Dogen NOMOTO, who was a sadoyaku (a tea-server sustaining Japanese tea ceremony of bakufu and domains) during the Genroku period, &apos;Sado Juko-ryu Keifu (family tree of the Juko school of tea ceremony)&apos; written by Bichoan SUZUKI, the tea master of almost the same period as Dogen NOMOTO, reads that the founder of the Juko school was Juko MURATA and the seventh-generation head of the school was Bichoan SUZUKI.</e>
<cmt>茶坊主とは書いてありません。用語集に統一しました。chabozu of the Tugaru domain (a tea-server sustaining Japanese tea ceremony of bakufu and domains) → sadoyaku (a tea-server sustaining Japanese tea ceremony of bakufu and domains)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although &apos;Juko-ryu kikigaki (dictation of oral narrative, or interview report about the Juko school)&apos; shows the family tree whose founder was Kogyoku Ichijuan, one of the disciples of Juko, written by Dogen NOMOTO, who was a sadoyaku (a tea-server sustaining Japanese tea ceremony of bakufu and domains) during the Genroku period, &apos;Sado Juko-ryu Keifu (family tree of the Juko school of tea ceremony)&apos; written by Bichoan SUZUKI, the tea master of almost the same period as Dogen NOMOTO, reads that the founder of the Juko school was Juko MURATA and the seventh-generation head of the school was Bichoan SUZUKI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="19">
<j>珠光流歴代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History of the Juko school</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History of the Juko school</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History of the Juko school</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Mzaki(id:61977), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>