<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>桐一葉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiri Hitoha (a single paulownia leaf)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiri Hitoha (a single paulownia leaf)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiri Hitoha (a single paulownia leaf)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>桐一葉（きりひとは）は、坪内逍遥作の歌舞伎の歌舞伎の演目一覧。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiri Hitoha (a single paulownia leaf) is a glance of Kabuki program of Shoyo TSUBOUCHI&apos;s Kabuki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiri Hitoha (a single paulownia leaf) is a glance Shoyo TSUBOUCHI&apos;s Kabuki program.</e>
<cmt>grammar, redundant</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiri Hitoha (a single paulownia leaf) is a glance Shoyo TSUBOUCHI&apos;s Kabuki program.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>1894年（明治27年）11月から1895年（明治28年）9月にかけ『早稲田文学』に連載。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was serialized in &quot;Waseda Bungaku (Waseda Literature)&quot; from November 1894 to September 1985.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was serialized in &quot;Waseda Bungaku (Waseda Literature)&quot; from November 1894 to September 1985.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was serialized in &quot;Waseda Bungaku (Waseda Literature)&quot; from November 1894 to September 1895.</e>
<cmt>1985→1895</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>1904年（明治37年）3月東京座初演。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first performance was given at Tokyo-za (kabuki theater) in March 1904.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first performance was given at Tokyo-za (kabuki theater) in March 1904.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first performance was given at Tokyo-za (kabuki theater) in March 1904.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>六幕十六場。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Six acts and sixteen scenes</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Six acts and sixteen scenes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Six acts and sixteen scenes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>新しい歌舞伎を求めて</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seeking new Kabuki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seeking new Kabuki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seeking new Kabuki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>すでに逍遥は『小説神髄』『当世書生気質』の二作で日本の近代文学創造に大きな業績をあげていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shoyo had already made great achievements in the creation of Japanese literature by publishing two works: &quot;Essence of Novels&quot; and &quot;Tosei shosei katagi (The Character of Modern Students, 1885-6).&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoyo had already made great achievements in the creation of Japanese literature by publishing two works: &quot;Essence of Novels&quot; and &quot;Tosei shosei katagi (The Character of Modern Students, 1885-6).&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoyo had already made great achievements in the creation of Japanese literature by publishing two works: &quot;Essence of Novels&quot; and &quot;Tosei shosei katagi (The Character of Modern Students, 1885-6).&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>イギリスのシェークスピアの翻訳に従事する傍ら、日本の近代劇の創造にも手を染めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While he was engaged in translation of Shakespeare&apos;s English works, he launched out the creation of Japanese modern dramas.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While he was engaged in translating Shakespeare&apos;s English works, he launched the creation of Japanese modern dramas.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While he was engaged in translating Shakespeare&apos;s English works, he launched the creation of Japanese modern dramas.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>そのきっかけが『桐一葉』である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kiri Hitoha&quot; is the beginning of such creations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kiri Hitoha&quot; is the beginning of such creations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Kiri Hitoha&quot; is the beginning of such creations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>従来の荒唐無稽な歌舞伎脚本やうわべだけの近代化に終わった活歴物と違う、新しい歌舞伎劇を目指すべく、1893年（明治26年）論文『我が邦の史劇』を発表、その実践例としてこの作品を創作した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Aiming at the creating a new kabuki drama unlike traditionally unrealistic scripts or the historical drama modernized only on the surface, he published a paper titled &quot;Wagakuni no Shigeki (Japan&apos;s historical drama)&quot; in 1893 and put his theory into practice by creating this work.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Aiming at creating a new kabuki drama unlike traditional unrealistic scripts or historical drama modernized only on the surface, he published a paper titled &quot;Wagakuni no Shigeki (Japan&apos;s historical drama)&quot; in 1893 and put his theory into practice by creating this work.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Aiming at creating a new kabuki drama unlike traditional unrealistic scripts or historical drama modernized only on the surface, he published a paper titled &quot;Wagakuni no Shigeki (Japan&apos;s historical drama)&quot; in 1893 and put his theory into practice by creating this work.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>逍遥は、1915（大正6）年に、活歴物への不満、シェークスピアの史劇の長所と歌舞伎の長所をうまく調和させたかったこと、深刻な悲劇を歌舞伎風のさまざまな挿話で作り上げたかったことなどが「桐一葉」創作の動機であると述べている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shoyo cited the following motives for creating &quot;Kiri Hitoha&quot; in 1915: A dissatisfaction with historical dramas; wishing to well combine advantages of Shakespeare&apos;s histories and Kabuki; and wishing to composing a serious tragedy of different episodes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoyo cited the following motives for creating &quot;Kiri Hitoha&quot; in 1915: Dissatisfaction with historical dramas; wishing to combine the advantages of Shakespeare&apos;s histories and Kabuki; and wishing to compose a serious tragedy of different episodes.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoyo cited the following motives for creating &quot;Kiri Hitoha&quot; in 1915: Dissatisfaction with historical dramas; wishing to combine the advantages of Shakespeare&apos;s histories and Kabuki; and wishing to compose a serious tragedy of different episodes.</e>
<cmt>「歌舞伎風の」が訳漏れか訳出不要か不明です。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>なお、逍遥は且元に九代目市川團十郎を、淀君には五代目尾上菊五郎をあてはめた書いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also wrote it on the assumption that Katsumoto would be acted by Danjuro ICHIKAWA the ninth and Yodogim by Kikugoro ONOE the fifth.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also wrote it on the assumption that Katsumoto would be acted by Danjuro ICHIKAWA the ninth and Yodogim by Kikugoro ONOE the fifth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also wrote it on the assumption that Katsumoto would be acted by Danjuro ICHIKAWA the ninth and Yodogimi by Kikugoro ONOE the fifth.</e>
<cmt>Yodogim→Yodogimi</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>しかし、いずれも存命中には初演できなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However neither of them survived the first performance.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However neither of them survived the first performance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However neither of them survived the first performance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>始め大坂夏の陣直後の豊臣家の混乱をテーマとして弟子の長谷川沙石に原案を書かせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shoyo made his disciple, Saseki HASEGAWA, write it as a draft on the theme of disturbance within the Toyotomi family immediately after Osaka Natsu no Jin (Summer Siege of Osaka).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処長谷川沙石の読み確認できていません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoyo made his disciple, Saseki HASEGAWA, write it as a draft on the theme of disturbance within the Toyotomi family immediately after Osaka Natsu no Jin (Summer Siege of Osaka).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoyo made his disciple, Saseki HASEGAWA, write it as a draft on the theme of disturbance within the Toyotomi family immediately after Osaka Natsu no Jin (Summer Siege of Osaka).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>しかし逍遥自身満足せず、結局彼自らが沙石案をもとに完成した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Shoyo was not satisfied with it and completed the final version by himself on the basis of the draft.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Shoyo was not satisfied with it and completed the final version by himself on the basis of the draft.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Shoyo was not satisfied with it and completed the final version by himself on the basis of the draft.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>発表当時は読本形式であったが、これでは実際の上演が困難であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiri Hitoha, when published first, was in the style of Yomihon (copy for reading)--a style not suited to present it on the stage..</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiri Hitoha, when published first, was in the style of Yomihon (copy for reading)--a style not suited for stage presentation.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiri Hitoha, when published first, was in the style of Yomihon (copy for reading)--a style not suited for stage presentation.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>そこで作者自身が歌舞伎風の脚本に改訂した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The author by himself revised it to a work in Kabuki style.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The author by himself revised it to Kabuki style.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The author by himself revised it to Kabuki style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>今日よく上演されるのは1915年（大正6年）4月帝国劇場上演時に「実演用」として書かれたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiri Hitoha commonly presented today is the script written &quot;for a dえmonstratio&quot;in performances at Teikoku-Gekijo Theatre in April 1915.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiri Hitoha script commonly presented today was written &quot;for a dえmonstratio&quot;in performances at Teikoku-Gekijo Theatre in April 1915.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiri Hitoha script commonly presented today was written &apos;for a demonstratio&apos;in performances at Teikoku-Gekijo Theatre in April 1915.</e>
<cmt>dえmonstratio→demonstration&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>「古き革嚢に新しき酒を盛る。」との逍遥の言葉がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shoyo said, &quot;new sake is put in an old kawabukuro (leather bag).&quot;</e>
<cmt>下のセルと一部合体</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoyo said, &quot;new sake is put in an old kawabukuro (leather bag).&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoyo said, &quot;new sake is put in an old kawabukuro (leather bag).&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>演出は浄瑠璃や下座、鳴物などを多用する旧来の歌舞伎狂言の形態であるが、内容はシェークスピアの影響の濃いスケールの大きな悲劇である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is performed in the traditional kabuki kyogen play with Joruri (dramatic narrative chanted to a samisen accompaniment), Shimoza, and narimono (musical instruments) frequently used for the stage effect but the contents of the play is a large scale tragedy greatly influenced by Shakespeare.</e>
<cmt>上のセルと一部合体一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is performed in the traditional kabuki kyogen play with Joruri (a dramatic narrative chanted to a samisen accompaniment), Shimoza, and narimono (musical instruments) frequently used for stage effect, but the contents of the play is a large scale tragedy greatly influenced by Shakespeare.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is performed in the traditional kabuki kyogen play with Joruri (a dramatic narrative chanted to a samisen accompaniment), Shimoza (background music player), and narimono (musical instruments) frequently used for stage effect, but the contents of the play is a large scale tragedy greatly influenced by Shakespeare.</e>
<cmt>下座の説明補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>新歌舞伎の嚆矢としてその文学的位置は大きい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its role in the field of literature is great as the beginning of new Kabuki.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its role in the field of literature is great as the beginning of new Kabuki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its role in the field of literature is great as the beginning of new Kabuki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="20">
<j>逍遥の言葉「・・・要するに、彼の貴族的な、英雄本位、淑女本位の高尚がりの活歴派に対しては、それとは反対の、平民的な、不作法な、凡人沢山、風情沢山の丸本式、草双紙式を発揚し、厳格な、窮屈な外国の審美論に対しては、無主義の、放埒な、いわば不即不離の国劇式を、暗に擁護しようという主張と抱負とが内心にあって、彼の作を書き始めたのである。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shoyo said, &quot;In short, I started to write this work with a view and ambition in my mind so as to inspire noble, hero- and lady-oriented, intellectual audience, who like historical drams, the maruhon shiki (style of complete set of books) and kusazoshi-style featuring common, rude people and having a lot of ordinary and interesting scenes--contrary to the characteristics of those audience--and imply my ambition to support the so-called kokugeki shiki (national drama style)--a non-doctorine, loose, and neutral style--to foreign aesthetes, who have a strict and rigid view.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoyo said, &quot;In short, I started to write this work with a view and ambition in my mind to inspire noble, hero- and lady-oriented, intellectual audience, who like historical dramas, the maruhon shiki (style of complete set of books) and kusazoshi-style featuring common, rude people and having a lot of ordinary and interesting scenes--contrary to the characteristics of those audiences--and imply my ambition to support the so-called kokugeki shiki (national drama style)--a non-doctorine, loose, and neutral style--to foreign aesthetes, who hold a strict and rigid view.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoyo said, &apos;In short, I started to write this work with a view and ambition in my mind to inspire noble, hero- and lady-oriented, intellectual audience, who like historical dramas, the maruhon shiki (style of complete set of books) and kusazoshi-style featuring common, rude people and having a lot of ordinary and interesting scenes--contrary to the characteristics of those audiences--and imply my ambition to support the so-called kokugeki shiki (national drama style)--a non-doctorine, loose, and neutral style--to foreign aesthetes, who hold a strict and rigid view.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「」部分に &apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>（『実演用桐一葉・序文』1915（大正6）年5月）より）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(&quot;Kiri Hitoha for performance on stage&quot; published in May 1915)</e>
<cmt>上のセルと一部合体</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(&quot;Kiri Hitoha for performance on stage&quot; published in May 1915)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Preface of &quot;Kiri Hitoha for performance on stage&quot; published in May 1915)</e>
<cmt>「序文」訳漏れ対応しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="22">
<j>続編の『沓手鳥孤城落月』は1905（明治38）年5月に大阪角座で初演された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its sequel, &quot;Hototogisu Kojo no Rakugetsu (The Sinking Moon over the Lonely Castle Where the Cuckoo Cries)&quot; was first performed at Osaka Kadoza theater in May 1905.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its sequel, &quot;Hototogisu Kojo no Rakugetsu (The Sinking Moon over the Lonely Castle Where the Cuckoo Cries)&quot; was first performed at Osaka Kadoza theater in May 1905.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its sequel, &quot;Hototogisu Kojo no Rakugetsu (The Sinking Moon over the Lonely Castle Where the Cuckoo Cries)&quot; was first performed at Osaka Kadoza theater in May 1905.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>あらすじ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary of the story</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary of the story</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary of the story</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="23">
<j>関ヶ原の戦い後の大阪が舞台で、豊臣氏の忠臣片桐且元の苦渋を描く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The drama describes distressed Katsumoto KATAGIRI, loyal vassal to the Toyotomi clan in Osaka after the Battle of Sekigahara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The drama describes a distressed Katsumoto KATAGIRI, loyal vassal to the Toyotomi clan in Osaka after the Battle of Sekigahara.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The drama describes a distressed Katsumoto KATAGIRI, loyal vassal to the Toyotomi clan in Osaka after the Battle of Sekigahara.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="24">
<j>豊臣家を滅ぼそうとする徳川家康は、方広寺の鐘銘に難癖を付けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ieyasu TOKUGAWA who wanted to ruin the Toyotomi family carped at the name given to a temple bell of Hoko-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ieyasu TOKUGAWA who wanted to ruin the Toyotomi family carped at the name given to a temple bell of Hoko-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ieyasu TOKUGAWA who wanted to ruin the Toyotomi family carped at the name given to a temple bell of Hoko-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>あまつさえ、豊臣秀頼を大和郡山に転封の上、将軍家に毎年参勤、高台院を人質に江戸にさし交わすこと、さもなくば攻めほろぼすとの無理難題を突きつけている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, he made an unreasonable demand for the transfer of Hideyori TOYOTOMI to Yamatokoriyama, annual sankin (daimyo&apos;s alternate-year residence in Edo), and offering Kodaiin to Edo as a hostage, intimidating to attack the family otherwise.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, he made an unreasonable demand for the transfer of Hideyori TOYOTOMI to Yamatokoriyama, annual sankin (daimyo&apos;s alternate-year residence in Edo), and offering Kodaiin to Edo as a hostage, intimidating to attack the family otherwise.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, he made an unreasonable demand for the transfer of Hideyori TOYOTOMI to Yamatokoriyama, annual sankin (daimyo&apos;s alternate-year residence in Edo), and offering Kodaiin to Edo as a hostage, intimidating to attack the family otherwise.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>豊臣家の人々は困惑し憤慨する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Peopole in the Toyotomi family got puzzled and irritated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Members of the Toyotomi family became puzzled and irritated.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Members of the Toyotomi family became puzzled and irritated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>勢い、豊臣家の攻撃の矢は、徳川氏との交渉役をつかさどる片桐且元に向けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Katsumoto KATAGIRI who acted as an negotiator with the Tokugawa clan inevitably became a target of attacks against the Toyotomi family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Katsumoto KATAGIRI who acted as a negotiator with the Tokugawa clan inevitably became a target of attacks against the Toyotomi family.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Katsumoto KATAGIRI who acted as a negotiator with the Tokugawa clan inevitably became a target of attacks against the Toyotomi family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>きゃつは不忠極まる輩で、内通しているとあらぬ噂が飛びかい、且元失脚を狙うきな臭い動きが大阪城内に立ち込めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A groundless rumor was circulated that he was a quite unfaithful guy and in a secrete communication with Tokugawa, and there were signs of attempts to overthrowing Katsumoto in the Osaka castle.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A groundless rumor was circulated that he was an unfaithful guy in secrete communication with Tokugawa, and there were signs of attempts at overthrowing Katsumoto in the Osaka castle.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A groundless rumor was circulated that he was an unfaithful guy in secrete communication with Tokugawa, and there were signs of attempts at overthrowing Katsumoto in the Osaka-jo castle.</e>
<cmt>城名に -jo 追記</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>第1幕 大阪城内奥殿の場</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Act 1: A scene of Okudono (manor) in the Osaka castle</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Act 1: A scene of Okudono (manor) in the Osaka castle</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Act 1: A scene of Okudono (manor) in the Osaka castle</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="29">
<j>城内では腰元と茶坊主の珍伯らが且元の陰口を言っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the castle, female servants and Chinpaku, chabozu (tea-server) were talking malicious gossip about Katsuyori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the castle, female servants and Chinpaku, chabozu (tea-server) are talking malicious gossip about Katsuyori.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the castle, female servants and Chinpaku, chabozu (tea-server) are talking malicious gossip about Katsumoto.</e>
<cmt>Katsuyori→Katsumoto</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>且元の娘蜻蛉はそんな父の評判に心を痛めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Katsuyori&apos;s daughter Kagero got hurt hearing such reputation of her father.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Katsuyori&apos;s daughter Kagero is hurt from hearing about such a reputation about her father.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Katsumoto&apos;s daughter Kagero is hurt from hearing about such a reputation about her father.</e>
<cmt>Katsuyori→Katsumoto</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>そこへ彼女に懸想する銀之丞が絡む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ginnojo who are in love with her then made a pass at her.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ginnojo who is in love with her makes a pass at her.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ginnojo who is in love with her makes a pass at her.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>銀之丞は豊臣家の重臣渡辺内蔵之介の弟、母は淀殿の腹心正栄尼という名家の御曹司である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ginnojo was a son of a distinguished family; he was a younger brother of Kuranosuke WATANABE, senior vassals of the Toyotomi family, and his mother was Shoeini, Yotdodono7s confidant.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ginnojo was the son of a distinguished family; he was a younger brother of Kuranosuke WATANABE, senior vassals of the Toyotomi family, and his mother was Shoeini, Yotdodono&apos;s confidant.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ginnojo was the son of a distinguished family; he was a younger brother of Kuranosuke WATANABE, senior vassals of the Toyotomi family, and his mother was Shoeini, Yotdodono&apos;s confidant.</e>
<cmt>Yotdono→Yododono</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>純真な心を持っているが、知恵が足らない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had a pure heart but lacks a wisdom.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He has a pure heart but lacks wisdom.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He has a pure heart but lacks wisdom.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>木村重成を許婚に持つ蜻蛉は相手にしない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kagero, a fiancé of Shigenari KIMURA, brushed him off</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kagero, a fiancé of Shigenari KIMURA, brushed him off.</e>
<cmt>period</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kagero, a fiancé of Shigenari KIMURA, brushed him off.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>争う二人を見ながら、珍伯は且元に見切りを付け政敵の大野道軒親子につくことを決意する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seeing the couple having an argument, Chinpaku decided to gave up katsuyori and sided with Doken ONO and his son, although they had been a political enemy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seeing the couple having an argument, Chinpaku decided to gave up katsuyori and sided with Doken ONO and his son, although they had been political enemies.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seeing the couple having an argument, Chinpaku decided to gave up katsumoto and sided with Doken ONO and his son, although they had been political enemies.</e>
<cmt>Katsuyori→Katsumoto</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>奥庭茶室の場</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A scene of chashitsu (tea-ceremony room) in a back garden.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A scene of chashitsu (tea-ceremony room) in a back garden.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A scene of chashitsu (tea-ceremony room) in a back garden.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="36">
<j>大野道軒は子の大野修理とともに且元を徳川の間者とみなし、直情な石川伊豆守をそそのかして城内にて討ち果たす手立てを講じる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Regarding Katsumoto as Kanja (spy) of Tokugawa, Doken ONO and his son Shuri ONO made a plot to tempt impulsive Ishikawa Izu no kami (Governor of Izu Province) to kill Katsumoto within the castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regarding Katsumoto as Kanja (spy) of Tokugawa, Doken ONO and his son Shuri ONO plot to tempt impulsive Ishikawa Izu no kami (Governor of Izu Province) to kill Katsumoto within the castle.</e>
<cmt>grammar, word spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regarding Katsumoto as Kanja (spy) of Tokugawa, Doken ONO and his son Shuri ONO plot to tempt impulsive Ishikawa Izu no kami (Governor of Izu Province) to kill Katsumoto within the castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>第2幕 吉野山桜狩の場</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Act 2: A scene of Sakuragari (Cherry Viewing) in Mt. Yoshino</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Act 2: Scene of Sakuragari (Cherry blossom Viewing) on Mt. Yoshino</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Act 2: Scene of Sakuragari (Cherry blossom Viewing) on Mt. Yoshino</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="37">
<j>淀君は秀吉とともに文禄・慶長の役の戦勝の宴を吉野山で祝っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yodogimi and Hideyoshi were celebrating a victory of the Bunroku-Keicho War in Mt. Yoshino.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yodogimi and Hideyoshi were celebrating a victory of the Bunroku-Keicho War in Mt. Yoshino.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yodogimi and Hideyoshi were celebrating a victory of the Bunroku-Keicho War in Mt. Yoshino.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>桜が満開の中での祝宴の最中、武悪の面をかぶった二人の奴が女馬子とともに現れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the celebratory feast under cherry blossoms in full bloom, two guys wearing mask of Buaku (demons) appeared with a female mago (packhorse driver).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the celebratory feast under cherry blossoms in full bloom, two guys wearing masks of Buaku (demons) appeared with a female mago (packhorse driver).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the celebratory feast under cherry blossoms in full bloom, two guys wearing masks of Buaku (demons) appeared with a female mago (packhorse driver).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>奴の一人、実は佐々成政が秀吉を暗殺する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of the guys, who was turned out to be Narimasa SASSA, killed Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One, who turned out to be Narimasa SASSA, kills Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One, who turned out to be Narimasa SASSA, kills Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>不思議にも死体が起き上がり石田三成の変装と分かる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The corpse incredibly stood up and turned out to be Mitsunari ISHIDA in disguise.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The corpse incredibly stands up and turns out to be Mitsunari ISHIDA in disguise.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The corpse incredibly stands up and turns out to be Mitsunari ISHIDA in disguise.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>実の秀吉は武悪の面をかぶったもう一人の奴。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hideyoshi in reality was the other guy wearing a mask of Buaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hideyoshi, in reality, was the other guy wearing a Buaku mask.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hideyoshi, in reality, was the other guy wearing a Buaku mask.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>馬子は淀君の変装であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yodogimi was found out to have been dressed as mago.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yodogimi is discovered to have been dressed as mago.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yodogimi is discovered to have been dressed as mago.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>改めて祝宴を張る二人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The two started to cerebrate a feast again.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The two start to cerebrate the feast again.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The two start to cerebrate the feast again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>だが、秀吉の姿はいつしか憤死した豊臣秀次へ…</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Hideyoshi was turning into Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI who had died in a fit of anger.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Hideyoshi turned into Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI who had died in a fit of anger.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Hideyoshi turned into Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI who had died in a fit of anger.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>畜生塚の場</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A scene of Chikushozuka (Mound of Beasts)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A scene of Chikushozuka (Mound of Beasts)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A scene of Chikushozuka (Mound of Beasts)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="45">
<j>華やかな吉野山はいつの間にか荒れ果てた墓になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A scene of Mt. Yoshino in a splendid atmosphere is turning into a desolate graveyard.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Scene of Mt. Yoshino in a splendid atmosphere is turning into a desolate graveyard.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Scene of Mt. Yoshino in a splendid atmosphere is turning into a desolate graveyard.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>ここは秀次の首を埋めた畜生塚である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was Chikushozuka where the head of Hidetsugu had been buried.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is Chikushozuka where the head of Hidetsugu had been buried.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is Chikushozuka where the head of Hidetsugu has been buried.</e>
<cmt>had→has （主節が現在形のため）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>淀君は秀次・小西行長・石田三成の怨霊に苦しむ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yodogimi suffered from vengeful ghosts of Hidetsugu, Yukinaga KONISHI, and Mitsunari ISHIDA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yodogimi suffered from the vengeful ghosts of Hidetsugu, Yukinaga KONISHI, and Mitsunari ISHIDA.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yodogimi suffers from the vengeful ghosts of Hidetsugu, Yukinaga KONISHI, and Mitsunari ISHIDA.</e>
<cmt>suffered→suffers （上の二文が現在形で、ここも現在形のほうが良いと考えます。）</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>淀君寝所密訴の場</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A scene of secret words of advice at Yodogimi&apos;s bedchamber</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Scene of secret words of advice given at Yodogimi&apos;s bedchamber</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Scene of secret words of advice given at Yodogimi&apos;s bedchamber</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="48">
<j>果てして今のはすべて淀君の夢であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">All that happened was found out to be a dream of Yodogimi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">All that happened was just a dream of Yodogimi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">All that happened was just a dream of Yodogimi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>心身ともに疲れ果てた淀君は、徳川家の仕打ちに憤然としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Exhausted physically and mentally, Yodogimi was indignant with the maltreat of the Tokugawa family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Exhausted physically and mentally, Yodogimi is indignant with the maltreat of the Tokugawa family.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Exhausted physically and mentally, Yodogimi is indignant with the maltreat of the Tokugawa family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>そこへ正栄尼が徳川家の三つの難題を知らせに来たため、淀君のヒステリーはひどくなるばかりである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then Shoeini came to inform her of the three unreasonable demands, which made her temper worse and worse.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then Shoeini came to inform her of the three unreasonable demands, that made her temper grow worse and worse.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then Shoeini came to inform her of the three unreasonable demands, that made her temper grow worse and worse.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>淀君の寵臣大野修理は、片桐且元を不忠者として粛清することを進言する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shuri ONO, Yodogimi&apos;s favorite retainer advised that Katsumoto KATAGIRI be purged as a treason.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shuri ONO, Yodogimi&apos;s favorite retainer advises that Katsumoto KATAGIRI be purged for treason.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shuri ONO, Yodogimi&apos;s favorite retainer advises that Katsumoto KATAGIRI be purged for treason.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>第3幕 城内溜りの場</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Act 3: A scene of tamari (a dark sauce) in the castle</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Act 3: Scene of tamari (a dark sauce) in the castle</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Act 3: Scene of tamari (a dark sauce) in the castle</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="52">
<j>大野親子にそそのかされた石川伊豆守は且元を面罵する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ishikawa Izu no kami tempered by the father and son of the Ono abused Katsumoto to his face.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ishikawa Izu no kami tempered by the father and son of the Ono abuses Katsumoto to his face.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ishikawa Izu no kami tempered by the father and son of the Ono abuses Katsumoto to his face.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>だが、且元はひたすら耐えるばかり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However Katsumoto did nothing but endure it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However Katsumoto does nothing, but endures it.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However Katsumoto does nothing, but endures it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>命乞いまでする態度に伊豆守はあざけり、且元を蹴り倒す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His behavior to beg for his life made Izu no kami insult and gave a kick to him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His behavior of begging for his life made Izu no kami feel insulted and he kicked him.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His behavior of begging for his life made Izu no kami despise him and he kicked him down.</e>
<cmt>「あざけり」は「feel insulted」ではないと思います。「despise」としましたが、ご確認願います。down も文末に加えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>黒書院内評議の場</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A scene of meeting at kuroshoin (private residential quarters)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Scene of meeting at kuroshoin (private residential quarters)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Scene of meeting at kuroshoin (private residential quarters)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="55">
<j>秀頼、淀君らが家臣を集め且元の処遇をめぐって評議している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hideyori and Yodogimi summoned vassals and they were discussing how to deal with Katsumoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hideyori and Yodogimi summoned some vassals and they were discussing how to deal with Katsumoto.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hideyori and Yodogimi summoned some vassals and they were discussing how to deal with Katsumoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>大野親子は処罰を主張する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The father and son of the Ono insisted a penalty.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The father and son of the Ono insisted on a penalty.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The father and son of the Ono insisted on a penalty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>折しも登城した木村重成の説得に、秀頼は重成を使者に立てて且元の本心を探ることを命じる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hideyori was pursuade by Shigenari KIMURA, who attended the castle at that time, ordered Shigenari to act as an envoy to find out Katsumoto&apos;s real intention.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hideyori was pursuade by Shigenari KIMURA, who attended the castle at that time, ordered Shigenari to act as an envoy to find out Katsumoto&apos;s real intentions.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hideyori was pursuade by Shigenari KIMURA, who attended the castle at that time, ordered Shigenari to act as an envoy to find out Katsumoto&apos;s real intentions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>片桐邸上使</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An envoy at Katagiri residence</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An envoy at the Katagiri residence</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An envoy at the Katagiri residence</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="58">
<j>且元は夜遅く一人算盤を手に軍用資金の遣り繰りに苦しんでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Late at night, Katsumoto was alone having hard time figuring out how to managing war funds with soroban (abacus) in his hands.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Late at night, Katsumoto is alone having a hard time trying to figure out how to managing war funds with a soroban (abacus) in his hands.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Late at night, Katsumoto is alone having a hard time trying to figure out how to manage war funds with an abacus in his hands.</e>
<cmt>managing→managesoroban 削除（abacus のみでＯＫと考えます。）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>奥方の一葉は夫が裏切り者や卑怯者と謗られるのに耐えきれず涙ながらに苦渋を訴える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His wife Hitoha shed tears and expressed her intolerable hardship that her husband was abused as a betrayer or coward.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His wife Hitoha shed tears and expressed the intolerable hardship about her husband being abused as a traitor or coward.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His wife Hitoha shed tears and expressed the intolerable hardship about her husband being abused as a traitor or coward.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>そこへ重成が秀頼の上使として来訪。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then Shigenari came as an envoy of Hideyori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then Shigenari came as an envoy of Hideyori&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then Shigenari came as an envoy of Hideyori&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>且元は本心を明かし、徳川家との衝突は早晩避けられないが、力を蓄えて時節を待つこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Katsuyori uncovered his opinion that a conflict with the Tokugawa family would be inevitable at some time or other but it was time to gain strength and wait for a ripe time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Katsuyori expresses his opinion that a conflict with the Tokugawa family is inevitable, but it is time to gain strength and wait for right time.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Katsuyori expresses his opinion that a conflict with the Tokugawa family is inevitable, but it is time to gain strength and wait for right time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>そのためには今は無理難題も受け付けておくことの大事さを説く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He urged the importance of accepting unreasonable demands now to do so.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He urged the importance of accepting unreasonable demands now in order to do so.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He urged the importance of accepting unreasonable demands now in order to do so.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>その深謀に感心する重成であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigenari was impressed by his farsightedness.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigenari is impressed by his farsightedness.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigenari is impressed by his farsightedness.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>そしてここにもう一人、且元を討とうと忍び込んだ伊豆守が現れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And here another man, Izu no kami, who had sneaked into the room, appeared.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And here another man, Izu no kami, who had sneaked into the room, appears.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And here another man, Izu no kami, who has sneaked into the room, appears.</e>
<cmt>had→has</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>身の不明を恥じ片目を刳りぬき謝罪する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ashamed of his ignorance, he apologized by cutting out an eye.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ashamed of his ignorance, he apologizes by cutting out his eye.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ashamed of his ignorance, he apologizes by cutting out his eye.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>且元は伊豆守に血気にはやることの愚かさを説く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Katsuyori explained how stupid it was to act impetuously.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Katsuyori explains how stupid it was to act so impetuously.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Katsuyori explains how stupid it was to act so impetuously.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>第4幕 豊国神社鳥居前の場</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Act 4: A scene in front of torii (an archway to a Shinto shrine) of Hokoku-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Act 4: Scene in front of the torii (an archway to a Shinto shrine) to Hokoku-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Act 4: Scene in front of the torii (an archway to a Shinto shrine) to Hokoku-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="67">
<j>大野親子の命を受けた珍伯は、通りかかった蜻蛉に父の命を助けたくば許婚の木村重成に取り次いでもらえと告げる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chinpaku ordered by the father and son of the Ono told Kagero to ask her fiancé, Shigenari KIMURA, for good offices in order to save her father.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chinpaku ordered by the father and son of the Ono tells Kagero to ask her fiancé, Shigenari KIMURA, for good offices in order to save her father.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chinpaku ordered by the father and son of the Ono tells Kagero to ask her fiancé, Shigenari KIMURA, for good offices in order to save her father.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>実は重成のとりなしで淀君の勘気を解かせ、且元を登城させて討つ陰謀なのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was in fact a plot to make him dispel Yodogimi&apos;s disfavor and attend the castle before killing him there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is in fact a plot to make him dispel Yodogimi&apos;s disfavor and attend the castle before killing him there.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is in fact a plot to make him dispel Yodogimi&apos;s disfavor and attend the castle before killing him there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>そうとは知らぬ蜻蛉はいそいそと文を書くが、銀之丞に奪われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Not knowing this plot, kagero soon wrote a letter but Ginnojo snatched it from her.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Not knowing about this plot, kagero soon writes a letter, but Ginnojo snatches it from her.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Not knowing about this plot, kagero soon writes a letter, but Ginnojo snatches it from her.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>さらに腰元椋鳥が文を奪い、三人ごっちゃのまま争って去る</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mukudori, a female servant, further snatched the letter, and the three left the stage scrambling for it.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mukudori, a female servant, further snatches the letter, and the three leave the stage scrambling for it.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mukudori, a female servant, further snatches the letter, and the three leave the stage scrambling for it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>随身門前</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A scene in front of Zuijinmon (gate of shrine)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Scene in front of Zuijinmon (gate of shrine)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Scene in front of Zuijinmon (gate of shrine)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="71">
<j>折悪くも三人は淀君の参詣に出くわす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Unfortunately the three happened to meet Yodogimi who were visiting the shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unfortunately the three happened to meet Yodogimi who is visiting the shrine.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unfortunately the three happened to meet Yodogimi who is visiting the shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>蜻蛉はとっさに文の半分を飲み込むが残りを取り上げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kagero swallowed a half of the letter but had the rest snatched.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kagero swallows half of the letter, but had the rest snatched.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kagero swallows half of the letter, but had the rest snatched.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>そこへ珍伯が来て文は重成への恋文と嘘の証言をする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then Chinpaku came and told a lie that it was a love letter to Shigenari.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then Chinpaku comes and lies that it is a love letter to Shigenari.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then Chinpaku comes and lies that it is a love letter to Shigenari.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>不審がった淀君は蜻蛉を腰元饗庭の部屋に連れ帰るよう命じる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yodogimi having a suspicion told Kagero to come to the room of Aeba, a female servant.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yodogimi, suspicious, tells Kagero to go to Aeba&apos;s room, a female servant.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yodogimi, suspicious, tells Kagero to go to Aeba&apos;s room, a female servant.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>第5幕　渡辺内蔵介邸の場</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Act 5: A scene of Kuranosuke WATANABE&apos;s residence</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Act 5: Scene of Kuranosuke WATANABE&apos;s residence</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Act 5: Scene of Kuranosuke WATANABE&apos;s residence</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="75">
<j>銀之丞は蜻蛉恋しさに駄々をこねて乳母のお虎ら周囲を困らせている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ginnojo in love with Kagero was throwing a tantrum, which created a headache for people surrounding him including his menoto (a woman providing breast-feed to a highborn baby), Totora.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ginnojo in love with Kagero, was throwing a tantrum, which created a headache for people surrounding him including his menoto (a woman providing breast-feeding to a highborn baby), Totora.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ginnojo in love with Kagero, was throwing a tantrum, which created a headache for people surrounding him including his menoto (a woman providing breast-feeding to a highborn baby), Otora.</e>
<cmt>Totora→Otora</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>母の正栄尼は内蔵介と何やら密談する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother Shoeini was talking secretly something with Kuranosuke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother Shoeini is talking secretly talking about something with Kuranosuke.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother Shoeini is secretly talking about something with Kuranosuke.</e>
<cmt>talking secretly talking→secretly talking</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="14">
<tit>
<j>饗庭局部屋の場</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A scene of the room of Aeba no Tsubone (one of wet nurses of Yodo-dono)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Scene in the room of Aeba no Tsubone (one of wet nurses for Yodo-dono)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Scene in the room of Aeba no Tsubone (one of wet nurses for Yodo-dono)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="77">
<j>蜻蛉のもとに正栄尼が訪れ、父の苦境を救う代わりに銀之丞と祝言を上げるよう、そして且元に登城を願う文を書けと迫る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shoeini visited Kagero and urged her to get married with Ginnojo and write a letter to Katsumoto to ask him to attend the castle, in exchange for saving the hardship of her father.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoeini visits Kagero and urges her to get married with Ginnojo and write a letter to Katsumoto to ask him to attend the castle, in exchange for saving the hardship of her father.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoeini visits Kagero and urges her to get married with Ginnojo and write a letter to Katsumoto to ask him to attend the castle, in exchange for saving the hardship of her father.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>蜻蛉はやむなく従う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kagero had no choice to agree.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kagero has no choice, but to agree.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kagero has no choice, but to agree.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>正栄尼が去った後入れ違いに来た饗庭は、大野親子の陰謀を明かし文を書けば父の命が危ないことを告げる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Aeba who came back after Shoeini had just gone out revealed the plot of the father and son of the Ono, saying that writing letter could put her father in jeopardy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Aeba who comes back after Shoeini and goes out and reveals the plot of the father and son of the Ono, saying that writing letter could put her father into jeopardy.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Aeba comes back after Shoeini goes out and reveals the plot of the father and son of the Ono, saying that writing letter could put her father into jeopardy.</e>
<cmt>and goes→goesAeba who→Aeba</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>陰謀の中にはまり込んだ蜻蛉は半狂乱となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She got half mad knowing that she had been involved in the plot.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She gets half mad knowing that she had been involved in the plot.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She gets half mad knowing that she had been involved in the plot.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="15">
<tit>
<j>奥殿長廊下乳母自害の場</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A scene of a suicide of a menoto at a long corridor of Okudono</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Scene of a suicide of a menoto in the long corridor of Okudono</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Scene of a suicide of a menoto in the long corridor of Okudono</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="81">
<j>銀之丞は蜻蛉と結ばれることを知って大喜び、腰元らと乱痴気騒ぎを演じている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ginnojo, knowing that he was able to get married with her, were indulged in orgies with female servants.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ginnojo, knowing that he is able to marry her, indulges in orgies with female servants.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ginnojo, knowing that he is able to marry her, indulges in orgies with female servants.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>そこへ蜻蛉自害の知らせ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A news of Kagero&apos;s suicide arrived.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The news of Kagero&apos;s suicide arrives.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The news of Kagero&apos;s suicide arrives.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>銀之丞は泣きわめき当たり散らすが、狂い出して池に投身する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ginnojo yelled in tears and took it out on the surrounding, going mad and throwing himself down in a pond.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ginnojo yells out in tears and takes it out on the surroundings, going mad and throwing himself down into a pond.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ginnojo yells out in tears and takes it out on the surroundings, going mad and throwing himself down into a pond.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>乳母も後を追って自害する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His menoto followed him and killed herself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His menoto follows him and kills herself.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His menoto follows him and kills herself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>（原作では、このあと道軒と正栄尼との間に且元暗殺の陰謀をめぐらせる場面と、淀君の精神が狂い始め大野修理がとりなしている報告の件がある。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(The original version subsequently includes a scene where Doken and Shoeini are planning a plot to kill Katsumoto and a report that Shuri ONO was soothing Yodogimi who was starting to go mad.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(The original version subsequently includes a scene where Doken and Shoeini are plotting to kill Katsumoto and a report that Shuri ONO was soothing Yodogimi who was starting to go mad.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(The original version subsequently includes a scene where Doken and Shoeini are plotting to kill Katsumoto and a report that Shuri ONO was soothing Yodogimi who was starting to go mad.)</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="16">
<tit>
<j>淀君寝所珍伯横死の場</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A scene of Chinpaku&apos;s unnatural death at Yodogimi&apos;s bedchamber</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Scene of Chinpaku&apos;s unnatural death at Yodogimi&apos;s bedchamber</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Scene of Chinpaku&apos;s unnatural death at Yodogimi&apos;s bedchamber</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="86">
<j>不安にさいなまれた淀君は、現実から逃れようと寵臣の大野修理と逢瀬を楽しんでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afflicted by anxieties, Yodogimi are enjoying her tryst with Shuri ONO to escape from a reality.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Afflicted by anxiety, Yodogimi is enjoying her tryst with Shuri ONO to escape reality.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Afflicted by anxiety, Yodogimi is enjoying her tryst with Shuri ONO to escape reality.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>しかしまたしても秀次の怨霊に苦しみ、来かかった珍伯を誤って殺害する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However she suffered again from a vengeful ghostof Hidetsugu and mistakenly killed Chinpaku who were coming to her.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However she suffers again from the vengeful ghostof Hidetsugu and mistakenly kills Chinpaku who was coming to her.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However she suffers again from the vengeful ghostof Hidetsugu and mistakenly kills Chinpaku who was coming to her.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="17">
<tit>
<j>第6幕　片桐邸奥書院の場</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Act 6: A scene of Oku Shoin, the inner drawing room of Katagiri residence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Act 6: Scene of Oku Shoin, the inner drawing room of the Katagiri residence.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Act 6: Scene of Oku Shoin, the inner drawing room of the Katagiri residence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="88">
<j>淀君からその方の忠節を疑わないという手紙が届き、且元は意を決して登城せんとする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Katsumo made an decision and was about to attend the castle when he received a letter from Yodogimi that she never doubt his royalty.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Katsumo makes a decision and is about to attend the castle when he receives a letter from Yodogimi that she never doubted his loyalty.</e>
<cmt>grammar, spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Katsumo makes a decision and is about to attend the castle when he receives a letter from Yodogimi that she never doubted his loyalty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>しかし、友人の織田常真から、淀君の手紙は大野親子の陰謀であることと娘蜻蛉の自害がもたらされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Joshin ODA, a friend of his, informed that the letter from Yodogimi was a plot of the father and son of the Ono and that his daughter Kagero had committed suicide.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Joshin ODA, a friend of his, informs that the letter from Yodogimi was a plot of the father and son of the Ono and that his daughter Kagero has committed suicide.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Joshin ODA, a friend of his, informs that the letter from Yodogimi was a plot of the father and son of the Ono and that his daughter Kagero has committed suicide.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>戦闘が始まった模様である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A war seemed to have started.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A war seemed to have started.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A war seemed to have started.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>皆がいぶかるところへ石川伊豆守が駆け付け、大野親子を誅せんと戦闘をしかけ共に闘うことを勧める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ishikawa Izu no kami rushed to people here who were feeling uneasy and urged him to start fighting together to defeat the father and son of the Ono.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ishikawa Izu no kami rush to people here who are feeling uneasy and urges them to start fighting together to defeat the father and son of the Ono.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ishikawa Izu no kami rush to people here who are feeling uneasy and urges them to start fighting together to defeat the father and son of the Ono.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>しかし且元はその短慮を攻め、豊臣家の内紛が徳川家に付け込まれる一因となり伊豆守の勝手な行為で自らの計画が潰れてしまったと嘆く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However Katsumoto criticized him for his shallow thinking and grieved to know that a internal conflict in the Totomi family had given an opportunity to the Tokugawa family of taking advantage of the conflict and that his plan had been bedeviled by inadvertent behaviors of Izu no kami.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However Katsumoto criticized him for his shallow thinking and grieved to know that an internal conflict in the Totomi family had given an opportunity to the Tokugawa family of taking advantage of the conflict and that his plan had been bedeviled by inadvertent behavior of Izu no kami.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However Katsumoto criticized him for his shallow thinking and grieved to know that an internal conflict in the Toyotomi family had given an opportunity to the Tokugawa family of taking advantage of the conflict and that his plan had been bedeviled by inadvertent behavior of Izu no kami.</e>
<cmt>Totomi→Toyotomi</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>伊豆守は申し訳なさに自害。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Izu no kami killed himself in self-reproach.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Izu no kami kills himself in self-reproach.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Izu no kami kills himself in self-reproach.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>大野親子が攻めてくるのも時間の問題となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was only a matter of time when the father and son of the Ono came for attacks.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is only a matter of time before the father and son of the Ono attack.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is only a matter of time before the father and son of the Ono attack.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>且元は屋敷を立ち退くことを決意。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Katsumoto decided to leave the residence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Katsumoto decided to leave the residence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Katsumoto decided to leave the residence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>庭の桐の葉が静かに散りゆくのを見ながら「我が名にちなむ庭前の、梧桐尽く揺落なし、蕭条たる天下の秋、ああ有情も洩れぬ栄枯盛衰、是非もなき定めじゃなあ。」と嘆息する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seeing paulownia leaves slowly falling, he sighed and said, &quot;</e>
<cmt>「」の中の意味解釈が困難なため訳出できず</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seeing paulownia leaves slowly falling, he sighs and says, &quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seeing paulownia leaves slowly falling, he sighs and says, &apos;我が名にちなむ庭前の、梧桐尽く揺落なし、蕭条たる天下の秋、ああ有情も洩れぬ栄枯盛衰、是非もなき定めじゃなあ。&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;意味解釈が困難なため訳出できず。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="18">
<tit>
<j>長柄堤訣別の場</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A scene of a farewell at Nagara zutsumi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A scene of farewell at Nagara zutsumi</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A scene of farewell at Nagara zutsumi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="97">
<j>且元を討とうとする大野親子の一味が鉄砲で追われた後、ただ一騎でやってきた且元は、夜明け前の淀川の堤で遠く大阪城をながめ感慨にふけりながら、木村重成を待つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After a member in the group of the father and son of the Ono had been driven away with a gun, Katsumoto who came to a bank of Yodo-gawa River alone before dawn was looking at the Osaka castle in the distant with emotion while waiting for Shigenari KIMURA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After a member in the group of the father and son of the Ono is driven away with a gun, Katsumoto who goes to the bank of the Yodo-gawa River alone before dawn stares at Osaka castle in the distance with emotion as he waits for Shigenari KIMURA.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After a member in the group of the father and son of the Ono is driven away with a gun, Katsumoto who goes to the bank of the Yodo-gawa River alone before dawn stares at Osaka-jo castle in the distance with emotion as he waits for Shigenari KIMURA.</e>
<cmt>城名に -jo 追記</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>やがて馬を馳せて駆けつけた重成に自身の思いを打ち明け、最後の最後まで豊臣家のために尽くしたのもむなしく、もはや徳川家との戦争は避けられなくなったことを共に嘆く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before long when Shigenari came, Katsumoto opened his heart and regretted together that he had devoted to the Toyotomi family to the very end in vain and that the war with the Tokugawa family became inevitable. any more.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before long when Shigenari arrives, Katsumoto opens his heart and regrets that he had been devoted to the Toyotomi family to the very end in vain and that the war with the Tokugawa family became inevitable.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before long when Shigenari arrives, Katsumoto opens his heart and regrets that he had been devoted to the Toyotomi family to the very end in vain and that the war with the Tokugawa family became inevitable.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>且元は重成に後の事を託しそれぞれ別れてゆく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Katsumoto left things in later days to Shigenari and two parted to their separate ways.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Katsumoto leaves things to Shigenari and the two part to their separate ways.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Katsumoto leaves things to Shigenari and the two part to their separate ways.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="19">
<tit>
<j>初演時の配役</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Casting at the first performance</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Casting for the first performance</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Casting for the first performance</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="20">
<tit>
<j>片桐且元</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Katsumoto KATAGIRI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Katsumoto KATAGIRI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Katsumoto KATAGIRI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="100">
<j>片岡仁左衛門 (11代目)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nizaemon KATAOKA (the 11th)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nizaemon KATAOKA (the eleventh)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nizaemon KATAOKA (the 11th)</e>
<cmt>ＮＣが数字をスペルアウトされていますが戻しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="21">
<tit>
<j>淀殿・女馬子</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yodo-dono/female mago</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yodo-dono/female mago</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yodo-dono/female mago</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="101">
<j>中村歌右衛門 (5代目)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Utaemon NAKAMURA (the fifth)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Utaemon NAKAMURA (the fifth)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Utaemon NAKAMURA (the fifth)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="22">
<tit>
<j>木村重成・佐々成政</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigenari KIMURA/Narimasa SASSA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigenari KIMURA/Narimasa SASSA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigenari KIMURA/Narimasa SASSA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="102">
<j>七代目松本幸四郎 (7代目)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koshiro MATSUMOTO VII (the seventh)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koshiro MATSUMOTO VII (the seventh)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koshiro MATSUMOTO VII (the seventh)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="23">
<tit>
<j>石川伊豆守・豊臣秀吉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ishikawa Izu no kami/Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ishikawa Izu no kami/Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ishikawa Izu no kami/Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="103">
<j>市川段四郎 (2代目)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Danshiro ICHIKAWA (the second)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Danshiro ICHIKAWA (the second)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Danshiro ICHIKAWA (the second)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="24">
<tit>
<j>銀之丞</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ginnojo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ginnojo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ginnojo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="104">
<j>澤村宗十郎 (7代目)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sojuro SAWAMURA (the seventh)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sojuro SAWAMURA (the seventh)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sojuro SAWAMURA (the seventh)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="25">
<tit>
<j>蜻蛉・一葉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kagero/Hitoha</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kagero/Hitoha</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kagero/Hitoha</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="105">
<j>市川門之助 (6代目)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Monnosuke ICHIKAWA (the sixth)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Monnosuke ICHIKAWA (the sixth)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Monnosuke ICHIKAWA (the sixth)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="26">
<tit>
<j>大野道軒</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Doken ONO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Doken ONO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Doken ONO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="106">
<j>市川寿美蔵 (5代目)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sumizo ICHIKAWA (the fifth)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sumizo ICHIKAWA (the fifth)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sumizo ICHIKAWA (the fifth)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="27">
<tit>
<j>大野修理</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shuri ONO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shuri ONO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shuri ONO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="107">
<j>澤村訥子 (7代目)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tosshi SAWAMURA (the seventh)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tosshi SAWAMURA (the seventh)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tosshi SAWAMURA (the seventh)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="28">
<tit>
<j>饗庭局・乳母お虎</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Aeba no Tsubone/Otora, menoto</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Aeba no Tsubone/Otora, menoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Aeba no Tsubone/Otora, menoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="108">
<j>中村伝九郎 (6代目)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Denkuro NAKAMURA (the sixth)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Denkuro NAKAMURA (the sixth)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Denkuro NAKAMURA (the sixth)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="29">
<tit>
<j>正栄尼</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shoeini</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoeini</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoeini</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="109">
<j>中村仲蔵 (4代目)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nakazo NAKAMURA (the fourth)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nakazo NAKAMURA (the fourth)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nakazo NAKAMURA (the fourth)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="110">
<j>名優たちと「桐一葉」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Great actors and &quot;Kiri Hitoha&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Great actors and &quot;Kiri Hitoha&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Great actors and &apos;Kiri Hitoha&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="111">
<j>五代目中村歌右衛門は淀君を、十一代目片岡仁左衛門は且元をそれぞれ当たり役とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yodogimi was a star role for Utaemon NAKAMURA the fifth and Yorimoto was a star role for KATAOKA Nizaemon the eleventh.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yodogimi was a star role for Utaemon NAKAMURA the fifth and Yorimoto was a star role for KATAOKA Nizaemon the eleventh.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yodogimi was a star role for Utaemon NAKAMURA the fifth and Yorimoto was a star role for KATAOKA Nizaemon the eleventh.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>その後もこの作品を幾度も再演した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The both actors repeatedly performed these roles.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Both actors repeatedly performed these roles.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Both actors repeatedly performed these roles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="113">
<j>歌右衛門は、ヒステリー気味の淀君を演じる際、わざわざ精神病院に出向いて患者を観察したほどの入れ込みようであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Utaemon was so obsessed with his performances of hysteric Yodogimi that he visited all the way to a mental hospital to observe patients.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Utaemon was so obsessed with his performance of hysteric Yodogimi that he visited a mental hospital to observe patients.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Utaemon was so obsessed with his performance of hysteric Yodogimi that he visited a mental hospital to observe patients.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="114">
<j>そんな努力によって形成された歌右衛門の淀君は第一級の評価を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Utaemon&apos;s performances of Yodogimi created through such efforts gained first-rate reputations.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Utaemon&apos;s performance of Yodogimi created through such efforts gained a first-rate reputation.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Utaemon&apos;s performance of Yodogimi created through such efforts gained a first-rate reputation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>彼自身「淀君集」という家の芸を確立したり、そのエロキューションの巧さは物真似になったりレコードで販売されるほどであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He himself established &quot;Yodogimi shu&quot; of his family&apos;s accomplishment and his skillful expression of her elocution was impersonated or recorded on discs for sales.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He himself established &quot;Yodogimi shu&quot; of his family&apos;s accomplishment and his skillful expression of her elocution was impersonated or recorded on discs offered for sale.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He himself established &apos;Yodogimi shu&apos; of his family&apos;s accomplishment and his skillful expression of her elocution was impersonated or recorded on discs offered for sale.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="116">
<j>その芸脈は子息の中村歌右衛門 (6代目)、片岡仁左衛門 (13代目)に継承された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The artistic proficiency was handed down to their sons, Utaemon NAKAMURA (the 6th) and KATAOKA Nizaemon (the 11th) (the 13th).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This artistic proficiency was handed down to their sons, Utaemon NAKAMURA (the sixth) and KATAOKA Nizaemon (the eleventh) (the thirteenth).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This artistic proficiency was handed down to their sons, Utaemon NAKAMURA (the sixth) and KATAOKA Nizaemon (the 13th).</e>
<cmt>ＮＣが数字をスペルアウトされていますが戻しました。(the eleventh) は原文にないため削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="117">
<j>また、市村羽左衛門 (15代目)、市川壽海 (3代目)の木村重成、尾上菊五郎 (6代目)・尾上梅幸 (7代目)の銀之丞は歴史に残る名演技であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, Shigenari KIMURA acted by Uzaemon ICHIMURA (the 15th) and Jukai ICHIKAWA (the 3rd) and Ginnojo acted by Kikugoro ONOE (the 6th) and Baiko ONOE (the 7th) were so great that they remained long in history.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, Shigenari KIMURA played by Uzaemon ICHIMURA (the fifteenth) and Jukai ICHIKAWA (the thirrd) and Ginnojo played by Kikugoro ONOE (the sixth) and Baiko ONOE (the seventh) were so great that they were long remembered in history.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, Shigenari KIMURA played by Uzaemon ICHIMURA (the 15th) and Jukai ICHIKAWA (the thirrd) and Ginnojo played by Kikugoro ONOE (the sixth) and Baiko ONOE (the seventh) were so great that they were long remembered in history.</e>
<cmt>fifteenth→15th</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="118">
<j>とくに1968年（昭和43年）に寿海が演じた木村重成は絶品であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In particular, Shigenari KIMURA acted by Jukai in 1968 were a perfection.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In particular, Shigenari KIMURA played by Jukai in 1968 was perfection.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In particular, Shigenari KIMURA played by Jukai in 1968 was perfection.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="119">
<j>演じた年が80を越えていたにもかかわらず、その清新な芸風と爽やかな口跡により、どう見ても台本に指定されている20歳の若者であったと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jukai was over 80 years old when he performed it but it is said that his fresh acting style and delightful delivery made himself look in every respect like a 20-year old young man as written in the script.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jukai was over eighty years old when he performed the role, but it is said that his fresh acting style and delightful delivery made himself look in every respect like a twenty-year old young man as written in the script.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jukai was over 80 years old when he performed the role, but it is said that his fresh acting style and delightful delivery made himself look in every respect like a twenty-year old young man as written in the script.</e>
<cmt>ＮＣが数字をスペルアウトされていますが戻しました。Ｔwenty-year は形容詞とし、そのままとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="120">
<j>片岡仁左衛門 (13代目)は、片岡仁左衛門 (11代目)の且元と十五代目羽左衛門の重成との素晴らしさが忘れられず、1960年代に、天竜寺で子息の孝夫（現片岡仁左衛門）と「長柄堤」を演じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">KATAOKA Nizaemon (the 13th), who was not able to forget great performances by KATAOKA Nizaemon (the 11th) who acted Katsumoto and by Uzaemon ICHIMURA who acted Shigenari, performed &quot;Nagara zutsumi&quot; with his son Takaoa (present Nizaemon KATAOKA) at Tenryu-ji Temple in the 1960&apos;s.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">KATAOKA Nizaemon (the thirteenth), who was not able to forget great performances by KATAOKA Nizaemon (the eleventh) who played Katsumoto and by Uzaemon ICHIMURA who played Shigenari, performed &quot;Nagara zutsumi&quot; with his son Takaoa (present Nizaemon KATAOKA) at Tenryu-ji Temple in the 1960&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nizaemon KATAOKA (the 13th), who was not able to forget great performances by Nizaemon KATAOKA (the 11th) who played Katsumoto and by Uzaemon ICHIMURA who played Shigenari, performed &apos;Nagara zutsumi&apos; with his son Takao (present Nizaemon KATAOKA) at Tenryu-ji Temple in the 1960&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>ＮＣが数字をスペルアウトされていますが戻しました。&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;Takaoa→TakaoKATAOKA Nizaemon →Nizaemon KATAOKA</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="121">
<j>その時、仁左衛門は父の科白回しを演じ、孝夫には羽左衛門の科白回しを伝授した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time Nizaemon performed his father&apos;s serifu mawashi (theatrical elocution) and taught Takao serifu mawashi of Uzaemon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time Nizaemon performed his father&apos;s serifu mawashi (theatrical elocution) and taught Takao serifu mawashi of Uzaemon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time Nizaemon performed his father&apos;s serifu mawashi (theatrical elocution) and taught Takao serifu mawashi of Uzaemon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="122">
<j>仁左衛門は一度は劇場の舞台で孝夫と「長柄堤」を共演するのが念願とし、1988年（昭和63年）11月、国立劇場の通し公演で実現することになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nizaemon&apos;s desire to perform &quot;Nagara zutsumi&quot; together with Takao at least once on a theater stage was achieved in run-through performances at National Theater in November 1988.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nizaemon&apos;s desire to perform &quot;Nagara zutsumi&quot; together with Takao at least once on a theater stage was achieved in run-through performances at National Theater in November 1988.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nizaemon&apos;s desire to perform &apos;Nagara zutsumi&apos; together with Takao at least once on a theater stage was achieved in run-through performances at National Theater in November 1988.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="123">
<j>（ほか、七代目尾上梅幸の淀君・市村羽左衛門 (17代目)の伊豆守）このとき千秋楽をフィルムに記録する予定であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(In addition, Yodogimi acted by Baiko ONOE the seventh and Izu no kami acted by Uzaemon ICHIMURA (the seventeenth) It was planed to record the performance of Senshuraku (the last day of a performance) in a film at that time.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(In addition, Yodogimi played by Baiko ONOE the seventh and Izu no kami played by Uzaemon ICHIMURA (the seventeenth) It was planned to record the performance of Senshuraku (the last day of a performance) in the film at that time.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(In addition, Yodogimi played by Baiko ONOE the seventh and Izu no kami played by Uzaemon ICHIMURA the 17th) It was planned to record the performance of Senshuraku (the last day of a performance) in the film at that time.</e>
<cmt>(the→the</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="124">
<j>しかし、前日に仁左衛門が急病で倒れたので残念ながら見ることが出来ない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, unfortunately it was no able to be seen because Nizaemon came down sick suddenly on a previous day.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, unfortunately it was realized because Nizaemon came down sick suddenly the previous day.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, unfortunately it was not realized because Nizaemon came down sick suddenly the previous day.</e>
<cmt>was→was not</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="30">
<tit>
<j>文学性豊かな「桐一葉」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kiri Hitoha&quot; rich in literary quality</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kiri Hitoha&quot; rich in literary quality</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiri Hitoha&apos; rich in literary quality</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="125">
<j>逍遥の手になる台詞は、それまでの歌舞伎のセリフと違い難解な語句を多用しながらも芸術性豊かな出来でこの劇の品格を高めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The words wrote by Shoyo, unlike traditional words of Kabuki, use difficult passage but are of high artistic quality, giving high dignity to this drama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Words written by Shoyo, unlike traditional words in Kabuki, uses a difficult passage, but are of high artistic quality, giving dignity to this drama.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Words written by Shoyo, unlike traditional words in Kabuki, uses a difficult passage, but are of high artistic quality, giving dignity to this drama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="126">
<j>最も有名なのが、「長柄堤」の且元、重成の悲痛な台詞・前述の第6幕第1場における且元の「我が名に因む庭前の」の独白、第2幕第3場の淀君の長台詞である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The most famous are the sorrowful words by Katsumoto and Shigenari at &quot;Nagara zutsumi,&quot; a monologue by Katsumoto of Scene 1, Act 6, &quot;Associated with the name of the family in a front yard&quot; as mentioned above starting, and long words by Yodogimi in the third Act 2.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The most famous are the sorrowful words by Katsumoto and Shigenari at &quot;Nagara zutsumi,&quot; a monologue by Katsumoto of Scene one, Act six, &quot;Associated with the name of the family in the front yard&quot; as mentioned above starting, and long words by Yodogimi in the third Act two.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The most famous are the sorrowful words by Katsumoto and Shigenari at &apos;Nagara zutsumi,&apos; a monologue by Katsumoto of Scene one, Act six, &apos;Associated with the name of the family in the front yard&apos; as mentioned above starting, and long words by Yodogimi in the third Act two.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;「starting」がどう繋がるのか不明です。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="127">
<j>それは、以下の通りである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The long words are as follows.</e>
<cmt>以下の通りである。を加えました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The words are as follows.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The words are as follows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="128">
<j>「咲き乱れたる山百合の、あの絵襖を見るにつけ、思いぞいずる過来しかた、所も加賀の白山なる、千蛇が池の名産と、世に聞こえたる黒百合の、その花くらべが原となり、北政所の憎しみ受け、はかなく滅びし佐々成政。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt>意味解釈が困難なため訳出できず</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">咲き乱れたる山百合の、あの絵襖を見るにつけ、思いぞいずる過来しかた、所も加賀の白山なる、千蛇が池の名産と、世に聞こえたる黒百合の、その花くらべが原となり、北政所の憎しみ受け、はかなく滅びし佐々成政。&apos;</e>
<cmt>意味解釈が困難なため訳出できず</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="129">
<j>いでそのころは自らが、盛りの花や春深き、聚楽殿の栄華の夢、我ひとたび笑むときは、布衣より出でて天が下、六十余州を掌握ありしあの太閤とて何の英雄。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt>意味解釈が困難なため訳出できず</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">いでそのころは自らが、盛りの花や春深き、聚楽殿の栄華の夢、我ひとたび笑むときは、布衣より出でて天が下、六十余州を掌握ありしあの太閤とて何の英雄。&apos;</e>
<cmt>意味解釈が困難なため訳出できず</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="130">
<j>栄えときめく諸大名も、皆みずからを憚りの、関とざさねど豊臣の、世は泰平と思いのほか、さんぬる三年の秋の風、頼みに思いし治部少輔も、小西と共に木枯らしの、荒れすさびゆく木の下かげ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt>意味解釈が困難なため訳出できず」を合体しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">栄えときめく諸大名も、皆みずからを憚りの、関とざさねど豊臣の、世は泰平と思いのほか、さんぬる三年の秋の風、頼みに思いし治部少輔も、小西と共に木枯らしの、荒れすさびゆく木の下かげ。&apos;</e>
<cmt>意味解釈が困難なため訳出できず</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="131">
<j>という格調高い美文調のもので、五代目中村歌右衛門の十八番であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is made with is a high-class beautiful tone of words, and drawing card for Utaemon NAKAMURA the fifth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is delivered in a high-class beautiful tone of words, and was a drawing card for Utaemon NAKAMURA the fifth.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is delivered in a high-class beautiful tone of words, and was a drawing card for Utaemon NAKAMURA the fifth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="132">
<j>内田魯庵は「桐一葉」の発表が革命的なものであったとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Roan UCHIDA regarded publishment of &quot;Kiri Hitoha&quot; as revolutionary.</e>
<cmt>大専制国の主語、を歌舞伎としました。一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Roan UCHIDA regarded publishing &quot;Kiri Hitoha&quot; as revolutionary.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Roan UCHIDA regarded publishing &apos;Kiri Hitoha&apos; as revolutionary.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="133">
<j>「坪内君が『桐一葉』を書いた時は、團十郎が羅馬法王で、桜痴居士が大宰相で、黙阿弥劇が憲法となっている大専制国であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;When Mr. Tsubouchi wrote &quot;Kiri Hitoha,&quot; Kabuki was just like an autocratic large country in which Kabuki Danjuro was the Pope, Ochi-koji was dai saiso (great prime minister), and Mokuamii was a Constitution.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;When Mr. Tsubouchi wrote &quot;Kiri Hitoha,&quot; Kabuki was just like an autocratic large country in which Kabuki Danjuro was the Pope, Ochi-koji was dai saiso (great prime minister), and Mokuamii was a Constitution.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Mr. Tsubouchi wrote &quot;Kiri Hitoha,&quot; Kabuki was just like an autocratic large country in which Kabuki Danjuro was the Pope, Ochi-koji was dai saiso (great prime minister), and Mokuamii geki (drama) was a Constitution.</e>
<cmt>「」の&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;「劇」　訳漏れ対応しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="134">
<j>この間に立って論難攻撃したり新脚本を書いたりするのは、ルーテルが法王の御教書を焼くと同一の勇気を要する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A courage was needed to made criticism or write new script, in this situation, just like Lutheran burned migyosho (documents for informing of decisions made by third or upper ranked authorities) of the Pope.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Courage was needed to criticize or write a new script, in this situation, just like when Lutheran burned migyosho (documents for informing of decisions made by third or upper ranked authorities) of the Pope.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Courage was needed to criticize or write a new script, in this situation, just like when Lutheran burned migyosho (documents for informing of decisions made by third or upper ranked authorities) of the Pope.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="135">
<j>・・・何百年間封鎖して余人の近づくを許さなかったランド・オブ・カブキの関門を開いた。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">・・・He opened a new gate of the land of Kabuki that had been closed for hundreds of years and kept away from others.&quot;</e>
<cmt>」を下のセルより合体</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">・・・He opened a new gate of the land of Kabuki that had been closed for hundreds of years and kept away from others.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">...He opened a new gate of the land of Kabuki that had been closed for hundreds of years and kept away from others.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;中黒をピリオドに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="136">
<j>（『中央公論・逍遥号』明治44年）と評している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He commented (in &quot;Shoyogo (number of Shoyo) Chuo Koronsha&quot; in 1911).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He commented (in &quot;Shoyogo (number of Shoyo) Chuo Koronsha&quot; in 1911).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He commented in (&quot;Shoyogo [number of Shoyo] Chuo Koronsha&quot; in 1911).</e>
<cmt>(in→in (括弧内の括弧を[]に変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="137">
<j>それまで、座付の狂言作者の脚本しか上演されなかった（明治32年に松井松翁作の『悪源太』が上演されたのを例外として）閉鎖的な歌舞伎界に近代の風を通す大きな穴を開けたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He opened a large hole to let modern air into the closed Kabuki world where only scripts written by Kabuki playwrights working in the theater had been performed so far (except for the performance in 1899 of &quot;Akugenta&quot; written by Shoo MATSUI).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He opened a large hole to let modern air into the closed world of Kabuki where only scripts written by Kabuki playwrights working in the theater had been performed so far (except for the performance in 1899 of &quot;Akugenta&quot; written by Shoo MATSUI).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He opened a large hole to let modern air into the closed world of Kabuki where only scripts written by Kabuki playwrights working in the theater had been performed so far (except for the performance in 1899 of &quot;Akugenta&quot; written by Shoo MATSUI).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="138">
<j>以降、岡鬼太郎・岡本綺堂・小山内薫・池田大伍・真山青果・舟橋聖一・谷崎潤一郎など外部からの新作歌舞伎が多く作られることになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since then, a large number of new Kabuki have been created by Onitaro OKA, Kido OKAMOTO, Kaoru OSANAI, Daigo IKEDA, Seika MAYAMA, Seiichi FUNAHASHI, Junichiro TANIZAKI and other outside writers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since then, a large number of new Kabuki have been created by Onitaro OKA, Kido OKAMOTO, Kaoru OSANAI, Daigo IKEDA, Seika MAYAMA, Seiichi FUNAHASHI, Junichiro TANIZAKI and other outside writers.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since then, a large number of new Kabuki have been created by Onitaro OKA, Kido OKAMOTO, Kaoru OSANAI, Daigo IKEDA, Seika MAYAMA, Seiichi FUNAHASHI, Junichiro TANIZAKI and other outside writers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="139">
<j>シェークスピアの作品の影響が見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An influence of Shakespeare&apos;s work can be found.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The influence of Shakespeare&apos;s work can be found.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The influence of Shakespeare&apos;s work can be found.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="140">
<j>且元の性格はハムレットに類似している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Katsumoto is quite similar to Hamlet in characteristics.,</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Katsumoto is quite similar to Hamlet&apos;s characteristics.,</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Katsumoto is quite similar to Hamlet&apos;s characteristics.,</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="141">
<j>蜻蛉はオフェーリアに、銀之丞は『リア王』から、その死は『ハムレット』オフェーリア水死の場、淀君の珍伯殺害はボローニアス殺害の場の影響が、淀君の性格は『マクベス』の妻からの影響などがそれぞれ指摘されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is pointed out that Kagero was inspired by Ophelia, Ginnojo by &quot;King Lear,&quot; their deaths by a scene of Ophelia&apos;s death by drawing in &quot;Hamlet,&quot; Yodogimi&apos;s killing of Chinpaku by the murder of Polonius, and Yodogimi&apos;s characteristics by the wife of Macbeth, and so forth.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is pointed out that Kagero was inspired by Ophelia, Ginnojo by &quot;King Lear,&quot; their deaths by a scene of Ophelia&apos;s death by drawing in &quot;Hamlet,&quot; Yodogimi&apos;s killing of Chinpaku by the murder of Polonius, and Yodogimi&apos;s characteristics by the wife of Macbeth, and so forth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is pointed out that Kagero was inspired by Ophelia, Ginnojo by &quot;King Lear,&quot; his death by a scene of Ophelia&apos;s death by drowning in &quot;Hamlet,&quot; Yodogimi&apos;s killing of Chinpaku by the murder of Polonius, and Yodogimi&apos;s characteristics by the wife of Macbeth, and so forth.</e>
<cmt>drawing→drowningtheir deaths→his death</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="142">
<j>一方、台詞や浄瑠璃の表現には近松門左衛門の影響がみられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In contrast, words and expression of Joruri (dramatic narrative chanted to a samisen accompaniment) show influences of Monzaemon CHIKAMATSU.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In contrast, words and expression of Joruri (dramatic narrative chanted to samisen accompaniment) show the influences of Monzaemon CHIKAMATSU.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In contrast, words and expression of Joruri (dramatic narrative chanted to samisen accompaniment) show the influences of Monzaemon CHIKAMATSU.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="143">
<j>東西の二大戯曲家を融合させる逍遥の壮大な構想が伺われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shoyo&apos;s grand ambition to combine the two greatest drama of the East and West ca be inferred.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoyo&apos;s grand ambition to combine the two greatest drama of the East and West can be inferred.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoyo&apos;s grand ambition to combine the two greatest drama of the East and West can be inferred.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kliment.A.K.(id:161714), 河端(id:194294), スーイ(id:193920), Boca samba(id:137526), FREEZA(id:68069), Championship2006(id:38664), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>