<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>宗旦狐</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sotan Gitsune</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sotan Gitsune</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sotan Gitsune</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>宗旦狐（そうたんぎつね）は、京都市上京区の相国寺に伝わる化けキツネ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sotan gitsune (fox) was the monster fox told down the Shokoku-ji Temple in Kamigyo Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sotan gitsune (fox) was a monster fox, a story of which has been passed down at the Shokoku-ji Temple in Kamigyo Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>言い回し、正確化</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sotan gitsune (fox) was a monster fox, a story of which has been passed down at the Shokoku-ji Temple in Kamigyo Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>「宗旦」の名の通り、千家茶道の基礎を固めた人物・千宗旦に化けてしばしば茶席に現れたといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the name, &apos;Sotan&apos; implies, it disguised itself as SEN no Sotan, who strengthened the foundation of Sen family tea ceremony school, to occasionally appear in tea parties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the name &apos;Sotan&apos; suggests, it disguised itself as SEN no Sotan, who strengthened the foundation of Sen-ke family tea ceremony school, to occasionally appear in tea parties.</e>
<cmt>形式</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the name &apos;Sotan&apos; suggests, it disguised itself as SEN no Sotan, who strengthened the foundation of Sen-ke family tea ceremony school, to occasionally appear in tea parties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>伝承</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tradition</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tradition</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tradition</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>あるときに相国寺で千宗旦の茶会が開かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Once upon a time, tea ceremony of SEN no Sotan was held at Shokoku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Once upon a time, a tea ceremony of SEN no Sotan was held at Shokoku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>文法</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Once upon a time, a tea ceremony of SEN no Sotan was held at Shokoku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>宗旦の見事な点前は、出席した茶人たちはもちろんのこと、普段からそれを見慣れている弟子たちですら見とれるほどだった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The wonderful temae (tea serving method) of Sotan made the participating chajin (master of the tea ceremony) as well as his disciples that usually saw the procedure to stare with awe.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The wonderful temae (tea serving method) of Sotan made the participating chajin (master of the tea ceremony) as well as his disciples that usually saw the procedure to stare with awe.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The wonderful temae (tea serving method) of Sotan made the participating chajin (master of the tea ceremony) as well as his disciples that usually saw the procedure to stare with awe.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>ところが宗旦がその場を去った後、また宗旦が現れ、遅刻して来たことを詫びた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Sotan appeared again after Sotan left and apologized for lateness.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Sotan appeared again after Sotan left and apologized for being late.</e>
<cmt>言い回し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Sotan appeared again after Sotan left and apologized for being late.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>そのようなことが何度かあり、弟子たちは宗旦に偽者がいると考え始めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This occurred several times that his disciples began to think that there was an imposer of Sotan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Similar incidents occurred several times, so that Sotan&apos;s disciples began to think that there should be an imposer of Sotan.</e>
<cmt>言い回し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Similar incidents occurred several times, so that Sotan&apos;s disciples began to think that there should be an imposer of Sotan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>後日、茶室に宗旦が現れたときを見計らい、弟子たちは宗旦本人が自宅にいることを確かめた上で偽宗旦を問い詰めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Several days later, they waited until Sotan appeared in a tea ceremony room and began to integrate the fake Sotan after confirming that real Sotan was at his own residence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Several days later, they waited until Sotan appeared in a tea ceremony room and began to interrogate the fake Sotan after confirming that real Sotan was at home.</e>
<cmt>誤字</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Several days later, they waited until Sotan appeared in a tea ceremony room and began to interrogate the fake Sotan after confirming that real Sotan was at home.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>すると偽宗旦は素直に自分が偽者であることを明かし、自分は寺の藪に住む古狐であり、ずっと宗旦の点前に憧れていたので、いつか自分もそのような点前をしてみたかった、もう二度と悪さをしないと詫び、狐の姿となって逃げ去った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, the fake Sotan honestly admitted that he was just an imposer but an old fox that lived among a bush of a temple that wanted to do a temae himself since he was always awed by the temae of Sotan, and swore to never cause a mischief ever again before escaping in a shape of a fox.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, the fake Sotan honestly admitted that he was just an imposer and an old fox living among bushes of a temple that wanted to do temae himself since he was always awed by the temae of Sotan, and swore to never cause a mischief ever again before escaping as a fox.</e>
<cmt>言い回し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, the fake Sotan honestly admitted that he was just an imposer and an old fox living among bushes of a temple that wanted to do temae himself since he was always awed by the temae of Sotan, and swore to never cause a mischief ever again before escaping as a fox.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>弟子たちは宗旦狐の腕前に感心し、狐を追うことはなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The disciples were impressed by the skills of Sotan Fox and did not chase after the fox.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The disciples were impressed by the skills of Sotan gitsune and did not chase after the fox.</e>
<cmt>用語</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The disciples were impressed by the skills of Sotan gitsune and did not chase after the fox.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>時は流れて幕末。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Time passed to the end of Edo Period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Time passed to the end of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>形式</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Time passed to the end of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>宗旦狐は雲水に化けて相国寺で勉強をしていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sotan Gitsune transformed as Unsui and studied at Shokoku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sotan Gitsune transformed as an Unsui (a wandering Buddhist monk) and studied at Shokoku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sotan Gitsune transformed as an Unsui (a wandering Buddhist monk) and studied at Shokoku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>他の雲水たちと共に座禅を組み、托鉢に回り、時には寺の財政難を建て直すべく力を尽くした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He meditated along with other Unsui, went around for Takuhatsu (a traditional form of begging, common to Buddhist monks in Japan), and occasionally tried all his power to recover the temple from its financial crisis.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He meditated along with other Unsui, went around for Takuhatsu (a traditional form of begging, common to Buddhist monks in Japan), and occasionally tried all his power to recover the temple from its financial crisis.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He meditated along with other Unsui, went around for Takuhatsu (a traditional form of begging, common to Buddhist monks in Japan), and occasionally tried all his power to recover the temple from its financial crisis.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>門前の家で碁を打つこともあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He sometimes played go in the house in front of the gate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He sometimes played go (a Japanese board game played with black and white stones) in the house in front of the gate.</e>
<cmt>後項との記載内容調整</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He sometimes played go (a Japanese board game played with black and white stones) in the house in front of the gate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>碁に熱中するあまり、狐の尻尾を出してしまうこともあったが、人々は狐の正体を知りつつも付き合っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He occasionally let out a fox tail by absorbing too much in go (a Japanese game played with black and white stones on a board), but people associated with him despite knowing his fox identity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He occasionally let out a fox tail by absorbing too much in go, but people associated with him despite knowing his fox identity.</e>
<cmt>前項との記載内容調整</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He occasionally let out a fox tail by absorbing too much in go, but people associated with him despite knowing his fox identity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>ある年の盆。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">End of One Year</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bon (annual Buddhist even) of One Year</e>
<cmt>原文読み間違い、改訳</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bon (annual Buddhist even) of One Year</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>門前の豆腐屋が資金難から倒産寸前に陥っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A tofu shop in front of a gate of a temple was on the verge of facing bankruptcy from having a financial difficulty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A tofu shop in front of a gate of the temple was on the verge of facing bankruptcy due to financial difficulty.</e>
<cmt>冠詞</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A tofu shop in front of a gate of the temple was on the verge of facing bankruptcy due to financial difficulty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>宗旦狐は蓮の葉をたくさん集めて来て、それを売って金に換えて大豆を買うよう勧めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sotan Gitsune advised the shop keeper to collect and sell a great amount of lotus leaves, and buy soy beans from the profit.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sotan Gitsune advised the shop keeper to collect and sell a great amount of lotus leaves, and buy soy beans from the profit.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sotan Gitsune advised the shop keeper to collect and sell a great amount of lotus leaves, and buy soy beans from the profit.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>豆腐屋はそのお陰で店を建て直すことができた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tofu shop was able to rebuild the business because of it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The tofu shop was able to rebuild the business because of it.</e>
<cmt>冠詞</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The tofu shop was able to rebuild the business because of it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>お礼をしようと考えた豆腐屋は、狐の大好物である鼠の天婦羅を作って宗旦狐に贈った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tofu shop decided to return the favor by making a tempura of a mouse considered to be the favorite food of foxes and sent it to Sotan Gitsune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The tofu shop keeper decided to return the favor by making a tempura of mice considered to be the favorite food of foxes and sent it to Sotan Gitsune.</e>
<cmt>用語</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The tofu shop keeper decided to return the favor by making a tempura of mice considered to be the favorite food of foxes and sent it to Sotan Gitsune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>しかし宗旦狐は、それを食べると神通力が失われるといって遠慮した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Sotan Gitsune refrained, saying that his divine power will be lost by eating it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Sotan Gitsune refrained, saying that his divine power will be lost by eating it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Sotan Gitsune refrained, saying that his divine power will be lost by eating it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>とはいうものの目は大好物に釘付けで、つい我慢できずにそれを食べてしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Despite saying so, he could not stop staring at his favorite food and ate it since he could not wait.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Despite saying so, he could not stop staring at his favorite food and ate it since he could not wait.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Despite saying so, he could not stop staring at his favorite food and ate it since he could not wait.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>途端に宗旦狐はもとの狐の姿に戻り、それを見た近所の犬たちが激しく吼え始めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sotan Gitsune immediately returned to the shape of a fox, and the neighbor&apos;s dog who saw it started barking hard.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sotan Gitsune immediately returned to a fox, and dogs in the neighborhood saw it and started barking hard.</e>
<cmt>正確化</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sotan Gitsune immediately returned to a fox, and dogs in the neighborhood saw it and started barking hard.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>狐は咄嗟に藪の中に逃げ込んだが、慌てたために井戸に落ち、命を落としてしまった（別説では猟師に鉄砲で撃たれた、または自ら死期を悟って別れの茶会を開いたともいう）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fox escaped instantaneously into the bush, but fell into a well to death due to being in rush (other theories stated that he was shot by a hunter with a gun or held the farewell tea ceremony by predicting his own death).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fox escaped instantaneously into the bush, but it was too frantic to see the destination and so fell into a well to death (according to other theories, the fox was shot by a hunter with a gun or held the farewell tea ceremony by predicting his own death).</e>
<cmt>言い回し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fox escaped instantaneously into the bush, but it was too frantic to see the destination and so fell into a well to death (according to other theories, the fox was shot by a hunter with a gun or held the farewell tea ceremony by predicting his own death).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="24">
<j>相国寺は寺のために尽くしてくれた宗旦狐の死を哀れみ、宗旦稲荷として祠を築き、狐を僧堂の守護神とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shokoku-ji Temple built a small shrine for Sotan Inari (fox deity) from mourning the death of Sotan Gitsune that contributed greatly for the temple, and made the fox as the guardian deity of So-do Hall (A hall for meditation).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shokoku-ji Temple built a small shrine for Sotan Inari (fox deity), mourning the death of Sotan Gitsune that had contributed greatly for the temple, and made the fox the guardian deity of the So-do Hall (a hall for meditation).</e>
<cmt>言い回し、形式</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shokoku-ji Temple built a small shrine for Sotan Inari (fox deity), mourning the death of Sotan Gitsune that had contributed greatly for the temple, and made the fox the guardian deity of the So-do Hall (a hall for meditation).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>現在でも宗旦稲荷は、相国寺境内に祀られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sotan Inari is still worshipped in a small shrine within the compound of the Shokoku-ji Temple even to the present day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even today Sotan Inari is still worshipped in a small shrine within the precincts of the Shokoku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>言い回し、用語</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even today Sotan Inari is still worshipped in a small shrine within the precincts of the Shokoku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 逃亡者(id:14864), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>