<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>弁当</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bento (lunch box)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bento (lunch box)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bento (lunch box)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>弁当（辨當、べんとう）とは、携帯できるようにした食品のうち、食事に相当するもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bento is a kind of portable food and equivalent of meal.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bento is a kind of portable food and is the equivalent of one meal.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bento is a kind of portable food and is the equivalent of one meal.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>家庭で作る手作り弁当と、市販される商品としての弁当の二種に大別される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It can be classified broadly into two kinds: Homemade bento and ready-made bento which is sellable.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It can be classified broadly into two kinds: Homemade and ready-made bento which is on sale.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It can be classified broadly into two kinds: Homemade and ready-made bento which is on sale.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース消去</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>本項では日本の弁当を中心に記述する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This section mainly describes Japanese bento.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This section mainly describes Japanese bento.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This section mainly describes Japanese bento.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>語源</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Origin of a word (etymology)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Origin of the word (etymology)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Origin of the word (etymology)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>「弁当」は、「好都合」「便利なこと」を意味する中国南宋時代の俗語「便當」が語源である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bento&apos; is derived from informal language &apos; &apos; in Chinese Southern Sung dynasty which means &apos;convenience&apos; or &apos;usefulness.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bento&apos; is derived from informal language &apos; &apos; in the Chinese Southern Sung dynasty which means &apos;convenience&apos; or &apos;usefulness.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bento&apos; is derived from informal language &apos;便當&apos; in the Chinese Southern Sung dynasty which means &apos;convenience&apos; or &apos;usefulness.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の一部が抜けていたため、ウェブより補いました。(読み方不明のため、訳文にも漢字表記のまま記載しております。)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>「便當」が日本に入り、「便道」、「辨道」などの漢字も当てられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&apos; came into Japan, and Kanji such as &apos;便道&apos;, &apos;辨道&apos; was applied to it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&apos; came into Japan, and Kanji such as &apos;便道&apos;, &apos;辨道&apos; were applied to it.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">便當&apos; came into Japan, and Kanji such as &apos;便道&apos;, &apos;辨道&apos; were applied to it.</e>
<cmt>原文の一部が抜けていたため、ウェブより補いました。(読み方不明のため、訳文にも漢字表記のまま記載しております。)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>「弁えて（そなえて）用に当てる」ことから、「辨當」の字が当てられ、「辨當箱」の意味として使われたと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because it has the meaning of &apos;prepared and applied for use&apos; &apos;弁えて(そなえて)用に当てる,&apos; Kanji letter &apos;辨當&apos; was applied and then it is considered to have been used as the meaning of &apos;辨當箱.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because it has the meaning of &apos;prepared and applied for use&apos; &apos;弁えて(そなえて)用に当てる,&apos; the Kanji characters &apos;辨當&apos; were applied and then were considered to have been used as the meaning of &apos;辨當箱.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because it has the meaning of &apos;prepared and applied for use&apos; &apos;弁えて(そなえて)用に当てる,&apos; the Kanji characters &apos;辨當&apos; were applied and then were considered to have been used as the meaning of &apos;辨當箱.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>調理が済んだ食べ物を携帯する習慣は世界中で見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Custom of carrying cooked food is found worldwide.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Custom of carrying cooked food is found worldwide.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Custom of carrying cooked food is found worldwide.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>例えば最も簡単な形式では、チベットのツァンパのような物がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Examples of the simplest kind include tsampa of Tibet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Examples of the simplest kind include tsampa of Tibet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Examples of the simplest kind include tsampa of Tibet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>インドではチャパティとカレーをダッバーワーラーと呼ばれる積み重ね式容器に入れ携帯する習慣が見られ、アメリカ合衆国（大陸）ではピーナッツバターとジャムを塗った簡単なサンドイッチ（enPeanut butter and jelly sandwichと呼ぶ）や果物などを弁当箱に入れ、昼食として携行する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">India has the custom of carrying chapati and curry in stackable containers called dabbawala while United States (mainland) has the custom of carrying a light sandwich with butter and jam (called peanut butter and jelly sandwich) and fruit in a lunch box.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">India has the custom of carrying chapati and curry in stackable containers called dabbawala while United States (mainland) has the custom of carrying a light sandwich with butter and jam (called peanut butter and jelly sandwich) and fruit in a lunch box.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">India has the custom of carrying chapati and curry in stackable containers called dabbawala while United States (mainland) has the custom of carrying a light sandwich with peanut butter and jam (called peanut butter and jelly sandwich) and fruit in a lunch box.</e>
<cmt>butter→peanut butterに修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>日本では古くから弁当の習慣が起こり、他の諸国では例を見ないほどの発展を遂げていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan has a long history of bento, and its development has been unparalleled in the world&apos;s history of bento.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan has a long history of bento, and its development has been unparalleled in the world&apos;s history of bento.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan has a long history of bento, and its development has been unparalleled in the world&apos;s history of bento.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>これは、日本で一般的に食べられるジャポニカ種が、インディカ種などと比べ、炊いた後冷めてしまってからでもおいしいという特徴を持つためであるとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Probably this is because Japonica-origin rice (generally eaten in Japan) tastes relatively good even when it becomes cold (after cooked) unlike indica-origin rice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Probably this is because Japonica-origin rice (generally eaten in Japan) tastes relatively good even when it becomes cold (after cooked) unlike india-origin rice.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Probably this is because Japonica-origin rice (generally eaten in Japan) tastes relatively good even when it becomes cold (after cooked) unlike india-origin rice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>伝統的な日本の弁当は、飯と魚介類や肉などの惣菜を主に、付け合わせとして梅干しなどの漬物を付ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Traditional Japanese bento comes with rice, fish and shellfish, seafood, and meat as a side dish, and tsukemono (Japanese pickled vegetables) like umeboshi (pickled ume (plum) as a relish.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Traditional Japanese bento comes with rice, fish and shellfish, seafood, and meat as a side dish, and tsukemono (Japanese pickled vegetables) like umeboshi (pickled ume (plum) as a relish.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Traditional Japanese bento comes with rice, seafood, and meat as a side dish, and tsukemono (Japanese pickled vegetables) like umeboshi (pickled ume (plum) as a relish.</e>
<cmt>fish and shellfish, seafood→seafoodのみとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>おにぎりや稲荷寿司などを詰めた弁当も人気が高い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bento filled with rice ball or stuffed sushi is also popular.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bento filled with rice ball or rice stuffed with sushi is also popular.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bento filled with rice ball or rice stuffed with sushi is also popular.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>弁当の具材は持ち運びがしやすい容器に入れられるのだが、その容器は「弁当箱」という名で呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Potable container used to put ingredients in is called a &apos;lunchbox.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The portable container used to put ingredients in is called a &apos;lunchbox.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar, spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The portable container used to put ingredients in is called a &apos;lunchbox.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>英語では日本語をそのままに「enbento」と呼ばれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Lunchbox in Japanese is literally translated into English as &apos;bento.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Lunchbox in Japanese is literally translated into English as &apos;bento.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Lunchbox in Japanese is literally translated into English as &apos;bento.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>日本における伝統的な弁当はそれぞれの家庭でこしらえていくものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Traditional Japanese bento is prepared by each family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Traditional Japanese bento is prepared by each family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Traditional Japanese bento is prepared by each family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>これは家事の一つとして重要な位置を占めていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Preparing bento used to be one of the most important houseworks.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Preparing bento used to be one of the most important roles for housewives.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Preparing bento used to be one of the most important roles for housewives.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="19">
<j>明治時代の日本では、鉄道駅で弁当が売られるようになり（駅弁）、第二次世界大戦後はスーパーマーケットや前述の販売店などでも販売され始めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Meiji Period, in Japan, railway stations started to sell bentos, and supermarkets and the above-mentioned outlet stores started to sell them after World War II.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Meiji Period, in Japan, railway stations started to sell bentos, and supermarkets and the above-mentioned outlet stores started to sell them after World War II.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Meiji period, in Japan, railway stations started to sell bentos, and supermarkets and the above-mentioned outlet stores started to sell them after World War II.</e>
<cmt>Periodの頭文字を小文字に変更、余分なスペース消去</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>1980年代後半から1990年代にかけての日本では、持ち帰り（テイクアウト）専門の弁当製造・販売店やコンビニエンスストアが台頭した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan, a bento store (vendor) which specializes takeout bento or a convenience store emerged from the late 1980&apos;s to the 1990&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan, a bento store (vendor) which specializes in takeout bento or a convenience stores emerged from the late 1980&apos;s to the 1990&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan, a bento store (vendor) which specialized in takeout bento or convenience stores emerged from the late 1980&apos;s to the 1990&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>specializes→specialized、a convenience stores→convenience storesに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>これらで販売される市販品の弁当を利用する者も増えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, the number of people who purchase a ready-made bento from these stores increased.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, the number of people who purchase ready-made bento from these stores increased.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, the number of people who purchased ready-made bento from these stores increased.</e>
<cmt>purchase→purchasedに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>日本のコンビニエンスストアに納入する弁当の製造工場は24時間体制で操業している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Manufacturer which supplies bentos to a convenience store operates 24 hours a day.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Suppliers that deliver bentos to convenience stores operate 24 hours a day.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Suppliers that deliver bentos to convenience stores operate 24 hours a day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="23">
<j>多いものでは日産数万食にも及ぶ規模となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some manufacturers makes tens of thousands of bentos a day.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some suppliers make tens of thousands of bentos a day.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some suppliers make tens of thousands of bentos a day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>団体旅行や法事など、弁当に大量かつ一定の豪華さが要求されるような状況に向け、これらの製造に当たる仕出し料理店や料亭なども多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are also many catering restaurants and fancy Japanese-style restaurants which can respond to event such as a group tour or a memorial service (Buddhist service) where large quantities of and a certain level of luxurious diet is required.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are also many catering restaurants and fancy Japanese-style restaurants that can respond to events such as a group tours or a memorial services (Buddhist service) where large quantities of and certain levels of luxurious diet bentos are required.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are also many catering restaurants and fancy Japanese-style restaurants that can respond to events such as group tours or memorial services (Buddhist service) where large quantities of and certain levels of luxurious diet bentos are required.</e>
<cmt>a group tours→group tours、a memorial services→memorial servicesに修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="25">
<j>また、日本が周辺諸国を併合していた時代に、弁当文化は日本国外にも広まっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, when neighboring nations were annexed by Japan, bento culture was spreaded outside Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, when neighboring nations were annexed by Japan, bento culture was spread outside Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, when neighboring nations were annexed by Japan, bento culture was spread outside Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="26">
<j>台湾では、日本に統治されていた時代に駅弁も含めて弁当を利用する習慣が根付いていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Taiwan, the custom of using bento including Ekiben (box lunch sold on a train or at a station) took root there when the nation was governed by Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Taiwan, the custom of using bento including Ekiben (box lunch sold on trains or at stations) took root there when the nation was governed by Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Taiwan, the custom of using bento including Ekiben (box lunch sold on trains or at stations) took root there when the nation was governed by Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>そのため、現在も台湾では市街地や国道沿いなどに多くの弁当店が店舗を構え、盛況を見せている（弁当ではなく「便當」と表記されるが）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, there are now many bento stores in urban area and on National Routes which are prosperous (though it is written as &apos;便當&apos; not 弁当).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, there are now many bento stores in urban area and on National Routes which are prosperous (though it is written as &apos;便當&apos; not 弁当).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, there are now many bento stores in urban area and on National Routes which are prosperous (though it is written as &apos;便當&apos; not 弁当).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>池上米など日本に近い品種の米が導入されたことも、台湾での弁当の普及に大きく関係しているものと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is thought that the spread of Bento in Taiwan is partly because rice variety such as Chi Shang rice, which is similar to Japanese rice, was introduced.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is thought that the spread of Bento in Taiwan is partly because of the rice variety such as Chi Shang rice, similar to Japanese rice, was introduced.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is thought that the spread of Bento in Taiwan is partly because the rice variety such as Chi Shang rice, similar to Japanese rice, was introduced.</e>
<cmt>because of→becauseに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>それと比べると韓国では（トシラクと呼ばれる）、駅弁を除くとあまり弁当はなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Unlike Taiwan, South Korea does not have many bentos available except Ekiben (called dosirak). Even so, bentos are sold in convenience stores.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unlike Taiwan, South Korea does not have many bentos available except Ekiben (called dosirak). Even so, bentos are sold in convenience stores.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unlike Taiwan, South Korea does not have many bentos available except Ekiben (called dosirak).</e>
<cmt>Even so, bentos are sold in convenience stores.→次文の内容のため削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>それでもコンビニエンスストアでは弁当が売られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even so, bentos are sold in convenience stores.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even so, bentos are sold in convenience stores.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even so, bentos are sold in convenience stores.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>中国にはそもそも冷めた米を食べる習慣がなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">China did not have the custom of eating cold rice at all.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">China did not have the custom of eating cold rice at all.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">China did not have the custom of eating cold rice at all.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="32">
<j>しかし、近年は米飯の入った弁当箱に料理を上から載せ、電子レンジなどで温めて食べるような習慣が形成されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In recent years, however, the habit of adding a main ingredient to rice in lunchbox and warming it in a microwave oven to eat, has been formed.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In recent years, however, the habit of adding a main ingredient to rice in a lunchbox and warming it in a microwave oven to eat, has been formed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In recent years, however, the habit of adding a main ingredient to rice in a lunchbox and warming it in a microwave oven to eat, has been formed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>同じ中国内でも上海市等では、日系のコンビニエンスストア等を中心に「弁当」の語源でもある「便当」として普及を狙い、現在では日本のものと似た弁当も売られるようになり一般化しつつある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Shanghai unlike other areas of China, bento is becoming more popular because convenience stores mainly Japanese convenience stores have been selling a bento intending to spread it as &apos;便当&apos; which is the origin of a word &apos;弁当&apos; (bento).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Shanghai unlike other areas of China, bento is becoming more popular because convenience stores mainly Japanese convenience stores have been selling bento intending to spread it as &apos;便当&apos; which is the origin of a word &apos;弁当&apos; (bento).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Shanghai unlike other areas of China, bento is becoming more popular because convenience stores mainly Japanese convenience stores have been selling bento intending to spread it as &apos;便当&apos; which is the origin of a word &apos;弁当&apos; (bento).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>（2005年3月5日NHKスペシャル『13億人の欲望をつかめ』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(TV Program called &quot;NHK Special: Win the hearts and minds of 1.3 billion consumers!&quot; which aired on March 5, 2005)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(TV Program called &quot;NHK Special: Win the hearts and minds of 1.3 billion consumers!&quot; which aired on March 5, 2005)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(TV Program called &quot;NHK Special: Win the hearts and minds of 1.3 billion consumers!&quot; which aired on March 5, 2005)</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース消去</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="35">
<j>弁当の起源は平安時代まで遡ることができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The origin of bento goes back to the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The origin of bento goes back to the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The origin of bento goes back to the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>当時は「頓食（とんじき）」と呼ばれたおにぎりのほか、「干し飯（ほしいい）」または「糒（ほしいい）」と呼ばれる調理済みの乾燥米が携帯用の食料として利用されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, besides &apos;tonjiki&apos; (egg-shaped glutinous rice ball), cooked dried-rice called &apos;dried boiled rice (&apos;干し飯&apos; (ほしいい)or &apos;糒&apos; (ほしいい)) was used as a potable food.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, besides &apos;tonjiki&apos; (egg-shaped glutinous rice ball), cooked dried-rice called &apos;dried boiled rice (&apos;干し飯&apos; (ほしいい or &apos;糒&apos; - ほしいい) was used as a potable food.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, besides &apos;tonjiki&apos; (egg-shaped glutinous rice ball), cooked dried-rice called &apos;dried boiled rice (&apos;干し飯&apos; (ほしいい or &apos;糒&apos; - ほしいい) was used as a potable food.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>干し飯は小さな入れ物に保管することができ、そのまま食べる、あるいはこれを水に入れて煮るなどして食べられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dried boiled rice could be kept in a small container, and could be eaten as is or after cooked in water.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dried boiled rice could be kept in a small container, and could be eaten as is or after cooked in water.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dried boiled rice could be kept in a small container, and could be eaten as is or after cooked in water.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>安土桃山時代には現代でも見られるような漆器の弁当箱が作られるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Azuchi-Momoyama period, a lacquer lanchbox that can be found Today was introduced.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Azuchi-Momoyama period, a lacquer lanchbox that can still be found Today was introduced.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Azuchi-Momoyama period, a lacquer lanchbox that can still be found Today was introduced.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="39">
<j>この時代より弁当は花見や茶道といった場で食べられるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, bentos came to be used for occasions like cherry blossom viewing or tea ceremony.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, bentos came to be used for occasions like cherry blossom viewing or a tea ceremony.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, bentos came to be used for occasions like cherry blossom viewing or a tea ceremony.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="40">
<j>江戸時代、天下泰平の時代、弁当はより広範な文化になると同時に優雅な文化となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Edo period when universal peace was maintained, bento became wide ranging culture and at the same time graceful culture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Edo period when universal peace was maintained, bento became a wide ranging culture and at the same time a graceful culture.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Edo period when universal peace was maintained, bento became a wide ranging culture and at the same time a graceful culture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>旅行者や観光客は簡単な「腰弁当」を作り、これを持ち歩いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Travelers and tourists prepared a simple &apos;packed lunch&apos; to carry around.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Travelers and tourists prepared a simple &apos;packed lunch&apos; to carry around.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Travelers and tourists prepared a simple &apos;packed lunch&apos; to carry around.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>腰弁当とはおにぎりをいくつかまとめたもので、竹の皮で巻かれたり、竹篭に収納されたりした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Packed lunch was a set of rice balls wrapped in bamboo sheath or placed in a bamboo basket.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Packed lunch was a set of rice balls wrapped in bamboo sheath or placed in a bamboo basket.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Packed lunch was a set of rice balls wrapped in bamboo sheath or placed in a bamboo basket.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>現代でも人気が高い弁当として「幕の内弁当」があるが、これも江戸時代に現れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Makunouchi-bento&apos; is still popular and which also emerged in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Makunouchi-bento&apos; is still popular and which also emerged in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Makunouchi-bento&apos; is still popular and which also emerged in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>能や歌舞伎を観覧する人々が幕間（まくあい）にこの特製の弁当を食べていたため「幕の内弁当」と呼ばれるようになったという説が有力である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a theory that the name Makunouchi-bento comes from the fact that people who saw Noh and Kabuki (traditional drama performed by male actors) had this special bento during the intervals (between acts), that is, Makuai, and this theory is widely accepted..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a theory that the name Makunouchi-bento comes from the fact that people who saw Noh and Kabuki (traditional drama performed by male actors) enjoyed this special bento during intervals (between acts), that is, Makuai, and this theory is widely accepted..</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a theory that the name Makunouchi-bento comes from the fact that people who saw Noh and Kabuki (traditional drama performed by male actors) enjoyed this special bento during intervals (between acts), that is, Makuai, and this theory is widely accepted..</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>そしてこの時代、弁当のハウトゥー本が多数出版されたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that many how-to books on bento were published at this time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that many how-to books on bento were published during that time.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that many how-to books on bento were published during that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>ひな祭りや花見に向けての準備を行う庶民のために、これらの本には弁当の具体的な調理方法や包み方、飾り方などが詳しく書かれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These book cover the detailed and specific instructions on how to cook, wrap, and decorate bentos intended for people who prepare for Doll&apos;s Festival or cherry blossom viewing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These books cover the detailed and specific instructions on how to cook, wrap, and decorate bentos intended for people who prepare for the Doll Festival or cherry blossom viewing.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These books covered the detailed and specific instructions on how to cook, wrap, and decorate bentos intended for people who prepared for the Doll Festival or cherry blossom viewing.</e>
<cmt>cover→covered、prepare→preparedに修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="47">
<j>明治時代、給食もなく、また現代のように外食施設が発達していなかったこの時代、役所に勤務する官吏たちは江戸時代からあるような腰弁当を提げて仕事に出掛けていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Unlike Today, in the Meiji period when school lunches were not available and food service business had not been well developed, government officials working at administrative institutions still went to work carrying a packed lunch like the one used during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unlike Today, during the Meiji period when school lunches were not available and the food service business had not been well developed, government officials working at administrative institutions still went to work carrying a packed lunch like ones used during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unlike Today, during the Meiji period when school lunches were not available and the food service business had not been well developed, government officials working at administrative institutions still went to work carrying a packed lunch like ones used during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>そのため、安月給の下級役人は「腰弁」などと呼ばれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, a low-paid lower ranked government official was called &apos;packed lunch.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, a low-paid lower ranked government official was called &apos;packed lunch.&apos;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, a low-paid lower ranked government official was called &apos;packed lunch.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>また、明治初期の学校では昼食を提供していなかったので、生徒と教師たちは弁当を持ってこなければならなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because schools in the Meiji period did not provide school lunches, students and teachers had to bring their own bentos.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because schools in the Meiji period did not provide school lunches, students and teachers had to bring their own bentos.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because schools in the Meiji period did not provide school lunches, students and teachers had to bring their own bentos.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>この頃、鉄道駅で最初の「駅弁」が発売された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time, the first Ekiben was put on sale.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this time, the first Ekiben were put on sale.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this time, the first Ekiben were put on sale.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>最初に駅弁の販売が始まった場所に関しては複数の説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are several theories regarding where Ekiben was started.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are several theories regarding where Ekiben was started.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are several theories regarding where Ekiben was started.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>はっきりとは判らないが、おおむね1870年代後半から1880年代前半にかけての時期ではないかと推測されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore it is not certain when but it has been estimated that Ekiben was started from the late 1870&apos;s to the early 1880&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore it is not certain when, but it has been estimated that Ekiben were started from the late 1870&apos;s to the early 1880&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore it is not certain when, but it has been estimated that Ekiben were started from the late 1870&apos;s to the early 1880&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>当初の駅弁はおにぎりと沢庵を竹の皮に包んだような簡易なものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Initial Ekiben was quite simple as it included only rice balls and takuan (pickled radish) wrapped in bamboo sheath.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Initial Ekiben was quite simple as it included only rice balls and takuan (pickled radish) wrapped in a bamboo sheath.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Initial Ekiben was quite simple as it included only rice balls and takuan (pickled radish) wrapped in a bamboo sheath.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>サンドウィッチのようなヨーロッパスタイルの弁当が現れ始めたのもこの頃からである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time, European style bento like sandwich came to be available.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this time, a European style bento like sandwich came to be available.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this time, a European style bento like sandwich came to be available.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="55">
<j>大正時代、学校に弁当を持って来る慣例を廃止する動きがあり、社会問題に発展した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Taisho period, there were a move to discard the custom of bringing a bento into the school, and it developed into social problem.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Taisho period, there were moves to discard the custom of bringing bento to school, and it developed into a social problem.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Taisho period, there were moves to discard the custom of bringing bento to school, and it developed into a social problem.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>第一次世界大戦とそれ以降に不作が続くと、東北地方からの都会への移住者が増えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After World War I and following continuous poor crops, the number of migrant from Tohoku region to urban area increased.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After World War I and following continuous poor crop yield, the number of migrants from Tohoku region to urban area increased.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After World War I and following continuous poor crop yield, the number of migrants from Tohoku region to urban area increased.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>そのため所得格差が大きくなり、弁当に大きな貧富の差が表われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, the income gap was widened, and big gap between rich and poor had emerged.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the income gap was widened, and large gap between rich and poor had emerged.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the income gap was widened, and large gap between rich and poor had emerged.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>当時の人々は、この現象が肉体的な面からと精神的な面から、子供たちに好ましからぬ影響を与えるのではないかと考えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">People of the time thought this phenomenon could give undesirable influence to children in both physically and mentally.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">People at the time thought this phenomenon could give undesirable influence to children both physically and mentally.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">People at the time thought this phenomenon could give undesirable influence to children both physically and mentally.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="59">
<j>昭和時代になり、アルミニウムをアルマイト加工した弁当箱が開発された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Showa period, anodized aluminum lunchbox was developed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Showa period, an anodized aluminum lunchbox was developed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Showa period, an anodized aluminum lunchbox was developed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>壺井栄の小説『二十四の瞳』に描写されるようにそれは目の覚めるような銀色をしており、またメンテナンスの容易さもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The lunchbox was bright silver as described in the novel &quot;Twenty-Four Eyes Trailer&quot; written by Sakae TSUBOI, and furthermore maintenance was easy.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The lunchbox was bright silver as described in the novel &quot;Twenty-Four Eyes Trailer&quot; written by Sakae TSUBOI, and furthermore maintenance was easy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The lunchbox was bright silver as described in the novel &quot;Twenty-Four Eyes Trailer&quot; written by Sakae TSUBOI, and furthermore maintenance was easy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>当時の人々から羨望の的となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">So it became the envy of people of that time.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">So it became the envy of people of that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">So it became the envy of people of that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>また、かつて小学校の冬の暖房装置にストーブ類が多用されていた頃は、持参したアルマイト弁当箱ごとストーブに上に置き、保温・加熱するということも行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When many elementary schools used a stove as a heating appliance, anodized aluminum lunchboxes brought to school were directly placed onto the stove in order to keep it warm or heat it up.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When many elementary schools used a stove as a heating appliance, anodized aluminum lunchboxes brought to school were directly placed onto the stove in order to keep it warm or heat it up.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When many elementary schools used a stove as a heating appliance, anodized aluminum lunchboxes brought to school were directly placed onto the stove in order to keep it warm or heat it up.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="63">
<j>第二次世界大戦の後、学校の昼食は給食に切り替えられ、全ての生徒と教師に対し用意されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After World War II, lunch at school was replaced to school lunch which came to be available for all students and teachers in schools.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After World War II, lunch at school was replaced by school lunches that came to be available for all students and teachers in schools.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After World War II, lunch at school was replaced by school lunches that came to be available for all students and teachers in schools.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>これによって徐々に学校に弁当を持参してくる習慣は少なくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This gradually reduced the custom of bringing bento to school.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This gradually reduced the custom of bringing bento to school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This gradually reduced the custom of bringing bento to school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>しかし、現代になって行政がコストを削減させる目的で、一部地域の学校では給食制度が廃止となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today, however, school lunch system was abolished in some areas due to the public administration&apos;s effort to reduce the cost.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, however, school lunch system was abolished in some areas due to the public administration&apos;s effort to reduce the cost.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, however, school lunch system was abolished in some areas due to the public administration&apos;s effort to reduce the cost.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>家から弁当を持ってくる習慣が復活しているという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, the custom of bringing bento from home is said to be revived.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, the custom of bringing bento from home is said to have been revived.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, the custom of bringing bento from home is said to have been revived.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>弁当の調理は家庭の主婦の仕事とされてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Preparing bento used to be work to be done by housewives.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Preparing bento used to be work done by housewives.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Preparing bento used to be work done by housewives.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>しかし、女性が外に勤めに出ることも多くなったなどの事情もあり、コンビニエンスストアで買ってきたおにぎりやパンを持参する生徒も多くなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, due to increased woman&apos;s chance of working outside, the number of students who buys rice balls or bread in a convenience store to bring them to school increased.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, due to increased woman&apos;s chance of working outside, the number of students who buy rice balls or bread at a convenience store to take to school have increased.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, due to increased woman&apos;s chance of working outside, the number of students who buy rice balls or bread at a convenience store to take to school have increased.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース消去</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>1970年代、駅弁は日本国有鉄道のディスカバー・ジャパンキャンペーンもあって、鉄道で観光旅行に出かける人が増えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1970&apos;s, with the help of Discover Japan campaign launched by Japan National Railways (JNR), the number of tourists who used railway increased.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the 1970&apos;s, with the help of the Discover Japan campaign launched by the Japan National Railways (JNR), the number of tourists who used the railway increased.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the 1970&apos;s, with the help of the Discover Japan campaign launched by the Japan National Railways (JNR), the number of tourists who used the railway increased.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="70">
<j>すると、各地の素材や郷土料理を活かしたもの、観光地にまつわる物など、より多様なものとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With this increase, Ekiben became diversified by using local products, local dishes, or something related to tourist spot.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With this increase, Ekiben became diversified by using local products, local dishes, or something related to a particular tourist spot.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With this increase, Ekiben became diversified by using local products, local dishes, or something related to a particular tourist spot.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>中小規模の企業で、自前の食堂を持たないところを対象に、弁当を配達する業者も一般的となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Vendor which delivered bentos to small businesses which did not have their own cafeteria became popular.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Vendor that delivered bentos to small businesses which did not have their own cafeteria became popular.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Vendor that delivered bentos to small businesses which did not have their own cafeteria became popular.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="72">
<j>またこの時代、ジャー式の保温弁当容器が開発され販売された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this time, a jar type thermos lunchbox was developed and sold.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During that time, a jar type thermos lunchbox was developed and sold.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During that time, a jar type thermos lunchbox was developed and sold.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>これが普及したことによって、職場や学校に弁当を持参していく者たちも温かい弁当を食べられるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The spread of this type of lunchbox allowed one who brought bentos to their workplaces or schools to have warm bentos.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The spread of this type of lunchbox allowed one who brought bentos to their workplaces or schools to enjoy a warm bento.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The spread of this type of lunchbox allowed one who brought bentos to their workplaces or schools to enjoy a warm bento.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>しかしこの容器はサイズが大きいという欠点があり、とても鞄の中に収まるようなサイズではなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, this type of lunchbox was disadvantageous in that it was too large to put in a bag.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, this type of lunchbox was disadvantageous in that it was too large to put in a bag.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, this type of lunchbox was disadvantageous in that it was too large to put in a bag.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>したがって、昼に温かい弁当を食べるためには鞄以外にもこの弁当容器を肩に提げて出掛けなければならなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, one had to carry lunchbox over one&apos;s shoulder besides a bag in order to have warm bentos.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, one had to carry a lunchbox over one&apos;s shoulder besides a bag in order to have a warm bento.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, one had to carry a lunchbox over one&apos;s shoulder besides a bag in order to have a warm bento at lunchtime.</e>
<cmt>at lunchtimeを追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>また、落とすと容器の内部が破損してしまうという問題もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was also a problem that dropping a lunchbox will damage its inside.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was also the problem if dropping a lunchbox, it will damage what&apos;s inside.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was also the problem if dropping a lunchbox, it would damage what was inside.</e>
<cmt>it will damage what&apos;s inside→it would damage what was insideとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="77">
<j>1970年代後半から1980年代にかけて、弁当は新たな市場にて登場する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the late 1970&apos;s to the 1980&apos;s, Bento reappeared in new markets.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the late 1970&apos;s to the 1980&apos;s, Bento reappeared in new markets.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the late 1970&apos;s to the 1980&apos;s, Bento reappeared in new markets.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="78">
<j>一つは持ち帰り弁当専門店（通称：ホカ弁）の台頭。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One is the rise of takeout bento (so-called Hokaben).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One is the rise of takeout bento (so-called Hokaben).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One was the rise of takeout bento (so-called Hokaben).</e>
<cmt>is→wasとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>1976年に創業したほっかほっか亭がフランチャイズシステムで急激に伸びたことがあげられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is notable that Hokka-Hokka Tei founded in 1976 dramatically increased its sales using the franchise system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is notable that Hokka-Hokka Tei founded in 1976 dramatically increased its sales using the franchise system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is notable that Hokka-Hokka Tei founded in 1976 dramatically increased its sales using the franchise system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>もう一つは、急激に普及したコンビニエンスストアでの販売であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The other is the sales at convenience stores which spreaded rapidly.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The other are the sales at convenience stores that spread rapidly.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The other were the sales at convenience stores that had spread rapidly.</e>
<cmt>are→were、spread→had spreadとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>そこで販売される弁当は店の電子レンジを使用して、いつでも温めて食べられることが売りとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its sales point is that anytime you can warm bentos in a microwave oven there to eat.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its sales point is you can warm a bento in a microwave oven there to eat.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its sales point was you could warm a bento in a microwave oven there to eat.</e>
<cmt>is→was、can→couldとし、余分なスペース消去</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>同時に、スーパーマーケットの惣菜コーナーにも弁当が並ぶようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, bentos also became available on sozai corner (selling corner of daily dish) at a supermarket.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, bentos also became available on sozai corner (selling corner of daily dish) at supermarkets.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, bentos also became available on sozai corner (selling corner of daily dish) at supermarkets.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>これらは「弁当を持ち帰って食べる」という新しい流れを作り出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These created a new trend of &apos;taking bentos home to eat.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These created a new trend of &apos;taking a bento home to eat.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These created a new trend of &apos;taking a bento home to eat.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="84">
<j>また都心部の食堂が少ない地域に、弁当を売りにくる業者も急増した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then number of vendors who came to sell lunch to the inner city which has only few dining halls increased rapidly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then number of vendors who came to sell lunches to the inner city, with few dining halls, increased rapidly.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then number of vendors who came to sell lunches to the inner city, with few dining halls, increased rapidly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>弁当の配達業者も、時間指定で温かいものを届けることを売りにするものが現れ始めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bento businesses which boast warm bento delivered at specified time also became available.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bento businesses boasting warm bento delivered at specified times also became available.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bento businesses boasting warm bento delivered at specified times also became available.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>これらの現象と呼応するように、どかべんに象徴される金属製の弁当箱は、耐熱性プラスティックなどの弁当箱に変わっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In response to such a move, heat-resistant plastic lunchbox gradually replaced metal lunchbox typified by a packed meal in an outsize lunch-box.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In response to such a move, heat-resistant plastic lunchbox gradually replaced metal lunchbox typified by a packed meal in an oversized lunch-box.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In response to such a move, heat-resistant plastic lunchbox gradually replaced metal lunchbox typified by a packed meal in an oversized lunch-box.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="87">
<j>平成時代へと突入した1990年代、コンビニエンスストアが地方でも一般的になり温かい弁当が一般化すると、駅弁でも化学反応を利用して加熱できるタイプのものが登場した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1990&apos;s when the Heisei period started, as convenience stores as well as warm bentos became popular in local areas, Ekiben which can be heated with chemical reaction became available.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the 1990&apos;s when the Heisei period started, convenience stores as well as warm bentos became popular in local areas, Ekiben heated by chemical reaction became available.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the 1990&apos;s when the Heisei period started, convenience stores as well as warm bentos became popular in local areas, Ekiben heated by chemical reaction became available.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース消去</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>2003年頃から、空港で販売される弁当「空弁」がブームとなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since about 2003, soraben (box lunch sold at airports) had been experiencing a boom.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since about 2003, soraben (box lunch sold at airports) had been experiencing a boom.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since about 2003, soraben (box lunch sold at airports) had been experiencing a boom.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>乗客は空港での待ち時間や飛行機に乗っている間にそれを食べている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Passengers eats it while waiting for or on board.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Passengers eat it while waiting to board their airplane.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Passengers eat it while waiting to board their airplane.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>2005年からは、（主に母から子への）愛情弁当の「キャラ弁」が流行となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since about 2005, chara-ben (character bento), bento with love (mainly from mother to child) had became prevalent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since about 2005, chara-ben (character bento), bento with love (mainly from mother to child) had became prevalent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since about 2005, kyara-ben (character bento), bento with love (mainly from mother to child) had become prevalent.</e>
<cmt>ローマ字表記のため、chara-ben→kyara-benとし、had became→had becomeに修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="91">
<j>2007年頃から低価格の250円弁当が、路面店で売り出され、採算の合う大都市中心部で流行している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since about 2007, low-priced 250 YEN bento had been available in shops along the street, and became prevalent in the center of metropolitan areas where economically sensible.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since about 2007, low-priced 250 YEN bento had been available in shops along the street, and became prevalent in the center of metropolitan areas where economically sensible.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since about 2007, low-priced 250 YEN bento had been available in shops along the street, and became prevalent in the center of metropolitan areas where economically sensible.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>以前から、低価格の弁当は存在していたが、カテゴリとして確立したのはこの頃である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Low-priced bentos had been available before 2007 but it was these days that this types of bentos was established as one of categories.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Low-priced bentos had been available before 2007, but it was these days that this type of bento was established as one of the categories.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Low-priced bentos had been available before 2007, but it was these days that this type of bento was established as one of the categories.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="93">
<j>2008年は不況の影響もあり、節約のために弁当持参をする人が増えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 2006, due to the recession, the number of people who bring their own bentos increased in an effort to cut corners.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 2006, due to the recession, the number of people who brought their own bento increased in an effort to cut corners.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 2008, due to the recession, the number of people who brought their own bento increased in an effort to cut corners.</e>
<cmt>In 2006→In 2008に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>弁当男子という独身男性が自ら弁当を作って持参する言葉が生まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That year spawned a new word &apos;bento boy&apos; which means a single man who prepares a bento by himself to bring.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That year spawned a new word &apos;bento boy&apos; which meant a single man who prepared bento by himself.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That year spawned a new word &apos;bento boy&apos; which meant a single man who prepared bento by himself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>さらに1970年代に開発、発売された保温弁当容器も進化を遂げて、一昔前の大きな弁当箱というイメージは薄れ、男性用ビジネス鞄に入るスリムなタイプが登場した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, a thermos lunchbox developed and released in 1970&apos;s further evolved, and it was not what used to be (large lunchbox of a decade ago) but a new type of thermos lunchbox slim enough to slip into men&apos;s bag.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, the thermos lunchbox developed and released in the 1970&apos;s further evolved, and it was not what used to be (large lunchbox of a decade ago) but a new type of thermos lunchbox slim enough to slip into a man&apos;s bag.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, the thermos lunchbox developed and released in the 1970&apos;s further evolved, and it was not what used to be (large lunchbox of a decade ago) but a new type of thermos lunchbox slim enough to slip into a man&apos;s bag.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>近年は女性向けに小型化されてカラフルでおしゃれなタイプの保温弁当箱も登場している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In recent years, colorful and fancy downsized thermos lunchboxes for woman are appearing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In recent years, colorful and fancy downsized thermos lunchboxes for woman are appearing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In recent years, colorful and fancy downsized thermos lunchboxes for woman are appearing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>弁当を作る方法</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">How to prepare bento</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">How to prepare bento</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">How to prepare bento</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="97">
<j>幕の内弁当など現在主流の弁当は、ご飯を主食として食べる日本古来の食習慣を反映している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mainstream bento now available such as Makunouchi-bento reflects the traditional Japanese dietary habit of having rice as staple diet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mainstream bento now available, such as Makunouchi-bento, reflects the traditional Japanese dietary habit of having rice as staple diet.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mainstream bento now available, such as Makunouchi-bento, reflects the traditional Japanese dietary habit of having rice as staple diet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>特に決まった様式があるわけではないが、一つの典型的な例として4321を比率とする分量で作られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is no specific set pattern but as a typical example, the volume of those bentos are set in the ratio of 4321:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is no specific set pattern but as a typical example, the volume of those bentos are set in the ratio of 4,3,2,1:</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is no specific set pattern but as a typical example, the volume of those bentos are set in the ratio of 4,3,2,1:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>4はご飯である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">4 for rice;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">four for rice;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Four for rice.</e>
<cmt>文頭の頭文字を大文字に、セミコロン→ピリオドに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>3は魚または肉からなるおかず。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">3 for accompanying dish consisting of fish or meat</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">three for an accompanying dish consisting of fish or meat</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Three for an accompanying dish consisting of fish or meat.</e>
<cmt>文頭の頭文字を大文字に、ピリオド追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>2は野菜、1は漬物、またはデザートとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">2 for vegetable; 1 for tsukemono (Japanese pickled vegetables) or dessert.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">two for vegetables; one for tsukemono (Japanese pickled vegetables) or dessert.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Two for vegetables; one for tsukemono (Japanese pickled vegetables) or dessert.</e>
<cmt>文頭の頭文字を大文字に変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="102">
<j>弁当を作るにあたって最も重要な点は、食中毒を避けることである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To prepare bento, the most important thing is to prevent food poisoning.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To prepare bento, the most important thing is to prevent food poisoning.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To prepare bento, the most important thing is to prevent food poisoning.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>特に夏には注意しなければならない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially during summer, you have to be very careful.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Especially during summer, you have to be very careful.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Especially during summer, you have to be very careful.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>いくつかの予防措置が必要となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Several preventive measures should be taken.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Several preventive measures should be taken.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Several preventive measures should be taken.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>まず、食品はよく調理（加熱）されなければならない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">First, food must be fully cooked or heated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">First, food must be fully cooked or heated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">First, food must be fully cooked or heated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>熱いご飯やおかずは密閉する前に冷ます必要がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hot rice and accompanying dish must be cooled before it is sealed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hot rice and an accompanying dish must be cooled before it is sealed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hot rice and an accompanying dish must be cooled before it is sealed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>また、弁当は涼しく湿気の少ない場所に保管されなければならない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, bento must be kept in cooler and less moisture place.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, bento must be kept in a cooler and in a place with less moisture.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, bento must be kept in a cool place with less moisture.</e>
<cmt>原文の内容に沿うよう一部訳文を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>腐敗防止のために梅干しがよく用いられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To prevent decay, pickled ume (plum) is often used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To prevent spoilage, pickled ume (plum) is often used.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To prevent spoilage, pickled ume (plum) is often used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="109">
<j>汁気の多いおかずは慎重に詰めるか、あるいは、全く避けられなければならない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moist food must be carefully packed or completely avoided.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moist food must be carefully packed or completely avoided.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moist food must be carefully packed or completely avoided.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>そうしなければ汁が他のおかずに混じり悲惨な状態になるかもしれないからである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If not, the liquid is mixed with other accompanying dish, and it might cause misery.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If not, liquids are mixed with other accompanying dishes, and might cause misery.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If not, liquids are mixed with other accompanying dishes, and might cause misery.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>ご飯が弁当に含まれるときは、通気性を良くしてよく冷やされるようにしなければならない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If a bento contains rice, you must try to cool it by ensuring proper airflow.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If a bento contains rice, you must try to cool it by ensuring a proper airflow.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If a bento contains rice, you must try to cool it by ensuring a proper airflow.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>弁当が密閉されると、ご飯からの水蒸気の露でおかずが水っぽくなってしまうからである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is because accompanying dishes become watery with due resulted from water vapor from rice if a bento is sealed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is because accompanying dishes become watery due to condensation from the rice if the bento is sealed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is because accompanying dishes become watery due to condensation from the rice if the bento is sealed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>様々な弁当</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Various bentos</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Various bentos</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Various bentos</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="113">
<j>愛妻弁当</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Aisai bento</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Aisai bento</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Aisai bento</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="114">
<j>- 妻が作り夫に持たせた弁当。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Packed lunch made by one&apos;s beloved wife&apos;s fair hands</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Packed lunch made by one&apos;s beloved wife&apos;s fair hands</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Packed lunch made by one&apos;s beloved wife&apos;s fair hands</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="115">
<j>駅弁</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ekiben (box lunch sold on a train or at a station)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ekiben (box lunch sold on a train or at a station)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ekiben (box lunch sold on a train or at a station)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="116">
<j>空弁</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soraben (box lunch sold at airports)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soraben (box lunch sold at airports)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soraben (box lunch sold at airports)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="117">
<j>速弁</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hayaben ((locally prepared) box lunch sold at an expressway service area)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hayaben (locally prepared box lunch sold at an expressway service area)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hayaben (locally prepared box lunch sold at an expressway service area)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="118">
<j>松花堂弁当</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shokado-bento</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shokado-bento</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shokado-bento</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="119">
<j>- 略式懐石で、十字に仕切った弁当箱に様々な料理をいれたもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Informal kaiseki (meal served in the doeml tea ceremony) which contains various foods in a crosswise-partitioned lunchbox.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Informal kaiseki (meal served during the doeml tea ceremony) which contains various foods in a crosswise-partitioned lunchbox.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Informal kaiseki (meal served during the doeml tea ceremony) which contains various foods in a crosswise-partitioned lunchbox.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="120">
<j>海苔弁当</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nori Bento (Seaweed Lunch Box)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nori Bento (Seaweed Lunch Box)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nori-bento (Seaweed Lunch Box)</e>
<cmt>他の表記と合わせ、Nori Bento→Nori-bentoとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="121">
<j>- ご飯に海苔を敷きつめた弁当。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Box lunch with dried seaweed placed on rice)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Box lunch with dried seaweed placed on rice)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Box lunch with dried seaweed placed on rice.</e>
<cmt>)→ピリオドに修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="122">
<j>日の丸弁当</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hinomaru-bento</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hinomaru-bento</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hinomaru-bento</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="123">
<j>- 日本の国旗に模して、白飯の中央に梅干しを一つのせた弁当。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Box lunch with a red pickled plum in the center of white rice which represents the Japanese national flag.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Box lunch with a red pickled plum in the center of white rice that represents the Japanese national flag.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Box lunch with a red pickled plum in the center of white rice that represents the Japanese national flag.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="124">
<j>最もシンプルな弁当の一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is one of the simplest box lunches.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is one of the simplest box lunches.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is one of the simplest box lunches.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="125">
<j>幕の内弁当</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Makunouchi-bento</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Makunouchi-bento</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Makunouchi-bento</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="126">
<j>ロケ弁</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Lunch provided to a film crew on location</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Lunch provided to a film crew on location</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Lunch provided to a film crew on location</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="127">
<j>宮城県仙台市宮城野区福室字弁当二番という地名がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a place-name called Fukushiaza bentoniban, Miyagino Ward, Sendai City, Miyagi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a place-name called Fukushiaza bentoniban, Miyagino Ward, Sendai City, Miyagi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a place-name called Fukumuro aza Bentoniban, Miyagino Ward, Sendai City, Miyagi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>Fukushiaza bentoniban→Fukumuro aza Bentonibanに修正 (参考: http://www.post.japanpost.jp/cgi-zip/zipcode.php?pref=4&amp;city=1041020&amp;id=14841)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="128">
<j>「弁当二番」までが地名であり、「二番」は地番ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">bentoniban&apos; is the part of place-name, and &apos;niban&apos; is not a lot number.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">bentoniban&apos; is the part of a place-name, and &apos;niban&apos; is not a lot number.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bentoniban&apos; is the part of a place-name, and &apos;niban&apos; is not a lot number.</e>
<cmt>Bentonibanとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="129">
<j>その昔、仙台藩の足軽たちがこの地で弁当を広げたことから、その地名（小字）となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The place-name (koaza: small administrative unit of a village) came from it because ashigaru (common foot soldier) of the Sendai Domain had bento there long time ago.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The place-name (koaza: small administrative unit of a village) originated because ashigaru (common foot soldier) of the Sendai Domain had bento there a long time ago.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The place-name (koaza: small administrative unit of a village) originated because ashigaru (common foot soldier) of the Sendai Domain had bento there a long time ago.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース消去</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="130">
<j>弁当一番から弁当三番まであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There used to be bentoichiban through bentosanban.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There used to be bentoichiban through bentosanban.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There used to be Bentoichiban through Bentosanban.</e>
<cmt>Bentoichiban、Bentosanbanとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="131">
<j>しかし、弁当一番は新住居表示制度により、消滅している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, bentoichiban is no more available because of change in addressing system.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, bentoichiban is no longer available because of changes in the addressing system.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Bentoichiban is no longer available because of changes in the addressing system.</e>
<cmt>Bentoichibanとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="132">
<j>俗に、禁錮刑・懲役刑の執行猶予期間のことを「お弁当」と呼ぶ場合がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Vulgarly, the suspended time of imprisonment or prison terms is sometimes called &apos;Obento.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Vulgarly, the suspended time of imprisonment or prison terms are sometimes called &apos;Obento.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Vulgarly, the suspended time of imprisonment or prison terms are sometimes called &apos;Obento.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="133">
<j>（例：二年のお弁当つき）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(for example, with two-years-obentos)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(for example, with two-year-obento)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(For example, with two-year-obento)</e>
<cmt>文頭の頭文字を大文字に変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="134">
<j>ファイルメーカー社のパーソナルコンピュータソフトウェア「Bento」の名称の由来は弁当から来ている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Name of personal computer software &apos;Bento&apos; produced by the FileMaker came from bento.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Name of personal computer software &apos;Bento&apos; produced by FileMaker came from bento.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Name of personal computer software &apos;Bento&apos; produced by FileMaker came from bento.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="135">
<j>そして、そのアイコンは弁当箱をモチーフにしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">So the icon is designed in the motif of lunchbox.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">So, the icon is designed in the motif of a lunchbox.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">So, the icon is designed in the motif of a lunchbox.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>日本の代表的な弁当専門店チェーン</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Typical bento chain store in Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Typical bento chain store in Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Typical bento chain store in Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="136">
<j>オリジン東秀</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Origin Toshu Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Origin Toshu Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Origin Toshu Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="137">
<j>どんどん</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Don Don</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Don Don</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Don Don</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="138">
<j>ヒライ (食品製造)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hirai Co. Inc. (food manufacture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hirai Co. Inc. (food manufacture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hirai Co. Inc. (food manufacture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="139">
<j>ほっかほっか亭業界チェーン3位</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hokka-Hokka Tei as the third biggest chain in the industry</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hokka-Hokka Tei is the third largest chain in the industry</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hokka-Hokka Tei: the third largest chain in the industry</e>
<cmt>原文表記に合わせ、一部訳文を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="140">
<j>本家かまどや業界最大チェーン</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Honkekamadoya as the biggest chain in the industry</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Honkekamadoya is the largest chain in the industry</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Honke Kamadoya: the largest chain in the industry</e>
<cmt>Honke Kamadoyaとし、原文表記に合わせ、一部訳文を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="141">
<j>ほっともっと（Hotto Motto）業界チェーン2位</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hotto Motto as the second biggest chain in the industry</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hotto Motto as the second largest chain in the industry</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hotto Motto: the second largest chain in the industry</e>
<cmt>原文表記に合わせ、一部訳文を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 AlleborgoBot(id:119729), Nnh(id:474), Hhaithait(id:37092), 経済準学士(id:22656), 0null0(id:582), Eskimbot(id:29676), Sina(id:10021), みっとし(id:13754), Kyst(id:219437), Suginamin(id:120015), Jnr bus(id:33651), Yonidebot(id:247998), Shusugai(id:45854), Jinshu(id:88538), Synthebot(id:123032), ＋－(id:17104), Opponent(id:720), 橄欖岩(id:24996), Michey.M(id:906), ラッパ食堂(id:255123), IwaimBot(id:190695), Point136(id:211299), Pipimaru(id:24707), Niboshi(id:46978), GENMEI(id:31879), DumZiBoT(id:230315), Kazov(id:9237), Starbacks(id:1018), いろはにほへと(id:89648), Carbuncle(id:346), マクガイア(id:33346), Utsuda(id:605), Zwobot(id:23873), Simple-phrase(id:294736), Album(id:74976), 東京ウォーカー(id:125399), 公平(id:27915), Fryed-peach(id:63402), Rusk(id:9895), Neko2(id:21083), SilvonenBot(id:190970), SuisuiBot(id:10165), Nekosuki600(id:21263), 集約臨ひのきのぼう(id:52190), やすとし(id:63220), Alexbot(id:157199), Suisui(id:69), 田無稲子(id:63575), Betoseha(id:253713), Roger(id:9883), Tara123(id:130635), Reedo(id:155043), Nevylax(id:38464), An-chan(id:14590), Rei-bot(id:94097), Chobot(id:20846), Loveless(id:129239), スミス16号(id:189050), Valsety(id:89707), KizLo(id:195789), Doppo1127(id:169097), MASA(id:2399), Tanabota(id:41684), Clarin(id:60278), 逆Ｌの男(id:8978), Vina-iwbot(id:56449), Tanuki Z(id:612), YurikBot(id:18605), Fromm(id:71291), N.Koike(id:280541), Enrich(id:148246), Room813(id:58177), LeonardoRob0t(id:25875), 博多商人コイツミ(id:63820), SieBot(id:126695), Kisitani(id:26556), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>