<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>表衣</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omoteginu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omoteginu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omoteginu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>表衣（おもてぎぬ）は十二単を構成する着物の一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omoteginu is one kimono of many kimonos forming juni-hitoe (a dress style of noble females of medieval times).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omoteginu is one of many kimonos forming juni-hitoe (twelve-layered ceremonial kimono).</e>
<cmt>シンプル化＋用語共有を反映</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omoteginu is one of many kimonos forming juni-hitoe (twelve-layered ceremonial kimono).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>単衣→五衣（五枚の袿）→打衣の上に着用する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The order of wearing kimonos of juni-hitoe is, first, one hitoe (kimono without lining), next, five uchikakes (formal kimonos), next, one uchiginu (kimono for adjusting the whole shape of juni-hitoe), and last, one omoteginu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is worn in the follwoing order; first, one hitoe (a single layer of kimono), next, five uchigi (ordinary kimono), next, one uchiginu (a beaten scarlet silk robe worn as a stiffener and support for the outer robes), and last, one omoteginu.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is put on in the following order: first, one hitoe (a single layer of a kimono) is put on; next, five uchigi (ordinary kimono) are put on; next, one uchiginu (a beaten scarlet silk robe worn as a stiffener and support for the outer robes) is put on; and finally, one omoteginu is put on.</e>
<cmt>書き換えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>形は単や袿と変わらないが、一番外側に羽織る着物で目に留まるため、他の着物と違い、二陪織物（ふたべおりもの）などの豪華な生地から調製するのが特徴である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The shape of omoteginu isn&apos;t different from hitoe or uchikake, however, since it is worn last covering the other kimonos of juni-hitoe, it is usually made of luxurious materials such as futabe-orimono (cloth drawn base pattern and front pattern on its base pattern).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shape of omoteginu isn&apos;t different from hitoe or uchigi, however, since it is worn last covering the other kimonos of juni-hitoe, it is usually made of luxurious materials such as futabe-orimono (silk double weave).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The shape of the omoteginu is no different to that of the hitoe or uchigi; however, since it is the outermost kimono that covers the other kimonos of the juni-hitoe, it is usually made of luxurious materials such as futabe-orimono (silk double weave).</e>
<cmt>last→outermost</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 BitBucket(id:30999), Rusk(id:9895), Goki(id:7107), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>