<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>焼酎</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shochu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shochu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shochu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>焼酎（しょうちゅう）とは酒類のうち蒸留酒の一種である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shochu is a kind of distilled liquor of alcoholic drinks.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shochu is a kind of distilled liquor amongst alcoholic drinks.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shochu is a kind of distilled liquor amongst alcoholic drinks.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>日本国内では酒税法によって種別基準が定められており、連続蒸留しょうちゅう（旧甲類）と単式蒸留しょうちゅう（旧乙類）に分けられている（2006年5月1日酒税法改正による変更）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan, it is classified into continuous distilled shochu (former group 甲 (Ko)) and single distilled shochu (former group 乙 (Otshu)) according to the standard of Liquor Tax Law (Revised on May 1, 2006 according to the revision of Liquor Tax Law).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan, it is classified into continuous distilled shochu (former group 甲 - Ko) and single distilled shochu (former group 乙 - Otshu) according to the standard of Liquor Tax Law (Revised on May 1, 2006 according to the revision of Liquor Tax Law).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan, it is classified into continuous distilled shochu (former group 甲 - Ko) and single distilled shochu (former group 乙 - Otshu) according to the standard of Liquor Tax Law (Revised on May 1, 2006 according to the revision of Liquor Tax Law).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>焼酎への酒税は政策的に安くされていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The liquor tax of shochu was set low according to the policy at the time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The liquor tax covering shochu was set low according to the policy at the time.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The liquor tax covering shochu was set low according to the policy at the time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>また、大衆酒として広く飲用されてきた歴史がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also shochu has a history of being drunk widely as popular liquor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also shochu has a history of being drunk widely as a popular liquor.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also shochu has a history of being drunk widely as a popular liquor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>南九州を中心に醸造が盛んである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is brewed mainly in the South Kyushu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is brewed mainly in South Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is brewed mainly in South Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="6">
<j>また、長崎県壱岐島や伊豆諸島など島嶼でも焼酎が醸造されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shochu is brewed also in ilands like Ikinoshima iland in Nakasaki Prefecture, the Izu iland chain and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shochu is brewed also on islands like Ikinoshima island in Nakasaki Prefecture, the Izu island chain and others.</e>
<cmt>spelling, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shochu is brewed also on islands like Ikinoshima island in Nagasaki Prefecture, the Izu island chain and others.</e>
<cmt>Nakasaki→Nagasaki</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>定義</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Definition</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Definition</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Definition</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>酒税法では「アルコール含有物を蒸留した酒類」のうち、以下の条件を満たす酒類を焼酎としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Liquor Tax Law, among liquors produced by the distillation of alcohol containing substances, shochu also must have the following conditions:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the Liquor Tax Law, among liquors produced by the distillation of alcohol containing substances, shochu must also have the following conditions:</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the Liquor Tax Law, among liquors produced by the distillation of alcohol containing substances, shochu must also have the following conditions:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>発芽した穀類を使用していない</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Not produced from malted cereals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Not produced from malt cereals.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Not produced from malt cereals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>シラカンバの炭などで濾過していない</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Not produced by filtering it through white birch charcoal or other substances specified.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Not produced by filtering it through white birch charcoal or other substances specified.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Not produced by filtering it through white birch charcoal or other substances specified.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>蒸留時に別途定められている物品以外を添加しない</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Not produced by adding substances other than those mentioned separately during distillation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Not produced by adding substances other than those mentioned separately during distillation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Not produced by adding substances other than those mentioned separately during distillation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="11">
<j>アルコール度数が連続式で36度未満、単式で45度以下を下回る</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It must be less than 36% vol in case distilled by a continuous still and must have an alcoholic strength of 45% vol or less in case distilled by a pot still.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It must be less than thirty-six percent volume in case of being distilled by a continuous still and must have an alcoholic strength of 45% vol or less in case distilled by a pot still.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It must be less than thirty-six percent volume in case of being distilled by a continuous still and must have an alcoholic strength of 45% vol or less in case distilled by a pot still.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="12">
<j>日本国内では文献記録で確認できる限り、少なくとも16世紀頃から焼酎が造られていたと見られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan, it seems that shochu has been produced since 16the century at least, as long as confirmed literature records.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan, it seems that shochu has been produced since the sixteenth century at least, as long as confirmed literature records.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan, it seems that shochu has been produced since the sixteenth century at least, as long as confirmed literature records.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>例えば1546年に薩摩国に上陸したポルトガルの商人ジョルジェ・アルバレス（フランシスコ・ザビエルにヤジロウを紹介し訪日を促した人物）は、当時の日本人が米から作る蒸留酒（原文ではorraquaオラーカアラビア語のアラクに由来するポルトガル語）を常飲していたことを記録に残している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, in 1546 Jorge Alvares, a merchant from Portugal who landed in Satsuma Province (who introduced Francisco Xavier to Yajiro and encouraged him to go to Japan) recorded that the Japanese at the time used to drink distilled liquor (written as orraqua in the original: a Portuguese word originated from araq in Arabic) made from rice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, in 1546 Jorge Alvares, a merchant from Portugal who landed in Satsuma Province (who introduced Francisco Xavier to Yajiro and encouraged him to go to Japan) recorded that the Japanese at the time used to drink distilled liquor (written as orraqua in the original: a Portuguese word originated from araq in Arabic) made from rice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, in 1546 Jorge Alvares, a merchant from Portugal who landed in Satsuma Province (who introduced Francisco Xavier to Yajiro and encouraged him to go to Japan) recorded that the Japanese at the time used to drink distilled liquor (written as orraqua in the original: a Portuguese word originated from araq in Arabic) made from rice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="14">
<j>また、鹿児島県伊佐市の郡山八幡神社 (伊佐市)には、永禄2年（1559年）に補修が行われた際に大工が残した「焼酎もおごってくれないけちな施主だ」という内容の落書きが伝わっており、焼酎の飲用について日本国内に残存する最も古い文献となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also at Koriyama Hachiman-jinja Shrine in Isa City in Kagoshima Prefecture, there was a graffiti written by a carpenter when it was repaired in 1559 as follows: &quot;So stingy client. He&apos;s never treated us to shochu.&quot; That is the oldest literature about drinking shochu that exists in Japan now.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also at Koriyama Hachiman-jinja Shrine in Isa City in Kagoshima Prefecture, there was some graffiti written by a carpenter when it was repaired in 1559 as follows: &quot;Such a stingy client. He&apos;s never treated us to shochu.&quot; That is the oldest literature about drinking shochu that exists in Japan now.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also at Koriyama Hachiman-jinja Shrine in Isa City in Kagoshima Prefecture, there was some graffiti written by a carpenter when it was repaired in 1559 as follows: &quot;Such a stingy client. He&apos;s never treated us to shochu.&quot; which is the oldest literature about drinking shochu that exists in Japan now.</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="15">
<j>その後、酒税法で「新式焼酎」にあたる「焼酎甲類」と、在来焼酎にあたる「焼酎乙類」の区分が制定された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later it was classified as new type, &quot;shochu group Ko&quot; or existing type, &quot;shochu group Otsu&quot; according to Liquor Tax Law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later it was classified as a new type, &quot;shochu group Ko&quot; or existing type, &quot;shochu group Otsu&quot; according to the Liquor Tax Law.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later it was classified as a new type, &quot;shochu group Ko&quot; or existing type, &quot;shochu group Otsu&quot; according to the Liquor Tax Law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>甲類と乙類</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Group Ko and group Otsu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Group Ko and group Otsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Group Ko and group Otsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>連続蒸留焼酎（焼酎甲類）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Continuous distilled shochu (shochu group Ko)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Continuous distilled shochu (shochu group Ko)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Continuous distilled shochu (shochu group Ko)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="16">
<j>一般に糖蜜等を原料とした発酵液をもとに、連続蒸留器で蒸留して高純度エチルアルコールを生成し、これに加水したものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In general, based on fermentation liquor made from substance like honey, it is distilled by continuous still to produce high-purity ethyl alcohol and water is added in it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In general, based on fermentation liquor made from substance like honey, it is distilled by continuous still to produce high-purity ethyl alcohol and water is added.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In general, based on fermentation liquor made from substance like honey, it is distilled by continuous still to produce high-purity ethyl alcohol and water is added.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="17">
<j>日本の税法上はアルコール度数36%未満。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It must be less than 36% vol according to the tax law in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It must be less than thirty-six percent volume according to the tax law in Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It must be less than thirty-six percent volume according to the tax law in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>製法上、何度も蒸留を行うため、アルコール (食品)純度が高くなり、原料本来の風味が失われるため、味覚の個性は薄い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Through the production process it is distilled many times and the alcohol purity becomes high, therefore its original taste of ingredients is lost and the taste has weak characteristics.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Through the production process it is distilled many times and the alcohol purity becomes high, therefore the original taste of ingredients is lost and the taste has some weak characteristics.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Through the production process it is distilled many times and the alcohol purity becomes high, therefore the original taste of ingredients is lost and the taste has some weak characteristics.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>また、甲類の範囲にてブレンド、熟成、蒸留回数、蒸留機、加水種類、原料、等で変化をつけることによって、ある程度の特徴的な風味を持つものも存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But some kinds of shochu of group Ko have characteristic tastes in a way by variations of blending, maturing, number of distillation, distillation machine, types of adding water, ingredients etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But some kinds of shochu of group Ko have achieved characteristic tastes in a way by variations of blending, maturing, number of distillation, distillation machine, types of water added, ingredients etc.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But some kinds of shochu of group Ko have achieved characteristic tastes in a way by variations of blending, maturing, number of distillation, distillation machine, types of water added, ingredients etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="20">
<j>低コストでの大量生産に適するため、大手企業によって量産され、それらの販売シェアが高い状況となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because it is suitable for mass production, it is mass produced by major companies, which occupies high share in the sales.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because it is suitable for mass production, it is mass produced by major companies, that occupies a high share in the sales.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because it is suitable for mass production, it is mass produced by major companies, that occupies a high share in the sales.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>手を加えて飲まれることもあり、チューハイなどのベースや、リキュールの材料、或いはカクテル作りの際に用いられたり、ジン (蒸留酒)・ウォッカなどの代用品として使用されることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also arranged in chuhai (shochu-based beverage), a substance of liqueur, an ingredient of cocktail and a substitute of jin (distilled liquor) and vodka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also arranged in chuhai (a shochu-based beverage), a substance of liqueur, an ingredients for a cocktail, and a substitute for jin (distilled liquor) and vodka.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also arranged in chuhai (a shochu-based beverage), a substance of liqueur, an ingredients for a cocktail, and a substitute for jin (distilled liquor) and vodka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>梅酒などの果実酒づくりに用いられる「ホワイトリカー」もこの甲類焼酎である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">White liqueur which is used to make fruit liquors like plum liqueur is also one of shochu group Ko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">White liqueur used to make fruit liquors like plum liqueur is also one of shochu group Ko.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">White liqueur used to make fruit liquors like plum liqueur is also one of shochu group Ko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>眞露に代表される甘味の強い大韓民国焼酎が盛んに輸入され、これも日本の税法上では焼酎甲類に区分されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Korean shochus with strong sweetness like Jinro which have been imported actively, are also classified into shochu group Ko according to the tax law in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Korean shochus with a strong sweetness like Jinro which have been imported actively, are also classified into shochu group Ko according to the tax law in Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Korean shochus with a strong sweetness like Jinro which have been imported actively, are also classified into shochu group Ko according to the tax law in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="24">
<j>税法上では「連続式蒸留焼酎」表記の代わりに「ホワイトリカー(1)」と表記することも認められる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also allowed to declare it as &quot;white liqueur (1)&quot; instead of &quot;continuous distilled shochu&quot; according to the tax law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also allowed to declare it as &quot;white liqueur (1)&quot; instead of &quot;continuous distilled shochu&quot; according to the tax law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also allowed to declare it as &quot;white liqueur (1)&quot; instead of &quot;continuous distilled shochu&quot; according to the tax law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>単式蒸留焼酎（焼酎乙類）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Single distilled shochu (shochu group Otsu)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Single distilled shochu (shochu group Otsu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Single distilled shochu (shochu group Otsu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="25">
<j>米、ムギなどを原料とし、単式蒸留器で蒸留して作る焼酎である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Based on ingredients like rice and barley, it is distilled by pot still.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based on ingredients like rice and barley, it is distilled in a pot still.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based on ingredients like rice and barley, it is distilled in a pot still.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="26">
<j>日本の税法上はアルコール度数45%以下。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It must have an alcoholic strength of 45% vol or less according to the tax.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It must have an alcoholic strength of fourty-five percent volume or less according to the tax.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It must have an alcoholic strength of forty-five percent volume or less according to the tax law.</e>
<cmt>fourty→forty、　税法　tax lawとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>基本的に1回のみの蒸留のため、原料本来の風味やうま味成分が生きていることが特徴である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Basically it is distilled only once, so the original taste and flavour of the ingredients are kept characteristically.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Basically it is distilled only once, so the original taste and flavour of the ingredients are characteristically kept.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Basically it is distilled only once, so the original taste and flavor of the ingredients are characteristically kept.</e>
<cmt>flavour→flavor</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>南九州地方が特産地として有名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The South Kyushu region is famous as the main production area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The South Kyushu region is famous for being the main production area.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The South Kyushu region is famous for being the main production area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="29">
<j>製造法の流れは以下の通りである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The production procedure is as follows;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The production procedure is as follows;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The production procedure is as follows;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="30">
<j>元の原材料（多くの場合は米ないしは麦）へこうじ菌を生やし、麹をつくる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Grow aspergillus on original ingredients (usually rice or barley) to make malted rice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Grow aspergillus on original ingredients (usually rice or barley) to make malted rice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Grow aspergillus on original ingredients (usually rice or barley) to make malted rice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="31">
<j>麹をタンクや甕（かめ）で発酵させ、もろみを作る（一次発酵）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fermented the rice malt in tanks and jars to make moromi (unrefined rice wine) (the first fermentation).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ferment the rice malt in tanks and jars to make moromi (unrefined rice wine) (the first fermentation).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ferment the rice malt in tanks and jars to make moromi (unrefined rice wine) (the first fermentation).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="32">
<j>一次発酵させたもろみの中へ原材料を投入させ、発酵させる（二次発酵）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Add ingredients into the moromi after the first fermentation to be fermented further (the second fermentation).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Add ingredients to moromi after the first fermentation to be fermented further (the second fermentation).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Add ingredients to moromi after the first fermentation to be fermented further (the second fermentation).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>このとき投入した原材料が焼酎の主要原材料として表記されることになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The added ingredients at this stage will be declared as the major ingredients of the shochu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The added ingredients at this stage will be declared as the major ingredients of the shochu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The added ingredients at this stage will be declared as the major ingredients of the shochu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>二次発酵としてサツマイモを投入すれば「芋焼酎」となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If sweet potatoes are added for the second fermentation, it will be &quot;sweet potato shochu&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If sweet potatoes are added for the second fermentation, it will be &quot;sweet potato shochu&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If sweet potatoes are added for the second fermentation, it will be &quot;sweet potato shochu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="35">
<j>アルコールが生成された発酵液を蒸留する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Distil the fermentation liquor in which alcohol is generated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Distill the fermentation liquor in which alcohol is generated.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Distill the fermentation liquor in which alcohol is generated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="36">
<j>産地の南九州では、お湯割りで飲まれる事が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the production area, the South Kyushu region, people drink it often with hot water.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the production area, the South Kyushu region, people drink it often with hot water.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the production area, the South Kyushu region, people drink it often with hot water.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>焼酎のお湯割りは、酒杯に先に湯を入れ、後から焼酎を静かに加えることによって、対流が発生し自然に混ざる状態となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">How to make shochu with hot water is; first, pour hot water in a glass, and then add shochu gently, then it is blended naturally by generated convection.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">How to make shochu with hot water is; first, pour hot water in a glass, and then gently add shochu, then it is blended naturally by generated convection.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">How to make shochu with hot water is; first, pour hot water in a glass, and then gently add shochu, then it is blended naturally by generated convection.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>こだわる人は先に焼酎と水を合わせておき、一日もしくは数日おいて馴染ませたものを黒ぢょか等の酒器にて燗をして飲むこともある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those who are particular about it, leave blended shochu and water for one or a few days until it is blended more and warm it up in kurorojoka (black pot to make hot shochu) and drink it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those who are particular about it, leave blended shochu and water for one or a few days until it is blended more and then warm it up in kurorojoka (black pot to make hot shochu) and drink it.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those who are particular about it, leave blended shochu and water for one or a few days until it is blended more and then warm it up in kurorojoka (black pot to make hot shochu) and drink it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="39">
<j>酒税法が制定された1940年以来、単式蒸留焼酎（乙種）は酒税の保全や過当競争防止等の理由にてムギ・米・サツマイモ・ソバの主要4品種については新規製造免許を認めない方針によって、製造の新規参入ができない状態が長らく続いていたが、聖域なき構造改革の一環として国税庁が2005年に規制緩和の見解を示し、一部地域・条件付きながら2006年以降に新規免許が認められる事となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Liquor Tax Law was established in 1940, to maintain liquor tax and prevent price war of single distilled shochu (group Otshu), for four major varieties of barley, rice, sweet potato, buckwheat it was refused to admit new manufacturing license and couldn&apos;t be started production for a long time, but in 2005 as a part of structural reform without sanctuaries, National Tax Agency presented its views on relaxation of regulations and admitted new licenses from 2006 though it was limited in areas and with conditions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the Liquor Tax Law was established in 1940, to maintain the liquor tax and prevent a price war of single distilled shochu (group Otshu), for four major varieties of barley, rice, sweet potato, buckwheat admitting new manufacturing licenses were refused and production couldn&apos;t commence for a long time, but in 2005 as a part of structural reform without sanctuaries, the National Tax Agency presented its views on the relaxation of regulations and admitted new licenses from 2006 though it was limited in areas and with conditions.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the Liquor Tax Law was established in 1940, to maintain the liquor tax and prevent a price war of single distilled shochu (group Otshu), for four major varieties of barley, rice, sweet potato, buckwheat admitting new manufacturing licenses were refused and production couldn&apos;t commence for a long time, but in 2005 as a part of structural reform without sanctuaries, the National Tax Agency presented its views on the relaxation of regulations and admitted new licenses from 2006 though it was limited in areas and with conditions.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="40">
<j>税法上では「単式蒸留焼酎」表記の代わりに「焼酎乙類」「ホワイトリカー(2)」と表記することも認められている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also allowed to declare it as &quot;white liqueur (2)&quot; instead of &quot;single distilled shochu&quot; according to the tax law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also allowed to declare it as &quot;white liqueur (2)&quot; instead of &quot;single distilled shochu&quot; according to the tax law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also allowed to declare it as &quot;shochu group Otsu&quot; or &quot;white liqueur (2)&quot; instead of &quot;single distilled shochu&quot; according to the tax law.</e>
<cmt>「焼酎乙類」を補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>また、後述するように、焼酎甲類に対して劣るという誤解を避けるために「本格焼酎」という呼称も用いられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As described herein below, to avoid misunderstanding that the quality is lower than shochu group Ko, it is also called &quot;Honkaku (authentic) Shochu&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As described herein below, to avoid misunderstanding that the quality is lower than shochu group Ko, it is also called &quot;Honkaku (authentic) Shochu&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As described herein below, to avoid misunderstanding that the quality is lower than shochu group Ko, it is also called &quot;Honkaku (authentic) Shochu&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>未納税移出</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shipment without tax payment</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shipments without tax payment</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shipments without tax payment</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="42">
<j>単式蒸留焼酎の世界では未納税移出、いわゆる「桶買い」「桶売り」という制度がよく使われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the single distilled shochu industry, there is an often used system, so-called &quot;buying in barrels&quot; &quot;selling in barrels&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the single distilled shochu industry, there is an often used system, the so-called &quot;buying in barrels&quot; &quot;selling in barrels.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the single distilled shochu industry, there is an often used system, the so-called &quot;buying in barrels&quot; &quot;selling in barrels.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>これは同一の酒類製造免許をもつ事業者同士で生産した酒類をやり取りする場合には酒税がかからないという制度を利用したもので、清酒の世界でもよく行われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is to use the system that enterprises having a same liquor manufacturing licenses can deal with each other without liquor taxes and it is also done in the rice wine industry often.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is to use the system that enterprises having the same liquor manufacturing licenses can deal with each other without paying liquor taxes and it is also often done in the rice wine industry.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is to use the system that enterprises having the same liquor manufacturing licenses can deal with each other without paying liquor taxes and it is also often done in the rice wine industry.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>単式蒸留焼酎業界では大分県の大手麦焼酎メーカーが鹿児島や宮崎の芋焼酎メーカーの閑散期に麦焼酎の生産を委託することが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the single distilled shochu industry, big barley shochu makers in Oita often outsource the production of barley shochu to sweet potato shochu makers in Kagoshima and Miyazaki during their off-season.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the single distilled shochu industry, big barley shochu makers in Oita often outsource the production of barley shochu to sweet potato shochu makers in Kagoshima and Miyazaki during their off-season.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the single distilled shochu industry, big barley shochu makers in Oita often outsource the production of barley shochu to sweet potato shochu makers in Kagoshima and Miyazaki during their off-season.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="45">
<j>この制度があるため、単式蒸留焼酎製造メーカーの統計を見ると生産量と出荷量と実際にそのメーカーのブランドで販売された量が異なっていることがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of this system, seeing the statistics of single distilled shochu makers, production and shipping volumes are sometimes different from the actual sales of the brands of the makers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of this system, seeing the statistics of single distilled shochu makers, production and shipping volumes are sometimes different from the actual sales of the brands of the makers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of this system, seeing the statistics of single distilled shochu makers, production and shipping volumes are sometimes different from the actual sales of the brands of the makers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>このことから国税庁の資料では出荷量や生産量ではなく、あくまで税金がかかる出荷をした場合の数量、すなわち課税移出数量で統計を管理している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of that, National Tax Agency maintains its statistics not with data of shipping and production volumes, but with those of only when shipped with tax, that is to say, taxable shipping volumes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of that, the National Tax Agency maintains its statistics not with data of shipping and production volumes, but only with those shipped with tax, that is to say, taxable shipping volumes.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of that, the National Tax Agency maintains its statistics not with data of shipping and production volumes, but only with those shipped with tax, that is to say, taxable shipping volumes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>マスメディアなどで「出荷量」という場合には未納税移出数量を含んだ「実出荷量」と未納税移出数量を除いた「課税移出数量」を混同して報道しているケースがあるので注意が必要である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When mass media mention &quot;shipping volume&quot;, they sometimes report mixing &quot;actual shipping volume&quot; including shipping volume without tax payment with &quot;taxable shipping volume&quot; excluding shipping volume without tax payment, so we have to be careful of that.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the mass media mentions &quot;shipping volume,&quot; they sometimes report mixing &quot;actual shipping volume&quot; including shipping volume without tax payment with &quot;taxable shipping volume&quot; excluding shipping volume without tax payment, so we have to be careful about that.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the mass media mentions &quot;shipping volume,&quot; they sometimes report mixing &quot;actual shipping volume&quot; including shipping volume without tax payment with &quot;taxable shipping volume&quot; excluding shipping volume without tax payment, so we have to be careful about that.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>混和焼酎</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mixed shochu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mixed shochu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mixed shochu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="48">
<j>甲類と乙類を混和したものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is mixed shochu of group Ko and Otsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is mixed shochu of group Ko and Otsu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is mixed shochu of group Ko and Otsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>甲類と乙類のどちらが多いかで呼び名が異なる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is called differently depending on which is mixed more of Ko and Otsu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is called differently depending upon which is mixed in more, Ko or Otsu</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is called differently depending upon which is mixed in more, Ko or Otsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>乙類を50%以上95%未満混和したものを「乙甲混和焼酎」、乙類を5%以上50%未満混和したものを「甲乙混和焼酎」と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shochu mixed more than 50% and less than 95% of group Otsu is called &quot;Otsu Ko mixed shochu&quot; and more than 5% and less than 50% of group Otsu is called &quot;Ko Otsh mixed shochu&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shochu mixed more than fifty percent and less than ninety-five percent of group Otsu is called &quot;Otsu Ko mixed shochu&quot; and more than five percent and less than fifty percent of group Otsu is called &quot;Ko Otsh mixed shochu&quot;.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shochu mixed more than fifty percent and less than ninety-five percent of group Otsu is called &quot;Otsu Ko mixed shochu&quot; and more than five percent and less than fifty percent of group Otsu is called &quot;Ko Otsu mixed shochu&quot;.</e>
<cmt>Otsh→Otsu</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="51">
<j>以前は本格焼酎と紛らわしい表示がされたり、混和率などの情報が表示されなかった商品もあったが、業界内で混和焼酎の表示に関する自主基準を設けて、2005年（平成17年）1月1日から実施している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was used to be labelled ambiguously as Honkaku Shochu and not shown the information like mixed rate, but the industry introduced its own rules of labelling mixed rate and it has been implemented since January 1, 2005.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It used to be labelled ambiguously as Honkaku Shochu and did not show any information like the mixed rate, but the industry introduced its own rules of labelling the mixed rate and it has been implemented since January 1, 2005.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It used to be labeled ambiguously as Honkaku Shochu and did not show any information like the mixed rate, but the industry introduced its own rules of labeling the mixed rate and it has been implemented since January 1, 2005.</e>
<cmt>labelling→labeling</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>乙甲混和焼酎</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Otsu Ko mixed shochu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Otsu Ko mixed shochu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Otsu Ko mixed shochu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="52">
<j>乙類100%では匂いが強いなどの理由で飲みにくいと敬遠されることがあるため、これらを和らげるために用いられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is for those who avoid 100% group Otsu shochu because of the features like the strong smell.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is for those who avoid 100% group Otsu shochu because of the strong smell.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is for those who avoid 100% group Otsu shochu because of the strong smell.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>飲みやすさへの志向が強い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is intended to make easy to drink.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is intended to make it easy to drink.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is intended to make it easy to drink.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>甲乙混和焼酎</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ko Otsu mixed shochu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ko Otsu mixed shochu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ko Otsu mixed shochu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="54">
<j>安価な甲類の利点を活かしながら、乙類の風味を加えることで安価で風味のある製品を作ることができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keeping the inexpensiveness of group Ko as its advantage, by adding flavour of group Otsu, inexpensive and flavoured products are realized.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keeping the low costs of group Ko as its advantage, by adding the flavour of group Otsu, inexpensive and flavoured products are realized.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keeping the low costs of group Ko as its advantage, by adding the flavour of group Otsu, inexpensive and flavoured products are realized.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>価格への志向が強い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is price-conscious.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is price-conscious.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is price-conscious.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>その他の焼酎</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other shochus</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other shochu</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other shochu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="56">
<j>上記の焼酎のほか、近年は日本各地で様々な原料を利用した焼酎が造られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Except the shochus above, recently various shchus are produced from various ingredients throughout the country.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Except the shochu above, recently various shochu are produced from various ingredients throughout the country.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Except the shochu above, recently various shochu are produced from various ingredients throughout the country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="57">
<j>一般的な主原料（糖蜜、麦などの穀類）以外を主原料に用いた甲類焼酎。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shochu group Ko using major ingredient other than common ingredients like molasses, barley and other cereals</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shochu group Ko using major ingredients other than common ingredients like molasses, barley and other cereals</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shochu group Ko using major ingredients other than common ingredients like molasses, barley and other cereals</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="58">
<j>乙類焼酎で米こうじか麦こうじを発酵に利用し、主原料のみ独自の原料を用いたもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shochu group Otsu fermented by malted rice or barley and using unique ingredients as major ingredients</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shochu group Otsu fermented by malted rice or barley and using unique ingredients as major ingredients</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shochu group Otsu fermented by malted rice or barley and using unique ingredients as major ingredients</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>そば焼酎はこの中でも抜きん出て成功した例と言える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among those, buckwheat shochu is a successful example especially.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among them, buckwheat shochu is an especially successful example.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among them, buckwheat shochu is an especially successful example.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="60">
<j>一般的な既存の甲類・乙類焼酎または混和焼酎に、独自原料の果汁・エキス類を混和した、リキュールの一種とも言うべきもの（柑橘類焼酎、シソ焼酎、コンブ焼酎、トマト焼酎など）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinds of liqueur such as citrus fruits shochu, shiso (Japanese basil) shochu, sea tangle shochu, tomato shochu etc., in which fruit juice and extracts of unique ingredients are mixed with generally existing group Ko, Otsu or mixed shochu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kinds of liqueur such as citrus fruits shochu, shiso (Japanese basil) shochu, sea tangle shochu, tomato shochu etc., in which fruit juice and extracts of unique ingredients are mixed with generally existing group Ko, Otsu or mixed shochu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinds of liqueur such as citrus fruits shochu, shiso (Japanese basil) shochu, sea tangle shochu, tomato shochu etc., in which fruit juice and extracts of unique ingredients are mixed with generally existing group Ko, Otsu or mixed shochu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>乙類の種類</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Types of group Otsu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Types of group Otsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Types of group Otsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="61">
<j>焼酎乙類は一次発酵・二次発酵を経てつくられたもろみを蒸留して製造されるものが主流をしめており、粕取り焼酎は1000klに満たない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among shochu group Otsu, the mainstream shochu is those produced by distillation of moromi which is made through first and second fermentation and the production of kasutori shochu (shochu made from rice wine lees) is only less than 1000kl.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among shochu group Otsu, the mainstream shochu are those produced by distillation of moromi which is made from first and second fermentation and the production of kasutori shochu (shochu made from rice wine lees) is only less than 1000kl.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among shochu group Otsu, the mainstream shochu are those produced by distillation of moromi which is made from first and second fermentation and the production of kasutori shochu (shochu made from rice wine lees) is only less than 1000kl.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>以下のような種類がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are some types as follows;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some types follow;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some types follow;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>米焼酎</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rice shochu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rice shochu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rice shochu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="63">
<j>日本酒同様、米を原料とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As in the case of rice wine, the major ingredient is rice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As in the case of rice wine, the major ingredient is rice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As in the case of rice wine, the major ingredient is rice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>味はやや濃厚。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It tastes rich a bit.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It tastes a bit rich.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It tastes a bit rich.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="65">
<j>主要生産地は熊本県南部の人吉盆地（人吉・球磨地方）で、28の蔵元がひしめく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The major production area is Hitoyoshi Bonchi basin in the southern Kumamoto Prefecture (Hitoyoshi/Kuma region) where there are remarkable 28 shochu breweries.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The major production area is Hitoyoshi Bonchi basin in southern Kumamoto Prefecture (Hitoyoshi/Kuma region) where there is a remarkable number of twenty-eight shochu breweries.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The major production area is Hitoyoshi Bonchi basin in southern Kumamoto Prefecture (Hitoyoshi/Kuma region) where there is a remarkable number of twenty-eight shochu breweries.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>人吉盆地で生産される米焼酎は特に「球磨焼酎」とよばれ、世界貿易機関の知的所有権の貿易関連の側面に関する協定に基づく産地表示の保護指定を受けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rice shochu produced in Hitoyoshi Bonchi basin is especially called &quot;Kuma shochu&quot; and labelled its origin because of the designation as protected production area based on Agreement on Trade-Related Aspects of Intellectual Property Rights of the World Trade Organization.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rice shochu produced in the Hitoyoshi Bonchi basin is especially called &quot;Kuma shochu&quot; and its origin is labelled because of the designation as protected production area based upon an Agreement on Trade-Related Aspects of Intellectual Property Rights of the World Trade Organization.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rice shochu produced in the Hitoyoshi Bonchi basin is especially called &quot;Kuma shochu&quot; and its origin is labelled because of the designation as protected production area based upon an Agreement on Trade-Related Aspects of Intellectual Property Rights of the World Trade Organization.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>また、2006年には地域団体商標として登録されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also in 2006 it was registered as a regional collective trademark.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also in 2006 it was registered as a regional collective trademark.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also in 2006 it was registered as a regional collective trademark.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>香りや味わいは日本酒に近くフルーティで、減圧蒸留の普及もあって初心者にも受け入れやすい焼酎である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has fruity aroma and flavor like rice wine and is acceptable also for beginners due to the widespread use of vacuum distillation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has a fruity aroma and flavor like rice wine and is acceptable also for beginners due to the widespread use of vacuum distillation</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has a fruity aroma and flavor like rice wine and is acceptable also for beginners due to the widespread use of vacuum distillation.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="69">
<j>この他、日本酒の名産地（秋田県、新潟県等）でも米焼酎が生産されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Except that area, rice shochu is also produced in the production areas of rice wine such as Akita Prefecture, Nigata Prefecture etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Except for that area, rice shochu is also produced in the production areas of rice wine such as Akita Prefecture, Nigata Prefecture etc.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Except for that area, rice shochu is also produced in the production areas of rice wine such as Akita Prefecture, Niigata Prefecture etc.</e>
<cmt>Nigata→Niigata</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>麦焼酎</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Barley shochu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Barley shochu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Barley shochu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="70">
<j>もともと長崎県壱岐で生産され始めたのが最初である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally it was started to be produced in Iki in Nagasaki Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally started to be produced in Iki in Nagasaki Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally started to be produced in Iki in Nagasaki Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>「壱岐焼酎」は世界貿易機関のTRIPS協定に基づく産地表示の保護指定を受けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Iki shochu&quot; has been designated as protected production area based on Agreement on Trade-Related Aspects of Intellectual Property Rights of the World Trade Organization</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Iki shochu&quot; has been designated as a protected production area based upon an Agreement on Trade-Related Aspects of Intellectual Property Rights of the World Trade Organization</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Iki shochu&quot; has been designated as a protected production area based upon an Agreement on Trade-Related Aspects of Intellectual Property Rights of the World Trade Organization</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>壱岐焼酎は米麹に麦を掛け合わせている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Iki shochu is produced by mixing barley into malted rice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Iki shochu is produced by mixing barley with malted rice.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Iki shochu is produced by mixing barley with malted rice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="73">
<j>麦焼酎は1960年代まで焼酎の中ではメジャーな存在ではなかったが、東京農業大学の柳田藤治によってイオン交換を麦焼酎へ応用する手法が開発され、宮崎県の柳田酒造によって実際の使用方法が確立すると多くの麦焼酎メーカーがイオン交換濾過法を導入することとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Until 1960&apos;s barley shochu was not major among various kinds of shochu but Fujiharu YANAGIDA at Tokyo University of Agriculture developed a technique to apply ion exchange to barley shochu and after Yanagita Shuzo in Miyazaki Prefecture established the actual use of the technique, a lot of barley shochu makers introduced the ion exchange filtration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Until 1960&apos;s barley shochu was not major among various kinds of shochu, but Fujiharu YANAGIDA at Tokyo University of Agriculture developed a technique to apply ion exchange to barley shochu and after Yanagita Shuzo in Miyazaki Prefecture established the actual use of the technique, a lot of barley shochu makers introduced the ion exchange filtration.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Until 1960&apos;s barley shochu was not major among various kinds of shochu, but Fujiharu YANAGIDA at Tokyo University of Agriculture developed a technique to apply ion exchange to barley shochu and after Yanagita Shuzo in Miyazaki Prefecture established the actual use of the technique, a lot of barley shochu makers introduced the ion exchange filtration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="74">
<j>その後、1960年代後半から大分県で生産されている麦麹に麦を掛け合わせる麦焼酎が日本各地で注目を浴び、現在では大分県も麦焼酎の一大産地となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, since the late 1960&apos;s barley shochu in which barley was mixed into malted barley produced in Oita prefecture, has been getting attention throughout the country and now Oita Prefecture is also one of the major production area of barley shochu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, since the late 1960&apos;s, barley shochu in which barley was mixed into malted barley produced in Oita prefecture, has been getting attention throughout the country and now Oita Prefecture is also one of the major production areas of barley shochu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, since the late 1960&apos;s, barley shochu in which barley was mixed into malted barley produced in Oita prefecture, has been getting attention throughout the country and now Oita Prefecture is also one of the major production areas of barley shochu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>なお、「大分麦焼酎」は地域団体商標として登録されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Oita Berley Shochu&quot; has been registered as a regional collective trademark.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Oita Berley Shochu&quot; has been registered as a regional collective trademark.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Oita Barley Shochu&quot; has been registered as a regional collective trademark.</e>
<cmt>Berley→Barley</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="14">
<tit>
<j>芋焼酎</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sweet potato shochu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sweet potato shochu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sweet potato shochu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="76">
<j>江戸時代から南九州で広く栽培されているサツマイモを原料とした焼酎。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a shochu made from sweet potatoes which are cultivated widely in the South Kyushu since the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is shochu made from sweet potatoes which are cultivated widely in Southern Kyushu since the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is shochu made from sweet potatoes which are cultivated widely in Southern Kyushu since the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>鹿児島県や宮崎県南部で広く飲まれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is drunk widely throughout Kagoshima Prefecture and the southern Miyazaki Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is drunk widely throughout Kagoshima Prefecture and southern Miyazaki Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is drunk widely throughout Kagoshima Prefecture and southern Miyazaki Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>味はかなり濃厚で、しばしば独特の臭みがあるため、地元以外では好き嫌いが分かれるが、近年は匂いを抑えたものも作られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because it has quite rich taste and often unique strong aroma, likes and dislikes of people outside the production area split into. In recent years some types reduced aroma are also produced.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because it has quite a rich taste and often unique strong aroma, likes and dislikes of people outside the production area split in two. In recent years some types with reduced the aroma are also produced.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because it has quite a rich taste and often unique strong aroma, likes and dislikes of people outside the production area split in two, but in recent years some types with reduced the aroma are also produced.</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>使用される麹はほとんどが米麹。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Malted rice is mostly used for the productions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Malted rice is mostly used for the production.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Malted rice is mostly used for the production.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>サツマイモ100%焼酎は製造されたことがなかったが、1997年に国分酒造協業組合が日本で初めてとなるサツマイモ100%焼酎を発売したことで、芋麹も一般化、現在では多くのメーカーがサツマイモ100%焼酎を発売している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">100% sweet potato shochu had never been produced, but since Kokubushuzo released the Japan&apos;s first 100% potato shochu in 1997, malted sweet potato has been generalized and a lot of makers release it nowadays.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">100% sweet potato shochu had never been produced, but since Kokubushuzo released Japan&apos;s first 100% potato shochu in 1997, malted sweet potato has been generalized and a lot of makers have released it nowadays.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">100% sweet potato shochu had never been produced, but since Kokubushuzo released Japan&apos;s first 100% potato shochu in 1997, malted sweet potato has been generalized and a lot of makers have released it nowadays.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="81">
<j>主産地は鹿児島県と宮崎県南部。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The major production areas are Kagoshima Prefecture and the southern Miyazaki Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Major production areas are Kagoshima and southern Miyazaki Prefectures.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Major production areas are Kagoshima and southern Miyazaki Prefectures.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>他の産地として、薩摩出身の流人である丹宗右衛門が製法を持ち込んだ八丈島などが挙げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The other area is Hachijojima island where Shoemon TANSO who was an exile from Satsuma, brought the process to make it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The other area is Hachijojima island where Shoemon TANSO who was an exile from Satsuma, brought the process to make it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The other area is Hachijojima island where Shoemon TANSO who was an exile from Satsuma, brought the process to make it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>鹿児島で生産される「薩摩焼酎」は、世界貿易機関のTRIPS協定に基づく産地表示の保護指定を受けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Satsuma shochu&quot; which is produced in Kagoshima, has been designated as protected production area based on Agreement on Trade-Related Aspects of Intellectual Property Rights of the World Trade Organization</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Satsuma shochu&quot; produced in Kagoshima, has been designated as a protected production area based upon an Agreement on Trade-Related Aspects of Intellectual Property Rights of the World Trade Organization</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Satsuma shochu&quot; produced in Kagoshima, has been designated as a protected production area based upon an Agreement on Trade-Related Aspects of Intellectual Property Rights of the World Trade Organization</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="15">
<tit>
<j>黒糖焼酎</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kokuto shochu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokuto shochu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kokuto shochu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="84">
<j>奄美諸島では江戸時代から第二次世界大戦以前まで、泡盛や黒糖酒（黒砂糖原料の蒸留酒）が製造されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Amami iland chain, Awamori and Kokutoshu (distilled liquor made from brown sugar) were produced from the Edo period until before World War II.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Amami island chain, Awamori and Kokutoshu (distilled liquor made from brown sugar) were produced since the Edo period until before World War II.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Amami island chain, Awamori and Kokutoshu (distilled liquor made from brown sugar) were produced since the Edo period until before World War II.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>だが、戦間期から戦後のアメリカ占領時代にかけ、米不足で泡盛の原料に事欠く一方、黒砂糖は日本本土に移出できず余剰だったことから黒糖酒が多く作られるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, from the wartimes until the period of occupation by the United States, there was a lack of rice, the ingredient of Awamori, while there was surplus of brown sugar which could not be shipped out to Japan&apos;s mainland and therefore people began to produce kokutoshu more.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, from wartime until the period of occupation by the United States, there was a lack of rice, the ingredient for Awamori, while there was a surplus of brown sugar which could not be shipped out to Japan&apos;s mainland and therefore people began to produce more kokutoshu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, from wartime until the period of occupation by the United States, there was a lack of rice, the ingredient for Awamori, while there was a surplus of brown sugar which could not be shipped out to Japan&apos;s mainland and therefore people began to produce more kokutoshu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="86">
<j>1953年、奄美諸島の日本返還に伴い日本の税法を適用するにあたり、黒糖酒は酒税法上「焼酎」として扱われず税率が高いことから、「焼酎」扱いを望む島民の要望もあり、取り扱いに関して議論がなされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Amami iland chain was returned to Japan in 1953 and therefore Japan&apos;s tax law was applied, there was occurred an argument about kokutoshu to treat it as shochu by people including the islanders, because it was not treated as shochu according to the tax law and therefore the tax rate was high.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Amami island chain was returned to Japan in 1953 and Japan&apos;s tax law was applied, there occurred an argument about to treating kokutoshu as shochu by the people including the islanders, because it was not treated as shochu according to the tax law and therefore the tax rate was high.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Amami island chain was returned to Japan in 1953 and Japan&apos;s tax law was applied, there occurred an argument about to treating kokutoshu as shochu by the people including the islanders, because it was not treated as shochu according to the tax law and therefore the tax rate was high.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>当時の大蔵省は奄美諸島の振興策の一環として、米こうじ使用を条件に、熊本国税局大島税務署の管轄区域（奄美諸島）に限って黒糖原料の焼酎製造を特認した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Finance Ministry at that time specially admitted productions of shochu made from brown sugar in the jurisdiction of Oshima tax office of Kumamoto Regional Taxation Bureau on the condition of using malted rice as part of its measures of promotion of the Amami island chain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Finance Ministry at that time specially admitted the production of shochu made from brown sugar in the jurisdiction of the Oshima tax office of Kumamoto Regional Taxation Bureau on condition of using malted rice as part of its measures to promote the Amami island chain.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Finance Ministry at that time specially admitted the production of shochu made from brown sugar in the jurisdiction of the Oshima tax office of Kumamoto Regional Taxation Bureau on condition of using malted rice as part of its measures to promote the Amami island chain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="88">
<j>以後、黒糖焼酎は奄美諸島でしか製造できない特産品となって現在に至っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since then, kokuto shochu has become a specialty product which is able to be produced only in the Amami island chain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since then, kokuto shochu has become a specialty product produced only in the Amami island chain.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since then, kokuto shochu has become a specialty product produced only in the Amami island chain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>口当たりは比較的柔らかく、癖が少ない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It tastes relatively mild.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It tastes relatively mild.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It tastes relatively mild.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>原料から想像されるほどに甘味は強くない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It doesn&apos;t taste very sweet as much as imagined from the ingredients.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It doesn&apos;t taste very sweet as would be imagined from the ingredients.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It doesn&apos;t taste very sweet as would be imagined from the ingredients.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="91">
<j>現在、奄美諸島では泡盛は製造されておらず、黒糖酒は奄美諸島全域で製造されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Awamori is not produced in the Amami island chain now and kokutoshu is produced throughout the Amami island chain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Awamori is not being produced in the Amami island chain now, but kokutoshu is.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Awamori is not being produced in the Amami island chain now, but kokutoshu is.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="92">
<j>小笠原諸島において、日本領土になった明治時代初期からサトウキビ栽培によって製糖業が盛んとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Ogasawara island chain, since it became Japanese territory in the early Meiji period, sugar manufacturing prospered from sugarcane cultivation.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Ogasawara island chain, since becoming Japanese territory during the early Meiji period, sugar manufacturing prospered from sugarcane cultivation.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Ogasawara island chain, since becoming Japanese territory during the early Meiji period, sugar manufacturing prospered from sugarcane cultivation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>その過程で生じた副産物を発酵・蒸留した製法で、焼酎に類似する「糖酎」「泡酒」「蜜酒」と呼ばれた酒が戦前に醸造されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With fermenting and distilling the by-products generated in the manufacturing proccess, liquors called &quot;tochu&quot; &quot;awazake&quot; &quot;mitsuzake&quot; which were similar to shochu were produced before the war.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With fermenting and distilling the by-products generated in the manufacturing proccess, liquors called &quot;tochu,&quot; &quot;awazake,&quot; &quot;mitsuzake,&quot; similar to shochu, were produced before the war.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With fermenting and distilling the by-products generated in the manufacturing process, liquors called &quot;tochu,&quot; &quot;awazake,&quot; &quot;mitsuzake,&quot; similar to shochu, were produced before the war.</e>
<cmt>proccess→process</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>戦中の島民疎開により途絶えていたが、1989年（平成元年）になって地域おこしの一環として小笠原村の役場・農業協同組合・商工会によってこれを扱う企業が設立され、その製法を模したラム酒が製造されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was discontinued because islanders evacuated during the war, but in 1989 as part of regional promotion, a company was established by the local government, Agricultural Cooperatives and Chamber of Commerce of Ogasawara village to produce it and rum was produced by following the manufacturing process.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was discontinued because the islanders evacuated during the war, but in 1989 as part of regional promotion, a company was established by the local government, Agricultural Cooperatives and Chamber of Commerce of Ogasawara village to produce it and rum was produced by following the manufacturing process.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was discontinued because the islanders evacuated during the war, but in 1989 as part of regional promotion, a company was established by the local government, Agricultural Cooperatives and Chamber of Commerce of Ogasawara village to produce it and rum was produced by following the manufacturing process.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>、税法上はラム酒（スピリッツ、もしくはリキュール類）の扱いとなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is rum (a sort of spirit or liqueur) according to the tax law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is rum (a sort of spirit or liqueur) according to the tax law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is rum (a sort of spirit or liqueur) according to the tax law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="96">
<j>最近では、焼酎や泡盛のルーツと言われるタイでもきび南蛮を始めとする黒糖焼酎が発売され話題となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Recently it is making news that kokuto shochu including Kibinanban was released in Thailand where it is thought that shochu and awamori have their roots.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Recently making news is that kokuto shochu including Kibinanban was released in Thailand where it is thought that shochu and awamori have their roots.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Recently making news is that kokuto shochu including Kibinanban was released in Thailand where it is thought that shochu and awamori have their roots.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="16">
<tit>
<j>そば焼酎</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Buckwheat shochu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Buckwheat shochu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Buckwheat shochu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="97">
<j>ソバを主原料とする焼酎。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is shochu made from buckwheat.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is shochu made from buckwheat.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is shochu made from buckwheat.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>発祥は新しく、1973年、宮崎県五ヶ瀬町の雲海酒造が、山間部での特産品であるソバを原料に取り上げ新たに開発した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is new shochu which was developed by Unkai Shuzo in Gokase-cho, Miyazaki Prefecture using the mountain area&apos;s specialty product, buckwheat as the ingredient in 1973.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A new shochu developed by Unkai Shuzo in Gokase-cho, Miyazaki Prefecture using the mountain area&apos;s specialty product, buckwheat as the ingredient in 1973.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A new shochu developed by Unkai Shuzo in Gokase-cho, Miyazaki Prefecture using the mountain area&apos;s specialty product, buckwheat as the ingredient in 1973.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>以後各地の焼酎メーカーで、米・麦との混和タイプも含めて広く作られるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since then, many shochu makers around the country have produced it including mixed types with rice and barley.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since then, many shochu makers around the country have produced it including mixed types with rice and barley.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since then, many shochu makers around the country have produced it including mixed types with rice and barley.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>味わいは麦焼酎より更に軽く、癖が少ない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It tastes mild and even lighter than barley shochu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It tastes mild and even lighter than barley shochu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It tastes mild and even lighter than barley shochu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>そば屋においてそばをゆでたそば湯で割ったそば焼酎を提供している事例も多く見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is often seen to provide buckwheat shochu in hot water after boiled noodles in buckwheat noodle restaurants.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is often seen to provide buckwheat shochu from the hot water from boiling noodles in buckwheat noodle restaurants.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is often seen to provide buckwheat shochu from the hot water from boiling noodles in buckwheat noodle restaurants.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>ただし、食物アレルギーを持つ人はアレルギー症状が出る可能性があるので注意を要する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">People with food allergy have to be careful because it may cause allergy symptoms.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">People with food allergies have to be careful because it may cause allergy symptoms.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">People with food allergies have to be careful because it may cause allergy symptoms.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="17">
<tit>
<j>泡盛</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Awamori</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Awamori</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Awamori</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="103">
<j>沖縄県特産の蒸留酒である泡盛は米を原料としており、その製法は一般的な焼酎と差異があるものの、税法上は焼酎乙類の範疇に入れられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Awamori, distilled liquor which is specialty product of Okinawa Prefecture, is made from rice and categorized into Shochu group Otsu according to the tax law though the manufacturing process is different from standard shochus.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Awamori, distilled liquor, a specialty product of Okinawa Prefecture, is made from rice and categorized into Shochu group Otsu according to the tax law though the manufacturing process is different from standard shochu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Awamori, distilled liquor, a specialty product of Okinawa Prefecture, is made from rice and categorized into Shochu group Otsu according to the tax law though the manufacturing process is different from standard shochu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="104">
<j>法制上、泡盛自体は日本全国で製造することができるが、「琉球泡盛」という表示は世界貿易機関のTRIPS協定に基づいて沖縄県産の物のみに認められている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Legislatively, Awanori itself is allowed to be produced throughout the country, but it is allowed to label &quot;Ryukyu Awamori&quot; only on products from Okinawa Prefecture based on Trade-Related Aspects of Intellectual Property Rights of the World Trade Organization.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Legislatively, Awanori itself is allowed to be produced throughout the country, but abeling it as &quot;Ryukyu Awamori&quot; is only allowed on products from Okinawa Prefecture based on Trade-Related Aspects of Intellectual Property Rights of the World Trade Organization.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Legislatively, Awanori itself is allowed to be produced throughout the country, but labeling it as &quot;Ryukyu Awamori&quot; is only allowed on products from Okinawa Prefecture based on Trade-Related Aspects of Intellectual Property Rights of the World Trade Organization.</e>
<cmt>abeling→labeling</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="18">
<tit>
<j>粕取り焼酎とカストリ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kasutori shochu and kasutori</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kasutori shochu and kasutori</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kasutori shochu and kasutori</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="19">
<tit>
<j>粕取り焼酎</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kasutori shochu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kasutori shochu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kasutori shochu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="105">
<j>もろみ取り焼酎とは別の製法で、清酒かす（日本酒の酒粕）を蒸留して造られる「粕取り焼酎」と呼ばれる焼酎がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With different process from that of moromitori shochu, shochu called &quot;kasutori shochu&quot; is produced by distillation of defined rice wine lees.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With different process from that of moromitori shochu, shochu called &quot;kasutori shochu&quot; is produced by distillation of defined rice wine lees.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With different process from that of moromitori shochu, shochu called &quot;kasutori shochu&quot; is produced by distillation of defined rice wine lees.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>粕取り焼酎は九州北部を中心に発達し、全国の清酒蔵で製造されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kasutori shochu has been developed mainly in the northern Kyushu and produced in rice wine breweries throughout the country.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kasutori shochu has been developed mainly in northern Kyushu and produced in rice wine breweries throughout the country.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kasutori shochu has been developed mainly in northern Kyushu and produced in rice wine breweries throughout the country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>江戸時代の本草書『本朝食鑑』に、「焼酒は新酒の粕を蒸籠で蒸留して取る」とあるように、清酒が醸造される地域で焼酎といえば粕取り焼酎のことであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shochu meant Kasutori shochu for the people in production area of shochu as it is written &quot;shochu is produced by distillation of fresh rice wine lees in a steam bascket&quot; in &quot;Honcho Shokkan&quot;, a materia medica of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shochu meant Kasutori shochu for people in production area of shochu as it is written that &quot;shochu is produced by the distillation of fresh rice wine lees in a steam basket&quot; in &quot;Honcho Shokkan,&quot; a materia medica of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>grammar, spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shochu meant Kasutori shochu for people in production area of shochu as it is written that &quot;shochu is produced by the distillation of fresh rice wine lees in a steam basket&quot; in &quot;Honcho Shokkan,&quot; a materia medica of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>新しくできた酒粕をそのまま蒸留する方法と、籾殻（もみがら）を混ぜて通気性を確保してから蒸留する方法があり、前者は吟醸粕取焼酎、後者を正調粕取焼酎と呼んで区別している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are two ways of distilling as follows; Distilling newly made rice wine lees without adding anything and mixing rice hulls to ensure proper airflow before distilling. The former is called ginjo kasutori shochu and the latter seicho kasutori shochu to distinguish those.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are two methods of distilling as follows; Distilling newly made rice wine lees without adding anything and mixing rice hulls to ensure proper airflow before distilling. The former is called ginjo kasutori shochu and the latter seicho kasutori shochu to distinguish them.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are two methods of distilling: the ginjo kasutori shochu method, which involves distilling newly made rice wine lees without adding anything, and the seicho kasutori shochu method, which involves mixing rice hulls to ensure proper airflow before distilling.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせて訳文を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="109">
<j>貯蔵した酒粕を蒸留し早苗饗（さなぶり）という田植え後のお祭りで飲んだことから、別名「早苗響焼酎」とも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because people distilled stored rice wine lees and drank it in a festival called Sanaburi which was hold after having finished planting rice, it is also called &quot;Sanaburi Shochu&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because people distilled stored rice wine lees and drank it in a festival called Sanaburi held after having finished planting rice, it is also called &quot;Sanaburi Shochu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because people distilled stored rice wine lees and drank it in a festival called Sanaburi held after having finished planting rice, it is also called &quot;Sanaburi Shochu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>蒸留した後の粕は田の肥料として使われていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rice wine lees were used as fertilizer for rice fields after distilled.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rice wine lees were used as fertilizer for rice fields after distilled.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rice wine lees were used as fertilizer for rice fields after distilled.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="111">
<j>太平洋戦争後、カストリと混同されたこと、独特の香りが時代の嗜好に合わなかったことなどから需要が低迷し粕取り焼酎の製造から撤退する蔵が相次いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Pacific War, because people confused it with kasutori and the unique aroma was not for the trend of the times, the demand was decreased and breweries eliminated kasutori shochu production one after another.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Pacific War, because people confused it with kasutori and the unique aroma did not suit the trend of the times, the demand decreased and breweries stopped kasutori shochu production one after another.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Pacific War, because people confused it with kasutori and the unique aroma did not suit the trend of the times, the demand decreased and breweries stopped kasutori shochu production one after another.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>また、かつては福岡県内を中心に粕取り焼酎専業の蔵も多くあったが、現在では米焼酎の製造を行うなど、専業蔵は消滅している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also there were a lot of shochu breweries which produced only kasutori shochu mainly in Fukuoka Prefecture before, but such breweries were disappeared and they produce rice shochu or others now.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also there were a lot of shochu breweries that produced only kasutori shochu mainly in Fukuoka Prefecture before, but such breweries disappeared and they produce rice shochu or other types now.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also there were a lot of shochu breweries that produced only kasutori shochu mainly in Fukuoka Prefecture before, but such breweries disappeared and they produce rice shochu or other types now.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="113">
<j>しかし、昨今の焼酎ブームにより、日本酒製造メーカーが粕取り焼酎に再び進出するケースが増えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But because of the recent shochu boom, there have been increasing cases that rice wine makers expanded to kasutori shochu again.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But because of the recent shochu boom, there has been increasing cases where rice wine makers have expanded to kasutori shochu again.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But because of the recent shochu boom, there has been increasing cases where rice wine makers have expanded to kasutori shochu again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="114">
<j>梅酒をつける際にベースとなるアルコールやみりんの主原料としても使われた他、日本酒の仕上げ工程において中途で発酵を止め、防腐や辛口に仕上げる目的で用いられる「柱焼酎」として使われる場合も多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was also used as the major ingredient of alcohol and mirin (sweet rice wine for seasoning) which were bases of plum wine and also often used as &quot;hashira jochu&quot; in the finish processing of rice wine to stop fermentation, preserve rice wine from decay and make it dry.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was also used as a major ingredient of alcohol and mirin (sweet rice wine for seasoning) the basis of plum wine and also often used as &quot;hashira jochu&quot; in the finished processing of rice wine to stop fermentation, preserve rice wine from decay, and make it dry.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was also used as a major ingredient of alcohol and mirin (sweet rice wine for seasoning) the basis of plum wine and also often used as &quot;hashira jochu&quot; in the finished processing of rice wine to stop fermentation, preserve rice wine from decay, and make it dry.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>また、外傷の消毒薬としても用いられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was also used as external antiseptic.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was also used as external antiseptic.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was also used as external antiseptic.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="20">
<tit>
<j>カストリ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kasutori</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kasutori</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kasutori</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="116">
<j>本来の粕取り焼酎とはまったく別な、粗悪焼酎に対する俗称である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Poor-quality shochus are commonly called &quot;Kasutori&quot; and it is completely different from kasutori shochu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Poor-quality shochu is commonly called &quot;Kasutori&quot; and it is completely different from kasutori shochu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Poor-quality shochu is commonly called &quot;Kasutori&quot; and it is completely different from kasutori shochu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="117">
<j>第二次大戦後の社会混乱期、酒不足の世相の中で粗悪な密造焼酎が出回った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the chaotic times after World War II poor-quality shochus which were brewed illegally were on the market in the lack of rice wine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the chaotic times after World War II poor-quality shochu brewed illegally were on the market because of the lack of rice wine.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the chaotic times after World War II poor-quality shochu brewed illegally were on the market because of the lack of rice wine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="118">
<j>原料・出所がまったく不明、甚だしい例では人体に有毒なメチルアルコールを水で薄めたものまで売られる始末で、これら悪酔い確実な代物が俗に「カストリ」と総称されたため、一般にも「カストリ＝粗悪な蒸留酒」というイメージが定着した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ingredients and manufacturers were unknown at all and watered-down methyl alcohol which was toxic to humans were sold at worst and all the bad products which would made people sick, called commonly &quot;kasutori&quot; and therefore the common image was established that kasutori were bad distilled liquors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ingredients and manufacturers were unknown and watered-down methyl alcohol, toxic to humans, was sold at worst and all the bad products that made people sick, were commonly called &quot;kasutori&quot; and therefore a common image was established that kasutori were bad distilled liquors.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ingredients and manufacturers were unknown and watered-down methyl alcohol, toxic to humans, was sold at worst and all the bad products that made people sick, were commonly called &quot;kasutori&quot; and therefore a common image was established that kasutori were bad distilled liquors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="119">
<j>その影響で、決して粗悪でない本来の粕取り焼酎まで誤解によってイメージダウンした時期がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For some time it damaged image of real kasutori shochu which had not bad quality.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For some time it spoiled the image of real kasutori shochu which did not have a bad quality.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For some time it spoiled the image of real kasutori shochu which did not have a bad quality.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="120">
<j>ここから派生した戦後の混乱期を象徴する表現として、「カストリ雑誌」という言葉もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was a word &quot;kasutori magazine&quot; derived from that and symbolizing the chaotic times after World War II.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was a word &quot;kasutori magazine&quot; derived from that and symbolizing the chaotic times after World War II.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was a word &quot;kasutori magazine&quot; derived from that and symbolizing the chaotic times after World War II.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="21">
<tit>
<j>本格焼酎</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Honkaku Shochu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Honkaku Shochu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Honkaku Shochu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="22">
<tit>
<j>「本格焼酎」とは</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">What does Honkaku Shochu mean</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">What does Honkaku Shochu mean?</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">What does Honkaku Shochu mean?</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="121">
<j>戦後1949年の酒税法で「甲類・乙類」の分類呼称が定められたが、通常甲乙の称は等級や順位でも使われる表現であるため、ややもすれば「乙類」が「甲類」に劣ると誤解されかねなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1949 after the war, shochus were classified as &quot;group Ko or group Otsu&quot; according to the Liquor Tax Law, but Ko and Otsu were used normally for grading and ranking, therefore it could be misunderstood that &quot;group Otsu&quot; had lower quality than &quot;group Ko&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1949 after the war, shochus were classified as &quot;group Ko or group Otsu&quot; according to the Liquor Tax Law, but Ko and Otsu were used normally for grading and ranking, therefore it could be misunderstood that &quot;group Otsu&quot; had a lower quality than &quot;group Ko&quot;.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1949 after the war, shochus were classified as &quot;group Ko or group Otsu&quot; according to the Liquor Tax Law, but Ko and Otsu were used normally for grading and ranking, therefore it could be misunderstood that &quot;group Otsu&quot; had a lower quality than &quot;group Ko.&quot;</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="122">
<j>これを危惧した江夏順吉（当時の霧島酒造社長）が1957年に九州旧式焼酎協議会において「本格焼酎」という呼称を提唱、1971年（昭和46年）12月10日に「酒税の保全及び酒類業組合等に関する法律施行規則」（昭和28年大蔵省令第11号）が一部改正され「本格しようちゆう」と呼称・表記することが可能となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1957 Junkichi ENATSU, the president of Kirishima Shuzo at that time proposed the name &quot;Honkaku Shochu&quot; at Kyushu old style sochu association and on December 10, 1971 it became possible to call and label &quot;Honkaku Shochu&quot; because of the partial revision of &quot;Act Concerning Liquor Business Associations and Measures for Securing Revenue from Liquor Tax&quot; &apos;(the Finance Ministry Law No. 11 in 1953).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1957 Junkichi ENATSU, the president of Kirishima Shuzo at that time proposed the name &quot;Honkaku Shochu&quot; at Kyushu old style sochu association and on December 10, 1971 it became possible to call and label it &quot;Honkaku Shochu&quot; because of the partial revision of &quot;Act Concerning Liquor Business Associations and Measures for Securing Revenue from Liquor Tax&quot; &apos;(the Finance Ministry Law No. 11 in 1953).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1957 Junkichi ENATSU, the president of Kirishima Shuzo at that time proposed the name &quot;Honkaku Shochu&quot; at Kyushu old style shochu association and on December 10, 1971 it became possible to call and label it &quot;Honkaku Shochu&quot; because of the partial revision of &quot;Act Concerning Liquor Business Associations and Measures for Securing Revenue from Liquor Tax&quot; &apos;(the Finance Ministry Law No. 11 in 1953).</e>
<cmt>sochu→shochu</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="123">
<j>（2008年12月現在、法令の条文上では「本格しようちゆう」のみが使用されており漢字の「本格焼酎」の登場例はないが、以下業界での慣用に倣って本節では後者を用いる。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(As of December 2008, shochu in hiragana as &quot;本格しょうちゅう&quot; has only used in the letter of the law and in Chinese character as &quot;本格焼酎&quot; has not appeared, but we use the latter in this text as the industry does.)</e>
<cmt>訳では漢字表記を入れない場合、どちらもhonkaku shochuなので、「本節では後者を用いる」は不要と思われます。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(As of December 2008, shochu in hiragana as &quot;本格しょうちゅう&quot; has only been used in the letter of the law and in Chinese characters as &quot;本格焼酎&quot; has not appeared, but we use the latter in this text as the industry does.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(As of December 2008, shochu in hiragana as &quot;本格しょうちゅう&quot; has only been used in the letter of the law and in Chinese characters as &quot;本格焼酎&quot; has not appeared, but we use the latter in this text as the industry does.)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="124">
<j>しかし、「本格焼酎」の呼称を用いる基準が必ずしも明確でなかったことから議論が生じ、その結果2002年11月1日に前述の省令の一部改正により基準が強化され、以下に掲げるアルコール含有物を蒸留したものでなければ本格焼酎と名乗ることはできなくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But it generated a discussion that the standard was not clarified enough to use the name &quot;Honkaku Shochu&quot;, as the result, on November 1, 2002 the standard was strengthened by the partial revision of the law mentioned above and it became impossible to be named Honkaku Shochu except the shochus produced by distillation of alcohol-containing substances as below.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But it generated a discussion about the standard not being clarified enough to use the name &quot;Honkaku Shochu,&quot; as the result, on November 1, 2002 the standard was strengthened by partial revision of the law mentioned above and it became impossible to name it Honkaku Shochu except for shochu produced by distillation of alcohol-containing substances as below:</e>
<cmt>punctuation, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But it generated a discussion about the standard not being clarified enough to use the name &quot;Honkaku Shochu,&quot; as the result, on November 1, 2002 the standard was strengthened by partial revision of the law mentioned above and it became impossible to name it Honkaku Shochu except for shochu produced by distillation of alcohol-containing substances as below:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="125">
<j>なお、単に「焼酎乙類」「単式蒸留焼酎」と表示するのであれば材料は制約されない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ingredients are not restricted when just labelling &quot;shochu group Otsu&quot; or &quot;single distilled shochu&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ingredients are not restricted when just labelling &quot;shochu group Otsu&quot; or &quot;single distilled shochu&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ingredients are not restricted when just labeling &quot;shochu group Otsu&quot; or &quot;single distilled shochu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置、labelling→labeling</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="126">
<j>穀類又はいも類、これらのこうじ及び水を原料として発酵させたもの</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Liquors produced by fermentation of the following ingredients: cereals or potatoes, malted cereals or potatoes, water.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Liquors produced by fermentation of the following ingredients: cereals or potatoes, malted cereals or potatoes, water.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Liquors produced by fermentation of the following ingredients: cereals or potatoes, malted cereals or potatoes, water.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="127">
<j>穀類のこうじ及び水を原料として発酵させたもの</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Liquors produced by fermentation of the following ingredients: malted cereals, water.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Liquors produced by fermentation of the following ingredients: malted cereals, water.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Liquors produced by fermentation of the following ingredients: malted cereals, water.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="128">
<j>清酒かす及び水を原料として発酵させたもの、清酒かす、米、米こうじ及び水を原料として発酵させたもの又は清酒かす</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Liquors produced by fermentation of the following ingredients: rice wine lees and water, rice wine lees, rice, malted rice and water, or Liquors produced by rice wine lees.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Liquors produced by fermentation of the following ingredients: rice wine lees and water, rice wine lees, rice, malted rice and water, or Liquors produced by rice wine lees.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Liquors produced by fermentation of the following ingredients: rice wine lees and water, rice wine lees, rice, malted rice and water, or Liquors produced by rice wine lees.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="129">
<j>砂糖（政令に掲げるものに限る）、米こうじ及び水を原料として発酵させたもの（黒糖焼酎）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Liquors produced by fermentation of the following ingredients: sugar (only stipulated in government ordinances), malted rice and water (kokuto shochu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Liquors produced by fermentation of the following ingredients: sugar (only stipulated in government ordinances), malted rice and water (kokuto shochu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Liquors produced by fermentation of the following ingredients: sugar (only stipulated in government ordinances), malted rice and water (kokuto shochu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="130">
<j>穀類又はいも類、これらのこうじ、水及び国税庁長官の指定する物品を原料として発酵させたもの（その原料中国税庁長官の指定する物品の重量の合計が穀類及びいも類及びこれらのこうじの重量を超えないものに限る）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Liquors produced by fermentation of the following ingredients: cereals or potatoes, malted cereals or potatoes, water, substances listed by Director-General of the National Tax Administration Agency (the total weight of substances listed by Director-General of the National Tax Administration Agency must be less than that of cereals, potatoes and malted cereals and potatoes).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Liquors produced by fermentation of the following ingredients: cereals or potatoes, malted cereals or potatoes, water, substances listed by Director-General of the National Tax Administration Agency (the total weight of substances listed by Director-General of the National Tax Administration Agency must be less than that of cereals, potatoes and malted cereals and potatoes).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Liquors produced by fermentation of the following ingredients: cereals or potatoes, malted cereals or potatoes, water, substances listed by Director-General of the National Tax Administration Agency (the total weight of substances listed by Director-General of the National Tax Administration Agency must be less than that of cereals, potatoes and malted cereals and potatoes).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="23">
<tit>
<j>本格焼酎ブーム</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Honkaku shochu boom</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Honkaku shochu boom</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Honkaku shochu boom</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="131">
<j>日本では、2003年頃から焼酎乙類を対象とする「本格焼酎ブーム」が起き、同年には焼酎類全体の出荷量が日本酒の出荷量を約50年ぶりに上回り、2004年には売上高もピークを迎えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan there was &quot;Honkaku Shochu boom&quot; of shochu group Otsu since about 2003 and the total shipping volume of shochu exceeded that of rice wine for the first time after 50 years in 2003 and also the sales amount peaked in 2004.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan there was a &quot;Honkaku Shochu boom&quot; of the shochu group Otsu since about 2003 and the total shipping volume of shochu exceeded that of rice wine for the first time after fifty years in 2003 and the sales amount peaked in 2004.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan there was a &quot;Honkaku Shochu boom&quot; of the shochu group Otsu since about 2003 and the total shipping volume of shochu exceeded that of rice wine for the first time after fifty years in 2003 and the sales amount peaked in 2004.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="132">
<j>ブームに伴って、本格焼酎を専門に扱う焼酎バーも登場している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Along with the boom, shochu bars appeared specializing Honkaku Shochus.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Along with the boom, shochu bars appeared specializing in Honkaku Shochus.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Along with the boom, shochu bars appeared specializing in Honkaku Shochus.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="133">
<j>ブームの影響によって、材料や製法にこだわった焼酎も盛んに市場へと送り出されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of the boom, shochus focusing on ingredients and manufacturing process were also released more and more.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of the boom, shochu focusing on ingredients and the manufacturing process were also released more and more.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of the boom, shochu focusing on ingredients and the manufacturing process were also released more and more.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="134">
<j>鹿児島県で本格焼酎は1500円前後の商品が消費の中心であるが、より美味しい焼酎を望むニーズと、作り手のこだわりによって高価格で本格志向である味の焼酎も登場した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kogoshima Prefecture, products around 1500 yen are consumed mainly, but higher price and quality conscious taste shochus were released by the needs for better taste and enthusiasm of makers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Kogoshima Prefecture, products costing around 1500 yen are mainly consumed, but higher price and quality conscious taste shochu were released to meet the needs for better taste and from the enthusiasm of makers.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Kogoshima Prefecture, products costing around 1500 yen are mainly consumed, but higher price and quality conscious taste shochu were released to meet the needs for better taste and from the enthusiasm of makers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="135">
<j>しかし、少なからぬ弊害も生じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were also harmful effects considerably.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were also considerable harmful effects.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were also considerable harmful effects.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="136">
<j>ブームのピーク時には芋焼酎の原料となるサツマイモが市場に不足する深刻な問題が起きたほか、一部銘柄ではプレミアがつき、一本数万円などという値段が付けられるようになり、森伊蔵については偽物が出回る事件にまで発展した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the peak of the boom, it caused a serious lack of sweet potatoes from which sweet potato shochu was made, in the market and also because some brands were put premium and priced at tens of thousands of yen in bottle, it was developed into a case that counterfeits of Moriizo appeared on the market.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the peak of the boom, it caused a serious lack of sweet potatoes from which sweet potato shochu was made, in the market and also because some brands labeled premium and priced at tens of thousands of yen per bottle, counterfeit Moriizo appeared on the market.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the peak of the boom, it caused a serious lack of sweet potatoes from which sweet potato shochu was made, in the market and also because some brands labeled premium and priced at tens of thousands of yen per bottle, counterfeit Moriizo appeared on the market.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="137">
<j>日本銀行鹿児島支店が2008年2月に公表した、今回の焼酎ブームについてまとめたリポートでは「今回のブームは終焉した」と指摘、「銘柄選別の時代に入った」と結論付けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In February 2008, the Kagoshima branch of Back of Japan noted that the boom was over and concluded that a time of selecting brands has started in the report of this shochu boom.</e>
<cmt>「日本銀行鹿児島支店が2008年2月に公表した、今回の焼酎ブームについてまとめたリポート」が抜けていたので補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In February 2008, the Kagoshima branch of the Bank of Japan noted that the boom was over and concluded that a time of selecting brands has started in the report of this shochu boom.</e>
<cmt>spelling, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In February 2008, the Kagoshima branch of the Bank of Japan noted that the boom was over and concluded that a time of selecting brands has started in the report of this shochu boom.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Los688(id:12316), Takafumi0815(id:158795), Green3558(id:59508), KMT(id:1772), おはぐろ蜻蛉(id:8405), ＲＪＡＮＫＡ(id:118019), Ihsanan(id:30330), Shoppe(id:10574), 高橋隆司(id:141561), 秋の虹(id:18259), Toukiti(id:10643), Di5ide(id:114540), らりた(id:1327), Moriizou(id:88069), Michey.M(id:906), 秀の介(id:490), Knua(id:66861), BotMultichill(id:132395), Point136(id:211299), Sprinkler(id:14399), Iwai.masaharu(id:50663), あら金(id:10820), Jpatokal(id:1566), Brave7(id:129379), Starbacks(id:1018), Deepimpact(id:129352), Esperiment(id:223982), Complex01(id:10454), 織部(id:21104), Kahusi(id:1523), 茶務(id:48052), Tietew(id:4054), Baroquer(id:82044), R28Bot(id:177951), Metatron(id:64025), Hyolee2(id:16439), 相央暇人(id:91014), 秋葉原(id:104066), けんち(id:5147), Riden(id:27573), Bunama(id:22778), Bình Giang(id:217715), Extrahitz(id:26245), Roger(id:9883), Rikumio(id:99645), Kumatora(id:16941), Left or Right(id:86257), TXiKiBoT(id:107492), Syrotyna(id:21563), 無言雀師(id:13124), 焼酎ファン(id:54978), Bandalgom(id:31841), CasinoKat(id:43789), Loveless(id:129239), スミス16号(id:189050), 竹麦魚(id:11012), Bankokuya(id:91191), あばさー(id:95106), Lonicera(id:20638), 韓の子(id:35815), Nighthawks(id:36125), OiOiO(id:94238), Sat.K(id:3751), Yanahan(id:2437), 大星(id:29770), LaaknorBot(id:220851), あるふぁるふぁ(id:209526), 紅乙女(id:35717), Kamitani(id:30757), Eroro(id:18146), よしえもん(id:59920), Vill(id:84153), 佐伯(id:1787), Louperibot(id:128971), Miya.m(id:4662), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>