<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>肉じゃが</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nikujaga</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nikujaga</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nikujaga</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>肉じゃが（にくじゃが）とは日本料理のひとつである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nikujaga is a Japanese dish.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nikujaga is a Japanese dish.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nikujaga is a Japanese dish.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>牛肉または豚肉、ジャガイモ、タマネギ、糸こんにゃくなどを醤油、砂糖、みりんで甘煮にしたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A dish made of beef or pork, potatoes, onions, konnyaku noodles and other ingredients stewed together with soy sauce, sugar, and mirin (sweet cooking rice wine).</e>
<cmt>用語集にはkonnyakuとkonjacの二通りのスペルがありましたが、konnyakuを採用しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A dish made of beef or pork, potatoes, onions, konnyaku noodles and other ingredients stewed together with soy sauce, sugar, and mirin (sweet cooking rice wine).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A dish made of beef or pork, potatoes, onions, konnyaku noodles and other ingredients stewed together with soy sauce, sugar, and mirin (sweet cooking rice wine).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>肉は西日本では牛肉、東日本では豚肉を使うのが一般的である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is typical to use beef in western Japan and pork in eastern Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is typical to use beef in western Japan and pork in eastern Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is typical to use beef in western Japan and pork in eastern Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>大日本帝国海軍が発祥で、栄養価が高く、栄養バランスもよく、また海軍カレーと同じ素材を使うために補給の都合がよく、水兵の食事として全国的に導入された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It originates from Imperial Japanese Navy and was introduced as a dish for sailors because it was high in nutrition and well-balanced, and also because it was easy to supply ingredients as it uses the same ingredients as Navy curry.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It originated in the Imperial Japanese Navy and was introduced as a dish for sailors because it was high in nutrition and well-balanced, and also because it was easy to supply the ingredients as they were the same as Navy curry.</e>
<cmt>Imperial Japanese Navyに定冠詞を付与、時制の調整、その他。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It originated in the Imperial Japanese Navy and was introduced as a dish for sailors because it was high in nutrition and well-balanced, and also because it was easy to supply the ingredients as they were the same as Navy curry.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>誕生の経緯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Story about its Origin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Story about its Origin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Story about its Origin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>1870年から1878年までイギリスのポーツマス (イングランド)に留学していた東郷平八郎が留学先で食べたビーフシチューの味を非常に気に入り、日本へ帰国後、艦上食として作らせようとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Heihachiro TOGO who studied in Portsmouth, England from 1870 to 1878 very much liked the taste of beef stew he had there, and after he went back to Japan he tried to order to cook it as a dish on board.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Heihachiro TOGO, who studied in Portsmouth, England from 1870 to 1878, very much enjoyed beef stew he had there, and after he came back to Japan he tried to have it served as an on-board dish.</e>
<cmt>文の構成全体の見直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Heihachiro TOGO, who studied in Portsmouth, England from 1870 to 1878, very much enjoyed beef stew he had there, and after he came back to Japan he tried to have it served as an on-board dish.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>しかし、ワインもドミグラスソースも無く、そもそも命じられた料理長はビーフシチューなど知らなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However there was no wine or demiglace sauce, and the cook who was ordered to cook beef stew had no idea what it was in the first place.</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However there was no wine or demiglace sauce, and the head cook who was ordered to cook beef stew had no idea what it was in the first place.</e>
<cmt>原文は「料理長」になっているので、the cook を the head cook とした。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However there was no wine or demiglace sauce, and the head chef who was ordered to cook beef stew had no idea what it was in the first place.</e>
<cmt>head cook→head chef</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>（料理長が）東郷の話からイメージして醤油と砂糖を使って作ったのが始まりと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said the cook made the first nikujaga with soy sauce and sugar based on his imagination from what Togo told.</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said the head cook made the first nikujaga with soy sauce and sugar based on an image of beef stew which he built from the story given by Togo.</e>
<cmt>文の構成全体の見直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said the head chef made the first nikujaga with soy sauce and sugar based on an image of beef stew which he built from the story given by Togo.</e>
<cmt>head cook→head chef</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>この説を脚色されたものとするものもいるが、牛肉を醤油と砂糖で煮るのはすき焼きや牛肉の大和煮と同様の手法である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some say this is a dramatized story, but stewing beef with soy sauce and sugar is the same method used to cook sukiyaki (thin slices of beef, cooked with various vegetables in a table-top cast-iron pan) and yamatoni (beef cooked in soy sauce).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some say this is a dramatized story, but stewing beef with soy sauce and sugar is the same method used to cook sukiyaki (thin slices of beef, cooked with various vegetables in a table-top cast-iron pan) and yamatoni (beef cooked in soy sauce).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some say this is a dramatized story, but stewing beef with soy sauce and sugar is the same method used to cook sukiyaki (thin slices of beef, cooked with various vegetables in a table-top cast-iron pan) and yamatoni (beef cooked in soy sauce).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>海軍カレーと材料が同じ料理という事で軍隊食として非常に都合が良く（補給の際の物資の種類を制限できる）定着した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As it was very convenient as military food because it used the same ingredients as Navy curry (and can limit variety of supply), it became a regular meal in the Navy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As it was very easy to serve as military food because it used the same ingredients as Navy curry (capable of limiting the number of items to supply), it became a regular meal in the Navy.</e>
<cmt>文の構成全体の見直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As it was very easy to serve as military food because it used the same ingredients as Navy curry (capable of limiting the number of items to supply), it became a regular meal in the Navy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>ただし牛肉やじゃがいもという当時の日本人には馴染みの薄い食材を使うせいか、一般社会の食卓には定着しなかった（牛鍋は外食、牛肉の大和煮は缶詰料理であり、ともに家庭料理ではない）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However it did not become popular as a dish in general public probably because it uses beef and potatoes which were not yet familiar to the Japanese those days (gyunabe (Japanese hot pot with beef and vegetables) was for eating out and yamatoni was canned food, both of which are not home cooking).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However it did not become popular as a dish in the general public probably because it uses beef and potatoes which were not yet familiar to the Japanese those days (gyunabe (Japanese hot pot with beef and vegetables) was for eating out and yamatoni was canned food, both of which were not home cooking).</e>
<cmt>general publicの前に定冠詞を追加。are not home cooking を were not home cookingと時制を変更。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However it did not become popular as a dish in the general public probably because it uses beef and potatoes which were not yet familiar to the Japanese those days (gyunabe (Japanese hot pot with beef and vegetables) was for eating out and yamatoni was canned food, both of which were not home cooking).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>肉じゃがが戦後の空白の時代を経て家庭食として再登場するのは昭和30年代の後半であり、また実際に定番メニューとして定着したのは早くても昭和40年代の後半とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was in the beginning of 1960s when nikujaga came back as a home cooking after the blank of post war days, and it is said to be the first half of 1970s when it actually became a regular dish.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was in the beginning of 1960s when nikujaga came back as home cooking after the blank in post war days, and it is said that it was in the first half of 1970s at the earliest when it actually became a regular dish.</e>
<cmt>a home cookingから不定冠詞を除去。the blank of を the blank in に変更。その他、構成の見直し。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was in the beginning of 1960s when nikujaga came back as home cooking after the blank in post war days, and it is said that it was in the first half of 1970s at the earliest when it actually became a regular dish.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>今では「おふくろの味」の代名詞として家庭料理の代表作と呼ばれるまでになっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nikujaga is now a representing home cooking as a synonym of a &quot;good old home cooking&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nikujaga has become representative of home cooking as a synonym for &quot;good old home cooking.&quot;</e>
<cmt>文の構成全体の見直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nikujaga has become representative of home cooking as a synonym for &quot;good old home cooking.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>この流れはカレーライスの普及と時を同じくしており、食材の牛肉とじゃがいもが日本の家庭に定着するのと軌を一にしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This happened simultaneously with popularization of curry and rice and followed the same process as its ingredients beef and potatoes became popular at home in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Beaf stew and currey rice became popular at the same time, in sync with a trend that beef and potatoes, which are ingredients of both beaf stew and currey rice, became popular at home in Japan.</e>
<cmt>文の構成全体の見直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Beaf stew and currey rice became popular at the same time, in sync with a trend that beef and potatoes, which are ingredients of both beaf stew and currey rice, became popular at home in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>当時は「甘煮」として人気を博した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nikujaga was called &quot;amani (sweet pot)&quot; and became popular.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nikujaga was called &quot;amani (sweet pot)&quot; at the time and was very popular.</e>
<cmt>文の構成見直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nikujaga was called &quot;amani (sweet pot)&quot; at the time and was very popular.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>海軍厨業管理教科書</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;The Textbook of Cooking at Navy&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;The Textbook of Cooking at Navy&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;The Textbook of Cooking at Navy&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="16">
<j>海軍経理学校で1938年に刊行された海軍厨業管理教科書（舞鶴総監部保管）にはレシピが次のように紹介されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Following is the recipe of nikujaga in &quot;The Textbook of Cooking at Navy&quot; published in 1938 at the Naval Paymasters&apos; School:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following is the recipe of nikujaga in &quot;The Textbook of Cooking at Navy&quot; published in 1938 by the Naval Paymasters&apos; School (held in Maritime Self-Defense Force Maizuru District Headquarters):</e>
<cmt>訳漏れあり。「舞鶴総監部保管」の訳がありませんが追加しておきました。followingの前に定冠詞を追加。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following is the recipe of nikujaga in &quot;The Textbook of Cooking at Navy&quot; published in 1938 by the Naval Paymasters&apos; School (held in Maritime Self-Defense Force Maizuru District Headquarters):</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="17">
<j>油入れ送気</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Add oil and send blow the bellow.</e>
<cmt>送気＝カマドの火にふいごで空気を送る（そして火を強める）ことと解釈しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Add oil and supply with air.</e>
<cmt>英次郎にある「送気する= supply with air」を採用。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Add oil and supply with air.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>3分後生牛肉入れ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Add beef after 3 minutes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Add beef after 3 minutes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Add beef after 3 minutes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>7分後砂糖入れ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Add sugar after 7 minutes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Add sugar after 7 minutes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Add sugar after 7 minutes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>10分後醤油入れ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Add soy sauce after 10 minutes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Add soy sauce after 10 minutes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Add soy sauce after 10 minutes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>14分後こんにゃく、馬鈴薯入れ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Add konnyaku and potatoes after 14 minutes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Add konnyaku and potatoes after 14 minutes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Add konnyaku and potatoes after 14 minutes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>31分後玉葱入れ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Add onions after 31 minutes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Add onions after 31 minutes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Add onions after 31 minutes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>34分後終了</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Finish cooking after 34 minutes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Finish cooking after 34 minutes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Finish cooking after 34 minutes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>発祥の地論争</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Disputes on its Origin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Disputes on its Origin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Disputes on its Origin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="24">
<j>京都府舞鶴市が1995年10月に「肉じゃが発祥の地」を宣言。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Maizuru City, Kyoto Prefecture declared to be the &quot;birthplace of nikujaga&quot; in October 1995.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Maizuru City, Kyoto Prefecture declared the city to be the &quot;birthplace of nikujaga&quot; in October, 1995.</e>
<cmt>declaredの後ろにthe cityを追加。Octoberの後ろにカンマを挿入</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Maizuru City, Kyoto Prefecture declared the city to be the &quot;birthplace of nikujaga&quot; in October, 1995.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>1998年3月に広島県呉市も「肉じゃが発祥の地?」（最初に宣言した舞鶴市に配慮して?をつけた）として名乗りを上げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kure City, Hiroshima Prefecture also declared itself to be a &quot;birthplace of nikujaga?&quot; (added &quot;?&quot; in consideration for Maizuru City that made the first declaration).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kure City, Hiroshima Prefecture also declared itself to be the &quot;birthplace of nikujaga?&quot; (added &quot;?&quot; in consideration for Maizuru City, which made the first declaration).</e>
<cmt>birth placeの冠詞を a からtheに変更。文中におけるMaizuru Cityの修飾方法を変更。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kure City, Hiroshima Prefecture also declared itself to be the &quot;birthplace of nikujaga?&quot; (added &quot;?&quot; in consideration for Maizuru City, which made the first declaration).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="26">
<j>根拠は、以下のとおりである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Their groundings are as follows.</e>
<cmt>後列の「～としている。」を統合して「以下のとおりである」としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their grounds are as follows.</e>
<cmt>groundingsを groundsに変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Their grounds are as follows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>舞鶴市：東郷平八郎が初めて司令長官として赴任したのが舞鶴鎮守府であり、現存する最古の肉じゃがのレシピが舞鶴鎮守府所属艦艇で炊烹員をしていた故人から舞鶴総監部に寄贈されたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Maizuru City: Maizuru Chinjufu (navy base) was the first place where Heihachiro TOGO was appointed as admiral, and existing oldest recipe of nikujaga was donated to Maizuru District Headquarters by the deceased who used to be a cook on the naval vessel belonging to Maizuru Chinjufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Maizuru City: Maizuru Chinjufu (a navy base) was the first place of Heihachiro TOGO&apos;s assignment as Admiral, and the oldest existing recipe of nikujaga was donated to Maizuru District Headquarters by the deceased who used to be a cook on a naval vessel belonging to Maizuru Chinjufu.</e>
<cmt>文の構成の全体的見直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Maizuru City: Maizuru Chinjufu (a navy base) was the first place of Heihachiro TOGO&apos;s assignment as Admiral, and the oldest existing recipe of nikujaga was donated to Maizuru District Headquarters by the deceased who used to be a cook on a naval vessel belonging to Maizuru Chinjufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="28">
<j>呉市：舞鶴赴任より10年前に呉鎮守府の参謀長として赴任している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kure City: Togo was appointed chief of staff of Kure Chinjufu ten years before he was appointed to Maizuru.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kure City: Togo was appointed chief of staff of Kure Chinjufu ten years before he was dispatched to Maizuru.</e>
<cmt>appointed to Maizuru を dispatched to Maizuru に変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kure City: Togo was appointed chief of staff of Kure Chinjufu ten years before he was dispatched to Maizuru.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="29">
<j>しかしながら資料が曖昧であり、最古のレシピが本当に舞鶴で作られたものなのか他の鎮守府から伝わったレシピを書き写したものではないのかという論争が決着していないため、両市とも大岡裁き的に「舞鶴・呉の双方が発祥地」としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as the data is precise and the dispute is not yet settled if the oldest recipe was really written in Maizuru or copied from a recipe passed from another chinjufu, both cities made a decision worthy of Solomon saying &quot;both Maizuru and Kure are birthplaces&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as the data is unclear and the dispute is not yet settled if the oldest recipe was really written in Maizuru or copied from a recipe having been passed from another chinjufu, both cities have made a decision worthy of Solomon, saying &quot;both Maizuru and Kure are the birthplace.&quot;</e>
<cmt>preciseをunclearに変更。その他、文の構成の見直し。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as the data is unclear and the dispute is not yet settled if the oldest recipe was really written in Maizuru or copied from a recipe having been passed from another chinjufu, both cities have made a decision worthy of Solomon, saying &quot;both Maizuru and Kure are the birthplace.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>以上の詳細は高森直史の『海軍 肉じゃが物語 ルーツ発掘者が語る海軍食文化史』（光人社 2006年）に詳しい叙述がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Detail of the above mentioned story is found in &quot;Navy Nikujaga Story: a Root Finder Tells a History of Food Culture in the Navy&quot; (Kojinsha, 2006).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Details of the above mentioned story are found in &quot;Navy Nikujaga Story: a Root Finder Tells a History of Food Culture in the Navy&quot; (Kojinsha, 2006).</e>
<cmt>detailをdetailsに変更（複数化）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Details of the above mentioned story are found in &quot;Navy Nikujaga Story: a Root Finder Tells a History of Food Culture in the Navy&quot; (Kojinsha, 2006).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>現在は舞鶴、呉がライバル関係をアピールしながら連携して肉じゃがと海軍ゆかりの街をアピールする活動が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today we see many activities in which Maizuru and Kure collaboratively promote nikujaga and their relations to the Navy enforcing their rivalry.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today we see many activities in which Maizuru and Kure collaborate with each other to gain attention for nikujaga and their cities associated with the Imperial Japanese Navy, while announcing they are in rivalry.</e>
<cmt>文の構成全体の見直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today we see many activities in which Maizuru and Kure collaborate with each other to gain attention for nikujaga and their cities associated with the Imperial Japanese Navy, while announcing they are in rivalry.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Los688(id:12316), Takoradee(id:82103), Ypacaraí(id:11031), ミソージル(id:20227), Charenji(id:7908), PATMAN(id:145791), Roger(id:9883), Kumatora(id:16941), ダニーワイルド(id:27783), Mishika(id:276), Hykw-a4(id:14184), やきとり(id:126941), 橄欖岩(id:24996), Nobue216bton(id:313430), Mitiwota(id:74485), Sea of Japan(id:3230), Bankokuya(id:91191), Kentin(id:6768), BoB774(id:148281), 万華鏡(id:24615), マクガイア(id:33346), WarddrBOT(id:105894), Miita(id:30561), Miyabi(id:967), Baldanders(id:81163), Himetv(id:21833), Shota(id:10854), VolkovBot(id:105371), Fromm(id:71291), TaBOT-zerem(id:257085), RIK 2(id:12097), KSKS(id:97637), Boberi(id:166163), 本屋(id:125948), SEKIUCHI(id:637), Iburi(id:48097), けんち(id:5147), Tokyosaka(id:139922), Khaosan Lover(id:161770), 1029man(id:93235), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>