<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>贈位</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zoui (conferral of a posthumous rank)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zoi (conferral of a posthumous rank)</e>
<cmt>Zoui を Zoi に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zoi (conferral of a posthumous rank)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>贈位（ぞうい）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zoui</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zoi</e>
<cmt>Zoui を Zoi に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zoi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>生前の功績に対して、没後に位階を贈ること。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zoui is awarding of a rank posthumously according to one&apos;s lifetime achievements.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zoi is awarding of a rank posthumously according to one&apos;s lifetime achievements.</e>
<cmt>Zoui を Zoi に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zoi is awarding of a rank posthumously according to one&apos;s lifetime achievements.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>追贈ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also referred to as &quot;tsuizo.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also referred to as &quot;tsuizo&quot; (conferring court rank posthumously).</e>
<cmt>(conferring court rank posthumously) を追記しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also referred to as &quot;tsuizo&quot; (conferring court rank posthumously).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>将棋や囲碁の大会に優勝し、タイトルを贈られること。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zoui means to receive a title when one wins in a Shogi (Japanese Chess) or Igo (board game of capturing territory) tournament.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zoi means to receive a title when one wins in a Shogi (Japanese Chess) or Igo (board game of capturing territory) tournament.</e>
<cmt>Zoui を Zoi に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zoi means to receive a title when one wins in a Shogi (Japanese Chess) or Igo (board game of capturing territory) tournament.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>就位ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also referred to as &quot;shui.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also referred to as &quot;shui.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also referred to as &quot;shui.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="6">
<j>位階における贈位</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zoui depending upon one&apos;s rank</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zoi depending upon one&apos;s rank</e>
<cmt>Zoui を Zoi に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zoi depending upon one&apos;s rank</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="7">
<j>以下、贈位の概要及び変遷について概説する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zoui and its history will be summarized as follows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zoi and its history will be summarized as follows.</e>
<cmt>Zoui を Zoi に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zoi and its history will be summarized as follows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="8">
<j>贈位のはじまり</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Start of Zoui</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Start of Zoi</e>
<cmt>Zoui を Zoi に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Start of Zoi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="9">
<j>天武天皇2年（673年）2月、壬申の乱の功臣であった坂本財が薨じ、大臣級の冠位であったことから小紫位を贈られたのにはじまる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It originates in February of 673, when SAKAMOTO no Takara who was a meritorious retainer of the Jinshin War passed away and was given shoshi no kurai, for he held a ministerial rank.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It originates in February of 673, when SAKAMOTO no Takara who was a meritorious retainer of the Jinshin War passed away and was given shoshi no kurai, for he held a ministerial rank.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It originates in February of 673, when SAKAMOTO no Takara who was a meritorious retainer of the Jinshin War passed away and was given shoshi no kurai, for he held a ministerial rank.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>その後、百済の沙宅昭明が没して外小紫位を贈られ、壬申の乱の功臣や渡来人に対して盛んに贈位が行われるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, Jomyo SATAKKU from Kudara (Baekje, Paekche) was given tono shoshi no kurai, and zoui was frequently carried out to meritorious retainers of the Jinshin War and toraijin (people from overseas, especially from China and Korea, who settled in early Japan and introduced Continental culture to the Japanese).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, Jomyo SATAKKU from Baekje was given tono shoshi no kurai, and zoi was frequently carried out to meritorious retainers of the Jinshin War and toraijin (people from overseas, especially from China and Korea, who settled in early Japan and introduced Continental culture to Japan).</e>
<cmt>Kudara (Baekje, Paekche) を Baekje に修正しました。Zoui を Zoi に修正しました。to the Japanese に to Japan に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, Jomyo SATAKKU from Baekje was given tono shoshi no kurai, and zoi was frequently carried out to meritorious retainers of the Jinshin War and toraijin (people from overseas, especially from China and Korea, who settled in early Japan and introduced Continental culture to Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>『養老令』『大宝令』では、戦死による贈位の場合、その子・孫への蔭位は、生前の帯位と同等とし、それ以外の贈位の場合、蔭位は通常の位階より一階降して授けることとされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is stipulated in &quot;Yoro-ryo&quot; (Yoro Code) and &quot;Taiho-ryo&quot; (Taiho Code) that in the case of zoui due to death at war, Oni (the automatic promotion of the persons at the age of 21, whose parents are from Imperial Prince to the fifth rank, or whose grandparents are upper than third rank) to his children and grandchildren would be equal to the rank he held while he was alive, and in other cases, Oni was usually with a rank, one lower to the rank which would normally be bestowed upon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is stipulated in &quot;Yoro-ryo&quot; (Yoro Code) and &quot;Taiho-ryo&quot; (Taiho Code) that in the case of zoi due to death at war, Oni (the automatic promotion of the persons at the age of 21, whose parents are from Imperial Prince to the fifth rank, or whose grandparents are upper than third rank) to his children and grandchildren would be equal to the rank he held while he was alive, and in other cases, Oni was usually with a rank, one lower to the rank which would normally be bestowed upon.</e>
<cmt>Zoui を Zoi に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is stipulated in &quot;Yoro-ryo&quot; (Yoro Code) and &quot;Taiho-ryo&quot; (Taiho Code) that in the case of zoi due to death at war, Oni (the automatic promotion of the persons at the age of 21, whose parents are from Imperial Prince to the fifth rank, or whose grandparents are upper than third rank) to his children and grandchildren would be equal to the rank he held while he was alive, and in other cases, Oni was usually with a rank, one lower to the rank which would normally be bestowed upon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="12">
<j>以後、贈位は亡くなった高位の貴族への恩典として、さらには無実の罪で亡くなった者、或いは派遣途上でなくなった遣唐使の慰霊や名誉回復を目的で行われるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From then on, zoui became a special dispensation for high ranked nobles that have passed away; moreover, it began to be carried out for the purposes of comforting the spirit and restoring impaired reputations of those who died on false charges, or for the Kento-shi (Japanese envoy to Tang Dynasty China) who died in their journey.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From then on, zoi became a special dispensation for high ranked nobles that have passed away; moreover, it began to be carried out for the purposes of comforting the spirit and restoring impaired reputations of those who died on false charges, or for the Kento-shi (Japanese envoy to Tang Dynasty China) who died in their journey.</e>
<cmt>Zoui を Zoi に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From then on, zoi became a special dispensation for high ranked nobles that have passed away; moreover, it began to be carried out for the purposes of comforting the spirit and restoring impaired reputations of those who died on false charges, or for the Kento-shi (Japanese envoy to Tang Dynasty China) who died in their journey.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="13">
<j>贈位の場合、通常の位階の上に「贈」の字を加える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the case of zoui, the letter &apos;贈&apos; is added at the head of the ordinary rank.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the case of zoi, the letter &apos;贈&apos; is added at the head of the ordinary rank.</e>
<cmt>Zoui を Zoi に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the case of zoi, the letter &apos;贈&apos; is added at the head of the ordinary rank.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>『例：贈正四位』。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;For example: 贈正四位&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;For example: Shoshii (Senior Fourth Rank), posthumously conferred&quot;.</e>
<cmt>贈正四位 を Shoshii (Senior Fourth Rank), posthumously conferred に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;For example: Shoshii (Senior Fourth Rank), posthumously conferred&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>なお、官職を贈る場合は贈官という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, when a government post is conferred, it is referred to as &quot;zokan.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, when a government post is conferred, it is referred to as &quot;zokan.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, when a government post is conferred, it is referred to as &quot;zokan.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>『例：贈太政大臣』。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;For example: 贈大政大臣&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;For example: Daijo-daijin (Grand Minister), posthumously conferred&quot;.</e>
<cmt>贈大政大臣 を Daijo-daijin (Grand Minister), posthumously conferred に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;For example: Daijo-daijin (Grand Minister), posthumously conferred&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="17">
<j>明治以降の贈位</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zoui from the Meiji era</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zoi after the Meiji period</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zoi after the Meiji period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="18">
<j>明治時代以降も引き続き死者の功績を称える目的で贈位が行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zoui also continued from the Meiji era for the purpose of commemorating the deeds of the deceased.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zoi has been continued also after the Meiji period for the purpose of commemorating the deeds of the deceased.</e>
<cmt>前半部を全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zoi has been continued also after the Meiji period for the purpose of commemorating the deeds of the deceased.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>特に幕末の尊皇攘夷や明治維新で功績を挙げながら亡くなった者、または南北朝時代の南朝方の公卿や武将への贈位も盛んに行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was frequently carried out especially for those who died while rendering great achievements during Sonno Joi (19th century slogan advocating reverence for the Emperor and the expulsion of foreigners) that took place at the end of Edo period and the Meiji Restoration, or to those court nobles and warlords of the Southern court during the period of the Northern and Southern Courts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was frequently carried out especially for those who died while rendering great achievements during Sonno Joi (19th century slogan advocating reverence for the Emperor and the expulsion of foreigners) that took place at the end of Edo period and the Meiji Restoration, or to those court nobles and warlords of the Southern court during the period of the Northern and Southern Courts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was frequently carried out especially for those who died while rendering great achievements during Sonno Joi (19th century slogan advocating reverence for the Emperor and the expulsion of foreigners) that took place at the end of Edo period and the Meiji Restoration, or to those court nobles and warlords of the Southern court during the period of the Northern and Southern Courts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>贈位は原則として従五位以上とされたが、明治2年（1869年）の官位制度改革以後は従四位以上の適用となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a general rule, ranks for zoui was Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank) or higher, but from the reformation of official rank system in 1869, ranks Jushii (Junior Fourth Rank) or higher were applied.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a general rule, ranks for zoi was Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank) or higher, but from the reformation of official rank system in 1869, ranks Jushii (Junior Fourth Rank) or higher were applied.</e>
<cmt>Zoui を Zoi に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a general rule, ranks for zoi was Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank) or higher, but from the reformation of official rank system in 1869, ranks Jushii (Junior Fourth Rank) or higher were applied.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>明治28年（1895年）、「戦死者贈位並叙位ノ件」が制定されたのに伴い、功績抜群なる軍人が戦死した場合は生前の位階に関わらず従五位以上を贈るものとし、準ずるものは生前の位階を一級ないし二級特進させることとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since &apos;Senshisha zoui narabi joi no ken&apos; (Matter for conferring and investiture of court ranks to those who died in the war) was enacted in 1895, when a military man with distinguished performance died in a war, Jugoi or higher was bestowed irrespective of the rank before his death, and those pursuant would receive an accelerated promotion by one or two ranks higher to the rank held before death.</e>
<cmt>「戦死者贈位並叙位ノ件」の読み方、定訳が不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since &apos;Senshisha zoi narabi joi no ken&apos; (Matter for conferring and investiture of court ranks to those who died in the war) was enacted in 1895, when a military man with distinguished performance died in a war, Jugoi or higher was bestowed irrespective of the rank before his death, and those pursuant would receive an accelerated promotion by one or two ranks higher to the rank held before death.</e>
<cmt>Zoui を Zoi に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since &apos;Senshisha zoi narabi joi no ken&apos; (Matter for conferring and investiture of court ranks to those who died in the war) was enacted in 1895, when a military man with distinguished performance died in a war, Jugoi or higher was bestowed irrespective of the rank before his death, and those pursuant would receive an accelerated promotion by one or two ranks higher to the rank held before death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>明治30年（1897年）戦死者贈位並叙位進階内則」では、将官は正四位以上、佐官は従五位から正四位の間、尉官は従五位から正五位の間、准士官、下士官、兵卒は従五位を贈るとされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the &apos;Senshisha zoui narabi joi shinkai naisoku&apos; (Rules for conferring of court ranks to those who died in the war and investiture of promotion) that was enacted in 1897, it was stipulated that Shoshiinojo (Senior Fourth Rank Upper Grade) was given to generals, ranks between Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank) and Shoshiinojo was given to field officers, ranks between Shogoi (Senior Fifth Rank) and Shoshiinojo were given to officers below the rank of major, and Jugoi was given to under-officers, noncommissioned officers, and soldiers.</e>
<cmt>「戦死者贈位並叙位ノ件」の読み方、定訳が不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the &apos;Senshisha zoi narabi joi shinkai naisoku&apos; (Rules for conferring of court ranks to those who died in the war and investiture of promotion) that was enacted in 1897, it was stipulated that Shoshii (Senior Fourth Rank) or higher was given to generals, ranks between Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank) and Shoshii was given to field officers, ranks between Jugoi and Shogoi (Senior Fifth Rank) were given to officers below the rank of major, and Jugoi was given to under-officers, noncommissioned officers, and soldiers.</e>
<cmt>Zoui を Zoi に修正しました。官位の部分を全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the &apos;Senshisha zoi narabi joi shinkai naisoku&apos; (Rules for conferring of court ranks to those who died in the war and investiture of promotion) that was enacted in 1897, it was stipulated that Shoshii (Senior Fourth Rank) or higher was given to generals, ranks between Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank) and Shoshii was given to field officers, ranks between Jugoi and Shogoi (Senior Fifth Rank) were given to officers below the rank of major, and Jugoi was given to under-officers, noncommissioned officers, and soldiers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>明治時代は栄典大権は天皇に属するものであり、贈位は内閣賞勲局が担当したが、太平洋戦争後、生存者に対する叙位が停止したのに伴い、贈位も一時停止状態となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Meiji period, the prerogatives of honoring belonged to the Emperor, and Decoration Bureau of the cabinet was in charge of zoui, but as joi for the survivors was suspended after the Pacific war, zoui also stopped at one point.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Meiji period, the prerogatives of honoring belonged to the Emperor, and Decoration Bureau of the cabinet was in charge of zoi, but as joi for the survivors was suspended after the Pacific War, zoi also stopped at one point.</e>
<cmt>Zoui を Zoi に修正しました。Pacific war を Pacific War に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Meiji period, the prerogatives of honoring belonged to the Emperor, and Decoration Bureau of the cabinet was in charge of zoi, but as joi for the survivors was suspended after the Pacific War, zoi also stopped at one point.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="24">
<j>今日までの変遷</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History until the present day</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Transition till today</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Transition till today</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="25">
<j>昭和39年（1963年）、池田勇人内閣において「戦没者に対する叙位叙勲について」が閣議決定され、第二次世界大戦の戦死者に対する叙位叙勲が復活する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Investiture of Court ranks and bestowal of orders to those who had died in a war&apos; was approved during the Hayato IKEDA&apos;s cabinet in 1963, and the bestowing a rank and conferment of a decoration to those who died while serving in World War II resumed.</e>
<cmt>「戦死者贈位並叙位ノ件」の読み方、定訳が不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Investiture of Court ranks and bestowal of orders to those who had died in a war&apos; was approved during the Hayato IKEDA&apos;s cabinet in 1963, and the bestowing a rank and conferment of a decoration to those who died while serving in World War II resumed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Investiture of Court ranks and bestowal of orders to those who had died in a war&apos; was approved during the Hayato IKEDA&apos;s cabinet in 1963, and the bestowing a rank and conferment of a decoration to those who died while serving in World War II resumed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>以後、位階は死没者にのみ贈られるものとなり、生存者に対し叙位が適用されなくなったため、通常の叙位が明治以前の贈位の機能を果たしている（但し、贈位とは異なり、叙位では「贈」の字は用いられない）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, court ranks were bestowed only to the deceased, and since the court ranks were no longer conferred to the survivors, standard form of joi served as a means of zoui before the Meiji era (however, unlike zoui, the letter &apos;贈&apos; is not used in joi).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, court ranks were bestowed only to the deceased, and since the court ranks were no longer conferred to the survivors, standard form of joi served as a means of zoi before the Meiji period (however, unlike zoi, the letter &apos;贈&apos; is not used in joi).</e>
<cmt>zoui を zoi に修正しました。era を period に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, court ranks were bestowed only to the deceased, and since the court ranks were no longer conferred to the survivors, standard form of joi served as a means of zoi before the Meiji period (however, unlike zoi, the letter &apos;贈&apos; is not used in joi).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="27">
<j>将棋における贈位</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zoui in Shogi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zoui in Shogi</e>
<cmt>Zoui を Zoi に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zoui in Shogi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="28">
<j>将棋の分野では、竜王、王将などのタイトルを取得した勝者に与えられるタイトルの授与を記した文書を贈位状という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the field of Shogi, zoijo means a document that shows conferment of titles to the winners which have gained the titles including ryuo (promoted rook), osho (king), and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the field of Shogi, zoijo means a document that shows conferment of titles to the winners which have gained the titles including ryuo (promoted rook), osho (king), and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the field of Shogi, zoijo means a document that shows conferment of titles to the winners which have gained the titles including ryuo (promoted rook), osho (king), and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 海衛士(id:19229), Jade0416(id:104181), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>