<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>流儀</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryugi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryugi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryugi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>流儀（りゅうぎ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryugi (style)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryugi (style)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryugi (style)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>日本の芸能や武術などにおいて、ひとつの分野について他との技術、手法、心構え、表現の目的、表現にあたっての解釈などの差異を理由として形成された集団。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Ryugi&quot; represents groups of people in Japanese performing arts and martial arts, each formed based on differences from other groups in techniques, approaches, purposes of expression, interpretation of arts to be expressed and so forth on one field of the arts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Ryugi&quot; represents groups of people in Japanese performing arts and martial arts, each formed based on differences from other groups in techniques, approaches, purposes of expression, interpretation of arts to be expressed and so forth in one field of the arts.</e>
<cmt>preposition</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Ryugi&quot; represents groups of people in Japanese performing arts and martial arts, each formed based on differences from other groups in techniques, approaches, purposes of expression, interpretation of arts to be expressed and so forth in one field of the arts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>またはその集団が奉ずる芸道に対する考えかた、取組みかたそのもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryugi also directly means the concept and attitude the group embraces toward the art.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryugi also directly means the concept and attitude the group embraces toward the art.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryugi also directly means the concept and attitude the group embraces toward the art.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>流派とほぼ同義。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryugi means almost the same as &quot;Ryuha&quot; (school).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryugi means almost the same as &quot;Ryuha&quot; (school).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryugi means almost the same as &quot;Ryuha&quot; (school).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>本項で説明する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This article explains this term.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This article explains this term.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This article explains this term.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>1から転じて、あるものに対するその人なりのやりかたを比喩的に言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term &quot;ryugi&quot; is extended from the meaning described in above 1, to mean figuratively one&apos;s own approach for doing a certain thing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term &quot;ryugi&quot; is extended from the meaning described in 1 above, to mean figuratively one&apos;s own approach for doing a certain thing.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term &quot;ryugi&quot; is extended from the meaning described in the above, to mean figuratively one&apos;s own approach for doing a certain thing.</e>
<cmt>1→the</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>基本的に、流儀は芸道における家元制度によって形成されるものであるので、それが存在する分野などについてはこれらの項目を参照されたい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Basically, since ryugi is established in the iemoto system in arts (the system of licensing the teaching of a traditional Japanese art), refer to the articles relevant to the iemoto system for information about fields of arts which include ryugi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Basically, since ryugi is established in the iemoto system in arts (the system of licensing the teaching of a traditional Japanese art), refer to the articles relevant to the iemoto system for information about fields of arts which include ryugi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Basically, since ryugi is established in the iemoto system in arts (the system of licensing the teaching of a traditional Japanese art), refer to the articles relevant to the iemoto system for information about fields of arts which include ryugi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>流儀とは、一言でいえば、あるものをどう行うか（敵とどう戦うか、ある戯曲をどう演じるか）ということについて個人の一代の技能でなく、ある一定の技術論に基づく技術が、集団的、伝統的に共有されている技能共同体を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To put it simply, ryugi is not one person&apos;s techniques for doing a certain thing (such as how to fight against enemies and how to perform a play) which last only in his lifetim, but fellowship in which a group of people traditionally share techniques based on a certain art theory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To put it simply, ryugi is not one person&apos;s techniques for doing a certain thing (such as how to fight against enemies and how to perform a play) which last only in his lifetime, but fellowship in which a group of people traditionally share techniques based on a certain art theory.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To put it simply, ryugi is not one person&apos;s techniques for doing a certain thing (such as how to fight against enemies and how to perform a play) which last only in his lifetime, but fellowship in which a group of people traditionally share techniques based on a certain art theory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>各流派の技術論の相違はなはだしく広く、分野ごとに多様である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Theories greatly differ among the respective schools, and include a broad variation in each field of arts.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Theories greatly differ among the respective schools, and include broad variation in each field of art.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Theories greatly differ among the respective schools, and include broad variation in each field of art.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>たとえば能であれば、所縁曲の相違、使用する謡曲の相違、戯曲に対する解釈の相違、舞の調子や工夫の相違、装束の選びかたの相違などがあげられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, in case of Noh, there are differences in music, songs used in dramas, interpretation of dramas, tones and ideas for dances, selection of costumes and so on among the schools.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, in case of Noh, schools have differences in music, songs used in dramas, interpretation of dramas, tones and ideas for dances, selection of costumes, and so on.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, in case of Noh, schools have differences in music, songs used in dramas, interpretation of dramas, tones and ideas for dances, selection of costumes, and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>これからもわかるように、能ならば能という対象はどの流儀にも共通するのに対して、それにいかに演ずるかの技術が異なるところに流儀というものの源流があるといってよい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As understood from this, in case of Noh, all of the Noh schools share the art of Noh while they differ in techniques for performing Noh dramas, from which each ryugi can be said to originate.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As understood from this, in the case of Noh, all of the Noh schools share the art of Noh while they differ in techniques for performing Noh dramas, from which each ryugi can be said to originate.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As understood from this, in the case of Noh, all of the Noh schools share the art of Noh while they differ in techniques for performing Noh dramas, from which each ryugi can be said to originate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>その点については芸術や技術的なすべての分野について洋の東西を問わず、こうした現象は見られるものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such a trend can be observed in all fields of arts and techniques in all countries.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such a trend can be observed in all fields of art and techniques in all countries.</e>
<cmt>singular</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such a trend can be observed in all fields of art and techniques in all countries.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>例えば近代以降のクラシック音楽ならば「個人的な解釈の違い」となるべきところを、集団で、伝統としてある程度、固定化して引継いでゆくところに流儀というものの特異性があるといっていい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryugi is unique in that the differences from other schools are fixed to some degree and handed down as traditions within the group while for example, western classical music of modern age and thereafter, differences in interpretation of music is considered to be only &quot;personal&quot;.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryugi is unique in that the differences from other schools are fixed to some degree and handed down as traditions within the group, while, for example, in western classical music of modern age and thereafter, differences in interpretation of music are considered to be only &quot;personal&quot;.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryugi is unique in that the differences from other schools are fixed to some degree and handed down as traditions within the group, while, for example, in western classical music of modern age and thereafter, differences in interpretation of music are considered to be only &quot;personal&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="14">
<j>制度としての流儀は、基本的に二つの要素によって成り立っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryugi as a system basically consists of two elements.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryugi as a system basically consists of two elements.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryugi as a system basically consists of two elements.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>一はその芸系の同一性であり、一はこれを実質的に保存し受継いでゆくための集団としての存在である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One is uniformity in the art style of each ryugi and the other is existence of the group of people who actually preserve and carry on the style.</e>
<cmt>「芸系」貴社用語検索ではentertainment systemと訳出してありましたが、文脈により適合するよう（この文脈ではentertainmentだけが「芸」ではない）ので別の言葉で訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One is uniformity in the art style of each ryugi and the other is existence of the group of people who actually preserve and carry on the style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One is uniformity in the art style of each ryugi and the other is existence of the group of people who actually preserve and carry on the style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>そして、前者の技芸的側面と、後者の制度的側面をともに管理し、その永続を保障するべき機関として家元というものが存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Iemoto (the head family of a school) exists as an authority which should monitor both the former, the artistic aspect, and the latter, the institutional aspect, in order to ensure that both may last long.</e>
<cmt>「技芸的側面」「制度的側面」貴社用語検索では別の訳語で訳出してありましたが、それぞれ　文脈により適合するよう、the artistic aspect, the institutional aspect　としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Iemoto (the head family of a school) exists as an authority which should monitor both the former, the artistic aspect, and the latter, the institutional aspect, in order to ensure that both may last long.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Iemoto (the head family of a school) exists as an authority which should monitor both the former, the artistic aspect, and the latter, the institutional aspect, in order to ensure that both may last long.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>ゆえに流儀という制度には家元もしくはそれに類する存在（たとえば職分会等の機関）が絶対に必要である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, iemoto or an entity equal thereto (such as organizations like shokubunkai (gathering of a school&apos;s occupational branch family) is indispensable for the ryugi system.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, iemoto or an entity equivalent thereto (such as organizations like shokubunkai (gathering of a school&apos;s occupational branch family)) is indispensable for the ryugi system.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, iemoto or an entity equivalent thereto (such as organizations like shokubunkai (gathering of a school&apos;s occupational branch family)) is indispensable for the ryugi system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>家元制度を抜きにして流儀を語ることは不可能である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, ryugi cannot be explained without referring to the iemoto system.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, ryugi cannot be explained without referring to the iemoto system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, ryugi cannot be explained without referring to the iemoto system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="19">
<j>ある分野について傑出した新しい技術をあみ出したものは、だれでも自分が家元となって流儀を創設することができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Anyone that invents novel and remarkable techniques in a field can establish a ryugi in which he or she is iemoto.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Anyone that invents novel and remarkable techniques in a field can establish a ryugi in which he or she is iemoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Anyone that invents novel and remarkable techniques in a field can establish a ryugi in which he or she is iemoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="20">
<j>実際にはこうした行動が比較的容易である分野とそうではない分野がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In some fields, however, such an action is not easy in reality while in other fields, it is relatively easy.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In some fields, however, such an action is not easy in reality, while in other fields it is relatively easy.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In some fields, however, such an action is not easy in reality, while in other fields it is relatively easy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>たとえば能のシテ方に梅若流が設立されたときには、ワキ方や囃子方が旧来のシテ方五流に同調して共演を拒否し、実質上演能不能の状態に陥ったために、最終的に梅若流の分派行動は失敗におわった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, when Umewaka-ryu was established as a ryugi of shite-kata (main roles) in Noh, waki-kata (supporting actors) and hayashi-kata (players for musical accompaniment), sympathizing with conventional five styles of shite-kata, refused to costar or play with Umewaka-ryu, forcing the new ryugi to give up playing any Noh play, and thus Umewaka-ryu&apos;s attempt to establish a new branch school ended in failure.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, when Umewaka-ryu was established as a ryugi of shite-kata (main roles) in Noh, waki-kata (supporting actors) and hayashi-kata (players for musical accompaniment), sympathizing with the five conventional styles of shite-kata, refused to costar or play with Umewaka-ryu, forcing the new ryugi to give up performing any Noh play, and thus Umewaka-ryu&apos;s attempt to establish a new branch school ended in failure.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, when Umewaka-ryu was established as a ryugi of shite-kata (main roles) in Noh, waki-kata (supporting actors) and hayashi-kata (players for musical accompaniment), sympathizing with the five conventional styles of shite-kata, refused to costar or play with Umewaka-ryu, forcing the new ryugi to give up performing any Noh play, and thus Umewaka-ryu&apos;s attempt to establish a new branch school ended in failure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>また流儀制度の経済的根幹である素人弟子の絶対数が少ない分野では、分派行動を起こしても経済的に立ちゆかないことが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In some fields where the absolute number of lay disciples who support the economic foundation of the iemoto system is small, attempts to establish new branch schools are stymied for financial reasons in many cases.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In some fields where the absolute number of lay disciples who support the economic foundation of the iemoto system is small, attempts to establish new branch schools are often stymied for financial reasons.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In some fields where the absolute number of lay disciples who support the economic foundation of the iemoto system is small, attempts to establish new branch schools are often stymied for financial reasons.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>逆に言えば、ほかの分野との共演が必要でなく、素人弟子の数が多い分野では新流創設が容易であり、実際に日本舞踊や華道においてはほぼ無数に流儀があると言っても過言ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Conversely, in fields where no cooperation with other fields is necessary and the number of lay disciples is large, a new branch is easy to be established and in fact, it is safe to say that the fields of buyo (dance) and kado (flower arrangement) include a myriad of ryugi schools.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Conversely, in fields where no cooperation with other fields is necessary and the number of lay disciples is large, a new branch is easy to establish and in fact, it is safe to say that the fields of buyo (dance) and kado (flower arrangement) include a myriad of ryugi schools.</e>
<cmt>verb</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Conversely, in fields where no cooperation with other fields is necessary and the number of lay disciples is large, a new branch is easy to establish and in fact, it is safe to say that the fields of buyo (dance) and kado (flower arrangement) include a myriad of ryugi schools.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="24">
<j>なお流儀内に、さらに芸の相違によって小グループができる場合にはこれを「派」と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When one ryugi is further divided into small groups by differences in techniques, each of such small groups is called &quot;ha&quot; (faction).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When one ryugi is further divided into small groups by differences in techniques, each of such small groups is called &quot;ha&quot; (faction).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When one ryugi is further divided into small groups by differences in techniques, each of such small groups is called &quot;ha&quot; (faction).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>派がどの程度の位置を占めるか（たとえば免状の発行権を持つか否か）はそれぞれの分野によって千差万別であるといっていい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It can be said that what status (for example, authorized to issue a license) each ha can occupy varies widely depending on the field to which it belongs to.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It can be said that what status (for example, authorized to issue a license) each ha can occupy varies widely depending on the field to which it belongs.</e>
<cmt>omitted &quot;to&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It can be said that what status (for example, authorized to issue a license) each ha can occupy varies widely depending on the field to which it belongs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Lupinoid(id:68), Izayohi(id:13095), Tietaw(id:36297), OAS(id:30639), D.h(id:79056), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>