<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>小袖</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kosode (literally means small sleeves, however, it became a generic term used to refer to the standard size kimono of today)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kosode (literally means small sleeves, however, it became a generic term used to refer to the standard size kimono of today)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kosode</e>
<cmt>タイトルとしては補足が長すぎるので、のぞきました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>小袖は平安時代中頃に誕生したと思われる和服の元になった衣類である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kosode is a clothing thought to be formed in the middle of the Heian period, and is a origin of Japanese Kimono (wafuku).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kosode is clothing thought to be designed in the middle of the Heian period, and is an origin of Japanese Kimono (wafuku).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kosode is clothing thought to be designed in the middle of the Heian period, and is an origin of Japanese Kimono.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>それまでの着物が袖口が大きく袖丈一杯まで開いていたので大袖と言うのに対し、小袖は袖口が狭いという特徴がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While up until then, kimono had large size of the wrist openings to the full sleeve width and was called Osode, kosode has small size of the wrist openings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While up until then, the kimono had large wrist openings to the full sleeve width and was called Osode, kosode has small wrist openings.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While up until then, the kimono had large wrist openings to the full sleeve width and was called Osode, kosode has small wrist openings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>平安時代初期までは下着として単衣が使われたが、中期以降の国風文化興隆に伴う服飾の変化により、単は巨大化して下着としての用を為さなくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although until the early Heian period, hitoe (unlined garment) was used as an undergarment, hitoe became larger and did not work as undergarment because of the rise of Japanese original national custom and manner and accompanied change of costume in and after the middle of Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although until the early Heian period, hitoe (unlined garment) was used as an undergarment, hitoe became larger and did not work as an undergarment because of the rise of Japanese original national customs and manners and accompanied change of costume during and after the middle of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although until the early Heian period, hitoe (unlined garment) was used as an undergarment, hitoe became larger and did not work as an undergarment because of the rise of Japanese original national customs and manners and accompanied change of costume during and after the middle of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>その代わりに庶民の着ていた筒袖の着物を下着としたのが小袖の始まりではないかとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Instead, it is thought that they used kimono with the tubular style of sleeves clad by common folks as undergarment, which became an origin of kosode.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Instead, it is thought that they used kimono with tubular style of sleeves clad by common folks as undergarment, that became the origin of kosode.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Instead, it is thought that they used kimono with tubular style of sleeves clad by common folks as undergarment, that became the origin of kosode.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペースをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>岩手県平泉の中尊寺金色堂に納められていた藤原基衡着用の物が現存最古の小袖とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the kosode clad by Motohira FUJIWARA, stored in the Chuson-ji Temple Konjiki-do (Golden Hall) in Hiraizumi, Iwate Prefecture is the existing oldest kosode that is left today.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the kosode clad by Motohira FUJIWARA, stored in the Chuson-ji Temple Konjiki-do (Golden Hall) in Hiraizumi, Iwate Prefecture is the existing oldest kosode left today.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the kosode clad by FUJIWARA no Motohira, stored in Konjiki-do (Golden Hall) of Chuson-ji Temple in Hiraizumi, Iwate Prefecture, is the existing oldest kosode left today.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>平安後期（院政期）から鎌倉時代初期には貴族の間に爆発的な小袖ブームが訪れ、袿の代わりに豪華な織物で仕立てた小袖を何重にもまとうことが流行するが、余りにもお金がかかるためにしばしば禁止令が出される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the late Heian period (&quot;In&quot; ruling period) to the early Kamakura period, explosive booming of kosode had come among the court nobles, and to wear many kosodes woven with luxurious textile layering instead of simple uchikake (ordinary kimono) was prevailing, however, it was often prohibited by ordinance because it was too much expensive.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the late Heian period (&quot;In&quot; ruling period) to the early Kamakura period, an explosive booming of kosode had come among the court nobles, and to wear many kosodes woven with luxurious textile layering instead of simple uchikake (ordinary kimono) was prevailing, however, it was often prohibited by ordinance because it was too expensive.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the late Heian period (insei period (during the period of the government by the retired Emperor)) to the early Kamakura period, an explosive booming of kosode had come among the court nobles, and to wear many kosodes woven with luxurious textile layering instead of simple uchikake (ordinary kimono) was prevailing, however, it was often prohibited by ordinance because it was too expensive.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>そのため、室町時代まで貴族や武士などの上層階級では小袖は下着の扱いのままであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to the ban, kosode was treated as undergarment among the upper class such as nobles and bushis (samurais) by the Muromcahi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to the ban, kosode was treated as undergarment among the upper class such as nobles and bushis (samurais) by the Muromcahi period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to the ban, kosode was treated as undergarment among the upper class such as court nobles and samurai by the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>室町時代後期（戦国時代 (日本)）になると、下克上や治安の低下などから、袖が小さく活動的な小袖が表着として武家の夫人の正装に採用されるようになり、織豊時代にはお市の方肖像画に見られるような豪華な打ち掛け型の小袖などが作られるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the time advanced to late Muromachi period (the Warring States period), because of the revolt of vassals against their lords and poor security, active kosode with smaller sleeves were adopted as formal outer wear of wives of bushis, and at the time of Shokuho era (Oda-Toyotomi era), a type of gorgeous uchikake (a full length formal and elegant outer robe) style kosodes were made which was seen in the portrait of Lady Oichi no kata.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the time advanced to the late Muromachi period (the Warring States period), because of the revolt of vassals against their lords and poor security, active kosode with smaller sleeves were adopted as formal outer wear of wives of bushis, and at the time of Shokuho era (Oda-Toyotomi era), a type of gorgeous uchikake (a full length formal and elegant outer robe) style kosodes were made as was seen in the portrait of Lady Oichi no kata.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the time advanced to the late Muromachi period (the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States)), because of the revolt of vassals against their lords and poor security, active kosode with smaller sleeves were adopted as formal outer wear of wives of samurais, and at the time of Shokuho (Oda-Toyotomi era), a type of gorgeous uchikake (a full length formal and elegant outer robe) style kosodes were made as was seen in the portrait of Lady Oichi no kata.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>また、武士の礼装となった裃でも小袖を表に出す着方が通例となり、小袖は上着に昇格した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And the kamishimo which became a full dress uniform of bushis, the way to wear kosode outside of kamishimo became a permitted custom and kosode was upgraded to outer garment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And the kamishimo which became a full dress uniform of bushis, the way to wear kosode outside of kamishimo became a permitted custom and kosode was upgraded to an outer garment.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And the kamishimo which became a full dress uniform of samurai, the way to wear kosode outside of kamishimo became a permitted custom and kosode was upgraded to an outer garment.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>この頃の小袖は「桃山小袖」といわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The kosode of around this time is called &quot;Momoyama kosode&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The kosode around this time is called &quot;Momoyama kosode.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The kosode around this time is called &apos;Momoyama kosode.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>その後、江戸幕府による士農工商の身分制により武士などの上層階級では小袖の柄行きが固定化されてしまうが、京・大坂などの上方や江戸の富裕な町人は平和になった余力を衣類に向けるようになり手の込んだ小袖が誕生する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, while due to the class distinctions (warriors, farmers, artisans and tradesmen in descending order of rank) set by Edo bakufu, the design of kosode was fixed among the upper class of bushis (samurais), richer townsmen in Kyoto, Ozaka and Edo spent their surplus of the fruits of regained peaceful time on clothing, and elaborately crafted kosode was born.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, while due to class distinctions (warriors, farmers, artisans, and tradesmen in descending order of rank) set by Edo bakufu, the design of kosode was fixed among the upper class of bushis (samurais), richer townsmen in Kyoto, Ozaka and Edo spent their surplus of the fruits of regained peaceful time on clothing, and elaborately crafted kosode were born.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, while due to class distinctions (warriors, farmers, artisans, and tradesmen in descending order of rank) set by Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), the design of kosode was fixed among the upper class of samurai, richer townsmen in Kyoto, Osaka and Edo spent their surplus of the fruits of regained peaceful time on clothing, and elaborately crafted kosode were born.</e>
<cmt>補足などをしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>しかし、やはり華美に過ぎるとしてしばしば江戸幕府より禁令が出ている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the newly born kosode was regarded by Edo bakufu that also too luxe a garment and often banned.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the newly born kosode was regarded by the Edo bakufu as too luxurious a garment and often banned it.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the newly born kosode was regarded by the Edo bakufu as too luxurious a garment and often banned it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="13">
<j>この時代の代表的な小袖として慶長小袖、寛文小袖、元禄小袖がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The typical kosode in this time are Keicho style kosode, Kanbun style kosode and Genroku style kosode.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The typical kosode at this time are Keicho style kosode, Kanbun style kosode, and Genroku style kosode.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The typical kosode at this time are Keicho style kosode, Kanbun style kosode, and Genroku style kosode.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="14">
<j>江戸時代も後期を過ぎると公家の間でも儀式以外では小袖を着るのが通例となり、また、小袖自体の袖も平和な時代の中で華美になり巨大化して振袖が誕生、そのため「小袖」と言う名称自体が実態に合わなくなり使われなくなってしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Edo era entered into the latter half, it became common for among the court nobles to wear kosode in cases other than the time of rituals, and &quot;sode&quot; (sleeves) of kosode became luxurious and larger in the peaceful time and furisode (a long sleeved type of kimono) was newly born and name &quot;kosode&quot; (literally means small sleeves) itself did not suitable to the reality of kimono, and the name kosode fell into disuse.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Edo era entered into the latter half, it became common among court nobles to wear kosode in situations other than for times of rituals, and &quot;sode&quot; (sleeves) of kosode became luxurious and larger in peaceful times and furisode (a long sleeved type of kimono) was newly born and name &quot;kosode&quot; (literally means small sleeves) itself were not suitable to the reality of kimono, and the name kosode fell into disuse.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Edo period entered into the latter half, it became common among court nobles to wear kosode in situations other than for times of rituals, and sode (sleeves) of kosode became luxurious and larger in peaceful times and furisode (a long sleeved type of kimono) was newly born and name &apos;kosode((literally means small sleeves) itself were not suitable to the reality of kimono, and the name kosode fell into disuse.</e>
<cmt>用語などを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>現在では「小袖」というと束帯や十二単など宮廷装束の下着を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today, &quot;kosode&quot; means undergarment of court costume like sokutai and junihiote.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, &quot;kosode&quot; means undergarment of a court costume like sokutai and junihiote.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, &apos;kosode&apos; means undergarment of a court costume like sokutai and junihiote.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>小袖の形式</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Type of kosode</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Type of kosode</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Type of Kosode</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>桃山小袖</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Momoyama kosode</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Momoyama kosode</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Momoyama Kosode</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="16">
<j>安土桃山時代に流行したタイプの小袖で、女性でも対丈に仕立てられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A type of kosode prevailing in Azuchi-Momoyama period and even women can tailor it to tsuitake (full length of height).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A type of kosode prevailing in Azuchi-Momoyama period and even women can tailor it to tsuitake (full length of height).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A type of kosode prevailing in Azuchi-Momoyama period and even women can tailor it to tsuitake (full length of height).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>南蛮貿易によるキリシタン文化の影響も受け、大胆で派手な柄行き・色使いの物が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were influenced by the Christian culture imported through Nanban-Boeki (the trade with Southern Barbarians) and thus there are many bold and gaudy design kosodes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were influenced by the Christian culture imported through Nanban-Boeki (trade with Southern Barbarians) and thus there are many bold and gaudy design kosodes.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were influenced by the Christian culture imported through Nanban-Boeki (trade with Southern Barbarians) and thus there are many bold and gaudy design kosodes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>時代の活気を反映してか、刺繍を全体に巡らしたり、辻が花染を多用しているのも特徴である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Perhaps reflecting the vibrant culture of the time, kosode full of embroidery and frequent use of tsujigahana-zome (dye of flower design) are characteristics of kosode of this type.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Perhaps reflecting the vibrant culture of the time, kosode full of embroidery and frequent use of tsujigahana-zome (dye of flower design) are characteristics of kosode of this type.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Perhaps reflecting the vibrant culture of the time, kosode full of embroidery and frequent use of tsujigahana-zome (dye of flower design) are characteristics of kosode of this type.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>この時代の代表作としては山形県米沢市に伝わる上杉謙信の遺品や久能山東照宮にある徳川家康の遺品があげられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Typical kosode in this period is memento of Kenshin UESUGI handed down to Yonezawa City, Yamagata Prefecture, and memento of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA possessed of Mount Kuno Toshogu Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Typical kosode in this period can be seen in a memento of Kenshin UESUGI handed down to Yonezawa City, Yamagata Prefecture, and mementos of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA possessed by the Mount Kuno Toshogu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Typical kosode in this period can be seen in a memento of Kenshin UESUGI handed down to Yonezawa City, Yamagata Prefecture, and mementos of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA possessed by Toshogu Shrine on Mt. Kuno.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>慶長小袖</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keicho kosode</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keicho kosode</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keicho Kosode</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="20">
<j>慶長年間に流行したタイプの小袖で、総柄であるが、模様が細かくなり、色調が桃山小袖に比べて暗いのが特徴とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A type of kosode prevailing in Keicho era (1596~1614) and it is said that a typical Keicho kosode is patterned all over the cloth and the pattern became minute, however, color tone used is darker than Momoyama kosode.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A type of kosode prevailing during the Keicho era (1596~1614) and it is said that a typical Keicho kosode is patterned all over the cloth and the pattern became minute, however, the color tone used is darker than Momoyama kosode.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A type of kosode prevailing during the Keicho era (from 1596 to 1614) and it is said that a typical Keicho kosode is patterned all over the cloth and the pattern became minute, however, the color tone used is darker than Momoyama kosode.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>奈良県立美術館にある「伝淀殿像」に描かれている物が代表的な慶長小袖とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said the one depicted in the &quot;Yodo dono portrait, unconfirmed&quot; in possession of Nara Prefectural Museum of Art is a typical Keicho kosode.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said the one depicted in the &quot;Yodo dono portrait, unconfirmed&quot; in possession of Nara Prefectural Museum of Art is a typical Keicho kosode.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said the one depicted in the &apos;attributed to Yodo dono portrait&apos; in possession of Nara Prefectural Museum of Art is a typical Keicho kosode.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>寛文小袖</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanbun kosode</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanbun kosode</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanbun Kosode</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="22">
<j>寛文年間に流行したタイプの小袖で、肩から裾の方に大胆に流れるような模様をとり余白が大きく、また文字を模様として使うのも特徴とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A type of kosode prevailing in Kanbun era (1661 ~ 1672) of which pattern is large streamline and dyed from shoulder to hem, and large blank space is left, and it is said a characteristic of Kanbun kosode is that letters are used as pattern.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A type of kosode prevailing in the Kanbun era (1661 ~ 1672) includes a large streamlined and dyed pattern from shoulder to hem, and large blank space is left, and it is said a characteristic of Kanbun kosode is that letters are used as a pattern.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A type of kosode prevailing in the Kanbun era (from 1661 to 1672) includes a large streamlined and dyed pattern from shoulder to hem, and large blank space is left, and it is said a characteristic of Kanbun kosode is that letters are used as a pattern.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>この小袖から現在の和服のように袖幅を大きく仕立てるようになる（慶長以前は肩幅が大きく、袖幅は肩幅の半分しかなかった）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From this type of kosode, sodehaba (sleeve size) was begun to be tailored wider like today&apos;s kimono (before Keicho era, shoulder width of the kosode is tailored larger and sodehaba was only a half of shoulder width).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From this type of kosode, the sodehaba (sleeve size) began to be tailored wider like today&apos;s kimono (before the Keicho era, shoulder width of the kosode was tailored larger and sodehaba was only a half of a shoulder width).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From this type of kosode, the sodehaba (sleeve size) began to be tailored wider like today&apos;s kimono (before the Keicho era, shoulder width of the kosode was tailored larger and sodehaba was only a half of a shoulder width).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="24">
<j>この流行を作ったのは東福門院とされ、和子の御用達だった「雁金屋」には注文が殺到して大儲けしたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said this fashion was made by Tofukumon-In Masako, and a purveyor of Masako, &quot;Kariganeya&quot; received a rush of orders and Kariganeya made a fortune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said this fashion was made by Tofukumon-In Masako, and a purveyor of Masako, &quot;Kariganeya&quot; received a rush of orders and Kariganeya made a fortune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said this fashion was made by Tofukumonin Masako, and a purveyor of Masako, &apos;Kariganeya&apos; received a rush of orders to make a fortune.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>後にこの雁金屋から元禄文化の重要な担い手だった尾形光琳、尾形乾山兄弟が誕生している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, the Kariganeya turned out Korin OGATAand Kanzan OGATA brothers who played a great role in the Genroku Culture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, the Kariganeya turned out the Korin OGATAand Kanzan OGATA brothers who played a great role in the Genroku Culture.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, the Kariganeya turned out the Korin OGATAand Kanzan OGATA brothers who played a great role in the Genroku Culture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>元禄小袖</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Genroku kosode</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Genroku kosode</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genroku Kosode</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="26">
<j>元禄年間に流行したタイプの小袖で、流行の発信源は上方の町人であったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A type of kosode prevailing in Genroku era (1688 ~ 1703) and it is said that the dispatcher of the fashion were townsmen of Kyoto and Ozaka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A type of kosode prevailing in Genroku era (1688 ~ 1703) and it is said that the dispatcher of the fashion were townsmen of Kyoto and Ozaka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A type of kosode prevailing in Genroku era (from 1688 to 1703) and it is said that the dispatcher of the fashion were townsmen of Kamigata (Kyoto and Osaka area).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>友禅の誕生により自由に模様を描き、明るい色彩が特徴とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the birth of yuzen (a kind of printed silk), its freely patterned design and bright colors are said to be the characteristics of the Genroku kosode.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the birth of yuzen (a kind of printed silk), its freely patterned design and bright colors are said to be characteristic of the Genroku kosode.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the birth of yuzen (a kind of printed silk), its freely patterned design and bright colors are said to be characteristic of the Genroku kosode.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>菱川師宣の代表作「見返り美人」の着物はこの元禄小袖である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The kimono clad by an lady depicted in the masterpiece of Moronobu HISHIKAWA, Mikaeri Bijin is this genroku kosode.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The kimono clad lady depicted in the masterpiece of Moronobu HISHIKAWA, Mikaeri Bijin is wearing this genroku kosode.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The kimono clad lady depicted in the masterpiece of Moronobu HISHIKAWA, &apos;Mikaeri Bijin&apos; (Beauty Looking Back) is wearing this Genroku kosode.</e>
<cmt>補足などしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>小袖の身分差</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Class difference in kosode</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Class difference in kosode</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Class Difference in Kosode</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="29">
<j>平和な時代が続き、庶民が次第に力を蓄え武士以上の豪奢な着物を着用するようになると、江戸幕府は士農工商身分確定のために躍起となって次々と禁令を発したのは先述の通りである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As aforementioned, common folks were gradually empowered as the peaceful time long continued, some of them wore more gorgeous kimono than the bushi class, Edo bakufu shogunate tried vehemently banned the luxurious kimono one after another in order to fix the class distinctions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As aforementioned, common folks were gradually empowered as peace continued, some of them wore more gorgeous kimono than the bushi class, Edo bakufu shogunate tried vehemently to ban luxurious kimono one after another in order to fix class distinctions.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As aforementioned, common folks were gradually empowered as peace continued, some of them wore more gorgeous kimono than the bushi class, Edo bakufu shogunate tried vehemently to ban luxurious kimono one after another in order to fix class distinctions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>また、大奥においては事細かに婦人の着物を規定したため、次第に身分によって着用される柄が固定化していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, in the O-oku (the inner halls of Edo Castle where the wife of the Shogun and her female servants reside), codes on women&apos;s costume, namely kimono became regulative in minute detail, and the patterns of kimono permitted to the class she belonged became fixed little by little.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further, in the O-oku (the inner halls of Edo Castle where the wife of the Shogun and her female servants reside), codes on women&apos;s costume, namely kimono became regulative in minute detail, and the patterns of kimono permitted to the class she belonged became fixed little by little.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further, in the O-oku (the inner halls of Edo-jo Castle where the wife of the Shogun and her female servants reside), codes on women&apos;s costume, namely kimono became regulative in minute detail, and the patterns of kimono permitted to the class she belonged became fixed little by little.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>また元禄以後も小袖には流行があったが、文化史上「○○小袖」とは呼称しない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was prevalence of kosode even after the genroku era, they were not called &quot;something kosode&quot; in the cultural history any longer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was prevalence of kosode even after the genroku era, they were not called &quot;something kosode&quot; in the cultural history any longer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was prevalence of kosode even after the genroku era, they were not called &apos;something kosode&apos; in the cultural history any longer.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>武家の小袖</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kosode of the Bushis</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kosode of the Bushis</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kosode of the samurai families</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="32">
<j>先述のように江戸幕府は大奥での着物を事細かに規定し、それが大名家にも普及し、武士階級全体で大奥慣習に準じるようになっていった（江戸中期以降）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As mentioned in the above, Edo bakufu regulate the way kimono were worn in minute detail in the O-oku, and the regulations passed on to the Daimyo families, and finally the dress codes of the whole bushi class became pursuant to the codes and conventions of the O-oku (in and after the middle of the Edo era).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As mentioned in the above, the Edo bakufu regulated the way kimono were worn in minute detail in the O-oku, and the regulations passed on to the Daimyo families, and finally the dress codes of the whole bushi class became pursuant to the codes and conventions of the O-oku (during and after the middle of the Edo era).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As mentioned in the above, the Edo bakufu regulated the way kimono were worn in minute detail in the O-oku, and the regulations passed on to daimyo families (feudal lord families), and finally the dress codes of the whole samurai class became pursuant to the codes and conventions of the O-oku (in and after the middle of the Edo period).</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>その規定は次の通り。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some of the codes are:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some of the codes are:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some of the codes are follows:</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="34">
<j>年始には正室はおすべらかしに髪を結い、将軍正室は十二単、大名家正室は袿袴装束をまとう</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the beginning of the year, legal wife dresses her hair in &quot;osuberakasi&quot; style (a women&apos;s hair style in the court), and the legal wife of the shogun wears junihiote (a women&apos;s layered ceremonial robe) and the legal wife of daimyo wears keiko-shozoku costume.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the beginning of the year, legal wife dresses her hair in &quot;osuberakasi&quot; style (a women&apos;s hair style in the court), and the legal wife of the shogun wears junihiote (a women&apos;s layered ceremonial robe) and the legal wife of daimyo wears keiko-shozoku costume.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the beginning of the year, legal wife dresses her hair in osuberakasi style (a women&apos;s hair style in the court), and the legal wife of the shogun wears junihiote (a women&apos;s layered ceremonial robe) and the legal wife of daimyo wears keiko-shozoku keiko (a type of female formal dress in white kosode).</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>三月三日、九月九日、式日には打掛着用</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On March 3rd, September 9th and on ritual days or ceremonial days, uchikake (formal dress of bushi class women) shall be worn.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On March 3rd, September 9th and on ritual days or ceremonial days, uchikake (formal dress of bushi class women) shall be worn.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 3, September 9 and on ritual days or ceremonial days, uchikake (formal dress of samurai class women) shall be worn.</e>
<cmt>日付表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>五月五日は絹縮か麻晒の帷子着用、ただし地の色は白か黒のみ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On May 5th, katabira (the light summer garment) made of kinu-chijimi (silk crepe) or asa-sarashi (bleached hemp) shall be worn, however, base color shall be limited to white or black.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On May 5th, katabira (the light summer garment) made of kinu-chijimi (silk crepe) or asa-sarashi (bleached hemp) shall be worn, however, the base color shall be limited to white or black.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On May 5, katabira (light summer garment) made of kinu-chijimi (silk crepe) or asa-sarashi (bleached hemp) shall be worn, however, the base color shall be limited to white or black.</e>
<cmt>日付表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>七月七日には帷子着用の上、腰巻をまとう</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 7th, katabira shall be worn over koshimaki (a full length garment).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 7th, katabira shall be worn over koshimaki (a full length garment).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 7, katabira shall be worn over koshimaki (a full length garment).</e>
<cmt>日付表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>打掛の色は黒、白、赤、桃色のみ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Color of uchikake shall be limited to black, white, red or pink.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Color of uchikake shall be limited to black, white, red or pink.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Color of uchikake shall be limited to black, white, red or pink.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>打掛の下に着る着物（間着）は白、赤、黄色のみ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Color of aida-gi (garment clad under uchikake) shall be limited to white, red or yellow.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Color of aida-gi (garment clad under uchikake) shall be limited to white, red, or yellow.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Color of aida-gi (garment clad under uchikake) shall be limited to white, red, or yellow.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>文様の間には隙間ができないよう花の刺繍を施す</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Between the patterns, embroidery shall be processed not to make a blank space.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Between the patterns, embroidery shall be processed so not to make a blank space.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Between the patterns, embroidery shall be processed so not to make a blank space.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>正装は綸子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Formal attire shall be rinzu, a Japanese silk satin damask.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Formal attire shall be rinzu, a Japanese silk satin damask.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Formal attire shall be rinzu, a Japanese silk satin damask.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>ちりめんは準正装か普段着にしか使えない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chirimen (Crepe Kimono) shall only be used as semiformal garment or casual wear.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chirimen (Crepe Kimono) shall only be used as semiformal garment or casual wear.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chirimen (Crepe Kimono) shall only be used as semiformal garment or casual wear.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>ただし下位の者は縮緬が正装。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the formal attire of the lower-ranked shall be crepe kimono.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the formal attire of the lower-ranked shall be crepe kimono.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the formal attire of the lower-ranked shall be crepe kimono.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="44">
<j>四月一日～五月四日、九月一日～九月八日は袷着用。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From April 1st to May 4th, and September 1st to 8th, awase (lined garment) shall be worn.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From April 1st to May 4th, and September 1st to 8th, awase (lined garment) shall be worn.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From April 1 to May 4, and September 1 to 8, awase (lined garment) shall be worn.</e>
<cmt>日付表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>九月九日～三月末日は綿入れ、五月五日～八月末日は単衣</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From September 9th to the end of March, wadded garment shall be worn, and from May 5th to the end of August, hitoe (single garment) shall be worn.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From September 9th to the end of March, a wadded garment shall be worn, and from May 5th to the end of August, hitoe (single garment) shall be worn.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From September 9 to the end of March, a wadded garment shall be worn, and from May 5 to the end of August, hitoe (single garment) shall be worn.</e>
<cmt>日付表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="46">
<j>（中に用いた日時はすべて旧暦）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The dates shown above are all of the lunar calendar dates.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The dates shown above are all based on lunar calendar dates.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The dates shown above are all based on lunar calendar dates.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>…などである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">…and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">…and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And so on.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>これほど規定が決まっていると創意工夫をこらす余地はほとんどなく、江戸時代中期以後、武士階級から着物の流行が生まれることは二度と無かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Where the provisions were detailed like the above, there were almost no room for originality and ingenuity, thus the fashion in kimono was never born among from the bushi class.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Where the provisions were detailed as above, there was almost no room for originality and ingenuity, thus the fashion in kimono was never born from among those from the bushi class.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Where the provisions were detailed as above, there was almost no room for originality and ingenuity, thus the fashion in kimono was never born from among those from the bushi class.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="49">
<j>文様は花鳥風月の刺繍の間に有職文様がまんべんなく全体に散らされている物、また源氏物語などの古典文学や能の風景から画題をとった「御所解」に大分されるが、後述する公家や庶民の着物に対して柄行きの大胆さにかけ、余白を嫌う傾向が挙げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though patterns are roughly demarcated to two types; one is &quot;yusoku-monyo&quot; (traditional design motifs, used either in single units or repeated to create patterns, based on designs from Heian courtly decoration) that are scattered over the whole of kimono between the embroidery of the beauty of the nature, and another is that motif are taken from traditional literary such as the Tale of Genji or scenery of noh play which are called &quot;goshoge&quot;, compared to the kimono of the court nobles and common folks as described later, it seems that the design lacks boldness and there is a tendency to avoid blank space.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though patterns are roughly demarcated to two types; one is &quot;yusoku-monyo&quot; (traditional design motifs, used either in single units or repeated to create patterns, based on designs from Heian courtly decorations) that are scattered over the whole of kimono between the embroidery of the beauty of nature, and another is that the motif are taken from traditional literarature such as the Tale of Genji or scenery of a noh play called &quot;goshoge,&quot; compared to the kimono of the court nobles and common folks as described later, it seems that the design lacks boldness and there is a tendency to avoid blank space.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though patterns are roughly demarcated to two types; one is yusoku-monyo (traditional design motifs, used either in single units or repeated to create patterns, based on designs from Heian courtly decorations) that are scattered over the whole of kimono between the embroidery of the beauty of nature, and another is that the motif are taken from traditional literature such as the Tale of Genji or scenery of a noh play called &apos;goshoge,&apos; compared to the kimono of the court nobles and common folks as described later, it seems that the design lacks boldness and there is a tendency to avoid blank space.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="50">
<j>これらの複雑な制度は江戸幕府の崩壊により消滅し、その後華族となった大名家には引き継がれなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These complicated system disappeared after the collapse of Edo bakufu and were never passed over to the former daimyo families who later became kazoku (the noble class).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These complicated systems that disappeared after the collapse of the Edo bakufu and were never passed over to the former daimyo families who later became kazoku (the noble class).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These complicated systems that disappeared after the collapse of the Edo bakufu and were never passed over to the former daimyo families who later became kazoku (the noble class).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="51">
<j>現在「茶屋辻」といわれる文様は、この武家の小袖で「夏服」として定められた物が残ったものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The pattern design currently called &quot;chayatsuji&quot; is a remain of a kosode stipulated as summer garment for bushi class.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The pattern design currently called &quot;chayatsuji&quot; is a remainder of a kosode stipulated as a summer garment for the bushi class.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The pattern design currently called &apos;chayatsuji&apos; is a remainder of a kosode stipulated as &apos;a summer garment&apos; for the samurai families.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>公家の小袖</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kosode of court nobles</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kosode of court nobles</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kosode of Court Nobles</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="52">
<j>公家社会で小袖が着用されるようになったのは先述のように徳川和子（東福門院）の入内の頃からと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As mentioned in the above, it is thought that the time kosode became common among the society of court nobles was around the time when Masako TOKUGAWA (Tofukumon-in) was sent to court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As mentioned above, it is thought that the time kosode became common among the society of court nobles was around the time when Masako TOKUGAWA (Tofukumon-in) was sent to court.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As mentioned above, it is thought that the time kosode became common among the society of court nobles was around the time when Masako TOKUGAWA (Tofukumonin) was sent to the Imperial court.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>その後次第に着用のルールが定められたと考えられるが、その正確な年月ははっきりしない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, it is thought that dress codes regarding kosode were decided gradually, however, exact month and year is not known clearly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, it is thought that dress codes regarding kosode were decided, however, the exact month and year is not clearly knowny.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, it is thought that dress codes regarding kosode were decided, however, the exact month and year is not clearly known.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="54">
<j>基本的には冬服として「掻取（かいどり）」、合服・夏服として「単衣（ひとえ）」、盛夏服として「帷子（かたびら）」という区分があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Basically, it was demarcated as &quot;kaidori&quot;, a full length outer robe as a winter wear, hitoe as spring and autumn wear/summer wear, and katabira as a mid-summer wear.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Basically, it was demarcated as &quot;kaidori,&quot; a full length outer robe as winter wear, hitoe as spring and autumn wear/summer wear, and katabira as mid-summer wear.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Basically, it was demarcated as &apos;kaidori,&apos; a full length outer robe as winter wear, hitoe as spring and autumn wear or summer wear, and katabira as mid-summer wear.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="55">
<j>「掻取」はいわゆる打掛と同じ物で、京都の剣術家としても知られる吉岡憲房が発明したとされる「憲法染（けんぽうぞめ）の掻取」（略して「憲法」とも言われる）、刺繍や染めで模様の入った「模様の掻取」、「素模様の掻取」の大まかに3種があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaidori is the same as so-called uchikake, and there were largely three types of kaidoris: Kenpo Zome (&quot;Kaidori of Kenpo dye&quot;), which is said that Kenpo YOSHIOKA who is also known as a swordsman of Kyoto invented (also called as kenpo for short), &quot;Moyo no kaidori&quot; (patterned kaidori) which is patterned with embroidery and dye, and &quot;simple patterned kaidori&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaidori is the same as so-called uchikake, and there were largely three types of kaidoris: Kenpo Zome (&quot;Kaidori of Kenpo dye&quot;), which is said that Kenpo YOSHIOKA who is also known as a swordsman of Kyoto invented (also called as kenpo for short), &quot;Moyo no kaidori&quot; (patterned kaidori) which is patterned with embroidery and dye, and &quot;simple patterned kaidori.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaidori&apos; is the same as so-called uchikake, and there were largely three types of kaidori: &apos;Kenpo Zome no Kaidori&apos; (Kaidori of Kenpo dye), which is said that Kenpo YOSHIOKA who was also known as a swordsman of Kyoto invented (also called as kenpo for short), &apos;Moyo no kaidori&apos; (patterned kaidori) which is patterned with embroidery and dye, and &apos;simple patterned kaidori.&apos;</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>このうち、黒地である「憲法染の掻取」は袿袴装束に匹敵する正装として扱われ、掻取の上に袴を着用することもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among these three, Kaidori of Kenpo dye which has black background was treated as a comparable formal attire with keiko shozoku, and sometimes they wore hakama (trousers) over kaidori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among these three, Kaidori of Kenpo dye which has a black background was treated as comparable formal attire with keiko shozoku, and sometimes they wore hakama (trousers) over kaidori.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among these three, &apos;Kenpo Zome no Kaidori&apos; which has a black background was treated as comparable formal attire with keiko shozoku, and sometimes they wore hakama (trousers) over kaidori.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>掻取の下に着用する「間着（あいぎ）」は28歳までは「濃色」（紫に近い濃い紅とされる）、29歳から40歳までは紅縮緬、40歳以上は白羽二重と規定されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Aigi&quot; (garment worn over under-garment) worn under kaidori was stipulated to use dark color (thick red close to purple) for the age in and younger 28-year old and those who are 29-year old to those under 40 shall be worn scarlet crepe, and those on and over 40-year old shall be worn white &quot;habutae&quot;, a thin, soft, durable Japanese silk..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Aigi&quot; (garment worn over an under-garment) worn under kaidori was stipulated to be a dark color (thick red close to purple) for the aged and those younger 28-years old and those who are 29-years old to those under 40 shall wear scarlet crepe, and those on and over 40-years old shall be wear white &quot;habutae,&quot; a thin, soft, durable Japanese silk..</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Aigi&apos; (garment worn over an under-garment) worn under kaidori was stipulated to be a &apos;dark color&apos; (thick red close to purple) for the aged and those younger 28-years old and those who are 29-years old to those under 40 shall wear scarlet crepe, and those on and over 40-years old shall be wear white habutae, a thin, soft, durable Japanese silk.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>ただし、上に羽織る掻取の色に規定はなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, color of kaidori slip on the aigi was not stipulated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, color of the kaidori slip on the aigi was not stipulated.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, color of the kaidori slip on the aigi was not stipulated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="59">
<j>「単衣」は現在の着物とよく似ているがお端折をつくらずに引きずって着用された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hitoe is very close to kimono today, however, there was no hemming and they wore it and dragged.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hitoe is very close to kimono today, however, there was no hemming and they wore it and it dragged.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hitoe&apos; is very close to kimono today, however, there was no hemming and they wore it and it dragged.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="60">
<j>「帷子」は刺繍や染めで模様が入った「細染（ほそぞめ）」と浴衣によく似た「地白（じしろ）」の2種があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were two types of katabira: a hosozome (narrow dye) which was patterned with embroidery and dyes and jishiro (white dyed) which is similar to yukata of today.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were two types of katabira: a hosozome (narrow dye) which was patterned with embroidery and dyes and jishiro (white dyed) which is similar to yukata of today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were two types of &apos;katabira&apos;: &apos;hosozome&apos; (narrow dye) which was patterned with embroidery and dyes and &apos;jishiro&apos; (white dyed) which is similar to yukata of today.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>細染は袴を着用して正装とすることもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hosozome was used as formal attire when combined with hakama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hosozome was used as formal attire when combined with hakama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hosozome was used as formal attire when combined with hakama.</e>
<cmt>IJ</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>素材は絹ではなく麻（奈良晒がよく使われた）で、現在の着物と同じようにお端折をつくって着用された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its textile was not silk but hemp (Nara sarashi, Nara bleach was often used) and has hemmings like today&apos;s kimono.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its textile was not silk, but hemp (Nara sarashi, Nara bleach was often used) and has a hem like today&apos;s kimono.</e>
<cmt>punctuation, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its textile was not silk, but hemp (Nara sarashi, Nara bleach was often used) and has a hem like today&apos;s kimono.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="63">
<j>公家社会では小袖はあくまで「2番手の衣装」だったため武家社会より規定は緩かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the society of court nobles, kosode is just the &quot;secondary&quot; clothes and thus the dress codes are more relaxed than that of bushi society.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the society of court nobles, kosode is just &quot;secondary&quot; clothing and thus the dress codes are more relaxed than that of the bushi society.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the society of court nobles, kosode was just &apos;secondary&apos; clothing and thus the dress codes are more relaxed than that of the samurai society.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>柄行きは「花鳥風月」を基調としており、有職文様を飛び柄で入れたり、着物全体をつかって刺繍や染めで文様が入っており、寛文小袖に似た雰囲気がある…などの特徴があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are characteristics that design is basically taken from the beauty of nature (Kacho-Fugetsu: flower, birds, wind and moon: a common Japanese motif for arts) and uses yusoku-monyo as juxtaposition pattern, or the kosode is patterned with embroidery and dyes all over the kimono, and has a similar atmosphere with Kanbun kosode.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The character of the design is basically taken from the beauty of nature (Kacho-Fugetsu: flower, birds, wind and moon: a common Japanese motif art form) and uses yusoku-monyo as juxtaposition pattern, or the kosode is patterned with embroidery and dyes all over the kimono, and has a similar atmosphere with Kanbun kosode.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The character of the design is basically taken from Kacho-Fugetsu (beauty of nature: flower, birds, wind and moon, common Japanese motifs for art) and uses yusoku-monyo as juxtaposition pattern, or the kosode is patterned with embroidery and dyes all over the kimono, and has a similar atmosphere with Kanbun kosode.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="65">
<j>これらの小袖は明治時代の復古化・西欧化のために徐々に廃止されたものの、貞明皇后の意向で昭和時代初期に一部復活した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although these kosodes were gradually diminished due to the reactionary and westernization during the Meiji era, a part of them revived in the early Showa era in complying with Empress Teimei&apos;s wish.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although these kosodes were gradually diminished due to the reactionary and westernization during the Meiji era, a part of them revived during the early Showa era in complying with Empress Teimei&apos;s wishes.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although these kosodes were gradually diminished due to the reactionary and westernization during the Meiji period, a part of them revived during the early Showa period in complying with Empress Teimei&apos;s wishes.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>しかし、貞明皇后の崩御とともに皇室の表舞台から完全に廃絶した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, these kosode were completely abolished from the front stage of the imperial family with the demise of the Empress Teimei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, these kosode were completely abolished from the front stage of the imperial family with the demise of Empress Teimei.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, these kosode were completely abolished from the front stage of the imperial family with the demise of Empress Teimei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>現在は宮中三殿の賢所に仕えるわずかな女官（掌典職）のみこの風俗を守っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today, only a few court ladies served at the kashikodokoro (a palace sanctuary) in the Three Palace in the Imperial palace keep this manner.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, only a few court ladies who served at the kashikodokoro (palace sanctuary) in the Imperial palace maintain this manner.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, only a few court ladies who served at the kashikodokoro (palace sanctuary) in the Imperial palace maintain this manner.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>庶民の小袖</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kosode of common folks</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kosode of common folks</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kosode of Common Folks</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="68">
<j>庶民の着物は江戸幕府のあい続く倹約令により、次第に裏地や裾など目立たない部分への贅沢に目が向けられるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the meantime, kimono fashion of common people gradually passed in direction to obscure part of kimono such as linings and hem due to the spate of thrift orders by Edo bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the meantime, kimono fashion of common people gradually took a direction to obscure part of the kimono such as linings and hems due to the spate of thrift orders by the Edo bakufu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the meantime, kimono fashion of common people gradually took a direction to obscure part of the kimono such as linings and hems due to the spate of thrift orders by the Edo bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>そこに入れられる文様は幕府の禁制により有職故実文様が使えなかったこともあり、身の回りの雑貨をデフォルメしたユニークな物、時にはドクロや性交シーンなどのエログロ趣味まであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The patterns used were unique kind of things such as deformation of personal effects or groceries, and sometimes erotic and grotesque taste motif such as skull and sex scene were used, because the bans on the use of yusoku-kojitsu (ancient practices and usages) by the Edo bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The patterns used were unique kinds of things such as the deformation of personal effects or groceries, and sometimes erotic and grotesque motifs such as skull and sex scenes were used, because of the ban on the use of yusoku-kojitsu (ancient practices and usages) by the Edo bakufu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The patterns used were unique kinds of things such as the deformation of personal effects or groceries, and sometimes erotic and grotesque motifs such as skull and sex scenes were used, because of the ban on the use of yusoku-kojitsu (ancient practices and usages) by the Edo bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>また地域差が非常に激しく、化政文化の頃、江戸では「江戸褄」といわれる足下に模様を入れることが流行ったのに対し上方では「島原褄」といわれる合褄に模様が入れることが流行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, regional difference is large, and at the time of Ka-Sei culture, at Edo, Edo tsuma which the patterns were located in the foot of kosode while at Kyoto and Ozaka, &quot;Shimabara tsuma which was main pattern were located in aizuma (from hem to collar tip) were in style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, regional differences are large, and at the time of Ka-Sei culture, at Edo, Edo tsuma of which the patterns were located in the foot of kosode while in Kyoto and Ozaka, &quot;Shimabara tsuma which was main pattern were located in aizuma (from hem to the collar tip) were in style.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, regional differences are large, and at the time of Kasei culture, at Edo, &apos;Edo tsuma&apos; of which the patterns were located in the foot of kosode while in Kyoto and Osaka, &apos;Shimabara tsuma&apos; which was main pattern were located in aizuma (from hem to the collar tip) were in style.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを補足するなどしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>その後「江戸褄」は「留袖」の原型になったのに対し、「島原褄」は上方限定の流行で終わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, while Edo tsuma became an origin of Tomesode (formal dress patterned only below the waistline worn by a married woman), Shimabara tsuma was prevailed only in Kyoto and Ozaka area and finally diminished.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, while Edo tsuma became an origin of Tomesode (formal dress patterned only below the waistline worn by a married woman), Shimabara tsuma prevailed only in the Kyoto and Ozaka areas and finally diminished.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, while &apos;Edo tsuma&apos; became an origin of &apos;Tomesode&apos; (formal dress patterned only below the waistline worn by a married woman), &apos;Shimabara tsuma&apos; prevailed only in the Kyoto and Osaka areas and finally diminished.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを補足するなどしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>着物の世界でもこのころには江戸上位の傾向が見られたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In also the world of kimono fashion, Edo was already at superior position in around this time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also in the world of kimono fashion, Edo was already in a superior position around this time.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also in the world of kimono fashion, Edo was already in a superior position around this time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="73">
<j>また、脇に「身八つ口」をつけるようになったのも庶民の小袖が発祥なのだが、この起源は着用の便宜を図るため、放熱のため、または遊女の発案によるなど諸説あり起源ははっきりしない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although &quot;miyatsuguchi&quot;, small opening in the side of some traditional Japanese clothing (located where the sleeve meets the bodice, below the armpit) at sides are also came from the kosode of common folks, its origin is not clear that whether it is for convenience of putting on and off, or some says it is for heat release and others say it is an invention of prostitutes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although &quot;miyatsuguchi,&quot; small opening in the side of some traditional Japanese clothing (located where the sleeve meets the bodice, below the armpit) at sides also came from the kosode of common folks, its origin is not clear as to whether it is for convenience of putting it on and taking it off, or some say it is for heat release and others say it is an invention of prostitutes.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although &apos;miyatsuguchi,&apos; small opening in the side of some traditional Japanese clothing (located where the sleeve meets the bodice, below the armpit) at sides also came from the kosode of common folks, its origin is not clear as to whether it is for convenience of putting it on and taking it off, or some say it is for heat release and others say it is an invention of prostitutes.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="74">
<j>「留袖」にしろ「身八つ口」にしろ、現在の着物の原型はこのころの庶民の着物に端を発する物が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many garments like tomesode and also miyatsuguchi, archetype of today&apos;s kimono take root of in the kimono of common people prevailed in around this time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many garments like tomesode and also miyatsuguchi, archetype of today&apos;s kimono are rooted in the kimono of common people prevailing around this time.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many garments like &apos;tomesode&apos; and also &apos;miyatsuguchi,&apos; archetype of today&apos;s kimono are rooted in the kimono of common people prevailing around this time.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>その流行の発端をつくるのはたいがい遊女、芸者、そして歌舞伎役者であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dispatcher of the fashion were almost always prostitutes, geisha and kabuki actors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dispatchers of fashion were almost always prostitutes, geisha and kabuki actors.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dispatchers of fashion were almost always prostitutes, geisha and kabuki actors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>ただし、これらの流行の恩恵にあずかれるのは地方の富裕な町人どまりであったと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it is thought that beneficiary of these new fashion were just the rich local townsmen at the longest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is thought that beneficiary of these new fashions were just the rich local townsmen in the long run.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is thought that beneficiary of these new fashions were just the rich local townsmen in the long run.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="77">
<j>「打掛」は庶民には無縁の物と考えられているが、公家や武家に準じた身分を持つ町人などの中には、家の儀礼などに打掛を着用するものもいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although it is thought that uchikake was not for common people, some townsmen who has etat of quasi-court noble or quasi-bushi class clad uchikake for rituals of the family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although it is thought that uchikake was not for common people, some townsmen who has etat of quasi-court noble or quasi-bushi class clad uchikake for rituals of the family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it is thought that &apos;uchikake&apos; was not for common people, some townsmen who has quasi-court noble or quasi-samurai class clad uchikake for rituals of the family.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションを補足するなどしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="78">
<j>ちなみに時代劇では庶民の着物は黒襟と決まっているが、この流行は幕末の物であり、元禄時代が舞台の「水戸黄門」に出てくるのはおかしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By the way, although in costume dramas, kimono of the common people are stock example that with black collars, this fashion came out from the last days of Tokugawa Shogunate, thus it is strange that this fashion appears in the drama &quot;Mito Komon&quot; where setting of the time is Genroku era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By the way, although in costume dramas, kimono of the common people are stock examples with black collars, this fashion came from the last days of the Tokugawa Shogunate, thus it is strange that this fashion appears in the drama &quot;Mito Komon&quot; where time is depicted as the Genroku era.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Incidentally, although in costume dramas, kimono of the common people are stock examples with black collars, this fashion came from the last days of the Tokugawa Shogunate, thus it is strange that this fashion appears in the TV drama &apos;Mitokomon&apos; where time is depicted as the Genroku era.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 こぶまき(id:38278), Mintleaf(id:2216), U.S.S.Momotaro(id:646), 紗羅 憐霞(id:170382), Goki(id:7107), 「あなたには関係ない」(id:49400), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>