<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>白酒 (日本酒)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">White sake (Japanese sake)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">White sake (Japanese sake)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">shirozake (Japanese sake)</e>
<cmt>white sake→shirozake</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>白酒（しろざけ）とは、雛祭りにおいて祝いのために出される酒のことを指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">White sake refers to a sake served to celebrate the Doll&apos;s Festival.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">White sake refers to a sake served to celebrate the Doll&apos;s Festival.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shirozake refers to a sake served to celebrate the Hinamatsuri (the Doll&apos;s Festival).</e>
<cmt>用語集に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>一般的な製法は、蒸したもち米に同量以上のみりんを加えてかき混ぜるか、蒸したもち米に焼酎と米麹を加えるなどして仕込んでおいたものを、数週間後に臼で引きおろす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is usually made by adding the equivalent or greater quantity of sweet cooking sake (mirin) to steamed mochi rice and mixing, or adding shochu (distilled liquor) and malted rice to steamed mochi rice and leaving it to ferment for a few weeks and then grinding with a mortar.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is usually made by adding the equivalent or greater quantity of sweet cooking sake (mirin) to steamed mochi rice and mixing, or adding shochu (distilled liquor) and malted rice to steamed mochi rice and leaving it to ferment for a few weeks and then grinding with a mortar.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is usually made by adding the equivalent or greater quantity of sweet cooking sake (mirin) to steamed mochi-gome (glutinous rice) and mixing, or adding shochu (distilled spirit) and malted rice to steamed mochi rice and leaving it to ferment for a few weeks and then grinding with a mortar.</e>
<cmt>用語集に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="3">
<j>白酒の製法は、博多地方において古くから造られていた「練酒」が起源であると伝えられており、江戸時代から雛祭りの供物として扱われるようになったのは、平安時代からの風習である上巳（桃の節句）において、室町時代からモモの花を浸した酒を飲んでいたものが変化したと伝えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the method of manufacturing white sake originates in the Nerizake brewed in the Hakata region from ancient times and that, from the Edo Period, it came to be used as an offering in the Doll&apos;s festival, a custom from the Heian Period, in place of the peach leaves soaked in sake which had been used from the Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the method of manufacturing white sake originates in the Nerizake brewed in the Hakata region from ancient times and that, from the Edo Period, it came to be used as an offering in the Doll&apos;s festival, a custom from the Heian Period, in place of the peach leaves soaked in sake which had been used from the Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the method of manufacturing shirozake originates in the &apos;nerizake&apos; brewed in the Hakata region from ancient times and that, from the Edo Period, it came to be used as an offering in the Doll&apos;s festival, a custom from the Heian Period, in place of the peach leaves soaked in sake which had been used from the Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt>white sake→shirozake</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Opponent(id:720), Izayohi(id:13095), Ponta2(id:129030), ととりん(id:31982), 水野白楓(id:22811), Nighthawks(id:36125), Point136(id:211299), Hamasaki gion higashi(id:144985), Greenland4(id:114494), JRE(id:153879), ウェルワィ(id:15692), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>