<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>ゆば</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yuba (bean curd skin)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yuba (bean curd skin)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yuba (bean curd skin)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>ゆば（湯葉、湯波、油皮）は、大豆の加工食品の一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yuba is a processed food made from soybeans.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yuba is a processed food made from soybeans.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yuba is a processed food made from soybeans.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>豆乳を加熱した時、ラムスデン現象によって液面に形成される膜を、竹串などを使って引き上げる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When soy milk is brought to boil, due to the Ramsden phenomenon, a film or skin forms on the surface which is lifted with utensils such as bamboo skewers.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When soy milk is brought to boil, due to the Ramsden phenomenon a film or skin forms on the surface, which is lifted with utensils such as bamboo skewers.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When soy milk is brought to boil, due to the Ramsden phenomenon a film or skin forms on the surface, which is lifted with utensils such as bamboo skewers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>これは湯葉として知られ、植物性蛋白質に富む精進料理の材料である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That protein-rich film is referred to as yuba which is one of the popular ingredients for vegetarian cuisine.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That protein-rich film is referred to as yuba, and is a popular ingredient for vegetarian cuisine.</e>
<cmt>replaced “which” with “and”; one of the-&gt;a</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That protein-rich film is referred to as yuba, and is a popular ingredient for vegetarian cuisine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>精進料理の材料の一つとして、日本のゆばは約1200年前に最澄が中国から仏教・茶・ゆばを持ち帰ったのが初めと云われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that, yuba, as an ingredient for vegetarian cuisine, was seen for the first time in Japan approximately 1200 years ago when Saicho brought it back from China along with the Buddhism and tea.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that yuba as an ingredient for vegetarian cuisine was seen for the first time in Japan approximately 1200 years ago, when Saicho brought it back from China along with Buddhism and tea.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that yuba as an ingredient for vegetarian cuisine was seen for the first time in Japan approximately 1200 years ago, when Saicho brought it back from China along with Buddhism and tea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>日本最初のゆばは、現在の京都府京都市と滋賀県大津市の間に位置する比叡山の天台宗総本山の延暦寺に伝わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first yuba in Japan was introduced to the Grand Head Temple of the Tendai sect Enryaku-ji Temple at Mt. Hiei located between the present Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture and Otsu City, Shiga Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first yuba in Japan was introduced to the Grand Head Temple of the Tendai sect Enryaku-ji Temple at Mt. Hiei, located between the present Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture and Otsu City, Shiga Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first yuba in Japan was introduced to the Grand Head Temple of the Tendai sect Enryaku-ji Temple at Mt. Hiei, located between the present Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture and Otsu City, Shiga Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>比叡山麓の坂本(現在の滋賀県大津市)に童歌「山の坊さん何食うて暮らす、ゆばの付け焼き、定心坊（お漬物）」として唄われたことが歴史的な記録に残る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to some historical records remaining today, there was an old children&apos;s song in Sakamoto at the base of Mt. Hiei with its lyrics including a passage saying, &apos;Grilled yuba and pickled vegetables are what do those monks in the mountain.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to some historical records remaining today, there was an old children&apos;s song in Sakamoto at the base of Mt. Hiei, the lyrics of which included a passage saying, &apos;what do those monks on the mountain eat, Grilled yuba and pickled vegetables.&apos;</e>
<cmt>rephrased the song lyric</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to some historical records remaining today, there was an old children&apos;s song in Sakamoto at the base of Mt. Hiei, the lyrics of which included a passage saying, &apos;what do those monks on the mountain eat, Grilled yuba and pickled vegetables.&apos;</e>
<cmt>シングルクォート</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>日本のゆば</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese Yuba</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese Yuba</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese Yuba</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>日本で最初にゆばの伝わった比叡山麗の京都市や近江(現在の滋賀県大津市)、日光市、身延町といった古くからの門前町が産地として有名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto City and Omi (the present Otsu City, Shiga Prefecture) at the base of Mt. Hiei where yuba was first introduced in Japan in addition to Nikko City and Minobu Town are well known as production centers of yuba.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto City and Omi (the present Otsu City, Shiga Prefecture) at the base of Mt. Hiei, where yuba was first introduced in Japan, along with Nikko City and Minobu Town, are well known as production centers of yuba.</e>
<cmt>prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto City and Omi (the present Otsu City, Shiga Prefecture) at the base of Mt. Hiei, where yuba was first introduced in Japan, along with Nikko City and Minobu Town, are well known as production centers of yuba.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>京都と身延では「湯葉」、日光では「湯波」と表記する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kyoto and Minobu, yuba is written in kanji representing &apos;leaves of hot water,&apos;whereas, in Nikko, it is written in kanji meaning &apos;ripples of hot water.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Kyoto and Minobu, yuba is written with kanji representing &apos;leaves of hot water,&apos; whereas in Nikko, it is written with kanji meaning &apos;ripples of hot water.&apos;</e>
<cmt>spacing; prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Kyoto and Minobu, yuba is written with kanji representing &apos;湯葉 (leaves of hot water),&apos; whereas in Nikko, it is written with kanji meaning &apos;湯波 (ripples of hot water).&apos;</e>
<cmt>漢字を追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>日本では、引き上げた湯葉を生湯葉（または引き上げ湯葉）と呼び、料理の材料にする他、刺身と同様にそのまま食べる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan, they call yuba lifted from boiling soy milk fresh yuba (a delicacy composed of fresh layers of the skin of soybean milk) (or hikiage (lifted) yuba) and, aside from using it as ingredient for cooking, eat it as is without cooking which is referred to as the&apos;yuba sashimi.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan, they call yuba lifted from boiling soy milk fresh yuba (or hikiage – lifted - yuba) and, aside from using it as an ingredient for cooking, eat it as is without cooking, which is referred to as &apos;yuba sashimi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>deleted the parenthetical explanation of yuba – it seemed odd, considering that this whole article is an explanation of what yuba is</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan, they call yuba lifted from boiling soy milk fresh yuba (or hikiage – lifted - yuba) and, aside from using it as an ingredient for cooking, eat it as is without cooking, which is referred to as &apos;yuba sashimi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>また、普茶料理でもよく使用される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yuba is also often used in the Fucha-ryori cuisine (Chinese-style Buddhist vegetarian cuisine).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yuba is also often used in Fucha-ryori cuisine (Chinese-style Buddhist vegetarian cuisine).</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yuba is also often used in Fucha-ryori cuisine (Chinese-style Buddhist vegetarian cuisine).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>京都の湯葉は膜の端に串を入れて引き上げるため一枚である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kyoto, since they slip the skewer underneath the outer edge of yuba to lift it, yuba comes out in single-sheet form.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Kyoto, since they slip the skewer underneath the outer edge of yuba to lift it, yuba comes out in single-sheet form.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Kyoto, since they slip the skewer underneath the outer edge of yuba to lift it, yuba comes out in single-sheet form.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>それに対し、日光の湯波は膜の中央に串を入れて二つ折りにするように引き上げるため二枚重ねとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Nikko, on the other hand, they slip the skewer underneath the center of yuba to lift it, yuba comes out in two-folded form.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Nikko, on the other hand, they slip the skewer underneath the center of yuba to lift it, yuba comes out folded in two.</e>
<cmt>folded in two</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Nikko, on the other hand, they slip the skewer underneath the center of yuba to lift it, yuba comes out folded in two.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>このため、京都のものは薄く、日光のものはボリューム感があるものになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In view of the above, the Kyoto yuba is thin, whereas, the Nikko yuba is more substantial.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In view of the above, the Kyoto yuba is thin, whereas, the Nikko yuba is more substantial.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In view of the above, the Kyoto yuba is thin, whereas, the Nikko yuba is more substantial.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="14">
<j>生湯葉のほかに、生湯葉を乾燥させた物、半乾燥の状態のうちに巻いたり、結び目を作った物など、様々な種類が市販されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yuba is available in various forms including dried yuba as well as yuba which has been made into a roll or knot while it was semidry.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yuba is available in various forms including dried yuba as well as yuba which has been made into a roll or knot while it was partially dry.</e>
<cmt>semi-&gt;partially</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yuba is available in various forms including dried yuba as well as yuba which has been made into a roll or knot while it was partially dry.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>巻いた状態の物は吸い物の具にされる事が多く、シート状の物は、復して各種の湯葉巻き料理にされる事が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rolled yuba is often used in soup, whereas, yuba sheets are often softened by soaking in warm water prior to being used for making various bean curd sheet rolls.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rolled yuba is often used in soup, whereas yuba sheets are often softened by soaking in warm water prior to being used for making various bean curd sheet rolls.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rolled yuba is often used in soup, whereas yuba sheets are often softened by soaking in warm water prior to being used for making various bean curd sheet rolls.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>中国のゆば</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chinese Yuba</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chinese Yuba</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chinese Yuba</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="16">
<j>中国では、シート状に干した「腐皮」（フーピー fǔpí）と、棒状に絞ってから干した「腐竹」（フーチュー fǔzhú）が多く、日本の湯葉のような巻いた形状で市販されることは希である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In China, yuba comes predominantly in either as &apos;fupi&apos; (fǔpí) which is dried yuba sheets or as &apos;fuchu&apos;(fǔzhú), dried yuba sticks that were made by wringing fresh yuba into the stick shape and it is very seldom available in the roll form that is common in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In China, yuba comes predominantly as either &apos;fupi&apos; (fǔpí), which is dried yuba sheets, or &apos;fuchu&apos; (fǔzhú), dried yuba sticks made by wringing fresh yuba into the stick shape, and it is very seldom available in the roll form that is common in Japan.</e>
<cmt>spacing; punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In China, yuba comes predominantly as either &apos;fupi&apos; (fǔpí), which is dried yuba sheets, or &apos;fuchu&apos; (fǔzhú), dried yuba sticks made by wringing fresh yuba into the stick shape, and it is very seldom available in the roll form that is common in Japan.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォート</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>結んだ状態の「腐皮結」（フーピージエ fǔpíjié）は中国でも作られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The &apos;fupijie&apos; (fǔpíjié) which is yuba in the form of knots is being made in China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yuba in the form of knots, called &apos;fupijie&apos; (fǔpíjié), is made in China.</e>
<cmt>rephrased for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yuba in the form of knots, called &apos;fupijie&apos; (fǔpíjié), is made in China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="18">
<j>浙江省の杭州市は、「腐皮」の産地として知られており、名物料理のひとつに、湯葉を素揚げにした「脆炸響鈴」（ツイジャーシアンリン cuìzháxiǎnglíng）という料理がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hangzhou City, Zhejiang Province is well known as the production center of the&apos;fupi&apos; yuba, with one of the signature dishes of the region being &apos;tsuijartialing&apos; (cuìzháxiǎnglíng) which is deep-fat fried yuba.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hangzhou City, Zhejiang Province, is well known as the production center of &apos;fupi&apos; yuba, with one of the signature dishes of the region being &apos;tsuijartialing&apos; (cuìzháxiǎnglíng), which is deep fried yuba.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hangzhou City, Zhejiang Province, is well known as the production center of &apos;fupi&apos; yuba, with one of the signature dishes of the region being &apos;tsuijartialing&apos; (cuìzháxiǎnglíng), which is deep fried yuba.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォート</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="19">
<j>香港や広州市でよく見られる広東料理の点心として、「鮮竹捲」（シンチョッキュン）、「鮮竹紮」（シンチョッザーッ）、「腐皮捲」（フーペイキュン）がよく食べられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the Cantonese dim sum dishes common in Hong Kong and Guangzhou City, sin jyut gyun (tofu skin rolls), sin jyut zaat (tofu skin rolls) and fu pei gyun (tofu skin rolls) are popular.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the Cantonese dim sum dishes common in Hong Kong and Guangzhou City, sin jyut gyun (tofu skin rolls), sin jyut zaat (tofu skin rolls) and fu pei gyun (tofu skin rolls) are popular.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the Cantonese dim sum dishes common in Hong Kong and Guangzhou City, sin jyut gyun (tofu skin rolls), sin jyut zaat (tofu skin rolls) and fu pei gyun (tofu skin rolls) are popular.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>これは豚肉、シイタケ、ニンジンなどの拍子木切りを湯葉で巻き、オイスターソースなどで煮る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These are tofu skin rolls stuffed with various ingredients including pork, shiitake mushrooms and carrots all cut into the matchstick size and then cooked in the sauce made with oyster sauce and other seasonings.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These are tofu skin rolls stuffed with various ingredients including pork, shiitake mushrooms and carrots all cut to matchstick size and then cooked in the sauce made with oyster sauce and other seasonings.</e>
<cmt>prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These are tofu skin rolls stuffed with various ingredients including pork, shiitake mushrooms and carrots all cut to matchstick size and then cooked in the sauce made with oyster sauce and other seasonings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>そのあと更に蒸籠で蒸したものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After being cooked in the sauce mentioned above, the tofu skin rolls are steamed in a bamboo steamer before being served.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then the tofu skin rolls are steamed in a bamboo steamer before being served.</e>
<cmt>shortened to “then” (that bit about “after being... mentioned above” is not in the original</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then the tofu skin rolls are steamed in a bamboo steamer before being served.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="22">
<j>「腐竹」は河南省の長葛腐竹、湖南省の永興腐竹、広西チワン族自治区の桂林腐竹など、各地に産地が点在している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fuchu&apos; is produced in various locations in China including Kanan Province where it is known as Changge fuzhu (the yuba of Changge City), Hunan Province where it is known as Yongxing fuzhu (the yuba of Yongxing Prefecture) and the Municipality of Guangxi Zhuangzu where it is known as Guilin fuzhu (the yuba of Guilin City).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fuchu&apos; is produced in various locations in China including Kanan Province where it is known as Changge fuzhu (the yuba of Changge City), Hunan Province where it is known as Yongxing fuzhu (the yuba of Yongxing Prefecture) and the Municipality of Guangxi Zhuangzu where it is known as Guilin fuzhu (the yuba of Guilin City).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fuchu&apos; is produced in various locations in China including Kanan Province where it is known as Changge fuzhu (the yuba of Changge City), Hunan Province where it is known as Yongxing fuzhu (the yuba of Yongxing Prefecture) and the Municipality of Guangxi Zhuangzu where it is known as Guilin fuzhu (the yuba of Guilin City).</e>
<cmt>シングルクォート</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>「腐竹」は、湯で戻して、煮物の材料にしたり、鍋料理の具として食べられることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is common that &apos;fuchu&apos;is softened by soaking in hot water prior to being cooked in sauce or used in hot pot cooking.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is common for &apos;fuchu&apos; to be softened by soaking in hot water prior to cooking in sauce or use in hot pot cooking.</e>
<cmt>prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is common for &apos;fuchu&apos; to be softened by soaking in hot water prior to cooking in sauce or use in hot pot cooking.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォート</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Tomchiukc(id:5469), Ypacaraí(id:11031), Aetos(id:111706), マクガイア(id:33346), 0null0(id:582), Hhaithait(id:37092), Kstigarbha(id:13376), Nighthawks(id:36125), 二八(id:10408), Kaidog(id:86957), Opponent(id:720), 竃馬(id:102733), VolkovBot(id:105371), SuisuiBot(id:10165), Point136(id:211299), Yas(id:739), 竹麦魚(id:11012), Corwin(id:973), Louperibot(id:128971), Mayuno(id:143771), Saniboh(id:10117), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>