<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>陰摩羅鬼</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Onmoraki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Onmoraki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Onmoraki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>陰摩羅鬼、陰魔羅鬼（おんもらき）は、中国や日本の古書にある怪鳥。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Onmoraki is a monster bird written in Chinese and Japanese classics.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Onmoraki is a monster bird written in Chinese and Japanese classics.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Onmoraki is a monster bird written in Chinese and Japanese classics.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>経典『経典大蔵経』によれば、新しい死体から生じた気が化けたものとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to a Buddhist scripture, &quot;Buddhist Scripture Daizo-kyo Sutra (the Tripitaka),&quot; it was a transformation of a spirit that rose from a new corpse.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to a Buddhist scripture, &quot;Kyoten (Buddhist Scripture) Daizo-kyo Sutra&quot; (the Tripitaka), it was the transformation of a spirit that rose from a new corpse.</e>
<cmt>形式</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to a Buddhist scripture, &quot;Kyoten (Buddhist Scripture) Daizo-kyo Sutra&quot; (the Tripitaka), it was the transformation of a spirit that rose from a new corpse.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>充分な供養を受けていない死体が化けたもので、経文読みを怠っている僧侶のもとに現れるともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was the transformation of a corpse that did not receive a proper kuyo (a memorial service for the dead) and said to have appeared before a monk that failed in reading Buddhist manuscripts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was the transformation of a corpse that did not receive a proper kuyo (a memorial service for the dead) and said to have appeared before a monk that failed in reading Buddhist manuscripts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was the transformation of a corpse that did not receive a proper kuyo (a memorial service for the dead) and said to have appeared before a monk that failed in reading Buddhist manuscripts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>古典の画図においては鳥山石燕の画集『今昔画図続百鬼』に描かれており、解説文には中国の古書『清尊録』からの引用で、姿は鶴のようで、体色が黒く、眼光は灯火のようで、羽を震わせて甲高く鳴くとある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its was depicted in a diagram within classics such as the art book by Sekien TORIYAMA, &quot;Konjaku Gazu Zoku Hyakki&quot; (Continued Illustrations of the Many Demons Past and Present), in a note quoted from a Chinese classic &quot;Seisonroku,&quot; and its appearance was like that of crane, had black body color, and its glittering eyes was that of a flame and sang in a high pitch note while shaking its wings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its was depicted in a diagram within classics such as the art book by Sekien TORIYAMA, &quot;Konjaku Gazu Zoku Hyakki&quot; (Continued Illustrations of the Many Demons Past and Present), in a note quoted from a Chinese classic &quot;Seisonroku,&quot; and its appearance was like that of a crane, having black body color, and its glittering eyes were like flame, and it sang in a high pitch note while shaking its wings.</e>
<cmt>文法</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its was depicted in a diagram within classics such as the art book by Sekien TORIYAMA, &quot;Konjaku Gazu Zoku Hyakki&quot; (Continued Illustrations of the Many Demons Past and Present), in a note quoted from a Chinese classic &quot;Seisonroku,&quot; and its appearance was like that of a crane, having black body color, and its glittering eyes were like flame, and it sang in a high pitch note while shaking its wings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>この『清尊録』には以下のような中国の陰摩羅鬼の話がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was a following story of Chinese onmoraki within this &quot;Seisonroku.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following story of Chinese onmoraki is included in the &quot;Seisonroku.&quot;</e>
<cmt>言い回し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following story of Chinese onmoraki is included in the &quot;Seisonroku.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>宋 (王朝)の時代のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was during the period of Sung Dynasty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was during the period of Sung Dynasty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was during the period of Sung Dynasty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>鄭州市の崔嗣復という人物が、都の外の寺の宝堂の上で寝ていたところ、自分を叱る声で目を覚ました。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The person named 崔嗣復 (Saishifuku) of Zhengzhou city woke from a voice that shouted to him while he slept on top of a hodo (treasure hall) of a temple outside a capital.</e>
<cmt>崔嗣復→Saishifuku [定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A person named &quot;崔嗣復&quot; (Shifuku SAI) of Zhengzhou city woke from a voice that shouted at him while he slept on top of a hodo (treasure hall) of a temple outside the capital city.</e>
<cmt>言い回し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A person named &quot;崔嗣復&quot; (Shifuku SAI) of Zhengzhou city woke from a voice that shouted at him while he slept on top of a hodo (treasure hall) of a temple outside the capital city.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>見ると、前述のような外観の怪鳥がおり、崔が逃げると姿を消した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was a monster bird of a similar appearance as mentioned before and disappeared when Sai escaped.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was a monster bird whose appearance was similar to the one described before, and it disappeared when Sai escaped.</e>
<cmt>言い回し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was a monster bird whose appearance was similar to the one described before, and it disappeared when Sai escaped.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>崔が寺の僧侶に事情を尋ねると、ここにはそのような妖怪はいないが、数日前に死人を仮置きしたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Sai asked the monk of the temple as what happened, there was no monster there as such but temporarily stored the dead several days ago.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Sai asked a monk of the temple about what had happened, there was no monster there as such but they temporarily stored a body of the dead several days ago.</e>
<cmt>言い回し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Sai asked a monk of the temple about what had happened, there was no monster there as such but they temporarily stored a body of the dead several days ago.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>都に戻って寺の僧に尋ねると、それは新しい死体の気が変化して生まれた陰摩羅鬼とのことだった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Upon returning to the capital, he asked a monk of a temple who told him that it was an onmoraki that was born by transforming from the spirit of the newly dead.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Upon returning to the capital, he asked a monk of a temple about the bird, who then told him that it should be an onmoraki that was born transmuting from the spirit of the newly dead.</e>
<cmt>言い回し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Upon returning to the capital, he asked a monk of a temple about the bird, who then told him that it should be an onmoraki that was born transmuting from the spirit of the newly dead.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>日本では江戸時代の書物『太平百物語』に、『清尊録』に類似した陰摩羅鬼の話がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was a story of Onmoraki similar as the one in &quot;Seisonroku&quot; in &quot;Taihei hyaku Monogatari&quot; (100 Ghost Stories) a literature written during the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A story of Onmoraki appears in &quot;Taihei hyaku Monogatari&quot; (100 Ghost Stories), written during the Edo period, which is similar to the one in the &quot;Seisonroku.&quot;</e>
<cmt>文脈調整</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A story of Onmoraki appears in &quot;Taihei hyaku Monogatari&quot; (100 Ghost Stories), written during the Edo period, which is similar to the one in the &quot;Seisonroku.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>山城国（現・京都府）で宅兵衛という男が寺でうたた寝をしていると、自分を呼ぶ声で目を覚ました。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When a man named Takube drifted off to sleep at the temple in Yamashiro Province (current Kyoto Prefecture), he woke from a voice calling out his name.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When a man named Takube drifted off to sleep at a temple in Yamashiro Province (present-day Kyoto Prefecture), he was awaken by a voice calling out his name.</e>
<cmt>文法、形式</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When a man named Takube drifted off to sleep at a temple in Yamashiro Province (present-day Kyoto Prefecture), he was awaken by a voice calling out his name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>見るとそこには怪鳥がいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He then saw a monster bird there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He then saw a monster bird there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He then saw a monster bird there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>驚いた宅兵衛が逃げ出して陰から様子を伺っていると、そのまま怪鳥は姿を消した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Surprised Takube escaped and while he observed from shadows, the monster bird just disappeared.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Surprised Takube escaped, and while he saw the bird from his hiding place, it disappeared.</e>
<cmt>言い回し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Surprised Takube escaped, and while he saw the bird from his hiding place, it disappeared.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>宅兵衛が寺の長老に尋ねたところ、新しい屍の気が陰摩羅鬼になると経典大蔵経にあり、最近寺に仮置きした死人によるものだろうということだった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Takube asked the elder of the temple, he was told that Buddhist scripture Daizokyo stated that the spirit of the newly dead transforms into Onmoraki, and it was caused by the corpse temporarily stored at the temple recently.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Takube asked the elder of the temple, he was told that &quot;Kyoten Daizo-kyo Sutra&quot; stated that the spirit of the newly dead would transform into Onmoraki, and it might be caused by the corpse temporarily stored at the temple recently.</e>
<cmt>形式</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Takube asked the elder of the temple, he was told that &quot;Kyoten Daizo-kyo Sutra&quot; stated that the spirit of the newly dead would transform into Onmoraki, and it might be caused by the corpse temporarily stored at the temple recently.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="16">
<j>陰摩羅鬼の名の由来は、仏教で悟りを妨げる魔物の摩羅（魔羅）に「陰」「鬼」の字をつけることで鬼・魔物の意味を強調したもの、もしくは障害を意味する「陰摩」と「羅刹天」の混合されたものとの説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The origin of the name of Onmoraki was adding words, &apos;in&apos; (negative) and &apos;oni&apos; (ogre) to the monster moro that prevented one&apos;s nirvana to stress on the definition of ogre and monster, and another theory stated that it was the mixture of &apos;Onmo&apos; and &apos;Rasetsuten&apos; (Rakshasa) having the definition of causing obstacles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name Onmoraki was reportedly created by adding words &apos;in&apos; (negative) and &apos;oni&apos; (ogre or ghost) to a monster &apos;mara&apos; that hindered Buddhists from attaining enlightenment, to put stress on the meanings of ogre and monster, while another theory has it that it was a mixture of &apos;Onmo&apos; meaning obstacles and &apos;Rasetsuten&apos; (Rakshasa, an evil spirit).</e>
<cmt>言い回し、補足</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name Onmoraki was reportedly created by adding words &apos;in&apos; (negative) and &apos;oni&apos; (ogre or ghost) to a monster &apos;mara&apos; that hindered Buddhists from attaining enlightenment, to put stress on the meanings of ogre and monster, while another theory has it that it was a mixture of &apos;Onmo&apos; meaning obstacles and &apos;Rasetsuten&apos; (Rakshasa, an evil spirit).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 逃亡者(id:14864), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>