<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>打太刀</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Uchitachi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Uchitachi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Uchitachi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>打太刀（うちたち）とは、武術（特に剣術）、武道（特に剣道）において用いられる用語の一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Uchitachi is one of the terms used in martial art, especially in swordplay, and Budo (martial arts), especially in Japanese art of fencing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Uchitachi is a term used in martial arts, especially in swordplay and budo (Japanese martial arts) such as in the Japanese art of fencing.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Uchitachi is a term used in martial arts, especially in swordplay and budo (Japanese martial arts) such as in the Japanese art of fencing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>型（形）を行う際に仕太刀に倒される（技を受ける）役の人物を意味する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term &quot;Uchitachi&quot; indicates a person who has the role to be defeated by Shidachi, or to receive Shidachi&apos;s techniques, in kata (standard form of a movement, posture, etc.) practice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term &quot;uchitachi&quot; indicates a person who has the role of being defeated by a shidachi, or to defend against that shidachi&apos;s techniques, in kata (standard form of a movement or posture) practice.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term &quot;uchitachi&quot; indicates a person who has the role of being defeated by a shidachi, or to defend against that shidachi&apos;s techniques, in kata (standard form of a movement or posture) practice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>日本剣道形では単に倒されるだけでなく、常に一瞬早く動き仕太刀の動作を引き出してやる師匠役でもあり、また、全て避けられることになっているとは言え打太刀からも技を打つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Nihon Kendo Kata, Uchitachi not only is defeated but also plays the role as an instructor who always moves one step earlier to withdraw Shidachi&apos;s movement and, though all Uchitachi&apos;s techniques are to be evaded, also initiates movement to attack.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Nihon Kendo Kata, the uchitachi is not only defeated but also plays the role of an instructor who always moves one step earlier to draw out the shidachi&apos;s attack movement and, though all uchitachi&apos;s techniques are designed to evade attack, he may also initiate movement to attack.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Nihon Kendo Kata, the uchitachi is not only defeated but also plays the role of an instructor who always moves one step earlier to draw out the shidachi&apos;s attack movement and, though all uchitachi&apos;s techniques are designed to evade attack, he may also initiate movement to attack.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Himazin(id:22034), Point136(id:211299), Izayohi(id:13095), Bit(id:2197), Hermeneus(id:380), FeZn(id:444), Amaki bo(id:13580), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>