<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>箏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soh (a long Japanese zither with thirteen strings)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soh (a long Japanese zither with thirteen strings)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soh (a long Japanese zither with thirteen strings)</e>
<cmt>trans1のcommentで「箏（そう）の表記は英語のso と紛らわしいため、能　（Noh) と同様に、Sohとしております」となっていました。本ファイル中はそのまま「Soh」にしています。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>箏（そう）は、日本の伝統楽器。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soh is a Japanese traditional musical instrument.</e>
<cmt>箏（そう）の表記は英語のso と紛らわしいため、能　（Noh) と同様に、Sohとしております</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soh is a Japanese traditional musical instrument.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soh is a Japanese traditional musical instrument.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>弦楽器のツィター属に分類される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is classified into the zither group of stringed instruments</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is classified into the zither group of stringed instruments</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is classified into the zither group of stringed instruments.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>一般にことと呼ばれ、「琴」の字を当てられるが、正しくは「箏」であり、「琴（きん）」は本来別の楽器である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is generally called koto and a Chinese character &quot;琴&quot; is used, but to be exact, it should be &quot;箏&quot; and &quot;琴 (kin)&quot; is another musical instrument.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is generally called koto and the Chinese character &quot;琴&quot; is used, but to be exact, it should be &quot;箏&quot; and &quot;琴 (kin)&quot; is another musical instrument.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is generally called koto and the Chinese character &apos;琴&apos; is used, but to be exact, it should be &apos;箏&apos; (soh) and &apos;琴&apos; (kin) is another musical instrument.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。(soh)と読みを補足しました。括弧の位置を訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>最大の違いは、箏では柱（じ）と呼ばれる可動式の支柱で弦の音程を調節するのに対し、琴（きん）では柱が無いことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The biggest difference between the two is that while the tune of Soh is modulated by movable props called ji, there is no prop in the case of kin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The biggest difference between the two is that while the tune of Soh is modulated by movable props called ji, there is no prop in the case of kin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The biggest difference between the two is that while the tune of Soh is modulated by movable props called ji, there is no prop in the case of kin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>※ただし、柱（箏の駒）は「琴柱」の方が一般的である（商品名も琴柱）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">* provided that ji (bridge of Soh) is normally called &quot;kotobasira (琴柱) (bridge of koto) (product&apos;s name is also kotobashira)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">* provided that ji (bridge of Soh) is normally called &quot;kotobasira (琴柱) (bridge of koto) (product&apos;s name is also kotobashira)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Note that ji (bridge of Soh) is normally called &apos;kotobasira&apos; (bridge of koto) (product&apos;s name is also kotobashira).</e>
<cmt>記号削除しました。Note that～に訂正しました。原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。ピリオド補足しました。漢字の表記削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>箏の台は琴台（きんだい）と必ず琴の方を使う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A stand on which Soh is put is called kindai (琴台), for which a Chainese character &quot;琴&quot; is always used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A stand on which Soh is put is called kindai (琴台), for which a Chainese character &quot;琴&quot; is always used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A stand on which Soh is put is called kindai, for which the term &quot;kin&quot; is always used.</e>
<cmt>Chineseスペル訂正しました。漢字の表記削除しました。the termに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>なお箏を数える時は一面、二面（いちめん、にめん）と数える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When counting the number of Soh, a figure should be followed by the term &quot;men (面)&quot;, like ichi (one)-men, ni (two)-men etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When counting the number of Soh, a figure should be followed by the term &quot;men (面),&quot; like ichi (one)-men, ni (two)-men etc.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When counting the number of Soh, a figure should be followed by the term &quot;men,&quot; like ichi (one)-men, ni (two)-men etc.</e>
<cmt>漢字の表記削除しました。不要なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>古代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ancient times</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ancient times</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ancient times</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>日本古来からある「こと」は和琴（「わごん」または「やまとごと」）と呼ばれ、6本の弦を持つ（まれに5本）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Koto&quot; in the ancient times of Japan was called &quot;wagon&quot; (or yamatogoto) and it had six strings (five strings in rare cases).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Koto&quot; in the ancient times of Japan was called &quot;wagon&quot; (or yamatogoto) and it had six strings (five strings in rare cases).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koto&apos; in the ancient times of Japan was called &apos;wagon&apos; (or &apos;yamatogoto&apos;) and it had six strings (five strings in rare cases).</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>弥生時代から奈良時代の遺跡などに発掘例がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some were found at the ruins that were constructed from the Yayoi period to the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some were found at the ruins that were constructed from the Yayoi period to the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some were found at the ruins that were constructed from the Yayoi period to the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>現在も雅楽に含まれる「国風歌舞」（御神楽など）で演奏される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At present, wagon is used for playing one of gagaku (ancient Japanese court dance and music) called &quot;Kokufu kabu&quot; (such as mikagura (music performed in court Shinto ceremony)).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At present, wagon is used for playing one of gagaku (ancient Japanese court dance and music) called &quot;Kokufu kabu&quot; (such as mikagura - music performed in court Shinto ceremony).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At present, wagon is used for playing one of gagaku (ancient Japanese court dance and music) called &apos;Kokufu kabu&apos; (such as mikagura - music performed in court Shinto ceremony).</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。不要なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>また、平安時代にはやはり雅楽の楽曲種類の一つである「催馬楽（さいばら）」（在来の民謡などを当時の渡来音楽である雅楽の編成に編曲した管絃伴奏付き歌曲）の伴奏楽器として、和琴が加わることがあった（現在では普通、催馬楽に和琴が加わることはない）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Heian period, wagon was used as an accompanying instrument for playing one of gagaku called &quot;Saibara&quot; (a song accompanied by wind and stringed instruments which was created by arranging indigenous folk music to the style of newly imported gagaku) (at present, wagon is rarely used for playing Saibara).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Heian period, wagon was used as an accompanying instrument for playing one of gagaku called &quot;Saibara&quot; (a song accompanied by wind and stringed instruments which was created by arranging indigenous folk music to the style of newly imported gagaku) (at present, wagon is rarely used for playing Saibara).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Heian period, wagon was used as an accompanying instrument for playing one of gagaku called &apos;Saibara&apos; (a song accompanied by wind and stringed instruments which was created by arranging indigenous folk music to the style of newly imported gagaku) (at present, wagon is rarely used for playing Saibara).</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="12">
<j>また、日本の古代音楽を最も古い形のまま現在まで伝承しているとされる恐山などのイタコが、交霊の際に演奏する楽器の一つとしても用いられる（ただし和琴を使うのはごく一部で、一般にイタコが用いる楽器は梓弓が多い）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wagon is also played by itako (the Japanese shaman) of Osore-zan Mountain in the ceremony of korei, and this music is believed to be the oldest existent Japanese ancient music (provided that a small minority of itako use wagon and azusayumi (a bow made of Japanese cherry birch) is generally used by other itako).</e>
<cmt>交霊→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wagon is also played by itako (the Japanese shaman) of Osore-zan Mountain in the ceremony of korei, and this music is believed to be the oldest existing Japanese ancient music (provided that a small minority of itako use wagon and azusayumi - a bow made of Japanese cherry birch - is generally used by other itako).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wagon is also played by itako (the Japanese shaman) of Osore-zan Mountain in the ceremony of necromancy, and this music is believed to be the oldest existing Japanese ancient music (provided that a small minority of itako use wagon and azusayumi - a bow made of Japanese cherry birch - is generally used by other itako).</e>
<cmt>交霊→necromancy</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>アイヌの伝統楽器の箏であるトンコリ（カーとも言う）」は、和琴と類似した構造を持つ（ただし弦は5本）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tonkori (also called ka), a traditional stringed instrument of Ainu tribe, has a similar structure with that of wagon (provided that it has five strings).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tonkori (also called ka), a traditional stringed instrument of Ainu tribe, has a similar structure with that of wagon (provided that it has five strings).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tonkori (also known as &quot;ka&quot;), a traditional stringed instrument of Ainu tribe, has a similar structure with that of wagon (provided that it has five strings).</e>
<cmt>(also known as &quot;ka&quot;)に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="14">
<j>一方、後述の奈良時代に唐より伝わることになる中国の箏の起こりは、秦の時代（紀元前3世紀頃）に蒙恬（もうてん）という人物が作ったのが始まりとされるが、伝説に過ぎない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, Chinese Soh, which was imported from Tang in the Nara period, is believed to have been created in the era of Qin (around the third century B.C) by a person called Moten, but it is nothing but a legend.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, the Chinese Soh, imported from Tang during the Nara period, is believed to have been created in the era of Qin (around the third century B.C) by a person called Moten, but it is nothing but a legend.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, the Chinese Soh, imported from Tang during the Nara period, is believed to have been created in the era of Qin (around the third century B.C) by a person called Moten, but it is nothing but a legend.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>奈良・平安時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nara and Heian period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nara and Heian periods</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nara and Heian periods</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="15">
<j>現在日本で広く知られている形の箏は、13本の弦を持ち、奈良時代に唐より伝わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soh which is widely known at present in Japan has thirteen strings, and it was imported from Tang in the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soh widely known at present in Japan has thirteen strings, and was imported from Tang during the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soh widely known at present in Japan has thirteen strings, and was imported from Tang during the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>奈良および平安時代に雅楽の中で用いられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was used in gagaku in the Nara and Heian period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was used in gagaku during the Nara and Heian periods.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was used in gagaku during the Nara and Heian periods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>龍の象徴とされ、現在でも箏の部分の名称として龍頭や龍尾などの名残がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was believed to be the symbol of ryu (dragon) (龍) and the vestage of such belief remains remains in the name of the parts of Soh, such as ryuto (龍頭) and ryubi (龍尾).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was believed to be the symbol of ryu (dragon) (龍) and the vestage of such belief remains remains in the name of the parts of Soh, such as ryuto (龍頭) and ryubi (龍尾).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was believed to be the symbol of ryu (dragon) and the vestige of such belief remains remains in the name of the parts of Soh, such as ryuto (dragon head) and ryubi (dragon tail).</e>
<cmt>vestigeスペル訂正しました。漢字表記を削除しました。説明訳補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>雅楽で用いられる箏を「楽箏（「がくごと」または「がくそう」）」と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soh which is used in gagaku is speciffically called &quot;gaku-goto&quot; or &quot;gaku-Soh&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soh which is used in gagaku is speciffically called &quot;gaku-goto&quot; or &quot;gaku-Soh&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soh which is used in gagaku is specifically called &apos;gaku-goto&apos; or &apos;gaku-Soh.&apos;</e>
<cmt>specificallyスペル訂正しました。原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="19">
<j>また奈良・平安時代より独奏楽器（および弾き歌いの伴奏）としても用いられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soh was also used as an musical instrument for solo performance (and for singing a song while playing Soh) in the Nara and Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soh was also used as a musical instrument for solo performance (and for singing a song while playing Soh) during the Nara and Heian periods.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soh was also used as a musical instrument for solo performance (and for singing a song while playing Soh) during the Nara and Heian periods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>これらは『源氏物語』などいくつかの平安文学の中に描写されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The scene of such performance was depicted in Heian literature including &quot;The Tale of Genji&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The scene of such performance was depicted in Heian literature including &quot;The Tale of Genji.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The scene of such performance was depicted in Heian literature including &quot;The Tale of Genji.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>ただし具体的な楽曲は現在残っていない（伝わっていない）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, no particular music is existent (has not been handed down).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, no particular music is existing today (has not been handed down).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, no particular music is existing today (has not been handed down).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="22">
<j>また龍と対を成していた鳳凰を象徴したハープ型の楽器「箜篌（くご）」は、伝統としては廃絶した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A harp-shaped musical instrument &quot;kugo&quot; which symbolized hoo (a phoenix), one of a pair of ryu and hoo, is not existent as a traditional instrument.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A harp-shaped musical instrument &quot;kugo&quot; which symbolized hoo (a phoenix), one of a pair of ryu and hoo, is not existent as a traditional instrument.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A harp-shaped musical instrument &apos;kugo&apos; which symbolized hoo (a phoenix), one of a pair of ryu and hoo, is not existent as a traditional instrument.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>正倉院に断片が宝物として保管され、現代においては復元された複製楽器が演奏されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its fragments have been preserved at Shoso-in and its reproduction is in use at present.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its fragments have been preserved at Shoso-in and its reproduction is in use at present.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its fragments have been preserved at Shoso-in and its reproduction is in use at present.</e>
<cmt>不要なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>また箏と同じツィター属の大型楽器である瑟（「しつ」、まれに「ひつ」とも読む）は正倉院の宝物が24本、中国の古代楽器では25本の弦を持つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shitsu (also called hitsu in rare cases), a large-sized musical instrument that belongs to zither group as with Soh, has 24 strings in the case of Shoso-in&apos;s property and 25 strings in the case of ancient Chinese musical instrument.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shitsu (also called hitsu in rare cases), a large-sized musical instrument that belongs to zither group as with Soh, has twenty-four strings in the case of Shoso-in&apos;s property and twenty-five strings in the case of the ancient Chinese musical instrument.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shitsu&apos; (also called &apos;hitsu&apos; in rare cases), a large-sized musical instrument that belongs to zither group as with Soh, has 24 strings in the case of Shoso-in&apos;s property and 25 strings in the case of the ancient Chinese musical instrument.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。数字に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>伝説では神がこの瑟を二つに割って、13弦の箏と12弦の箏（別の名がある）が作られたと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A legend says that a god split this shitsu into two and created Soh with 13 strings and Soh with 12 strings (it had another name).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A legend says that a god split this shitsu into two and created Soh with thirteen strings and Soh with twelve strings (it had another name).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A legend says that a god split this shitsu into two and created Soh with 13 strings and Soh with 12 strings (it had another name).</e>
<cmt>数字に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>これも現在日本の伝統では廃絶したが、現代になって復元された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also not existent in Japan today but was reproduced recently.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also not existent in Japan today, but was reproduced recently.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also not existent in Japan today, but was reproduced recently.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>中世</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The medieval times</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Medieval times</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Medieval times</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="27">
<j>平安時代末期から室町時代までにおいては、歴史的な記録が明らかでない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">No historical records are existent from the end of Heian period to the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">No historical records are existing from the end of the Heian period to the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">No historical records are existing from the end of the Heian period to the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>安土・桃山時代には北九州で僧侶の賢順（1574年 - 1636年）により、中国、在来の独奏箏曲、雅楽の箏曲をまとめて「筑紫箏（つくしごと）」が起こった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Azuchi-Momoyama period, Kenjun (1574 - 1636), a monk in Kitakyushu, created &quot;Tsukushigoto&quot; by integrating Chinese as well as indigenous Soh music for solo performance and Soh music of gagaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Azuchi-Momoyama period, Kenjun (1574 - 1636), a monk in Kitakyushu, created &quot;Tsukushigoto&quot; by integrating Chinese as well as indigenous Soh music for solo performance and Soh music of gagaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Azuchi-Momoyama period, Kenjun (1574 - 1636), a monk in Kitakyushu, created &apos;Tsukushigoto&apos; by integrating Chinese as well as indigenous Soh music for solo performance and Soh music of gagaku.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>江戸時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Edo period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Edo period</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Edo period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="29">
<j>雅楽の「楽箏」に対し、近世の箏曲は「俗箏（「ぞくそう」または「ぞくごと」）」と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Soh music of gagaku was called &quot;gaku-Soh&quot;, Soh music in the pre-modern times was called &quot;zoku-Soh (or zokugoto)&quot; (modern Sho music).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While Soh music of gagaku was called &quot;gaku-Soh&quot;, Soh music in the pre-modern times was called &quot;zoku-Soh (or zokugoto)&quot; (modern Sho music).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While Soh music of gagaku was called &apos;gaku-Soh,&apos; Soh music in the pre-modern times was called &apos;zoku-Soh&apos; (or zokugoto) (modern Sho music).</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。括弧の位置を訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="30">
<j>前述の筑紫箏を基本として、楽器としての箏および箏曲の基礎を大成させたのが、江戸時代初期に活躍した八橋検校（やつはし・けんぎょう、1614年 - 1685年）であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Based on the above-mentioned Tsukusigoto, Kengyo YATSUHASHI (1614 - 1685), who was active in the early Edo period, established the basis of musical instrument Soh as well as Soh music.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based on the above-mentioned Tsukusigoto, Kengyo YATSUHASHI (1614 - 1685), who was active during the early Edo period, established the basis of the musical instrument Soh as well as Soh music.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based on the above-mentioned Tsukusigoto, Yatsuhashi Kengyo (1614 - 1685), who was active during the early Edo period, established the basis of the musical instrument Soh as well as Soh music.</e>
<cmt>検校は職の名前なので表記を訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>特に重要なのは、箏の調弦をそれまでの律音階から、当時民間で一般的になりつつあった都節音階にもとづくものに変えたことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among others, what was most important was that he changed the tuning of Soh from ritsu scale (anhemitonic pentatonic scale) to miyakobushi scale (characteristic Japanese hemitonic pentatonic scale) which then increasingly became common among ordinary people.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among others, what was most important was that he changed the tuning of Soh from ritsu scale (anhemitonic pentatonic scale) to miyakobushi scale (characteristic Japanese hemitonic pentatonic scale) which then increasingly became common among ordinary people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among others, what was most important was that he changed the tuning of Soh from ritsu scale (anhemitonic pentatonic scale) to miyakobushi scale (characteristic Japanese hemitonic pentatonic scale) which then increasingly became common among ordinary people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>また多数の作曲をして、ここで現在の箏曲の基本形が整った（一説には、箏曲の基本形の一つである「段もの」と呼ばれるいわゆる変奏曲に類似した形式は、八橋検校が何らかの形で洋楽、特にチェンバロの変奏曲に接触したことによって生まれたという）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also composed lots of Soh music and the basic form of contemporary Soh music was established at the time (one theory is that Kengyo YABASHI created one of basic pattern of Soh music called &quot;danmono&quot;, which is similar to a variation, when he came in contact in some way with western music, especially cembalo variations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also composed lots of Soh music and the basic form of contemporary Soh music was established at the time (one theory is that Kengyo YABASHI created one of the basic patterns of Soh music called &quot;danmono,&quot; similar to a variation, when he came in contact in some way with western music, especially cembalo variations.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also composed lots of Soh music and the basic form of contemporary Soh music was established at the time (one theory is that Yatsuhashi Kengyo created one of the basic patterns of Soh music called &apos;danmono,&apos; similar to a variation, when he came in contact in some way with western music, especially cembalo variations.</e>
<cmt>検校は職の名前なので表記を訂正しました。Yatsuhashiに訂正しました。原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。不要なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>独奏曲としての箏という楽器を代表する楽曲「六段」（の調べ）は、この八橋検校の作曲によると伝えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has been handed down that &quot;Rokudan (no shirabe)&quot;, a representative Soh solo, was composed by Kengyo YABASHI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has been handed down that &quot;Rokudan (no shirabe),&quot; a representative Soh solo, was composed by Kengyo YABASHI.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has been handed down that &apos;Rokudan&apos; (no shirabe), a representative Soh solo, was composed by Yatsuhashi Kengyo.</e>
<cmt>検校は職の名前なので表記を訂正しました。Yatsuhashiに訂正しました。原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。括弧の位置を訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>ちなみに「検校（けんぎょう）」という言葉は当時の盲人音楽家が作る組合制度「当道座」の中で与えられる最高位の名前である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Incidentally, &quot;Kengyo&quot; was the highest-ranking title which was given by &quot;Todoza&quot;, a guild organized by blind musicians at the time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Incidentally, &quot;Kengyo&quot; was the highest-ranking title given by &quot;Todoza,&quot; a guild organized by blind musicians at the time.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Incidentally, &apos;Kengyo&apos; was the highest-ranking title given by &apos;Todo-za,&apos; a guild organized by blind musicians at the time.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。ハイフン補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>八橋検校の没年1685年は、西洋音楽ではヨハン・セバスチャン・バッハ、ジョージ・フレデリック・ヘンデル、ドメニコ・スカルラッティの生年でもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1685, the year of Kengyo YABASHI&apos;s death, was the year of birth of Yohhan Sebastian Bach, Georg Friedrich Handel and Domenico Scarlatti.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1685, the year of Kengyo YABASHI&apos;s death, was the year of birth of Yohhan Sebastian Bach, Georg Friedrich Handel and Domenico Scarlatti.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1685, the year of Yatsuhashi Kengyo&apos;s death, was the year of birth of Yohhan Sebastian Bach, Georg Friedrich Handel and Domenico Scarlatti.</e>
<cmt>検校は職の名前なので表記を訂正しました。Yatsuhashiに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>八橋検校の名は京都の菓子「八ツ橋」の名としても残っており、（生ではなく焼いた、本来の）八ツ橋の形は箏を模している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name Kengyo Yabashi still remains as the name of Kyoto Confectionary &quot;Yatsuhasi&quot;, and its shape (baked one, not unbaked one) is modelled after the shape of Soh.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name Kengyo Yabashi still remains as the name of Kyoto Confectionary &quot;Yatsuhasi,&quot; and its shape (baked one, not unbaked one) is modelled after the shape of the Soh.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name Yatsuhashi Kengyo still remains as the name of Kyoto Confectionary &apos;Yatsuhasi,&apos; and its shape (baked one, not unbaked one) is modeled after the shape of the Soh.</e>
<cmt>modeledスペル訂正しました。検校は職の名前なので表記を訂正しました。Yatsuhashiに訂正しました。原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="37">
<j>八橋検校以降、江戸時代中期の特に重要な箏曲家としては、生田検校と山田検校が挙げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Kengyo YABASHI&apos;s death, Kengyo IKUTA and Kengyo YAMADA were prominent Soh musicians in the middle of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Kengyo YABASHI&apos;s death, Kengyo IKUTA and Kengyo YAMADA were prominent Soh musicians during the middle of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Yatsuhashi Kengyo&apos;s death, Ikuta Kengyo and Yamada Kengyo were prominent Soh musicians during the middle of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>modeledスペル訂正しました。検校は職の名前なので表記を訂正しました。Yatsuhashiに訂正しました。原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>まず京都の生田検校が元禄頃、箏の楽器法（調弦および奏法や爪の改良）や楽曲を大きく発展させたといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Kengyo IKUTA in Kyoto developed the way of playing Soh (tuning, playing method, improvement of a pick) as well as Soh music in the era of Genroku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Kengyo IKUTA in Kyoto developed the way of playing Soh (tuning, playing method, improvement of a pick) as well as Soh music in the era of Genroku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Ikuta Kengyo in Kyoto developed the way of playing Soh (tuning, playing method, improvement of a pick) as well as Soh music in the era of Genroku.</e>
<cmt>検校は職の名前なので表記を訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>この流れが現在の生田流系諸派である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the origin of existing various Ikuta schools.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the origin of existing various Ikuta schools.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the origin of existing various Ikuta schools.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>しかし、実際には当時上方にはいくつもの新流派が生まれ、それぞれ独自に爪の改良や楽曲の作曲を行なっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a matter of fact, however, a lot of new schools were born in kamigata region (Kansai region) at that time and each of them independently strived to improve a pick or compose music.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a matter of fact, however, a lot of new schools were born in kamigata region (Kansai region) at that time and each of them independently strived to improve the pick or compose music.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a matter of fact, however, a lot of new schools were born in kamigata region (Osaka and Kyoto regions) at that time and each of them independently strived to improve the pick or compose music.</e>
<cmt>(Osaka and Kyoto regions)と訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>現在ではこれらをひっくるめて「生田流」と呼んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today, these are collectively called &quot;Ikuta school&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, these are collectively called &quot;Ikuta school.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, these are collectively called &apos;Ikuta school.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>生田検校は三味線（地歌）と箏を合奏させた功績が大きいと言われて来たが、これも実際には諸流派でも行なわれたらしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Kengyo IKUTA is credited for performing the ensemble of shamisen (three-stringed Japanese banjo) (jiuta (traditional songs with shamisen accompaniment)) and Soh, such performance seems to have been conducted by other schools as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Kengyo IKUTA is credited for performing the ensemble of shamisen (three-stringed Japanese banjo) (jiuta - traditional songs with shamisen accompaniment) and Soh, such performance seems to have been conducted by other schools as well.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Ikuta Kengyo is credited for performing the ensemble of shamisen (three-stringed Japanese banjo) (jiuta - traditional songs with shamisen accompaniment) and Soh, such performance seems to have been conducted by other schools as well.</e>
<cmt>検校は職の名前なので表記を訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>それからしばらくの間、箏曲は上方を中心に栄えていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For a while since then, Soh music prospered mainly in kamigata region.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For a while since then, Soh music prospered mainly in the kamigata region.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For a while since then, Soh music prospered mainly in the kamigata region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>18世紀後半に山田検校が江戸で浄瑠璃風の歌ものを中心とした楽曲の作曲や楽器の改良を行い、山田流の始祖となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Edo, Kengyo Yamada composed jorui (dramatic narrative chanted with shamisen accompaniment)-style music and improved a pick in the late 18th century, and he became the founder of Yamada school.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Edo, Kengyo Yamada composed jorui (dramatic narrative chanted with shamisen accompaniment)-style music and improved a pick in the late eighteenth century, and he became the founder of Yamada school.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Edo, Yamada Kengyo composed jorui (dramatic narrative chanted with shamisen accompaniment)-style music and improved a pick in the late 18th century, and he became the founder of Yamada school.</e>
<cmt>検校は職の名前なので表記を訂正しました。数字に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>山田流は江戸を中心に東日本に広まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamada scool became popular in the eastern region of Japan with Edo being the center.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Yamada school became popular in the eastern region of Japan with Edo being the center.</e>
<cmt>grammar, spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Yamada school became popular in the eastern region of Japan with Edo being the center.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>こうして幕末までには、西日本では生田流系が、東日本では山田流が盛んに行なわれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, Ikuta schoo prospered in the western region of Japan while Yamada school prospered in the eastern region of Japan until the end of Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, the Ikuta school prospered in the western region of Japan while Yamada school prospered in the eastern region of Japan until the end of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>grammar, spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, the Ikuta school prospered in the western region of Japan while Yamada school prospered in the eastern region of Japan until the end of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>その他、八橋検校の直接の流れである八橋流が一部に伝えられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, Yabashi school, a direct linage of Kengyo YABASHI, existed in some region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, Yabashi school, a direct linage of Kengyo YABASHI, existed in some regions.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, Yatsuhashi school, a direct linage of Yatsuhashi Kengyo, existed in some regions.</e>
<cmt>Yatsuhashiに訂正しました。検校は職の名前なので表記を訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>その他江戸時代の重要な箏曲家は次のとおりである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other prominent Soh musicians in the Edo period were as follows.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other prominent Soh musicians during the Edo period were as follows.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other prominent Soh musicians during the Edo period were as follows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>初期：八橋検校の弟子で生田検校の師匠である北島検校</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The early Edo period : Kengyo KITAJIMA, a disciple of Kengyo YABASI and a tutor of Kengyo IKUTA</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The early Edo period: Kengyo KITAJIMA, a disciple of Kengyo YABASI and a tutor of Kengyo IKUTA</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The early Edo period: Kitajima Kengyo, a disciple of Yatsuhashi Kengyo and a tutor of Ikuta Kengyo</e>
<cmt>検校は職の名前なので表記を訂正しました。Yatsuhashiに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>中期：組歌の作曲で有名な三橋検校、安村検校</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The middle Edo period : Kengyo MITSUHASHI, who was known as the compser of kumiuta (koto suites of Sohngs), and Kengyo YASUMURA</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The middle Edo period: Kengyo MITSUHASHI, who was known as the compser of kumiuta (koto suites of Sohngs), and Kengyo YASUMURA</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The middle Edo period: Mitsuhashi Kengyo, who was known as the composer of kumiuta (koto suites of Sohngs), and Yasumura Kengyo</e>
<cmt>composer スペル訂正しました。検校は職の名前なので表記を訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>後期：京流手事物の地歌曲に複音楽的な箏の手付をした浦崎検校、八重崎検校、光崎検校</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The late Edo period : Kengyo URASAKI who adapted Kyoryu tegotomono (Kyoto-style chamber music) to Soh music, Kengyo YAEZAKI and Kengyo MITSUZAKI</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The late Edo period: Kengyo URASAKI who adapted Kyoryu tegotomono (Kyoto-style chamber music) to Soh music, Kengyo YAEZAKI and Kengyo MITSUZAKI</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The late Edo period: Urasaki Kengyo who adapted Kyoryu tegotomono (Kyoto-style chamber music) to Soh music, Yaezaki Kengyo and Mitsuzaki Kengyo</e>
<cmt>検校は職の名前なので表記を訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>幕末：吉沢検校</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The end of Edo period : Kengyo YOSHIZAWA</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The end of Edo period: Kengyo YOSHIZAWA</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The end of Edo period: Yoshizawa Kengyo</e>
<cmt>検校は職の名前なので表記を訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="53">
<j>また江戸時代において、箏は当道制度、つまり盲人音楽家の専売特許であったため、一般人がプロの職業として箏の演奏家になることは認められなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Edo period, ordinary people were not allowed to become professional Soh musician because this profession was exclusive for blind persons under Todo system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Edo period, ordinary people were not allowed to become professional Soh musician because this profession was exclusive for blind persons under Todo system.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Edo period, ordinary people were not allowed to become professional Soh musician because this profession was exclusive for blind persons under Todo system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>このため地歌以外の三味線音楽が歌舞伎や人形浄瑠璃などの視覚的要素を伴う伴奏音楽として発展したのに対し、箏曲は劇場とは関係のない純音楽として発展した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, while shamisen music other than jiuta developed as accompanying music of kabuki and ningyo joruri (traditional Japanese puppet theater) that involve visual elements, Soh music developed as pure music independently from theater arts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, while shamisen music other than jiuta developed as accompanying music for kabuki and ningyo joruri (traditional Japanese puppet theater) that involve visual elements, Soh music developed as purely music independently from theater arts.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, while shamisen music other than jiuta developed as accompanying music for kabuki and ningyo joruri (traditional Japanese puppet theater) that involve visual elements, Soh music developed as purely music independently from theater arts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>その中心となるものは箏の伴奏付き歌曲である「組歌」と、器楽独奏曲である「段物」であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The central components of Soh music were &quot;kumiuta&quot;, songs accompanied by Soh, and &quot;danmono&quot;, solo of musical instrument.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The central components of Soh music were &quot;kumiuta,&quot; songs accompanied by Soh, and &quot;danmono,&quot; solo of musical instrument.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The central components of Soh music were &apos;kumiuta,&apos; songs accompanied by Soh, and &apos;danmono,&apos; solo of musical instrument.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>そして地歌に合奏することで、多くの地歌曲、ことに手事物をレパートリーとして、大いに発展した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, Soh music added many jiuta, especially tegotomono, to its repertoire through ensemble and further developed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, Soh music added many jiuta, especially tegotomono, to its repertoire through ensemble and further developed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, Soh music added many jiuta, especially tegotomono, to its repertoire through ensemble and further developed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>また三味線音楽が遊里との結びつきも持っていて、どちらかといえば三味線が庶民の楽器として普及したのに対し、箏曲は王朝文学に取材したものが多いなど高雅な精神性を持ち、このため武家では「高尚な音楽」として、箏は武家の娘のたしなみ（アマチュア）としてもてはやされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While shamisen developed as a kind of ordinary people&apos;s musical instrument because shamisen music linked with the red-light district, Soh music was regarded as &quot;music of high spirituality&quot; by samurai family because many pieces were created based on dynastic style literature, and it was praised as an essential achievement for the daughters of samurai family (amateur).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While shamisen developed as a kind of ordinary people&apos;s musical instrument because shamisen music linked with the red-light district, Soh music was regarded as &quot;music of high spirituality&quot; by samurai families because many pieces were created based on dynastic style literature, and it was praised as an essential achievement for the daughters of samurai families (amateur).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While shamisen developed as a kind of ordinary people&apos;s musical instrument because shamisen music linked with the red-light district, Soh music was regarded as &apos;music of high spirituality&apos; by samurai families because many pieces were created based on dynastic style literature, and it was praised as an essential achievement for the daughters of samurai families (amateur).</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。不要なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>近代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The early moden times</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Early moden times</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Early moden times</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="58">
<j>明治時代以降は当道制度が廃止され、盲人以外の一般にも箏の演奏が職業として認められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Todo system was abolished in the Meiji era and people other than blind persons were allowed to become professional Soh musician.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Todo system was abolished during the Meiji era and people other than blind persons were allowed to become professional Soh musician.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Todo system was abolished during the Meiji era and people other than blind persons were allowed to become professional Soh musician.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>この頃作曲された作品を「明治新曲」と呼ぶが、洋楽の影響はまだ少なく、また当時流行していた明清楽の影響も見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Pieces composed in this era were called &quot;Meiji shinkyoku pieces&quot; (literally, new songs of Meiji), but they were not so much affected by western music as Ming &amp; Xing era Chinese music.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Pieces composed in this era were called &quot;Meiji shinkyoku pieces&quot; (literally, new songs of Meiji), but they were not so much affected by western music as Ming &amp; Xing era Chinese music.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Pieces composed in this era were called &apos;Meiji shinkyoku pieces&apos; (literally, new songs of Meiji), but they were not so much affected by western music as Ming and Xing era Chinese music.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。＆をandに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>ただし国民思潮全般が維新による革新的思想であふれていた時代であり、また盲人以外にも広く箏曲が解放され多数の人間が箏曲界へ参入したこともあって、多くの曲がこの頃作られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, many pieces were composed around that time thanks to the situation where the society was filled with revolutionary philosohphy in the wake of the Meiji Restoration and many people other than the blind entered the world of Soh music.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, many pieces were composed around that time thanks to the situation where the society was filled with revolutionary philosohphy in the wake of the Meiji Restoration and many people other than the blind entered the world of Soh music.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, many pieces were composed around that time thanks to the situation where the society was filled with revolutionary philosophy in the wake of the Meiji Restoration and many people other than the blind entered the world of Soh music.</e>
<cmt>philosophyスペース訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>特に大阪において非常に盛んであり、これらを「明治新曲」と総称している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In particular, many pieces were created in Osaka and these were collectively called &quot;Meiji shinkyoku pieces&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In particular, many pieces were created in Osaka and these were collectively called &quot;Meiji shinkyoku pieces&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In particular, many pieces were created in Osaka and these were collectively called &apos;Meiji shinkyoku pieces.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>しかしこの頃のレパートリーは現在の奏者にとって満足できるレベルで作曲された楽曲は少ないとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it is regarded that few of such pieces reached the level that satisfies current players.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is regarded that few of such pieces reached the level that satisfies current players.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is regarded that few of such pieces reached the level that satisfies current players.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>ただこの時期独特の清新な雰囲気もあり、西山徳茂都（とくもいち）の『秋の言の葉』、松坂春栄の『楓の花』、菊末検校の『嵯峨の秋』、菊塚与一の『明治松竹梅』などは現在でも名曲として良く演奏される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thanks to the unique social atmosphere at the time, &quot;Aki no kotonoha&quot; composed by Tokumoichi NISHIYAMA, &quot;Kaede no hana&quot; composed by Shunei MATSUZAKA, &quot;Saga no aki&quot; composed by Kengyo KIKUSUE and &quot;Meiji shochikubai&quot; composed by Yoichi KIKUZUKA etc. are often played even now as the excellent pieces.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thanks to the unique social atmosphere at the time, &quot;Aki no kotonoha&quot; composed by Tokumoichi NISHIYAMA, &quot;Kaede no hana&quot; composed by Shunei MATSUZAKA, &quot;Saga no aki&quot; composed by Kengyo KIKUSUE and &quot;Meiji shochikubai&quot; composed by Yoichi KIKUZUKA etc. are often played even now as the excellent pieces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thanks to the unique social atmosphere at the time, &quot;Aki no kotonoha&quot; composed by Tokumoichi NISHIYAMA, &quot;Kaede no hana&quot; composed by Shunei MATSUZAKA, &quot;Saga no aki&quot; composed by Kikusue Kengyo and &quot;Meiji shochikubai&quot; composed by Yoichi KIKUZUKA etc. are often played even now as the excellent pieces.</e>
<cmt>検校は職の名前なので表記を訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>また寺島花野の作品『白菊』など、現在では忘れられかけている佳曲も少なくない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, there are quite a few excellent pieces of music, such as &quot;Shiragiku&quot; composed by Hanano TERASHIMA, which tend to be forgotten at present.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, there are quite a few excellent pieces of music, such as &quot;Shiragiku&quot; composed by Hanano TERASHIMA, which tend to be forgotten at present.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, there are quite a few excellent pieces of music, such as &quot;Shiragiku&quot; composed by Hanano TERASHIMA, which tend to be forgotten at present.</e>
<cmt>不要なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>山田流においても『都の春』などの名曲が作られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Excellent pieces of music such as &quot;Miyako no haru&quot; etc. were created by Yamada school as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Excellent pieces of music such as &quot;Miyako no haru&quot; etc. were created by the Yamada school as well.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Excellent pieces of music such as &quot;Miyako no haru&quot; etc. were created by the Yamada school as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="66">
<j>大正時代および昭和初期の箏曲には、宮城道雄の名がまずもって挙げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When talking about Soh music in the Taisho and early Showa era, Michio MIYAGI is on the top of the list.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When talking about Soh music during the Taisho and early Showa era, Michio MIYAGI is on the top of the list.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When talking about Soh music during the Taisho and early Showa era, Michio MIYAGI is on the top of the list.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>西洋音楽の要素を導入した新日本音楽の中心的存在に立ち、箏のみならず邦楽全般の活性化につとめた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a pivotal figure of new Japanese music in which the elements of western music was introduced, and he strived to activate not only Soh but also whole of traditional Japanese music.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a pivotal figure of new Japanese music in which the elements of western music was introduced, and he strived to activate not only Soh, but also whole of traditional Japanese music.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a pivotal figure of new Japanese music in which the elements of western music was introduced, and he strived to activate not only Soh, but also whole of traditional Japanese music.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>特に代表作「春の海」は、尺八（正確には一尺六寸という、尺八より小さい同属楽器）との合奏において、それまでのヘテロフォニーな邦楽の合奏には見られなかった和声的伴奏を駆使した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In his representative piece &quot;Haru no umi&quot;, he used harmonic accompaniment, which was rarely used in heterophony ensemble of traditional Japanese music, in the ensemble with shakuhachi (to be exact, an instrument which is shorter than shakuhachi called isshaku-rokusun).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In his representative piece &quot;Haru no umi,&quot; he used harmonic accompaniment, which was rarely used in heterophony ensemble of traditional Japanese music, in the ensemble with shakuhachi (to be exact, an instrument which is shorter than shakuhachi called isshaku-rokusun).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In his representative piece &apos;Haru no umi,&apos; he used harmonic accompaniment, which was rarely used in heterophony ensemble of traditional Japanese music, in the ensemble with shakuhachi (to be exact, an instrument which is shorter than shakuhachi called isshaku-rokusun).</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>さらに尺八と交代して主旋律も奏でるといった、邦楽の語法として新しく楽器の性能も十分に駆使した書法により、現在でも箏という楽器を代表する名曲の位置を占める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also used Soh, instead of shakuhachi, for playing melody in order to make the most of instruments property, and this piece is regarded today as an excellent piece of music that represents the musical instrument Soh.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also used Soh, instead of shakuhachi, for playing the melody in order to make the most of the instruments property, and this piece is regarded today as an excellent piece of music that represents the musical instrument Soh.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also used Soh, instead of shakuhachi, for playing the melody in order to make the most of the instruments property, and this piece is regarded today as an excellent piece of music that represents the musical instrument Soh.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>尺八の代わりにヴァイオリンやフルートなどでも演奏される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In playing this piece, violin or flute is also used in place of shakuhachi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In playing this piece, a violin or flute is also used in place of shakuhachi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In playing this piece, a violin or flute is also used in place of shakuhachi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>特にヴァイオリンとの演奏はフランスの女性ヴァイオリニスト、ルネ・シュメーにより広く演奏され、作品はもちろん宮城道雄の名と箏という楽器を世界的に紹介した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He played this piece together with French violinist Renee Chemet at various places and introduced not only this piece of music but also his name Michio MIYAGI as well as musical instrument Soh around the world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He played this piece together with French violinist Renee Chemet at various places and introduced not only this piece of music, but also his name Michio MIYAGI as well as musical instrument Soh around the world.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He played this piece together with French violinist Renee Chemet at various places and introduced not only this piece of music, but also his name Michio MIYAGI as well as musical instrument Soh around the world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>また楽器改良や作品の開拓だけでなく、古典作品の復刻や教育活動にも力を注いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other than the improvement of instrument and the creation of pieces of music, he also strived for reviving classical pieces and education activities.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other than the improvement of instrument and the creation of the pieces of music, he also strived for reviving classical pieces and educational activities.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other than the improvement of instrument and the creation of the pieces of music, he also strived for reviving classical pieces and educational activities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>また、それまで主に口承に拠る稽古が主な伝承であったのに対し、楽譜（五線譜、および弦名譜＝タブラチュア譜の一種）の普及にもつとめた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, he also strived to spread musical scores (music in five-line staff notation and genmeifu (a kind of taburachua music)) since Soh music had been handed down orally.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処 弦名譜＝タブラチュア譜→読み不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further, he also strived to spread musical scores (music in five-line staff notation and genmeifu - a kind of taburachua music) since Soh music had been handed down orally.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further, he also strived to spread musical scores (music in five-line staff notation and genmeifu - a kind of taburachua music) since Soh music had been handed down orally.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>宮城道雄は生田流に属する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Michio MIYAGI belonged to Ikuta school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Michio MIYAGI belonged to the Ikuta school.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Michio MIYAGI belonged to the Ikuta school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="75">
<j>この流れは宮城に留まらず三曲界全体の主潮流となり、中村双葉や山田流系の久本玄智、中能島欣一をはじめ、多くの箏曲家が宮城の影響を受けた作品を多数残した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This school became the mainstream of sankyokukai and many Soh musicians, including Futaba NAKAMURA, Genchi HISAMOTO of Yamada school and Kinichi NAKANOSHIMA, composed many pieces which were affected by Miyagi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処 三曲界→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This school became the mainstream of sankyokukai and many Soh musicians, including Futaba NAKAMURA, Genchi HISAMOTO of Yamada school and Kinichi NAKANOSHIMA, composed many pieces affected by Miyagi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This school became the mainstream of sankyokukai and many Soh musicians, including Futaba NAKAMURA, Genchi HISAMOTO of Yamada school and Kinichi NAKANOSHIMA, composed many pieces affected by Miyagi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>また箏曲家以外でも町田佳聲や高森高山らによって、多くの和楽器を合奏させる作品が多数作られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, many pieces of music in which varieties of traditional Japanese insruments are played in concert were created by other persons than Soh musicians, such as Kasho MACHIDA and Takayama TAKAMORI etc.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, many pieces of music in which varieties of traditional Japanese insruments are played in concert were created by other persons than Soh musicians, such as Kasho MACHIDA and Takayama TAKAMORI etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, many pieces of music in which varieties of traditional Japanese instruments are played in concert were created by other persons than Soh musicians, such as Kasho MACHIDA and Takayama TAKAMORI etc.</e>
<cmt>instrumentsスペル訂正しました。不要なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>現代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="77">
<j>現代の箏は伝統的な流派の伝承（草の根の稽古も含む）はもちろん、クラシック音楽との交流も行われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today, Soh is played not only by people belonging to traditional schools (including those who are learning) but also in collaboration with classical musicians.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, Soh is played not only by people belonging to traditional schools (including those who are learning) but also in collaboration with classical musicians.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, Soh is played not only by people belonging to traditional schools (including those who are learning) but also in collaboration with classical musicians.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>具体的には1964年ごろより洋楽系の現代音楽の作曲家の間での「邦楽器ブーム」により、洋楽系現代音楽の中に箏を含む邦楽器が広く用いられるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under &quot;the boom of traditional Japanese instruments&quot; started from 1964 among the composers of contemporary western music, varieties of traditional Japanese instruments including Soh were introduced in contemporary western music.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under &quot;the boom of traditional Japanese instruments&quot; that started from 1964 among the composers of contemporary western music, varieties of traditional Japanese instruments including Soh were introduced in contemporary western music.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under &apos;the boom of traditional Japanese instruments&apos; that started from 1964 among the composers of contemporary western music, varieties of traditional Japanese instruments including Soh were introduced in contemporary western music.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>これらの多くは邦楽本来の楽器および演奏法の特色の長所をなるべく活かす形で使われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In these pieces, traditional Japanese instruments were used in a way to make the most of their characteristics and playing style.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In these pieces, traditional Japanese instruments were used in a way to make the most of their characteristics and playing style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In these pieces, traditional Japanese instruments were used in a way to make the most of their characteristics and playing style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>その点、このブーム以前の洋楽における邦楽器の使われ方として多かった「別に箏でなくてもピアノやハープでも代用できる洋楽流の書法」とは一線を画する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this sense, it is completely different from &quot;using Soh in substitute for piano and/or harp&quot;, which was a common way of using traditional Japanese instruments in western music before the boom started.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this sense, it is completely different from &quot;using Soh in substitute for piano and/or harp,&quot; which was a common way of using traditional Japanese instruments in western music before the boom started.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this sense, it is completely different from &apos;using Soh in substitute for piano and/or harp,&apos; which was a common way of using traditional Japanese instruments in western music before the boom started.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>それに先立って1957年に結成された邦楽四人の会、邦楽器ブーム初期の1964年より活動を続けている日本音楽集団の活動も、洋楽系現代音楽における重要な邦楽活動として挙げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Activities of Hogaku Yonin no kai (the four players group), which was organized in 1957, and Nihon Ongaku shudan (the group of Japanese musicians), which started activities in 1964 prior to the boom of Japanese traditional instruments, were also significant as the activities of Japanese traditional music conducted by the western contemporary musicians.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Activities of Hogaku Yonin no kai (the four players group), which was organized in 1957, and Nihon Ongaku shudan (the group of Japanese musicians), which started activities in 1964 prior to the boom of Japanese traditional instruments, were also significant as the activities of Japanese traditional music conducted by the western contemporary musicians.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Activities of Hogaku Yonin no kai (the four players group), which was organized in 1957, and Nihon Ongaku shudan (the group of Japanese musicians), which started activities in 1964 prior to the boom of Japanese traditional instruments, were also significant as the activities of Japanese traditional music conducted by the western contemporary musicians.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>ただし大正・昭和初期の新日本音楽における邦楽界の洋楽受容が、和声的な書法で作曲しやすい箏を中心としたのに対し、1960年代の洋楽系現代音楽界の邦楽受容においては箏は必ずしも主役ではなく、むしろノイズ的書法で作曲しやすい尺八が中心となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Provided, however, that while Soh music, which is easy to compose by the way of harmony, was mainly introduced into Western music in the case of new Japanese music in the era of Taisho and early Showa, shakuhachi music, which is easy to compose by the way of noise, was mainly introduced, instead of Soh, into the contemporary Western music of 1960&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>ノイズ的書法→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Provided, however, that while Soh music, which is easy to compose by the way of harmony, was mainly introduced into Western music in the case of new Japanese music in the era of Taisho and early Showa, shakuhachi music, which is easy to compose by the way of noise, was mainly introduced, instead of Soh, into the contemporary Western music of 1960&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Provided, however, that while Soh music, which is easy to compose by the way of harmony, was mainly introduced into Western music in the case of new Japanese music in the era of Taisho and early Showa, shakuhachi music, which is easy to compose by the way of noise, was mainly introduced, instead of Soh, into the contemporary Western music of 1960s.</e>
<cmt>1960ｓに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>洋楽系現代音楽における箏の作品</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Pieces of Soh music introduced into contemporary western music</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Pieces of Soh music introduced into contemporary western music</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Pieces of Soh music introduced into contemporary western music</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="83">
<j>箏とオーケストラのための作品</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Pieces for Soh and orchestra</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Pieces for Soh and orchestra</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Pieces for Soh and orchestra</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="84">
<j>湯浅譲二 「（八面の）箏とオーケストラのためのプロジェクション・花鳥風月」(1967)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Joji YUASA : &quot;Projection for (eight) Soh and orchestra : flower, bird, wind and moon&quot; (1967)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Joji YUASA: &quot;Projection for (eight) Soh and orchestra: flower, bird, wind and moon&quot; (1967)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Joji YUASA: &apos;Projection for (eight) Soh and orchestra, flower, bird, wind and moon&apos; (1967)</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。:をコンマに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="85">
<j>三木稔 「鳳凰三連・破の曲」「春琴抄・序曲と春鶯囀（しゅんおうでん）」「松の協奏曲」「箏協奏曲第五番」（以上は洋楽オーケストラとの協奏曲）「コンチェルト・レクイエム」（邦楽オーケストラとの協奏曲）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Minoru MIKI : &quot;Eurasian Trilogy ha-no kyoku&quot;, &quot;Shunkinsho Jokyoku to Shunoden&quot;, &quot;aka Pine Concerto&quot;, &quot;Soh Concerto No.5&quot; (these are concerto with Western music orchestra), &quot;Concerto Requiem&quot; (concerto with traditional Japanese music orchestra)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Minoru MIKI: &quot;Eurasian Trilogy ha-no kyoku,&quot; &quot;Shunkinsho Jokyoku to Shunoden,&quot; &quot;aka Pine Concerto,&quot; &quot;Soh Concerto No.5&quot; (these are concerto with Western music orchestra), &quot;Concerto Requiem&quot; (concerto with traditional Japanese music orchestra)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Minoru MIKI: &apos;Eurasian Trilogy ha-no kyoku,&apos; &apos;Shunkinsho Jokyoku to Shunoden,&apos; &apos;ka Pine Concerto,&apos; &apos;Soh Concerto No.5&apos; (these are concerto with Western music orchestra), &apos;Concerto Requiem&apos; (concerto with traditional Japanese music orchestra)</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="86">
<j>伊福部昭 「二十絃箏とオーケストラのための交響的エグログ」(1982)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akira IFUKUBE : &quot;SYMPHONIC EGLOGUE for 20-Stringed Soh and orchestra&quot; (1982)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akira IFUKUBE: &quot;SYMPHONIC EGLOGUE for 20-Stringed Soh and orchestra&quot; (1982)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akira IFUKUBE: &apos;SYMPHONIC EGLOGUE for 20-Stringed Soh and orchestra&apos; (1982)</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="87">
<j>ソフィア・グバイドゥーリナ In the shadow of the tree 一人の奏者の三面の箏とオーケストラのための(1999)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sohphia Gubaidulina : &quot;In the shadow of the tree (for one player, three Soh and orchestra&quot; (1999)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sohphia Gubaidulina: &quot;In the shadow of the tree (for one player, three Soh and orchestra&quot; (1999)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sohphia Gubaidulina: &apos;In the shadow of the tree, for one player, three Soh and orchestra&apos; (1999)</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="88">
<j>箏独奏のための作品</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Pieces for Soh solo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Pieces for Soh solo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Pieces for Soh solo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="89">
<j>下総皖一 「箏独奏のためのソナタ」（1938）洋楽系作曲家初の箏独奏曲</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanichi SHINOFUSA : &quot;Sonata for Soh Solo&quot; (1938) the first Soh Soh composed by Western music compser</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanichi SHINOFUSA: &quot;Sonata for Soh Solo&quot; (1938) the first Soh Soh composed by Western music compser</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanichi SHINOFUSA: &apos;Sonata for Soh Solo&apos; (1938), the first Soh composed by Western music composer</e>
<cmt>composerスペル訂正しました。原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。コンマ補足しました。スペース削除しました。不要な繰り返しを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="90">
<j>三木稔 「天如」（1969）二十絃箏初の独奏曲</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Minoru MIKI : &quot;Tenjo&quot; (1969) the first solo for 20-stringed Soh.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Minoru MIKI: &quot;Tenjo&quot; (1969) the first solo for 20-stringed Soh.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Minoru MIKI: &apos;Tenjo&apos; (1969), the first solo for 20-stringed Soh.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。コンマ補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="91">
<j>細川俊夫 「箏歌（ことうた）」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toshio HOSohKAWA : &quot;Kotouta&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toshio HOSohKAWA: &quot;Kotouta&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toshio HOSOKAWA: &apos;Kotouta&apos;</e>
<cmt>HOSOKAWAに訂正しました。原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="92">
<j>望月京 Intermezzi II</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Misato MOCHIZUKI : &quot;Intermezzi II&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Misato MOCHIZUKI: &quot;Intermezzi II&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Misato MOCHIZUKI: &apos;Intermezzi II&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="93">
<j>箏と室内楽（邦楽器および洋楽器）のための作品</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Pieces for Soh and chamber music (traditional Japanese instruments and Western instruments)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Pieces for Soh and chamber music (traditional Japanese instruments and Western instruments)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Pieces for Soh and chamber music (traditional Japanese instruments and Western instruments)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>流派</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Schools</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Schools</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Schools</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="94">
<j>主に生田流（いくたりゅう）と山田流（やまだりゅう）がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ikuta school and Yamada school are principal schools.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ikuta school and Yamada school are the principal schools.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ikuta school and Yamada school are the principal schools.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>外見上の目立った違いは爪の形および楽器を構える姿勢である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Conspicuous differences in outward appearance are the shape of a pick and players&apos; position against the instrument.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Conspicuous differences in outward appearance are the shape of the pick and players&apos; position against the instrument.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Conspicuous differences in outward appearance are the shape of the pick and players&apos; position against the instrument.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>生田流は角爪を用い、この角を有効に使うため楽器に対し左斜め約45度に構える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the case of Ikuta school, players use kakuzume (square-shaped pick) and position themselves at an angle of about 45°left oblique against the instrument in order to use kakuzume effectively.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the case of the Ikuta school, players use kakuzume (square-shaped pick) and position themselves at an angle of about fourty-five degrees left oblique against the instrument in order to use kakuzume effectively.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the case of the Ikuta school, players use kakuzume (square-shaped pick) and position themselves at an angle of about forty-five degrees left oblique against the instrument in order to use kakuzume effectively.</e>
<cmt>forty-fiveスペル訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>山田流は丸爪を用い正面に構える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the case of Yamada school, players use maruzume (round-shaped pick) and position themselves in front of the instrument.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the case of the Yamada school, players use maruzume (a round-shaped pick) and position themselves in front of the instrument.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the case of the Yamada school, players use maruzume (a round-shaped pick) and position themselves in front of the instrument.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="98">
<j>レパートリーについては、双方の流派が双方のレパートリーを広く扱うため、あまり差異は無い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">No particular difference exists in their repertoire since both schools mutually use their repertoire.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">No particular differences exists in their repertoire since both schools mutually use their repertoire.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">No particular differences exists in their repertoire since both schools mutually use their repertoire.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>相対的な比較としては山田流が生田流よりも「歌もの」を多く扱い、生田流は独奏曲において技巧が発達している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Relatively, Ikuta school deals with &quot;utamono&quot; (a music genre) more than Ikuta school and Ikuta school excelled in the technique of Solo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Relatively, the Ikuta school deals with &quot;utamono&quot; (a music genre) and the Ikuta school excelled in the technique of Solo.</e>
<cmt>redundancy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Relatively, the Ikuta school deals with &apos;utamono&apos; (a music genre) and the Ikuta school excelled in the technique of Solo.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>楽器の形状（長さ、楽器の膨らみ、音穴、細部の装飾など）は生田流の箏は楽箏（雅楽の箏）の形をかなり残している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are traces of gaku-Soh (Soh used in gagaku) in the shape of instrument (length, bulge of instrument, sound hole, detailing) used by Ikuta school.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are traces of gaku-Soh (Soh used in gagaku) in the shape of instrument (length, bulge of instrument, sound hole, detailing) used by the Ikuta school.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are traces of gaku-Soh (Soh used in gagaku) in the shape of instrument (length, bulge of instrument, sound hole, detailing) used by the Ikuta school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>俗箏として改良を加えられた山田流式の方が音量が大きく豊かな音色である為、現在製作されている箏は一部を除いてほとんどが山田流式の箏である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the instrument used by Yamada school, which was improved for playing zoku-Soh, creates bigger volume and better tone, current products are all but the ones of Yamada school style.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the instrument used by Yamada school, improved for playing zoku-Soh, it creates a bigger volume and a better tone, current products are all but the ones of Yamada school style.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the instrument used by Yamada school, improved for playing zoku-Soh, it creates a bigger volume and a better tone, current products are all but the ones of Yamada school style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="102">
<j>ただ沖縄諸島、または沖縄の文化を伝えている地域では、八橋流の流れをくむ独自の琉球箏曲が発展・継承されていて、そちらは現在でも生田流式の箏を使っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as unique Ryukyu Sohkyoku (Okinawa Soh music) which originated from Yabashi school has been handed down in Okinawa as well as other regions where Okinawa culture remains, Soh of Ikuta school style is being used in these regions even today.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as the unique Ryukyu Sohkyoku (Okinawa Soh music) which originated from the Yabashi school has been handed down in Okinawa as well as in other regions where Okinawa culture remains, Soh of the Ikuta school style is being used in these regions even today.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as the unique Ryukyu Sohkyoku (Okinawa Soh music) which originated from the Yatsuhashi school has been handed down in Okinawa as well as in other regions where Okinawa culture remains, Soh of the Ikuta school style is being used in these regions even today.</e>
<cmt>Yatsuhashiに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>それ以外は生田流の奏者でもほとんど山田流式の箏を使用している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Except for the above, even the players of Ikuta school are using Soh of Yamada school style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Except for the above, even the players of Ikuta school are using Soh of Yamada school style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Except for the above, even the players of Ikuta school are using Soh of Yamada school style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>調子（調弦）において、一部の調子の名が双方の流派で異なるため注意を要する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When tuning Soh, attention should be paid on the fact that the name of tune is different in two schools.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When tuning Soh, attention should be paid to the fact that the name of a tune is different between the two schools.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When tuning Soh, attention should be paid to the fact that the name of a tune is different between the two schools.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>（例：生田流の中空調子＝山田流の曙調子、生田流の曙調子＝山田流の二重中空調子、など）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(example : Nagazora -choshi scale of Ikuta school = Akebono-choshi scale of Yamada school, Akebono-choshi scale of Ikuta school = Double Nagazora -choshi scale of Yamada school)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(example: Nagazora -choshi scale of Ikuta school = Akebono-choshi scale of Yamada school, Akebono-choshi scale of Ikuta school = Double Nagazora -choshi scale of Yamada school)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Example: Nagazora-choshi scale of Ikuta school = Akebono-choshi scale of Yamada school, Akebono-choshi scale of Ikuta school = Double Nagazora -choshi scale of Yamada school)</e>
<cmt>Exemple大文字にしました。スペース削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="106">
<j>その他ごく少数ではあるが、八橋検校の当時の演奏様式を伝える八橋流、筑紫箏の様式を伝える筑紫流がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though the number of players is quite small, there exist Yabashi school, which is keeping up the playing style of the time of Kengyo YABASI, and Tsukushi school, which is keeping up the playing style of Tsukushi-Soh.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though the number of players is quite small, there exist Yabashi school, which is keeping up the playing style of the time of Kengyo YABASI, and Tsukushi school, which is keeping up the playing style of Tsukushi-Soh.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though the number of players is quite small, there exist Yatsuhashi school, which is keeping up the playing style of the time of Yatsuhashi Kengyo, and Tsukushi school, which is keeping up the playing style of Tsukushi-Soh.</e>
<cmt>検校は職の名前なので表記を訂正しました。Yatsuhashiに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>楽器解説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Explanation on the musical instrument</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Explanation of the musical instrument</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Explanation of the musical instrument</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="107">
<j>箏は、前後にアーチのかかった横に細長い板状で内部が中空の胴に、13本の絃を張り渡した楽器である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soh is a musical instrument that is composed of a hollow body, an arch-shaped long and thin board, and thirtenn strings stretched over a body.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soh is a musical instrument that is composed of a hollow body, an arch-shaped long and thin board, and thirteen strings stretched over the body.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soh is a musical instrument that is composed of a hollow body, an arch-shaped long and thin board, and 13 strings stretched over the body.</e>
<cmt>不要なスペースを削除しました。数字に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>柱（じ）を用いて音程を調節し、奏者の右手に嵌めた爪（義甲）によって絃をはじいて音を出し演奏する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Players adjust music intervals by the use of ji (bridge) and play it by plucking strings with picks (giko (tools put on the fingertip to pluck the strings)) put on the fingertips of the right hand.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Players adjust music intervals by the use of ji (bridge) and play it by plucking strings with picks (giko - tools put on the fingertip to pluck the strings) put on the fingertips of the right hand.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Players adjust music intervals by the use of ji (bridge) and play it by plucking strings with picks (giko - tools put on the fingertip to pluck the strings) put on the fingertips of the right hand.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="109">
<j>長さは生田流の本間（ほんげん）と呼ばれる高級なものが6尺3寸（約190cm）、山田流が約6尺（約182cm）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its length is about 190cm in the case of high-quality product called hongen, which is used by Ikuta school, and about 182cm in the case of product used by Yamada school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has a length is about 190cm in the case of high-quality product called hongen, used by the Ikuta school, and about 182cm in the case of products used by the Yamada school.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has a length is about 190cm in the case of high-quality product called hongen, used by the Ikuta school, and about 182cm in the case of products used by the Yamada school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>その他これに前後する長さのものが多数あったが、現在では学校教育用の箏を除けば大部分が山田流の箏である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There used to be various products whose length was slightly different from the above, but Soh of Yamada school type is dominant today except for the products for school education purpose.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There used to be various products where the length was slightly different from the above, but Soh of the Yamada school type is dominant today except for the products used for school education purpose.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There used to be various products where the length was slightly different from the above, but Soh of the Yamada school type is dominant today except for the products used for school education purpose.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="111">
<j>正倉院にも箏の残欠が保存されているが、現在のものと造りが異なっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some fragments of Soh are being preserved at Shosoh-in, but it was produced by a different method from current products.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some fragments of Soh are being preserved at Shosoh-in, but it was produced by a different method from the current products.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some fragments of Soh are being preserved at Shoso-in, but it was produced by a different method from the current products.</e>
<cmt>Shoso-inに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>四枚の板を箱状に張り合わせて作られており、各板はかなり薄い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was produced by putting four boards together in the shape of box and each board was rather thin.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was produced by putting four boards together in the shape of box and each board was rather thin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was produced by putting four boards together in the shape of box and each board was rather thin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="113">
<j>現代の箏は上面と両側面は一つの材をくり抜いて作り、下面だけ別材を張り合わせる構造である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the case of current Soh, the top side and both sides of Soh is produced by hollowing a piece of board and seperate piece of board is attached only to the underside.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the case of the current Soh, the top side and both sides of the Soh is produced by hollowing a piece of board and a seperate piece of board is attached only to the underside.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the case of the current Soh, the top side and both sides of the Soh is produced by hollowing a piece of board and a separate piece of board is attached only to the underside.</e>
<cmt>separateスペル訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="114">
<j>このような方法になったのは平安時代と思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered that such production method became in use in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered that such a production method became in use during the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered that such a production method became in use during the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>その後山田検校により改良されたのが、基本的に現在の主流を成す「山田箏」である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">What was later improved by Kengyo Yamada is today&apos;s mainstream product &quot;Yamada Soh&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">What was later improved by Kengyo Yamada is today&apos;s mainstream product &quot;Yamada Soh.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">What was later improved by Yamada Kengyo is today&apos;s mainstream product &apos;Yamada Soh.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。検校は職の名前なので表記を訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="116">
<j>本体は桐で作る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The body is made of empress tree.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The body is made from the empress tree.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The body is made from the empress tree.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="117">
<j>製法により「ベタ」と「刳甲（くりこう）」とがあり、後者が高級品である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are two types of product called &quot;beta&quot; and &quot;kuriko&quot; depending on the method of production, and the latter is a high-grade product.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are two types of products called &quot;beta&quot; and &quot;kuriko&quot; depending upon the method of production, and the latter is a high-grade product.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are two types of products called &apos;beta&apos; and &apos;kuriko&apos; depending upon the method of production, and the latter is a high-grade product.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="118">
<j>かつては富裕層のステイタスとして蒔絵や木画などで美しく装飾されるものが多かったが、やはり山田検校以来、装飾は最低限に抑え、音色を重視するシンプルなものが次第に多くなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although many products were decorated with makie (Japanese lacquer sprinkled with gold or silver powder) or mokuga (wood painting) in the past in order to show the status of wealthy people, simple products which emphasized tone quality rather than decorations gradually increased since the era of Kengyo Yamada.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although many products were decorated with makie (Japanese lacquer sprinkled with gold or silver powder) or mokuga (wood painting) in the past in order to show the status of wealthy people, simple products which emphasized tone quality rather than decorations gradually increased since the era of Kengyo Yamada.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although many products were decorated with makie (Japanese lacquer sprinkled with gold or silver powder) or mokuga (wood painting) in the past in order to show the status of wealthy people, simple products which emphasized tone quality rather than decorations gradually increased since the era of Yamada Kengyo.</e>
<cmt>検校は職の名前なので表記を訂正しました。不要なスペース削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="119">
<j>ただし良い音の出る楽器と木目の美しさにはかなり密接な関係がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Provided, however, that the good tone quality of instrument is closely linked to the beautiful grain of wood.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Provided, however, that the good tone quality of instrument is closely linked to the beautiful grain of wood.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Provided, however, that the good tone quality of instrument is closely linked to the beautiful grain of wood.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="120">
<j>楽器の各部分には、「龍角」「劉眼」「龍手」など、箏を竜に見立てた名称がつけられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name of each part of the instrument, such as &quot;龍角&quot; (ryukaku), &quot;劉眼 (ryugan) and &quot;龍手&quot; (ryushu), derived from the belief that Soh was the symbol of ryu (竜).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name of each part of the instrument, such as &quot;龍角&quot; (ryukaku), &quot;劉眼 (ryugan) and &quot;龍手&quot; (ryushu), derived from the belief that Soh was the symbol of ryu (竜).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name of each part of the instrument, such as &apos;ryukaku&apos; (dragon horns), &apos;ryugan&apos; (dragon eyes) and &apos;ryushu&apos; (dragon hands), derived from the belief that Soh was the symbol of ryu (dragon).</e>
<cmt>漢字の表記を削除しました。説明訳補足しました。原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="121">
<j>これを題材に書かれた推理小説が島田荘司の龍臥亭事件である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shoji SHIMADA wrote his detective story &quot;Ryugatei jiken&quot; (The Ryugatei Nurders) based on the above.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoji SHIMADA wrote his detective story &quot;Ryugatei jiken&quot; (The Ryugatei Nurders) based on the above.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoji SHIMADA wrote his detective story &quot;Ryugatei jiken&quot; (The Ryugatei Murders) based on the above.</e>
<cmt>Murdersスペル訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>絃(糸)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">String (ito)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">String (ito)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">String (ito)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="122">
<j>和楽器では普通絃とは呼ばず「糸」と称する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the case of Japanese traditional musical instruments, a string is usually called &quot;ito&quot; (糸).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the case of Japanese traditional musical instruments, a string is usually called &quot;ito&quot; (糸).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the case of Japanese traditional musical instruments, a string is usually called &apos;ito.&apos;</e>
<cmt>漢字の表記を削除しました。原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="123">
<j>通常の箏は十三本の糸を有し、奈良時代より変わらないが、江戸時代には更に多絃の箏が作られたこともある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While the number of ito of standard type Soh has been thirtenn since the Nara period, Soh with more strings was once produced in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While the number of ito for standard type Soh has been thirteen since the Nara period, Soh with more strings was once produced during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>grammar, spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While the number of ito for standard type Soh has been 13 since the Nara period, Soh with more strings was once produced during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>数字に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="124">
<j>また明治時代以降、十七絃箏をはじめ、種々の多絃箏が作られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the Meiji era, various kinds of multiple-string Soh, including seventeen-stringed Soh, have been produced.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the Meiji era, various kinds of multiple-string Soh, including seventeen-stringed Soh, have been produced.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the Meiji era, various kinds of multiple-string Soh, including 17-stringed Soh, have been produced.</e>
<cmt>数字に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="125">
<j>十三本の糸には名称があり、演奏する側の反対側から一、二、三、四と数え、十以降の糸は斗（と）、為（い）、巾（きん）と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Each of thirteen ito has its name; namely, starting from the opposite side of player, ito is counted ichi (first), ni (second), san (third), shi (fourth) and from the tenth ito, it is called to (斗), i (為) and kin (巾).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Each thirteen ito has a name; namely, starting from the opposite side of player, ito is counted ichi (first), ni (second), san (third), shi (fourth) and from the tenth ito, it is called to (斗), i (為) and kin (巾).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Each 13 ito has a name; namely, starting from the opposite side of player, ito is counted &apos;ichi&apos; (first), &apos;ni&apos; (second), &apos;san&apos; (third), &apos;shi&apos; (fourth) and from the 10th ito, it is called &apos;to&apos;, &apos;i&apos; and &apos;kin&apos;.</e>
<cmt>数字に訂正しました。読みを&apos; &apos;に入れました。漢字の表記を削除しました。不要なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="126">
<j>筑紫箏では別の呼び方もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another name is used in the case of Tsukushi-Soh.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another name is used in the case of Tsukushi-Soh.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another name is used in the case of Tsukushi-Soh.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="127">
<j>太さには色々なサイズがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thickness of ito varies widely.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thickness of ito varies widely.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thickness of ito varies widely.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="128">
<j>以前は黄色く染色したものが普通で、稀に青や赤に染めることもあったが、現在では生成りの白が好まれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yellow-colored ito was common previously with few exeptions of blue or red ones, but plain white ones are popular at present.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yellow-colored ito was common previously with few exeptions of blue or red ones, but plain white ones are popular at present.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yellow-colored ito was common previously with few exceptions of blue or red ones, but plain white ones are popular at present.</e>
<cmt>exceptionsスペルを訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="129">
<j>糸の構造は他の多くの和楽器糸と同じく、単糸を更に四本撚り合わせ、糊で固めたもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As with ito of other traditional Japanese musical instruments, ito is produced by twisting four threads and pasting them together.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As with ito of other traditional Japanese musical instruments, ito is produced by twisting four threads and pasting them together.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As with ito of other traditional Japanese musical instruments, ito is produced by twisting four threads and pasting them together.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="130">
<j>材質は本来は絹製であるが、俗箏では現在はポリエステル製が主流になっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its material was originally silk, but polyester is mainly used for zoku-Soh (modern Soh) at present.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its material was originally silk, but polyester is mainly used for zoku-Soh (modern Soh) at present.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its material was originally silk, but polyester is mainly used for zoku-Soh (modern Soh) at present.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="131">
<j>テトロンは張力が強く、強く張ると余韻が長く、いい音色がでるからである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reason for the above is that thanks to Tetron&apos;s strong tension, players can create good tone quality with long-lasting resonance by stretching it strongly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reason for the above is that thanks to Tetron&apos;s strong tension, players can create good tone quality with long-lasting resonance by stretching it tightly.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reason for the above is that thanks to Tetron&apos;s strong tension, players can create good tone quality with long-lasting resonance by stretching it tightly.</e>
<cmt>不要なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="132">
<j>また、演奏中に切れる心配が無いこと、絹製に比較するとかなり安価であることも普及している要因である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other reasons are that players are not required to worry about the incident where ito is broke off while playing, and that its price is less expensive compared with silk product.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other reasons are that players are not required to worry about an incident where ito is broken while playing, and that its price is less expensive compared with the silk product.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other reasons are that players are not required to worry about an incident where ito is broken while playing, and that its price is less expensive compared with the silk product.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="133">
<j>しかし、絹糸の独特の響きを気に入っている奏者も多く、特に擦り爪におけるシュッという音色ははるかに絹の方が良い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there exists players who favor the unique sound of silk thread, and its tone quality of surizume (rubbing strings by picks) is far better than polyester.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there exists players who favor the unique sound of silk thread, and its tone quality of surizume (rubbing strings by picks) is far better than polyester.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there exists players who favor the unique sound of silk thread, and its tone quality of surizume (rubbing strings by picks) is far better than polyester.</e>
<cmt>不要なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="134">
<j>楽箏では今でも絹糸が主流である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Silk thread is mainly used for gaku-Soh even today.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Silk thread is mainly used for gaku-Soh even today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Silk thread is mainly used for gaku-Soh even today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="135">
<j>爪</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsume (pick)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsume (pick)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsume (pick)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="136">
<j>爪（義甲）は右手の親指、人差し指、中指の3本の指の腹側に嵌める（人間の手の爪の側ではないことに注意）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsume (giko) should be put on the cushions of three fingers, thumb, forefinger and middlefinger, of the right hand (be careful that not on fingernails).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsume (giko) should be placed on the pads of three fingers, thumb, forefinger and middlefinger, of the right hand (be careful that it&apos;s not on the fingernails).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsume (giko) should be placed on the pads of three fingers, thumb, forefinger and middle finger, of the right hand (be careful that it&apos;s not on the fingernails).</e>
<cmt>middle fingerスペースを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="137">
<j>雅楽の爪は丸くて小さい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsume used for gagaku is round-shaped and small.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsume used for gagaku is round-shaped and small.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsume used for gagaku is round-shaped and small.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="138">
<j>生田流は角爪と呼ばれ、先が広く四角い形をしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsume used by Ikuta school is called kakuzume and its tip is wide and square-shaped.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsume used by the Ikuta school is called kakuzume and its tip is wide and square-shaped.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsume used by the Ikuta school is called kakuzume and its tip is wide and square-shaped.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="139">
<j>山田流は丸爪と呼ばれ、尖頭の丸形である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsume used by Yamada school is called maruzume and its tip is round-shaped.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsume used by the Yamada school is called maruzume and its tip is round-shaped.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsume used by the Yamada school is called maruzume and its tip is round-shaped.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="140">
<j>この形状の差異により音色が微妙に異なる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tone quality is subtly different due to the difference in the shape of tsume.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tone quality is subtly different due to the difference in the shape of tsume.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tone quality is subtly different due to the difference in the shape of tsume.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="141">
<j>この他歴史的に、先の広がった四角形など多少の差異がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other than the above, other types, such as the one whose tip becomes wider, were used historically.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other than the above, other types, such as one where the tip becomes wider, were used historically.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other than the above, other types, such as one where the tip becomes wider, were used historically.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="142">
<j>厚みは戦後に移るにしたがって徐々に薄くなってきている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thickness has gradually become thinner after the war.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thickness has gradually become thinner after the war.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thickness has gradually become thinner after the war.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="143">
<j>材質は（雅楽を除き）象牙でつくられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsume is made of ivory (except for the products for gagaku).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsume is made of ivory (except for products for gagaku).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsume is made of ivory (except for products for gagaku).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="144">
<j>最近は絶滅のおそれのある野生動植物の種の国際取引に関する条約（ワシントン条約）により象牙の入手が困難のため高騰してはいるが、代用樹脂は学校教育用などに限られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the price of ivory has soared recently because of unavailability caused by the Convention on International Trade in Endangered Species of Wild Fauna and Flora (Washington Convention), substitute plastic is being used only for the products for school education purpose.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the price of ivory has soared recently because of unavailability caused by the Convention on International Trade in Endangered Species of Wild Fauna and Flora (Washington Convention), substitute plastic is being used only for the products for school educational purpose.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the price of ivory has soared recently because of unavailability caused by the Convention on International Trade in Endangered Species of Wild Fauna and Flora (Washington Convention), substitute plastic is being used only for the products for school educational purpose.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>柱(じ)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ji</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ji</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ji</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="145">
<j>柱（じ）は他の弦楽器でいう駒、ブリッジで、糸を支え音高を定め、振動を胴に伝える部品である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">ji is a part of Soh which corresponds to koma or bridge of other stringed instruments, and its functions are propping ito, defining pitch and transmitting vibration to the body.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">ji is a part of Soh which corresponds to koma or bridge of other stringed instruments, and its function is to prop ito, defining pitch and transmitting vibration to the body.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ji is a part of Soh which corresponds to koma or bridge of other stringed instruments, and its function is to prop ito, defining pitch and transmitting vibration to the body.</e>
<cmt>文頭を大文字にしました。不要なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="146">
<j>楽箏のものは小さく低いが、大音量を求める近代のものは大型になっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although small and short ones are used for gaku-Soh, bigger ones are commonly used for current Soh which requires big volume.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although small and short ones are used for gaku-Soh, bigger ones are commonly used for current Soh which requires a large volume.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although small and short ones are used for gaku-Soh, bigger ones are commonly used for current Soh which requires a large volume.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="147">
<j>補助的に小型の柱や、最高音弦用の脚部に変化を加えた柱、その他倒れにくくしたりするために工夫が施された特殊な柱なども種々使用される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Various kinds of ji, such as the one to which supplementary small prop is attched, the one whose foot proping the string of the highest note is modified or the one which is designed to prevent it from falling, are being in use.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Various kinds of ji, such as one to which a supplementary small prop is attched, one where foot proping the string of the highest note is modified or one which is designed to prevent it from falling, are in use.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Various kinds of ji, such as one to which a supplementary small prop is attached, one where foot propping the string of the highest note is modified or one which is designed to prevent it from falling, are in use.</e>
<cmt>attached、proppingスペル訂正しました、</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="148">
<j>材質は古くは唐木が多かったが、現在では象牙製が最高とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Karaki (imported wood) was mainly used as material in the past, but the product made of ivory is regarded as the best one today.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Karaki (imported wood) was mainly used as material in the past, but the product made of ivory is regarded as the best today.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Karaki (imported wood) was mainly used as material in the past, but the product made of ivory is regarded as the best today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="149">
<j>しかし大変に高価であるので、現在は合成樹脂製のものが広く用いられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, plastic products are widely used at present since ivory is very expensive.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, plastic products are widely used at present since ivory is very expensive.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, plastic products are widely used at present since ivory is very expensive.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="150">
<j>その他、以前はクジラ骨製のものもしばしば使用された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other than the above, products made of whale bone were also often used previously.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other than the above, products made of whale bone were also often used previously.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other than the above, products made of whale bone were also often used previously.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="151">
<j>古いものでは美しい蒔絵が施されたものもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some old products were decorated with makie.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some old products were decorated with makie.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some old products were decorated with makie.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>近代以降に改良された楽器</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Musical instruments which were improved since the early modern times</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Musical instruments improved since the early modern times</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Musical instruments improved since the early modern times</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="152">
<j>近年において開発された箏を「新箏」と言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Recently developed Soh is called &quot;shin-Soh&quot; (literally, new Soh).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Recently developed Soh is called &quot;shin-Soh&quot; (literally, new Soh).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Recently developed Soh is called &apos;shin-Soh&apos; (literally, new Soh).</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="153">
<j>宮城道雄の開発した十七絃箏がもっとも有名であり、既に一般化している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among others, jushichigen-Soh (seventeen-stringed Soh) developed by Michio MIYAGI is the most famous one and it has already become common.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among others, jushichigen-Soh (seventeen-stringed Soh) developed by Michio MIYAGI is the most famous one and it has already become common.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among others, jushichigen-Soh (17-stringed Soh) developed by Michio MIYAGI is the most famous one and it has already become common.</e>
<cmt>数字に訂正しました。不要なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="154">
<j>合奏で用いられるように特に低音部が良く鳴るように拡張されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order to be used in an ensemble, its number of strings was increased so that the bass register sound good.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to be used in an ensemble, its number of strings was increased so that the bass register sounds good.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to be used in an ensemble, its number of strings was increased so that the bass register sounds good.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="155">
<j>宮城以降の楽曲では広く用いられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is commonly used in many pieces of Soh music composed since the era of Miyagi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is commonly used in many pieces of Soh music composed since the era of Miyagi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is commonly used in many pieces of Soh music composed since the era of Miyagi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="156">
<j>宮城道雄が開発した楽器はほかにも教育用普及楽器の短箏（たんごと）、試験的に作られた超大型楽器八十絃がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other instruments developed by Michio MIYAGI are tangoto (short stringed instrument), which was developed for education and promotion purpose, and super-large hachijugen (eighty-stringed instrument), which was produced on a trial basis.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other instruments developed by Michio MIYAGI are tangoto (short stringed instrument), which was developed for education and promotion purpose, and super-large hachijugen (eighty-stringed instrument), which was produced on a trial basis.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other instruments developed by Michio MIYAGI are tangoto (short stringed instrument), which was developed for education and promotion purpose, and super-large hachijugen (80-stringed instrument), which was produced on a trial basis.</e>
<cmt>数字に訂正しました。不要なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="157">
<j>このほか、現代において作られた箏として1969年に作曲家三木稔と箏曲家野坂恵子が共同開発した二十絃箏（実際は21本の絃がある）、それから二十五絃箏、三十絃、三十二絃箏などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other than the above, various types of Soh were invented recently such as nijugen-Soh (twenty-stringed Soh) (actually it was twenty-one-stringed), which was jointly developed by composer Minoru MIKI and Soh musician Keiko NOSAKA in 1969, nijugogen-Soh (twenty-five-stringed Soh), sanjugen-Soh (thirty-stringed Soh) and sanjunigen-Soh (thirty-two-stringed Soh).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other than the above, various types of Soh were invented recently such as nijugen-Soh (twenty-stringed Soh) (actually it was twenty-one-stringed), which was jointly developed by composer Minoru MIKI and Soh musician Keiko NOSAKA in 1969, nijugogen-Soh (twenty-five-stringed Soh), sanjugen-Soh (thirty-stringed Soh) and sanjunigen-Soh (thirty-two-stringed Soh).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other than the above, various types of Soh were invented recently such as nijugen-Soh (20-stringed Soh, actually it was 21-stringed), which was jointly developed by composer Minoru MIKI and Soh musician Keiko NOSAKA in 1969, nijugogen-Soh (25-stringed Soh), sanjugen-Soh (30-stringed Soh) and sanjunigen-Soh (32-stringed Soh).</e>
<cmt>数字に訂正しました。不要なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="158">
<j>それぞれ現代の（邦楽系の「現代邦楽」および洋楽系の「現代音楽」双方の分野の）作曲家によって新しい音楽作品を作る試みが行われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Contemporary composers (those of &quot;modern Japanese traditional music&quot; whose origin are Japanese traditional music as well as those of &quot;modern music&quot; whose origin are western music) are trying to create new musical pieces using such newly developed instruments.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Contemporary composers (those of &quot;modern Japanese traditional music&quot; whose origin are Japanese traditional music as well as those of &quot;modern music&quot; whose origin are western music) are trying to create new musical pieces using such newly developed instruments.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Contemporary composers (those of &apos;modern Japanese traditional music&apos; whose origin are Japanese traditional music as well as those of &apos;modern music&apos; whose origin are western music) are trying to create new musical pieces using such newly developed instruments.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。スペース削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="159">
<j>特に二十絃箏は多く用いられ、徐々に一般化しつつある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among others, nijugen-Soh is often used and has been popularizing gradually.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among others, nijugen-Soh is often used and has been gradually popularized.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among others, nijugen-Soh is often used and has been gradually popularized.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="160">
<j>ちなみに大正琴は発音原理が琴（きん）に属する楽器のため、ここで扱う箏とは基本的分類において異なる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Incidentally, taishogoto (Japanese harp with three to five strings) is a fundamentally different instrument from Soh because it is categorized into kin group based on the law of making sound.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Incidentally, taishogoto (Japanese harp with three to five strings) is a fundamentally different instrument from Soh because it is categorized into kin group based on the law of making sound.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Incidentally, taishogoto (Japanese harp with three to five strings) is a fundamentally different instrument from Soh because it is categorized into kin group based on the law of making sound.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="14">
<tit>
<j>主要産地</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Principal production centers</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Principal production centers</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Principal production centers</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="161">
<j>福山市（全国生産量の7割を生産）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fukuyama City (its production amount accounts for 70% of nation&apos;s total amount)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fukuyama City (its production amount accounts for seventy percent of nation&apos;s total amount)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fukuyama City (its production amount accounts for seventy percent of nation&apos;s total amount)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="15">
<tit>
<j>日本国以外の類似楽器</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Similar musical instruments in other countries than Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Similar musical instruments in other countries than Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Similar musical instruments in other countries than Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="162">
<j>中国の撥弦楽器のうちツィター属のものだけでも時代、地方、様式により多くの種類がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In China, there exist many kinds of stringed instrument that belong to zither group depending on the ages, regions or styles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In China, there exist many kinds of stringed instrument that belong to zither group depending upon the ages, regions, or styles.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In China, there exist many kinds of stringed instrument that belong to zither group depending upon the ages, regions, or styles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="163">
<j>一般的には「ツェン」と呼ばれる楽器が箏を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Generally, a musical instrument called &quot;tzen&quot; refers to Soh.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Generally, a musical instrument called &quot;tzen&quot; refers to Soh.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Generally, a musical instrument called &apos;tzen&apos; refers to Soh.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="164">
<j>（字は同じ「箏」の字）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(same Chinese character &quot;箏&quot; is used)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(same Chinese character &quot;箏&quot; is used)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Same Chinese character &apos;Soh&apos; (箏) is used.)</e>
<cmt>文頭を大文字にしました。表記を訂正しました。ピリオド補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="165">
<j>朝鮮には伽耶琴（カヤグム）と呼ばれる12弦の箏があり、前部を膝に乗せ指頭で弾奏する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Korean peninsula, there exists a twelve-stringed instrument called &quot;kayagumu&quot;, and people play it by fingertips while putting its front part on their knee.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Korean peninsula, there exists a twelve-stringed instrument called &quot;kayagumu,&quot; and people play it with their fingertips while placing the front part on their knee.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Korean peninsula, there exists a 12-stringed instrument called &quot;kayagumu,&quot; and people play it with their fingertips while placing the front part on their knee.</e>
<cmt>数字に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="166">
<j>正倉院に伝わる「新羅琴」はその初期の頃のものと言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Shiragigoto&quot; preserved at Shosoh-in is said to be the initial-stage kayagumu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Shiragigoto&quot; preserved at Shosoh-in is said to be the initial-stage kayagumu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shiragigoto&apos; preserved at Shoso-in is said to be the initial-stage kayagumu.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。Shoso-inに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="167">
<j>また、6本の弦と固定フレットを持ち棒（匙）で弾奏する玄琴（コムンゴ）がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There also exists six-stringed instrument with fixed fret called komungo, and people play it with the use of stick (spoon).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There also exists six-stringed instrument with fixed fret called komungo, and people play it using a stick (spoon).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There also exists six-stringed instrument with fixed fret called komungo, and people play it using a stick (spoon).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="168">
<j>他にレンギョウの枝で擦って奏する7弦の牙箏（アジェン）がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, there exists seven-stringed instrument called ajen, and people play it by rubbing strings with a branch of weeping forsythia.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, there exists a seven-stringed instrument called ajen, and people play it by rubbing strings with a branch of weeping forsythia.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, there exists a seven-stringed instrument called ajen, and people play it by rubbing strings with a branch of weeping forsythia.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="169">
<j>箏は楽器分類上ツィター属に含まれることもあり、ヨーロッパでの類似楽器としてはツィターが挙げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As seen from the fact that Soh is categorized into zither group, zither is a similar musical instrument in Europe.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As seen from the fact that Soh is categorized into the zither group, zither is a similar musical instrument in Europe.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As seen from the fact that Soh is categorized into the zither group, zither is a similar musical instrument in Europe.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="170">
<j>ツィターはヨーロッパの楽器としては一般的なほうではなく、アルプス地方の民俗楽器（特にオーストリア）として扱われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zither is not a commonly-used musical instrument in Europe but a folk instrument of Alpine region (especially Austria).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zither is not a commonly-used musical instrument in Europe, but a folk instrument of the Alpine region (especially Austria).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zither is not a commonly-used musical instrument in Europe, but a folk instrument of the Alpine region (especially Austria).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="171">
<j>他に、フィンランドの民俗楽器カンテレも類似楽器の一つに挙げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another similar musical instrument in Europe is kantere, a folk musical instrument of Finland.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another similar musical instrument in Europe is kantere, a folk musical instrument of Finland.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another similar musical instrument in Europe is kantere, a folk musical instrument of Finland.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 ドラムスコ(id:40234), 十勝産(id:111739), Suguri F(id:11127), Polyphonie(id:270990), 30rKs56MaE(id:11801), Eskimbot(id:29676), Mintleaf(id:2216), G-Sounds(id:198992), OKBot(id:143139), Opponent(id:720), 氷鷺(id:73707), AlnoktaBOT(id:135808), Rei-bot(id:94097), Loveless(id:129239), CompUTOSer(id:1008), Point136(id:211299), Yas(id:739), Nopira(id:29335), Lanbea(id:14420), Hermes(id:21387), 詠狸庵(id:41048), Dintriq(id:2719), Mitsunari.u(id:103954), Balmung0731(id:99201), TS(id:481), ぽえこ(id:88711), Kiku b(id:14507), Hatsune(id:26654), MDR-SK(id:192066), Cik(id:6227), VolkovBot(id:105371), Tietew(id:4054), SilvonenBot(id:190970), YurikBot(id:18605), M-Falcon(id:1227), SuisuiBot(id:10165), 貘(id:106080), 曖(id:41245), Iokseng(id:92490), Suisui(id:69), SieBot(id:126695), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>