<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>絲鞋</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigai, Shiai, Ito no Kutsu (Silk shoes)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigai</e>
<cmt>国語辞典で使用されている読みを採用しました(yahoo辞書)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>絲鞋（しがい・いとのくつ・しあい）とは、未成年の皇族や童舞の舞楽装束や神道の儀式に参加する幼い巫女に用いられる絹糸製の靴。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigai, Shiai, or Ito no Kutsu is a pair of silk shoes worn by Imperial family members who are underage or little shrine maidens who participate in the Shinto rituals, or used for the costume of Bugaku (traditional Japanese court music accompanied by dancing) such as Domai (children&apos;s dances).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigai (also known as Ito no Kutsu, or Shiai) is a pair of silk shoes worn by underage member of Imperial family, performers of Dobu (also known as Warawamai Dance, performed by children), or young shrine maidens who participate in the Shinto rituals.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigai (also known as Ito no Kutsu, or Shiai) is a pair of silk shoes worn by underage member of Imperial family, performers of Dobu (also known as Warawamai Dance, performed by children), or young shrine maidens who participate in the Shinto rituals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>「絲」とは絹糸の事を指し、本体は白い絹糸を菱形を浮かせて編んだもので、中敷は筵、底は牛革製。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The word &quot;Shi 絲&quot; means &quot;silk yarn;&quot; the body of the shoes is knitted with silk yarn with diamond patterns in relief, the insole made of a straw mat, and the sole constructed from cattle skin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The word &apos;Shi&apos; (絲) means silk yarn; the body of the shoes is knitted with silk yarn with diamond patterns in relief, the insole made of a straw mat, and the sole constructed from cattle skin.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The word &apos;Shi&apos; (絲) means silk yarn; the body of the shoes is knitted with silk yarn with diamond patterns in relief, the insole made of a straw mat, and the sole constructed from cattle skin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="3">
<j>足首部分に糸が通してあり、二重に足首を括って蝶結び（装束用語では諸鉤）に結ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A shoelace, which traverses the ankle of the shoes, comes around one&apos;s ankle twice and are tied in a bow (Morokagi [bowknot] in the costume terminology).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A shoelace, which traverses the ankle of the shoes, comes around one&apos;s ankle twice and are tied in a bow (Morokagi [bowknot] in the costume terminology).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A shoelace, which traverses the ankle of the shoes, comes around one&apos;s ankle twice and are tied in a bow (Morokagi [bowknot] in the costume terminology).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="4">
<j>構造は現代のズック靴やアメリカ先住民のモカシンに似る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The construction of the shoes resembles that of modern canvas shoes or the American Indian&apos;s moccasins.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The construction of the shoes resembles that of modern canvas shoes or the Native American&apos;s moccasins.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The construction of the shoes resembles that of modern canvas shoes or the Native American&apos;s moccasins.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="5">
<j>もともと六位以下の下級武官の履く苧麻製の「麻鞋（まかい）」がルーツということもあり軽快で活動性に優れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Shigai was originated from Makai (hemp yarn shoes) worn by low-ranking military officers under the Sixth Court Rank, it was light and comfortable as well as suitable for active movements.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Shigai was originated from &apos;Makai,&apos; hemp yarn shoes worn by low-ranking military officers at and under the rank of Rokui (Sixth Rank), it was light and comfortable as well as suitable for active movements.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Shigai was originated from &apos;Makai,&apos; hemp yarn shoes worn by low-ranking military officers at and under the rank of Rokui (Sixth Rank), it was light and comfortable as well as suitable for active movements.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>童水干などと同様の経緯で貴族の子供用になり高級化して絹糸製の「絲鞋」が誕生した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Following the same developments as Dosuikan (the Heian costume for children), it was upgraded for the use of children of nobility; that is the beginning of &quot;Shigai&quot; made of silk.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Following the same developments as Dosuikan (the Heian costume for children), it was upgraded for the noble children; that is the beginning of &apos;Shigai&apos; made of silk.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Following the same developments as Dosuikan (the Heian costume for children), it was upgraded for the noble children; that is the beginning of &apos;Shigai&apos; made of silk.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="7">
<j>同じく「麻鞋」から発展したものに、下級武官用の藁製の靴「草鞋（わらうず）」がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The straw-made shoes called &quot;Warauzu&quot; worn by low-ranking military officials are also developed out of Makai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The straw-made shoes called &apos;Warauzu&apos; worn by low-ranking military officials were also developed out of &apos;Makai.&apos;</e>
<cmt>過去形にし、クォーテーションを補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The straw-made shoes called &apos;Warauzu&apos; worn by low-ranking military officials were also developed out of &apos;Makai.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Dinosaur(id:99960), 桜井悠士(id:72420), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>