<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>敦盛 (能)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Atsumori (Noh)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Atsumori (Noh play)</e>
<cmt>他のファイルと統一しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Atsumori (Noh play)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>『敦盛』（あつもり）は、能の演目のひとつで、二番目物、公達物。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Atsumori&quot; is the title of a Noh program, which belongs to the category of nibanme-mono (second-category play) and the subcategory of Kindachi mono (play featuring a courtier).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Atsumori&quot; is the title of a Noh program, which belongs to the category of nibanme-mono (second-category play) and the subcategory of Kindachi mono (play featuring a courtier).</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Atsumori&quot; is the title of a Noh program, which belongs to the category of nibanme-mono (second-category play) and the subcategory of Kindachi mono (play featuring a courtier).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>平家物語の「敦盛最期」の章をもとに、世阿弥が編作した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is written by Zeami as an arranged version of the chapter &quot;Atsumori no saigo (the death of Atsumori) in &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; (The tale of the Heike).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is written by Zeami as an arranged version of the chapter &quot;Atsumori no Saigo (the Death of Atsumori)&quot; in Heike Monogatari (The Tale of the Heike).</e>
<cmt>“を調整しました。大文字／小文字を調整しました。スペースを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is written by Zeami as an arranged version of the chapter &apos;Atsumori no Saigo&apos; (the Death of Atsumori) in Heike Monogatari (The Tale of the Heike).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション調整</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>中之舞（黄鐘早舞・男舞）を舞う優雅な演目である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is an elegant program in which chu-no-mai dances (medium-tempo dance) including oshiki-haya-mai dance (dance of male ghost) and otoko-mai dance (male dance) are performed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is an elegant program in which chu-no-mai dances (medium-tempo dance) (oshiki-haya-mai dance [dance of male ghost] and otoko-mai dance [male dance]) are performed.</e>
<cmt>括弧の使用をoriginalと統一しました。スペースを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is an elegant program in which chu-no-mai dances (medium-tempo dance) (oshiki-haya-mai dance [dance of male ghost] and otoko-mai dance [male dance]) are performed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>演者</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Actors</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Characters</e>
<cmt>他のファイルと統一しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Characters</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>前シテ - 草刈男</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mae-Shite (the leading role in the first half of a Noh play): a mowing man</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mae-Shite (leading role in the first half): Grass-cutter</e>
<cmt>他のファイルと統一しました。Mowing manをgrass-cutterにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mae-Shite (leading role in the first half): Grass-cutter</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>後シテ - 平敦盛（霊形）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ato-Shite (the leading role in the latter half of a Noh play): TAIRA no Atsumori</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ato-Shite (leading role in the latter half): TAIRA no Atsumori</e>
<cmt>他のファイルと統一しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ato-Shite (leading role in the latter half): TAIRA no Atsumori</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>前ツレ - 草刈男</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mae-Tsure (the companion of Mae-Shite): a mowing man</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mae-Tsure (companion of Mae-Shite): Grass-cutter</e>
<cmt>他のファイルと統一しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mae-Tsure (companion of Mae-Shite): Grass-cutter</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>ワキ - 蓮生（出家した熊谷直実）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Waki (the supporting actor): Rensho (Naozane KUMAGAI as a priest)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Waki (supporting role): Rensho (Naozane KUMAGAI as a priest)</e>
<cmt>他のファイルと統一しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Waki (supporting role): Rensho (Naozane KUMAGAI as a priest)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>アイ - 里人</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ai (narrator) : villager</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ai (narrator): Villager</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ai (narrator): Villager</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>あらすじ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Story line</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Synopsis</e>
<cmt>訳し直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Synopsis</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>源平の戦いの緒戦に疲れた源氏の武将熊谷直実は、出家して法名熊谷直実と名乗った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Drained from the first battle of the Genpei War (the war between the Minamoto clan and the Taira clan), Naozane KUMAGAI, busho (military commander) of the Minamoto clan, becomes a priest and calls himself Priest Naozane KUMAGAI.</e>
<cmt>「法名熊谷直実」は「法名蓮生」の間違いと思われます。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Drained from the first battle of the Genpei War (the war between the Minamoto clan and the Taira clan), Naozane KUMAGAI, a busho (military commander) of the Minamoto clan, becomes a priest and calls himself Priest Rensho.</e>
<cmt>冠詞を追加しました。法名を蓮生にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Drained from the first battle of the Genpei War (the war between the Minamoto clan and the Taira clan), Naozane KUMAGAI, a busho (military commander) of the Minamoto clan, becomes a priest and calls himself Priest Rensho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>秋八月、蓮生はかつて一ノ谷の戦いで討った平敦盛の菩提を弔うために摂津国須磨の浦へ赴いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In August of autumn, Rensho visits Sumanoura Bay in Settsu Province for the purpose of offering prayers to Buddha for the happiness of TAIRA no Atsumori he killed in the Battle of Ichinotani.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In August of autumn, Rensho visits Sumanoura Bay in Settsu Province for the purpose of offering prayers to the Buddha of TAIRA no Atsumori whom he had killed in the Battle of Ichinotani.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。Buddha for the happinessをthe Buddha ofにしました。時制を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In August of autumn, Rensho visits Sumanoura Bay in Settsu Province for the purpose of offering prayers to the Buddha of TAIRA no Atsumori whom he had killed in the Battle of Ichinotani.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>笛の音が聞え、草刈男らに出会う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There, he hears a flute sound and encounters men mowing grass.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There, he hears the sound of a flute and encounters men cutting grass.</e>
<cmt>A flute soundをthe sound of a fluteにしました。Mowingをcuttingにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There, he hears the sound of a flute and encounters men cutting grass.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>蓮生が男らに誰が笛を吹いていたのかと尋ねると、男らの一人が笛にまつわる因縁について語り、十念を授けて欲しいと言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Rensho asks them who was playing the flute, one of them tells him about the history of the flute and asks Rensho to give him Buddhist invocations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Rensho asks them who was playing the flute, one of them tells him about the unfortunate history of the flute and asks Rensho to give ten Buddhist invocations.</e>
<cmt>Unfortunateを追加しました。Himをtenに変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Rensho asks them who was playing the flute, one of them tells him about the unfortunate history of the flute and asks Rensho to give ten Buddhist invocations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>蓮生が理由を質すと、その男は敦盛の化身である事をほのめかして姿を消す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Rensho asks the man why, he hints that he is an incarnation of Atsumori and then disappears.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Rensho asks the man why, he hints that he is an incarnation of Atsumori and then disappears.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Rensho asks the man why, he hints that he is an incarnation of Atsumori and then disappears.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>夜、蓮生が読経していると敦盛の霊が現れて平家一門の栄枯盛衰を語り、平家最後の宴を懐かしんで中之舞を舞い、一ノ谷合戦での討ち死にの模様を再現して見せる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Rensho is chanting sutra in the night, the ghost of Atsumori appears to tell about the ups and downs of the Taira clan, perform chu-no-mai dance with nostalgia for the final feast of the Taira clan, and reproduce the scene of his own death in the Battle of Ichinotani in face of Rensho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Rensho is chanting sutra at night, the ghost of Atsumori appears to tell about the ups and downs of the Taira clan, performs a chu-no-mai dance with nostalgia for the final feast of the Taira clan, and reproduces the scene of his own death in the Battle of Ichinotani.</e>
<cmt>in theをatにしました。スペースを削除しました。冠詞を追加しました。不要な部分を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Rensho is chanting sutra at night, the ghost of Atsumori appears to tell about the ups and downs of the Taira clan, performs a chu-no-mai dance with nostalgia for the final feast of the Taira clan, and reproduces the scene of his own death in the Battle of Ichinotani.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>そしてやっと敵である直実に巡り会えたと仇を討とうとするが、すでに出家して蓮生となって弔いにつとめる直実はもはや敵ではないと悟り、極楽浄土では共に同じ蓮に生まれる身になろうと言い残して敦盛の霊は姿を消す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Atsumori tries to revenge Naozane, saying that he has finally found his enemy, he learns that Naozane who has become Priest Rensho is no longer his enemy and the ghost of Atsumori disappears, leaving words of suggestion that he and Rensho be born to be lotus in Gokuraku Jodo (the Amida Pure Land).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Atsumori, on having finally found his enemy tries to take revenge on Naozane, he learns that Naozane has become a priest and as Rensho was dedicated to reading sutra and was no longer his enemy; the ghost of Atsumori disappears, leaving words that he and Rensho both be born as lotus (&apos;ren&apos; in Rensho&apos;s name means lotus) in Gokuraku Jodo (the Amida Pure Land).</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。蓮の意味を追加しました。Revengeの使用を修正しました。大部分を訳し直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Atsumori, on having finally found his enemy tries to take revenge on Naozane, he learns that Naozane has become a priest and as Rensho was dedicated to reading sutra and was no longer his enemy; the ghost of Atsumori disappears, leaving words that he and Rensho both be born as lotus (&apos;ren&apos; in Rensho&apos;s name means lotus) in Gokuraku Jodo (the Amida Pure Land).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 ささがに(id:228586), Grayterms(id:204076), Yas(id:739), Shouden(id:38327), NISYAN(id:169936), Ｋｓ(id:15319), Miya(id:1881), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>