<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>雑煮</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zoni</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zoni</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zoni</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>雑煮（ぞうに）とは正月に多く食べられる、餅を主と具材をあしらった汁料理である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zoni is a soup dish which contains mochi (rice cakes) and other ingredients, and it is usually eaten in the New Year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zoni is a soup dish which contains mochi (rice cakes) and other ingredients, and it is usually eaten in the New Year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zoni is a soup dish which contains mochi (rice cakes) and other ingredients, and it is usually eaten in the New Year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>雑煮の由来については、歴史学を中心とする考え方と民俗学を中心とする考え方に大きな意見の相違が存在している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are two seriously contradicting views about the origin of zoni: a viewpoint of historians and a viewpoint of folklorists.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are two opposing views about the origin of zoni: the viewpoint of historians and the viewpoint of folklorists.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are two opposing views about the origin of zoni: the viewpoint of historians and the viewpoint of folklorists.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>そもそも正月料理の歴史そのものの研究が不十分であり、どちらが正しいかを判断するには至っていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This issue has not been settled yet, because the history of New Year&apos;s dishes has been insufficiently studied.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This issue has not been settled yet, because the history of New Year&apos;s dishes has been insufficiently studied.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This issue has not been settled yet, because the history of New Year&apos;s dishes has been insufficiently studied.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>歴史学的な考え</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Theory from the viewpoint of historians</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Viewpoint of the historians</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Viewpoint of the historians</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>元来は武家社会における料理であり、餅や野菜、乾燥食品などを一緒に煮込んだ野戦料理だったのでは無いかと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered to have been a dish of the samurai world prepared in battle fields by simmering mochi, vegetables, and dried foods in a pot.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered to have been a dish of the samurai world prepared in battle fields by simmering mochi, vegetables, and dried foods in a pot.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered to have been a dish of the samurai world prepared in battle fields by simmering mochi, vegetables, and dried foods in a pot.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>正月に餅料理を食する慣習は古代より「歯固」の儀式と結びついた形で存在しており、それと関連して発生したと見られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The custom of eating mochi dishes in the New Year has been associated with the ceremony of &apos;Hagatame&apos; (strengthening teeth) since ancient times, and this is considered to have given birth to zoni.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The custom of eating mochi dishes in the New Year has been associated with the ceremony of &apos;Hagatame&apos; (strengthening teeth) since ancient times, and this is considered to have given birth to zoni.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The custom of eating mochi dishes in the New Year has been associated with the ceremony of &apos;Hagatame&apos; (strengthening teeth) since ancient times, and this is considered to have given rise to zoni.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>雑煮は元は烹雑（ほうぞう）と呼ばれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zoni was initially called hozo (烹雑).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zoni was initially called hozo (烹雑).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zoni was initially called hozo (烹雑).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>室町時代に書かれた『鈴鹿家記』に初めて「雑煮」という言葉が登場する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The word &apos;zoni&apos; first appeared in &quot;Suzukake-ki&quot; (Journal of the Suzuka family) written in the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The word &apos;zoni&apos; first appeared in &quot;Suzukake-ki&quot; (Journal of the Suzuka family) written in the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The word &apos;zoni&apos; first appeared in &quot;Suzukake-ki&quot; (Journal of the Suzuka family) written in the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>‘→&apos;“→&quot;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>この料理が次第に武家社会において儀礼化していき、やがて一般庶民に普及したものとみられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This dish probably developed to become one of the rituals in the samurai world, and later has spread among common people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This dish probably developed to become one of the rituals in the samurai world, and later spread among common people.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This dish probably became one of the rituals in the samurai world, and later spread among common people.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>本膳料理においては最初に雑煮が出され、武家社会における饗宴には欠かす事のできない料理であったと見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Considering the fact that zoni is first served in the course of honzen ryori (formally arranged dinner), it was probably an essential dish for banquets for welcoming guests in the samurai world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Considering the fact that zoni is first served in the course of honzen ryori (a formally arranged dinner), it was probably an essential dish for banquets for welcoming guests in the samurai world.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Considering the fact that zoni is first served in the course of honzen ryori (a formally arranged dinner), it was probably an essential dish for banquets for welcoming guests in the samurai world.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>江戸時代、尾張藩を中心とした東海地方の諸藩では、武家の雑煮には餅菜と呼ばれる小松菜の一種のみを具とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Edo period, zoni of samurai families in Owari Domain and other domains of Tokai region contained only mochi and a type of brassica rapa (a kind of Chinese cabbage) called mochina.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Edo period, zoni of samurai families in Owari Domain and other domains of Tokai region contained only mochi and a type of brassica rapa (a kind of Chinese cabbage) called mochina.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Edo period, zoni of samurai families in Owari Domain and other domains of Tokai region contained only mochi and a type of brassica rapa (a kind of Chinese cabbage) called mochina.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>餅と菜を一緒に取り上げて食べるのが習わしで、「名（＝菜）を持ち（＝餅）上げる」という縁起担ぎだったという（上記の習わしが武家社会一般の作法だったという説は、誤伝による俗説）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said to have been a practice of picking up mochi and a piece of vegetable together to eat, which was for good luck with a pun: &apos;mochi ageru&apos; (raise a mochi = win), and &apos;na&apos; (vegetable, or &apos;name&apos; in Japanese) to make it &apos;win one&apos;s name.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said to have been a practice of picking up mochi and a piece of vegetable together to eat, which was for good luck with a pun: &apos;mochi ageru&apos; (raise a mochi = win), and &apos;na&apos; (vegetable, or &apos;name&apos; in Japanese) to make it &apos;win one&apos;s name.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said to have been a practice of picking up mochi and a piece of vegetable together to eat, which was for good luck with a pun: &apos;mochi ageru&apos; (raise a mochi = win), and &apos;na&apos; (vegetable, or &apos;name&apos; in Japanese) to make it &apos;win one&apos;s name.&apos;</e>
<cmt>‘→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>民俗学的な考え</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Theory from the viewpoint of folklorists</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Viewpoint of folklorists</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Viewpoint of folklorists</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="12">
<j>これに対して民俗学の観点からは、こうした考え方を強く否定する考え方が出されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In response to this, folklorists present a theory that strongly contradict those mentioned above.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In response to this, folklorists present a theory that strongly contradicts those mentioned above.</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In response to this, folklorists present a theory that strongly contradicts those mentioned above.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>これは、餅を主体とする雑煮は近世以後に全国的に普及したもので、それ以前においては民衆社会に根ざした正月用の儀礼料理であり、餅主体の雑煮は畿内周辺にしか存在しなかったとするものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This theory argues that zoni (without mochi) was one of ritual dishes of the New Year in the common people society, and zoni containing mochi as essential ingredients was eaten only in the Kinai region (provinces surrounding Kyoto and Nara) before the early-modern times, since when it has spread across the country.</e>
<cmt>「それ以前においては民衆社会に根ざした正月用の儀礼料理」は雑煮と呼ばれた，餅のない儀礼料理，と解釈できますが，「餅が含まれていない」という語句が原文にはないので，わかりにくいのですが，英文では括弧に入れました．日本史の近世が安土桃山から江戸時代の３００年を指すということで　the early-modern times が使われているのに習いました．近世「以前」と「以後」においては，ここでは，「以前」が近世を含まず，「以後」は近世を含むと解釈できます．</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This theory argues that zoni (without mochi) was one of the ritual dishes of the New Year among common people, and zoni containing mochi as essential ingredients was eaten only in the Kinai region (provinces surrounding Kyoto and Nara) before the early-modern times, since then it has spread across the country.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This theory argues that zoni (without mochi) was one of the ritual dishes of the New Year among common people, and zoni containing mochi as essential ingredients was eaten only in the Kinai region (provinces surrounding Kyoto and Nara) before the early-modern times, and since then it has spread across the country.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="14">
<j>古来においては一日は夕方から始まるとする風習があり、元旦は大晦日の夕方から始まると考えられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A day was thought to begin at dusk in old times; and the New Year&apos;s Day was thought to begin at the dusk of the New Year&apos;s Eve.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A day was thought to begin at dusk in old times; and the New Year&apos;s Day was thought to begin at the dusk of the New Year&apos;s Eve.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A day was thought to begin at dusk in old times; and the New Year&apos;s Day was thought to begin at the dusk of New Year&apos;s Eve.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>大晦日の夕方に神仏に供えた餅や飯を日の出後に降ろして、具材を加えて煮た物が雑煮のルーツとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">mochi and cooked rice were placed in the alters of deities as offerings in the evening of New Year&apos;s Eve, and they were taken down before the dawn the next day and simmered with other ingredients to prepare a soup, which is believed to have been the origin of zoni.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">mochi and cooked rice were placed in the alters of deities as offerings in the evening of New Year&apos;s Eve, and they were taken down before dawn the next day and simmered with other ingredients to prepare a soup, which is believed to have been the origin of zoni.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mochi and cooked rice were placed on the altars of deities as offerings in the evening of New Year&apos;s Eve, and they were taken down before dawn the next day and simmered with other ingredients to prepare a soup, which is believed to have been the origin of zoni.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="16">
<j>また近世以前においては、「餅なし正月」と呼ばれる、正月三箇日に餅を神仏に供えたり食することを禁忌とする風習が、畑作地帯を中心として広く存在していたことも指摘されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also pointed out that, so called &apos;mochinashi shogatsu&apos; (New Year days without mochi), a custom that made it a taboo to offer mochi to deities or to eat them within the first three days of New Year, was widely practiced in dry field crop regions before the early-modern times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also pointed out that, so called &apos;mochinashi shogatsu&apos; (New Year days without mochi), a custom that made it taboo to offer mochi to deities or to eat them within the first three days of New Year, was widely practiced in dry field crop regions before the early-modern times.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also pointed out that, so called &apos;mochinashi shogatsu&apos; (New Year days without mochi), a custom that made it taboo to offer mochi to deities or to eat them within the first three days of New Year, was widely practiced in farming regions before the early-modern times.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>こうした地域は関東地方・中部地方・中国地方・四国地方などに広がっており、その多くはかつては水田を作るには不適当であったため、米以外の作物で定畑や焼畑を行っていた地域とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kanto region, the Chubu region, the Chugoku region, and Shikoku region included these dry fields, where people cultivated fields or practiced slash and burns for produce other than rice, because those lands had not been suited for rice paddies in those days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kanto region, the Chubu region, the Chugoku region, and Shikoku region included these dry fields, where people cultivated fields or practiced slash and burn techniques for products other than rice, because those lands had not been suited for rice paddies in those days.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kanto region, the Chubu region, the Chugoku region, and Shikoku region included these dry fields, where people cultivated fields or practiced slash and burn techniques for products other than rice, because those lands had not been suited for rice paddies in those days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>これらの地域では、米及びそれを原料とする餅は自己の土地からは生み出されない外来の食物であり、神仏に土地の豊饒を願う儀式の場において、こうした外来の食物を用いることは禁忌であったと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In these regions, rice and mochi were foreign foods which their fields did not produce, so it is considered to have been a taboo to use these foreign foods at those sacred rituals to pray for fertility of their lands.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In these regions, rice and mochi were foreign foods which their fields did not produce, so it is considered to have been a taboo to use these foreign foods at those sacred rituals to pray for the fertility of their lands.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In these regions, rice and mochi were foreign foods which their fields did not produce, so it is considered to have been a taboo to use these foreign foods at those sacred rituals to pray for the fertility of their lands.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>こうした地域は、蕎麦やサトイモなどの自己の土地から産する作物を神仏に捧げ、またこうした食材を主体として雑煮などを作っていたと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In these regions, indigenous produce, such as soba (buckwheat) or satoimo (taro), is thought to have been offered to the deities, and also these ingredients were probably used to prepare zoni.</e>
<cmt>[一原文一訳文の例外処置]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In these regions, indigenous products, such as soba (buckwheat noodles) or satoimo (sweet potato), is thought to have been offered to the deities, and also these ingredients were probably used to prepare zoni.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In these regions, indigenous products, such as buckwheat noodles or taro are thought to have been offered to the deities and these ingredients were probably used to prepare zoni.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>今日でも「餅を使わない雑煮」を作る地域には、かつてそうした禁忌のあった地方が含まれていると考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those rural areas where zoni without mochi is made today are thought to have been included in the regions that kept such a taboo.</e>
<cmt>[一原文一訳文の例外処置]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those rural areas where zoni without mochi is made today are thought to have been included in the regions that had this taboo.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those rural areas where &apos;zoni without mochi&apos; is made today are thought to have been part of the regions that had this taboo.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。クォーテーションをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>また、東北地方や九州地方では、正月に餅を食する習慣が成立したのは時代が下ってからと考えられており、それらの地域を除くと、餅を主体とした雑煮が食されていたのは畿内周辺及び地方の米作地帯に限定されることとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eating mochi in the New Year is considered to have become a custom in more recent years in the regions of Tohoku and Kyushu, so zoni containing mochi as a main ingredient was eaten only in the Kinai region and other rural rice-producing areas.</e>
<cmt>「それらの地域を除くと」は論理的に不要の語句と判断できます．</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eating mochi in the New Year is considered to have become a custom in more recent years in the regions of Tohoku and Kyushu, so zoni containing mochi as a main ingredient was eaten only in the Kinai region and other rural rice-producing areas.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eating mochi in the New Year is considered to have become a custom in more recent years in the regions of Tohoku and Kyushu, so zoni containing mochi as a main ingredient was eaten only in the Kinai region and other rural rice-producing areas.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="22">
<j>こうした風習に代わって餅を主体とする雑煮が全国的に広がっていく背景には、交通や情報伝達の発達もさることながら、石高制に基づく幕藩制による米の生産への政治的・経済的な圧力が畑作地帯を含めて加えられ、実際に灌漑設備の整備や新田開発によって、こうした地域も米作地帯に転換していった影響が大きいとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This theory argues that the reasons why zoni of mochi took over these practices of zoni without mochi all over the country include not only the development of traffic and communication means but also the transformation of these non-rice regions to rice producing areas by the development of irrigation facilities and new rice paddies, which was promoted by the political and economical pressures on those dry fields to produce rice in the period of Shogunate system based on the kokudaka system (tax system based on rice, measured by reference to the rated annual yield of the domain).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This theory argues that the reasons why zoni of mochi took over these practices of zoni without mochi throughout the country include, not only the development of traffic and communication means, but also the transformation of these non-rice regions to rice-producing areas through the development of irrigation facilities and new rice paddies. This was promoted through political and economic pressure on those dry fields to produce rice during the period of the Shogunate system based on the kokudaka system (tax system based on rice, measured by reference to the rated annual yield of the domain).</e>
<cmt>wording; run-on sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is argued that the reasons why zoni containing mochi became more common than zoni without mochi throughout the country include, not only the development of traffic and communication means, but also the transformation of these non-rice regions to rice-producing areas through the development of irrigation facilities and new rice paddies; and this was promoted through political and economic pressure on those farming regions to produce rice during the period of the Shogunate system based on the kokudaka system (tax system based on rice, measured by reference to the rated annual yield of the domain).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。1文にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>代表的な具材</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Typical ingredients</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Typical ingredients</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Typical ingredients</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="23">
<j>具材の代表的なものは、餅・鶏肉の切身または肉団子にしたもの・青味（小松菜、ミツバ、 ホウレンソウ）・色気（彩りを添えるため）に蒲鉾やニンジン・香りにユズなどを載せる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The typical ingredients are: mochi; chicken fillets or balls; greens (brassica rapa, Japanese honewort, or spinach); boiled fish paste or carrots for colors; and citron for flavors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The typical ingredients are: mochi; chicken fillets or balls; greens (brassica rapa, Japanese honewort, or spinach); boiled fish paste or carrots for colors; and citron for flavors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The typical ingredients are: Mochi, chicken fillets or chicken dumplings; greens (komatsuna, Japanese honewort, or spinach); boiled fish paste or carrots for color; and citron for flavor.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>地方による違い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Regional characteristics</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regional characteristics</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regional characteristics</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="24">
<j>雑煮の調理法は地域ごとに特色がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Every region has its own recipe for zoni.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Every region has its own recipe for zoni.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Every region has its own recipe for zoni.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>また土地の特産物を入れるなど、地方によって特色がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Special local products unique to each region are used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Special local products unique to each region are used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Special local products unique to each region are used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>例えば千葉県東北部では、濃口醤油の澄まし汁仕立てで焼き角餅のお雑煮に「ハバノリのふりかけ」（鰹節も混ぜる場合があり）をかけて食べる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, in the north-eastern region of Chiba Prefecture, people eat zoni of baked square mochi and strong soy-sauce soup sprinkled with &apos;Babanori no furikake&apos; (dried and parched laver seaweed) (sometimes shaved bonito is mixed into it).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, in the north-eastern region of Chiba Prefecture, people eat zoni of baked square mochi and strong soy-sauce soup sprinkled with &apos;Babanori no furikake&apos; (dried and parched laver seaweed) (sometimes shaved bonito is mixed into it also).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, in the north-eastern region of Chiba Prefecture, people eat zoni made with baked square mochi and strong soy-sauce soup sprinkled with &apos;Habanori no furikake&apos; (dried and parched laver seaweed) (sometimes shaved bonito is mixed into it also).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>また愛知県名古屋周辺の特徴的なお雑煮では、餅とコマツナの一種である「もち菜」（正月菜とも呼ばれる）を入れて醤油の澄まし汁仕立てで鰹節をかけたものがあり、富山県ではそれに加えて魚や蒲鉾などを入れて食べるものがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zoni unique to Nagoya area in Aichi Prefecture contains mochi, a type of brassica rapa called &apos;mochina&apos; (also called &apos;shogatsuna&apos;) with a soy-sauce soup sprinkled with shaved bonito, and in Toyama Prefecture fish or boiled fish paste is added to that.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zoni unique to the Nagoya area in Aichi Prefecture contains mochi, a type of brassica rapa called &apos;mochina&apos; (also called &apos;shogatsuna&apos;) with a soy-sauce soup sprinkled with shaved bonito, and in Toyama Prefecture fish or boiled fish paste is also added.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zoni unique to the Nagoya area in Aichi Prefecture contains mochi, a type of brassica rapa called &apos;mochina&apos; (also called &apos;shogatsuna&apos;) with a soy-sauce soup sprinkled with shaved bonito, and in Toyama Prefecture fish or boiled fish paste is also added.</e>
<cmt>‘→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>島根県や鳥取県の一部では、一般に「汁粉」や「ぜんざい」と使われることが多いアズキに餅を入れたものを雑煮と呼ぶ場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In some areas of Shimane Prefecture and Tottori Prefecture, zoni is a soup with mochi and azuki beans which are usually used for making &apos;shiruko&apos; (sweet red-bean soup with pieces of mochi) or &apos;zenzai&apos; (baked mochi with red bean sauce).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In some areas of Shimane Prefecture and Tottori Prefecture, zoni is a soup with mochi and azuki beans which are usually used for making shiruko (sweet red-bean soup with pieces of mochi) or zenzai (baked mochi with red bean sauce).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In some areas of Shimane Prefecture and Tottori Prefecture, zoni is a soup with mochi and azuki beans which are usually used for making shiruko (sweet red-bean soup with pieces of mochi) or zenzai (baked mochi with red bean sauce).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="29">
<j>なお長崎県島原市の具雑煮のように、季節や風習にとらわれずに通年食べられる物もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Shimabara City of Nagasaki Prefecture, there is a dish called guzoni which is enjoyed throughout the year regardless of seasons or practices.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Shimabara City, Nagasaki Prefecture, there is a dish called guzoni which is enjoyed throughout the year regardless of the seasons or practices.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Shimabara City, Nagasaki Prefecture, there is a dish called guzoni which is enjoyed throughout the year regardless of the seasons or practices.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>また、一部の喫茶店や茶店では軽食メニューとして雑煮がある店もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, some coffee shops and tea parlors serve zoni as a light meal.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, some coffee shops and tea parlors serve zoni as a light meal.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, some coffee shops and tea parlors serve zoni as a light meal.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="31">
<j>気候的に米作に適さず、近代まで米食の習慣がなかった沖縄県には現在も雑煮を食べる風習はないが、同じ琉球王国に属する鹿児島県奄美地方においては比較的普及している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Okinawa Prefecture, where there had not been a practice of eating rice until the modern times because its climate is not suited for producing rice, there is still no custom to eat zoni today; while zoni is relatively popular in the Amami region of Kagoshima Prefecture, which used to belong to the same Ryukyu Kingdom as Okinawa did.</e>
<cmt>「琉球王国に属する」は事実誤認というよりもミスプリントと解し，「琉球王国に属していた」と修正して訳しました．</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Okinawa Prefecture, where the practice of eating rice had not begun until modern times due to its rice-hostile climate, there is still no custom to eat zoni today; while zoni is relatively popular in the Amami region of Kagoshima Prefecture, which used to belong to the same Ryukyu Kingdom as Okinawa.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Okinawa Prefecture, where the practice of eating rice had not begun until modern times as rice was not produced there due to the climate, there is still no custom of eating zoni today; while zoni is relatively popular in the Amami region of Kagoshima Prefecture, which used to belong to the same Ryukyu Kingdom as Okinawa.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。スペースを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>ダシの種類</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Types of soup stock</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Types of soup stock</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Types of soup stock</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="32">
<j>出汁については地域によって種類がいろいろある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The soup stock of zoni differs from region to region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The soup stock of zoni differs from region to region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The soup stock of zoni differs from region to region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>例えばコンブ、鰹節、カタクチイワシの煮干し（瀬戸内海沿岸など）、スルメ（岡山県県北地域など）などである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, kelp, shaved bonito, or boiled-dried anchovy is used in the Inland Sea coastal regions, and dried squid in the north area of Okayama Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, kelp, shaved bonito, or boiled-dried anchovy is used in the Inland Sea coastal regions, and dried squid in the north area of Okayama Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, kelp, shaved bonito, or boiled-dried anchovy is used in the Inland Sea coastal regions, and dried squid in the north area of Okayama Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>汁の種類</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Types of soup</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Types of soup</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Types of soup</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="34">
<j>雑煮の汁は地域によって色々なものがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are different varieties of zoni soups from region to region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are different varieties of zoni soups from region to region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are different varieties of zoni soups from region to region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>主として東日本及び九州は澄まし汁が多く、関西は白味噌仕立てが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Typically, sumashijiru (a clear soup) is common in Eastern Japan and in Kyushu; a white miso soup is popular in the Kansai region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Typically, sumashijiru (a clear soup) is common in Eastern Japan and in Kyushu; a white miso soup is popular in the Kansai region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A clear soup is common in Eastern Japan and in Kyushu while a white miso soup is popular in the Kansai region.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="36">
<j>お吸い物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Clear soup</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Clear soup</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Clear soup</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="37">
<j>食塩</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Salt</e>
<cmt>以下のリストの意味が不明ですが，単語だけですので，そのまま訳しました．</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Salt</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Salt</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="38">
<j>醤油</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soy sauce</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soy sauce</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soy sauce</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="39">
<j>醤油</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soy sauce</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soy sauce</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soy sauce</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="40">
<j>醤油</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soy sauce</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soy sauce</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soy sauce</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="41">
<j>味噌汁</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Miso soup</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Miso soup</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Miso soup</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="42">
<j>麦味噌</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mugi (barley) miso (bean paste)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mugi (barley) miso (bean paste)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mugi (barley) miso (bean paste)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="43">
<j>米味噌</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kome (rice) miso</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kome (rice) miso</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kome (rice) miso</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="44">
<j>白味噌</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">White miso</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">White miso</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">White miso</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="45">
<j>赤味噌</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Red miso</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Red miso</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Red miso</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="46">
<j>汁粉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shiruko (sweet red-bean soup with pieces of mochi)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shiruko (sweet red-bean soup with pieces of mochi)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shiruko (sweet red-bean soup with pieces of mochi)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>餅の種類</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Types of mochi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Types of mochi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Types of mochi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="47">
<j>雑煮に入れる餅の大きさや形は地域ごとに差異がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Each region has its own shapes and sizes of mochi for zoni.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Each region has its own shapes and sizes of mochi for zoni.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Each region has its own shapes and sizes of mochi for zoni.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>主として北海道を除く東日本では四角形の切り餅（角餅）、西日本では丸餅に大別される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Typically, squarely cut mochi (kakumochi) are used in Eastern Japan except for Hokkaido; round mochi are used in West Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Typically, squarely cut mochi (kakumochi) are used in Eastern Japan except for Hokkaido; round mochi are used in West Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Typically, squarely cut mochi (kakumochi) are used in Eastern Japan except for Hokkaido; round mochi are used in West Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>おおむね新潟・長野・岐阜・三重県以東は角餅で富山・石川・福井は混在、それより西は丸餅である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Roughly speaking, square mochi are used in prefectures of Niigata, Nagano, Gifu, Mie, and areas to the east of them; either square or round mochi are used in prefectures of Toyama, Ishikawa, and Fukui; and in the regions to the west of them are used round ones.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Roughly speaking, square mochi are used in prefectures of Niigata, Nagano, Gifu, Mie, and areas to the east of them. Either square or round mochi are used in the prefectures of Toyama, Ishikawa, and Fukui; and in the regions to the west of them round ones are used.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Roughly speaking, usually square mochi are used in the prefectures of Niigata, Nagano, Gifu, Mie, and areas to the east while either square or round mochi are used in the prefectures of Toyama, Ishikawa, and Fukui; and in the regions to the west round ones are used.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>北海道では丸餅と角餅が混在しているが、これは明治以降に移り住んだ人たちによって全国各地の雑煮が持ち込まれたためである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Hokkaido, some people eat round mochi and others square ones, because people who have immigrated into Hokkaido from all over the country brought various types of zoni there since the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Hokkaido, some people eat round mochi and others square ones, because people who have immigrated into Hokkaido from all over the country brought various types of zoni there since the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Hokkaido, some people eat round mochi and others eat square ones, because people migrated to Hokkaido from all over the country and brought various types of zoni there since the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>また糸魚川静岡構造線以東は焼き餅で、西は焼かずに入れるという傾向があるものの、個別の地域差が大きく、これだけで割り切れるものではないが、日本の東西の食習慣の違いを表わす例としてよく持ち出されるものでもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A slight regional tendency that mochi are baked before used in zoni in the areas to the east of the geotectonic line of Shizuoka-Itoigawa, and they are not baked in the areas to the west of the line is often mentioned to point out a difference in eating habit between the east and the west in Japan, but the difference is not so distinctive because regional variations also exist within each area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a slight regional tendency that mochi are baked before being used in zoni in the areas to the east of the geotectonic line of Shizuoka-Itoigawa. the fact that they are not baked in the areas to the west of the line is often mentioned to point out a difference in eating habits between the east and the west in Japan. However, the difference is not so distinctive, because regional variations also exist within each area.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a slight regional tendency that mochi are baked before being used in zoni in the areas to the east of the geotectonic line of Shizuoka-Itoigawa. the fact that they are not baked in the areas to the west of the line is often mentioned to point out a difference in eating habits between the east and the west in Japan, however, the difference is not so distinctive, because regional variations also exist within each area.</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="52">
<j>このほか、香川県や岡山県真鍋島のように、小豆の餡（あん、餡子）を入れた餡餅（あんもち）を入れる地域もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, mochi folding an (sweet red-bean paste), or anmochi, are used in some areas, such as Kagawa Prefecture or Manabe-shima island in Okayama Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, mochi folding an (sweet red-bean paste), or anmochi, are used in some areas, such as Kagawa Prefecture or Manabe-shima island in Okayama Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, mochi with sweet red-bean paste are used in some areas such as Kagawa Prefecture or Manabe-shima island in Okayama Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>雑煮に入れる餅は関東のように汁に入れる前に焼いて香ばしさを意図したものと、関西以西の生のまま汁に入れて煮るものとに細分される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Preparation of mochi for making zoni is divided into two types: in the Kanto region they are baked to enjoy an aroma of scorched surface before putting in a soup; in the Kansai region and to the west of Kansai they are put into a soup to simmer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Preparation of mochi for making zoni is divided into two types: in the Kanto region they are baked to enjoy the aroma of scorched surface before being placed in soup. In the Kansai region and to the west of Kansai they are put into a soup to simmer.</e>
<cmt>wording; run-on sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mochi for zoni is prepared in two ways: In the Kanto region they are baked to enjoy the smoky aroma before being placed in soup; in the Kansai region and to the west of Kansai they are put into a soup to simmer.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。1文にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>なお、近年は角餅を使うエリアが徐々に西へと広がっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The area of squared mochi are gradually expanding toward the west today.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The areas with squared mochi are gradually expanding toward the west today.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The areas with squared mochi are gradually expanding toward the west today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>これは食品流通の進歩で、大量生産の角餅が全国の小売店で扱われるようになった影響と考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is probably because mass-produced squared mochi have come to be sold at retailers all over the country thanks to the development of food distribution.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is probably because mass-produced squared mochi have come to be sold at retailers all over the country thanks to the development of food distribution.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is probably because mass-produced squared mochi have come to be sold at retailers all over the country thanks to the development of food distribution.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>また「餅を使わない雑煮」を作る地方もあり、里芋や豆腐が餅の代替となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In some areas, &apos;zoni without mochi&apos; contains taro or tofu (bean curd) instead.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In some areas, &apos;zoni without mochi&apos; contains taro or tofu (bean curd) instead.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In some areas, &apos;zoni without mochi&apos; contains taro or tofu (bean curd) instead.</e>
<cmt>‘→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>こうした雑煮は稲作の盛んでない山間部や島嶼部に残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These types of zoni are made in mountainous areas or in island areas where rice is rarely produced.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These types of zoni are made in mountainous areas or in island areas where rice is rarely produced.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These types of zoni are made in mountainous areas or in island areas where rice is rarely produced.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kdo84221(id:6188), Ligar(id:12623), BoB774(id:148281), Izayohi(id:13095), Hanabi123(id:10476), Zoominshiodome(id:149045), Ceridwen(id:36889), Nnh(id:474), マクガイア(id:33346), Kstigarbha(id:13376), Koba-chan(id:860), Roger(id:9883), Kotoito(id:21045), JINKY.ECLEO(id:141716), Tigers boy(id:15761), Yiuchan(id:28580), Greenland4(id:114494), Ygn kamiya(id:627), Borg(id:4390), Opponent(id:720), VolkovBot(id:105371), SuisuiBot(id:10165), Parayan(id:214526), RIK 2(id:12097), Shikai shaw(id:14306), FOMALHAUT(id:16135), 梅桃桜(id:35850), 竹麦魚(id:11012), FlaBot(id:30804), SieBot(id:126695), Hotei(id:7664), Ete(id:28565), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>