<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>鷹山</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takayama</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takayama</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takayama</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>鷹山（たかやま）は、かつて京都の祇園祭に有った山鉾の1つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Once having a parade in Gion Matsuri Festival in Kyoto, Takayama is a &quot;yamaboko,&quot; which is a festival float mounted with a decorative long-handled sword.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seen in a parade during the Gion Matsuri Festival in Kyoto, Takayama is one of a &quot;yamaboko,&quot; which is a festival float mounted with a decorative long-handled sword.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seen in a parade during the Gion Matsuri Festival in Kyoto, Takayama is one of a &quot;yamaboko,&quot; which is a festival float mounted with a decorative long-handled sword.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>現在の京都市中京区三条通室町西入ル衣棚町。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its location is in the present Koromonotana-cho, Sanjo-dori Muromachi Nishi-iru, Nakagyo Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>※「その所在地は」を文章の最初に補って訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This festival is held in present day Koromonotana-cho, Sanjo-dori Muromachi Nishi-iru, Nakagyo Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This festival is held in present day Koromonotana-cho, Sanjo-dori Muromachi Nishi-iru, Nakagyo Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>応仁の乱以前に起源を持ち、大舩鉾の直前を巡行した大規模な曳山だったが、文政9年（1826年）に激しい夕立に遭って懸装品に甚だしい汚損を被ってしまい、休山していたところに元治元年（1864年）の蛤御門の変による大火で御神体と一部の懸装品を残して焼失。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takayama originated before the Onin War, and it was a giant-float parading the streets of Kyoto right before &quot;Ofuneboko&quot; (a different yamaboko), but in 1826 the ornaments of Takayama got grossly stained with the raindrop of a hard shower, so the float stopped parading, and in 1864, the big fire breaking out in &quot;Hamagurigomon no Hen&quot; (the rebellion at the Hamaguri Gate) burned the float except for some ornaments &amp; &quot;Goshintai&quot; (the object of worship in Shinto).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takayama originated before the Onin War, and it was a giant-float parading the streets of Kyoto before &quot;Ofuneboko&quot; (a different yamaboko), but in 1826 the ornaments of Takayama become grossly stained from the raindrops of a hard shower, so parading the float stopped and in 1864, a big fire broke out at &quot;Hamagurigomon no Hen&quot; (the rebellion at the Hamaguri Gate) and burned the float except for some of it&apos;s ornaments &amp; &quot;Goshintai&quot; (object of worship in Shinto).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takayama originated before the Onin War, and it was a giant-float parading the streets of Kyoto before &quot;Ofuneboko&quot; (a different yamaboko), but in 1826 the ornaments of Takayama become grossly stained from the raindrops of a hard shower, so parading the float stopped and in 1864, a big fire broke out at &quot;Hamagurigomon no Hen&quot; (the rebellion at the Hamaguri Gate) and burned the float except for some of it&apos;s ornaments and &quot;Goshintai&quot; (object of worship in Shinto).</e>
<cmt>&amp;をandに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>現在は宵山に限って残された御神体と懸装品が同山の町内で展示（居祭・いまつり）されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At present, the Goshintai and ornaments that survived the fire are on display in Koromotana-cho just in &quot;Yoiyama&quot; (the pre-parade event), and the display is called &quot;Imatsuri.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At present, the Goshintai and ornaments that survived the fire are on display in Koromotana-cho just in &quot;Yoiyama&quot; (the pre-parade event), and the display is called &quot;Imatsuri.&quot;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At present, the Goshintai and ornaments that survived the fire are on display in Koromotana-cho just in &quot;Yoiyama&quot; (the pre-parade event), and the display is called &quot;Imatsuri.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Rusk(id:9895), Takax(id:20802), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>