<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>村米制度</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Muramai System</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Muramai System</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Muramai System</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>村米制度（むらまいせいど）は播磨地方の酒米産地と灘五郷をはじめ特定の蔵元との間で結ばれる、酒米取引制度（現酒造業者）のことを言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The muramai system refers to a sake rice dealing system which is contacted between sake rice production areas in Harima chiho (regions) and specific kuramoto (brewery owners) in Nada gogo (five districts in Nada) and other areas.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The muramai system refers to a sake rice dealing system which is concluded between sake rice production areas in Harima region and specific Kuramoto (sake brewer) including Nada gogo (five districts in Nada).</e>
<cmt>contact→conclude、in Nada→ including、brewer owners→sake brewerに修正、余分なスペース等を除きました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The muramai system refers to a sake rice dealing system which is concluded between sake rice production areas in Harima region and specific Kuramoto (sake brewer) including Nada gogo (five districts in Nada).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>1875年（明治7年）に地租改正により、農家が納める税金は米から金に変わり、農家では収量を重視するようになり、米の品質が落ちてきたが、一方で、酒の需要が増加し、蔵本では酒米を確保しようとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of the land-tax reform in 1875, the tax paid by farmers changed from rice to money, and farmers began to weigh harvest volume heavily to reduce quality while demand for sake increased to have sake brewers endeavor to secure rice for brewing sake.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of the land-tax reform in 1875, the tax paid by farmers changed from rice to money, and farmers began to make a point of the harvest volume to reduce the quality of rice while demand for sake increased to have Kuramoto endeavor to secure rice for brewing sake.</e>
<cmt>weigh～の部分を修正、上の文で蔵元の英語説明があるので単に「Kuramoto」としました。「米の」が訳抜け。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of the land-tax reform in 1875, the tax paid by farmers changed from rice to money, and farmers began to make a point of the harvest volume to reduce the quality of rice while demand for sake increased to have Kuramoto endeavor to secure rice for brewing sake.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>その結果、品質の良い酒米を求める蔵元と安定した販売先を求める農家の思いが一致し、この制度がはじまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result of this, the desire of the sake brewers for acquiring high-quality rice for brewing sake and that of the farmers for finding the buyers coincided to start this system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, Kuramoto acquiring high-quality rice for brewing sake and the farmers looking for the stable buyers coincided on those desires to start this system.</e>
<cmt>of this, for等を除き、Kuramoto、find→look forに修正、「安定した」が訳抜け。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, Kuramoto acquiring high-quality rice for brewing sake and the farmers looking for the stable buyers coincided on those desires to start this system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>しかし、発祥地は二説あり、明治26年に現在の三木市吉川町 (兵庫県)市野瀬の山田篤治朗が発起人となり、現在の西宮市にある蔵元の辰馬悦蔵と交渉し、取引を開始した説と、明治24年から翌明治25年頃に現在の加東市社町上久米集落の住民が現在の神戸市灘区の本嘉納商店と取引を開始した説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there are two theories for its birthplace; and according to one of them, in 1894 Atsujiro YAMADA, who resided at the place the present address of which is Ichinose, Yoshikawa-cho, Miki City, Hyogo Prefecture, as originator negotiated with Etsuzo TATSUMA who was a sake brewery owner presently located in Nishinomiya City and started dealing, and according to another theory, from 1891 to 1892 residents at Kamikume settlement, Yashiro-cho, Kato City started transactions with Honkano Shoten located presently in Nada Ward, Kobe City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there are two theories for its birthplace; one is that in 1894 Atsujiro YAMADA lived in the present Ichinose, Yoshikawa-cho, Miki City, Hyogo Prefecture, as the originator, negotiated with Etsuzo TATSUMA who was Kuramoto presently located in Nishinomiya City and started dealings, and another theory is that from 1891 to 1892 residents lived in Kamikume settlement, Yashiro-cho, Kato City started dealings with Honkano Shoten located presently in Nada Ward, Kobe City.</e>
<cmt>; and～、who resided～、蔵元、according to～、transactionの部分を修正、その他冠詞、複数(s)を補足。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there are two theories for its birthplace; one is that in 1894 Atsujiro YAMADA lived in the present Ichinose, Yoshikawa-cho, Miki City, Hyogo Prefecture, as the originator, negotiated with Etsuzo TATSUMA who was Kuramoto presently located in Nishinomiya City and started dealings, and another theory is that from 1891 to 1892 residents lived in Kamikume settlement, Yashiro-cho, Kato City started dealings with Honkano Shoten located presently in Nada Ward, Kobe City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>現在も三木市吉川町を中心に、村米制度が残っており、干ばつや水害、また、震災などの災害にも互いに助け合うなど、単に酒米の取引だけでなく、強いつながりが続いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even now there remains muramai systems centering around Yoshikawa-cho, Miki City and is serving as a strong connection not only to deal rice for brewing sake, but also to help each other in the occurrences of disasters such as droughts, floods, earthquakes, and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even now there remains the muramai systems centering around Yoshikawa-cho, Miki City and is serving as a strong connection not only to deal rice for brewing sake, but also to help each other in the occurrences of disasters such as droughts, floods, earthquakes, and so on.</e>
<cmt>the muramaiのtheを補足。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even now there remains the muramai systems centering around Yoshikawa-cho, Miki City and is serving as a strong connection not only to deal rice for brewing sake, but also to help each other in the occurrences of disasters such as droughts, floods, earthquakes, and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>発祥地</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Birthplace</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Birthplace</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Birthplace</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>兵庫県美嚢郡吉川町 (兵庫県)市野瀬（現三木市吉川町市野瀬）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ichinose, Yoshikawa-cho, Mino County, Hyogo Prefecture (presently Ichinose, Yoshikawa-cho, Miki City)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ichinose, Yoshikawa-cho, Mino County, Hyogo Prefecture (presently Ichinose, Yoshikawa-cho, Miki City)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ichinose, Yoshikawa-cho, Mino County, Hyogo Prefecture (presently Ichinose, Yoshikawa-cho, Miki City)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>兵庫県加東郡社町上久米（現加東市社町上久米）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kamikume, Yashiro-cho, Kato County, Hyogo Prefecture (presently Kamikume, Yashiro-cho, Kato City)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kamikume, Yashiro-cho, Kato County, Hyogo Prefecture (presently Kamikume, Yashiro-cho, Kato City)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kamikume, Yashiro-cho, Kato County, Hyogo Prefecture (presently Kamikume, Yashiro-cho, Kato City)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Fievarsty(id:201483), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>