<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>本膳料理</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Honzen ryori (Formally arranged meal)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Honzen ryori (Formally arranged meal)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Honzen Ryori (Formally arranged meal)</e>
<cmt>r大文字にしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>ここでは日本料理の中にある和食の一分野である本膳料理を紹介する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Here, we are introducing to you Honzen ryori (Formally arranged meal), which is one branch of the traditional Japanese food among all the Japanese-style cuisines.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">We will introduce Honzen ryori (Formally arranged meal), one type of traditional food among Japanese-style cuisines.</e>
<cmt>wordiness reduced</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">We will introduce Honzen ryori (formally arranged meal), one type of traditional food among Japanese-style cuisines.</e>
<cmt>F小文字にしました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>本膳料理（ほんぜんりょうり）とは、日本料理の正式な膳立て。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The so-called Honzen ryori (Formally arranged meal) is a formal arranged Japanese-style meal course.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Honzen ryori is a formal Japanese-style meal course.</e>
<cmt>redundancy, wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Honzen ryori is a formal Japanese-style meal course.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="3">
<j>「食事をとる」という行為自体に儀式的な意味合いを持たせているのが特徴。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The characteristic is that the behavior of &quot;having a meal&quot; itself has been given a ceremonious implication.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Enjoying a meal&quot; is a ceremonious occasion.</e>
<cmt>wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It gives &apos;meal&apos; a ceremonious purpose.</e>
<cmt>一般的な食事の分野ではないので注記すべきだと思います。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="4">
<j>室町時代に確立された武家の礼法から始まり江戸時代に発展した形式。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a form that started from the manners of samurai community established in Muromachi Period and developed in Edo Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It began with the manners of the samurai community established in the Muromachi Period and developed during the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It began with the manners of the samurai community established in the Muromachi period and developed during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>Period →periodに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="5">
<j>しかし明治時代以降ほとんど廃れてしまい、現在では冠婚葬祭などの儀礼的な料理にその面影が残されている程度である（婚礼の際の三々九度など）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, since Meiji Era, these manners had been out of fashion, and now, we can only see a trace of it during formal ceremonial occasions such as a coming-of-age ceremony, marriage ceremony or funeral. (For example, san-san-kudo, the manner for the bride and the groom to drink sake at a wedding ceremony)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the Meiji Era, these manners have been out of fashion, and we can only see a trace of them during formal ceremonial occasions such as a coming-of-age day, marriage, or funeral ceremonies. (For example, san-san-kudo, when the bride and the groom drink sake during a wedding ceremony)</e>
<cmt>wordiness reduced</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the Meiji period, these manners have been out of fashion, and we can only see a trace of them during formal ceremonial occasions such as a coming-of-age day, marriage, or funeral ceremonies (for example, san-san-kudo, when the bride and the groom drink sake during a wedding ceremony).</e>
<cmt>括弧書きの位置を修正。Meiji Era→Meiji periodに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>更に、肝心の料理店自体が用語の使い方を誤っている例がしばしば見られる（単なる婚礼や法事の会席料理や仕出し弁当に「本膳料理」という名前を付けている例がある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, examples where a restaurant uses the term improperly can often be seen. (There are examples of naming the delivery box lunches &quot;formal arranged meals&quot; for only a marriage or a Buddhist service.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, examples where a restaurant uses the term improperly can often be seen. (There are examples of naming the delivery box lunches &quot;formal arranged meals&quot; for only a marriage or a Buddhist service.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, examples where a restaurant uses the term improperly can often be seen (there are examples of naming the delivery box lunches &apos;formal arranged meals&apos; for only a marriage or a Buddhist service).</e>
<cmt>括弧書きの位置を修正。原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="7">
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>鎌倉時代、武家の間には「おう飯」（※「おう」は「土」偏に「完」）という正月に御家人から将軍に料理を献上する儀式があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Kamakura Era, there was among the samurai community a ceremony in which a samurai presented to his master shogun the dish &quot;Ohan&quot; in the New Year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Kamakura Era, there was a ceremony in which samurai presented the dish &quot;Ohan&quot; to his master shogun at the beginning of the New Year.</e>
<cmt>wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Kamakura period, there was a ceremony in which samurai presented the dish &apos;Ohan&apos; to his master shogun at the beginning of the New Year.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;にKamakura Era→Kamakura periodに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>当初は鯉一匹など簡単な物であったが、室町時代になり武家の経済的政治的優位が確立し、幕府政治の本拠地も公家文化の影響が深い京に移るに至って、料理の品数も増え、料理自体にも派手な工夫が凝らされるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At first, it was just a simple dish such as carp. However, entering Muromachi Period when Samurai&apos;s economical and political domination became established, the stronghold of the government by the shogunate came to move to the capital where the influence of the court noble cultures was deep too. Not only the number of dishes increased, but more effort and showy ideas were put into the dishes of foods.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At first, it was just a simple dish like carp. However, during the Muromachi Period when Samurai dominated the economy and politics, the shogunate moved to the capital where the cultural influence of the court nobles ran deep. Not only the number of dishes increased, but more eleaborate ideas were put into the meals.</e>
<cmt>wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At first, it was just a simple dish like carp, however, during the Muromachi period when Samurai dominated the economy and politics, the shogunate moved to the capital where the cultural influence of the court nobles ran deep; not only the number of dishes increased, but more eleaborate ideas were put into the meals.</e>
<cmt>一文一訳文にするため訂正しました。Period →periodに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>特に室町幕府の将軍を接待する「御成」が盛んになってからは次第に宴会料理の形式が整えられていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially, after becoming &quot;onari&quot; for receiving the shoguns of the Muromachi Shogunate, it gradually developed into a form of feast dishes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Especially, after becoming &quot;onari&quot; for receiving the Muromachi Shogunate, it gradually developed into a feast.</e>
<cmt>wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Especially, after becoming &apos;onari&apos; for receiving the Muromachi Shogunate, it gradually developed into a feast.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>ここに本膳料理が成立したと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered that honzen ryori (Formally arranged meal) was established at this time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It&apos;s thought that honzen ryori (Formally arranged meal) was established at this time.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It&apos;s thought that honzen ryori (formally arranged meal) was established at this time.</e>
<cmt>F小文字にしました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="12">
<j>形式</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Form</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Form</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Form</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>式三献、雑煮、本膳、二の膳、三の膳、硯蓋からなり、大規模な饗宴では七の膳まであったとの記録もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Literatures recorded that it may consist of 7 dishes of food; namely shikisankon (three trays of drink and food), zoni (vegetable soup containing rice cakes), honzen (the first tray), ninozen (the second tray), and sannozen (the third tray). The scale ranged from a mouthful container just like a suzuributa (a lid of an ink stone) to a large-scale banquet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Records show that it may consist of 7 dishes of food; namely shikisankon (three trays of drink and food), zoni (vegetable soup containing rice cakes), honzen (the first tray), ninozen (the second tray), and sannozen (the third tray). The scale ranged from a mouthful container just like a suzuributa (a lid of an ink stone) to a large-scale banquet.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Records show that it may consist of 7 dishes of food; namely shikisankon (three trays of drink and food), zoni (vegetable soup containing rice cakes), honzen (the first tray), ninozen (the second tray), and sannozen (the third tray), and the scale ranged from a mouthful container just like a suzuributa (a lid of an ink stone) to a large-scale banquet.</e>
<cmt>一文一訳文にするため訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>ただし、特徴的なのはこうした膳の多くが「見る」料理であり、実際に食べる事ができる料理は決して多くは無かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the characteristic is that such many of these dishes were for &quot;Seeing&quot;, those actually for eating were not that many.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, most of these dishes were for &quot;Show,&quot; those actually for eating were not that many.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, most of these dishes were for &apos;show,&apos; those in fact for eating were not that many.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;にSを小文字にしました。actually →in factに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>この本膳料理は少なからず儀礼的な物であり、この後に能や狂言などの演技が行われつつ、後段と呼ばれるうどんや素麺といった軽食類や酒肴が出されて、ここで本来の意味での酒宴になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This Honzen ryori (formally arranged meal) was just ceremonial thing. After this was the Noh play and the Noh farce. Then served was the light meal and sake such as udon (Japanese thick white noodles) and thin wheat noodles which was the real feast.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This Honzen ryori (formally arranged meal) was just ceremonial. After this was the Noh play and the Noh farce. Then a light meal and sake was served such as udon (Japanese thick white noodles) and thin wheat noodles which was the actual feast.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This Honzen ryori (formally arranged meal) was just ceremonial; after this was the Noh play and the Noh farce, then a light meal and sake was served such as udon (Japanese thick white noodles) and thin wheat noodles which was the actual feast.</e>
<cmt>一文一訳文にするため訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>なかには三日近く行われた宴もあったようだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Occasionally, some feasts lasted almost three days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Occasionally, some feasts lasted almost three days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Occasionally, some feasts lasted almost three days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="17">
<j>献立としては一汁三菜、一汁五菜、二汁五菜、二汁七菜、三汁五菜、三汁七菜、三汁十一菜などがあったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A menu might have one soup and three side dishes, one soup and five side dishes, two soups and five side dishes, two soups and seven side dishes, three soups and five side dishes, three soups and seven side dishes, or three soups and eleven side dishes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A menu might have one soup and three side dishes, one soup and five side dishes, two soups and five side dishes, two soups and seven side dishes, three soups and five side dishes, three soups and seven side dishes, or three soups and eleven side dishes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A menu might have one soup and three side dishes, one soup and five side dishes, two soups and five side dishes, two soups and seven side dishes, three soups and five side dishes, three soups and seven side dishes, or three soups and eleven side dishes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>もっとも基本的な形は、本膳には七菜（七種の料理）、二の膳には五菜（五種の料理）、三の膳には三菜（三種の料理）を配膳するものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The most basic form is a combination set trays such that, the honzen (the first tray) has seven dishes (seven kinds of foods), the ninozen (the second tray) has five dishes (five kinds of foods), and the sannozen (the third tray) has three dishes (three kinds of foods).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The most basic form is a combination set of trays; the honzen (the first tray) has seven dishes (seven kinds of food), the ninozen (the second tray) has five dishes (five kinds of food), and the sannozen (the third tray) has three dishes (three kinds of food).</e>
<cmt>wordiness, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The most basic form is a combination set of trays; the honzen (the first tray) has seven dishes (seven kinds of food), the ninozen (the second tray) has five dishes (five kinds of food), and the sannozen (the third tray) has three dishes (three kinds of food).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="19">
<j>本膳料理の「家元」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The head of a school for honzen ryori (formally arranged meal)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The head of a school for honzen ryori (formally arranged meal)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The head of a school for honzen ryori (formally arranged meal)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>室町時代の中期頃には、複雑になった本膳料理を専門に調理する料理流派が成立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During mid Muromachi Period, the becoming complicated honzen ryori (formally arranged meal) emerged out cuisine schools specializing in making it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During mid Muromachi Period, complicated honzen ryori (formally arranged meal) emerged from schools specializing in preparing cuisine.</e>
<cmt>wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During mid Muromachi period, complicated honzen ryori (formally arranged meal) emerged from schools specializing in preparing cuisine.</e>
<cmt>Period→periodに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>「大草流」「進士流」が有名で、『大草殿より相伝之聞書』など師匠から弟子へ一子相伝の料理の”秘法”を伝えていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;The Ogusa School&quot; and &quot; the Shinshi School&quot; were famous. Each &quot;Secret recipe&quot;, such as &quot;The record of what Mister Ogusa said&quot;), was inherited along, from one master to one student.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;The Ogusa School&quot; and &quot; the Shinshi School&quot; were famous. Each &quot;Secret recipe,&quot; such as &quot;The record of what Mister Ogusa said,&quot; was inherited from master to student.</e>
<cmt>wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&apos;The Ogusa school&apos; and &apos;the Shinshi school&apos; were famous, and each &quot;secret recipe,&quot; such as &quot;The record of what Ogusa-dono said,&quot; was inherited from master to student.</e>
<cmt>一文一訳文にするため訂正しました。原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;にスペース削除schoolに訂正しました。Ogusa-donoに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>一方、礼法家の立場からは、本膳料理の食事作法を定めるようになり、小笠原流の『食物服用之巻』などのハウツー本が生まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, from the standpoint of a manner specialist, it became that they wanted to fix the table manners for honzen ryori (formally arranged meal). Thus, the how-to book by the Ogasawara school called &quot;shokumotsufukuyo-no-maki (a book for taking meals)&quot; was published.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Manner specialist wanted to fix the table manners for honzen ryori (formally arranged meal). So, a how-to book by the Ogasawara school called &quot;shokumotsufukuyo-no-maki (a book for taking meals)&quot; was published.</e>
<cmt>wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Manner specialist wanted to fix the table manners for honzen ryori (formally arranged meal), so a how-to book by the Ogasawara school called &quot;Shokumotsufukuyo-no-maki&quot; (a book for taking meals) was published.</e>
<cmt>一文一訳文にするため訂正しました。“sを&quot;Sに訂正、&quot;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="23">
<j>「硯蓋」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">suzuributa (a lid of an ink stone)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">suzuributa (a lid of an ink stone)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Suzuributa (a lid of an ink stone)</e>
<cmt>sを大文字にしました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>硯蓋は、江戸時代に出現したもので、卓袱料理や砂糖の普及とも絡んでいると思われる特異な献立である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Suzuributa, appearing in Edo period, was a peculiar menu whose popularity seems to be associated with the spread of Shippoku cuisine (special Chinese cuisine in Nagasaki Prefecture, to which Japanese cooking methods were introduced) and sugar.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Suzuributa, appeared during the Edo period, and was a peculiar menu, its popularity associated with the spread of Shippoku cuisine (special Chinese cuisine in Nagasaki Prefecture, to which Japanese cooking methods were introduced) and sugar.</e>
<cmt>wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Suzuributa, appeared during the Edo period, and was a peculiar menu, its popularity associated with the spread of Shippoku cuisine (special Chinese cuisine in Nagasaki Prefecture, to which Japanese cooking methods were introduced) and sugar.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>当初は文字通り、硯の蓋に供されたともいわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the name suggests, it is said that it was at first put onto the lid of an ink stone.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the name suggests, it was first put on the lid of an ink stone.</e>
<cmt>wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the name suggests, it was first put on the lid of an ink stone.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>硯蓋に出される料理はきんとん、羊羹、寒天菓子等の甘味類（料理の一品として出されるため料理菓子とも呼ばれる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The dishes served to Suzuributa may be sweets such as kinton (mashed sweet potatoes), yokan (a bar of sweetened and jellied bean paste), kanten-gashi (agar-used confectionary). These are called confectionary cuisines because they are put out as a dish of cuisine. Or Suzuributa may be dishes of tsukudani (boiled foods in sweetened soy sauce) such as kamaboko (boiled fish paste), burdock, or little fish. These are foods ready for preservation. After all, the guests are used to take the Suzuributa home.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The dishes served to Suzuributa may be sweets such as kinton (mashed sweet potatoes), yokan (a bar of sweetened and jellied bean paste), kanten-gashi (agar-used confectionary). These are called confectionary cuisines. Or Suzuributa may be dishes of tsukudani (boiled foods in sweetened soy sauce) such as kamaboko (boiled fish paste), burdock, or little fish. These are foods ready for preservation, as the guests were used to taking the Suzuributa home.</e>
<cmt>wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The dishes served to Suzuributa may be sweets such as kinton (mashed sweet potatoes), yokan (a bar of sweetened and jellied bean paste), kanten-gashi (agar-used confectionary); these are called confectionary cuisines.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理一文一訳文にするため訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>あるいは蒲鉾、牛蒡や小魚の佃煮といった保存の効く食物が多く、これらは賓客が持ち帰る慣わしであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Or Suzuributa may be dishes of tsukudani (boiled foods in sweetened soy sauce) such as kamaboko (boiled fish paste), burdock, or little fish; these are foods ready for preservation, as the guests were used to taking the Suzuributa home.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理一文一訳文にするため訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>ちなみに、御節料理としてお馴染みの伊達巻も硯蓋でよく出された料理といわれ、長崎では食感や製法の類似性から「カステラかまぼこ」とも呼ばれており、この三つの関連性は高いと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By the way, datemaki (a rolled omelet mixed with fish paste), which is a familiar osechi food (special food for New Years in Japan), is often put out as the Suzuributa. Since the texture and the manufacturing method is very like that in Nagasaki, it is called &quot;Sponge cake boiled fish paste&quot;. It seems that the relationship among these three is high.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Datemaki (a rolled omelet mixed with fish paste), a familiar osechi food (special food for New Years in Japan), is often put out as Suzuributa. Since the texture and the manufacturing method is very similar to that in Nagasaki, it is called &quot;Sponge cake boiled fish paste.&quot; It seems that the relationship among these three is high.</e>
<cmt>wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Datemaki (a rolled omelet mixed with fish paste), a familiar osechi food (special food for New Years in Japan), is often put out as Suzuributa, since the texture and the manufacturing method is very similar to that in Nagasaki, which is called &apos;sponge cake boiled fish paste&apos; and it seems that the relationship among these three is high.</e>
<cmt>一文一訳文にするため訂正しました。原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="29">
<j>懐石における八寸に似ているが、八寸がその場で食べて（これを食い切りという）、料理も酒肴に近い物が供されるが、硯蓋は前記のように菓子類や保存性の高い食品が盛られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though it looks like hassun (a tray of about 24 cm square for serving several dishes) in kaisei-ryori (a light meal served before a ceremonial tea), hassun is eaten in situ (this is called &quot;kuikiri (eating up)&quot;). The dishes of cuisines supplied are also good for being taken with sake. However, as mentioned previously, Suzuributa are confectioneries or foods readily for preservation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though it looks like hassun (a tray of about 24 cm square for serving several dishes) in kaisei-ryori (a light meal served before a ceremonial tea), hassun is eaten in situ (this is called &quot;kuikiri (eating up)&quot;). The dishes supplied are also good with sake. However, as mentioned previously, Suzuributa are confectioneries or food ready for preservation.</e>
<cmt>wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it looks like hassun (a tray of about 24cm square for serving several dishes) in kaisei-ryori (a light meal served before a ceremonial tea), hassun is eaten in situ (this is called &quot;kuikiri (eating up)&quot;), also the dishes supplied are good with sake, however, as mentioned previously, Suzuributa are confectioneries or food ready for preservation.</e>
<cmt>一文一訳文にするため訂正しました。スペース削除“→&quot;Though →Althoughに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>関西では硯蓋の料理を口取りといい、内容は似ているがその場で食べる慣わしであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kansai area, a Suzuributa is called kuchidori (a mouthful dish of assorted delicacies). The contents are similar but the custom is to eat in situ there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Kansai, Suzuributa is called kuchidori (a mouthful dish of assorted delicacies). The contents are similar, but the custom is to eat in situ there.</e>
<cmt>wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Kansai, Suzuributa is called kuchidori (a mouthful dish of assorted delicacies); the contents are similar, but the custom is to eat in situ there.</e>
<cmt>一文一訳文にするため訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>現在はコストや慣習の問題から廃れている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Now, the problems of cost and customs are out of fashion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Now, cost and customs are out of fashion.</e>
<cmt>wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Now, cost and customs are out of fashion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 藤崎景子＠コナ研(id:89741), Nighthawks(id:36125), こぶまき(id:38278), ＲＪＡＮＫＡ(id:118019), Yas(id:739), トホホ川(id:50502), Corwin(id:973), 555accele(id:85185), 梅の里(id:15035), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>