<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>ほめことば</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Homekotoba (words of praise)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Homekotoba (words of praise)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Homekotoba (words of praise)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>ほめことばは、歌舞伎で、役者をほめたたえるために発し、投げかけられることばである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Homekotoba&quot; means words of parise to be uttered or shooted to applaud playactors of Kabuki play on stage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Homekotoba refers to words of praise to be uttered or shouted to applaud playactors of Kabuki play on stage.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Homekotoba refers to words of praise to be uttered or shouted to applaud playactors of Kabuki play on stage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>コロンを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>舞台上のある役者が、あらたに登場してくる役者をほめる場合と、舞台上で演技中の役者に観客席の観客が投げかける場合とがあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were two cases where homekotoba were used; one case being for a player on stage to make a compliment to a newly appearing player, and another case being for some audience to shoot applause to a player on stage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were two cases where homekotoba were used; one case being for a player on stage to make a compliment to a newly appearing player, and another case being for some audience to shout applause to a player on stage.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were two cases where homekotoba were used; one case being for a player on stage to make a compliment to a newly appearing player, and another case being for some audience to shout applause to a player on stage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>前者は、天和 (日本)以前から、あるいは元禄ころから、作者は脚本の一部に「ほめことば」を挿入し、役者の口から、共演役者の容貌的な魅力をほめさせたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the first case, a script writer put &quot;homekotoba&quot; as a part of script from the beginning and let a player speak them to praise the costar for his attractive visage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the first case, script writers began to put &apos;homekotoba&apos; as a part of script and let a player speak them to praise the costar for his attractive visage, from before the Tenna era (1681-1683) or around Genroku era (1688-1703).</e>
<cmt>翻訳を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the first case, script writers began to put &apos;homekotoba&apos; as a part of script and let a player speak them to praise the costar for his attractive visage, from before the Tenna era (1681-1683) or around Genroku era (1688-1703).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>「続耳塵集」にある、若立役の出端を女形がほめる言葉を引けば、次のようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Quoting from &quot;Zoku-Jijinshu&quot;(a sequel of collection of commentary discourses), an actor of female roles praises the first appearance of a young leading player as follows:</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Quoting from &apos;Zoku-Jijinshu&apos; (a sequel of collection of commentary discourses), an actor of female roles praises the first appearance of a young leading player as follows:</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Quoting from &apos;Zoku-Jijinshu&apos; (a sequel of collection of commentary discourses), an actor of female roles praises the first appearance of a young leading player as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>「ようよう立艶姿に伊達風流股立袴すそ高くたつたの川にあらねとも紅葉の顔に薄化粧浅黄羽織の紐きやしやに結ひとめたる恋の括り目は在原の業平もあんまりよそには御座んすまいやりたい金やりたい小指かはるなかはらし二世までとかはす枕ににくまれて浮世も後生も後の日も思ひの淵に身は沈むさてもさても見事な御器量てあるわいな」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oh! Oh! How amorous his standing pose is, with his skirts kilted high in an elegant men&apos;s style, with his lightly made-up face having autumnal tint like crimson foliage, and with delicately tied braids of his drape of pale yellow, who must not be far from ARIWARA no Narihira, a typical man of handsome feature, alluring his fans to spend money and to lock their pinky fingers to his, while he desires no change forever untill next generation, staying together in bed, playing a bad guy for pillows, sinking himself on the verge of thinking in this and another worlds in future days.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oh! Oh! How amorous his standing pose is, with his skirts kilted high in an elegant men&apos;s style, with his lightly made-up face having autumnal tint like crimson foliage, and with delicately tied braids of his drape of pale yellow, who must not be far from ARIWARA no Narihira, a typical man of handsome feature, alluring his fans to spend money and to lock their pinky fingers to his, while he desires no change forever until next generation, staying together in bed, playing a bad guy for pillows, sinking himself on the verge of thinking in this and another worlds in future days.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oh! Oh! How amorous his standing pose is, with his skirts kilted high in an elegant men&apos;s style, with his lightly made-up face having autumnal tint like crimson foliage, and with delicately tied braids of his drape of pale yellow, who must not be far from ARIWARA no Narihira, a typical man of handsome feature, alluring his fans to spend money and to lock their pinky fingers to his, while he desires no change forever until next generation, staying together in bed, playing a bad guy for pillows, sinking himself on the verge of thinking in this and another worlds in future days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>縁語、掛詞などをふんだんに自由自在に用い、美文的なものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As above, &quot;homekotoba&quot; were usually written in an ornate style, including a lot of &quot;engo&quot; (two words related in meaning), &quot;kakekotoba&quot; (pivot words) and the like at will.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As above, homekotoba were usually written in an ornate style, including a lot of engo (two words related in meaning), kakekotoba (pivot words) and the like at will.</e>
<cmt>ダブルクォーテーションを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As above, homekotoba were usually written in an ornate style, including a lot of engo (two words related in meaning), kakekotoba (pivot words) and the like at will.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>後者の場合は、1人または複数の決められた観客が花道上に上がり、ひいきの役者に対して賛辞的なつらねを発した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the latter case, one or more fixed spectators ascended onto hanamichi (an elevated runway through audience leading to stage) and uttered complimentary speech of &quot;tsurane&quot; (a long declamatory speech) toward their favorite player.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the latter case, one or more fixed spectators ascended onto hanamichi (an elevated runway through audience leading to stage) and uttered complimentary speech of tsurane (a long declamatory speech) toward their favorite player.</e>
<cmt>ダブルクォーテーションを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the latter case, one or more fixed spectators ascended onto hanamichi (an elevated runway through audience leading to stage) and uttered complimentary speech of tsurane (a long declamatory speech) toward their favorite player.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>江戸に起こり、のち上方でも行われるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This custom arose in Edo and was later introduced to Kamigata (Kyoto-Osaka area).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This custom arose in Edo and was later introduced to Kamigata (Kyoto-Osaka area).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This custom arose in Edo and was later introduced to Kamigata (Kyoto-Osaka area).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>劇場においては明治29年、市川團十郎 (9代目)が歌舞伎座で助六を演じた時、吉原の幇間によっておこなわれたのが最後であろうという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The last performance of &quot;homekotoba&quot; in theater was supposedly made by hokan (professional entertainers) of Yoshiwara in 1896 when Danjuro ICHIKAWA (the nineth head) played a role of Sukeroku at Kabuki theater.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The last performance of homekotoba in theater was supposedly made by hokan (a professional male entertainers) of Yoshiwara in 1896 when Danjuro ICHIKAWA (the ninth head) played a role of Sukeroku at Kabuki-za theater.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The last performance of homekotoba in theater was supposedly made by hokan (a professional male entertainers) of Yoshiwara in 1896 when Danjuro ICHIKAWA (the ninth head) played a role of Sukeroku at Kabuki-za theater.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="11">
<j>正本として刊行されたものもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some of them were written and published in authentic texts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some of them were written and published in authentic texts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some of them were written and published in authentic texts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>この成功者の代表は近松門左衛門であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Monzaemon CHIKAMATSU was a representative of successful writers of those texts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Monzaemon CHIKAMATSU was a representative of successful writers of those texts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Monzaemon CHIKAMATSU was a representative of successful writers of those texts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="13">
<j>歌舞伎が「古典芸能」扱いされるようになると、舞台と観客席との間のこのような遊戯的即興的な交流はおこなわれなくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Kabuki became classified in the category of &quot;classical art of theater,&quot; no more improvising playgame-like communications between the stage and audience was performed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Kabuki became classified in the category of &apos;classical art of theater,&apos; no more improvising playgame-like communications between the stage and audience was performed.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Kabuki became classified in the category of &apos;classical art of theater,&apos; no more improvising playgame-like communications between the stage and audience was performed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>