<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>赤れんがフェスタ (舞鶴)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akarenga-Festa (Red Brick Festival) (Maizuru City)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akarenga-Festa (Red Brick Festival) (Maizuru City)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akarenga-Festa (Red Brick Festival) (Maizuru City)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>赤れんがフェスタとは毎年、京都府舞鶴市で行われる観光イベント。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Red Brick Festival is a sightseeing event held in Maizuru City of Kyoto Prefecture every year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Red Brick Festival is a sightseeing event held in Maizuru City of Kyoto Prefecture every year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Akarenga-Festa&quot; (the Red Brick Festival) is a sightseeing event held in Maizuru City of Kyoto Prefecture every year.</e>
<cmt>用語部分補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>毎年10月の第2土曜・日曜に行われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is held on the second Saturday and Sunday of October every year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is held on the second Saturday and Sunday of October every year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is held on the second Saturday and Sunday of October every year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>軍港の街として発展した舞鶴市が、旧日本海軍が利用していた舞鶴赤レンガ倉庫群を活用したイベントで、舞鶴が発祥といわれる肉じゃがや海軍料理などのグルメコーナーや日本海でとれた魚介類などの物産展。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Maizuru City developed as a town of naval port. This festival is an event that uses the Maizuru Aka-renga Soko-gun (red-brick warehouses of Maizuru) that the Imperial Japanese Navy was using, The gourmet corner displays Nikujaga (simmered meat and potatoes) and naval dishes. The local product exhibition introduces seafood taken in the Japan Sea and other local production. There are also exhibitions of art that uses bricks, and Kyu-gunko yonshi Kindaika Isan Shashin-ten (photographic exhibition of the site of modernization of four cities of former military ports).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Maizuru City developed as a naval port town. This festival is an event that uses the Maizuru Aka-renga Soko-gun (red-brick warehouses of Maizuru) that the Imperial Japanese Navy was using, The gourmet corner displays Nikujaga (simmered meat and potatoes) and naval dishes. The local product exhibition introduces seafood taken from the Japan Sea and other local production. There are also exhibitions of art that uses bricks, and Kyu-gunko yonshi Kindaika Isan Shashin-ten (photographic exhibition of the site of modernization of four cities of former military ports).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Maizuru City developed as a naval port town and this festival is an event that uses the Maizuru Aka-renga Soko-gun (red-brick warehouses of Maizuru) that the Imperial Japanese Navy was using: the gourmet corner displays Nikujaga (simmered meat and potatoes) and naval dishes; the local product exhibition introduces seafood taken from the Japan Sea and other local production.</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。一原文一訳文の例外処理。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>レンガを用いたアート展示会、旧軍港4市近代化遺産写真展などが行われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are also exhibitions of art that uses bricks, and Kyu-gunko yonshi Kindaika Isan Shashin-ten (photographic exhibition of the site of modernization of four cities of former military ports).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>舞鶴は戦前の煉瓦建築物が日本で最も多数現存している街で、その一部倉庫群は夜間ライトアップされるため、幻想的でロマンチックな光景を観ることができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Maizuru is the town with the most brick buildings of prewar days remaining in Japan. Because some of the warehouses are lighted up at nighttime, it creates a fantastic, romantic spectacle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Maizuru is the town with the most brick buildings of prewar days remaining in Japan. Because some of the warehouses are lit up at night, it creates a fantastic, romantic spectacle.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Maizuru is the town with the most brick buildings of prewar days remaining in Japan, some of the warehouses are lit up at night, it creates a fantastic, romantic spectacle.</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="6">
<j>アクセス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Access</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Access</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Access</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>鉄道</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">railway</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">railway</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Railway</e>
<cmt>Rを大文字にしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>西日本旅客鉄道 舞鶴線 東舞鶴駅から徒歩約15分。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It takes about 15 minutes on foot from Higashi-Maizuru Station of Maizuru Line, West Japan Railway Company (JR West).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It takes about 15 minutes on foot from Higashi-Maizuru Station of Maizuru Line, West Japan Railway Company (JR West).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It takes about 15 minutes on foot from Higashi-Maizuru Station of Maizuru Line, West Japan Railway Company (JR West).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>バス (交通機関)・タクシーなら約5分。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It takes about five minuites by bus or taxi.</e>
<cmt>訳を追加しました。交通機関は必要がないと考え、訳出しておりません。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>京都駅から特別急行列車「まいづる (列車)」「タンゴディスカバリー」で約1時間30分で東舞鶴駅着。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From Kyoto Station, there are special express trains &quot;Maizuru&quot; and &quot;Tango Disukabari (Tango Discovery)&quot; that arrives at Higashi-Maizuru Station in about one hour and 30 minutes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From Kyoto Station, there are special express trains &quot;Maizuru&quot; and &quot;Tango Disukabari (Tango Discovery)&quot; that arrives at Higashi-Maizuru Station in about one hour and 30 minutes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From Kyoto Station, there are special express trains &apos;Maizuru&apos; and &apos;Tango Discovery&apos; that arrives at Higashi-Maizuru Station in about one hour and 30 minutes.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。&apos;Tango Discovery&apos;の読みは不要と考え削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>金沢駅から特急「サンダーバード (列車)」で敦賀駅乗換え、小浜線に乗り、約2時間で東舞鶴駅着。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From Kanazawa Station, one may take the Limited Express train &quot;Thunder Bird&quot;, transfer at Tsuruga Station to Obama Line, and arrive Higashi-Maizuru Station in about two hours.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From Kanazawa Station, one may take the Limited Express train &quot;Thunder Bird,&quot; transfer at Tsuruga Station to Obama Line, and arrive Higashi-Maizuru Station in about two hours.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From Kanazawa Station, one may take the Limited Express train &apos;Thunder Bird,&apos; transfer at Tsuruga Station to Obama Line, and arrive Higashi-Maizuru Station in about two hours.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>道路</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Road</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Road</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Road</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>舞鶴若狭自動車道 舞鶴東インターチェンジから車で約15分。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Using Maizuru Wakasa Highway from Maizuru-higashi Interchange, it takes about 15 minutes by car.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Using Maizuru Wakasa Highway from Maizuru-higashi Interchange, it takes about 15 minutes by car.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Using Maizuru Wakasa Highway from Maizuru-higashi Interchange, it takes about 15 minutes by car.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>主催・後援</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sponsoring and backup</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sponsoring and backup</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sponsoring and backup</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="12">
<j>主催 - 舞鶴市、舞鶴市教育委員会、赤れんがフェスタ実行委員会</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sponsoring-Maizuru City, Maizuru City Board of Education, and Akarenga festa jikko-iinkai (Red Brick Festival Execution Committee)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sponsoring-Maizuru City, Maizuru City Board of Education, and Akarenga festa jikko-iinkai (Red Brick Festival Execution Committee)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sponsoring - Maizuru City, Maizuru City Board of Education, and Akarenga-festa jikko-iinkai (Red Brick Festival Execution Committee)</e>
<cmt>改行削除。スペース補足。表記統一のため、Akarenga-festaとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>後援 - 朝日新聞舞鶴支局、京都新聞、産経新聞舞鶴支局、毎日新聞舞鶴支局、読売新聞大阪本社、日本放送協会京都放送局、京都放送、エフエム京都</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Backup: Maizuru branch of the Asahi Shinbun Company, the Kyoto Shinbun, Maizuru branch of the Sankei Shinbun, Maizuru branch office of the Mainichi Shinbun, Osaka Headquarters of the Yomiuri Shinbun, Kyoto broadcast station of Japan Broadcasting Corporation, Kyoto Broadcasting System Company Limited, and FM Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Backup: Maizuru branch of the Asahi Shinbun Company, the Kyoto Shinbun, Maizuru branch of the Sankei Shinbun, Maizuru branch office of the Mainichi Shinbun, Osaka Headquarters of the Yomiuri Shinbun, Kyoto broadcast station of Japan Broadcasting Corporation, Kyoto Broadcasting System Company Limited, and FM Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Backup - Maizuru branch of the Asahi Shinbun Company, the Kyoto Shinbun, Maizuru branch of the Sankei Shinbun, Maizuru branch office of the Mainichi Shinbun, Osaka Headquarters of the Yomiuri Shinbun, Kyoto broadcast station of Japan Broadcasting Corporation, Kyoto Broadcasting System Company Limited, and FM Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>表記統一のため、:を-に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>周辺の名所・文化施設</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Famous spots and cultural facilities in the surroundings</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Famous spots and cultural facilities in local surroundings</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Famous spots and cultural facilities in local surroundings</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="14">
<j>赤れんが博物館</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akarenga Hakubutsukan (Red-brick Museum)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akarenga Hakubutsukan (Red-brick Museum)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akarenga Hakubutsukan (Red-brick Museum)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="15">
<j>舞鶴引揚記念館</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Maizuru Hikiage Kinenkan (Maizuru Repatriation Memorial Museum)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Maizuru Hikiage Kinenkan (Maizuru Repatriation Memorial Museum)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Maizuru Hikiage Kinenkan (Maizuru Repatriation Memorial Museum)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="16">
<j>舞鶴市政記念館（12棟の舞鶴赤レンガ倉庫群）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Maizuru Shisei Kinenkan (Maizuru Municipal Government Memorial Hall) (12 buildings of Maizuru red brick warehouses)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Maizuru Shisei Kinenkan (Maizuru Municipal Government Memorial Hall) (12 buildings of Maizuru red brick warehouses)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Maizuru Shisei Kinenkan (Maizuru Municipal Government Memorial Hall) (12 buildings of Maizuru red brick warehouses)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 663highland(id:18755), Fuji-77(id:22233), ぱむ(id:24323), 893(id:9349), Suisui(id:69), Sea of Japan(id:3230), Bankokuya(id:91191), Hatsune(id:26654), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>