<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>麩</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fu (gluten cakes)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fu (gluten cakes)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fu</e>
<cmt>タイトルのため、括弧内の補足を削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>麩（ふ）は、グルテンを主原料とした加工食品。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wheat gluten cakes are processed food made with wheat gluten being the main ingredient.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wheat gluten cakes are a processed food made with wheat gluten being the main ingredient.</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Fu&quot; refers to a processed food made with wheat gluten being the main ingredient.</e>
<cmt>日本語の「Fu」から文章を始めました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>グルテンは、水で練った小麦粉に含まれるたんぱく質のひとつである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gluten is a type of protein contained in the water and wheat flour mixture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gluten is a type of protein contained in the water and wheat flour mixture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gluten is a type of protein contained in the water and wheat flour mixture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>モチモチした食感をもつ生麩（なまふ）と、サクサクカリカリした食感の焼き麩（やきふ）、中華料理などで使われる揚げ麩（あげふ）がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wheat gluten cakes are available in various forms including the chewy nama-fu (fresh gluten cakes), the crisp yaki-fu (toasted gluten cakes) and age-fu (deep-fat fried gluten cakes) used in Chinese cooking.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wheat gluten cakes are available in various forms including the chewy nama-fu (fresh gluten cakes), the crisp yaki-fu (toasted gluten cakes) and age-fu (deep-fat fried gluten cakes) used in Chinese cooking.</e>
<cmt>spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fu are available in various forms including the chewy nama-fu (fresh gluten cakes), the crisp yaki-fu (toasted gluten cakes) and age-fu (deep-fat fried gluten cakes) used in Chinese cooking.</e>
<cmt>wheat gluten cakes→ fu としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>煮物や汁物に用いられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are used in simmered dishes and soups.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are used in simmered dishes and soups.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are used in simmered dishes and soups.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>すき焼きなどの鍋物の具や、沖縄料理の炒め物の材料としても多く用いられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gluten cakes are often used in various nabemono (stew, food cooked in a pot) such as sukiyaki and also in fried dishes in Okinawa cuisine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gluten cakes are often used in various nabemono (stew, food cooked in a pot) such as sukiyaki and also in fried dishes in Okinawa cuisine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are often used in various nabemono (stew, food cooked in a pot) such as sukiyaki and also in fried dishes in Okinawa cuisine.</e>
<cmt>Gluten cakes →they 　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>日本での主要産地は以下のとおり</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The major production centers of gluten cakes in Japan are as follows:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The major production centers of gluten cakes in Japan are as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The major production centers of fu in Japan are as follows:</e>
<cmt>gluten cakes→ fu としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>生麩や飾り麩は京都市や金沢市</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fresh gluten cakes and kazari-fu (decorative gluten cakes) are produced in Kyoto City and Kanazawa City</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fresh gluten cakes and kazari-fu (decorative gluten cakes) are produced in Kyoto City and Kanazawa City</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nama-fu and kazari-fu (decorative gluten cakes) are produced in Kyoto City and Kanazawa City.</e>
<cmt>fresh gluten cakes →　nama-fu としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>焼き麩は新潟県村上市の岩船地区、山形県、沖縄県など</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yaki-fu (toasted gluten cakes) is produced in various regions including the Iwafune district of Murakami City, Niigata Prefecture, Yamagata Prefecture and Okinawa Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yaki-fu (toasted gluten cakes) is produced in various regions including the Iwafune district of Murakami City, Niigata Prefecture, Yamagata Prefecture and Okinawa Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yaki-fu is produced in various regions including the Iwafune district of Murakami City, Niigata Prefecture, Yamagata Prefecture and Okinawa Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>焼き麩　補足を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>揚げ麩は宮城県</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Age-fu (deep-fat fried gluten cakes) is made in Miyagi Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Age-fu (deep-fat fried gluten cakes) is made in Miyagi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Age-fu is made in Miyagi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>揚げ麩　補足を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>中華人民共和国では、江蘇省無錫は揚げ麩の産地として知られており、上海料理の煮物によく用いられいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the People&apos;s Republic of China, Wuxi City, Jiangsu Province is known as a production center of deep-fat fried gluten cakes that are often used in simmered dishes of Shanghai cuisine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the People&apos;s Republic of China, Wuxi City, Jiangsu Province, is known as a production center of deep-fat fried gluten cakes that are often used in simmered dishes of Shanghai cuisine.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the People&apos;s Republic of China, Wuxi City, Jiangsu Province, is known as a production center of age-fu that are often used in simmered dishes of Shanghai cuisine.</e>
<cmt>deep-fat fried gluten cakes→ age-fu としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>また、麩の中に豚の挽肉などを詰めた、「麺筋塞肉」などの加工品もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, there are some processed gluten cake products such as Mian Jin Sai Rou which is gluten cakes with stuffing made of ground pork and other ingredients.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, there are some processed gluten cake products such as Mian Jin Sai Rou which is gluten cakes with stuffing made of ground pork and other ingredients.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, there are some processed gluten cake products such as &apos;Mian Jin Sai Rou&apos; which is gluten cakes with stuffing made of ground pork and other ingredients.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>精進料理（日本・中国）、もしくは欧米では健康または宗教上の理由で肉類を食べない菜食主義者向けの、肉を模した代用食品の原料として麩が使われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gluten cakes are also used in the Buddhist cuisine (in both Japan and China) and as ingredients for meat-substitute products for vegetarians in North America and Europe who do not eat meat for the health or religious reasons.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gluten cakes are also used in the Buddhist cuisine (in both Japan and China) and as ingredients for meat-substitute products for vegetarians in North America and Europe who do not eat meat for health or religious reasons.</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fu are also used in the Buddhist cuisine (in both Japan and China) and as ingredients for meat-substitute products for vegetarians in North America and Europe who do not eat meat for health or religious reasons.</e>
<cmt>gluten cakes→ fu としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>感謝祭で供される七面鳥の代用品としてトーファーキーがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tofurkey is available as a substitute for turkeys that are commonly served for Thanksgiving dinner.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tofurkey is available as a substitute for turkeys that are commonly served for Thanksgiving dinner.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tofurkey is available as a substitute for turkeys that are commonly served for Thanksgiving dinner.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="14">
<j>生麩や焼き麩は、料理以外に、菓子として用いられる事がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fresh gluten cakes and toasted gluten cakes are sometimes used to make confectioneries in addition to being used in cooking.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fresh gluten cakes and toasted gluten cakes are sometimes used to make confectioneries in addition to being used in cooking.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nama-fu and yaki-fu are sometimes used to make confectioneries in addition to being used in cooking.</e>
<cmt>mana-fu, yaki-fu としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>生麩は小豆餡を包んで麩饅頭、焼き麩は生地に着色して砂糖を練りこみ、麩菓子などの駄菓子とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They fill fresh gluten cakes with red bean jam to make fu-manju pastries while they add food colorings and sugar to the dough of toasted gluten cakes to make confectioneries such as fugashi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They fill fresh gluten cakes with red bean jam to make fu-manju pastries while they add food colorings and sugar to the dough of toasted gluten cakes to make confectioneries such as fugashi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They fill nama-fu with red bean jam to make fu-manju pastries while they add food colorings and sugar to the dough of yaki-fu to make confectioneries such as fugashi.</e>
<cmt>mana-fu, yaki-fu としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>黒糖で花林糖のような風味をもたせた麩かりんとうもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is fu karinto sweetened with black sugar to simulate the taste of karinto (dough cut into sticks, deep-fat fried and sweetened).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is fu karinto sweetened with black sugar to simulate the taste of karinto (dough cut into sticks, deep-fat fried and sweetened).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is fu karinto sweetened with black sugar to simulate the taste of karinto (dough cut into sticks, deep-fat fried and sweetened).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>作り方</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Recipe</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Recipe</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Recipe</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="17">
<j>小麦粉に食塩水を加えてよく練って生地を作る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Add brine to flour and knead the mixture to make dough.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Add brine to flour and knead the mixture to make dough.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Add brine to flour and knead the mixture to make dough.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>粘りが出たところで生地を布製の袋に入れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the dough becomes sticky, transfer it in a cloth bag.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the dough becomes sticky, transfer it to a cloth bag.</e>
<cmt>prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the dough becomes sticky, transfer it to a cloth bag.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>生地を水中で更に揉む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Submerge the cloth bag in water and continue kneading the dough.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Submerge the cloth bag in water and continue kneading the dough.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Submerge the cloth bag in water and continue kneading the dough.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="20">
<j>デンプンが流出した後に残ったグルテンを蒸して生麩（もち麩）が作られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When starch in the dough has flowed out in water, gluten remaining is steamed to make fresh gluten cake (or mochi-fu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When starch in the dough has flowed out into the water, the remaining gluten is steamed to make fresh gluten cake (or mochi-fu).</e>
<cmt>prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When starch in the dough has flowed out into the water, the remaining gluten is steamed to make nama-fu (or mochi-fu).</e>
<cmt>fresh gluten cakes →　nama-fu としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="21">
<j>上記のようにして作られたグルテンに、小麦粉、ベーキングパウダー、もち米粉などを加えて練り合わせ、焙り焼きしたものが焼き麩である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Knead together the above gluten, wheat flour, baking powder and glutinous rice flour and toast this dough to make toasted gluten cakes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Knead together the above gluten, wheat flour, baking powder and glutinous rice flour and toast this dough to make toasted gluten cakes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Knead together the above gluten, wheat flour, baking powder and glutinous rice flour and toast this dough to make yaki-fu.</e>
<cmt>toasted gluten cakes→yaki-fu　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="22">
<j>また、生麩を油で揚げると揚げ麩になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Deep-fat fried gluten cakes are made by deep-fat frying fresh gluten cakes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Deep-fat fried gluten cakes are made by deep-fat frying fresh gluten cakes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Age-fu are made by deep-fat frying nama-fu.</e>
<cmt>age-fu, nama-fu としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="23">
<j>生麩には、ゴマ、ヨモギ、紅花などの素材を加えて、風味や色をつけたものもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fresh gluten cakes are available in various flavors and colors that are made by adding other materials such as sesame seeds, mugwort leaves and safflower.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fresh gluten cakes are available in various flavors and colors that are made by adding other materials such as sesame seeds, mugwort leaves and safflower.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nama-fu are available in various flavors and colors that are made by adding other materials such as sesame seeds, mugwort leaves and safflower.</e>
<cmt>fresh gluten cakes →　nama-fu としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="24">
<j>なお、流出したデンプンを集めて乾燥させたものを正麩（しょうふ、漿麩）と呼んで糊や菓子の原料にされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, starched discharged from the dough in the foregoing is collected and dried to make shofu which becomes an ingredient of confectioneries.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, starch discharged from the dough in this process is collected and dried to make shofu which becomes an ingredient of confectioneries.</e>
<cmt>the foregoing-&gt;this process</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, starch discharged from the dough in this process is collected and dried to make shofu which becomes an ingredient of confectioneries.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>形による種類</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gluten cakes of various shapes</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gluten cakes of various shapes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fu of various shapes</e>
<cmt>gluten cakes →fu としました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="25">
<j>板麩</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ita-fu (gluten sheets)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ita-fu (gluten sheets)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ita-fu (gluten sheets)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="26">
<j>山形県庄内町の「庄内麩」が有名であるが、板状に焼いた物。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As to Ita-fu, gluten cakes formed into sheets and toasted, Shonai-fu (gluten cakes of the Shonai district) in Shonai Town, Yamagata Prefecture is well known.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As to Ita-fu, gluten cakes formed into sheets and toasted, Shonai-fu (gluten cakes of the Shonai district) in Shonai Town, Yamagata Prefecture are well known.</e>
<cmt>is-&gt;are</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As to Ita-fu, those formed into sheets and toasted, &apos;Shonai-fu&apos; (fu of the Shonai district) in Shonai Town, Yamagata Prefecture are well known.</e>
<cmt>gluten cakes →fu としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="27">
<j>まんじゅう麩（岩船麩）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Manju-fu (gluten cakes in the manju (Japanese pastry) shape) (also known as Iwafune-fu (gluten cakes of the Iwafune district))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Manju-fu (gluten cakes in the manju shape - also known as Iwafune-fu).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Manju-fu (gluten cakes in the manju shape - also known as Iwafune-fu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>饅頭型をした麩。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Manju-shaped gluten cakes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Manju-shaped gluten cakes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are manju-shaped.</e>
<cmt>翻訳を一部変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>新潟県村上市岩船地区が発祥地とされ、「岩船麩」として知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that the Iwafune district of Murakami City, Niigata Prefecture is the birthplace of the manju-shaped gluten cakes known as &apos;Iwafune-fu.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that the Iwafune district of Murakami City, Niigata Prefecture is the birthplace of the manju-shaped gluten cakes known as &apos;Iwafune-fu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that the Iwafune district of Murakami City, Niigata Prefecture is the birthplace of manju-shaped fu, known as &apos;Iwafune-fu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>gluten cakes →fu としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>同県の下越地方で作られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These are made in the Kaetsu district.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These are made in the Kaetsu district.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These are made in the Kaetsu district.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="31">
<j>つぶし麩</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsubushi-fu (flattened gluten cakes)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsubushi-fu (flattened gluten cakes)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsubushi-fu (flattened gluten cakes)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>まんじゅう麩に蒸気を当てて蒸し、軟らかくなったところを円盤状に押しつぶしたもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These are made by steaming the manju-shaped gluten cakes and pressing them into the shape of discs when soft.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These are made by steaming the manju-shaped gluten cakes and pressing them into the shape of discs when soft.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These are made by steaming the manju-fu and pressing them into the shape of discs when soft.</e>
<cmt>gluten cakes →fu としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>密度が高い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The flattened gluten cakes have high density.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The flattened gluten cakes have high density.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They have high density.</e>
<cmt>gluten cakes →they としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="34">
<j>車麩</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kurumabu (wheel-shaped gluten cakes)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kurumabu (wheel-shaped gluten cakes)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kuruma-bu (wheel-shaped gluten cakes)</e>
<cmt>ハイフンを追加し、他の麩の表現を合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>竹輪のように、アルミの棒に麩の生地を巻いて、回転させながら直火焼きする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The process of making kurumabu is similar to that of chikuwa, fish sausage, whereby aluminum posts are coated with fresh gluten dough that are roasted over an open fire.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The process of making kurumabu is similar to that of chikuwa, fish sausage, whereby aluminum posts are coated with fresh gluten dough that are roasted over an open fire.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The process of making kuruma-bu is similar to that of chikuwa, fish sausage, whereby aluminum posts are coated with fresh gluten dough that are roasted over an open fire.</e>
<cmt>ハイフンを追加しkuruma-bu としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>この工程を3回ほど繰り返し、層状にしたもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The above process is repeated a few times to form layers of roasted gluten cake.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The above process is repeated a few times to form layers of roasted gluten cake.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The above process is repeated a few times to form layers of roasted gluten cake.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>沖縄料理に欠かせない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is an essential ingredient for Okinawa cooking.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is an essential ingredient for Okinawa cooking.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is an essential ingredient for Okinawa cooking.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="38">
<j>押し麩</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oshi-fu (pressed kurumabu (wheel-shaped gluten cakes))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oshi-fu (pressed, wheel-shaped gluten cakes)</e>
<cmt>nested parentheses</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oshi-fu (pressed, wheel-shaped gluten cakes)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>車麩を春巻きのように押しつぶしたもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is made by pressing kurumabu like spring rolls.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is made by pressing kurumabu like spring rolls.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is made by pressing kuruma-bu like spring rolls.</e>
<cmt>ハイフンを追加しkuruma-bu としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>山形県などで作られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Pressed kurumabu is made in some areas including Yamagata Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Pressed kurumabu is made in some areas including Yamagata Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are made in some areas including Yamagata Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>they としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="41">
<j>揚げ麩</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Age-fu (deep-fat fried gluten cakes)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Age-fu (deep-fat fried gluten cakes)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Age-fu</e>
<cmt>既出のため、補足を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>団子状に丸めた生麩を、菜種油などで揚げて作る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Age-fu is made by deep-fat frying fresh gluten that has been formed into small balls in oils such as canola oil.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Age-fu is made by deep-fat frying fresh gluten that has been formed into small balls in oils such as canola oil.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Age-fu is made by deep-fat frying nama-fu that has been formed into small balls in oils such as canola oil.</e>
<cmt>fresh gluten →nama-fu としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>中国無錫のものは、揚げることで気泡を作り、直径6cm程度の大きな球に膨らませてある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When frying in hot oil, gluten cakes develop air bubbles expanding into balls of about 6cm in diameterwhich is the characteristic of deep-fat fried gluten cakes of Wuxi City, China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When frying in hot oil, gluten cakes develop air bubbles expand into balls of about 6cm in diameterwhich is the characteristic of deep-fat fried gluten cakes of Wuxi City, China.</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When frying in hot oil, they develop air bubbles and expand into balls of about 6 cm in diameterwhich is the characteristic of age-fu of Wuxi City, China.</e>
<cmt>develop air bubbles の後にand を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="44">
<j>油麩（あぶらふ）と呼ばれるモノは棒状にしたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gluten cakes referred to as abura-fu are deep-fat fried gluten cakes that had been formed into sticks.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gluten cakes referred to as abura-fu are deep-fat fried gluten cakes that have been formed into sticks.</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those referred to as abura-fu are age-fu that have been formed into sticks.</e>
<cmt>deep-fat fried gluten cakes →age-fu としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>宮城県登米地方の伝統食材。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a traditional foodstuff of the Tome region of Miyagi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a traditional foodstuff of the Tome region of Miyagi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a traditional foodstuff of the Tome region of Miyagi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="46">
<j>汁物に使う時は、水もどしせずに料理に使える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When used in soup, there is no need to develop aburafu by soaking in water.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When used in soup, there is no need to develop aburafu by soaking in water.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When used in soup, there is no need to develop abura-fu by soaking in water.</e>
<cmt>abura-fu としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>適当な大きさに切って煮物に入れることによりコクが出る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Abura-fu can be cut into bite size pieces and added to simmered dishes to lend a rich flavor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Abura-fu can be cut into bite size pieces and added to simmered dishes to lend a rich flavor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Abura-fu can be cut into bite size pieces and added to simmered dishes to lend a rich flavor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>汁気の少ない料理に使う時は、水戻しが必要。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When used in cooking with small amount of liquids, abura-fu has to be developed by soaking in water.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When used in cooking with small amount of liquids, abura-fu has to be developed by soaking in water.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When used in cooking with small amount of liquids, abura-fu has to be developed by soaking in water.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="49">
<j>飾り麩</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kazari-fu (decorative gluten cakes)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kazari-fu (decorative gluten cakes)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kazari-fu</e>
<cmt>既出のため、補足を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>花の形や、手まりの形などを食紅などを使って彩りよく形どったもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kazari-fu is gluten cakes formed into various shapes such as flowers and traditional Japanese handballs that are also dyed in attractive colors with food colorings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kazari-fu are gluten cakes formed into various shapes such as flowers and traditional Japanese handballs that are also dyed in attractive colors with food colorings.</e>
<cmt>is-&gt;are</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kazari-fu are gluten cakes formed into various shapes such as flowers and traditional Japanese handballs that are also dyed in attractive colors with food colorings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>京都の「京小町麩」、「花麩」、石川県の「加賀飾り麩」などが有名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among various types of kazari-fu, &apos;Kyokomachi-fu&apos; and &apos;Hana-fu&apos; (flower-shaped gluten cakes) of Kyoto and &apos;Kaga kazari-fu&apos; (decorative gluten cakes of the Kaga region) are well known.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among various types of kazari-fu, &apos;Kyokomachi-fu&apos; and &apos;Hana-fu&apos; (flower-shaped gluten cakes) of Kyoto and &apos;Kaga kazari-fu&apos; (decorative gluten cakes of the Kaga region) are well known.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among various types of kazari-fu, &apos;Kyokomachi-fu&apos; and &apos;Hana-fu&apos; (flower-shaped fu) of Kyoto and &apos;Kaga kazari-fu&apos; (decorative fu of the Kaga region) are well known.</e>
<cmt>gluten cakes → fu としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="52">
<j>角麩</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaku-fu (the rectangular gluten cakes)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaku-fu (rectangular gluten cakes)</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaku-fu (rectangular gluten cakes)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>すだれを使って板状に成型し蒸し上げたもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gluten cakes that are formed into the board shape by using bamboo mats and steamed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gluten cakes that are formed into a board shape by using bamboo mats and steamed.</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaku-fu are those that are formed into a board shape by using bamboo mats and steamed.</e>
<cmt>gluten cakes →those としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>面には波状の模様がつく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The corrugated surface of the sides of gluten cakes is the characteristic of the kaku-fu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The corrugated sides of gluten cakes is characteristic of kaku-fu.</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They have a corrugated surface.</e>
<cmt>翻訳を一部変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>主に名古屋市周辺で作られており、この地方ではスーパーでもよく見かけるポピュラーな食材。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaku-fu is mainly produced around Nagoya City being a popular food that is commonly available at supermarkets in the area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaku-fu is mainly produced around Nagoya City and is a popular food that is commonly available at supermarkets in the area.</e>
<cmt>being-&gt;and is</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaku-fu is mainly produced around Nagoya City and is a popular food that is commonly available at supermarkets in the area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>主な原材料はグルテンと小麦粉。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The main ingredients of kaku-fu are gluten and wheat flour.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The main ingredients of kaku-fu are gluten and wheat flour.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The main ingredients of kaku-fu are gluten and wheat flour.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="57">
<j>安平麩（あんぺいふ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ampei-fu (round-shaped gluten cakes)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ampei-fu (round-shaped gluten cakes)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Anpei-fu (round-shaped fu)</e>
<cmt>Ampei →Anpei としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>山口県で生産される丸型の焼き麩。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ampei-fu is round gluten cake that is produced in Yamaguchi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ampei-fu is round gluten cake that is produced in Yamaguchi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Anpei-fu is round yaki-fu that is produced in Yamaguchi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>Ampei →Anpei としました。Yaki-fu を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>原材料はグルテンと小麦粉。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gluten and wheat flour are the ingredients of Ampei-fu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gluten and wheat flour are the ingredients of Ampei-fu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gluten and wheat flour are the ingredients of Anpei-fu.</e>
<cmt>Ampei →Anpei としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>一見シュークリームを思わせる外見をしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ampei-fu gluten cakes look like cream puffs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ampei-fu gluten cakes look like cream puffs.</e>
<cmt>spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They look like cream puffs.</e>
<cmt>Ampei-fu →Theyとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="61">
<j>中国では古くは麪筋（めんきん）と呼ばれ、宋 (王朝)に書かれた『夢渓筆談』にもその名が登場する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In old China, fu was referred to as mian jin (gluten) and was mentioned in &quot;Meng Xi Bi Tan&quot; (Dream Stream Essays) which was written during the Sung Dynasty era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In old China, fu was referred to as mian jin (gluten) and was mentioned in &quot;Meng Xi Bi Tan&quot; (Dream Stream Essays) which was written during the Sung Dynasty era.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In old China, fu was referred to as mian jin (gluten) and was mentioned in &quot;Meng Xi Bi Tan&quot; (Dream Stream Essays) which was written during the Sung Dynasty era.</e>
<cmt>ダブルクォーテーションを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>日本では「麩」という字で糠（ふすま）を指し、後にその加工品である麪筋にもこの字が当てられた（『本朝食鑑』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan, the kanji representing &apos;fu&apos; means rice bran and that character was used for mian jin (gluten) which is a processed food made from rice bran later on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan, the kanji representing &apos;fu&apos; means rice bran and that character was used for mian jin (gluten) which is a processed food made from rice bran later on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan, the kanji representing &apos;fu&apos; means rice bran and that character was used for mian jin which is a processed food made from rice bran later on (&quot;Honcho shokkan&quot; [Mirror of food in our country])</e>
<cmt>『本朝食鑑』　と補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>また、小麦そのものが中国大陸から伝来されたことから唐粉（からこ、殻粉）とも称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, since wheat came from China, it was also referred to as Chinese flour.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, since wheat came from China, it was also referred to as Chinese flour.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, since wheat came from China, it was also referred to as Karako (Chinese flour).</e>
<cmt>唐粉　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>鎌倉時代には唐粉を宮廷に貢納する供御人（唐粉供御人）がいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Kamakura Period, there were Kugonin (purveyors to the imperial household) who paid a tribute of Chinese flour to the Imperial household.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Kamakura Period, there were Kugonin (purveyors to the imperial household) who paid a tribute of Chinese flour to the Imperial household.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Kamakura period, there were Kugonin (Karako kugonin) who paid a tribute of Karako to the Imperial household.</e>
<cmt>唐粉供御人　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>「麩＝ふ」としての最古の記録は南北朝時代 (日本)に書かれた『嘉元記』正平 (日本)7年（1352年）5月10日条に登場する「フ」の記述である（なお、同条に「フ」と併記されている「ウトム」がうどんの最古の記録とされている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The oldest documented record on &apos;fu&apos; is the description of &apos;fu&apos;in the article, dated May 10, 1352, in&quot;Kagenki&quot; which was written during the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (and it is said that &apos;utomu&apos; which was mentioned along with &apos;fu&apos; in that article is the oldest documented record on udon (Japanese wheat noodles)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The oldest documented record on &apos;fu&apos; is the description of &apos;fu&apos; in the article dated May 10, 1352, in&quot;Kagenki&quot; which was written during the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (and it is said that &apos;utomu&apos; which was mentioned along with &apos;fu&apos; in that article is the oldest documented record on udon - Japanese wheat noodles).</e>
<cmt>spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The oldest documented record on &apos;fu&apos; is the description of &apos;fu&apos; in the article dated June 30, 1352, in &quot;Kagenki&quot; which was written during the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan) (and it is said that &apos;utomu&apos; which was mentioned along with &apos;fu&apos; in that article is the oldest documented record on udon - Japanese wheat noodles).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションマークの種類を変更しました。グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>禅宗の広まりとともに精進料理や懐石料理などで麩が採用され、日本の食卓でも馴染みのものになっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the Zen sect gained its popularity, fu began to be used in the Buddhist cuisine and kaiseki ryori (a simple meal served before a ceremonial tea) becoming a common food item on dining tables in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the Zen sect gained popularity, fu began to be used in the Buddhist cuisine and kaiseki ryori (a simple meal served before a ceremonial tea), becoming a common food item on dining tables in Japan.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the Zen sect gained popularity, fu began to be used in the Buddhist cuisine and kaiseki ryori (a simple meal served before a ceremonial tea), becoming a common food item on dining tables in Japan.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Karasu619(id:210500), ととりん(id:31982), マクガイア(id:33346), Hhaithait(id:37092), Eskimbot(id:29676), Siriusplot(id:64626), ThreeStar(id:86488), TXiKiBoT(id:107492), Hykw-a4(id:14184), 樒(id:35770), 杉山真大(id:2297), Pilsen(id:104004), 竃馬(id:102733), VolkovBot(id:105371), A-Taul(id:41790), Parayan(id:214526), Chlewbot(id:33904), Almabot(id:280069), M氏＠白CURREN(id:60026), Knua(id:66861), れおなるどだまいや(id:221264), 絶対◆2BenKiTYKw(id:11959), Corwin(id:973), FlaBot(id:30804), SieBot(id:126695), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>