<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>かき氷</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shaved Ice (Flavored with Syrup)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shaved Ice (Flavored with Syrup)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shaved Ice (Flavored with Syrup)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>かき氷（かきごおり、欠き氷）とは、氷を細かく削るか、砕いてシロップ（またはシラップ）等をかけた冷菓。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shaved ice is chilled sweets made with finely shaved or cracked ice flavored with syrup, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shaved ice is a chilled sweet made with finely shaved or cracked ice flavored with syrup, etc.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shaved ice is a frozen sweet made from finely shaved or crushed ice that is flavored with syrup, for example.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>日本の夏の風物詩、夏の季語。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a special feature of summer in Japan. It is a season word (phrase) for summer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a special feature of summer in Japan, and a seasonal word for the summer.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a special feature of summer in Japan, and a seasonal word for the summer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>夏氷とも言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called natsugori (literarily, summer ice).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called natsugori (literarily, summer ice).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called natsugori (literally, summer ice).</e>
<cmt>「literarily」→「literally」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>かき氷とは、削った氷にシロップ等をかけた氷菓である（近年は削ったというよりも砕いたような切片状の氷がまん延しており、「これでは砕き氷だ」という意見もある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shaved ice is chilled sweets made with shaved ice flavored with syrup, etc. (Recently, small chips of ice made by cracking ice rather than shaved ice have been spreading and some says &quot;It is crashed ice.&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shaved ice is a chilled sweet made with shaved ice flavored with syrup, etc. (Recently, small chips of ice made by cracking ice rather than shaving the ice have been spreading and some call it &quot;crushed ice&quot;).</e>
<cmt>spelling, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shaved ice is a chilled sweet made with shaved ice flavored with syrup, etc. (Recently, small chips of ice made by cracking ice rather than shaving the ice have been spreading and some call it &quot;crushed ice&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>餡やコンデンスミルクをかけたものもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are shaved ice that has topping of bean jam or condensed milk.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is also shaved ice with a topping of bean jam or condensed milk.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is also shaved ice with a topping of bean jam or condensed milk.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>広義には、出来合いの市販品としてカップ入りのアイスクリームと同様の器に細かく砕いた氷と各種シロップを混ぜたものも指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a broad sense, it covers ready-made product available on the market that is mixture of finely crashed ice and various syrup in a container similar to that of ice cream packed in a cup.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is a ready-made product available on the market that is mixture of finely crushed ice and various syrupss in containers similar to ice cream in a cup.</e>
<cmt>spelling, wordiness, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In a broad sense, shaved ice covers a ready-made product available on the market that is mixture of finely crushed ice and various syrups in containers similar to ice cream in a cup.</e>
<cmt>「In a broad sense」を再追加し「this is」→「shaved ice covers」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>市販品では、袋入りもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Product packed in a bag is also available on the market.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The product packed in a bag is also available on the market.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The product packed in a bag is also available on the market.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>また、近似品としては甲子園球場名物となっているかち割りもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As similar product, there is kachiwari (crushed ice) that is a famous specialty of Koshien baseball park.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As similar product, kachiwari (crushed ice) is a famous specialty at the Koshien baseball park.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A similar product, kachiwari (crushed ice) is a famous specialty at the Koshien baseball park.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>かき氷を売っている店では、氷旗（白地に赤い文字で「氷」と書かれた幟（のぼり））を掲げていることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many shops that sell shaved ice display koribata (flag with red character &quot;氷 (ice)&quot; on white background).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many shops that sell shaved ice display a koribata (flag with red character &quot;氷 (ice)&quot; on white background).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many shops that sell shaved ice display a koribata (flag with red character &quot;氷 (ice)&quot; on white background).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>夏季に社寺の境内で催される祭礼や縁日などでは綿飴・たこ焼き・焼きそばとともに代表的な縁日物（えんにちもの）の一つである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In rites and festivals as well as fairs held in summer in precincts of shrine or temple, it is one of typical ennichimono (things to be sold at festival) same as &quot;wataame (cotton candy)&quot;, &quot;takoyaki (octopus dumplings)&quot; and &quot;yakisoba (fried soba)&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In rites and festivals as well as at fairs held in summer in precincts of a shrine or temple, it is one of typical ennichimono (items to be sold at festival) same as &quot;wataame (cotton candy),&quot; &quot;takoyaki (octopus dumplings)&quot; and &quot;yakisoba (fried soba).&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation,</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In rites and festivals as well as at fairs held in summer in precincts of a shrine or temple, it is one of typical ennichimono (items to be sold at festival) same as &quot;wata-ame (cotton candy),&quot; &quot;takoyaki (octopus dumplings)&quot; and &quot;yakisoba (fried soba).&quot;</e>
<cmt>「wataame」→「wata-ame」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>史実上の記録は平安時代に清少納言の『枕草子』「あてなるもの」（上品なもの、良いもの）の段に、「削り氷にあまづら入れて、新しき金鋺（かなまり）に入れたる」と記述されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a historical record, Seishonagon wrote in the section of &quot;atenarumono&quot; (what is elegant or good) in her &quot;Makura no soshi&quot; (The Pillow Book) &quot;kezurihini amazurairete atarasikikanamarini iretaru..&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a historical record, Seishonagon wrote in the section of &quot;atenarumono&quot; (what is elegant or good) in her &quot;Makura no soshi&quot; (The Pillow Book) &quot;kezurihini amazurairete atarasikikanamarini iretaru..&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a historical record, Sei-shonagon wrote in the section of &quot;atenarumono&quot; (what is elegant or good) in her &quot;Makura no soshi&quot; (The Pillow Book) &quot;kezurihini amazurairete atarasikikanamarini iretaru.&quot;</e>
<cmt>「Seishonagon」→「Sei Shonagon」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>金属製の器に氷を刃物で削った削り氷（けずりひ、文中では「けつりひ」）に蔓草の一種であるアマヅラ（あまかづら・あまづら、ツタの樹液またはアマチャヅルの茎の汁と思われる）をかけたとの意味である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It means that Kezurihi (in the sentence, &quot;ketsurihi&quot;) prepared by shaving ice with a knife is put in a new metal bowl and amazura, that is a type of vine,(it seem that sap from vine or juice from stem of Gynostemma pentaphyllum) is poured.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処「蔓草」は「蔓草の樹液」であるべきと思われますが、原文に沿って訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It means that Kezurihi (in the sentence, &quot;ketsurihi&quot;) prepared by shaving ice with a knife is put into a new metal bowl and amazura, that is a type of vine,(it seem that sap from vine or juice from stem of Gynostemma pentaphyllum) is poured on top of the ice.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It means that Kezurihi (in the original sentence, &quot;ketsurihi&quot;) prepared by shaving ice with a knife is put into a metal bowl and amazura, that is a type of vine, (it seem that sap from vine or juice from stem of Gynostemma pentaphyllum) is poured on top of the ice.</e>
<cmt>「in the sentence」→「in the original sentence」とし「new」を除きました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>1869年（明治2年）、神奈川県横浜市にある馬車道で初めての氷水店が開店する（日本においてアイスクリームを発祥させた店でもある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1869, the first shop selling shaved ice with syrup was opened in Bashamichi in Yokohama City, Kanagawa Prefecture (This shop is also the fist shop from which ice cream was originated).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1869, the first shop selling shaved ice with syrup was opened in Bashamichi in Yokohama City, Kanagawa Prefecture (This shop is also the first shop from which ice cream originated).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1869, the first shop selling shaved ice with syrup was opened in Bashamichi in Yokohama City, Kanagawa Prefecture (This shop is also the first shop from which ice cream originated).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>1882年（明治15年）頃に博物学者のエドワード・S・モースが、かき氷を食べたことを自著に記している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Edward S. Morse, who was a botanist, recorded in his book that he ate shaved ice flavored with syrup around 1882.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Edward S. Morse, who was a botanist, recorded in his book that he ate shaved ice flavored with syrup around 1882.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Edward S. Morse, who was a botanist, recorded in his book that he ate shaved ice flavored with syrup around 1882.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>昭和初期に氷削機が普及し、一般化する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In early Showa era, ice shaving machine became common and went mainstream.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the early Showa era, ice shaving machines became common and went mainstream.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the early Showa period, ice shaving machines became common and went mainstream.</e>
<cmt>「Showa era」→「Showa period」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>種類</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Types</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Types</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Types</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="16">
<j>同一のものであっても地域によって呼び名や盛りつけ方が異なる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Depending on area, same type has different name or way of setout.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Depending upon the area, the same type goes by a different name or way of preparation.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Depending upon the area, the same type goes by a different name or way of preparation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="17">
<j>シロップ類</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Syrups</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Syrups</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Syrups</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="18">
<j>イチゴシロップ：赤色のシロップ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Strawberry syrup: Red syrup</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Strawberry syrup: Red syrup</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Strawberry syrup: Red syrup</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="19">
<j>メロンシロップ：緑色のシロップ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Melon syrup: Green syrup</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Melon syrup: Green syrup</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Melon syrup: Green syrup</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="20">
<j>レモンシロップ：黄色のシロップ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Lemon syrup: Yellow syrup</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Lemon syrup: Yellow syrup</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Lemon syrup: Yellow syrup</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="21">
<j>ブルーハワイ：青色のシロップでカクテルのブルーハワイを連想させる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Blue Hawaii: Brue syrup that remind us cocktail, blue Hawaii.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Blue Hawaii: Blue syrup that reminds us of the cocktail, blue Hawaii.</e>
<cmt>spelling, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Blue Hawaii: Blue syrup that reminds us of the cocktail, blue Hawaii.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>トロピカルフルーツ各種を添えることも多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Often, various tropical fruits are added.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Often, various tropical fruits are added.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Often, various tropical fruits are added.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>ハワイアンブルーと呼ぶこともある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called Hawaiian blue.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called Hawaiian blue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called Hawaiian blue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>レモン・オレンジ等の香料が使われ、ソーダに近い風味のものが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sweet spices such as lemon and orange are used and many has a flavor similar to soda.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sweet spices such as lemon and orange are used and many have flavors similar to carbonated drinks.</e>
<cmt>grammar, terminology</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sweet flavors such as lemon and orange are used and many have flavors similar to carbonated drinks.</e>
<cmt>「spices」→「flavors」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="25">
<j>水（すい）：砂糖水（さとうすい）を略して水と言い、砂糖を煮詰めて作る無色のガムシロップをかけたもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sui: Sugared water is abbreviated as sui and colorless gomme syrup, prepared by boiling down sugar is poured.</e>
<cmt>「砂糖を煮詰める」は、「砂糖水を煮詰める」の誤りと思われますが、原文のとおりに訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sui: Sugared water abbreviated as sui, is a colorless gomme syrup, prepared by boiling down sugar.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sui: Sugared water abbreviated as sui, is a colorless gomme syrup, prepared by boiling down sugar.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>「氷水（こおりすい）」・「みぞれ」・「せんじ」・「甘露（かんろ）」と呼ばれることがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sometimes, it is called &quot;korisui&quot;, &quot;mizore&quot;, &quot;senji&quot; or &quot;kanro.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sometimes, it is called &quot;korisui,&quot; &quot;mizore,&quot; &quot;senji&quot; or &quot;kanro.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sometimes, it is called &quot;korisui&quot; (iced water) &quot;mizore&quot; (sleety), &quot;senji&quot; (decoction), or &quot;kanro&quot; (honeydew).</e>
<cmt>それぞれ英訳をつけました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="27">
<j>レインボー：いろんな色のシロップをかけた多色のもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rainbow: Syrups in various colors are poured to make shaved ice multioolored.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rainbow: Syrups in various colors are used to make shaved ice multicolored.</e>
<cmt>terminology</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rainbow: Syrups in various colors are used to make shaved ice multicolored.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="28">
<j>濃縮乳酸菌飲料：カルピスなどの濃縮液。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Condensed lactic acid bacteria beverage: Concentrated liquid from Calpis</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Condensed lactic acid bacteria beverage: Concentrated liquid from Calpis</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Condensed lactic acid bacteria beverage: Concentrated liquid from Calpis (uncarbonated soft drink, manufactured by Calpis Co., Ltd).</e>
<cmt>「Calpis」→「Calpis(uncarbonated soft drink, manufactured by Calpis Co., Ltd)」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>地域によってはそのまま「カルピス」と呼ばれることがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Depending on areas, it is called &quot;Calpis&quot; straight.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Depending upon the area, it is called by it&apos;s commercial brand name &quot;Calpis.&quot;</e>
<cmt>revised for clairity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Depending upon the area, it is called by it&apos;s commercial brand name &quot;Calpis.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="30">
<j>コーヒー：濃く淹れたコーヒー。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Coffee: Strong brewed coffee</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Coffee: Strongly brewed coffee</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Coffee: Strongly brewed coffee</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>シロップや加糖練乳とともにかける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is poured with syrup or sweetened condensed milk.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is used together with syrup or sweetened condensed milk.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is used together with syrup or sweetened condensed milk.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="32">
<j>黒蜜黒糖を湯で溶かしたもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Black syrup or brown sugar lump dissolved in hot water</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Black syrup or brown sugar lump dissolved in hot water</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Black syrup or brown sugar lump dissolved in hot water</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>台湾のかき氷では一般的。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Quite popular among shaved ice flavored with syrup in Taiwan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Quite popular among shaved ice flavored with syrup in Taiwan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Quite popular among shaved ice flavored with syrup in Taiwan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="34">
<j>加糖練乳：コンデンスミルク、単独でかけるよりもトッピングにされることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sweetened condensed milk: Condensed milk, often used as topping rather than independent usage</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sweetened condensed milk: Condensed milk, often used as a topping in addition to standard usage.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sweetened condensed milk: Condensed milk, often used as a topping in addition to standard usage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="35">
<j>梅酒：一応「大人だけ」と書いてあるが、適当である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ume liquer: At least, it is written &quot;adult only&quot;, but not applied strictly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ume liquer: includeds a notice; &quot;adults only,&quot; but not strictly enforced.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ume (plum) liquor: includes a notice; &quot;adults only,&quot; but not strictly enforced.</e>
<cmt>「ume」→「ume (plum)」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="36">
<j>イチゴシロップなどは、無果汁で着色料で色を付けたものがほとんどだが、果汁や果肉を混ぜたものも一部には存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most syrups like strawberry syrup do not contain any fruit juice and colored with artificial color, but there are some that contain fruit juice or flesh of fruit.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most syrups like strawberry syrup do not contain any fruit juice and used artificial coloring, but there are some that contain fruit juice or the actual pulp of the fruit.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most syrups like strawberry syrup do not contain any fruit juice and used artificial coloring, but there are some that contain fruit juice or the actual pulp of the fruit.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="37">
<j>アイスクリーム：かき氷の上のトッピングとしてアイスクリームを乗せる場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ice cream: In certain cases, ice cream is placed on shaved ice as topping.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ice cream: In certain cases, ice cream is placed on shaved ice as a topping.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ice cream: In certain cases, ice cream is placed on shaved ice as a topping.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="38">
<j>宇治金時（うじきんとき）：銘茶として名高い宇治茶を連想させる抹茶に砂糖と水を加え、茶筅で泡立てたシロップをかき氷にかけ、アズキの別称の金時（きんとき）を載せたもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ujikintoki: Syrup, which is prepared by adding sugar and water to green powdered tea that suggests ujicha (famous as refined tea) and whisked using a chasen (a bamboo tea whisk), is poured onto shaved ice and kintoki, that is another name of red beans, is placed as topping.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ujikintoki: Syrup, prepared by adding sugar and water to green powdered tea to give an ujicha flavor (famous as refined tea) is whisked using a chasen (a bamboo tea whisk), and poured onto shaved ice and kintoki, another name for red beans, as a topping.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ujikintoki: Syrup, prepared by adding sugar and water to green powdered tea to give an ujicha flavor (famous as refined tea) is whisked using a chasen (a bamboo tea whisk), and poured onto shaved ice and kintoki, another name for red beans, as a topping.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>つぶ餡のばあいは、抹茶の上に載せるようにかけ、漉し餡の場合はボール状にして添えることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Usually, sweet beans are put like placing on green powdered tea nad koshian (strained bean jam) is added in ball-like shape.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Usually, sweet beans are placed on green powdered tea and koshian (strained bean jam) is added in a ball-like shape.</e>
<cmt>redundancy, wordiness, spelling, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Usually, sweet beans are placed on green powdered tea and koshian (strained bean jam) is added in a ball-like shape.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>下部に埋設することもあり、この場合単なる宇治氷と区別がつかない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sometimes, bean jam is put under ice and, in this case, it cannot be distinguished from plain uji kori (shaved ice and sweetened tea only).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sometimes, bean jam is put under the ice and, in this case, it cannot be distinguished from plain uji kori (shaved ice and sweetened tea only) in appearance.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sometimes, bean jam is put under the ice and, in this case, it cannot be distinguished from plain uji kori (shaved ice and sweetened tea only) in appearance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>金時のアズキ色とかき氷の白、抹茶の緑の対比をさせるためにアズキの上に抹茶をかけることはない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order to contrast azuki iro (color of azuki) of kintoki, white of ice and green of powdered tea, powdered tea is never poured onto red beans.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To contrast the color of azuki, kintoki, white ice, and green powdered tea, powdered tea is never poured onto red beans.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To contrast the color of azuki, kintoki, white ice, and green powdered tea, powdered tea is never poured onto red beans.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>勿論、宇治だけのものもある（抹茶だけ）、また、宇治にミルクをかけたものを「宇治時雨」と呼ぶことがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Needless to say, there is shaved ice with only uji (with only green powdered tea) and sometimes uji having topping of milk is called &quot;uji shigure.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is shaved ice using only uji (with only green powdered tea) and sometimes uji with milk is called &quot;uji shigure.&quot;</e>
<cmt>wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is shaved ice using only uji (with only green powdered tea) and sometimes uji with milk is called &quot;uji shigure.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>組み合わせのバリエーションは相当考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Considerable number of variations in combination can be thought of.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">jA considerable number of variations iand combinations can be thought of.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A considerable number of variations and combinations can be thought of.</e>
<cmt>「jA」→「A」、「iand」→「and」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="44">
<j>氷小豆（こおりあずき）：前記、水をシロップとしてアズキを載せたもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kori azuki: Above-mentioned water is replaced with syrup and red beans are put on the top.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kori azuki: Above-mentioned water is replaced with syrup and red beans are put on the top.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kori azuki: Above-mentioned water is replaced with syrup and red beans are put on the top.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="45">
<j>酢だまり氷（すだまりごおり）：山形県山辺町周辺に伝わる酢醤油（酢溜まり）をかけた氷。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sudamari gori: Ice poured with soy sauce mixed with vinegar (sudamari) that is handed down in the vicinity of Yamabe Town in Yamagata Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sudamari gori: Ice poured with soy sauce mixed with vinegar (sudamari) a receipe handed down in the vicinity of Yamabe Town in Yamagata Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sudamari gori: Ice poured with sudamari (soy sauce mixed with vinegar) a recipe handed down in the vicinity of Yamabe Town in Yamagata Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>「soy sauce mixed with vinegar (sudamari)」→「sudamari (soy sauce mixed with vinegar)」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>イチゴシロップなどとともにかけられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is poured with strawberry syrup, for example.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is used together with strawberry syrup, for example.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is used together with strawberry syrup, for example.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>第二次世界大戦後の貧しい時期に、シロップなどが手に入らず何もかけないかき氷が食べられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Second World War, in the poor period, syrups could not be obtained and shaved ice without any additive was eaten.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Second World War, during the depression, syrups could not be obtained and shaved ice without any additives was eaten.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Second World War, during the depression, syrups could not be obtained and shaved ice without any additives was eaten.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>その頃にところてんなどに用いられていた酢醤油をかけ始めたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is told that, around that time, people commenced to pour soy sauce mixed with vinegar that was used for tokoroten (gelidium jelly).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During that time, people used soy sauce mixed with vinegar that was used for tokoroten (gelidium jelly).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During that time, people used sudamari that was used for tokoroten (gelidium jelly).</e>
<cmt>「soy sauce mixed with vinegar」→「sudamari」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="49">
<j>あかふく氷（あかふくごおり）：伊勢路の夏の風物詩の一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akfuku gori: One of special features in summer in Ise-ji Route.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akfuku gori: One of special features in summer in the Ise-ji area.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akafuku gori: One of the Ise-ji area&apos;s special attractions in the summer.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>かき氷に赤福餅ならではの餡と餅、抹茶仕立てのシロップをかけたもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is shaved ice on which bean jam and mochi (rice cake), unique for akafukumochi are placed and syrup prepared with green powdered tea is poured.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is shaved ice topped off with bean jam and mochi (rice cake), unique as akafukumochi, and a green powdered tea syrup is poured on top of this.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is shaved ice topped off with bean jam and mochi (rice cake), unique as akafuku mochi (Japanese mochi confection made by placing an sweet bean paste on mochi), and a green powdered tea syrup is poured on top of this.</e>
<cmt>「akafukumochi」→「akafuku mochi (Japanese mochi confection made by placing an sweet bean paste on mochi)」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>ほうじ茶が添えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is served with hojicha (roasted green tea).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is served with hojicha (roasted green tea).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is served with hojicha (roasted green tea).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>1961年（昭和36年）7月に三重県の伊勢名物である赤福餅を「赤福アイス」の名称で氷菓として海水浴客に供したのが興りとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The origin was akafuku mochi (Japanese mochi confection made by placing an sweet bean jam on mochi (pounded rice)), which is a specialty of Ise in Mie Prefecture, served in July 1961to sea bathers as a frozen sweets under the name of &quot;Akafuku ice.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The origin was akafuku mochi, Japanese mochi confectionary made by placing sweet bean jam on top of mochi (pounded rice), a specialty of Ise in Mie Prefecture, served in July 1961to sun bathers at beaches as a frozen sweets under the name of &quot;Akafuku ice.&quot;</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The origin was akafuku mochi, a specialty of Ise in Mie Prefecture, served in July 1961 to sun bathers at beaches as a frozen sweets under the name of &quot;Akafuku ice.&quot;</e>
<cmt>「, Japanese mochi confectionary made by placing sweet bean jam on top of mochi (pounded rice)」を除きました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>夏季には氷旗とは異なり赤福の赤い文字と青い氷の文字が書かれた看板が店先に置かれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In summer, flags with red characters &quot;赤福 (akafuku)&quot; and blue character &quot;氷 (kori = ice)&quot;, which are different from koribata, are displayed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In summer, flags with red characters &quot;赤福 (akafuku)&quot; and blue character &quot;氷 (kori = ice),&quot; different from koribata, are displayed.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In summer, signs with red characters &quot;赤福 (akafuku)&quot; and blue character &quot;氷 (kori = ice),&quot; different from koribata, are displayed.</e>
<cmt>「flags」→「signs」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>餡はこし餡で、餅については白玉団子より柔らかく、ゆでた後に搗いた餅が入っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bean jam is koshian (strained bean jam) and, with respect to rice cake, rice cakes, which is softer than shiratama dango (Japanese rice-flour dumplings), prepared by pounding after boiling, are contained.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bean jam is koshian (strained bean jam) and rice cake, softer than shiratama dango (Japanese rice-flour dumplings), are prepared by pounding after being boiled.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bean jam is koshian and rice cake, softer than shiratama dango (Japanese rice-flour dumplings), are prepared by pounding after being boiled.</e>
<cmt>「(strained bean jam)」を除きました（既出のため）。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="55">
<j>白くま（しろくま）：発祥の鹿児島県、および九州でよく見られる名物氷菓。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shirokuma (polar bear): Famous frozen sweets often seen in Kagoshima Prefecture, place of origin, and Kyushu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shirokuma (polar bear): Famous frozen sweets often seen in Kagoshima Prefecture, place of origin, and Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shirokuma (polar bear): Famous frozen sweets often seen in Kagoshima Prefecture, place of origin, and Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>ミカンやパイナップルの缶詰などの果物を盛り込み、アズキを乗せ、練乳をかけたもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fruits such as canned mandarin orange and pineapple are filled and red beans are put on the top and condensed milk is poured</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fruit, like canned mandarin oranges and pineapple, are used and red beans used as a topping and condensed milk is poured over this.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fruit, like canned mandarin oranges and pineapple, are used and red beans used as a topping and condensed milk is poured over this.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>この組み合わせでカップ入りの氷菓やアイスキャンディーも作られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Frozen sweets in a cup or in the form of icelolly with this combination are also produced.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Frozen sweets in a cup or in the form of icelolly with this combination are also sold.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Frozen sweets in a cup or in the form of ice-lolly with this combination are also sold.</e>
<cmt>「icelolly」→「ice-lolly」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="58">
<j>ぜんざい：沖縄県の名物氷菓。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zenzai: Famous frozen sweets in Okinawa Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zenzai: Famous frozen sweets in Okinawa Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zenzai: Famous frozen sweets in Okinawa Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>アズキなどをシロップで煮たものの上にかき氷をかけている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shaved ice is placed on the top of red beans cooked with syrup.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shaved ice is placed on the top of red beans cooked in syrup.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shaved ice is placed on the top of red beans cooked in syrup.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>しかし元来、「ぜんざい（善哉）」の語は関西などでつぶしあんの汁粉を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the word &quot;Zenzai&quot; originally means shiruko (sweet red-bean soup with pieces of rice cake) prepared with coarse sweet red-bean jam.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the word &quot;Zenzai&quot; originally meant shiruko (sweet red-bean soup with pieces of rice cake) prepared with coarse sweet red-bean jam.</e>
<cmt>tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the word &quot;Zenzai&quot; originally meant shiruko (sweet red-bean soup with pieces of rice cake) prepared with coarse sweet red-bean jam.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="61">
<j>白雪（しらゆき）：プレーンのかき氷。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shirayuki: Plain shaved ice</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shirayuki: Plain shaved ice</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shirayuki: Plain shaved ice</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>「プレーンはかき氷ではなくかち割りだ」とする人もいるが、中には愛好家もいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although some say &quot;Plain should be kachiwari, not shaved ice&quot;, there are certain number of followings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although some say &quot;Plain should be called kachiwari, not shaved ice,&quot; there are a certain number of those who use the term shaved ice.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although some say &quot;Plain should be called kachiwari, not shaved ice,&quot; there are a certain number of those who use the term shaved ice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="63">
<j>雪くま（ゆきくま）：夏の猛暑で知られる埼玉県熊谷市で、町おこしの一環として、地元の水を利用したかき氷を考案し、市内の飲食店でオリジナルかき氷を競作した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yukikuma: In Kumagaya City, Saitame Prefecture that is well known with violent heat in summer, shaved ice, for which local water is used, is devised as a part of movement for revitalization of the town and eating and drinking establishments in the city competed to create own menu for shaved ice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yukikuma: In Kumagaya City, Saitama Prefecture that is well known for it&apos;s violent heat during the summer, shaved ice, for which local water is used, is devised as a part of movement to revitalize the town and eating and drinking establishments in the city compete to create their own original menu for shaved ice.</e>
<cmt>grammar, tense, spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yukikuma: In Kumagaya City, Saitama Prefecture that is well known for it&apos;s violent heat during the summer, shaved ice, for which local water is used, is devised as a part of movement to revitalize the town and eating and drinking establishments in the city compete to create their own original menu for shaved ice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="64">
<j>みかん氷・パイナップル氷：横浜スタジアムで売られているかき氷。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mikan gori (shaved ice with mandarin orange)/pineapple gori (shaved ice with pineapple): Shaved ice sold in the Yokohama stadium.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mikan gori (shaved ice with mandarin orange)/pineapple gori (shaved ice with pineapple): Shaved ice sold at Yokohama stadium.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mikan gori (shaved ice with mandarin orange)/pineapple gori (shaved ice with pineapple): Shaved ice sold at Yokohama stadium.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>缶詰みかんもしくは缶詰パイナップルを乗せ、その上に缶詰のシロップをかけただけの、シンプルなもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Simple dishes prepared by putting canned mandarin orange or canned pineapple on shaved ice and pouring syrup in the can</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Simple dishes prepared by putting canned mandarin orange or canned pineapple on shaved ice and adding the syrup from the can</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Simple dishes prepared by putting canned mandarin orange or canned pineapple on shaved ice and adding the syrup from the can</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>作り方</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Recipe</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Recipe</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Recipe</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="66">
<j>作り方の一例を示す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An example of a recipe is shown below.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An example of a recipe is shown below.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An example of a recipe is shown below.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>これらシロップのかけ方や量は地域差がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are regional difference with respect to way to pour syrup and the amount of syrup.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are regional differences with respect to pouring and the amount of syrup used.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are regional differences with respect to pouring and the amount of syrup used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="68">
<j>あらかじめかき氷を入れる器を冷凍庫などで冷却しておく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dishes in which shaved ice is served shall be cooled in advance, for example, with a refrigerator.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dishes used for shaved ice are pre-cooled in a refrigerator.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dishes used for shaved ice are pre-cooled in a refrigerator.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="69">
<j>器にかき氷器を用いてかき氷を若干載せ、シロップをレードル（甘露尺）一杯分をかける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Using an ice shaving machine, a little amount of shaved ice is put in the dish and a ladleful of syrup is poured on it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Using an ice shaving machine, a little amount of shaved ice is put into a dish and a ladleful of syrup is poured on top.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Using an ice shaving machine, a little amount of shaved ice is put into a dish and a ladleful of syrup is poured on top.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="70">
<j>続けて、かき氷器を用いてかき氷を盛る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, shaved ice is again put using the ice shaving machine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, more shaved ice is added using the ice shaving machine again.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, more shaved ice is added using the ice shaving machine again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>この時、器は斜めに満遍なく回転させ山盛りになるように盛りつける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During this operation, the dish is rotated evenly and shaved ice should be placed so that a mountain-like shape is created.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The dish is rotated evenly and the shaved ice is formed into a mountain-like shape.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The dish is rotated evenly and the shaved ice is formed into a mountain-like shape.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="72">
<j>シロップを1-2杯程度かける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One to two ladleful syrup is poured.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One to two ladlefuls of syrup is poured on top.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One to two ladlefuls of syrup is poured on top.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="73">
<j>各種盛りつける果物や添え物などのトッピングを載せる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Put various toppings such as fruits and additives.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Various toppings such as fruits and additives can be added.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Various toppings such as fruits and additives can be added.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>呼称</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Name</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Name</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Name</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="74">
<j>かき氷：もっとも一般的に普及している呼び名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kakigori (literally, shaved ice): Most commonly used name</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kakigori (literally, shaved ice): Most commonly used name</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kakigori (literally, shaved ice): Most commonly used name</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>東京方言の「ぶっかきごおり」から。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was derived from &quot;bukkaki gori&quot; in Tokyo dialect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was derived from &quot;bukkaki gori&quot; in the Tokyo dialect.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was derived from &quot;bukkaki gori&quot; in the Tokyo dialect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>近畿で「かちわり（ごおり）」、奥羽で「こおりみず」など様々。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kinki region, &quot;kachiwari (gori)&quot; and in Ou region, &quot;Korimizu&quot;, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Kinki region, &quot;kachiwari (gori)&quot; and in the Ou region, &quot;Korimizu,&quot; etc.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Kinki region, &quot;kachiwari (gori)&quot; and in the Ou region, &quot;Korimizu,&quot; etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="77">
<j>フラッペ (Frappe) ：本来はクラッシュドアイスにリキュールなどの酒類を注いだ飲料。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Frappe: Originally, a type of drink prepared by pouring alcoholic drink such as liquer onto crashed ice</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Frappe: Originally, a type of drink prepared by pouring an alcoholic drink such as liquer onto crushed ice</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Frappe: Originally, a type of drink prepared by pouring an alcoholic drink such as liquor onto crushed ice.</e>
<cmt>「liquer」→「liquor」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>日本ではかき氷にシロップをかけたものを指す事が多く、かき氷と同一のものとなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan, it usually refers to shaved ice with poured syrup, and became same as shaved ice flavored with syrup.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan, it usually refers to shaved ice with syrup, and it became the same as shaved ice flavored with syrup.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan, it usually refers to shaved ice with syrup, and it became the same as shaved ice flavored with syrup.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>和風喫茶や甘味喫茶ではかき氷と呼び、喫茶店やパーラーなどの和洋折衷または洋風の飲食店ではフラッペと呼ぶことが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japanese-style teahouses and sweet parlors, it is called kakigori (shaved ice flavored with syrup) and, in semi-Western and Western-style eating and drinking facilities, such as teahouses and parlors, it is called frappe.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japanese-style teahouses and sweet parlors, it is called kakigori (shaved ice flavored with syrup) and, in semi-Western and Western-style eating and drinking facilities, such as teahouses and parlors, it is called frappe.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japanese-style teahouses and sweet parlors, it is called kakigori (shaved ice flavored with syrup) and, in semi-Western and Western-style eating and drinking facilities, such as teahouses and parlors, it is called frappe.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>なお、岸和田市などの大阪府泉南では、かき氷屋さんが「かき氷にする?フラッペにする?」と聞いてくることがあり、その際、フラッペを選択すると、かき氷を手でぐっと押し固めたものにシロップをかける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Sennan in Osaka Prefecture, such as Kishiwada City, you might be asked in the shop for shaved ice &quot;Kakigori? Or, frappe?&quot;, and if you choose frappe, shaved ice is pressed together before pouring syrup.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Sennan in Osaka Prefecture, such as Kishiwada City, you might be asked in the shop whether you want shaved ice &quot;Kakigori or frappe and if you choose frappe, the shaved ice will be pressed together before pouring on the syrup.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Sennan district in Osaka Prefecture, such as Kishiwada City, you might be asked in the shop whether you want shaved ice &quot;Kakigori or frappe&quot; and if you choose frappe, the shaved ice will be pressed together before pouring on the syrup.</e>
<cmt>「Sennan」→「Sennan district」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="81">
<j>器</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Serving dishes</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Serving dishes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Serving dishes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="82">
<j>和風：涼しさを演出する透明なガラスや切子（きりこ）の広口の器を用いることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese style: Transparent glass dishes or wide-mouth dishes of cut glass are usually used for showing coolness.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese style: Transparent glass dishes or wide-mouth dishes of cut glass are usually used to emphasize the coolness.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese style: Transparent glass dishes or wide-mouth dishes of cut glass are usually used to emphasize the coolness.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>氷が溶けにくいように、肉厚の陶器の丼が用いられることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sometimes, thick ceramic bowl is used to prevent ice melting quickly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sometimes, a thick ceramic bowl is used to prevent ice from melting quickly.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sometimes, a thick ceramic bowl is used to prevent ice from melting quickly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>明治時代には水呑コップや小圷などの汎用のコップが使われていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Meiji era, general purpose cups, such as water glass or koakutsu (a type of cup) were used for serving shaved ice.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Meiji era, general purpose cups, such as water glass or a koakutsu (a type of cup) were used for serving shaved ice.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Meiji period, general purpose cups, such as water glass or a koakutsu (a type of cup) were used for serving shaved ice.</e>
<cmt>「Meiji era」→「Meiji period」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>明治の終わり頃から氷コップと呼ばれる専用のガラス器も使われるようになり、この器は大正時代から昭和の戦前頃まであぶり出し技法などを駆使した独特の発達を遂げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since around the end of Meiji era, dedicated glassware called kori koppu (cup for ice) was introduced and this type of dishes had developed in the period from Taisho era to Showa era just before the Second World War fully utilizing a technique called aburidashi, etc.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around the end of the Meiji era, dedicated glassware called kori koppu (cup for ice) was introduced and this type of dishe had developed during the period from Taisho era to the Showa era just before the Second World War fully utilizing a technique called aburidashi, etc.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around the end of the Meiji period, dedicated glassware called kori koppu (cup for ice) was introduced and this type of dishes had developed during the period from Taisho period to the Showa period just before the Second World War fully utilizing a technique called aburidashi (a technique of glass-works that motifs come to the surface by difference in temperature), etc.</e>
<cmt>「era」→「period」「aburidashi」→「aburidashi (a technique of glass-works that motifs come to the surface by difference in temperature.)」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="86">
<j>洋風：器を手で持ったときに手の体温で氷が溶けにくいように細い脚が付いたガラス器を用いることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Western style: Glassware with a slim stem is usually used so that ice does not melt away with temperature of the hand when the dish is hold with a hand.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Western style: Glassware with a slim stem is usually used so that ice does not melt away from temperature of the hand when the dish is held.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Western style: Glassware with a slim stem is usually used so that ice does not melt away from temperature of the hand when the dish is held.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="87">
<j>発泡スチロール：露店での販売では発泡スチロールの器がよく使われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Foamed polystylene: For sale by street stall, dishes made of formed polystylene are often used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Foamed polystylene: Street stalls often use dishes made of formed polystylene.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Foamed polystyrene: Street stalls often use dishes made of foamed polystyrene.</e>
<cmt>「Foamed polystylene」→「Foamed polystyrene」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="88">
<j>コップ：露店での販売では紙コップが用いられる場合がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cup: For sale by street stall, paper cups are sometimes used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cup: street stalls also sometimes use paper cups.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cup: street stalls also sometimes use paper cups.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>スムージーに近い、シロップや果汁の多い物もガラスコップ（グラス）に盛られる場合がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Smoothie-like shaved ice containning a lot of syrup or fruit juice is sometimes put in glass cup.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Smoothie-like shaved ice containning a lot of syrup or fruit juice is sometimes put in a glass cup.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Smoothie-like shaved ice containing a lot of syrup or fruit juice is sometimes put in a glass cup.</e>
<cmt>「containning」→「containing」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>かき氷器</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ice shaving machine</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ice shaving machine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ice shaving machine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="90">
<j>天然氷を刃物の刃先で削ぎ落としたのが始まりとされ、この方法は現代でも日本料理で用いられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is told that the origin of shaved ice is natural ice shaved with the blade of cutting tool, and this method is used in Japanese cooking even today.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The origin of shaved ice is natural ice shaved with the blade of a cutting tool, and this method is used in Japanese food preparation even today.</e>
<cmt>wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The origin of shaved ice is natural ice shaved with the blade of a cutting tool, and this method is used in Japanese food preparation even today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>さらに簡便な方法としては、野菜を薄切りにするスライサーを用いても同様のことができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a simpler way, we can use a slicer for slicing vegetable to do the similar job.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For a simpler way, we can use a vegetable slicer to do a similar job.</e>
<cmt>wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For a simpler way, we can use a vegetable slicer to do a similar job.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>その後、鉋の刃を上にしたカツオブシを削る鰹箱（かつばこ）、または前述のスライサーのような状態にした大鉋の上で滑り止めとして布巾などを被せた氷を滑らせ、削り落ちてきたものをすくうようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, it is changed to slide ice, which is covered with a dish towel in order to prevent sliping, on a katsubako (Japanese food slicer) for slicing dried bonito of which blade of plane is directed upward or a large plane placed in same condition as that of above-mentioned slicer and dropped shaved ice is scooped.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, it is changed to slide ice, which is covered with a dish towel to prevent sliping, on a katsubako (Japanese food slicer) normally used for slicing dried bonito of which blade of plane is facing upward or a large plane can be used placed in same position as that of the above-mentioned slicer and dropped shaved ice is scooped up.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, it is changed to slide ice, which is covered with a dish towel to prevent slipping, on a katsubako (Japanese food slicer) normally used for slicing dried bonito of which blade of plane is facing upward or a large plane can be used placed in same position as that of the above-mentioned slicer and dropped shaved ice is scooped up.</e>
<cmt>「sliping」→「slipping」としました。。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>1887年（明治20年）に氷商の村上半三郎が特許を取得して公に知られるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1887, Hanzaburo MURAKAMI, who was an ice trader obtained a patent and became publicly known.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1887, Hanzaburo MURAKAMI, who was an ice trader obtained a patent and became publicly known.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1887, Hanzaburo MURAKAMI, who was an ice trader obtained a patent and became publicly known.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="94">
<j>現代のかき氷器は鉋状の刃のついた台座の上で氷の塊が回転し、氷をスライス状に削りながら氷の塊を繰り下げていく仕組みをもつ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Present ice shaving machine has such mechanism that a block of ice rotates on a pedestal equipped with saw-like blade and it is shaved like slicing and the block of ice is pressed down.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A present ice shaving machine rotates a block of ice on a pedestal and the block of ice is shaved as it is being pressed down against a saw-like blade.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A contemporary ice shaving machine rotates a block of ice on a pedestal, and the block of ice is shaved as it is pressed down against a saw-like blade.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>氷削機、かき氷メーカー、フラップメーカー、ブロックアイスシェーバー、ブロックアイススライサーなどと呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is called ice shaving machine, shaved ice maker, flap maker, block ice shaver, or block ice slicer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is called an ice shaving machine, shaved ice maker, flap maker, ice block shaver, or ice block slicer.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity and grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is called an ice shaving machine, shaved ice maker, furappu meka (frappe maker), ice block shaver, or ice block slicer.</e>
<cmt>「flap maker」→「furappu meka (frappe maker)」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>英名はIce block shaver。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">English name is ice block shaver.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">English name is ice block shaver.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The English name for this machine is ice block shaver.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="97">
<j>かき氷器には粉雪のように細かい粒子のかき氷を削り出すことができるものと氷の薄い切片状のかき氷になるものがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are two types of ice shaving machine; one is for shaving ice to produce very fine particles of ice like powder snow and the other to produce small chips of ice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are two types of ice shaving machines; one is for shaving ice to produce very fine particles of ice like powdered snow and the other to produce small chips of ice.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are two types of ice shaving machines; one is for shaving ice to produce very fine particles of ice like powdered snow and the other to produce small chips of ice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>この要因として用いる氷の違いが挙げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The cause of this difference is difference in ice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The cause of this difference is the difference in the ice.</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The cause of this difference is the difference in the ice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>近年、小型で高性能ながらアイスストッカー付きのキューブアイス用製氷機が出回ってきたことや各種電化製品の普及により、かつては氷を入手するために必須であった氷商への依存度が激減した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Recently, the degree of dependence to ice trader, that was indispensable for obtaining ice in the past, drastically decreased because of penetration of small and high performance ice-making machine for cube ice equipped with an ice stocker and various consumer electric products.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Recently, the degree of dependence on ice trades, that was indispensable for obtaining ice in the past, drastically decreased because of newly developed small, high performance ice-making machines for ice cubes equipped with an ice stocker and various othe relectric consumer products.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Recently, the degree of dependence on ice trades, that was indispensable for obtaining ice in the past, drastically decreased because of newly developed small, high performance ice-making machines for ice cubes equipped with an ice stocker and various other electric consumer products.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>加えて重さ一貫（約3.75キロ）の角氷と言われるブロックアイスを扱う氷商も減少傾向にあることから、長い時間をかけて空気を抜きながら凍らせた角氷の入手は難しくなってきている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, the number of ice traders, who handle block ice called kaku gori (literally, square ice) weighing one kan (approximately, 3.75 kilogram) has been decreasing, it became difficult to obtain kakugori produced spending long time and taking away air.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, the number of ice traders, who handle block ice called kaku gori (literally, square ice) weighing one kan (approximately, 3.75 kilogram) has been decreasing, and it became difficult to obtain and producing kakugori took a long time.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, the number of ice traders, who handle block ice called kaku gori (literally, square ice) weighing one kan (approximately, 3.75 kilogram) has been decreasing, and it became difficult to obtain and producing kaku gori took a long time.</e>
<cmt>「kakugori」→「kaku gori」にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>さらに天然氷のように冬の間に暴露で凍らせておき需要があるまで氷室（ひむろ）でストックできる生産者も減ってきている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, the number of ice manufacturers who can produce ice by freezing water in winter by exposing same as natural ice and stock them in an icehouse until demand occurs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, the number of ice manufacturers who can produce ice from naturally freezing water in winter the same way as natural ice forms and and then stocking the blocks of ice in an icehouse until demand occurs, have declined.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, the number of ice manufacturers who can produce ice from naturally freezing water in winter the same way as natural ice forms and then stocking the blocks of ice in an icehouse until demand occurs, have declined.</e>
<cmt>不要な「and」を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>このためかき氷器の製造メーカーはブロックアイス用からキューブアイス用に移行し、粉雪状のかき氷と薄い切片状のかき氷に二分された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, manufacturers of ice shaving machine shifted from machine for block ice to machin for cube ice and shaved ice is devided into powder snow-like one and small chips of ice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, manufacturers of the ice shaving machine shifted from machine for block ice to machines for producing cubed ice and shaved ice is divided into two types, powdered snow and small chips of ice.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, manufacturers of the ice shaving machine shifted from machine for block ice to machines for producing cubed ice and shaved ice is divided into two types, powdered snow and small chips of ice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="103">
<j>業務用は、古くは鋳物のフレームに大きな手回しハンドルが本体横に付いたものが主流であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For commercially used machines in the past, machine having a frame of cast iron equipped with a hand-driven handle on the side was the main stream.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For commercially used machines in the past, machines having a frame of cast iron equipped with a hand-driven handle on the side were main stream.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For commercially used machines in the past, machines having a frame of cast iron equipped with a hand-driven handle on the side were main stream.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>後に氷を回転させるモーターが剥き出しで取り付けられているものに代わっていき、近年ではモーターを内蔵したスタイルに移行している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, it was changed to one equipped with bare motor that rotates ice and, in recent years, it was shifted to one with a built-in motor.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, it was changed to one equipped with an exposed motor that rotates ice and, in recent years, it shifted to one with a built-in motor.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, it was changed to one equipped with an exposed motor that rotates ice and, in recent years, it shifted to one with a built-in motor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>併せてキューブアイス用のかき氷器が製造され、粉雪状ではなく細かい氷の粒のかき氷が普及するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Parallelly, ice shaving machines for cube ice were produced resulting in penetration of shaved ice not in the powder snow-like form but fine chip-like shaved ice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ice shaving machines for ice cubes were produced resulting in shaved ice, not in the powder snow-like form, but fine chip-like ice.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ice shaving machines for ice cubes were produced resulting in shaved ice, not in the powder snow-like form, but fine chip-like ice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>現在でも手回し式のものはレトロ調として販売されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even today, hand-driven type is on market as retro-style item.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even today, the hand-driven type is on market as retro-style item.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even today, the hand-driven type is on market as retro-style item.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="107">
<j>家庭用は手回しのものが多く、専用の円筒形の製氷皿で作った氷を用いる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For home use, hand-driven type is popular and it uses ice produced using a dedicated cylindrical ice tray.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For home use, the hand-driven type is popular and it uses ice produced using a dedicated cylindrical ice tray.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For home use, the hand-driven type is popular and it uses ice produced using a dedicated cylindrical ice tray.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>近年では一般的な製氷皿で作るキューブアイスを用いてもかき氷を作ることができる機種がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In recent years, models, that can produce shaved ice using cube ice made by usual ice tray, is available.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In recent years, models, that can produce shaved ice using ice cubes made in the usual ice tray, is available.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nowadays, models that can produce shaved ice using ice cubes made in the usual ice tray are available.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="109">
<j>主に子供向けとして需要が高いため、安全面から金属製の刃は用いられないことも多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As demand is high for use by children, many machines do not use metal blace for safety sake.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As demand is high for use by children, many machines do not use a metal brace for safety sake.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As demand is high for use by children, many machines do not use a metal brace for safety sake.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>またペンギンや白熊など寒冷地の動物を模した形状のものも発売されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, machine in the shape of animal in the cold district such as penguin or polar bear is on market.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, machines in the shape of animals that live in the Artic regions such as penguins or polar bears are on the market.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, machines in the shape of animals that live in the arctic regions such as penguins or polar bears are on the market.</e>
<cmt>「Artic」→「arctic」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Miscellaneous</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Miscellaneous</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Miscellaneous</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="111">
<j>夏氷の日：日本かき氷協会が、かき氷の別名である夏氷の読みであるなつごおりを7, 2, 5と語呂合わせして7月25日を夏氷の日として制定。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Natsugori no hi (day of summer ice): Nihon Kakigori Kyokai (literally, Nihon Shaved Ice Association) established July 25 as the Natsugori no hi by making sound connection between natsugori (another name of shaved ice) and 7, 2, 5.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Natsugori no hi (day of summer ice): Nihon Kakigori Kyokai (literally, Nihon Shaved Ice Association) established July 25 as the Natsugori no hi by making sound connection between natsugori (another name of shaved ice) and 7, 2, 5.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Natsugori no hi (day of summer ice): Nihon Kakigori Kyokai (literally, Nihon Shaved Ice Association) established July 25 as the Natsugori no hi by making sound connection between natsugori (another name of shaved ice) and 7, 2, 5.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="112">
<j>冷蔵庫の発達しない時期などは衛生的に優れないことがあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before refrigerator was developed, shaved ice was sometimes not good from hygenic point of view.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Beforethe refrigerator was developed, shaved ice was sometimes not hygenic.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before the refrigerator was developed, shaved ice was sometimes not hygienic.</e>
<cmt>「hygenic」→「hygienic」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="113">
<j>水を凍らす前に水に砂糖を溶かしてから凍らすと出来た氷がサラサラになっておいしくなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If sugar is dissolveed in water before freezing water, produced ice becomes smooth and dry and more tasty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If sugar is dissolveed in the water before freezing it, the ice becomes smoother and drier and more tasty.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If sugar is dissolved in the water before freezing it, the ice becomes smoother, drier and more tasty.</e>
<cmt>「and」→「,」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>各国のかき氷</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shaved ice in various countries</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shaved ice in various countries</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shaved ice in various countries</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="114">
<j>日本より暑い時期が長い台湾やフィリピンでは、年中食べられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shaved ice is eaten in Taiwan and Puilippines, where the hot period is longer than in Japan, throughout the year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shaved ice is eaten in Taiwan and the Philippines, where the hot season is longer than in Japan, and often throughout the year.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shaved ice is eaten in Taiwan and the Philippines, where the hot season is longer than in Japan, and often throughout the year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>中国語では「」（バオビン、、）という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Chinese, it is called &apos;&apos;(バオビン、、)</e>
<cmt>中国語の読みの部分は原文のとおりに表記しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Chinese, it is called &apos;&apos;(バオビン、、)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Chinese, it is called &quot;Bao Bing&quot;.</e>
<cmt>中国語を英語表記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="116">
<j>台湾語では「」（ツォーピン）ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Taiwanese, it is also called &apos;&apos;(ツォーピン)</e>
<cmt>台湾語の読みの部分は原文のとおりに表記しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Taiwanese, it is also called &apos;&apos;(ツォーピン)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Taiwanese, it is also called &quot;Tsua Bing&quot;.</e>
<cmt>台湾語を英語表記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="117">
<j>アメリカではshaved ice（剃り氷）、snow cone（円錐形の雪）と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the State, its is called shaved ice or snow cone.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the States, its is called shaved ice or snow cone.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the United States, its is called shaved ice or snow cone.</e>
<cmt>「the States」→「the United States」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="118">
<j>芒果冰（マングォビン、）：2004年（平成16年）ごろから流行した、マンゴーの切り身をたっぷり乗せ、マンゴーシロップと加糖練乳をかけたもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">芒果冰(マングォビン、): It became popular since around 2004; it is prepared by putting a lot of cut mango and mango syrup and sweetened condensed milk.</e>
<cmt>芒果冰（マングォビン、）の英語表記を確認できないため、原文のとおりに表記しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">芒果冰(マングォビン、): It became popular since around 2004; it is prepared by adding a lot of cut mango and mango syrup and sweetened condensed milk.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mango Bing (芒果冰, Mango ice): It became popular since around 2004; it is prepared by adding a lot of cut mango and mango syrup and sweetened condensed milk.</e>
<cmt>英語表記が確認できず仮訳のため、「英語表記、漢字、英訳」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="119">
<j>台湾台北市の「冰館」（ピングァン、）という店から台湾各地に広がり、日本にも上陸した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It outspreaded from a shop named &apos;冰館&apos;(ピングァン、) in Taipei City in Taiwan to various places in Taiwan and also landed in Japan.</e>
<cmt>「冰館」（ピングァン、）英語表記を確認できないため、原文のとおりに表記しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It spread from a shop named &apos;冰館&apos;(ピングァン、) in Taipei City in Taiwan to various places in Taiwan and also landed in Japan.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It spread from a shop named &quot;Ping Guan&quot; (冰館, Ice Monster) in Taipei City in Taiwan to various places in Taiwan and also landed in Japan.</e>
<cmt>英語表記が確認できず仮訳のため、「英語表記、漢字、英訳」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="120">
<j>マンゴーだけでなく、イチゴと2種盛り合わせたものも人気がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One with two kinds of fruits, not only mango but also strawberry, is also well accepted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One with two kinds of fruit, not only mango, but also strawberries, is also well accepted.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One with two kinds of fruit, not only mango, but also strawberries, is also well accepted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="121">
<j>また、水ではなく、牛乳を氷らせたもので作るタイプのかき氷「雪花冰（シュエファービン、）」もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is also 雪花冰(シュエファービン、) which is prepared not with ice from water but frozen milk.</e>
<cmt>「雪花冰（シュエファービン、）の英語表記を確認できないため、原文のとおりに表記しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is also 雪花冰(シュエファービン、) prepared from frozen milk rather than ice made from water.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is also &quot;Xue-hua-bing&quot; (雪花冰, literally, ice of snow flakes) prepared from frozen milk rather than ice made from water.</e>
<cmt>「英語表記、漢字、英訳」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="122">
<j>ちなみに台湾のかき氷（）は、上に乗せる具の名前の後に「冰（氷）」という字を付けていう事がふつうである</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For your information, shaved ice is named in Taiwan by adding the character &quot;冰(氷)&quot; after the name of material that is put on the top.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For your information, shaved ice is named in Taiwan by adding the character &quot;冰(氷)&quot; after the name of ingredients listed on top.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For your information, shaved ice is named in Taiwan by adding the character &quot;冰(氷)&quot; after the name of ingredients listed on top.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="123">
<j>八寶冰（バーバオビン、）：かき氷の上に甘い煮豆をはじめ、多くの具を盛り合わせた物をものを台湾では「八寶冰（八宝氷）」という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">八寶冰(バーバオビン、): Shaved ice having toppings of various materials starting with sweet boiled beans is called &quot;八寶冰(八宝氷) in &quot;Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>「八寶冰（バーバオビン、）」、「八寶冰（八宝氷）」の英語表記を確認できないため、原文のとおりに表記しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">八寶冰(バーバオビン、): Shaved ice having toppings of various materials starting with sweet boiled beans is called &quot;八寶冰(八宝氷) in &quot;Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Babao Bing (八寶冰, Eight Treasure Ice): Shaved ice having toppings of various materials starting with sweet boiled beans is called &quot;Babao bing (八寶冰 (八宝氷))&quot; in Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>「英語表記、漢字、英訳」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="124">
<j>好みで果肉、ジャム、蜜煮の果物、QQと呼ばれる弾力のある団子、ライスヌードル、ナッツ、加糖練乳、鶏卵などが選べる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In accordance with your taste, you can choose flesh of fruits, jam, fruits compote, resilient dumpling called QQ, rice noodle, nuts, sweetened condensed milk and egg.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to your taste, you can choose fruit pulp, jam, fruit compote, resilient dumplings called QQ, rice noodles, nuts, sweetened condensed milk and eggs.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to your taste, you can choose fruit pulp, jam, fruit compote, resilient dumplings called QQ, rice noodles, nuts, sweetened condensed milk and eggs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="125">
<j>刀削冰（ダオシャオビン、）：台湾の別のタイプのかき氷。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">刀削冰(ダオシャオビン、): Another type of shaved ice in Taiwan</e>
<cmt>刀削冰（ダオシャオビン、）の英語表記を確認できないため、原文のとおりに表記しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">刀削冰(ダオシャオビン、): Another type of shaved ice in Taiwan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dao Siao Bing (刀削冰, knife shaved ice): Another type of shaved ice in Taiwan</e>
<cmt>「英語表記、漢字、英訳」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="126">
<j>手で包丁を持って削るので、粗い氷に近いものができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As ice is shaved with a knife hold in hand, coarse ice is obtained.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As ice is shaved with a hand held knife, coarse ice is obtained.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As ice is shaved with a hand held knife, coarse ice is obtained.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="127">
<j>各種シロップと練乳をかけて食べる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is eaten after pouring various syrup and condensed milk.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is eaten after pouring various syrups and condensed milk.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is eaten after pouring various syrups and condensed milk.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="128">
<j>ピンス（朝鮮語：氷水、）：大韓民国のかき氷。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">ピンス(朝鮮語:氷水、): Shaved ice of the Republic of Korea</e>
<cmt>ピンス（朝鮮語：氷水、）の英語表記を確認できないため、原文のとおりに表記しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">ピンス(朝鮮語:氷水、): Shaved ice in the Republic of Korea</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bing Su (氷水&quot; in Korean): Shaved ice in the Republic of Korea</e>
<cmt>「英語表記、漢字」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="129">
<j>代表的なのがパッピンス（）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Representative one is パッピンス().</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処朝鮮語の部分は英語表記を確認できないため、原文のとおりに表記しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One example is パッピンス().</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One example is Pa Bing Su.</e>
<cmt>英語表記にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="130">
<j>代表的なのがパッピンス（）で、名前には小豆（パッ）が付いているが、日本の氷小豆とは異なる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although its name includes red bean (パッ), it is different from kori azuki (shaved ice with sweetened red beans).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処朝鮮語の部分は英語表記を確認できないため、原文のとおりに表記しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although its name includes red bean (パッ), it is different from kori azuki (shaved ice with sweetened red beans).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although its name includes red bean (Pa), it is different from kori azuki (shaved ice with sweetened red beans).</e>
<cmt>英語表記にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="131">
<j>湾の八寶氷同様に、小豆餡、缶詰フルーツ、餅などの具が豊富に盛られおり、味付けによくきな粉を使う点と、ピビンパ同様に食べる前に徹底的に混ぜるのが特徴的。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Same as 八寶冰 in Taiwan, plenty of materials such as red bean jam, canned fruits and rice cake are put and characteristic points are that soybean flour is often used for seasoning and it is completely paddled before eating same as in ピビンパ.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処朝鮮語、台湾語の部分は英語表記を確認できないため、原文のとおりに表記しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Same as 八寶冰 in Taiwan, plenty of materials such as red bean jam, canned fruits, and rice cake are included and characteristically soybean flour is often used for seasoning and it is completely paddled before eating same as in ピビンパ.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Same as Babao Bing in Taiwan, plenty of materials such as red bean jam, canned fruits, and rice cake are included and characteristically soybean flour is often used for seasoning and it is completely paddled before eating same as in Bibimpa (rice with beef and vegetables in a hot stone bowl).</e>
<cmt>英語表記にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="132">
<j>他に小豆抜きで、フルーツを乗せたクヮイルピンス（果実氷水、）など、いろいろな種類がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, there are various types such as クヮイルピンス (shaved ice with fruits) that does not contain red bean but includes lot of fruits.</e>
<cmt>クヮイルピンスの英語表記を確認できないため、原文のとおりに表記しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, there are various types such as クヮイルピンス (shaved ice with fruit) that do not contain red beans, but includes lots of fruit.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, there are various types such as Kwa-il Ping Su (果実氷水、 shaved ice with fruit) that do not contain red beans, but includes lots of fruit.</e>
<cmt>「英語表記、漢字、英訳」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="133">
<j>ハロハロ (Halohalo) ：フィリピン風の、豆の餡、ナタ・デ・ココ、アイスクリームなど、豊富な具を乗せたかき氷。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Halohalo: Philippine style shaved ice with plenty of toppings such as bean jam, nata de coco and ice cream.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Halohalo: Philippine style shaved ice with plenty of toppings such as bean jam, nata de coco and ice cream.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Halohalo: Philippine style shaved ice with plenty of toppings such as bean jam, nata de coco and ice cream.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="134">
<j>Halohaloはタガログ語でごちゃまぜを意味する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Halohalo means &quot;mixed&quot; in Tagalog.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Halohalo means &quot;mixed&quot; in Tagalog.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Halohalo means &quot;mixed&quot; in Tagalog.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="135">
<j>タッチェー：ベトナムのかき氷。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">タッチェー: Vetnamese shaved ice</e>
<cmt>タッチェーの英語表記を確認できないため、原文のとおりに表記しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">タッチェー: Vetnamese shaved ice</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thach che: Vietnamese shaved ice</e>
<cmt>英語表記にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="136">
<j>緑豆やココナッツ入りの白玉ぜんざい（チェー/che）がかき氷の上にかかっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shiratama zenzai (rice cake and Icecream with red bean sauce) containing mung beans and coconut (che) is poured onto shaved ice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shiratama zenzai (rice cake and Icecream with red bean sauce) containing mung beans and coconut (che) is poured onto shaved ice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shiratama zenzai (che) (rice cake and ice cream with red bean sauce) containing mung beans and coconut is poured onto shaved ice.</e>
<cmt>「(che)」の位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="137">
<j>シーフードかき氷：台湾には塩味のエビなどシーフードをトッピングしたかき氷を出す店がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shaved ice with sea food: In Taiwan, there is a shop that serves shaved ice with topping of sea food such as salty shrimps.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shaved ice with sea food: In Taiwan, there is a shop that serves shaved ice with sea food toppings such as salty shrimp.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shaved ice with sea food: In Taiwan, there is a shop that serves shaved ice with sea food toppings such as salty shrimp.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="138">
<j>コバルトアイス：蜂楽饅頭が出しているかき氷。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cobalt ice: Shaved ice sold by Horaku Manju</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cobalt ice: Shaved ice sold by Horaku Manju</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cobalt ice: Shaved ice sold by Horaku Manju Ltd.</e>
<cmt>蜂楽饅頭→Horaku Manju→Minamata Horaku Manju Ltd.[http://www.houraku.co.jp/kaisyagaiyou.html]</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="139">
<j>コバルトミルクと呼ばれる場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sometimes, it is called cobalt milk.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sometimes, it is called cobalt milk.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sometimes, it is called cobalt milk.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="140">
<j>主に熊本県をはじめとした九州付近では知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is know in Kyushu starting with Kumamoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is well known in Kyushu starting with Kumamoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is well known in Kyushu starting with Kumamoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="141">
<j>ブルーハワイと加糖練乳をかけたもの</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prepared by pouring blue Hawaii and sweetened condense milk</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prepared by pouring blue Hawaian, sweetened condensed milk</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prepared by pouring Blue Hawaii syrup, sweetened condensed milk</e>
<cmt>「blue Hawaian」→「Blue Hawaii syrup」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Ligar(id:12623), Tangobot(id:47812), 無責任飛行物体(id:156883), Takoradee(id:82103), こたつ狼(id:27622), Ypacaraí(id:11031), Nnh(id:474), 遊翔(id:153881), 0null0(id:582), Hhaithait(id:37092), Ainda há muito a cobra(id:231267), Lupinoid(id:68), Koba-chan(id:860), Insidewest(id:212859), Charon(id:9162), Sutou(id:32), やきとり(id:126941), 南大門で会いましょう(id:189701), 日本一弱い男(id:92046), Edogawa(id:9879), Tamago915(id:11009), Point136(id:211299), Yas(id:739), 赤鉛筆(id:2434), Aska27(id:9690), Sampo(id:1041), PuzzletChung(id:13816), Bankokuya(id:91191), Hari-ruri(id:300294), カタ(id:156632), ヴォルフラム(id:228220), クロウ(id:21337), 中部コーポレーション(id:133734), たね(id:10372), しるふぃ(id:11247), マクガイア(id:33346), MlolM(id:24777), Bloodserver(id:33911), HALPHA(id:51616), Aoiya(id:44787), 2for6(id:83303), MH(id:1586), ウェルワィ(id:15692), Shinkansen(id:13703), Hajimari(id:205606), 竃馬(id:102733), Doratea(id:37080), リトルデビル(id:34455), YurikBot(id:18605), Hadge(id:9555), Ribbon(id:172), 蕎麦茶(id:129703), Nekosuki600(id:21263), Baffclan(id:499), Blackdream(id:139776), Corwin(id:973), ばろむわん(id:262), Plemling(id:90161), SieBot(id:126695), ホイップ(id:44812), Wybot(id:81801), 1029man(id:93235), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>