<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>鰻丼</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Unadon or Unagi-donburi (a bowl of boiled rice topped with broiled eel)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unadon or Unagi-donburi (a bowl of boiled rice topped with broiled eel)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unadon or Unagi-donburi (a bowl of boiled rice topped with broiled eel)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>鰻丼（うなどん、うなぎどんぶり）は、丼に入れた飯の上にウナギの蒲焼を乗せ、タレと好みによりサンショウの粉を振りかけた日本料理。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Unadon or unagi-donburi is a Japanese cuisine made of boiled rice in a bowl topped with kabayaki (broiled eel) and sprinkled with tare (a special sauce for broiled eel) and, if you like, with some powder of sansyo (pepper).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unadon, or unagi-donburi, is a Japanese cuisine consisting of boiled rice in a bowl topped with kabayaki (broiled eel) and sprinkled with tare (a special sauce for broiled eel) and, if you like, some powdered sansyo (pepper).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unadon, or unagi-donburi, is a Japanese cuisine consisting of boiled rice in a bowl topped with kabayaki (broiled eel) and poured tare (a special sauce for broiled eel) on it, and as one&apos;s preference, some powdered sansho (Sichuan pepper) added on top.</e>
<cmt>sprinkled→poured, sansyo (pepper)→sansho (Sichuan pepper)と修正しました。if you like→as one&apos;s preference,added on top を挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>山椒は、消化を助ける効果があるとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sansho pepper is believed to be effective in promoting digestion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sansho pepper is believed to be effective in promoting digestion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sansho pepper is believed to be effective in helping digestion.</e>
<cmt>promoting→helping</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>また、泥臭さを消し、脂の多い鰻をさっぱりと食べることが出来る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It also removes smelling of mud and makes the taste of fatty eel rather simple to eat.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It also removes the muddy smell and makes the taste of fatty eel rather simple to eat.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It also removes the muddy smell and makes the taste of fatty eel rather simple to eat.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>タレは、醤油と砂糖を主に作られるが、各店は門外不出の秘伝のタレとして作り方に工夫を凝らしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tare sauce for unadon or unagi-donburi is made from soy sauce and sugar, but its ingenious recipe is traditionally and secretly reserved in each shop.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tare sauce for unadon or unagi-donburi is made from soy sauce and sugar, but its ingenious recipe is traditionally and secretly reserved in each shop.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tare sauce for unadon or unagi-donburi is mainly made from soy sauce and sugar, but its ingenious recipe is traditionally and secretly reserved in each shop.</e>
<cmt>mainly を挿入して補強しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>このタレは、まず御飯に掛け、鰻の蒲焼を乗せた後に再度掛けるのが一般的である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Usually, this tare sauce is first sprinkled on the plain boiled rice and then sprinked again after putting broiled eel on it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Usually, the tare sauce is first sprinkled on the plain boiled rice and then sprinkled again after the broiled eel is placed on it.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Usually, the tare sauce is first poured on the plain boiled rice and then poured again after the broiled eel is placed on it.</e>
<cmt>sprinkled→poured</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>山椒の粉は最後に振り掛ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Powdered pepper may be sprinkled at the last.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Powdered pepper may be sprinkled as a finishing touch.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sansho powder may be sprinkled on top at the end.</e>
<cmt>Powdered pepper→Sansho powder,on top を挿入し、as a finishing touch→at the end と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>「俗事百工起源(1885)宮川政運」によると、堺町(現在の東京人形町)で大久保今助がこの鰻丼を考え出したとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Zokuji Hyakko Kigen (1885) Masayasu MIYAGAWA&quot; (literally, the &quot;Origins of Mundane Affairs and Crafts and Arts written in 1885 by Masayasu MIYAGAWA,&quot;) unadon or unagi-donburi was said to have been devised by Imasuke OKUBO in Sakai-cho (current Ningyo-cho in Tokyo.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Zokuji Hyakko Kigen (1885) Masayasu MIYAGAWA&quot; (literally, the &quot;Origins of Mundane Affairs and Crafts and Arts written in 1885 by Masayasu MIYAGAWA,&quot;) unadon (or unagi-donburi) was said to have been devised by Imasuke OKUBO in Sakai-cho (the present-day Ningyo-cho, Tokyo).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Zokuji Hyakko Kigen (1885) Masayasu MIYAGAWA&quot; (literally, the &quot;Origins of Mundane Affairs and Crafts and Arts written in 1885 by Masayasu MIYAGAWA,&quot;), unadon (or unagi-donburi) was said to have been devised by Imasuke OKUBO in Sakai-cho (the present-day Ningyo-cho, Tokyo).</e>
<cmt>カンマを挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>この御飯にタレが染込んだ味はこの芝居町で大人気となり、葺屋町にある大野屋が「元祖鰻めし」という看板で売り出したのが最初だと言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The taste of boiled rice with the tare sauce seeped in it was so popularly liked in this Shibai-cho area (including Sakai-cho), and Onoya in Fukiya-cho (a part of Shibai-cho) was believed to have been an originator of this dish since it started its sale under the catchword &quot;Ganso Unagi-meshi&quot; (the originator of a dish of broiled eel on boiled rice.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The taste of boiled rice with the tare sauce seeped in it was so popular in the Shibai-cho area (including Sakai-cho), and Onoya in Fukiya-cho (a part of Shibai-cho) was believed to have been an originator of this dish since it started being sold under the catch phrase &quot;Ganso Unagi-meshi&quot; (the originator of a dish of broiled eel on boiled rice).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The taste of boiled rice with the tare sauce seeped in it became so popular in the Shibai-cho area, and it is said that Onoya in Fukiya-cho as the origin started selling it under the catch phrase, &quot;Ganso Unagi-meshi&quot; (the originator of a dish of broiled eel on boiled rice).</e>
<cmt>was→became,これらの記述、(including Sakai-cho) (a part of Shibai-cho)は必要ないと思われ削除し、修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>近世風俗史の基本文献とされている守貞謾稿によると、鰻飯は「鰻丼飯」の略。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Unagi-meshi is an abbreviation of &quot;unagi donburi meshi&quot; (&quot;a bowl of boiled rice topped with broiled eel,&quot;) according to Morisada Manko (a kind of encyclopedia of folkways and other affairs in the Edo Period written by Morisada KITAGAWA) which is regarded as a basic document for the history of early modern folkways.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unagi-meshi is an abbreviation for &quot;unagi donburi meshi (a bowl of boiled rice topped with broiled eel,)&quot; according to Morisada Manko (a kind of encyclopedia of folkways and other affairs in the Edo period, written by Morisada KITAGAWA), which is regarded as a basic document on the history of early modern folkways.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unagi-meshi is an abbreviation for &quot;unagi donburi meshi (a bowl of boiled rice topped with broiled eel),&quot; according to Morisada Manko (a kind of encyclopedia of folkways and other affairs in the Edo period, written by Morisada KITAGAWA), which is regarded as a basic document on the history of early modern folkways.</e>
<cmt>カッコ内のカンマを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>明治に入る頃まで「どんぶり」と言えば、この「鰻丼」を指した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before entering the Meiji Period, the term &quot;donburi&quot; (&quot;a bowl&quot;) meant this &quot;unagi donburi&quot; (&quot;a bowl of boiled rice topped with broiled eel.&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prior to the Meiji period, the term &quot;donburi (bowl)&quot; meant &quot;unagi donburi (a bowl of boiled rice topped with broiled eel).&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prior to the Meiji period, the term &quot;donburi (bowl)&quot; meant &quot;unagi donburi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>(a bowl of boiled rice topped with broiled eel)を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>また、このときに割り箸が登場した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In those days, waribashi (disposable wooden chopsticks) appeared.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In those days, waribashi (disposable wooden chopsticks) appeared.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, in those days, waribashi (splittable wooden chopsticks) were introduced.</e>
<cmt>Also を挿入し、カッコ内を修正しました。 appeared→were introduced</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>現在も「鰻飯」という言葉を使う地域や店舗がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even today, the term &quot;unagi meshi&quot; is used in some shops and areas.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even today, the term &quot;unagi meshi&quot; is used in some shops and areas.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even today, the term &quot;unagi meshi&quot; is used in some shops and areas.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>鰻重との違い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Difference between unadon (or unagi-donburi) and unaju:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The difference between unadon (or unagi-donburi) and unaju</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The difference between unadon (or unagi-donburi) and unaju</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="16">
<j>「鰻重丼」の略である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Unaju is an abbreviation of &quot;unaju donburi.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unaju is an abbreviation for &quot;unaju donburi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unaju is an abbreviation for &quot;unaju don.&quot;</e>
<cmt>unaju domburi→unaju don</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>用いる食器が重箱なら鰻重になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The dish contained in jubako (tiered food boxes) is called unaju.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The dish contained in jubako (tiered food boxes) is called unaju.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The dish contained in jubako (tiered food boxes) is called unaju.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>また、鰻と御飯が二重になっている物をそう呼ぶ事がある(器の底から「御飯-鰻-御飯-鰻と「重」ねる意味から)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sometimes, the dish is called unaju when broiled eels and boiled rice are served in double layer (in such alternate way of order from the bottom, as rice-eel-rice-eel.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Occasionally, the dish is called unaju when broiled eel and boiled rice are served in a double layer (in such an alternate order from the bottom, as rice-eel-rice-eel).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Occasionally, the dish is called unaju when broiled eel and boiled rice are served in a double layer (&quot;ju &apos;pile-up&apos;&quot;, in such an alternate order from the bottom, as rice-eel-rice-eel).</e>
<cmt>「重」の部分を挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>鰻の肝の入った肝吸いが付く事が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kimosui (a clear soup with eel&apos;s guts) are often served together.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kimosui (a clear soup with eel guts) is often served along with it.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kimosui (a clear soup with eel guts) is often served along with it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>重箱を使うものは大正時代に登場し、漆器を使うなど高級な印象を与えることを狙ったようで、現在でも鰻丼と比べると価格が高い傾向がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jubako boxes made its appearance in town in the Taisho Period using lacquer or others on a quest to create a luxury impression, so that even today unaju in a jubako box tends to be more expensive than unadon or unagi-donburi in a bowl.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The jubako box made its appearance in town during the Taisho period, and lacquer or other material was used in an effort to create the impression of luxury, so that even today unaju in a jubako box tends to be more expensive than unadon or unagi-donburi in a bowl.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The jubako box made its appearance during the Taisho period, and lacquer or other material was used in an effort to create the impression of luxury, so that even today unaju in a jubako box tends to be more expensive than unadon or unagi-donburi in a bowl.</e>
<cmt>in town を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="21">
<j>備考</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Remarks:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Remarks</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Remarks</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>浜名湖周辺では、ウナギの養殖が盛んであったこともあって代表的な名物となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These dishes of broiled eel have become a speciality of the Lake Hamana and its surrounding area, because cultivation of eels were once the prosperous industry of the area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These broiled-eel dishes have become a specialty of Lake Hamana and its surrounding area, because the cultivation of eel was once the prosperous industry of the area.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The broiled-eel dish has been a specialty of Lake Hamana and its surrounding area, since the cultivation of eel was once the prosperous industry of the area.</e>
<cmt>原文より修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="23">
<j>以前は東海道新幹線（一部山陽新幹線）車内でも、鰻丼に似た「うなぎ弁当」（通称「うな弁」）を販売していたが、現在では見かけない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Previously, &quot;unagi-bento&quot; (a box lunch containing broiled eel, commonly known as &quot;una-ben&quot;) used to be sold in Tokaido Shinkansen (partly in Sanyo Shinkansen,) which can no longer be seen today.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Previously, &quot;unagi-bento&quot; (a box lunch containing broiled eel, commonly known as &quot;una-ben&quot;) used to be sold on the Tokaido Shinkansen (and partly on the Sanyo Shinkansen), but that is no longer the case.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Previously, &quot;unagi-bento&quot; (a box lunch containing broiled eel, commonly known as &quot;una-ben&quot;) used to be sold on the Tokaido Shinkansen (and partly on the Sanyo Shinkansen), but that is no longer the case.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Asura2007(id:78364), QFJ(id:66538), マクガイア(id:33346), 水野白楓(id:22811), Araisyohei(id:378), Roger(id:9883), Kumatora(id:16941), Robbot(id:3063), Mercurius(id:57130), Revth(id:12179), Zerozeroman00(id:13101), Mishika(id:276), Simple-phrase(id:294736), 死郎(id:1683), るがこむ(id:181), Opponent(id:720), VolkovBot(id:105371), Moss(id:46638), Skink(id:11281), Muneco(id:30867), Loveless(id:129239), Knua(id:66861), Doe A Deer(id:237297), Point136(id:211299), 百楽天(id:5266), 竹麦魚(id:11012), Nipponcha3(id:189481), 1029man(id:93235), Hotei(id:7664), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>