<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>香木</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koboku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koboku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koboku (fragrant wood)</e>
<cmt>補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>香木（こうぼく）とは、心地よい芳香を持つ木材のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koboku is wood that gives off a pleasant aroma.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koboku is kind of wood that gives off a pleasant aroma.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koboku is kind of wood that gives off a pleasant aroma.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>沈香（ぢんすいこうぼく、または沈香、ぢんこう、ちんこう）と白檀（びゃくだん）が有名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jinsui Koboku (aka Jinko or Chiko) and Byakudan are famous.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jinsui Koboku (aka Jinko or Chiko) and Byakudan are famous.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jinsui Koboku (also known as Jinko or Chinko) and Byakudan are famous.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>香りのことを香という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japanese, Ko means aroma.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japanese, &quot;Ko&quot; means aroma.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japanese, &quot;Ko&quot; means aroma.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>薄片に削ったものを加熱して芳香を楽しむのに用いられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thinly split wood gives off an enjoyable aroma when heated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The thinly split wood, when heated, gives off an enjoyable aroma.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The thinly split wood, when heated, gives off an enjoyable aroma.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>白檀は熱することなく香るため、それ以外にも仏像などの彫刻や扇子や数珠などの材料として用いられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even when it is not heated, Byakudan gives off a pleasant smell; therefore, it is commonly used for sculptures of Buddha, folding fans and Juzu (rosary strings of beads).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even when it isn&apos;t heated, Byakudan gives off a pleasant smell; therefore, it&apos;s commonly used for sculptures of Buddha, folding fans and Juzu (strings of rosary beads).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even when it isn&apos;t heated, Byakudan gives off a pleasant smell; therefore, it&apos;s commonly used for sculptures of Buddha, folding fans and Juzu (strings of rosary beads).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>推古天皇3年（595年）4月に淡路島に香木が漂着したのが沈香に関する最古の記録であり、沈香の日本伝来といわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koboku dates back to April 595, when Jinsui koboku was washed ashore on Awajishima Island, and this is the oldest history reference to the koboku in Japanese culture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koboku dates back to April 595, when Jinsui koboku had washed ashore on Awajishima Island; this is the oldest historical reference to the koboku in Japanese culture.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koboku dates back to May (April in the old lunar calendar) 595, when Jinsui koboku had washed ashore on Awaji-shima Island; this is the oldest historical reference to the koboku in Japanese culture.</e>
<cmt>Awaji-shima Island としました。グレゴリオ暦に変更しましたが、後で「4月」という記述が話題になるため、（旧暦で4月）と付け足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>漂着木片を火の中にくべたところ、よい香りがした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is noted in a Japanese document that the koboku that washed ashore was thrown into a fire and a sweet aroma began to arise.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is noted in a Japanese document that the koboku that washed ashore was thrown into a fire and a sweet aroma began to arise.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is noted in a Japanese document that the koboku that washed ashore was thrown into a fire and a sweet aroma began to arise.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>その木を朝廷に献上したところ重宝されたという伝説が日本書紀にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The wood was presented to the court, and thereafter became an item of appreciation.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The wood was presented to the court, and thereafter became an item of appreciation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The wood was presented to the court, and thereafter became an item of appreciation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>東大寺正倉院宝物の中には長さ156cm、最大径43cm、重さ11.6kgという巨大な香木「黄熟香」（おうじゅくこう）が納められている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Todai-ji Temple Shosoin Homotsu, is a huge piece of koboku called Ojukoku, measuring 156cm long and 43cm wide at its widest and weighing 11.6kg.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Todai-ji Temple Shosoin Homotsu, is a large piece of koboku called Ojukoku, measuring 156cm long and 43cm wide at its widest and weighing 11.6kg.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the treasures at Todai-ji Temple Shoso-in Treasure Repository, is a large piece of koboku called &apos;Ojukuko,&apos; measuring 156 cm long and 43 cm wide at its widest and weighing 11.6 kg.</e>
<cmt>単位の前にスペースを追加しました。正倉院宝物→treasures at Todai-ji Temple Shoso-in Treasure Repository としました。Ojukuko に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>これは、鎌倉時代以前に日本に入ってきたと見られており、以後、権力者たちがこれを切り取っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is thought to have come into Japan before the Kamakura period, and thereafter, men of power tried to get pieces of this huge koboku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is thought to have come into Japan before the Kamakura period, and thereafter men of power tried to obtain pieces of it.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is thought to have come into Japan before the Kamakura period, and thereafter men of power tried to obtain pieces of it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>室町幕府8代将軍足利義政、織田信長、明治天皇の3人は付箋によって切り取り跡が明示されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The sections taken by the eighth Shogun Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA of the Muromachi Shogunate, Nobunaga ODA and Emperor Meiji are shown with a signage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sections taken by the eighth shogun Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA, of the Muromachi Shogunate, as well as Nobunaga ODA and Emperor Meiji, are shown with signage.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sections taken by the eighth shogun Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA, of the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), as well as Nobunaga ODA and Emperor Meiji, are shown with signage.</e>
<cmt>幕府　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>東大寺の記録によれば、信長は1寸四方2個を切り取ったとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Todai-ji Temple&apos;s record, Nobunaga cut off two pieces off the wood about 3cm around.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Todai-ji Temple&apos;s record, Nobunaga cut off two pieces off the wood, each about 3cm around.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Todai-ji Temple&apos;s record, Nobunaga cut off two pieces off the wood, each about 3 cm around.</e>
<cmt>単位の前にスペースを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>現在では、1992年（平成4年）4月に、全国薫物線香組合協議会が、上記の日本書紀の記述に基づいて沈水香木が伝来した4月と、「香」の字を分解した「一十八日」をあわせて4月18日を、「お香の日」として制定している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In April 1992, Zenkoku Takimono Senko Kumiai Kyogikai established April 18 as Incense Day, based on the notation in the Chronicle of Japan that Jinsui Koboku first washed ashore in Japan in April and disassembling the kanji &quot;香&quot; into 一十八日 (18th).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April 1992, Zenkoku Takimono Senko Kumiai Kyogikai established April 18 as Incense Day, based on the notation in the Chronicle of Japan that Jinsui Koboku first washed ashore in Japan in April and disassembling the kanji &quot;香&quot; into 一十八日 (eighteenth).</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April 1992, Zenkoku Takimono Senko Kumiai Kyogikai (National Council of Fragrant Woods and Incense Association) established April 18 as Incense Day, based on the notation in the Nihonshoki (Chronicle of Japan) that Jinsui koboku first washed ashore in Japan in April (in the old lunar calendar) and disassembling the kanji &apos;香&apos; into 一十八日 (eighteenth).</e>
<cmt>全国薫物線香組合協議会→National Council of Fragrant Woods and Incense Association　と補足を追加しました(定訳は不明です）。&quot; → &apos;　としました。4月　の後に（旧暦）を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 ドラムスコ(id:40234), ロリ(id:613), 0null0(id:582), Eskimbot(id:29676), Tgmsito(id:15714), Tiyoringo(id:70026), Aoiya(id:44787), Greenland4(id:114494), Hatsune(id:26654), 文姫(id:66661), ぎゅうひ(id:9206), Kenpei(id:11349), Corwin(id:973), YAMANEKO(id:66068), Tom-kitten(id:100275), Calvero(id:38360), 小太刀(id:18154), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>