<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>琴伝流</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kindenryu School</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kindenryu School</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinden School</e>
<cmt>ryu削除</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>琴伝流（きんでんりゅう）は、全国に40万人以上の会員と1万人以上の講師 (教育)陣を擁する日本最大の大正琴流派である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kindenryu school is the largest school of taishogoto (Taisho lyre) in Japan which have more than four hundred thousand members and more than ten thousand teachers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kindenryu school is the largest school of taishogoto (Taisho lyre) in Japan which have more than four hundred thousand members and more than ten thousand teachers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinden school is the largest school of taishogoto (Taisho lyre) in Japan which have more than four hundred thousand members and more than ten thousand teachers throughout Japan.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>（有）日本ヴァイオリン研究所大正琴全国普及会が運営し、組織の正式名称は琴伝流大正琴全国普及会。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is operated by Nihon Violin Kenkyusho Taishogoto Zenkoku Fukyukai and the official name of the organization is Kindenryu Taishogoto Zenkoku Fukyukai.</e>
<cmt>組織名の正規の英文の表記が確認できないため、ローマ字綴りで表記しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is operated by Nihon Violin Kenkyusho Taishogoto Zenkoku Fukyukai and the official name of the organization is Kindenryu Taishogoto Zenkoku Fukyukai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The school is operated by Nihon Violin Kenkyusho Taishogoto Zenkoku Fukyukai and the official name of the organization is Kindenryu Taishogoto Zenkoku Fukyukai (Extension Association of Kinden school of Taishogoto).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>本社所在地</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Address of the headquarters</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Address of the headquarters</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Head Office Address</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>郵便番号399-4117　長野県駒ヶ根市赤穂字福岡14番地545</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">14-545, Aza Fukuoka, Ako, Komagane City, Nagano Prefecture 399-4117</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">14-545, Aza Fukuoka, Ako, Komagane City, Nagano Prefecture 399-4117</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">14-545, Aza Fukuoka, Ako, Komagane City, Nagano Prefecture 399-4117</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>アクセス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Access</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Access</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Access</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>鉄道利用の場合</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By railway</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By railway</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By railway</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>東海旅客鉄道飯田線伊那福岡駅下車、徒歩約20分</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From Inafukuoka Station (Central Japan Railway Company (JR Central), Iida Line), approximately twenty minutes on foot</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From Inafukuoka Station (Central Japan Railway Company (JR Central), Iida Line), approximately twenty minutes on foot</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From Inafukuoka Station, Iida Line, Central Japan Railway Company (JR Central,, aka, JR Tokai), approximately twenty minutes on foot</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>自家用車利用の場合</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By private car</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By private car</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By car</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>中央自動車道駒ヶ根インターチェンジ下車、伊那広域農道を南下して約15分</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From Komagane Interchange, Chuo Expressway, approximately fifteen minutes by driving to the south on Ina Koiki Nodo route</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From Komagane Interchange, Chuo Expressway, approximately fifteen minutes driving south on Ina Koiki Nodo route</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the Komagane Interchange, Chuo Expressway, approximately fifteen minutes driving south on Ina Koiki Nodo route</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>全国各地の本部教室</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Classrooms operated by the headquarters in various places in Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Classrooms operated by headquarters in various places in Japan</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Classrooms operated by headquarters throughout Japan</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>※2005年4月現在</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">* As of April 2005</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">* As of April 2005</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">* As of April 2005</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>本社工場</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Headquarters plant</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Headquarters plant</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Head Office Factory</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>東北本部（〒980-0873 仙台市青葉区 (仙台市)広瀬町3番40号　高昇ビル2階）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tohoku Headquarters (Akashi Bldg. 2nd Floor, 3-40, Hirosecho, Aoba Ward, Sendai City, 980-0873)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tohoku Headquarters (Akashi Bldg. 2nd Floor, 3-40, Hirosecho, Aoba Ward, Sendai City, 980-0873)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tohoku Headquarters (Akashi Bldg. 2nd Floor, 3-40, Hirosecho, Aoba Ward, Sendai City, 980-0873)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>関東本部（〒192-0045 東京都八王子市大和田町四丁目7番8号）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanto Headquarters (7-8, Owadacho 4-chome, Hachioji City, Tokyo Prefecture 192-0045)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanto Headquarters (7-8, Owadacho 4-chome, Hachioji City, Tokyo Prefecture 192-0045)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanto Headquarters (7-8, Owadacho 4-chome, Hachioji City, Tokyo Prefecture 192-0045)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>東海本部（〒460-0022　名古屋市中区 (名古屋市)金山二丁目16番22号　守随ビル2階）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokai Headquarters (Shuzui Bldg. 2nd FLOOR, 16-22, Kanayama 2-chome, Naka Ward, Nagoya City, 460-0022)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokai Headquarters (Shuzui Bldg. 2nd FLOOR, 16-22, Kanayama 2-chome, Naka Ward, Nagoya City, 460-0022)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokai Headquarters (Shuzui Bldg. 2nd FLOOR, 16-22, Kanayama 2-chome, Naka Ward, Nagoya City, 460-0022)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>金沢会場（〒920-0855 金沢市武蔵町17-27）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanazawa Classroom (17-27, Musashimachi, Kanazawa City, 920-0855)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanazawa Classroom (17-27, Musashimachi, Kanazawa City, 920-0855)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanazawa Classroom (17-27, Musashimachi, Kanazawa City, 920-0855)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>関西本部（〒530-0056　大阪市北区 (大阪市)兎我野町15番13号　ミユキビル9階）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kansai Headquarters (Miyuki Bldg. 9th Floor, Toganocho, Kita Ward, Osaka City 530-0056)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kansai Headquarters (Miyuki Bldg. 9th Floor, Toganocho, Kita Ward, Osaka City 530-0056)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kansai Headquarters (Miyuki Bldg. 9th Floor, 15-13, Toganocho, Kita Ward, Osaka City 530-0056)</e>
<cmt>番地を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>京都会場（〒601-8468　京都市南区 (京都市)唐橋西平垣町1番地　中塚ビル3階）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Classroom (Nakatsuka Bldg. 3rd Floor, 1 Karahashi Nishi Hiragakicho, Minami Ward, Kyoto City, 601-8468)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Classroom (Nakatsuka Bldg. 3rd Floor, 1 Karahashi Nishi Hiragakicho, Minami Ward, Kyoto City, 601-8468)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Classroom (Nakatsuka Bldg. 3rd Floor, 1 Karahashi Nishi Hiragakicho, Minami Ward, Kyoto City, 601-8468)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>神戸会場（〒650-0022 神戸市中央区 (神戸市)元町通三丁目12番17号　マルシンビル4階）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kobe Classroom (Marushin Bldg. 4th Floor, 12-17, Motomachidori 3-chome, Chuo Ward, Kobe City, 650-0022)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kobe Classroom (Marushin Bldg. 4th Floor, 12-17, Motomachidori 3-chome, Chuo Ward, Kobe City, 650-0022)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kobe Classroom (Marushin Bldg. 4th Floor, 12-17, Motomachidori 3-chome, Chuo Ward, Kobe City, 650-0022)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>中国本部（〒700-0023　岡山市北区 (岡山市)駅前町二丁目2番4号　かもいビル1・2階）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chugoku Headquarters (Kamoi Bldg. 1st and 2nd Floors, 2-4, Ekimaecho 2-chome, Kita Ward, Okayama City, 700-0023)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chugoku Headquarters (Kamoi Bldg. 1st and 2nd Floors, 2-4, Ekimaecho 2-chome, Kita Ward, Okayama City, 700-0023)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chugoku Headquarters (Kamoi Bldg. 1st and 2nd Floors, 2-4, Ekimaecho 2-chome, Kita Ward, Okayama City, 700-0023)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>九州本部（〒810-0022　福岡市中央区 (福岡市)薬院一丁目6番14号　ZZZ-2ビル1・4階）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyushu Headquarters (ZZZ-2 Bldg. 1/4 Floors, Yakuin 1-chome, Chuo Ward, Fukuoka City 810-0022)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyushu Headquarters (ZZZ-2 Bldg. 1/4 Floors, Yakuin 1-chome, Chuo Ward, Fukuoka City 810-0022)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyushu Headquarters (ZZZ-2 Bldg. 1/4 Floors, 6-14, Yakuin 1-chome, Chuo Ward, Fukuoka City 810-0022)</e>
<cmt>番地を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>主な特徴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Main features</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Main features</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Main features</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="19">
<j>他の流派にはない大正琴アンサンブルというこれまでの常識を大きく覆す新境地を開拓した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has broke new ground, taishogoto music ensemble, which no other school has and went beyond common practice until that time.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It broke new ground with its taishogoto music ensemble not seen in any other schools..</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It broke new ground with its taishogoto music ensemble not seen at any other schools.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>（従来からあるソプラノに加えて、昭和50年代前半にアルト・テナー・ベース、計3種の大正琴を開発した。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(In addition to existing soprano, it developed three types of Taishogoto, alto, tenor and bass, in the latter half of 1970&apos;s.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(In addition to existing soprano, it developed three types of Taishogoto, alto, tenor and bass, in the latter half of the 1970&apos;s.)</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(In addition to conventional soprano, it developed three types of taishogoto, alto, tenor and bass, in the latter half of the 1970&apos;s.)</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>新たな音楽文化の第一歩を踏み出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With this, it too a step forward to new culture of music.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With this, it brought a new step forward to the culture of music.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With this, it took the first step on a new music culture.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>最大流派の優位性を生かして大正琴及び属品の価格も他流派より安く設定し、老若男女あらゆる世代が大正琴を楽しめるよう様々な取り組みをしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By making the most of predominance of the largest school, it set prices of taishogoto and accessories cheaper than other schools and making various efforts so that people of all generations can enjoy taishogoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By making the most of their dominance among the largest schools, it set cheaper prices for taishogoto and accessories than other schools and made various efforts so that people of all generations could enjoy taishogoto.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By making the most of their dominance as the largest schools, it set lower prices for taishogoto and accessories than other schools and makes various efforts so that people of all ages and both sexes can enjoy taishogoto.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>さらに全国各地で日頃の練習の成果を発表する場としてコンサートを積極的に開催している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, it has been holding concerts positively in various places nationwide as places to disclose publicly the results of daily practice.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, it has been holding concerts in various places nationwide as a venue to publicly disclose the results of daily practice.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, it has been holding concerts throughout Japan for providing opportunities for students to show the results of daily practice.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>各地区や都道府県単位の発表会から全国大会まで、大正琴の美しい音色（アンサンブル）を聴ける場を多くの人に幅広く提供している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has been providing a large number of persons places to hear beautiful sound of taishogoto (music ensemble) from school performance in each area or prefecture to nationwide assemblies.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has been providing a large number of people a place to hear the beautiful sound of taishogoto (music ensemble) from local school performances to prefecture and nationwide assemblies.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has been providing a large number of people a place to hear the beautiful sound of taishogoto (music ensemble) from local school performances to prefecture and nationwide assemblies.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="25">
<j>また本社では大正琴の製造工程が見学できる他、歴代（森田伍郎発明当時の品から現代に至るまで）の大正琴及び古い楽譜やレコードが展示され、大正琴の歴史を知ることができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In headquarters also, in addition to observation tour of the manufacturing processes of taishogoto, taishogoto of each generation (from one at the time of invention by Goro MORITA to current one), old sheets of music and records are displayed and we can learn the history of taishogoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At headquarters, in addition to an observation tour of the manufacturing processes of taishogoto, taishogoto of each generation (which ranges from the original taishogoto invented by Goro MORITA to the most modern one), old sheets of music and records are displayed allowing people to learn the history of taishogoto.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the head office, in addition to an observation tour of the manufacturing processes of taishogoto, taishogoto of each generation (which ranges from the original taishogoto invented by Goro MORITA to the present one), old sheets of music and record albums are displayed allowing people to learn the history of taishogoto.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>さらにここの見学者は希望により大正琴の演奏を体験でき、これをきっかけに本格的に大正琴を習い始めたい場合はスタッフが全国各地の琴伝流講師陣を紹介してくれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Visitors to this place, if wished, may try to perform taishogoto, and if any of visitors want to start learning taishogoto with this as a start, the staff will introduce instructors of Kindenryu in various places nationwide.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Visitors to this place, if wished, may try to perform taishogoto, and if any visitors want to start learning taishogoto, the staff will introduce instructors of Kindenryu from various places nationwide.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Visitors to this place, if they wish, will have an opportunity to perform taishogoto, and if visitors want to start learning taishogoto, the staff will introduce instructors of Kinden school from various places nationwide.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="27">
<j>なお大正琴及びその属品（楽譜・アンプ・ケーブル・チューナー・各種補修部品等）は一般店頭販売を行っていないが、同社ホームページからも入手できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although taishogoto and accessories (scores, amplifiers, cables, tuners, various spare parts, etc.) are not available in usual stores, but they can be purchased through the homepage of the company.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although taishogoto and accessories (scores, amplifiers, cables, tuners, various spare parts, etc.) are not available in normal stores, they can be purchased through the company homepage.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although taishogoto and accessories (scores, amplifiers, cables, tuners, various spare parts, etc.) are not available in normal stores, they can be purchased through the company homepage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="28">
<j>平成18年からは、次世代の大正琴音楽文化を担う後継者育成のため流派を問わず参加できる「全国子供大正琴コンクール」をスタートさせたほか、大正琴愛好者に最も好まれた曲を歌った歌手に贈られる「大正琴音楽大賞」も創設した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From 2006, in order to foster successors the next generation who promote musical culture of taishogoto, &quot;Nationwide Children&apos;s Taishogoto Contest,&quot; for which player of any school may take part in, was launched and Taishogoto Ongaku Taisho (literally, big award of taishogoto music) to be give to a singer who sings a song which was most liked by taishogoto fan was established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From 2006, in order to foster successors for the next generation to promote the musical culture of taishogoto, a &quot;Nationwide Children&apos;s Taishogoto Contest,&quot; open to players from any school was launched and the Taishogoto Ongaku Taisho (literally, big award of taishogoto music)is given to the singer who sings a song most liked by taishogoto fans.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From 2006, in order to foster the next generation of players who will promote the music culture of taishogoto, a &apos;Nationwide Children&apos;s Taishogoto Contest,&apos; open to players from any school was launched and the &apos;Taishogoto Ongaku Taisho&apos; was established, and is given to the singer who sings the song most liked by taishogoto fans.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>なお「大正琴音楽大賞」の受賞者は、平成18年の第1回が北島三郎(「風雪ながれ旅」で受賞)、平成19年が秋川雅史(「千の風になって」で受賞)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The prize winners of the &quot;Taishogoto Ongaku Taisho&quot; were Saburo KITAJIMA for the first time in 1906 (with the song &quot;Fusetsu Nagaretabi&quot;) and, for 1907, Masashi AKIKAWA (with the song &quot;Sen no kazeni natte&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The winner of the first &quot;Taishogoto Ongaku Taisho&quot; in 1906 was Saburo KITAJIMA (with the song &quot;Fusetsu Nagaretabi&quot;) followed by Masashi AKIKAWA (with the song &quot;Sen no kazeni natte&quot;) in 1907.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The winner of the first &apos;Taishogoto Ongaku Taisho&apos; in 2006 was Saburo KITAJIMA (for the song &apos;Fusetsu Nagaretabi&apos;) followed by Masafumi AKIKAWA (for the song &apos;Sen no kazeni natte&apos;) in 2007.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。Masashi→Masafumiに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="30">
<j>平成20年には琴伝流会員2,864名により大正琴の一斉演奏のギネス記録(従来記録1,034名)の更新をした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1908, 2,864 members of Kindenryu school renewed the Guinness record for group performance of taishogoto (record before that was 1,34 players).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1908, 2,864 members of Kindenryu school renewed the Guinness record for largest group performance of taishogoto (record before that was 1,034 players).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 2008, 2,864 members of Kinden school broke its own Guinness record for largest group performance of taishogoto (record before that was 1,034 players).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>また、全長210.5cm重さ23.2kgの世界一大きな大正琴もギネス記録として認定され、２つのギネス記録を持っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The biggest taishogoto in the world, with the total length of 210.5 cm, and weight of 23.2 kg was approved as a Guinness record and, eventually, it has two Guinness records.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The biggest taishogoto in the world, with a total length of 210.5 cm, and weight of 23.2 kg was approved as a Guinness record eventually leading to two Guinness records.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The biggest taishogoto in the world, with a total length of 210.5 cm, and weight of 23.2 kg was awarded a Guinness record; eventually, Kinden became a two Guinness records holder..</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="32">
<j>更に、平成20年の5月から6月にかけてANA全日本空輸の国際線機内放送「スカイチャンネル」に琴伝流の大正琴が採用された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From May to June 2008, taishogoto by Kindenryu school was adopted for &quot;Sky Channel&quot; (in-flight music for international flight) of the All Nippon Airways (ANA).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From May to June 2008, taishogoto by Kindenryu school was adopted for &quot;Sky Channel&quot; (in-flight music for international flight) by All Nippon Airways (ANA).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From May to June 2008, taishogoto by Kindenryu school was adopted for &apos;Sky Channel&apos; (in-flight music for international flight) by All Nippon Airways (ANA).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Mixtures(id:29234), Mikeneko(id:18205), Point136(id:211299), Rusk(id:9895), Sin145(id:227156), 江口磐世☆(id:168037), Phronimos(id:293969), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>