<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>ウメ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese plum</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Japanese plum (Ume)</e>
<cmt>the. (ume)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japanese plum (Ume)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>ウメ（梅、学名：Prunus mume）は、バラ科サクラ属の落葉高木、またはその果実のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese plum (binomial name: Prunus Mume) is a deciduous tall tree of Rosaceae Prunusor or its fruits.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese plum (technical name: Prunus Mume) refers to a deciduous tall tree of Rosaceae Prunusor or its fruits.</e>
<cmt>binomial &gt; technical. Is a &gt; refers to a.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese plum (technical name: Prunus Mume) refers to a deciduous tall tree of Rosaceae Prunusor or its fruits.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>別名に好文木（こうぶんぼく）、春告草（はるつげぐさ）、木の花（このはな）、初名草（はつなぐさ）、香散見草（かざみぐさ）、風待草（かぜまちぐさ）、匂草（においぐさ）などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another Japanese names include Kobunboku, Harutsugegusa, Konohana, Hatsunagusa, Kazamigusa, Kazemachigusa and Nioigusa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other Japanese names include Kobunboku, Harutsugegusa, Konohana, Hatsunagusa, Kazamigusa, Kazemachigusa and Nioigusa.</e>
<cmt>another &gt; other</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other Japanese names include Kobunboku, Harutsugegusa, Konohana, Hatsunagusa, Kazamigusa, Kazemachigusa and Nioigusa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>江戸時代以降、花見といえばサクラということになっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Edo period, Hanami (flower viewing) is associated with cherry blossom.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the Edo period, Hanami (flower viewing) has come to be associated with cherry blossoms.</e>
<cmt>after &gt; since. Is &gt; has come to be. Blossom &gt; blossoms.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the Edo period, Hanami (flower viewing) has come to be associated with cherry blossoms.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>しかし奈良時代以前に「花」といえば、むしろ梅を指すことの方が多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before the Nara period, however, when people referred to flower, they almost always meant Japanese plum.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before the Nara period, however, when people referred to &apos;flowers&apos;, they almost always meant Japanese plum.</e>
<cmt>flower &gt; &apos;flowers&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before the Nara period, however, when people referred to &apos;flowers&apos;, they almost always meant Japanese plum.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>梅が次第に桜によって駆逐されはじめるのは、平安時代中頃からのことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around the mid Heian period, Japanese plum came to be driven out by cherry blossom.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around the mid Heian period, Japanese plums came to be endangered by the presence of cherry blossoms.</e>
<cmt>driven out &gt; endangered by the presence.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around the mid Heian period, Japanese plums came to be endangered by the presence of cherry blossoms.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>天文 (日本)14年（1545年）4月17日 (旧暦)に当時の天皇が、京都の賀茂神社に梅を奉納したと『御湯殿上日記』にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As it is written in &quot;Oyudono no ue no Nikki&quot; that on April 17, 1545, the emperor of that time dedicated Japanese plums to Kamo-jinja Shine in Kyoto, the &apos;Kishu ume no kai&quot; (Kishu Japanese plum&apos;s association) set June 6 as the Japanese plum day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is written in &quot;Oyudono no ue no Nikki&quot; that on April 17 (of the old Calendar), 1545, the Emperor of the time made an offering of Japanese plums to Kamo-jinja Shine in Kyoto,</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is written in &apos;Diary of the Ladies-in-Waiting&apos; (Oyudono no ue no Nikki) that on April 17, 1545 (in the lunar calendar), the Emperor of that time made an offering of Japanese plums to Kamo-jinja Shine in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>ピリオドにしました。御湯殿上日記に説明を加えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>それにちなみ、「紀州梅の会」が新暦の6月6日を梅の日に定めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based on this, the &apos;Kishu ume no kai&quot; (Kishu Japanese plum&apos;s association) set June 6 as the Japanese plum day.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based on this, the &apos;Kishu Japanese Plum&apos;s Association&apos; set June 6 as the Japanese plum day.</e>
<cmt>左記のように変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>特徴および品種</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Characteristics and variety</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Characteristics and variety</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Characteristics and variety</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>アンズの近縁種であり、容易に交雑する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is related species of apricot and crosses easily.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is closely related to the apricot and crossbreeds easily.</e>
<cmt>related species &gt; closely related. Crosses&gt; crossbreeds.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is closely related to the apricot and crossbreeds easily.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>野梅系（やばいけい）の果実は小型であり、果実を利用する豊後系（ぶんごけい）（肥後系（ひごけい）とも呼ばれる）ではアンズとの交雑により大型化している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fruits of Yabaikei (one kind of Japanese plum) are small but those of Bungokei (another kind) (or Higokei), which are edible, are larger by intercrossing with apricot.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fruits of Yabaikei (one kind of Japanese plum) are small in size but the edible Bungokei or Higokei species have become larger through crossbreeding with the apricot.</e>
<cmt>small &gt; small in size. Intercrossing &gt; crossbreeding.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fruits of the Yabai line are small in size but the edible species of the Bungo line (also called the Higo line) have become larger through crossbreeding with the apricot.</e>
<cmt>左記のように変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>ただし、完熟しても果肉に甘味を生じることはない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the fruits are not sweet even if they are completely ripe.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the fruits are not sweet even if they are completely ripe.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the fruits are not sweet even if they are completely ripe.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="12">
<j>花芽はモモと異なり、一節につき1個となるため、モモに比べ、開花時の華やかな印象は薄い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Different from peach, as Japanese plum has one flower per flower bud, it looks less gorgeous than peach at the time of bloom.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the Japanese plum only has one flower per bud, it appears less flamboyant than the peach when it blooms.</e>
<cmt>gorgeous &gt; flamboyant.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the Japanese plum only has one flower per bud, it appears less flamboyant than the peach when it blooms.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>毎年2月から4月に5枚の花弁のある1センチメートルから3センチメートルほどの花を葉に先立って咲かせる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During every February to April, the Japanese plum tree produces 1 to 3centimeter flowers with five petals ahead of leaves.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Every February to April, before growing leaves the Japanese plum tree produces 1-3 centimeter flowers with five petals.</e>
<cmt>during X. ahead of leaves &gt; before growing leaves.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Every February to April, before growing leaves the Japanese plum tree produces 1-3 centimeter flowers with five petals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>花の色は白、またはピンクから赤。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The flower is white or in a color between pink and red.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The flower is white or a pinky red.</e>
<cmt>between pink and red &gt; a pinky red.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The flower is white or a pinky red.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>葉は互生で先がとがった卵形で、周囲が鋸歯状。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has alternate leaves, which are acute and serrate-sided in egg shape.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has alternate egg-shaped leaves with serrated edges.</e>
<cmt>Serrate-sided &gt; with serrated edges.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has alternate egg-shaped leaves with serrated edges.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>果実は2センチメートルから3センチメートルのほぼ球形の核果でみの片側に浅い溝がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The plum is a 2 to 3centimeter stone fruit in almost spherical shape, which is scrobiculated in one side.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The plum is a 2-3 centimeter spherical fruit with a stone and an indent on one side.</e>
<cmt>stone &gt; with a stone. Spherical shape &gt; spherical. Scrobiculated &gt; indent.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The plum is a 2-3 centimeter spherical fruit with a stone and an indent on one side.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>6月頃に黄色く熟す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese plum matures in yellow around June.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It ripens into a yellow shade around June.</e>
<cmt>matures &gt; ripens in yellow &gt; into a yellow shade.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It ripens into a yellow shade around June.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>七十二候の芒種末候には「梅子黄（梅の実が黄ばんで熟す）」と、ある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is written in Boshu Makko in Shichijuniko (72 divisions of the solar year) that &apos;the fruits of the Japanese plum trees mature in yellow.&apos;</e>
<cmt>芒種末候→定訳不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is written in Boshu Makko in Shichijuniko (72 divisions of the solar year) that &apos;the fruit of the Japanese plum trees ripen yellow.&apos;</e>
<cmt>mature in &gt; ripen</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is written in Boshu Makko in Shichijuniko (72 divisions of the solar year) that &apos;the fruit of the Japanese plum trees ripen yellow.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>梅には300種以上の品種があり、野梅系、紅梅系、豊後系の3系統に分類される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are more than 300 different kinds of Japanese plum trees, which are classified in to three kinds: Yabaikei, Kobaikei and Bungokei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are more than 300 different kinds of Japanese plum trees, which are classified in to three kinds: Yabaikei, Kobaikei and Bungokei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are more than 300 different kinds of Japanese plum trees, which are classified in to three lines: the Yabai, the Kobai and the Bungo.</e>
<cmt>左記のように変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>梅の実を採るのは主に豊後系である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fruits for edible use is mainly Bungokei plum trees.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The edible fruit mainly comes from the Bungokei plum trees.</e>
<cmt>for edible use &gt; edible fruits. Is &gt; comes from</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The edible fruit mainly comes from the Bungo line plum trees.</e>
<cmt>左記のように変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>果実</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fruit</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fruit</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fruit</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>薬効と毒性</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Medical effect and toxicity</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Medical effect and toxicity</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Medical effect and toxicity</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="21">
<j>花を観賞するほか、果実を梅干し、梅酒、梅酢やジャムなどにして食用とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">People view the flowers and the plums are eaten as Umeboshi (pickled plum), plum liquor, plum vinegar, plum jam, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Whilst the flowers are valued for their aesthetic value, the plums are eaten as Umeboshi (pickled plums), plum liquor, plum vinegar, plum jam, etc.</e>
<cmt>people view the &gt; are valued for their aesthetic value.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Whilst the flowers are valued for their aesthetic value, the plums are eaten as Umeboshi (pickled plums), plum liquor, plum vinegar, plum jam, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>また甘露梅やのし梅などの菓子や、梅肉煮などの料理にも用いられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The plums also used for Japanese sweets, such as Kanrobai (plums stewed in syrup) and Noshiume (a thin solid jelly consisting sweet plum jam) and for Japanese dishes, like braised fish with dried plum.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The plums are also used for Japanese sweets, such as Kanrobai (plums stewed in syrup) and Noshiume (a thin solid jelly consisting of sweet plum jam) and for Japanese dishes, like braised fish with dried plum.</e>
<cmt>also used &gt; are also used</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The plums are also used for Japanese sweets, such as Kanrobai (plums stewed in syrup) and Noshiume (a thin solid jelly consisting of sweet plum jam) and for Japanese dishes, like braised fish with dried plum.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="23">
<j>漢方薬では燻蒸（くんじょう）して真っ黒になった実を烏梅（うばい）といい、健胃、整腸、駆虫、止血、強心作用があるといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a Chinese herbal drug, the Japanese plum that is burnt black by fumigation is called Ubai and is believed to have stomachic action, intestinal regulation action, anthelmintic action, hemostatic action and cardiac action.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a Chinese herbal drug, Japanese plums blackened by smoking are called Ubai and are believed to have effects on the stomach, regulation of intestines, as insecticide, for haemostatis and cardiac issues.</e>
<cmt>fumigation &gt; smoking. Action &gt; effects.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a Chinese herbal drug, Japanese plums blackened by smoking are called Ubai and are believed to have effects of calming gastric and intestinal disorders, vermifuge, haemostatis and cardiotonic.</e>
<cmt>左記のように変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>中国では話梅（広東語 ワームイ）と呼ばれる干して甘味を付けた梅が菓子として売られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In China, sweet dried plum called Wamui is sold as a Chinese confectionery.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In China, sweet dried plums called Wamui are sold as Chinese confectionery.</e>
<cmt>plum &gt; 複数形</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In China, sweet dried plums called Wamui are sold as Chinese confectionery.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="25">
<j>バラ科の葉や未成熟の青い果実、核の中の種子には青酸配糖体が含まれ、未熟な種子や腸内細菌の酵素により、シアン化物を生成する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Leaves, immature green plums and seeds in the nucleus of Rosaceae contain cyanogenetic glycoside and formulate cyanide by enzyme of immature seeds and bacterium flora in the intestine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Leaves, immature green plums and seeds in the nucleus of Rosaceae contain cyanogenetic glycoside, thus cyanide can be produced by the reaction of immature seeds and bacterium flora with enzymes in the human intestine.</e>
<cmt>and &gt; thus. Formulate &gt; can be produced by the reaction.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Leaves, immature green plums and seeds in the nucleus of Rosaceae contain cyanogenetic glycoside, thus cyanide can be produced by immature seeds and enzymes of bacterium flora in the human intestine.</e>
<cmt>左記のように変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>これが胃酸によりシアン化水素毒性を発揮すると、痙攣や呼吸困難、さらには麻痺状態になって死亡するといわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that if this causes hydrogen cyanide toxicity by gastric acid, people will develop spasticity and breathing difficulties and die from paralysis.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that if this causes hydrogen cyanide toxicity by gastric acid, people can develop spasticity and breathing difficulties and die from paralysis.</e>
<cmt>will &gt;can</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that if gastric acid causes hydrogen cyanide toxicity, people can develop spasticity, difficulty in breathing, and in the worst case die from paralysis.</e>
<cmt>左記のように変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>シアンの生成は胃酸や胃の消化酵素によるものではないので、大量の種子をかみ砕いた場合を除いて誤摂取による中毒の危険は限られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As cyanide formation is not by stomach acid and digestive enzyme in the stomach, except crunching large amounts of seeds, it poses a limited risk to poisoning by accidental ingestion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As cyanide cannot be formed by acid and digestive enzymes in the stomach (except in the case of large quantities of seeds), they pose only a very limited risk of poisoning by accidental ingestion.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As cyanide cannot be formed by acid and digestive enzymes in the stomach, the risk of poisoning by accidental intake is limited to the cases where large quantities of seeds are crunched.</e>
<cmt>左記のように変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>アンズの種子による重症例がある一方、幼児が青梅の果肉を囓った程度では心配ないとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While apricot seeds cause severe cases, it is safe for infants to gnaw Japanese green plums.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While apricot seeds can cause severe incidents, it is safe for infants to consume Japanese green plums.</e>
<cmt>gnaw &gt; consume. Cases &gt; incidents.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While apricot seeds can cause severe incidents, it is safe for infants to nibble Japanese green plums.</e>
<cmt>左記のように変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>また、梅酒の青い実や梅干しの種の中身などは、アルコールや熱により酵素が失活し、毒性は低下している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, in case of green plums in plum liquor and inside of the seed of Umeboshi, alcohol and heat reduce the toxicity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, in the case of green plums and pickled plum seeds contained in plum liquor, the toxicity is reduced by alcohol and heat.</e>
<cmt>inside of the seed of Umeboshi &gt; dried plum seeds.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, in the case of green plums and dried plum seeds contained in plum liquor, the toxicity is reduced because alcohol and heat have inactivated enzymes.</e>
<cmt>酵素が失活の部分を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="30">
<j>クエン酸をはじめとする有機酸などを多く含むので健康食品としても販売されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As it contains a lot of organic acids, including citric acid, it is also sold as a health food.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As it contains a lot of natural acids, in particular citric acid, it is also sold as a health food.</e>
<cmt>organic &gt; natural. Including &gt; in particular.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As it contains a lot of organic acids, in particular citric acid, it is also sold as a health food.</e>
<cmt>有機酸をorganic acidとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>日本における作付けと収穫</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Planting and harvesting in Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Planting and harvesting in Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Planting and harvesting in Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="31">
<j>農林水産省が平成20年（2008年）11月に公表した統計によると、日本全国で作付面積は1万7400ヘクタール、収穫量は12万2000トン、出荷量は10万3600トンである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the statistics released by Ministry of Agriculture, Forestry and Fisheries in November 2008, its cropping acreage was 17,400 hectares, its harvest</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to statistics released by Ministry of Agriculture, Forestry and Fisheries in November 2008, its cropping acreage was 17,400 hectares, its total harvest was 122,000 tons, the total shipped was 103,600 tons.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to statistics released by Ministry of Agriculture, Forestry and Fisheries in November 2008, its cropping acreage was 17,400 hectares, its total harvest 122,000 tons, and the total shipment 103,600 tons.</e>
<cmt>左記のように変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>収穫量の都道府県別では、北から青森 1930トン、群馬 6800トン、福井 1270トン、山梨 2100トン、長野 1990トン、奈良 2020トン、和歌山 6万7600トン、徳島 822トンである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By region, the total harvest was 1930 tons from the Northern peak of Japan to Aomori, 6800 tons in Gunma, 1270 in Fukui, 2100 tons in Yamanashi, 1990 tons in Nagano, 2020 tons in Nagano, 67,600 tons in Wakayama and 822 tons in Tokushima.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The total harvests by the region from the north were 1,930 tons in Aomori, 6,800 tons in Gunma, 1,270 tons in Fukui, 2,100 tons in Yamanashi, 1,990 tons in Nagano, 2,020 tons in Nara, 67,600 tons in Wakayama and 822 tons in Tokushima.</e>
<cmt>左記のように変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>語源</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The origin of the word</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The origin of the word</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The origin of the word</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="33">
<j>「ウメ」の語源には諸説ある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are various stories about the origin of &apos;ume.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are various stories about the origin of &apos;ume.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are various stories about the origin of &apos;ume.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="34">
<j>ウメには大きな薬効があるため、「ｕ(見たこともない)+ｍｅ(本当に大切な)」でウメと呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the plums have significant medical benefits, from the combination of &apos;u (never-seen-before) and me (truly-important)&apos;, it is named ume.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the plums have significant medical benefits, it may be named Ume after the combination of &apos;u (never-seen-before) and me (truly-important)&apos;.</e>
<cmt>it is named &gt; it may be named.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the plums have significant medical benefits, it may be named Ume after the combination of &apos;u (never-seen-before) and me (truly-important).&apos;</e>
<cmt>.と&apos;の位置をかえました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="35">
<j>中国語の「梅」（マイあるいはメイ）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also believed to be derived from &apos;梅&apos; in Chinese (mai/mei).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also believed to be derived from &apos;梅&apos; in Chinese (mai/mei).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also believed to be derived from &apos;梅&apos; in Chinese (mai/mei).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>伝来当時の日本人は、鼻音の前に軽い鼻音を重ねていた（現在も東北方言などにその名残りがある）ため、meを/mme/（ンメ）のように発音していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Japanese people of the time of introduction reduplicated a light nasal sound before a nasal sound (this vestige remains in the Tohoku dialect today), they pronounced me as mme (ンメ).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Japanese people of the time of introduction inserted a light nasal sound before n and m, (this vestige remains in the Tohoku dialect today), they pronounced mei as nme.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese pronounciation at that time of introduction inserted a light nasal sound before n and m, (this vestige still remains in the Tohoku dialect today), and they pronounced mei as nme.</e>
<cmt>左記のように変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>これが「ムメ」のように表記され、さらに読まれることで/mume/となり/ume/へと転訛する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was written as &apos;ンメ&apos; and changed to mume and to ume over time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was written as &apos;ンメ&apos; (nme) and changed to mume and to ume over time.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was written as &apos;ンメ&apos; (nme) and changed to mume and to ume over time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>一方で、今も「ンメ」のように発音する方言もまた残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time, ume is still pronounced as mme in some dialects.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the same time, ume is still pronounced as mme in some dialects.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the same time, ume is still pronounced as mme in some dialects.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>ただし/ume/が先にあって、唇音の/u/が次にくる唇音の/m/に同化 (音声学)する音韻過程により/mme/へと変化したとする説も存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there is a theory that as the labial sound u was assimilated into the subsequent labial sound m, it changed to mme.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there is a theory that as the labial sound u was assimilated into the subsequent labial sound m, it changed to mme.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there is a theory that as the labial sound u was assimilated into the subsequent labial sound m, which changed to mme.</e>
<cmt>左記のように変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="40">
<j>他にも幾つかの異説があり、現在のところ、どれもまだ定説となるには至っていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are several other theories but none of them have become an established theory so far.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are several other theories but none of them have become an established theory so far.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are several other theories but none of them has become an established theory so far.</e>
<cmt>左記のように変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>家紋</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Crest</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Crests</e>
<cmt>複数形にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Crests</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="41">
<j>梅紋（うめもん）は、ウメの花を図案化した日本の家紋である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">ume-mon is a Japanese crest designed based on the Japanese plum flower.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ume-mon is a Japanese crest designed based on the Japanese plum flower.</e>
<cmt>文頭を大文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ume-mon is a Japanese crest designed based on the Japanese plum flower.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>その一種で「梅鉢（うめばち）」と呼ばれるものは、中心から放射線状に配置した花弁が太鼓の撥に似ていることに由来している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of them called Umebachi originated from the fact that petals arranged in radiation order resembles drumsticks.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One type of crest called Umebachi was inspired by the spiral pattern of petals which resembles drumsticks.</e>
<cmt>radiation order &gt; spiral</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One type of crest called Umebachi was inspired by the spiral pattern of petals which resembles drumsticks (bachi in Japanese).</e>
<cmt>鉢の由来がわかるように説明を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>奈良時代に模様として用いられはじめ、菅原道真が梅の花を好んだことにより天満宮の神紋として用いられ始めたと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that Umebachi came to be used as a pattern in the Nara period and as SUGAWARA no Michizane loved Japanese plum flowers, it was used as a crest for a shrine of Tenman-gu Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that Umebachi came to be used as a pattern in the Nara period and as SUGAWARA no Michizane loved Japanese plum flowers, it was used as the crest for a section Tenman-gu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>a crest &gt; the crest. shrine &gt; section.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that Umebachi came to be used as a pattern in the Nara period and as SUGAWARA no Michizane loved Japanese plum flowers, it was used as the crest of Tenman-gu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>左記のように変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="44">
<j>図案</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Design</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Design</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Design</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>図案は、「梅（うめ）」、「梅鉢（うめばち）」、「捻じ梅（ねじうめ）」、「実梅鉢（みうめばち）」などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Crest designs include &apos;ume,&apos; &apos;umebachi,&apos; &apos;neziume&apos; and &apos;miumebachi.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Crest designs include &apos;ume,&apos; &apos;umebachi,&apos; &apos;neziume&apos; and &apos;miumebachi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Crest designs include &apos;ume,&apos; &apos;umebachi,&apos; &apos;neziume&apos; and &apos;miumebachi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>「匂い梅（においうめ）」や「向う梅（むこううめ）」などの写実的な図案の梅花紋と、「梅鉢」などの簡略的な図案の梅鉢紋に大別される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The designs are divided broadly into two types: photographed design, such as &apos;nioiume&apos; and &apos;mukoue,&apos; and simplified one, such as &apos;umebachi.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The designs are divided broadly into two types: realistic design, such as &apos;nioiume&apos; and &apos;mukoue,&apos; and simplified ones, such as &apos;umebachi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>photographed &gt; realistic. one &gt; ones.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The designs are divided broadly into two types: realistic design, such as &apos;nioiume&apos; and &apos;mukoue,&apos; and simplified ones, such as &apos;umebachi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="47">
<j>使用</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Usage</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Usage</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Usage</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>「梅」は、太宰府天満宮、「星梅鉢」は北野天満宮が用いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The &apos;ume&apos; crest is used in Dazaifu Tenman-gu Shrine and the &apos;hoshi umebachi&apos; crest is used in Kitano Tenman-gu Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &apos;ume&apos; crest is used in Dazaifu Tenman-gu Shrine and the &apos;hoshi umebachi&apos; crest is used in Kitano Tenman-gu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &apos;ume&apos; crest is used in Dazaifu Tenman-gu Shrine and the &apos;hoshi umebachi&apos; crest is used in Kitano Tenman-gu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>武家では、菅原氏の末裔や美濃斉藤氏の一族が菅原天神信仰に基づいて用いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among sumurai families, the descendant of the Sugawara clan and families of the Mino Saito clan use it based on Tenjin shrine faith (SUGAWARA no Michizane).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among samurai families, the descendants of the Sugawara clan and families of the Mino Saito clan used it following the SUGAWARA Tenjin shrine faith.</e>
<cmt>descendant &gt; descendants. Based on &gt; following</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among samurai families, the descendants of the Sugawara clan and families of the Mino Saito clan used it following the SUGAWARA Tenjin shrine faith.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>主に、加賀前田氏の「加賀梅鉢」や相良氏の「相良梅鉢」などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mainly there are &apos;Kaga umebachi&apos; crest of the Kaga Maeda clan, &apos;Sagara umebachi&apos; crest of the Sagara clan, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The main crests include are &apos;Kaga umebachi&apos; of the Kaga Maeda clan and &apos;Sagara umebachi&apos; crest of the Sagara clan, etc.</e>
<cmt>main there are &gt; the main crests include</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The main crests include &apos;Kaga umebachi&apos; of the Kaga Maeda clan and &apos;Sagara umebachi&apos; crest of the Sagara clan, etc.</e>
<cmt>左記のように変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>ウメにまつわる言葉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Words involving Japanese plum</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Phrases including the Japanese plum</e>
<cmt>words &gt; phrases. Involving &gt; including</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Phrases including the Japanese plum</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="51">
<j>「桜伐（き）る馬鹿、梅伐らぬ馬鹿」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fool who prunes cherry trees, and the fool who doesn&apos;t trim apricot trees.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Anyone who prunes cherry trees is a fool, as is anyone who doesn&apos;t trim apricot trees.&apos;</e>
<cmt>The fool who &gt; any who…is a fool.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Anyone who prunes cherry trees is a fool, as is anyone who doesn&apos;t trim apricot trees.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>春先に咲く代表的な花であるサクラと梅のふたつを対比しつつ、栽培上の注意を示したもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By comparing the cherry blossom, which is a representative flower in early spring and the Japanese plum, it shows cultivation precautions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This expresses precautions about cultivation by comparing the Japanese plum, and cherry blossom, which is a representative flower of early Spring.</e>
<cmt>it shows cultivation precautions &gt; this expresses precations.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This expresses precautions about cultivation by comparing the Japanese plum and cherry blossom, which are both representative flowers of early Spring.</e>
<cmt>左記のように変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>桜はむやみに伐ると切り口から腐敗しがちであり、剪定には注意が必要。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If cherry trees are cut unnecessarily, they become corrupt from the cut end surface and so pruning of them requires attention.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If cherry trees are cut unnecessarily, the cut surface can start to decay, so pruning of them requires care.</e>
<cmt>curropt &gt; start to decay. Attention &gt; care.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If cherry trees are cut unnecessarily, the cut surface can start to decay, so pruning of them requires care.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>一方、梅の樹は剪定に強く、むしろかなり切り詰めないと徒枝が伸びて樹形が雑然となって台無しになるばかりでなく、実の付き方も悪くなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, Japanese plum trees are resistant to pruning and if they are trimmed considerably, their tree shape became scattered with their branches stooling and ripening of their fruits get spoiled.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, Japanese plum trees are resistant to pruning and if they are not trimmed sufficiently, not only can their shape be ruined, ripening of fruit can be affected.</e>
<cmt>trimmed considerably &gt; not trimmed sufficiently. became scattered &gt; not only can…be ruined. Spoiled &gt; affected.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, Japanese plum trees are resistant to pruning and if they are not trimmed sufficiently, not only can their shape be ruined, ripening of fruit can be affected.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>花芽は年々枝先へと移動する結果、実が付く枝は通常数年で枯れ込んでしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the buds move to branches year by year, branches that produce fruits die in a few years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the buds move to the tips of the branches year on year, fruit-yielding branches generally die after a number of years.</e>
<cmt>branches that produce fruits &gt; fruit-yielding. In a few &gt; after a number of.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the buds move to the tips of the branches year on year, fruit-yielding branches generally die after a number of years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>実の収穫を目的とするのであれば、定期的に枝の更新を図る必要があるからである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order to harvest the fruits, regular renewal of branches is needed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to harvest the fruits, regular renewal of branches is needed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to harvest the fruits, regular renewal of branches is needed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="57">
<j>「東風〔こち〕吹かば にほひおこせよ梅の花 主なしとて 春な忘れそ」（菅原道真）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the wind is in the east, I want it to deliver the scent of Japanese plum flowers to me, even if I disappear from here, you, Japanese plum flowers, do not forget spring.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the wind is in the east, I want it to blow the scent of Japanese plum flowers to me; even if I disappear from here, you, Japanese plum flowers, do not forget spring.&apos; (SUGAWARA no Michizane)</e>
<cmt>. Deliver &gt; blow. SUGAWARA no Michizane.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the wind is in the east, I want it to blow the scent of Japanese plum flowers to me; even if I disappear from here, you, Japanese plum flowers, do not forget spring.&apos; (SUGAWARA no Michizane)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>道真が大宰府に左遷されるとき、道真の愛した庭の梅の花に別れを惜しんで詠んだ歌。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is the Japanese poetry written when Michizane was demoted and transferred to Dazai-fu (local government office in Kyushu region, parting reluctantly from his loved Japanese plum flowers in the garden.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is a Japanese poem written when Michizane was demoted and transferred to Dazai-fu (local government office in the Kyushu region), parting reluctantly from the beloved Japanese plum flowers in his garden.</e>
<cmt>poetry &gt; poem. Loved &gt; beloved</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is a Japanese poem written when Michizane was demoted and transferred to Dazaifu (local government office in the Kyushu region), parting reluctantly from the beloved Japanese plum flowers in his garden.</e>
<cmt>大宰府は今でもある地名なので、Dazaifuとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>後に庭の梅木が道真を追って大宰府に飛んできた、という「飛梅」がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later there was the legend of TOBIUME that the Japanese plum trees in the garden flied to Daszai-fu, following him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later there was a legend known as TOBIUME that the Japanese plum trees in the garden flew to Daszai-fu, following him.</e>
<cmt>the &gt; a. flied &gt; flew</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later there was a legend known as a flying plum tree (tobuume) that the Japanese plum trees in the garden flew to Daszaifu, following him.</e>
<cmt>飛梅に説明を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="60">
<j>「桃栗三年、柿八年、柚（ゆず）の馬鹿野郎十八年、梅はすいすい十六年」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Peach and chestnut seeds take three years to bear fruit, plums take eight, Yuzu (Japanese citron) takes eighteen years and Japanese plum trees take sixteen years.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Peach and chestnut seeds take three years to bear fruit, plums take eight, Yuzu (Japanese citron) takes eighteen years and Japanese plum trees take sixteen years.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Peach and chestnut seeds take three years to bear fruit, plums take eight, Yuzu (Japanese citron) takes eighteen years and Japanese plum trees take sixteen years.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>種を植えてから実を収穫できるまでの期間を指す民謡。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is a Minyo (a traditional folk song) that shows periods from planting to harvesting of fruits.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is a Minyo (a traditional folk song) that shows the time from planting to harvesting for various fruits.</e>
<cmt>periods &gt; time. Of &gt; for various.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is a traditional folk song that shows the time from planting to harvesting for various fruits.</e>
<cmt>音訳を略しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>本来は「桃栗三年柿八年」で一つの諺。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally &apos;peach and chestnut seeds take three years to bear fruit, plums take eight&apos; is one proverb.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It originates from a single proverb &apos;Peach and chestnut seeds take three years to bear fruit, plums take eight.&apos;</e>
<cmt>originally..is one proverb &gt; it originates from a single proverb</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It originates from a single proverb &apos;Peach and chestnut seeds take three years to bear fruit, plums take eight.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>｢物事は簡単にうまくいくものではなく、一人前になるには地道な努力と忍耐が必要だ」という教訓である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is a lesson that things do not come easy and it often takes it often takes steady efforts and patience to become independent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The moral is that things do not come easily and often it takes a steady effort and patience to achieve adulthood.</e>
<cmt>it often takes it often takes &gt; often it akes. Steady efforts &gt; a steady effort. Become independent &gt; achieve adulthood.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The moral is that things do not come easily and often it takes a steady effort and patience to become full-fledged.</e>
<cmt>一人前の表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>日本の梅の名所</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Places famous for beautiful Japanese plum trees</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Places famous for beautiful Japanese plum trees</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Places famous for beautiful Japanese plum trees</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>全国の天満宮</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tenman-gu Shrines across the country</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tenman-gu Shrines across the country</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tenman-gu Shrines across the country</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="64">
<j>- 梅がシンボルになっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese plum trees become a symbol.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese plum trees are symbolic.</e>
<cmt>become a symbol &gt; are symbolic</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese plum trees are symbolic.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>みかさ梅林邦梅園（北海道三笠市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mikasa plum-grove park named Hobaien (Mikasa City, Hokkaido)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hobien, Mikasa plum-grove park (Mikasa City, Hokkaido)</e>
<cmt>Hobien first.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hobaien, Mikasa plum-grove park (Mikasa City, Hokkaido)</e>
<cmt>「ほうばいえん」が正確な読み方です。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="65">
<j>- 北海道最大の梅園であり、約1万本が植栽されている</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is the largest Japanese plum orchard and has about 10 thousand Japanese plum trees.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is the largest Japanese plum orchard and has about 10 thousand Japanese plum trees.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is the largest Japanese plum orchard and has about 10 thousand Japanese plum trees.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="66">
<j>平岡公園（北海道札幌市清田区）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hiraoka Park (Kiyota Ward, Sapporo City, Hokkaido)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hiraoka Park (Kiyota Ward, Sapporo City, Hokkaido)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hiraoka Park (Kiyota Ward, Sapporo City, Hokkaido)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="67">
<j>- 広さ6.5ヘクタールの敷地に約1,200本の梅がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This park has around 1,200 Japanese plum trees on the 6.5-hectare site.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This park has around 1,200 Japanese plum trees on its 6.5-hectare site.</e>
<cmt>the &gt; its.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This park has around 1,200 Japanese plum trees on its 6.5-hectare site.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>紅梅種と白梅種との比率は約6：4</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ratio of red plum blossoms to white plum blossoms is about 6 : 4.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ratio of red plum blossoms to white plum blossoms is about 6 : 4.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ratio of red plum blossoms to white plum blossoms is about 6 : 4.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>水戸偕楽園（茨城県水戸市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mito Kairaku-en Garden (Mito City, Ibaraki Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mito Kairaku-en Garden (Mito City, Ibaraki Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mito Kairaku-en Garden (Mito City, Ibaraki Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="69">
<j>- 約3千本の梅がある日本庭園。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is a Japanese garden with around 3,000 Japanese plum trees.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is a Japanese garden with around 3,000 Japanese plum trees.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is a Japanese garden with around 3,000 Japanese plum trees.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>日本三名園の一つ、また関東三大梅林の一つ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is one of the three outstanding gardens in Japan and of the three major Japanese plum hardens in Kanto region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is one of the three most outstanding gardens in Japan and of the three major Japanese plum gardens in the Kanto region.</e>
<cmt>outstanding &gt; most outstanding. Hardens &gt; gardens.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is one of the three most outstanding gardens in Japan and of the three major Japanese plum gardens in the Kanto region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>筑波山（茨城県つくば市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mt. Tsukuba (Tsukuba City, Ibaraki Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mt. Tsukuba (Tsukuba City, Ibaraki Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mt. Tsukuba (Tsukuba City, Ibaraki Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="71">
<j>- 約3千本の梅がある、日本百名山の一つ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is one of the one hundred top mountains of Japan with around 3,000 Japanese plum trees.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is one of the one hundred top mountains of Japan with around 3,000 Japanese plum trees.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is one of the one hundred top mountains of Japan with around 3,000 Japanese plum trees.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="72">
<j>吉野梅郷（東京都青梅市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshino baigo (The forest of Japanese plum) (Ome City, Tokyo)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshino baigo (The home of the Japanese plum) (Ome City, Tokyo)</e>
<cmt>forest &gt; home</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshino baigo (The home of the Japanese plum) (Ome City, Tokyo)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="73">
<j>- 約2万5千本の梅がある</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This has around 25,000 Japanese plum trees.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This has around 25,000 Japanese plum trees.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This has around 25,000 Japanese plum trees.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>府中市郷土の森博物館梅園（東京都府中市 (東京都)）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fuchu City Kyodo no Mori Museum, baien (Japanese plum garden)</e>
<cmt>府中市郷土の森博物館→Fuchu City Kyodo no Mori Museum　[http://www.culturalprofiles.net/japan/units/5780.html]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fuchu City Kyodo no Mori Museum, Baien (Japanese plum garden)</e>
<cmt>baien &gt; Baien</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fuchu City Kyodo no Mori Museum, Baien (Japanese plum garden)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="74">
<j>- 広さ17ヘクタールの敷地内に、約60種、1100本の梅がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This has about 1.1 thousand Japanese plum trees of around 60 different varieties on the 17-hectare site.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This has around 1,100 Japanese plum trees of around 60 different varieties on its 17-hectare site.</e>
<cmt>1.1 thousnad &gt; 1,100. the &gt; its</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This has around 1,100 Japanese plum trees of around 60 different varieties on its 17-hectare site.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="14">
<tit>
<j>秋間梅林（群馬県安中市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akima bairin (The forest of Japanese plum) (Annaka City, Gunma Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akima bairin (The forest of the Japanese plum) (Annaka City, Gunma Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>the</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akima bairin (The forest of the Japanese plum) (Annaka City, Gunma Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="75">
<j>- 約50ヘクタールの敷地に35,000本を超える梅がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This forest has more than 35,000 Japanese plum trees on the around 50-hectare site.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This forest has more than 35,000 Japanese plum trees on a site of roughly 50-hectares.</e>
<cmt>the around…site &gt; a site of roughly…</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This forest has more than 35,000 Japanese plum trees on a site of roughly 50-hectares.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="76">
<j>越生梅林（埼玉県越生町）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ogose bairin (Ogose Town, Saitama Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ogose bairin (Ogose Town, Saitama Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ogose bairin (Ogose Town, Saitama Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="77">
<j>- 関東三大梅林のひとつ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is one of the three major Japanese plum forests in Kanto region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is one of the three largest Japanese plum forests in the Kanto region.</e>
<cmt>major &gt; largest. Kanto region &gt; the Kanto region.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is one of the three largest Japanese plum forests in the Kanto region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="78">
<j>熱海梅園（静岡県熱海市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Atami bairin (Atami City, Shizuoka Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Atami bairin (Atami City, Shizuoka Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Atami bairin (Atami City, Shizuoka Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="79">
<j>- 関東三大梅林のひとつ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is one of the three major Japanese plum forests in Kanto region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is one of the three largest Japanese plum forests in the Kanto region.</e>
<cmt>major &gt; largest. Kanto region &gt; the Kanto region.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is one of the three largest Japanese plum forests in the Kanto region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="80">
<j>岩本山公園（静岡県富士市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Iwamotoyama Park (Fuji City, Shizuoka Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Iwamotoyama Park (Fuji City, Shizuoka Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Iwamotoyama Park (Fuji City, Shizuoka Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="81">
<j>- 400本程度しかないが、富士山との撮影ポイントとして有名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although this park has only 400 Japanese plum trees, it is famous as a shooting location with Mr. Fuji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although this park has only 400 Japanese plum trees, it is famous as a location for shooting Mt. Fuji.</e>
<cmt>a shooting location with &gt; a location for shooting. Mr. &gt; Mt.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although this park has only 400 Japanese plum trees, it is famous as a location for shooting Mt. Fuji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="15">
<tit>
<j>青谷梅林（京都府城陽市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Aodani bairin (Joyo City, Kyoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Aodani bairin (Joyo City, Kyoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Aodani bairin (Joyo City, Kyoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="82">
<j>- 約1万本の梅がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This has around 10,000 Japanese plum trees.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is host to roughly 10,000 Japanese plum trees.</e>
<cmt>has &gt; is host to. + roughly</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is host to roughly 10,000 Japanese plum trees.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>広さ20ヘクタール、鎌倉時代からの歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is about 20 hectares in area and has a history since the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is about 20 hectares in area and dates back to the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>has a history since &gt; dates back to.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is about 20 hectares in area and dates back to the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="84">
<j>月ヶ瀬梅林（奈良県奈良市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsukigase bairin (Nara City, Nara Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsukigase bairin (Nara City, Nara Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsukigase bairin (Nara City, Nara Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="85">
<j>- 日本国指定名勝。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">National Sites of Scenic Beauty</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">National Sites of Natural Beauty</e>
<cmt>scenic &gt; natural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">National Sites of Natural Beauty</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>旧添上郡月ヶ瀬村の梅林。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is a Japanese plum forest in Tsukigase-mura, former Soekami district</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is a Japanese plum forest in Tsukigase-mura, former Soekami district</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is a Japanese plum forest in Tsukigase-mura Village, former Soekami County.</e>
<cmt>郡はCountyとし、ピリオドをつけました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>約1万3千本の梅がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has around 13,000 Japanese plum trees.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has around 13,000 Japanese plum trees.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has around 13,000 Japanese plum trees.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>樹齢600年の古木が存在。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a 600 year-old tree.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is home to a 600 year-old tree.</e>
<cmt>has &gt; is home to.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is home to a 600 year-old tree.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="16">
<tit>
<j>賀名生梅林（奈良県五條市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ano bairin (Gojo City, Nara Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ano bairin (Gojo City, Nara Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ano bairin (Gojo City, Nara Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="89">
<j>- 南北朝時代の和歌にも詠まれる、約2万本の梅林</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is a Japanese plum forest, which is written in a Japanese poem, with around 20,000 Japanese plum trees.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is a Japanese plum forest, referenced in poetry, with around 20,000 Japanese plum trees.</e>
<cmt>which is written &gt; referenced. A Japanese poem &gt; poetry.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is a Japanese plum forest, referenced in poetry written in the period of the Northern and Southern Dynasties, with around 20,000 Japanese plum trees.</e>
<cmt>南北朝時代の部分を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="17">
<tit>
<j>綾部山・室津（兵庫県たつの市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ayabeyama/Murotsu (Tatsuno City, Hyogo Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ayabeyama/Murotsu (Tatsuno City, Hyogo Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ayabeyama/Murotsu (Tatsuno City, Hyogo Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="90">
<j>- 瀬戸内海を「ひとめ2万本」と称される</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is called &apos;20,000 Japanese plum trees in one view&apos; with a full view of the Seto Inland Sea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is known as &apos;A Glimpse of 20,000 trees&apos; from the Seto Inland Sea.</e>
<cmt>called &gt; known as. With a full view &gt; from the.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is known as &apos;A Glimpse of 20,000 trees&apos; from the Seto Inland Sea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="18">
<tit>
<j>南部梅林（和歌山県みなべ町）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nanbu bairin (Minabe Town, Wakayama Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nanbu bairin (Minabe Town, Wakayama Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nanbu bairin (Minabe Town, Wakayama Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="91">
<j>- 「一目100万本、香り十里」と称される南高梅の梅林</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is a Nanko-ume plum forest called &apos;1,000 trees in one view with the scent spreading for about forty kilometers.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is a Nanko-ume plum forest famed for its &apos;Glimpse of 1,000 trees with a fragrance spreading for miles.&apos;</e>
<cmt>called &gt; fames for.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is a Nanko-ume plum forest famed for its &apos;Glimpse of 1,000 trees with a fragrance spreading for miles.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="19">
<tit>
<j>岩代大梅林（和歌山県みなべ町）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Iwashirodai bairin (Minabe Town, Wayakama Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Iwashirodai bairin (Minabe Town, Wayakama Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Iwashirodai bairin (Minabe Town, Wayakama Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="92">
<j>- 広さ30ヘクタール、梅木2万本の南高梅の梅林</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is a Nanko-ume plum forest with 20,000 trees on the 30-hectare site.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is a Nanko-ume plum forest with 20,000 trees on its 30-hectare site.</e>
<cmt>the &gt;its</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is a Nanko-ume plum forest with 20,000 trees on its 30-hectare site.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="20">
<tit>
<j>千里梅林（和歌山県みなべ町）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Senri bairin (Minabe Town, Wakayama Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Senri bairin (Minabe Town, Wakayama Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Senri bairin (Minabe Town, Wakayama Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="93">
<j>- 熊野古道の千里の浜を見おろす丘にある約6千本の南高梅の梅林</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is a Nanko-ume plum forest located on the hill overlooking the Senri no hama Beach of the Kumanokodo Road with around 6,000 trees.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is a Nanko-ume plum forest located on a hill overlooking the Senri no hama Beach of the Kumanokodo Road, containing around 6,000 trees.</e>
<cmt>the hill &gt; a hill. With &gt; containing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is a Nanko-ume plum forest located on a hill overlooking the Senri no hama Beach of the Kumanokodo Road, containing around 6,000 trees.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="21">
<tit>
<j>紀州田辺梅林（和歌山県田辺市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kishu-tanabe bairin (Tanabe City, Wakayama Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kishu-tanabe bairin (Tanabe City, Wakayama Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kishu-tanabe bairin (Tanabe City, Wakayama Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="94">
<j>- 30万本の梅木、大蛇峰山麓にある</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has 300,000 Japanese plum trees and is located in the Daijaminesanroku (at the foot of Mt. Daija).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has 300,000 Japanese plum trees and is located in the Daijaminesanroku (at the foot of Mt. Daija).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has 300,000 Japanese plum trees and is located at the foot of Mt. Daija.</e>
<cmt>音訳を略しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="22">
<tit>
<j>阿川梅の里（徳島県名西郡神山町）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Agawa ume no sato (The forest of Japanese plum) (Kamiyama Town, Tokushima Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Agawa ume no sato (The forest of Japanese plum) (Kamiyama Town, Tokushima Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Agawa ume no sato (The forest of Japanese plum) (Kamiyama Town, Tokushima Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="95">
<j>- 30ヘクタールの敷地に1万6千本の鶯宿梅の梅林</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is a Oshuku ume plum forest with 16,000 trees on the 30-hectare site.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is a Oshuku ume plum forest with 16,000 trees on the 30-hectare site.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is a Oshuku ume plum forest with 16,000 trees on the 30-hectare site.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="23">
<tit>
<j>梅関連の施設</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese plum-related facilities</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese plum-related facilities</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese plum-related facilities</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="96">
<j>道の駅みなべうめ振興館・うめ振興館（和歌山県）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Michi-no-eki Minabe development and promotion center of Japanese plum/development and promotion center of Japanese plum (Wakayama Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Michi-no-eki Minabe development and promotion center of Japanese plum/development and promotion center of Japanese plum (Wakayama Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Michi-no-eki (Roadside Station Minabe), the Promotion Center of Japanese Plum (Wakayama Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>紀州梅干館</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dried plum promotion center of Kishu Province</e>
<cmt>定訳不明です</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dried plum promotion center of Kishu Province</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kishu Umeboshi (pickled plum) Promotion Center</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>- 梅干しの企業博物館</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dried plum corporate museum</e>
<cmt>定訳不明です</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dried plum corporation museum</e>
<cmt>corporate &gt; corporation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">a corporation museum of umeboshi (pickled plum)</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>農林水産総合技術センターうめ研究所（和歌山県）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wakayama Research Center of Agriculture, Forestry and Fisheries, Japanese plum research center</e>
<cmt>農林水産総合技術センター→Wakayama Research Center of Agriculture, Forestry and Fisheries [http://read.jst.go.jp/public/cs_kdi_008EventAction.do?action4=event&amp;lang_act4=E&amp;judge_act4=2&amp;knky_kdi_code=0350011793]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wakayama Research Center of Agriculture, Forestry and Fisheries, Japanese plum research center</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wakayama Research Center of Agriculture, Forestry and Fisheries, Japanese plum research center</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>全国梅サミット</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">National Japanese plum summit conference</e>
<cmt>定訳不明です</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">National Japanese plum summit</e>
<cmt>conference X</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">National Japanese plum summit</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 AlleborgoBot(id:119729), Los688(id:12316), Ypacaraí(id:11031), Nnh(id:474), 天然ガス(id:98149), Lupinoid(id:68), Revth(id:12179), Electric goat(id:2935), Tribot(id:186681), 柑橘類(id:112137), Alex K(id:86829), Daddy t3(id:26516), Opponent(id:720), Mocchy(id:146197), Michey.M(id:906), Riku(id:16088), Shinku(id:22505), Knua(id:66861), Meltbeen(id:160811), Yas(id:739), Kurayamizaka(id:7150), Mogumin(id:28886), Sesirec(id:27279), 甲信赤八(id:97613), マクガイア(id:33346), 梅竹松(id:289214), YukkeBot(id:251107), Martin(id:6394), Zwobot(id:23873), 樒(id:35770), Dolfin(id:4331), Rusk(id:9895), SuisuiBot(id:10165), あんも騎士(id:139357), R28Bot(id:177951), ビスケット柵崎(id:30272), 人造人間だみゃ～ん(id:119413), Rosan(id:19310), Bakkai(id:7233), E-190(id:74680), K66星雲(id:16609), Excl-zoo(id:47086), Bigei(id:51684), PLANT(id:16515), Charenji(id:7908), Cureless(id:85558), ぎぶそん(id:261394), MelancholieBot(id:31942), Hachikou(id:10676), Kumatora(id:16941), Im224(id:57113), てぃらみす(id:191639), Mintleaf(id:2216), NipponDaemon(id:10068), Okia(id:73923), ムカイ(id:72972), Toto-tarou(id:16648), 死郎(id:1683), こんせ(id:262022), ノン(id:124203), サニードレッシング(id:15736), Goki(id:7107), Frei(id:12101), Edogawa(id:9879), Loveless(id:129239), シェイク(id:305656), 竹麦魚(id:11012), PuzzletChung(id:13816), Tamakko(id:284921), LERK(id:4460), ぶるるるる(id:130462), Hirasen(id:43505), Tmonzenet(id:92869), Jony(id:8631), Petronius(id:41844), LaaknorBot(id:220851), Kwakkun(id:19105), 如如月(id:288523), Carkuni(id:79281), Green(id:24154), Mochi(id:9489), Symauma(id:78765), Thijssie!bot(id:111619), 663highland(id:18755), SEKIUCHI(id:637), Muyo(id:14948), Huzzlet the bot(id:85960), Louperibot(id:128971), Tomorrow0622(id:26939), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>