<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>甘酒</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amazake</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amazake</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amazake</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>甘酒（あまざけ、醴）は日本の伝統的な甘味飲料の一種で、見た目はどぶろく（濁酒）に類似する白濁液である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amazake is a kind of Japanese traditional sweet beverages, which is a white cloudy liquid similar to Doburoku (cloudy sake).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amazake is a traditional Japanese sweet beverage, which is a cloudy liquid similar to doburoku (unrefined sake).</e>
<cmt>Rewritten to read naturally.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amazake is a traditional Japanese sweet beverage, which is a cloudy liquid similar to doburoku (unrefined sake).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Overview</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Overview</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>統一用語</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>古くは「一夜酒（ひとよざけ）」または「醴酒（こさけ、こざけ（「濃い酒」の意））」と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was called as &quot;Hitoyo-zake&quot; (literally over-night sake) or &quot;Ko-sake&quot; (thick sake) long ago.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was called as &quot;Hitoyo-zake&quot; (literally over-night sake) or &quot;Ko-sake&quot; (thick sake) long ago.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was called as &quot;Hitoyo-zake&quot; (literally over-night sake) or &quot;Ko-sake&quot; (thick sake) long ago.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>かつては夏に、冷やしたものまたは熱したものを暑気払いに飲む習慣があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cold Amazake or hot Amazake used to be drunk in summer in order to forget the summer heat.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cold amazake or hot amazake used to be drunk during summer in order to forget the summer heat.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Amazake&quot; &gt; &quot;amazake&quot;&quot;in&quot; &gt; &quot;during&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cold amazake or hot amazake used to be drunk during summer in order to forget the summer heat.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>俳句では現在でも夏の季語となっているが、現在は冬に温めて飲むのが一般的である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, the term Amazake is still included in Kigo of Haiku poetry (words or phrases associated with a particular season) for summer, although Amazake is seldom drunk in summer now.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the term amazake remains one of the kigo (seasonal words) for summer used in haiku poetry even though amazake is now seldom drunk during summer.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten to read naturally.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the term amazake remains one of the kigo (seasonal words) for summer used in haiku poetry even though amazake is now seldom drunk during summer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>体が温まるだけでなく、夏に飲む場合は夏バテを防ぐ意味合いもあり、健康的な飲料として好まれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amazake is popular as a healthy beverage because Amazake not only has an effect of warming your body but also has an effect of preventing Natsubate (summer lethargy) when it is drunk in summer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amazake is popular as a healthy beverage because it not only has the effect of warming the body but also prevents natsubate (summer lethargy) when drunk during summer.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten to read naturally.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amazake is popular as a healthy beverage because it not only has the effect of warming the body but also prevents natsubate (summer lethargy) when drunk during summer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>正月には、初詣客に有料または無料で甘酒を振る舞ったり、自宅に持ち帰る甘酒を初詣客に販売する寺社が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many temples and shrines provide their visitors with Amazake at a charge or free of charge on New Year&apos;s Day and sell Amazake for the visitors to bring home.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many temples and shrines either sell amazake or provide it free of charge to worshippers on New Year&apos;s Day, and sell it for visitors to bring home.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten to read professionally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many temples and shrines either sell amazake or provide it free of charge to worshippers on New Year&apos;s Day, and sell it for visitors to bring home.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>また、米農家が収穫を感謝するため、甘酒を造ったり、祭りに甘酒を供える風習が残っている土地もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In some regions, rice farmers still preserve their old custom to make Amazake and offer it on the alter during festival in order to thank for good harvest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In some regions, rice farmers still preserve the old custom of making amazake and placing it on an alter during festivals as an offering of thanks for a good harvest.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten to read professionally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In some regions, rice farmers still preserve the old custom of making amazake and placing it on an alter during festivals as an offering of thanks for a good harvest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>甘酒を供する店としては、箱根の『甘酒茶屋』や神田明神の『天野屋』などが有名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Famous shops which serve Amazake includes Amazake-chaya in Hakone, Amano-ya in Kanda-myojin, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Famous shops which serve amazake include Amazake-chaya in Hakone and Amano-ya in Kanda-myojin.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten to read professionally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Famous shops which serve amazake include Amazake-chaya in Hakone and Amano-ya in Kanda-myojin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="9">
<j>ビタミンB1、ビタミンB2、ビタミンB6、パントテン酸、すべての必須アミノ酸、そして大量のブドウ糖が含まれているが、これらの栄養は病院の点滴静脈注射とほぼ同じ内容であり、ブドウ糖以外は製法（後述）による差異も少ない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amazake contains Vitamin B1, Vitamin B2, Vitamin B6, pantothenic acid, all the essential amino acids, and a large amount of glucose; these nutrients are the same as those contained in intravenous drips provided at hospitals and the production method (described later) is also similar to that of the intravenous drips except for glucose.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amazake contains vitamin B1, vitamin B2, vitamin B6, pantothenic acid, all the essential amino acids, and a large amount of glucose; these nutrients are the same as those contained in intravenous drips provided at hospitals and the production method (described later) is also similar to that of the intravenous drips except for the addition of glucose.</e>
<cmt>CapitalizationAdded &quot;for the addition of&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amazake contains vitamin B1, vitamin B2, vitamin B6, pantothenic acid, all the essential amino acids, and a large amount of glucose; these nutrients are the same as those contained in intravenous drips provided at hospitals and the production method (described later) is also similar to that of the intravenous drips except for the addition of glucose.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="10">
<j>「酒」の名は付くが、実際にはアルコール飲料ではなく、未成年者でも飲用が許されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although, as its name shows, Amazake is called as &quot;sake&quot;, it is a non-alcoholic beverage, and minors are allowed to drink.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although called &quot;amazake&quot;, it is not an alcoholic beverage and can therefore be consumed by minors.</e>
<cmt>Poor translation.Completely retranslated.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although called &quot;amazake&quot;, it is not an alcoholic beverage and can therefore be consumed by minors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>しかし、原料に含有され、あるいは製造過程で生成されることでエタノールが含まれることがあり、酒に弱い者（特に幼児）が大量に飲むとエタノールと人体可能性がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, because ethanol may be included in its materials or may be produced during its production process, people who get drunk easily (particularly children) may get drunk if they drink a large amount of Amazake..</e>
<cmt>「エタノールと人体可能性がある」の部分は、この部分に該当する箇所をウェブ上でを確認し、「酔う可能性がある」という内容で訳出致しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, because ethanol may be included in its ingredients or may be produced during its production process, people who get drunk easily (particularly children) may get drunk if they consume a large amount of amazake.</e>
<cmt>&quot;materials&quot; &gt; &quot;ingredients&quot;&quot;drink&quot; &gt; &quot;consume&quot;&quot;Amazake&quot; &gt; &quot;amazake&quot;Deleted full-stop</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, because ethanol may be included in its ingredients or may be produced during its production process, people who get drunk easily (particularly children) may get drunk if they consume a large amount of amazake.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="12">
<j>酒粕が甘酒の原料に使用されることがあるが、酒粕には、日本食品標準成分表によるとアルコール分が約8％程度残存している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sakekasu (remains of rice when making &quot;sake&quot; or &quot;mirin&quot;), which is sometimes used as one of materials for Amazake, includes about eight percent of alcohol according to &quot;the standard tables of food composition in Japan.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sakekasu (sake lees), which is sometimes used as one of ingredients of amazake, includes about eight percent alcohol according to &quot;the standard tables of food composition in Japan.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Rewritten to read professionally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sakekasu (sake lees), which is sometimes used as one of ingredients of amazake, includes about eight percent alcohol according to &quot;the standard tables of food composition in Japan.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="13">
<j>このことから、アルコール飲料としての清酒と同様の扱いをして、本来アルコール飲料でないにもかかわらず、ドライバーが出席する場や未成年の集まる集会での振る舞いが見送られることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this reason, Amazake is often treated in a similar manner to that of sake, which is an alcoholic beverage, and serving Amazake is avoided in meetings of drivers or minors although it is a non-alcoholic beverage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this reason, although amazake is not an alcoholic beverage, is often treated in a similar manner to sake, which is an alcoholic beverage, and the serving of amazake is of avoided when drivers or children are present.</e>
<cmt>Poor translation.Completely retranslated.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For this reason, although amazake is not an alcoholic beverage, is often treated in a similar manner to sake, which is an alcoholic beverage, and the serving of amazake is of avoided when drivers or children are present.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="14">
<j>マクロビオティックでは砂糖の代わりに甘味料として使われることが多く、海外での需要も高まっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the macrobiotic therapy, Amazake is often used as an sweetener instead of sugar, and demand for Amazake is increasing in overseas markets.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the macrobiotic diet, amazake is often used as a sweetener instead of sugar, and the demand for amazake is increasing in overseas markets.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten to read professionally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the macrobiotic diet, amazake is often used as a sweetener instead of sugar, and the demand for amazake is increasing in overseas markets.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="15">
<j>山陰地方では「甘粥（アマガユ）」と言う所もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In some areas in Sanin region, Amazake is also called as Amagayu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In some parts of the Sanin region, amazake is also called as amagayu.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten to read professionally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In some parts of the Sanin region, amazake is also called as amagayu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>製法</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Production method</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Production Method</e>
<cmt>Title case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Production Method</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="16">
<j>製法は次のどちらかである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The production method of Amazake is one of the followings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amazake is produced according to one of the following methods.</e>
<cmt>Poor translation.Completely retranslated.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amazake is produced according to one of the following methods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="17">
<j>本格的製法（米こうじと米を原料とする）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Orthodox production method (rice koji (fungal spore) and rice are used as major materials)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Orthodox production method (using Aspergillus oryzae and rice)</e>
<cmt>Poor translation.Completely retranslated.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Orthodox production method (using Aspergillus oryzae and rice)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>日本酒と同様に米こうじを用い、米の粥、または水分を多めに柔らかく炊いた飯を50 - 60℃程度に保温し、1晩（10 - 12時間）程度かけて発酵させ、デンプンを糖化することで甘味を得る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a similar manner to that of sake, rice koji is mixed into rice porridge or rice cooked to contain a large amount of moisture, and the mixture is kept overnight (ten to twelve hours) at temperature of 50 to 60 degrees Celsius to cause the mixture to ferment, thus saccharifing starch contained in the mixture and obtaining sweetness.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In a similar manner to the production of sake, Aspergillus oryzae is mixed into rice porridge or rice cooked to contain a large amount of moisture, and the mixture is kept overnight (ten to twelve hours) at a temperature of 50-60°C in order to cause the mixture to ferment, thus saccharifying the starch contained within the mixture and creating a sweet taste.</e>
<cmt>Poor translation.Completely retranslated.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In a similar manner to the production of sake, Aspergillus oryzae is mixed into rice porridge or rice cooked to contain a large amount of moisture, and the mixture is kept overnight (ten to twelve hours) at a temperature of 50-60°C in order to cause the mixture to ferment, thus saccharifying the starch contained within the mixture and creating a sweet taste.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>古く「一夜酒（ひとよざけ）」と呼ばれたのはこの製法から来たものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amazake was once called as Hitoyo-zake (literally overnight rice wine) because of this production method.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amazake was once called as Hitoyo-zake (literally overnight rice wine) because of this production method.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amazake was once called as Hitoyo-zake (literally overnight rice wine) because of this production method.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>冬でないと酒を造れない造り酒屋が夏の副業に手掛けていたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that sake brewers, who could produce sake only in winter, produced Amazake as their side work in summer.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that sake brewers, who could produce sake only in winter, produced amazake as a side job during summer.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten to read naturally.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that sake brewers, who could produce sake only in winter, produced amazake as a side job during summer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="21">
<j>発酵の過程で乳酸菌が少量混入し、コウジカビの酵素による発酵のほか、乳酸発酵も進行する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the process of fermentation, as a small amount of lactic acid bacteria is mixed into the materials, lactic acid fermentation is also occurs simultaneously with fermentation due to enzymes of Aspergillus.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Lactic fermentation occurs due to a small amount of lactic acid bacteria that are added during fermentation, and fermentation by Aspergillus enzymes.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten to read professionally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Lactic fermentation occurs due to a small amount of lactic acid bacteria that are added during fermentation, and fermentation by Aspergillus enzymes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>温度が高すぎるとコウジカビの酵素が充分に作用せずに糖化が進まず甘味が乏しくなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the temperature is too high, the enzymes of Aspergillus are not active, and saccharification is therefore suppressed, resulting in less sweet Amazake</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If the temperature is too high, Aspergillus enzymes will not be sufficiently active, meaning that saccharification cannot occur and resulting in a less sweet amazake</e>
<cmt>Poor translation.Completely retranslated.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If the temperature is too high, Aspergillus enzymes will not be sufficiently active, meaning that saccharification cannot occur and resulting in a less sweet amazake</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>逆に温度が低すぎると乳酸発酵が進行しすぎ、雑菌も繁殖するので、酸味が強く風味が損なわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Conversely, when the temperature is too low, lactic acid fermentation occurs excessively and unrelated bacteria proliferate, resulting in Amazake having sour and poor flavor.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Conversely, if the temperature is too low, excessive lactic acid fermentation occurs and unrelated bacteria proliferate, resulting in bad-tasting sour amazake.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten to read professionally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Conversely, if the temperature is too low, excessive lactic acid fermentation occurs and unrelated bacteria proliferate, resulting in bad-tasting sour amazake.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>本来は砂糖を加えないが、市販のものでは砂糖など糖類を加えたものも少なくない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Amazake is traditionally served as-is, many of commercially available Amazake contain saccharides such as sugar.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Amazake is traditionally served as-is, many of the commercially available varieties contain carbohydrates such as sugar.</e>
<cmt>&quot;saccharides&quot; &gt; &quot;carbohydrates&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Amazake is traditionally served as-is, many of the commercially available varieties contain carbohydrates such as sugar.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="25">
<j>砂糖を加えないものは自然な甘さがあり、乳酸のほのかな酸味もある場合が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amazake produced by this method added with no sugar has natural sweetness and often has slightly sour flavor due to lactic acid.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amazake with no added sugar has a natural sweetness and a slightly sour taste due to lactic acid.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten to read more easily.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amazake with no added sugar has a natural sweetness and a slightly sour taste due to lactic acid.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>従って、2.の「簡略製法」よりさっぱりした味わいで珍重されるが、製造には手間がかかる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, it is highly valued due to its plain flavor as compared to those produced by the simplified production method described below, but this production method is labor-consuming.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is therefore highly valued for its flavor which is plainer when compared to varieties produced by the simplified production method described below, but this production method is labor-intensive.</e>
<cmt>Poor translation.Completely retranslated.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is therefore highly valued for its flavor which is plainer when compared to varieties produced by the simplified production method described below, but this production method is labor-intensive.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>一部の茶店や中小メーカーが現在でもこの方法を採っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some of tea shops and small to middle scale brewers produces Amazake using this production method.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some tea shops and small to middle scale brewers produces amazake using this production method.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;of&quot;&quot;Amazake&quot; &gt; &quot;amazake&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some tea shops and small to middle scale brewers produces amazake using this production method.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="28">
<j>簡略製法（酒粕を原料とする）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The simplified production method (Sakekasu is used as a major material)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Simplified production method (using sakekasu)</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for consistency</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Simplified production method (using sakekasu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>湯に酒粕を溶いて煮込み、甘味に砂糖を加える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sakekasu is simmered in water and sugar is added to add sweetness.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sakekasu is simmered in water and sugar is added for sweetness.</e>
<cmt>&quot;to add&quot; &gt; &quot;for&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sakekasu is simmered in water and sugar is added for sweetness.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>一般家庭ではこちらの製法が普通。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This production method is popular when Amazake is made at home.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This production method is popular when amazake is made at home.</e>
<cmt>Capitalization</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This production method is popular when amazake is made at home.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>通常は日本酒由来の酒粕を用いるが、こぼれ梅（みりん粕）を混ぜるのもよい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although sakekasu originated from production of sake is typically used, Kobore-ume (Mirinkasu: remains of rice when making &quot;mirin&quot;) may also be mixed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although sakekasu originating from sake production is typically used, kobore-ume (mirin lees) may also be added.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten to read professionally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although sakekasu originating from sake production is typically used, kobore-ume (mirin lees) may also be added.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>酒粕はすり鉢などを用いてよく砕いておく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sakekasu needs to be ground well by using Suribachi (Japanese mortar used with a pestle called a surikogi) in advance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sakekasu needs to be ground well by using a mortar and pestle.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten to read professionally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sakekasu needs to be ground well by using a mortar and pestle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>また、塩を一つまみ加えるといっそう味がよくなるなどといった工夫もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, addition of a pinch of salt may further improve the flavor of Amazake.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A pinch of salt may also be added to improve the flavor.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten to read professionally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A pinch of salt may also be added to improve the flavor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="34">
<j>なお、奈良時代の歌人である山上憶良が、『貧窮問答歌』において「糟湯酒」と書き記した歌を残しており、その頃から既に酒粕による甘酒の原型もあったことが窺える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Okura YAMANOUE, a poet in the Nara period left a poem including a term &quot;Kasuyuzake&quot; (literally sakekasu soup sake) in his anthology &quot;Hinkyu-mondoka&quot;, it can be considered that Amazake was already made from sakekasu at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Okura YAMANOUE, a poet in the Nara period left a poem including the term &quot;kasuyuzake&quot; (literally sakekasu soup sake) in his anthology &quot;Hinkyu-mondoka&quot;, it can be considered that amazake was already made from sakekasu at that time.</e>
<cmt>Capitalization</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Okura YAMANOUE, a poet in the Nara period left a poem including the term &quot;kasuyuzake&quot; (literally sakekasu soup sake) in his anthology &quot;Hinkyu-mondoka&quot;, it can be considered that amazake was already made from sakekasu at that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>市販の甘酒</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Commercially available Amazake</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Commercially Available Amazake</e>
<cmt>Title case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Commercially Available Amazake</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="35">
<j>主にビニール袋詰めで販売されているが、缶入りで売られている甘酒もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Amazake is typically sold in vinyl packs, some of them are sold in cans.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although amazake is typically sold in plastic packs, some varieties are sold in cans.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten to read professionally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although amazake is typically sold in plastic packs, some varieties are sold in cans.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>冬場に自動販売機で多く見かけられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In winter, Amazake is often available through vending machines</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In winter, amazake is often available at vending machines.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Amazake&quot; &gt; &quot;amazake&quot;&quot;through&quot; &gt; &quot;at&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In winter, amazake is often available at vending machines.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>これらの製法は、袋詰めについては上記の1.を、缶入りについては2.をとっている場合が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While most of Amazake sold in vinyl packs are produced by the first production method, those sold in cans are often produced by the second production method.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While most of the amazake sold in plastic packs is produced by the first production method, those sold in cans are often produced by the second production method.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Amazake&quot; &gt; &quot;amazake&quot;&quot;vinyl&quot; &gt; &quot;plastic&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While most of the amazake sold in plastic packs is produced by the first production method, those sold in cans are often produced by the second production method.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>缶入りの中身はストレートだが、袋詰めは中身を濃縮している物もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While the contents in cans are straight, the contents in vinyl packs are sometimes concentrated.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While those sold in cans are straight, those sold in plastic packs are sometimes concentrated.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten to read professionally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While those sold in cans are straight, those sold in plastic packs are sometimes concentrated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>なお森永製菓の缶入り甘酒については製法1.と2.を複合して製作しているという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Amazake sold in cans produced by Morinaga confectionary is produced by a method in which the first and second production methods are combined.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Amazake sold in cans produced by Morinaga confectionary is produced by a method in which the first and second production methods are combined.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten to read professionally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Amazake sold in cans produced by Morinaga confectionary is produced by a method in which the first and second production methods are combined.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="40">
<j>製法2.については製法1.のように発酵のために必要なスペースが不要となり、そのため製造設備もはるかに簡素ですむ（つまり設備投資が安い）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the second production method, space for fermentation, which is required in the case of the first method, is not needed, resulting in much simper (or much more economical)production facilities than that of the first production method.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the second production method, space for fermentation, which is required in the case of the first method, is not needed, resulting in much simper (or much more economical) production facilities than those of the first production method.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten to read professionally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the second production method, space for fermentation, which is required in the case of the first method, is not needed, resulting in much simper (or much more economical) production facilities than those of the first production method.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>その上に大量生産に向いているほか、酒粕はあくまで酒造の副産物であるため材料コストがはるかに安上がりという面もあると考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, in addition to the suitability to mass-production, the second method also has an advantage of the much cheaper material cost because the material, or sakekasu, is a by-product of sake production.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, in addition to the suitability to mass-production, the second method also has the advantage of much cheaper ingredient costs because sakekasu is a by-product of sake production.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten to read professionally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, in addition to the suitability to mass-production, the second method also has the advantage of much cheaper ingredient costs because sakekasu is a by-product of sake production.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="42">
<j>また、現代人の味覚が砂糖に慣らされており、従来の製法1.の方式では酸味も含むことから（現代人全般にとっては）ややさっぱりしすぎているため、濃厚な甘みをつけることが容易である製法2.を好む向きがあるとも考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, it can be considered that modern people may tend to prefer the second production method in which it is easy to add strong sweetness because modern people are accustomed to the flavor of sugar and the taste of Amazake produced by the first production method is too plain (for modern people) due to inclusion of sour taste.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Modern people are accustomed to sugar, and may find amazake produced by the first production method too bland due to its sour taste, so it could be considered that the second production method in which it is easy to add strong sweetness is preferable.</e>
<cmt>Retranslated to read more naturally.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Modern people are accustomed to sugar, and may find amazake produced by the first production method too bland due to its sour taste, so it could be considered that the second production method in which it is easy to add strong sweetness is preferable.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>飲み方</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Drinking method</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Drinking Method</e>
<cmt>Title case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Drinking Method</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="43">
<j>概要のように、今では冬季に飲まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As described in the overview, Amazake is drunk in winter recently.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As described in the overview, amazake is now drunk in winter.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Amazake&quot; &gt; &quot;amazake&quot;Added &quot;now&quot;Deleted &quot;recently&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As described in the overview, amazake is now drunk in winter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>体が温まるように(風邪の予防としても)、甘酒を熱くしショウガ汁を入れて飲まれることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hot amazake added with ginger juice is often drunk to warm your body (for the prevention of colds).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hot amazake with ginger juice added is often drunk to warm the body (to prevent colds).</e>
<cmt>Rewritten to read professionally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hot amazake with ginger juice added is often drunk to warm the body (to prevent colds).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>缶入りにもショウガ入りの製品がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amazake added with ginger juice is also sold in cans.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amazake added with ginger juice is also sold in cans.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amazake added with ginger juice is also sold in cans.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 AlleborgoBot(id:119729), Tangobot(id:47812), Kazov(id:9237), Izayohi(id:13095), Ceridwen(id:36889), Doppo1127(id:169097), マクガイア(id:33346), MASA(id:2399), 水野白楓(id:22811), Nighthawks(id:36125), 織部(id:21104), 春野秋葉(id:36725), L III (N)(id:72793), あすぺん(id:22344), 瑠璃川(id:108322), Robert De Smith(id:28533), ウェルワィ(id:15692), Hatsune(id:26654), Opponent(id:720), Doratea(id:37080), ょーこ(id:180530), リトルデビル(id:34455), A-Taul(id:41790), Koon16000(id:43615), Aoisola(id:64785), Loveless(id:129239), Nekosuki600(id:21263), Yas(id:739), FlaBot(id:30804), Suisui(id:69), Saaki(id:43602), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>