<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>人力車</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jinrikisha</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jinrikisha</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jinrikisha</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>人力車（じんりきしゃ）とは、主に明治から大正・昭和初期に移動手段として用いられた、人を輸送するための人力による車。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jinrikisha (or rickshaw) is a human-powered vehicle to transport people, mainly used as means of traveling from the Meiji period to the Taisho and the early Showa period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jinrikisha (or rickshaw) is a human-powered vehicle for transporting people, used as a means of getting around mainly from the Meiji period to the Taisho and early Showa periods.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jinrikisha (or rickshaw) is a human-powered vehicle for transporting people, used as a means of getting around mainly from the Meiji period to the Taisho and early Showa periods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>横に並べた2つの輪を持つ車に乗客を乗せ、車夫（しゃふ）がこれを曳く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A rickshaw man pulls this vehicle with transversely-arranged two wheels on which passengers sit.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Passengers sit in a carriage with two wheels on a transverse axle and which is pulled by a rickshaw man.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Passengers sit in a carriage with two wheels on a transverse axle and which is pulled by a rickshaw man.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>略して人力（じんりき）、力車（りきしゃ）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is called &apos;jinriki&apos; or &apos;rikisha&apos; for short.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is called &apos;jinriki&apos; or &apos;rikisha&apos; for short.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is called &apos;jinriki&apos; or &apos;rikisha&apos; for short.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>車夫は俥夫とも書き、また車力（しゃりき）とも言った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A rickshaw man (&apos;車夫&apos;) is also written as &apos;俥夫,&apos; and called &apos;shariki,&apos; too.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A rickshaw man (&apos;車夫&apos;) is also written as &apos;俥夫,&apos; and called &apos;shariki,&apos; too.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A rickshaw man (&apos;車夫&apos;) is also written as &apos;俥夫,&apos; and called &apos;shariki,&apos; too.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>また英語の Rickshaw（発音＝リクショウ）は「リキシャ」を語源とする日本語由来の英単語。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And the English word rickshaw (pronounced as/ri&apos;kʃɔː/) originates from the Japanese word &apos;rikisha.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The English word rickshaw comes from the Japanese word &apos;rikisha.&apos;</e>
<cmt>*I don&apos;t think the IPA symbols would help the average English speaker</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The English word rickshaw comes from the Japanese word &apos;rikisha.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>人力車には乗客が一人乗りのものや二人乗りのものなどがあるが、日本で普及したのは一人乗りのものが圧倒的に多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although jinrikisha can hold one or two passengers, the one-seater jinrikisha was overwhelmingly popular in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although jinrikisha can hold one or two passengers, the one-seater jinrikisha was overwhelmingly popular in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although jinrikisha can hold one or two passengers, the one-seater jinrikisha was overwhelmingly popular in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>また車夫は通常一人だが、特に急ぎの場合などは二人以上で引いたり、時には押したり、交代要員の車夫が併走したりすることもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jinrikisha was usually operated by one rickshaw man; however, when a passenger was in a hurry, more than two rickshaw men could pull or push together, or sometimes a replacement rickshaw man could accompany and run together.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jinrikisha were usually operated by one rickshaw man; however, when a passenger was in a hurry, two or more rickshaw men could pull, and sometimes push, together or a replacement rickshaw man would run alongside.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jinrikisha were usually operated by one rickshaw man; however, when a passenger was in a hurry, two or more rickshaw men could pull, and sometimes push, together or a replacement rickshaw man would run alongside.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>現代の日本における人力車</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jinrikisha in Japan today</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jinrikisha in Japan today</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jinrikisha in Japan today</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>運送手段としての人力車</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jinrikisha as a mode of transport</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jinrikisha as a mode of transport</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jinrikisha as a mode of transport</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>都市圏では昭和元年頃、地方でも昭和10年頃をピークに減少し、戦後、車両の払底・燃料難という事情から僅かに復活したことがあるが、現在では一般的な交通・運送手段としての人力車は存在していない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The number of jinrikisha decreased in the metropolitan area of Tokyo around 1926, as well as in the countryside after the peak year around 1935, followed by a slight increase in number after the war when the vehicles became scarce and the fuel crisis occurred; however, there is no jinrikisha used for travel and transport nowadays.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The number of jinrikisha decreased in the Tokyo metropolitan area around 1926, and peaked in the provinces around 1935, followed by a slight increase in number after the war when the vehicles and fuel were scarce; however, no jinrikisha are used for travel and transport nowadays.</e>
<cmt>*Revised for clarity, though I think this sentence could be split in half</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The number of jinrikisha decreased in the Tokyo metropolitan area around 1926, and peaked in the provinces around 1935, followed by a slight increase in number after the war when the vehicles and fuel were scarce; however, no jinrikisha are used for travel and transport nowadays.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>現在は主に観光地での遊覧目的に営業が行われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today, jinrikisha is mainly used for sightseeing tour business in tourist spots.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, jinrikisha are mainly used for sightseeing tours in tourist spots.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, jinrikisha are mainly used for sightseeing tours in tourist spots.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>当初、京都、鎌倉といった風雅な街並みが残る観光地、又は浅草などの人力車の似合う下町での営業が始まり、次第に伊豆伊東、道後温泉といった温泉町や「無法松の一生」にちなむ門司港、有名観光地である中華街などに広がっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The business initially started in the tourist spots with the tasteful townscapes such as Kyoto and Kamakura, or in downtown like the Asakusa region of Tokyo where jinrikisha could blend well with scenery, and it gradually spread to hot-spring resorts such as Ito Onsen in the Izu area and Dogo Onsen, to the port of Moji related to the Japanese movie &apos;Muhomatsu no issho (Wild Matsu the Rickshaw Man)&apos;, and to Chinatowns in the famous tourist spots.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such businesses initially started in tourist spots with elegant townscapes such as Kyoto and Kamakura, or in downtown areas like Asakusa in Tokyo where jinrikisha blend in well with the scenery, and gradually spread to hot-spring resorts such as Ito Onsen in the Izu area and Dogo Onsen, and the port of Moji, which appears in the movie &apos;Muhomatsu no issho (Wild Matsu the Rickshaw Man)&apos;, and to famous Chinatowns.</e>
<cmt>*The various versions of 無法松の一生 have different English names, including &apos;Rickshaw Man&apos; and &apos;The Life of Matsu the Untamed&apos; but left it as originally translated</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such businesses initially started in tourist spots with elegant townscapes such as Kyoto and Kamakura, or in downtown areas like Asakusa in Tokyo where jinrikisha blend in well with the scenery, and gradually spread to hot-spring resorts such as Ito Onsen in the Izu area and Dogo Onsen, and the port of Moji, which appears in the movie &apos;Muhomatsu no issho&apos; (Wild Matsu the Rickshaw Man), and to famous Chinatowns.</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>観光名所をコースで遊覧し、車夫が観光ガイドとして解説してくれるものが一般的である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In general, jinrikisha takes you to tourist attractions on sightseeing tours accompanied by a rickshaw man who gives the commentary as a tour guide.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In general, jinrikisha take people to tourist attractions on sightseeing tours, with commentary provided by the rickshaw man, who acts as a tour guide.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In general, jinrikisha take people to tourist attractions on sightseeing tours, with commentary provided by the rickshaw man, who acts as a tour guide.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>北海道では小樽市、東京都内では浅草、埼玉県では川越市、千葉県では成田市、神奈川県では鎌倉市と中華街、静岡県では伊東市と掛川市、松崎町、岐阜県では高山市・郡上八幡、京都府では嵐山・左京区・東山区、奈良県では奈良公園、愛媛県では松山道後温泉、九州地方では福岡県の門司港、大分県の由布市で利用できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The sightseeing tours are available in the following locations: Otaru City in Hokkaido Prefecture; the Asakusa region of Tokyo; Kawagoe City in Saitama Prefecture; Narita City in Chiba Prefecture; Kamakura City and Chinatown in Kanagawa Prefecture; Ito City, Kakegawa City, and Matsuzaki Town in Shizuoka Prefecture; Takayaka City and Gujohachiman Town in Gifu Prefecture; the Arashiyama district, the Sakyo Ward, and the Higashiyama Ward in Kyoto Prefecture; Nara Park in Nara Prefecture; Dogo Onsen, Matsuyama, in Ehime Prefecture; and the port of Moji in Fukuoka Prefecture and Yufu City in Oita Prefecture in the Kyushu region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sightseeing tours are available in the following locations: Otaru City in Hokkaido Prefecture; the Asakusa district of Tokyo; Kawagoe City in Saitama Prefecture; Narita City in Chiba Prefecture; Kamakura City and Chinatown in Kanagawa Prefecture; Ito City, Kakegawa City, and Matsuzaki Town in Shizuoka Prefecture; Takayaka City and Gujohachiman Town in Gifu Prefecture; the Arashiyama district, Sakyo Ward, and Higashiyama Ward in Kyoto Prefecture; Nara Park in Nara Prefecture; Dogo Onsen, Matsuyama, in Ehime Prefecture; and, in Kyushu, the port of Moji in Fukuoka Prefecture and Yufu City in Oita Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sightseeing tours are available in the following locations: Otaru City in Hokkaido Prefecture; the Asakusa district of Tokyo; Kawagoe City in Saitama Prefecture; Narita City in Chiba Prefecture; Kamakura City and Chinatown in Kanagawa Prefecture; Ito City, Kakegawa City, and Matsuzaki Town in Shizuoka Prefecture; Takayama City and Gujohachiman Town in Gifu Prefecture; the Arashiyama district, Sakyo Ward, and Higashiyama Ward in Kyoto Prefecture; Nara Park in Nara Prefecture; Dogo Onsen, Matsuyama, in Ehime Prefecture; and, in Kyushu, the port of Moji in Fukuoka Prefecture and Yufu City in Oita Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>現行の道路交通法では人力車は軽車両の扱いとなるが、自転車とはならないため、自転車道および道路標識によって自転車通行可とされた歩道を通行する事は出来ない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under the current Road Traffic Act, jinrikisha is regarded as a light vehicle, not a bicycle; thus, it cannot be driven on either bicycle roads or sidewalks where bicycles can travel based on the road sign.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the current Road Traffic Act, jinrikisha are regarded as light vehicles, rather than bicycles, and therefore cannot use bicycle lanes or sidewalks where signposts permit bicycles.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the current Road Traffic Act, jinrikisha are regarded as light vehicles, rather than bicycles, and therefore cannot use bicycle lanes or sidewalks where signposts permit bicycles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="14">
<j>観光人力車の乗車料金は10分程度の移動時間中に観光案内を含めた初乗り運賃が1人当たり1000 - 2000円から15分・30分・60分・貸切などさまざまである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The jinrikisha fare for sightseeing varies depending on the duration of the ride, for example 1,000 to 2,000 yen per person as the minimum fare including the sightseeing while traveling for approximately 10 minutes, or other fares for 15-, 30-, or 60-minute ride, or for a chartered jinrikisha.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fares start at 1,000 to 2,000 yen per person for about ten minutes, including sightseeing, with various other fares for fifteen, thirty, or sixty minutes, or for a chartered jinrikisha.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fares start at 1,000 to 2,000 yen per person for about ten minutes, including sightseeing, with various other fares for fifteen, thirty, or sixty minutes, or for a chartered jinrikisha.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>2人乗りのものに3人乗車することも可能であるが、相当な重さになることから、観光人力車では料金を割り増しとするものが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although it is possible to have three people ride on a two-seater jinrikisha for sightseeing, the extra fare will be added in most cases due to the considerable weight.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although it is possible to have three people ride on a two-seater jinrikisha for sightseeing, the extra fare will be added in most cases due to the considerable weight.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it is possible to have three people ride on a two-seater jinrikisha for sightseeing, the extra fare will be added in most cases due to the considerable weight.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="16">
<j>観光人力車では到着した後の観光客への観光案内時間中の駐輪場所の整備、客待ち時における待機場所の整備が遅れている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for jinrikisha for sightseeing, there are some delays in developing parking spaces in which jinrikisha can be kept while tourists are given escorted tours at the destination, and in securing waiting positions in which it can be kept before serving customers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There have been some delays in developing parking spaces in which jinrikisha can be kept while tourists are given tours at the destination, and in securing rickshaw ranks where they can wait for customers.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There have been some delays in developing parking spaces in which jinrikisha can be kept while tourists are given tours at the destination, and in securing rickshaw ranks where they can wait for customers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="17">
<j>観光人力車の他、結婚式やお祭りなどでの演出としての使用や、歌舞伎役者のお練りなどに使用されることがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides sightseeing, jinrikisha is sometimes used in performance at wedding ceremonies or festivals, as well as in parades of kabuki actors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides sightseeing, jinrikisha are sometimes used in wedding ceremonies and festivals, as well as in parades of kabuki actors.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides sightseeing, jinrikisha are sometimes used in wedding ceremonies and festivals, as well as in parades of kabuki actors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>人力車の保存</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Preservation of jinrikisha</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Preservation of Jinrikisha</e>
<cmt>Capital letter</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Preservation of jinrikisha</e>
<cmt>文頭のみ大文字にしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="18">
<j>昭和初期までは一般的に存在した庶民的な車両であるため、交通博物館（2006年5月14日に移転の為閉鎖）をはじめ、各地の博物館や資料館などで保存されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because jinrikisha was a popular vehicle which was commonly found before the early Showa period, it is stored in the Transportation Museum (which closed down on 14 May, 2006 due to relocation), or in museums and resource centers at various locations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because jinrikisha were a common and popular form of transport until the early Showa period, they were stored in Tokyo&apos;s Transportation Museum (which closed down on 14 May, 2006 due to relocation), and are kept in museums and resource centers around the country.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because jinrikisha were a common and popular form of transport until the early Showa period, they were stored in Tokyo&apos;s Transportation Museum (which closed down on 14 May, 2006 due to relocation), and are kept in museums and resource centers around the country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>ただし、展示されてる人力車には修復されたものや展示のために新たに製造されたものもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, some jinrikisha on display were once repaired or newly-built for display.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, some jinrikisha on display have been refurbished or specially built for display.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, some jinrikisha on display have been refurbished or specially built for display.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>人力車の製造</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Production of jinrikisha</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Production of Jinrikisha</e>
<cmt>Capital letter</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Production of jinrikisha</e>
<cmt>文頭のみ大文字にしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="20">
<j>観光人力車や博物館展示用の人力車製造が続けられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jinrikisha for sightseeing and museum display are still in production.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jinrikisha are still produced for sightseeing and museum display.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jinrikisha are still produced for sightseeing and museum display.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>製造台数の多いメーカーとしては静岡県伊東市の株式会社升屋製作所を挙げることができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Masuya Seisakujo factory located in Ito City, Shizuoka Prefecture, could be the leading manufacturer of jinrikisha.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Masuya Seisakujo factory located in Ito City, Shizuoka Prefecture, could be the leading manufacturer of jinrikisha.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Masuya Seisakujo factory located in Ito City, Shizuoka Prefecture, could be the leading manufacturer of jinrikisha.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>欧米における歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History of jinrikisha in Europe and the United States</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History of Jinrikisha in the West</e>
<cmt>Capital letter</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History of jinrikisha in the west</e>
<cmt>文頭のみ大文字にしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="22">
<j>クロード・ジロー (Claude Gillot) が1707年に描いた「Les Deux Carrosses」（直訳：「両方に客がいる」）という滑稽な絵がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a comical painting titled &apos;Les Deux Carrosses&apos; (literally translated: &apos;The Two Coaches&apos;) by Claude Gillot, created in 1707.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1707, Claude Gillot painted the comical work &apos;Les Deux Carrosses&apos; (literally &apos;The Two Coaches&apos;).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1707, Claude Gillot painted the comical work &apos;Les Deux Carrosses&apos; (literally &apos;The Two Coaches&apos;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>この中に、2台の人力車のような手押し車が描かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This painting shows two jinrikisha-like carts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The painting shows two jinrikisha-like carts.</e>
<cmt>Article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The painting shows two jinrikisha-like carts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>これらの手押し車は、17世紀から18世紀にかけてパリの街中で使われていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These carts were used in the city of Paris in the seventeenth and the eighteenth centuries.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These carts were used in the city of Paris in the seventeenth and eighteenth centuries.</e>
<cmt>Article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These carts were used in the city of Paris in the seventeenth and eighteenth centuries.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>ワイナリーでワイン樽のような大きな荷物を運ぶのを目的として作られたものに似ていたことから、ビネグレット (vinaigrettes) と呼ばれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were called &apos;vinaigrettes&apos; for the reason that they resembled the products created for transporting big packages like wine casks at wineries.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were called &apos;vinaigrettes&apos; for the reason that they resembled the carts made for transporting large items like wine casks at wineries.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were called &apos;vinaigrettes&apos; for the reason that they resembled the carts made for transporting large items like wine casks at wineries.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>人力車の発明</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Invention of jinrikisha</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Invention of Jinrikisha</e>
<cmt>Capital letter</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Invention of jinrikisha</e>
<cmt>文頭のみ大文字にしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="26">
<j>現在世界中で使われている人力車の起源は、1868年頃の明治初期の日本であると考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that the origin of jinrikisha currently used around the world goes back around 1868, the early Meiji period in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that the jinrikisha currently used around the world originated in Japan in 1868, during the early Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that the jinrikisha currently used around the world originated in Japan in 1868, during the early Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="27">
<j>当時の日本で発明された人力車は、それまで使われていた駕籠より速かったのと、ウマよりも人間の労働コストのほうがはるかに安かったため、すぐに人気の交通手段になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because jinrikisha invented in Japan at that time could go faster than the previously used palanquins, and human labor was considerably cheaper than using horses, it soon became a popular mode of transportation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since jinrikisha, invented in Japan at that time, could go faster than the previously used palanquins, and human labor was considerably cheaper than using horses, it soon became a popular mode of transportation.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since jinrikisha, invented in Japan at that time, could go faster than the previously used palanquins, and human labor was considerably cheaper than using horses, it soon became a popular mode of transportation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="28">
<j>人力車のはっきりとした発明者は判っていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is uncertain who invented jinrikisha.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is uncertain who invented the jinrikisha.</e>
<cmt>Article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is uncertain who invented the jinrikisha.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>僅かな根拠からアメリカ合衆国国民の鍛冶屋アルバート・トルマン (Albert Tolman) ではないかとも言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some sources say it could be Albert Tolman, an American blacksmith.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some sources say it could be Albert Tolman, an American blacksmith.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some sources say it could be Albert Tolman, an American blacksmith.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>彼は1848年にマサチューセッツ州のウォルセスターで宣教師のために人力車を発明したと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that he invented jinrikisha for a missionary in Worcester, Massachusetts, in 1848.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that he invented the jinrikisha for a missionary in Worcester, Massachusetts, in 1848.</e>
<cmt>Article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that he invented the jinrikisha for a missionary in Worcester, Massachusetts, in 1848.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="31">
<j>また、日本に滞在していたアメリカ合衆国国民宣教師・ジョナサン・ゴーブル（またはジョナサン・スコビー (Jonathan Scobie)）が1869年頃に発明したという説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Others claim that Jonathan Scobie, an American missionary to Japan, invented jinrikisha around 1869.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Others claim that Jonathan Scobie, an American missionary to Japan, invented the jinrikisha around 1869.</e>
<cmt>Article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Others claim that Jonathan Scobie, an American missionary to Japan, invented the jinrikisha around 1869.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>彼の妻は病弱だったため、彼女を人力車に乗せて横浜市の往来を行き来したと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that he transported his invalid wife on the jinrikisha through the streets of Yokohama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that he transported his invalid wife in a jinrikisha through the streets of Yokohama.</e>
<cmt>PrepositionArticle</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that he transported his invalid wife in a jinrikisha through the streets of Yokohama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>日本での普及</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Popularity in Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Popularity in Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Popularity in Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="33">
<j>日本では和泉要助、高山幸助、鈴木徳次郎が発明者だと信じられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed in Japan that jinrikisha was invented by Yosuke IZUMI, Kosuke TAKAYAMA, and Tokujiro SUZUKI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed in Japan that the jinrikisha was invented by Yosuke IZUMI, Kosuke TAKAYAMA, and Tokujiro SUZUKI.</e>
<cmt>Article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed in Japan that the jinrikisha was invented by Yosuke IZUMI, Kosuke TAKAYAMA, and Tokujiro SUZUKI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>彼らは東京で見た馬車から人力車を発想し、1868年に人力車を発明した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were inspired by the horse-drawn carriages they saw in Tokyo and invented jinrikisha in 1868.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were inspired by the horse-drawn carriages they saw in Tokyo and invented jinrikisha in 1868.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were inspired by the horse-drawn carriages they saw in Tokyo and invented jinrikisha in 1868.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="35">
<j>1870年、東京府は彼らに人力車の製造と販売の許可を与えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1870, Tokyo Prefecture issued a permission to build and sell jinrikisha to these men.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1870, Tokyo Prefecture gave them permission to build and sell jinrikisha.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1870, Tokyo Prefecture gave them permission to build and sell jinrikisha.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>条件として人力車は華美にしないこと、事故を起こした場合には処罰する旨があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It required them to decorate jinrikisha in a less ostentatious manner, and in case of accidents, they were subject to the penalty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This required them to decorate jinrikisha in a less ostentatious manner, and in case of accidents, they would be subject to a penalty.</e>
<cmt>ArticlePronoun</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This required them to decorate jinrikisha in a less ostentatious manner, and in case of accidents, they would be subject to a penalty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>この許可をもって「人力車総行司」と称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With this permission, they were called &apos;Jinrikisha Sogyoji.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With this permission, they were called &apos;Jinrikisha Sogyoji.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With this permission, they were called &apos;Jinrikisha Sogyoji.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>人力車を新たに購入する場合にはこの3名の何れかから許可をもらうこととなったが、後述のとおり数年で有名無実となってしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An authorization from one of these men was required to purchase a new jinrikisha; however, it became ineffective in a few years as described below.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Authorization from one of these men was required to purchase a new jinrikisha, although, as described below, this became ineffective after a few years.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Authorization from one of these men was required to purchase a new jinrikisha, although, as described below, this became ineffective after a few years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>同年、人力車の運転免許証の発行が開始されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same year, the license to operate jinrikisha started being issued.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same year, licenses to operate jinrikisha started being issued.</e>
<cmt>Plural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same year, licenses to operate jinrikisha started being issued.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="40">
<j>その後1872年までにそれまで東京市内にあった1万の籠は姿を消したかわり、人力車は4万台まで増加し、日本の代表的な公共輸送機関になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, 10,000 palanquins that had previously existed in Tokyo City disappeared by 1872, and the number of jinrikisha increased up to 40,000 instead, which made it the chief form of public transportation in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The 10,000 palanquins that had previously existed in Tokyo City disappeared by 1872, while the number of jinrikisha rose to 40,000, making it the chief form of public transportation in Japan.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The 10,000 palanquins that had previously existed in Tokyo City disappeared by 1872, while the number of jinrikisha rose to 40,000, making it the chief form of public transportation in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>1876年には東京府内で2万5038台と記録されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is reported that the number of jinrikisha was 25,038 in Tokyo Prefecture in 1876.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is reported that the number of jinrikisha in Tokyo Prefecture in 1876 was 25,038.</e>
<cmt>Word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is reported that the number of jinrikisha in Tokyo Prefecture in 1876 was 25,038.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>19世紀末の日本には20万台を越す人力車があったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also said that there were over 200,000 jinrikisha in Japan at the end of the 19th century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also said that there were over 200,000 jinrikisha in Japan at the end of the 19th century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also said that there were over 200,000 jinrikisha in Japan at the end of the 19th century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="43">
<j>また、1870年代半ばより中国を中心として東南アジアやインドに至るアジア各地への輸出が始まり、特に東京銀座に秋葉商店を構えた秋葉大助はほろや泥除けのある現在見るような人力車を考案し、性能を高め贅を凝らした装飾的な人力車を制作し、その多くを輸出して大きな富を得た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, from the middle of the 1870s the export of jinrikisha started to the various countries of Asia, ranging from Southeast Asia, centered in China, to India; and in particular, Daisuke AKIBA, who set up a company called Akiba Store in Ginza, Tokyo, invented the current version of jinrikisha with a covered top and mud flaps, produced the decorative jinrikisha with high performance and sumptuous appearance, and made huge profits by exporting most of the products.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, from the mid-1870s, jinrikisha began to be exported to various Asian countries, ranging from Southeast Asia, centered on China, to India; in particular, Daisuke AKIBA, who opened a shop called Akiba Store in Ginza, Tokyo, invented the current version of the jinrikisha with a covered top and mud flaps, producing decorative jinrikisha with high performance and a sumptuous appearance and making huge profits by exporting most of them.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, from the mid-1870s, jinrikisha began to be exported to various Asian countries, ranging from Southeast Asia, centered on China, to India; in particular, Daisuke AKIBA, who opened a shop called Akiba Store in Ginza, Tokyo, invented the current version of the jinrikisha with a covered top and mud flaps, producing decorative jinrikisha with high performance and a sumptuous appearance and making huge profits by exporting most of them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>他方、当初人力車の製造と使用を許可された和泉たちは激増する車夫たちすべてから使用料を取ることができず、また当時の特許制度（「専売略規則」）の不備・使いにくさもあいまってほとんど利益を上げることができなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the contrary, Izumi and others, who were initially authorized to build and use jinrikisha, had difficulty collecting the usage fees from all the drastically-increasing number of rickshaw men, and they could not gain any profit, coupled with the fact that the original patent system (&apos;Summary Rules of Monopoly&apos;) was inadequate and hard to use.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, Izumi and the others, who had initially been authorized to build and use jinrikisha, had difficulty collecting the usage fees from all the drastically-increasing rickshaw men, which, coupled with the fact that the original patent system (&apos;Summary Rules of Monopoly&apos;) was inadequate and hard to use, meant they were unable to make any profit.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, Izumi and the others, who had initially been authorized to build and use jinrikisha, had difficulty collecting the usage fees from all the drastically-increasing rickshaw men, which, coupled with the fact that the original patent system (&apos;Summary Rules of Monopoly&apos;) was inadequate and hard to use, meant they were unable to make any profit.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>この事実が、後に日本に本格的な特許制度の誕生をうながした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This eventually accelerated the introduction of the actual patent system in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This eventually accelerated the introduction of a comprehensive patent system in Japan.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This eventually accelerated the introduction of a comprehensive patent system in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>アジア各地への展開</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Expansion into Asia</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Expansion into Asia</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Expansion into Asia</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="46">
<j>1880年頃、人力車はインドに導入される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around 1880, jinrikisha was introduced to India.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around 1880, jinrikisha were introduced to India.</e>
<cmt>Plural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around 1880, jinrikisha were introduced to India.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>最初はシムラー、20年遅れてコルカタ（カルカッタ）に現れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It first appeared in Shimla, and 20 years later, in Kolkata (Calcutta).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They first appeared in Shimla, and 20 years later, in Kolkata (Calcutta).</e>
<cmt>Pronoun</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They first appeared in Shimla, and 20 years later, in Kolkata (Calcutta).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>インドでは、まず中国人の運搬装置の商人が使い始めた1914年にその中国人たちが人力車を乗物として使用できるように許可を申請した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In India, Chinese traders to transport goods initially started using jinrikisha in 1914 and applied for permission to use it to transport passengers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In India, Chinese traders initially started using them in 1914 to transport goods and then applied for permission to use them to transport passengers.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In India, Chinese traders initially started using them in 1914 to transport goods and then applied for permission to use them to transport passengers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="49">
<j>そのあとすぐに、人力車は東南アジアの多くの大都市で見られるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soon after, jinrikisha appeared in many big cities in Southeast Asia.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soon after, jinrikisha appeared in many big cities in Southeast Asia.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soon after, jinrikisha appeared in many big cities in Southeast Asia.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>多くの場合、人力車の運転手は、都市に移住してきた地方労働者の最初にありつく仕事であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In many cases, pulling jinrikisha was the first job available for workers migrating to these cities.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In many cases, pulling jinrikisha was the first job available for workers migrating to these cities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In many cases, pulling jinrikisha was the first job available for workers migrating to these cities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="51">
<j>中国では日本製の人力車が爆発的に広まり、「黄包車」の別名でも呼ばれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In China, the Japanese jinrikisha became explosively widespread and was also called &apos;Huang bao che (hired car).&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In China, where it was also known as a &apos;huang bao che&apos; (hired car), Japanese-made jinrikisha spread explosively throughout the country.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In China, where it was also known as a &apos;huang bao che&apos; (hired car), Japanese-made jinrikisha spread explosively throughout the country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>さらに国産の人力車工場が各地に建てられ、全土に人力車が広まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, the factories to produce the domestic jinrikisha were built in the various locations, and jinrikisha became popular throughout China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, factories to produce domestic jinrikisha were built in various locations throughout China, and jinrikisha became popular all over the country.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, factories to produce domestic jinrikisha were built in various locations throughout China, and jinrikisha became popular all over the country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>上海市には大小100を超える人力車工場があったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that there were over 100 jinrikisha factories of various sized in the city of Shanghai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that there were over 100 jinrikisha factories of various sizes in Shanghai.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that there were over 100 jinrikisha factories of various sizes in Shanghai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="54">
<j>ただし1949年以降、中国を統治した中国共産党により、人力車は禁止されるに至った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the use of jinrikisha was prohibited after 1949 by the Chinese Communist Party that governed China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the use of jinrikisha was prohibited after 1949 when the Chinese Communist Party came to power.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the use of jinrikisha was prohibited after 1949 when the Chinese Communist Party came to power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>アジア各国での人力車</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jinrikisha in Asia</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jinrikisha in Asia</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jinrikisha in Asia</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="55">
<j>アジア各国へ日本から人力車が輸出され、地元に根付いたことから、現在でもリキシャなどの名前で人力車が残っていることがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because jinrikisha was exported from Japan to the various countries of Asia and it took root in these areas, there are still some remaining jinrikisha called rikisha.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jinrikisha can still be seen in various Asian countries, where they took root after being exported from Japan and go by names such as &apos;rikisha.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jinrikisha can still be seen in various Asian countries, where they took root after being exported from Japan and go by names such as &apos;rikisha.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>その多くは装飾が施されて派手なものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most of them are brightly and boldly decorated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most of them are gaudily decorated with ornaments.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most of them are gaudily decorated with ornaments.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>また、人が歩いて引くのではなくて自転車が引くように改良されたものも見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are also some modified-style jinrikisha which can be pulled by a bicycle, not by a man.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are also some modified jinrikisha which can be pulled by a bicycle, rather than a man.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are also some modified jinrikisha which can be pulled by a bicycle, rather than a man.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="58">
<j>またインドでは、しばしばリキシャはリクシャとも発音される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In India, &apos;rikisha&apos; is sometimes pronounced as &apos;rikusha.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In India, &apos;rikisha&apos; is sometimes pronounced as &apos;rikusha.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In India, &apos;rikisha&apos; is sometimes pronounced as &apos;rikusha.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>人力車の運転手をリクシャワーラーまたはリクシャプーラーと言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A rickshaw man is called &apos;rickshawer&apos; or &apos;rickshaw puller.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A rickshaw man is called a &apos;rickshaw wallah&apos; or &apos;rickshaw puller.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A rickshaw man is called a &apos;rickshaw wallah&apos; or &apos;rickshaw puller.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="60">
<j>コルカタの人力車</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jinrikisha in Kolkata</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jinrikisha in Kolkata</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jinrikisha in Kolkata</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="61">
<j>1919年、市が正式な交通手段として認定する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1919, the city approved jinrikisha as a proper means of transportation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1919, the city approved jinrikisha as a proper means of transportation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1919, the city approved jinrikisha as a proper means of transportation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="62">
<j>1972年以降、インドのコルカタではいくつかの通りで人力車が禁止された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After 1972, the use of jinrikisha was prohibited on some streets in Kolkata, India.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since 1972, the use of jinrikisha has been prohibited on some streets in Kolkata, India.</e>
<cmt>*Since this section is titled &quot;Jinrikisha in Kolkatta&quot;, I&apos;m not sure that the &quot;in Kolkata, India&quot; bit is necessary, but I left it in</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since 1972, the use of jinrikisha has been prohibited on some streets in Kolkata, India.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="63">
<j>1982年、市当局は1万2000台以上の人力車を押収し、廃棄した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1982, the city seized more than 12,000 jinrikisha and destroyed them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1982, the city seized more than 12,000 jinrikisha and destroyed them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1982, the city seized more than 12,000 jinrikisha and destroyed them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="64">
<j>1992年の調査では、3万台以上の人力車が営業中で、そのうち6千台が違法車両や未許可車両であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1992, it was estimated that over 30,000 jinrikisha were operating, including 6,000 jinrikisha as illegal or unauthorized vehicles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1992, it was estimated that over 30,000 jinrikisha were operating, including 6,000 illegal or unauthorized vehicles.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1992, it was estimated that over 30,000 jinrikisha were operating, including 6,000 illegal or unauthorized vehicles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="65">
<j>新しい許可は1945年以降出されれていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">No new licenses have been issued since 1945.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">No new licenses have been issued since 1945.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">No new licenses have been issued since 1945.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="66">
<j>料金は1回の移動につき2、3ドルである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The jinrikisha fare per ride is around two to three dollars.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The jinrikisha fare is around two to three dollars per ride.</e>
<cmt>Word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The jinrikisha fare is around two to three dollars per ride.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>リクシャワーラーのほとんどは簡易な宿舎に住み、仕送りをするために節約している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most of rickshawers live in makeshift dorms, trying to save money to send home.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most rickshaw wallahs live in makeshift dorms, trying to save money to send home.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most rickshaw wallahs live in makeshift dorms, trying to save money to send home.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="68">
<j>2005年8月に西ベンガル共産政府は完全に人力車を締め出す計画を発表したが、リクシャワーラーの抗議とストライキに終始した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In August 2005, the Communist government of West Bengal announced a plan to completely exclude jinrikisha, resulting in protests and strikes of the rickshawers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In August 2005, the Communist government of West Bengal announced a plan to completely bar jinrikisha, resulting in protests and strikes by the rickshaw wallahs.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In August 2005, the Communist government of West Bengal announced a plan to completely bar jinrikisha, resulting in protests and strikes by the rickshaw wallahs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="69">
<j>年現在、かなりの数の人力車がコルカタにまだ残っており、約8000台、2万人の車夫がいるとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As of 2009, there are still many jinrikisha remaining in Kolkata, estimated to be around 8,000 jinrikisha and 20,000 rickshaw men.</e>
<cmt>年号をウェブから補いました</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As of 2009, there are still many jinrikisha remaining in Kolkata, with an estimated 8,000 vehicles and 20,000 rickshaw men.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As of 2009, there are still many jinrikisha remaining in Kolkata, with an estimated 8,000 vehicles and 20,000 rickshaw men.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>リクシャワーラーの組合は、人力車の禁止に強く反対している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The union of rickshawers is strongly against the prohibition of jinrikisha.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The rickshaw wallahs&apos; union is strongly against the prohibition of jinrikisha.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The rickshaw wallahs&apos; union is strongly against the prohibition of jinrikisha.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 AlleborgoBot(id:119729), Tomzo(id:16777), 竹富島(id:97808), 松浸史(id:78240), Shizhao(id:1325), Neruru(id:95432), 経済準学士(id:22656), 0null0(id:582), Herr Weißes(id:71029), Eskimbot(id:29676), TXiKiBoT(id:107492), ＲＪＡＮＫＡ(id:118019), 田舎者(id:66312), DrFO.Tn.Bot(id:219878), Gnsin(id:12351), OKBot(id:143139), Toto-tarou(id:16648), Opponent(id:720), Vini 17bot5(id:230303), IwaimBot(id:190695), Loveless(id:129239), Itlum(id:181571), Chobot(id:20846), Point136(id:211299), Pipimaru(id:24707), 赤鉛筆(id:2434), Way of Five Pecks of Rice(id:32668), Starbacks(id:1018), ArthurBot(id:265089), Lombroso(id:20212), Escarbot(id:59151), Zwobot(id:23873), Shinkansen(id:13703), Hatsune(id:26654), レッドバロン(id:173220), Rusk(id:9895), Usagito(id:2150), Thijs!bot(id:69644), VolkovBot(id:105371), SilvonenBot(id:190970), 電脳プリオン(id:5424), Kyube(id:9866), Samiadon(id:13976), SuisuiBot(id:10165), Mochi(id:9489), 茶品(id:120570), Alexbot(id:157199), Louperibot(id:128971), SieBot(id:126695), ToePeu.bot(id:157833), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>