<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>葛餅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kuzu-mochi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kuzumochi (kudzu starch cake)</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kuzumochi (kudzu starch cake)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>葛餅、（くずもち、くず餅）は、葛粉から作られる和菓子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kuzu-mochi cake is a Japanese cake produced from kuzu-ko powder (powdered kuzu starch).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kuzumochi&quot; are Japanese cakes made of kuzuko (kudzu starch).</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Kuzumochi&quot; are Japanese cakes made of kuzuko (kudzu starch).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>久寿餅は、小麦粉を発酵した物で作り、主に関東地区で食べられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is another kind of kuzu-mochi which is produced from fermented wheat flour and which is mainly eaten in Kanto Region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is another kind of kuzumochi which is made of fermented wheat flour and mainly eaten in Kanto Region.</e>
<cmt>kind of から先を全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is another kind of kuzumochi which is made of fermented wheat flour and mainly eaten in Kanto Region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="3">
<j>また沖縄でのくず餅は葛粉の代わりに芋くずと呼ばれるサツマイモデンプンからつくられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kuzu-mochi in Okinawa is produced from sweet potato starch called imo-kuzu (potato garbage) instead of kuzu-ko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kuzumochi in Okinawa are made of sweet potato starch called imokuzu instead of kuzuko.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kuzumochi in Okinawa are made of sweet potato starch called imokuzu instead of kuzuko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>色は透明～半透明で、ぷるんとした独特の食感がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kuzu-mochi is transparent to translucent and provides the feeling unique to it such as smoothness and elasticity when eaten.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The color of kuzumochi is transparent to translucent and it has a unique texture with smoothness and elasticity.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The color of kuzumochi is transparent to translucent and it has a unique texture with smoothness and elasticity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>透明な生地に餡を包んだものは饅頭和菓子としての饅頭 と呼ばれ、涼しげな見た目から夏の菓子として人気があり、神奈川県川崎市平間寺と東京都大田区池上本門寺と東京都江東区亀戸天神社の名物でもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A cake produced by wrapping an (sweet sticky beans) with transparent dough is called manju (dumpling) as a manju Japanese cake and is popular as a cake in summer because of its cool appearance and this cake is a famous souvenir of Hirama-ji temple in Kawasaki City in Kanagawa Prefecture, Ikegami-honmon-ji temple in Ota Ward in Tokyo, and Kameid-tenjinja shrine in Koto Ward in Tokyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those with transparent dough wrapped around red bean paste are called &quot;manju&quot; (dumpling) as manju Japanese cakes, which are popular summer desserts because of their cool appearance, and specialties of Hirama-ji Temple in Kawasaki City, Kanagawa Prefecture, Ikegami-honmon-ji Temple in Ota Ward, Tokyo, and Kameidoten-jinja Shrine in Koto Ward, Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those with transparent dough wrapped around red bean paste are called &quot;manju&quot; (dumpling) as manju Japanese cakes, which are popular summer desserts because of their cool appearance, and specialties of Hirama-ji Temple in Kawasaki City, Kanagawa Prefecture, Ikegami-honmon-ji Temple in Ota Ward, Tokyo, and Kameidoten-jinja Shrine in Koto Ward, Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>江戸後期に入り、小麦粉を発酵したものから作られた菓子もくずもち（久寿餅）とよばれるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In late Edo period, people started to call a cake produced from fermented wheat flour, also kuzu-mochi (which is written in different Chinese characters).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In late Edo period, people started to call those made of fermented wheat flour also kuzumochi (in different Chinese characters).</e>
<cmt>started to call から先を全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In late Edo period, people started to call those made of fermented wheat flour also kuzumochi (in different Chinese characters).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>混同される事も多いが、東日本の小麦粉澱粉を発酵させて作る久寿餅と西日本の本葛から作る葛餅は製法・歴史的経緯含め全く別のものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though these two kinds of kuzu-mochi are often confused, kuzu-mochi in eastern Japan which is produced by fermenting wheat flour starch and kuzu-mochi in western Japan which is produced from the genuine kuzu plant are completely different from each other also in the production method and historical details.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though these two kinds of kuzumochi are often confused, those of eastern Japan made of fermenting wheat flour starch and those in western Japan made of hon-kuzu (real kudzu powder) are completely different from each other, including their recipes and historical backgrounds.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though these two kinds of kuzumochi are often confused, those of eastern Japan made of fermenting wheat flour starch and those in western Japan made of hon-kuzu (real kudzu powder) are completely different from each other, including their recipes and historical backgrounds.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>これは小麦粉から精製したデンプンを乳酸菌で発酵させたものであり、独特の風味がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This kuzu-mochi is produced from starch produced by purifying wheat flour and by fermenting this starch, and has a unique flavor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This kuzumochi are made of starch refined from wheat flour and fermented by lactic acid bacteria, and have a unique flavor.</e>
<cmt>「乳酸菌で」訳漏れのため、lactic acid bacteria を追記の上、全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This kuzumochi are made of starch refined from wheat flour and fermented by lactic acid bacteria, and have a unique flavor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>ただし、食べ方は関西風の葛餅同様、黄粉（きなこ）をまぶす他、黒蜜などでも賞味する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the eating style of kuzu-mochi is similar to that of western-Japan kuzu-mochi and, according to it, kuzu-mochi is appreciated with kuro-mitsu (black sweet syrup), etc., in addition to appreciating it with kina-ko powder (powdered roasted soy beans) sprinkled over it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the way to serve kuzumochi is similar to that of western-Japan, sprinkled with soy flour or dark molasses.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the way to serve kuzumochi is similar to that of western-Japan, sprinkled with soy flour or dark molasses.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>作り方</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Production method</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Recipe</e>
<cmt>全部修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Recipe</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>水で溶いた葛粉に砂糖を加え、火にかけ透明感が出るまでよく練る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kuzu-ko powder is solved in water and this solution is added with sugar, and is kneaded being heated on a fire until some transparency appears.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dissolve kuzuko in water and add sugar to it, then heat it and stir well until it turns transparent.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dissolve kuzuko in water and add sugar to it, then heat it and stir well until it turns transparent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>練りあがったものを水で冷やして適当な形に切るか、濡らした手でちぎって丸めるとでき上がり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The kneaded stuff is cooled by water, and cut into pieces of proper sizes or ripped and rounded with wet hands and, thereby, kuzu-mochi is completed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Let it cool in water and cut into pieces of proper size, or shape into round dumplings with wet hands.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Let it cool in water and cut into pieces of proper size, or shape into round dumplings with wet hands.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>好みできな粉や黒蜜をかけて食べる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The finished kuzu-mochi is eaten with kina-ko powder and/or kuro-mitsu syrup sprinkled over it according to the taste of the one who eats it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Serve with soy flour or dark molasses according to your taste.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Serve with soy flour or dark molasses according to your taste.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>生地に砂糖を入れることもあるが、でき上がったものに砂糖をかけたほうがより強く甘味を感じられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though sugar is sometimes added to the dough, the sweetness of kuzu-mochi can more strongly be tasted than this when sugar is sprinkled over the finished kuzu-mochi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sugar may be added to the dough, but it tastes much sweeter if sprinkled over the completed kuzumochi.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sugar may be added to the dough, but it tastes much sweeter if sprinkled over the completed kuzumochi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>冷蔵庫に入れると色が濁って食感が落ちるので、流水か氷水で冷やすとよい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the kuzu-mochi is stored in a refrigerator, the transparent dough becomes milky and the feeling of eating it becomes degraded and, therefore, it is recommended to cool kuzu-mochi with running water or water with ice therein.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As cooling it in a refrigerator spoils the transparency of the dough and its texture, it is better to cool it with running water or water with ice.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As cooling it in a refrigerator spoils the transparency of the dough and its texture, it is better to cool it with running water or water with ice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>本くず粉（くずでんぷん）を使用した葛餅はジャガイモ等のデンプンで作った葛餅に比べて、冷やしても透明感が失われにくくなめらかな口当たりである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kuzu-mochi produced from the genuine kuzu-ko (kuzu starch) tends to be difficult to lose its transparency and to keep its smoothness felt in the mouth even when it is cooled, compared to kuzu-mochi produced from starch of potato, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those made of real kuzuko (kudzu starch) keeps transparency and smooth texture even when it is cooled, compared with those made of potato starch, etc.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those made of real kuzuko (kudzu starch) keeps transparency and smooth texture even when it is cooled, compared with those made of potato starch, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="16">
<j>手作りのものではおいしく食べられる期間は2日ほどだが、スーパーマーケットなどで安く出回っているものは、砂糖が大量に入っており、長く保存できるような加工がされているため若干日持ちが良い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though hand-made kuzu-mochi can be tastily eaten only for about two days, the kuzu-mochi inexpensively available in super markets, etc., contains much sugar, is processed to be suitable for storing for a long time and, therefore, can be eaten for a somewhat longer time period than hand-made one.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The hand-made products can be enjoyed only for about two days, but those sold at supermarkets in low prices are added much sugar and have been processed for longer preservation, thus they are enjoyable for somewhat longer than hand-made ones.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The hand-made products can be enjoyed only for about two days, but those sold at supermarkets in low prices are added much sugar and have been processed for longer preservation, thus they are enjoyable for somewhat longer than hand-made ones.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>本葛粉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hon-kuzu-ko</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hon-kuzu</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hon-kuzu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="17">
<j>クズの根から作られる粉は本葛粉と呼ばれ、なめらかで口当たりが良が、本来多少の苦味を伴う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The powder produced from the roots of kuzu plant is referred to as hon-kuzu-ko powder (genuine kuzu powder) and the surface of the product made from this power is smooth and nice to eat while it originally has some bitterness.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The powder produced from the roots of kudzu plant is called hon-kuzu, which has smooth texture and some bitterness originally.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The powder produced from the roots of kudzu plant is called hon-kuzu, which has smooth texture and some bitterness originally.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>この苦味が薄いと薬効が落ちるとも言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also said that the medical effect of kuzu-mochi is degraded when this bitterness is weak.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also said that the medical effect is degraded when this bitterness is weak.</e>
<cmt>of kuzu-mochi を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also said that the medical effect is degraded when this bitterness is weak.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="19">
<j>本葛粉は生産量が少なく高価であるため、現在「本葛粉」として市販されている物でさえコムギやジャガイモ、サツマイモ（甘藷）やなどのデンプンを混入した物が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because the production of hon-kuzu-ko powder is a little and the powder is expensive, even most of the products which are sold as &apos;hon-kuzu-ko&apos; is mixed with starch such as starch of wheat, potato, and sweet potate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because the production of hon-kuzu is little and it is expensive, even most of the products sold as &apos;hon-kuzu&apos; is mixed with starch of wheat, potato, sweet potato and so on.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because the production of hon-kuzu is little and it is expensive, even most of the products sold as &apos;hon-kuzu&apos; is mixed with starch of wheat, potato, sweet potato and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>（ジャガイモは、体を冷やす作用がある）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Potato has an action to cool down the human body.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Potato has an action to cool down the human body.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Potato has an action to cool down the human body.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="21">
<j>ただし、西日本、特に産地の多い近畿や九州では本葛粉が比較的手に入りやすい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in western Japan, especially in Kinki and Kyushu Regions which have many production sites kuzu-ko powder, hon-kuzu-ko powder is relatively more available.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in western Japan, especially in Kinki and Kyushu regions, it is relatively more available thanks to many production areas.</e>
<cmt>後半部を全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in western Japan, especially in Kinki and Kyushu regions, it is relatively more available thanks to many production areas.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>本葛粉の生産の現状</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Current state of production of hon-kuzu-ko</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Current state of production of hon-kuzu</e>
<cmt>hon-kuzu-ko を hon-kuzu に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Current state of production of hon-kuzu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="22">
<j>本葛粉の生産はクズの根を掘り出す人の高齢化と天然資源の減少によって、現在、国内で出回る本葛粉にしめる中国製の割合が高まっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As to production of hon-kuzu-ko powder, because of the aging of those who dig the roots of kuzu plant and decrease of natural resource, the ratio of the China-made hon-kuzu-ko powder accounting for in the hon-kuzu-ko powder available in Japan is currently increasing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As to production of hon-kuzu, because of the aging of those who dig the roots of kudzu plant and decrease of natural resource, the ratio of the China-made powder available in Japan is currently increasing.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As to production of hon-kuzu, because of the aging of those who dig the roots of kudzu plant and decrease of natural resource, the ratio of the China-made powder available in Japan is currently increasing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="23">
<j>中国製については、中国から寒根葛（葛）の根を輸入し国内で製造した物を国産本葛と表示している例や、国産本葛と中国産葛を混ぜ合わせて国産本葛としている例が多々見受けられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As to the China-made hon-kuzu-ko powder, there are many cases where the powder produced by importing the roots of jikkon-kuzu (kuzu plant) and processed in Japan into powder is sold stating that the powder is made from Japanese genuine kuzu plant, and where the product made from Japanese genuine kuzu plant and Chinese one mixed with each other is sold stating that the product is made from the Japanese genuine kuzu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regarding the Chinese products, there are many cases to call them Japanese hon-kuzu, which are made of jikkon-kudzu (kudzu plant) imported from China and processed in Japan, or Japanese powder mixed with Chinese one.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regarding the Chinese products, there are many cases to call them Japanese hon-kuzu, which are made of jikkon-kudzu (kudzu plant) imported from China and processed in Japan, or Japanese powder mixed with Chinese one.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="24">
<j>中国産の寒根葛（葛）の根のポストハーベスト（残留農薬）の危険性が問題になっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The danger of the post-harvest agricultural chemicals (residual agricultural chemicals) in the roots of jikkon-kuzu (kuzu) imported from China is problematic.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The danger of agricultural chemicals left in the roots of jikkon-kudzu (kudzu) produced in China has become a problem.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The danger of agricultural chemicals left in the roots of jikkon-kudzu (kudzu) produced in China has become a problem.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="25">
<j>国内産本葛の大生産地は、現在、鹿児島であるが南九州産を原料とする三軒は、信頼のおける生産者といえるだろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Currently, the large production site of genuine kuzu produced in Japan is Kagoshima Prefecture and three farmers that produce the powder using the kuzu produced in southern part of Kyushu can be said to be reliable producers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Currently, the major production area of hon-kuzu in Japan is Kagoshima Prefecture, but you can rely on the three farmers using the products made in southern Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。※原文「三軒は」の意味が通じないように思われます。ウィキペディアのサイトを確認しましたが、当該部分の表記はありませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Currently, the major production area of hon-kuzu in Japan is Kagoshima Prefecture, but you can rely on the three farmers using the products made in southern Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="26">
<j>※　台湾産の葛根は、タイワンクズ、中国産の葛根は、シナノクズ、日本産の葛根とは、植物学的には同種類ではない</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">* Kuzu-ne roots produced in Taiwan are roots of Taiwan kuzu, those produced in China are root of Shina-no-kuzu (Chinese kuzu) and they are not botanically same species as those produced in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">* Kuzu-ne roots produced in Taiwan are roots of Taiwan kuzu, those produced in China are root of Shina-no-kuzu (Chinese kuzu), thus, from a botanical standpoint, they are not same species as those produced in Japan.</e>
<cmt>後半部を全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">* Kuzu-ne roots produced in Taiwan are roots of Taiwan kuzu, those produced in China are root of Shina-no-kuzu (Chinese kuzu), thus, from a botanical standpoint, they are not same species as those produced in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="27">
<j>本葛の原料原産地名表示の現状</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Current state of indication of raw materials and place of origin of hon-kuzu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Current state of indication of raw materials and place of origin of hon-kuzu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Current state of indication of raw materials and place of origin of hon-kuzu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="28">
<j>現在、本葛には、原料原産地名の表示義務がない為、本葛の表示があっても国産とは限らないのが現状、商品内容表示に原料原産地名の表示のない物については、外国産が混じっていると言える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Currently, there is no obligation for hon-kuzu (genuine kuzu) concerning the indication of the raw materials and the place of origin and, therefore, the current state is that, even when a product has indication describing that the product is made from hon-kuzu, the product is not always uses the Japan-made hon-kuzu and, therefore, it can be said that products which each have no description concerning its raw materials and the place of its origin in its product information label includes those made in foreign countries.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Currently, as there is no obligation for hon-kuzu concerning the indication of the raw materials and the place of origin, the indication of hon-kuzu may not guarantee that it is a domestic product, which means that products without description concerning its raw materials and the place of its origin on its product information label may be mingled with those made in foreign countries.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。※原文「現状、」は尻切れトンボな感じがいたします。「現状であることから、」の意味かと思われます。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Currently, as there is no obligation for hon-kuzu concerning the indication of the raw materials and the place of origin, the indication of hon-kuzu may not guarantee that it is a domestic product, which means that products without description concerning its raw materials and the place of its origin on its product information label may be mingled with those made in foreign countries.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 奈緒(id:33238), M-ogino(id:65364), 北大(id:110491), Rambler(id:59491), Charenji(id:7908), Woz(id:150200), Milanotaka(id:95055), Kogane(id:28186), Tr-909(id:25414), Kjwnxdsaz(id:160046), Bbcs(id:140588), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>