<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>カップ麺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kappumen&quot; (cup-packaged instant noodles)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kappumen&quot; (cup-packaged instant noodles)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kappumen (cup-packaged instant noodles)</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>カップ麺（カップめん）とは、乾燥麺や生タイプ麺等の即席麺類のうち、食器として使用できる容器（カップ状の耐熱耐水容器等）に入れたもので、加薬を添付したものをいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kappumen indicates the item consisted of the instant noodles such as dried noodles and fresh noodles put into a container usable as tableware and the attached ingredients.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kappumen indicates the item consisting of instant noodles such as dried noodles and fresh noodles put into a container usable as tableware and the attached ingredients.</e>
<cmt>consisting</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kappumen indicates the item consisting of instant noodles such as dried noodles and fresh noodles put into a container usable as tableware and the attached ingredients.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>熱湯を注ぐだけで調理が可能で鍋が要らずお湯さえあればどこでも食べられるのが特徴。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is characterized by being cookable only by pouring hot water and eatable anywhere if hot water is available.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is characterized by being cookable only by pouring hot water and eatable anywhere if hot water is available.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is characterized by being cookable only by pouring hot water and eatable anywhere if hot water is available.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>つまりカップは調理器具であると同時に食器（陳列時にはパッケージとしての役割も果たしている）でもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That is, the cup serves not only as cookware, but also as tableware (with a role of the package on display).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That is, the cup serves not only as cookware, but also as tableware (with a role of the package on display).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That is, the cup serves not only as cookware, but also as tableware (with a role of the package on display).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>規約上の正式名は「即席カップめん」である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The official name on the code is &quot;Sokuseki Kappumen&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The official name on the code is &quot;Sokuseki Kappumen&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The official name on the code is &apos;Sokuseki Kappumen.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。ピリオド位置を訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>内容物がインスタントラーメンのものをカップラーメン、蕎麦、うどんのものをカップそば、カップうどん、やきそばのものをカップやきそば（インスタント焼きそば）とも言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also those of which contents are instant ramen noodles are called Kappu-ramen, soba (noodles made from buckwheat) and udon (noodles made of wheat flour) are called Kappu-soba and Kappu-udon respectively, and yakisoba (fried noodles) are called Kappu-yakisoba (instant yakisoba).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also those whose contents are instant ramen noodles are called Kappu-ramen, soba (noodles made from buckwheat) and udon (noodles made of wheat flour) are called Kappu-soba and Kappu-udon respectively, and yakisoba (fried noodles) are called Kappu-yakisoba (instant yakisoba).</e>
<cmt>of which-&gt;whose</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also those whose contents are instant ramen noodles are called Kappu-ramen, soba (noodles made from buckwheat) and udon (noodles made of wheat flour) are called Kappu-soba and Kappu-udon respectively, and yakisoba (fried noodles) are called Kappu-yakisoba (instant yakisoba).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>日本全国で発売されている一部の商品では、東日本と西日本など地域別毎でそれぞれ味付けを変えているケースもある（どん兵衛やマルちゃん赤いきつねと緑のたぬき等）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Part of the products sold nationwide in Japan is differently seasoned per region in the eastern Japan and western Japan (such as Donbe, Maruchan&apos;s Akai Kitsune (instant udon bowl) and Midori no Tanuki (Green Raccoon) (instant soba bowl)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some of the products sold nationwide in Japan are differently seasoned per region in eastern Japan and western Japan (such as Donbe, Maruchan&apos;s Akai Kitsune (instant udon bowl) and Midori no Tanuki (Green Raccoon) (instant soba bowl)).</e>
<cmt>part-&gt;some</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some of the products sold nationwide in Japan are differently seasoned per region in eastern Japan and western Japan (such as Donbe, Maruchan&apos;s Akai Kitsune [instant udon bowl] and Midori no Tanuki [Green Raccoon] [instant soba bowl]).</e>
<cmt>括弧内括弧を[]に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>また、地域限定発売の商品もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, there are some products sold only locally.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, there are some products sold only locally.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, there are some products sold only locally.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>「青葉」などラーメン店のカップ麺も存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kappumen made by ramen shops also exists, such as &apos;Aoba&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are also Kappumen made by ramen shops, such as &apos;Aoba&apos;.</e>
<cmt>exist-&gt;there are</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are also Kappumen made by ramen shops, such as &apos;Aoba.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>非常用食糧</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emergency food</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emergency food</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emergency food</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="9">
<j>電気・ガス・水道などライフラインが影響を受ける非常事態では、お湯の確保が困難な場合が多く、その場合はカップ麺は役に立たない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the emergency situation that the lifeline such as electricity, gas, and water is affected, it is very often difficult to secure hot water and Kappumen is useless in such a case.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the emergency situation that the lifeline such as electricity, gas, and water is affected, it is very often difficult to secure hot water and Kappumen is useless in such a case.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the emergency situation that the lifeline such as electricity, gas, and water is affected, it is very often difficult to secure hot water and Kappumen is useless in such a case.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>災害直後は、火気使用はガス爆発を起こす危険も高く、集団避難生活では火気が使えないために容器一杯の熱湯を得るのも難しいケースもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The use of fire has a greater risk to cause a gas explosion immediately after the disaster and even obtaining hot water fully in a container is difficult because fire is not usable at a refuge life in groups.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The use of fire has a greater risk to cause a gas explosion immediately after the disaster and even obtaining hot water fully in a container is difficult because fire is not usable at a refuge in groups.</e>
<cmt>deleted “life”</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The use of fire has a greater risk to cause a gas explosion immediately after the disaster and even obtaining hot water fully in a container is difficult because fire is not usable at a refuge in groups.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="11">
<j>中期以降でも、少なくともインスタントラーメンよりは調理は簡便ではあるが、これの調理に必要な水や燃料・簡易焜炉（カセットガスコンロなど）といった他の備えも必要である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even after the midterm, at least cooking is easier than instant ramen noodles, but other equipments such as water, fuel, and a simple cooking range (a portable gas burner and others) necessary for cooking are required.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even after the midterm, at least cooking is easier than instant ramen noodles, but other equipment such as water, fuel, and a simple cooking range (a portable gas burner and others) necessary for cooking are required.</e>
<cmt>equipment</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even after the midterm, at least cooking is easier than instant ramen noodles, but other equipment such as water, fuel, and a simple cooking range (a portable gas burner and others) necessary for cooking are required.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="12">
<j>日清食品が1971年9月18日に発売（事前に行われた試験販売を除く）した「カップヌードル」が最初の製品である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Cup Noodle&quot; is the first product put on the market by NISSIN FOOD PRODUCTS on September 18, 1971 (except the test marketing done immediately before).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Cup Noodle&quot; is the first product put on the market by NISSIN FOOD PRODUCTS on September 18, 1971 (except the test marketing done immediately before).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cup Noodle&apos; is the first product put on the market by NISSIN FOOD PRODUCTS on September 18, 1971 (except the test marketing done immediately before).</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>欧米に即席ラーメンのセールスに行った際、ラーメン用のどんぶりが無かったため、紙コップにチキンラーメンを割り入れて湯を注ぎフォークで試食する姿からの発想だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The idea is originated from a trip to Europe and America for selling instant ramen noodles, in which cracked Chicken Ramen into a paper cup because ramen bowls were not available, poured hot water, and tried out with a folk.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The idea originated from a trip to Europe and America for selling instant ramen noodles, in which someone cracked Chicken Ramen into a paper cup because ramen bowls were not available, poured hot water, and tried out with a fork.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The idea originated from a trip to Europe and America for selling instant ramen noodles, in which someone cracked Chicken Ramen into a paper cup because ramen bowls were not available, poured hot water, and tried out with a fork.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>今では主食として広く親しまれているが、当初は間食としての普及を視野に入れて開発されたという経緯がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has attracted widespread popularity as a staple food, but initially it was developed in perspective of spreading as a between-meal snack.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has attracted widespread popularity as a staple food, but initially it was developed in perspective of spreading as a between-meal snack.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has attracted widespread popularity as a staple food, but initially it was developed in perspective of spreading as a between-meal snack.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>通常の袋麺（約90～100g）よりも麺の容量が少ない（麺重量60～70g）のはその名残りであり、通常は「大盛サイズ」を謳うカップ麺が袋麺の容量と同等である場合が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Less quantity of noodles (60 to 70g) than normal noodles in a plastic bag (approximately 90 to 100g) is a remnant of this and quantity of Kappumen, usually advocating &quot;Large-serving size&quot;, is often the same as that of noodles in a plastic bag.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Less quantity of noodles (60 to 70g) than normal noodles in a plastic bag (approximately 90 to 100g) is a remnant of this and the quantity of Kappumen, usually advertised as &quot;Large-serving size&quot;, is often the same as that of noodles in a plastic bag.</e>
<cmt>advocating-&gt;advertised as</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Less quantity of noodles (60 to 70g) than normal noodles in a plastic bag (approximately 90 to 100g) is a remnant of this and the quantity of Kappumen, usually advertised as &apos;Large-serving size,&apos; is often the same as that of noodles in a plastic bag.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。コンマの位置を訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="16">
<j>このカップ麺が日本人に受け入れられ、普及したきっかけは、あさま山荘事件の際、機動隊員が寒さの中これを食べている姿がテレビでたびたび放映されたため、とするのが通説となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The often broadcasted scenes that riot police officers ate this in freezing temperatures in the Asama-Sanso incident in 1972 triggered this Kappumen to be accepted and spread among Japanese people is thepopular theory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That the often broadcast scenes of riot police officers eating this in freezing temperatures in the Asama-Sanso incident in 1972 triggered this Kappumen to be accepted and spread among Japanese people is a popular theory.</e>
<cmt>added “that”</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That the often broadcast scenes of riot police officers eating this in freezing temperatures in the Asama-Sanso incident in 1972 triggered this Kappumen to be accepted and spread among Japanese people is a popular theory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="17">
<j>現在ではラーメンのほか蕎麦やうどん、やきそばやスパゲッティ、そうめん、冷麺、春雨 (料理)、フォーなどもあり、麺類全般が製品化されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At present, noodles in general are commercialized such as ramen, soba, udon, yakisoba, spaghetti, somen (fine white noodles), reimen (cold noodles in Korean style), harusame (bean-starch vermicelli) (cuisine), and pho (noodles in Vietnamese style).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At present, noodles in general are commercialized such as ramen, soba, udon, yakisoba, spaghetti, somen (fine white noodles), reimen (cold noodles in Korean style), harusame (bean-starch vermicelli) (cuisine), and pho (noodles in Vietnamese style).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At present, noodles in general are commercialized such as ramen, soba, udon, yakisoba, spaghetti, somen (fine white noodles), reimen (cold noodles in Korean style), harusame (bean-starch vermicelli) (cuisine), and pho (noodles in Vietnamese style).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="18">
<j>カップラーメンは海外での生産・販売も行われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kappu-ramen is produced and sold overseas as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kappu-ramen is produced and sold overseas as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kappu-ramen is produced and sold overseas as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>主な生産および消費地は東アジア地域であるが、北米大陸（特にメキシコ）でもヒスパニック系住民を中心に人気がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The main production and consumption region is the East Asian region and also it is popular in the North America (especially Mexico), especially among the Hispanic residents.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The main production and consumption region is the East Asian region and also it is popular in North America (especially Mexico), especially among the Hispanic residents.</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The main production and consumption region is the East Asian region and also it is popular in North America (especially Mexico), especially among the Hispanic residents.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>日本のメーカーの現地生産も行われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Japanese manufacturers are also producing locally.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Japanese manufacturers are also producing locally.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japanese manufacturers are also producing locally.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>容器</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Container</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Container</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Container</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="21">
<j>容器は通常、発泡スチロールか紙が使われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Foaming polystyrol or paper is usually used for the container.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Styrofoam or paper is usually used for the container.</e>
<cmt>styrofoam</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Styrofoam or paper is usually used for the container.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>保温性がよく、持ったときに熱くないという理由からである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Good heat retention and heatless holding are the reason.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Good heat retention and the fact that it is not hot to the touch are the reason.</e>
<cmt>reworded “heatless holding”</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Good heat retention and the fact that it is not hot to the touch are the reason.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>紙製の容器の場合、容器外側を段ボール状にして、この点を克服している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Paper containers overcome these points by making the outside cardboard-shaped.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Paper containers overcome these points by making the outside cardboard-shaped.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Paper containers overcome these points by making the outside cardboard-shaped.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>代表的なものが『サンヨー食品主な商品』である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The typical item is &quot;the main product of SANYO FOODS.Co.,Ltd.&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The typical item is &quot;the main product of SANYO FOODS.Co.,Ltd.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The typical item is &quot;the main product of SANYO FOODS Co.,Ltd.&quot;</e>
<cmt>不要なピリオドを削除しました。スペース補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>最近のものはカップを二重構造にするだけで段の無い容器になっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The recent containers have no tier only with double structure of the cup.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The recent containers have no tier only with double structure of the cup.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The recent containers have no tier only with double structure of the cup.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>近年では紙製でも発泡スチロールのように紙に空間を持たせたものも存在する（日清カップヌードル系列のものに多い）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also some paper containers have space in paper like foaming polystyrol (many in the Nissin Cup Noodle series).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also some paper containers have space in paper like styrofoam (many in the Nissin Cup Noodle series).</e>
<cmt>styrofoam</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also some paper containers have space in paper like styrofoam (many in the Nissin Cup Noodle series).</e>
<cmt>スペース削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>紙の容器に比べ発泡スチロールのほうが多彩な形状のものを作ることが可能である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is possible to create various shapes by foaming polystyrol than paper containers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is easier to create various shapes with styrofoam than paper containers.</e>
<cmt>possible-&gt;easier</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is easier to create various shapes with styrofoam than paper containers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>初期のものはすべて発泡スチロールだが、日清食品が特許を持っていたため、後発メーカーは主に紙容器のものを作った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">All initial containers were made by foaming polystyrol, but late-started manufacturers created mainly the paper containers because NISSIN FOOD PRODUCTS owned the patent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">All initial containers were made of styrofoam, but late-started manufacturers created mainly the paper containers because NISSIN FOOD PRODUCTS owned the patent.</e>
<cmt>prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">All initial containers were made of styrofoam, but late-started manufacturers created mainly the paper containers because NISSIN FOOD PRODUCTS owned the patent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="29">
<j>1998年に当時の環境庁（現環境省）より提出されたSPEED98リスト（「内分泌攪乱化学物質問題への環境庁の対応方針について」）により、高熱の熱湯を注ぐことで発泡スチロール製の容器から内分泌攪乱化学物質（スチレンダイマー、スチレントリマー）が溶出し、スープや麺と一緒に摂取することで人体への影響があるとマスメディアからの批判を浴び、各メーカーが緊急に紙容器に切り替えるなど大きな問題となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Based on the SPEED98 list (&quot;the policy to handle the problem of endocrine-disrupting chemical material by the Environmental Agency&quot;) provided by the then Environmental Agency (the current Ministry of the Environment) in 1998, the mass media criticized that it would affect to human body by consuming endocrine-disrupting chemical material (styrene dimer and styrene trimer) eluted from a foamed polystyrene container after putting soup and noodles and pouring very hot water, consequently it became such a big problem that each manufacturer immediately switched to a paper container.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based on the SPEED98 list (&quot;the policy to handle the problem of endocrine-disrupting chemical material by the Environmental Agency&quot;) provided by the then Environmental Agency (the current Ministry of the Environment) in 1998, the mass media criticized that it would affect to human body by consuming endocrine-disrupting chemical material (styrene dimer and styrene trimer) eluted from a foamed polystyrene container after putting soup and noodles and pouring very hot water, consequently it became such a big problem that every manufacturer immediately switched to a paper container.</e>
<cmt>each-&gt;every</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based on the SPEED98 list (&apos;the policy to handle the problem of endocrine-disrupting chemical material by the Environmental Agency&apos;) provided by the then Environmental Agency (the current Ministry of the Environment) in 1998, the mass media criticized that it would affect to human body by consuming endocrine-disrupting chemical material (styrene dimer and styrene trimer) eluted from a foamed polystyrene container after putting soup and noodles and pouring very hot water, consequently it became such a big problem that every manufacturer immediately switched to a paper container.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>後に同説はカップ麺業界等により再調査され、2000年に旧通産省・旧環境庁が「内分泌攪乱作用があるとの証拠は見いだせない」「作用を否定する報告が大半」と発表したが、2006年に東京都健康安全研究センターは動物実験により、生物への影響が確認されたと発表した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later the Kappumen industry and others reexamined this theory and the former Ministry of International Trade and Industry and former Environment Agency announced in 2000 that &quot;there is no evidence that it has endocrine-disrupting effect&quot; and &quot;most reports denied any effect&quot;, but Tokyo Metropolitan Institute of Public Health announced in 2006 that it has confirmed the affect on living things by animal test.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later the Kappumen industry and others reexamined this theory and the former Ministry of International Trade and Industry and former Environment Agency announced in 2000 that &quot;there is no evidence that it has endocrine-disrupting effect&quot; and &quot;most reports denied any effect&quot;, but Tokyo Metropolitan Institute of Public Health announced in 2006 that it has confirmed the affect on living things by animal test.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later the Kappumen industry and others reexamined this theory and the former Ministry of International Trade and Industry and former Environment Agency announced in 2000 that &apos;there is no evidence that it has endocrine-disrupting effect&apos; and &apos;most reports denied any effect,&apos; but Tokyo Metropolitan Institute of Public Health announced in 2006 that it has confirmed the affect on living things by animal test.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。コンマの位置を訂正しました。不要なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>しかし、これは通常の10倍以上を摂取する状況下での結果であり、実際の人体への影響がどの程度かは不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Still this is a result under the situation to consume 10 times or more than usual and to what extent it affects the actual human body is unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Still this is a result under the situation to consume 10 times or more than usual and to what extent it affects the actual human body is unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Still this is a result under the situation to consume 10 times or more than usual and to what extent it affects the actual human body is unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>なお発泡スチロール（ポリスチレン）は前述のとおり、環境ホルモンと関連する物質の疑いが2000年11月に晴れたとされ、同リストより除外されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, foamed polystyrene (polystyrene) is removed from the list because the doubt for the material related to the environmental hormone has been cleared in November 2000 as described above.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, styrofoam (polystyrene) is removed from the list because the doubt for the material related to the environmental hormone has been cleared in November 2000 as described above.</e>
<cmt>styrofoam</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, styrofoam (polystyrene) is removed from the list because the doubt for the material related to the environmental hormone has been cleared in November 2000 as described above.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>しかし、2004年には当時流行した健康食品のエゴマが、このスチロール製カップを溶かすとして話題となり、国民生活センターが調査を行った所、このしそ油をカップに入れ、100度の熱湯を注いだ際に一定の溶解が見られたため、消費者に注意を呼びかけている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, a health food Egoma which was popular in 2004 became a major talking point that it would melt this styrofoam cup, and NCAC (National Consumer Affairs Center of Japan) examined and alerted consumers because a certain amount of it melted when putting this beefsteak plant oil into a cup and pouring hot water of 100 degrees.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, a health food Egoma which was popular in 2004 became a major talking point because it would melt this styrofoam cup, and NCAC (National Consumer Affairs Center of Japan) examined and alerted consumers because a certain amount of it melted when putting this beefsteak plant oil into a cup and pouring hot water of 100 degrees.</e>
<cmt>that-&gt;because</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, a health food Egoma which was popular in 2004 became a major talking point because it would melt this styrofoam cup, and NCAC (National Consumer Affairs Center of Japan) examined and alerted consumers because a certain amount of it melted when putting this beefsteak plant oil into a cup and pouring hot water of 100 degrees.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="34">
<j>これらの容器は、洗った後に埋め立てごみとして家庭から排出されるが、一部自治体では洗ってない物は燃えるゴミとして排出してもよい地域もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These containers are washed and discharged from homes as landfill waste, but it is possible to discharge unwashed things as combustible garbage under some local governments.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These containers are washed and discharged from homes as landfill waste, but it is possible to discharge unwashed things as combustible garbage under some local governments.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These containers are washed and discharged from homes as landfill waste, but it is possible to discharge unwashed things as combustible garbage under some local governments.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>地域によって排出基準が違う（→ごみ問題）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The discharge standard varies depending on the region (=&gt; garbage problem).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The discharge standard varies depending on the region (=&gt; garbage problem).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The discharge standard varies depending on the region (=&gt; garbage problem).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="36">
<j>乾燥麺タイプは直接容器に麺が入っているケースが殆どであるが、生タイプ麺はすべてその麺を真空パック包装した上で容器に入れた状態となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most of dried noodles are directly put in a container, while all fresh noodles are vacuum-packed and then put in a container.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most dried noodles are directly put in a container, while all fresh noodles are vacuum-packed and then put in a container.</e>
<cmt>prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most dried noodles are directly put in a container, while all fresh noodles are vacuum-packed and then put in a container.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>調理</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cooking</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cooking</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cooking</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="37">
<j>製品の多くは熱湯を注いで3分（約1～5分の幅で各種ある）で調理が完了する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cooking completes by pouring hot water and waiting for three minutes (it varies for approximately one to five minutes) in many products.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cooking completes by pouring hot water and waiting for three minutes (it varies for approximately one to five minutes) in many products.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cooking completes by pouring hot water and waiting for three minutes (it varies for approximately one to five minutes) in many products.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>一時期各会社より乾燥麺タイプで調理時間が1分の製品が発売されたが、食べ終わる前に麺がのびてしまう等の問題が在ったため多くは短命に終わり、一部の焼きそばタイプで存続するに留まっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The dried noodle products of which cooking time is one minute were sold by the companies for a certain period of time, but many of them were short-lived due to the problem, such as noodles lost texture before eating, thereby only the part of yakisoba type remains.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The dried noodle products of which cooking time is one minute were sold by the companies for a certain period of time, but many of them were short-lived due to problems, such as noodles lost texture before eating, thereby only the yakisoba type remains.</e>
<cmt>prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The dried noodle products of which cooking time is one minute were sold by the companies for a certain period of time, but many of them were short-lived due to problems, such as noodles lost texture before eating, thereby only the yakisoba type remains.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>汁を用いない焼きソバの場合は湯切の作業が必要となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For yakisoba without soup, it is necessary to drain hot water.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For yakisoba without soup, it is necessary to drain hot water.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For yakisoba without soup, it is necessary to drain hot water.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>また生タイプ麺などの製品でも湯切りをし再度お湯を注ぐものもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for some products of fresh noodles and others, it is necessary to drain hot water and pouring it again.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for some products of fresh noodles and others, it is necessary to drain hot water and pour it again.</e>
<cmt>verb conjugation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for some products of fresh noodles and others, it is necessary to drain hot water and pour it again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>しかし生タイプ麺を使用したものは調理時間がやや短めの傾向である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, those used fresh noodles tend to have a little shorter time for cooking.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, those with fresh noodles tend to have a little shorter time for cooking.</e>
<cmt>used-&gt;with</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, those with fresh noodles tend to have a little shorter time for cooking.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="42">
<j>なお湯は基本的にほぼ摂氏100度の物を使う事を前提としているため、ポット等の湯では再沸騰機能を用いても、美味しく出来ない場合がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, basically the use of approximately 100 degrees of hot water is assumed, therefore occasionally hot water in a pot and others cannot make it tasty even if using a reboiling function.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, basically the use of approximately 100 degrees of hot water is assumed, therefore occasionally hot water in a pot and others cannot make it tasty even if using a reboiling function.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, basically the use of approximately 100 degrees of hot water is assumed, therefore occasionally hot water in a pot and others cannot make it tasty even if using a reboiling function.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>また熱湯を使うため火傷に対する警戒も必要で、これにまつわる事故事例も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Warning for a scald is also required because of using hot water and there are many accidents and cases involved this.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Warning for a scald is also required because of using hot water and there are many accidents and cases involved this.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Warning for a scald is also required because of using hot water and there are many accidents and cases involved this.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>各メーカーでは注意を呼びかけると共に、児童などがこれを食べる場合には保護者が管理するよう求めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Each manufacturer alerts as well as asks to manage by guardians when children and others eat this.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Each manufacturer alerts as well as asks for supervision by guardians when children and others eat this.</e>
<cmt>manage-&gt;supervision</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Each manufacturer alerts as well as asks for supervision by guardians when children and others eat this.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="45">
<j>添え付けのスープや具材はフリーズドライを用い乾燥させたものが主流だが、袋入りのインスタントラーメンと同様、高価格の製品にはスープ・具が別添のものも存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The attached soup and ingredients are mainly dried by freeze-drying, and also separate bags of them are attached to high-priced products similarly as instant ramen noodles in a plastic bag.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The attached soup and ingredients are mainly dried by freeze-drying, and also separate bags of them are attached to high-priced products similarly as instant ramen noodles in a plastic bag.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The attached soup and ingredients are mainly dried by freeze-drying, and also separate bags of them are attached to high-priced products similarly as instant ramen noodles in a plastic bag.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>それらの製品では袋を取り出し、麺の上に置いてから湯を注ぐなど、製品ごとに様々な違いも見られるため、湯を注ぐ前にパッケージに記載された説明書きなどを読んでおく事が勧められる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those products vary such as taking out the bag, putting on noodles, and pouring hot water, thereby it is recommended to read the instructions and others described in a package before pouring hot water.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those products vary such as taking out the bag, putting on noodles, and pouring hot water, thereby it is recommended to read the instructions and others described in a package before pouring hot water.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those products vary such as taking out the bag, putting on noodles, and pouring hot water, thereby it is recommended to read the instructions and others described in a package before pouring hot water.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>中にはレトルト食品の具材が付属していて、その具材を湯煎する事を勧める製品も存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ingredients of retort foods are attached to some of them and it is recommended to warm up the ingredients in hot water for some products.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ingredients of retort foods are attached to some of them and it is recommended to warm up the ingredients in hot water for some products.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ingredients of retort foods are attached to some of them and it is recommended to warm up the ingredients in hot water for some products.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="48">
<j>なお、カップ麺は日本農林規格によって「標準」と「上級」に分類されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, Kappumen is classified into &quot;Standard&quot; and &quot;Upper grade&quot; by the Japan Agricultural Standards.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, Kappumen is classified into &quot;Standard&quot; and &quot;Upper grade&quot; by the Japan Agricultural Standards.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, Kappumen is classified into &apos;Standard&apos; and &apos;Upper grade&apos; by the Japan Agricultural Standards.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>麺の重量に対して具材（かやく）が6%以上のものが標準、15%以上のものが上級、カップ焼きそばやスパゲティの場合、4%以上が標準、10%以上が上級となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Standard is those of which ingredients are 6% or more to the weight of noodles and Upper grade, 15% or more, and for Kappu-yakisoba or spaghetti, Standard, 4% or more and Upper grade, 10% or more.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Standard is those of which ingredients are 6% or more to the weight of noodles and Upper grade, 15% or more, and for Kappu-yakisoba or spaghetti, Standard, 4% or more and Upper grade, 10% or more.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Standard is those of which ingredients are 6% or more to the weight of noodles and Upper grade, 15% or more, and for Kappu-yakisoba or spaghetti, Standard, 4% or more and Upper grade, 10% or more.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="50">
<j>また、電子レンジ調理専用の商品も少数存在する（日清食品「日清焼そばU.F.O./どん兵衛 NEXT GENERATION」シリーズ等）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, there are a few products exclusive for cooking by a microwave oven (NISSIN FOOD PRODUCTS &quot;Nissin Yakisoba U.F.O./Donbe NEXT GENERATION&quot; series and others).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, there are a few products exclusively for cooking by microwave oven (NISSIN FOOD PRODUCTS &quot;Nissin Yakisoba U.F.O./Donbe NEXT GENERATION&quot; series and others).</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, there are a few products exclusively for cooking by microwave oven (NISSIN FOOD PRODUCTS &apos;Nissin Yakisoba U.F.O./Donbe NEXT GENERATION&apos; series and others).</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>それ以外のものは電子レンジ調理不可のケースが日本では多いが、米国で販売されているものは “microwavable”（電子レンジ調理可能）と明記されたものが多く存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many of other than the above are not cookable by a microwave oven in Japan, but in America, many described as &quot;microwavable&quot; (cookable by a microwave oven) are sold.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many others are not cookable by microwave oven in Japan, but in America, many described as &quot;microwavable&quot; (cookable by a microwave oven) are sold.</e>
<cmt>deleted “of the above”</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many others are not cookable by microwave oven in Japan, but in America, many described as &quot;microwavable&quot; (cookable by a microwave oven) are sold.</e>
<cmt>全角の”を半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>市場</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Market</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Market</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Market</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="52">
<j>長いこと「カップヌードル」や「赤いきつね」などの初期に登場したブランドが市場占有率の首位を独走してきたが、2008年に原材料費などの高騰で大手メーカー製品の売価が上がったことで、カップヌードルは値上げ前比-52％と半減した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The initially appeared brands such as &quot;Cup Noodle&quot; and &quot;Akai Kitsune&quot; had a commanding lead in market share for a long time, but Cup Noodle was sold only half in 2008, -52% compared before the price increase, due to steep rise of raw material cost and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first brands such as &quot;Cup Noodle&quot; and &quot;Akai Kitsune&quot; had a commanding lead in market share for a long time, but Cup Noodle sales were only half in 2008, -52% compared before the price increase, due to steep rise of raw material cost and others.</e>
<cmt>initial-&gt;first</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first brands such as &apos;Cup Noodle&apos; and &apos;Akai Kitsune&apos; had a commanding lead in market share for a long time, but Cup Noodle sales were only half in 2008, -52% compared before the price increase, due to steep rise of raw material cost and others.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。不要なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>一方で、大手スーパーマーケットで展開している安価な自社プライベートブランド商品の売れ行きが大きく躍進した</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, inexpensive own private brand products deployed in major super markets have made a big leap.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, inexpensive own-brand products deployed in major super markets have made a big leap.</e>
<cmt>Own-brand</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, inexpensive own-brand products deployed in major super markets have made a big leap.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Ligar(id:12623), 唐変木(id:17050), Tommy6-bot(id:171289), 妖精書士(id:101212), Ypacaraí(id:11031), Modeha(id:1276), Nnh(id:474), NISYAN(id:169936), Sunflowerbed(id:152950), Afarus(id:146955), 0null0(id:582), The Side(id:69360), Wgy(id:14956), もち猫(id:210460), JINKY.ECLEO(id:141716), Kamakura(id:472), SSGB(id:48486), Episteme(id:32386), Yatobi(id:9686), Opponent(id:720), Gogo Lawrence(id:32120), 飛ぶ鳥(id:158139), Goki(id:7107), Stthb(id:87826), Chobot(id:20846), Kmoris(id:105714), Bit(id:2197), Yas(id:739), Tyuta0055(id:205797), ロリ(id:613), Starbacks(id:1018), Lonicera(id:20638), MikeAz800o(id:58193), Washisama(id:9333), クロウ(id:21337), なおぞー(id:80442), 江口磐世☆(id:168037), マクガイア(id:33346), Hiyotada(id:50494), 砂の妖精(id:24382), COCKY(id:19672), Open-box(id:17893), 神代 刹那(id:94620), Tassi-(id:81774), 茶務(id:48052), Kiraken(id:117691), Shinkansen(id:13703), Baldanders(id:81163), Vina-iwbot(id:56449), Alesha(id:130748), 竃馬(id:102733), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), Tietew(id:4054), 地吹雪(id:38741), R28Bot(id:177951), Sanctus(id:38120), You-kan(id:33117), けんち(id:5147), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>