<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>移菊</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Utsuroi-giku&quot; (The White Chrysanthemum Changing Its Color Into Purple)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Utsuroi-giku&quot; (The White Chrysanthemum Changing Its Color to Purple)</e>
<cmt>preposition</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Utsuroi-giku (the white Chrysanthemum changing its color to purple)</e>
<cmt>ダブルクォーテーションを削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>移菊（うつろいぎく）とは晩秋のころ白菊が花弁の端から紫がかって来たものを言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Utsuroi-giku&quot; is the white chrysanthemum whose petals begin to be tinged with purple from their edge around the late autumn.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Utsuroi-giku&quot; is the variety of white chrysanthemum whose petals begin to be tinged with purple from their edges around late autumn.</e>
<cmt>article, word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Utsuroi-giku refers to the variety of white chrysanthemum whose petals begin to be tinged with purple from their edges around late autumn.</e>
<cmt>ダブルクォーテーションを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>有体に言ってしまえば、花弁に霜が触れるなどして植物組織が損傷を受け色が変わったもので、園芸用語で言う「霜焼け」に過ぎない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As it is, the petals change their color simply because the tissues are damaged by, for example, the frost, which is called &quot;frostbite&quot; in the gardening term.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As it is, the petals change their color simply because the tissues are damaged by, for example, frost; this is called &quot;frostbite&quot; in gardening terms.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As it is, the petals change their color simply because the tissues are damaged by, for example, frost; this is called &apos;frostbite&apos; in gardening terms.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="3">
<j>しかし、平安貴族の紫への愛着から、ともすれば通常の白菊よりも美しいとさえされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, nobles in the Heian period loved the purple color so much that they sometimes dared to rate utsuroi-giku higher than the white chrysanthemum.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, nobles in the Heian period loved the purple color so much that they sometimes dared to rate utsuroi-giku higher than the white chrysanthemum.</e>
<cmt>italics</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, nobles in the Heian period loved the purple color so much that they sometimes dared to rate utsuroi-giku higher than the white chrysanthemum.</e>
<cmt>一部イタリック体を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="4">
<j>原産地の中国で菊は晩秋の野に凛と立つ姿と清清しい芳香から四君子の一つとされ、「不正を寄せ付けぬ高潔さ」「不遇の際も変わらぬ友情」「長寿をもたらす仙人の霊薬」などとのイメージで愛された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In China (the home of the chrysanthemum), it was praised as one of four valued plants for its noble atmosphere distinctive in the late autumn field, and for its fresh fragrance, so Chinese people loved the chrysanthemum as the symbol of something valuable, such as the noble spirit keeping oneself away from injustice, the friendship unchanged even in one&apos;s dark days, and the mountain hermit&apos;s miraculous medicine promising longevity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In China (the home of the chrysanthemum), it was praised as one of four valued plants for its noble atmosphere distinctive in the late autumn field, and for its fresh fragrance, so Chinese people loved the chrysanthemum as the symbol of something valuable, such as the noble spirit keeping oneself away from injustice, friendship unchanged even in one&apos;s dark days, and the mountain hermit&apos;s miraculous medicine promising longevity.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In China (the home of the chrysanthemum), it was praised as one of four valued plants for its noble atmosphere distinctive in the late autumn field and for its fresh fragrance, so Chinese people loved the chrysanthemum as the symbol of something valuable, such as &apos;the noble spirit keeping oneself away from injustice,&apos; &apos;friendship unchanged even in one&apos;s dark days,&apos; and &apos;the mountain hermit&apos;s miraculous medicine promising longevity.&apos;</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="5">
<j>ところが、日本に渡ってからは同じく中国から渡来した桜のように儚げなイメージをもたれるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, when the chrysanthemum came to Japan, it was deemed as the symbol of ephemera, just like the blossoms of cherry which also came from China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, when the chrysanthemum came to Japan, it was deemed the symbol of ephemera, just like the cherry blossoms, which also came from China.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, when the chrysanthemum came to Japan, it was deemed the symbol of ephemera, just like the cherry blossoms, which also came from China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="6">
<j>平安朝の貴族は、盛りを過ぎかけた白菊がほのかに紫がかった風情をことさら優美なものとして愛好し、「一年に二度の盛りを迎える花」「冬枯れの直前まで美しく咲く花」と愛でた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The court nobles in the Heian period praised the white chrysanthemum that was at a little time past its prime and tinged with a slight purple as having a quite delicate charm, so they described it as &quot;the flower that has two peaks in a year,&quot; or &quot;the flower in beautiful bloom until just before the winter.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The court nobles in the Heian period praised the white chrysanthemum that was at a little time past its prime and tinged with a slight purple as having a quite delicate charm, so they described it as &quot;the flower that has two peaks in a year,&quot; or &quot;the flower in beautiful bloom until just before winter.&quot;</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The court nobles in the Heian period praised the white chrysanthemum that was at a little time past its prime and tinged with a slight purple as having a quite delicate charm, so they described it as &apos;the flower that has two peaks in a year,&apos; or &apos;the flower in beautiful bloom until just before winter.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="7">
<j>重ねの色目にも採用されており、表が中紫で裏は青、あるいは表が紫で裏は白（山科流）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Purple was used in the color combinations for the court attire, and in Yamashina school (a school of the dressing method of the formal attire in those days), for example, the attire&apos;s outside was middle purple and the liner was blue - or, the outside was purple and the liner was white.</e>
<cmt>・「山科流」については、下記のホームページを参照の上括弧内で「当時の正装の着付け方法に関する一流派」と解説しています。[http://www.kariginu.jp/kikata/3-1.htm]（日本語）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Purple was used in the color combinations for court attire, and in Yamashina school (a school of the dressing method of the formal attire in those days), for example, the attire&apos;s outside was medium purple and the liner was blue - or, the outside was purple and the liner was white.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Purple was used in the color combinations for court attire, and in Yamashina school (a school of the dressing method of the formal attire in those days), for example, the attire&apos;s outside was medium purple and the liner was blue - or, the outside was purple and the liner was white.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="8">
<j>源氏物語にも「うつろひたる菊」などという呼び方で登場し、鑑賞するほかに挿頭や手紙の付け枝として利用されていたことがわかる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;The Tale of Genji&quot; also described utsuroi-giku as &quot;the color-changing chrysantemum,&quot; and the tale shows us that people at that time not only enjoyed looking at the chrysanthemum but also used it as &quot;kazashi&quot; (flowers worn in one&apos;s hair in a shrine ritual) and as a twig attached to a letter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;The Tale of Genji&quot; also described utsuroi-giku as &quot;the color-changing chrysantemum,&quot; and the tale shows us that people at that time not only enjoyed looking at the chrysanthemum but also used it as &quot;kazashi&quot; (flowers worn in one&apos;s hair in a shrine ritual) and as a twig attached to a letter.</e>
<cmt>italics</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;The Tale of Genji&quot; also described utsuroi-giku as &apos;the color-changing chrysanthemum,&apos; and the tale shows us that people at that time not only enjoyed looking at the chrysanthemum but also used it as kazashi (flowers worn in one&apos;s hair in a shrine ritual) and as a twig attached to a letter.</e>
<cmt>ダブルクォーテーションを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="9">
<j>秋をおきて時こそ有けれ菊の花うつろふからに色のまされば（紀貫之「古今和歌集」）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;In addition to autumn, the chrysanthemum seems to have another peak season, because it becomes more beautiful on changing its color into purple.&quot; (a poem in &quot;A Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry,&quot; selected by &quot;KI no Tsurayuki&quot; and other poetry masters)</e>
<cmt>・現代語訳(日本語)が下記ホームページの「秋」の項に出ています。（「秋以外にも盛りの時があったのですね、菊の花は。色が変わったと思った途端、その色が一層濃くなったのですから。」）[http://www.asahi-net.or.jp/&quot;SG2H-ymst/yamatouta/sennin/sadahumi.html] ・紀貫之はこの歌の作者ではなく、その撰者（のひとり）ですので、その旨を英訳では明らかにしています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;In addition to autumn, the chrysanthemum seems to have another peak season, because it becomes more beautiful on changing its color to purple.&quot; (a poem in &quot;A Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry,&quot; selected by &quot;KI no Tsurayuki&quot; and other poetry masters)</e>
<cmt>preposition</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to autumn, the chrysanthemum seems to have another peak season, because it becomes more beautiful on changing its color to purple (a poem by KI no Tsurayuki and selected in &quot;Kokin Wakashu&quot; [A Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry])</e>
<cmt>ダブルクォーテーションを削除しました。紀貫之による和歌　としました。「古今和歌集」　日本名も追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="10">
<j>紫にやしほ染めたる菊の花うつろふ花と誰かいひけん（藤原義忠「後拾遺和歌集」）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;The beauty of the chrysanthemum purple tempted the court noble to dye the attire into the same color, thereby keeping its life, so I wonder who ever said it ephemeral.&quot; (a poem composed by &quot;FUJIWARA no Noritada&quot; and selected in &quot;Later Collection of Gleanings of Japanese Poetry&quot;)</e>
<cmt>・現代訳をネットから発見することはできませんでした。そこで古語辞典（旺文社）を参照しつつ自分なりに解釈すると、「菊の花はこれを愛でる宮廷人の衣服の色を紫に染めた。こうして菊の花の美は形をとどめているのにこれをはかない花と誰が言ったのか。」で、英訳もこれに沿って行ったつもりです。・なおここでは、藤原義忠（ふじわらののりただ）が歌の作者です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;The beauty of the chrysanthemum purple tempted the court nobles to dye their attire the same color, thereby keeping its life, so I wonder whoever said it was ephemeral.&quot; (a poem composed by &quot;FUJIWARA no Noritada&quot; and selected in &quot;Later Collection of Gleanings of Japanese Poetry&quot;)</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The beauty of the chrysanthemum purple tempted the court nobles to dye their attire the same color, thereby keeping its life, so I wonder whoever said it was ephemeral (a poem by FUJIWARA no Noritada and selected in &quot;Goshui Wakashu&quot; [Later Collection of Gleanings of Japanese Poetry])</e>
<cmt>ダブルクォーテーションを削除しました。「後拾遺和歌集」　日本名も追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), 桜井悠士(id:72420), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>