<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>胡弓</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kokyu (a stringed instrument)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokyu (a stringed instrument)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kokyu (a stringed instrument)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>胡弓（こきゅう）は日本の擦弦楽器。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kokyu is a stringed instrument in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokyu is a stringed instrument in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kokyu is a Japanese stringed instrument.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>概説1および歴史以下に説明する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its summary is described in summary 1below and its history is also described there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its summary is described below and its history is also described there.</e>
<cmt>redundancy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary 1 and its history are described below.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>胡弓 (くーちょー) は沖縄の擦弦楽器。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kucho is a stringed instrument in Okinawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kucho is a stringed instrument in Okinawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kucho is an Okinawan stringed instrument.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>概説2に説明する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its summary is described in summary 2.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">See summary 2.</e>
<cmt>grammar, redundant</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">See summary 2.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>胡弓 (こきゅう) は広義として擦弦楽器の総称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a broad sense, Kokyu is a name covering the stringed instruments as a whole.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In a broad sense, Kokyu is a name covering stringed instruments as a whole.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In a broad sense, Kokyu is a generic name covering all the stringed instruments.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>ことにアジアの擦弦楽器の総称として使われることがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In particular, the term of Kokyu is sometimes used for indicating the stringed instruments in Asia as a whole.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In particular, the term Kokyu is sometimes used to indicate stringed instruments in Asia as a whole.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In particular, Kokyu is sometimes indicate all the Asian stringed instruments.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>概説3に説明する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This subject is described in summary 3.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This subject is described in summary 3.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This subject is described in summary 3.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>概説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>和楽器であり、多くのものは3本の弦を持ち（4本のものなどもある）、ほぼ三味線を小型にした形をしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Being an instrument in Japan, Kokyu is mostly provided with three strings (although some with four strings), and its shape is roughly a smaller version of Shamisen (a three-stringed Japanese banjo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Being an instrument in Japan, Kokyu is mostly provided with three strings (although some have four strings), and its shape is roughly a smaller version of the Shamisen - a three-stringed Japanese banjo).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Being a Japanese instrument, Kokyu is mostly provided with three strings (although some have four strings), and its shape is roughly a smaller version of the Shamisen - a three-stringed Japanese banjo.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>素材も三味線とほぼ同じで、現在では棹に紅木 (こうき)、紫檀 (したん)、普及品にはカリン (マメ科) (かりん)が使われ、胴は花梨で、皮はネコまたは犬、弦 (糸) は絹製である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Almost the same materials as those for Shamisen are used: Nowadays, for the neck part, koki (literally, a red wood) or Shitan (rosewood) is used or quince (Fabaceae) for popular versions, and for the main body, Chinese quince is used, with leather of a cat or dog and silk strings utilized as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Almost the same materials for Shamisen are used: Nowadays, for the neck part, koki (literally, red wood) or Shitan (rosewood) is used or quince (Fabaceae) for popular versions, and for the main body, Chinese quince is used, with leather of a cat or dog and silk strings utilized as well.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Almost the same materials for Shamisen are used; nowadays, for the neck part, koki (literally, red wood) or Shitan (rosewood) is used or quince (Fabaceae) for popular versions, and for the main body, Chinese quince is used, with leather of cat or dog and silk strings utilized as well.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>三味線と大きく異なるのは駒で、設置する位置も全く違うが、作りや材質も大きく異なっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bridges of Kokyu are quite different from those of Shamisen: The places where they are placed are completely different, and their shapes and materials are also different considerably.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bridges of Kokyu are quite different from those of the Shamisen: The places where they are placed are completely different, and their shapes and materials are also differ considerably.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bridges of Kokyu are quite different from those of the Shamisen; the places where they are placed are completely different, and their shapes and materials are also considerably different.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>弓 (楽器)は紫檀、花梨、竹などを用い、漆が塗られることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A bow is made of Shitan, quince or bamboo, and some of them are lacquered.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bow is made of Shitan, quince or bamboo, and some of them are lacquered.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bow is made of Shitan, quince or bamboo, and it is sometimes lacquered.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>弓の棹は中央部が毛側に向けてやや湾曲し、つまり内向きにわずかに反っているものが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The central portion of the wood part of the bow is mostly bent slightly towards the hair side, or warped slightly inwards.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The central portion of the wood part of the bow is mostly bent slightly towards the hair side, or warped slightly inwards.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The central portion of the wood part of the bow is bent slightly towards the hair side, or warped slightly inwards in the most cases.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>これは弓に弾力を持たせるためで、現代のヴァイオリンと同じである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is for increasing the resilience level of a bow, as for violins at present.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is for increasing the resilience level of a bow, as done for violins at present.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is for increasing the resilience of a bow, as for violins at present.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>たいていは中央部で二つに分解できるようになっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most of these bows are made so as to be separated into two parts at the central portion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most of these bows are made so as to be separated into two parts at the central portion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most of the bows are made so as to be separated into two parts at the central portion.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>細部の仕様は流派、個人により異なる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The specification of details depend on the Kokyu school or the person who uses Kokyu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The specification of details depend on the Kokyu school or the person who uses Kokyu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The specifications of details depend on the Kokyu school or the person who uses Kokyu.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>毛は円筒状に束ねたウマ尾毛である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The hair of horse tails is bound to make the hair of a bow.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The hair of horse tails is bound to make the hair for the bow.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Horse tail hair is bound to make the hair for the bow.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>これは取り外しができ、手元側に紐が付けられ、それを弓の棹に取り付けられた金属の小さな輪に結わえて留める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This hair can be removed and attached again: A cord is attached to the tip of the hair, on the side near to the hand, and the cord is tied to a small metallic ring attached to the wood part of the bow.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This hair can be removed and attached again: A cord is attached to the tip of the hair, on the side near to the hand, and the cord is tied to a small metallic ring attached to the wood part of the bow.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This hair is detachable; a cord is attached to the tip of the hair on the side of the hand; and the cord is tied to a small metallic ring attached to the wood part of the bow.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>三曲系で使われる弓は長いものが多く、毛の長さ70センチメートル、全長1メートルを超えるものも珍しくない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bows of Kokyu that are used in the genre of Sangyoku (played in combination with Kokyu and two other Japanese instruments) are mostly long, and bows with a hair length of 70 cm and a total length exceeding 1 meter are not rare.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bows of Kokyu that are used in the genre of Sangyoku (played in combination with Kokyu and two other Japanese instruments) are mostly long, and bows with a hair length of 70 cm and a total length exceeding 1 meter are common.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most of the bows of Kokyu that are used in the genre of Sangyoku (played in combination with Kokyu and two other Japanese instruments) are long, and bows with a hair length of seventy centimeters and a total length exceeding one meter are common.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>また毛の量も非常に多く、それを緩やかに張るのが特徴である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, a large amount of hair is used, and it is a feature of the bows of this type to attach the hair string at a moderate tension.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, a large amount of hair is used, and it is a feature of the bows of this type to attach the hair string at a moderate tension.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, a large amount of hair is used, and it is a feature of the bows of this type to have the hair string attached at a moderate tension.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>流派によっては手元に大きな絹製の房をつける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some Kokyu schools use bows with a big tassel at the near-to-hand side of them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some Kokyu schools use bows with a big tassel at the near-to-hand side of them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some Kokyu schools use bows with a big tassel at the side of the hand.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>いっぽう民謡系で使用される弓は非常に短く、棹も細い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, for the Kokyu used for fork songs, a quite short bow with a thin wood part is used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, for Kokyu used in fork songs, a quite short bow with a thin wood part is used.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, for Kokyu used in ballads, a quite short bow with a thin wood part is used.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>毛の量もごくわずかである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The amount of hair used is quite small.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The amount of hair used is quite a bit less.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The amount of hair used is quite small.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>世界的に見ても同じ楽器で種目によりこれほど弓に大きな差があるものは珍しい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is worldly unusual that, for the same instruments, such a big difference exists for the bows depending on the music genre where they are used.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is worldly unusual that, for the same instruments, such a big difference exists for the bows depending upon the music genre where they are used.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is unusual in the world that, for the same instruments, such a big difference exists for the bows depending upon the music genre where they are used.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>音楽としては、胡弓楽、地歌、義太夫節などで用いられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kokyu is played in Kokyu-gaku (music played with Kokyu alone), for Jiuta songs and for Gidayu-bushi (musical narrative of the puppet theatre).</e>
<cmt>胡弓楽：　読み方が不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokyu is played in Kokyu-gaku (music played with Kokyu alone), for Jiuta songs and for Gidayu-bushi (musical narrative of the puppet theatre).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kokyu is played in Kokyu-gaku (music played with Kokyu alone), for the accompaniment to Jiuta songs (traditional Japanese shamisen music), and for the accompaniment to Gidayu-bushi (musical narrative of the puppet theatre).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>「三曲」のひとつであり、三曲合奏の構成楽器の一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kokyu is one of &quot;Sangyoku,&quot; or one of the instruments that are used for playing Sangyoku together.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokyu is one of &quot;Sangyoku,&quot; or one of the instruments that are used for playing Sangyoku together.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kokyu is one of &apos;Sangyoku,&apos; or one of the instruments that are used for Sangyoku three instrument ensemble.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>また日本の民謡で、特に北陸から関西にかけて使用される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kokyu is used for Japanese fork songs in the areas from the Hokuriku region to the Kansai region.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokyu is used for Japanese folk songs in the areas from the Hokuriku region to the Kansai region.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kokyu is used for Japanese ballads of the areas from the Hokuriku region to the Kansai region.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>そのほか、各地の民俗芸能や一部の宗教において演奏される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, it is also played in local entertainments in various areas, and in some religions.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, it is also played for local entertainment in various areas, and in some religions.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, it is also played for folk entertainment in various areas, and in some religions.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>特徴として、弾く弦を変えるために弓ではなく本体を回す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its feature is that, to change the string (on the main body) to be played, not the bow but the main body itself is rotated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its feature is that, to change the string (on the main body) to be played, not the bow, but the main body itself, is rotated.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its feature is that the player rotates the main body to change the string on the main body to be played, instead of rotating the bow.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="30">
<j>琉球の擦弦楽器で、胡弓と書いてクーチョーと読む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A stringed instrument in Okinawa: The same Chinese characters, 胡弓, are used but pronounced &quot;Kucho.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A stringed instrument in Okinawa: The same Chinese characters, 胡弓, are used but pronounced &quot;Kucho.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A stringed instrument in Okinawa &quot;Kucho&quot; is written as the same Chinese characters for different pronunciation.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>本体は黒木（黒檀）やユシギ（イスの木）で作られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The main body is made of black wood (ebony) or Distylium racemosum.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The main body is made of black wood (ebony) or Distylium racemosum.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The main body is made of blackwood (ebony) or Distylium racemosum.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>胴は内地の胡弓と異なって椀型になっており（古くは椰子の実を二つに割って胴にした）、三線と同様にニシキヘビの皮を張る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The trunk part is made in the shape of a bowel, being different from that of Kokyu in the main islands of Japan (in older times, such a trunk was made by splitting a nut of coconut palms into halves), and the leather of python is used for covering the trunk as for Sanshin (Okinawan traditional three-stringed instrument)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The trunk part is made in the shape of a bowel, being different from that of Kokyu in the main islands of Japan (in olden times, such a trunk was made by splitting the nut of coconut palms into halves), and the leather of a python is used for covering the trunk as for Sanshin (Okinawan traditional three-stringed instrument)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The trunk is made in the shape of a bowl, being different from that of Kokyu in the main islands of Japan (in olden times, the trunk was made by splitting the nut of coconut palms into halves), and the leather of a python is used for covering the trunk as those for Sanshin (Okinawan traditional three-stringed instrument).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>弦は三線と同じく本来３本であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The number of strings was three originally as in Sanshin.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The number of strings was originally three as in Sanshin.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The number of strings was originally three as that in Sanshin.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>しかし、古典音楽の譜には三弦胡弓の最低音より低い音があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in the scores of classical music, there existed tones lower than the lowest tone that can be produced with three-stringed Kucho.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in the scores of classical music, there existed tones lower than the lowest tone that can be produced with a three-stringed Kucho.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in the scores of classical music, there existed sounds lower than the lowest sound that can be produced with a three-stringed Kucho.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>そこで、三線の名工で胡弓演奏家としても著名であった又吉真栄が低音用の弦を新たに設けた四弦胡弓を開発し、普及させた（三弦胡弓では１オクターブ上の音を弾いて代用していた）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, Shinei MATAYOSHI, who was an expert of manufacturing Sanshin and was also famous as a Kucho player, developed four-stringed Kucho provided with a string for lower tones additionally and made the instrument used widely (with three-string Kucho, the scores of these lower tones were played with them raised by an octave).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, Shinei MATAYOSHI, who was an expert of manufacturing Sanshin and was also famous as a Kucho player, developed four-stringed Kucho provided with a string for lower tones additionally and made the instrument used widely (with three-string Kucho, the scores of these lower tones were played raised by an octave).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, Shinei MATAYOSHI, who was an expert of manufacturing Sanshin and was also famous as a Kucho player, developed four-stringed Kucho provided with a string for bass part additionally and made the instrument used widely (with three-stringed Kucho, the scores of these lower tones were played raised by an octave).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>また、棹の形状も三線と同じくいくつかの型に分けられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The shapes of the neck part can be classified into several types as for Sanshin.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shapes of the neck part can be classified into several types as for Sanshin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The shape of the neck can be classified into several types as for Sanshin.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>しかしながら、弦が４本になり糸倉を長く取る必要が生じたので、元々糸倉の長い型である与那城型（ユナグシク型）で製作されることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, since four strings have become to be provided, making it necessary to increase the length of the peg box, Kucho is mostly made in the Yunagushiku type that originally uses a longer peg box.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, since four strings were provided, making it necessary to increase the length of the peg box, Kucho is mostly made in the Yunagushiku type that originally uses a longer peg box.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, since four strings were provided, making it necessary to increase the length of the peg box, most of the Kucho is made in the Yunagushiku type that originally uses a longer peg box.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>奏法については内地の胡弓と同じく、弓ではなく本体を回転させて弦を移動し演奏する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To change the string to be played, Kucho also rotates not the bow but the main body, as Kokyu in the main islands of Japan does.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To change the string to be played, Kucho also rotates not the bow, but the main body, as Kokyu on the main islands of Japan do.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To change the string to be played, the Kucho player rotates not the bow, but the main body, as the Kokyu player on the mainland do.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>楽譜は三線と同様の工工四（クンクンシー）に押し弓弾き・引き弓弾きの指示を加えたものが用いられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For the music scores, those in which an instruction for pushing the bow and another instruction for pulling the bow are added to the scores of Kunkunshi (Score for Okinawa Traditional 3-stringed instrument) for Sanshin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For the music scores, those in which instructions for pushing the bow and other instructions for pulling the bow are added to the scores of Kunkunshi (Score for Okinawa Traditional 3-stringed instrument) for Sanshin.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For the Kucho music scores, instructions for pushing the bow and other instructions for pulling the bow are added to the scores of Kunkunshi (score for Okinawa traditional three-stringed instrument) for Sanshin.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>その起源や、内地の胡弓との関連については不明。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its origin and the relationship with Kokyu in the main islands of Japan are not known.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its origin and the relationship with Kokyu from the main islands of Japan are not known.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its origin and the relationship with Kokyu from the mainland are not known.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>ただし東南アジアに類似楽器が多く存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, many similar instruments are found in Southeast Asia.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, many similar instruments are found in Southeast Asia.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, quite a few similar instruments are found in Southeast Asia.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>したがって、琉球がさかんに貿易をしていた15世紀頃にタイ王国やマラッカから原型が渡来した可能性がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, there is a possibility that its original type of Kucho was brought to Okinawa from Kingdom of Thailand or Malacca in the 15th century when Ryukyu conducted trade with these areas actively.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, there is a possibility that the original type of Kucho was brought to Okinawa from the Kingdom of Thailand or Malacca in the 15th century when Ryukyu actively conducted trade with these areas.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, there is a possibility that the origin of Kucho was brought to Okinawa from the Kingdom of Thailand or Malacca in the fifteenth century when Ryukyu actively conducted trade with these areas.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>専ら古典音楽の演奏に脇役として用いられ、民謡にはあまり登場しない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kucho is exclusively used for supporting performances of classical music, and is not used often for playing folk songs.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kucho is exclusively used for supporting performances of classical music, and is not used often for playing folk songs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kucho is exclusively used for supporting performances of classical music, and is not used often for accompanying ballads.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>そのため、昨今流行の三線とは異なって地味な存在である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, Kucho does not attract much attention unlike Sanshin that has become popular recently.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, Kucho does not attract much attention unlike Sanshin that has become popular recently.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, Kucho does not attract much attention, unlike Sanshin that has become popular recently.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="45">
<j>広義として、擦弦楽器を総称する時に「胡弓」の語を用いることがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a broad sense, the term of &quot;kokyu&quot; is sometimes used for indicating stringed instruments as a whole.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In a broad sense, the term of &quot;kokyu&quot; is sometimes used for indicating stringed instruments as a whole.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In a broad sense, the term &apos;kokyu&apos; is sometimes used for collectively calling stringed instruments.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>明治初期にはヴァイオリンも胡弓と呼ばれたことがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the early Meiji period, even violins were sometimes called Kokyu as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the early Meiji period, even violins were sometimes called Kokyu as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the early Meiji period, even violins were called Kokyu.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>一般的にはアジアの擦弦楽器を総称する時に使われることがあるが、定義は曖昧である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Generally, it is sometimes used for indicating stringed instruments in Asia as a whole, but the definition is not clear.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Generally, it is sometimes used for indicating stringed instruments in Asia as a whole, but the definition is not clear.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Generally, it is sometimes used for indicating all the stringed instruments in Asia, but the definition is not clear.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>そのためもあり特に、中国の擦弦楽器である二胡、高胡などを俗に胡弓と呼ぶことすらある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, even erhu (2-stringed Chinese instrument played with a bow) and gaohu (Chinese bowed string instrument developed from the erhu) that are Chinese stringed instruments are sometimes called Kokyu commonly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, even erhu (2-stringed Chinese instrument played with a bow) and gaohu (Chinese bowed string instrument developed from the erhu) that are Chinese stringed instruments are sometimes called Kokyu commonly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, even Chinese stringed instruments erhu (two-stringed Chinese instrument played with a bow) and gaohu (Chinese bowed string instrument developed from the erhu) are sometimes commonly called Kokyu.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>現代では単に胡弓といった場合、むしろこれらを指すことも多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nowadays, when the term of Kokyu is used without any context, it often means these instruments rather than Kokyu in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nowadays, when the term of Kokyu is used without any context, it often means these instruments rather than Kokyu in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nowadays, when the term of Kokyu is used without any context, it often means these instruments rather than Japanese Kokyu.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>しかしこれは明らかに誤用である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, this use of the term is incorrect.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, this use of the term is incorrect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, this usage is apparently incorrect.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>そのために本来の胡弓との間に混同が生じており、問題化している（中国の擦弦楽器との区別のため和楽器の胡弓が「和胡弓」「大和胡弓」「日本胡弓」といった名称で呼ばれることもある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, confusion between original Kokyu and these Chinese stringed instruments is generated, causing a problem (to differentiate between them, Kokyu as a Japanese instrument is sometimes called &quot;Wa-Kokyu,&quot; &quot;Yamato-Kokyu&quot; or &quot;Japanese Kokyu&quot; (both &quot;Wa&quot; and &quot;Yamato&quot; mean Japan or Japanese)).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, confusion between original Kokyu and these Chinese stringed instruments is generated, causing a problem (to differentiate between them, Kokyu as a Japanese instrument is sometimes called &quot;Wa-Kokyu,&quot; &quot;Yamato-Kokyu&quot; or &quot;Japanese Kokyu&quot; - both &quot;Wa&quot; and &quot;Yamato&quot; mean Japan or Japanese).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, confusion between original Kokyu and these Chinese stringed instruments is generated, causing a problem (to differentiate from these Chinese stringed instruments, Japanese Kokyu is sometimes called &apos;Wa-Kokyu,&apos; &apos;Yamato-Kokyu&apos; or &apos;Japanese Kokyu&apos; - both &quot;Wa&quot; and &quot;Yamato&quot; mean Japan or Japanese).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>このため、一部の胡弓関係者、二胡関係者により、正しい呼称の使用が呼びかけられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Consequently, some persons concerned with Kokyu and those concerned with erhu voiced that these terms should be used correctly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequently, some persons concerned with Kokyu and those concerned with erhu voiced that these terms should be used correctly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently, some persons concerned with Kokyu and those concerned with erhu voice that these terms should be used correctly.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="53">
<j>以下は和楽器の胡弓についてである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following descriptions are concerned with Kokyu in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following descriptions are concerned with Kokyu in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following descriptions are about Japanese Kokyu.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="54">
<j>胡弓が最初に文献に現れるのは江戸時代初期であり、三味線と比較するとやや遅い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first document including descriptions of Kokyu appeared in the early Edo period, slightly later than that of Shamisen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first document including descriptions of Kokyu appeared in the early Edo period, slightly later than that of Shamisen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kokyu first appeared in a document in the early Edo period, slightly later than that of Shamisen.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>その起源は諸説があり定かではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its origin is unclear, with various theories provided.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its origin is unclear, with various theories provided.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its origin is uncertain, with various theories provided.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>中国の二胡など胡琴系楽器とはやや縁が遠く、むしろ東南アジアの楽器に近いのではないかという説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to a theory, Kokyu is not much related to kokin (huqin (any Chinese string instrument played with a bow))-related instruments, such as erhu, but is more related to instruments in Southeast Asia.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to a theory, Kokyu is not related to kokin (huqin - any Chinese string instrument played with a bow) related instruments, such as the erhu, but is more closely related to instruments in Southeast Asia.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to a theory, Kokyu is not close to kokin (huqin - any Chinese string instrument played with a bow) related instruments, such as the erhu, but is closer to instruments in Southeast Asia.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>また、南蛮貿易によりもたらされたヨーロッパのレベックやヴィオールに起源を求める説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In another theory, it is considered that Kokyu originates in the Rebec or viol brought to Japan from Europe through trade with Spain and Portugal.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In another theory, it is considered that Kokyu originates from the Rebec or viol brought to Japan from Europe through trade with Spain and Portugal.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In another theory, it is considered that Kokyu originates from the Rebec or Viol brought to Japan from Europe through trade with Spain and Portugal.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>当初は門付（かどつけ）などの民俗音楽に用いられていたようだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is likely that Kokyu was initially used for fork music, such as Kadotsuke (performance in front of the gate of houses).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is likely that Kokyu was initially used for folk music, such as Kadotsuke (performances in front of the gate of houses).</e>
<cmt>spelling.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is likely that Kokyu was initially used for ballads, such as Kadotsuke (performances in front of the gate of houses).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>しかいながら、一説によると三味線音楽の祖である石村検校も胡弓の名手だったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, according to a theory, Kengyo ISHIMURA, the founder of Shamisen music, was an expert Kokyu player as well.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, according to a theory, Kengyo ISHIMURA, the founder of Shamisen music, was an expert Kokyu player as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, according to a theory, the founder of Shamisen music Kengyo ISHIMURA was an expert Kokyu player as well.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>また、八橋検校と親交のあった藤本箕山が1678年に著した『色道大鑑』には、八橋検校によって胡弓の弓が改良され音色が著しく変わったことが書かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Shikido Okagami&quot; (The Great Minor of the Erotic Way) written by Kizan FUJIMOTO, who had an intimate relationship with Kengyo YATSUHASHI, describes that the bow of Kokyu was improved by Kengyo YATSUHASHI, changing its tones drastically.</e>
<cmt>&quot;該当する書籍が見当たらず、藤本箕山（ふじもときざん）著の「色道大鏡」あるいは「好色大鑑」を指すとおもわれます。ここでは「色道大鏡」として訳してあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Shikido Okagami&quot; (The Great Minor of the Erotic Way) written by Kizan FUJIMOTO, who had an intimate relationship with Kengyo YATSUHASHI, describes that the bow of Kokyu was improved by Kengyo YATSUHASHI, changing its tones drastically.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Shikido Okagami&quot; written by Kizan FUJIMOTO in 1678, who had an intimate relationship with Kengyo YATSUHASHI, describes that Kengyo YATSUHASHI improved the bow of Kokyu, changing its tones drastically.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>このように、地歌・箏曲の成立とほぼ同時に当道座の盲人音楽家たちによって胡弓が演奏されていたことが分かる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this way, it is known that blind musicians at Todo-za (the traditional guild for the blind) played Kokyu at almost the same era when Jiuta songs and Sokyoku (koto music) had been established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this way, it is known that blind musicians at Todo-za (the traditional guild for the blind) played Kokyu during almost the same era when Jiuta songs and Sokyoku (koto music) had been established.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this way, it is known that blind musicians at Todo-za (the traditional guild for the blind) played Kokyu during almost the same period when Jiuta songs and Sokyoku (koto music) had been established.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>また、初期の胡弓は胴が丸形をしており、三味線とは異なった形をしていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The initial shape of the trunk part of Kokyu was round, unlike that of Shamisen.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The initial shape of the trunk part of Kokyu was round, unlike that of Shamisen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The initial shape of the trunk of Kokyu was round, unlike that of the Shamisen.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>が、江戸時代中期までにはほぼ三味線と同形となり、形が定まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, by the middle of the Edo period, the shape became almost the same as that of Samisen, being altered little after that.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, by the middle of the Edo period, the shape became almost the same as that of Samisen, being altered little after that.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, by the middle of the Edo period, the shape became almost the same as that of the Shamisen, being altered little after that.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="64">
<j>その後、胡弓音楽は三味線 (三弦) の音楽である地歌、箏の音楽である箏曲と同時に発展した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, Kokyu music developed together with Jiuta songs using Samisen (with three strings) and with So music (played with So (13-stringed Koto)).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, Kokyu music developed together with Jiuta songs using Samisen (with three strings) and with So music (played with So - 13-stringed Koto).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, Kokyu music developed consequently with Jiuta songs using Shamisen (with three strings) and with So music (played with So - thirteen-stringed Koto).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>これらを総称して「三曲」といい、相互に深くかかわり合って来た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The music played with these three instruments are called &quot;Sangyoku&quot; (literally, three kinds of music) as a whole, and these three kinds of music have been deeply interacted with each other.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The music played with these three instruments are called &quot;Sangyoku&quot; (literally, three kinds of music) as a whole, and these three kinds of music have deeply interacted with each other.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The music played with these three instruments are collectively called &apos;Sangyoku&apos; (literally, three kinds of music), and these three kinds of music have deeply interacted with each other.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>また地歌や箏曲に加わり他の楽器と合奏することも多くなり、特に三曲すべてを合わせる三曲合奏の形式が出来上がっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, the occasions had increased in which Kokyu was played with other instruments, for example, for Jiuta songs or So music, and in particular, the form of playing these three instruments together had been established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, occasions ncreased in which Kokyu was played with other instruments, for example, for Jiuta songs or So music, and in particular, the form of playing these three instruments together had been established.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, Kokyu became increasingly played for Jiuta songs or So music with other instruments, and in particular, the form of playing these three instruments in concert had been established.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>江戸時代を通じて三曲合奏が盛んであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These three instruments were played together actively throughout the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These three instruments were played together actively throughout the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These three instruments were played together frequently throughout the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>このようにして、胡弓音楽は当道座の盲人音楽家たちによって作られ、今に至るまで伝承されてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this way, Kokyu music was established by blind musicians at Todo-za and has been handed down to subsequent generations until now.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this way, Kokyu music was established by blind musicians at Todo-za and has been handed down to subsequent generations until now.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this way, Kokyu music was composed by blind musicians at Todo-za and has been handed down to subsequent generations until now.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>今日、マスコミなどでは民謡の胡弓が取り上げられることが多く、一般にも知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today, being often reported in mass media, Kokyu in fork music is known by general public as well.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, being often reported in the mass media, Kokyu in folk music is known by the general public as well.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, being often reported in the mass media, Kokyu accompanying ballads is known to the general public as well.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>しかし胡弓音楽の主体は歴史的、内容的に見ても三曲にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the core of Kokyu music is Sangyoku from the viewpoint of its contents as well as of the history.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the core of Kokyu music is Sangyoku from the viewpoint of its contents as well as of the history.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the core of Kokyu music consists in Sangyoku from the viewpoint of its contents as well as of the history.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>現在でも新しい曲が作られ、演奏活動や伝承も行なわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even today, Sangyoku is played, with new scores written for it, and the efforts to hand down the music to subsequent generations are made as well.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even today, Sangyoku is played, with new scores written for it, and the efforts to hand down the music to subsequent generations are made as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even today, Sangyoku is played, with new pieces composed for it, and the efforts to hand down the music to subsequent generations are made as well.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>種類</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinds of Kokyu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kinds of Kokyu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Types of Kokyu</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="72">
<j>胡弓の種類については、通常の三弦のもののほかに、江戸時代中期に江戸において藤植検校が藤植流を創始し、四弦の胡弓が伝承されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Concerning the kinds of Kokyu, four-stringed one in addition to three-stringed one Kokyu has been handed down to subsequent generations through the Fujiue school that was started by Kengyo FUJIUE in Edo in the middle of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Concerning the kinds of Kokyu, four-stringed one in addition to three-stringed one Kokyu has been handed down to subsequent generations through the Fujiue school that was started by Kengyo FUJIUE in Edo during the middle of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Concerning the types of Kokyu, four-stringed one in addition to three-stringed one has been handed down to subsequent generations through the Fujiue school that was started by Kengyo FUJIUE in Edo during the middle of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>明治以降には宮城道雄が、通常使われている胡弓を大型にした大胡弓を開発し、この楽器を用いた楽曲を作曲している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In and after the Meiji period, Michio MIYAGI developed Kokyu larger than the one that had been used ordinarily, or Dai-Kokyu (large Kokyu), and composed music for this instrument.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In and after the Meiji period, Michio MIYAGI developed Kokyu larger than tose that had been ordinarily used, or Dai-Kokyu (large Kokyu), and composed music for this instrument.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Meiji period, Michio MIYAGI developed Kokyu larger than those that had been ordinarily used, or Dai-Kokyu,, and composed music for this instrument.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>他に、大正時代に音楽学者田辺尚雄が考案した「玲琴」がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, Hisao TANABE, a scholar in music, devised &quot;Reikin&quot; in the Taisho period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, Hisao TANABE, a scholar in music, devised &quot;Reikin&quot; during the Taisho period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, a scholar in music Hisao TANABE devised &apos;Reikin&apos; during the Taisho period.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>これは三本弦だが胡弓のように皮張りではなく板張りの台形胴を持っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reikin was provided with three strings, but a wood plate instead of leather was used for the cover of the trunk part.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reikin was provided with three strings, but a wood plate instead of leather was used for the cover of the trunk part.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reikin was provided with three strings, but a wood plate instead of leather was used for the cover of the trunk.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>外見はモンゴルの馬頭琴に類似しており、はじめは民謡の一形態である「追分」の伴奏に使われていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the exterior view similar to Matouqin (stringed musical instrument) of Mongolian origin, it was initially played for accompanying Oiwake fork songs</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the exterior view similar to the Matouqin (stringed musical instrument) of Mongolian origin, it was initially played for accompanying Oiwake folk songs</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With its appearance similar to the Matouqin (stringed musical instrument) of Mongolian origin, it was initially played for accompanying Oiwake ballad.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>しかしながら、やがて当時盛んになっていた「新日本音楽」に取り入れられ、様々な合奏で使われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, before long, it became to be played in New Japanese Music (music using Japanese instruments), which was popular at that time, enabling it to be played together with various instruments.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, before long, it became to be played in New Japanese Music (music using Japanese instruments), that were popular at that time, enabling it to be played together with various instruments.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, before long, it became to be played in New Japanese Music (music using Japanese instruments), which were popular at that time, enabling it to be played together with various instruments.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>主に低音部を受け持ったが、戦後はほとんど使用されなくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reikin mostly played lower tone parts, but almost ceased to be played after the war.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reikin mostly played lower tone parts, but almost ceased to be played after the war.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reikin mostly played bass part, but almost ceased to be played after the war.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>また平成になって胡弓演奏家の原一男により低音域を拡張させた五弦胡弓が考案されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, Kazuo HARA, a Kokyu player, devised five-stringed Kokyu that enabled further lower tones to be generated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, Kazuo HARA, a Kokyu player, devised five-stringed Kokyu that enabled further lower tones to be generated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, a Kokyu player Kazuo HARA devised five-stringed Kokyu that enabled further lower tones to be generated after the Heisei period.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>三曲 (胡弓楽・地歌・箏曲) における胡弓</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kokyu in Sangyoku (Kokyu-gaku, Jiuta songs and So music)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokyu in Sangyoku (Kokyu-gaku, Jiuta songs and So music)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kokyu in Sangyoku (Kokyu-gaku, Jiuta songs and So music)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="80">
<j>江戸時代中期には盲人音楽家たちにより芸術音楽化が進み、胡弓独自の流派が立てられ、胡弓専門の音楽がつくられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the middle era of the Edo period, the artistic level of music was raised by blind musicians and a school dedicated for Kokyu was established, creating music specialized for Kokyu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the middle era of the Edo period, the artistic level of music was raised by blind musicians and a school dedicated for Kokyu was established, creating music specialized for Kokyu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the middle of the Edo period, the artistic level of music for Kokyu was raised by blind musicians and a school dedicated for Kokyu was established, composing music specialized for Kokyu.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>これを後世「胡弓楽」と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This music was called &quot;Kokyu-gaku&quot; in later ages.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This music was called &quot;Kokyu-gaku&quot; in later ages.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This music was called &apos;Kokyu-gaku&apos; (胡弓楽) in future generations.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>これに、同じく盲人音楽家たちの専門である地歌・箏曲を合わせて三曲と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The music including Kokyu-gaku as well as Jiuta songs and So music, both of which were also specialties of blind musicians, is called Sangyoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Music including Kokyu-gaku as well as Jiuta songs and So music, both of which were also specialties of blind musicians, is called Sangyoku.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Music including Kokyu-gaku as well as Jiuta songs and So music, both of which were also specialties for blind musicians, is called Sangyoku.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>胡弓専用の曲のほか、これら地歌曲の多くや箏曲の一部に胡弓を合奏することも盛んになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to music specialized for Kokyu, Kokyu was played widely for many of Jiuta songs and for some of So music as well.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to music specialized for Kokyu, Kokyu was played widely for many Jiuta songs and for some So music as well.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to the music specialized for Kokyu, Kokyu was played widely for a lot of Jiuta songs and for some So music as well.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>ことに三曲の楽器すべてを合奏することを三曲合奏といい、盛んに行なわれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In particular, the performance in which all of the three instruments are played together is called Sangyoku-gassou (Sangyoku performance) and such concerts were held actively.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In particular, the performance in which all three instruments are played together is called Sangyoku-gassou (Sangyoku performance) and such concerts were held actively.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In particular, the performance in which all three instruments are played together is called Sangyoku-gasso and such concerts were held actively.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>こうして独奏楽器として、また三味線・胡弓合奏、箏・胡弓合奏、三曲合奏の1パートとして胡弓楽のジャンルが広がり発展することになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this way, Kokyu was not only used for playing music specialized for Kokyu alone but also played together with Samisen or So or as a part of Sangyoku-gassou, expanding the music genres where Kokyu was played and making it used more widely.</e>
<cmt>胡弓楽：　ここでは、”胡弓専用の音楽”の意味では、おかしいように思いましたので、”胡弓を用いた音楽”として訳してあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this way, Kokyu was not only used for playing music specialized for Kokyu alone, but also played together with Samisen or So or as a part of Sangyoku-gassou, expanding music genres where Kokyu was played and making it used more widely.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this way, Kokyu was not only used for playing music specialized for Kokyu alone, but also played together with Shamisen or So or as a part of Sangyoku-gasso, which expanded music genres where Kokyu was played and made Kokyu used more widely.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>ただし、特に江戸時代後半となると、胡弓楽と地歌、箏曲は交流が著しくほとんど一体化してしまっているので、胡弓楽という言葉はあまり使われない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, entering the latter half of the Edo period in particular, Kokyu-gaku, Jiuta songs and So music were intermingled considerably to the extent that they were almost integrated, and the term of Kokyu-gaku almost ceased to be used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, entering the latter half of the Edo period in particular, Kokyu-gaku, Jiuta songs, and So music were intermingled considerably to the extent that they were almost integrated, and the term of Kokyu-gaku almost ceased to be used.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, after entering the latter half of the Edo period in particular, Kokyu-gaku, Jiuta songs, and So music were intermingled considerably to the extent that they were almost integrated, and the term of Kokyu-gaku almost ceased to be used.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>また明治時代になると、三曲合奏は胡弓の代わりに尺八を用いることが多くなり、胡弓の演奏は減少した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, entering the Meiji period, Shakuhachi bamboo flutes instead of Kokyu became to be used mostly, reducing the occasions in which Kokyu was played.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, entering the Meiji period, Shakuhachi bamboo flutes instead of Kokyu mostly came to be used, reducing the occasions in which Kokyu was played.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, after entering the Meiji period, Shakuhachi bamboo flutes instead of Kokyu mostly came to be used, reducing the occasions in which Kokyu was played.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>いかしながら、多くの地歌・箏曲の伝承流派は現在も胡弓の曲を伝承している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, even now, many of the traditional Jiuta song schools and of So music schools have handed down music using Kokyu to subsequent generations.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, even now, many of traditional Jiuta song schools and So music schools have handed down music using Kokyu to subsequent generations.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, even now, many of traditional Jiuta song schools and So music schools have been handing down music using Kokyu to subsequent generations.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>ただし胡弓楽は地歌、箏曲とは半ば独立した伝承系統を持っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Kokyu-gaku has a handing-down-for-generations system independent of those for Jiuta songs and So music.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Kokyu-gaku has a handing-down-for-generations system independent of those for Jiuta songs and So music.</e>
<cmt>word spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Kokyu-gaku has a handing-down line independent of those for Jiuta songs and So music.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>したがって、流派としては、地歌や箏曲の生田流に対応するものは流派を名乗っていないが大きく分けて大阪系、京都系、名古屋系がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, although there is no named school, the three large lines of Osaka line, the Kyoto line and the Nagoya line exist corresponding to the Ikuta school for Jiuta songs and So music.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, although there is no named school, the three large lines of the Osaka line, the Kyoto line and the Nagoya line exist corresponding to the Ikuta school for Jiuta songs and So music.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, although there is no named school, the three large lines of the Osaka line, the Kyoto line and the Nagoya line exist correspondingly to the Ikuta school for Jiuta songs and So music.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>一方、山田流箏曲に対応するものとして藤植流、松翁流がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, the Fujiue school and the Sho school exist corresponding to the Yamada school for So music.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, the Fujiue school and the Sho school exist corresponding to the Yamada school for So music.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, the Fujiue school and the Sho school exist correspondingly to the Yamada school for So music.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>ほかに、大阪の政島検校(18世紀中頃)の創始による政島流がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, Kengyo MASAJIMA established the Masajima school (in around the middle of the 18th century).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, Kengyo MASAJIMA established the Masajima school (in around the middle of the 18th century).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, Kengyo MASAJIMA in Osaka established the Masajima school (around the middle of the eighteenth century).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>幕末に伝承が絶えてしまったが、現在の大阪系と関係があると思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the school followers became extinct towards the end of the Edo period, it is considered that the school has some relations with the present Osaka line.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the school followers became nonexistent towards the end of the Edo period, it is considered that the school has some relationship with the present Osaka line.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the school followers ceased to exist towards the end of the Edo period, it is considered that the school has some relationship with the present Osaka line.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>また19世紀初頭に京都で活躍した名手腕崎検校の流れである腕崎流が存在したとも言われ、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also said that there existed the Wakizaki school following Kengyo WAKIZAKI, who was an active and expert Kokyu player in Kyoto in the early 19th century.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also said that there existed the Wakizaki school following Kengyo WAKIZAKI, who was an active and expert Kokyu player in Kyoto in the early 19th century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also said that there existed the Wakizaki school following Kengyo WAKIZAKI, who was an expert Kokyu player active in Kyoto in the early nineteenth century.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>現在の京都系もそう名乗っているが、確かなことは分かっていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although followers of the present Kyoto line use the name, nothing certain about the matter is known.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although followers of the present Kyoto line use the name, nothing certain about the matter is known.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although followers of the present Kyoto line use the name, the matter remains uncertain.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>その他品川検校による品川流があったとも伝えられるが、これについてはまったくわかっていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, it is also said that the Shinagawa school by Kengyo SHINAGAWA existed, but nothing at all is known about the matter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, it is also said that the Shinagawa school of Kengyo SHINAGAWA existed, but nothing at all is known about it.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, it is also said that the Shinagawa school of Kengyo SHINAGAWA existed, but anything about the school remains uncertain.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>名古屋系はもっともよく胡弓の伝承を守っており、吉沢派、寺島派に分けられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Nagoya line keeps the tradition of Kokyu most faithfully, with two separate schools of the Yoshizawa school and the Terajima school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Nagoya line keeps the tradition of Kokyu most faithfully, with two separate schools of the Yoshizawa school and the Terajima school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Nagoya line keeps the tradition of Kokyu most faithfully, with two branches of the Yoshizawa school and the Terajima school.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>吉沢派は幕末に活躍した吉沢検校の流れである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Yoshizawa school follows the line of Kengyo YOSHIZAWA who played Kokyu actively towards the end of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Yoshizawa school follows the line of Kengyo YOSHIZAWA who played Kokyu actively towards the end of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Yoshizawa school follows the line of Kengyo YOSHIZAWA, who was active towards the end of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>地歌曲や箏曲に胡弓を合奏させる場合、多くはほとんどユニゾンで目立ち過ぎぬように合わせる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Playing for a Jiuta song or a piece of So music, Kokyu usually plays the same melody as that of the song or music inconspicuously.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Playing for a Jiuta song or a piece of So music, Kokyu usually plays the same melody as that of the song or music inconspicuously.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Playing for a Jiuta song or a piece of So music, Kokyu usually plays in unison with the song or music inconspicuously.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>しかしながら、吉沢は胡弓に独自の旋律を与え、非常に技巧的な作曲、編曲をしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Yoshizawa gave independent melodies to Kokyu, composing pieces of music that needed skill to play or arranging pieces of music in ways of needing skill to play.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Yoshizawa gave independent melodies to Kokyu, composing pieces of music that needed skill to play or arranging pieces of music in ways needing skill to play.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Yoshizawa gave independent melodies to Kokyu, arranging and composing highly technical pieces of music.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>作品のひとつ「千鳥の曲」は胡弓の本曲、名曲として、また箏の名曲として名高い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Chidori no kyoku&quot; (a song for plover), one of his compositions, is famous as a Kokyu-specific, great piece of music, and is also well-known as a great piece of music for So.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Chidori no kyoku&quot; (a song for plover), one of his compositions, is famous as a Kokyu-specific, great piece of music, and is also well-known as a great piece of music for So.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chidori no kyoku&apos; (a song for plover), one of his compositions, is famous as an excellent Kokyu-specific piece of music, and is also well-known as an excellent piece of music for So.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>また、たとえば箏曲「六段の調」に、吉沢の手付による胡弓パートが合奏される場合、特別に「長崎六段」と呼ばれるほど独自で技巧的な手付になっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, when, for example, Kokyu was played together with So in &quot;Rokudan no shirabe&quot; (Music of Six Steps), a piece of music for So, using the music score written by Yosizawa, the score was so unique and needed such a high skill level to play that it is called &quot;Nagasaki, sixth-dan level.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, when, for example, Kokyu was played together with So in &quot;Rokudan no shirabe&quot; (Music of Six Steps), a piece of music for So, using the music score written by Yosizawa, the score was so unique and needed such a high skill level to play that it is called &quot;Nagasaki, sixth-dan level.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, when, for example, Kokyu was played together with So in &apos;Rokudan no shirabe&apos; (Music of Six Steps), a piece of music for So, using the music score written by Yoshizawa, it is specifically called &apos;Nagasaki Rokudan&apos; because the score was so unique and needed such a high skill level to play.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>大阪系でも明治以降に菊原琴治などが独自の手付を残している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In and after the Meiji period, Kinji KIKUHARA in the Osaka line also wrote original music scores for Kokyu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In and after the Meiji period, Kinji KIKUHARA in the Osaka line also wrote original music scores for Kokyu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Meiji period, Kinji KIKUHARA in the Osaka line also wrote original music scores for Kokyu.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="104">
<j>地歌・箏曲とともに発展し、当道座の盲人音楽家によって伝承されてきた胡弓音楽を胡弓楽と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kokyu-using music that has evolved together with Jiuta songs and So music and has been handed down to subsequent generations by blind musicians at Todo-za is called Kokyu-gaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kokyu-using music that has evolved together with Jiuta songs and So music and has been handed down to subsequent generations by blind musicians at Todo-za is called Kokyu-gaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kokyu music that has evolved together with Jiuta songs and So music and has been handed down to subsequent generations by blind musicians at Todo-za is called Kokyu-gaku.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>胡弓楽としてみた場合、その音楽は「本曲」と「外曲」に分けられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the viewpoint of Kokyu-gaku, the music includes Honkyoku (Kokyu-specific music) and Gaikyoku (literally, outside music).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the viewpoint of Kokyu-gaku, the music includes Honkyoku (Kokyu-specific music) and Gaikyoku (literally, outside music).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Kokyu-gaku is considered, the music includes Honkyoku (Kokyu-specific music) and Gaikyoku (literally, outside music).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>本曲は本手組とも呼ばれ、胡弓本来のために作られた曲であり、各流派がほぼ独自の本曲を持っている(一部本曲のない流派もある)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Honkyoku, also called Honte-gumi, indicates pieces of music written specifically for Kokyu, and each school has its own Honkyoku (although some schools have not their own Honkyoku).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Honkyoku, also called Honte-gumi, indicates pieces of music written specifically for Kokyu, and each school has its own Honkyoku (although some schools do not).</e>
<cmt>grammar, wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Honkyoku, also called Honte-gumi, indicates pieces of music composed specifically for Kokyu, and each school has its own Honkyoku (although some schools do not).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>曲によっては『鶴の巣籠』のように尺八楽との交流によって生まれたものもあるし、先の『千鳥の曲』のように箏との二重奏曲的性格の強いものもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some pieces of music for Kokyu, for example, Tsuru-no-Sugomori (a song depicting various aspects of the life cycle of the crane), were produced through playing for Shakuhachi bamboo flute music, and there are also pieces of music provided strongly with features of duets for Kokyu and So, for example, &quot;Chidori no kyoku&quot; described above,.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some pieces of music for Kokyu, for example, Tsuru-no-Sugomori (a song depicting various aspects of the life cycle of the crane), were produced through playing for Shakuhachi bamboo flute music, and there are also pieces of music provided strongly with features of duets for Kokyu and So, for example, &quot;Chidori no kyoku&quot; described above,.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some pieces of music for Kokyu, for example, &quot;Tsuru-no-Sugomori&quot; (a song depicting various aspects of the life cycle of the crane), were composed through playing for Shakuhachi bamboo flute music, and there are also pieces of music provided strongly with features of duets for Kokyu and So, for example, &quot;Chidori no kyoku&quot; described above.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>このほか、有名な胡弓本曲に『蝉の曲 (名古屋系・吉沢検校作曲)』、『岡安砧』 (藤植流・作曲者不詳) などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, &quot;Semi no uta (a song of cicadas) (composed by Kengyo YOSHIZAWA, and handed down in the Nagoya line)&quot; and &quot;Okayasu-ginuta&quot; (handed down in the Fujiue school, but its composer is not known) are famous Honkyoku for Kokyu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, &quot;Semi no uta (a song of cicadas) (composed by Kengyo YOSHIZAWA, and handed down in the Nagoya line)&quot; and &quot;Okayasu-ginuta&quot; (handed down in the Fujiue school, but its composer is not known) are famous Honkyoku for Kokyu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, &quot;Semi no uta&quot; (a song of cicadas) (composed by Kengyo YOSHIZAWA, and handed down in the Nagoya line) and &quot;Okayasu-ginuta&quot; (handed down in the Fujiue school, but its composer is unknown) are famous Honkyoku of Kokyu.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="109">
<j>特に藤植流には多くの本曲が伝えられており、また幕末に断絶してしまった政島流には更に多くの本曲があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In particular, many pieces of Honkyoku have been handed down for generations in the Fujiue line, and even more pieces of Honkyoku existed in the Masajima school that became extinct towards the end of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In particular, many pieces of Honkyoku have been handed down for generations in the Fujiue line, and even more pieces of Honkyoku existed in the Masajima school that became died out towards the end of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>grammar, wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In particular, many pieces of Honkyoku have been handed down for generations in the Fujiue school, and even more pieces of Honkyoku existed in the Masajima school that became extinct towards the end of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>外曲は箏曲、地歌曲を指し、きわめて多くの曲がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gaikyoku indicates music for So and music for Jiuta songs, and many pieces of Gaikyoku exist.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gaikyoku indicates music for So and music for Jiuta songs, and many pieces of Gaikyoku exist.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gaikyoku indicates music for So and music for Jiuta songs, and a large number of pieces of Gaikyoku exist.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>ただし胡弓演奏家はほとんど必ず地歌、箏曲演奏家でもあるので、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, almost all of the Kokyu players are also players for Jiuta and so players.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, almost all of the Kokyu players are also players for Jiuta and so players.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, almost all of the Kokyu players are also the players of Jiuta and So players.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>本曲でも伴奏として箏や三味線が入ったり、また地歌や箏曲に取り入れられたりしている曲もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, some pieces of Honkyoku are played accompanied by So or Shamisen, or are taken into music for Jiuta songs or for So.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, some pieces of Honkyoku are played accompanied by So or Shamisen, or are taken into music for Jiuta songs or for So.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, some pieces of Honkyoku are accompanied by So or Shamisen, or are taken into music for Jiuta songs or for So.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="113">
<j>しかしながら、このような分け方は尺八ほど厳密ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the classification of the music into Honkyoku and Gaikyoku is not so strict as for Shakuhachi bamboo flutes.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the classification of the music into Honkyoku and Gaikyoku is not so strict as for Shakuhachi bamboo flutes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the classification of the music into Honkyoku and Gaikyoku is not so strict as that for Shakuhachi bamboo flutes music.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="114">
<j>また宮城道雄以降、今に至るまで胡弓のための新作曲も多くはないながら作られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even after Michio MIYAGI, new pieces of music for Kokyu have been composed, although the number is not many.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even after Michio MIYAGI, new pieces of music for Kokyu have been composed, although the number is not many.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even after Michio MIYAGI, new pieces of music for Kokyu have been composed, although they are not so many.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>義太夫節における胡弓</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kokyu in Gidayu-bushi (musical narrative of the puppet theatre)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokyu in Gidayu-bushi (musical narrative of the puppet theatre)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kokyu in Gidayu-bushi (a style of reciting the dramatic narrative of the puppet theatre)</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="115">
<j>義太夫節は上方で盛んだったためか、三曲の影響を色濃く受けている側面があり、そのひとつが胡弓を使う演奏といえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Having been popular in Osaka, Gidayu-bushi is significantly affected by Sangyoku, and such an example is use of Kokyu in the performance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Having been popular in Osaka, Gidayu-bushi is significantly affected by Sangyoku, and such an example is use of Kokyu in the performance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Having been popular in Osaka, Gidayu-bushi is significantly affected by Sangyoku, and such an example is the use of Kokyu in the performance.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="116">
<j>特に『壇浦兜軍記』の「阿古屋琴責の段」では、頼朝を仇と狙い姿を消した、悪七兵衛景清の馴染みの傾城、阿古屋が景清の行方を詮議され、琴（箏）、三味線 (地歌三味線)、胡弓を見事に弾いて、その旋律に迷いがないことから、景清の行方を知っているのではないかという疑いを晴らすという場面で、胡弓が用いられることが有名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In particular, it is well known that Kokyu is played in the following scene: In &apos;the act of &apos;Akoya-kotozeme&apos; of &quot;Dannoura kabuto gunki&quot; (The War Chronicles at Dannoura), Akoya, a woman of peerless beauty intimate with Aku (bad) Shichibei Kagekiyo, who has disappeared seeking for Yoritomo, his enemy, is questioned severely about the whereabouts of Kagekiyo but the doubt is cleared because she splendidly played Koto (So), Shamisen (Shamisen for Jiuta songs) and Kokyu, with no confusion in the melodies she played.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In particular, it is well known that Kokyu is played in the following scene: In &apos;the act of &apos;Akoya-kotozeme&apos; of &quot;Dannoura kabuto gunki&quot; (The War Chronicles at Dannoura), Akoya, a woman of peerless beauty intimate with Aku (bad) Shichibei Kagekiyo, who has disappeared seeking for Yoritomo, his enemy, is questioned severely about the whereabouts of Kagekiyo, but the doubt is cleared because she splendidly played the Koto (So), the Shamisen (Shamisen for Jiuta songs) and the Kokyu, with no confusion in the melodies she played.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In particular, it is well known that Kokyu is played in the following scene: In &apos;the act of &apos;Akoya-kotozeme&apos; of &quot;Dannoura kabuto gunki&quot; (The War Chronicles at Dannoura), Akoya, a woman of peerless beauty intimate with Aku Shichibei Kagekiyo (who has disappeared seeking for his enemy Yoritomo) is questioned severely about the whereabouts of Kagekiyo, and the doubt is cleared because she splendidly played the Koto (So), the Shamisen (Shamisen for Jiuta songs) and the Kokyu, with no confusion in the melodies she played.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="117">
<j>この3つの楽器を用いている点も三曲の影響といえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fact that the three instruments are used here indicates an influence of Sangyoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fact that the three instruments are used here indicates an influence of Sangyoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fact that the three instruments are used here proves an influence of Sangyoku.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="118">
<j>ちなみに、この演目が歌舞伎で上演される場合は、阿古屋を演ずる女形が3つの楽器を実際に演奏することが通例となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By the way, when this number is played in Kabuki, it is customary that the male actor playing the female role of Akoya plays the three instruments actually.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By the way, when this number is played in Kabuki, it is customary that the male actor playing the female role of Akoya actually plays the three instruments.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Incidentally, when this program is played in Kabuki, it is customary that the male actor playing the female role of Akoya actually plays the three instruments.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="119">
<j>そのほかの曲でも『生写朝顔話』など義太夫節では胡弓が用いられる曲は少なくない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kokyu is also played in not a few other pieces of music for Gidayu-bushi, for example, in Shoutsushi-Asagao-banashi (Morning Glory Diary).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokyu is also played in not a few other pieces of music for Gidayu-bushi, for example, in Shoutsushi-Asagao-banashi (Morning Glory Diary).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kokyu is also played in not a few other pieces of music for Gidayu-bushi such as in &quot;Shoutsushi-Asagao-banashi&quot; (Morning Glory Diary).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>民謡における胡弓</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kokyu in folk songs</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokyu in folk songs</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kokyu in folk songs</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="120">
<j>民謡における胡弓としては富山県富山市八尾地区の風の盆で演奏される「越中おわら節」などで使用されるのが有名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Concerning Kokyu in folk songs, it is famous that Kokyu is used in &quot;Etchu Owara bushi (a song for Japanese folk dance in Etchu (Present Toyama Prefecture)) played in &quot;Kaze-no Bon&quot; (literally, wind Bon: Bon is a Buddhist festival for dead ancestors, held in summer) in the Yao area of Toyama City, Toyama Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Concerning Kokyu in folk songs, it is well known that Kokyu is used in &quot;Etchu Owara bushi (a song for Japanese folk dance in Etchu - present day Toyama Prefecture) played in &quot;Kaze-no Bon&quot; (literally, wind Bon: Bon is a Buddhist festival for dead ancestors, held in summer) in the Yao area of Toyama City, Toyama Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Concerning Kokyu in ballad, it is well known that Kokyu is used in &apos;Etchu Owara bushi&apos; (a song for Japanese folk dance in Etchu - present day Toyama Prefecture) played in &quot;Kaze-no Bon&quot; (literally, wind Bon: Bon is a Buddhist festival for dead ancestors, held in summer) in the Yao area of Toyama City, Toyama Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="121">
<j>ただし胡弓が加わるようになったのは明治以降である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it is in the Meiji period or later that Kokyu became to be added to the performance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is during the Meiji period or later that Kokyu was added to the performance.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it was during the Meiji period or later that Kokyu was added to the performance.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="122">
<j>おわら用とされている胡弓には近年、通常のものよりもやや棹が長く作られたものがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some of Kokyu specialized for Owara folk songs have recently been provided with a neck part slightly longer than that of ordinary Kokyu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some Kokyu specialized for Owara folk songs have recently been provided with a neck part slightly longer than that of ordinary Kokyu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some Kokyu specialized for Owara ballad have recently been provided with a neck slightly longer than that of standard Kokyu.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="123">
<j>これは野外での演奏のため、弦長を大きくして張力を高め、音量の増大をはかったものと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered that this is because these songs are played outdoors, making it necessary to make the lengths of the strings longer to increase the volume of the generated sounds.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered that this is because these songs are played outdoors, making it necessary to make the lengths of the strings longer to increase the volume of the generated sounds.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered that as these songs were played outdoors, it was necessary to make the lengths of the strings longer to increase the volume of the sounds.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="124">
<j>弓は古典系のものよりもかなり短い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bow is considerably shorter than those of classical Kokyu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bow is considerably shorter than those of classical Kokyu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bow is considerably shorter than those of classical Kokyu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="125">
<j>ただし湾曲部より先はむしろ長めにしてあり、つまり手元から先に向けての棹と毛の離角が大きい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the portion up from the bent part is made longer than the other portion from the bent part, which is nearer to the playing hand, and therefore, the angle between the hair and the wood part of the bow is larger at the portion nearer to the playing hand.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the portion up from the bent part is made longer than the other portion from the bent part, which is nearer to the playing hand, and therefore, the angle between the hair and the wood part of the bow is larger at the portion nearer to the playing hand.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the portion from the bend is made longer than the other portion from the bend, which is nearer to the playing hand, and therefore, the angle between the hair and the wood of the bow is larger at the portion nearer to the playing hand.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="126">
<j>毛量は少なく弛みを持たせずに張られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The amount of hair is small, and the hair is attached to the bow without being slackened</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The amount of hair is less, and the hair is attached to the bow without being slackened.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The amount of hair is less, and the hair is attached to the bow without being loosened.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="127">
<j>その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="128">
<j>その他、胡弓が使われる音楽として次のものがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kokyu is also used in the following music.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokyu is also used in the following music.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kokyu is also used in the following types of music:</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="129">
<j>歌舞伎の下座音楽として、哀切な場面に胡弓が使われることがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Geza music (music supporting kabuki performances effectively) in Kabuki, Kokyu is sometimes used in pathetic scenes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Geza music (music supporting kabuki performances effectively) in Kabuki, Kokyu is sometimes used in pathetic scenes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Geza music (music supporting kabuki performances effectively) in Kabuki, Kokyu is sometimes used in moving scenes.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="130">
<j>地方の人形芝居や祭りの囃子など民俗芸能に使われることもあり、かつて地方によっては農民の冬の副業として、また瞽女（ごぜ）によって、門付として演奏されることもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kokyu is sometimes used in traditional local entertainments, such as puppet shows and hayashi (music performed with traditional Japanese instruments for making the atmosphere cheerful) in festivals, and in some areas, Kokyu was played in the past by farmers as one of their side jobs or by Goze (blind female musicians) as Kadotsuke (performance in front of the gate of houses).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokyu is sometimes used in traditional local entertainments, such as puppet shows and hayashi (music performed with traditional Japanese instruments for making the atmosphere cheerful) in festivals, and in some areas, Kokyu was played in the past by farmers as one of their side jobs or by Goze (blind female musicians) as Kadotsuke (performance in front of the gate of houses).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kokyu is sometimes used in traditional local attractions, such as puppet shows and hayashi (music performed with traditional Japanese instruments for making the atmosphere cheerful) in festivals, and in some areas, Kokyu was played in the past by farmers as one of their side jobs or by Goze (blind female musicians) as Kadotsuke (performance in front of the gate of houses).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="131">
<j>天理教及びその傍系宗教において、儀礼音楽の中で他の楽器と共に演奏される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Tenrikyo and its related religions, Kokyu is played together with other instruments in its ceremonial music.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Tenrikyo and its related religions, Kokyu is played together with other instruments in its ceremonial music.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Tenrikyo and its related sects, Kokyu is played together with other instruments in its ceremonial music.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="132">
<j>この場合、「初瀬琴」と呼ばれる弓奏のツィター属弦楽器が使われたことがあるが、現在ではほとんど使用されず、もっぱら胡弓を使用するようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this case, a zither-related stringed instrument called Hatsuse goto is sometimes used, but nowadays, Hatsuse is seldom used and it seems that Kokyu is mostly used instead.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this case, a zither-related stringed instrument called Hatsuse goto is sometimes used, but nowadays, Hatsuse is seldom used and it seems that Kokyu is mostly used instead.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this case, a zither-family stringed instrument called Hatsuse goto is sometimes used, but nowadays, Hatsuse is seldom used and it seems that Kokyu is mostly used instead.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>調弦</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tuning the strings</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tuning the strings</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tuning methods of Kokyu</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="133">
<j>三味線を小型にしたような形を持つ胡弓は、三味線と同様の三味線調弦が可能である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kokyu is made in the same shape as that of Shamisen but smaller in size, and its tuning can be made in the same way as that of Shamisen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokyu is made in the same shape as that of Shamisen, but smaller in size, and tuning can be made in the same way as that of Shamisen.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kokyu is made in the same shape as that of the Shamisen, but smaller in size, and the tuning can be made in the same way as that of the Shamisen.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="134">
<j>主なものとして、本調子、二上がり、三下がりがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are three major tuning methods of Hon-choshi (the basic tuning method), Ni-agari (the second string is tuned slightly differently from that for Hon-shoshi) and San-sagari (the third string is tuned slightly differently from that for Hon-shoshi).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are three major tuning methods of Hon-choshi (the basic tuning method), Ni-agari (the second string is tuned slightly differently from that for Hon-shoshi) and San-sagari (the third string is tuned slightly differently from that for Hon-shoshi).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are three major tuning methods of Hon-choshi (the basic tuning method), Ni-agari (the second string is tuned slightly differently from that for the Hon-shoshi) and San-sagari (the third string is tuned slightly differently from that for the Hon-shoshi).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="135">
<j>胡弓楽、地歌、箏曲の胡弓は圧倒的に三下がりが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kokyu for Kokyu-gaku, for Jiuta songs and for So music uses San-sagari dominantly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokyu for Kokyu-gaku, for Jiuta songs and for So music uses San-sagari dominantly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kokyu for Kokyu-gaku, for Jiuta songs and for So music uses San-sagari tuning dominantly.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="136">
<j>義太夫節や民謡では二上がりの調弦を用いる曲も少なくない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ni-agari tuning is used for not a few pieces of music for Gidayu-bushi and for folk music.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ni-agari tuning is used for many pieces of music, for Gidayu-bushi, and for folk music.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ni-agari tuning is used for many pieces of music, for Gidayu-bushi, and for ballads.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 AlleborgoBot(id:119729), MikeAz800o(id:58193), 十勝産(id:111739), TS(id:481), ＲＪＡＮＫＡ(id:118019), Hiroshi777(id:81098), 赤井彗星(id:18381), プリン寿司(id:199038), Point136(id:211299), Yas(id:739), NDR(id:5500), FlaBot(id:30804), Hermes(id:21387), Sampo(id:1041), Ptbotgourou(id:229657), Louperibot(id:128971), 詠狸庵(id:41048), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>