<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>飛鳥鍋</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Asukanabe (hodgepodge from Asuka)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Asukanabe (hodgepodge from Asuka)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Asukanabe (hodgepodge from Asuka)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>飛鳥鍋（あすかなべ）とは奈良地方の郷土料理。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Asukanabe is one of the local dishes of Nara region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Asukanabe is one of the local dishes of Nara region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Asukanabe is one of the local dishes of Nara region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>鶏ガラの出汁とともに、牛乳を加え、まろやかさとコクを加えるもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Milk is combined with chicken soup to add smoothness and richness.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Milk is combined with chicken soup to add smoothness and richness.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Milk is combined with chicken soup to add smoothness and richness.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>具は普通の鍋料理と同じ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its ingredients are the same as that of ordinary pot dishes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its ingredients are the same as that of ordinary pot dishes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its ingredients are the same as that of ordinary pot dishes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>好みでネギやショウガを加えたり、片栗粉を水で溶かして加えて、汁に少しとろみを加えて食べることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If desired, green onions and ginger may be added, and there are times when it is eaten by slightly thickening the soup with starch mixed with water.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sometimes people have it with green onions and ginger, or slightly thickening the soup with starch mixed with water according to their taste.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sometimes people have it with green onions and ginger, or slightly thickening the soup with starch mixed with water according to their taste.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>飛鳥時代に唐から来た僧侶が、寒さをしのぐためにヤギの乳で鍋料理を作ったのが始まりとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Asukanabe is said to have originated when a monk that came to Japan from Tang during the Asuka era, made pot dish with a goat&apos;s milk in order to save himself from the cold.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Asukanabe is said to have been originated from a priest who came to Japan from Tang (China) in the Asuka period made a pot dish with goat milk to prevent himself from the cold weather.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Asukanabe is said to have been originated in the Asuka period when a priest from Tang (China) made a pot dish with goat milk to protect himself against the cold.</e>
<cmt>originated from a priest who came to Japan from Tang (China) in the Asuka period made a pot dish with goat milk→originated in the Asuka period when a priest from Tang (China) made a pot dish with goat milk</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 パの字(id:34188), Egana(id:54003), 1029man(id:93235), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>