<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>梅干し</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Umeboshi (pickled and sun-dried ume (Japanese apricots))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Umeboshi (pickled and sun-dried ume (Japanese apricots))</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Umeboshi</e>
<cmt>タイトルのため、補足を削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>梅干し（うめぼし）とは、ウメの果実を塩漬けした後に日干しにした塩漬け。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An &quot;umeboshi&quot; is a shiozuke (a salted food), which is dried in the sun after being preserved in salt.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An &quot;umeboshi&quot; is a shiozuke (a salted food), which is dried in the sun after being preserved in salt.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An &quot;umeboshi&quot; is a shiozuke (a salted food) of ume (Japanese apricots), which is dried in the sun after being preserved in salt.</e>
<cmt>ウメ　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>漬物のひとつ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a kind of tsukemono (pickles).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It&apos;s a kind of tsukemono (pickle).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It&apos;s a kind of tsukemono (pickle).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>「日の丸弁当」や「おにぎり」など、日本人にとって身近な食材である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a familiar ingredient in a &apos;hinomaru bento&apos; (a box lunch with a red umeboshi in the center of the white rice), &apos;onigiri&apos; (rice balls), and so forth for Japanese people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For the Japanese people, it&apos;s a familiar ingredient in a &apos;hinomaru bento&apos; (a box lunch with a red umeboshi in the center of the white rice), &apos;onigiri (rice balls)&apos; and so forth.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For the Japanese people, it&apos;s a familiar ingredient in a &apos;hinomaru bento&apos; (a box lunch with a red umeboshi in the center of the white rice), &apos;onigiri&apos; (rice balls) and so forth.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションマークを括弧の前に移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>なお、塩漬けのみで日干していないものは、「梅漬け」という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, an ume that is salted but is not sun-dried is called an &apos;umezuke&apos; (a pickled ume).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, an ume that is salted but isn&apos;t sun-dried is called an &apos;umezuke (pickled ume).&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, an ume that is salted but isn&apos;t sun-dried is called an &apos;umezuke&apos; (pickled ume).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションマークを括弧の前に移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>梅酒が熟していない青梅を用いるのに対し、梅干しは6月頃の熟した果実を用いる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While umeshu (ume liquor) is prepared from aoume (unripe ume), umeboshi are made with fruits picked ripe around June.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While umeshu (ume liquor) is prepared from aoume (unripe ume), umeboshi are made with fruits picked ripe in or around June.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While umeshu (ume liquor) is prepared from aoume (unripe ume), umeboshi are made with fruits picked ripe in or around June.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>塩漬けにした後3日ほど日干し（これを「土用干し」という）にする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ume are dried in the sun for about three days after being pickled in salt (this is called &apos;doyo-boshi&apos; (summer airing)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ume are dried in the sun for about three days after being pickled in salt (this is called &apos;doyo-boshi&apos; (summer airing)).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ume are dried in the sun for about three days after being pickled in salt (this is called &apos;doyo-boshi&apos; ((summer airing)).</e>
<cmt>括弧を一部変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>この状態のものを白干しと呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Umeboshi in this condition are called shiroboshi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Umeboshi in this condition are called shiroboshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Umeboshi in this condition are called shiroboshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>保存性に優れているが、塩分が多い（塩分20%前後）ためとても塩辛い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They have a very long shelf life, but they are very salty because of a high salt content (a salinity of about 20%).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They have a very long shelf life but a high salt content (with salinity of about 20%).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They have a very long shelf life but a high salt content (with salinity of about 20%), which makes them very salty.</e>
<cmt>翻訳を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>近年市販の一般的な梅干しでは、白干しのものを水につけ、塩分を抑えて味付けを施した調味漬けの梅干しが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many generic umeboshi that have been put on the market in recent years are umeboshi that are pickled in a sodium-controlled seasoning after being soaked in water as shiroboshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many generic umeboshi that have been put on the market in recent years are umeboshi that are pickled in a sodium-controlled seasoning after being soaked in water as shiroboshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many generic umeboshi that have been put on the market in recent years are umeboshi that are pickled in a sodium-controlled seasoning after being soaked in water as shiroboshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>調味漬けの梅干しには、シソ（赤じそ）の葉とともに漬けて赤く染め風味をつけたしそ梅、コンブとともにつけて昆布の味をつけた昆布梅、鰹節を加えて調味した鰹梅、蜂蜜を加えて甘くしたはちみつ梅などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seasoned umeboshi include shiso-ume that are dyed red and flavored by being pickled with the leaves of shiso (perilla) (akajiso (red perilla)), konbu-ume that are given the flavor of konbu (kelp) by being preserved with konbu, katsuo-ume that are seasoned with katsuobushi (dried bonito), and hachimitu-ume that are sweetened with hachimitsu (honey).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seasoned umeboshi include shiso-ume, which are dyed red and flavored by being pickled with the leaves of shiso (perilla) (akajiso (red perilla)); konbu-ume, which are given the flavor of konbu (kelp) by being preserved with konbu; katsuo-ume, which are seasoned with katsuobushi (dried bonito); and hachimitsu-ume, which are sweetened with hachimitsu (honey).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seasoned umeboshi include shiso-ume, which are dyed red and flavored by being pickled with the leaves of shiso (perilla) (akajiso (red perilla)); konbu-ume, which are given the flavor of konbu (kelp) by being preserved with konbu; katsuo-ume, which are seasoned with katsuobushi (dried bonito); and hachimitsu-ume, which are sweetened with hachimitsu (honey).</e>
<cmt>括弧を一部変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>このような梅干は「調味梅干」と表記される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These types of umeboshi are labeled &apos;chomi-umeboshi&apos; (seasoned umeboshi).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These types of umeboshi are labeled as &apos;chomi-umeboshi (seasoned umeboshi).&apos;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These types of umeboshi are labeled as &apos;chomi-umeboshi&apos; (seasoned umeboshi).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションマークを括弧の前に移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>なお、減塩梅干や調味梅干は保存性が大きく劣り、防腐効果がかなり低い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By comparison, genen-umeboshi (low-salt umeboshi) and chomi-umeboshi have a much shorter shelf life and a very weak antiseptic effect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By comparison, genen-umeboshi (low-salt umeboshi) and chomi-umeboshi have a much shorter shelf life and a very weak antiseptic effect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By comparison, genen-umeboshi (low-salt umeboshi) and chomi-umeboshi have a much shorter shelf life and a very weak antiseptic effect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>そのため保存料を使用する場合が増えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, the use of preservatives is increasing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, the use of preservatives is increasing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, the use of preservatives is increasing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="14">
<j>すべての梅干しに共通した大きな特徴として、非常に酸味が強い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The prominent characteristic common to all types of umeboshi is a very strong acid taste.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The prominent characteristic common to all types of umeboshi is a strongly acidic taste.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The prominent characteristic common to all types of umeboshi is a strongly acidic taste.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>この酸味はレモンなどの柑橘類に多く含まれるクエン酸に由来する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This acidity comes from the citric acid which is contained in citrus like lemons in large quantities</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This acidity comes from citric acid, which is found in large quantities in citrus fruits such as lemons.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This acidity comes from citric acid, which is found in large quantities in citrus fruits such as lemons.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>そのため梅干しは健康食品としても有名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this reason, umeboshi are also famous as health foods.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For that reason, umeboshi are also renowned as health foods.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For that reason, umeboshi are also renowned as health foods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="17">
<j>特に紀伊国（和歌山県）の梅干しは有名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Umeboshi from Ki no kuni (Wakayama Prefecture) are particularly well-known.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Umeboshi from Ki no kuni (Wakayama Prefecture) are particularly well known.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Umeboshi from Ki no kuni (Wakayama Prefecture) are particularly well known.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>みなべ町や田辺市は一大生産地で、南高梅と呼ばれる品種のウメを用いた梅干しが最高級品とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Minabe Town and Tanabe City are major production areas, and umeboshi made with a kind of ume called nankobai are considered the finest product.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Minabe Town and Tanabe City are major production areas, and umeboshi made with a kind of ume called nankobai is considered to be the finest product.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Minabe Town and Tanabe City are major production areas, and umeboshi made with a kind of ume called nankobai is considered to be the finest product.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>また、和歌山県推薦優良土産品に指定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are also designated excellent gift and souvenir items officially endorsed by Wakayama Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are also considered to be excellent gifts and are souvenir items officially endorsed by Wakayama Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are also considered to be excellent gifts and are souvenir items officially endorsed by Wakayama Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="20">
<j>俳句では夏の季語である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Umeboshi&quot; is a summer kigo (season word) in haiku (a Japanese poem of seventeen syllables in five-seven-five syllabic form).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Umeboshi&quot; is a summer kigo (a seasonal term) in haiku (a Japanese poem of seventeen syllables in the sequential form of five, seven and five syllables).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Umeboshi&quot; is a summer kigo (a seasonal term) in haiku (a Japanese poem of seventeen syllables in the sequential form of five, seven and five syllables).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="21">
<j>加工食品として販売されている梅干しは、昔ながらの梅干しは「梅干」、水に晒しハチミツ漬などにしてさらに調味されたものは「調味梅干」と表示するようJAS法(品質表示基準制度の名称)に義務づけられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The JAS System under the Law Concerning Standardization and Proper Labeling of Agricultural and Forestry Products (the name of the quality labeling system) makes it an obligation that the umeboshi sold as processed foods are labeled &apos;umeboshi&apos; when they are old fashioned and &apos;chomi-umeboshi&apos; when they are seasoned by being soaked in water and pickled in hachimitsu, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The JAS System under the Law Concerning Standardization and Proper Labeling of Agricultural and Forestry Products (the name of the quality labeling system) makes it obligatory that the umeboshi sold as processed foods are labeled &apos;umeboshi&apos; when they&apos;re old fashioned and &apos;chomi-umeboshi&apos; when they&apos;re seasoned by being soaked in water and pickled in hachimitsu, etc.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The JAS System under the Law Concerning Standardization and Proper Labeling of Agricultural and Forestry Products (the name of the quality labeling system) makes it obligatory that the umeboshi sold as processed foods are labeled &apos;umeboshi&apos; when they&apos;re old fashioned and &apos;chomi-umeboshi&apos; when they&apos;re seasoned by being soaked in water and pickled in hachimitsu, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>五訂日本食品標準成分表によれば、塩分は梅干が22.1％、調味梅干が7.6%となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the fifth edition of the Japanese Standard Tables of Food Composition, the salt content of umeboshi is 22.1% and that of chomi-umeboshi is 7.6%.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the fifth edition of the Japanese Standard Tables of Food Composition, the salt content of umeboshi is 22.1% and that of chomi-umeboshi is 7.6%.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the fifth edition of the Japanese Standard Tables of Food Composition, the salt content of umeboshi is 22.1% and that of chomi-umeboshi is 7.6%.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>その味の差やその保存能力の差が際立っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The differences in the taste and storage capability of the two types of umeboshi are striking.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The differences in the taste and storage capability of the two types of umeboshi are striking.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The differences in the taste and storage capability of the two types of umeboshi are striking.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>甘く調味された調味梅干は比較的新しく(戦後生まれである)、お年寄りと若者とで食べ慣れた梅干しが異なるので、梅干の好みに差が広がっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The sweetened chomi-umeboshi are relatively new (born after the war), and a difference in preferred umeboshi is growing between the elderly and the young who are used to eating different kinds of umeboshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sweetened chomi-umeboshi are relatively new (having emerged after the war), and a difference in preferred umeboshi is growing between the elderly and the young, who are used to eating different kinds of umeboshi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sweetened chomi-umeboshi are relatively new (having emerged after the war), and a difference in preferred umeboshi is growing between the elderly and the young, who are used to eating different kinds of umeboshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="25">
<j>白飯の真ん中に梅干しをのせただけの弁当を、日本の国旗（日章旗）に見立てて日の丸弁当と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A box lunch that has only an umeboshi in the center of the white rice is called a hinomaru bento comparing it to the Japanese flag (the Rising Sun flag).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A box lunch that has only an umeboshi in the center of the white rice is called a hinomaru bento, thus being compared to the Japanese flag (the Rising Sun).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A box lunch that has only an umeboshi in the center of the white rice is called a hinomaru bento, thus being compared to the Japanese flag (the Rising Sun).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="26">
<j>海外旅行に出かける邦人の中には、外国の畜肉や乳製品の多い料理に飽きた時や気分不快の際に、口直しや気分転換を目的として梅干しを持参する旅行者が多いと云われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that many Japanese people who travel abroad take umeboshi to cleanse their palates or for a change in case they get tired of foreign foods containing a lot of livestock meat and dairy products or in case they feel ill.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It&apos;s said that many Japanese people who travel abroad take umeboshi to cleanse their palates or for a change in case they get tired of foreign foods containing large amounts of livestock meat and dairy products, or in the event they feel ill.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It&apos;s said that many Japanese people who travel abroad take umeboshi to cleanse their palates or for a change in case they get tired of foreign foods containing large amounts of livestock meat and dairy products, or in the event they feel ill.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="27">
<j>梅干しの表面はしわになっているので、しわが多いお婆さんの事を俗に「梅干婆さん」という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because the surface of umeboshi is crumpled, wrinkly old ladies are commonly called &apos;umeboshi-basan&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because the surface of umeboshi is crumpled, wrinkly old ladies are commonly called &apos;umeboshi-basan.&apos;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because the surface of umeboshi is crumpled, wrinkly old ladies are commonly called &apos;umeboshi-basan.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="28">
<j>アルミに酸化皮膜をほどこしたアルマイトの弁当箱では、毎日同じ場所に梅干しを乗せた場合、酸によって蓋が溶けることがあったという体験をした人は多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are many people who experienced that the lid of the lunch box made of anodized aluminum, which is aluminum covered with an oxidized skin, had melted because of the acid when umeboshi were placed in the same spot everyday.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many people have had the experience whereby the lid of the lunch box made of anodized aluminum, which is aluminum covered with an oxidized skin, had melted because of the acid when umeboshi were placed in the same spot every day.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many people have had the experience whereby the lid of the lunch box made of anodized aluminum, which is aluminum covered with an oxidized skin, had melted because of the acid when umeboshi were placed in the same spot every day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>しかしこれは終戦直後の技術が劣っていたこと、アルミの純度が低かったためと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it is thought that this happened because the technology was inferior and the purity of the aluminum was low immediately after the end of the war.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, this is thought to have occurred because the technology available after the end of the war was inferior and the purity of the aluminum was low.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, this is thought to have occurred because the technology available after the end of the war was inferior and the purity of the aluminum was low.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="30">
<j>スーパーマーケットなどで市販されている梅干しは実質酢で漬けただけの酢漬けが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many umeboshi marketed in supermarkets and other stores are suzuke (pickles in vinegar) that are virtually only pickled in vinegar.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many umeboshi sold in supermarkets and other outlets are suzuke (pickles in vinegar), in which vinegar is virtually the sole pickling ingredient.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many umeboshi sold in supermarkets and other outlets are suzuke (pickles in vinegar), in which vinegar is virtually the sole pickling ingredient.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>これは、もちろん防腐効果を持たない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These, of course, do not have an antiseptic effect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These, of course, do not have an antiseptic effect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These, of course, do not have an antiseptic effect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>また、原材料名に保存料が含まれていたり、防腐剤が同封されていたり、賞味期限が設定されているようなものは自身が腐る可能性を持っているため、弁当などには向かない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those that have a preservative as one of the ingredients, come with a preservative in the same package, or have an expiration date are also unfit for a box lunch, etc. because they themselves have the possibility of going bad.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those that have a preservative as one of the ingredients, come with a preservative in the same package or have an expiration date are also unfit for a box lunch, etc., because they&apos;re at the risk of spoiling.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those that have a preservative as one of the ingredients, come with a preservative in the same package or have an expiration date are also unfit for a box lunch, etc., because they&apos;re at the risk of spoiling.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="33">
<j>伝統的製法によって作られた梅干は土蔵などの保管に適した環境では腐らず、100年前に作られたものでも食べられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Umeboshi made according to the traditional method do not rot in an environment suitable for storage like a dozo (an earthen storehouse), and even those made one hundred years ago can be eaten.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Umeboshi made according to the traditional method don&apos;t rot in an environment suitable for storage such as a dozo (an earthen storehouse), and even those made 100 years ago can be eaten.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Umeboshi made according to the traditional method don&apos;t rot in an environment suitable for storage such as a dozo (an earthen storehouse), and even those made 100 years ago can be eaten.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>但し、希に黒色に腐ることがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, on rare occasions, they spoil and turn black.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, on rare occasions they spoil and blacken.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, on rare occasions they spoil and blacken.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>この為、地方によっては普段腐ることがない梅干しが腐るため、何らかの異変が起きると言う迷信が伝えられている所もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of this, a superstition has been told in some regions that something unusual will happen when umeboshi, which usually do not go bad, go rotten.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequently, in some regions the superstition has emerged that something unusual will happen when umeboshi, which usually don&apos;t go bad, begin to rot.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently, in some regions the superstition has emerged that something unusual will happen when umeboshi, which usually don&apos;t go bad, begin to rot.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="36">
<j>現存最古のものでは、奈良県の中家に伝わる梅干しで、天正4年（1576年）に漬け込まれたものが状態良好に保存されている(補充が利かないため試食はしていないという）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The oldest extant umeboshi are those that have been handed down in the Naka family in Nara Prefecture, and those pickled in 1576 are kept in good condition (it is reported that they have not been sampled because they cannot be replenished).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The oldest extant umeboshi have been handed down in the Naka family in Nara Prefecture, and those pickled in 1576 are still in good condition (it is reported that they have not been sampled because they can&apos;t be replenished).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The oldest extant umeboshi have been handed down in the Naka family in Nara Prefecture, and those pickled in 1576 are still in good condition (it is reported that they have not been sampled because they can&apos;t be replenished).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>また、同家に同じく伝わる江戸時代の安永年間に漬けられた梅干しを試食したところ、全く問題なく食べられたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also said that when tasted the umeboshi pickled in the Anei period that have been passed down in the same family could be eaten without any problems.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It&apos;s also said that when tasted the umeboshi pickled in the Anei period, which have been passed down in the same family, could be eaten without a problem.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It&apos;s also said that when tasted the umeboshi pickled in the Anei eras (1764 - 1780) during the Edo period, which have been passed down in the same family, could be eaten without a problem.</e>
<cmt>安永年間　に補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="38">
<j>地方によって梅ではなく近隣種である杏を使用する場合がある（青森、岩手の八助梅など）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some regions use an neighboring species, anzu (apricots), instead of ume (such as hachisuke-ume of Aomori Prefecture and Iwate Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some regions use a neighboring species, anzu (apricots), instead of ume (such as the hachisuke-ume of Aomori Prefecture and Iwate Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some regions use a neighboring species, anzu (apricots), instead of ume (such as the hachisuke-ume of Aomori Prefecture and Iwate Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>効用</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Effects</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Effects</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Effects</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="39">
<j>梅干には次のような効能があると言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that umeboshi have the following effects.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It&apos;s said that umeboshi have the following effects:</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It&apos;s said that umeboshi have the following effects:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="40">
<j>唾液の分泌を促す</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They stimulate the secretion of saliva.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They stimulate the secretion of saliva.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They stimulate the secretion of saliva.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="41">
<j>クエン酸の酸味が唾液の分泌を促して消化吸収を良くするとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The acid taste of the citric acid is believed to improve digestion and absorption by facilitating the secretion of saliva.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The acid taste of the citric acid is believed to improve digestion and absorption by facilitating the secretion of saliva.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The acid taste of the citric acid is believed to improve digestion and absorption by facilitating the secretion of saliva.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>但し梅干を見ただけで唾液が分泌されるのは、梅干を実際に食べてみて酸味を感じた経験を有することに由来するのであって、梅干を食べたことがない人が梅干を見ても唾液の分泌を促すことはない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the secretion of saliva at the mere sight of umeboshi comes from the experience of feeling an acid taste after actually eating an umeboshi, and the sight of umeboshi in the case of an individual who has never eaten an umeboshi does not induce the secretion of saliva (it occurs only when an umeboshi is actually put into the mouth and an acid taste is experienced.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the secretion of saliva at the mere sight of umeboshi comes from the experience of feeling an acid taste after eating an umeboshi, and the sight of umeboshi in the case of an individual who has never eaten an umeboshi does not induce the secretion of saliva (it occurs only when an umeboshi is actually placed in the mouth and an acid taste is experienced.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the secretion of saliva at the mere sight of umeboshi comes from the experience of feeling an acid taste after eating an umeboshi, and the sight of umeboshi in the case of an individual who has never eaten an umeboshi does not induce the secretion of saliva.</e>
<cmt>セルの文章を、括弧の前までの文のみとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>（実際に口に入れて酸味を感じて初めて唾液が分泌される。特に梅干を食すことが少ない外国人は唾液が分泌されることは無い。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Particularly, foreigners who rarely eat umeboshi do not produce saliva.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Particularly, foreigners who rarely eat umeboshi don&apos;t experience an increase in saliva.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(It occurs only when an umeboshi is actually placed in the mouth and an acid taste is experienced; particularly, foreigners who rarely eat umeboshi don&apos;t experience an increase in saliva.)</e>
<cmt>括弧の文章をこちらに移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="44">
<j>疲労回復などの薬効</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Medicinal effects like fatigue recovery</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Medicinal effects such as recovery from fatigue</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Medicinal effects such as recovery from fatigue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="45">
<j>クエン酸の効能のほか、各種薬効があるとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Aside from the effect of the citric acid, umeboshi are believed to have various medicinal effects.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Aside from the effect of the citric acid, umeboshi are believed to have various medicinal effects.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Aside from the effect of the citric acid, umeboshi are believed to have various medicinal effects.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>そのために、病人食は粥と梅干が定番である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hence, kayu (rice gruel) and umeboshi are regular diets for patients.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hence, kayu (rice gruel) and umeboshi are regular parts of the diet for patients.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hence, kayu (rice gruel) and umeboshi are regular parts of the diet for patients.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="47">
<j>解熱</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Antipyretic effect</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Antipyretic effect</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Antipyretic effect</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="48">
<j>梅干を潰し、おでこに貼り付けることにより熱を下げると言う作用。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Umeboshi alleviate fever when they are crashed and applied to the forehead.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Umeboshi alleviate fever when they&apos;re crushed and applied to the forehead.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Umeboshi alleviate fever when they&apos;re crushed and applied to the forehead.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>主に、老人の知恵袋的な療法である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is primarily a remedy that is similar to the pearls of wisdom of elderly people</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It&apos;s primarily a remedy similar to the &quot;pearls of wisdom&quot; among elderly people.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It&apos;s primarily a remedy similar to the &quot;pearls of wisdom&quot; among elderly people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="50">
<j>抗菌・防腐</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Antibacterial and antiseptic effects</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Antibacterial and antiseptic effects</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Antibacterial and antiseptic effects</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="51">
<j>抗菌の効能があるとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Umeboshi are believed to have antibacterial effects.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Umeboshi are believed to have antibacterial effects.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Umeboshi are believed to have antibacterial effects.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>このことから、弁当やおにぎりに梅干が入れられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this reason, they are put in box lunches and onigiri.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For that reason, they&apos;re placed in box lunches and onigiri.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For that reason, they&apos;re placed in box lunches and onigiri.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>但し、1個丸ごと入れただけでは梅干しの周囲しか効果は期待できない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, if a whole umeboshi is placed, the desired effects will be achieved only in the area around it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, if a whole umeboshi is placed, the desired effects will be achieved only in the area around it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, if a whole umeboshi is placed, the desired effects will be achieved only in the area around it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>この為、潰してご飯と混ぜ合わせることが推奨される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, it is recommended that umeboshi are smashed and mixed with boiled rice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, it is recommended that umeboshi are smashed and mixed with boiled rice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, it is recommended that umeboshi are smashed and mixed with boiled rice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>また、弁当に入れるときはアルミなどの金属などを溶かすことがあるので注意が必要である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Attention is also required when a umeboshi is put in a box lunch because it can melt metals like aluminum.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Attention is also required when an umeboshi is placed in a box lunch, because it can melt metal such as aluminum.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Attention is also required when an umeboshi is placed in a box lunch, because it can melt metal such as aluminum.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>なお、この効能は伝統的な製法の梅干に限られ、減塩の梅干（調味梅干）ではこの効能は期待できず、弁当に入れると調味梅干が先に腐る場合すらある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, these effects are limited to the umeboshi made according to the traditional method, and they cannot be expected to be produced by reduced-sodium umeboshi (chomi-umeboshi), which may even go bad first when they are included in a box lunch.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, these effects are limited to the umeboshi made according to the traditional method, so they can&apos;t be expected to be produced by reduced-sodium umeboshi (chomi-umeboshi), which may even go bad when it&apos;s first included in a box lunch.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, these effects are limited to the umeboshi made according to the traditional method, so they can&apos;t be expected to be produced by reduced-sodium umeboshi (chomi-umeboshi), which may even go bad when it&apos;s first included in a box lunch.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="57">
<j>成分</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Components</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Components</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Components</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="58">
<j>蛋白質・脂質・カルシウム・リン・鉄・ビタミン・カルボン酸</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Protein, lipid, calcium, phosphorus, iron, vitamin, and carboxylic acid</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Protein, lipid, calcium, phosphorus, iron, vitamins and carboxylic acid</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Protein, lipid, calcium, phosphorus, iron, vitamins and carboxylic acid</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>古代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ancient Times</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ancient Times</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ancient times</e>
<cmt>小タイトルのため、一部小文字にしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="59">
<j>梅は中国が原産である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ume originally came from China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ume originally came from China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ume originally came from China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>本来梅干は梅酢を作った後の副産物であり、利用法としてはこれを黒焼きにして腹痛・虫下し・解熱・腸内の消毒の効用を目的に食用よりもむしろ漢方薬として用いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Umeboshi were primarily the byproducts of umesu (ume vinegar), and they were charred and used as herbal medicines for treating stomach aches, expelling parasitic intestinal worms, alleviating fever, and sterilizing intestines, rather than as foods.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Umeboshi were primarily the byproducts of umesu (ume vinegar), and they were charred and used as herbal medicines for treating stomach aches, expelling parasitic intestinal worms, alleviating fever and sterilizing intestines, instead of being used as food.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Umeboshi were primarily the byproducts of umesu (ume vinegar), and they were charred and used as herbal medicines for treating stomach aches, expelling parasitic intestinal worms, alleviating fever and sterilizing intestines, instead of being used as food.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>紀元前200年頃のものという馬王堆からも、梅干しが入っていたと考えられる壷が出土している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A jar considered to have contained umeboshi has also been excavated from the Mawangdui Tomb that is said to be of around B.C. 200.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A jar considered to have contained umeboshi has also been excavated from the Mawangdui Tomb, which is said to date from around B.C. 200.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A jar considered to have contained umeboshi has also been excavated from the Mawangdui Tomb, which is said to date from around B.C. 200.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>これが日本に伝えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These were introduced into Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These were introduced into Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These were introduced into Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>また、クエン酸を主成分とする梅酢は器具や人体の傷口の消毒の他、金属のめっきやはんだ付け、青銅器・鉄器の酸化皮膜処理(酸化銅(II)および酸化鉄(II)：酸化第一鉄による『黒留め』と呼ばれる酸化皮膜による防錆処理)のためにも用いられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Umesu, which contains citric acid as the main component, was used for metal plating and soldering and the oxidation coating treatment of bronze and iron ware (copper oxide (II) and iron oxide (II): an anti-rust treatment using an oxide film made of ferrous oxide called &quot;kurodome&quot;), in addition to the sterilization of tools and bodily wounds.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Umesu, which contains citric acid as the main component, was used for metal plating and soldering and the oxidation coating treatment of bronze and iron ware (copper oxide (II) and iron oxide (II), an anti-rust treatment using an oxide film made of ferrous oxide called &quot;kurodome&quot;), in addition to the sterilization of tools and bodily wounds.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Umesu, which contains citric acid as the main component, was used for metal plating and soldering and the oxidation coating treatment of bronze and iron ware (copper oxide (II) and iron oxide (II), an anti-rust treatment using an oxide film made of ferrous oxide called &quot;kurodome&quot;), in addition to the sterilization of tools and bodily wounds.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>東大寺の大仏に金を鍍金する際にも使われたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also said to have been used to gild the daibutsu (the Great Buddha) of the Todai-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It&apos;s also said to have been used to gild the daibutsu (Great Buddha) of Todai-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It&apos;s also said to have been used to gild the daibutsu (Great Buddha) of Todai-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>梅酢はシアン化水素が登場する昭和中期まで大量に使われていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was used on a massive scale until hydrogen cyanide made an appearance in the middle of the Showa period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was used on a massive scale until hydrogen cyanide made an appearance in the middle of the Showa period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was used on a massive scale until hydrogen cyanide made an appearance in the middle of the Showa period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>平安時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Heian Period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Heian Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Heian period</e>
<cmt>小タイトルのため、一部小文字にしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="66">
<j>平安時代には村上天皇が梅干しと昆布茶で病を治したという言い伝えが残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tradition has it that the Emperor Murakami cured his disease with umeboshi and kobu-cha (tea made of powdered kelp).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tradition has it that Emperor Murakami cured his disease with umeboshi and kobu-cha (tea made of powdered kelp).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tradition has it that Emperor Murakami cured his disease with umeboshi and kobu-cha (tea made of powdered kelp).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>また、菅原道真が梅を詠んだ短歌は有名で、後に「釣りのときの弁当に梅干しを入れると、魚が釣れなくなる」という縁起かつぎを生んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, a tanka (a Japanese poem of thirty-one syllables) composed by Michizane SUGAWARA about ume blossoms is well-known, and it later gave rise to a superstition that &apos;if you put an umeboshi in a box lunch you take when you go fishing, you will not catch fish&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, a tanka (a 31-syllable Japanese poem) composed by Michizane SUGAWARA about ume blossoms is well known, having given rise to a superstition that &apos;if you place an umeboshi in a box lunch you take when you go fishing, you will not catch fish.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, a tanka (a 31-syllable Japanese poem) composed by Michizane SUGAWARA about ume blossoms is well known, having given rise to a superstition that &apos;if you place an umeboshi in a box lunch you take when you go fishing, you will not catch fish.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>戦国時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Sengoku Period (the Period of Warring States)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sengoku (Warring States) Period</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sengoku (warring states) period</e>
<cmt>小タイトルのため、一部小文字にしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="68">
<j>武士の時代になると梅干しは保存食としてだけではなく、傷の消毒や戦場での食中毒、伝染病の予防になくてはならないものとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the era of samurai (warriors), umeboshi became indispensable not only as preserved food but also for the sterilization of wounds and the prevention of food poisoning and contagious diseases in the battlefield.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the era of samurai (warriors), umeboshi became indispensable not only as preserved food but also for the sterilization of wounds and the prevention of food poisoning and contagious diseases on the battlefield.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the era of samurai (warriors), umeboshi became indispensable not only as preserved food but also for the sterilization of wounds and the prevention of food poisoning and contagious diseases on the battlefield.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>合戦中の休息に梅干しを見ることで唾液分泌を促進させ息切れを防ぐ目的にも使われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were also used to visually stimulate the secretion of saliva to prevent shortness of breath during a break in the battle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were also used to visually stimulate the secretion of saliva to prevent shortness of breath during breaks in battle.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were also used to visually stimulate the secretion of saliva to prevent shortness of breath during breaks in battle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>梅干しは戦略物資の一つとなり、武将たちは梅の植林を奨励した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They became one of the strategic items, and the busho (the Japanese military commanders in the Sengoku Period) encouraged the planting of ume trees.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They became one of the strategic items, and the busho (the Japanese military commanders of the Sengoku period) encouraged the planting of ume trees.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They became one of the strategic items, and the busho (the Japanese military commanders of the Sengoku period) encouraged the planting of ume trees.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>これは現在でも梅の名所や梅干しの産地として残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These areas of afforestation remain as plum blossom viewing spots and umeboshi production centers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These areas of afforestation remain as plum-blossom viewing spots and umeboshi production centers.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These areas of afforestation remain as plum-blossom viewing spots and umeboshi production centers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>かの上杉謙信も酒の肴に梅干しをよく取っていたと言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That Kenshin UESUGI is also said to have nibbled umeboshi as sakana (appetizers taken with alcoholic drinks) when he drank sake.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenshin UESUGI is also said to have nibbled umeboshi as sakana (appetizers taken with alcoholic drinks) when he drank sake.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenshin UESUGI is also said to have nibbled umeboshi as sakana (appetizers taken with alcoholic drinks) when he drank sake.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>江戸時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Edo Period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Edo Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Edo period</e>
<cmt>小タイトルのため、一部小文字にしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="73">
<j>当時の銀山では、坑内に立ちこめる鉱塵（こうじん）による粉塵公害「けだえ」が問題であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the silver mines of the time, a dust pollution, &apos;kedae&apos; (a respiratory disease), caused by the mine dust filling the pit was a problem.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the silver mines of the time, &apos;kedae&apos; (a respiratory disease), caused by the mine dust filling the pit, was a problem.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the silver mines of the time, &apos;kedae&apos; (a respiratory disease), caused by the mine dust filling the pit, was a problem.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>備後国の医師宮太柱は数々の「けだえ」防止の装置を発明したが、鉄の枠に梅肉を挟み薄絹を張った防毒マスク「福面（ふくめん）」は、酸の効果で鉱塵を寄せつけず効果が絶大だったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tachu MIYA, a doctor of Bingo no kuni (Bingo Province) invented many devices to prevent &apos;kedae&apos;, but a gas mask, &apos;fukumen&apos; (literally, a fortune mask)&apos;, which had bainiku (the pulp of umeboshi) between an iron frame and a piece of thin silk, is reported to have had a great effect because it did not let mine dust inside thanks to the acid.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tachu MIYA, a doctor of Bingo no kuni (Bingo Province), invented many devices to prevent &apos;kedae,&apos; but the gas mask, &apos;fukumen&apos; (literally, a fortune mask), which had bainiku (the pulp of umeboshi) between an iron frame and a fine piece of silk, is reported to have had a great effect because it prevented the infiltration of mine dust thanks to the acid content.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tachu MIYA, a doctor of Bingo no kuni (Bingo Province), invented many devices to prevent &apos;kedae,&apos; but the gas mask, &apos;fukumen&apos; (literally, a fortune mask), which had bainiku (the pulp of umeboshi) between an iron frame and a fine piece of silk, is reported to have had a great effect because it prevented the infiltration of mine dust thanks to the acid content.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>これがきっかけとなり後年、坑夫たちの家族によって梅紫蘇巻という食品が生み出された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This later on inspired the families of the miners to invent umejiso-maki (ume-shiso rolls).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This later on inspired the families of the miners to invent umejiso-maki (ume-shiso rolls).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This later on inspired the families of the miners to invent umejiso-maki (ume-shiso rolls).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>近代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Modern Period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Modern Period</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The modern period</e>
<cmt>小タイトルのため、一部小文字にしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="76">
<j>昭和期などは日の丸弁当は弁当の定番であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Showa period, the hinomaru bento was a standard box lunch.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Showa period, the hinomaru bento was a standard box lunch.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Showa period, the hinomaru bento was a standard box lunch.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>日中戦争から太平洋戦争の時期には、興亜奉公日・大詔奉戴日にこれを推奨（半ば強制）していたこともある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the period between the Sino-Japanese War and the Pacific War, it was recommended (half coerced) on Koa hokobi (Day for Patriotic Services) and Taisho hotaibi (Day to Reverently Accept the Imperial Edict).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the period between the Sino-Japanese War and the Pacific War, it was recommended (half-coerced) on Koa hokobi (Day for Patriotic Services) and Taisho hotaibi (Day to Reverently Accept the Imperial Edict).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the period between the Sino-Japanese War and the Pacific War, it was recommended (half-coerced) on Koa hokobi (Day for Patriotic Services) and Taisho hotaibi (Day to Reverently Accept the Imperial Edict).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>梅干しの成分がアルミを溶かすため、日の丸弁当に長年使用すると弁当箱に穴が空くなどのトラブルもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because a component of umeboshi melts aluminum, it also caused such a trouble as making a hole in the lunch box that has been used for many years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because a component of umeboshi melts aluminum, it could also make a hole in the lunch box that has been used for many years.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because a component of umeboshi melts aluminum, it could also make a hole in the lunch box that has been used for many years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="79">
<j>現在では調味梅など塩以外にハチミツなども使用した物が登場している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today, there are umeboshi like chomi-ume that are prepared with honey, etc. other than salt.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, there are umeboshi (such as chomi-ume) that are prepared with honey, etc., instead of salt.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, there are umeboshi (such as chomi-ume) that are prepared with honey, etc., instead of salt.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>また、低塩の志向を受け、真水によって塩抜きされた後、調味を施した「調味梅干」が主流となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Following low sodium consciousness, &apos;chomi-ume&apos; that are given a flavor after excess salt is removed from umeboshi in mamizu (fresh water) have become the mainstream.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Following the low-sodium consciousness, &apos;chomi-ume,&apos; which are given a flavor after the excess salt is removed from umeboshi in mamizu (fresh water), have become the mainstream.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Following the low-sodium consciousness, &apos;chomi-ume,&apos; which are given a flavor after the excess salt is removed from umeboshi in mamizu (fresh water), have become the mainstream.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>種の仁</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kernel of the Seed</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kernel of the Seed</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The kernel of the seed</e>
<cmt>小タイトルのため、一部小文字にしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="81">
<j>梅干しの種子の仁（中身）を俗に天神様と言い、この部分を好んで食べる人もいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The kernels (the interior) of the seeds of umeboshi are commonly called Tenjin-sama (the deified spirit of Michizane ZUGAWARA), and some people like to eat this part.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The kernels (the interior) of the seeds of umeboshi are commonly called Tenjin-sama (the deified spirit of Michizane ZUGAWARA), and some people like to eat them.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The kernels (the interior) of the seeds of umeboshi are commonly called Tenjin-sama (the deified spirit of Michizane SUGAWARA), and some people like to eat them.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="82">
<j>天神様という俗称は菅原道真の飛梅伝説に由来する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The popular name of Tenjin-sama derives from the legend of Tobiume (literally, &quot;flying plum tree&quot;) of Michizane SUGAWARA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The popular name of Tenjin-sama derives from the legend of Tobiume (literally, &quot;flying plum tree&quot;) of Michizane SUGAWARA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The popular name of Tenjin-sama derives from the legend of Tobiume (literally, &quot;flying plum tree&quot;) of Michizane SUGAWARA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="83">
<j>しかし、ウメの実には元々青酸配糖体であるアミグダリンという成分が含まれており、これが胃腸などで酵素によって加水分解されると毒であるシアン化水素（青酸）を生成する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, ume fruits contain a component called amygdaline, which is a cyanogenetic glycoside, and it forms poisonous hydrogen cyanide (hydrocyanic acid) when hydrolyzed by an enzyme in the stomach, intestines, and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, ume fruit contains a component called amygdaline, which is a cyanogenetic glycoside that forms poisonous hydrogen cyanide (hydrocyanic acid) when hydrolyzed by an enzyme in the stomach, intestines and so on.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, ume fruit contains a component called amygdaline, which is a cyanogenetic glycoside that forms poisonous hydrogen cyanide (hydrocyanic acid) when hydrolyzed by an enzyme in the stomach, intestines and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>これは特に仁（天神様）の部分に多く、多量に食べると青酸中毒に陥り、最悪の場合は死に至る可能性がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is found a lot, particularly in the part of the kernel (Tenjin-sama), and if eaten in sufficient quantity poisoning with hydrocyanic acid can be developed and in the worse-case scenario result in death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It&apos;s found a lot, particularly in the part of the kernel (Tenjin-sama); if eaten in a sufficient quantity, poisoning with hydrocyanic acid can develop and, in the worse-case scenario, result in death.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It&apos;s found a lot, particularly in the part of the kernel (Tenjin-sama); if eaten in a sufficient quantity, poisoning with hydrocyanic acid can develop, which, in the worse-case scenario, may result in death.</e>
<cmt>一部翻訳を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="85">
<j>ただし、漬ける事でアミグダリンはほぼ消失し、食べても人体にはほとんど影響がないとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, pickling makes the amygdaline almost disappear, and eating the kernels has almost no effect on the human body.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, pickling removed nearly all the amygdaline, so eating the kernels will have almost no effect on the human body.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, pickling removed nearly all the amygdaline, so eating the kernels will have almost no effect on the human body.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Green3558(id:59508), Ypacaraí(id:11031), Nnh(id:474), 0null0(id:582), Lupinoid(id:68), JINKY.ECLEO(id:141716), 0太郎(id:7375), Tribot(id:186681), Tsk(id:1153), Michey.M(id:906), RON ST(id:156891), Point136(id:211299), 川野直己(id:50600), Korokoro(id:42329), FlaBot(id:30804), Hotei(id:7664), 目白梅(id:141468), ロリ(id:613), Naranja(id:30069), Syasue(id:135239), Kkkdc(id:32227), マクガイア(id:33346), 219市115丁223番151号(id:15789), Escarbot(id:59151), Zwobot(id:23873), ハイゼン(id:21182), Hyolee2(id:16439), Suisui(id:69), Yoyuuu!(id:18690), JAnDbot(id:66507), Andre Engels(id:202), Kawai(id:5634), Pippi(id:37264), Kumatora(id:16941), Mintleaf(id:2216), Toto-tarou(id:16648), Naru-W(id:17852), Textex(id:27452), Khoriuchi(id:139877), X4852(id:53769), Nevylax(id:38464), Tenko(id:102318), NobelBot(id:272277), 竹麦魚(id:11012), 赤鉛筆(id:2434), Kurihaya(id:132524), 梅の里(id:15035), マイタケ(id:106207), Izayohi(id:13095), Ekoeko(id:117859), Robbot(id:3063), Etorofu island(id:180956), 竃馬(id:102733), Green(id:24154), 貘(id:106080), Minque(id:40595), Unamu(id:14627), 663highland(id:18755), SEKIUCHI(id:637), DoWhile(id:34638), Corwin(id:973), Satob(id:42268), Numamidabutz(id:140287), Louperibot(id:128971), Tomorrow0622(id:26939), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>