<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>影武者 (映画)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kagemusha (The Shadow Warrior) (movie)</e>
<cmt>影武者→ Kagemusha (The Shadow Warrior)[http://www.amazon.com/Kagemusha-Criterion-Collection-Tatsuya-Nakadai/dp/B00005JLEJ]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kagemusha (The Shadow Warrior) (movie)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kagemusha (The Shadow Warrior) (movie)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>『影武者』（かげむしゃ）は、1980年に公開された黒澤明監督の日本映画。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kagemusha&quot; (The Shadow Warrior) is a 1980 Japanese film directed by Akira KUROSAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kagemusha&quot; (The Shadow Warrior) is a 1980 Japanese film directed by Akira KUROSAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Kagemusha&quot; (The Shadow Warrior) is a 1980 Japanese film directed by Akira KUROSAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>カンヌ国際映画祭グランプリ受賞。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The film won the Grand Prix at the Cannes International Film Festival.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The film won the Grand Prix at the Cannes International Film Festival.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The film won the Grand Prix at the Cannes International Film Festival.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>黒澤を敬愛するフランシス・フォード・コッポラ、ジョージ・ルーカスが外国版プロデューサーに名を連ねた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Francis Ford Coppola and George Lucas, who adore Kurosawa, served as executive producers for its international version.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Francis Ford Coppola and George Lucas, who adore Kurosawa, served as executive producers for its international version.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Francis Ford Coppola and George Lucas, who adore Kurosawa, served as executive producers for its international version.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>またこの作品から、助監督時代からの盟友であった本多猪四郎が演出補佐として（影武者では演出部チーフとしてクレジット）スタッフに加わるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From this title, Ishiro HONDA, who was an old friend of Kurosawa since his assistant director&apos;s days, joined as the assistant producer (credited as the chief of production in Kagemusha).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, starting with Kagemusha, Ishiro HONDA, an old friend of Kurosawa since his assistant director days, joined forces as assistant producer (credited as the chief of production).</e>
<cmt>from this title &gt; starting with Kagemusha. Who was X. an Z</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, starting with Kagemusha, Ishiro HONDA, an old friend of Kurosawa since his assistant director days, joined forces as assistant producer (credited as the chief of production).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>黒澤作品では唯一、実在の戦国武将にまつわるエピソードを取り上げたスペクタクル巨編。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among Kurosawa titles, this is the only spectacle film that deals with episodes invoking real busho (Japanese military commander) in the Sengoku period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Out of all the Kurosawa films, this is the only spectacle film that deals with episodes invoking real busho (Japanese military commanders) in the Sengoku period.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Out of all the Kurosawa films, this is the only spectacle film that deals with episodes invoking real samurai commanders in the Warring States period.</e>
<cmt>音訳を略しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>黒澤監督は次回作『乱 (映画)』の撮影準備（リハーサル）としてこの作品を作ったとも語っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Director Kurosawa also told that he produced this title as a rehearsal of his next film &quot;Ran&quot; (chaos).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kurosawa also claims that he produced Kagemusha as a test-run for his next film &quot;Ran&quot; (chaos).</e>
<cmt>this title &gt; Kagemsuah. Rehearsal &gt; test-run.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kurosawa also claims that he produced Kagemusha as a test-run for his next film &quot;Ran&quot; (chaos).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>あらすじ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Story line</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Storyline</e>
<cmt>deleted space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Storyline</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>小泥棒が戦国武将・武田信玄の影武者として生きる運命を背負わされた悲喜劇。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is a tragicomedy about a thief who lived as Kagemusha (body double) for Shingen TAKEDA, busho in the Sengoku period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The story is a tragicomedy about a thief who lived as Kagemusha (body double) for Shingen TAKEDA, busho in the Sengoku period.</e>
<cmt>This &gt; the story</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The story is a tragicomedy about a thief who lived as a body double (kagemusha) for Shingen TAKEDA, a samurai commander in the Warring States period.</e>
<cmt>音訳を略しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>武田信玄が徳川家康の野田城 (三河国)攻めの際に死亡した事実を隠すため、弟・武田信廉らは信玄の影武者を立てる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order to conceal the fact that Shingen TAKEDA died in the attack on Noda-jo Castle (Mikawa Province) by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, his younger brother Nobukado TAKEDA and others used him as Shingen&apos;s Kagemusha.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to conceal the fact that Shingen TAKEDA died in the attack on Noda-jo Castle (Mikawa Province) by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, his younger brother Nobukado TAKEDA and others used him as Shingen&apos;s Kagemusha.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to conceal the fact that Shingen TAKEDA died in the attack on Noda-jo Castle (Mikawa Province) by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, his younger brother Nobukado TAKEDA and others used him as Shingen&apos;s body double.</e>
<cmt>音訳を略しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>この男は盗みの罪で処刑されるところを信玄と瓜二つだったことから信廉に助けられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This man, who was being executed for theft, was saved by Nobukado because he was like two peas in a pod withShingen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The man, who was about to be executed for theft, was saved by Nobukado because he was the spitting image of Shingen.</e>
<cmt>being &gt; about to be. Like two peas in a pod with &lt; the spitting image of.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The man, who was about to be executed for theft, was saved by Nobukado because he was the spitting image of Shingen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>当初は逃亡を企てた男も、一度対面した信玄の威容に圧倒され、影武者としての人生を受け入れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although this man had initially attempted to run away, he was overawed by Shingen&apos;s dignified attitude just by looking and accepted his life as a body double for Shingen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the man had initially attempted to run away, with just one look at Shingen he was overpowered by his majestic appearance and accepted his lot as a body double for Shingen.</e>
<cmt>this &gt; the. Just by looking &gt; with just one look. Overawed &gt; overpowered. Dignified attitude &gt; majestic appearance.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the man had initially attempted to run away, with just one look at Shingen he was overpowered by his majestic appearance and accepted his lot as a body double for Shingen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>だが、一方、歴史の歯車は織田信長の台頭、武田家没落という運命に向かって大きく回り始めていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, the wheel of history began to spin toward the rising of Nobunaga ODA and the declining of the Takeda family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, the wheel of fate began to spin in favour of the rising Nobunaga ODA, to the decline of the Takeda family.</e>
<cmt>history &gt; fate. Toward &gt; in favour of</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, the wheel of fate began to spin in favour of the rising Nobunaga ODA, to the decline of the Takeda family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>キャスト、スタッフを巡るトラブル</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Troubles relating to casts and staffs</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Issues with cast and staff</e>
<cmt>Troubles &gt; issues. Relating to &gt; with</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Issues with cast and staff</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>当初主演だった勝新太郎は撮影開始後に黒澤と衝突し、降板した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shintaro KATSU, who had initially been going to play the lead character, conflicted with Kurosawa and left the film after starting filming.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shintaro KATSU, who was originally going to play the lead character, had a conflict with Kurosawa and left the project shorty after filming began.</e>
<cmt>initially &gt; originally. Conflicted &gt; had a conflict. Film &gt; project. Starting filimng &gt; fliming began.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shintaro KATSU, who was originally going to play the lead character, had a conflict with Kurosawa and left the project shorty after filming began.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>直接の原因は、勝が自分の演技をビデオカメラで撮影し、役作りの参考にしようとしたことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The immediate cause for this is that Katsu tried to shoot his performance with a video camera to prepare for his role.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The main cause of this was that Katsu tried to film his own performance with a video camera to rehearse for his role.</e>
<cmt>immediate &gt; main. Shoot his &gt; film his own. Prepare &gt; rehearse.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The main cause of this was that Katsu tried to film his own performance with a video camera to rehearse for his role.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>これについて黒澤は「監督は二人いらない」との言葉を残した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">About his action, Kurosawa left the words, &apos;I don&apos;t needs two directors.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seeing this, Kurosawa remarked, &apos;I don&apos;t need two directors.&apos;</e>
<cmt>about his action &gt; seeing this. Left the wrods &gt; remarked. Needs &gt; need.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seeing this, Kurosawa remarked, &apos;I don&apos;t need two directors.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>勝の降板により、『乱』の主演が内定していた仲代達矢が起用された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the leave of Katsu, Tatsuya NAKADAI, who had unofficially been decided to play the lead character in &quot;Ran,&quot; was hired for that role.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Katsu left, Tatsuya NAKADAI, who had unofficially been chosen to play the lead character in &quot;Ran,&quot; was hired for Katsu&apos;s role.</e>
<cmt>the leave of katsu &gt; katsu left. Decided &gt; chosen. That &gt; katsu.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Katsu left, Tatsuya NAKADAI, who had unofficially been chosen to play the lead character in &quot;Ran,&quot; was hired for Katsu&apos;s role.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>仲代は独自の影武者像を作り上げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nakadai established his own character of Kagemusha.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nakadai made the character of Kagemusha his own.</e>
<cmt>established &gt; made his own.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nakadai made the character of Kagemusha his own.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>劇場公開の際に映画を観にきた勝は「（映画は）面白くなかった」とコメントした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Katsu, who came to watch the movie at theatrical opening, said, &apos;this movie was not interesting.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Katsu, who came to the premiere, commented, &apos;The movie was boring.&apos;</e>
<cmt>watch the movie at theatrical opening &gt; premiere. Said &gt; commented. Not interesting &gt; boring</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Katsu, who came to the premiere, commented, &apos;The movie was boring.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="20">
<j>山城新伍が語った所によれば、当初は勝が武田信玄と影武者を、勝の実兄の若山富三郎が信玄の弟武田信廉役を演じる案があったという（実際の兄弟関係を逆転させた配役）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the story by Shingo YAMASHIRO, Katsu was originally supposed to play the roles of Shingen TAKEDA and Kagemusha and his natural older brother Tomisaburo WAKAYAMA to play the role of Shingen&apos;s younger brother Nobukado TAKEDA (the casting of reverse fraternity).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Shingo YAMASHIRO, Katsu was originally supposed to play the roles of Shingen TAKEDA and Kagemusha, and his older brother Tomisaburo WAKAYAMA was to play the role of Shingen&apos;s younger brother Nobukado TAKEDA (the opposite of their true ages).</e>
<cmt>the story by X. natural X. the casting of reverse fraternity &gt; the opposite of their true ages..</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Shingo YAMASHIRO, Katsu was originally supposed to play the roles of Shingen TAKEDA and his body double, and his older brother Tomisaburo WAKAYAMA was to play the role of Shingen&apos;s younger brother Nobukado TAKEDA (the opposite of their true ages).</e>
<cmt>影武者をbody doubleとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>だが、若山は勝と黒澤のトラブルを予期し、それに巻き込まれることを嫌って出演依頼を断ったため、実現には至らなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, anticipating trouble between Katsu and Kurosawa, Wakayama declined the movie offer to stay out of the trouble and this casting was not realized.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, anticipating trouble between Katsu and Kurosawa, Wakayama declined the offer to avoid incident, thus this casting was not realized.</e>
<cmt>stay out of the trouble &gt; avoid incident.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, anticipating trouble between Katsu and Kurosawa, Wakayama declined the offer to avoid incident, thus this casting was not realized.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="22">
<j>音楽については『どん底 (1957年の映画)』から『赤ひげ』までコンビを組んできた佐藤勝が黒澤と対立して降板、武満徹の推薦で急遽池辺晋一郎が起用されることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Masaru SATO, who had worked together in terms of music from &quot;Donzoko&quot; (the Lower Depths) (the 1957 movie) to &quot;Akahige&quot; (Red Beard), clashed with Kurosawa and left the movie, Shinichiro IKEBE was used in place of him at the recommendation of Toru TAKEMITSU.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Masaru SATO, who had produced the music for &quot;Donzoko&quot; (the Lower Depths, 1957) and &quot;Akahige&quot; (Red Beard), clashed with Kurosawa and left the movie, Shinichiro IKEBE was used in place of him at the recommendation of Toru TAKEMITSU.</e>
<cmt>worked together in term of &gt; who had produced the music for.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Masaru SATO, who had produced the music for &quot;Donzoko&quot; (the Lower Depths, 1957) and &quot;Akahige&quot; (Red Beard), clashed with Kurosawa and left the movie, Shinichiro IKEBE was used in place of him at the recommendation of Toru TAKEMITSU.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>武満の映画音楽のアシスタントをしていた池辺は『どですかでん』にも関わっており、その後『乱』を除く全作品を手がけることになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ikebe, who had worked as an assistant of Takemitsu in movie&apos;s music, was also involved with &quot;Dodesukaden&quot; and worked on all titled except &quot;Ran&quot; thereafter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ikebe, who had worked as Takemitsu&apos;s musical assistant, was also involved with &quot;Dodesukaden&quot; and worked on all of Kurasawa&apos;s films except &quot;Ran&quot; thereafter.</e>
<cmt>in movie&apos;s music &gt; musical assistant. All titled &gt; all of Kurosawa&apos;s films.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ikebe, who had worked as Takemitsu&apos;s musical assistant, was also involved with &quot;Dodesukaden&quot; and worked on all of Kurasawa&apos;s films except &quot;Ran&quot; thereafter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>なお、『乱』で音楽を手掛けた武満とも黒澤は激しく対立し、降板こそしなかったものの決別に至っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kurosawa was also in fierce conflict with Takemitsu, who had produced music for &quot;Ran&quot; and after the completion of the movie, he broke away with Takemitsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kurosawa was also in fierce conflict with Takemitsu, who had produced music for &quot;Ran&quot; and after the completion of the movie, he broke ties with Takemitsu.</e>
<cmt>away &gt; ties.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kurosawa was also in fierce conflict with Takemitsu, who had produced music for &quot;Ran&quot; and after the completion of the movie, he broke ties with Takemitsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="25">
<j>その他に、撮影の宮川一夫が体調不良により交代している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Except above, cinematographer Kazuo MIYAGAWA was replaced owing to bad health.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to the above, cinematographer Kazuo MIYAGAWA fell ill and was replaced.</e>
<cmt>owing to bad health &gt; and was replaced.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to the above, cinematographer Kazuo MIYAGAWA fell ill and was replaced.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="26">
<j>出演者</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Performers</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Performers</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Performers</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>ほとんどの出演者がオーディションで選ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most of performers were chosen in an audition.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most performers were chosen by audition.</e>
<cmt>of X. in an &gt; by</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most performers were chosen by audition.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>油井昌由樹や隆大介、清水大敬（当時は「清水のぼる」名義）、阿藤海、島香裕など、無名の俳優、新人俳優から演技経験の全くない素人までが数々の重要な役で出演した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many unknown and new actors, and of amateurs with no acting experience, including Masayuki YUI, Daisuke RYU, Taikei SHIMIZU (&apos;Noboru SHIMIZU&apos; at the time), Kai ATO, Yu SHIMAKA, were cast in leading roles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many unknown and new actors, plus amateurs with no acting experience, including Masayuki YUI, Daisuke RYU, Taikei SHIMIZU (&apos;Noboru SHIMIZU&apos; at the time), Kai ATO, Yu SHIMAKA, were cast in leading roles.</e>
<cmt>and of &gt;plus.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many unknown and new actors, plus amateurs with no acting experience, including Masayuki YUI, Daisuke RYU, Taikei SHIMIZU (&apos;Noboru SHIMIZU&apos; at the time), Kai ATO, Yu SHIMAKA, were cast in leading roles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="29">
<j>電撃ネットワークの南部虎弾（出演者クレジットは南部虎太となっている）、柳葉敏郎、山田五郎（クレジットなし）といった面々が、全く無名だった若き日に雑兵や死体役などのエキストラとして出演している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Present prominent figures, including Torata NAMBU (南部虎弾) (credited as 南部虎太) of Dengeki Network, Toshiro YANAGIBA, Goro YAMADA (no credit), appeared as an extra, such as the roles of zohyo (common soldier) and the dead, in the movie when they were young and unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Current prominent figures, including Torata NAMBU of Dengeki Network, Toshiro YANAGIBA, Goro YAMADA (uncredited), appeared as extras, such as in the roles of zohyo (common soldier) and the dead, when they were young and unknown.</e>
<cmt>Present &gt; current. Kanji X. no creadit &gt;uncredited.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Current prominent figures, including Torata NAMBU of Dengeki Network, Toshiro YANAGIBA, Goro YAMADA (uncredited), appeared as extras, such as in the roles of common soldiers and the dead, when they were young and unknown.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>当時大学生だった鴻上尚史はオーディションに合格したが、当日の都合で参加できず、石田純一はオーディションに落とされたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Shoji KOKAMI, who was an university student at that time, passed an audition test, he was unable to take part in the film shooting, and Junichi ISHIDA failed an audition.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Shoji KOKAMI, a university student at the time, passed the audition, he was unable to take part in filming, and Junichi ISHIDA was unsuccessful at audition.</e>
<cmt>who was X. the film shooting &gt; filming. Failed an &gt; unsuccessfull at.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Shoji KOKAMI, a university student at the time, passed the audition, he was unable to take part in filming, and Junichi ISHIDA was unsuccessful at audition.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="31">
<j>外国版と国内版</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">International version and domestic version</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">International version and domestic version</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">International version and domestic version</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>外国版では、国内版の一部シーンが日本の歴史を知らない外国人には理解しにくいとの理由でカットされた（上杉謙信が、信玄の訃報を聞く場面など）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Part of scenes in the domestic version were cut in the international version, because they were difficult for foreigners who do not know the Japanese history to understand (like the scene where Kenshin UESUGI heard the news of Shingen&apos;s death).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some scenes from the domestic version were cut for the international version, because they were difficult for foreigners unfamiliar with Japanese history to understand (like the scene where Kenshin UESUGI hears the news of Shingen&apos;s death).</e>
<cmt>part of &gt; some. Cut in &gt; cut for. Who do not know the &gt; unfamiliar with.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some scenes from the domestic version were cut for the international version, because they were difficult for foreigners unfamiliar with Japanese history to understand (like the scene where Kenshin UESUGI hears the news of Shingen&apos;s death).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>だがそれだけではなく、公開時の淀川長治との雑誌対談で黒澤は「国内版は時間がなかったため編集が不十分、もっと切りたかったが、外国版は時間が許す限り再編集した。」という主旨の発言をしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, during the magazine interview with Nagaharu YODOGAWA (Movie critic), Kurosawa said, &apos;film cutting of the domestic version was inadequate due to lack of time but recutting was made for the international version as far as time permits.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, during a magazine interview with Nagaharu YODOGAWA (film critic), Kurosawa said, &apos;Editing of the domestic version was inadequate due to lack of time but we made as many further cuts as time allowed for the international version.&apos;</e>
<cmt>the magazine &gt; a magazine. &apos;film cutting &gt; editing. Recutting was made &gt; we made further cuts. As far as time permits &gt; as many as time allowed.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, during a magazine interview with Nagaharu YODOGAWA (film critic), Kurosawa said, &apos;Editing of the domestic version was inadequate due to lack of time but we made as many further cuts as time allowed for the international version.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="34">
<j>ドキュメンタリー他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Documentary and others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Documentaries etc.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Documentaries etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="35">
<j>1979年11月2日に日本放送協会で放送された『NHK特集・黒澤明の世界』では「影武者」製作の舞台裏が伝えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The &quot;NHK feature/The World of Akira Kurosawa&quot; broadcasted by Japan Broadcasting Corporation conveyed the behind-the-scenes secrets in the production of &apos;Kagemusha.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;NHK feature/The World of Akira Kurosawa&quot; broadcasted by Japan Broadcasting Corporation exposed behind-the-scenes secrets during the production of &apos;Kagemusha.&apos;</e>
<cmt>conveyed &gt; exposed. In &gt; during</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &quot;NHK feature/The World of Akira Kurosawa&quot; broadcasted by Japan Broadcasting Corporation exposed behind-the-scenes secrets during the production of &apos;Kagemusha.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="36">
<j>『全集黒澤明　第6巻』岩波書店に台本他が所収。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The movie script and others are included in &quot;Akira KUROSAWA complete works, The 6th volume&quot; published by Iwanami Shoten.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The movie script and others are included in &quot;Akira KUROSAWA complete works, The 6th volume&quot; published by Iwanami Shoten.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The movie script and others are included in &quot;Akira KUROSAWA complete works, The 6th volume&quot; published by Iwanami Shoten.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Miuharehareyukai(id:172205), Eskimbot(id:29676), Ooiei(id:218534), Mintleaf(id:2216), Kamakura(id:472), Uraios(id:72687), MorinoMashio(id:250265), Nevylax(id:38464), Azucar(id:20348), Loveless(id:129239), XX RAY(id:128401), Yas(id:739), FlaBot(id:30804), Bankokuya(id:91191), Caminante(id:39410), タケナカ(id:28800), COCKY(id:19672), 松茸(id:27535), Syatex(id:1501), Utsuda(id:605), エンピツ(id:44912), よもすがら(id:212112), Amaki bo(id:13580), HSS2B(id:137935), Rusk(id:9895), 平凡児朗(id:23570), VolkovBot(id:105371), YurikBot(id:18605), TaBOT-zerem(id:257085), Elwood Link(id:46556), NDR(id:5500), Ptbotgourou(id:229657), Yoyuuu!(id:18690), Botz(id:83566), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>