<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>浦終い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Urajimai</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Urajimai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Urajimai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>浦終い（うらじまい）とは、日本の海難事故に際して行われる伝統的な儀式や事後処理の慣習。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Urajimai (浦終い) is a custom to conduct traditional ceremonies and to cope with aftermath of marine accidents in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Urajimai is a Japanese custom of conducting traditional ceremonies and handling the aftermath of accidents at sea.</e>
<cmt>sentence reworded</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Urajimai is a Japanese custom of conducting traditional ceremonies and handling the aftermath of accidents at sea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>浦仕舞とも記す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Urajimai is also written as 浦仕舞 in Chinese characters.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Urajimai is also written as 浦仕舞 in Chinese characters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Urajimai is also written as 浦仕舞 in Chinese characters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>由来は江戸時代、廻船が海難にあった場合の処置である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its origin comes from a measure taken in the Edo period to deal with a cargo vessel which met with a disaster.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its origin is the measures taken in the Edo period when cargo vessels met disasters.</e>
<cmt>sentence reworded</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its origin is the measures taken in the Edo period when cargo vessels met disasters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>室町時代後期に設定された海事法「廻船式目」に端を発する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It originated from the law of maritime affairs named &apos;Kaisen Shikimoku (The Oldest Sea Law of Japan) established in the late Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It originated from the law of maritime affairs named &apos;Kaisen Shikimoku&apos; (The Oldest Sea Law of Japan) established in the late Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>quotation mark closed</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It originated from the law of maritime affairs named &apos;Kaisen Shikimoku&apos; (The Oldest Sea Law of Japan) established in the late Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>その後豊臣秀吉によって慣習法をまとめた「海路諸法度」により海難処理の詳細が制定され、江戸幕府に於いても慣習法として生き残る事となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, details in dealing with marine disasters were stipurated in a customary named &apos;Kaiji Shohatto&apos; (various laws on sea routes) by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, and they still remained as common laws in the Edo bakufu.</e>
<cmt>海路諸法度→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, details in dealing with marine disasters were stipulated in a customary law named &apos;Kaiji Shohatto&apos; (various laws on sea routes) by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, and they remained as common laws in the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>bakufu explanation added</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, details in dealing with marine disasters were stipulated in a customary law named &apos;Kaiji Shohatto&apos; (various laws on sea routes) by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, and they remained as common laws in the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>海難に際しての宗教的儀式にとどまらず、現場検証や補償、役人の証文交付など一連の必要な手続きをくるめて浦終いと呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Urajimai included not only religious ceremonies but also a series of necessary procedures such as investigations at the scenes, compensation, and issuance of a bond by officials and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Urajimai included not only religious ceremonies, but also a series of necessary procedures such as on-site investigations, compensations, bond issuance by officials and so on.</e>
<cmt>end of the sentence reworded</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Urajimai included not only religious ceremonies, but also a series of necessary procedures such as on-site investigations, compensations, bond issuance by officials and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>神戸市内の神社の石碑などにこの浦終いについての言及がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are mentions about Urajimai on a stone monument and the like of a shrine in Kobe City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are mentions of urajimai on a stone monument at a shrine in Kobe City.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are mentions of urajimai on a stone monument at a shrine in Kobe City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>現在でも沿岸の地域にこの風習が残る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even today, the custom of Urajimai still remains in coastal areas.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even today, the custom of urajimai still remains in coastal areas.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Urajimai&quot; changed to &quot;urajimai&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even today, the custom of urajimai still remains in coastal areas.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="10">
<j>概略</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>難船のしらせが来ると、廻船問屋の行司、荷主の総代が改人としてその浦方に出張し、海難の程度を検査し（これを「浦改」（うらあらため）という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">when a news about a wrecked ship was conveyed, Gyogi (manager) of Kaisen donya (wholesaler in port) and Sodai (representative of consignors) were dispatched to the gulf coast near the accident site, where they investigated the extent of damage (this is called &apos;Ura-aratame&apos;).</e>
<cmt>行司→定訳不明改人→定訳不明浦方→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When there was a news about a shipwreck, gyogi (manager) of kaisen donya (wholesaler in port) and sodai (representative of consignors) were dispatched to the coast near the accident site, where they investigated the extent of damage (this is called &apos;ura-aratame&apos;).</e>
<cmt>beginning of the sentence reworded, &quot;wrecked ship&quot; changed to &quot;shipwreck&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When there was a news about a shipwreck, gyogi (manager) of kaisen donya (wholesaler in port) and sodai (representative of consignors) were dispatched to the coast near the accident site, where they investigated the extent of damage (this is called &apos;ura-aratame&apos;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>浦役人が封印した残荷物、揚荷物を査収して、浦役人の連署した浦証文を受け取り、濡荷の臨時処分、積荷の再輸送、浦入費の支払いなど一切の処理を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They dealt with all the tasks such as verifying and accepting wrecked and discharged cargo from the wrecked ship, which had been sealed by the port officials, receiving Ura-shomon (a certification of the wreckage) which was jointly-signed by the port officials, occasional disposing of wet cargo, reshipping of cargo, and paying moorage at the port.</e>
<cmt>浦役人→定訳不明浦証文→定訳不明浦入費→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They dealt with all tasks such as verifying and accepting wrecked and unloaded cargo from the wrecked ship, which had been sealed by the port officials, receiving ura-shomon (a certification of the wreckage) which was jointly signed by the port officials, occasional disposing of wet cargo, reshipping of the cargo, and paying moorage at the port.</e>
<cmt>&quot;all the tasks&quot; changed to &quot;all tasks,&quot; &quot;discharged cargo&quot; changed to &quot;unloaded cargo,&quot; &quot;jointly-signed&quot; changed to &quot;jointly signed&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They dealt with all tasks such as verifying and accepting wrecked and unloaded cargo from the wrecked ship, which had been sealed by the port officials, receiving ura-shomon (a certification of the wreckage) which was jointly signed by the port officials, occasional disposing of wet cargo, reshipping of the cargo, and paying moorage at the port.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="13">
<j>浦証文は、通航の浦港で、当地の代官、手代、庄屋などの立ち会いの上、難船の残存荷物、船具などを証明したもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ura-shomon was a bond to certify wrecked cargo and fittings left on a wrecked ship, which was issued in the presence of such persons as a magistrate, a clerk, and a village headman.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ura-shomon was a bond to certify wrecked cargo and fittings left on a wrecked ship, which was issued in the presence of such persons as a magistrate, a clerk, and a village headman.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ura-shomon was a bond to certify wrecked cargo and fittings left on a wrecked ship, which was issued in the presence of such persons as a magistrate, a clerk, and a village headman.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>江戸幕府は、船員がしばしば浦々の者と共謀して、難破のために投荷をしたと偽って貨物を盗むのを防ぐために、寛永13年8月、難船取締令を発布。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In August 1636, the Edo bakufu issued an order of controlling wrecked ships to prevent crew members of a ship from stealing cargo on the ship in conspiracy with port workers by telling a lie that as their ship was wrecked, they threw away the cargo into the sea.</e>
<cmt>浦々の者→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In August 1636, the Edo bakufu issued a shipwreck control ordinance in order to prevent crew members of the wrecked ship from stealing the ship&apos;s cargo, because they often conspired with the port workers, lying that they had to throw the cargo into the sea because of the shipwreck.</e>
<cmt>sentence reworded</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In August 1636, the Edo bakufu issued a shipwreck control ordinance in order to prevent crew members of the wrecked ship from stealing the ship&apos;s cargo, because they often conspired with the port workers, lying that they had to throw the cargo into the sea because of the shipwreck.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>浦々に掲示し（「浦高札」という）、難船を立証するにはこの証文を必要とするとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bond (called &apos;Ura-Kousatsu&apos;), which was posted on the bulletin board, was required to verify a shipwreck.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bond (called &apos;Ura-Kousatsu&apos;), which was posted on the bulletin board, was required to verify a shipwreck.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bond (called &apos;Ura-Kousatsu&apos;), which was posted on the bulletin board, was required to verify a shipwreck.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>全てこれによって船頭、荷主の責任、損害の負担が定められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In all cases, responsibilities and shares of burden of damages borne by a boatman and a consignor were decided by the bond.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In all cases, cargo owner&apos;s and the captain&apos;s responsibilities for the damages were decided by the bond.</e>
<cmt>sentence reworded</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In all cases, cargo owner&apos;s and the captain&apos;s responsibilities for the damages were decided by the bond.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="17">
<j>事例</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Case example</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Case example</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Case example</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>2008年2月19日、海上自衛隊のイージス艦あたご (護衛艦)が千葉県の野島崎沖で漁船と衝突（イージス艦衝突事故）、乗組員の親子2人が行方不明となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 19, 2008, the Aegis (escort ship) Atago of Japan&apos;s Marine Defense Force collided with a fishing boat off the coast of Nojimazaki, Chiba Prefecture, where two crew members of the fishing boat, who were actually a father and son, went missing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 19, 2008, the Aegis (escort ship) Atago of Japan&apos;s Marine Defense Force collided with a fishing boat off the coast of Nojimazaki, Chiba Prefecture, where two crew members of the fishing boat, who were actually a father and son, went missing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 19, 2008, the Aegis (escort ship) Atago of Japan&apos;s Marine Defense Force collided with a fishing boat off the coast of Nojimazaki, Chiba Prefecture, where two crew members of the fishing boat, who were actually a father and son, went missing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>海上自衛隊、海上保安庁および地元の漁業協同組合による懸命な捜索にもかかわらず親子は発見なかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Despite desperate searches by the Marine Self-Defense Force, Japan Coast Guard and the local fishermen&apos;s association, the father and son were not found, and when the fishermen&apos;s association gave up searching for them on February 25, such ceremonies as reciting sutra and offering of flowers were conducted as Urajimai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Despite the desperate search by the Marine Self-Defense Force, Japan Coast Guard and the local fishermen&apos;s association, the father and son were not found.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処, &quot;desperate searches&quot; changed to &quot;the desperate search&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Despite the desperate search by the Marine Self-Defense Force, Japan Coast Guard and the local fishermen&apos;s association, the father and son were not found.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>2月25日を持って漁協での捜索を打ち切り、浦終いとして読経や海への献花などの儀式が執り行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the fishermen&apos;s association gave up the search on February 25, ceremonies such as reciting Buddhist sutras and offering of flowers were conducted as urajimai.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処　&quot;such ceremonies&quot; changed to &quot;ceremonies such,&quot; &quot;Buddhist&quot; added before &quot;sutra&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the fishermen&apos;s association gave up the search on February 25, ceremonies such as reciting Buddhist sutras and offering of flowers were conducted as urajimai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Libertas(id:40611), 経済準学士(id:22656), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>