<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>納豆</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Natto (fermented soybeans)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Natto (fermented soybeans)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Natto (fermented soybeans)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>納豆（なっとう）は大豆を納豆菌によって発酵させた日本の食品。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Natto is a Japanese food produced by fermenting soybeans with bacillus subtilis natto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Natto is a Japanese food produced by fermenting soybeans with bacillus subtilis natto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Natto is a Japanese food produced by fermenting soybeans with bacillus subtilis natto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>現在では単に「納豆」と言えば、糸引き納豆の事を指すのが一般的である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today, when we simply say &quot;natto&quot;, it generally refers to itohiki-natto (sticky natto).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, when we simply say &quot;natto&quot; it generally refers to itohiki-natto (sticky natto).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, when we simply say &apos;natto&apos; it generally refers to itohiki-natto (sticky natto).</e>
<cmt>括弧を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>糸引き納豆以外の種類は種類を参照のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For other types than itohiki-natto, refer to the section of types.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For types other than itohiki-natto, refer to the corresponding section.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For types other than itohiki-natto, refer to the corresponding section.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>日本全国において食べられているが、以前は近畿地方・四国地方ではあまり消費されなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Natto is eaten nationwide in Japan, but, in the past, it was not consumed so much in Kinki and Shikoku regions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Natto is eaten throughout Japan, but in the past it was not consumed as much in the Kinki and Shikoku regions.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Natto is eaten throughout Japan, but it was not consumed as much in the Kinki and Shikoku regions before.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>製法や菌の改良などで匂いを少なくしたり、含まれる成分の内「ナットウキナーゼ」の健康増進効果がテレビなどのメディア (媒体)で伝えられるようになった結果、1990年代後半にはほぼ日本中で消費されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result of decrease in smell by improving the manufacturing method and bacteria, and partly because that medias such as TV reported the effect for promoting health of one of components of natto &quot;nattokinase&quot;, since the latter half of 1990s, natto became to be consumed almost all over Japan. of</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result of the reduction in odor achieved through improved manufacturing methods and bacteria, and partly because TV and other media have reported the health benefits of one component, &quot;nattokinase,&quot; since the latter half of the 1990s natto has come to be consumed in nearly all of Japan.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result of the reduction in odor achieved through the improvement in manufacturing methods and bacteria, and partly due to the TV and other media reports regarding the health benefits of one of the components of natto, &apos;nattokinase&apos; natto came to be consumed in nearly all parts of the country since the latter half of the 1990s.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。「&amp;apos;」→「&apos;」に修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>7月10日は「納豆の日」とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">July 10 is designated for &quot;Natto no Hi&quot; (day of natto).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">July 10 is designated as &quot;Natto no Hi&quot; (day of natto).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">July 10 is designated as &apos;Natto no Hi&apos; (day of natto).</e>
<cmt>括弧を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>これは1981年、関西での納豆消費拡大のため、関西納豆工業協同組合がなっ(7)とう(10)の語呂合わせで制定したものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was determined by Kansai Natto Kogyo Kyodokumiai in 1981 by making sound connection (nat (= 7) to (= 10)) in order to promote consumption of natto in Kansai region.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was determined by Kansai Natto Kogyo Kyodokumiai in 1981, which made a sound connection (nat (= 7) to (= 10)) in order to promote the consumption of natto in the Kansai region.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was determined by Kansai Natto Kogyo Kyodokumiai (Kansai Natto Processors Cooperative Association) in 1981, which made a sound connection (nat (= 7) to (= 10)) in order to promote the consumption of natto in the Kansai region.</e>
<cmt>関西納豆工業協同組合を補足しました。関西納豆工業協同組合→Kansai Natto Processors Cooperative Association　[定訳不明]</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>1992年、全国納豆工業協同組合連合会が改めて「納豆の日」として制定した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1992, Zenkoku Natto Kogyo Kyodo Kumiai Rengokai renewedly determined as &quot;Natto no Hi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1992, Zenkoku Natto Kogyo Kyodo Kumiai Rengokai renewed the designation as &quot;Natto no Hi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1992, Zenkoku Natto Kogyo Kyodo Kumiai Rengokai (National Federation of Natto Processors Cooperative Associations) formally designated the &apos;Natto no Hi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。「&amp;apos;」→「&apos;」に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>しかし「納豆」「納豆汁」が冬の季語である事や、「納豆時に医者要らず」という諺があったように、元々納豆の時期は冬とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as &quot;natto&quot; and &quot;natto jiru (miso soup with natto)&quot; are the season words for winter and there is a proverb &quot;In natto season, no need for a doctor&quot;, originally, the season for natto is understood as winter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as &quot;natto&quot; and &quot;natto jiru (miso soup with natto)&quot; are the seasonal words for winter and there is the proverb, &quot;In natto season, no need for a doctor,&quot; the season for natto has been taken to be winter.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as &apos;natto&apos; and &apos;natto jiru&apos; (miso soup with natto) are the season words for winter for haiku (Japanese seventeen-syllable poem) and also as there is a proverb saying that &apos;in the natto season, there is no need for a doctor,&apos; winter had been the season for natto.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。「&amp;apos;」→「&apos;」に修正、クォーテーションの位置を移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>そのため7月に納豆の日を設けることには異論もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, there are objecting opinions against determining the Natto no Hi for July.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus there are objections to designating July as the time for Natto no Hi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus there are objections to designating July as the time for Natto no Hi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>栄養・効果</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nutrition and effects</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nutrition and effects</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nutrition and effects</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>血液凝固因子を作るのに不可欠なビタミンKや大豆由来のタンパク質も豊富であり、現在でも重要なタンパク質源となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Natto is rich in vitamin K, which is indispensable for producing blood coagulation factors and protein derived from soybean and it is still important source for protein.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Natto is rich in vitamin K, which is indispensable for producing blood coagulation factors and assimilating the protein derived from soybeans, so the food is still considered an important source of protein.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As natto is rich in vitamin K which is vital for producing blood coagulation factors and the protein derived from soybeans, the food is still considered as an important source of protein.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>総務省統計局の全国物価統計調査の調査品目にも採用されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has been included in the items for research for the national price statistics survey by the Bureau of Statistics of the Ministry of Public Management, Home Affairs, Posts and Telecommunications.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has been included in the items of research in the national price-statistics survey conducted by the Bureau of Statistics of the Ministry of Public Management, Home Affairs, Posts and Telecommunications.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has been included in the research items of the national price-statistics survey conducted by the Bureau of Statistics of the Ministry of Internal Affairs and Communications.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>食物繊維は100グラム中に4.9～7.6グラムと豊富に含まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Natto also abounds in dietary fiber and contains 4.9 to 7.6 gram in 100 gram.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Natto is also abundant in dietary fiber; in fact, 100 grams of natto will contain 4.9 to 7.6 grams of fiber.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Natto is also abundant in dietary fiber; in fact, 100 grams of natto will contain 4.9 to 7.6 grams of fiber.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>食物繊維はオリゴ糖等と共にプレバイオティクスと呼ばれる腸内環境に有用な成分である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dietary fiber, together with oligosaccharide, etc., is one of ingredient called prebiotics, which is useful for enteral environment.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dietary fiber, together with oligosaccharide, etc., is among the so-called prebiotics, which are useful for the gastric environment.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dietary fiber is, along with oligosaccharide, etc., among the so-called prebiotics which are useful for the intestinal environment.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>納豆菌はプロバイオティクスと呼ばれ、これも腸内環境に有用と考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bacillus subtilis natto is called probiotics and is understood useful for enteral environment.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bacillus subtilis natto is called a probiotic and is considered useful for the gastric environment.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bacillus subtilis natto is a probiotic and is also considered useful for the intestinal environment.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>O157を抗菌することがわかっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is known that it is antibacterial against O157.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is known to function as an antibacterial against O157.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is known to function as an antibacterial against O157.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="17">
<j>納豆には血栓を溶かす酵素が含まれており、納豆の摂取によって血栓が溶けた場合の分解成分であるFDPが血中に増えることが確認されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Natto contains enzyme that dissolves blood clot and it has been made sure that, if natto is eaten, FDP, that is cracked component when blood clot is dissolved, increases in the blood.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Natto contains an enzyme that dissolves blood clots, and it has been confirmed that if natto is eaten, FDP--which is the cracked component resulting from the dissolution of clotting--increases in the blood.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Natto contains an enzyme that dissolves blood clots, and it has been confirmed that when a person eats natto, an FDP which is a cracked component resulting from the dissolution of clot increases in his/her blood.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>名称</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Name</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Name</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Name</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="18">
<j>納豆は元来精進料理として納所（なっしょ、寺院の倉庫）で作られた食品であり、これが名前の由来である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally, natto is a food produced in nassho (nassho (temple storage)) as a vegetarian dish and this is the origin of its name.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally, natto was produced in nassho (nassho (temple storage)) as a vegetarian dish, and this is how the name originated.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally, natto was produced in nassho (temple storage) as a vegetarian dish, and this is how the name originated.</e>
<cmt>ダブりを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="19">
<j>「本来は豆を納めたものが『納豆』、豆を腐らせたものが『豆腐』だったのが、いつの間にか名前が取り違えられた」などとも言われるが、近代になって作られた俗説に過ぎない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said &quot;Originally, &quot;natto&quot; is stored beans and &quot;tofu&quot; is addled beans, but at some time or other, those names were exchanged,&quot; but this story is a common belief formed in the modern era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that originally &quot;natto&quot; meant stored beans and &quot;tofu&quot; meant addled beans, but at a certain point those names were exchanged; this story, however, is a common belief that emerged during the modern era.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that originally &quot;natto&quot; meant stored soybeans and &quot;tofu&quot; meant fermented soybeans and at a certain point those names were exchanged; this theory, however, is just a popular saying that emerged during the modern era.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。「&amp;quot;」→「&quot;」に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>漢語における豆腐の「腐」は腐る意味ではなく、チーズのように凝固した食品（英語のカード (食品) curd にあたる）を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The character &quot;腐&quot; in Chinese word tofu does not mean to go bad but it refers to curdled food such as cheese (corresponding to curd in English).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The character &quot;腐&quot; in Chinese word tofu doesn&apos;t mean &quot;to go bad&quot; but instead refers to curdled food such as cheese (corresponding to &quot;curd&quot; in English).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The character &apos;腐&apos; in Chinese word tofu doesn&apos;t mean &quot;to go bad&quot;; instead, it refers to curdled food such as cheese (corresponding to &quot;curd&quot; in English).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。「&amp;apos;」→「&apos;」、「&amp;quot;」→「&quot;」に修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>作り方</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Producing method</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Production method</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Production method</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="21">
<j>伝統的な納豆の作り方は、蒸した大豆を稲の藁で包み、40度程度に保温し約1日ほど置いておく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Traditional method for producing natto is to wrap steamed soybeans with a rice straw wrapper and maintain the temperature around 40 degree and leave it for approximately one day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The traditional method for producing natto is to enfold the steamed soybeans in a rice-straw wrapper, maintain the temperature at around 40 degrees and leave it for approximately one day.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The traditional method for producing natto is to enfold the steamed soybeans in a rice-straw wrapper, maintain the temperature at around forty degrees and leave it for approximately one day.</e>
<cmt>数字をスペルアウトしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>稲藁に付着している納豆菌が大豆に移行し、増殖することによって発酵が起こり、納豆ができあがる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As bacillus subtilis natto adhered to rice straw is transferred to soybeans and increases, fermentation occurred and natto is completed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the bacillus subtilis natto adhered to rice straw is transferred to the soybeans and increases, fermentation occurs and the natto is completed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rice straw naturally contains the bacillus subtilis natto, which is supplied to the soybeans, the fermentation occurs and natto is done.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="23">
<j>近年では、大量生産の要求に応えるため、あるいは伝統的な製法では良質の藁を確保すること等が困難なこともあり、純粋培養した納豆菌を用いる製造が主流である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In recent years, in order to meet the requirement of mass production, or as it is difficult to obtain good quality straws for traditional method, the mainstream is to use pure cultured bacillus subtilis natto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In recent years, in order to meet the requirements of mass production, or because of the difficulty in obtaining good-quality straw for the traditional method, the mainstream practice has been to use pure cultured bacillus subtilis natto.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In recent years, in order to meet the requirements of mass production, or because of the difficulty in obtaining good-quality straw for the traditional method, the mainstream practice has been to use pure cultured bacillus subtilis natto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>つまり、蒸した大豆を発泡スチロール容器や紙パックに装填し、これに純粋培養した納豆菌の分散液をかける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In other words, steamed soybeans are packed in formed polystyrene or paper container and dispersion liquid containing pure cultured bacillus subtilis natto is sprayed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In other words, steamed soybeans are packed in formed polystyrene or paper containers and a dispersion liquid containing pure cultured bacillus subtilis natto is sprayed onto them.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In other words, steamed soybeans are packed in formed polystyrene or paper containers and a dispersion liquid containing pure cultured bacillus subtilis natto is sprayed onto them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>これを適温で保温すると、納豆菌が増殖し発酵する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If it is kept to appropriate temperature, bacillus subtilis natto increased and fermentation occurs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If it is kept at the appropriate temperature, the bacillus subtilis natto increase and fermentation will occur.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If it is kept at the appropriate temperature, the bacillus subtilis natto increases and fermentation will occur.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>流通段階での発酵の進み具合も勘案し、適度な発酵に至った段階で、消費期限やブランド銘が記された包装を施し出荷する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taking into consideration progress of fermentation in the distribution stage, it is packed as a package having expiry period and brand indicated, when it reached appropriate degree of fermentation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taking into consideration the progress of fermentation at the distribution stage, it is packed as a package having an expiry period and brand indication when it reaches the appropriate degree of fermentation.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Natto is packed and shipped in a package which has an expiry date and brand indication when it reaches the appropriate degree of fermentation taking into consideration the progress of fermentation during transportation.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>納豆と衛生面</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Natto and hygienic aspects</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Natto and its hygienic aspects</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Natto and its hygienic aspects</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="27">
<j>製法にかかわらず、業として納豆を製造するには、食品衛生法に基づき都道府県知事の許可が必要である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Regardless of the manufacturing method, in order to manufacture natto as a business, the permission from the governor of the prefecture is necessary under the Food Sanitation Act.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regardless of the manufacturing method, in order to produce natto as a business, permission from the governor of the prefecture is necessary under the Food Sanitation Act.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regardless of the manufacturing method, in order to produce natto as a business, permission from the governor of the prefecture is necessary under the Food Sanitation Act.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="28">
<j>市販の納豆の大部分は、純粋培養した納豆菌を種菌（たねきん）として用いる製法によって製造されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most of natto on the market are produced by a manufacturing method in which pure cultured bacillus subtilis natto is used as seed.,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bulk of natto on the market is produced through a manufacturing method in which pure cultured bacillus subtilis natto is used as seed.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bulk of natto on the market is produced through a manufacturing method in which pure cultured bacillus subtilis natto is used as seed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="29">
<j>稲藁を用いた伝統的な製法による納豆も少ないながら製造され流通している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although volume is very small, natto by traditional method in which rice straw is used is still produced and distributed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the volume is very small, natto produced through the traditional method in which rice straw is used is still distributed.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the volume is very small, natto produced through the traditional method in which rice straw is used is still distributed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>この製法での納豆菌は耐熱性の高い芽胞となって藁に付着している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this manufacturing method, bacillus subtilis natto is adhered to straw as highly heat-resistant spore.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this manufacturing method, bacillus subtilis natto is adhered to straw as a spore that&apos;s highly resistant to heat.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this manufacturing method, bacillus subtilis natto is adhered to straw as a spore that&apos;s highly resistant to heat.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>100°Cで沸騰している湯に数分浸すと大部分の雑菌が煮沸されて死滅し、納豆菌芽胞が生き残る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If it is dipped in boiling water of 100 °C for few minutes, most of sundry germs are boiled and become extinct, and spores of bacillus subtilis natto survive.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If it is dipped in boiling water of 100oC for a few minutes, most of the sundry germs will boiled and die, but the spores of bacillus subtilis natto will survive.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If it is dipped in boiling water of 100°C for a few minutes, most of the sundry germs will boil and die, but the spores of bacillus subtilis natto will survive.</e>
<cmt>Make sure that the actual degree symbol is used though: a similar looking Greek letter is not a suitable alternative!</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>その後、ゆでた大豆を藁と接触させ37度から42度に保つと、納豆菌は芽胞から発芽し増殖を始める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, boiled soybeans are placed in contact with the straw and maintain the temperature in a range from thirty-seven degree to forty-two degree, bacillus subtilis natto germinate from the spores and start increasing.,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The boiled soybeans are then placed in contact with the straw and the temperature is maintained in the range of 37o to 42o, whereupon the bacillus subtilis natto germinates from the spores and starts to increase.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The boiled soybeans are then placed in contact with the straw and the temperature is maintained in the range of 37 to 42°C, whereupon the bacillus subtilis natto germinates from the spores and starts to increase.</e>
<cmt>Make sure that the actual degree symbol is used though: a similar looking Greek letter is not a suitable alternative!</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>そして、その旺盛な繁殖力で、死滅を逃れた他の芽胞菌類に先んじて栄養となる物質を消費し、他の微生物の繁殖を阻む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And, with its active propagating power, bacillus subtilis natto consume materials, which become nutrition, in advance of other sporular bacteria that have survived preventing increase of other microorgasms.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, given its active propagating power, the bacillus subtilis natto consumes materials, which become nutrition, in advance of other sporular bacteria that have survived, thus preventing the increase of other microorganisms.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, given its active propagating power, the bacillus subtilis natto consumes nutrition materials ahead of other sporular bacteria that have survived, thus preventing the increase of other microorganisms.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="34">
<j>いずれにせよ、日本国内で流通する市販品は、食品としての基準に適合するよう管理され製造されていると見做して良い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Anyway, commercialized products, which are distributed in Japan can be understood that they are manufactured under control to meet standards for food.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At any rate, the commercialized products that are distributed in Japan can be understood as being manufactured under control sufficient to satisfy the food standards.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At any rate, the commercialized products that are distributed in Japan can be understood as being manufactured under control sufficient to satisfy the food standards.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="35">
<j>なお、敢えて自家で納豆を作ることを試みる場合には、いくつかの留意点がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When you dare to try manufacturing natto at home, there are several precautions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When attempting to produce natto at home, several precautions must be taken.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When attempting to produce natto at home, several precautions must be taken.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>納豆菌は酸にはやや弱く、乳酸菌の活動によって生まれる乳酸によって活動が阻害される事がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bacillus subtilis natto is rather weak against acid and sometimes its activity is interfered by lactic acid produced by activity of lactobacillus.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bacillus subtilis natto is rather weak against acid, and sometimes its activity is hindered by the lactic acid produced through the activity of lactobacillus.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bacillus subtilis natto is rather weak against acid, and sometimes its activity is hindered by the lactic acid produced through the activity of lactobacillus.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>また技術開発の結果普及した匂いの弱い種の納豆では、活動がさほどおう盛ではない菌株が用いられており、環境によっては雑菌が繁殖する余地がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For natto with less smell which has become popular as a result of technical development, bacterial strain of which activity is not strong is used and, therefore, there is a room for sundry bacteria to increase depending on environment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For natto with less odor, which has become popular as a result of technical development, a bacterial strain that is less active is used; consequently there is a room for sundry bacteria to increase, depending on the environment.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, a less active bacterial strain is used for natto with less odor which has become popular as a result of technical development, and such natto may consequently let sundry bacteria grow depending on the environment.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>また、納豆菌の天敵として細菌寄生性ウイルスのバクテリオファージがあり、ファージ活動後に雑菌が繁殖する事もありうる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a natural enemy of bacillus subtilis natto, there is bacteriophage of bacterium parasitic virus and after the activity of the phage, sundry bacteria may increase.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a natural enemy of bacillus subtilis natto, there is bacteriophage of bacterium parasitic virus, but after the activity of the phage, sundry bacteria may increase.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bacteriophage (viruses that infest bacteria) is a natural enemy of bacillus subtilis natto, and sundry bacteria may increase after the phage became active.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>特に納豆菌繁殖前の茹でた大豆には雑菌が極めて繁殖しやすい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In boiled soybean before bacillus subtilis natto increases, especially, sundry bacteria quite easily increase.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Particularly in the case of boiled soybean before the increase of bacillus subtilis natto, sundry bacteria can proliferate quite easily.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sundry bacteria can proliferate quite easily especially in the case of boiled soybean before the increase of bacillus subtilis natto.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>自家製といえども食用に供するには衛生面でのそれなりの配慮が必要である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even if it is home-made, minimum consideration for hygienic aspects are required when it is eaten.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even if it is home-made, minimal consideration for hygienic aspects is required when it is eaten.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even if it is home-made for the home consumption, some consideration needs to be given for hygienic aspects.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="41">
<j>納豆が苦手なひとのなかには納豆を指して「腐った煮豆」などと形容する例も見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In certain cases, those who do not like natto calls natto &quot;rotten boiled soybean.&quot;and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In certain cases, people who don&apos;t like natto call it &quot;rotten boiled soybeans,&quot; and so on.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In certain cases, people who don&apos;t like natto call it &apos;rotten boiled soybeans,&apos; and so on.</e>
<cmt>括弧を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>しかし腐敗と発酵との違いは、専ら、微生物が作用した結果が有害（無益）なものかあるいは有用なものかという価値判断に基づくものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, difference between rottenness and fermentation is based on the value judgment whether or not result of action of microorganism is harmful (fruitless) or useful.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the difference between rottenness and fermentation is based on the value judgment as to whether or not the result of the action of microorganisms is harmful (fruitless) or useful.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the difference between rottenness and fermentation is based on the value judgment as to whether or not the result of the action of microorganisms is harmful (fruitless) or useful.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>したがって、食品として十分衛生的に製造され、（世界的に見れば一部かもしれないが）多くの人に嗜好され、栄養的に価値が高い納豆は優れた「発酵」食品である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, natto is an excellent &quot;fermented food&quot; because it is produced in sufficiently sanitary manner as a food and liked by many persons (although it may be only a part, if viewed globally) and has high value from the nutrition point of view.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, natto is an excellent &quot;fermented food&quot; because it&apos;s produced in a sufficiently sanitary manner as a food; it&apos;s enjoyed by many people (although it may be only a part, if viewed globally) and has high nutritional value.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, natto is an excellent &apos;fermented food&apos; because it is produced as a food in a sufficiently sanitary manner, is enjoyed by many people (although it may be only a part of the world), and has high nutritional value.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。「&amp;apos;」→「&apos;」に修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="44">
<j>日本酒を作る際に、熱に強い芽胞を形成しかつ繁殖力も旺盛な納豆菌が蒸米に混入すると、コウジカビよりも先に繁殖し駆逐し得る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a process of producing sake (Japanese liquor), if bacillus subtilis natto, which forms highly heat-resistant spore and has active propagating power, is mixed in steamed rice, it may increase in advance of Aspergillus oryzae and cleanse the latter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the process of producing sake (a Japanese liquor), if bacillus subtilis natto, which forms highly heat-resistant spores and has active propagating power, is mixed into steamed rice, it may increase in advance of Aspergillus oryzae and neutralize the latter.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If bacillus subtilis natto, which forms highly heat-resistant spores and has an active propagating power, is mixed into steamed rice in the process of producing sake (a Japanese liquor), it may increase faster than Aspergillus oryzae and neutralize the latter.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>この場合納豆菌は粘り麹を生む好ましからざる雑菌となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this case, bacillus subtilis natto is an undesirable sundry bacterium that generates sticky rice molt. [粘り麹:定訳不明です:]</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this case, bacillus subtilis natto is an undesirable sundry bacterium that generates sticky rice malt.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In such a case, bacillus subtilis natto becomes an unwanted sundry bacterium that generates sticky rice malt.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>酒造り職人の食卓において、日本酒の仕込み期間中の納豆は禁忌とされている所以である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is the reason why it is prohibited, during the period for preparation for sake brewing, to serve natto on the table of person who is involved in sake brewing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is the reason it is prohibited, during the period of preparation for sake brewing, to serve natto on the table of a person involved in that process.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is the reason why eating natto is prohibited for sake brewing professionals during the preparation period for the sake brewing.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>食べ方</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">How to eat</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">How to eat natto</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">How to eat natto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="47">
<j>最も典型的な食べ方はいわゆる納豆ご飯で、白米を炊いたご飯と、納豆を一緒に食べるもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The most representative way of eating is so-called natto gohan (literally, boiled rice with natto), and this means to eat steamed polished rice together with natto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The most typical way to eat natto is the so-called natto gohan (literally, boiled rice with natto), in which one eats it along with steamed, polished rice.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The most typical way to eat natto is the so-called natto gohan (literally, boiled rice with natto), in which one eats it along with steamed, polished rice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>これは一般的に醤油やタレ、からしを加える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Generally, natto is mixed with soy sauce or other type of sauce and mustard and stirred until sticky threads appear before eating.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Generally, natto is combined with soy sauce or another type of sauce and mustard; the mixture is stirred until sticky threads appear, after which it&apos;s eaten.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Generally, natto is combined with soy sauce or another type of sauce and mustard.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。一原文一訳文例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>かき混ぜ、粘性のある糸が現れてから食べる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The mixture is stirred until sticky threads appear before eating.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。一原文一訳文例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>鶏卵やウズラの卵、ネギ、ミョウガ、大根おろし、鰹節など、様々な食品を混ぜて食べることも多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is often eaten mixed with various foods such as egg of hen or quail, leek, Japanese ginger, grated daikon radish and katsuobushi (small pieces of sliced dried bonito).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is often eaten mixed with various foods such as egg of hen or quail, leek, Japanese ginger, grated daikon radish and katsuobushi (small pieces of sliced dried bonito).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is often eaten mixed with various foods such as egg of hen or quail, leek, Japanese ginger, grated daikon radish and katsuobushi (small pieces of sliced dried bonito).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>食文化としては、ご飯にかけずに納豆だけを食べる地方の存在が知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As food culture, it is known that there is a area where natto is not eaten by putting on steamed rice but independently and in a part of Hokkaido and Tohoku region, sugar is added.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a food culture, it is known that there is an area where natto isn&apos;t served over steamed rice but is eaten independently; in parts of Hokkaido and the Tohoku region, sugar is added.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is known that in some areas natto isn&apos;t served over cooked rice but is eaten independently.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。一原文一訳文例外処理「&amp;apos;」→「&apos;」に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>また、北海道・東北地方の一部で砂糖を加えることが知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also known that in some parts of Hokkaido and the Tohoku region, sugar is added to natto.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。一原文一訳文例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="53">
<j>ネギやからしを加えると納豆のアンモニア臭を抑える効果があり、優れた薬味といえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If leek or mustard is added, they suppress smell of ammonium in natto and, therefore, they can be deemed wonderful spice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If leek or mustard is added, these ingredients will suppress smell of the ammonium in the natto; consequently, they can be considered useful as spices.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Leek and mustard are considered as excellent condiments for natto because they can reduce its ammonium smell.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>ネギやからしを途中で加えずに、蕎麦のネギやわさびと同様に最後に少しだけ載せた方がおいしいという人もいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some say that it tastes better if leek or mustard is not added in the midway but put on the top in small quantity at the end similar to leek or wasabi (Japanese horseradish) in eating soba (buckwheat noodle).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some say it tastes better if leek or mustard isn&apos;t added at the midpoint but instead placed on the top in a small quantity at the end, similar to the addition of leek or wasabi (Japanese horseradish) when eating soba (buckwheat noodles).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some say it tastes better if leek or mustard isn&apos;t added while stirring but small quantity of them are placed on the top after stirring, similar to the manner of adding leek or wasabi (Japanese horseradish) when eating soba (buckwheat noodles).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。「&amp;apos;」→「&apos;」に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>臭いが苦手の人の中には、からしの代わりにワサビを載せる人もいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some persons who does not like the smell of natto, put wasabi instead of mustard.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some people who don&apos;t like the smell of natto use wasabi instead of mustard.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some people who don&apos;t like the smell of natto use wasabi instead of mustard.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="56">
<j>納豆を美味しく食べるためには良く練ることである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order to enjoy eating natto, it is important to knead sufficiently.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to enjoy eating natto, it is important to knead it sufficiently.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to enjoy eating natto, it is important to knead it sufficiently.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>これは、先にタレなどを加えると水分過多となってしまい、グルタミン酸（旨味成分）を含む粘りがあまり出なくなってしまうからである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is because that, if sauce is added in advance, there is too much moisture and it prevent generating sticky substance, which includes glutamic acid (umami ingredient).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is because, if sauce is added in advance, the excessive moisture will prevent the generation of the sticky substance that includes glutamic acid (umami ingredient).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is because the excessive moisture could prevent the generation of the sticky substance that includes glutamic acid (umami ingredient) if sauce is added before stirring.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>また、100回ほど混ぜると、ポリグルタミン酸をグルタミン酸に変えることができるという根拠のない迷信が伝わっているが、実際にはそこまで混ぜなくてもグルタミン酸に変わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although there is a groundless superstition that if it is stirred for around a hundred times, polyglutamic acid can be changed into glutamic acid, but it is changed into glutamic acid even if it is not stirred so much.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although there is a groundless superstition that if it&apos;s stirred approximately 100 times the polyglutamic acid can change into glutamic acid; however, it can change into glutamic acid even if it isn&apos;t stirred that much.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although there is a groundless belief that if it&apos;s stirred approximately 100 times the polyglutamic acid can be changed into glutamic acid, changing polyglutamic acid into glutamic actually does not take that much stirring.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。「&amp;apos;」→「&apos;」に修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="59">
<j>和風スパゲッティのトッピング、お好み焼きの具、カレーライス、ラーメンにかけるなどとしても用いられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Natto is also used as topping for Japanese-style spaghetti and a material for okonomiyaki (savory pancake with various ingredients) or used for curry and rice or ramen (Chinese soup noodle).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Natto is also used as topping for Japanese-style spaghetti and as a material for okonomiyaki (savory pancake with various ingredients), or it is used in curry and rice or ramen (Chinese soup noodles).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Natto is also used as a topping for Japanese-style spaghetti, an ingredient for okonomiyaki (savory pancake with various ingredients), or a topping for curry and rice or ramen (Chinese soup noodles).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>また納豆を叩き刻んで味噌汁に入れた納豆汁は、江戸時代までは納豆ご飯よりも頻繁に食卓に上っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Natto jiru, which is prepared by adding finely chopped natto to miso soup was eaten more often that natto gohan in the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Natto jiru, which is prepared by adding finely chopped natto to miso soup, was eaten more often that natto gohan during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Natto jiru, which is prepared by adding finely chopped natto to miso soup, was eaten more often that natto gohan during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="61">
<j>加熱調理については、匂いが強くなるので好みが分かれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As cooking by heating increases the smell, some are while some are against.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because cooking by heating causes the odor to increase, some favor that method but others oppose it.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because cooking natto with heat can cause a stronger odor, some favor cooked natto but others don&apos;t.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>ただし納豆天ぷらの場合、油で揚げることによって匂いがあらかた飛び、さらに天ぷらの衣で匂いが抑えられるのでむしろ食べやすくなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the case of natto tenpura, however, a large part of smell disappeared by frying with oil and smell is suppressed by the coating of batter, it becomes easier to eat.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in the case of natto tempura, a considerable proportion of the odor disappears as it is fried in oil; the odor is further suppressed by the coating of batter, so it becomes easier to eat.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in the case of natto tempura, a considerable proportion of the odor disappears by being deed fried and by the coating of batter, so it becomes easier to eat.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>販売形態</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Form of sales</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Form of sale</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Form of sale</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>販売方法</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Selling method</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Selling method</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Selling method</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="63">
<j>近年では減っているが、「納豆売り」と呼ばれる行商人が納豆を売り歩くこともあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the number is decreased in recent years, peddlers called &quot;natto uri&quot; peddled natto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the number has decreased in recent years, traditionally peddlers called &quot;natto uri&quot; would sell natto.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the number has decreased in recent years, traditionally peddlers called &apos;natto uri&apos; used to sell natto on the road.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。「&amp;apos;」→「&apos;」に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>売り声は「なっと〜〜、なっと〜〜ィ（語尾をあげる）」というものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Peddler&apos;s cry was &quot;Natto, natto, natto; natto, natto, natto, i&quot; (raising at the end).,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The peddler&apos;s cry was &quot;Natto, natto, natto; natto, natto, natto, i&quot; (with a rise in pitch at the end).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The peddler&apos;s cry was &apos;Natto, natto, natto; natto, natto, natto, i&apos; (with a rise in pitch at the end).</e>
<cmt>括弧を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="65">
<j>現在では主にスーパーマーケットの食料品売り場などで販売されている他、自動販売機での販売も増えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nowadays, while natto is mainly sold through food sections of supermarkets, sales through automatic selling machines has been increasing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, while natto is mainly sold in supermarkets, sales through automatic vending machines have increased.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, while natto is mainly sold in supermarkets, sales through automatic vending machines have increased.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>また、茨城県や埼玉県川越市などでは土産物（名産品）として販売している場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Ibaraki Prefecture and Kawagoe City, Saitama Prefecture, natto is sold in certain places as souvenir (local specialty).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Ibaraki Prefecture and Kawagoe City, Saitama Prefecture, natto is sold in certain places as a souvenir (local specialty).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Ibaraki Prefecture and Kawagoe City, Saitama Prefecture, natto is sold as souvenir (local specialty).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>包装方法</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Packaging method</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Packaging method</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Packaging method</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="67">
<j>伝統的な包装方法では、納豆の製造で使用した藁をそのまま藁苞（わらづと）とするか、経木に納豆を包んでいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In traditional packaging method, natto was wrapped with warazuto (straw wrapper) made with rice straw used in manufacture of natto or kyogi (paper-thin sheet of wood).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the traditional packaging method, natto was wrapped in warazuto (straw wrapper) made from rice straw used in the manufacture of natto or kyogi (paper-thin sheets of wood).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The traditional packaging methods were wrapping natto in warazuto (straw wrapper) used in the manufacture of natto or wrapping in kyogi (paper-thin sheets of wood).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="68">
<j>1960年代以降は、流通面で効率的なことなどから、一般的には発泡スチロール容器が使われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since 1960 and onward, foamed polystyrene containers have been generally used, because it is efficient in distribution.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since 1960 and onward, foamed polystyrene containers have generally been used, because such packaging facilitates efficient shipping and distribution.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since 1960 and onward, foamed polystyrene containers have generally been used, because such packaging facilitates efficient shipping and distribution.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>発泡スチロール容器は積み重ねられる形状になっていて、2～4つを1セットとして売られている場合も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Formed polystyrene containers are formed so that they can be piled up and in many cases sold as a set of two to four.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Formed polystyrene containers are formed so that they can be stacked up, and in many cases they&apos;re sold in sets of two or four.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Formed polystyrene containers are formed so that they can be stacked up, and in many cases they&apos;re sold in sets of two to four.</e>
<cmt>2～4　という表現に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>また、納豆を容器に入れたままかき混ぜて糸を引くことができるように、底に凹凸が付けられるなどの工夫もなされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has been devised to provide the bottom of container with unevenness so that natto can be stirred in the container until threads are generated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A method has been devised to make the bottom of container uneven so that the natto can be stirred in the container until threads are created.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A method has been devised to make the bottom of container hubbly so that it is easier to stir the natto in the container until threads appear.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="71">
<j>発泡スチロール容器の普及は納豆の消費拡大に大きく貢献した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Popularization of foamed polystyrene containers helped expansion of consumption of natto very much.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The popularization of foamed polystyrene containers has helped achieve a dramatic increase in the consumption of natto.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The popularization of foamed polystyrene containers has helped achieve a dramatic increase in the consumption of natto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>ただし、藁に比べると通気性が悪く、また納豆の臭い成分を吸着しにくいために、納豆独特の臭いがこもって強くなる傾向がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Compared to rice straw, however, it is less permeable and it absorbs less smelling ingredient of natto, unique smell of natto tends to become stronger.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Compared to rice straw, however, it is less permeable and it absorbs less of the natto&apos;s characteristic odor, so that this unique odor tends to become stronger.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Compared to rice straw, however, it is less permeable and absorbs less odor, and the unique odor tends to become stronger.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>こうした風味の違いや、「自然食品」的なイメージから、一部の高級品や自然志向の商品、土産物では現在でも藁や経木を使う場合がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of such difference in flavor and the &quot;natural food&quot;-like image, rice straws and kyogi are used even today for certain high class products, nature-oriented product and products for souvenir.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of such difference in flavor and the image of a &quot;natural food,&quot; rice straw and kyogi are used even today for certain high-class products, nature-oriented products and souvenirs.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of such difference in flavor and for the purpose of showing the image of a &apos;natural food,&apos; rice straw and kyogi are used even today for certain high-class products, nature-oriented products and souvenirs.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。「&amp;apos;」→「&apos;」に修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="74">
<j>なお、現在の納豆には、カラシと納豆用のタレが付属することが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Currently, mustard and sauce for natto is ususally attached to natto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Currently, mustard and sauce for natto are usually attached to the natto package.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Currently, mustard and sauce for natto are usually attached to the natto package.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="75">
<j>2008年には、ミツカンが新改良の発泡スチロール容器の製品を発売した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In j2008, Mitsukan launched products packed in newly improved foamed polystyrene.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 2008, Mitsukan launched products packed in an improved type of foamed polystyrene.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 2008, Mizkan launched products packed in an improved type of foamed polystyrene.</e>
<cmt>Mizkan　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>これは同梱のタレを従来の液状袋入りからペースト状にして容器内の小室に直接注入したものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this product, sauce attached to the package is changed from conventional one, liquid packed in a bag to paste-like form and directly injected into a small space in the container.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this product the sauce attached to the package is changed from the conventional one--a liquid packed in a bag--to a paste-like form, and is directly injected into a small space within the container.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this product, instead of attaching a conventional bag containing a liquid sause, a jellied sauce is directly injected into a small space in the container.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>これにより、納豆とタレ袋を分離するフィルムを廃して通気性を向上させると共にタレとの混合を容易にしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Through this arrangement, a film separating natto and the bag for sauce is abolished improving permeability and making it easier to mix sauce with natto.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Through this arrangement, the film that would otherwise separate the natto and the bag of sauce is eliminated, thus improving the permeability and making it easier to mix the sauce with the natto.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Through this arrangement, the film that would otherwise separate the natto and the bag of sauce is eliminated, thus improving the permeability and making it easier to mix the sauce with the natto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>ただし長時間容器を傾けて運搬・保存できないという欠点がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it has disadvantage that it cannot be transported or stored for a long time period with the container in tilted condition.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is disadvantageous in that it can&apos;t be transported or stored for a long period with the container in a tilted state.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is disadvantageous in that it can&apos;t be transported or stored for a long period with the container in a tilted state.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>種類</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Types</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Types</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Types</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="79">
<j>下記の他に、大豆の粒の大小による区別もあり、概して東北地方は大粒が目立つ傾向がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to the types described below, there are incrimination with the size of grain of soybean and, generally speaking, large-sized soybeans are used in Tohoku region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to the types described below, there are classifications according to the soybean grain size, and generally speaking, large-size soybeans are used in the Tohoku region.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to the types described below, natto can be classified according to the soybean grain size, and large-size soybeans are generally preferred in the Tohoku region.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>また、山形県酒田市の塩納豆、熊本県の金山寺納豆などローカル色に富んだ納豆もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are certain natto with local features such as shio natto (shiokara natto with konbu kelp) of Sakata City of Akita Prefecture and kinzanji natto (Japanese traditional koji (mould grown on rice) -fermentation food which is made from soy beans) of Kumamoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are certain types of natto with local features such as shio natto (shiokara natto with konbu kelp) of Sakata City, in Akita Prefecture, and kinzanji natto (Japanese traditional koji (mold grown on rice), a fermentation food that is made from soybeans) in Kumamoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are certain types of natto with local features including shio natto made and eaten in Sakata City, in Yamagata Prefecture, which is a type of natto seasoned with salt, konbu kelp and other ingredients, and also Kinzanji natto in Kumamoto Prefecture, which is a type of natto made of soybean, wheat and salt, and seasoned with konbu kelp and ginger.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。Akita Prefecture→Yamagata Prefectureに修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>塩辛納豆（寺納豆）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shiokara natto (soybeans fermented with komekoji (mould grown on rice) and salt)(tera natto (natto made in a temple))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shiokara natto (soybeans fermented with komekoji (mold grown on rice) and salt) (tera natto (natto made in a temple))</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shiokara natto (soybeans fermented with komekoji (mold grown on rice) and salt) (tera natto (natto made in a temple))</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="81">
<j>現在では、納豆と言えば、納豆菌を発酵させたいわゆる糸引き納豆を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At present, if we mention natto, it refers to so-called itohiki-natto (sticky natto), which is produced by fermenting bacillus subtilis natto.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処「納豆菌を発酵させた」は、「納豆菌で発酵させた」の誤りと思われますが、原文に従って訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, if we mention natto we refer to the so-called itohiki-natto (sticky natto), which is produced by fermenting bacillus subtilis natto.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, if we mention natto we refer to the so-called itohiki-natto (sticky natto), which is produced by fermenting bacillus subtilis natto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>その他にも麹菌を発酵させた後乾燥させてから熟成した塩辛納豆（寺納豆）と呼ばれる納豆がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to it, there is natto called shiokara natto (tera natto) which is produced by fermenting Aspergillus oryzae, drying it and then letting it mature. it</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処「麹菌を発酵させた」は、「麹菌で発酵させた」の誤りと思われますが、原文に従って訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there is also natto called shiokara natto (tera natto), which is produced by fermenting Aspergillus oryzae, drying it and then letting it mature.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is also a type of natto called shiokara natto (tera natto), which is made by fermenting soybeans with Aspergillus oryzae, and drying it and then letting mature.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>麹菌納豆は古代中国(紀元前2世紀頃)からの遺跡等から出土している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Natto by koji mold was found in remains of ancient China (around the Second Century B.C.).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Natto produced by koji mold was found in ancient Chinese remains uncovered in or around the second century B.C.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Natto produced by koji mold was found in ancient Chinese remains uncovered in or around the second century B.C.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>日本にはおそらく奈良時代頃に伝来した豉（し、日本ではくきと読まれ久喜の字もあてられていた）と考えられている塩豉（後の塩辛納豆）と淡豉（平安以降歴史から姿を消す）との2種類がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan, there were two types, enshi (later shiokara natto) and tanshi (disappeared in the history since the Heian Period) and they are considered to correspond to shi (it was pronounced as &quot;kuki&quot; and characters &quot;久喜&quot; were also used.), which is deemed to have been introduced in around the Nara Period</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan there were two types--enshi (later shiokara natto) and tanshi (which vanished into history after the Heian Period)--and they&apos;re believed to correspond to shi (it was pronounced as &quot;kuki&quot; but the characters &quot;久喜&quot; were also used.), which is deemed to have been introduced in around the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan there were two types: enshi (later shiokara natto) and tanshi (which vanished into history after the Heian period), and they are believed to be shi (pronounced as &quot;kuki&quot; in Japan and the kanji &quot;久喜&quot; was also used for the word) which is deemed to have been introduced in around the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。「&amp;quot;」→「&quot;」に修正、余分なスペース消去</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>そのままではなく調味料として使われていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were not used independently, but used as seasoning agent.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were not used independently but together as seasoning agents.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were not used independently but together as seasoning agents.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="86">
<j>平安時代の文献にも塩辛納豆の名は残っているが、一般に広まったのは室町時代以降。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name shiokara natto remained in literatures of the Heian Period, but it spread among general public only in the Muromachi Period and on.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name shiokara natto remained in the literature of the Heian period, but it spread among the general public only in the Muromachi period and afterward.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The word shiokara natto can be found in the literature from the Heian period, but it is thought that it spread among the general public in the Muromachi period and afterward.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>この頃から糸引き納豆も登場しており区別するために塩辛納豆を久喜と呼び糸引き納豆を単に納豆と呼ぶようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around that time, itohiki natto also entered the stage and, in order to distinguish them, shiokara natto was called as kuki and itohiki natto as natto.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around that time, itohiki natto also emerged and, in order to distinguish them, shiokara natto was called kuki and itohiki natto was called natto.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around that time, itohiki natto also appeared and, in order to differentiate itohiki natto from shiokara natto, shiokara natto came to be called as kuki and itohiki natto as natto.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。shiokata→shiokaraに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>またこの頃北宋・南宋に渡航した僧が再度持ち帰り広めたことから寺納豆とも呼ばれるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, around this time, priests who visited Northern Sung Dynasty and Southern Sung Dynasty brought back again and spread it, it became also called tera natto.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, around this time, priests who visited the Northern Sung and Southern Sung dynasties brought it back and spread it, whereupon it also became known as tera natto.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also during this period, since priests who visited the Northern Sung and Southern Sung dynasties brought back shiokara natto in Japan again and it spread in the country, it also became known as tera natto.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>今でも京都府の大徳寺納豆・天竜寺納豆・一休寺納豆や静岡県浜松市の浜納豆（浜名納豆）などが作り続けられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even today, Daitokuji natto (natto made in Daitoku-ji Temple), Tenryuji natto (natto made in Tenryu-ji Temple), Ikkyuji natto (natto made in Ikkyu-ji Temple) and Hama-natto (Hamana natto (soybeans fermented with komekoji (mould grown on rice) and flour, pickled in salt water and dried out)) are still produced.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even today, Daitokuji natto (natto made in Daitoku-ji Temple), Tenryuji natto (natto made in Tenryu-ji Temple), Ikkyuji natto (natto made in Ikkyu-ji Temple) and Hama-natto (Hamana natto (soybeans fermented with komekoji (mold grown on rice) and flour, pickled in saltwater and dried)) are still produced.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even today, Daitokuji natto (natto made in Daitoku-ji Temple), Tenryuji natto (natto made in Tenryu-ji Temple), Ikkyuji natto (natto made in Ikkyu-ji Temple) and Hama-natto (Hamana natto (soybeans fermented with komekoji (mold grown on rice) and flour, pickled in saltwater and dried)) are still produced.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>ひきわり納豆</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hikiwari natto (crashed natto)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hikiwari natto (crushed natto)</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hikiwari natto (crushed natto)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="90">
<j>挽き割り、即ち砕いた大豆によって作られる納豆。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Natto made with ground, namely crushed soybeans</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Natto made with ground (hence &quot;crushed&quot;) soybeans</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Natto made with ground (hence &quot;crushed&quot;) soybeans</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>納豆汁によく用いられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is often used for natto jiru.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is often used for natto jiru.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is often used for natto jiru.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>普通の納豆より発酵が早く、消化が良いとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that it is fermented quicker and better digested than usual natto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that it ferments more quickly and is better digested than the usual natto.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that it ferments more quickly natto and is easier to be digested than the usual natto.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>ひきわり納豆に対し、通常の割っていない大豆を使った納豆は「粒納豆」と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In contrast to hikiwari natto, usual natto, for which non-ground soybeans are used, is called tsubu natto (whole-bean natto).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In contrast to hikiwari natto, the usual natto, for which non-ground soybeans are used, is called tsubu natto (whole-bean natto).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In contrast to hikiwari natto, the usual natto, for which non-ground soybeans are used, is called &apos;tsubu natto&apos; (whole-bean natto).</e>
<cmt>括弧を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="94">
<j>秋田県で古くから作られていた手法で、一般にはヤマダフーズが販売したものが発祥とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This technique have been used in Akita Prefecture from old times and it is told that Yamada Foods first launched it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This technique has been used in Akita Prefecture since the old times, and it is said that Yamada Foods first introduced it.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This technique had been used in Akita Prefecture since the old times, and it is said that Yamada Foods first introduced it throughout the country.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>同社によると、大豆1粒を6つくらいに割る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Yamada Foods, each grain is divided into six or so.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Yamada Foods, each grain is divided into approximately six parts.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Yamada Foods, each grain is divided into approximately six parts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>また同社では、15ほどに細かく割った「きざみ納豆」も販売している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamada Foods also sells &quot;kizami natto (literally, minced natto)&quot; for which a grain is divided into fifteen or so.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yamada Foods also sells &quot;kizami natto (literally, minced natto)&quot; for which a grain is divided into approximately 15 parts.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamada Foods also sells &apos;kizami natto&apos; (literally, minced natto) for which a grain is divided into approximately fifteen parts.</e>
<cmt>括弧を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>そぼろ納豆</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soboro natto (natto mixed with kiriboshi daikon (thinly sliced and dried strips of daikon))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soboro natto (natto mixed with kiriboshi daikon (thinly sliced and dried strips of daikon))</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soboro natto (natto mixed with kiriboshi daikon (thinly sliced and dried strips of daikon))</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="97">
<j>茨城県特産。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Specialty of Ibaraki Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A specialty of Ibaraki Prefecture</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A specialty of Ibaraki Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>おぼろ納豆、しょぼろ納豆とも呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called oboro natto or shoboro natto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called oboro natto or shoboro natto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called oboro natto or shoboro natto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>納豆に刻んだ切り干し大根を混ぜ込み、醤油等の調味料で味をつけたもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soboro natto is prepared by mixing minced kiriboshi daikon in natto and seasoning with seasoning agent such as soy sauce.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soboro natto is prepared by mixing minced kiriboshi daikon in natto and adding a seasoning agent such as soy sauce.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soboro natto is prepared by mixing minced kiriboshi daikon in natto and adding a seasoning agent such as soy sauce.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>そのまま酒のつまみとして食べたり、ご飯にかけて食べたりする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is eaten as nibbles independently or together with rice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is nibbled independently or together with rice.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is eaten as nibbles for drinks or with rice.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="14">
<tit>
<j>干し納豆</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hoshi natto (sun-dried natto)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hoshi natto (sun-dried natto)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hoshi natto (sun-dried natto)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="101">
<j>茨城県特産。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Specialty of Ibaraki Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A specialty of Ibaraki Prefecture</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A specialty of Ibaraki Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>納豆を天日干しすることにより長期保存可能にしたもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Natto which was dried in the sun in order to make it possible to be kept for long time</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Natto has been dried in the sun so that it would keep for a long time.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Natto has been dried in the sun so that it would keep for a long time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>なお納豆を乾燥させても、納豆菌は死滅しない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even if natto is dried, bacillus subtilis natto does not die out.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even if natto is dried, the bacillus subtilis natto will not die out.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even if natto is dried, the bacillus subtilis natto will not die out.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>食べ方としてはそのまま食べるほか、湯につけてもどす、お茶漬けにするなどがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is eaten as it is, or by reconstituting with hot water or together with ochaduke (boiled rice with tea poured over it)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is eaten as it is, or by reconstituting with hot water or together with ochaduke (boiled rice with tea poured over it).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is eaten as it is, or by reconstituting with hot water or together with ochazuke (boiled rice with tea poured over it).</e>
<cmt>Ochazukeとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="105">
<j>元来は保存食だったとされるが、現在は納豆の入手できない海外へ旅行に行く際に持っていく場合があるという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is told that hoshi natto was originally prepared as preserved food, but, nowadays, it is brought with when travelling to overseas country where natto is unavailable.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that hoshi natto was originally prepared as a preserved food, but today it is brought with when traveling to overseas destinations where natto is unavailable.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that hoshi natto was originally prepared as a preserved food, but today it is brought with when traveling to overseas destinations where natto is unavailable.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="15">
<tit>
<j>揚げ納豆</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Age natto (fried natto)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Age natto (fried natto)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Age natto (fried natto)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="106">
<j>干し納豆に近いが、これは納豆を油で揚げ、粘り気を取り去ったもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It resembles hoshi natto, but it is prepared by frying natto with fat or oil removing stickiness.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It resembles hoshi natto, but it is prepared by frying natto in fat or oil in order to eliminate the stickiness.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It resembles hoshi natto, but it is prepared by frying natto in fat or oil in order to eliminate the stickiness.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>納豆独特の臭いも目立たない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Smell that is unique to natto is not noticeable.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The odor so characteristic of natto isn&apos;t noticeable.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The characteristic odor of natto isn&apos;t too strong.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。「&amp;apos;」→「&apos;」に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>揚げても納豆菌が死滅しないように、特別な製造技術が用いられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Special manufacturing technique is used so that bacillus subtilis natto does not die out even after frying with fat or oil.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Special manufacturing technique is used so that bacillus subtilis natto doesn&apos;t die out even after frying in fat or oil.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Special manufacturing technique is used so that bacillus subtilis natto doesn&apos;t die out even when deep fried.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。「&amp;apos;」→「&apos;」に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="109">
<j>そのまま酒のつまみとして食べる事が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is usually eaten as nibbles as it is.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is usually nibbled just as it is.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is usually eaten as nibbles for drinks without cooking.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>しょうゆ・塩・梅・一味唐辛子などの味がつけられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is seasoned with soy sauce, salt, umeboshi (pickled &quot;ume&quot; - Japanese apricot) and/or ground red pepper.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is seasoned with soy sauce, salt, umeboshi (pickled &quot;ume,&quot; or Japanese apricot) and/or ground red pepper.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is seasoned with soy sauce, salt, umeboshi (pickled &quot;ume,&quot; or Japanese apricot) and/or ground red pepper.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>日本航空の国際線機内でも酒肴として提供されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">it is served in a cabin of international flight of Japan Air Lines as nibbles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">it is served as a snack on the international flights of Japan Air Lines.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">it is served as a snack on the international flights of Japan Air Lines.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="16">
<tit>
<j>塩納豆</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shio natto (natto made in Kochi prefecture, fried with salt and rice bran)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shio natto (natto made in Kochi Prefecture, fried with salt and rice bran)</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shio natto (natto made in Kochi Prefecture, fried with salt and rice bran)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="112">
<j>高知県の一部の地域の郷土料理。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A local dish in certain part of Kochi Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A local dish in certain parts of Kochi Prefecture</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A local dish in certain parts of Kochi Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="113">
<j>納豆に塩と糠をまぶして鉄鍋で炒る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Natto is sprinkled with salt and bran and parched with an iron pan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Natto is sprinkled with salt and bran and then parched with an iron pan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Natto is sprinkled with salt and bran and then parched with an iron pan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="114">
<j>伝統的な製法では、市販の納豆の代わりに蒸した大豆を籾殻の中に入れ、糸を引くようになったものを用いる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In traditional manufacturing method, steamed soybeans, instead of natto on the market, are put in rice husks and used after thread becomes noticeable.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the traditional manufacturing method, steamed soybeans (instead of natto available on the market) are placed in rice husks and used once the threads become noticeable.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the traditional manufacturing method, steamed soybeans (instead of natto available on the market) are placed in rice husks and used once the threads become noticeable.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="17">
<tit>
<j>甘納豆</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ama natto (sugared red beans)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ama natto (sugared red beans)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ama natto (sugared red beans)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="115">
<j>1857年（安政4年）に栄太楼が開発した和菓子で、ここまで述べてきた発酵食品の納豆とは全く別物である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a Japanese confectionery developed in 1857 by Eitaro and it is quite different from above-mentioned natto, which was fermented food.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A Japanese confectionery developed in 1857 by Eitaro, it is quite different from the above-mentioned natto, which is a fermented food.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is quite different from the above-mentioned natto, which is a fermented food; ama natto is a Japanese confectionery developed in 1857 by Eitaro.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="116">
<j>当初は浜名納豆（浜納豆）に似せて甘名納糖と名づけられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the beginning, it was named amana natto modelling after hamana natto (hama natto).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Initially, it was named amana natto, being modeled after hamana natto (hama natto).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Initially, it was named amana natto, being modeled after hamana natto (hama natto).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="117">
<j>名前が簡略化されて甘納豆と呼ばれるようになったのは戦後のことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was only after the Second World War that the name was shortened as ama natto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was only after the Second World War that the name was shortened to &quot;ama natto.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was only after the Second World War that the name was shortened to &quot;ama natto.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="118">
<j>近畿地方では、単に納豆と言えば甘納豆を指す場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kinki region, if you mention simply natto, sometimes it refers to ama natto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Kinki region, the use of the word &quot;natto&quot; can sometimes refer to ama natto.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Kinki region, the use of the word &quot;natto&quot; can sometimes refer to ama natto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="18">
<tit>
<j>地域別状況</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Situation of each region</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The situation in each region</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The situation in each region</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="19">
<tit>
<j>秋田県</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akita Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akita Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akita Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="119">
<j>- 仙北郡美郷町_(秋田県)に「納豆発祥の地」の碑がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a monument of &quot;Birthplace of Natto&quot;in Misato Town in Senboku County (Akita Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a monument indicating &quot;Birthplace of Natto&quot; in Misato Town, in Senboku County (Akita Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a monument indicating &apos;Birthplace of Natto&apos; in Misato-cho, Senboku-gun (Akita Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>住所表記を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="120">
<j>また、秋田音頭に「桧山納豆」（能代市桧山地区）が秋田名物の一つとして謳われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, in Akita ondo (folk song), &quot;hiyama natto (natto from Hiyama in Akita Prefecture)&quot;(Hiyama district in Noshiro City) is mentioned as one of specialties of Akita.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, in Akita ondo (folk song), &quot;hiyama natto (natto from Hiyama, in Akita Prefecture)&quot; (the Hiyama district of Noshiro City) is mentioned as one of specialties of Akita.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, in Akita ondo (folk song), &apos;hiyama natto&apos; (natto from Hiyama, in Akita Prefecture) (the Hiyama district of Noshiro City) is mentioned as one of specialties of Akita.</e>
<cmt>括弧を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="20">
<tit>
<j>茨城県水戸市</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mito City, Ibaraki Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mito City, Ibaraki Prefecture</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mito City, Ibaraki Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="121">
<j>- 明治以降、鉄道（水戸線）の開通に伴い、土産品として売られた（天狗納豆が発祥とされる）のをきっかけに、産地としてもっとも知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Meiji era and on, in line with opening of railway (Mito Line), natto was sold for souvenir (it is told the first one was Tengu natto), it is most famous as production area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the Meiji era, in keeping with the opening of the railway (Mito Line), natto has been sold as a souvenir (it is said that the first one was Tengu natto), and this area is famous for the production of natto.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the Meiji period, in keeping with the opening of the railway (Mito Line), natto has been sold as a souvenir (it is said that the first one was Tengu natto), and this area is famous for the production of natto.</e>
<cmt>era→period　に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="122">
<j>毎年3月10日 (水戸の日)に「納豆早食い大会」が開催されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On March 10 (day of Mito), every year, &quot;natto hayagui taikai (literally, competition of eating natto quickly)&quot; is held.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On March 10 (day of Mito) of each year, &quot;natto hayagui taikai (literally, a competition of eating natto quickly)&quot; is held.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 10 (day of Mito) of each year, &apos;natto hayagui taikai&apos; (literally, a competition of eating natto quickly) is held.</e>
<cmt>括弧を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="21">
<tit>
<j>熊本県</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kumamoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kumamoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kumamoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="123">
<j>- 九州では例外的に古くから普及している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Exceptionally for Kyushu, natto is wide spread from old times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Exceptionally for Kyushu, natto has been widespread since the old times.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As an exceptional case, natto has been widespread in Kyushu since the old times.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="124">
<j>これは、加藤清正が文禄・慶長の役の際濡れた大豆を馬に積んでいたのが馬の高い体温で発酵し納豆になったとの言い伝えがあるからだとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is told that this is because there is a legend that, at the time of the Bunroku-Keicho War, Kiyomasa KATO loaded wet soybean on the back of a horse and soybean was fermented because of high body heat of the horse and became natto.</e>
<cmt>「言い伝えがあるから普及した」というのは、論理的におかしいと思われますが、原文に忠実に訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that this is because there is a legend that, at the time of the Bunroku-Keicho War, Kiyomasa KATO loaded wet soybeans onto the back of a horse; they fermented because of high body heat of the horse and became natto.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that because there is a legend that, at the time of the Bunroku-Keicho War, Kiyomasa KATO loaded wet soybeans onto the back of a horse which fermented because of high body heat of the horse, and became natto.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="125">
<j>全国規模の納豆製造会社（丸美屋）がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a natto manufacturing company on national basis (Marumiya) and natto is sold in supermarkets regularly and the amount of consumption is big..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a natto manufacturing company that operates on a national basis (Marumiya); moreover, natto is regularly sold in supermarkets, so the consumption statistics are impressive.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a natto manufacturing company that operates on a national basis (e.g. Marumiya).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。一原文一訳文例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="126">
<j>スーパーマーケットで普通に売られていて、消費量も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, natto is regularly sold in supermarkets, so the consumed amount is impressive.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。一原文一訳文例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="127">
<j>一般に消費量は東日本が多く、特に北関東から南東北にかけて消費量が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Generally speaking, the amount of consumption is bigger in eastern Japan and, especially big in the area from northern Kanto to southern Kanto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Generally speaking, the amount of consumption is greater in eastern Japan, particularly in the area from northern Kanto to southern Kanto.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Generally speaking, the amount of consumption is greater in eastern Japan, particularly in the area from northern Kanto to southern Tohoku.</e>
<cmt>南東北　に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="128">
<j>生産量日本一は茨城県、消費量日本一は福島県である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ibaraki Prefecture has the biggest amount of production and Fukushima Prefecture has the biggest amount of consumption.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ibaraki Prefecture is the top producer, and Fukushima Prefecture is the top consumer.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ibaraki Prefecture is the top producer, and Fukushima Prefecture is the top consumer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="129">
<j>西日本（特に近畿）ではあまり食べる習慣が無いとされ、消費量最下位は和歌山県である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is understood that in western Japan (especially Kinki region), custom of eating natto does not exist and the amount of consumption is smallest in Wakayama Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is understood that in western Japan (especially the Kinki region) the custom of eating natto doesn&apos;t exist, and consequently the amount of consumption is smallest in Wakayama Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is understood that in western Japan (especially the Kinki region) people do not eat natto often, and the amount of consumption is smallest in Wakayama Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="130">
<j>しかし、近年は関西地方でもスーパーなどで10銘柄程度の商品が普通に売られ、陳列スペースもほとんど関東と変わらなくなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In recent years, however, around ten different brands of products are usually sold in supermarkets and displaying space became almost same as those in Kanto region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in recent years about ten different brands of products have been sold in supermarkets, and the amount of display space has become nearly equal to that of the Kanto region.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in recent years about ten different brands of natto products are sold in supermarkets in the Kinki region, and the amount of display space has become nearly equal to that of the Kanto region.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="131">
<j>日本国外</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Outside Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Outside Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Natto overseas</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="132">
<j>日系アメリカ人移民の多いハワイ州では、現地の豆腐製造業者が実際に納豆を製造、販売している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the State of Hawaii where a large number of Japanese-American immigrants live, local tofu manufacturers actually produce and sell natto.</e>
<cmt>「日系アメリカ人移民」はどうかと思われますが、「Japanese-American immigrant」としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the U.S. state of Hawaii, which is home to large numbers of Japanese-American immigrants, local tofu manufacturers actually produce and sell natto.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the U.S. state of Hawaii, which is home to large numbers of Japanese-American immigrants, local tofu manufacturers actually produce and sell natto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="133">
<j>以下の地域では、納豆と似た大豆発酵食品が製造されている</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the following regions, soybean-based fermented food similar to natto is sold.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the following regions, soybean-based fermented foods similar to natto are sold.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the following regions, soybean-based fermented foods similar to natto are sold.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="134">
<j>ヒマラヤ山脈麓のネパールなど南アジア、中国雲南省から東南アジアにかけた地域。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Southern Asia covering Nepal in the foot of the Himalayas and area from Yunnan Province of China to Southeastern Asia</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Southern Asia, covering Nepal at the base of the Himalayas and the area from Chin&apos;a Yunnan Province to Southeast Asia</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Southern Asia, covering Nepal at the base of the Himalayas and the area from China&apos;s Yunnan Province to Southeast Asia</e>
<cmt>China&apos;s としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="135">
<j>朝鮮半島：清麹醤。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Korean Peninsula: 清麹醤</e>
<cmt>「清麹醤」は朝鮮語と思われますので、そのまま残しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Korean Peninsula: 清麹醤</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Korean Peninsula: 清麹醤</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="22">
<tit>
<j>ブーム</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Boom</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Boom</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Boom</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="136">
<j>2007年1月7日に放送された関西テレビ放送・フジテレビジョンの教養番組「発掘!あるある大事典」で、納豆の摂取はダイエットに効果があると紹介された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As it was announced on January 7, 2007 in the cultural program &quot;Hakkutsu aruaru daijiten&quot; (literally, encyclopedia for findings of digging) broadcast by Kansai Telecasting Corporation and Fuji Television Networks, Inc. that natto is effective for dieting, consumers bought natto a lot, and natto became scarce temporarily.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As it was announced on January 7, 2007 in the cultural program &quot;Hakkutsu aruaru daijiten&quot; (literally, encyclopedia for findings of digging) broadcast by Kansai Telecasting Corporation and Fuji Television Networks, Inc., that natto was effective for dieting; consequently, consumers bought lots of natto and caused a temporary shortage of supplies.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the cultural program &apos;Hakkutsu! Aru Aru Daijiten&apos; (Encyclopedia of Living) broadcasted by Kansai Telecasting Corporation and Fuji Television Networks, Inc. on January 7, 2007, it was announced that natto was effective for dieting.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。一原文一訳文例外処理余分なスペース消去</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="137">
<j>そのため、消費者がこぞって納豆を買い求め、一時品薄状態になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, many consumers bought lots of natto and caused a temporary shortage of supplies.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。一原文一訳文例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="138">
<j>しかし、番組で紹介されたデータは捏造だったことが後に判明した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it was revealed later that the data introduce by the program was a trumped-up story.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it was later revealed that the data introduced by the program was a trumped-up story.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it was later revealed that the data introduced in the program was a fabrication.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Nack(id:168243), Tak(id:149), 0null0(id:582), Jjok(id:55405), 木製歯車(id:91177), Hykw-a4(id:14184), ぎゅうひ(id:9206), A-Taul(id:41790), Singing(id:134656), あおいつき(id:92473), 海獺(id:153448), 百楽天(id:5266), Slime Chida(id:17046), FlaBot(id:30804), Way of Five Pecks of Rice(id:32668), Kazov(id:9237), ロリ(id:613), Starbacks(id:1018), ラオウ2号(id:249933), Kuriyasan(id:164752), Trinity68star(id:247502), Bletilla(id:38919), Hukurou(id:115254), MULTIVAC(id:110454), Y tambe(id:11092), KoshiMAX(id:75762), TessarA110(id:78325), SuisuiBot(id:10165), やる気man-man(id:36512), R28Bot(id:177951), Kuha455405(id:35818), Bigben(id:1039), Abovebeen(id:203100), エクリプス(id:67623), Suisui(id:69), Haguii(id:1313), Kstigarbha(id:13376), Roger(id:9883), Rikumio(id:99645), Rai koku(id:1661), Kumatora(id:16941), Kcrt(id:5180), Ix680(id:25168), Yatobi(id:9686), くろすけ(id:88235), Melon pie(id:196693), 微風(id:204945), 氷鷺(id:73707), Izu(id:98801), An-chan(id:14590), Yuukie(id:50892), Union of the Snakeman(id:184576), LERK(id:4460), Yaizawa(id:17578), Kentin(id:6768), 蒼海牧菜(id:78923), Yanahan(id:2437), LaaknorBot(id:220851), Marine-Blue(id:20162), Carkuni(id:79281), XEXEX(id:232358), Kazukiokumura(id:142935), 竃馬(id:102733), Yukichin(id:725), CScheme(id:217149), Miya(id:1881), Muyo(id:14948), Nattou(id:184910), Weep(id:30189), BBB(id:112), SieBot(id:126695), 1029man(id:93235), AlleborgoBot(id:119729), Ypacaraí(id:11031), Eskimbot(id:29676), 天然ガス(id:98149), 花いちもんめ(id:39081), Goldenv825(id:73603), Jazzy(id:3202), Oneuchi(id:70845), Opponent(id:720), 橄欖岩(id:24996), ラッパ食堂(id:255123), Yas(id:739), Sprinkler(id:14399), Meltbeen(id:160811), Niboshi(id:46978), Hotei(id:7664), K-ichi586(id:253622), めるびす・おが(id:153862), マクガイア(id:33346), Tomos(id:10), くさのしんや(id:21550), Tietew(id:4054), MWE(id:41027), KSKS(id:97637), Teekam(id:90012), Alexbot(id:157199), Poeticos(id:307776), ウミユスリカ(id:9504), ぬるペディア(id:250200), Bakkai(id:7233), COLONEL-J(id:12059), BOTarate(id:185620), Cassiopeia sweet(id:29811), Tekune(id:2690), 春野秋葉(id:36725), VVVN(id:64040), Ohura(id:5986), 死郎(id:1683), 白文鳥(id:103465), Bandalgom(id:31841), Nevylax(id:38464), 怪蘇(id:45514), Fffkk(id:261100), 曼珠沙華(id:26417), Some007(id:260733), 山本花菜(id:90506), Izayohi(id:13095), Belle Equipe(id:39537), Onsentaro(id:23863), しるふぃ(id:11247), Nighthawks(id:36125), J8takagi(id:20409), Bore(id:463), Vina-iwbot(id:56449), Gleam(id:4760), BehBeh(id:55215), VolkovBot(id:105371), Mooko(id:36162), TottyBot(id:101680), Ete(id:28565), Salix(id:85042), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>