<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>越中褌</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ecchu Fundoshi (a simple rectangular loincloth with strings)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ecchu Fundoshi (a Japanese loincloth with strings)</e>
<cmt>wikiのタイトルとしては日本のloinclothの方が分かりやすいと思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ecchu Fundoshi (a Japanese loincloth with strings)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>越中褌（えっちゅうふんどし・越中ふんどし）とは、ふんどしの一種。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ecchu fundoshi (越中褌) is a kind of fundoshi (the traditional Japanese undergarment for adult males).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ecchu fundoshi (越中褌) is a kind of fundoshi, a traditional Japanese undergarment for adult males.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ecchu fundoshi (越中褌) is a kind of fundoshi, a traditional Japanese undergarment for adult males.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>長さ100cm程度、幅34cm程度の布の端に紐をつけた下着である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is an undergarment made from a length of cotton with the material string tied to its end, the dimensions being about 100 cm long and about 34 cm wide.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is made from a lengthy cloth, about 100 cm long by 34 cm wide, with strips on both sides of the cloth.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is made from a lengthy cloth, about 100 cm long by 34 cm wide, with strips on both sides of the cloth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>一部ではクラシックパンツ、サムライパンツとも呼ばれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called Classic Pants or Samurai Pants by some people.</e>
<cmt>「クラシックパンツ」、「サムライパンツ」は和製英語なので、あえて左記のように記述しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called Classic Pants or Samurai Pants by some people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called Classic Pants or Samurai Pants by some people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>医療用の下着であるT字帯も越中褌の一種。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">T-jitai (a bandage sewn in the form like &apos;T&apos;) which is an undergarment for medical use is also a kind of Ecchu fundoshi.</e>
<cmt>「T字帯」の正式な英語表記を見つけられなかったのでローマ字表記にして（我流の）説明を付記しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">T-jitai (T-shaped undergarment for medical use) is also a kind of Ecchu fundoshi.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">T-jitai (T-shaped undergarment for medical use) is also a kind of Ecchu fundoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>禊（水行）の時に使われる場合が多い他、一部の裸祭りでは六尺褌に代って、こちらが使われる場合がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Not only are Ecchu fundoshi often used when you carry out misogi (purification ceremony, or suigyo [cold water ablutions]), but also they are sometimes used instead of Rokushaku fundoshi (a loincloth of about 2.4 m length) in some of the naked festival (a Japanese festival in which the men go naked except for fundoshi loincloths).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fundoshi is used not only in a case of misogi or suigyo, a purification ceremony particularly in cold water, but also in some of hadaka matsuri (literally, naked festival in which men are naked except for fundoshi loincloths).</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fundoshi is used not only in a case of misogi or suigyo, a purification ceremony particularly in cold water, but also in some of hadaka matsuri (literally, naked festival in which men are naked except for fundoshi loincloths).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>名前の由来には越中富山の置き薬の景品で全国に普及したことに由来する説や、越中守だった細川忠興が考案者とする説など、複数の説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As to the origin of the name, there are several opinions: for example, it originated from spreading throughout Japan as a free gift of okigusuri (a medicine chest left behind by a salesman who collects for only the amount used) of Ecchu Toyama; Tadaoki HOSOKAWA who was Ecchu no kami (governor of Ecchu Province) was its originator, and so on.</e>
<cmt>Excel原稿の「越中国富山の配置販売業」をWeb原稿に合わせて「越中富山の置き薬」に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Several theories have been told as regard to the name of this fundoshi: it came from a gift from the medicine distributors from Ecchu Toyama region (they distributed medicines across the country, placing medicines at individual homes, and collecting the money for the used amount when they visit next time); it came from Tadaoki HOSOKAWA because he invented this type of fundoshi and his official title was Ecchu no kami (a govonor of Ecchu Province).</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Several theories have been told as regard to the name of this fundoshi: it came from a gift from the medicine distributors from Ecchu Toyama region (they distributed medicines across the country, placing medicines at individual homes, and collecting the money for the used amount when they visit next time); it came from Tadaoki HOSOKAWA because he invented this type of fundoshi and his official title was Ecchu no kami (a govonor of Ecchu Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>江戸時代にも存在していて、隠居した武士、肉体労働を伴わない医者や神職、僧侶、文化人、商人の間で用いられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ecchu fundoshi also existed in the Edo period, and they were used by retired samurai (warriors), as well as doctors, Shinto priests, Buddhist monks, men of culture, and merchants who were not involved in physical labor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ecchu fundoshi existed in the Edo period, and they were used by retired samurai (warriors), as well as people who were not engaged in physical labor, such as medical doctors, Shinto priests, Buddhist monks, men of culture and merchants.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ecchu fundoshi existed in the Edo period, and they were used by retired samurai (warriors), as well as people who were not engaged in physical labor, such as medical doctors, Shinto priests, Buddhist monks, men of culture and merchants.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>越中褌が本格的に普及したのは明治末期頃から。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ecchu fundoshi have spread in earnest since the end of the Meiji era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But the fundoshi spread in a larger scale from the end of the Meiji period onwards.</e>
<cmt>Meiji era --&gt; Meiji period</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But the fundoshi spread in a larger scale from the end of the Meiji period onwards.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>1873年（明治6年）に徴兵令が制定され、1889年（明治22年）に国民皆兵が義務付けられ、徴用された成人男子に軍隊が官給品として支給（貸興、給興）し、使用を強制したことで一般化するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ecchu fundoshi became accepted generally, as the Conscription Ordinance was enacted in 1873, the universal conscription was made obligatory in 1889, and the army provided (lent, supplied) it to the conscripted adult males as one of the government-issued supplies and forced them to use it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ecchu fundoshi became accepted generally, as the Conscription Ordinance was enacted in 1873, the universal conscription was made obligatory in 1889, and the army provided (lent, supplied) it to the conscripted adult males as one of the government-issued supplies and forced them to use it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ecchu fundoshi became accepted generally, as the Conscription Ordinance was enacted in 1873, the universal conscription was made obligatory in 1889, and the army provided (lent, supplied) it to the conscripted adult males as one of the government-issued supplies and forced them to use it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>兵役除隊後、前垂れが陰部を隠し、軽くて清々しいとの使用感や、着脱が容易で布の使用が少ない経済性もあり、若者を中心に全国に普及した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After getting discharged from the military service, the adult males, mainly the younger ones, spread it throughout Japan, because its maedare (front apron) concealed the private parts, it felt light and refreshing in use, it was easy to put on and take off, and it was economical thanks to using only a small piece of cloth.</e>
<cmt>原稿では、「兵役除隊後」の主語は「元兵士」であるのに対し、「前垂れ」以降「普及した。」までの主語は「越中褌」であり、視点が首尾一貫していません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After getting discharged from the military service, the adult males, mainly the younger ones, they brought back the fundoshi and made it popularized throughout Japan, as its maedare (front apron) concealed the private parts, it felt light and refreshing in use, it was easy to put on and take off, and it was economical becausethe length of cloth it needed was shorter than the one for the previous style of loincloth.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After getting discharged from the military service, the adult males, mainly the younger ones, they brought back the fundoshi and made it popularized throughout Japan, as its maedare (front apron) concealed the private parts, it felt light and refreshing in use, it was easy to put on and take off, and it was economical becausethe length of cloth it needed was shorter than the one for the previous style of loincloth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>それまでの六尺褌に代わり日本人成人男性の主な下着に代わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ecchu fundoshi had taken the place of Rokushaku fundoshi until then to be the main undergarment for Japanese adult males.</e>
<cmt>Excel原稿の「ふんどし六尺褌」をWeb原稿に合わせて「六尺褌」に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ecchu fundoshi took the place of Rokushaku fundoshi to be the main undergarment for Japanese adult males.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ecchu fundoshi took the place of Rokushaku fundoshi to be the main undergarment for Japanese adult males.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="13">
<j>越中褌は簡易なものであることから、戦前では市中で販売されるよりも自家で縫製して使用するものが多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Ecchu fundoshi was easy to make, those which were sewn in the home to use outnumbered those which were sold in the town before the war.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Ecchu fundoshi was easy to make, it was made at home rather than bought at store up until 1945.</e>
<cmt>戦前では　before the warでは、戦争の前まで、ですが、原文の意味するところは戦争時代が終わるまでは、ということだと思います。しかし、戦前、戦後というのは日本では用語化していますが英語では不明ですので、1945年まではとしました（基本的に全世界共通でターニングポイントとして認識されると思われますので）。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Ecchu fundoshi was easy to make, it was made at home rather than bought at store up until 1945.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="14">
<j>大正期から太平洋戦争終了時までの間は日本人成年男子の主な下着は「越中褌」となり、越中褌が「褌」や「男性下着」の代名詞となる程、越中褌の全盛期を迎えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Between the Taisho era and the end of the Pacific War, the main undergarment for the Japanese adult males was &quot;Ecchu fundoshi&quot;, and Ecchu fundoshi was at the height of its prosperity so that the term &quot;Ecchu fundoshi&quot; was used as an alias of &quot;fundoshi&quot; or &quot;undergarment for male</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ecchu fundoshi was the main undergarment for Japanese adult males from the Taisho period up to the end of the Pacific War, and it was its prime as the word of fundoshi directly referred to this type of fundoshi, or even the word of male undergarment meant this fundoshi.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ecchu fundoshi was the main undergarment for Japanese adult males from the Taisho period up to the end of the Pacific War, and it was its prime as the word of fundoshi directly referred to this type of fundoshi, or even the word of male undergarment meant this fundoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="15">
<j>戦後は、以下のような事情の影響を受けて、褌の使用人口は大幅に減少して、年配者が使用する過去の下着のような存在となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the war, the number of the fundoshi users decreased considerably, and fundoshi was reduced to something like an out-of-date undergarment that only elderly men wore, under the influence of following circumstances.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。訳文が長くなってしまい、表示しきれなくなったので、主節の部分（この行の文）とそれに影響を与えたさまざまな事情を列挙した部分（下の行の文）に分けました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the war, the number of the fundoshi users decreased considerably, and fundoshi was reduced to something like an out-of-date undergarment that only elderly men wore, under the influence of following circumstances.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the war, the number of the fundoshi users decreased considerably, and fundoshi was reduced to something like an out-of-date undergarment that only elderly men wore, under the influence of following circumstances.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>日本人の洋装化が一段と進んだこと、敗戦で軍隊で強制されていたことの嫌悪感から旧文化が否定される風潮になったこと、日本の工業化の進展で農村部から都市部に人口の移動が起こり、核家族化が進行して「褌祝」の私的祭事に象徴される褌継承の文化が断絶したこと、女性の社会進出で家事が簡略化されて自家で縫製する機会がなくなったこと、製造販売する業者も少なく店頭に並ばず、入手性に難があったこと、ブリーフ、トランクス等の新しい下着が廉価で出現して、機能性だけでなくファッション性のある下着が若者を中心に普及したことなどである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese had made further progress in adoption of western clothes; the loss of the war had brought about a tendency to deny the former culture from the antipathy toward being forced to wear fundoshi by the army; because industrialization had advanced in Japan, the population began to move from the agricultural community area to the urban districts and the trend toward the nuclear family progressed, so that the culture to inherit fundoshi symbolized by the private rituals of &quot;Fundoshi-iwai&quot; (a coming-of-age celebration for a boy by wearing a loincloth) had been broken off; women&apos;s going out into the world had simplified the household chores and reduced the occasions to sew fundoshi in the home; there were few companies that manufactured and sold fundoshi and there were few fundoshi that were on sale, so it became difficult to get one; and, because the new types of undergarments such as briefs and trunks had appeared at low prices, the undergarments that were not only functional but also fashionable became popular mainly among younger people.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。余りに長いので1文ずつ分割して箇条書きにでもしたほうが読みやすくなると思われますが、そこまで文の構造を変えてもよいのかわからないので、とりあえずセミコロン（;）で区切って各事情を列挙しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(1) Western clothes became more popular than ever in Japan; (2) there brought about a tendency to deny the previous culture because of the loss of the war, and, to make the matter worse, the fundoshi was something the military forced them to wear; (3) because of the advancement of industrialization, people moved from agricultural communities to urban areas to change the traditional family form to a nuclear family, and thus it made it hard to continue the culture in which wearing fundoshi was often symbolically celebrated as a rite of passage to be a grown-up man; (4) as women were encouraged to participate in society, household chores were simplified and thus the time for sewing fundoshi at home became limited; (5) manufacturers of fundoshi were practically decreased and it made it hard for people to get fundoshi at stores; and (6) new types of undergarments, such as a brief type and a trunks type of underpants, appeared at low prices, those functional, and were seen fashionable, undergarments became popular mainly among young people.</e>
<cmt>文章を変更しました。また、読みにくいので番号を付けました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(1) Western clothes became more popular than ever in Japan; (2) there brought about a tendency to deny the previous culture because of the loss of the war, and, to make the matter worse, the fundoshi was something the military forced them to wear; (3) because of the advancement of industrialization, people moved from agricultural communities to urban areas to change the traditional family form to a nuclear family, and thus it made it hard to continue the culture in which wearing fundoshi was often symbolically celebrated as a rite of passage to be a grown-up man; (4) as women were encouraged to participate in society, household chores were simplified and thus the time for sewing fundoshi at home became limited; (5) manufacturers of fundoshi were practically decreased and it made it hard for people to get fundoshi at stores; and (6) new types of undergarments, such as a brief type and a trunks type of underpants, appeared at low prices, those functional, and were seen fashionable, undergarments became popular mainly among young people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>このため、褌の用語は卑語のように扱われ、「下帯」、「締め込み」などの用語で代用されるようになるに至った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That&apos;s why the term &quot;fundoshi&quot; has come to be treated like a vulgar word and to be replaced with the terms such as &quot;shitaobi&quot; (a belt for underwear) and &quot;shimekomi&quot; (a sumo wrestler&apos;s cloth belt).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the changing period, the term &apos;fundoshi&apos; gradually treated like a vulgar word, and to be replaced with terms such as &apos;shitaobi&apos; (a belt for underwear) or &apos;shimekomi&apos; (a thing to tighten up, such as a sumo wrestler&apos;s cloth belt).</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the changing period, the term &apos;fundoshi&apos; gradually treated like a vulgar word, and to be replaced with terms such as &apos;shitaobi&apos; (a belt for underwear) or &apos;shimekomi&apos; (a thing to tighten up, such as a sumo wrestler&apos;s cloth belt).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="18">
<j>戦後、何度かマスコミュニケーションに取り上げられて一時的なブームが起こったことがあったが、定着することは無く、男性下着売り場の一角を占めるに至らない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the war, fundoshi has been featured by the mass media several times and the temporary craze for it has arisen, but it has never taken root and has never resulted in occupying one corner of the male undergarment shop.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the period, fundoshi got some attention for sevel times, featured by the mass media, and each time invoked a temporal boom; but it has never taken root and has never resulted in occupying one of corners of the male undergarment shop.</e>
<cmt>戦後、という語があまりにも大雑把に使用されているので（廃れたのも戦後なのでここでafter the warというと混乱すると思われますし）、この間にも　during the period　で受けました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the period, fundoshi got some attention for sevel times, featured by the mass media, and each time invoked a temporal boom; but it has never taken root and has never resulted in occupying one of corners of the male undergarment shop.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="19">
<j>これは以下のような理由から大手下着製造業者が積極的に手掛けにくいニッチ商品であることが、大手流通網に乗らず、広く店頭に並ばない理由と推測される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As to this state of things, we can guess that it is the reason why Ecchu fundoshi are not delivered on the major distribution network and don&apos;t go on sale extensively, that Ecchu fundoshi are niche goods which are difficult for the major undergarment manufacturers to deal with actively for the following reasons.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。「推測される」の主語は「ニッチ商品であることが」であると思われるので、文頭の「これは」の役割、用法を明確に解釈できないため、前文を受けて「この状況については」としてみました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This can be understood that because the fundoshi is a niche item that the major undergarment manufacturers cannot easily embarked on the production with the following reasons, the undergarment cannot be traded on the major distribution network, and thus it&apos;s rare to find them in stores.</e>
<cmt>大手製造業者が手がけにくい→大手流通網に乗らない→店頭に並ばない、そのため上記のように下着売り場の一角を占めないことがおきた、その理由は後列だ、という構成だと思います。原文が非常にわかりづらいですが。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This can be understood that because the fundoshi is a niche item that the major undergarment manufacturers cannot easily embarked on the production with the following reasons, the undergarment cannot be traded on the major distribution network, and thus it&apos;s rare to find them in stores.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>越中褌が究極の形状であることから、昔からデザインの変化がないことで、材質や色か柄でしか商品として差別化ができないこと、白色が定番の越中褌では色物や柄物では極端に需要が少なく採算に合わないこと、個人でも縫製できるものであるため、単価も安く利益率が低いこと、他の下着と比べて需要の伸びが大きく見込めず、設備投資に見合う大量販売が見込めないことなどである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Ecchu fundoshi are in the ultimate shape, their design has not been changed since a long time ago, so they can barely be differentiate as merchandise only in materials, colors, or patterns; as white is the standard color of Ecchu fundoshi, there is extremely little demand for those colored or patterned, so they will not pay; as even an individual person can sew Ecchu fundoshi, their unit price is low and their profit ratio is also low; and the demand for Ecchu fundoshi can&apos;t be expected to grow so great as the demand for the other undergarments, and large quantities of sales proportionate to the capital investment can&apos;t be estimated.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。この文も箇条書きにしたほうがわかりやすくなると思われます。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The seasons are: (1) as Ecchu fundoshi has the ultimate shape in its kind, the design has not changed for a long time, manufacturers can only make a difference in material, color or pattern; (2) as the most typical color for the fundoshi is white, there is extremely limited demand for other colors or patterns, and thus making a difference cannot be paid off; (3) since this is not so difficult to make, as they were made at home in the previous period, the price and profit rate should be low accordingly; and (4) it&apos;s hard to expect a large sale that can pay off the capital investment, as it&apos;s hard to expect a growing demand in comparison to other undergarments.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The seasons are: (1) as Ecchu fundoshi has the ultimate shape in its kind, the design has not changed for a long time, manufacturers can only make a difference in material, color or pattern; (2) as the most typical color for the fundoshi is white, there is extremely limited demand for other colors or patterns, and thus making a difference cannot be paid off; (3) since this is not so difficult to make, as they were made at home in the previous period, the price and profit rate should be low accordingly; and (4) it&apos;s hard to expect a large sale that can pay off the capital investment, as it&apos;s hard to expect a growing demand in comparison to other undergarments.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="21">
<j>一部の百貨店や呉服店で販売されているに過ぎないが、近年ではインターネットの出現でインターネット通販を用いた褌製造販売専門業者などが生まれ、容易に購入できるようになり、ブリーフやトランクスしか知らない世代が「褌」を新鮮な下着として認識し始めたことで、新たな購買層となっているようだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Ecchu fundoshi are only sold at some of the department stores or the kimono shops, in recent years the advent of the Internet has brought about appearance of the companies that are devoted to manufacturing and selling fundoshi using Internet mail order and made it easy to buy them, and so the generation who had known only briefs and trunks seem to be turning into a new buyer group as a result of beginning to regard &quot;fundoshi&quot; as a new undergarment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While Ecchu fundoshi are only sold at some of the department stores or the kimono shops, in recent years the advent of the Internet has brought about appearance of the companies that are devoted to manufacturing and selling fundoshi using Internet mail order and made it easy to buy them, and so the generation who had known only briefs and trunks seem to be turning into a new buyer group as a result of beginning to regard &quot;fundoshi&quot; as a new undergarment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While Ecchu fundoshi are only sold at some of the department stores or the kimono shops, in recent years the advent of the Internet has brought about appearance of the companies that are devoted to manufacturing and selling fundoshi using Internet mail order and made it easy to buy them, and so the generation who had known only briefs and trunks seem to be turning into a new buyer group as a result of beginning to regard &quot;fundoshi&quot; as a new undergarment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="22">
<j>パンツのようにゴムを使わず、高温多湿の日本の気候で褌の持つ機能や効能を支持する愛好家は現在でも確かに存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is certain that there exist the fanciers even now who uphold the function and effectiveness that fundoshi bring about in the Japanese climate with high temperature and high humidity since elastic is not used for fundoshi unlike underpants.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is certain that there exist the fanciers even now who uphold the function and effectiveness that fundoshi bring about in the Japanese climate with high temperature and high humidity since elastic is not used for fundoshi unlike underpants.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is certain that there exist the fanciers even now who uphold the function and effectiveness that fundoshi bring about in the Japanese climate with high temperature and high humidity since elastic is not used for fundoshi unlike underpants.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>虚飾性を排し、単純な一枚の布で全ての機能が完結する「潔さ」が、日本人が古来から持つ「美意識」と共通するものがあり、日本の古典的な理想の男子像にも例えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Manly graciousness&quot; that excludes vanity and concludes all the functions with a simple piece of cloth has something common to &quot;the sense of beauty&quot; that Japanese have cherished since ancient times, and is compared to the classic and ideal image of a man in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It can represent &apos;graciousness&apos; that excludes vanity and completes all the functions with a simple piece of cloth, and it reminds us &quot;the sense of beauty&quot; that the Japanese have cherished since ancient times, and can even exemplify the classic and ideal image of a man in Japan.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It can represent &apos;graciousness&apos; that excludes vanity and completes all the functions with a simple piece of cloth, and it reminds us &quot;the sense of beauty&quot; that the Japanese have cherished since ancient times, and can even exemplify the classic and ideal image of a man in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>越中褌の独特の形状から、白い越中褌を締めた東洋人男性ならば「日本人男性」であるとの暗黙知が日本人にあり、映画、テレビなどの劇中で、しばしば日本人男性を示す象徴として用いられたりしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the shape of Ecchu fundoshi is unique, the Japanese have an implicit knowledge that an Eastern man who wears white Ecchu fundoshi must be &quot;a Japanese man&quot;, and Ecchu fundoshi is often used as a symbol suggesting a Japanese man in dramas of the movies or on TV.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of the unmistakable shape of Ecchu fundoshi, an acknowledgement has implicitly been held by the Japanese that an oriental man who wears a white Ecchu fundoshi must be a Japanese man, and indeed the fundoshi is often used as a symbol that indicates a Japanese man in movies or TV dramas.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of the unmistakable shape of Ecchu fundoshi, an acknowledgement has implicitly been held by the Japanese that an oriental man who wears a white Ecchu fundoshi must be a Japanese man, and indeed the fundoshi is often used as a symbol that indicates a Japanese man in movies or TV dramas.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="25">
<j>褌を着用することで、虚飾を排し、時流に流されることなく本質を求道する理想の日本人男子像を具現化するものとして、褌にこだわりを抱く愛好家は少なくない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Not a few fanciers have an obsession with fundoshi as something that realizes an ideal image of a Japanese man who will exclude vanity and won&apos;t swim with the current of the times to seek the essence by wearing fundoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Not a few fanciers have an obsession with fundoshi as something that realizes an ideal image of a Japanese man who will exclude vanity and won&apos;t swim with the current of the times to seek the essence by wearing fundoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Not a few fanciers have an obsession with fundoshi as something that realizes an ideal image of a Japanese man who will exclude vanity and won&apos;t swim with the current of the times to seek the essence by wearing fundoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>一部下着メーカーの越中褌の製造出荷量は、戦後から現在でも一定で、しかも相当数の販売数を保っていることからも推測される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This can be guessed from the fact that some of the undergarment makers have manufactured and shipped almost the same volume of Ecchu fundoshi since the post war period till now, and what is more, they are keeping considerably large quantity of sales.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This can be guessed from the fact that some of the undergarment makers have manufactured and shipped almost the same volume of Ecchu fundoshi since the post war period till now, and what is more, they are keeping considerably large quantity of sales.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This can be guessed from the fact that some of the undergarment makers have manufactured and shipped almost the same volume of Ecchu fundoshi since the post war period till now, and what is more, they are keeping considerably large quantity of sales.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="27">
<j>軍隊と越中褌</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Army and Ecchu Fundoshi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Army and Ecchu Fundoshi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Army and Ecchu Fundoshi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>特に、軍隊で支給された下着（官給品）であったことで全国に普及する下着となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ecchu fundoshi became the undergarments that spread all over the country, particularly because they are the undergarments that were provided in the army (as articles supplied at official expense).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ecchu fundoshi became the undergarments that spread all over the country, particularly because they are the undergarments that were provided in the army (as articles supplied at official expense).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ecchu fundoshi became the undergarments that spread all over the country, particularly because they are the undergarments that were provided in the army (as articles supplied at official expense).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>十代の少年が入校する陸軍幼年学校（13歳）や海軍兵学校 （17歳）でさえ、入校したら、「娑婆っ気」を排斥する目的で、下着を含めて一切の私物は自宅に送り返すように指導し、入校者に下着として白い越中褌を支給した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even in the case of the Army Cadet School or the Naval Academy which teenage boys entered (the former at thirteen years old, and the latter at seventeen years old), once a boy entered them, the staff directed him to send back all his personal belongings including undergarments to his home in order to exclude &quot;yearning for the outside world&quot;, and provided the new student with white Ecchu fundoshi as undergarments.</e>
<cmt>原文の「海軍兵学校 (日本)」をWeb原稿に合わせて「海軍兵学校」に訂正しました。訳文では「十代の・・・」を学校名の後に記述したので、各学校の入学年齢をその後にまとめて記載しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even in the case of the Army Cadet School or the Naval Academy which teenage boys entered (the former at thirteen years old, and the latter at seventeen years old), once a boy entered them, the staff directed him to send back all his personal belongings including undergarments to his home in order to exclude &quot;yearning for the outside world&quot;, and provided the new student with white Ecchu fundoshi as undergarments.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even in the case of the Army Cadet School or the Naval Academy which teenage boys entered (the former at thirteen years old, and the latter at seventeen years old), once a boy entered them, the staff directed him to send back all his personal belongings including undergarments to his home in order to exclude &quot;yearning for the outside world&quot;, and provided the new student with white Ecchu fundoshi as undergarments.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>軍隊組織において、制服を始めとして、下着まで統一することで個性を否定して規律を維持する必要があったからである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because it was required to reject each personality and maintain discipline by unifying not only the uniforms but also the undergarments in the armed forces&apos; organization.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because it was required to reject each personality and maintain discipline by unifying not only the uniforms but also the undergarments in the armed forces&apos; organization.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because it was required to reject each personality and maintain discipline by unifying not only the uniforms but also the undergarments in the armed forces&apos; organization.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="31">
<j>（現在でも軍隊では下着まで統一している国が多い）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Even now, many countries unify as far as undergarments in the army.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Even now, many countries adopt an unified undergarment in the army.)</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Even now, many countries adopt an unified undergarment in the army.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="32">
<j>明治政府が徴兵制度を導入したのは、義務教育と並び、国民の生活様式や言語を標準化させて富国強兵策を遂行する目的を担っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Meiji government introduced the conscription system in order to standardize the lifestyle and language of the nation with it as well as with the compulsory education and to accomplish the measure to enrich and strengthen the country.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The conscription system that was introduced by the Meiji government involved an aim, along with the compulsory education, to standardizethe lifestyle and the language of the nation to make the country rich and strong.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The conscription system that was introduced by the Meiji government involved an aim, along with the compulsory education, to standardizethe lifestyle and the language of the nation to make the country rich and strong.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>越中褌は六尺褌と比較して着脱が容易で生地も少ない経済性が官給品として軍隊で採用されたものと推測される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It can be guessed that Ecchu fundoshi were adopted as articles supplied at official expense because they were easier to put on and take off and they were economical for being made from less cloth than Rokushaku fundoshi.</e>
<cmt>原文では「経済性が」の係る先が見当たらないので「経済性があったので」と解釈しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It can be guessed that Ecchu fundoshi were adopted as articles supplied at official expense because they were easier to put on and take off and they were economical for being made from less cloth than Rokushaku fundoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It can be guessed that Ecchu fundoshi were adopted as articles supplied at official expense because they were easier to put on and take off and they were economical for being made from less cloth than Rokushaku fundoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="34">
<j>戦前までは徴兵検査を受けることで「成人男子に達した証」と社会的に認知されるようになっており、徴兵検査（陸軍身体検査規則）で褌の着用を指導していたことも、疑似「褌祝」として成人男子に越中褌が普及した背景があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Until the end of the war, to take the examination for conscription led to being recognized as &quot;proof of becoming an adult male&quot; in the society, and to direct the examinee to wear fundoshi in the examination for conscription (the regulations for physical examination of the army) was also in the background of the spread of Ecchu fundoshi among adult males as pseudo &quot;Fundoshi-iwai&quot;.</e>
<cmt>「陸軍身体検査規則」の正式な英語表記は未確認です。原文は舌足らずで、「普及した背景があったから指導していた」とも「「指導していたことが普及した背景にあった」とも読み取れるので、後者として解釈しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Until the end of the war, taking an examination to be drafted was regarded as a proof of becoming an adult man in the society, and people were encouraged to wear fundoshi at the examination (the regulations for physical examination of the army); and thus this helped Ecchu fundoshi to spread across the country, reminding people a &apos;fundoshi iwai&apos;, a rite to wear fundoshi as an adult man.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Until the end of the war, taking an examination to be drafted was regarded as a proof of becoming an adult man in the society, and people were encouraged to wear fundoshi at the examination (the regulations for physical examination of the army); and thus this helped Ecchu fundoshi to spread across the country, reminding people a &apos;fundoshi iwai&apos;, a rite to wear fundoshi as an adult man.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="35">
<j>「陸軍身体検査規則」（1928年3月26日陸軍省令第9号／昭和3年第15号）第二十三条七号に以下のように記述されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Article 23, Item 7 of &quot;the regulations for physical examination of the army&quot; (March 26, 1928, Ordinance No. 9 of Ministry of Army/the third year of the Showa era [1928], No.15) is described as follows.</e>
<cmt>後列の文の冒頭にあった「と記述され、」を「以下のように記述されている。」に変更してこの文の末尾に結合しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Article 23, Item 7 of &quot;the regulations for physical examination of the army&quot; (March 26, 1928, Ordinance No. 9 of Ministry of Army/the third year of the Showa era [1928], No.15) is described as follows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Article 23, Item 7 of &quot;the regulations for physical examination of the army&quot; (March 26, 1928, Ordinance No. 9 of Ministry of Army/the third year of the Showa era [1928], No.15) is described as follows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="36">
<j>陰部ノ検査ハ受検者ヲシテ脱褌セシメ両脚ヲ開キ検者ニ正面シテ立タシメ鼠蹊部、陰茎、陰嚢、精系、睾丸及副睾丸ノ異常ノ有無ヲ検査シ排尿ノ難易、遺尿ノ有無ヲ検シ必要アルトキハ排尿セシメテ尿ノ性状ヲ検査ス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To examine the pubic region, make an examinee take off his fundoshi, make him stand with legs apart and facing the examiner, inspect the groin, the penis, the scrotum, the spermatic cord, the testicles, and the epididymis for their abnormalities, check whether it is hard to pass urine or not and whether there is enuresis or not, and if necessary, make him pass urine and test the properties of the urine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To examine the pubic region, make an examinee take off his fundoshi, make him stand with legs apart and facing the examiner, inspect the groin, the penis, the scrotum, the spermatic cord, the testicles, and the epididymis for their abnormalities, check whether it is hard to pass urine or not and whether there is enuresis or not, and if necessary, make him pass urine and test the properties of the urine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To examine the pubic region, make an examinee take off his fundoshi, make him stand with legs apart and facing the examiner, inspect the groin, the penis, the scrotum, the spermatic cord, the testicles, and the epididymis for their abnormalities, check whether it is hard to pass urine or not and whether there is enuresis or not, and if necessary, make him pass urine and test the properties of the urine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="37">
<j>徴兵検査受験者に褌の着用を指導していたことがわかる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This item shows that an examinee of the examination for conscription was directed to wear fundoshi.</e>
<cmt>文頭の「と記述され、」を前列に移動して上の文と分断し、末尾を「していたことがわかる。」に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This shows that examinees of the test were directed to wear fundoshi.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This shows that examinees of the test were directed to wear fundoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="38">
<j>戦後は、褌の着用を強制されていたことでの反発から旧軍隊の遺物の象徴のような存在として否定的なとらえ方をされるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the war, fundoshi came to be looked upon negatively as an existence just like a symbol of what the former army left behind, from the antipathy toward having been forced to wear it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the war, fundoshi came to be looked upon negatively as an existence just like a symbol of what the former army left behind, from the antipathy toward having been forced to wear it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the war, fundoshi came to be looked upon negatively as an existence just like a symbol of what the former army left behind, from the antipathy toward having been forced to wear it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="39">
<j>愛好家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fanciers</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fundoshi Fans</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fundoshi Fans</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>越中褌の愛好家は他の下着には無い、独特の軽い着装感から愛好している例が多いと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that there are many instances in which the fanciers of Ecchu fundoshi love Ecchu fundoshi because of the unique light feeling of wearing that no other undergarments have.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that there are many instances in which the fanciers of Ecchu fundoshi love Ecchu fundoshi because of the unique light feeling of wearing that no other undergarments have.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that there are many instances in which the fanciers of Ecchu fundoshi love Ecchu fundoshi because of the unique light feeling of wearing that no other undergarments have.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>高温多湿の日本の風土に合った吸湿性の高い下着として支持が集まるものと推測される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It can be supposed that the support for Ecchu fundoshi gathers because Ecchu fundoshi are the absorbent undergarments which are suitable for the natural features of Japan with the high temperature and high humidity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It can be supposed that the support for Ecchu fundoshi gathers because Ecchu fundoshi are the absorbent undergarments which are suitable for the natural features of Japan with the high temperature and high humidity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It can be supposed that the support for Ecchu fundoshi gathers because Ecchu fundoshi are the absorbent undergarments which are suitable for the natural features of Japan with the high temperature and high humidity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>他に、健康指向で愛用されている例が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to those, there are many instances of Ecchu fundoshi used habitually for the health-oriented purpose.</e>
<cmt>この場合の「健康指向」は、意味を推測すると「健康志向」のほうが適切であると解釈しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to those, there are many instances of Ecchu fundoshi used habitually for the health-oriented purpose.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to those, there are many instances of Ecchu fundoshi used habitually for the health-oriented purpose.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="43">
<j>ゆったりとしていてゴムがないため、かぶれを回避できるなどの理由からアトピー性皮膚炎を患う患者や、ブリーフのように体に密着せず通気性があることが高温多湿な日本の風土にも合っていて身体に良く、精巣の温度を適度に保ち精子数を増加させる効能もあるらしいとの評判から不妊に悩む男性に利用されているようだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, Ecchu fundoshi seem to be utilized by the patients who suffer from atopic dermatitis because a rash can be averted thanks to their looseness and lack of elastic, and by the men who suffer from sterility based on the rumor that because they don&apos;t adhere to the body and they breathe well, they are suitable to the natural features of Japan with high temperature and high humidity and good for the body, and that they have the effectiveness to keep the temperature of the testis moderately and increase the number of sperms.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, Ecchu fundoshi seem to be utilized by the patients who suffer from atopic dermatitis because a rash can be averted thanks to their looseness and lack of elastic, and by the men who suffer from sterility based on the rumor that because they don&apos;t adhere to the body and they breathe well, they are suitable to the natural features of Japan with high temperature and high humidity and good for the body, and that they have the effectiveness to keep the temperature of the testis moderately and increase the number of sperms.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, Ecchu fundoshi seem to be utilized by the patients who suffer from atopic dermatitis because a rash can be averted thanks to their looseness and lack of elastic, and by the men who suffer from sterility based on the rumor that because they don&apos;t adhere to the body and they breathe well, they are suitable to the natural features of Japan with high temperature and high humidity and good for the body, and that they have the effectiveness to keep the temperature of the testis moderately and increase the number of sperms.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>また、片足を上げたり、屈んだりせずに着脱ができることや、靴やズボンを脱がずに下着を交換できることから、ヘルニアなどの腰痛に苦しむ人々に加えて、実用面でも、吸湿性が良いことから夏場に野外で作業をする人達や、着替えに場所や時間の制約がある人達の他に長時間着席を余儀なくされる業務を行う人達にも愛用されているようだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">What is more, Ecchu fundoshi seem to be used habitually not only by the people who suffer from lumbago such as a rupture because they can be put on and taken off without lifting one leg nor bending down, or because undergarments can be exchanged without taking off shoes nor trousers, but also, for the practical purpose, by the people who work outdoors in the summer because they are absorbent, by the people who are restricted about the place or the time to change their clothes, and also by the people who, while working, are obliged to be seated for a long time.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">What is more, Ecchu fundoshi seem to be used habitually not only by the people who suffer from lumbago such as a rupture because they can be put on and taken off without lifting one leg nor bending down, or because undergarments can be exchanged without taking off shoes nor trousers, but also, for the practical purpose, by the people who work outdoors in the summer because they are absorbent, by the people who are restricted about the place or the time to change their clothes, and also by the people who, while working, are obliged to be seated for a long time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">What is more, Ecchu fundoshi seem to be used habitually not only by the people who suffer from lumbago such as a rupture because they can be put on and taken off without lifting one leg nor bending down, or because undergarments can be exchanged without taking off shoes nor trousers, but also, for the practical purpose, by the people who work outdoors in the summer because they are absorbent, by the people who are restricted about the place or the time to change their clothes, and also by the people who, while working, are obliged to be seated for a long time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="45">
<j>T字帯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">T-jitai</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">T-jitai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">T-jitai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>医療用の下着としてT字帯（てぃじたい）とも呼ばれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ecchu fundoshi is also called T-jitai as a medical undergarment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ecchu fundoshi is also called T-jitai as a medical undergarment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ecchu fundoshi is also called T-jitai as a medical undergarment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>紐を拡げた形状がアルファベットの「T」の字に似ていることから呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is called so because the shape with its strings spread horizontally looks like an alphabet &apos;T&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is called so because the shape with its strings spread horizontally looks like an alphabet &apos;T&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is called so because the shape with its strings spread horizontally looks like an alphabet &apos;T&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="48">
<j>介護の際、下着の交換が容易で、患者や介護者の肉体的負担を減らすことから用いられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">T-jitai are used because, when someone takes care of a patient, they can make it easy to change the undergarments and can relieve the physical load on a patient and a caregiver.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">T-jitai are used because, when someone takes care of a patient, they can make it easy to change the undergarments and can relieve the physical load on a patient and a caregiver.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">T-jitai are used because, when someone takes care of a patient, they can make it easy to change the undergarments and can relieve the physical load on a patient and a caregiver.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>特に開腹手術を行う患者や、足腰に外傷を負った患者に用いられている例が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially, there are many instances where T-jitai are used by a patient who will undergo a laparotomy or a patient who has received an external injury around the legs or hips.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Especially, there are many instances where T-jitai are used by a patient who will undergo a laparotomy or a patient who has received an external injury around the legs or hips.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Especially, there are many instances where T-jitai are used by a patient who will undergo a laparotomy or a patient who has received an external injury around the legs or hips.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>材質も医療用ガーゼを用いたものが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As to the quality of the material, medical gauze is used for many of T-jitai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As to the quality of the material, medical gauze is used for many of T-jitai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As to the quality of the material, medical gauze is used for many of T-jitai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>病院の売店、薬局・薬店、ベビー用品店で発売されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are sold at hospital stores, pharmacies, drugstores, and baby product stores.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are sold at hospital stores, pharmacies, drugstores, and baby product stores.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are sold at hospital stores, pharmacies, drugstores, and baby product stores.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>他にも越中褌に似てるが前垂れの部分が二股に割れてるT字帯もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides, there is another type of T-jitai which resembles Ecchu fundoshi but whose maedare is split into two.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides, there is another type of T-jitai which resembles Ecchu fundoshi but whose maedare is split into two.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides, there is another type of T-jitai which resembles Ecchu fundoshi but whose maedare is split into two.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>前垂れ以外の部分にビニールを貼ってある製品もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is also a product that has plastic sheets stuck on all the parts except the maedare.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is also a product that has plastic sheets stuck on all the parts except the maedare.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is also a product that has plastic sheets stuck on all the parts except the maedare.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>患部を保護するガーゼ、パッドの上から越中褌と同様に装着後、2つに割れた前垂れの部分を両側の紐に巻きつけるので、もっこ褌のような形状になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This type of T-jitai becomes a shape like Mokko fundoshi (earth-basket loincloth), because after putting on in the same way as Ecchu fundoshi over the gauze or pad that protects the diseased part, the parts of the maedare which is split into two will be wound around to the strings on the both sides.</e>
<cmt>「もっこ褌」の正式な英語表記、説明は未確認です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This type of T-jitai becomes a shape like Mokko fundoshi (literally, earth-basket loincloth), because after putting on in the same way as Ecchu fundoshi over the gauze or pad that protects the diseased part, the parts of the maedare which is split into two will be wound around to the strings on the both sides.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This type of T-jitai becomes a shape like Mokko fundoshi (literally, earth-basket loincloth), because after putting on in the same way as Ecchu fundoshi over the gauze or pad that protects the diseased part, the parts of the maedare which is split into two will be wound around to the strings on the both sides.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>クラシックパンツ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Classic Pants</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Classic Pants</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Classic Pants</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="55">
<j>1965年（昭和40年）に肌着に自社ブランドを立ち上げた三越が、高級感を持たせるためや女性が代理購入する場合でも恥ずかしくないように越中褌を「クラシックパンツ」と命名して販売したため、他の百貨店などでもそう呼ぶようになったとの説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is an opinion that because Mitsukoshi which started up the company&apos;s store brand in underwear in 1965 sold Ecchu fundoshi by naming them &quot;Classic Pants&quot; in order to make them create an impression of the high-grade undergarment and for women not to be embarrassed when they buy one on behalf of men, the other department stores and shops have come to call them by the same name.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is an opinion that because Mitsukoshi which started up the company&apos;s store brand in underwear in 1965 sold Ecchu fundoshi by naming them &quot;Classic Pants&quot; in order to make them create an impression of the high-grade undergarment and for women not to be embarrassed when they buy one on behalf of men, the other department stores and shops have come to call them by the same name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is an opinion that because Mitsukoshi which started up the company&apos;s store brand in underwear in 1965 sold Ecchu fundoshi by naming them &quot;Classic Pants&quot; in order to make them create an impression of the high-grade undergarment and for women not to be embarrassed when they buy one on behalf of men, the other department stores and shops have come to call them by the same name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>因みに、「クラシックパンツ」は和製英語で、英語表記では褌を loincloth と表する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By the way, the term &quot;Classic Pants&quot; is a Japanese English (Japanese word constructed of elements from one or more English terms), and fundoshi is expressed as &quot;loincloth&quot; in English expression.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It should be noted that the term &quot;Classic Pants&quot; is a Japanese English word (an English word or phrase coined in Japan), and the nearest word for fundoshi in English is loincloth.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It should be noted that the term &quot;Classic Pants&quot; is a Japanese English word (an English word or phrase coined in Japan), and the nearest word for fundoshi in English is loincloth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="57">
<j>2005年（平成17年）になってテレビ番組『トリビアの泉』でとりあげられたことがきっかけとなり、銀座三越ではふんどしが2週間で年間売り上げの倍以上が売れたり、 買い求める女性客が目立つようになったという報道が流れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was reported by the mass media that as fundoshi was featured in a television program &quot;Toribia no izumi&quot; (the fountain of trivia) in 2005, with this as a turning point, at the Mitsukoshi Ginza Store fundoshi sold more than twice the annual sales in two weeks, and the women customers who purchased fundoshi increased prominently.</e>
<cmt>原文の「『トリビアの泉 〜素晴らしきムダ知識〜』」をWeb原稿に合わせて「『トリビアの泉』」に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was reported by the mass media that as fundoshi was featured in a television program &quot;Toribia no izumi&quot; (the fountain of trivia) in 2005, with this as a turning point, at the Mitsukoshi Ginza Store fundoshi sold more than twice the annual sales in two weeks, and the women customers who purchased fundoshi increased prominently.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was reported by the mass media that as fundoshi was featured in a television program &quot;Toribia no izumi&quot; (the fountain of trivia) in 2005, with this as a turning point, at the Mitsukoshi Ginza Store fundoshi sold more than twice the annual sales in two weeks, and the women customers who purchased fundoshi increased prominently.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>しかし、「クラシックパンツ」の名称で他社でも市販していることから、「クラシックパンツ」は三越独自の登録商標ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But since the other companies also put fundoshi on the market with the name &quot;Classic Pants&quot;, &quot;Classic Pants&quot; is not a registered trademark proper to Mitsukoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But since the other companies also put fundoshi on the market with the name &quot;Classic Pants&quot;, &quot;Classic Pants&quot; is not a registered trademark proper to Mitsukoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But since the other companies also put fundoshi on the market with the name &quot;Classic Pants&quot;, &quot;Classic Pants&quot; is not a registered trademark proper to Mitsukoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="59">
<j>「クラシックパンツ」の呼称は三越が命名したと言われる以前（1963年（昭和38年）頃）から、コミック・コントを手掛けた音楽バンドのドンキーカルテットが、舞台コント上でメンバーの一人であるジャイアント吉田によって既に取り上げられてもいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name &quot;Classic Pants&quot; had already been referred to also in a comic short play on the stage by Giant YOSHIDA, a member of Donkey Quartet, a musical band that performed a comic skit, since before the time when it was said that Mitsukoshi named it (about 1963).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before Mitsukoshi was said to name it a &apos;Classic Pants&apos; around 1963, the name had already been used in a comic short play by Giant YOSHIDA, a member of Donkey Quartet, a musical band that performed a comic skit.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before Mitsukoshi was said to name it a &apos;Classic Pants&apos; around 1963, the name had already been used in a comic short play by Giant YOSHIDA, a member of Donkey Quartet, a musical band that performed a comic skit.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="60">
<j>「クラシックパンツ」の名称で三越と同様にアングル・ミユキ株式会社やオグラン株式会社でも製造販売を行っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ecchu fundoshi were also manufactured and sold with the name &quot;Classic Pants&quot; by Angle-Miyuki Co., Ltd. and Ogran Co., Ltd. as well as Mitsukoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ecchu fundoshi were also manufactured and sold with the name &quot;Classic Pants&quot; by Angle-Miyuki Co., Ltd. and Ogran Co., Ltd. as well as Mitsukoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ecchu fundoshi were also manufactured and sold with the name &quot;Classic Pants&quot; by Angle-Miyuki Co., Ltd. and Ogran Co., Ltd. as well as Mitsukoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="61">
<j>アングル・ミユキ製の方が三越製よりも流通チャネルが多岐に渡ることから販売量は三越製よりも上回る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The distribution channels of those made by Angle-Miyuki are more diverse than the distribution channels of those made by Mitsukoshi, so the sales volume of those made by Angle-Miyuki exceeds the sales volume of those made by Mitsukoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The products by Angle-Miyuki has more diversified distribution network than Mitsukoshi&apos;s, and thus the volume of sales is greater than the one by Mitsukoshi.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The products by Angle-Miyuki has more diversified distribution network than Mitsukoshi&apos;s, and thus the volume of sales is greater than the one by Mitsukoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>全国有名デパートの紳士用品売り場に置かれる「クラシックパンツ」はアングル・ミユキ製の方が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As to &quot;Classic Pants&quot; that are displayed in the men&apos;s goods shops of the famous department stores in the whole Japan, those made by Angle-Miyuki outnumber those made by Mitsukoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">So the pants by Angle-Miyuki can be found more easily in the men&apos;s section in major department stores across Japan.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">So the pants by Angle-Miyuki can be found more easily in the men&apos;s section in major department stores across Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>同社製の販売量は三越製の販売量を凌駕している（アングル・ミユキ製の年間製造量は1万枚に対し三越製の販売量は3千枚と言われている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Classic pants&quot; made by Angle-Miyuki surpassed those made by Mitsukoshi in sales volume (It is said that while the number of those made by Angle-Miyuki in a year is 10,000, the sales volume of those made by Mitsukoshi is 3,000.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sales of the pants by Angle-Miyuki surpassed the one of Mitsukoshi&apos;s (it is estimated that Angle-Miyuki manufactures 10,000 a year, and Mitsukoshi sells 3,000 pants a year).</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sales of the pants by Angle-Miyuki surpassed the one of Mitsukoshi&apos;s (it is estimated that Angle-Miyuki manufactures 10,000 a year, and Mitsukoshi sells 3,000 pants a year).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="64">
<j>アングル・ミユキ株式会社は2002年（平成14年）にアングル株式会社が経営不振により御幸毛織グループの傘下に入ったことで社名が変更になったものだが、前身は1894年（明治27年）にメリヤス肌着の製造販売を開始したことから始まる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Angle-Miyuki Co., Ltd. is a company which changed the company name from Angle Co., Ltd. because Angle Co., Ltd. came under the umbrella of the Miyukikeori group because of its financial difficulties in 2002, and its predecessor started business by beginning to manufacture and sell knitted underwear in 1894.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Angle-Miyuki Co., Ltd. is a company which changed the company name from Angle Co., Ltd. because Angle Co., Ltd. came under the umbrella of the Miyukikeori group because of its financial difficulties in 2002, and its predecessor started business by beginning to manufacture and sell knitted underwear in 1894.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Angle-Miyuki Co., Ltd. is a company which changed the company name from Angle Co., Ltd. because Angle Co., Ltd. came under the umbrella of the Miyukikeori group because of its financial difficulties in 2002, and its predecessor started business by beginning to manufacture and sell knitted underwear in 1894.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>同社製の越中褌は三越が「クラシックパンツ」と命名したと言われる以前から同名で販売しており、その頃既に包装紙に「クラシックパンツ」と記載されていることから、「クラシックパンツ」の名称が「三越」で命名されたとの説には疑問が残る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ecchu fundoshi made by the said company had been sold by the name &quot;Classic Pants&quot; since before Mitsukoshi was said to have named them so, and in those days the name &quot;Classic Pants&quot; had already been printed on the wrapping paper, and therefore, there remains question about the opinion that &quot;Classic Pants&quot; is a name which &quot;Mitsukoshi&quot; gave.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ecchu fundoshi made by the said company had been sold by the name &quot;Classic Pants&quot; since before Mitsukoshi was said to have named them so, and in those days the name &quot;Classic Pants&quot; had already been printed on the wrapping paper, and therefore, there remains question about the opinion that &quot;Classic Pants&quot; is a name which &quot;Mitsukoshi&quot; gave.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ecchu fundoshi made by the said company had been sold by the name &quot;Classic Pants&quot; since before Mitsukoshi was said to have named them so, and in those days the name &quot;Classic Pants&quot; had already been printed on the wrapping paper, and therefore, there remains question about the opinion that &quot;Classic Pants&quot; is a name which &quot;Mitsukoshi&quot; gave.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>因みに同社の「クラシックパンツ」の包装紙は販売開始以来同じデザインを続けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By the way, the wrapping paper for &quot;Classic Pants&quot; of the said company has been kept the same in its design since the start of the sales.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By the way, the wrapping paper for &quot;Classic Pants&quot; of the said company has been kept the same in its design since the start of the sales.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By the way, the wrapping paper for &quot;Classic Pants&quot; of the said company has been kept the same in its design since the start of the sales.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>現在、アングル・ミユキでは年間生産量を決めると日本国内で一括発注して製造している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At present, Angle-Miyuki issues a bulk order to manufacture Ecchu fundoshi when it decides the annual production.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At present, Angle-Miyuki issues a bulk order to manufacture Ecchu fundoshi when it decides the annual production.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At present, Angle-Miyuki issues a bulk order to manufacture Ecchu fundoshi when it decides the annual production.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>同社の「クラシックパンツ」は同じ製品でも製造年度によっては生地が異なることがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Classic Pants&quot; of the said company sometimes differ in fabric according as the manufacturing year even though they are the same product.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Classic Pants&quot; of the said company sometimes differ in fabric according as the manufacturing year even though they are the same product.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Classic Pants&quot; of the said company sometimes differ in fabric according as the manufacturing year even though they are the same product.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>同社の「クラシックパンツ」の年間製造枚数は販売以来ほぼ一定の生産枚数を保っていることから、年月を経ても一定の需要があることは、買い換え層以外にも新たな「褌」愛好家が生まれている証左であると推測される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because the annual manufacturing number of &quot;Classic Pants&quot; of the said company has held a constant production since the start of sales, that there has been a constant demand for many years can be supposed to be the evidence that new &quot;fundoshi&quot; fanciers have been produced as well as the group of purchasers for replacement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because the annual manufacturing number of &quot;Classic Pants&quot; of the said company has held a constant production since the start of sales, that there has been a constant demand for many years can be supposed to be the evidence that new &quot;fundoshi&quot; fanciers have been produced as well as the group of purchasers for replacement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because the annual manufacturing number of &quot;Classic Pants&quot; of the said company has held a constant production since the start of sales, that there has been a constant demand for many years can be supposed to be the evidence that new &quot;fundoshi&quot; fanciers have been produced as well as the group of purchasers for replacement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="70">
<j>また、オグラン株式会社が同様に「クラシックパンツ」の名称で販売しており、リボン紐を用いて廉価なことに特徴がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides, Ogran Co., Ltd. sells Ecchu fundoshi by the name &quot;Classic Pants&quot; as well, and they are characterized by the use of ribbon strings and the low price.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides, Ogran Co., Ltd. sells Ecchu fundoshi with the name &quot;Classic Pants&quot; as well, and the company is featured with low price, using ribbon strings.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides, Ogran Co., Ltd. sells Ecchu fundoshi with the name &quot;Classic Pants&quot; as well, and the company is featured with low price, using ribbon strings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="71">
<j>このほか、「クラシックパンツ」の名称は用いず、堂々と「褌」の名称を用いて販売している会社もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to these, there are some companies that also sell them, not using the name &quot;Classic Pants&quot;, but confidently using the name &quot;Fundoshi&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to them, there are some companies that also sell fundoshi, not using the name &quot;Classic Pants&quot;, but confidently using the exact name, &quot;Fundoshi&quot;.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to them, there are some companies that also sell fundoshi, not using the name &quot;Classic Pants&quot;, but confidently using the exact name, &quot;Fundoshi&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>株式会社レナウンがその代表で、セロファンの包装紙に毛筆字体で大きく「褌」と記載して販売している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Renown Incorporated is typical of those companies, which sells Ecchu fundoshi using cellophane wrapping sheets on which a large Chinese character &quot;褌&quot; (fundoshi) is written in a writing brush type.</e>
<cmt>原稿の「レナウン (企業)」をWeb原稿に合わせて「レナウン」に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Renown Incorporated can be the most notable example, and that sells Ecchu fundoshi wrapped by a cellophane film, on which a large kanji character &quot;褌&quot; (fundoshi) is written in a writing brush font.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Renown Incorporated can be the most notable example, and that sells Ecchu fundoshi wrapped by a cellophane film, on which a large kanji character &quot;褌&quot; (fundoshi) is written in a writing brush font.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>同社では目の粗い独特のガーゼ地にリボン紐の越中褌を伊勢丹を中心に販売しているのに加え、最近では総合衣料チェーンの株式会社しまむらを通じてブロード地の越中褌を「大黒柱」の商品名で、同じくセロファンの包装紙に毛筆書体で「褌」と記載して販売している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The said company sells Ecchu fundoshi made from coarse-meshed peculiar gauze texture with ribbon strings mainly in Isetan department stores, and in addition to that, recently through a general clothing chain Shimamura Co., Ltd., it sells Ecchu fundoshi made from broadcloth by a brand name &quot;Daikokubashira&quot; (the main column of the house) using cellophane wrapping sheets on which a large Chinese character &quot;褌&quot; (fundoshi) is written in a writing brush calligraphic style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The said company sells Ecchu fundoshi made from coarse-meshed peculiar gauze texture with ribbon strings mainly in Isetan department stores, and in addition to that, recently through a general clothing chain Shimamura Co., Ltd., it sells Ecchu fundoshi made from broadcloth by a brand name &quot;Daikokubashira&quot; (the main column of the house) using cellophane wrapping sheets on which a large Chinese character &quot;褌&quot; (fundoshi) is written in a writing brush calligraphic style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The said company sells Ecchu fundoshi made from coarse-meshed peculiar gauze texture with ribbon strings mainly in Isetan department stores, and in addition to that, recently through a general clothing chain Shimamura Co., Ltd., it sells Ecchu fundoshi made from broadcloth by a brand name &quot;Daikokubashira&quot; (the main column of the house) using cellophane wrapping sheets on which a large Chinese character &quot;褌&quot; (fundoshi) is written in a writing brush calligraphic style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="74">
<j>現在の三越製の「クラシックパンツ」は2001年（平成13年）に三越に納品していた業者が製造から撤退したことから、その製造を株式会社アズが引き継いでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As to the present &quot;Classic Pants&quot; made by Mitsukoshi, because the company which had delivered them to Mitsukoshi withdrew from manufacturing them in 2001, As Corporation took over manufacturing them.</e>
<cmt>「株式会社アズ」のホームページを見ると社名のロゴは「as COPORATION」と綴られていますが、訳文では大文字小文字を通常の表記に変えました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As to the present &quot;Classic Pants&quot; made by Mitsukoshi, because the company which had delivered them to Mitsukoshi withdrew from manufacturing them in 2001, As Corporation took over manufacturing them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As to the present &quot;Classic Pants&quot; made by Mitsukoshi, because the company which had delivered them to Mitsukoshi withdrew from manufacturing them in 2001, As Corporation took over manufacturing them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>この引き継ぎに対して「採算に乗らない」と何社からも断られた経緯があったと言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that many companies rejected this taking over saying, &quot;It will be unprofitable,&quot; in the course of business negotiations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that many companies rejected this taking over saying, &quot;It will be unprofitable,&quot; in the course of business negotiations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that many companies rejected this taking over saying, &quot;It will be unprofitable,&quot; in the course of business negotiations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="76">
<j>以前の製品が定番の白色以外に、ライトブルーを始めとした色物の「クラシックパンツ」の製品販売主体から近年は柄物を主体とした販売に変わった背景がここにある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Here is a background to the transition in recent years, from selling mainly the products in which the previous products were the colored &quot;Classic Pants&quot; including the light blue ones in addition to the standard white ones, to selling mainly the patterned ones.</e>
<cmt>原文の「以前の製品が」のつながる先が判然としないが、とりあえず「以前の製品が・・・「クラシックパンツ」であった製品販売」と解釈しました（かなり無理がある気がしますが）。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Here is one of the backgrounds of the recent shift from selling the products in various colors, notably in light blue, not to mention the while ones, to selling mainly the patterned products.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。以前の製品にはライトブルーなど色物でそれを販売していた→近年は柄物を売るようになった、その理由には上記のようなことがある、という意味だと判断しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Here is one of the backgrounds of the recent shift from selling the products in various colors, notably in light blue, not to mention the while ones, to selling mainly the patterned products.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>付加価値を付けることで販売単価を上げて売上高を増やす営業政策上の理由と伺えるが、反面、定番の白い越中褌を買い求める常連客の足が遠のき、「クラシックパンツ」が一過性のブームに終わりそうな懸念がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It can be gathered that this is the reason on the business policy to raise the selling unit price to increase the net sales by creating added value, but on the other hand, it is feared that the regular customers who would purchase the standard white Ecchu fundoshi begin to keep away from the shops, and that &quot;Classic Pants&quot; is likely to end in a quickly passing craze</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It can be gathered that this is the reason on the business policy to raise the selling unit price to increase the net sales by creating added value, but on the other hand, it is feared that the regular customers who would purchase the standard white Ecchu fundoshi begin to keep away from the shops, and that &quot;Classic Pants&quot; is likely to end in a quickly passing craze</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It can be gathered that this is the reason on the business policy to raise the selling unit price to increase the net sales by creating added value, but on the other hand, it is feared that the regular customers who would purchase the standard white Ecchu fundoshi begin to keep away from the shops, and that &quot;Classic Pants&quot; is likely to end in a quickly passing craze</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>1997年（平成9年）に東京駅近くにある大丸百貨店が父の日を前に「東京褌祭り」と称して派手な柄物の越中褌の大量展示販売を行ったことがあったが、定着することなく終わった過去があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1997, the Daimaru department store which is near to Tokyo Station once carried out the large-scale exhibition and sale of showy patterned Ecchu fundoshi called &quot;Tokyo Fundoshi Matsuri&quot; (Tokyo fundoshi festival) before Father&apos;s Day, but it ended as a past event without taking root.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1997, the Daimaru department store which is near to Tokyo Station once carried out the large-scale exhibition and sale of showy patterned Ecchu fundoshi called &quot;Tokyo Fundoshi Matsuri&quot; (Tokyo fundoshi festival) before Father&apos;s Day, but it ended as a past event without taking root.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1997, the Daimaru department store which is near to Tokyo Station once carried out the large-scale exhibition and sale of showy patterned Ecchu fundoshi called &quot;Tokyo Fundoshi Matsuri&quot; (Tokyo fundoshi festival) before Father&apos;s Day, but it ended as a past event without taking root.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="79">
<j>一部の業者が、過去に越中褌の紐の部分を面ファスナーに代えて着用する商品を販売したことがあり、「サムライパンツ」の名称で販売していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some manufacturers have once sold the products to put on with a hook-and-loop fastener instead of the string parts of Ecchu fundoshi in the past, and named them &quot;Samurai Pants&quot; to sell (samurai is a warrior in and before the Edo period).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some manufacturers have once sold the products to put on with a hook-and-loop fastener instead of the string parts of Ecchu fundoshi in the past, and named them &quot;Samurai Pants&quot; to sell (samurai is a warrior in and before the Edo period).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some manufacturers have once sold the products to put on with a hook-and-loop fastener instead of the string parts of Ecchu fundoshi in the past, and named them &quot;Samurai Pants&quot; to sell (samurai is a warrior in and before the Edo period).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>なお、現在でも「サムライパンツ」の名称で一般の越中褌を販売している業者もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By the way, even now there are some manufacturers which sell normal Ecchu fundoshi by the name &quot;Samurai Pants&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By the way, even now there are some manufacturers which sell normal Ecchu fundoshi by the name &quot;Samurai Pants&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By the way, even now there are some manufacturers which sell normal Ecchu fundoshi by the name &quot;Samurai Pants&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>複数の業者で使用されていることから、特定業者の登録商標ではないようだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since this name is used by more than one manufacturer, it does not seem to be a registered trademark of a specific manufacturer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since this name is used by more than one manufacturers, it seems this is not a registered trademark of a specific manufacturer.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since this name is used by more than one manufacturers, it seems this is not a registered trademark of a specific manufacturer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="82">
<j>市販の越中褌には各社のブランドのタグが腰紐部分取付けられているので、市販の越中褌の購入者は自家製の越中褌の利用者と比べて越中褌の表裏を間違えないような仕組みになっている（越中褌は前垂れの端の折り返しが内側にあるものが表となる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because Ecchu fundoshi on the market have a tag which shows the brand of each company stuck to the waist string parts, the purchasers of Ecchu fundoshi on the market are intended not to mistake the front and the back of Ecchu fundoshi unlike the users of the home-sewed Ecchu fundoshi (The front of Ecchu fundoshi is the face on which the turn-ups at the edge of the maedare are inside.)</e>
<cmt>原文の「腰紐部分取付けられて」は「腰紐部分に取付けられて」と解釈しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because Ecchu fundoshi on the market have a tag, which shows the brand of the maker, attached to the waist string part, the purchasers of Ecchu fundoshi on the market are supposed not to mistake the front and back sides of Ecchu fundoshi, unlike the users of the home-sewed Ecchu fundoshi (The front of Ecchu fundoshi is the side on which the turn-ups around the edge of the maedare are inside.)</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because Ecchu fundoshi on the market have a tag, which shows the brand of the maker, attached to the waist string part, the purchasers of Ecchu fundoshi on the market are supposed not to mistake the front and back sides of Ecchu fundoshi, unlike the users of the home-sewed Ecchu fundoshi (The front of Ecchu fundoshi is the side on which the turn-ups around the edge of the maedare are inside.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 西原恭次(id:190768), Iyasaka77(id:236678), ふんどし王子(id:186706), MDR-SK(id:192066), ルプス・サンフィッシュ・フヨウ(id:112117), September rain(id:237830), Rusk(id:9895), Carkuni(id:79281), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), Miya(id:1881), Golza(id:40641), 曾禰越後守(id:183605), アセルス(id:87426), Kan1234(id:158649), 竹麦魚(id:11012), 北極熊(id:182750), フンドシ(id:185687), Mikomaid(id:56139), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>