<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>皇朝十二銭</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kocho-Junisen (twelve coins casted in Japan)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kocho-Junisen (twelve coins cast in Japan)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kocho-Junisen (twelve coins cast in Japan)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>皇朝十二銭（こうちょうじゅうにせん）とは、708年（和銅元年）から963年（応和3年）にかけて、日本で鋳造された12種類の銅貨の総称である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kocho-Junisen&quot; is a collective term for twelve kinds of copper coins casted in Japan during the period from 708 A.D to 963 AD.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kocho-Junisen&quot; is a collective term for twelve kinds of copper coins cast in Japan during the period from 708 AD to 963 AD.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Kocho-Junisen&quot; is a collective term for twelve kinds of copper coins cast in Japan during the period from 708 AD to 963 AD.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>本朝十二銭（ほんちょうじゅうにせん）、皇朝十二文銭（こうちょうじゅうにもんせん）とも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called &quot;Honcho-Junisen&quot; and &quot;Kocho-Junimonsen.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are also called &quot;Honcho-Junisen&quot; and &quot;Kocho-Junimonsen.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are also called &quot;Honcho-Junisen&quot; and &quot;Kocho-Junimonsen.&quot;</e>
<cmt>)→&quot;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>発行と経緯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its Issue and History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its Issue and History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its Issue and History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>皇朝十二銭は、以下の12種類である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kocho-Junisen includes the following twelve kinds of coins.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kocho-Junisen includes the following twelve kinds of coins.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kocho-Junisen includes the following twelve kinds of coins.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>和同開珎　708年（和銅元年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wado-kaichin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wado-kaichin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wado-kaichin, in 708.</e>
<cmt>年抜け</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>万年通宝　760年（天平宝字4年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mannen-tsuho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mannen-tsuho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mannen-tsuho, in 760.</e>
<cmt>年抜け</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>神功開宝　765年（天平神護元年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jingu-kaiho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jingu-kaiho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jingu-kaiho, in 765.</e>
<cmt>年抜け</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>隆平永宝　796年（延暦15年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryuhei-eiho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryuhei-eiho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryuhei-eiho, in 796.</e>
<cmt>年抜け</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>富寿神宝　818年（弘仁9年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fuju-shinpo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fuju-shinpo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fuju-shinpo, in 818.</e>
<cmt>年抜け</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>承和昌宝　835年（承和 (日本)2年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jowa-shoho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jowa-shoho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jowa-shoho, in 835.</e>
<cmt>年抜け</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>長年大宝　848年（嘉祥元年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chonen-taiho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chonen-taiho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chonen-taiho, in 848.</e>
<cmt>年抜け</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>饒益神宝　859年（貞観 (日本)元年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nyoeki-shinpo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nyoeki-shinpo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nyoeki-shinpo, in 859.</e>
<cmt>年抜け</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>貞観永宝　870年（貞観12年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jogan-eiho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jogan-eiho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jogan-eiho, in 870.</e>
<cmt>年抜け</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>寛平大宝　890年（寛平2年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanpyo-taiho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanpyo-taiho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanpyo-taiho, in 890.</e>
<cmt>年抜け</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>延喜通宝　907年（延喜7年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Engi-tsuho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Engi-tsuho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Engi-tsuho, in 907.</e>
<cmt>年抜け</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>乾元大宝　958年（天徳 (日本)2年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kengen-taiho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kengen-taiho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kengen-taiho, in 958.</e>
<cmt>年抜け</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="17">
<j>いずれも形は円形で中央に正方形の穴が開いている円形方孔の形式である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Each coin of the above has a rectangle hole in the circular form..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Each coin of the above has a square hole in the circular form..</e>
<cmt>terminology</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Each coin of the above has a square hole in the circular form.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>貨幣価値としては、律令政府が定めた通貨単位である1文 (通貨単位)として通用した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They circulated as currency of one mon each (an old currency unit in Japan) as ordained by the ritsuryo government (ancient Japanese government of centralized governance.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They circulated as currency of one mon each (an old currency unit in Japan) as ordained by the ritsuryo government (ancient Japanese government of centralized governance.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They circulated as currency of one mon each (an old currency unit in Japan) as ordained by the ritsuryo government (ancient Japanese government of centralized governance.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>このほかに金銭の開基勝宝、銀銭の太平元宝なども試鋳しているが（760年）、これらは銅銭とは異なり、広く流通したものではなかったようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Beside the avove, gold coins named Kaiki-shoho and silver coins named Taihei-genpo were casted on trial in 760 AD, but they failed to circulate so widely as copper coins.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Beside the above, gold coins named Kaiki-shoho and silver coins named Taihei-genpo were cast on a trial basis in 760 AD, but they failed to circulate as widely as the copper coins.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Beside the above, gold coins named Kaiki-shoho and silver coins named Taihei-genpo were cast on a trial basis in 760 AD, but they failed to circulate as widely as the copper coins.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="20">
<j>律令期に皇朝十二銭が発行された目的としては、唐の開元通宝を手本とし、貨幣制度を整えるため、また、平城京遷都に必要となる莫大な経費を、銅地金本来の価値と貨幣価値との差額で賄うためということが挙げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kocho-Junisen are considered to have been issued for the purpose of setting Japan&apos;s currency system in order by modelling the example of the Kaigen-tsuho of Tang dynasty of China and also for the purpose of raising funds to cover huge costs required for transferring the national capital to Heijo with margins of profit from the value of currency and the original value of material copper.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kocho-Junisen are considered to have been issued for the purpose of setting Japan&apos;s currency system in order by modelling the example of the Kaigen-tsuho of the Tang dynasty of China and also for the purpose of raising funds to cover huge costs required for transferring the national capital to Heijo with margins of profit from the value of currency and the original value of copper material.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kocho-Junisen are considered to have been issued for the purpose of setting Japan&apos;s currency system in order by modeling the example of the Kaigen-tsuho of the Tang dynasty of China and also for the purpose of raising funds to cover huge costs required for transferring the national capital to Heijo with margins of profit from the value of currency and the original value of copper material.</e>
<cmt>modelling→ modeling</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="21">
<j>和同開珎は、日本で実際に流通したことがはっきりしている貨幣としては最古のものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wado-kaichin is the oldest one among the currencies eviidently believed to have realy circulated in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wado-kaichin is the oldest one among the currencies eviidently believed to have actually circulated in Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wado-kaichin is the oldest one among the currencies evidently believed to have in fact circulated in Japan.</e>
<cmt>eviidently→evidentlyactually →in factに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>これより古い貨幣に富本銭があるが、これは実際に流通したかどうかはっきりしない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fuhonsen coins which appear to be older than Wado-kaichin are not distinctly defined yet to have realy existed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fuhonsen coins which appear to be older than Wado-kaichin are not distinctly defined yet to have actually existed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fuhonsen coins which appear to be older than Wado-kaichin are not distinctly defined yet to have in fact existed.</e>
<cmt>actually →in factに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>和同開珎発行から3年後の711年には、貨幣を多く蓄えたものに位階を与えるとする蓄銭叙位令が発布された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 711, three years after issue of Wado-kaichin, Chikusen-joirei (an ordinance to ordain a court rank to someone who saved a certain amount of money) was issued.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 711, three years after issue of Wado-kaichin, Chikusen-joirei (an ordinance to ordain a court rank to someone who saved a certain amount of money) was issued.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 711, three years after issue of Wado-kaichin, Chikusen-joirei (an ordinance to ordain a court rank to someone who saved a certain amount of money) was issued.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>蓄銭奨励と流通促進とは矛盾しているが、銭貨の流通を促進するために発令されたと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though paradoxical it is, this ordinance of chikusen-shorei (encouragement to save money) is considered to have been issued in order to promote circulation of the currency.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though paradoxical it is, this ordinance of chikusen-shorei (encouragement to save money) is considered to have been issued in order to promote circulation of the currency.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although paradoxical it is, this ordinance of chikusen-shorei (encouragement to save money) is considered to have been issued in order to promote circulation of the currency.</e>
<cmt>Though →Althoughに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>しかし、実際に位階を与えた記録は、同年11月の1例しか残っていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, no real execution of such ordainment has been reported except the case implemented in November of the same year of the ordinance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, no real execution of such an order has been reported except the case implemented in November of the same year of the ordinance.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, no real execution of such an order has been reported except the case implemented in November of the same year of the ordinance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>当時の日本は米や布などの物品貨幣が一般的であり、社会経済水準が貨幣を必ずしも要していなかったため、畿内とその周辺国以外にはあまり普及しなかったとも考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time in Japan, rice and cloth were the poplular items to exchange as material money, because then-current society of Japan had not reached yet to the economic level to necessiate money currencies, and therefore circulation of money was limited to Kinai area (countries near Kyoto.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time in Japan, rice and cloth were the poplular items to exchange as material money, because then-current society of Japan had not reached yet to the economic level to necessiate money currencies, and therefore circulation of money was limited to the Kinai area (countries near Kyoto.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time in Japan, rice and cloth were the popular items to exchange as material money, because then-current society of Japan had not reached yet to the economic level to necessiate money currencies, and therefore circulation of money was limited to the Kinai area (countries near Kyoto.)</e>
<cmt>poplular→popular</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>また、仮に需要があったとしてもそもそも銅の生産量が絶対的に少なかった当時の日本では実物貨幣に代わるだけの銅銭の製造は始めから困難であった（銅鉱の発見を機に元号を「和銅」と改めてしまう程当時銅は貴重であり、また後述のように時代が下るにつれて急速に品質が悪化している）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, even if there have been enough demands, volumes of copper production had been absolutely small, which made it impossible from the beginning to supply sufficient copper coins and substitute material money then-current in Japan (for your reference, copper was so precious then in Japan that its era was renamed to &quot;Wado (literally, Japanese copper)&quot; upon discovery of copper ore mines, and, as described afterward, the quality of copper coins had rapidly deteriorated as the time went on.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, even if there had been enough demand, the volume of copper production had been absolutely small, which made it impossible, from the beginning, to supply sufficient copper coins and substitute material money then-current in Japan (copper was so precious then in Japan that its era was renamed &quot;Wado (literally, Japanese copper),&quot; upon discovery of copper ore mines, and, as described afterward, the quality of copper coins had rapidly deteriorated as time went on.)</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation, wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, even if there had been enough demand, the volume of copper production had been absolutely small, which made it impossible, from the beginning, to supply sufficient copper coins and substitute material money then-current in Japan (copper was so precious then in Japan that its era was renamed &apos;Wado (literally, Japanese copper),&apos; upon discovery of copper ore mines, and, as described afterward, the quality of copper coins had rapidly deteriorated as time went on.)</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>ただし、発見地は北海道から熊本県まで全国各地に及んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And, locations of the copper mines had spreaded everywhere in Japan, from Hokkaido to Kumamoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And, locations of the copper mines had spreaded everywhere in Japan, from Hokkaido to Kumamoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And, locations of the copper mines had spreaded everywhere in Japan, from Hokkaido to Kumamoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="29">
<j>和同開珎が発行されてから52年後、万年通宝への改鋳が行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Only after 52 years from the issue, Wado-kaichin was renewed into Mannen-tsuho coins.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Only after 52 years from issue, Wado-kaichin was renewed into Mannen-tsuho coins.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Only after 52 years from issue, Wado-kaichin was renewed into Mannen-tsuho coins.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>この時、和同開珎10枚と万年通宝1枚との価値が等しいと定められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, the value of one new Mannen-tsuho coin was decided to be equivalent to ten coins of old Wado-kaichin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, the value of one new Mannen-tsuho coin was decided to be equivalent to ten coins of the old Wado-kaichin.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, the value of one new Mannen-tsuho coin was decided to be equivalent to ten coins of the old Wado-kaichin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>この定めはその後の改鋳にも踏襲された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Similar decision was made repeatedly in the subsequent coin renewals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A similar decision was made, repeatedly, in the subsequent coin renewals.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A similar decision was made, repeatedly, in the subsequent coin renewals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>皇朝十二銭は改鋳を重ねるごとに大きさが縮小し、重量も減少、素材も劣悪化していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At every time to renew its coins, Kocho-Junisen (twelve coins casted in Japan) decreased its size and weight and worsened its materials.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Every time the coins were renewed, Kocho-Junisen (twelve coins cast in Japan) decreased in size and weight and materials became worse.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Every time the coins were renewed, Kocho-Junisen (twelve coins cast in Japan) decreased in size and weight and materials became worse.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>当時の精錬法では利用できる銅資源が限られていたため、原材料の銅の生産量が年々低下したためである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of reasons for the above was that usable materials by then-current technology of copper refinery was limited to certain resources, so that production of such usable copper resources continued to decrease year by year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of reasons for the above was that usable materials by the then-current technology of copper refinery, was limited to certain resources, so that production of such usable copper resources continued to decrease year by year.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of reasons for the above was that usable materials by the then-current technology of copper refinery, was limited to certain resources, so that production of such usable copper resources continued to decrease year by year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>和同開珎が発行されて間もない頃には、銭1文で米2キログラムが買えたが、9世紀中頃には、買える米の量は100分の1から200分の1にまで激減してしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the beginning of Wado-Kaichin era, people could buy two- kilogram rice by one mon each, but in the middle of nineth century available quantity of rice for one mon decreased drastically to a one-hundredth or two-hundredth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the beginning of Wado-Kaichin era, people could buy two- kilograms of rice at one mon each, but in the middle of nineth century the available quantity of rice for one mon decreased drastically to a one-hundredth or two-hundredth.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the beginning of Wado-Kaichin era, people could buy 2kg of rice at one mon each, but in the middle of ninth century the available quantity of rice for one mon decreased drastically to a one-hundredth or two-hundredth.</e>
<cmt>two- kilograms→2kgnineth→ninth</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>延喜通宝や最後の乾元大宝は、銅銭ではなく鉛銭であると言われるほど鉛の含有量が高いものが多く存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many coins of Engi-tsuho and the last Kangen-taiho contained so much lead that they were called lead coins instead of copper ones.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many coins of Engi-tsuho and the last Kangen-taiho contained so much lead that they were called lead coins instead of copper ones.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many coins of Engi-tsuho and the last Kangen-taiho contained so much lead that they were called lead coins instead of copper ones.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>価値の低下した銭は、流通と交易の現場から忌避されるようになり、宋銭が大量に流入する12世紀後半まで、日本国内での銭の流通は限定されたものとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Degraded coins became gradually being avoided in the market of distribution and trading of commodities, and thus circulation of the coins inside Japan became limited in quantity beforel the latter half of 12th century when a lot of currency of Sung dynasty of China entered into Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Degraded coins became gradually avoided in the market of distribution and trading of commodities, and thus circulation of the coins inside Japan became limited in quantity before the latter half of 12th century when a lot of Sung dynasty currency from China entered Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Degraded coins became gradually avoided in the market of distribution and trading of commodities, and thus circulation of the coins inside Japan became limited in quantity before the latter half of 12th century when a lot of Sung dynasty currency from China entered Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="37">
<j>破銭運動</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hasen-undo (movement to melt coins to use as crude materials)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hasen-undo (movement to melt coins to use as raw materials)</e>
<cmt>terminology</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hasen-undo (movement to melt coins to use as raw materials)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>当時の貨幣は小額通貨であり、穴あき銭ともいわれるように高額取引では束ねて用いることが多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then-current coins were small in unit value and used mostly in bundles as they were perforated and called perforated coins.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then-current coins were small in unit value and used mostly in bundles as they had square holes in the center and were called holed coins.</e>
<cmt>grammar, terminology</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then-current coins were small in unit value and used mostly in bundles as they had square holes in the center and were called holed coins.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>このため、いちいちほどいて刻印を鑑定する手間がかかるうえ、これをおろそかにすれば贋金や沽価のひくい唐宋銭がまじりやすく、インフレを招いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, they were so inconvenient because they had to be unbandled each time for identifying engraved official marks, which process was very necessary to eliminate any false money or devalued currency of Tang and Sung dynasty that had a tendency to invite inflation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, they were so inconvenient to use because they had to be unbundled each time to identify official marks, a very necessary process to eliminate any false money or devalued currency from the Tang and Sung dynasty and that had a tendency to invite inflation.</e>
<cmt>grammar, revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, they were so inconvenient to use because they had to be unbundled each time to identify official marks, a very necessary process to eliminate any false money or devalued currency from the Tang and Sung dynasty and that had a tendency to invite inflation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>これを「銭の値が卑しくなる」と表現している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such acts of using false money or devalued currency were called &quot;degradation of money.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such acts of using false money or devalued currency were called &quot;degradation of money.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such acts of using false money or devalued currency were called &apos;degradation of money.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>政府は東西の市司に命じて物価を統制し、銭の価値を高く固定しようとしたが、このことはかえって安く仕入れた中国銭を素材に両替詐欺まがいの行為を助長させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then government had ordered its ichi-no-tsukasa (governmental organization) to regulate prices of commodities for fixing at high the value of currency, but as a result, such initiation of the government helped to increase fraudulent acts of money-exchanges by using cheap coins made and used in China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then government had ordered its ichi-no-tsukasa (governmental organization) to regulate prices of commodities for fixing at high the value of currency, but as a result, such initiation of the government helped to increase fraudulent acts of money-exchange by using cheap coins made and used in China.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then government had ordered its ichi-no-tsukasa (governmental organization) to regulate prices of commodities for fixing at high the value of currency, but as a result, such initiation of the government helped to increase fraudulent acts of money-exchange by using cheap coins made and used in China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>品位の低下はこれに拍車をかけた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This tendency was accelerated by lowering their dignity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This tendency was accelerated by lowering the dignity of the coins.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This tendency was accelerated by lowering the dignity of the coins.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>和銅銭にちかい大きな中国銭を薄く小さな銭に変造するのはたやすいことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was not difficult to alter such large-size Chinese coins as Wadosen (Japanese copper coins) into thin and small-size coins to be used in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was not difficult to alter such large-size Chinese coins as Wadosen (Japanese copper coins) into thin and small-size coins to be used in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was not difficult to alter such large-size Chinese coins as Wadosen (Japanese copper coins) into thin and small-size coins to be used in Japan.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="44">
<j>さらに問題なのは、新銭の発行ごとに行われた1000％のデノミネーションである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further problem was caused by redenomination of each new currency into one thousandth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A further problem was caused by redenomination of each new currency into one thousandth.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A further problem was caused by redenomination of each new currency into one thousandth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>もともと政府の設定した銭の価値に問題があり、新銭の価値が10倍である根拠がなかったため、市民からみれば、貯蔵している旧貨が両替によって10分の1に減ることは、大きな打撃であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the beginning, the government&apos;s way to decide new denomination was problemsome, because, for example, it made a groundless decision to fix new money&apos;s value at 10 times of the old, citizens were forced to suffer devaluation of reserved old money into one tenth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the beginning, the government&apos;s way to decide a new denomination was problematic, because, for example, it made a groundless decision to fix the new money&apos;s value at 10 times the old, citizens were forced to suffer devaluation of their savings of old money to one tenth their original value.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the beginning, the government&apos;s way to decide a new denomination was problematic, because, for example, it made a groundless decision to fix the new money&apos;s value at 10 times the old, citizens were forced to suffer devaluation of their savings of old money to one tenth their original value.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>このため、大量に溶解して銅材とし、両替を拒んだのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That is why people refused exchanges of old money, but melted them into copper materials.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That is why people refused exchanging old money, and rather preferred to melt them down into copper products.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That is why people refused exchanging old money, and rather preferred to melt them down into copper products.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>たとえば10枚の10円玉を新10円一枚に取り替えられるとすれば、旧10円は1円の価値でしかなくなるので銅にしたほうが得、という理屈だ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Suppose, for example, 10 coins of old ten-yen currency could be changed to 1 new ten-yen coin, the value of the old ten-yen coin becomes one tenth only, which means melted copper materiald may have more value than the new copper coins.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Suppose, for example, 10 coins of the old ten-yen currency could be changed into 1 new ten-yen coin, the value of the old ten-yen coin becomes only one tenth, which means melted copper ingots may have more value than the new copper coins.</e>
<cmt>grammar, terminology</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Suppose, for example, 10 coins of the old ten-yen currency could be changed into 1 new ten-yen coin, the value of the old ten-yen coin becomes only one tenth, which means melted copper ingots may have more value than the new copper coins.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>新10円に100円の価値があると認められなければ、現在でも同様のことが起こりうる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even today, a similar problem may happen unless a newly issued ten-yen coin will be acknowledged to have the equivalent value to 100 yen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even today, a similar problem may occur unless a newly issued ten-yen coin is acknowledged to have the equivalent of 100 yen value.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even today, a similar problem may occur unless a newly issued ten-yen coin is acknowledged to have the equivalent of 100 yen value.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>さらに、前述したように、当時の精錬技術では、自然銅のなかでも大量に存在する硫化銅は利用できず、銅酸化物と呼ばれる限られた鉱石しか利用できなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, as mentioned above, native copper ores used by then-current refining technology were limited to cuprate only and abundantly reserved copper sulfide under the ground could not be used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, as mentioned above, native copper ores used by then-current refining technology were limited to cuprate only and the abundant reserves of copper sulfide under the ground could not be used.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, as mentioned above, native copper ores used by then-current refining technology were limited to cuprate only and the abundant reserves of copper sulfide under the ground could not be used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>日本各地の酸化銅鉱山では深刻な資源の枯渇にさらされており、銅の価値は上がっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Every copper oxide mine located around Japan had severe fears of depletion of resources, causing to raise the value of copper material.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">All copper oxide mines located around Japan had drastic fear of the depletion of resources, which caused a raise in the value of copper.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">All copper oxide mines located around Japan had drastic fear of the depletion of resources, which caused a raise in the value of copper.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>少なくとも数億枚は発行が確認されている銭が、いくら経済発展があるとはいえなかなか回収できず、品位を下げざるをえなかったのは、破銭（銭を溶かして銅地金として利用する行為）が広く行われたためと理解される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is now understood that, no matter how the economy had developed at that time, people then carried out extensively the hasen (to melt coins to use as crude materials) so that at least a few thousand million pieces of issued coins could hardly be retrieved and the remaining coins were compelled to degrade their values.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is now understood that, no matter how the economy had developed at that time, people then carried out extensively the hasen (to melt coins to use as a raw material) so that at least a few thousand million pieces of issued coins could hardly be retrieved and the remaining coins were compelled to degraded values.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is now understood that, no matter how the economy had developed at that time, people then carried out extensively the hasen (to melt coins to use as a raw material) so that at least a few thousand million pieces of issued coins could hardly be retrieved and the remaining coins were compelled to degraded values.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="52">
<j>これに対し永観二年(984)には「禁破銭令」が出される事態となり、新銭発行が極めて困難な状況になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In response, the government officially announced in 984 the Kin-hasen Rei (an act of banning to melt coins to use as crude materials), making the circumstances extremely difficult to issue new money.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In response, the government officially announced in 984 the Kin-hasen Rei (an act banning the melting of coins to use as raw materials), making it extremely difficult to issue new money.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In response, the government officially announced in 984 the Kin-hasen Rei (an act banning the melting of coins to use as raw materials), making it extremely difficult to issue new money.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>この禁令は社寺などに出されていることから見ても、朝廷が反対できないよう、銅灯篭など「国家安泰を祈願するため」の仏具に事寄せて溶解する方式が取られたのであろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This Kin-hasen Rei was promulgated toward shrines and temples, who used to melt copper coins to produce, for example, Buddhist alter articles such as hanging copper lanterns&quot; made to pray for national peace and security,&quot; and therefore to whom the Imperial court could hardly complain against their illegal acts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This Kin-hasen Rei was promulgated toward shrines and temples, who used to melt copper coins to produce, for example, Buddhist alter articles such as hanging copper lanterns&quot; made to pray for national peace and security,&quot; and therefore, to whom the Imperial court could hardly complain against their illegal acts.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This Kin-hasen Rei was promulgated toward shrines and temples, who used to melt copper coins to produce, for example, Buddhist alter articles such as hanging copper lanterns &apos;made to pray for national peace and security,&apos; and therefore, to whom the Imperial Court could hardly complain against their illegal acts.</e>
<cmt>lanterns&quot; made→lanterns &apos;made原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;にcourt→Court</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>この結果、皇朝銭の現存枚数は記録と比較してもきわめて少ないものとなり、とくに後期のものは低品質の影響で錆び、刻字が読めるものはごく稀で現在の古銭市場ではかえって莫大な値打ちをまねいている程である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, number of existing Kocho-sen coins has become far fewer than recorded, with specifically inferior quality casted particularly in the latter period making them now rusty and difficult to read their engraved letters, while quite a few coins with readable letters are now priced at high.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, number of existing Kocho-sen coins has become far fewer than recorded, with specifically inferior quality casting particularly in the latter period making them now corroded and difficult to read their engraved letters, while quite a few coins with readable letters are now priced high.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, number of existing Kocho-sen coins has become far fewer than recorded, with specifically inferior quality casting particularly in the latter period making them now corroded and difficult to read their engraved letters, while quite a few coins with readable letters are now priced high.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="55">
<j>皇朝銭の終わり</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The End of the Kocho-sen Coins</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The End of the Kocho-sen Coins</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The End of the Kocho-sen Coins</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>こうして、民間での、政府が発行する銅銭への信頼は失墜してしまい、使用されなくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, copper coins issued by the government had lost the trust of people and ceased to be used in the market.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, copper coins issued by the government had lost the trust of the people and ceased to be used in the market.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, copper coins issued by the government had lost the trust of the people and ceased to be used in the market.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>乾元大宝が発行されたあと、朝廷の弱体化もあり、銅銭は発行されなくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">No copper coins followed after Kangen-taiho, partly due to weakening power and dignity of Imperial courts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">No copper coins followed after Kangen-taiho, partly due to weakening power and dignity of the Imperial courts.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">No copper coins followed after Kangen-taiho, partly due to weakening power and dignity of the Imperial Courts.</e>
<cmt>court→Court</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>その後、日本では11世紀初頭をもって貨幣使用の記録は途絶え、米や絹などの物品貨幣経済へと逆戻りしてしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Subsequently, there could be found no record about then-used currencies in Japan since the beginning of 11th century, when the economy had returned back to old material money system using rice, silk and other commodities as medium.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently, there could be found no record concering the then-used currencies in Japan since the beginning of 11th century, when the economy had returned back to the old material bartering system using rice, silk, and other commodities as a trading medium.</e>
<cmt>grammar, revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently, there could be found no record concerning the then-used currencies in Japan since the beginning of 11th century, when the economy had returned back to the old material bartering system using rice, silk, and other commodities as a trading medium.</e>
<cmt>concering→concerning</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>ただし畿内などでは300年かけて形成された金属貨幣そのもののに対する需要が完全に無くなった訳ではなく、估価法などの公定価格の決定には貨幣換算によるものが用いられてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, this does not mean that the demand for metal currencies vanished completely, after three hundred years or so for forming them in the Kinai area (countries near Kyoto,) but that they remained as a method of conversion to decide official prices by Kokaho (acts of conversion rate of goods.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, this does not mean that the demand for metal currencies vanished completely, after three hundred years or so for forming them in the Kinai area (countries near Kyoto,) but they remained as a method of conversion to decide official prices by Kokaho (acts of conversion rate of goods.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, this does not mean that the demand for metal currencies vanished completely, after three hundred years or so for forming them in the Kinai area (countries near Kyoto,) but they remained as a method of conversion to decide official prices by Kokaho (acts of conversion rate of goods.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>やがて経済が発達すると、中国から輸入した宋銭、元銭、明銭などが用いられるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Along with the development of economy in Japan, there appeared use of new currencies imported from China, such as those of Yuan and Ming.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Along with the development of economy in Japan, there appeared the use of new currencies imported from China, such as those of Yuan and Ming.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Along with the development of economy in Japan, there appeared the use of new currencies imported from China, such as those of Yuan and Ming.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="61">
<j>皇朝十二銭が発行されなくなってから、長い間日本では公鋳貨幣は作られなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan for a long time since abolishment of Kocho-Junisen (twelve coins casted in Japan,) no official currency was casted by the government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan for a long time since abolishment of Kocho-Junisen (twelve coins cast in Japan,) no official currency was cast by the government.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan for a long time since abolishment of Kocho-Junisen (twelve coins cast in Japan,) no official currency was cast by the government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>銅銭の公鋳の再開は、皇朝十二銭の600年以上後の1608年（慶長13年）に鋳造された慶長通宝あるいは1627年（寛永4年）の寛永通宝鋳造まで待つこととなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Resumption to use official copper currencies casted by the government happened only more than 600 years after the period of Kocho-Junisen, when Keicho-tsuho and Kanei-tsuho appeared in the market in 1608 and in 1627, respectively.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Resumption to use official copper currencies cast by the government happened more than 600 years after the period of Kocho-Junisen, when Keicho-tsuho and Kanei-tsuho appeared in the market in 1608 and in 1627, respectively.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Resumption to use official copper currencies cast by the government happened more than 600 years after the period of Kocho-Junisen, when Keicho-tsuho and Kanei-tsuho appeared in the market in 1608 and in 1627, respectively.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="63">
<j>付言</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additional Remarks</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additional Remarks</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additional Remarks</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>和同開珎以前に別の銭貨が造られた可能性がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before Wado Kaichin coins, other currencies might have possibly been casted for use.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before Wado Kaichin coins, other currencies might have possibly been cast for use.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before Wado-kaichin coins, other currencies might have possibly been cast for use.</e>
<cmt>表記統一のため、-補足、K小文字に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>一つは無文銀銭であり、他にもう一つは富本銭である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One possibiliry is Mumon-ginsen coin (Japan&apos;s oldest private silver coinage) and another one is Fuhon-sen coin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One possibiliry is Mumon-ginsen coin (Japan&apos;s oldest private silver coinage) and another one is the Fuhon-sen coin.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One possibility is Mumon-ginsen coin (Japan&apos;s oldest private silver coinage) and another one is the Fuhon-sen coin.</e>
<cmt>possibiliry→possibiliｔy</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="66">
<j>また、準貨幣として用いられたものに「布貨」がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also used as quasi-money were Fuka coins (spade-shaped bronze coins.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also used as quasi-money were Fuka coins (spade-shaped bronze coins.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also used as quasi-money were Fuka coins (spade-shaped bronze coins.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>中国では唐銭以前にも穴あき銭はあったが、その空白期には布や米などを貨幣代わりに用いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In China, perforated coins had circulated in the market before Tosen coins (Chinese currency of Tang dynasty) appeared, but, during the blank period without such currencies, it was cloths and rices that played the roles as currencies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In China, holed coins had circulated in the market before Tosen coins (Chinese currency of the Tang dynasty) appeared, but, during the blank period without such currencies, it was cloth and rice that played the role as a bartering currency.</e>
<cmt>grammar, terminology</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In China, holed coins had circulated in the market before Tosen coins (Chinese currency of the Tang dynasty) appeared, but, during the blank period without such currencies, it was cloth and rice that played the role as a bartering currency.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>国税にあたる「調布」はその名残である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of the reminders of this fact is the term &quot;Chofu (literally, procurement of cloth,)&quot; which meant the national tax.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of the reminders of this fact is the term &quot;Chofu (literally, procurement of cloth,)&quot; which meant the national tax.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of the reminders of this fact is the term &apos;Chofu (literally, procurement of cloth),&apos; which meant the national tax.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>また「贖銅（罰金）」にもちいられた銅や砂金、銀なども秤量貨幣の一種と見なすことができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Copper, gold dust, silver and others which were used as &quot;Shokudo (penalty charges)&quot; may be regarded as a kind of Hyoryo kahei (currency valued by weight.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Copper, gold dust, silver, and others which were used as &quot;Shokudo (penalty charges)&quot; may be regarded as a kind of Hyoryo kahei (currency valued by weight.)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Copper, gold dust, silver, and others which were used as &apos;Shokudo (penalty charges)&apos; may be regarded as a kind of Hyoryo kahei (currency valued by weight.)</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>古代中国の刀銭などに代表される準貨幣としての貨布は、古墳時代の鉄?（てってい）などがこれにあたるとの見方がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tettei (iron rod) of Kofun period (tumulus period) may be regarded as equivalent to Kafu (ancient Chinese currency made of bronze,) used as Quasi-money, which is typically represented by Tosen currency (bronze coin shaped like an opened straight razor) of ancient China,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tettei (iron rod) of the Kofun period (tumulus period) may be regarded as equivalent to Kafu (ancient Chinese currency made of bronze,) used as Quasi-money, which is typically represented by Tosen currency (bronze coin shaped like an opened straight razor) of ancient China,</e>
<cmt>grammar, terminology</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tettei (iron rod) of the Kofun period (tumulus period) may be regarded as equivalent to Kafu (ancient Chinese currency made of bronze,) used as Quasi-money, which is typically represented by Tosen currency (bronze coin shaped like an opened straight razor) of ancient China.</e>
<cmt>,→.</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Higashi(id:8842), Ligar(id:12623), Blue sapphire(id:130304), 浩(id:70121), Nnh(id:474), Enirac Sum(id:12090), 水野白楓(id:22811), VoidAimai(id:212464), Yusasa(id:13562), Tcyiswalk(id:7279), Alma mater(id:45042), のりまき(id:53470), Nakanoootsuka(id:17040), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>