<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>五徳猫</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gotokuneko</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gotokuneko</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gotokuneko</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>五徳猫（ごとくねこ）は、鳥山石燕の『画図百器徒然袋』にある日本の妖怪。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gotokuneko refers to a Japanese specter portrayed in Sekien TORIYAMA&apos;s &quot;Hyakki Tsurezure Bukuro&quot; (One hundred bags in idleness).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A Gotoku-neko (literally, tripod cat) is one of Japanese yokai (ghosts, spirits and monsters) that was portrayed in Sekien TORIYAMA&apos;s yokai art collection book: &quot;Gazu Hyakki Tsurezure Bukuro&quot; (The Illustrated Bag of One Hundred Random Demons; the term &apos;hyakki&apos; in its title is a pun on the usual hyakki, replacing the character for demon which is written as &quot;鬼&quot; in Japanese with a character for vessel written as &quot;器,&quot; and sure enough, most of the yokais shown in this book are tsukumogami [a type of Japanese spirits that originate in items or artifacts that have reached their 100th birthday and become alive]).</e>
<cmt>原文に「画図」を補足のうえ再訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gotoku-neko (literally, tripod cat) is one of Japanese yokai (ghosts, spirits and monsters) that was portrayed in Sekien TORIYAMA&apos;s yokai art collection book: &quot;Gazu Hyakki Tsurezure Bukuro&quot; (The Illustrated Bag of One Hundred Random Demons; the term &apos;hyakki&apos; in its title is a pun on the usual hyakki, replacing the character for demon which is written as &quot;鬼&quot; in Japanese with a character for vessel written as &quot;器,&quot; and sure enough, most of the yokais shown in this book are tsukumogami [a type of Japanese spirits that originate in items or artifacts that have reached their 100th birthday and become alive]).</e>
<cmt>A Gotoku-neko→Gotoku-neko</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>付喪神の一種ともいわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It may be considered a kind of Tsukumo-gami (gods to a variety of things).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is viewed as a kind of the tsukumogami.</e>
<cmt>前項との兼ね合いで修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is viewed as a kind of the tsukumogami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>2本の尻尾を持つ猫又が、五徳（囲炉裏でやかんなどを乗せる台）を冠のように頭に頂き、火吹き竹を持って囲炉裏で火を起こしている姿で描かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the picture, Nekomata (mythical two-tailed monster cat) puts a gotoku (triped, three or four-legged kettle stand used at a sunken fireplace) like a crown on the head and is making fire with a hifuki-dake (bamboo blowpipe used to stimulate a fire) by the sunken fireplace.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the picture, a Nekomata (a mythical two-tailed monster cat) placed a gotoku (a tripod, and more particularly, a three or four-legged kettle stand used at a sunken hearth) on the head like a crown and is making fire with a hifuki-dake (bamboo blowpipe used to stimulate a fire) in the sunken hearth.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正、用語修正、文法</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the picture, a Nekomata (a mythical two-tailed monster cat) placed a gotoku (a tripod, and more particularly, a three or four-legged kettle stand used at a sunken hearth) on the head like a crown and is making fire with a hifuki-dake (bamboo blowpipe used to stimulate a fire) in the sunken hearth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>土佐光信による室町時代の妖怪画『百鬼夜行絵巻』にも同様に五徳を頭に乗せた猫の姿がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is also a figure of a cat with a gotoku on the head in the same manner in the specter drawings, &quot;Hyakki yagyo (Night Parade of One Hundred Demons) picture scroll&quot; by Mitsunobu TOSA in the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A similar cat with the gotoku placed on the head is depicted in &quot;Hyakki Yagyo Emaki&quot; (The &apos;Night Parade of One Hundred Demons&apos; Picture Scroll), a collection of yokai illustrations drawn by Mitsunobu TOSA in the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>表現修正、用語選択</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A similar cat with the gotoku placed on the head is depicted in &quot;Hyakki Yagyo Emaki&quot; (The &apos;Night Parade of One Hundred Demons&apos; Picture Scroll), a collection of yokai illustrations drawn by Mitsunobu TOSA in the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>五徳猫はこの猫をモデルにしたと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is thought that the Gotokuneko was modeled on this cat.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is thought that the Gotokuneko was modeled on this cat.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is thought that the Gotokuneko was modeled on this cat.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>また『百器徒然袋』の解説では、『平家物語』の作者とされる信濃前司行長が引き合いに出されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, in the exposition of &quot;Hyakki Tsurezure Bukuro (One hundred bags in idleness)&quot;, Shinano no Zenji Yukinaga, who is considered the author of &quot;Tale of the Heike,&quot; is mentioned.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, Sekien, in his comment on the Gotokuneko in the &quot;Gazu Hyakki Tsurezure Bukuro,&quot; refers to Shinano no Zenji Yukinaga who is considered to be the author of the &quot;Tale of the Heike.&quot;</e>
<cmt>文脈調整、文法修正、用語選択</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, Sekien, in his comment on the Gotokuneko in the &quot;Gazu Hyakki Tsurezure Bukuro,&quot; refers to Shinano no Zenji Yukinaga who is considered to be the author of the &quot;Tale of the Heike.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>行長は本来は学識ある人物だったが、唐の太宗の武の七徳に基づく舞曲「七徳の舞」の内の二つの徳を忘れたことから「五徳の冠者」と渾名され、世間に嫌気がさして遁世したという説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to one theory, although Yukinaga was an scholar, he had failed two of seven virtues in the dance music &quot;Dance of the Seven Virtues,&quot; based on seven virtue of the military arts of Tang Emperor Taiso (Tang tai zong) and was nicknamed &quot;Young Gentleman of the Five Virtues&quot;; he got tired of the society and retired from it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One theory has it that although Yukinaga was basically an educated person, he failed to recall two of the seven virtues described in the dance music named &quot;Dance of the Seven Virtues&quot; which had followed the seven virtues of the military arts of Emperor Taiso of Tang (Tang Taizong,) thereby being scornfully nicknamed the &quot;Young man of the Five Virtues,&quot; and therefore he became thoroughly tired of this world and retired to live in seclusion.</e>
<cmt>文脈調整、パンクチュエーション、文法、用語選択</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One theory has it that although Yukinaga was basically an educated person, he failed to recall two of the seven virtues described in the dance music named &apos;Dance of the Seven Virtues&apos; which had followed the seven virtues of the military arts of Emperor Taiso of Tang (Tang Taizong,) thereby being scornfully nicknamed the &apos;Young man of the Five Virtues,&apos; and therefore he became thoroughly tired of this world and retired to live in seclusion.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot; → &apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>五徳猫はこの五徳と器物の五徳との言葉あわせで創作されたものとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gotokuneko is thought to be created by word play of the Five Virtues (called gotoku in Japanese) and the gotoku of a vessel.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term Gotokuneko was supposedly created to be a pun on the word gotoku: the Five Virtues (called gotoku in Japanese) and the gotoku as an object.</e>
<cmt>用語選択、表現修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term Gotokuneko was supposedly created to be a pun on the word gotoku: the Five Virtues (called gotoku in Japanese) and the gotoku as an object.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>囲炉裏のそばで自分で火を起こす妖怪とする説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some say that it is the specter who makes fire by himself near a sunken fireplace.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some believe that the Gotokuneko is a yokai which makes a fire itself by the sunken hearth.</e>
<cmt>表現修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some believe that the Gotokuneko is a yokai which makes a fire itself by the sunken hearth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>しかし、これは画図を見た者が後に想像したことに過ぎないといわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, many say that it was only the imagination of viewers.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Others, however, doubt the believability of it, insisting that the Gotokuneko making a fire itself was no more than the product of the imagination of those who had viewed the illustration.</e>
<cmt>表現修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Others, however, doubt the believability of it, insisting that the Gotokuneko making a fire itself was no more than the product of the imagination of those who had viewed the illustration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 逃亡者(id:14864), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>