<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>付喪神</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsukumogami</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsukumogami</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsukumogami</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>付喪神（つくもがみ）とは、日本の民間信仰における観念で、長い年月を経て古くなったり、長く生きた依り代（道具や生き物や自然の物）に、神 (神道)や霊魂などが宿ったものの総称である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsukumogami is the notion of Japanese folk beliefs and it is a collective name of old or long-used yorishiro (object representative of a divine spirit) (tools, living things and natural things) in which deities (Shinto religion) or divine spirits reside.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsukumogami, the notion of Japanese folk beliefs, is a collective name of old or long-used yorishiro (objects representative of divine spirits) (tools, living things and natural things) in which deities (Shinto religion) or divine spirits reside.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsukumogami, the notion of Japanese folk beliefs, is a collective name of old or long-used yorishiro (objects representative of divine spirits) (tools, living things and natural things) in which deities (Shinto religion) or divine spirits reside.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>荒ぶれば（荒ぶる神・九尾の狐など）禍を齎し、和ぎれば（和ぎる神・お狐様など）幸を齎すとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that Tsukumogami brings misfortune if it becomes violent (Araburu-kami (violent deity), Kyubi no kitsune (fox having nine tails) etc), and it brings good fortune if it becomes calm (Nagiru-kami (calm deity), Okitsune sama (the fox worshiped as a harvest deity) etc.).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that Tsukumogami brings misfortune if it becomes violent (Araburu-kami (violent deity), Kyubi no kitsune (a fox having nine tails) etc.), and it brings good fortune if it becomes calm (Nagiru-kami (calm deity), Okitsune sama (the fox worshiped as a harvest deity) etc.).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that Tsukumogami brings misfortune if it becomes violent (Araburu-kami [violent deity], Kyubi no kitsune [a fox having nine tails] etc.), and it brings good fortune if it becomes calm (Nagiru-kami [calm deity], Okitsune sama [the fox worshiped as a harvest deity] etc.).</e>
<cmt>カッコ表記修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>「付喪」自体は当て字で、正しくは「九十九」と書く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;付喪&quot; is a Chinese character used as a phonetic symbol rather than for its meaning and it is written &quot;九十九&quot; by right.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;付喪&quot; is a Chinese character used as a phonetic symbol rather than for its meaning, and it&apos;s written as &quot;九十九&quot; by right.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;付喪&quot; is a Chinese character used as a phonetic symbol rather than for its meaning, and it is written as &quot;九十九&quot; by right.</e>
<cmt>it&apos;s→it isとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>この九十九は「長い時間（九十九年）や経験」「多種多様な万物（九十九種類）」などを象徴する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;九十九&quot; symbolizes &quot;long time (99 years) or long experience&quot; and/or &quot;varieties of things (99 kinds)&quot;.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;九十九&quot; symbolizes &quot;long time (99 years) or long experience&quot; and/or &quot;varieties of things (99 kinds).&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;九十九&quot; symbolizes &quot;long time (99 years) or long experience&quot; and/or &quot;varieties of things (99 kinds).&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>また九十九髪と表記される場合もあるが、「髪」は「白髪」に通じ、同様に長い時間経過や経験を意味し、「多種多様な万物が長い時間や経験を経て神に至る物（者）」のような意味を表すとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This word is also written &quot;九十九髪&quot;, and it also means &quot;things which have become deities over the long time or experience&quot; since &quot;髪&quot; (hair) implies &quot;白髪&quot; (grey hair).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This word is also written as &quot;九十九髪,&quot; and it also means &quot;things that have become deities over a long time or experience&quot; since &quot;髪&quot; (hair) implies &quot;白髪&quot; (gray hair).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This word is also written as &quot;九十九髪,&quot; and it also means &quot;things that have become deities over a long time or experience&quot; since &quot;髪&quot; (hair) implies &quot;白髪&quot; (gray hair).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>背景</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Background</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Background</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Background</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>古神道との共通性</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Common ground with ancient Shinto</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Common ground with ancient Shinto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Common ground with ancient Shinto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>日本の古神道においては、古来より森羅万象に八百万（やおよろず）の神が宿るとするアニミズム的な世界観（八百万の神・汎神論）が定着していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A world view that yaoyorozu no kami (eight million deities) reside in shinrabansho (all things in nature, the whole creation), a kind of animism, took root in Japanese ancient Shinto.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A world view that yaoyorozu no kami (eight million deities) reside in shinrabansho (all things in nature, the whole of creation), a kind of animism, took root in Japan&apos;s ancient Shinto.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A world view that yaoyorozu no kami (eight million deities) reside in shinrabansho (all things in nature, the whole of creation), a kind of animism, took root in Japan&apos;s ancient Shinto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>その特徴の一つとして「神さび」という言葉が、古くから使われ、長く生きたものや、古くなったものはそれだけで、神聖であり神々しいとされてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As seen from the term &quot;Kamusabi&quot; (to believe like a deity), people believed that things which lived long or things which they used for long time were sacred by themselves.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As seen from the term &quot;Kamusabi&quot; (to believe like a deity), people believed things that lived long or things they used for a long time were sacred by themselves.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As seen from the term &quot;Kamusabi&quot; (to believe like a deity), people believed things that lived long or things they used for a long time were sacred by themselves.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>その具体的なものとして、神籬（ひもろぎ・木々のこと）や磐座（いわくら・岩や山のこと）信仰があり、長く生きた大木や昔からある岩に神が宿ると考え、それらを神体とし、依り代の証しとして注連縄を巻き信仰している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The concrete examples of the above are himorogi (trees) belief and iwakura (rock and mountain) belief, under which people believed deities resided in old big trees or old rocks and worshiped them as shintai (deities) by putting shimenawa (a sacred rope) around them as the proof of yorishiro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The concrete examples of the above are himorogi (trees) belief and iwakura (rock and mountain) belief, in which people believed deities resided in large big trees or old rocks and worshiped them as shintai (deities) by putting shimenawa (a sacred rope) around them as proof of yorishiro.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The concrete examples of the above are himorogi (trees) belief and iwakura (rock and mountain) belief, in which people believed deities resided in large big trees or old rocks and worshiped them as shintai (deities) by putting shimenawa (a sacred rope) around them as proof of yorishiro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>付喪神となりうる寄り代も森羅万象であり、人工の器物（道具）や建造物の他、動植物や自然の山河などに及ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yorishiro which could become Tsukumogami were shinrabansho, including artificial tools and buildings, animals and plants as well as natural mountains and rivers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yorishiro that could become Tsukumogami were shinrabansho, including artificial tools and buildings, animals and plants as well as natural mountains and rivers.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yorishiro that could become Tsukumogami were shinrabansho, including artificial tools and buildings, animals and plants as well as natural mountains and rivers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>付喪神は、必ずしも人に幸をもたらすとは限らず、禍をもたらすものであり、妖怪として語られることも多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Tsukumogami brings not only good fortune but also misfortune, it is often told as the tale of apparition.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because Tsukumogami brings not only good fortune but also misfortune, it is often expressed as a tale of apparition.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because Tsukumogami brings not only good fortune but also misfortune, it is often expressed as a tale of apparition.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>作られて誕生して長い時間を経て、健在でありつづけた器物や生き物などには、霊魂が宿るとして「畏怖や畏敬の念を抱く」といった習慣・価値観は、日本に普遍的に存在するものであり、根底に流れる思想は神道や古神道と同じものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The practice/sense of values of believing the existence of spirits in long-lived articles/living things and &quot;having a feeling of reverence/awe&quot; for them was commonly in existence in Japan, and the philosophy of Tsukumogami is same with that of Shinto and ancient shinto.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The practice/sense of values of believing in the existence of spirits in long-lived articles/living things and &quot;having a feeling of reverence/awe&quot; for them was common in Japan, and the philosophy of Tsukumogami is the same with that of contemporary and ancient Shinto.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The practice/sense of values of believing in the existence of spirits in long-lived articles/living things and &quot;having a feeling of reverence/awe&quot; for them was common in Japan, and the philosophy of Tsukumogami is the same with that of contemporary and ancient Shinto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>またそれらを、鎮めるため（和御魂・荒御魂という神霊の2つの様相の変化）に建立した碑や塚や供養塔も日本各地に多数存在し、例としては包丁塚や人形塚や道具塚などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, a lot of monuments, mounds and memorial towers, such as hocho-zuka (mound of kitchen knives), ningyo-zuka (mound of dolls) and dogu-zuka (mound of tools), were constructed at various places in Japan in order to assuage the anger of Tsukumogami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, many monuments, mounds and memorial towers, such as hocho-zuka (mound of kitchen knives), ningyo-zuka (mound of dolls) and dogu-zuka (mound of tools), were constructed at various places in Japan in order to assuage the anger of Tsukumogami.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, many monuments, mounds and memorial towers, such as hocho-zuka (mound of kitchen knives), ningyo-zuka (mound of dolls) and dogu-zuka (mound of tools), were constructed at various places in Japan in order to assuage the anger of Tsukumogami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>感謝</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gratitude</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gratitude</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gratitude</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="16">
<j>これらの価値観をもたらす背景としては、道具や家畜などを「大切に扱い手入れを絶やさぬように」という教訓的なものや、手入れの疎かな古道具を安易に用いることによる破損や事故の回避、長く身の回りの役に立ってくれた道具や家畜・愛玩動物に対する感謝の心として解釈される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Behind the above-mentioned sense of values, there seems to be teachings of &quot;taking good care of tools and domestic animals &quot;, precautions for avoiding the damage or accident arising from the use of old tools in poor condition and gratitude for tools, domestic animals and pets which were the belongings of people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Behind the above-mentioned sense of values, there seem to be teachings of &quot;taking good care of tools and domestic animals,&quot; precautions for avoiding damage or accidents arising from the use of old tools in poor condition, and gratitude for tools, domestic animals and pets that had belonged to people.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Behind the above-mentioned sense of values, there seem to be teachings of &quot;taking good care of tools and domestic animals,&quot; precautions for avoiding damage or accidents arising from the use of old tools in poor condition, and gratitude for tools, domestic animals and pets that had belonged to people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>丁重に扱われ、付喪神となったものが、恩を返すなどした伝承もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a legend saying that a thing which was treated courteously and became Tsukumogami repaid the owner.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One legend states that a thing that was treated courteously and became Tsukumogami would repay the owner.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One legend states that a thing that was treated courteously and became Tsukumogami would repay the owner.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>また粗末に扱ったり供養を絶やすと、付喪神となり荒ぶるとする考えから、役目を終えた道具や生き物に対する供養を行う習慣につながっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The practice of holding memorial services for tools and living things which served their purposes derived from the belief that such things become violent Tsukumogami if people treat them without due respect or don&apos;t hold their memorial services.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The practice of holding memorial services for tools and living things that had served their purposes derived from the belief that such things would become violent Tsukumogami if people treated them without due respect or didn&apos;t hold memorial services for them.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The practice of holding memorial services for tools and living things that had served their purposes derived from the belief that such things would become violent Tsukumogami if people treated them without due respect or did not hold memorial services for them.</e>
<cmt>didn&apos;t→did notとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="19">
<j>森羅万象の擬人化</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Personification of shinrabansho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The personification of shinrabansho</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The personification of shinrabansho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="20">
<j>道具や、一般に人格を認められることのない家畜・動植物・自然などに、神霊が宿り意志を持つといった価値観は、戯画や漫画などの擬人化の一環とし考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The sense of values that believes the existence of divine spirit in tools, domestic animals, animals, plants and nature, whose personality is not recognized generally, is considered to have derived from the fact that they were personified in caricatures and comics.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sense of values that believes divine spirits exist in tools, domestic animals, animals, plants and nature, in which personality isn&apos;t generally recognized, is considered to have derived from the fact that they were personified in caricatures and comics.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sense of values that believes divine spirits exist in tools, domestic animals, animals, plants and nature, in which personality is not generally recognized, is considered to have derived from the fact that they were personified in caricatures and comics.</e>
<cmt>isn&apos;t→is notとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>現に妖怪の唐傘などは目・鼻・口・手足をもって描かれ、猫又などの動物の妖怪も付喪神に含めることが可能であり、長命によって魂（人格）を獲得するとする図式に漏れない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As karakasa (a monster of umbrella), a kind of apparition, was drawn as the one that has eyes, a nose, a mouth, hands and feet, apparitions of animal like nekomata (mythical two-tailed cat) can be categorized into Tsukumogami as the ones that acquired spirit (personality) by longevity.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As karakasa (a monster of umbrella), a kind of apparition, was drawn as the one that has eyes, a nose, a mouth, hands and feet, apparitions of animals such as nekomata (mythical two-tailed cat) can be categorized into Tsukumogami as ones that acquired spirit (personality) due to their longevity.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As karakasa (a monster of umbrella), a kind of apparition, was drawn as the one that has eyes, a nose, a mouth, hands and feet, apparitions of animals such as nekomata (mythical two-tailed cat) can be categorized into Tsukumogami as ones that acquired spirit (personality) due to their longevity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>これは山や川などの「ヌシ（主）の伝承」にしても同様の構図を持つものであり、付喪神もまた日本古来よりのアニミズム的な価値観から、人格や生命すら持ち得ない対象でさえ時にこれらを獲得し得る、あるいは借景（しゃっけい）や和菓子の造形と同様の「見立ての精神」における、解釈して楽しむといった擬人観が、普遍的な価値観としてこれらの根底に存在するということである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As seen in &quot;Nushi no densho&quot; (transmission of nushi (master)), mountains and rivers can also acquire personality or life based on the Japanese traditional philosophy of animism, and they are utilized for shakkei (making use of the surrounding landscape in the design of a garden) or the design of Japanese cakes based on the &quot;mitate no seishin&quot; (spirit of simulation).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As seen in &quot;Nushi no densho&quot; (transmission of nushi (master)), mountains and rivers can also acquire personality or life based on the Japanese traditional philosophy of animism, and they&apos;re utilized for shakkei (making use of the surrounding landscape in the design of a garden) or the design of Japanese cakes based on the &quot;mitate no seishin (spirit of simulation).&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As seen in &quot;Nushi no densho&quot; (transmission of nushi [master]), mountains and rivers can also acquire personality or life based on the Japanese traditional philosophy of animism, and they are utilized for shakkei (making use of the surrounding landscape in the design of a garden) or the design of Japanese cakes based on the &quot;mitate no seishin&quot; (spirit of simulation).</e>
<cmt>カッコ表記修正、クォーテーションの位置を移動、they&apos;re→they areとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="23">
<j>鎌倉時代以前は、道具や身近な家畜や飼い猫・飼い犬などは、妖怪としてほとんど描かれていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tools, domestic animals, cats and dogs were seldom drawn as apparitions before the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tools, domestic animals, cats and dogs were seldom drawn as apparitions before the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tools, domestic animals, cats and dogs were seldom drawn as apparitions before the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>古神道そのままに自然の具現化としての、龍や蛇や狐などが、その脅威を表すかのように荒々しく描かれているものだけである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Only dragons, snakes and foxes, which were the embodiment of nature according to ancient Shinto, were drawn violently in order to show their menace.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Only dragons, snakes and foxes, which were the embodiment of nature according to ancient Shinto, were drawn violently in order to show their menace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Only dragons, snakes and foxes, which were the embodiment of nature according to ancient Shinto, were drawn violently in order to show their menace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="25">
<j>鎌倉時代（かまくらじだい、1185年頃-1333年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kamakura period (around 1185 -1333)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kamakura period (around 1185 -1333)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kamakura period (around 1185 -1333)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>『土蜘蛛草子』には、九十九神の原型ともいえる描写があり、鶏や狐の姿をした女性や妖怪としての獏が描かれ、五徳と牛が合体したものや、杵に蛇の体と人の腕が2本くっついたものや、角盥（つのだらい）の縁に歯が生えそのまま顔になっている人形（ひとがた）が描かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Paintings of the model of Tsukumogami (九十九神) are seen in &quot;Tsuchugumo no soshi&quot;, such as women whose figures are chicken and fox, apparitions of baku (mythological Chinese chimera), things which are the combination of gotoku (kettle stand) and cattle, kine (pounder) on which a snake and human teeth are attached, and hitogata (doll) whose face is tsuno-darai (horned basin) with teeth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Paintings of the model of Tsukumogami (九十九神) are seen in &quot;Tsuchugumo no soshi,&quot; such as women whose figures are the chicken and fox, apparitions of baku (mythological Chinese chimera), things that combine the gotoku (kettle stand) and cattle, the kine (pounder) to which a snake and human teeth are attached, and the hitogata (doll) whose face is tsuno-darai (horned basin) with teeth.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Paintings of the model of Tsukumogami (九十九神) are seen in &quot;Tsuchigumo no Soshi,&quot; such as women whose figures are the chicken and fox, apparitions of baku (mythological Chinese chimera), things that combine the gotoku (kettle stand) and cattle, the kine (pounder) to which a snake and human teeth are attached, and the hitogata (doll) whose face is tsuno-darai (horned basin) with teeth.</e>
<cmt>Tsuchugumo→Tsuchigumo、soshi→Soshiに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>『不動利益縁起絵巻』にも安倍晴明とその使役される式神が5体描かれていて、鶏や角盥や五徳を擬人化したものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seimei ABE and five shikigami (deity which performs according to Onmyoshi) are seen in &quot;Fudo Rieki Engi Emaki&quot; and these shikigami are the personified chicken, tsuno-daira and gotoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seimei ABE and five shikigami (deity which performs according to Onmyoshi) are seen in &quot;Fudo Rieki Engi Emaki,&quot; and these shikigami are the personified chicken, tsuno-daira and gotoku.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">ABE no Seimei and five shikigami (deity which performs according to Onmyoshi) are seen in &quot;Fudo Rieki Engi Emaki,&quot; and these shikigami are the personified chicken, tsuno-daira and gotoku.</e>
<cmt>ABE no Seimeiとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="28">
<j>室町時代（むろまちじだい、1336年 - 1573年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Muromachi period (1336 - 1573)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Muromachi period (1336 - 1573)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Muromachi period (1336 - 1573)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>この時代に単なる妖怪ではなく、その由来や設定がなされ九十九神と命名された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this period, histories of apparitions were created and they were named Tsukumogami (九十九神).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this period, histories of apparitions were created and were called Tsukumogami (九十九神).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this period, histories of apparitions were created and were called Tsukumogami (九十九神).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>『付喪神記』の冒頭に「陰陽雑記に云ふ。器物百年を経て、化して精霊を得てより、人の心を誑かす、これを付喪神と号すと云へり」とある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the beginning of &quot;Tsukumogami-ki&quot;, there is a description saying &quot; according to &quot;Inyo Zakki&quot;, tools acquired souls and deceived people&apos;s heart 100 years after they were produced. They were named Tsukumogami&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the beginning of &quot;Tsukumogami-ki,&quot; there is a description that states, &quot;According to &apos;Inyo Zakki,&apos; tools acquired souls and deceived people&apos;s hearts 100 years after they were produced. They were called Tsukumogami.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the beginning of &quot;Tsukumogami-ki,&quot; there is a description that states, &quot;According to &apos;Inyo Zakki,&apos; tools acquired souls and deceived people&apos;s hearts 100 years after they were produced. They were called Tsukumogami.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>絵画や絵巻では『鼠草紙』・『十二類合戦』とよばれる生き物を模した物や、『化物草子』では、案山子や柄杓の九十九神が描かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Paintings or picture scrolls in which living things were painted, such as &quot;Nezumi Zoshi&quot; and &quot;Juni-rui Gassen&quot;, were creared, and the Tsukumogami of kakashi (scarecrow) and hishaku (ladle) were painted in &quot;Bakemono Zoshi&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Paintings or picture scrolls in which living things were painted, such as &quot;Nezumi Zoshi&quot; and &quot;Juni-rui Gassen,&quot; were created, and the Tsukumogami of kakashi (scarecrow) and hishaku (ladle) were painted in &quot;Bakemono Zoshi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Paintings or picture scrolls in which living things were painted, such as &quot;Nezumi Zoshi&quot; and &quot;Juni-rui Gassen,&quot; were created, and the Tsukumogami of kakashi (scarecrow) and hishaku (ladle) were painted in &quot;Bakemono Zoshi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>室町時代に軽工業の発達から生活道具が大量に出回り、臼や釜や鍋などから、桶や壷が、安易に消費されるようになり、これらも九十九神として描かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As household utensils, such as mortars, pots, pans, tubs and jars, became popular in the Muromachi period thanks to the development of light industry, these were also painted as Tsukumogami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As household utensils, such as mortars, pots, pans, tubs and jars, became popular in the Muromachi period thanks to the development of light industry, they were also painted as Tsukumogami.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As household utensils, such as mortars, pots, pans, tubs and jars, became popular in the Muromachi period thanks to the development of light industry, they were also painted as Tsukumogami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>土佐光信の『百鬼夜行図』は、これまで描かれた文字通り鬼が主流であった百鬼夜行とは違い、九十九神を中心にかかれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsukumogami were painted as main characters in Mitsunobu TOSA&apos;s &quot;Hyakki Yagyo-zu&quot; (painting of Night Procession of Hundred Demons), unlike other Hyakki Yagyo-zu that were painted before then in which demons were painted as main characters.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsukumogami were painted as main characters in Mitsunobu TOSA&apos;s &quot;Hyakki Yagyo-zu&quot; (a painting of Night Procession of Hundred Demons), unlike other Hyakki Yagyo-zu that were painted before then, in which demons were painted as the main characters.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsukumogami were painted as main characters in Mitsunobu TOSA&apos;s &quot;Hyakki Yagyo-zu&quot; (a painting of Night Procession of Hundred Demons), unlike other Hyakki Yagyo-zu that were painted before then, in which demons were painted as the main characters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>この時代が、九十九神の黄金期であったことがうかがえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Judging from the above, this period seemed to be the golden age of Tsukumogami.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Judging from the above, this period seemed to be the golden age of Tsukumogami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Judging from the above, this period seemed to be the golden age of Tsukumogami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="35">
<j>江戸時代以降</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Edo period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Edo period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Edo period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>もっぱら妖怪として描かれ、その造形は江戸時代以前からあった自然の具現化と九十九神などの生活必需品（家畜などを含め）を踏襲したものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsukumogami were painted solely as apparitions and their models were the embodiment of nature and daily necessities (including domestic animals) that had existed before the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsukumogami were painted solely as apparitions, and their models were the embodiment of nature and daily necessities (including domestic animals) that had existed before the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsukumogami were painted solely as apparitions, and their models were the embodiment of nature and daily necessities (including domestic animals) that had existed before the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>ただ、九十九神における歳を経たものという特筆が見られる場合が少なくなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, paintings on which a note explaining that the object is the old one is seldom seen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, paintings on which a note explaining that the object is the old one are seldom found today.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, paintings on which a note explaining that the object is the old one are seldom found today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>これは、太平の庶民文化の隆盛から、口碑伝承のないこの時代の作家に創作された妖怪の類の氾濫と、杉浦日向子などの江戸時代研究家や学者が説明する「江戸時代は世界に類を見ない資源還元（リサイクル）社会であった」という事実と合致する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The above coincides with the fact that a lot of apparitions were created by painters in this period, a peaceful period during which culture of ordinary people was prosperous and folklore didn&apos;t exist, and that &quot;the Edo period was a recycling society without parallel in the world&quot; as the researchers of Edo period, such as Hinako SUGIURA, pointed out.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The above coincides with the fact that many apparitions were created by painters in this period, a peaceful time in which the culture of ordinary people was prosperous and folklore didn&apos;t exist, and that &quot;the Edo period was a recycling society without parallel in the world&quot; as researchers of the Edo period, such as Hinako SUGIURA, have pointed out.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The above coincides with the fact that many apparitions were created by painters in this period, a peaceful time in which the culture of ordinary people was prosperous and folklore did not exist, and that &quot;the Edo period was a recycling society without parallel in the world&quot; as researchers of the Edo period, such as Hinako SUGIURA, have pointed out.</e>
<cmt>didn&apos;t→did notとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>棒手振り（棒手売）が幕府による経済振興や弱者救済として奨励され、古物の修理・回収が盛んになり、物の消費に一定の罪悪感が無くなったことや、鯨などの食料や資源の徹底した活用や、それによって生ずる人糞までも肥料化による利用と売買など、消費が振興となったことが大きいといえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Behind the above, there was a fact that a sense of sin for consumption declined because the repair/collection of used articles became vigorous thanks to bakufu&apos;s policy to encourage bote-furi (bote-uri) (vending with calling to customers), which was introduced for the promotion of economy and the relief of the socially vulnerable, as well as the use and sale of various food stuff including whale meat and night soil.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Behind the above, there was a fact that a sense of sin for consumption declined because the repair/collection of used articles became vigorous thanks to the Bakufu&apos;s policy of encouraging bote-furi (bote-uri) (vending while calling to customers), which was introduced for the promotion of economy and the relief of the socially vulnerable, as well as the use and sale of various foodstuffs such as whale meat and night soil.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Behind the above, there was a fact that a sense of sin for consumption declined because the repair/collection of used articles became vigorous thanks to the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun)&apos;s policy of encouraging bote-furi (bote-uri) (vending while calling to customers), which was introduced for the promotion of economy and the relief of the socially vulnerable, as well as the use and sale of various foodstuffs such as whale meat and night soil.</e>
<cmt>the Bakufu→the bakufuとし、初出のため補足追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="40">
<j>現在</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The present time</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The present time</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The present time</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>江戸時代の人海戦術と社会制度による資源還元にまでは、至っていないが、「もったいない」や「里山・鎮守の森」のように、九十九神や妖怪は自然保護を含めたものとして、日本はもとより世界に発信されるべき観念や価値観ともいえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the level of recycling of resources doesn&apos;t reach the level of the Edo period, when bakufu encouraged recycling by human-wave tactics and social system, Tsukumogami or apparitions are the notion or the sense of values of nature conservation which Japan should send to the world, as with &quot;mottainai&quot; (wasteful) and &quot;satoyama/ chinju no mori&quot; (outskirt of country/sacred shrine forest),.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the level of recycling of resources doesn&apos;t reach the level of the Edo period, when bakufu encouraged recycling through human-wave tactics and the social system, Tsukumogami or apparitions are the notion or the sense of values of nature conservation which Japan should send to the world, as with &quot;mottainai&quot; (wasteful) and &quot;satoyama/ chinju no mori&quot; (outskirts of country/sacred shrine forest).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the level of recycling of resources does not reach the level of the Edo period, when the bakufu encouraged recycling through human-wave tactics and the social system, Tsukumogami or apparitions are the notion or the sense of values of nature conservation which Japan should send to the world, as with &quot;mottainai&quot; (wasteful) and &quot;satoyama/chinju no mori&quot; (outskirts of country/sacred shrine forest).</e>
<cmt>doesn&apos;t→does not、bakufu→the bakufuとし、スペース消去</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="42">
<j>現代の目撃談</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Witness testimony at present</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Witness testimony at present</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Witness testimony at present</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>現代社会の例としては、全国各地の第三セクターにある放棄され廃墟と化している無人遊園地では、深夜になると無人のジェットコースターがひとりでに走り、白馬のメリーゴーランドが生身の白馬に変化し苦しみもがき、迷子の子供がマンホールから次々と這い出てくる不思議な目撃話が語られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At some amusement parks of joint public-private venture that fell into ruin, according to eyewitnesses, roller coasters with no staff started to run, white horses of merry-go-round became living white horses and were tormented and lost children crawled out from manholes in the middle of the night.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At some amusement parks of joint public-private ventures that had fallen into ruin, according to eyewitnesses, roller coasters with no staff would start to run, the white horses of merry-go-rounds became living white horses and were tormented, and lost children crawled out from manholes in the middle of the night.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At some amusement parks of joint public-private ventures that had fallen into ruin, according to eyewitnesses, roller coasters with no staff would start to run, the white horses of merry-go-rounds would become living white horses and be tormented, and lost children would crawl out from manholes in the middle of the night.</e>
<cmt>would start to runとなっているためこれに合わせ、became→would become、were tormented→be tormented、crawled out→would crawl outとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>霊能力者によれば遊園地に残っているのは当時の入場客の「想い」であるといい、その「想い」が器物につき怪奇現象を起こすのだという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to psychics, what remained at the amusement parks is the &quot;thought&quot; of visitors at the time and such &quot;thought&quot; attached to instruments caused mysterious phenomenon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to psychics, what remained at the amusement parks is the &quot;thought&quot; of visitors at the time, and such &quot;thought,&quot; when attached to the instruments, caused mysterious phenomena.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to psychics, what remained at the amusement parks is the &quot;thought&quot; of visitors at the time, and such &quot;thought,&quot; when attached to the instruments, caused mysterious phenomena.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Sogiya(id:82968), Toroia(id:31889), Xqbot(id:273540), Mooko(id:36162), ハラヘッタ(id:13395), Asterat(id:89123), Kumakichi9(id:244759), MIO(id:31681), Loveless(id:129239), 逃亡者(id:14864), Misakawa(id:208485), FlaBot(id:30804), Nopira(id:29335), Dorudgar(id:136090), Hetareguma(id:102862), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>