<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>日本画</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nihon-ga</e>
<cmt>訳出しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>日本画（にほんが）は、絵画のジャンルのひとつで、日本独特のもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nihon-ga(Japanese style painting) is a genre of painting unique to Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nihon-ga(Japanese style painting) is a genre of painting unique to Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nihon-ga (Japanese style painting) is a genre of painting unique to Japan.</e>
<cmt>スペースを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>明治時代に日本に導入された油絵を「洋画」と呼ぶのに対して、油彩に依らず、それまでの日本の伝統的な技法や様式の上に育てられた絵画を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While oil painting, which was introduced to Japan in the Meiji period, is called Yo-ga(foreign style painting), Nihon-ga refers to paintings which utilize traditional Japanese techniques and styles and rather than being reliant on oil paint.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While oil painting, which was introduced to Japan in the Meiji period, is called Yo-ga(foreign style painting), Nihon-ga refers to paintings which utilize traditional Japanese techniques and styles and rather than being reliant on oil paint.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While oil painting, which was introduced to Japan in the Meiji period, is called Yo-ga (foreign style painting), Nihon-ga refers to paintings which utilize traditional Japanese techniques and styles and rather than being reliant on oil paint.</e>
<cmt>スペースを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>狭義には明治以降のものであるが、それ以前のものにも拡張して呼ぶことがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nihon-ga is narrowly defined as those paintings created after the Meiji period but it sometimes also refers those before that period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nihon-ga is narrowly defined as those paintings created after the Meiji period but it sometimes also refers those before that period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nihon-ga is narrowly defined as those paintings created after the Meiji period but it sometimes also refers those before that period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>その場合、中国や朝鮮半島に由来しながらも主題や様式において日本的特徴を持つものを意味するのか、あるいは油彩技法が到来する以前に日本で制作された図画一般まで指すのか、定義があいまいなまま使われることも多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In that case, the term Nihon-ga is used loosely and it is unclear whether it refers to those drawings having origins in China or the Korean peninsula but with themes and styles that have Japanese characteristics, or those drawings in general which originated in Japan before the arrival of the oil painting technique.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In that case, the term Nihon-ga is used loosely and it is unclear whether it refers to those drawings having origins in China or the Korean peninsula but with themes and styles that have Japanese characteristics, or those drawings in general which originated in Japan before the arrival of the oil painting technique.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In that case, the term &apos;Nihon-ga&apos; is used loosely and it is unclear whether it refers to those drawings having origins in China or the Korean peninsula but with themes and styles that have Japanese characteristics, or those drawings in general which originated in Japan before the arrival of the oil painting technique.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>日本画の誕生</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The birth of Nihon-ga</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The birth of Nihon-ga</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Birth of Nihon-ga</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>奈良時代から平安時代にかけて、中国や朝鮮半島などから渡来した技法や様式、あるいはそれに倣い日本で描かれた図画が「唐絵」と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the the Nara Period through to the Heian period, drawings using the technique and style derived from China or the Korean peninsula, or those imitating them and painted in Japan were called &quot;Kara-e&quot; (Chinese Paintings).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the the Nara Period through to the Heian period, drawings using the technique and style derived from China or the Korean peninsula, or those imitating them and painted in Japan were called &quot;Kara-e&quot; (Chinese Paintings).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the Nara period through to the Heian period, drawings using the technique and style derived from China or the Korean peninsula, or those imitating them and painted in Japan were called &apos;Kara-e&apos; (Chinese Paintings).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>これに対して日本的な主題を描くものが産まれ、「大和絵」と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By comparison, drawings with Japanese themes were called &quot;Yamatoe&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By comparison, drawings with Japanese themes were called &quot;Yamatoe&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By comparison, drawings with Japanese themes were called &apos;Yamato-e.&apos;</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>その後「漢画」に対する「和画」や、「唐画」に対する「和画」などと、呼び方やその区分は時代によって異るが、海外から新しく流入した画風に対し、旧来のものを日本の伝統的なものと考えるパターンは繰り返されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Subsequently, the terms used, such as &quot;Kanga(Chinese)&quot; compared with &quot;Waga(Japanese)&quot;, or &quot;Kara-e(Chinese)&quot; compared with Waga(Japanese), varied according to the era, however the trend to consider those paintings and techniques from the past as traditional Japanese in comparison with the new styles imported from overseas has continued.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently, the terms used, such as &quot;Kanga(Chinese)&quot; compared with &quot;Waga(Japanese)&quot;, or &quot;Kara-e(Chinese)&quot; compared with Waga(Japanese), varied according to the era, however the trend to consider those paintings and techniques from the past as traditional Japanese in comparison with the new styles imported from overseas has continued.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently, the terms used, such as &apos;Kanga&apos; (Chinese painting) compared with &apos;Waga&apos; (Japanese painting), or &apos;Kara-e&apos; compared with &apos;Waga,&apos; varied according to the era, however the trend to consider those paintings and techniques from the past as traditional Japanese in comparison with the new styles imported from overseas has continued.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションなどを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>「日本画」は明治初期にヨーロッパからもたらされた油彩画すなわち西洋画（または「洋画」）に対して、それまでの日本にあった図画に対して用いられた用語である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term Nihon-ga came into use in the beginning of the Meiji Period to distinguish drawing styles which had already existed from Western style oil painting (or Yo-ga) imported from Europe at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term Nihon-ga came into use in the beginning of the Meiji Period to distinguish drawing styles which had already existed from Western style oil painting (or Yo-ga) imported from Europe at that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term &apos;Nihon-ga&apos; came into use in the beginning of the Meiji period to distinguish drawing styles which had already existed from Western style oil painting (or Yo-ga) imported from Europe at that time.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="10">
<j>明治初期の1876年、明治政府は西洋画法を学ぶためイタリアからアントニオ・フォンタネージを招き、工部美術学校を創立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1876, at the beginning of the Meiji Period, in order to promote the study of Western Art, the Meiji government established an art school and invited Antonio Fontanesi from Italy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1876, at the beginning of the Meiji Period, in order to promote the study of Western Art, the Meiji government established an art school and invited Antonio Fontanesi from Italy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1876, at the beginning of the Meiji period, in order to promote the study of Western Art, the Meiji government established an art school and invited Antonio Fontanesi from Italy.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>浅井忠らがその第1期生であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Asai Tadashi and other students were members of the inaugural class.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Asai Tadashi and other students were members of the inaugural class.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadashi ASAI and other students were members of the inaugural class.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="12">
<j>その2年後の1878年にフォンタネージは帰国。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fontanesi went back to Italy two years later, in 1878.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fontanesi went back to Italy two years later, in 1878.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fontanesi went back to Italy two years later, in 1878.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>いっぽうアメリカ合衆国からアーネスト・フェノロサが来日し、東京大学で哲学などを教えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, Ernest Fenollosa came to Japan and taught philosophy and other subjects at Tokyo university.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, Ernest Fenollosa came to Japan and taught philosophy and other subjects at Tokyo university.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, Ernest Fenollosa came to Japan and taught philosophy and other subjects at Tokyo University.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="14">
<j>フェノロサが日本の美術に強い関心を示し、評価したことは有名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is well-known that Fenollosa showed a strong interest in Japanese art and evaluated it highly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is well-known that Fenollosa showed a strong interest in Japanese art and evaluated it highly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is well-known that Fenollosa showed a strong interest in Japanese art and evaluated it highly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="15">
<j>フェノロサが1882年に龍池会で行った講演『美術真説』で使った Japanese painting の翻訳が「日本画」という言葉の初出である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The word Nihon-ga was adopted from the translation of the term &apos;Japanese painting&apos; for the first time when Fenollosa gave his lecture on The New Theory of Art at the Dragon Pond Society (Ryuchikai) in 1882.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The word Nihon-ga was adopted from the translation of the term &apos;Japanese painting&apos; for the first time when Fenollosa gave his lecture on The New Theory of Art at the Dragon Pond Society (Ryuchikai) in 1882.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The word &apos;Nihon-ga&apos; was adopted from the translation of the term &apos;Japanese painting&apos; for the first time when Fenollosa gave his lecture on &quot;The New Theory of Art&quot; at the Dragon Pond Society (Ryuchikai) in 1882.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="16">
<j>この講演でフェノロサは次のような点を日本画の特徴として挙げ、優れたところと評価している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the lecture Fenollosa pointed out the following as characteristics of Nihon-ga and evaluated its excellence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the lecture Fenollosa pointed out the following as characteristics of Nihon-ga and evaluated its excellence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the lecture Fenollosa pointed out the following as characteristics of Nihon-ga and evaluated its excellence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="17">
<j>写真のような写実を追わない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It does not seek realism as in a photograph.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It does not seek realism as in a photograph.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It does not seek realism as in a photograph.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="18">
<j>陰影が無い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It does not have shadows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It does not have shadows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It does not have shadows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="19">
<j>鉤勒（こうろく、輪郭線）がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It does have an outline.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It does have an outline.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It does have an outline.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="20">
<j>色調が濃厚でない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The color tone is not rich.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The color tone is not rich.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The color tone is not rich.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="21">
<j>表現が簡潔である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The expression is simple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The expression is simple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The expression is simple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="22">
<j>フェノロサの通訳を勤めており助手であった岡倉覚三（のちの天心）らはこれに大きく力づけられ、1889年に東京美術学校（後の東京藝術大学）を開くと、西洋画の教育を排し、絵画としては橋本雅邦らを教師として日本画科をのみ設けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Okakura Kakusan(later called Tenshin), who worked as a interpreter and assistant for Fenollosa, was much encouraged by this experience and established The Tokyo Art School(later Tokyo Art University) in 1889 which did not teach western painting but had only a Nihon-ga faculty with teachers including Hashimoto Gaho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Okakura Kakusan(later called Tenshin), who worked as a interpreter and assistant for Fenollosa, was much encouraged by this experience and established The Tokyo Art School(later Tokyo Art University) in 1889 which did not teach western painting but had only a Nihon-ga faculty with teachers including Hashimoto Gaho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kakusan (later called Tenshin) OKAKURA, who worked as a interpreter and assistant for Fenollosa, was much encouraged by this experience and established The Tokyo Art School (later Tokyo Art University) in 1889 which did not teach western painting but had only a Nihon-ga faculty with teachers including Gaho HASHIMOTO.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>第1期生には横山大観らがいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yokoyama Taikan was one of the inaugural class members.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yokoyama Taikan was one of the inaugural class members.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taikan YOKOYAMA was one of the inaugural class members.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="24">
<j>西洋画を教えていた工部美術学校は、これに先立ち1883年に閉鎖されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By this time, the art school (Kobu Bijutsu Gakko), which taught western painting, had been closed in 1883.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By this time, the art school (Kobu Bijutsu Gakko), which taught western painting, had been closed in 1883.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By this time, the art school (Kobu Bijutsu Gakko), which taught western painting, had been closed in 1883.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="25">
<j>岡倉は1890年には東京美術学校の校長にもなるが、1898年に職を追われ、横山らと日本美術院を作った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Okakura was inaugurated as the Head of Tokyo Art School but was forced out of the school, then established The Japan Art Academy with Yokoyama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Okakura was inaugurated as the Head of Tokyo Art School but was forced out of the school, then established The Japan Art Academy with Yokoyama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Okakura was inaugurated as the Head of Tokyo Art School in 1890 but was forced out of the school in 1898, then established The Japan Art Academy with Yokoyama.</e>
<cmt>年号補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="26">
<j>岡倉らが東京美術学校、日本美術院で育てようとした日本画は旧来の技法や様式を守るだけのものではなく、西洋画から採り入れるものを採り、それと対抗できるような日本の絵画であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Nihon-ga which Okakura intended to foster was not just preserving traditional Japanese technique and style, but also brought in some necessary western techniques aiming to create Japanese drawings which could hold their own against western paintings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Nihon-ga which Okakura intended to foster was not just preserving traditional Japanese technique and style, but also brought in some necessary western techniques aiming to create Japanese drawings which could hold their own against western paintings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Nihon-ga which Okakura intended to foster was not just preserving traditional Japanese technique and style, but also brought in some necessary western techniques aiming to create Japanese drawings which could hold their own against western paintings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="27">
<j>橋本雅邦は兄弟子狩野芳崖とともに狩野派の出身でありながら、独自の画風を拓こうとした画家であったし、横山も新しい技法を開発している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gaho Hashimoto, while being from the Karino sect with Karino Hougai as his senior pupil, was a painter who sought to develop his own style. Similarly, Yokoyama also developed new techniques.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gaho Hashimoto, while being from the Karino sect with Karino Hougai as his senior pupil, was a painter who sought to develop his own style. Similarly, Yokoyama also developed new techniques.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gaho HASHIMOTO, while being from the Kano School with Hogai KANO as his senior pupil, was a painter who sought to develop his own style; similarly, Yokoyama also developed new techniques.</e>
<cmt>表記を変え、1文にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="28">
<j>フェノロサが最初に使った「日本画」という言葉は、西洋から渡来した油彩画に対して、それまでに日本にあった図画全般を単に指すものではなく、中国や朝鮮半島に由来しながらも、日本の中で熟成、独自に発展した様式について言っているものであろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is thought that the term Nihon-ga used by Fenellosa for the first time did not simply refer to all drawings existing in Japan prior to the arrival of western oil painting, but more specifically to the style which had roots in China and the Korean Peninsula but was developed independently and matured in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is thought that the term Nihon-ga used by Fenellosa for the first time did not simply refer to all drawings existing in Japan prior to the arrival of western oil painting, but more specifically to the style which had roots in China and the Korean Peninsula but was developed independently and matured in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is thought that the term &apos;Nihon-ga&apos; used by Fenollosa for the first time did not simply refer to all drawings existing in Japan prior to the arrival of western oil painting, but more specifically to the style which had roots in China and the Korean Peninsula but was developed independently and matured in Japan.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>しかし、これに発して岡倉らが育てて現在に至る日本画はそれとも異り、洋画の対抗勢力としてその後に発達したものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the Nihon-ga established then and fosterd by Okakura and others up until the present has continued to develop as a rival force to Yo-ga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the Nihon-ga established then and fosterd by Okakura and others up until the present has continued to develop as a rival force to Yo-ga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the Nihon-ga established then and fostered by Okakura and others up until the present has continued to develop as a rival force to Yo-ga.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>その意味では日本画は明治以降のものであり、明治の横山大観が日本画家であっても、江戸時代の狩野永徳は日本画家ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In that sense, Nihon-ga is defined as those created after the Meiji period, which means that Yokoyama Taikan of Meiji is classified as a painter of Nihonga but the Edo Period painter Karino Eitoku is not.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In that sense, Nihon-ga is defined as those created after the Meiji period, which means that Yokoyama Taikan of Meiji is classified as a painter of Nihonga but the Edo Period painter Karino Eitoku is not.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In that sense, Nihon-ga is defined as those created after the Meiji period, which means that Taikan YOKOYAMA of Meiji was classified as a painter of Nihon-ga but the Edo period painter Eitoku KANO was not.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="31">
<j>日本画の誕生は、明治政府の欧化政策のもとでの西洋文化の急速な流入に対する国粋主義的な危機感と、当時のアメリカ合衆国でヨーロッパ由来の文化との対抗軸を模索していたフェノロサとの出会いと共感が造り出したものかもしれない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nihonga may have been a product of a nationalistic feeling of crisis due to the rapid influx of western culture under the Meiji government&apos;s westernization policy combined with an affinity felt in the encounter with Fenellosa who sought to create a foothold in America to counter the dominance of European culture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nihonga may have been a product of a nationalistic feeling of crisis due to the rapid influx of western culture under the Meiji government&apos;s westernization policy combined with an affinity felt in the encounter with Fenellosa who sought to create a foothold in America to counter the dominance of European culture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nihon-ga may have been a product of a nationalistic feeling of crisis due to the rapid influx of western culture under the Meiji government&apos;s westernization policy combined with an affinity felt in the encounter with Fenollosa who sought to create a foothold in America to counter the dominance of European culture.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>イギリスから独立を果たし、南北戦争を経て安定したアメリカ合衆国では、1876年にボストン美術館が設立された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Boston Museum of Fine Arts was established in 1876, at a time when America had gained independence from England and was becoming more stable after the In America, who is stabilized after the Civil War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Boston Museum of Fine Arts was established in 1876, at a time when America had gained independence from England and was becoming more stable after the In America, who is stabilized after the Civil War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Boston Museum of Fine Arts was established in 1876, at a time when United States had gained independence from England and was becoming more stable after the Civil War.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>フェノロサは1890年に帰国後その初代日本部長となり、岡倉はその後を引き継いで1910年、ボストン美術館中国・日本美術部長となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1890, Fenollosa, after returning to America from Japan, was installed as the first head of the Japanese Art Division of the Boston Museum of Fine Arts, and in 1910 Okakura succeeded him as head of the Oriental Division.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1890, Fenollosa, after returning to America from Japan, was installed as the first head of the Japanese Art Division of the Boston Museum of Fine Arts, and in 1910 Okakura succeeded him as head of the Oriental Division.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1890, Fenollosa, after returning to United States from Japan, was installed as the first head of the Japanese Art Division of the Boston Museum of Fine Arts, and in 1910 Okakura succeeded him as head of the Oriental Division.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="34">
<j>日本における洋画と日本画はその後、互いに影響を与えながらも対抗的に併存、発展してきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since then Yoga and Nihonga have continued to their symbiotic relationship, coexisting and developing as rival forces in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since then Yoga and Nihonga have continued to their symbiotic relationship, coexisting and developing as rival forces in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since then Yo-ga and Nihon-ga have continued to their symbiotic relationship, coexisting and developing as rival forces in Japan.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>しかし今日では、主題や様式において、その境界を定めることは難しく、違いは画材にしか求められない状況とも言える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However thesedays it is difficult to delineate the boundary in themes and styles between them, and it is said that the only difference is in painting tools.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However thesedays it is difficult to delineate the boundary in themes and styles between them, and it is said that the only difference is in painting tools.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However these days it is difficult to delineate the boundary in themes and styles between them, and it is said that the only difference is in painting tools.</e>
<cmt>スペース補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>日本画教育</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nihonga Education</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nihonga Education</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nihon-ga Education</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="36">
<j>日本の、芸術系学科以外の高等学校までの美術 (教科)では日本画を教えることはまずない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nihonga is rarely taught in the ordinary art classes up to high school level, apart from in specialized art schools.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nihonga is rarely taught in the ordinary art classes up to high school level, apart from in specialized art schools.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nihon-ga is rarely taught in the ordinary art classes up to high school level, apart from in specialized art schools.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>画材が高価であること、専門の教員の確保が難しいことも理由のひとつであろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is because the painting tools are expensive and it is difficult to employ specialized teachers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is because the painting tools are expensive and it is difficult to employ specialized teachers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is because the painting tools are expensive and it is difficult to employ specialized teachers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>もっとも、油彩画も義務教育では教えられていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The oil painting is not taught as part of the compulsory education either.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The oil painting is not taught as part of the compulsory education either.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The oil painting is not taught as part of the compulsory education either.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="39">
<j>代わりに比較的容易な水彩を教えるのが一般的である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Instead, it is common to teach water painting as it is relatively simpler.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Instead, it is common to teach water painting as it is relatively simpler.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Instead, it is common to teach water painting as it is relatively simpler.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>また美術大学の日本画科の入学試験は水彩絵具による着彩、または、まれに鉛筆によるデッサンのみで行われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, the entrance examinations for Nihonga departments in the art universities include coloring with water paints, and also very rarely dessin pencil drawing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, the entrance examinations for Nihonga departments in the art universities include coloring with water paints, and also very rarely dessin pencil drawing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, the entrance examinations for Nihon-ga departments in the art universities include coloring with water paints, and also very rarely pencil drawing.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="41">
<j>モチーフとなるものは、人物（女性）もしくは静物が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The motif is usually a character (female) portrait or still object.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The motif is usually a character (female) portrait or still object.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The motif is usually a character (female) portrait or still object.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>制作方法</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Method of creation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Method of creation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Method of Creation</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="42">
<j>日本画の制作には様々な種類の岩絵具を主として若干の有機色料を併せ用いる</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nihonga are created mainly with a variety of mineral colors and a small amount of organic colors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nihonga are created mainly with a variety of mineral colors and a small amount of organic colors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nihon-ga are created mainly with a variety of mineral colors and a small amount of organic colors.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>胡粉などの顔料、膠、硯、墨、絹、和紙、刷毛、付立筆や彩色筆等の筆、陶磁器の筆洗（ひっせん）などが必要である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Pigments such as shell lime as well as glue, ink slabs, ink sticks, silk, Japanese paper, paint brushes, tsuketate-fude (paint brushes), coloring brushes and ceramic brush washers and other items are needed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Pigments such as shell lime as well as glue, ink slabs, ink sticks, silk, Japanese paper, paint brushes, tsuketate-fude (paint brushes), coloring brushes and ceramic brush washers and other items are needed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Pigments such as shell lime as well as glue, ink slabs, ink sticks, silk, Japanese paper, paint brushes, tsuketate-fude (paint brushes), coloring brushes and ceramic brush washers and other items are needed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>水彩よりも溶解しない性質があり、何度も絵具を薄く重ねて制作することが可能であるという特徴を持つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One characteristic of Nihonga is that the many layers of paint can be applied due to the property of the paint which does not dissolve compared with water painting.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One characteristic of Nihonga is that the many layers of paint can be applied due to the property of the paint which does not dissolve compared with water painting.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One characteristic of Nihon-ga is that the many layers of paint can be applied due to the property of the paint which does not dissolve compared with water painting.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>近年では、油彩画の影響を受け、絵具を厚く塗り重ねた表現や抽象的描画など、いわゆる伝統的な技法にとらわれない表現技法もみられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In recent years, with the influence of oil painting, we have seen the development of abstract drawings or artworks using thickly daubed paint and other such methods of expression which are not bound by traditional techniques.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In recent years, with the influence of oil painting, we have seen the development of abstract drawings or artworks using thickly daubed paint and other such methods of expression which are not bound by traditional techniques.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In recent years, with the influence of oil painting, we have seen the development of abstract drawings or artworks using thickly daubed paint and other such methods of expression which are not bound by traditional techniques.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>伝統的な方法</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Traditional Method</e>
<cmt>下セルから訳文をコピーしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="46">
<j>絵具は、膠水で溶いて使う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Paint is dissolved in glue solution.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Paint is dissolved in glue solution.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Paint is dissolved in glue solution.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>岩絵具のなかで緑青は青一番から青三番くらいまで、紺青、群青のようなその他これに類する粗さの、俗に砂絵具というほどのものは、ほとんど膠水だけで溶かし、深皿に絵具よりも多い膠水を入れ、羊毛のようなやわらかい筆で絵具をすくうようにして画面に塗る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among mineral colors, malchite No.1 to 3, or those having same coarseness and called sandcolor such as dark blue and pulverized lapis lasuli should be dissolved in a bowl with just the glue solution, using an amount greater than the mineral color; and using a soft brush skim the paint onto the brush and paint.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among mineral colors, malchite No.1 to 3, or those having same coarseness and called sandcolor such as dark blue and pulverized lapis lasuli should be dissolved in a bowl with just the glue solution, using an amount greater than the mineral color; and using a soft brush skim the paint onto the brush and paint.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among mineral colors, malachite No.1 to 3, or those having same coarseness and called sandcolor such as dark blue and pulverized lapis lasuli should be dissolved in a bowl with just the glue solution, using an amount greater than the mineral color; and using a soft brush skim the paint onto the brush and paint.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>きわめて粗い岩ものならば一粒一粒を画面にならべてゆく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If the color is very coarse, put the grains on the drawing one by one.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If the color is very coarse, put the grains on the drawing one by one.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If the color is very coarse, put the grains on the drawing one by one.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>乾くのを待って色調の出るまで何回でも重ね塗りをする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wait till it dry, then repeat painting again and again until the target tint is obtained.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wait till it dry, then repeat painting again and again until the target tint is obtained.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wait till it dry, then repeat painting again and again until the target tint is obtained.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>岩絵具は、2回目ははじいてうまくつかないことが多いが、そのような場合は溶いた絵具にハッカ油かゴマ油を一滴落とすという手法が存在するが、熟練の技術を要する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With mineral colors the color is often repelled on the second coat and does not settle on the paper, however in this case adding a drop of mint oil or sesame oil to the dissolved color may be helpful, but this requires great skill.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With mineral colors the color is often repelled on the second coat and does not settle on the paper, however in this case adding a drop of mint oil or sesame oil to the dissolved color may be helpful, but this requires great skill.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With mineral colors the color is often repelled on the second coat and does not settle on the paper, however in this case adding a drop of mint oil or sesame oil to the dissolved color may be helpful, but this requires great skill.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペースをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>岩絵具で群青の薄群、白群、緑青の白一番から白緑までの粉状のものは、皿の絵具に膠水をまぜて、中指で十分磨り、何回か水を少量加えて適当な粘稠度にして使う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mix the powdery mineral color such as pulverized azurite, byakugun (a light blue pigment) or malchite(white No.1 to byakuroku (a pale green pigment)) on a pallet with a small amount of glue solution and mash it well with the middle finger until it reaches the required viscosity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mix the powdery mineral color such as pulverized azurite, byakugun (a light blue pigment) or malchite(white No.1 to byakuroku (a pale green pigment)) on a pallet with a small amount of glue solution and mash it well with the middle finger until it reaches the required viscosity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mix the powdery mineral color such as pulverized azurite, byakugun (a light blue pigment) or malchite (white No.1 to byakuroku (a pale green pigment)) on a pallet with a small amount of glue solution and mash it well with the middle finger until it reaches the required viscosity.</e>
<cmt>スペース補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>どのような色であっても、一度に濃い色を塗るとまだらになって、画面を汚すから、うすめて二度三度と塗り重ねてようにする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Regardless of the color, the paint should be well diluted and painted a few times rather than applying a thick color because this will mottle or smudge the drawing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regardless of the color, the paint should be well diluted and painted a few times rather than applying a thick color because this will mottle or smudge the drawing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regardless of the color, the paint should be well diluted and painted a few times rather than applying a thick color because this will mottle or smudge the drawing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>土絵具その他は、この方法で溶いて使用する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">How to dissolve and use earth pigments and other colors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">How to dissolve and use earth pigments and other colors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">How to dissolve and use earth pigments and other colors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>胡粉は、溶き方が不用意であると、塗ってから剥落したり、鮮やかな色沢を出すことなどできなかったりする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the case of shell lime, if it is not dissolved correctly, it may peel off and a rich luster will not be obtained.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the case of shell lime, if it is not dissolved correctly, it may peel off and a rich luster will not be obtained.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the case of shell lime, if it is not dissolved correctly, it may peel off and a rich luster will not be obtained.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>水飛が十分に細密な胡粉であれば、最上か一番胡粉で丁寧な錬磨をすれば心配ない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If the shell lime has adequate fineness in water spray, there will be no problems if using the best grade or No.1 shell lime and kneading it carefully.</e>
<cmt>水飛は 水飛沫のことだと解釈しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If the shell lime has adequate fineness in water spray, there will be no problems if using the best grade or No.1 shell lime and kneading it carefully.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If the shell lime has adequate fineness in water spray, there will be no problems if using the best grade or No.1 shell lime and kneading it carefully.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>たくさん使う時は、乳鉢で胡粉をよくすり、まずごく少量の膠液を加えよくすり、また膠液を入れてすり、と、これを三、四回くりかえせば、胡粉と膠液がよく融和し粘りが出てもう乳棒が動かないほどになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If using a substantial amount, knead the shell lime well in a mortar then a add small amount of glue solution and knead it again, and after repeating this process three to four times the shell lime and glue solution will be well mixed and the viscosity such that the pestle is no longer easy to move.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If using a substantial amount, knead the shell lime well in a mortar then a add small amount of glue solution and knead it again, and after repeating this process three to four times the shell lime and glue solution will be well mixed and the viscosity such that the pestle is no longer easy to move.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If using a substantial amount, knead the shell lime well in a mortar then add small amount of glue solution and knead it again, and after repeating this process three to four times the shell lime and glue solution will be well mixed and the viscosity such that the pestle is no longer easy to move.</e>
<cmt>余分な語をのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>これに水をすこしずつ加え、適当な濃さにする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, add water little by little until the required hue is achieved.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, add water little by little until the required hue is achieved.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, add water little by little until the required hue is achieved.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>またこれを別の皿に少し移し、水を加え溶きゆるめ、淡く塗る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Take a little of this and put on a different plate, then add some water to dissolve further and dilute before painting.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Take a little of this and put on a different plate, then add some water to dissolve further and dilute before painting.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Take a little of this and put on a different plate, then add some water to dissolve further and dilute before painting.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>また胡粉は、団子にして保存し、使用時に溶かしてつかう方法もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, the shell lime can be preserved in a dumpling shape and dissolved before using.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, the shell lime can be preserved in a dumpling shape and dissolved before using.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, the shell lime can be preserved in a dumpling shape and dissolved before using.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>膠液は、膠4gにたいして水30ccくらいで煮沸し、よく溶けるのを待ち、用布で濾す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The glue solution should be made by boiling four grams of hide glue in thirty cc of water until well dissolved and filtering it through cloth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The glue solution should be made by boiling four grams of hide glue in thirty cc of water until well dissolved and filtering it through cloth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The glue solution should be made by boiling four grams of hide glue in 30 cc of water until well dissolved and filtering it through cloth.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>水絵具は、膠液をいれず皿ですり、指ですって水を滴下してうすめてつかう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Water paint should be dissolved by kneading it in a plate, without adding any glue solution, and adding water a drop at a time while kneading with a finger.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Water paint should be dissolved by kneading it in a plate, without adding any glue solution, and adding water a drop at a time while kneading with a finger.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Water paint should be dissolved by kneading it in a plate, without adding any glue solution, and adding water a drop at a time while kneading with a finger.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>藍は、膠液を数滴、皿に注ぎ、これを磨り、火でかわかし、水に滴して指で溶く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Indigo should be used by putting a few drops of glue solution into a plate, kneading it, drying it by heating and dissolving it by adding a few drops of water and kneading with a finger.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Indigo should be used by putting a few drops of glue solution into a plate, kneading it, drying it by heating and dissolving it by adding a few drops of water and kneading with a finger.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Indigo should be used by putting a few drops of glue solution into a plate, kneading it, drying it by heating and dissolving it by adding a few drops of water and kneading with a finger.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>洋紅は、膠液少量を皿にいれ洋紅を磨り、水をくわえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Carmine should be used by kneading it with a small amount of glue solution in a plate and adding some water.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Carmine should be used by kneading it with a small amount of glue solution in a plate and adding some water.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Carmine should be used by kneading it with a small amount of glue solution in a plate and adding some water.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>代赭は、膠液を皿にそそぎ、磨り、火であぶってかわかし、水をすこしずつ加えて指で溶く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Red ocher should be used by placing some glue solution in a plate, kneading it, drying it by heat, and dissolving it by adding a few drops of water and kneading with a finger.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Red ocher should be used by placing some glue solution in a plate, kneading it, drying it by heat, and dissolving it by adding a few drops of water and kneading with a finger.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Red ocher should be used by placing some glue solution in a plate, kneading it, drying it by heat, and dissolving it by adding a few drops of water and kneading with a finger.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>藤黄は、水を数滴皿にそそぎ、すれば鮮黄色になるが、使用時に膠液をくわえればなおよい、臙脂は、綿にひたしてあるから、綿を使用分切り取り、皿に入れ、熱湯を少し加え、あぶら分の無い杉箸などで強く搾れば、濃赤色の液汁が出る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gamboge should be used by placing some water into a plate and kneading it until it turns a vivid yellow, and it is good to add some glue solution when using; while dark red pigment has usually already been soaked into a cotton cloth so cut the necessary amount of cloth when needed and put it on a plate, then add a small amount of boiling water and squeeze it hard with bamboo chop sticks which do not contain oil, to release the dark red pigment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gamboge should be used by placing some water into a plate and kneading it until it turns a vivid yellow, and it is good to add some glue solution when using; while dark red pigment has usually already been soaked into a cotton cloth so cut the necessary amount of cloth when needed and put it on a plate, then add a small amount of boiling water and squeeze it hard with bamboo chop sticks which do not contain oil, to release the dark red pigment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gamboge should be used by placing some water into a plate and kneading it until it turns a vivid yellow, and it is good to add some glue solution when using; while dark red pigment has usually already been soaked into a cotton cloth so cut the necessary amount of cloth when needed and put it on a plate, then add a small amount of boiling water and squeeze it hard with Japanese cedar chop sticks which do not contain oil, to release the dark red pigment.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>これを用紙か用布で濾し、滓を取り去り、湯煎にしかわかして使う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Filter it through paper or cloth for removing residue, and double boil to dry it before using.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Filter it through paper or cloth for removing residue, and double boil to dry it before using.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Filter it through paper or cloth for removing residue, and double boil to dry it before using.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>湯煎前に酒を一滴たらすと色が乾燥せず、潤いを保つという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said if you add a drop of sake when double boiling, the color will not dry out and it will keep the moisture in.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said if you add a drop of sake when double boiling, the color will not dry out and it will keep the moisture in.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said if you add a drop of sake (Japanese liquor) when double boiling, the color will not dry out and it will keep the moisture in.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>湯煎にした皿の絵具を使うのは、筆に水をふくませ、必要分だけを皿で溶き、この場合、膠を少量加えることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To use the colors on the bowl used in double boiling, put water on the brush and dissolve the minimum amount necessary in the bowl; and sometimes a little glue is added in this case.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To use the colors on the bowl used in double boiling, put water on the brush and dissolve the minimum amount necessary in the bowl; and sometimes a little glue is added in this case.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To use the colors on the bowl used in double boiling, put water on the brush and dissolve the minimum amount necessary in the bowl; and sometimes a little glue is added in this case.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>臙脂は、浸透性が強く、塗り方は難しく、熟練した技術を要する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dark red color has strong permeability, and is difficult to paint with, requiring experience and skill.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dark red color has strong permeability, and is difficult to paint with, requiring experience and skill.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dark red color has strong permeability, and is difficult to paint with, requiring experience and skill.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>臙脂は胡粉（膠液で正式に溶いたものがよい）をごく少量加えれば、色沢を失わない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If a small amount of shell lime (preferably one properly dissolved with glue solution) is added to the dark red color it will retain its luster.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If a small amount of shell lime (preferably one properly dissolved with glue solution) is added to the dark red color it will retain its luster.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If a small amount of shell lime (preferably one properly dissolved with glue solution) is added to the dark red color it will retain its luster.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペースをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>技法</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Technique</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Technique</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Technique</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="71">
<j>没骨法</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mokkotsu (painting without an outline) Technique</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mokkotsu (painting without an outline) Technique</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mokkotsu (painting without an outline) Technique</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>箔</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Leaf</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Leaf</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Leaf</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="73">
<j>礬水引き（どうさびき）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sizing</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sizing</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dosabiki (Sizing)</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>具墨</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Guzumi (dark grey pigment)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Guzumi (dark grey pigment)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Guzumi (dark grey pigment)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>鉄線</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tessen (iron wire) Line drawing</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tessen (iron wire) Line drawing</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tessen (iron wire) Line drawing</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="76">
<j>画壇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Artists&apos; Society</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Artists&apos; Society</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Artists&apos; Society</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>日本美術院</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Japan Art Academy</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Japan Art Academy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japan Art Academy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>創画会</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sogakai</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sogakai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sogakai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>日本美術展覧会（日展）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Japan Fine Arts Exhibition (Nitten)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Japan Fine Arts Exhibition (Nitten)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japan Fine Arts Exhibition (Nitten)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Tommy6-bot(id:171289), クモハモハ大王(id:185685), 江口磐世☆(id:168037), SPR(id:141947), Tantant(id:7195), Martin(id:6394), Xqbot(id:273540), Shinobar(id:42025), VolkovBot(id:105371), Loveless(id:129239), Onyx(id:196961), Avxz(id:123412), Peanut(id:22687), Uryah(id:17871), TeaServer(id:55403), Ws227(id:208643), YukkeBot2(id:251491), Ddaa(id:200501), Chuta(id:10457), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>