<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>ゆがけ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yugake (a glove on the right hand)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yugake (a glove on the right hand)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yugake (a glove on the right hand)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>弽（ゆがけ、かけ、しょう）は日本の弓道・弓術に於いて使用される和弓を引くための道具で、鹿革製の手袋状のもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yugake (&quot;弽&quot;) is a deerskin glove-like gear for drawing Japanese bow used in Japanese kyudo (Japanese art of archery) or the art of Japanese archery.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yugake, also referred as Kake, Sho is a deerskin glove-like gear for drawing Japanese bow used in Japanese kyudo (Japanese art of archery) or the art of Japanese archery.</e>
<cmt>Yugake (&quot;弽&quot;)→Yugake, also referred as Kake, Sho) と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yugake, also referred as Kake, Sho is a deerskin glove-like gear for drawing Japanese bow used in Japanese kyudo (Japanese art of archery) or the art of Japanese archery.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>弓懸けとも表記する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also spelled &quot;弓懸け.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also written &quot;弓懸け.&quot;</e>
<cmt>spelled→written と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also written &quot;弓懸け.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>原則として弓は左手、弽（ユガケ）は右手に嵌め、弦は親指根に掛けて弓を引くが、その際弦から右手親指を保護する為に使う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In principle they grip a bow with the left hand and wear a yugake on the right hand and draw a bow by putting a string on the base of the right hand thumb, at this moment a yugake protects the thumb from a string.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In principle, they grip the bow with the left hand and wear a yugake on the right hand and draw a bow by putting the string on the base of the right hand thumb, at this moment the yugake protects the thumb from the string.</e>
<cmt>カンマを挿入しました。a,the を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In principle, they grip the bow with the left hand and wear a yugake on the right hand and draw a bow by putting the string on the base of the right hand thumb, at this moment the yugake protects the thumb from the string.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>概論</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>ユガケは和弓の登場時から親指に弦を掛け弓を引く「蒙古式（右図Fig.3）」の取り掛けをする日本の射法に合わせて独自に発展した道具であり、時代毎の流派や射術、弓射のあり方の変遷に伴いユガケもその時代毎に改良が重ねられ、現在の形に至る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yugake is the gear which uniquely developed with Japanese way of shooting that had applied the way of setting of &quot;Menggu (Mongol) style (right figure. 3)&quot; where a bow was drawn with a thumb since Japanese bow appeared and improved repeatedly with the changes of schools in successive periods, shajutsu (technique to shoot a bow) or yumiire(or kyusha, ceremonial shooting) and have become a present form.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yugake is the gear which uniquely developed with Japanese way of shooting that had applied the way of setting of &apos;Menggu&apos; (Mongol) style (right figure. 3) where a bow was drawn with a thumb since Japanese bow appeared and improved repeatedly with the changes of schools in successive periods, shajutsu (technique to shoot a bow) or yumiire(or kyusha, ceremonial shooting) and have become a present form.</e>
<cmt>クォーツを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yugake is the gear which uniquely developed with Japanese way of shooting that had applied the way of setting of &apos;Menggu&apos; (Mongol) style (right figure. 3) where a bow was drawn with a thumb since Japanese bow appeared and improved repeatedly with the changes of schools in successive periods, shajutsu (technique to shoot a bow) or yumiire(or kyusha, ceremonial shooting) and have become a present form.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>今日使われているユガケは日本に武士が使用していたユガケとは基本的な作りから異なり、一般的には三ツガケ、或は四ツガケと呼ばれる親指（帽子）と手首（控え）が固めてあるものが使用されるている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The yugake which is used today is different from the one used by samurais in Japan in the basic structure and in general the one which fixes the thumb (boshi, a part of a yugake glove covering a thumb) and the wrist (hikae) is used and it is called mitsugake (three-fingered shooting glove) or yotsugake (four-fingered shooting glove).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The yugake which is used today is different from the one used by samurais in Japan in the basic structure, and in general, the one which is called mitsugake (three-fingered shooting glove) or yotsugake (four-fingered shooting glove), the thumb (boshi, a part of a yugake glove covering a thumb) and the wrist (hikae) are reinforced are used.</e>
<cmt>カンマを挿入しました。文章の流れをスムースに、また、”固めてある”を reinforced とし、修正しました。　</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The yugake which is used today is different from the one used by samurais in Japan in the basic structure, and in general, the one which is called mitsugake (three-fingered shooting glove) or yotsugake (four-fingered shooting glove), the thumb (boshi, a part of a yugake glove covering a thumb) and the wrist (hikae) are reinforced are used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>ユガケを嵌める事を『ユガケを挿す』と言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To wear a yugake is called &apos;yugake wo sasu (insert a yugake).&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To wear a yugake is called &quot;yugake wo sasu&quot; (insert a yugake).</e>
<cmt>クォーツを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To wear a yugake is called &quot;yugake wo sasu&quot; (insert a yugake).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>原則として『正座をしてユガケを挿す・外す』『弓射以外の作業を行う際は必ずユガケを外す』事が基本的な作法である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In principle, as basic manners, &apos;they put a yugake on or off sitting straight,&apos; or &apos;when they do the job except for kyusha they always put a yugake off.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In principle, as basic manners, &quot;sitting straight when we put a yugake on or off,&quot; or &quot;always take a yugake off when we do anything except for kyusha.&quot;</e>
<cmt>クォーツを修正しました。they→we,put→take と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In principle, as basic manners, &quot;sitting straight when we put a yugake on or off,&quot; or &quot;always take a yugake off when we do anything except for kyusha.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>ユガケを挿す際、下に「下ガケ」と呼ばれる木綿等の薄い生地で出来た肌着のようなものを付けるが、これは手汗を吸い取り湿気からユガケを保護する為のもので、手汗を掻いた場合はこまめに取り替えるのが好ましい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When wearing a yugake, they put on something like an underclothing, called &quot;shitagake (cotton underglove),&quot; which is made from a thin material such as cotton and so on and the purpose of shitagake is to absorb a hand sweat and protect a yugake from the humidity and when sweating on the hand it should frequently be changed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When wearing a yugake, they put on something like an underclothing, called &apos;shitagake&apos; (cotton underglove), which is made from a thin material such as cotton and so on and the purpose of shitagake is to absorb a hand sweat and protect a yugake from the humidity, and when sweating on the hand, it is better to change it frequently.</e>
<cmt>クォーツを修正しました。カンマを挿入しました。it should frequently be changed→it is better to change it frequently と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When wearing a yugake, they put on something like an underclothing, called &apos;shitagake&apos; (cotton underglove), which is made from a thin material such as cotton and so on and the purpose of shitagake is to absorb a hand sweat and protect a yugake from the humidity, and when sweating on the hand, it is better to change it frequently.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="10">
<j>三ツガケは親指・人差指・中指、四ツガケは親指〜薬指までを覆い、親指には木（或は水牛等の角）を指筒状に刳り貫いたものが親指全体を覆うように仕込まれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitsugake covers a thumb, a forefinger and a middle finger and yotsugake covers fingers from a thumb to an annular finger and it is equipped with a thimble-like wood (or a horn of water buffalo and so on) which is hollowed out, covering a whole of a thumb.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitsugake covers the thumb, the forefinger and the middle finger and yotsugake covers fingers from the thumb to the annular finger and it is equipped with a thimble-like wood (or a horn of water buffalo and so on) which is hollowed out, covering a whole of the thumb.</e>
<cmt>a,the を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitsugake covers the thumb, the forefinger and the middle finger and yotsugake covers fingers from the thumb to the annular finger and it is equipped with a thimble-like wood (or a horn of water buffalo and so on) which is hollowed out, covering a whole of the thumb.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>さらに親指根〜手首部分が固めてあり、ユガケを挿しカケ紐で手首を適度に巻き締めることにより、手首〜親指は動きの自由度が殆ど無くなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, as all the parts from the base of a thumb to a wrist are fixed, the parts has little degree of freedom for movement by lacing and tightening the wrist when wearing a yugake.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, as the part from the base of the thumb to the wrist is reinforced, the part has little degree of freedom for movement by twining kake himo (a leather strap for securing a yugake) and tightening the wrist when wearing a yugake.</e>
<cmt>a→the,fixed→reinforced,lacing→twining kakehimo, と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, as the part from the base of the thumb to the wrist is reinforced, the part has little degree of freedom for movement by twining kake himo (a leather strap for securing a yugake) and tightening the wrist when wearing a yugake.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>この為ユガケを挿したままでは物を掴む等の行為が困難になるため、弓射以外の作業を行う際はユガケを外す事となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this reason, it is difficult to grasp something and so on with a yugake on and they have to put it off when doing things except for kyusha.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this reason, it is difficult to grasp something and so on with a yugake on, and they have to take it off when doing things except for kyusha.</e>
<cmt>カンマを挿入しました。put→take と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For this reason, it is difficult to grasp something and so on with a yugake on, and they have to take it off when doing things except for kyusha.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="13">
<j>ユガケの親指根には弦が引っかかる程度の浅い段差（弦枕）が付けられており、ここに弦を掛け、三ツガケは中指、四ツガケなら薬指を親指先に掛け、手首に適度な捻りを加える事により弦は保持される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yugake has a bump (tsurumakura, a part of a yugake glove to set a string) which is shallow enough to set a string at the base of thumb and they set a string here and put a middle finger (mitsugake) or an annular finger (yotsugake) on the tip of a thumb and add an appropriate twist to the wrist and then the string comes to be held.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yugake has a shallow bump (tsurumakura, a part of a yugake glove to set a string) which is enough to set a string at the base of thumb, and they set a string this part and put the middle finger for mitsugake, or the annular finger for yotsugake on the tip of a thumb and add an appropriate twist to the wrist and then the string comes to be held.</e>
<cmt>文脈に応じてshallow の場所変更、カッコを外し、修正しました。a, an を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yugake has a shallow bump (tsurumakura, a part of a yugake glove to set a string) which is enough to set a string at the base of thumb, and they set a string this part and put the middle finger for mitsugake, or the annular finger for yotsugake on the tip of a thumb and add an appropriate twist to the wrist and then the string comes to be held.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>滑り止めに「ギリ粉（ぎりこ：松脂を煮詰めて乾燥、粉末状に砕いたもの）」を中指〜人指し指、或は薬指〜人指し指と親指先にまぶし、馴染ませて使用する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As an anti-slip device, they dust a middle finger to a forefinger or from an annular finger to a forefinger and a thumb tip with &quot;giriko rosin powder (pine resin is boiled down, dried and broken into powdered state)&quot; and after it fits comfortably in the hand, they start to use a yugake.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As an anti-slip technique, they dust the middle finger to the forefinger, or from an annular finger to a forefinger and a thumb tip with &apos;giriko rosin powder&apos; (pine resin is boiled down, dried and broken into powdered state) and make it fit in.</e>
<cmt>device→techniqueと修正しました。 クォーツを修正しました。カンマの挿入、after it fits comfortably in the hand, they start to use a yugake→make it fit in と修正しました。a, an を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As an anti-slip technique, they dust the middle finger to the forefinger, or from an annular finger to a forefinger and a thumb tip with &apos;giriko rosin powder&apos; (pine resin is boiled down, dried and broken into powdered state) and make it fit in.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="15">
<j>弓射に於いて、ユガケの作りの善し悪しは行射の善し悪しに直接関わる極めて重要な要素であり、また、長年使い込まれ射手の手に馴染んだユガケはそう簡単に新調出来るものではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In kyusha, the good or ill of making of a yugake is very important because it directly relates with the good or ill of shooting and the yugake which has long been used and fitted in the hand of a shooter can not be easily renewed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In kyusha, the good or ill of making of a yugake is very important because it directly relates with the good or ill of shooting and the yugake which has long been used and fitted in the hand of a shooter can not be easily renewed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In kyusha, the good or ill of making of a yugake is very important because it directly relates with the good or ill of shooting and the yugake which has long been used and fitted in the hand of a shooter can not be easily renewed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>良い作りのユガケは適切な手入れを行っていれば一生涯持つと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The well-made yugake is said to be durable whole life long if it is appropriately cared.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The well-made yugake is said to last whole life long if it is appropriately cared.</e>
<cmt>be durable→last と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The well-made yugake is said to last whole life long if it is appropriately cared.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>これらの事からユガケは大切に扱う事が大事であるとされ、また（言語学的根拠に乏しいが）『カケ、変え』から転じて『掛け替えの無い…』という言葉の語源だと弓道家の間でしばしば言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this reason, it is vital to treat a yugake importantly and (without a linguistic ground) it is often said among kyudo-ka (those who does kyudo) that &quot;kake (set, hook or place), kae (change)&quot; is the word origin of &quot;kakegae no nai (irreplaceable).&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this reason, it is vital to treat the yugake with great care, and (without a linguistic ground) it is often said among kyudo-ka (those who do kyudo) that &quot;kake, kae&quot; (set, hook or place and change) is the word originated &quot;kakegae no nai&quot; (irreplaceable).</e>
<cmt>a yogake→the yogake,importantly→with great care,カンマを挿入しました。does→do,クォーツを修正しました。origin of→originated と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For this reason, it is vital to treat the yugake with great care, and (without a linguistic ground) it is often said among kyudo-ka (those who do kyudo) that &quot;kake, kae&quot; (set, hook or place and change) is the word originated &quot;kakegae no nai&quot; (irreplaceable).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="18">
<j>構造</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Structure</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Structure</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Structure</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>素材</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Materials</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Materials</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Materials</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>ユガケの親指には指筒状に刳り貫かれた木、或は水牛等の角（総称して「角」と呼ばれる）が入り、控え（手首部分）には牛革が固めの為に入っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yugake&apos;s thumb is a thimble-like wood or horn of water buffalo and so on, which is hollowed out, (generally called &quot;tsuno&quot;) and the hikae (wrist part) is a cowhide for fixation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Inside of yugake&apos;s thumb, there is a hollowed out thimble-like wood or horn of water buffalo (generally called &apos;tsuno&apos;) and so on, and there is a cowhide in the hikae (wrist part) for reinforcement.</e>
<cmt>”刳り貫かれた”という部分を挿入し、文脈より修正しました。クォーツを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Inside of yugake&apos;s thumb, there is a hollowed out thimble-like wood or horn of water buffalo (generally called &apos;tsuno&apos;) and so on, and there is a cowhide in the hikae (wrist part) for reinforcement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>親指に角を入れ固める事によって、弦の圧力から親指を保護し、控えを固める事によって手首の負担を軽減、また控えによって機械的なバネの効果を持たせ“弓道射法八節”の際有利に働くようになっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To fix a thumb part by putting a tsuno protects the thumb from a pressure of a string and decreases the burden of a wrist by fixing the hikae which gives a mechanical spring effect and a yugake advantageously works when doing the kyudo-shaho hassetsu (eight arts of shooting an arrow).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reinforcing the thumb part by putting tsuno inside protects the thumb from a pressure of a string and decreases the burden of a wrist by reinforcing the hikae which gives a mechanical spring effect and yugake advantageously works when doing the &quot;Kyudo-shaho hassetsu&quot; (eight arts of shooting an arrow).</e>
<cmt>To fix→Reinforcing,fixing→reinforcing と修正しました。クォーツを挿入しました。kyudo→Kyudo と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reinforcing the thumb part by putting tsuno inside protects the thumb from a pressure of a string and decreases the burden of a wrist by reinforcing the hikae which gives a mechanical spring effect and yugake advantageously works when doing the &quot;Kyudo-shaho hassetsu&quot; (eight arts of shooting an arrow).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="22">
<j>皮革には原則としてシカ革が使用される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In principle, deerskin is used as a hide.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In principle, deerskin is used as a leather.</e>
<cmt>hide→leather と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In principle, deerskin is used as a leather.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>これは柔軟性、吸湿性、耐久性、肌理が細かく肌触りが良い、という点から、鹿革が最も適している為である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is because the deerskin is the most appropriate in flexibility, moisture absorbency, durability and fine texture which feels soft.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is because the deerskin is the most appropriate in flexibility, moisture absorbency, durability and fine texture which feels soft.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is because the deerskin is the most appropriate in flexibility, moisture absorbency, durability and fine texture which feels soft.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>稀に装飾目的で別の皮革が使用される場合もあるが、装飾に於いても多くは印伝等の鹿革由来のものが使われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In rare cases, the other hides are used for decorative purposes, but the hides originating from deerskin such as inden (tanned deerskin or sheepskin) and so on are used in many decorations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In rare cases, other leather is used for decorative purposes, but the leather originating from deerskin such as inden (tanned deerskin or sheepskin) and so on are used in many decorations.</e>
<cmt>the other hides are→other leather is,hides→leather と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In rare cases, other leather is used for decorative purposes, but the leather originating from deerskin such as inden (tanned deerskin or sheepskin) and so on are used in many decorations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="25">
<j>鹿革は「燻革（ふすべかわ）」に加工したものを使う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They use the deerskin which is processed into &quot;kusube-gawa (a smoked skin).&quot;</e>
<cmt>本文は「ふすべかわ」とありますが、用語検索ではkusube-gawaと出てきました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They use the deerskin which is processed into &apos;fusube-gawa&apos; (a smoked skin).</e>
<cmt>クォーツを修正しました。kusube-gawa→fusube-gawa（”燻革”はウェブで確認したところ、ふすべがわ、くすべがわの両方を確認しましたが、アルファベットでは　fusube-gawa の使用が確認できましたので修正しました）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They use the deerskin which is processed into &apos;fusube-gawa&apos; (a smoked skin).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>これは鞣した鹿革を、藁を燃した煙で燻しヤニを付ける（燻染め）事によって茶色に染めたものだが、燻染めを施すことで防菌、防虫効果を高め、また皮革を柔らかくしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tanned deerskins are dyed in brown by burning straws, smoking and tarring (&quot;kusube-zome,&quot; smoked dyeing) and by this the deerskins have the effect of antibacterial and insect deterrent and are softened.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is tanned deerskin which is dyed brown by burning straws, smoking and tarring (kusube-zome, smoked dyeing), and by this, the leather has the effect of antibacterial and insect deterrent and is softened.</e>
<cmt>This is, which を挿入しました。deerskins are→deerskin is,クォーツを削除しました。カンマを挿入しました。the deer skins have→the leather has, と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is tanned deerskin which is dyed brown by burning straws, smoking and tarring (kusube-zome, smoked dyeing), and by this, the leather has the effect of antibacterial and insect deterrent and is softened.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>鹿革をその他の色に染める場合も燻染めを施してから染められている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also when deerskins are dyed in the other colors, after smoked dyeing they are dyed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also when deerskin is dyed other colors, it is dyed after the kusube-zome.</e>
<cmt>deerskins are→deerskin is,in the を削除、文中後半部分を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also when deerskin is dyed other colors, it is dyed after the kusube-zome.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>ユガケの縫い目は一般的な縫製品に比べ非常に細かく、特に名人とされる弽師（ゆがけし・かけし）の手縫いは精緻を極める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The stitching of a yugake is very fine compared with general sewn products and especially the stitching of yugakeshi or kakeshi (maker of a yugake) who are the master is extremely elaborate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The stitching of yugake is very fine compared with general sewn products and especially the hand-stitching of yugakeshi or kakeshi (maker of yugake), who are masters, are extremely elaborate.</e>
<cmt>”手縫い”の部分を補いました。 a yugake→yugake,the master→masters と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The stitching of yugake is very fine compared with general sewn products and especially the hand-stitching of yugakeshi or kakeshi (maker of yugake), who are masters, are extremely elaborate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="29">
<j>鹿革には「大唐（おおとう）」「中唐（ちゅうとう）」「小唐（ことう）」「チビ小唐（ちびことう）」といったグレード分けがされており、大唐は大人、小唐は子鹿と言ったように鹿の年齢からなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Deerskins are divided into the grades such as &quot;oto quality,&quot; &quot;chuto quality,&quot; &quot;koto quality&quot; and &quot;chibikoto quality&quot; and they are decided by the age of deer such as oto one by adult deer and koto one by deerlet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Deerskin is graded into &apos;oto quality,&apos; &apos;chuto quality,&apos; &apos;koto quality&apos; and &apos;chibikoto quality&apos; by the age of deer such as oto one from adult deer and koto one from young deer.</e>
<cmt>Deerskins are→deerskin is, divided into the grades such as→graded into, クォーツを修正しました。 and they are decided を削除しました。by→from,deerlet→young deer と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Deerskin is graded into &apos;oto quality,&apos; &apos;chuto quality,&apos; &apos;koto quality&apos; and &apos;chibikoto quality&apos; by the age of deer such as oto one from adult deer and koto one from young deer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>若い皮革の方が肌理が細かく柔らかいためユガケには最適だが、高価である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the texture of young hides is finer and softer, they are the most appropriate for a yugake but expensive.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the texture of young leather is finer and softer, they are the most appropriate for a yugake, but expensive.</e>
<cmt>hides→leather,カンマを挿入しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the texture of young leather is finer and softer, they are the most appropriate for a yugake, but expensive.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>１枚の鹿の皮革の中で最適な厚みや肌理、傷の有無等一番良い所から皮革を取るため、鹿一頭からはユガケ１つ分の皮革しか取れない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Only one portion of deerskin for a yugake can be taken out from one deer because it is taken out from the best part which has the most appropriate thickness and texture and has no scar and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Only one portion of deerskin for a yugake can be taken out from one deer because it is taken out from the best part which has the most appropriate thickness and texture and has no scars and so on.</e>
<cmt>scar→scars と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Only one portion of deerskin for a yugake can be taken out from one deer because it is taken out from the best part which has the most appropriate thickness and texture and has no scars and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>現在日本の鹿は天然記念物として保護されているため、鹿革は全て中国等外国からの輸入品であるが、近年養鹿業は採算が合わないとして数が減りつつあり、将来的な供給が危ぶまれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At present Japanese deers are protected as natural treasures and thus all the deerskins are imported from foreign countries such as China and so on, but recently the number of deer farming industries decreased because they are unprofitable and the future supply is under threat.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At present Japanese deer are protected as natural treasures and thus all the deerskin is imported from foreign countries such as China and so on, but recently the number of deer farming industries is decreasing because they are unprofitable and the future supply is under threat.</e>
<cmt>deers→deer,deerskins are→deerskin is,decreased→is decreasing と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At present Japanese deer are protected as natural treasures and thus all the deerskin is imported from foreign countries such as China and so on, but recently the number of deer farming industries is decreasing because they are unprofitable and the future supply is under threat.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="33">
<j>部位別</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Difference of the parts</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Different parts</e>
<cmt>Difference of the parts→Different parts と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Different parts</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>堅帽子（かたぼうし）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kataboshi (a glove with hardened thumb)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kataboshi (a glove with hardened thumb)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kataboshi (a glove with hardened thumb)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>三ツガケ、四ツガケ、諸ガケに見られる現在最も一般的な作り。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has the most common making seen in mitsugake, yotsugake and morogake (a five-fingered shooting glove).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is the most common structure seen in mitsugake, yotsugake and morogake (a five-fingered shooting glove).</e>
<cmt>making→structure,has→is と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is the most common structure seen in mitsugake, yotsugake and morogake (a five-fingered shooting glove).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>帽子（親指）に「角（木、或は水牛等の角を指筒状に刳り貫いた芯材）」が仕込まれており、それに覆われた親指先の自由度は全くない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Tsuno (a core material which is a thimble-like wood or horn of water buffalo and so on, which is hollowed out)&quot; is put on boshi (thumb) and the tip of thumb covered with it has no degree of freedom.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsuno&apos; (a core material which is a thimble-like wood or horn of water buffalo and so on, which is hollowed out) is put inside of boshi (thumb), and the tip of thumb covered with it has no degree of freedom.</e>
<cmt>クォーツを修正しました。on→inside of,カンマを挿入しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsuno&apos; (a core material which is a thimble-like wood or horn of water buffalo and so on, which is hollowed out) is put inside of boshi (thumb), and the tip of thumb covered with it has no degree of freedom.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>弦の圧力が親指に直接掛かる事が無く親指への負担が少ない為、矢数を掛ける事に適している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As there are no direct pressure of a string and little burden over a thumb, it is appropriate for shooting lots of arrows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As there are no direct pressure of a string and little strain on a thumb, it is appropriate for shooting lots of arrows.</e>
<cmt>burden over→strain on と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As there are no direct pressure of a string and little strain on a thumb, it is appropriate for shooting lots of arrows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>親指根部分に弦を掛ける段差（弦枕）があり、弦枕の形状は射の運行、矢の飛び方に関わる極めて重要な部分。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The base part of a thumb has a bump (tsurumakura) and the form of tsurumakura is a very important part because it is related with shooting and the movement of a flying arrow.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The base part of the thumb has a bump (tsurumakura) and the form of tsurumakura is a very important part, since it affects shooting and the movement of a flying arrow.</e>
<cmt>a thumb→the thumb,because→since,is related with→affects,カンマを挿入しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The base part of the thumb has a bump (tsurumakura) and the form of tsurumakura is a very important part, since it affects shooting and the movement of a flying arrow.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>帽子から控えまで固めた「堅帽子・控え付き」が現在最も一般的な作りで、「本ガケ」とも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kataboshi with a hikae&quot; which fixes the parts from a boshi to a hikae is now the most common making and called &quot;hongake&quot; (an ordinary yugake shooting glove).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kataboshi with hikae&apos; which reinforces the parts from a boshi to a hikae is now the most common structure and called &apos;hongake&apos; (an ordinary yugake shooting glove).</e>
<cmt>making→structure,fixes→reinforces と修正しました。クォーツを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kataboshi with hikae&apos; which reinforces the parts from a boshi to a hikae is now the most common structure and called &apos;hongake&apos; (an ordinary yugake shooting glove).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="40">
<j>柔帽子・和帽子（やわらかぼうし・わぼうし）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yawaraka boshi or wa boshi (a soft glove (without a hardened thumb))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yawaraka boshi, also referred to as Wa boshi (a soft glove [without a hardened thumb])</e>
<cmt>Yawaraka boshi or wa boshi の部分を修正しました。カッコ内を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yawaraka boshi, also referred to as Wa boshi (a soft glove [without a hardened thumb])</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>帽子（親指）に固めの為の角が入っておらず、皮革が２枚以上重ねてあるのみである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The boshi (thumb) has no tsuno for fixation and puts on just more than two sheets of hide.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The boshi (thumb) has no tsuno inside to be reinforced, and there is just more than two sheets of leather on it.</e>
<cmt>文脈より修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The boshi (thumb) has no tsuno inside to be reinforced, and there is just more than two sheets of leather on it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>このため親指の自由が効き“弓道射法八節”の際に余分な抵抗が無いため有利であるとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That is why a thumb can move freely and is said to be advantageous in kyudo-shaho hassetsu (eight arts of shooting an arrow) because there is no extra resistance against a thumb.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That is why a thumb can move freely and is said to be advantageous in &quot;Kyudo-shaho hassetsu&quot; (eight arts of shooting an arrow) because there is no extra resistance against a thumb.</e>
<cmt>クォーツを挿入しました。kyudo→Kyudo と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That is why a thumb can move freely and is said to be advantageous in &quot;Kyudo-shaho hassetsu&quot; (eight arts of shooting an arrow) because there is no extra resistance against a thumb.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="43">
<j>柔帽子・控え無しの三ツガケは、弦を掛ける感触が掴み易く且つ手首が自由な事から、初心者が弓を引き始める頃、または未経験者が体験的に弓を引く際に使わせる事もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitsugake of yawaraka boshi without a hikae is sometimes used when the beginner starts to draw a bow or when the amateur experientially does so because the feel of setting a string is easy and the wrist can move freely.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitsugake without yawaraka boshi and hikae is sometimes used when a beginner starts to draw a bow or when an amateur experimentally does so because the feel of setting a string is easy and the wrist can move freely.</e>
<cmt>Mitsugake of yawaraka boshi without a hikae→Mitsugake without yawaraboshi and hikae と修正しました。the をそれぞれ修正しました。experientially→experimentally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitsugake without yawaraka boshi and hikae is sometimes used when a beginner starts to draw a bow or when an amateur experimentally does so because the feel of setting a string is easy and the wrist can move freely.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>弓道用のユガケの中では最も歴史が古く、武士が使っていたユガケに近い作りをしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is historically the oldest yugake for kyudo and is structurally similar to the yugake used by samurais.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has the oldest history in the yugake for kyudo and is structurally similar to the yugake used by samurais.</e>
<cmt>文脈より修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has the oldest history in the yugake for kyudo and is structurally similar to the yugake used by samurais.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="45">
<j>節抜き（ふしぬき）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fushinuki (yugake shooting glove)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fushinuki (yugake shooting glove)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fushinuki (yugake shooting glove)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>帽子の角の親指背にあたる部分が刳り貫かれ開いている造り。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has the making where the backside part of thumb of boshi&apos;s tsuno is hollowed out.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is the structure where the backside part of thumb of boshi&apos;s tsuno is hollowed out.</e>
<cmt>making→structure,has→is と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is the structure where the backside part of thumb of boshi&apos;s tsuno is hollowed out.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>親指全周を固めないため、親指の太さに合わせ易い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It does not fix the entire perimeter of a thumb and is easy to adjust for the perimeter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It does not reinforce around the thumb and is easy to adjust for the size of thumb.</e>
<cmt>fix→reinforce,”親指全周”around the thumb,”太さ”size として修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It does not reinforce around the thumb and is easy to adjust for the size of thumb.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>堅帽子のユガケの作りの一種で、竹林ガケ等が節抜き。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a kind of kataboshi yugake and chikuringake shooting glove and so on are fushinuki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a kind of kataboshi yugake and chikuringake shooting glove and so on are fushinuki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a kind of kataboshi yugake and chikuringake shooting glove and so on are fushinuki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="49">
<j>控え付き（ひかえつき、俗称）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With a hikae (commonly called hikaetsuki, a yugake glove with a hard guard to immobilize a wrist)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With hikae (commonly called hikaetsuki, a yugake glove with a hard guard to immobilize a wrist)</e>
<cmt>a hikae→hikae と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With hikae (commonly called hikaetsuki, a yugake glove with a hard guard to immobilize a wrist)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>手首（控え）部分に固めの為の硬い牛革等が入っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The wrist (hikae) part has a hard cowhide and so on for fixation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The wrist (hikae) part has a hard cowhide and so on for reinforcement.</e>
<cmt>fixation→reinforcement と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The wrist (hikae) part has a hard cowhide and so on for reinforcement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>三ツガケ、四ツガケに見られる最も一般的な作り。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has the most common making as seen in mitsugake and yotsugake.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is the most common structure as seen in mitsugake and yotsugake.</e>
<cmt>has→is,making→structure と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is the most common structure as seen in mitsugake and yotsugake.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>柔帽子、堅帽子の別なく見られる造りの一種で、控えを固める事によって手首〜親指根の自由が無くなり手首が安定しやすい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The making is the one seen irrespective of yawarakaboshi or kataboshi and by fixing a hikae the part from a wrist to a thumb cannot move freely and is likely to stabilize.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The structure is the one seen irrespective of yawarakaboshi or kataboshi and by reinforcing hikae, the part from wrist to thumb cannot move freely and is likely to stabilize.</e>
<cmt>making→structure,fixing→reinforcing,カンマを挿入しました。a を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The structure is the one seen irrespective of yawarakaboshi or kataboshi and by reinforcing hikae, the part from wrist to thumb cannot move freely and is likely to stabilize.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>「堅帽子・控え付き」が現在最も一般的な作りで、「本ガケ」とも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kataboshi with a hikae&quot; is the most common making and is also called &quot;hongake.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kataboshi with hikae&apos; is the most common structure and is also called &apos;hongake.&apos;</e>
<cmt>making→structure,クォーツを修正しました。a hikae→hikae</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kataboshi with hikae&apos; is the most common structure and is also called &apos;hongake.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>“弓道射法八節”に於いて控えの固めがバネのように働き、親指の跳ね上げが促され弦の運行を妨げないとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;kyudo-shaho hassetsu&quot; the fixation by a hikae works like a spring and promotes the flip-up of a thumb and do not prevent the movement of a string.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;Kyudo-shaho hassetsu&quot; the reinfarcement by hikae works like a spring and promotes the flip-up of a thumb and do not prevent the movement of a string.</e>
<cmt>kyudo→Kyudo,a hikake→hikake,fixation→reinforcement と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;Kyudo-shaho hassetsu&quot; the reinfarcement by hikae works like a spring and promotes the flip-up of a thumb and do not prevent the movement of a string.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="55">
<j>控え無し（ひかえなし、俗称）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Without a hikae (commonly called hikaenashi, a yugake glove without a hard guard to immobilize a wrist)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Without hikae (commonly called hikaenashi, a yugake glove without a hard guard to immobilize a wrist)</e>
<cmt>a hikae→hikae と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Without hikae (commonly called hikaenashi, a yugake glove without a hard guard to immobilize a wrist)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>『控え付き』に対して、手首（控え）部分に固めが入っていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Contrary to &quot;hikaetsuki,&quot; the wrist (hikae) part is not fixed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Contrary to &quot;hikaetsuki,&quot; the wrist (hikae) part is not reinforced.</e>
<cmt>fixed→reinforced と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Contrary to &quot;hikaetsuki,&quot; the wrist (hikae) part is not reinforced.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>三ツガケに見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is seen in mitsugake.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is seen in mitsugake.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is seen in mitsugake.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>また、諸ガケはもともと騎射ガケの流れを汲むため控えが無い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, morogake originally comes from ishagake (a yugake glove for yabusame shooting on horseback) and has no hikae.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, morogake originally comes from ishagake (a yugake glove for yabusame shooting on horseback) and has no hikae.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, morogake originally comes from ishagake (a yugake glove for yabusame shooting on horseback) and has no hikae.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>柔帽子、堅帽子の別なく見られる造りの一種で、堅帽子では手首の固めが無い事から親指の動きが比較的自由になる為、“弓道射法八節”に於いて弦の運行を親指が邪魔し難いとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The making is a kind of the ones seen irrespective of yawarakaboshi or kataboshi and kataboshi has no wrist fixation, which makes the movement of a thumb relatively free, and the thumb tends to interfere with the movement of a string in &quot;kyudo-shaho hassetsu.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The structure is a kind which is seen irrespective of yawarakaboshi or kataboshi, and kataboshi has no wrist reinforcment, which makes the movement of a thumb relatively free, and the thumb unlikely interfere with the movement of a string in &quot;Kyudo-shaho hassetsu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>of the ones を削除しました。カンマを挿入しました。making→structure,fixation→reinforcment,tends to→unlikely,kyudo→Kyudo と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The structure is a kind which is seen irrespective of yawarakaboshi or kataboshi, and kataboshi has no wrist reinforcment, which makes the movement of a thumb relatively free, and the thumb unlikely interfere with the movement of a string in &quot;Kyudo-shaho hassetsu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="60">
<j>種類別</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Classification by category</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Classification by category</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Classification by category</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>三ツ弽（みつがけ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitsugake (a three-fingered glove)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitsugake (a three-fingered glove)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitsugake (a three-fingered glove)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>親指、人差し指、中指の三指を覆う形状。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has a form which covers a thumb, a forefinger and a middle finger.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has a form which covers thumb, forefinger and middle finger.</e>
<cmt>a を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has a form which covers thumb, forefinger and middle finger.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>「三ツガケ」と言えば堅帽子で控え付きのものを指し、初心者はまず三ツガケをあてがわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Mitsugake&quot; refers to kataboshi with a hikae and the beginner uses mitsugake at first.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitsugake&apos; refers to kataboshi with a hikae and a beginner uses mitsugake at first.</e>
<cmt>クォーツを修正しました。the→a と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitsugake&apos; refers to kataboshi with a hikae and a beginner uses mitsugake at first.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>初心者〜中級者まで広く一般的に使われ、最も使用者数が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Generally it is widely used by beginners to intermediate grade people and the number of the users is the largest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is generally used widely by beginners to intermediate level people, and the number of the users of this is the largest.</e>
<cmt>文脈に応じて修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is generally used widely by beginners to intermediate level people, and the number of the users of this is the largest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>帽子に固めの角が入っておらず、控えが無いものを「柔帽子」或は「和帽子」、帽子の背の部分を刳り抜いてあるものを「節抜き」と呼び、区別している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Boshi has no tsuno for fixation and the one without a hikae is called &quot;yawarakaboshi&quot; or &quot;waboshi&quot; and the one where the back of a boshi is hollowed out is called &quot;fushinuki&quot; for differentiation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Boshi has no tsuno inside to be reinforced, and the one without hikae is called &apos;yawarakaboshi&apos; or &apos;waboshi&apos;, and the one where the back of the boshi is hollowed out is called &apos;fushinuki&apos; to distinguish.</e>
<cmt>カンマを挿入、クォーツを修正、文脈より修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Boshi has no tsuno inside to be reinforced, and the one without hikae is called &apos;yawarakaboshi&apos; or &apos;waboshi&apos;, and the one where the back of the boshi is hollowed out is called &apos;fushinuki&apos; to distinguish.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="66">
<j>四ツ弽（よつがけ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yotsugake (a four-fingered glove)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yotsugake (a four-fingered glove)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yotsugake (a four-fingered glove)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>親指、人差し指、中指、薬指の四指を覆う形状。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has a form which covers a thumb, a forefinger, a middle finger and an annular finger.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has a form which covers thumb, forefinger, middle finger and annular finger.</e>
<cmt>a, an を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has a form which covers thumb, forefinger, middle finger and annular finger.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>「四ツガケ」と言えば堅帽子で控え付きのものを指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Yotsugake&quot; refers to kataboshi with a hikae.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yotsugake&apos; refers to kataboshi with a hikae.</e>
<cmt>クォーツを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yotsugake&apos; refers to kataboshi with a hikae.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>薬指から親指に掛ける為、三ツガケより取り掛け（弦の保持）が楽であるとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A string is hooked by an annular finger, a middle finger, a forefinger and a thumb and thus to hold a string is easier than that of mitsugake.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered that torikake (nocking on with the right hand) is easier than mitsugake since a string is hooked by the annular finger, the middle finger, the forefinger and the thumb.</e>
<cmt>”取り掛け”部分を補い、文脈よりオーダー等を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered that torikake (nocking on with the right hand) is easier than mitsugake since a string is hooked by the annular finger, the middle finger, the forefinger and the thumb.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>上級者の間で広く使われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is widely used among those who are in the advanced-level.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is widely used among those who are in advanced-level.</e>
<cmt>the を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is widely used among those who are in advanced-level.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="71">
<j>竹林弽（ちくりんがけ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chikuringake</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chikuringake</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chikuringake</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>日置流竹林派（ちくりんは）独自のユガケ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A unique yugake of Heki-ryu Chikurin-ha school (of Kyudo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A unique yugake of Heki-ryu Chikurin-ha school (of Kyudo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A unique yugake of Heki-ryu Chikurin-ha school (of Kyudo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>三ツガケ、節抜きの堅帽子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a mitsugake and kataboshi of fushinuki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a mitsugake and kataboshi of fushinuki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a mitsugake and kataboshi of fushinuki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>親指先、中指の腹の取り掛けの際に接触する部分に当て皮革がされており、全体的に独特な作りとなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The tip of a thumb and ball of a middle finger which a string touches are covered with a hide and wholly it has a unique making.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The tip of a thumb and ball of a middle finger which a string touches are patched with a leather, and it is a unique making overall.</e>
<cmt>covered with a hide→patched with a leather,wholly it has a unique making→it is a unique making overall と修正しました。カンマを挿入しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The tip of a thumb and ball of a middle finger which a string touches are patched with a leather, and it is a unique making overall.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="75">
<j>柔らかく作られている為、“弓道射法八節”に於ける帽子の働きを助ける為に「小紐」を一回り親指に絡めてカケ紐を締める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As it has a soft making, &quot;kohimo&quot; (a thin strap) is put around a thumb and the strap is tightened to assist the movement of a boshi in &quot;kyudo-shaho hassetsu.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As it is made soft, &apos;kohimo&apos; (a thin strap) is put around a thumb and the strap is tightened to assist the movement of a boshi in &quot;Kyudo-shaho hassetsu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>it has a soft making→it is made soft,クォーツを修正しました。kyudo→Kyudo と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As it is made soft, &apos;kohimo&apos; (a thin strap) is put around a thumb and the strap is tightened to assist the movement of a boshi in &quot;Kyudo-shaho hassetsu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="76">
<j>諸弽（もろがけ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Morogake</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Morogake</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Morogake</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>五本全指を覆う形状。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has a form which covers all the five fingers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has a form which covers all five fingers.</e>
<cmt>the を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has a form which covers all five fingers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>堅帽子、控え無し。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kataboshi without a hikae</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kataboshi without hikae.</e>
<cmt>a hikae→hikae,ピリオドを挿入しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kataboshi without hikae.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>取り掛け方は、使用者によって変わる（元々三つを使用していた場合は三つの取り掛け、四つを使用していた場合は四つの取り掛けをし、当然、前者と後者で帽子の角度や長さも違う。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The way of setting a string depends on the users (those who have originally used three fingers use a mitsugke and those who have originally used four fingers use a yotsugake.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The way of setting a string depends on the users (those who have originally used three fingers use a mitsugke and those who have originally used four fingers use a yotsugake, naturally, the former and the latter are different in the angle and length of a boshi).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処カッコの場所を修正と同時にセルで分けられていた原文を合わせました。ピリオドの場所を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The way of setting a string depends on the users (those who have originally used three fingers use a mitsugke and those who have originally used four fingers use a yotsugake, naturally, the former and the latter are different in the angle and length of a boshi).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>小笠原流の免許ユガケ『紫二本継指』が有名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The yugake &quot;Murasaki nihon tsugiyubi&quot; which Ogasawara School licensed is famous.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The yugake &quot;Murasaki nihon tsugiyubi&quot; which Ogasawara School licensed is famous.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The yugake &quot;Murasaki nihon tsugiyubi&quot; which Ogasawara School licensed is famous.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>一部上段者が使用している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some of those who are in the advanced-level use it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some of those who are in advanced-level use it.</e>
<cmt>theを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some of those who are in advanced-level use it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="82">
<j>控えが固められていない為、“弓道射法八節”に於ける帽子の働きを助ける為に「小紐」を一回り親指に絡めてカケ紐を締める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a hikae is not fixed, &quot;kohimo&quot; is put around a thumb and the strap is tightened to assist the movement of a boshi in &quot;kyudo-shaho hassetsu.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since hikae is not reinforced, &apos;kohimo&apos; is twined around thumb once and tighten kake himo (a leather strap for securing a yugake) to assist the movement of boshi in &quot;Kyudo-shaho hassetsu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>As→Since,fixed→reinforced, a を削除しました。クォーツを修正しました。”「小紐」を一回り親指に絡めてカケ紐を締める”という部分を補い修正しました。kyudo→Kyudo と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since hikae is not reinforced, &apos;kohimo&apos; is twined around thumb once and tighten kake himo (a leather strap for securing a yugake) to assist the movement of boshi in &quot;Kyudo-shaho hassetsu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="83">
<j>騎射弽（きしゃがけ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kishagake</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kishagake</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kishagake</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>両手全指を覆う形状。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has a form which covers a whole hand and fingers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has a form which covers a whole hand and fingers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has a form which covers a whole hand and fingers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>造りは右手親指根に当て革がされているだけであり、革手袋と言った方がイメージが近い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has the making where the base of a right hand thumb is attached only with a hide and looks like a leather glove.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is only a small leather pad on the base of thumb as its structure, it looks more likely a leather glove.</e>
<cmt>文脈より修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is only a small leather pad on the base of thumb as its structure, it looks more likely a leather glove.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>「騎射」の名の通り流鏑馬で使われ、手綱を取る為に親指、手首共に固めが入っていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the name &quot;kisha&quot; (to shoot an arrow with riding a horse) suggests, it is used in yabusame (horseback archery) and a thumb and a wrist are not fixed because of holding the reins.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the name &apos;kisha&apos; (to shoot an arrow with riding a horse) suggests, it is used in yabusame (horseback archery) and a thumb and a wrist are not reinforced because of holding the reins.</e>
<cmt>クォーツを修正しました。fixed→reinforcedと修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the name &apos;kisha&apos; (to shoot an arrow with riding a horse) suggests, it is used in yabusame (horseback archery) and a thumb and a wrist are not reinforced because of holding the reins.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>中世に武士が使用していたものとほぼ同型。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The yugakes used by samurais in medieval times were almost the same type.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The yugake used by samurais in medieval times were almost the same type.</e>
<cmt>yugakes→yugake と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The yugake used by samurais in medieval times were almost the same type.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>戦時は弓の落下を防ぐ為に左手に薬練を引いて弓と手を半接着していたが、この事が『手ぐすねを引いて待つ』という言葉の語源になっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To avoid the fall of a bow in wartime, the bow and hand are loosely bonded by kusune (pine resin), which is the word origin of &quot;tegusune wo hiite matsu&quot; (to wait in a ready state).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To avoid dropping a bow in wartime, the bow and hand were loosely bonded by kusune (pine resin), which is the word originated &quot;tegusune wo hiite matsu&quot; (to wait in a ready state).</e>
<cmt>the fall of a bow→dropping a bow, are→were,origin of→originated と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To avoid dropping a bow in wartime, the bow and hand were loosely bonded by kusune (pine resin), which is the word originated &quot;tegusune wo hiite matsu&quot; (to wait in a ready state).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="25">
<sen id="89">
<j>押し手弽（おしてがけ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oshiteyugake (a yugake glove for the left hand)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oshitegake (a yugake glove for the left hand)</e>
<cmt>Oshiteyugake→Oshitegake と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oshitegake (a yugake glove for the left hand)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>左手に挿すユガケ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yugake for a left hand.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yugake for left hand.</e>
<cmt>a を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yugake for left hand.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>親指のみ覆うもの、人差し指・親指を覆うもの、手首まで覆うもの、形状は様々ある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has various types such as the one covering only a thumb, the one covering a forefinger and a thumb, the one covering a whole hand and a wrist and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are various types such as the one covering only a thumb, the one covering a forefinger and a thumb, the one covering a whole hand and a wrist and so on.</e>
<cmt>It has→There are</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are various types such as the one covering only a thumb, the one covering a forefinger and a thumb, the one covering a whole hand and a wrist and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>主に左手を保護する為のもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The yugake for the purpose of mainly protecting a left hand</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The main purpose of this is to protect the left hand,</e>
<cmt>a →the,ピリオドを挿入しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The main purpose of this is to protect the left hand,</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>感覚に合わなければ使用する必要もなく使用者は多く無い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those who do not like the feel do not need to use it and the number of users is not large.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is not necessary to wear it if the feeling is not right for the user, so the number of the user is not big.</e>
<cmt>文の流れをスムースに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is not necessary to wear it if the feeling is not right for the user, so the number of the user is not big.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="26">
<sen id="94">
<j>各部名称</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Part names</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Names of parts</e>
<cmt>Part names→Names of parts と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Names of parts</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>帽子（ぼうし）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Boshi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Boshi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Boshi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>親指先から親指根にあたる5cm前後の部分。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is the part from the tip to the base of a thumb, which is about five centimeters long.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is the part from the tip to the base of the thumb, which is about 5cm long.</e>
<cmt>a→the,five centimeters→5cm と修正しました。（一桁の数字ではありますがcmと合わせて）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is the part from the tip to the base of the thumb, which is about 5cm long.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>弦を掛け、弦の圧力を受ける部分で、帽子の取り付け角度、太さ、形状等、行射の善し悪しに関わる重要な部位である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is an important part because it sets a string and is under pressure from a string and relates with the good or ill of shooting such as the angle at which the boshi is set, the thickness, the form and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is an important part because it sets a string and receives pressure from the string, and affects the good or ill of shooting such as the angle at which the boshi is set, the thickness, the form and so on.</e>
<cmt>is under pressure→receives, relates with→affects と修正しました。カンマを挿入しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is an important part because it sets a string and receives pressure from the string, and affects the good or ill of shooting such as the angle at which the boshi is set, the thickness, the form and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="27">
<sen id="98">
<j>角（つの）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsuno</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsuno</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsuno</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>弦からの圧力から親指を保護する目的で帽子部分に入れられる木、或は水牛等の角を指筒状に刳り貫いた芯材。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a thimble-like wood or horn of water buffalo and so on, which is hollowed out and set in the boshi part to protect a thumb from the pressure of a string.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a thimble-like wood or horn of water buffalo and so on, which is hollowed out and set in the boshi part to protect the thumb from the pressure of the string.</e>
<cmt>a thumb→the thumb,a string→the string と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a thimble-like wood or horn of water buffalo and so on, which is hollowed out and set in the boshi part to protect the thumb from the pressure of the string.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>現在では入手、加工が容易な木材を使用したものが主流。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Currently, wooden materials have become mainstream because they are easy to get and process.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Currently, wooden materials which are easy to get and process have become mainstream.</e>
<cmt>オーダーを変更して流れを良くしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Currently, wooden materials which are easy to get and process have become mainstream.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>親指先から親指根辺りまで親指全体を覆う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It covers a whole thumb which is from the tip to the base of a thumb.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It covers a whole thumb which is from the tip to the base of a thumb.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It covers a whole thumb which is from the tip to the base of a thumb.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>角が入れられた造りのユガケ、或は帽子を「堅帽子」、角が入れられていないユガケ、或は帽子を「柔帽子」と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The yugake which has a tsuno or boshi are called &quot;kataboshi&quot; and the yugake which does not have a tsuno or boshi are called &quot;yawarakaboshi.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The yugake which has tsuno inside or boshi are called &apos;kataboshi,&apos; and the yugake which does not have tsuno inside or boshi are called &apos;yawarakaboshi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーツを修正しました。カンマを挿入しました。a tsuno→tsuno inside,</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The yugake which has tsuno inside or boshi are called &apos;kataboshi,&apos; and the yugake which does not have tsuno inside or boshi are called &apos;yawarakaboshi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="28">
<sen id="103">
<j>腰・二の腰（こし・にのこし）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koshi, ninokoshi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koshi, ninokoshi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koshi, ninokoshi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>帽子と控えを繋ぐ部分。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The part which connects a boshi with a hikae.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The part which connects boshi with hikae.</e>
<cmt>a を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The part which connects boshi with hikae.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>堅帽子は牛革が二枚程度重ねられたものが入れられ、固められている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kataboshi is fixed by inserting about two sheets of cowhide.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kataboshi is reinforced by inserting about two sheets of cowhide.</e>
<cmt>fixed→reinforced と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kataboshi is reinforced by inserting about two sheets of cowhide.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>外見上は帽子から腰まで１つに繋がった膨らみを持っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It looks like a ball-like figure from a boshi to a koshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has a round shape appearance which all connects from boshi to koshi.</e>
<cmt>文脈に応じて修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has a round shape appearance which all connects from boshi to koshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>この膨らみや硬さ如何によって、“弓道射法八節”への影響のが変わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This ball-like figure or the hardness differently influence &quot;kyudo-shaho hassetsu.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It changes the effect to &quot;Kyudo-shaho hassetsu&quot; by the differences of its shape and stiffness.</e>
<cmt>文脈に応じて修正しました。kyudo→Kyudo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It changes the effect to &quot;Kyudo-shaho hassetsu&quot; by the differences of its shape and stiffness.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>尚、竹林弽は堅帽子であるが、節抜き構造によって二の腰が無い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And a chikuringake is a boshi, but it does not have a ninokoshi because of the fushinuki structure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And, although chikuringake is kataboshi, it does not have ninokoshi because of the fushinuki structure.</e>
<cmt>カンマを挿入、but→although,boshi→kataboshi,a を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And, although chikuringake is kataboshi, it does not have ninokoshi because of the fushinuki structure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="29">
<sen id="109">
<j>控え・一の腰（ひかえ・いちのこし）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hikae, ichinokoshi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hikae, ichinokoshi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hikae, ichinokoshi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>腰を囲うように親指根から手首、ユガケの下端まで橈骨側を覆う部分。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The part which surrounds a koshi and covers the base of a thumb to a wrist and covers the lower end of a yugake, which is the radius side.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The part which surrounds koshi and covers the base of the thumb to the wrist and covers the lower end of yugake, which is the radius side.</e>
<cmt>a, the を削除、修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The part which surrounds koshi and covers the base of the thumb to the wrist and covers the lower end of yugake, which is the radius side.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>控え付きはここに牛革が入れられ固められている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the case of the yugake with a hikae, here is fixed by inserting sheets of cowhide.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For the yugake with hikae, a piece of cowhide is inserted to reinforce in this part.</e>
<cmt>In the case of→For,a hikae→hikae,後半部分を文脈より修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For the yugake with hikae, a piece of cowhide is inserted to reinforce in this part.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>やはり控えの形状や硬さ如何によって弓道射法八節への影響のが変わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As before, the figure or hardness of a hikae differently influence the kyudo-shaho hassetsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, the figure or hardness of a hikae differently influence the Kyudo-shaho hassetsu.</e>
<cmt>As before→Also,kyudo→Kyudo と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, the figure or hardness of a hikae differently influence the Kyudo-shaho hassetsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="30">
<sen id="113">
<j>弦枕（つるまくら）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsurumakura</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsurumakura</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsurumakura</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="114">
<j>弦が掛かる部分で、弦から掛かる弓力を直に受ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The part is where a string is set and is under direct pressure from a string.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The part where a string is set and receives direct pressure from a string.</e>
<cmt>is を削除しました。is under→receives と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The part where a string is set and receives direct pressure from a string.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>堅帽子は弦を掛ける段差を付ける為に親指の爪大程の牛革が入れられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kataboshi has a thumbnail cowhide for a bump where a string is set.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kataboshi has a thumbnail sized cowhide inside to make a bump where a string is set.</e>
<cmt>thumbnail cowhide→thumbnail sized cowhide inside,for→to make と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kataboshi has a thumbnail sized cowhide inside to make a bump where a string is set.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="116">
<j>弦の滑りを良くする為に蝋や薬練が塗られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wax or kusune are put on here in order for a string to slip smoothly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wax or kusune are put on here in order to the string to slide smoothly.</e>
<cmt>for a→to the,slip→slide と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wax or kusune are put on here in order to the string to slide smoothly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="117">
<j>弦枕の形状、位置、角度、段差の高低が極めて重要で、形が悪いとまともに弓が引けない、矢が飛ばない等の弊害が出る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The form, position, angle and a bump&apos;s height in tsurumakura is very important and if the form is not good the problems happen, for example, a bow cannot be drawn properly or an arrow cannot fly and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The form, position, angle and the bump&apos;s height in tsurumakura are very important, and if the form is not good, the problems happen, for example, a bow cannot be drawn properly or an arrow cannot fly and so on.</e>
<cmt>a→the,is→are,カンマを挿入しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The form, position, angle and the bump&apos;s height in tsurumakura are very important, and if the form is not good, the problems happen, for example, a bow cannot be drawn properly or an arrow cannot fly and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="118">
<j>流派や射法、射手の志向によって正しい位置・形は一定ではなく、その形状や位置によって、十文字、筋交い、浅ガケ、深ガケ等数種類ある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The right position and form vary depending on the school, the ways of shooting and the intention of the shooters, and depending on the form and position there are several kinds of gloves such as the glove whose shape is a cross, the oblique glove, the asagake shooting glove, the fukageke shooting glove and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The right position and form vary according to the school, the ways of shooting and the intention of the shooters, and depending on the form and position, there are several kinds of gloves such as the glove whose shape is a cross, the oblique glove, the asagake shooting glove, the fukageke shooting glove and so on.</e>
<cmt>depending on→according to と修正しました。カンマを挿入しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The right position and form vary according to the school, the ways of shooting and the intention of the shooters, and depending on the form and position, there are several kinds of gloves such as the glove whose shape is a cross, the oblique glove, the asagake shooting glove, the fukageke shooting glove and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="31">
<sen id="119">
<j>弦溝（つるみぞ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsurumizo (a groove of a yugake glove to set a string)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsurumizo (a groove of a yugake glove to set a string)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsurumizo (a groove of a yugake glove to set a string)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="120">
<j>弦枕の内、段差の下、弦が乗る部分。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a part which is inside of tsurumakura, under a bump and the part where a string is set.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a part which is inside of tsurumakura, under a bump and the part where a string is set.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a part which is inside of tsurumakura, under a bump and the part where a string is set.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="32">
<sen id="121">
<j>胴（どう）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Do</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Do</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Do</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="122">
<j>手首から手の甲まで繋がる部分。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The part which links a wrist and a top of hand.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The part which is from the wrist to the top of hand.</e>
<cmt>links→connects,a→the と修正しました。links→is from,（”繋がっている部分”と理解して修正しています）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The part which is from the wrist to the top of hand.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="123">
<j>鹿革一枚からなり、手首部分は手首に巻けるよう巻きしろが取られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It consists of a sheet of deerskin and the wrist part has a margin for winding.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It consists of a sheet of deerskin and the wrist part has a margin for wrapping the wrist.</e>
<cmt>winding→wrapping the wrist と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It consists of a sheet of deerskin and the wrist part has a margin for wrapping the wrist.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="124">
<j>三ツガケ、四ツガケは人差し指、中指まで一枚に繋がった裁断がされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the case of a mitsugake and a yotsugake, one sheet of deerskin covers from a forefinger to a middle finger.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For mitsugake and yotsugake, one sheet of deerskin covers from the forefinger to the middle finger.</e>
<cmt>In the case of→For,a, the を削除、修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For mitsugake and yotsugake, one sheet of deerskin covers from the forefinger to the middle finger.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="33">
<sen id="125">
<j>小紐（こひも）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kohimo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kohimo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kohimo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="126">
<j>控え部分から付けられ紐を結び付ける鹿革製の細い帯状の紐。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a belt-like lace made from a deerskin, which links a hikae and the other lace.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a thin belt-like strap made from a deerskin, which is attached to hikae and tied to himo.</e>
<cmt>thin belt と修正、lace→strap,後半部分を文脈より修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a thin belt-like strap made from a deerskin, which is attached to hikae and tied to himo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="127">
<j>竹林ガケや諸ガケ等は小紐を親指に絡めるため長目に造られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chikuringake, morogake and so on are made to be a bit long for linking a kohimo and a thumb.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chikuringake, morogake and so on are made longer for kohimo to twine the thumb.</e>
<cmt>to be a bit long→longer,linking a kohimo and a thumb→kohimo to twine the thumb と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chikuringake, morogake and so on are made longer for kohimo to twine the thumb.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="34">
<sen id="128">
<j>紐・緒（ひも・お）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Himo, o</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Himo, o</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Himo, o</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="129">
<j>ユガケを手首部分で巻き止める帯状のもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a belt-like thing which fixes a yugake at the wrist part.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a belt-like thing which ties a yugake at the wrist part.</e>
<cmt>fixes→ties と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a belt-like thing which ties a yugake at the wrist part.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="130">
<j>胴、小紐、紐の順で巻かれ、手の甲側、或は内側で結び止める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The laces are wound in the order of do, kohimo and himo, and tied up at the top of hand or inside of hand.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The himo is wound in the order of do, kohimo and himo, and tied up at the top of hand or inside of hand.</e>
<cmt>laces are→himo is と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The himo is wound in the order of do, kohimo and himo, and tied up at the top of hand or inside of hand.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="131">
<j>ユガケの中で唯一交換可能な部分。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the parts of a yugake, it is the only one which is interchangeable.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the parts of a yugake, it is the only one which is interchangeable.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the parts of a yugake, it is the only one which is interchangeable.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="132">
<j>ユガケと同色か紫に染められた紐が一般的。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Generally a himo is dyed in the same color as a yugake or purple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Generally a himo is dyed in the same color as a yugake or purple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Generally a himo is dyed in the same color as a yugake or purple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 こんせ(id:262022), 銀色しっぽ(id:197919), アセルス(id:87426), Ｔ／Ｙ(id:24368), 福太郎(id:132415), Kumatora(id:16941), Point136(id:211299), Uraios(id:72687), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>