<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>栃餅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tochi mochi (conker rice cake)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tochi mochi (conker rice cake)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tochi mochi (conker rice cake)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>栃餅（とちもち）は、灰汁灰汁抜きした栃の実（トチノキの実）をもち米とともに蒸してからつき、餅にしたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tochi mochi is a rice cake made by steaming conker after removal of harshness with glutinous rice and then pounding them.</e>
<cmt>原文は「灰汁灰汁抜き」と「灰汁」が重複していますが、「灰汁」と１つのみ訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tochi mochi is a rice cake made by steaming conkers after removal of harshness with glutinous rice and then pounding them.</e>
<cmt>conkers としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tochi mochi is a rice cake made by steaming conkers after removal of harshness with glutinous rice and then pounding them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>もち米だけの餅よりも黄土色や茶色がかっており、独特の苦味がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tochi mochi has tinges of yellow ocher and brown comparing to a rice cake made from only glutinous rice, and has unique bitterness.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tochi mochi has tinges of yellow ocher and brown compared to a rice cake made from only glutinous rice, and has unique bitterness.</e>
<cmt>compared to としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tochi mochi has tinges of yellow ocher and brown compared to a rice cake made from only glutinous rice, and has unique bitterness.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>かつては米がほとんど取れない山村では重要な食糧であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tochi mochi was important foodstuffs once in the mountain village where rice is hardly grown. It has been sold as one of the souvenirs as of the beginning in the 21st century.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tochi mochi was important foodstuffs once in the mountain village where rice is hardly grown.</e>
<cmt>文章を一文削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tochi mochi was important foodstuffs once in the mountain village where rice is hardly grown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>21世紀初頭現在では土産物の1つとしても売られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has been sold as one of the souvenirs as of the beginning in the 21st century.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has been sold as one of the souvenirs as of the beginning of the 21st century.</e>
<cmt>in→ of としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has been sold as one of the souvenirs as of the beginning of the 21st century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>砂糖を付ける、餡に絡めるあるいは包む、塩茶漬けにするなどして食べる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tochi mochi is eaten with sugar, by dressing or wrapping it with beam jam, or with salt, soaked in tea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tochi mochi is eaten with sugar, by dressing or wrapping it with bean jam, or with salt which is soaked in tea.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tochi mochi is eaten with sugar, by dressing or wrapping it with bean jam, or with salt which is soaked in tea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>栃の実の灰汁抜きは手間と時間が掛かり、また各地方・家庭で受け継がれているコツなどもあるため、未経験者にはやや難しい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Removal of harshness from conker is a little difficult for inexperienced persons, since it requires time and effort to remove harshness, and each district and home has its skills inherited.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since it requires time and effort and also each district and home has its skills inherited, removal of harshness from conkers is a little difficult for inexperienced persons.</e>
<cmt>語順を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since it requires time and effort and also each district and home has its skills inherited, removal of harshness from conkers is a little difficult for inexperienced persons.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>そのためあらかじめ灰汁抜きされた栃の実も販売されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, the conker has been sold from which harshness is removed in advance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, conkers are sold from which harshness is removed in advance.</e>
<cmt>conkers としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, conkers are sold from which harshness is removed in advance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Balmung0731-AWB(id:223943), Sheepech(id:111676), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>