<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>文化財</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>文化財（ぶんかざい）は次のとおりである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Cultural Properties&quot; means,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The meaning of &quot;cultural properties&quot;</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The meanings of &quot;cultural properties&quot; are as follows:</e>
<cmt>原文を変更しました。「文化財は」→「文化財は次のとおりである」</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>広義では、人類の文化的活動によって生み出された有形・無形の文化的所産のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">in the broad sense, any tangible or intangible cultural products invented by the human beings&apos; cultural activities.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the broad sense, it refers to any tangible or intangible cultural product invented through human cultural activity.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the broad sense, it refers to any tangible or intangible cultural product invented through human cultural activity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>「文化遺産」とほぼ同義である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is almost synonymous with the terms &quot;Cultural Heritages&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is basically synonymous with the term &quot;cultural heritage.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is basically synonymous with the term &quot;cultural heritage.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>詳細は文化遺産を参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Please refer to &quot;cultural heritages&quot; for details.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Please refer to the section &quot;Cultural Heritages&quot; for details.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Please refer to the section &quot;Cultural Heritages&quot; for details.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>武力紛争の際の文化財の保護に関する条約、文化財不法輸出入等禁止条約、文化財の不法な輸出入等の規制等に関する法律などの条約および法令において規定されている「文化財」のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">“Cultural properties” as stated in treaties or ordinances such as agreements concerning protection of cultural properties at armed conflict, prohibition agreements on illegal import or export of cultural properties, and restrictions on illegal import or export of cultural properties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Cultural properties&quot; as stated in treaties or ordinances such as agreements concerning protection of cultural properties at armed conflict, prohibition agreements on illegal import or export of cultural properties, and restrictions on illegal import or export of cultural properties.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Cultural properties&quot; as stated in treaties or ordinances such as agreements concerning protection of cultural properties at armed conflict, prohibition agreements on illegal import or export of cultural properties, and restrictions on illegal import or export of cultural properties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>詳細は文化遺産保護制度を参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Please refer to the System for the Protection of Cultural Heritages</e>
<cmt>文化遺産保護制度→System for the Protection of Cultural Heritages</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Please refer to &quot;System for the Protection of Cultural Heritages.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Please refer to &quot;System for the Protection of Cultural Heritages.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>日本の文化財保護法第2条および文化財保護条例において規定されている「文化財」のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">“Cultural properties” as stated in Ordinance 2 of the Law for Protection of Cultural Properties and the Ordinance for Protection of Cultural Properties of Japan.</e>
<cmt>文化財保護条例→Ordinance for the Protection of Cultural Properties</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Cultural properties,&quot; are defined in Ordinance 2 of the Law for Protection of Cultural Properties and the Ordinance for the Protection of Cultural Properties of Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Cultural properties,&quot; are defined in Article 2 of the Law for Protection of Cultural Properties and the Ordinance for the Protection of Cultural Properties of Japan.</e>
<cmt>第2条は「Article」のほうがよいと判断しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="8">
<j>本項では3について詳述する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Point 3 is explained in details in this Article.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This article explains point 3 in detail.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This section explains point 3 in detail.</e>
<cmt>article →sectionに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Outline</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Outline</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>統一用語</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="9">
<j>文化財保護法第2条第1項は「文化財」について次の通り規定している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under the Law for Protection of Cultural Properties Ordinance 2 Clause 1, &quot;Cultural properties&quot; are specified as follows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the Law for the Protection of Cultural Properties, Ordinance 2, Clause 1, cultural properties are defined as follows:</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the Law for the Protection of Cultural Properties, Article 2, Clause 1, cultural properties are defined as follows:</e>
<cmt>第2条は「Article」のほうがよいと判断しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>この法律で「文化財」とは、次に掲げるものをいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This law specifies that a so-called &quot;cultural property&quot; should belong to one of the categories listed below.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This law specifies that a so-called &quot;cultural property&quot; should belong to one of the categories listed below:</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This law specifies that a so-called &quot;cultural property&quot; should belong to one of the categories listed below:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>一　建造物、絵画、彫刻、工芸品、書跡、典籍、古文書その他の有形の文化的所産で我が国にとつて歴史上又は芸術上価値の高いもの（これらのものと一体をなしてその価値を形成している土地その他の物件を含む。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1. Tangible items (such as buildings, paintings, sculptures, crafts, calligraphies, literatures, ancient documents, and other tangible cultural products) which are high-valued historical or artistically in our nation. (And that includes all the auxiliary parts or land attached for its value)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1. Tangible items (such as buildings, paintings, sculptures, crafts, calligraphies, literatures, ancient documents and other tangible cultural products) that are highly valued in our nation, either historically or artistically (including all the auxiliary parts or land attached to such value)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1. Tangible items (such as buildings, paintings, sculptures, crafts, calligraphies, literatures, ancient documents and other tangible cultural products) that are highly valued in our nation, either historically or artistically (including all the auxiliary parts or land attached to such value)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>並びに考古資料及びその他の学術上価値の高い歴史資料（以下「有形文化財」という。)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">High-valued archaeological resources or historical resources (hereafter referred as “tangible cultural properties”).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Highly valued archaeological resources or historical resources (hereinafter referred to as &apos;tangible cultural properties&apos;)</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Highly valued archaeological resources or historical resources (hereinafter referred to as &apos;tangible cultural properties&apos;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>二　演劇、音楽、工芸技術その他の無形の文化的所産で我が国にとつて歴史上又は芸術上価値の高いもの（以下「無形文化財」という。)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">2. Intangible cultural products (such as plays, music pieces, and craft technologies) which are high-valued historical or artistically in our nation. (These products are hereafter referred as “intangible cultural properties”)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">2. Intangible cultural products (such as plays, musical pieces and craft technologies) that are highly valued in our nation, either historically or artistically (such products being hereinafter referred as intangible cultural properties)</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">2. Intangible cultural products (such as plays, musical pieces and craft technologies) that are highly valued in our nation, either historically or artistically (such products being hereinafter referred as intangible cultural properties)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="14">
<j>三　衣食住、生業、信仰、年中行事等に関する風俗慣習、民俗芸能、民俗技術及びこれらに用いられる衣服、器具、家屋その他の物件で我が国民の生活の推移の理解のため欠くことのできないもの（以下「民俗文化財」という。)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">3. The indispensables in order for our nationals to appreciate the flowing of life (such as foods, clothing, housings, industries or livelihoods, beliefs, folk customs about festivals, public entertainments, and traditional skills with the associated costumes, tools, stages). (These indispensables are hereafter referred as “folk cultural properties”)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">3. The indispensables in order for our nationals to appreciate the flow of life (such as food, clothing, housings, industry or livelihood, beliefs, folk customs about festivals, public entertainments, and traditional skills with the associated costumes, tools and stages) (such indispensables being hereinafter referred to as folk cultural properties)</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">3. The indispensables in order for our nationals to appreciate the flow of life (such as food, clothing, housings, industry or livelihood, beliefs, folk customs about festivals, public entertainments, and traditional skills with the associated costumes, tools and stages) (such indispensables being hereinafter referred to as folk cultural properties)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="15">
<j>四　貝づか、古墳、都城跡、城跡、旧宅その他の遺跡で我が国にとつて歴史上又は学術上価値の高いもの、庭園、橋梁、峡谷、海浜、山岳その他の名勝地で我が国にとつて芸術上又は観賞上価値の高いもの並びに動物（生息地、繁殖地及び渡来地を含む。）、植物（自生地を含む。）及び地質鉱物（特異な自然の現象の生じている土地を含む。）で我が国にとつて学術上価値の高いもの（以下「記念物」という。)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">4. Buildings and constructions (such as shell mounds, ancient tombs, citadel style castle sites, castle sites, and old residences) which are high-valued historical or academically in our nation, landscapes (such as gardens, bridges, canyons, coasts, mountains and other places of scenic beauty) which are high-valued artistically or visually in our nation, animals (including their habitats, their breeding areas, and their origins), plants (including their habitats), and geological minerals (including the landscapes produced by natural phenomena) which are high-valued academically in our nation (These natural features are hereafter referred as “monuments”.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">4. Buildings and structures (such as shell mounds, ancient tombs, citadel-type castle sites, castle sites and old residences) which are highly valued in our nation, either historically or academically; landscapes (such as gardens, bridges, canyons, coasts, mountains and other places of scenic beauty) that are highly valued in our nation for their artistic or visual merit; animals (including their habitats, their breeding areas, and their origins), plants (including their habitats), and geological minerals (including the landscapes produced by natural phenomena) that are highly valued academically in our nation (such natural features being hereinafter referred to as &apos;monuments&apos;.)</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">4. Buildings and structures (such as shell mounds, ancient tombs, citadel-type castle sites, castle sites and old residences) which are highly valued in our nation, either historically or academically; landscapes (such as gardens, bridges, canyons, coasts, mountains and other places of scenic beauty) that are highly valued in our nation for their artistic or visual merit; animals (including their habitats, their breeding areas, and their stopovers), plants (including their habitats), and geological minerals (including the landscapes produced by natural phenomena) that are highly valued academically in our nation (such natural features being hereinafter referred to as &apos;monuments&apos;)</e>
<cmt>「渡来地」は「stopovers」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="16">
<j>五　地域における人々の生活又は生業及び当該地域の風土により形成された景観地で我が国民の生活又は生業の理解のため欠くことのできないもの（以下「文化的景観」という。)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">5. The indispensables in order for our nationals to appreciate the livings or livelihoods of a local region (such as the sceneries formed by the customs of that region that reflect the locals’ lives and livelihoods). (These indispensables are hereafter referred as “cultural sceneries”.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">5. The indispensables in order for our nationals to appreciate the life and livelihood of a local region (such as the scenes formed by the customs of the region that reflects the locals’ lives and livelihoods) (such indispensables being hereinafter referred to as cultural scenes&quot;)</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">5. The indispensables in order for our nationals to appreciate the life and livelihood of a local region (such as the scenes formed by the customs of the region that reflects the locals’ lives and livelihoods) (such indispensables being hereinafter referred to as cultural landscapes&quot;)</e>
<cmt>cultural scene→cultural landscape</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="17">
<j>六　周囲の環境と一体をなして歴史的風致を形成している伝統的な建造物群で価値の高いもの（以下「伝統的建造物群」という。)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">6. High-valued traditional architectures (hereafter referred as “classic architectures”) that merge harmoniously with the surrounding environment forming a historical scenic beauty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">6. Highly valued traditional architecture (hereinafter referred to as &quot;classic architecture&quot;) that merges harmoniously with the surrounding environment to represent historical scenic beauty</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">6. Highly valued traditional architecture (hereinafter referred to as &quot;classic architecture&quot;) that merges harmoniously with the surrounding environment to represent historical scenic beauty</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="18">
<j>すなわち、歴史上、芸術上、学術上、観賞上等の観点から価値の高い有形文化財、無形文化財、民俗文化財、記念物、文化的景観、伝統的建造物群の6種類が、指定等の有無にかかわらず「文化財」に該当する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In other words, the 6 categories highly valued historically, artistically, academically, or visually, are “tangible cultural properties”, “intangible cultural properties”, “folk cultural properties”, “monuments, “cultural sceneries”, and “classic architectures”. Regardless of whether they are designated or not, they are classified as “cultural properties”.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In other words, the six categories that are highly valued historically, artistically, academically or visually are &quot;tangible cultural properties,&quot; &quot;intangible cultural properties,&quot; &quot;folk cultural properties,&quot; &quot;monuments,&quot; &quot;cultural sceneries&quot; and &quot;classic architecture&quot;; regardless of whether they are designated or not, they&apos;re classified as cultural properties.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In other words, the six categories that are highly valued historically, artistically, academically or visually are &quot;tangible cultural properties,&quot; &quot;intangible cultural properties,&quot; &quot;folk cultural properties,&quot; &quot;monuments,&quot; &quot;cultural landscapes&quot; and &quot;classic architecture&quot;; regardless of whether they are designated or not, they&apos;re classified as cultural properties.</e>
<cmt>cultural scene→cultural landscape</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>文部科学大臣は文化財のうち重要なものを指定、認定、選定、登録、選択し、保護のもとにおくことができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Minister of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology can designate, approve, determine, register the important ones from among the cultural properties, and put them under protection.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Minister of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology can designate, approve, determine, register the important ones from among the cultural properties, and place them under protection.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Minister of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology can designate, approve, determine, register the important ones from among the cultural properties, and place them under protection.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>ただし指定等およびその解除にあたっては、文部科学大臣はあらかじめ文化審議会に諮問しなければならない（第153条）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, for designation or cancellation of designation, the Minister of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology should consult Council for Cultural Affairs beforehand (Ordinance 153).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, for the purpose of designation or the cancellation of designation, the Minister of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology should consult the Council for Cultural Affairs beforehand (Ordinance 153).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, for the purpose of designation or the cancellation of designation, the Minister of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology should consult the Council for Cultural Affairs beforehand (Article 153).</e>
<cmt>条＝Article としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>文化財の種類</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Categories of cultural properties</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Categories of Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt>capital</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Categories of Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>有形文化財</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tangible cultural properties</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tangible Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt>capital</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tangible Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="21">
<j>建築物、美術工芸品（絵画、彫刻、伝統工芸品、書跡、典籍）、古文書その他の有形の文化的所産（これらと一体をなしてその価値を形成している土地、工作物などを含む場合がある）および考古資料、歴史資料は有形文化財と定義されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tangible cultural properties are defined to be such things as buildings, art crafts (paintings, sculptures, traditional crafts, calligraphies, literatures), ancient documents and other tangible cultural outcomes or products (including all the auxiliary parts, tools or land attached for its value), as well as archeological or historical resources.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tangible cultural properties are defined as being such things as buildings, art crafts (paintings, sculptures, traditional crafts, calligraphies, literature), ancient documents and other tangible cultural outcomes or products (including all the auxiliary parts, tools or land attached to its value), as well as archeological or historical resources.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tangible cultural properties are defined as being such things as buildings, art crafts (paintings, sculptures, traditional crafts, calligraphies, literature), ancient documents and other tangible cultural outcomes or products (including all the auxiliary parts, tools or land attached to its value), as well as archeological or historical resources.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>文部科学大臣は、有形文化財のうち特に重要と判断されるものを重要文化財に指定することができる（第27条第1項）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the tangible cultural properties, the Minister of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology can designate the ones judged to be especially important as “important cultural properties”. (Ordinance　27 Clause 1).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the tangible cultural properties, the Minister of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology can designate the ones judged to be especially important as &quot;important cultural properties&quot; (Ordinance 27, Clause 1).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the tangible cultural properties, the Minister of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology can designate the ones judged to be especially important as &quot;important cultural properties&quot; (Article 27, Clause 1).</e>
<cmt>条＝Article としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>さらに、重要文化財のうち世界文化の見地から価値の高いもので、たぐいない国民の宝たるものを国宝に指定することができる（第27条第2項）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, among the “important cultural properties”, he can designate the ones culturally high-valued from the world’s perspective as “national treasures”. (Ordinance　27 Clause 2).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, among the important cultural properties he can designate as national treasures those that are of high cultural value from the world&apos;s perspective (Ordinance 27, Clause 2).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, among the important cultural properties he can designate as national treasures those that are of high cultural value from the world&apos;s perspective (Article 27, Clause 2).</e>
<cmt>条＝Article としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="24">
<j>1996年（平成8年）の文化財保護法改正により、主に近代化遺産を保護する目的から、国または地方公共団体の指定を受けていない有形文化財のうち、保存と活用が特に必要なものを登録有形文化財に登録する制度が創設された（第57条）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In accordance with the revision (Ordinance　57) in the Law for Protection of Cultural Properties in 1996, a registration system was established for those the tangible cultural properties which have not been designated by the nation or a local public entity, but at the same time need necessary preservation and proper usage. This revision was mainly aiming at protecting heritages from modernization.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1996, according to the revision (Ordinance 57) of the Law for the Protection of Cultural Properties, a registration system was established for those whose tangible cultural properties have not been designated by the nation or a local public entity but at the same time need necessary preservation and proper usage; this revision was mainly aimed at protecting heritages from modernization.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1996, according to the revision (Article 57) of the Law for the Protection of Cultural Properties, a registration system was established for those whose tangible cultural properties have not been designated by the nation or a local public entity but at the same time need necessary preservation and proper usage; this revision was mainly aimed at protecting heritages from modernization.</e>
<cmt>条＝Article としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>登録の対象は当初は建造物に限定されていたが、2004年（平成16年）の法改正でそれ以外の有形文化財にも適用範囲が拡大された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At first, the scope of registration was limited to the buildings. However, with the revision of the law in 2004, the coverage has been expanded to other tangible cultural properties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Initially, the scope of registration was limited to the buildings, but with the revision of the law in 2004 the coverage was expanded to other tangible cultural properties.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Initially, the scope of registration was limited to the buildings, but with the revision of the law in 2004 the coverage was expanded to other tangible cultural properties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>無形文化財</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Intangible cultural properties</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Intangible Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt>capital</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Intangible Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="26">
<j>演劇、音楽、工芸技術その他の無形の文化的所産は無形文化財と定義されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Intangible cultural properties are defined as the intangible cultural products or outcomes such as plays, music pieces, and craft skills..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Intangible cultural properties are defined as the intangible cultural products or outcomes such as plays, musical pieces and craft skills.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Intangible cultural properties are defined as the intangible cultural products or outcomes such as plays, musical pieces and craft skills.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>文部科学大臣は、無形文化財のうち特に重要と判断されるものを重要無形文化財に指定することができる（第71条第1項）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the intangible cultural properties, the Minister of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology can designate the ones judged to be especially important as “important intangible cultural properties”. (Ordinance　71 Clause 1).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the intangible cultural properties, the Minister of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology can designate the ones judged to be especially important as &quot;important intangible cultural properties&quot; (Ordinance 71, Clause 1).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the intangible cultural properties, the Minister of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology can designate the ones judged to be especially important as &quot;important intangible cultural properties&quot; (Article 71, Clause 1).</e>
<cmt>条＝Article としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>同時に、その重要無形文化財の保持者または保持団体が認定される（第71条第2項）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time, the holders or the maintenance bodies of such important intangible cultural properties are recognized. (Ordinance　71 Clause 2)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the same time, the holders or the maintenance bodies of such important intangible cultural properties are recognized (Ordinance 71, Clause 2).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the same time, the holders or the maintenance bodies of such important intangible cultural properties are recognized (Article 71, Clause 2).</e>
<cmt>条＝Article としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>保持者認定には、個人を各個別に認定する各個認定と、複数の保持者を一体として認定する総合認定がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The holder recognition is divided into personal recognition (which recognizes a person individually as a holder) and integrated recognition (which recognizes multiple holders as a body).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The holder recognition is divided into personal recognition (which recognizes a person individually as a holder) and integrated recognition (which recognizes multiple holders as a body).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The holder recognition is divided into personal recognition (which recognizes a person individually as a holder) and integrated recognition (which recognizes multiple holders as a body).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>各個認定を受けている保持者は人間国宝とも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A holder who has received personal recognition is called a “living national treasure”.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A holder who has received personal recognition is called a &quot;living national treasure.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A holder who has received personal recognition is called a &quot;living national treasure.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>重要無形文化財以外の無形文化財のうち、その記録を作成し、保存し、または公開するための措置を講ずるものは「記録作成等の措置を講ずべき無形の文化財」として選択される（第77条）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the intangible cultural properties other than the important intangible cultural properties, those deserve to have measures aiming at compiling, preserving or disclosing their recording documents are selected as “intangible cultural properties that deserve measures of documentation.” (Ordinance 77)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the intangible cultural properties other than the important intangible cultural properties, those that merit measures aimed at compiling, preserving or disclosing their recording documents are selected as &quot;intangible cultural properties that deserve measures of documentation&quot; (Ordinance 77).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the intangible cultural properties other than the important intangible cultural properties, those that merit measures aimed at compiling, preserving or disclosing their recording documents are selected as &quot;intangible cultural properties that deserve measures of documentation&quot; (Article 77).</e>
<cmt>条＝Article としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>これを選択無形文化財ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are called “selected intangible cultural properties”.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are called &quot;selected intangible cultural properties.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are called &quot;selected intangible cultural properties.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>民俗文化財</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Folk cultural properties</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Folk Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt>capital</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Folk Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="33">
<j>衣食住、生業、信仰、年中行事等に関する風俗慣習、民俗芸能、民俗技術及びこれらに用いられる衣類、器具、家屋その他の物件は民俗文化財と定義されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">“Folk cultural properties” are defined to be the folk customs, public entertainments, traditional skills, and the associated costumes, tools, stages, which are related to the indispensables such as foods, clothing, housings, livelihoods, beliefs, and annual events.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Folk cultural properties are defined as being the folk customs, public entertainments and traditional skills, and the associated costumes, tools and stages related to the indispensables such as foods, clothing, housings, livelihoods, beliefs and annual events.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Folk cultural properties are defined as being the folk customs, public entertainments and traditional skills, and the associated costumes, tools and stages related to the indispensables such as foods, clothing, housings, livelihoods, beliefs and annual events.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="34">
<j>文部科学大臣は、無形の民俗文化財に用いられる衣服、器具、家具など有形の民俗文化財のうち、特に重要なものを重要有形民俗文化財に指定することができる（第78条第1項）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the tangible folk cultural properties such as costumes, tools, stages which are associated with the intangible folk cultural properties, the Minister of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology can designate the ones judged to be especially important as “important tangible folk cultural properties”. (Ordinance　78 Clause 1).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the tangible folk cultural properties such as costumes, tools and stages associated with the intangible folk cultural properties, the Minister of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology can designate the ones judged to be especially important as &quot;important tangible folk cultural properties&quot; (Ordinance 78, Clause 1).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the tangible folk cultural properties such as costumes, tools and stages associated with the intangible folk cultural properties, the Minister of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology can designate the ones judged to be especially important as &quot;important tangible folk cultural properties&quot; (Article 78, Clause 1).</e>
<cmt>条＝Article としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>2004年（平成16年）の文化財保護法改正により、国または地方公共団体の指定を受けていない有形の民俗文化財のうち保存と活用が特に必要なものを年中行事に登録できることになった（第90条第1項）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In accordance with the revision (Ordinance　90 Clause 1) in the Law for Protection of Cultural Properties in 2004, a registration system was established for those tangible folk cultural properties which have not been designated by the nation or a local public entity, but at the same time need necessary preservation and proper usage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In accordance with the 2004 revision (Ordinance 90, Clause 1) of the Law for the Protection of Cultural Properties, a registration system was established for those tangible folk cultural properties that have not been designated by the nation or a local public entity but at the same time need necessary preservation and proper usage.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In accordance with the 2004 revision (Article 90, Clause 1) of the Law for the Protection of Cultural Properties, a registration system was established for those tangible folk cultural properties that have not been designated by the nation or a local public entity but at the same time need necessary preservation and proper usage as annual events.</e>
<cmt>「年中行事に」の部分を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>最初の登録物件は「若狭めのう玉磨用具」「勝沼のぶどう栽培用具及び葡萄酒醸造用具」「雲州そろばんの製作用具」の3件で、2006年（平成18年）3月15日に官報告示された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were three first registered cases; namely the “wakasa agate grinding tools”, the “grape cultivation tools and wine brewing tools of Katsunuma&quot; and the &quot;Unshu abacus making tool,&quot; as announced in the official gazette on March 15, 2006.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first three cases to be registered were the &quot;wakasa agate grinding tools,&quot; the &quot;grape cultivation tools and winemaking tools of Katsunuma&quot; and the &quot;Unshu abacus-making tool,&quot; as announced in the official gazette on March 15, 2006.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first three cases to be registered were the &quot;wakasa agate grinding tools,&quot; the &quot;grape cultivation tools and winemaking tools of Katsunuma&quot; and the &quot;Unshu abacus-making tool,&quot; as announced in the official gazette on March 15, 2006.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="37">
<j>また、文部科学大臣は、風俗慣習、民俗芸能、民俗技術などの無形の民俗文化財のうち特に重要なものを重要無形民俗文化財に指定することができる（第78条第1項）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the intangible folk cultural properties (such as folk customs, public entertainments, and traditional skills), the Minister of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology can designate the ones judged to be especially important as “important intangible folk cultural properties”. (Ordinance　78 Clause 1).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the intangible folk cultural properties (such as folk customs, public entertainments and traditional skills), the Minister of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology can designate the ones judged to be especially important as &quot;important intangible folk cultural properties&quot; (Ordinance 78, Clause 1).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the intangible folk cultural properties (such as folk customs, public entertainments and traditional skills), the Minister of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology can designate the ones judged to be especially important as &quot;important intangible folk cultural properties&quot; (Article 78, Clause 1).</e>
<cmt>条＝Article としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>また、重要無形民俗文化財以外の無形の民俗文化財のうち、その記録を作成し、保存し、または公開するための措置を講ずるものを「記録作成等の措置を講ずべき無形の民俗文化財」として選択することができる（第87条第1項）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the intangible folk cultural properties other than the important intangible folk cultural properties, those deserve to have measures aiming at compiling, preserving or disclosing their recording documents are selected as “intangible folk cultural properties that deserve measures of documentation.” (Ordinance 87 Clause 1)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the intangible folk cultural properties other than the important intangible folk cultural properties, those that merit measures aimed at compiling, preserving or disclosing their recording documents are selected as &quot;intangible folk cultural properties that deserve measures for documentation&quot; (Ordinance 87, Clause 1).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the intangible folk cultural properties other than the important intangible folk cultural properties, those that merit measures aimed at compiling, preserving or disclosing their recording documents are selected as &quot;intangible folk cultural properties that deserve measures for documentation&quot; (Article 87, Clause 1).</e>
<cmt>条＝Article としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>これを選択無形民俗文化財ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are called “selected intangible folk cultural properties”.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are called &quot;selected intangible folk cultural properties.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are also called &quot;selected intangible folk cultural properties.&quot;</e>
<cmt>also追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>記念物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Monuments</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Monuments</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Monuments</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="40">
<j>貝塚、古墳、都城跡、城、旧宅などの遺跡、庭園、橋、峡谷、海浜、山岳などの名勝地、動物、植物、地質鉱物などの自然の産物は記念物と総称されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Historical sites (such as shell mounds, ancient tombs, citadel style castle sites, castle sites, and old residences), famous places of scenic beauty (such as gardens, bridges, canyons, coasts, and mountains), and natural creations (such as animals, plants, and geological minerals) are collectively called monuments.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Historical sites (such as shell mounds, ancient tombs, citadel style castle sites, castle sites and old residences), famous places of scenic beauty (such as gardens, bridges, canyons, coasts and mountains), and natural creations (such as animals, plants and geological minerals) are collectively called monuments.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Historical sites (such as shell mounds, ancient tombs, citadel style castle sites, castle sites and old residences), famous places of scenic beauty (such as gardens, bridges, canyons, coasts and mountains), and natural creations (such as animals, plants and geological minerals) are collectively called monuments.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>文部科学大臣は、記念物のうち重要なものを史跡、名勝、天然記念物に指定することができる（第109条第1項）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the &quot;monuments,&quot; the Minister of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology can designate the ones judged to be especially important as “historic spots, places of natural scenery, natural monuments”. (Ordinance　109 Clause 1).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among such monuments, the Minister of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology can designate the ones judged to be especially important as &quot;historical spots, places of natural scenery and natural monuments&quot; (Ordinance 109, Clause 1).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among such monuments, the Minister of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology can designate the ones judged to be important as &quot;historical spots, places of natural scenery and natural monuments&quot; (Article 109, Clause 1).</e>
<cmt>especially 削除。条＝Article としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>さらに、その中でも特に重要なものを特別史跡、特別名勝、特別天然記念物に指定し、重点的な保護のもとにおくことができる（第109条第2項）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the &quot;monuments,&quot; the Minister of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology can designate the ones judged to be especially important as “historic spots, places natural scenery, natural monuments”. (Ordinance　109 Clause 1).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among such monuments, the Minister of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology can designate the ones judged to be especially important as &quot;historical spots, places of natural scenery and natural monuments&quot; (Ordinance 109, Clause 1).</e>
<cmt>REPEATED TEXT</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Minister can designate those of the monuments listed above that are judged to be especially important as &quot;special historical spots, special places of natural scenery and special natural monuments&quot; and place them under special care (Article 109, Clause 2).</e>
<cmt>訳を変更しました。条＝Article としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="43">
<j>2004年（平成16年）の文化財保護法改正により、国または地方公共団体の指定を受けていない記念物のうち、保存と活用が特に必要なものを登録記念物に登録できることになった（第132条第1項）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In accordance with the revision (Ordinance　132 Clause 1) in the Law for Protection of Cultural Properties in 2004, a registration system was established for those &quot;monuments&quot; which have not been designated by the nation or a local public entity, but at the same time need necessary preservation and proper usage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In accordance with the 2004 revision (Ordinance 132, Clause 1) of the Law for the Protection of Cultural Properties, a registration system was established for monuments that have not been designated by the nation or a local public entity but at the same time need necessary preservation and proper usage.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In accordance with the 2004 revision (Article 132, Clause 1) of the Law for the Protection of Cultural Properties, a registration system was established for monuments that have not been designated by the nation or a local public entity but at the same time need necessary preservation and proper usage as registered monuments.</e>
<cmt>as registered monumentsを追加。条＝Article としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>最初の登録物件は「函館公園」（北海道函館市）、「再度公園」（神戸市）、「相楽園」（神戸市）の3件で、2006年（平成18年）1月26日に官報告示された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were three first registered cases; namely &quot;Hakodate Park&quot;(Hakodate City, Hokkaido), &quot;Futatabi Park&quot;(Kobe City and &quot;Sorakuen Garden&quot;(Kobe City)”, as announced in the official gazette on January 26, 2006.</e>
<cmt>「函館公園」（北海道函館市）→&quot;Hakodate Park&quot;(Hakodate City, Hokkaido)「再度公園」（神戸市)→&quot;Futatabi Park&quot;(Kobe City) 「相楽園」（神戸市）→&quot;Sorakuen Garden&quot;(Kobe City) 官報告示→announced through official gazetts</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first three cases to be registered were Hakodate Park (Hakodate City, Hokkaido), Futatabi Park (Kobe City) and Sorakuen Garden (Kobe City), as announced in the official gazette on January 26, 2006.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first three cases to be registered were Hakodate Park (Hakodate City, Hokkaido), Futatabi Park (Kobe City) and Sorakuen Garden (Kobe City), as announced in the official gazette on January 26, 2006.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>文化的景観</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cultural scenery</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cultural Scenery</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cultural Landscapes</e>
<cmt>Cultural Landscapesに変更しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="45">
<j>地域における人々の生活または生業、および当該地域の風土により形成された景観地は文化的景観と定義されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">“Cultural sceneries” are defined to be the locals’ lives and livelihoods of a region, and the sceneries formed by the customs of that region that reflect the locals’ lives and livelihoods.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A cultural scene is defined as being the local life and livelihood of a region, as well as the scenes formed by the customs of that region that reflect the local people&apos;s lives and livelihoods.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A cultural landscape is defined as being the local life and livelihood of a region, as well as the scenes formed by the customs of that region that reflect the local people&apos;s lives and livelihoods.</e>
<cmt>cultural scene→cultural landscape</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>2004年（平成16年）の文化財保護法改正により創設された文化財のジャンルであり、「日本の原風景」などと呼ばれるような、棚田や里山などの景観がこれに該当する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In accordance with the revision in the Law for Protection of Cultural Properties in 2004, this genre of cultural properties was established. The so-called &quot;original sceneries of Japan&quot; such as tanada (terraced rice fields) and satoyama (outskirt of country) fall in this genre.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In accordance with the 2004 revision in the Law for the Protection of Cultural Properties, this genre of cultural properties was established; the so-called &quot;original scenery of Japan&quot; such as tanada (terraced rice fields) and satoyama (outskirts of the country) fall within this genre.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In accordance with the 2004 revision in the Law for the Protection of Cultural Properties, this genre of cultural properties was established; the so-called &quot;original scenery of Japan&quot; such as tanada (terraced rice fields) and satoyama (outskirts of the country) fall within this genre.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>文化庁は文化的景観の保存・活用事業を実施しており、文化庁の「文化的景観の保存・整備に関する検討委員会」が第三次調査で180の重要地域を選定した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The “Advisory committee for preservation and maintenance of cultural sceneries &quot; of the Agency for Cultural Affairs has determined 180 important regions on the third investigation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Advisory Committee for the Preservation and Maintenance of Cultural Scenes of the Agency for Cultural Affairs identified 180 important regions in its third investigation.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As part of the project for the preservation and usage of the Cultural Landscapes, the Advisory Committee for the Preservation and Maintenance of Cultural Landscapes of the Agency for Cultural Affairs identified 180 important regions in its third investigation.</e>
<cmt>[文化庁は文化的景観の保存・活用事業を実施しており」の部分を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>文部科学大臣は、景観地区などとして都道府県または市町村が保存措置を講じている文化的景観の中から特に重要なものを重要文化的景観として選定することができる（第134条第1項）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Minister (of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology) can select, from among the cultural sceneries which deserve to have preservation measures from the prefecture or the municipality, the especially important ones as “important cultural sceneries”. (Ordinance　134 Clause 1).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Minister of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology can select, from among the cultural scenes that deserve to have preservation measures from the prefecture or the municipality, the especially important ones as &quot;important cultural sceneries&quot; (Ordinance 134, Clause 1).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Minister of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology can select, from among the cultural landscapes that deserve to have preservation measures from the prefecture or the municipality, the especially important ones as &quot;important cultural landscapes&quot; (Article 134, Clause 1).</e>
<cmt>条＝Article としました。cultural scene→cultural landscape</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>重要文化的景観選定の第1号は滋賀県近江八幡市の「近江八幡の水郷」で、2006年（平成18年）1月26日に官報告示された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first selected case of &quot;important cultural sceneries&quot; was the &quot;scenery of Omi-hachiman lakeside region &quot; in Oumi-Hachiman City of Shiga Prefecture, as announced in the official gazette on January 26, 2006.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first selected case of an &quot;important cultural scene&quot; was the &quot;scenery of the Omi-hachiman lakeside region&quot; in Oumi-Hachiman City of Shiga Prefecture, as announced in the official gazette on January 26, 2006.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first selected case of an &quot;important cultural landscape &quot; was the &quot;scenery of the Omi-hachiman lakeside region&quot; in Omi-Hachiman City of Shiga Prefecture, as announced in the official gazette on January 26, 2006.</e>
<cmt>cultural scene→cultural landscapeOumi→Omi</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>第2号は岩手県一関市の「一関本寺の農村景観」で2006年（平成18年）7月28日に選定された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The second selected case was the &quot;farm village scenery of Ichinoseki Hondera Temple&quot; in Ichinoseki City of Iwate Prefecture, as announced in the official gazette on July 28, 2006.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The second selected case was the &quot;farm village scenery of Ichinoseki Hondera Temple&quot; in Ichinoseki City of Iwate Prefecture, as announced in the official gazette on July 28, 2006.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The second selected case was the &quot;farm village scenery of Ichinoseki Hondera Temple&quot; in Ichinoseki City of Iwate Prefecture, as announced in the official gazette on July 28, 2006.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>伝統的建造物群</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Classic Architectures</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Classic Architectures</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Classic Architectures</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="51">
<j>周囲の環境と一体をなして歴史的風致を形成している伝統的な建造物群は伝統的建造物群と定義されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">“Classic Architectures” are defined to be the high-valued traditional architectures that merge harmoniously with the surrounding environment forming a historical scenic beauty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Classic architecture is defined as being the highly valued traditional architecture that merges harmoniously with the surrounding environment to form a scene of historical beauty.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Classic architecture is defined as being the highly valued traditional architecture that merges harmoniously with the surrounding environment to form a scene of historical beauty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>宿場町や城下町などの集落や町並みがこれに該当する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A post-town or castle town (such as community, settlement, village, old rows of houses) fall into this category.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A post town or a castle town (such as a community, settlement, village or an old row of houses) would fall within this category.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A post town or a castle town (such as a community, settlement, village or an old row of houses) would fall within this category.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>他の制度とは異なり、まず市町村が都市計画もしくは条例により、歴史的な集落や町並みの保存を図ることを目的として伝統的建造物群保存地区を定める（第143条第1項）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Different from other systems, in order to preserve historical villages and towns, the municipality decides at first the classic architectures preservation districts, in accordance with city planning or regulations. (Ordinance 143 Clause 1)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unlike other systems, in order to preserve historical villages and towns the municipality first determines the districts for preservation of classic architecture, doing so in accordance with city planning or regulations (Ordinance 143, Clause 1).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unlike other systems, in order to preserve historical villages and towns the municipality first determines the districts for preservation of classic architecture, doing so in accordance with city planning or regulations (Article 143, Clause 1).</e>
<cmt>条＝Article としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>伝統的建造物群保存地区の中から特に価値が高いものを文部科学大臣が重要伝統的建造物群保存地区に選定することができる（第144条第1項）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the preservation districts of &quot;classic architectures,&quot; the Minister of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology can designate the ones judged to be especially important as preservation districts of “important classic architectures”. (Ordinance　144 Clause 1).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the preservation districts of classic architecture, the Minister of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology can designate the ones judged to be especially important as preservation districts of &quot;important classic architecture.&quot; (Ordinance　144 Clause 1).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the preservation districts of classic architecture, the Minister of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology can designate the ones judged to be especially important as preservation districts of &quot;important cluster of classical buildings protection area.&quot; (Article　144 Clause 1).</e>
<cmt>重要伝統的建造物群保存地区→ important cluster of classical buildings protection area条＝Article としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>埋蔵文化財</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Buried cultural properties</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Buried Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt>capital</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Buried Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="55">
<j>埋蔵文化財は、他の文化財とは異なり土地に埋蔵されている状態にある文化財である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Buried cultural properties, differing from other cultural properties, are cultural properties that exist in a state buried under the ground.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Buried cultural properties, unlike other cultural properties, are cultural properties that exist in such a state that they&apos;re buried underground.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Buried cultural properties, unlike other cultural properties, are cultural properties that exist in such a state that they&apos;re buried underground.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>埋蔵文化財の発掘調査を行う場合は事前に文化庁長官へ届け出なければならない（第92条第1項）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order to conduct an excavation investigation of a buried cultural property, it is necessary to report beforehand to director general of Agency for Cultural Affairs. (Ordinance 92 Clause 1)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To conduct an investigative excavation of a buried cultural property, it is necessary to report beforehand to the director-general of the Agency for Cultural Affairs (Ordinance 92, Clause 1).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To conduct an investigative excavation of a buried cultural property, it is necessary to report beforehand to the director-general of the Agency for Cultural Affairs (Article 92, Clause 1).</e>
<cmt>条＝Article としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>埋蔵文化財を包蔵する土地は遺跡地図等により周知が図られている（第95条）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for land where a buried cultural property is contained, the public is to be notified with the site map etc. (Ordinance 95).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for the land that contains a buried cultural property, the public is to be notified by means of a site map, etc. (Ordinance 95).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for the land that contains a buried cultural property, the public is to be notified by means of a site map, etc. (Article 95).</e>
<cmt>条＝Article としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>こうした周知の埋蔵文化財包蔵地において土木工事を行う場合も同様に文化庁長官へ届け出なければならない（第93条第1項）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Similarly, in the case if one wants to carry out engineering works on such well-known place containing a burial cultural property, it is necessary to report to chief director of Agency for Cultural Affairs. (Ordinance 93 Clause 1)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Similarly, if one wants to carry out engineering work on such a well-known place containing a buried cultural property, it is necessary to report to the director-general of the Agency for Cultural Affairs (Ordinance 93, Clause 1).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Similarly, if one wants to carry out engineering work on such a well-known place containing a buried cultural property, it is necessary to report to the director-general of the Agency for Cultural Affairs (Article 93, Clause 1).</e>
<cmt>条＝Article としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>地中から発見された埋蔵物が文化財と認められるときは、警察署長は都道府県教育委員会へ物件を提出し、都道府県教育委員会は物件が文化財であるかどうかを鑑査する（第102条）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When it is realized that item buried discovered in the ground is a cultural property, the police chief has to submit the item to the prefectural or municipal board of education to inspect whether or not the item is a cultural property.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When it is realized that the item buried in the ground is a cultural property, the chief of police must submit the item to the prefectural or municipal board of education for an inspection in order to determine whether or not the item is a cultural property.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When it is realized that the item buried in the ground is a cultural property, the chief of police must submit the item to the prefectural or municipal board of education for an inspection in order to determine whether or not the item is a cultural property.（Article 102)</e>
<cmt>第102条追加。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>選定保存技術</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Selected preserving techniques</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Selected Techniques for Preservation</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Selected Techniques for Preservation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="60">
<j>文化財の保存のために欠くことのできない材料製作、修理、修復などの伝統的な技術は、文化財には該当しないが、文化財保護法による保護の対象となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the material production, repair, restoration, and traditional skills indispensible for the preservation of the cultural properties are not “cultural properties”, they are in the protection scope under the Law for Protection of Cultural Properties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the material production, repair, restoration and traditional skills indispensible for the preservation of cultural properties aren&apos;t &quot;cultural properties,&quot; they are within the scope of protection under the Law for the Protection of Cultural Properties.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the material production, repair, restoration and traditional skills indispensable for the preservation of cultural properties aren&apos;t &quot;cultural properties,&quot; they are within the scope of protection under the Law for the Protection of Cultural Properties.</e>
<cmt>indispensible→indispensable</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>文部科学大臣は、選定保存技術を選定し（第147条第1項）、その技術の保持者または保持団体を認定する（第147条第2項）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Minister of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology determines the selected preserving techniques (Ordinance 147 clause 1), and recognizes the holders or the maintenance bodies of such techniques (Ordinance 147 clause 2).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Minister of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology determines the selected preservation techniques (Ordinance 147, Clause 1) and recognizes the holders or the maintenance bodies of such techniques (Ordinance 147, Clause 2).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Minister of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology determines the selected preservation techniques (Article 147, Clause 1) and recognizes the holders or the maintenance bodies of such techniques (Article 147, Clause 2).</e>
<cmt>条＝Article としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>文化財の保存と活用</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Preservation and Usage of Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Preservation and Usage of Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Preservation and Usage of Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="62">
<j>文化財の所有者は、個人、財団法人、地方公共団体（都道府県・市区町村）、国など多岐にわたるが、文化財の所有者および関係者は、文化財を公共のために大切に保存するとともに、できるだけこれを公開する等その文化的活用に努めなければならない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The owner of a cultural property can be a person, a foundation, a local public entity (prefecture or municipality, city, district, town or village), or the nation. Besides preserving the cultural property for the public, the owner or parties concerned must try all the best to put it into proper cultural use and open it to public as much as possible.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The owner of a cultural property can be a person, a foundation, a local public entity (a prefecture, municipality, city, district, town or village), or the nation; besides preserving the cultural property for the public, the owner or parties concerned must do their utmost to put it into proper cultural use and open it to public as much as possible.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The owner of a cultural property can be a person, a foundation, a local public entity (a prefecture, municipality, city, district, town or village), or the nation; besides preserving the cultural property for the public, the owner or parties concerned must do their utmost to put it into proper cultural use and open it to public as much as possible.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>特に指定を受けた文化財の所有者は、文化財を文部科学省令及び文化庁長官の指示に従って指定文化財を管理しなければならず（第31条）、所有者による管理が著しく不適当な場合には、文化庁長官は地方公共団体などを管理団体に指定し、所有者に代わって管理にあたらせることができる（第31条の2）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially for a designated cultural property, the owner must maintain the designated cultural property in accordance with the ordinances from the Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology and instructions from the chief director of Agency for Cultural Affairs (Ordinance 31). In the case when the management by the owner is remarkably improper, the chief director of Agency for Cultural Affairs can assign a local public entity as the management body in lieu of the owner (Ordinance 31 Clause 2).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Particularly in regard to a designated cultural property, the owner must maintain the designated cultural property in observance of the ordinances from the Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology and the instructions from the director-general of the Agency for Cultural Affairs (Ordinance 31); in the case when the management by the owner is noticeably insufficient, the director-general of the Agency for Cultural Affairs can assign a local public entity as the management body in lieu of the owner (Ordinance 31, Clause 2).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Particularly in regard to a designated cultural property, the owner must maintain the designated cultural property in observance of the ordinances from the Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology and the instructions from the director-general of the Agency for Cultural Affairs (Article 31); in the case when the management by the owner is noticeably insufficient, the director-general of the Agency for Cultural Affairs can assign a local public entity as the management body in lieu of the owner (Article 31, Clause 2).</e>
<cmt>条＝Article としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="64">
<j>指定文化財の現状変更には文化庁長官の許可が必要である（第43条）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To change the current state of a designated cultural property, it is necessary to have the permission from the chief director of Agency for Cultural Affairs. (Ordinance 43)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To change the current state of a designated cultural property, it is necessary to obtain permission from the director-general of the Agency for Cultural Affairs (Ordinance 43).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To change the current state of a designated cultural property, it is necessary to obtain permission from the director-general of the Agency for Cultural Affairs (Article 43).</e>
<cmt>条＝Article としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>特に指定文化財の輸出は原則として禁止されている（第44条）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially, the export of designated cultural properties, as a rule, is prohibited (Ordinance 44).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Particularly, the export of designated cultural properties is, as a rule, prohibited (Ordinance 44).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Particularly, the export of designated cultural properties is, as a rule, prohibited (Article 44).</e>
<cmt>条＝Article としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>また、文化庁長官は指定文化財の公開を勧告することができる（第51条）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, chief director of Agency for Cultural Affairs can recommend the public opening of a designated cultural property (Ordinance 51).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, the director-general of the Agency for Cultural Affairs can recommend the public opening of a designated cultural property (Ordinance 51).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, the director-general of the Agency for Cultural Affairs can recommend the public opening of a designated cultural property (Article 51).</e>
<cmt>条＝Article としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>一方で、指定文化財の管理又は修理につき多額の経費を要する場合は、所有者又は管理団体には補助金が交付される（第35条）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, when enormous expenditure is required for management or repair of a designated cultural property, a subsidy is granted to the owner or the management body. (Ordinance 35)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, when an enormous expenditure is required for the management or repair of a designated cultural property, a subsidy is granted to the owner or the management body (Ordinance 35).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, when an enormous expenditure is required for the management or repair of a designated cultural property, a subsidy is granted to the owner or the management body (Article 35).</e>
<cmt>条＝Article としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>登録文化財に関する規定は、指定文化財に関するものに比べてゆるやかなものとなっており、例えば現状変更は届出制となっている（第64条第1項）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Compared with the laws that concerns designated cultural properties, regulations concerning registered cultural properties are more flexible. For instance, a change of current state may be a written report system. (Ordinance 64 Clause 1)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Compared with the laws concerning designated cultural properties, regulations concerning registered cultural properties are more flexible; for example, a change from the current state may involve a system for the submittal of written reports (Ordinance 64, Clause 1).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Compared with the laws concerning designated cultural properties, regulations concerning registered cultural properties are more flexible; for example, a change from the current state may involve a system for the submittal of written reports (Article 64, Clause 1).</e>
<cmt>条＝Article としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>条例における文化財</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cultural properties in ordinance</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cultural Properties in the Ordinances</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cultural Properties in the Ordinances</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="69">
<j>文化財保護法第182条第2項は次のとおり規定している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Law for Protection of Cultural Properties Ordinance 182 Clause 2 provides as follows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Law for the Protection of Cultural Properties (Ordinance 182, Clause 2) provides the following:</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Law for the Protection of Cultural Properties (Article 182, Clause 2) provides the following:</e>
<cmt>条＝Article としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="70">
<j>地方公共団体は、条例の定めるところにより、重要文化財、重要無形文化財、重要有形民俗文化財、重要無形民俗文化財及び史跡名勝天然記念物以外の文化財で当該地方公共団体の区域内に存するもののうち重要なものを指定して、その保存及び活用のため必要な措置を講ずることができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Apart from the “important cultural properties”, “important intangible cultural properties”, “important tangible folk cultural properties”, “important intangible folk cultural properties”, and “historic spots, places of natural scenery, natural monuments”, a local public entity can designate the important ones among the cultural properties within its territory, and legislate for the necessary preservations and their proper usage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Apart from the &quot;important cultural properties,&quot; &quot;important intangible cultural properties,&quot; &quot;important tangible folk cultural properties,&quot; &quot;important intangible folk cultural properties&quot; and &quot;historic spots, places of natural scenery, natural monuments,&quot; a local public entity can designate the important ones among the cultural properties within its territory so as to legislate on behalf of the necessary preservation measures and their proper usage.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Apart from the &quot;important cultural properties,&quot; &quot;important intangible cultural properties,&quot; &quot;important tangible folk cultural properties,&quot; &quot;important intangible folk cultural properties&quot; and &quot;historic spots, places of natural scenery, natural monuments,&quot; a local public entity can designate the important ones among the cultural properties within its territory so as to legislate on behalf of the necessary preservation measures and their proper usage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="71">
<j>この規定に基づき、地方公共団体（都道府県、区市町村）の多くがそれぞれ「文化財保護条例」等の名称の条例を制定し、国指定の文化財以外の重要な文化財について、教育委員会が指定等を行い保護を図っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Based on this regulation, many local public entities (prefecture or municipality) enact respectively their own ordinances with names such as &quot;Ordinance for the Protection of Cultural Properties &quot;. The board of education carries out the prefectural or municipal designations with an attempt to protect those important cultural properties other than the nation designated cultural properties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based on this regulation, many local public entities (prefecture or municipality) enact respectively their own ordinances with names such as &quot;Ordinance for the Protection of Cultural Properties &quot;; the Board of Education carries out the prefectural or municipal designations with an attempt to protect those important cultural properties other than the nation designated cultural properties.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based on this regulation, many local public entities (prefecture or municipality) enact respectively their own ordinances with names such as &quot;Ordinance for the Protection of Cultural Properties &quot;; the Board of Education carries out the prefectural or municipal designations with an attempt to protect those important cultural properties other than the nation designated cultural properties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>ただし、地方指定の文化財が国指定となった場合は地方指定は解除される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, when a prefectural or municipal cultural property becomes nation designated, the prefectural or municipal designation is cancelled.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, when a prefectural or municipal cultural property becomes nationally designated, the prefectural or municipal designation is canceled.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, when a prefectural or municipal cultural property becomes nationally designated, the prefectural or municipal designation is canceled.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>地方公共団体の制度はおおむね国の制度に準じたものであるが、それぞれの考え方に応じて下記の例のように個々の特色を持った制度が定められている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although a prefectural or municipal system is mainly based on the national system, it can be established with individual traits in accordance with respective ideas as the following examples show.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although a prefectural or municipal system is mainly based on the national system, it can be established based on its particular traits, as the following examples show:</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although a prefectural or municipal system is mainly based on the national system, it can be established based on its particular traits, as the following examples show:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="74">
<j>東京都文化財保護条例</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokyo Metropolitan Ordinance for Protection Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokyo Metropolitan Ordinance for the Protection of Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokyo Metropolitan Ordinance for the Protection of Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>有形文化財のうち重要なものを東京都指定有形文化財に指定することができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the tangible cultural properties, those important ones can be designated as “Tokyo Metropolitan designated tangible cultural properties”.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the tangible cultural properties, the important ones can be designated as &quot;Tokyo Metropolitan Area-designated tangible cultural properties.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the tangible cultural properties, the important ones can be designated as &quot;Tokyo Metropolitan Area-designated tangible cultural properties.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="76">
<j>無形文化財のうち重要なものを東京都指定無形文化財に指定することができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the intangible cultural properties, those important ones can be designated as “Tokyo Metropolitan designated intangible cultural properties”.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the intangible cultural properties, the important ones can be designated as &quot;Tokyo Metropolitan-Area designated intangible cultural properties.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the intangible cultural properties, the important ones can be designated as &quot;Tokyo Metropolitan-Area designated intangible cultural properties.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="77">
<j>有形の民俗文化財のうち重要なものを東京都指定有形民俗文化財に、無形の民俗文化財のうち重要なものを東京都指定無形民俗文化財に指定することができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the tangible folk cultural properties, those important ones can be designated as “Tokyo Metropolitan designated tangible folk cultural properties”. Among the intangible folk cultural properties, those important ones can be designated as “Tokyo Metropolitan designated intangible folk cultural properties”.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the tangible folk cultural properties, the important ones can be designated as &quot;Tokyo Metropolitan Area-designated tangible folk cultural properties&quot;; among the intangible folk cultural properties, the important ones can be designated as &quot;Tokyo Metropolitan Area-designated intangible folk cultural properties.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the tangible folk cultural properties, the important ones can be designated as &quot;Tokyo Metropolitan Area-designated tangible folk cultural properties&quot;; among the intangible folk cultural properties, the important ones can be designated as &quot;Tokyo Metropolitan Area-designated intangible folk cultural properties.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="78">
<j>記念物のうち重要なものを、東京都指定史跡、東京都指定旧跡、東京都指定名勝又は東京都指定天然記念物に指定することができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the &quot;monuments,&quot; those important ones can be designated as “Tokyo Metropolitan designated historic sites”, “Tokyo Metropolitan designated ancient sites”, “Tokyo Metropolitan designated spots of scenic beauty”, or “Tokyo Metropolitan designated natural monuments”.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the monuments, important ones can be designated as &quot;Tokyo Metropolitan Area-designated historic sites,&quot; &quot;Tokyo Metropolitan Area-designated ancient sites,&quot; &quot;Tokyo Metropolitan Area-designated spots of scenic beauty&quot; or &quot;Tokyo Metropolitan Area-designated natural monuments.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the monuments, important ones can be designated as &quot;Tokyo Metropolitan Area-designated historic sites,&quot; &quot;Tokyo Metropolitan Area-designated ancient sites,&quot; &quot;Tokyo Metropolitan Area-designated spots of scenic beauty&quot; or &quot;Tokyo Metropolitan Area-designated natural monuments.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="79">
<j>山梨県文化財保護条例</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamanashi Prefecture Ordinance for Protection Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yamanashi Prefecture Ordinance for the Protection of Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamanashi Prefecture Ordinance for the Protection of Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>有形文化財のうち重要なものを山梨県指定有形文化財に指定することができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the tangible cultural properties, those important ones can be designated as “Yamanashi Prefectural designated tangible cultural properties”.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the tangible cultural properties, those important ones can be designated as &quot;Yamanashi Prefectural designated tangible cultural properties.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the tangible cultural properties, those important ones can be designated as &quot;Yamanashi Prefectural designated tangible cultural properties.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="81">
<j>無形文化財のうち重要なものを山梨県指定無形文化財に指定することができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the intangible cultural properties, those important ones can be designated as “Yamanashi Prefectural designated intangible cultural properties”.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the intangible cultural properties, the important ones can be designated as &quot;Yamanashi Prefecture-designated intangible cultural properties.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the intangible cultural properties, the important ones can be designated as &quot;Yamanashi Prefecture-designated intangible cultural properties.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="82">
<j>有形の民俗文化財のうち重要なものを山梨県指定有形民俗文化財に、無形の民俗文化財のうち重要なものを山梨県指定無形民俗文化財に指定することができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the tangible folk cultural properties, those important ones can be designated as “Yamanashi Prefectural designated tangible folk cultural properties”. Among the intangible folk cultural properties, those important ones can be designated as “Yamanashi Prefectural designated intangible folk cultural properties”.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the tangible folk cultural properties, the important ones can be designated as &quot;Yamanashi Prefecture-designated tangible folk cultural properties&quot;; among the intangible folk cultural properties, the important ones can be designated as &quot;Yamanashi Prefecture-designated intangible folk cultural properties.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the tangible folk cultural properties, the important ones can be designated as &quot;Yamanashi Prefecture-designated tangible folk cultural properties&quot;; among the intangible folk cultural properties; the important ones can be designated as &quot;Yamanashi Prefecture-designated intangible folk cultural properties.&quot;</e>
<cmt>セミコロン追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="83">
<j>記念物のうち重要なものを山梨県指定史跡、山梨県指定名勝又は山梨県指定天然記念物に指定することができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the &quot;monuments,&quot; those important ones can be designated as “Yamanashi Prefectural designated historic sites”, “Yamanashi Prefectural designated spots of scenic beauty”, or “Yamanashi Prefectural designated natural monuments”.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the monuments, the important ones can be designated as &quot;Yamanashi Prefecture-designated historic sites,&quot; &quot;Yamanashi Prefecture-designated spots of scenic beauty&quot; or &quot;Yamanashi Prefecture-designated natural monuments.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the monuments, the important ones can be designated as &quot;Yamanashi Prefecture-designated historic sites,&quot; &quot;Yamanashi Prefecture-designated spots of scenic beauty&quot; or &quot;Yamanashi Prefecture-designated natural monuments.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="84">
<j>文化的景観のうち重要なものを山梨県選定文化的景観として選定することができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the cultural sceneries, those important ones can be selected as “Yamanashi Prefectural selected cultural sceneries”.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the cultural sceneries, those important ones can be selected as &quot;Yamanashi Prefectural selected cultural sceneries.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the cultural sceneries, those important ones can be selected as &quot;Yamanashi Prefectural selected cultural landscapes.&quot;</e>
<cmt>cultural scene→cultural landscape</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="85">
<j>伝統的建造物群保存地区で価値が特に高いものを山梨県選定伝統的建造物群保存地区として選定することができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the preservation districts of &quot;classic architectures,&quot; those especially valuable ones can be selected as “Yamanashi Prefectural selected preservation districts of &quot;classic architectures&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the preservation districts of classic architecture,&quot; the particularly valuable ones can be selected as &quot;Yamanashi Prefectural selected preservation districts of &quot;classic architecture.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the preservation districts of classic architecture,&quot; the particularly valuable ones can be selected as &quot;Yamanashi Prefectural selected preservation districts of &quot;classic architecture.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="86">
<j>岐阜県文化財保護条例</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gifu Prefecture Ordinance for Protection Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gifu Prefecture Ordinance for the Protection of Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gifu Prefecture Ordinance for the Protection of Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>有形文化財のうち特に価値の高いものを岐阜県重要文化財に指定することができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the tangible cultural properties, those especially valuable ones can be designated as “Gifu Prefectural important important cultural properties”.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the tangible cultural properties, the particularly valuable ones can be designated as &quot;Gifu Prefectural important cultural properties.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the tangible cultural properties, the particularly valuable ones can be designated as &quot;Gifu Prefectural important cultural properties.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="88">
<j>無形文化財のうち特に価値の高いものを岐阜県重要無形文化財に指定することができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the intangible cultural properties, those especially valuable ones can be designated as “Gifu Prefectural important intangible cultural properties”.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the intangible cultural properties, the particularly valuable ones can be designated as &quot;Gifu Prefectural important intangible cultural properties.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the intangible cultural properties, the particularly valuable ones can be designated as &quot;Gifu Prefectural important intangible cultural properties.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="89">
<j>民俗文化財のうち特に価値の高いものを岐阜県重要有形民俗文化財又は岐阜県重要無形民俗文化財に指定することができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the folk cultural properties, those especially valuable ones can be designated as “Gifu Prefectural important tangible folk cultural properties” or “Gifu Prefectural important intangible folk cultural properties”.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the folk cultural properties, the particularly valuable ones can be designated as &quot;Gifu Prefectural important tangible folk cultural properties&quot; or &quot;Gifu Prefectural important intangible folk cultural properties.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the folk cultural properties, the particularly valuable ones can be designated as &quot;Gifu Prefectural important tangible folk cultural properties&quot; or &quot;Gifu Prefectural important intangible folk cultural properties.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="90">
<j>記念物のうち特に価値の高いものを岐阜県史跡、岐阜県名勝又は岐阜県天然記念物に指定することができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the &quot;monuments,&quot; those especially valuable ones can be designated as “Gifu Prefectural historic sites”, “Gifu Prefectural spots of scenic beauty”, or “Gifu Prefectural natural monuments”.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the monuments, the particularly valuable ones can be designated as &quot;Gifu Prefectural historic sites,&quot; &quot;Gifu Prefectural spots of scenic beauty&quot; or &quot;Gifu Prefectural natural monuments.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the monuments, the particularly valuable ones can be designated as &quot;Gifu Prefectural historic sites,&quot; &quot;Gifu Prefectural spots of scenic beauty&quot; or &quot;Gifu Prefectural natural monuments.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="91">
<j>横浜市文化財保護条例</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yokohama City Ordinance for Protection Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yokohama City Ordinance for the Protection of Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yokohama City Ordinance for the Protection of Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>文化財のうち、地域住民が守ってきたもの及び地域を知る上で必要な文化財を横浜市地域文化財として登録することができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the cultural properties, those being kept by local residents or those necessarily known by the locals can be as registered as Yokohama City local cultural properties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the cultural properties, those that are kept by local residents or are necessarily known by the locals can be registered as Yokohama City local cultural properties.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the cultural properties, those that are kept by local residents or are necessarily known by the locals can be registered as Yokohama City local cultural properties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="93">
<j>金沢市における伝統環境の保存および美しい景観の形成に関する条例</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ordinance concerning the preservation of a tradition environment and the formation of a beautiful spectacle in Kanazawa City</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ordinance concerning the preservation of a traditional environment and the formation of a beautiful spectacle in Kanazawa City</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ordinance concerning the preservation of a traditional environment and the formation of a beautiful spectacle in Kanazawa City</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>伝統環境を保存育成するために必要な土地の区域（以下「伝統環境保存区域」という。)または近代的都市景観を創出するために必要な土地の区域（以下「近代的都市景観創出区域」という。）を指定することができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The necessary land or zone in order to preserve and cultivate a traditional environment (hereafter referred as &quot;traditional environment preservation zone &quot;), or the land or zone necessary in order to create a modern cityscape (hereinafter referred as a &quot;modern urban scenery creation zone&quot;) can be designated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The land or zone necessary in order to preserve and cultivate a traditional environment (hereinafter referred as a &quot;traditional environment preservation zone&quot;), or the land or zone necessary in order to create a modern cityscape (hereinafter referred as a &quot;modern urban scenery creation zone&quot;) can be designated.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The land or zone necessary in order to preserve and cultivate a traditional environment (hereinafter referred as a &quot;traditional environment preservation zone&quot;), or the land or zone necessary in order to create a modern cityscape (hereinafter referred as a &quot;modern urban scenery creation zone&quot;) can be designated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="95">
<j>都市景観の形成のため、建築物等および木竹を保存対象物として指定することができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order for the formation of city scenery, a building or a natural scenery can be designated as a candidate for preservation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A building or a natural scenery can be designated as a candidate for preservation and thereby constitute city scenery.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A building or a woody plant can be designated as a candidate for preservation and thereby constitute city scenery.</e>
<cmt>「木竹」は「woody plant」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="96">
<j>神戸市文化財の保護及び文化財等を取り巻く文化環境の保全に関する条例</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kobe City Ordinance concerning the protection of cultural properties and the maintenance of the surrounding cultural environment</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kobe City Ordinance concerning the protection of cultural properties and the maintenance of the surrounding cultural environment</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kobe City Ordinance concerning the protection of cultural properties and the maintenance of the surrounding cultural environment</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>文化財のうち必要なものを神戸市登録文化財として登録することができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the cultural properties, those being kept by local residents or those necessarily known by the locals can be as registered as Yokohama City local cultural properties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the cultural properties, those that are kept by local residents or necessarily known by the locals can be registered as Yokohama City local cultural properties.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the cultural properties, the necessary ones can be registered as Kobe City registered cultural properties.</e>
<cmt>訳し直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="98">
<j>文化財のうち必要なものを神戸市地域文化財として認定することができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the cultural properties, those necessary ones can be registered as “Kobe City registered cultural properties”.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the cultural properties, the necessary ones can be registered as &quot;Kobe City registered cultural properties.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the cultural properties, the necessary ones can be registered as Kobe City local cultural properties.</e>
<cmt>Kobe City registered cultural properties→Kobe City local cultural properties&quot;&quot; を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="99">
<j>文化環境を保存するため必要な区域を文化環境保存区域として指定することができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order to preserve a cultural environment, the necessary district can be designated as “cultural environment preservation zones”.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to preserve a cultural environment, the necessary district can be designated as a &quot;cultural environment preservation zone.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to preserve a cultural environment, the necessary district can be designated as a &quot;cultural environment preservation zone.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="100">
<j>文化環境保存区域内に存する有形文化財のうち重要なものを神戸市歴史的建造物その他の有形の文化的所産に選定することができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the tangible cultural properties existing in the environmental preservation zones, those important ones can be registered as “historical buildings of Kobe City” or other tangible cultural products.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the tangible cultural properties existing in the environmental preservation zones, the important ones can be registered as &quot;historical buildings of Kobe City&quot; or other tangible cultural products.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the tangible cultural properties existing in the environmental preservation zones, the important ones can be registered as &quot;historical buildings of Kobe City&quot; or other tangible cultural products.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Demi(id:74698), 月と太陽(id:16140), Nnh(id:474), Charenji(id:7908), Urania(id:7213), D.h(id:79056), Siyajkak(id:9402), Kamakura(id:472), Greenland4(id:114494), Toto-tarou(id:16648), ミッキーマウスのぬいぐるみ(id:80103), Penpen(id:18815), Hy48(id:82977), Chobot(id:20846), Yosemite(id:5808), Hermes(id:21387), Aduma(id:32899), Stanislaus(id:1806), OiOiO(id:94238), Vina-iwbot(id:56449), Rusk(id:9895), SuisuiBot(id:10165), Qwert1234(id:169540), Dddeco(id:140375), Shifumi(id:15485), トマ(id:42664), 663highland(id:18755), Muyo(id:14948), Baffclan(id:499), Nekosuki600(id:21263), Ha～Ha(id:36403), LeonardoRob0t(id:25875), Kinoukyouasu(id:10389), Suisui(id:69), 10cm(id:147838), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>