<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>浦安の舞</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dance of Urayasu no Mai</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Urayasu no Mai Dance</e>
<cmt>Moved Dance</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Urayasu no Mai Dance</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>浦安の舞（うらやすのまい）は、神楽（巫女舞）の1つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Urayasu no Mai is a kagura, or a shinto music and dancing, and specifically, it is a mikomai, or a shinto ceremonial dance performed by priestresses holding a ritual object in the hand.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Urayasu no Mai is a type of kagura, or shinto music and dancing; more specifically, it is a mikomai, or ceremonial dance performed by shrine maidens holding ritual objects.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Urayasu no Mai is a type of kagura (sacred music and dancing performed at shrines) (mikomai (female Shinto dance that the young girls each carry a small baton with bells)).</e>
<cmt>巫女舞、神楽の定訳を入れました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>近代に作られた神楽である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dance of Urayasu no Mai was composed in modern era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was created in the modern era.</e>
<cmt>Revised to make less wordy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was created in the modern era.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>1940年（昭和15年）11月10日に開かれる「皇紀皇紀二千六百年奉祝会」に合わせ、全国の神社で奉祝臨時祭を行うに当たり、祭典中に奉奏する神楽を新たに作ることが立案され、当時の宮内省楽部の楽長である多忠朝が国風歌舞を下地に作曲作舞した神楽舞である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was proposed that composing a new kagura for performing in an extraordinary festival of honor, a concurrent event for the celebration of the two thousand six hundredth anniversary of Imperial era, held on November 10, 1940; a special kaguramai (shinto dance) was composed by Tadatomo ONO, the then Kapellmeister of the Music Department of the Imperial Household Agency, based on Kuniburi no utamai dance, a traditional Japanese dance which has existed since the ancient times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was decided that a new kagura should be made for the special festivals that were to be held as part of the 2,600th anniversary of Imperial rule on November 10, 1940, and Tadatomo ONO, head of the Imperial Household Ministry&apos;s Music Department, composed the dance based on traditional Kuniburi no utamai dances.</e>
<cmt>Revised to make less wordy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was decided that a new kagura should be made for the special festivals that were to be held as part of &apos;the 2,600th anniversary of Imperial rule&apos; on November 10, 1940, and Tadatomo ONO, head of the Imperial Household Ministry&apos;s Music Department, composed the dance and music based on traditional Kuniburi no utamai songs and dances.</e>
<cmt>dance→dance and music「皇紀皇紀二千六百年奉祝会」の訳に　&apos; &apos; を付けました。utamai dances→utamai songs and dances</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>1933年（昭和8年）の昭和天皇御製</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The poem written by Emperor Showa in 1933 was used in the kagura:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Lyrics written by Emperor Showa in 1933 are used in the kagura:</e>
<cmt>Article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Lyrics written by Emperor Showa in 1933:</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせて、&quot;are used in the kagura&quot; を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>天地（あめつち）の神にぞ祈る朝なぎの海のごとくに波たたぬ世を</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">I pray the deity of heaven and earth that the world be just like a placid sea before dawn.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">I pray to the deity of heaven and earth that the world be just like a placid sea before dawn.</e>
<cmt>Preposition</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">I pray to the deity of heaven and earth that the world be just like a placid sea before dawn.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>これが神楽の歌詞となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These lyrics are used in the kagura.</e>
<cmt>「これが」を原文に追加しました。原文に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>皇紀二千六百年奉祝臨時祭に合わせて奉奏する為に日本全国で講習会が開かれ、海外鎮座の神社でも奉奏されるべく朝鮮・台湾などの外地へも講師が派遣された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Workshops were held nationwide to prepare for the performance for extraordinary festival of honor the two thousand six hundredth anniversary of Imperial era</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Workshops were held nationwide to prepare for the special festivals of the 2,600th anniversary of Imperial rule and instructors were even sent to shrines in overseas territories such as Korea and Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarityAdded missing translation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Workshops were held nationwide to prepare for the special festivals of the 2,600th anniversary of Imperial rule and instructors were even sent to shrines in overseas territories such as Korea and Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>奉祝会当日午前10時には全国一斉に奉奏された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The dance was performed at 10 o&apos;clock in the morning on the day at shrines all over Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The dance was performed at 10 o&apos;clock in the morning on the day at shrines all over Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The dance was performed at 10 o&apos;clock in the morning on the day at shrines all over Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>以降各神社で舞われるようになり、現在に至っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The dance has been performed occasionally at every shrine since then.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The dance has been performed occasionally at every shrine since then.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The dance has been performed occasionally at every shrine since then.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="11">
<j>明治以降整備されてきた神社祭祀制度には女性による奉仕に関する規定が無かったが、舞の制定により神社祭祀に女性が奉仕する機会が作られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">No provision regarding the women&apos;s services was specified in the religious services program in a shrine, which had been developed since Meiji era; the establishment of the dance provided opporunities for women&apos;s activities in the shrine services.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the Meiji period, there had been no official provision for shrine services by women and the establishment of this dance provided them with an opportunity to participate in services</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the Meiji period, there had been no official provision for shrine services by women and the establishment of this dance provided them with an opportunity to participate in services</e>
<cmt>「整備されてきた神社祭祀制度」が削られていますが、入れると「clarity」がなくなるようですので、そのままにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>また全国規模の講習会と奉奏の徹底は神社における神楽舞の普及に大きく貢献した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, conducting nationwide scale workshops and performance of the dance in full-scale contributed popularizing kagura dances among the shrines.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, conducting nationwide workshops and full-scale performances of the dance contributed to popularizing kagura dances among the shrines.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;scale&quot;Changed word orderGrammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, conducting nationwide workshops and full-scale performances of the dance contributed to popularizing kagura dances among the shrines.</e>
<cmt>and の後のスペース短縮</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="13">
<j>尚、浦安の舞などの近代に作られた神楽は国風歌舞や舞楽を下地に創作されたものであり、広義では雅楽の延長線としても考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kagura that were made in modern era, including Urayasu no mai, were composed based on Kuniburi no utamai dance or bugaku (a classical Japanese court dance); therefore, it can be categorized as a part of gagaku in a broad sense.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kagura made in the modern era, including Urayasu no mai, are based on Kuniburi no utamai dances or bugaku (a classical Japanese court dance) and, in a broad sense, can be seen as a continuation of gagaku court music.</e>
<cmt>ArticleGrammarRevised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kagura made in the modern era, including Urayasu no mai, are based on Kuniburi no utamai songs and dances or bugaku (traditional Japanese court music accompanied by dancing) and, in a broad sense, can be seen as a continuation of gagaku court music.</e>
<cmt>utamai dances→utamai song and dances舞楽の定訳一原文一訳文例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>しかし、神社祭祀に特化した新たな創作神楽であることから、狭義では雅楽と明確に区分される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a narrow sense, however, it is common to draw a line between bugaku and gagaku, because the former is a new creative kagura specialized in shrine ceremonies.</e>
<cmt>文章を足しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In a narrow sense, however, they are distinct from gagaku, being specifically created for religious festivals.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, accuracy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In a narrow sense, however, they are distinct from gagaku, being specifically created for religious festivals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>特に多忠朝は制作に当たって神社祭祀に於ける日本神話に基づく神楽の重要性を主張している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the process of composition, Tadatomo ONO, namely, emphasized the importance of kagura for shrine ceremonies being based on Japanese mythology.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In particular, Tadatomo ONO, in his composition, emphasized the importance of kagura being based on Japanese mythology for shrine ceremonies.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In particular, Tadatomo ONO, in his composition, emphasized the importance of kagura being based on Japanese mythology for shrine ceremonies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="16">
<j>構成</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Structure</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Structure</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Structure</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>浦安の舞は舞姫 (曖昧さ回避)（巫女）によって一人舞、二人舞、四人舞で舞われる女舞である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Urayasu no mai is a onna mai (literally, female dance) which is performed by Maihime (disambiguation), or priestress, as hitorimai, futarimai, and yonin mai, or solo dance, dance in pairs, dance by four people, respectively.</e>
<cmt>現在、maihimeの曖昧さ回避(disambiguation) page はないようです。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Urayasu no mai is a dance for women performed by shrine maidens as a solo, in pairs or by four people.</e>
<cmt>Revised to make less wordy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Urayasu no mai is a dance for women performed by shrine maidens as a solo, in pairs or by four people.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>正式は四人舞である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The formal form of dance is performed by four dancers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The formal form of the dance is performed by four dancers.</e>
<cmt>Article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The formal form of the dance is performed by four dancers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>舞は前半の扇舞と後半の鈴舞とがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The dance consists of two parts: the first half, ogi no mai, which is a dance using formal folding fan made of hinoki cypress; and the second half, suzu no mai, which is a dance using bells with straps.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The dance consists of two parts: the first half, ogi no mai, is a dance using a formal folding fan made of hinoki cypress; and the second half, suzu no mai, is a dance using bells attached to straps.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;which&quot;ArticlePreposition</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The dance consists of two parts: the first half, ogi no mai, is a dance using a formal folding fan made of hinoki cypress; and the second half, suzu no mai, is a dance using bells attached to straps.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="20">
<j>｢浦安｣の語義</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Terminology of urayasu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Etymology of urayasu</e>
<cmt>&quot;Terminology&quot;→&quot;Etymology&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Etymology of &apos;urayasu&apos;</e>
<cmt>urayasu→&apos;urayasu&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>｢うら｣は心を指す古語であり、｢うらやす｣で心中の平穏を表す語であるとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Ura&quot; is a ancient Japanese word meaning mind or heart; &quot;urayasu&quot; therefore means supposedly &quot;peace of mind.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Ura&quot; is a ancient Japanese word meaning mind or heart; &quot;urayasu&quot; therefore means supposedly &quot;peace of mind.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ura&apos; is an ancient Japanese word meaning mind or heart; &apos;urayasu&apos; therefore means supposedly &apos;peace of mind.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;a→an</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>また、日本書紀に｢昔伊弉諾尊目此国曰。日本者浦安国。」とある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Nohon Shoki, or Chronicles of Japan, there is a phrase: 昔伊弉諾尊目此国曰。日本者浦安国。 Mukashi, Izanagi no mikoto kono kuni wo nazukete iwaku Yamato ha Urayasu no kuni. (Long ago, Izanagi, a male deity of creation, said here is the country of Yamato, a country of urayasu, a land of peaceful mind.)</e>
<cmt>日本者浦安国。日本国の異号として｢浦安国｣（美称）・・・という記載が多く見られました。それで、ここでの意味は「やまと、それは心安らぐ国、と名づけ・・・」という意味合いと解釈しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Nohon Shoki, or Chronicles of Japan, there is a phrase: Long ago, Izanagi, a male deity of creation, said here is the country of Yamato, a country of urayasu, a land of peaceful mind.</e>
<cmt>Deleted Japanese - doesn&apos;t add much to the sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Nihonshoki, or Chronicles of Japan, there is a phrase: Long ago, Izanagi, a male deity of creation, said here is the country of Yamato, a country of urayasu, a land of peaceful mind.</e>
<cmt>the Nohon Shoki→Nihonshoki</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>他の文献にも日本国の異号として｢浦安国｣とあることから、天津神・国津神の安寧慰撫と国の平穏無事が、題名である｢浦安｣の語に込められている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The use of &quot;Urayasu no kuni&quot; as the synonym of Japan is found in other literature, suggesting that the term &quot;urayasu&quot; in the title encompasses the wish for pacification and consolation of Amatsukami (heavenly gods) and Kunitsukami (earthly deities), and peace of teh people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The use of &quot;Urayasu no kuni&quot; as a synonym for Japan is found in other literature, suggesting that the term &quot;urayasu&quot; in the title of the dance encompasses the wish for reconciliation between of Amatsukami (heavenly gods) and Kunitsukami (earthly deities), and peace throughout the land.</e>
<cmt>ArticlePrepositionRevised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The use of &apos;Urayasu no kuni&apos; as a synonym for Japan is found in other literature, suggesting that the term &apos;urayasu&apos; in the title of the dance is used to encompass the pacification and appeasement of the Amatsu kami (god of heaven) and Kunitsu kami (gods of the land), as well as peace throughout the land.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;天津神・国津神の定訳原文と一致するように修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="24">
<j>楽器</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Musical instruments</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Musical instruments</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Musical instruments</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>使用する楽器は神楽笛、篳篥、筝、太鼓である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Musical instruments used are: kagurabue flute, hichiriki (double reed Japanese flute), koto (Japanese harp), and taiko (Japanese drum).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Musical instruments used are: kagurabue flute, hichiriki (double reed Japanese flute), koto (Japanese harp), and taiko (Japanese drum).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Musical instruments used are: kagurabue flute, hichiriki (double reed Japanese flute), koto (Japanese harp), and taiko (Japanese drum).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>太鼓は雅楽用の物（釣太鼓）を用いるのが主とされるが、一般的な太鼓でも差し支えないとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The standard type of drums fo be used are the ones for gagaku, that is, tsuri-daiko (a hanging drum suspended in a frame with a painted upright stand); however, general types of drums are also acceptable.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The drum most often used is the tsuridaiko, a drum that hangs in a frame and is used in gagaku, but standard drums are also acceptable.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The drum most often used is the tsuridaiko, a drum that hangs in a frame and is used in gagaku, but standard drums are also acceptable.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>太鼓は拍子を取るのに用いられるが、太鼓が無い場合は笏拍子を用いる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A drum is typically used to keep other instruments in time; if a drum is not available, shaku byoshi (clappers) can be used instead.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Drums are typically used to keep other instruments in time; if a drum is not available, shaku byoshi (clappers) can be used instead.</e>
<cmt>Made &quot;drum&quot;plural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Drums are typically used to keep other instruments in time; if a drum is not available, shaku byoshi (clappers) can be used instead.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>使用する笛に関しては神楽笛を用いることが厳重に指導されており、龍笛、篠笛等の笛は用いてはならないとされる（そもそも神楽笛以外の笛は音域が合わず、吹奏に適切ではない）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With respect to the flute, the use of kagura flute is strongly recommended, and other types of flutes such as otekii and shinobue, are notrecommded; the sounding range of these flutes do not match the music in any way, thus unsuitable to use except for the flutes made for kagura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The flute used should be a kagura flute; other types of flutes, such as the otekii and shinobue, are not recommded as their pitch does not match the music in any way and they are thus unsuitable for kagura.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarityArticlesGrammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The flute used should be a kagura flute; other types of flutes, such as the ryuteki and shinobue, are not suitable as their pitch does not match the music in any way.</e>
<cmt>otekii→ryuteki「unsuitable for kagura.」神楽に適さなければ浦安の舞に適さないのですが、ここでは「浦安の舞の吹奏に適さない」ということです。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>又、弦楽器に関しては当初は和琴・楽箏両方の譜面が用意されたが、俗箏でも構わないとされたことから箏での演奏が普及し、現在に至っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With regard to chordophones, originally, music sheets for both wagon (six or seven stringed Japanese native harp) and gakugoto (koto for gagaku) were provided in the past; however, the use of zokuso (non-gagaku koto) became popular after it was allowed to be used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Music for stringed instruments was originally written for both the six-stringed wagon and the thirteen-stringed gakugoto but since the use of zokuso (common koto) was permitted, the koto has become more popular.</e>
<cmt>Reorded for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Music for stringed instruments was originally written for both the six-stringed wagon and the thirteen-stringed gakugoto but since the use of zokuso (common koto) was permitted, the koto has become more popular.</e>
<cmt>和琴の定訳がありますが、ここでの訳のほうが楽琴と対比できて適切なので変更していません。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="30">
<j>装束</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Costumes</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Costumes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Costumes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>装束は十二単を下地に製作された、昭和15年に制定されたものが正式とされる（あこめ装束又は本装束と呼称する）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The costume that was established in 1940 based on twelve-layered ceremonial kimono is regarded as the formal costume for Urayasu no mai; the costume is called akome shozoku or honshozoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The costume that was established in 1940 based on twelve-layered ceremonial kimono is regarded as the official costume for Urayasu no mai and is called akome shozoku or honshozoku.</e>
<cmt>&quot;formal&quot;→&quot;official&quot;&quot;; the costume&quot;→&quot;and&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The costume that was established in 1940 based on twelve-layered ceremonial kimono is regarded as the official costume for Urayasu no mai and is called akome shozoku or honshozoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>単、衵（あこめ）、小忌衣（おみごろも）、裳（も）、緋袴で構成され、扇舞で用いる檜扇を採物として手に取る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The costume consists of hitoe (one layer), akome (layer of clothing worn by nobles (worn beneath the robe but over the undergarments)), omigoromo (ceremonial jacket used for the Shinto rites at the Imperial Court since the reign of Emperor Saga), mo (ancient skirt), and hinohakama/hibakama (red priestless pants), with a hi-ogi (wooden fan) in the dancer&apos;s hand as a symbolic object, which is used in a fan dance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The costume consists of hitoe (kimono with no lining), akome (layer of clothing worn by nobles beneath the robe but over the undergarments), omigoromo (ceremonial jacket used for Shinto rites at the Imperial Court), mo (ancient skirt), and scarlet hinohakama/hibakama (worn over the kimono), with a symbolic hi-ogi (wooden fan) held by the dancer, which is used in the fan dance.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, accuracyDeleted &quot;since the reign of Emperor Saga&quot; -probably meaningless for most English speakers</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The costume consists of hitoe (kimono with no lining), akome (inner wear), omigoromo (ceremonial jacket used for Shinto rites at the Imperial Court), mo (long pleated skirts), and hinohakama/hibakama (scarlet Japanese pants for men), with a symbolic hi-ogi (wooden fan) held by the dancer, which is used in the fan dance.</e>
<cmt>衵、裳、緋袴の定訳緋袴は定訳で「for men」となっていますが、そのまま入れてあります。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>特に青摺の小忌衣を着用する点がこの舞が神祇祭祀に特化されたものであることを物語っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The blue color of omigoromo indicates that the dance is specifically performed forcereminial purpose.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The blue color of the omigoromo indicates that the dance is specifically performed for ceremonial purposes.</e>
<cmt>ArticleSpellingGrammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The blue color of the omigoromo indicates that the dance is specifically performed for ceremonial purposes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="34">
<j>鈴舞で用いる鈴は舞の途中で檜扇と持ち替える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The dancers switch wooden fan over to bells in the bell dance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The dancers swap the wooden fan for bells during the bell dance.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The dancers swap the wooden fan for bells during the dance.</e>
<cmt>bell dance→dance</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>また、額には挿頭若しくは天冠を著け、髪は後ろで束ねて絵元結（熨斗紙・水引・丈長を組み合わせた装飾）を結ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The dancers wear kazashi (flowers worn in one&apos;s hair in shrine ritual) or tenkan (white cloth worn in the ghost&apos;s head) on her forehead, with her hair tied in the back in Emotoyui style (combination of noshigami, mizuhiki and takenaga).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The dancers wear flowers in their hair or a tenkan (a kind of headband) round their forehead, with their hair tied in the back in a style known as Emotoyui.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarityDeleted the final brackets - the Japanese terms are not useful (or necessary) for English speakers and explaining them would take up lots of space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The dancers wear flowers in their hair or a tenkan (golden crown) on their head, with their hair tied in the back in a style known as Emotoyui.</e>
<cmt>天冠の定訳round their forehead→on their head</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>髪が短い場合は髢（かもじ）を付ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Short hair is decorated with kamoji, or hairpiece.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If the dancers have short hair, they wear a wig.</e>
<cmt>Revised for accuracy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If the dancers have short hair, they wear a wig.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="37">
<j>略装束</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Demitoilet</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Informal costume</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Informal costume</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>装束については千早と緋袴を略の装束としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chihaya (female priest coat) and hibakama are the demitoilet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The informal costume consists of chihaya (female priest coat) and hibakama.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The informal costume consists of chihaya (Japanese coat for female priests) and hibakama.</e>
<cmt>千早の定訳</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>千早の青摺模様は松鶴をあしらったものが多いが、浦安の舞の略装束として菊の青摺模様をあしらった「浦安柄」と称する千早も用意されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The coat has blue decorative pattern, called aozuri, which is typically a pattern of pines and cranes, but also a pattern chrysanthemum, called Urayasu pattern, is available as a demitoilet of Urayasu no mai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The coat has a blue pattern, called aozuri, usually of pines and cranes, but there is also a chrysanthemum pattern, called a Urayasu pattern, for use in the Urayasu no mai.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarityArticleWord order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The coat has a blue pattern, called aozuri, usually of pines and cranes, but there is also a chrysanthemum pattern, called a &apos;Urayasu pattern&apos;, for use in the Urayasu no mai.</e>
<cmt>Urayasu pattern→&apos;Urayasu pattern&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>神社によっては檜扇の代りに俗楽の舞踊の舞扇に檜扇と同様の飾り紐を付けたもので舞う場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In some shrines, a Mai-ogi (a type of fan used for Japanese dance) for wordly music is fitted with decorative cords, which look like hi-ogi, wooden fan, is used instead of using hi-ogi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In some shrines, instead of using a hi-ogi fan, a mai-ogi fan, used for dancing to zokugaku (vulgar or common music, as opposed to gagaku court music) is decorated with cords to look like a hi-ogi fan.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In some shrines, instead of using a hi-ogi fan, a mai-ogi fan, used for dancing to zokugaku (vulgar or common music, as opposed to gagaku court music) is decorated with cords to look like a hi-ogi fan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="41">
<j>尚、合繊の略装束は比較的安価で、比較的軽量であること、子供用も用意されてることから年少者が舞う場合は殆どが略装束となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, synthetic costumes are relatively inexpensive and lightweight, and child size is available; therefore, most childrendancers wear demitoilet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, synthetic costumes being relatively inexpensive, lightweight, and available in children&apos;s sizes, the informal costume is worn by most young dancers.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, synthetic costumes being relatively inexpensive, lightweight, and available in children&apos;s sizes, the informal costume is worn by most young dancers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>鈴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bells</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bells</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bells</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="43">
<j>鈴については鉾鈴を正式とし、神楽鈴を代用してもよい事となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hoko-suzu, which consists of lond-handled spear with bells, is the official bells; it may be substituted with kagura-suzu, a bell for kagura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although officially the hoko-suzu, a spear with bells attached, is used, it may be substituted for kagura-suzu, or kagura bells.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity - although 鉾 is usually a pike-like weapon, I think it&apos;s more like a dagger in this caseArticle</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although officially the hoko-suzu, a dagger with bells attached, is used, it may be substituted for kagura-suzu, or kagura bells.</e>
<cmt>写真を見たところ、dagger に鈴が付いたようなものです。daggerと訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="44">
<j>鉾鈴は柄に20cm程の鉾と鍔が付けられ、鍔の部位に6個、又は8個の鈴が付けられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The hoko-suzu is fitted with about 20cm of baton and guard on the handle, and 6 or 8 bells are attached to the guard.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The hoko-suzu has a 20cm blade and a guard attached to the handle, and 6 or 8 bells attached to the guard.</e>
<cmt>Revised for accuracy, clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The hoko-suzu has a 20cm blade and a guard attached to the handle, and 6 or 8 bells attached to the guard.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>これは三種の神器を模したものであり、鉾は天叢雲剣、鍔は八咫鏡、鈴は八尺瓊勾玉とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This style of hoko-suzu represesnts the three sacred imperial treasures in which the baton is the Tsurugi sword of Ama no Murakumo, guard is the Yata no Kagami Mirror, and bells are Yasakani no Magatama (comma shaped jewel).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The hoko-suzu symbolizes the three sacred imperial treasures with the blade representing the Tsurugi sword of Ama no Murakumo, the guard the Yata no Kagami Mirror, and the bells the Yasakani no Magatama jewel.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarityArticles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The hoko-suzu symbolizes the three sacred imperial treasures with the blade representing the Tsurugi sword of Ama no Murakumo, the guard the Yata no Kagami Mirror, and the bells the Yasakani no Magatama jewel.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="46">
<j>神楽鈴は輪が3つ付けられ、上から3個、5個、7個の鈴が付けられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kagura-suzu is fitted with three rings, each attached with three, five, and seven bells from the top.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kagura-suzu is fitted with three rings, the top ring having three bells, the middle ring five bells and the bottom ring seven bells.</e>
<cmt>Revised for accuracy, clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kagura-suzu is fitted with three rings, the top ring having three bells, the middle ring five bells and the bottom ring seven bells.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>これは稲穂を模したものであり、五穀豊穣の祈願の意味がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This represents the rice ear, praying for the productiveness of grain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This represents an ear of rice, and is meant to pray for an abundant harvest.</e>
<cmt>ArticleWord order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This represents an ear of rice, and is meant to pray for an abundant harvest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="48">
<j>どちらの鈴にも柄の端には5尺～6尺の五色の鈴緒が付けられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Each bell is attached with suzuo,1.5 to 1.8 meters long five color straps.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Each bell has five 1.5 to 1.8 meter long colored staps attached to it.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Each bell has five 1.5 to 1.8 meter long colored straps attached to it.</e>
<cmt>staps→straps</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="49">
<j>化粧について</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Makeup</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Makeup</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Makeup</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>舞姫の化粧については特に規程は無く、一般的に女性が普通に施す程度である場合が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is no specific rules for the female dancer&apos;s makeup; the makeup often does not stand out, about the same as everyday makeup.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are no specific rules for the dancers&apos; makeup; it is often about the same as most women wear everday.</e>
<cmt>GrammarRevised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are no specific rules for the dancers&apos; makeup; it is often about the same as most women wear everday.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>各神社や地域ごとによって、顔におしろい（おしろい）を塗ったり、目元を強調したりといった特色ある例が散見される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in some shrines or in some regions, characteristic makeup is found: such as face powder, or emphasized eye makeup.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in some shrines and regions, characteristic makeup such as white face powder or heavy eye makeup is found.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, accuracy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in some shrines and regions, characteristic makeup such as white face powder or heavy eye makeup is found.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="52">
<j>備考</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other</e>
<cmt>Deleted &apos;s&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>本装束の浦安の舞が見られる祭祀等</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ceremonies with Urayasu no mai in which the formal costumes are worn.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ceremonies where Urayasu no mai is performed in formal formal costumes.</e>
<cmt>Revised to sound more natural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ceremonies where Urayasu no mai is performed in formal costumes.</e>
<cmt>formal formal→formal</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="53">
<j>鑑賞、撮影可能なもの　※は氏子等の少女が奉仕</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dances that are open to public, and filming is allowed. * indicates the dance is performed by girls including daughters of shrine parishioners.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dances that are open to the public, and filming is allowed. * indicates the dance is performed by girls including daughters of shrine parishioners.</e>
<cmt>Article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dances that are open to the public, and filming is allowed; * indicates the dance is performed by girls including daughters of shrine parishioners.</e>
<cmt>二文を一文にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="54">
<j>北海道</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hokkaido Region</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hokkaido Region</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hokkaido</e>
<cmt>Region を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="55">
<j>6月14～15日：例祭 - 北海道神宮（札幌市中央区 (札幌市)）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Annual celebration: June 14 to 15 in Hokkaido-jingu Shrine, Chuo Ward, Sapporo City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Annual celebration: June 14 to 15, Hokkaido-jingu Shrine, Chuo Ward, Sapporo City.</e>
<cmt>Preposition</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">June 14 to 15: Annual festival held at Hokkaido-jingu Shrine, Chuo Ward, Sapporo City</e>
<cmt>以降、日付：説明　に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="56">
<j>東北</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tohoku Region</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tohoku Region</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tohoku</e>
<cmt>region 削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="57">
<j>9月14～16日：白河提灯まつり - 鹿嶋神社（白河市、2年に1度、次回は2009年）※</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shirakawa Chochin Matsuri (Lantern Festival in Shirakawa) in Kashima-jinja Shrine, in Shirakawa City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shirakawa Chochin Matsuri (Lantern Festival in Shirakawa), Kashima-jinja Shrine, Shirakawa City.</e>
<cmt>Preposition</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September 14 to 16: Shirakawa Chochin Matsuri (Shirakawa Lantern Festival) held at Kashima-jinja Shrine, Shirakawa City (every two years, next one in 2009)</e>
<cmt>「２年に一度、次回は２００９年」追記。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="58">
<j>北関東</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Northern Kanto Region</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Northern Kanto Region</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Northern Kanto</e>
<cmt>region 削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="59">
<j>4月19日、10月19日：例大祭 - 倉賀野神社（高崎市）※</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Regular-basis festival: April 19 and October 19 at Kuragano-jinja Shrine in Takasaki City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regular-basis festival: April 19 and October 19, Kuragano-jinja Shrine, Takasaki City.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Regular-basis&quot;→&quot;Annual&quot;Prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 19 and October 19: Annual festival held at Kuragano-jinja Shrine, Takasaki City</e>
<cmt>日付：説明</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>4月25日、10月25日：例大祭 - 唐沢山神社（佐野市）※</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Regular-basis festival: April 25 and October 25 at Karasawayama-jinja Shrine in Sano City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regular-basis festival: April 25 and October 25, Karasawayama-jinja Shrine, Sano City.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Regular-basis&quot;→&quot;Annual&quot;Prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 25 and October 25: Annual festival held at Karasawayama-jinja Shrine, Sano City</e>
<cmt>日付：説明</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>5月上旬：雅楽鑑賞の夕べ - 群馬県護国神社（高崎市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gagaku (Japanese traditional music and dance) Evening Concert: Early May at Gokoku-jinja Shrine in Takasaki City in Gunma Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gagaku (Japanese traditional music and dance) Evening Concert: Early May, Gokoku-jinja Shrine, Takasaki City, Gunma Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>Prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Early May: Gagaku (Japanese traditional music and dance) Evening Concert held at Gokoku-jinja Shrine, Takasaki City, Gunma Prefecture</e>
<cmt>日付：説明</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>10月上旬：雅楽秋の演奏会 - 貫前神社（富岡市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gagaku Autumn Concert: Early October at Nukisaki-jinja Shrine in Tomioka City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gagaku Autumn Concert: Early October, Nukisaki-jinja Shrine, Tomioka City.</e>
<cmt>Prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Early October: Gagaku Autumn Concert held at Nukisaki-jinja Shrine, Tomioka City</e>
<cmt>日付：説明</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>10月上旬：例大祭 - 八幡神社（深谷市）※（単、衵は省略）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Regular-basis festival: Early October at Yahata-jinja Shrine in Fukaya City. *Costumes of Hitoe and akome are not worn.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Annual festival: Early October, Yahata-jinja Shrine, Fukaya City. *Hitoe and akome are not worn.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Regular-basis&quot;→&quot;Annual&quot;PrepositionsDeleted &quot;Costumes of&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Early October: Annual festival held at Yahata-jinja Shrine, Fukaya City *(Hitoe and akome are not worn.)</e>
<cmt>※の後に括弧を加えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="64">
<j>10月下旬：大杉祭 - 大杉神社（稲敷市）※</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Osugi Matsuri Festival: Early October at Osugi-jinja Shrine in Inashiki City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Osugi Matsuri Festival: Early October, Osugi-jinja Shrine, Inashiki City.</e>
<cmt>Prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Early October: Osugi Matsuri Festival held at Osugi-jinja Shrine, Inashiki City</e>
<cmt>日付：説明</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>11月中旬：舞楽祭 - 笠間稲荷神社（笠間市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bugaku Festival: Early November at Kasamainari-jinja Shrine in Kasama City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bugaku Festival: Early November, Kasamainari-jinja Shrine, Kasama City.</e>
<cmt>Prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mid-November: Bugaku Festival held at Kasamainari-jinja Shrine, Kasama City</e>
<cmt>Early→mid</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="66">
<j>南関東</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Southern Kanto Region</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Southern Kanto Region</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Southern Kanto</e>
<cmt>region 削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="67">
<j>5月15日：神田祭 - 神田神社（千代田区）（例大祭は毎年この日に固定）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanda Matsuri Festival: May 15 at Kanda-jinja Shrine in Chiyoda Ward, Tokyo. (The festival is held every year on the same day.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanda Matsuri Festival: May 15, Kanda-jinja Shrine, Chiyoda Ward, Tokyo (the festival is held every year on the same day).</e>
<cmt>PrepositionsPunctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">May 15: Kanda Matsuri Festival held at Kanda-jinja Shrine, Chiyoda Ward, Tokyo (the Grand Festival is held every year on the same day.)</e>
<cmt>the festival→the Grand Festival</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>7月上旬：雅楽の夕べ - 大宮八幡宮 (杉並区)（杉並区）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gagaku Evening Concert: Early July, Omiya Hachimangu Shrine in Suginami Ward, Tokyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gagaku Evening Concert: Early July, Omiya Hachimangu Shrine, Suginami Ward, Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>Prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Early July: Gagaku Evening Concert held at Omiya Hachiman-gu Shrine, Suginami Ward, Tokyo</e>
<cmt>Hachimangu→Hachiman-gu</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>8月中旬：例祭 - 寒川神社 (千葉市)（千葉市中央区 (千葉市)）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Regular-basis festival: Early August at Samukawa-jinja Shrine in Chuo Ward, Chiba City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Annual festival: Early August, Samukawa-jinja Shrine, Chuo Ward, Chiba City.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Regular-basis&quot;→&quot;Annual&quot;Prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mid-August: Annual festival held at Samukawa-jinja Shrine, Chuo Ward, Chiba City</e>
<cmt>Early→Mid</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>9月13日：十二社はだか祭り - 玉前神社（一宮町）※</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Junisha Hadaka Matsuri (twelve shrines&apos; Festival of naked men): September 13 at Tamasaki-jinja Shrine in Ichinomiya Town.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Junisha Hadaka Matsuri (twelve shrines&apos; Festival of naked men): September 13, Tamasaki-jinja Shrine, Ichinomiya Town.</e>
<cmt>Prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September 13: Junisha Hadaka Matsuri (twelve shrines&apos; Festival of naked men) held at Tamasaki-jinja Shrine, Ichinomiya Town</e>
<cmt>日付：説明</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>9月下旬：秋季大祭 - 香取護国神社（香取市）（香取神宮の巫女が奉納）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Autumn Grand Festival: Late September at Katori Gokoku-jinja Shrine in Katori City. (Offering made by priestless dancers of Katori-jing Shrine)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Autumn Grand Festival: Late September, Katori Gokoku-jinja Shrine, Katori City (performed by shrine maidens from Katori-jingu Shrine)</e>
<cmt>PrepositionsRevised section in brackets</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Late September: Autumn Grand Festival held at Katori Gokoku-jinja Shrine, Katori City (performed by shrine maidens from Katori-jingu Shrine)</e>
<cmt>日付：説明</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>11月1日：例大祭 - 大宮神社（市原市）※</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Regular-basis festival: November 1 at Omiya-jinja Shrine in Ichihara City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Annual festival: November 1, Omiya-jinja Shrine, Ichihara City.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Regular-basis&quot;→&quot;Annual&quot;Prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November 1: Annual festival held at Omiya-jinja Shrine, Ichihara City</e>
<cmt>日付：説明</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>12月頃：神楽舞公演 - 明治神宮（渋谷区、2年に1度、入場有料だが撮影可能）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kagura-mai performance: Around December at Meiji-jingu Shrine in Shibuya Ward, Tokyo. (The performance is held every two years, with admission fees, filming is allowed)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kagura-mai performance: Around December, Meiji-jingu Shrine, Shibuya Ward, Tokyo. (The performance is held every two years, with admission fees, filming is allowed)</e>
<cmt>Prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around December: Kagura-mai performance held at Meiji-jingu Shrine, Shibuya Ward, Tokyo. (The performance is held every two years, with admission fees, filming is allowed)</e>
<cmt>日付：説明</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="74">
<j>甲信越</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koshinetsu Region</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koshinetsu Region</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koshinetsu</e>
<cmt>region 削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="75">
<j>東海</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokai Region</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokai Region</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokai</e>
<cmt>region 削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="76">
<j>元旦：元旦祭 - 富士山本宮浅間大社（富士宮市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">New Year&apos;s Festival: January 1 at Fujisan Hongu Sengentaisha Shrine in Fujinomiya City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">New Year&apos;s Festival: January 1, Fujisan Hongu Sengentaisha Shrine, Fujinomiya City.</e>
<cmt>Prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 1: New Year&apos;s Festival held at Fujisan Hongu Sengen-taisha Shrine, Fujinomiya City</e>
<cmt>Sengentaisha→Sengen-taisha</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>2月10～11日：鬼祭 - 安久美神戸神明社（豊橋市）※(厚化粧)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oni matsuri (ogre festival): February 10 and 11 in Akumikanbe shinmeisha Shrine in Toyohashi City. *thick makeup</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oni matsuri (ogre festival): February 10 and 11, Akumikanbe shinmeisha Shrine, Toyohashi City. *thick makeup</e>
<cmt>Prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 10 and 11: Oni matsuri (ogre festival) held at Akumikanbe shinmeisha Shrine, Toyohashi City *thick makeup</e>
<cmt>日付：説明</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>8月15～16日：三島夏祭り - 三嶋大社（三島市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mishima Natsu Matsuri (Mishima Summer Festival): August 15 and 16 at Mishima Taisha in Mishima City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mishima Natsu Matsuri (Mishima Summer Festival): August 15 and 16, Mishima Taisha Shrine, Mishima City.</e>
<cmt>PrepositionsAdded &quot;shrine&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August 15 and 16: Mishima Natsu Matsuri (Mishima Summer Festival) held at Mishima Taisha Shrine, Mishima City</e>
<cmt>日付：説明</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>11月4日：例祭 - 富士山本宮浅間大社（富士宮市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Regular-basis festival:November 4 at Fujisan Hongu Sengentaisha Shrine in Fujinomiya City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Annual festival: November 4, Fujisan Hongu Sengentaisha Shrine, Fujinomiya City.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Regular-basis&quot;→&quot;Annual&quot;SpacePrepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November 4: Annual festival held at Fujisan Hongu Sengen-taisha Shrine, Fujinomiya City</e>
<cmt>Sengentaisha→Sengen-taisha</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="80">
<j>北陸</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hokuriku Region</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hokuriku Region</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hokuriku</e>
<cmt>region 削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="81">
<j>9月13日：例祭 - 高瀬神社（南砺市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Regular-basis festival: September 13 at Takase-jinja Shrine in Nanto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Annual festival: September 13, Takase-jinja Shrine, Nanto City.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Regular-basis&quot;→&quot;Annual&quot;Prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September: Annual festival held at Takase-jinja Shrine, Nanto City</e>
<cmt>日付：説明</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="82">
<j>京都府</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="83">
<j>元旦：元旦祭 - 平安神宮（京都市東山区）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">New Year&apos;s Festival: January 1 at Heian-jingu Shrine in Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">New Year&apos;s Festival: January 1, Heian-jingu Shrine, Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>Prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 1: New Year&apos;s Festival held at Heian-jingu Shrine, Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City</e>
<cmt>日付：説明</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="84">
<j>その他の近畿地方</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinki Region</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kinki Region</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other Kinki</e>
<cmt>region削除Other 追記。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="85">
<j>3月上旬：てんま天神梅まつり - 大阪天満宮（大阪市北区 (大阪市)）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tenma Tenjin Plum Festival: Early March at Osaka Tenmangu Shrine in Kita Ward, Osaka City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tenma Tenjin Plum Festival: Early March, Osaka Tenmangu Shrine, Kita Ward, Osaka City.</e>
<cmt>Prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Early March: Tenma Tenjin Plum Festival held at Osaka Tenman-gu Shrine, Kita Ward, Osaka City</e>
<cmt>Tenmangu→Tenman-gu</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>4月4日：神楽祭 - 佐備神社（富田林市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kagura Matsuri: April 4 at Sabi-jinja Shrine in Tondabayashi City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kagura Matsuri: April 4, Sabi-jinja Shrine, Tondabayashi City.</e>
<cmt>Prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 4: Kagura Matsuri Festival held at Sabi-jinja Shrine, Tondabayashi City</e>
<cmt>Festival 追記</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>9月下旬：雅楽の夕べ - 生田神社（神戸市中央区 (神戸市)）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gagaku Evening Concert: Late September at Ikuta-jinja Shrine in Chuo Ward, Kobe City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gagaku Evening Concert: Late September, Ikuta-jinja Shrine, Chuo Ward, Kobe City.</e>
<cmt>Prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Late September: Gagaku Evening Concert held at Ikuta-jinja Shrine, Chuo Ward, Kobe City</e>
<cmt>日付：説明</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>10月20日：秋季大祭 - 大阪護国神社（大阪市住之江区）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Autumn Festival: October 20 at Osaka Gokoku-jinja Shrine in Suminoe Ward, Osaka City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Autumn Festival: October 20, Osaka Gokoku-jinja Shrine, Suminoe Ward, Osaka City.</e>
<cmt>Prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 20: Autumn Grand Festival held at Osaka Gokoku-jinja Shrine, Suminoe Ward, Osaka City</e>
<cmt>Grand 追記</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="89">
<j>中国</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chugoku Region</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chugoku Region</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chugoku</e>
<cmt>region 削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="90">
<j>5月下旬：万灯みたま祭り - 広島護国神社（広島市中区 (広島市)）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Banto Mitama Matsuri (Festival of Lanterns of spirits): Late May at Hiroshima Gokoku Shrine in Naka Ward, Hiroshima City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Banto Mitama Matsuri (Festival of Lanterns of spirits): Late May at Hiroshima Gokoku Shrine in Naka Ward, Hiroshima City.</e>
<cmt>Prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Late May: Banto Mitama Matsuri (Festival of Lanterns of spirits) held at Hiroshima Gokoku-jinja Shrine in Naka Ward, Hiroshima City</e>
<cmt>jinja 追記</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>9月中旬：浦安の舞 - 美保神社（松江市）※</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Urayasu no mai: Middle September at Miho-jinja Shrine in Matsue City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Urayasu no mai: Middle September at Miho-jinja Shrine in Matsue City.</e>
<cmt>Prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mid-September: Urayasu no mai held at Miho-jinja Shrine in Matsue City</e>
<cmt>日付：説明</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="92">
<j>四国</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shikoku Region</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shikoku Region</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shikoku</e>
<cmt>region 削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="93">
<j>1月10日：初十日祭 - 金刀比羅宮（琴平町）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hatsu Toka matsuri (Festival of January 10th): January 10 at Kotohiragu Shrine in Kotohira Town.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hatsu Toka matsuri (Festival of January 10th): January 10, Kotohiragu Shrine, Kotohira Town.</e>
<cmt>Prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 10: Hatsu Toka matsuri (Festival of January 10th) held at Kotohiragu Shrine, Kotohira Town</e>
<cmt>日付：説明</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>9月中旬：秋季例大祭 - 大野原八幡神社（観音寺市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Annual autumn festival: Middle September at Onohara Hachiman-jinja Shrine in Kannonji City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Annual autumn festival: Middle September, Onohara Hachiman-jinja Shrine, Kannonji City.</e>
<cmt>Prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mid-September: Annual autumn festival held at Onohara Hachiman-jinja Shrine, Kannonji City</e>
<cmt>Middle→-mid</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>9月下旬：観月神楽の夕べ - 野村三嶋神社（西予市）※</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mizuki (moon-viewing) Kagura (ancient Shinto music and dancing) Night: Middle September at Mishima-jinja Shrine of Nomura, Seiyo City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mizuki (moon-viewing) Kagura (ancient Shinto music and dancing) Night: Middle September, Mishima-jinja Shrine, Nomura, Seiyo City.</e>
<cmt>Prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Late September: Mizuki (moon-viewing) Kagura Night held at Mishima-jinja Shrine, Nomura, Seiyo City</e>
<cmt>Middle→Late神楽の説明、既出のため削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="96">
<j>九州</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyushu Region</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyushu Region</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyushu</e>
<cmt>region 削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="25">
<sen id="97">
<j>7月10日：博多祇園山笠 - 櫛田神社 (福岡市)（福岡市博多区）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hakata Gion Yamagasa summer festival: July 10 at Kushida-jinja Shrine in Hakata Ward, Fukuoka City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hakata Gion Yamagasa summer festival: July 10, Kushida-jinja Shrine, Hakata Ward, Fukuoka City.</e>
<cmt>Prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">July 10: Hakata Gion Yamagasa summer festival held at Kushida-jinja Shrine, Hakata Ward, Fukuoka City</e>
<cmt>日付：説明</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>9月25日：千灯明 - 太宰府天満宮（太宰府市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sentomyo (Ceremony of a thousand candles): September 25 at Dazaifu Temmangu Shrine in Dazaifu City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sentomyo (Ceremony of a thousand candles): September 25, Dazaifu Temmangu Shrine, Dazaifu City.</e>
<cmt>Prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sentomyo (Ceremony of a thousand candles): September 25, Dazaifu Temmangu Shrine, Dazaifu City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="26">
<sen id="99">
<j>装束に関して</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">About the costumes:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">About the costumes</e>
<cmt>Deleted colon</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">About the costumes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>本装束は高額であり、転用も利かないため経済的な側面でこれを調達できる神社は限られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Authentic costumes are expensive and cannot be used for occasions other than Urayasu no mai; consequently, only few shrines can afford them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Authentic costumes are expensive and can only be used for the Urayasu no mai; consequently, only a few shrines can afford them.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Authentic costumes are expensive and can only be used for the Urayasu no mai; consequently, only a few shrines can afford them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>又、殆どが成人女性用に仕立てられる為、装束の重量や小忌衣や裳の長さの点で後述の略装束よりも舞の難易度（手振り・裳の捌き方など）が高くなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, majority of the authentic costumes are made for female adult sizes; the weight of the whole costume and the lengths of the jacket and skirt make performance more challenging (e.g., hand movement and the way to move neatly with the skirt) compared to the dance with demitoilet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, the majority of authentic costumes are made for female adult sizes, the weight of the whole costume and the lengths of the jacket and skirt make performance more challenging (e.g., hand movements and moving smoothly with the skirt) than with informal costumes.</e>
<cmt>ArticlesRevised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, the majority of authentic costumes are made for female adult sizes, the weight of the whole costume and the lengths of the jacket and skirt make performance more challenging (e.g., hand movements and moving smoothly with the skirt) than with informal costumes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>その為、年少者が本装束を着用して舞うのは希少な例といえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this reason, it is very rare for younger dancers to perform in authentic costumes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this reason, it is very rare for younger dancers to perform in authentic costumes.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For this reason, it is very rare for younger dancers to perform in authentic costumes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kafuka1964(id:105407), 神祇官(id:99217), Nnh(id:474), A. J. Kuonji(id:68661), Knua(id:66861), Wikindexan(id:10060), Aipiee(id:30747), Mikomaid(id:56139), Dream100(id:41924), 弥(id:61590), Jade0416(id:104181), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>