<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>笙</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>笙（しょう）とは、雅楽などで使う管楽器の1つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sho is a type of wind instrument used in Gagaku (Court music in Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sho is a type of wind instrument used in gagaku (Court music in Japan).</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;The&quot;&quot;Gagaku&quot; &gt; &quot;gagaku</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sho is a type of wind instrument used in gagaku (Court music in Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>フリーリード (楽器)類に属する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It belongs to type of free reed (instrument).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a free reed musical instrument.</e>
<cmt>Poor translation. Completely retranslated.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a free reed musical instrument.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>同様の楽器が東アジア各地に見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Similar instruments can be seen in many places in Eastern Asia.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Similar instruments can be seen in many places in Eastern Asia.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Similar instruments can be seen in many places in Eastern Asia.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>中国名・ション (enSheng (instrument))。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chinese name is Sheng (instrument).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is called the &apos;sheng&apos; in Chinese.</e>
<cmt>Poor translation. Completely retranslated.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is called the &apos;sheng&apos; in Chinese.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>日本には奈良時代ごろに雅楽とともに伝わってきたと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that it has been introduced to Japan in around the Nara period, along with Gagaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is thought to have been introduced to Japan along with gagaku around the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>Reworded to read more naturally.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is thought to have been introduced to Japan along with gagaku around the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>雅楽で用いられる笙は、その形を翼を立てて休んでいる鳳凰に見立てられ、鳳笙（ほうしょう）とも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The shape of sho used in Gagaku is liken to hoo (a mythological sacred bird in Chinese lore, a phoenix) resting with wing holding up, and is also is called hosho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shape of sho used in gagaku is resembles a Chinese phoenix (hoo) resting with its wings aloft and for this reason is also called the &apos;hosho.</e>
<cmt>Reworded to read more professionally.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The shape of sho used in gagaku is resembles a Chinese phoenix (hoo) resting with its wings aloft and for this reason is also called the &apos;hosho.&apos;</e>
<cmt>用語を読みやすくするため&apos; &apos;補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>匏（ふくべ）と呼ばれる部分の上に17本の細い竹管を円形に配置している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">17 thin bamboo pipes are placed in a circle on a part called fukube.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">17 thin bamboo pipes are arranged in a circle on a part known as the &apos;fukube.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;placed&quot; &gt; &quot;arranged&quot;&quot;called&quot; &gt; &quot;known as&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">17 thin bamboo pipes are arranged in a circle on a part known as the &apos;fukube.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>竹管に空けられた指穴を押さえ、匏の横側に空けられた吹口より息を吸ったり吐いたりして、17本のうち15本の竹菅の下部に付けられた金属製の簧（した：リード (楽器)）を振動させて音を出す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A player should cover finger holes on these bamboo pipes and should inhale or exhale his or her breath into a mouthpiece attached to the side of the fukube, and the instrument produces sound from the vibration of metal shita (reeds) which are attached to the bottom of 15 out of 17 pipes.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The player covers the finger holes along the bamboo pipes, inhales or exhales into the mouthpiece attached to the side of the fukube and the instrument produces a sound from the vibration of metal shita (reeds) which are attached to the bottom of 15 of the 17 pipes.</e>
<cmt>Slightly reworded to read naturally.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The player covers the finger holes along the bamboo pipes, inhales or exhales into the mouthpiece attached to the side of the fukube and the instrument produces a sound from the vibration of metal shita (reeds) which are attached to the bottom of 15 of the 17 pipes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>音程は簧の固有振動によって決定し、竹管で共鳴させて発音する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The key is decided by shita&apos;s peculiar vibration, and the sound is made by resonating in the bamboo tubes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The key is determined by the natural oscillation of the shita, and the sound is created by resonating in the bamboo tubes.</e>
<cmt>&quot;decided by shita&apos;s peculiar vibration&quot; &gt; &quot;determined by the natural oscillation of the shita&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The key is determined by the natural oscillation of the shita, and the sound is created by resonating in the bamboo tubes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>オルガンのリード管と同じ原理である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is the same principle with reed pipe of an organ.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is the same principle as the reed pipe of an organ.</e>
<cmt>&quot;It&quot; &gt; &quot;This&quot;&quot;with&quot; &gt; &quot;as the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is the same principle as the reed pipe of an organ.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>いくつかの竹管には屏上（びょうじょう）と呼ばれる長方形の穴があり、共鳴管としての管長は全長ではなくこの穴で決まる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are rectangular holes called byojo on several bamboo tubes, and the length as resonant tube is decided by location of this hole, not the whole length of the bamboo tubes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are rectangular holes called byojo on several of the bamboo tubes, and their lengths as resonant tubes are determined by the locations of this holes, not by the entire length of the bamboo tubes.</e>
<cmt>Reworded to read more professionally.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are rectangular holes called byojo on several of the bamboo tubes, and their lengths as resonant tubes are determined by the locations of this holes, not by the entire length of the bamboo tubes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>そのため見かけの竹管の長さと音程の並びは一致しない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of that, the length of the bamboo tubes in appearance and the keys do not match up.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is because of this that the apparent lengths of the bamboo tubes do not match their keys.</e>
<cmt>Reworded to read more professionally.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is because of this that the apparent lengths of the bamboo tubes do not match their keys.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>屏上は表の場合と裏の場合があるが、表の場合は装飾が施されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Byojo are put on both front side and back side, and the byojo in front side are decorated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Byojo can be on either the front or back of the instrument but decorated when on the front.</e>
<cmt>Reworded to read more professionally.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Byojo can be on either the front or back of the instrument but decorated when on the front.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>指穴を押さえていない管で音が出ないのは、共鳴しない位置に指穴が開けられているためである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reason a sound doesn&apos;t come out of a tube where finger hole is not closed is because that the finger hole is opened at a location where resonance is not made.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reason why no sound comes out of a tube where the finger hole has not been covered is because the finger holes are opened at locations where there is no resonance.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten so that it makes sense.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reason why no sound comes out of a tube where the finger hole has not been covered is because the finger holes are opened at locations where there is no resonance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="16">
<j>ハーモニカと異なり、吸っても吹いても同じ音が出せるので、他の管楽器のような息継ぎが不要であり、同じ音をずっと鳴らし続けることも出来る（呼吸を替える時に瞬間的に音量が低下するのみ）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As inhaling and exhaling does not make any difference in sound unlike a harmonica, the player does not need to stop to take a breath as to play another wind instrument, and this allows a long period of uninterrupted play of the same sound (the volume of the sound is briefly lowered when the player switches his or her breath from inhaling to exhaling and vice versa).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unlike with a harmonica, inhaling or exhaling does not make any difference to the sound produced, and the player does not need to stop to take breaths as with another wind instruments, allowing a long period of uninterrupted play of the same sound (the volume of the sound is briefly lowered when the player switches his or her breath from inhaling to exhaling and vice versa).</e>
<cmt>Slightly reworded to read naturally.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unlike with a harmonica, inhaling or exhaling does not make any difference to the sound produced, and the player does not need to stop to take breaths as with another wind instruments, allowing a long period of uninterrupted play of the same sound (the volume of the sound is briefly lowered when the player switches his or her breath from inhaling to exhaling and vice versa).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>押さえる穴の組み合わせを変えることで11種類の合竹（あいたけ）と呼ばれる和音を出すことができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By changing the combination of hole to be closed, eleven types of chords called aitake can be made.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By changing the combination of holes covered, eleven chords called aitake can be produced.</e>
<cmt>Reworded to read more professionally.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By changing the combination of holes covered, eleven chords called aitake can be produced.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>通常は基本の合竹による奏法が中心であるが、調子、音取、催馬楽、朗詠では一竹（いっちく：単音で旋律を奏すること）や特殊な合竹も用いる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Normally it is performed mainly with aitake, but in choshi, netori (tuning in Japanese instruments), Saibara (genre of Heian period Japanese court music), and Roei recitation, icchiku (playing melody with single sound) and special aitake are also used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The instrument is usually played using the basic aitake but icchiku (playing melody with single sound) and special aitake are used in choshi, netori, saibara and roei performances.</e>
<cmt>Completely retranslated in order to make sense.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The instrument is usually played using the basic aitake but icchiku (playing melody with single sound) and special aitake are used in choshi, netori, saibara and roei performances.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="19">
<j>その音色は天から差し込む光を表すといわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The tone is said to express the light shining down from the sky.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The tone is said to express the light shining down from the sky.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The tone is said to express the light shining down from the sky.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="20">
<j>構造上、呼気によって内部が結露しやすく、そのまま演奏し続けると簧に水滴が付いて音高が狂い、やがて音そのものが出なくなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From its structure, condensation is easily made by breath, and if performed continually, the key will be out of tune, and the sound itself will not be made at the end.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to its structure, internal condensation from breath easily builds up and, if performed continually, water drops on the shita will distort the pitch and eventually lead to loss of sound.</e>
<cmt>Poor, incomplete translation.Completely retranslated.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to its structure, internal condensation from breath easily builds up and, if performed continually, water drops on the shita will distort the pitch and eventually lead to loss of sound.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>そのため、火鉢やコンロなどで演奏前や間に楽器を暖めることが必要である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of that, warming of instrument by brazier or stove before or in between a performance is needed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is therefore necessary to warm the instrument using a brazier or stove before and in between performances.</e>
<cmt>Reworded to read more naturally.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is therefore necessary to warm the instrument using a brazier or stove before and in between performances.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="22">
<j>現代では雅楽だけでなく、クラシック音楽の作曲家によって管弦楽や室内楽のなかで、あるいは声楽の伴奏楽器として活用されることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today, it is not only used in Gagaku, but also used by composer of classical music in orchestral music and chamber music, or used as accompaniment instrument for vocal music.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, the instrument is not only used in gagaku, but also used by classical music composers in orchestral music and chamber music, or as accompaniment for vocal music.</e>
<cmt>Reworded to read more naturally.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, the instrument is not only used in gagaku, but also used by classical music composers in orchestral music and chamber music, or as accompaniment for vocal music.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="23">
<j>笙より１オクターブ低い音域が鳴る（う）という楽器もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is also an instrument called u, making sound that is 1 octave lower than sho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is also an instrument called an u, which produces a sound one octave lower than a sho.</e>
<cmt>Reworded to read more naturally.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is also an instrument called an &apos;u,&apos; which produces a sound one octave lower than a sho.</e>
<cmt>用語を読みやすくするため&apos; &apos;補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>これは雅楽の伝統では一度断絶したものの、正倉院の宝物等を参考に、戦後になって復元された楽器の一つである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is one of the instruments that were once wiped out in Gagaku tradition, but were restored after the World War II, referring to treasures in Shosoin Treasure House.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This instrument disappeared from gagaku tradition but was restored after World War II by referring to the treasures in the Shosoin Treasure House.</e>
<cmt>Reworded to read more naturally.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This instrument disappeared from gagaku tradition but was restored after World War II by referring to the treasures in the Shosoin Treasure House.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>現代において蘇演（復曲）された作品や、新たな新作の現代雅楽、例えば黛敏郎の「昭和天平楽」などで用いられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is used in piece of work which was restored in present days, or newly made modern Gagaku, such as &apos;Showa Tempyoraku&apos; by Toshiro MAYUZUMI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is used in revived classics as well as newly composed modern gagaku music such as &apos;Showa Tempyoraku&apos; by Toshiro MAYUZUMI.</e>
<cmt>Reworded to read more naturally.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is used in revived classics as well as newly composed modern gagaku music such as &apos;Showa Tempyoraku&apos; by Toshiro MAYUZUMI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="26">
<j>中国には北京語でシェン(shēng)、広東語でサンという、同じ「笙」の字を書く楽器がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is an instrument in China called sheng in Beijing and san in Guangdong, written with same letter, &apos;sho.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is an instrument in China called the &apos;sheng&apos; in Mandarin and &apos;san&apos; in Cantonese that is written using the same character as &apos;sho.</e>
<cmt>Incorrect translation. Completely retranslated.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is an instrument in China called the &apos;sheng&apos; in Mandarin and &apos;san&apos; in Cantonese that is written using the same character as &apos;sho.&apos;</e>
<cmt>用語を読みやすくするため&apos; &apos;補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>これは笙より大型で、音域は日本の笙の倍以上あり、素早い動きにも対応している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is larger than sho, has more than twice the range of Japanese sho, and can correspond to rapid movement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is larger than the Japanese sho, has more than twice its range and can respond to rapid movements.</e>
<cmt>Reworded to read more naturally.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is larger than the Japanese sho, has more than twice its range and can respond to rapid movements.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>もともと奈良時代に日本に伝わった時点では、日本の笙もパイプのような吹き口が付属していたが、現在ではそれをはずし、直接胴に口をあてて演奏する形に変わっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally when it was introduced to Japan in the Nara period, there was a mouthpiece like a pipe attached to Japanese sho, too, but in present days, that mouthpiece is removed and is performed by putting mouth directly to its body.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When first introduced to Japan during the Nara period, the Japanese sho also had a pipe-like mouthpiece but this has since been removed and the instrument is now played by placing the mouth directly on the body.</e>
<cmt>Poor translation.Completely retranslated.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When first introduced to Japan during the Nara period, the Japanese sho also had a pipe-like mouthpiece but this has since been removed and the instrument is now played by placing the mouth directly on the body.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="29">
<j>ラオス、タイ王国北東部では笙と同じ原理のケーンという楽器があり、一説では、これが中国の笙の原型であると言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is an instrument called Kaen in Laos and Northeastern part of Thailand having the same structure as sho, and in one theory, it is said to be the archetype of sho in China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is an instrument from Laos and the Northeastern part of Thailand called the khene that works according to the same principle and one theory states that this is the predecessor of the Chinese sheng.</e>
<cmt>Poor translation.Completely retranslated.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is an instrument from Laos and the Northeastern part of Thailand called the khene that works according to the same principle and one theory states that this is the predecessor of the Chinese sheng.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="30">
<j>竹の順番</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Order of bamboo tubes</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Order of Bamboo Tubes</e>
<cmt>Title case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Order of Bamboo Tubes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>音程は竹の長さとは無関係で、吹き口から向かって右側から時計回りに、以下の通りとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The key has no relation with the length, and from the right side of the blowing hole, it is put in clockwise by the orders mentioned below.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The key has no relationship to the length of the bamboo tube, and the following are listed in clockwise order from the right a viewed from the mouthpiece.</e>
<cmt>Poor translation.Completely retranslated.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The key has no relationship to the length of the bamboo tube, and the following are listed in clockwise order from the right a viewed from the mouthpiece.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="32">
<j>也・毛は、現行の笙ではリード (楽器)が付けられておらず、音が出ない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ya and Mo do not make sound, since reed (instrument) is not attached in present sho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ya and mo are silent in modern sho because they do not contain a reeds.</e>
<cmt>Reworded to read more naturally.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ya and mo are silent in modern sho because they do not contain a reeds.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Darkoneko(id:17431), Nnh(id:474), Shun Zero(id:197329), 30rKs56MaE(id:11801), 久太郎(id:188054), Iwatake(id:32921), おはぐろ蜻蛉(id:8405), Tokek(id:17356), Sasuore(id:17780), Zzzz(id:16596), Toto-tarou(id:16648), 寒漁夫(id:99134), Hatsune(id:26654), Opponent(id:720), Mymelo(id:122034), SuisuiBot(id:10165), Nnn(id:26535), Whiz(id:15769), Mazbot(id:181195), Tamago915(id:11009), Point136(id:211299), Aloha-vodka(id:22493), Ryukei(id:71385), FlaBot(id:30804), Bankokuya(id:91191), 弥(id:61590), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>