<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>土蜘蛛</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Tsuchigumo&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Tsuchigumo&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Tsuchigumo&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>土蜘蛛（つちぐも）とは、実在するクモの名前ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Tsuchigumo&quot; is not a name of a living spider.</e>
<cmt>※「実在する」の訳ですが、ここでは&quot;existent&quot;では若干不明確になると考え、「生きている」（living) と訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Tsuchigumo&quot; is not the actual name of a living spider.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsuchigumo is not a name of an actual living spider.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>以下のような意を持つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has some meanings as follows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has some of the following meanings.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has the following meaning:</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>天皇に恭順しなかった古代の土豪の名前。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name of ancient local clans who did not swear allegiance to the emperor</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name of ancient local clans who did not swear allegiance to the emperor</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The collective name for ancient local clans who did not swear allegiance to the emperor</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>日本に伝わる巨大なクモの妖怪で、別名「八握脛（やつかはぎ）」「大蜘蛛（おおぐも）」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A folkloric spider-limbed monster in Japan (also called &quot;Yatsukahagi&quot; or &quot;Ogumo&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A folkloric spider-limbed monster in Japan (also called &quot;Yatsukahagi&quot; or &quot;Ogumo&quot;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A folkloric spider monster in Japan (also called &apos;Yatsukahagi&apos; or &apos;Ogumo&apos;)</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="5">
<j>能の演目。五番目物の鬼退治物。土蜘蛛 (能)を参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A program of Noh (a program of &quot;Onitaiji-mono&quot; [the wiping-out-ogres category plays] in &quot;Gobanme-mono&quot; [the fifth-category plays]) cf. the article of &quot;Tsuchigumo (Noh)&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A program of Noh (a program of &quot;Onitaiji-mono&quot; [the wiping-out-ogres category plays] in &quot;Gobanme-mono&quot; [the fifth-category plays]) cf. the article of &quot;Tsuchigumo (Noh)&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A program of Noh that is one of &quot;Gobanme-mono&quot; (the fifth-category plays), also called &quot;Onitaiji-mono&quot; (the wiping-out-ogres category plays) (cf. the article of &quot;Tsuchigumo (Noh)&quot;.)</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="6">
<j>また、海外の熱帯地方に生息する大型の地表徘徊性蜘蛛のグループタランチュラ科は、これらに因んで和名が付けられているが命名は後年近代に入ってからであり、直接的にはやはり無関係である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family of tarantula, which falls under the category of the big ground spider living in the tropical region abroad, was given the Japanese name of &quot;Tsuchigumo&quot; after the above-mentioned meanings, but this name was given later in the modern age, so the family of tarantula has nothing to do with &quot;Tsuchigumo&quot; here.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A family of tarantula, which falls under the category of the big ground spider living in the tropical region abroad, was given the Japanese name of &quot;Tsuchigumo&quot; after the above-mentioned meanings, but this name was given later in the modern age, so the family of tarantula has nothing to do with &quot;Tsuchigumo&quot; here.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A family of tarantula, which falls under the category of the big ground spider living in the tropical region abroad, was given the Japanese name &quot;Tsuchigumo&quot; after the above-mentioned meanings, but this name was given later in the modern age, so the family of tarantula has nothing to do with &quot;Tsuchigumo&quot; mentioned here.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="7">
<j>土蜘蛛（土豪）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Tsuchigumo&quot; (the name of the local clans)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Tsuchigumo&quot; (the name of the local clans)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsuchigumo (the local clans)</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>古代日本における、天皇への恭順を表明しない土着の豪傑などに対する蔑称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Tsuchigumo&quot; was the derogatory name of native bold men in ancient Japan who did not swear allegiance to the emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Tsuchigumo&quot; was the derogatory name of native bold men in ancient Japan who did not swear allegiance to the emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsuchigumo was the derogatory name of indigenous hero in ancient Japan who did not swear allegiance to the emperor.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>『古事記』『日本書紀』に「土蜘蛛」または「都知久母（つちぐも）」の名が見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters) and &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), the name tsuchigumo was used.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters) and &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), the name tsuchigumo was used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters) and &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), the name &apos;tsuchigumo&apos; appears.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>この名は、陸奥国、越後国、常陸国、摂津国、豊後国、肥前国など、各国の風土記などでも頻繁に用いられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was also used frequently in &quot;fudoki&quot; (description of regional climate, culture, etc.) of various provinces, such as that in Mutsu Province, Echigo Province, Hitachi Province, Settsu Province, Bungo Province and Hizen Province.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was also used frequently in &quot;fudoki&quot; (description of regional climate, culture, etc.) of various provinces, such as that in Mutsu Province, Echigo Province, Hitachi Province, Settsu Province, Bungo Province and Hizen Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name frequently appears in &quot;fudoki&quot; (description of regionalclimate, culture, etc.) of various provinces, such as that of Mutsu Province, Echigo Province, Hitachi Province, Settsu Province, Bungo Province and Hizen Province.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="11">
<j>例えば、「肥前国風土記」には、こんな記事がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, &quot;Hizen no kuni fudoki&quot; (the topography of Hizen Province) carried an article as follows :</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処*ここセル20を受け、21、22は記事の中身紹介をしているので、セル20の文末はコロンにし、21の文末はセミコロンにしています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, &quot;Hizen no kuni fudoki&quot; (the topography of Hizen Province) carried an article as follows :</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, &apos;Hizen no kuni fudoki&apos; (the topography of Hizen Province) contains an article as follows :</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>景行天皇が志式島（しきしま。平戸島）に行幸（72年）した際、海の中に島があり、そこから煙が昇っているのを見て探らせてみると、小近島の方には大耳、大近島の方には垂耳という土蜘蛛が棲んでいるのがわかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Emperor Keiko visited Shiki-shima Island (the present Hirado-shima Island) in A.D. 72, he saw a smoke rising from another island, so he had his retainers examine who lived there, and he found that tsuchigumo called &quot;Omimi&quot; lived in Kojika-jima Island and that another tsuchigumo called &quot;Tarimimi&quot; lived in Ojika-jima Island;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Emperor Keiko visited Shiki-shima Island (the present Hirado-shima Island) in A.D. 72, he saw smoke rising from another island, so he had his retainers examine who lived there, and he found that tsuchigumo called &quot;Omimi&quot; lived in Kojika-jima Island and that another tsuchigumo called &quot;Tarimimi&quot; lived in Ojika-jima Island;</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Emperor Keiko visited Shiki-shima Island (the present Hirado-shima Island) in AD 72, he saw smoke rising from another island, so he had his retainers examine who lived there, and he found that tsuchigumo called &quot;Omimi&quot; lived in Kojika-jima Island and that another tsuchigumo called &quot;Tarimimi&quot; lived in Ojika-jima Island;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>そこで両者を捕らえて殺そうとしたとき、大耳達は地面に額を下げて平伏し、「これからは天皇へ御贄を造り奉ります」と海産物を差し出して許しを請うた、という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">so the emperor captured them, and when the emperor was about to execute them, they prostrated themselves on the ground, offered marine products, pledged to dedicate products to the emperor thereafter, and asked for forgiveness.</e>
<cmt>※「御贄」とは、「朝廷や神に奉る産物」のことです。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">so the emperor captured them, and when the emperor was about to execute them, they prostrated themselves on the ground, offered marine products, pledged to dedicate products to the emperor thereafter, and asked for forgiveness.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, the emperor captured them, and when the emperor was about to execute them, they prostrated themselves on the ground, offered marine products, pledged to dedicate products to the emperor thereafter, and asked for forgiveness.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>また、「豊後国風土記」にも、五馬山の五馬姫（いつまひめ）、禰宜野の打猴（うちさる）・頸猴（うなさる）・八田（やた）・國摩侶、網磯野（あみしの）の小竹鹿奥（しのかおさ）・小竹鹿臣（しのかおみ）、鼠の磐窟（いわや）の青・白などの多数の土蜘蛛が登場する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And &quot;Bungo no kuni fudoki&quot; (the topography of Bungo Province) mentioned many tsuchigumo, such as &quot;Itsumahime&quot; on Mt. Itsuma, &quot;Uchisaru&quot; &amp; &quot;Unasaru&quot; &amp; &quot;Yata&quot; &amp; &quot;Kunimaro,&quot; all in Negino, &quot;Shinokaosa&quot; &amp; &quot;Shinokaomi,&quot; both in Amishino, and &quot;Ao&quot; &amp; &quot;Shiro,&quot; both in &quot;Nezumi no Iwaya.&quot;</e>
<cmt>※「鼠の磐窟」は、地名です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And &quot;Bungo no kuni fudoki&quot; (the topography of Bungo Province) mentioned many tsuchigumo, such as &quot;Itsumahime&quot; on Mt. Itsuma, &quot;Uchisaru&quot; &amp; &quot;Unasaru&quot; &amp; &quot;Yata&quot; &amp; &quot;Kunimaro,&quot; all in Negino, &quot;Shinokaosa&quot; &amp; &quot;Shinokaomi,&quot; both in Amishino, and &quot;Ao&quot; &amp; &quot;Shiro,&quot; both in &quot;Nezumi no Iwaya.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And &apos;Bungo no kuni fudoki&apos; (the topography of Bungo Province) describes many tsuchigumo, such as &quot;Itsumahime&quot; on Mt. Itsuma; &quot;Uchisaru,&quot; &quot;Unasaru,&quot; &quot;Yata&quot; and &quot;Kunimaro,&quot; all of which were in Negino; &quot;Shinokaosa&quot; and &quot;Shinokaomi,&quot; both of which were in Amishino; and &quot;Ao&quot; and &quot;Shiro,&quot; both of which were in &quot;Nezumi no Iwaya.&quot;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="15">
<j>また一説では、神話の時代から朝廷へ戦いを仕掛けたものを朝廷は鬼や土蜘蛛と呼び、朝廷から軽蔑されると共に、朝廷から恐れられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And a theory says that the Yamato Court called those who waged war against itself &quot;oni&quot; (a demon) or &quot;tsuchigumo&quot; from ancient times, and that the court despised - and feared - them.</e>
<cmt>※「神話の時代」とは、その時代について古事記や日本書紀に神話的な記述があるだけで、それを裏付ける客観的な史料、根拠が存在しない時代を指しています。ただ、これを説明していると冗長になるので、左では「古代」と意訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And a theory says that the Yamato Court called those who waged war against itself &quot;oni&quot; (a demon) or &quot;tsuchigumo&quot; from ancient times, and that the court despised - and feared - them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And a theory says that the Imperial Court called those who forced war against the Imperial Court &quot;oni&quot; (a demon) or &quot;tsuchigumo&quot; from ancient times, and that the court despised - and feared - them.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="16">
<j>土蜘蛛の中でも、奈良県の大和葛城山にいたというものは特に知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Of all tsuchigumo, one on Yamato Katsuragi Mountain is well-known.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Of all tsuchigumo, one on Yamato Katsuragi Mountain is well-known.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among others, tsuchigumo on Mt. Yamato-Katsuragi is well-known.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>大和葛城山の葛城一言主神社には土蜘蛛塚という小さな塚があるが、これは神武天皇が土蜘蛛を捕え、彼らの怨念が復活しないように頭、胴、足と別々に埋めた跡といわれる（神武天皇怒濤の進撃も参照）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Within the premises of Katsuragi Hitokotonushi-jinja Shrine on Yamato Katsuragi Mountain, there exists a burial mound called &quot;Tsuchigumo-zuka,&quot; and it is said that Emperor Jinmu captured tsuchigumo and buried separately the parts of their dead bodies (the head, the trunk and the legs) for containing their curses (cf. the section of &quot;Surging waves of the march&quot; in the article of &quot;Emperor Jinmu&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Within the premises of Katsuragi Hitokotonushi-jinja Shrine on Yamato Katsuragi Mountain, there exists a burial mound called &quot;Tsuchigumo-zuka,&quot; and it is said that Emperor Jinmu captured tsuchigumo and buried separately the parts of their dead bodies (the head, the trunk and the legs) for containing their curses (cf. the section of &quot;Surging waves of the march&quot; in the article of &quot;Emperor Jinmu&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Within the precincts of Katsuragi Hitokotonushi-jinja Shrine on Mt. Yamato-Katsuragi, there exists a burial mound called &quot;Tsuchigumo-zuka,&quot; and it is said that Emperor Jinmu captured tsuchigumo and buried separately the parts of their dead bodies (the head, the trunk and the limbs) for removing their curses (cf. the section of &quot;Surging waves of the march&quot; in the article of &quot;Emperor Jinmu&quot;).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="18">
<j>一般に土蜘蛛は、背が低く、手足が長く、洞穴で生活していたといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In general, tsuchigumo is said to have been short in height but long in arms &amp; legs, and to have lived in caves.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In general, tsuchigumo is said to have been short in height but long in arms &amp; legs, and to have lived in caves.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In general, tsuchigumo is said to have been short in stature and had long limbs, and to have lived in caves.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>これは縄文人の体形と、農耕ではなく狩猟や採集を主とする穴居生活から連想されたものらしく、このような生活習慣の違いなどが人々からさげすまれた原因とも考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But this seems to be the association of the physique &amp; the cave-dwelling life - mainly based on hunting and herborising, not on farming - of the Jomon people (in the Neolithic Age), and this association is supposed to be the cause of people&apos;s disdain for tsuchigumo.</e>
<cmt>※「縄文人」については、&quot;the Jomon people&quot; だけでは外人にはわからないであろうと考え、括弧内で「新石器時代の」と補っています。　　　　　　　なお、内容的に考えて、オリジナル1行目の「縄文人の」は、「体形」と、「穴居生活」との両方にかかると考えられます。とすると、2行目から3行目にかけての「このような生活習慣の違いなどが」は、やや日本語として不正確となる（「洞穴での生活」は想像の産物に過ぎないわけですから。）ので、「このような連想が」と変えて訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But this seems to be the association of the physique &amp; the cave-dwelling life - mainly based on hunting and herborising, not on farming - of the Jomon people (in the Neolithic Age), and this association is supposed to be the cause of people&apos;s disdain for tsuchigumo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It seems that the name tsuchigumo was associated with their physiques and the cave-dwelling life--mainly based on hunting and gathering instead of farming--of the Jomon people (in the Neolithic Age), and this association is supposed to be the cause of people&apos;s disdain for tsuchigumo.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="20">
<j>土蜘蛛（妖怪）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Tsuchigumo&quot; (the monster)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Tsuchigumo&quot; (the monster)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsuchigumo (monster)</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="21">
<j>時代を経るに従い、土蜘蛛は妖怪として定着していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As times went by, &quot;Tsuchigumo&quot; took root as a word to mean a monster.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As times went by, &quot;Tsuchigumo&quot; took root as a word to mean a monster.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As times changed, &quot;Tsuchigumo&quot; took root as a word to mean a monster.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="22">
<j>人前に現われる姿は鬼の顔、虎の胴体に長いクモの手足の巨大ないでたちであるともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When in front of a human, Tsuchigumo is a monster, having a face of a demon, a trunk of a tiger and limbs of a spider, they say.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When in front of a human, Tsuchigumo is a monster, having a face of a demon, a trunk of a tiger and limbs of a spider, they say.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Tsuchigumo had a demon&apos;s head, a tiger&apos;s trunk and spider&apos;s limbs.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>いずれも山に棲んでおり、旅人を糸で雁字搦めにして捕らえて喰ってしまうといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Every Tsuchigumo lives on a mountain, ties up a hiker firmly with its thread and preys on it, they say.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that every Tsuchigumo lives on a mountain, ties up a hiker firmly with its thread and preys on them.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that every Tsuchigumo lives in a mountain, ties up a hiker firmly with its thread and preys on them.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="24">
<j>14世紀頃に書かれた『土蜘蛛草紙』では、京の都で大蜘蛛の怪物として登場する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Tsuchigumo zoshi&quot; (a storybook of Tsuchigumo), written around fourteenth century, portrayed Tsuchigumo as a monster spider in Kyoto as follows :</e>
<cmt>※ここでも、セル40を受け41から46までは内容紹介がなされているので、40の文末はコロンに、41から45の文末はセミコロンにしています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Tsuchigumo zoshi&quot; (a storybook of Tsuchigumo), written around the fourteenth century, portrayed Tsuchigumo as a monster spider in Kyoto as follows :</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsuchigumo zoshi (a storybook of Tsuchigumo) written in the fourteenth century, portrayed Tsuchigumo as a monster spider in Kyoto as follows:</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>酒呑童子討伐で知られる平安時代中期の武将・源頼光が家来の渡辺綱を連れて京都の洛外北山の蓮台野に赴くと、空を飛ぶ髑髏に遭遇した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;MINAMOTO no Yorimitsu,&quot; known as a warlord in the middle of the Heian period who subdued &quot;Shuten Doji&quot; (the leader of a group of bandits that roamed the region around Kyoto), went with his retainer &quot;WATANABE no Tsuna&quot; to Rendaino in Kitayama of &quot;Rakuhoku&quot; (outside area of the capital), where they met with a skull flying in the sky;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;MINAMOTO no Yorimitsu,&quot; known as a warlord in the middle of the Heian period who subdued &quot;Shuten Doji&quot; (the leader of a group of bandits that roamed the region around Kyoto), went with his retainer &quot;WATANABE no Tsuna&quot; to Rendaino in Kitayama of &quot;Rakuhoku&quot; (outside area of the capital), where they were met with a skull flying in the sky;</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Yorimitsu, known as a warlord in the middle of the Heian period who subdued &quot;Shuten Doji&quot; (the leader of a group of bandits that roamed the region around Kyoto), went with his retainer WATANABE no Tsuna to Rendaino in Kitayama of Rakugai (outside area of the capital Kyoto), where they met with a skull flying in the sky;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>不審に思った頼光たちがそれを追うと、古びた屋敷に辿り着き、様々な異形の妖怪たちが現れて頼光らを苦しめた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">being suspicious of the skull, they went after it and reached an old house, where various strangely-shaped ghosts emerged and bothered them;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">being suspicious of the skull, they went after it and reached an old house, where various strangely-shaped ghosts emerged and bothered them;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">being suspicious of the skull, they went after it and reached an old house, where various goblins and bugbears hideous in appearance emerged and frightened them;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>夜明け頃には美女が現れて目くらましを仕掛けてきたが、頼光はそれに負けずに刀で斬りかかると、女の姿は消え、あとに血痕が残っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">at dawn or so, a beautiful woman appeared and used something dazzling, but Yorimitsu counterattacked on her with his sword, when the woman disappeared with some bloodstains left on the ground;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">at dawn or so, a beautiful woman appeared and used something dazzling, but Yorimitsu counterattacked her with his sword, when the woman disappeared with some bloodstains left on the ground;</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">at dawn, a beautiful woman appeared and tried to razzle dazzle them, but Yorimitsu counterattacked her with his sword; when the woman disappeared some bloodstains were left on the ground;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>それを辿って行くと、やがて山奥の洞窟に至り、そこには巨大なクモがおり、このクモがすべての怪異の正体だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">tracing the bloodstains, they reached a cave far up on a mountain, where they found a monster spider, the source of all evil phenomena;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">tracing the bloodstains, they reached a cave far up on a mountain, where they found a monster spider, the source of all evil phenomena;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">tracing the bloodstains, they reached a cave far up on a mountain, where they found a monster spider, the original form of all evil phenomena;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>激しい戦いの末に頼光がクモの首を刎ねると、その腹からは1990個もの死人の首が出てきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">after fighting a fierce battle, Yorimitsu cut off the monster&apos;s head, and he found as many as 1990 heads of the dead in the monster&apos;s trunk;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">after fighting a fierce battle, Yorimitsu cut off the monster&apos;s head, and he found as many as 1990 heads of the dead in the monster&apos;s trunk;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">after fighting a fierce battle, Yorimitsu cut off the monster&apos;s head, and he found as many as 1990 heads of the dead in the monster&apos;s stomach;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>さらに脇腹からは無数の子グモが飛び出したので、そこを探ると、さらに約20個の小さな髑髏があったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">seeing millions of offsprings of spiders rushing out from the monster&apos;s flank, they inspected there and also found about 20 small skulls.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">seeing millions of offsprings of spiders rushing out from the monster&apos;s flank, and upon inspection, also found about 20 small skulls.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">seeing millions of offsprings of spiders rushing out from the monster&apos;s flank, Yorimitsu examined there and found about twenty more small skulls.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="31">
<j>土蜘蛛の話は諸説あり、『平家物語』には以下のようにある（ここでは「山蜘蛛」と表記されている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Various stories exist about Tsuchigumo, and &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of the Heike) described a story about it by the name of &quot;Yamagumo&quot; as follows :</e>
<cmt>※ここもセル48を受け49から55で内容紹介をしているので、同上の処理をしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Various stories exist about Tsuchigumo, and &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of the Heike) described a story about it by the name of &quot;Yamagumo&quot; as follows :</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Various stories about Tsuchigumo exist, and &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of the Heike) describes a story about it by the name of &apos;Yamagumo&apos; as follows:</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>頼光が瘧（マラリア）を患って床についていたところ、身長7尺（約2.1メートル）の怪僧が現れ、縄を放って頼光を絡めとろうとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Yorimitsu was in bed with &quot;okori&quot; (an intermittent [malarial] fever), an evil monk of about 2.1 meters in height emerged and tried to catch and bind up Yorimitsu with ropes;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Yorimitsu was in bed with &quot;okori&quot; (an intermittent [malarial] fever), an evil monk of about 2.1 meters in height emerged and tried to catch and bind Yorimitsu with ropes;</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Yorimitsu was bed-ridden with &quot;okori&quot; (an intermittent [malarial] fever), an evil monk of about 2.1 meters tall emerged and tried to catch and bind Yorimitsu with ropes;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>頼光が病床にもかかわらず名刀・膝丸で斬りつけると、僧は逃げ去った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">though Yorimitsu was in bed, he slashed the monk with his &quot;Hizamaru,&quot; an excellent sword, and the monk ran away;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">though Yorimitsu was in bed, he slashed the monk with his &quot;Hizamaru,&quot; an excellent sword, and the monk ran away;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">although Yorimitsu suffered from the illness, he slashed at the monk with his noted &quot;Hizamaru&quot; sword, and the monk ran away;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>翌日、頼光が四天王を率いて僧の血痕を追うと、北野天満宮裏手の塚に辿り着き、そこには全長4尺（約1.2メートル）の巨大グモがいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">on the next day, leading &quot;Shitenno&quot; (four guardian kings), Yorimitsu traced the bloodstains left on the ground and arrived at the mound back of Kitano Tenman-gu Shrine, where they found a monster spider of about 1.2 meter in full length;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">on the next day, leading &quot;Shitenno&quot; (four guardian kings), Yorimitsu traced the bloodstains left on the ground and arrived at the mound back of Kitano Tenman-gu Shrine, where they found a monster spider of about 1.2 meter in full length;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">on the next day, leading &quot;Shitenno&quot; (four guardians), Yorimitsu traced the bloodstains left on the ground and arrived at the mound at the back of Kitano Tenman-gu Shrine, where they found a monster spider of about 1.2 meter in full length;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>頼光たちはこれを捕え、鉄串に刺して川原に晒した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">so they captured it, pierced it with an iron spit and gibbeted it on the shore of a river;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">so they captured it, pierced it with an iron spit and gibbeted it on the shore of a river;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">so they captured it, pierced it with an iron bar, and gibbeted it on the shore of a river;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>頼光の病気はその後すぐに回復し、土蜘蛛を討った膝丸は以来「蜘蛛切り」と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">then, Yorimitsu soon recovered from illness, and thereafter the sword &quot;Hizamaru,&quot; with which Yorimitsu slashed Tsuchigumo, began to be called &quot;Kumogiri&quot; (Tsuchigumo cutter);</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">then, Yorimitsu soon recovered from illness, and thereafter the sword &quot;Hizamaru,&quot; with which Yorimitsu slashed Tsuchigumo, began to be called &quot;Kumogiri&quot; (Tsuchigumo cutter);</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">then, Yorimitsu soon recovered from his illness, and thereafter the sword &quot;Hizamaru,&quot; with which Yorimitsu slashed Tsuchigumo, began to be called &apos;Kumogiri&apos; (Tsuchigumo cutter);</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>この土蜘蛛の正体は、前述の神武天皇が討った土豪の土蜘蛛の怨霊だったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the original form of this Tsuchigumo is said to have been the vengeful spirits of the above-mentioned local clans put down by Emperor Jinmu;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">the original form of this Tsuchigumo is said to have been the vengeful spirits of the above-mentioned local clans put down by Emperor Jinmu;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">the original form of this Tsuchigumo is said to have been vengeful spirits of the above-mentioned local clans put down by Emperor Jinmu;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>この説話は能の五番目物の『土蜘蛛』でも知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">this story is known to the public also by the Noh program &quot;Tsuchigumo&quot; in &quot;Gobanme-mono&quot; (the fifth-category plays).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">this story is known to the public also by the Noh program &quot;Tsuchigumo&quot; in &quot;Gobanme-mono&quot; (the fifth-category plays).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">this story is also known by the Noh program &quot;Tsuchigumo&quot; in &quot;Gobanme-mono&quot; (the fifth-category plays).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="39">
<j>一説では、頼光の父・源満仲は前述の土豪の鬼・土蜘蛛たちの一族と結託して藤原氏に反逆を企んだが、安和の変の際に一族を裏切って保身を図ったため、彼の息子である頼光と四天王が鬼、土蜘蛛といった妖怪たちから呪われるようになったともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yorimitsu&apos;s father &quot;MINAMOTO no Mitsunaka&quot; conspired with &quot;oni&quot; &amp; &quot;tsuchigumo,&quot; the above-mentioned local clans, to revolt against the Fujiwara clan, but on the occasion of Anna Incident, Mitsunaka betrayed the local clans to defend his own interests, so his son Yorimitsu and Shitenno began to be cursed by the ghosts of &quot;oni&quot; and &quot;tsuchigumo,&quot; some people say.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yorimitsu&apos;s father &quot;MINAMOTO no Mitsunaka&quot; conspired with &quot;oni&quot; &amp; &quot;tsuchigumo,&quot; the above-mentioned local clans, to revolt against the Fujiwara clan, but on the occasion of Anna Incident, Mitsunaka betrayed the local clans to defend his own interests, so his son Yorimitsu and Shitenno began to be cursed by the ghosts of &quot;oni&quot; and &quot;tsuchigumo,&quot; some people say.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A theory has it that Yorimitsu&apos;s father MINAMOTO no Mitsunaka conspired with &quot;oni&quot; and &quot;tsuchigumo,&quot; the above-mentioned local clans, to revolt against the Fujiwara clan, but on the occasion of Anna Incident, Mitsunaka betrayed the local clans to defend his own interests, so his son Yorimitsu and Shitenno began to be cursed by the ghosts of &quot;oni&quot; and &quot;tsuchigumo.&quot;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="40">
<j>京都市北区の上品蓮台寺には頼光を祀った源頼光朝臣塚があるが、これが土蜘蛛が巣くっていた塚だといい、かつて塚のそばの木を伐採しようとしたところ、その者が謎の病気を患って命を落としたという話がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Within the premises of Jobonrendai-ji Temple in Kita Ward, Kyoto City, there exists the burial mound that MINAMOTO no Yorimitsu is enshrined, where the ghosts of tsuchigumo are said to have hung out, and a person, who intended to cut down a tree by the mound, is said to have died from an unknown disease.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Within the premises of Jobonrendai-ji Temple in Kita Ward, Kyoto City, there exists the burial mound where MINAMOTO no Yorimitsu is enshrined, where the ghosts of tsuchigumo are said to have hung out, and a person, who intended to cut down a tree by the mound, is said to have died from an unknown disease.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Within the precincts of Jobonrendai-ji Temple in Kita Ward, Kyoto City, there exists the burial mound where MINAMOTO no Yorimitsu is enshrined, where the ghosts of tsuchigumo are said to have haunted; it is said that someone who intended to cut down a tree by the mound died from an unknown disease.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>また、上京区一条通にも土蜘蛛が巣くっていたといわれる塚があり、ここからは灯籠が発掘されて蜘蛛灯籠といわれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And on Ichijo Street, Kamigyo Ward, there exists another mound that is said to have been hung out by the ghosts of tsuchigumo, and a stone lantern was excavated from here and began to be called &quot;Kumo Doro&quot; (the stone lantern of tsuchigumo).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And on Ichijo Street, Kamigyo Ward, there exists another mound that is said to have been hung out by the ghosts of tsuchigumo, and a stone lantern was excavated from here and began to be called &quot;Kumo Doro&quot; (the stone lantern of tsuchigumo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Ichijo-dori, Kamigyo Ward, there exists another mound that is said to have been haunted by the ghosts of tsuchigumo, and a stone lantern was excavated from here and began to be called &quot;Kumo Doro&quot; (the stone lantern of tsuchigumo).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>これを貰い受けた人の家運がたちまちに傾くことが続き、土蜘蛛の祟りかと恐れられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The person who was given the lantern soon lost its family fortunes, and this phenomenon repeated, so people feared it must be the curse of tsuchigumo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The person who was given the lantern soon lost its family fortunes, and this phenomenon repeated, so people feared it must be the curse of tsuchigumo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The people who were handed over the lantern had their family fortunes declined immediately after receiving the lantern, so people feared it must be the curse of tsuchigumo.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>現在、蜘蛛灯籠は上京区馬喰町の東向観音寺に奉納されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At present, &quot;Kumo Doro&quot; is dedicated to Higashimukai Kannon-ji Temple in Bakuro-cho, Kamigyo Ward.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At present, &quot;Kumo Doro&quot; is dedicated to Higashimukai Kannon-ji Temple in Bakuro-cho, Kamigyo Ward.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At present, &quot;Kumo Doro&quot; is kept in Higashimukai Kannon-ji Temple in Bakuro-cho, Kamigyo Ward.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="44">
<j>似た妖怪に海蜘蛛がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There exists another ghost &quot;Umigumo&quot; similar to &quot;Tsuchigumo.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There exists another ghost &quot;Umigumo&quot; similar to &quot;Tsuchigumo.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is another story of ghost &quot;Umigumo&quot; similar to &quot;Tsuchigumo.&quot;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>口から糸を吐き人を襲うという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Umigumo&quot; is said to attack a human by spitting out thread.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Umigumo&quot; is said to attack humans by spitting out thread.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Umigumo is said to attack humans by spitting out to them.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>九州の沿岸に出るとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said to appear on a coast of Kyusyu region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said to appear on the Kyushu coastal region.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said to haunt the Kyushu coastal region.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Xqbot(id:273540), Nnh(id:474), Kawai(id:5634), Ttkkss(id:119005), Metatron(id:64025), Sina(id:10021), 逃亡者(id:14864), Point136(id:211299), Yanahan(id:2437), Greenland4(id:114494), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>