<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>家風</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kafu (family tradition)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kafu (family tradition)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kafu</e>
<cmt>タイトルのため、補足部分は削除いたしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>家風（かふう）は、個々の特定の家において世代を越えて踏襲される固有の慣習・流儀などの行動様式である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kafu&quot; (family tradition) is a style of behavior, including custom and procedure, which has been specifically inherited beyond generations within certain individual families.</e>
<cmt>流儀：procedure (styleとすると”家風”と重複するため英辞郎on the webを参照して記載しました）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kafu&quot; (family tradition) is a style of behavior, including custom and procedure, which has been specifically inherited down the generations within certain individual families.</e>
<cmt>「世代を越えて」の訳を&quot;beyond generations&quot;から&quot;down the generations&quot;に変更しました。down the generationsがより適切な訳と考えます。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kafu (family tradition) is a style of behavior, including custom and procedure, which has been specifically inherited down the generations within certain individual families.</e>
<cmt>他の多くの記事と統一するため、ダブルクォーテーションマークは削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>古代の氏制度以来、一族の家系・家格・家祭・家業・家産・家門・家職の維持・継承が日本の上流階層特に本家・嫡流と呼ばれる家においては最も重要視されてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ever since the clan system was established in ancient Japan, it has been deemed to be most important for those people in the upper class, especially in the families called &quot;honke&quot; (the head family) or &quot;chakuryu&quot; (the main branch of the family) to maintain and succeed for generations the line, status, rite, business, properties, kamon (family), and trade or profession of the family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処　(8行目と9行目に記載）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ever since the clan system was established in ancient Japan, it has been deemed to be most important for those people in the upper class, especially in the families called &quot;honke&quot; (the head family) or &quot;chakuryu&quot; (the main branch of the family) to maintain and succeed for generations the line, status, rite, business, properties, kamon (family), and trade or profession of the family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ever since the clan system was established in ancient Japan, it has been deemed to be most important for those people in the upper class, especially in the families called honke (the head family) or chakuryu (the main branch of the family) to maintain and succeed for generations the line, status, rite, business, properties, kamon (family), and trade or profession of the family.</e>
<cmt>他の多くの記事と統一するため、新出語彙のダブルクォーテーションマークは削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>そのための一定の慣習・流儀として整備されたのが家風であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For that purpose, certain customs and styles of each family were formed and maintained and were gradually nurtured as &quot;kafu&quot; (family tradition).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処　(8行目と9行目に記載）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For that purpose, certain customs and procedures of each family were formed and maintained and were gradually nurtured as &quot;kafu&quot; (family tradition).</e>
<cmt>翻訳者のコメントで「流儀」の訳をprocedureにすると述べています。それに合わせて&quot;customs and styles&quot;を&quot;customs and procedures&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For that purpose, certain customs and procedures of each family were formed and maintained and were gradually nurtured as kafu.</e>
<cmt>家風　既出のため、補足を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>そのために公家や武家においては早くから家訓・家憲・家法などと呼ばれる家風の成文法化が進められ、当主以下構成員が守るべき原則とされてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, the written code of family tradition, which was called &quot;kakun&quot; (family percept), &quot;kaken&quot; (family code) or &quot;kaho&quot; (family rules), has been prepared since the early days in those families including court nobles and warrior households and was regarded as the principle that should be met by all family members headed by the family head.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the written code of family tradition, which was called &quot;kakun&quot; (family motto), &quot;kaken&quot; (family code) or &quot;kaho&quot; (family rules), had been prepared since the early days in those families including court nobles and warrior households and was regarded as the principle that should be followed by all family members headed by the family head.</e>
<cmt>(1)家訓をfamily perceptからfamily mottoに変更しました（ジーニアス和英で家訓をfamily mottoとしています）。(2)時制を一致させるためhas been をhad beenに変更しました。(3)should be metをshould be followedに変更しました。人間が規則を守る場合はmeetよりもfollowの方が適切な動詞と考えます。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the written code of family tradition, which was called kakun (family motto), kaken (family code) or kaho (family rules), had been prepared since the early days in those families including court nobles and warrior households and was regarded as the principle that should be followed by all family members headed by the family head.</e>
<cmt>他の多くの記事と統一するため、新出語彙のダブルクォーテーションマークは削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>江戸時代の幕藩体制のもとではどこの大名家にも確たる家風と家訓が存在したと言われ、更に一部の商人や農民の間でも家風の確立と家訓・家憲の作成が行われていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Edo period, every Daimyo family (feudal lord family) under the feudal system characteristic of the shogunate is said to have maintained a firm &quot;kafu&quot; and &quot;kakun&quot;, and even among some merchants and peasantry families, &quot;kafu&quot; was established and &quot;kakun&quot; and &quot;kaken&quot; were prepared.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Edo period, every &quot;daimyo family&quot; (feudal lord family) under the shogunate system was said to have a firm &quot;kafu&quot; and &quot;kakun&quot;, and even among some merchants and peasantry families, &quot;kafu&quot; was established and &quot;kakun&quot; and &quot;kaken&quot; were prepared.</e>
<cmt>(1)Daimyoからdaimyoに変更しました(大名の訳はdaimyoが適切と理解）。(2)大名家を引用符で囲んで&quot;daimyo family&quot;としました。本文書では、新たに出現した用語を引用符で囲み、その意味を直後の括弧の中で述べるスタイルになっています。それに合わせました。(3)「藩幕体制」の訳を&quot;the feudal system characteristic of the shogunate&quot;から&quot;shogunate system&quot;に変更しました。その方が日本文に忠実と考えます。(4)is said to have maintainedをwas said to haveに変更しました。そちらの方が日本文に忠実と考えます。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Edo period, every daimyo (feudal lord) family under the shogunate system was said to have a firm kafu and kakun, and even among some merchants and peasantry families, kafu was established and kakun and kaken were prepared.</e>
<cmt>他の多くの記事と統一するため、新出語彙のダブルクォーテーションマークは削除しました。チェッカーの方の質問ですが、was said to have でよいと判断しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>各大名家においては当主や家老以下の家臣を問わず家風を尊重・保持することが御家への忠誠の証と考えられてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In each Daimyo family, the family head and all vassals including Karo (chief retainer) and other retainers regardless of their rank believed that it was the proof of fealty to oie (family of his lord) to respect and maintain &quot;kafu&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In each daimyo family, the family head and all vassals including &quot;karo&quot; (chief retainer) and other retainers regardless of their rank believed that it was the proof of fealty to &quot;oie&quot; (family of his lord) to respect and maintain &quot;kafu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>(1)上で述べた理由によりDaimyoをdaimyoとしました。(2)Karoをkaroとし（家老の訳はkaroが適切と理解）、引用符で囲みました。本文書における、新用語が出現した場合のスタイルに合わせました。(3)oieを引用符で囲み&quot;oie&quot;としました。理由は(2)と同じです。(4)文の最後の&quot;kafu&quot;を&quot;kafu.&quot;とし、ピリオドを引用符の中に入れました。仕様指示書の指示に従いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In each daimyo family, the family head and all vassals including karo (chief retainer) and other retainers regardless of their rank believed that it was the proof of fealty to the family of their lord to respect and maintain kafu.</e>
<cmt>他の多くの記事と統一するため、新出語彙のダブルクォーテーションマークは削除しました。御家 oie　を削除し、family of their lord のみとしました（無いほうが自然な流れだと思います）。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>一方、他家からの養子が大名家を継承した場合には、実家の家風になじんだ新当主が養子先の家風に慣れずに家臣たちと反目して御家騒動に至る可能性もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, when a person adopted from a different family succeeded a Daimyo family, the new family head, who had got used to the tradition of his family home, might possibly have not fitted into the &quot;kafu&quot; in the Daimyo family he was adopted to, and he might have quarreled with the retainers to cause family troubles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, when a person adopted from a different family succeeded a daimyo family, the new family head, who was used to the tradition of his family home, might possibly have not fitted into the kafu in the daimyo family he was adopted by, and he might have quarreled with the retainers to cause family troubles.</e>
<cmt>(1)Daimyoからdaimyoに2箇所変更しました（理由は上述）。(2)had got used to をwas used toに変更しました。実家の家風に既になじんでいる状態にいることからwas used to の方を選択しました。(3)the &quot;kafu&quot;をthe kafuとしました。定冠詞(the)がついているので引用符は不要と考えます。(4)he was adopted to をhe was adopted byに変更しました。the daimyou family adopted a person(him)の受身形であるので、toではなくてbyが適切と考えます。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, when a person adopted from a different family succeeded a daimyo family, the new family head, who was used to the tradition of his family home, might possibly have not fitted into the kafu in the daimyo family he was adopted by, and he might have quarreled with the retainers to cause family troubles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>秋月家から養子に入った上杉治憲は実家の秋月家家老から上杉家の作法に背かないことの訓戒を受けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Harunori UESUGI, who was adopted from the Akizuki family, had been told cautiously by Karo of his home Akizuki family not to be against the manner of the Uesugi family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処　（15行目と16行目に記載） 　秋月家：the Akizuki family (出典：用語統一リスト。用語集ではthe Akizuki clanとなっていましたが、他の例に従い、用語統一リストの記載を遵守しました。）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Harunori UESUGI, who was adopted from the Akizuki family, had been told cautiously by the karo of his home Akizuki family not to be against the manner of the Uesugi family.</e>
<cmt>Karoをkaroにしました（理由は上述）。加えて定冠詞を付けてthe karoにしました。ここでは特定の家老（=秋月家の家老)を示しているためです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Harunori UESUGI, who was adopted from the Akizuki family, had been told cautiously by the karo of his home Akizuki family not to be against the manner of the Uesugi family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>田安家から養子に入った松平定信は実家の田安家の家老から田安家の家風をひけらかして久松松平家の人々の反感を買わないように訓戒を受けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sadanobu MATSUDAIRA, who was adopted from the Tayasu family, had been told cautiously by Karo of his home Tayasu family not to invite antipathy from the Hisamatsu-Matsudaira family people by showing off the kafu of the Tayasu family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処　（15行目と16行目に記載）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sadanobu MATSUDAIRA, who was adopted from the Tayasu family, had been told cautiously by the karo of his home Tayasu family not to invite antipathy from the people in the Hisamatsu-Matsudaira family by showing off the kafu of the Tayasu family.</e>
<cmt>(1)Karoをkaroにしました（理由は上述）。加えて定冠詞を付けてthe karoにしました。ここでは特定の家老（=田安家の家老)を示しているためです。(2)from the Hisamatsu-Matsudaira　family peopleはやや冗長な表現なので、from the people in the Hisamatsu-Matsudaira familyとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sadanobu MATSUDAIRA, who was adopted from the Tayasu family, had been told cautiously by the karo of his home Tayasu family not to invite antipathy from the people in the Hisamatsu-Matsudaira family by showing off the kafu of the Tayasu family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>明治時代以後、財閥の確立とともに本家を中心とした一族及び幹部による経営体制を維持するために家憲・家訓が制定されたことが知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Meiji period and later, along with the formation of several company syndicates (Zaibatsu), &quot;kaken&quot; and &quot;kakun&quot; were known to be established in order to maintain the management mainly by the head family, including family members and executive officers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Meiji period and later, along with the formation of several company syndicates (zaibatsu), &quot;kaken&quot; and &quot;kakun&quot; were known to be established in order to maintain the management mainly by the head family, including family members and executive officers.</e>
<cmt>Zaibatsuをzaibatsuとしました。財閥の訳はzaibatsuが適切という理解です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Meiji period and later, along with the formation of several zaibatsu (company syndicates), kaken and kakun were known to be established in order to maintain the management mainly by the head family, including family members and executive officers.</e>
<cmt>日本語（英語）の並びに従い、zaibatsu (company syndicates)　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>これは江戸時代以来の商家、明治以後の新興を問わずに行われ、社長の権限の強い三菱財閥では「畏服」、本家と番頭（幹部）のつながりが強い三井財閥では「扈従」、番頭（幹部）が重用される住友財閥では「敬愛」が家風と言われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was done regardless of whether the family was a Shoka (mercantile house) since the Edo period or was a newly-emerging house in the Meiji period or later; it was said that the kafu in the Mitsubishi Zaibatsu, in which the president had a strong power, the Mitsui Zaibatsu, in which there was a strong relationship between the head family and general manager (executive officer), and in the Sumitomo Zaibatsu, in which the general manager (executive officer) was given an important post, was &quot;ifuku&quot; (awe), &quot;kosho&quot; (attendant of a noble person), and &quot;keiai&quot; (to love and respect), respectively.</e>
<cmt>番頭：general manager (出典：PDIC ver.5.0.15) 敬愛：to love and respect (敬愛する：love and respect, 出典：PDIC ver. 5.0.15)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was done regardless of whether the family was a &quot;shoka&quot; (mercantile house) since the Edo period or was a newly-emerging house in the Meiji period or later; it was said that the kafu in the Mitsubishi zaibatsu, in which the president had a strong power, the Mitsui zaibatsu, in which there was a strong relationship between the head family and the general manager (executive officer), and in the Sumitomo zaibatsu, in which the general manager (executive officer) was given an important post, was &quot;ifuku&quot; (awe), &quot;kosho&quot; (attendant of a noble person), and &quot;keiai&quot; (to love and respect), respectively.</e>
<cmt>(1)Shokaをshokaとしました。商家の訳はshokaが適切という理解です。(2)Zaibatsuをzaibatsuに変更しました（3か所）。理由は上述。(3)a strong relationship between the head family and general managerのgeneral manegerの前に定冠詞(the)を付けました。managerは可算名詞であるので冠詞が必要と考えます。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was done regardless of whether the family was a shoka (mercantile house) since the Edo period or was a newly-emerging house in the Meiji period or later; it was said that the kafu in the Mitsubishi zaibatsu, in which the president had a strong power, the Mitsui zaibatsu, in which there was a strong relationship between the head family and the general manager (executive officer), and in the Sumitomo zaibatsu, in which the general manager (executive officer) was given an important post, was &apos;ifuku&apos; (awe), &apos;kosho&apos; (attendant of a noble person), and &apos;keiai&apos; (to love and respect), respectively.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　に変更しました。Shoka のダブルクォーテーションを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>また、家制度とともに「家風」の考え方は一般家庭にも浸透し、夫やその両親に反抗する「家風に合わない」嫁の放逐は離婚の正当な理由とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The idea of &quot;kafu&quot; also penetrated through general families together with the notion of ie seido (family system), and expulsion of a son&apos;s wife who expressed disobedience against her husband or in-laws was justified as a reason for divorce.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The idea of &quot;kafu&quot; also penetrated through general families together with the notion of &quot;ie seido&quot; (family system), and expulsion of a son&apos;s wife who expressed disobedience to her husband or in-laws was justified as a reason for divorce.</e>
<cmt>(1)ie seidoを引用符で囲んで&quot;ie seido&quot;としました。上述した新用語の出現に伴う措置です。(2)disobedience against&quot;をdisobedience to&quot;にしました。ここでの前置詞はtoが適切と考ます。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The idea of kafu also penetrated through general families together with the notion of family system, and expulsion of a son&apos;s wife who expressed disobedience to her husband or in-laws was justified as a reason for divorce.</e>
<cmt>ie seido ですが、英語のままでもよいと考え、ie seidoは削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>戦後、家制度の解体や核家族化の進行とともに家風の変質・消滅が急速に進んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the war, as the ie seido collapsed with the trend toward the nuclear family being in progress, the idea of &quot;kafu&quot; has been changing and disappearing rapidly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Second World War, as the ie seido collapsed with the trend toward the nuclear family being in progress, the idea of &quot;kafu&quot; has been changing and disappearing rapidly.</e>
<cmt>日本で言う「戦後」は第二次世界大戦後のことですので、&quot;After the Second World War&quot;としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the World War II, with the collapse of the family system and the trend toward the nuclear family being in progress, the idea of kafu has been changing and disappearing rapidly.</e>
<cmt>ie seido ですが、英語のままでもよいと考えて削除し、family system としました。「家制度の解体や核家族化の進行とともに」　の翻訳を一部変更しました。第二次世界大戦→World War II　として統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 伊勢佐木町メランコリー(id:304952), Nyao148(id:93723), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>