<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>月ヶ瀬梅林</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsukigase Bairin (plum-grove park)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsukigase Bairin (Plum-grove Park)</e>
<cmt>大文字を使いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsukigase Bairin (Plum-grove Park)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>月ヶ瀬梅林（つきがせばいりん）は奈良県奈良市月ヶ瀬尾山とその周辺（旧添上郡月ヶ瀬村）に位置する梅林である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsukigase Bairin refers to the plum grove located in Mt. Tsukigaseoyama of Nara City (Nara Prefecture) and its surrounding areas (former Tsukigase Village, Soekami district).</e>
<cmt>月ヶ瀬村→他の個所で村民villagersを使用しているので、Tsukigase-muraではなく、Tsukigase Villageとしています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsukigase Bairin refers to the plum grove located at Mt. Tsukigaseoyama and its surrounding areas (former Tsukigase Village, Soekami County) in Nara City, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。inをatにしました。順序を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsukigase Bairin refers to the plum grove located at Mt. Tsukigaseoyama and its surrounding areas (former Tsukigase Village, Soekami County) in Nara City, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>五月川の渓谷沿いにウメの木が広がる様から月ヶ瀬梅渓とも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called Tsukigase Baikei (plum valley), as a wide expanse of plum trees stretches along the valleys of Satsuki River.</e>
<cmt>月ヶ瀬梅渓→Tsukigase ume gardenでは規模が小さいので、Tsukigase Valleyにしています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called Tsukigase Baikei (plum valley), as a wide expanse of plum trees stretches along the valleys of Satsuki River.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called Tsukigase Baikei (plum valley), as a wide expanse of plum trees stretches along the valleys of Satsuki River.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>古くから有名な梅林で、日本政府が最初に指定した名勝の一つである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a famous Bairin which dates back many years, and also one of the first scenic-beauty places designated by the Japanese government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a famous plum grove which dates back many years, and also one of the first to be designated a place of scenic beauty by the Japanese government.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。Plum groveという言葉を既に使っているので、統一しました。順序を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a famous plum grove which dates back many years, and also one of the first to be designated a place of scenic beauty by the Japanese government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>2007年現在、約1万3千本の梅が栽培されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As of 2007, approx. 13,000 plum trees are grown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As of 2007, approximately 13,000 plum trees are grown there.</e>
<cmt>Approximatelyをフルで書きました。thereを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As of 2007, approximately 13,000 plum trees are grown there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>現況</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Current Situation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Current Situation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Current Situation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>地勢</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Geographic Features</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Geographic Features</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Geographic Features</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>月ヶ瀬梅林は奈良盆地と伊賀盆地の境に広がる大和高原の北側、京都府・三重県・奈良府県境付近に位置する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsukigase Bairin is situated on the north of the Yamato highlands which lie between the Nara Basin and the Iga Basin, close to the borders of three prefectures of Kyoto, Mie and Nara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsukigase Bairin is situated to the north of the Yamato highlands which lie between the Nara Basin and the Iga Basin, close to the borders of three prefectures of Kyoto, Mie and Nara.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。onをtoにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsukigase Bairin is situated to the north of the Yamato highlands which lie between the Nara Basin and the Iga Basin, close to the borders of three prefectures of Kyoto, Mie and Nara.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>奈良市中心部からは東に約30キロメートル、三重県伊賀市中心部からは南西に約12キロメートルの距離にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is about 30 kilometers east of the center of Nara City and about 12 kilometers southwest of the center of Iga City of Mie Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is about 30 kilometers east of the center of Nara City and about 12 kilometers southwest of the center of Iga City, Mie Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。ofを削除し、コンマを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is about 30 kilometers east of the center of Nara City and about 12 kilometers southwest of the center of Iga City, Mie Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>大和高原北側の府県境付近は木津川 (京都府)水系名張川の渓谷が続いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around the prefectural borders on the north of the Yamato highlands, the valley of Nabari-gawa River of Kizu-gawa River system (Kyoto Prefecture) stretches.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The valleys of Nabari-gawa River of Kizu-gawa River system (Kyoto Prefecture) stretches around the prefectural borders on the north of the Yamato highlands.</e>
<cmt>valleyを複数形にしました。順序を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The valleys of Nabari-gawa River of Kizu-gawa River system (Kyoto Prefecture) stretches around the prefectural borders on the north of the Yamato highlands.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>特に月ヶ瀬梅林のある名張川下流域は五月川と呼ばれ、深いV字谷を形成している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially, the lower reach of Nabari-gawa River, where Tsukigase Bairin is situated, is called Satsuki River, and a V-shaped Valley is formed there.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The lower reach of Nabari-gawa River, where Tsukigase Bairin is situated, is called Satsuki River, and a deep V-shaped valley is formed there.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。valleyを小文字にしました。especiallyを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The lower reach of Nabari-gawa River, where Tsukigase Bairin is situated, is called Satsuki River, and a deep V-shaped valley is formed there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>月ヶ瀬梅林はこのV字谷の斜面に広がる梅林である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsukigase Bairin stands on the hillsides of this V-shaped valley.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsukigase Bairin stands on the hillsides of this V-shaped valley.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsukigase Bairin stands on the hillsides of this V-shaped valley.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>「月ヶ瀬梅渓」と呼ばれる所以となった雄大な渓流は高山ダムの完成（1969年）によりダム湖の底に沈んだが、近年はダム湖－月ヶ瀬湖の湖水と梅林が調和し、新たな景観を形成している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the magnificent mountain streams, after which &apos;Tsukigase Baikei&apos; was named, were submerged under water of a dam lake when Takayama Dam was built in 1969, new landscape was created recently where the lake extended from the dam lake through Lake Tsukigase blends in with the Bairin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the magnificent mountain streams, after which &apos;Tsukigase Baikei&apos; was named, were submerged under water when Takayama Dam was built in 1969, in recent years the manmade Lake Tsukigase&apos;s waters and the plum groves have harmonized to create a new scenic view.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。Of a dam lakeを削除しました。後半の訳出をやり直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the magnificent mountain streams, after which &apos;Tsukigase Baikei&apos; was named, were submerged under water when Takayama Dam was built in 1969, in recent years the manmade Lake Tsukigase&apos;s waters and the plum groves have harmonized to create a new scenic view.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>月ヶ瀬梅林は海抜200メートルから300メートルの高原である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsukigase Bairin is located on highlands, 200 to 300 meters above sea level.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsukigase Bairin is located on highlands, 200 to 300 meters above sea level.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsukigase Bairin is located on highlands, 200 to 300 meters above sea level.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>高原の影響を受けるため、月ヶ瀬梅林に生育する梅の開花期は奈良市中心部よりも半月ほど遅れ、3月の中旬から下旬に満開となることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As situated on the highlands, the plum trees in Tsukigase Bairin tend to reach full bloom around mid- to late March, half a month later than those in the center of Nara City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because it is situated on highlands, the plum trees in Tsukigase Bairin tend to reach full bloom around mid- to late March, half a month later than those in the center of Nara City.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。asをbecause it isにしました。冠詞を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because it is situated on highlands, the plum trees in Tsukigase Bairin tend to reach full bloom around mid- to late March, half a month later than those in the center of Nara City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>梅林の用途</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Usage of Bairin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Usage of the Plum Groves</e>
<cmt>Bairinをplum grovesにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Usage of the Plum Groves</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="13">
<j>※月ヶ瀬梅林の歴史については歴史の節をご参照ください。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Please refer to the corresponding section for the history of Tsukigase Bairin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Please refer to the corresponding section for the history of Tsukigase Bairin.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Please refer to the corresponding section for the history of Tsukigase Bairin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="14">
<j>明治時代に入る頃まで月ヶ瀬村は烏梅（若い梅の実の燻製。ベニバナ染料に必要な材料。）の一大生産地であり、月ヶ瀬梅林は烏梅の原料となる梅の実を収穫する用途で規模を拡大していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Until early Meiji period, the Tsukigase Village had been the major producer of Ubai (a smoked young plum. An ingredient for Safflower dyes), which contributed to the growing size of Tsukigase Bairin to gather more plums for Ubai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Until early Meiji period, Tsukigase Village had been the major producer of Ubai (a smoked young plum required to produce Safflower dyes), which contributed to the growing size of Tsukigase Bairin to gather more plums for Ubai.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。解説をピリオドなしでできるようにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Until early Meiji period, Tsukigase Village had been the major producer of Ubai (a smoked young plum required to produce Safflower dyes), which contributed to the growing size of Tsukigase Bairin to gather more plums for Ubai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>最盛期の江戸時代には約10万本の梅の木が成育していたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that approx. 100,000 plum trees were grown at its peak in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that approximately 100,000 plum trees were grown at its peak in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。Approximatelyをフルで書きました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that approximately 100,000 plum trees were grown at its peak in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="16">
<j>20世紀に入ると合成染料の発達により、烏梅はほとんど生産されなくなったため、月ヶ瀬梅林は観光資源として利用や食用の青梅の栽培に軸足を移した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the 20th century, as development of synthesized dyes helped to reduce the production of Ubai next to nil, Tsukigase Bairin was transformed into one of the tourist resources or into a production site of food plums.</e>
<cmt>青梅→food plums.(食用か染色用かの違いに焦点をあててており、梅との混乱を避けるため、「青」の訳出は特にしていません）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the 20th century, as development of synthesized dyes reduced the production of Ubai to next to nil, Tsukigase Bairin shifted its focus to tourism and the production of plums for consumption.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。Helped toを削除しました。toを追加しました。後半を意訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the 20th century, as development of synthesized dyes reduced the production of Ubai to next to nil, Tsukigase Bairin shifted its focus to tourism and the production of plums for consumption.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>梅林の規模・栽培種</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Size of Tsukigase Bairin and Type of Cultivated Plum Trees</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Area of Tsukigase Bairin and Type of Cultivated Plum Trees</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。Sizeをareaにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Area of Tsukigase Bairin and Type of Cultivated Plum Trees</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="17">
<j>1950年の名勝再指定時に月瀬梅林として登録された梅林の規模は旧月ヶ瀬村全体で 畑573筆、約10町3反8畝（約104平方キロメートル）、梅樹3108本である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As of 1950 when the Bairin was re-designated as a place of scenic beauty, the size of Tsukigase Bairin was registered as about 104 sq.k with 3,108 plum trees grown in the entire former Tsukigase Village.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As of 1950 when the Bairin was re-designated as a place of scenic beauty, the surface area of Tsukigase Bairin was registered as about 104 square kilometers with 3,108 plum trees in the entire former Tsukigase Village.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。sizeをsurface areaにしました。Square kilometersをフルで書きました。grownを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As of 1950 when the Bairin was re-designated as a place of scenic beauty, the surface area of Tsukigase Bairin was registered as about 104 square kilometers with 3,108 plum trees in the entire former Tsukigase Village.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>2007年現在、この登録上の規模が変更されていないとの報道がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As of 2007, it is reported that no change to this registered size has been made.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As of 2007, there was a report that no change to this registered size had been made.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。時制を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As of 2007, there was a report that no change to this registered size had been made.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>1988年の月ヶ瀬梅渓保勝会概要によると、月ヶ瀬梅林保勝会管理対象の梅樹は約1万本とあり、名勝に登録されていない梅樹が相当数栽培されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the 1988&apos;s summary of Tsukigase Baikei hoshokai, the number of plum trees under the hoshokai &apos;s protection is approx.10,000, indicating that a huge number of unregistered plum trees is grown in the area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the summary of Tsukigase Baikei Hoshokai (association managing Tsukigase Baikei) from 1988, the number of plum trees under the hoshokai&apos;s protection is approximately 10,000, indicating that a huge number of unregistered plum trees are grown in the area.</e>
<cmt>月ヶ瀬梅渓保勝会の説明を追加しました。スペースを削除しました。approximatelyをフルで書きました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the summary of Tsukigase Baikei Hoshokai (association managing Tsukigase Baikei) from 1988, the number of plum trees under the hoshokai&apos;s protection is approximately 10,000, indicating that a huge number of unregistered plum trees are grown in the area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>月ヶ瀬村を合併した奈良市は2007年までに梅林の規模や衰退状況等を正確に調査した上「保存管理計画」を取りまとめる予定である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nara City which merged with Tsukigase Village is to conduct a thorough study on the Tsukigase Bairin in terms of its size and current waning situation, and to compile the &apos;plan for conservation and management&apos; by 2007.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nara City, which has absorbed Tsukigase Village, was to conduct a thorough study on the Tsukigase Bairin in terms of its size and current waning situation, and to compile a &apos;Conservation and Management Plan&apos; by 2007.</e>
<cmt>mergeをabsorbにしました。時制を修正しました。計画のタイトルを変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nara City, which has absorbed Tsukigase Village, was to conduct a thorough study on the Tsukigase Bairin in terms of its size and current waning situation, and to compile a &apos;Conservation and Management Plan&apos; by 2007.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="21">
<j>また「指定統計第26号『農林業センサス』」によると2000年の時点で旧月ヶ瀬村には約5.6ヘクタール（56 km2）の農業用梅林が存在し、21戸の農家がウメを栽培しているとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the &apos;Designated Statistics No. 26 &quot;Census of Agriculture and Forestry&quot;&apos;, the former Tsukigase Village had approx. 5.6 ha (56 sq.km) of agricultural plum fields, and 21 farmers grew plums as of 2000.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the &apos;Designated Statistics No. 26 &quot;Census of Agriculture and Forestry,&quot;&apos; as of 2000 the former Tsukigase Village had approximately 5.6 hectares (56 sq.km) of agricultural plum fields managed by 21 farms.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。コンマを移動しました。As of 2000を移動しました。Approximatelyとhectaresをフルで書きました。最終部分を大幅に変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the &apos;Designated Statistics No. 26 &quot;Census of Agriculture and Forestry,&quot;&apos; as of 2000 the former Tsukigase Village had approximately 5.6 hectares (56 sq.km) of agricultural plum fields managed by 21 farms.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>ただし、農林業センサスの記録からは月ヶ瀬梅渓保勝会の管理対象に農業用梅林が含まれるか否かは読み取れない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the record of the Census of Agriculture and Forestry does not say whether or not the plum-tree protection by Tsukigase Baikei hoshokai extends to these agricultural plum fields.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the records of the Census of Agriculture and Forestry do not indicate whether or not the plum-tree protection by Tsukigase Baikei Hoshokai extends to these agricultural plum fields.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。hoshokaiを大文字にしました。recordを複数形にしました。sayをindicateにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the records of the Census of Agriculture and Forestry do not indicate whether or not the plum-tree protection by Tsukigase Baikei Hoshokai extends to these agricultural plum fields.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="23">
<j>月ヶ瀬梅林で栽培されるウメの種類に関しては1957年に発表された「名勝月瀬学術調査」において「月ヶ瀬梅林では、梅の実の収穫量の多い遅咲きのウメばかりを栽培したために『春に先駆けて咲く梅の花』の魅力を感じられなくなった（意訳）」との考察がなされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for the types of plum trees cultivated in Tsukigase Bairin, &apos;The Academic Research on Scenic Beauty Tsukigase&apos; released its observations in 1957 that &apos;most plum trees in Tsukigase Bairin are prolific late bloomers, which has ruined one of the attractive features of the plum blossoms &quot;which heralded the arrival of spring&quot; (free translation)&apos;.</e>
<cmt>名勝月瀬学術調査→The Academic Research on Scenic Beauty Tsukigaseと訳出しています。 『』の位置を、英訳では少し後ろにずらしています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for the types of plum trees cultivated in Tsukigase Bairin, &apos;The Academic Research on Scenic Beauty Tsukigase&apos; released its observation in 1957 that &apos;most plum trees in Tsukigase Bairin are prolific late bloomers, which means one cannot appreciate the charm of &quot;plum blossoms heralding the arrival of spring&quot; (paraphrase).&apos;</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。observationを単数形にしました。Free translationをparaphraseにしました。ピリオドを移動しました。後半を大幅に変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for the types of plum trees cultivated in Tsukigase Bairin, &apos;The Academic Research on Scenic Beauty Tsukigase&apos; released its observation in 1957 that &apos;most plum trees in Tsukigase Bairin are prolific late bloomers, which means one cannot appreciate the charm of &quot;plum blossoms heralding the arrival of spring&quot; (paraphrase).&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="24">
<j>烏梅生産末期の明治時代ごろまでは未改良の野性的な品種のウメが栽培されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Until around the Meiji period when Ubai production came close to an end, unimproved wild plums had been cultivated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Until around the Meiji period when Ubai production came close to an end, unaltered wild plums had been cultivated.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。unimprovedをunalteredにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Until around the Meiji period when Ubai production came close to an end, unaltered wild plums had been cultivated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>野生種の梅果はクエン酸等の含有量が多く、烏梅の利用目的には適していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As wild plums contain a lot of citric acid, they were appropriate for Ubai production.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As wild plums contain a lot of citric acid, they were appropriate for Ubai production.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As wild plums contain a lot of citric acid, they were appropriate for Ubai production.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>しかし、酸味が強いため食用青梅としては市場から歓迎されず、烏梅から食用青梅生産に軸足を移す足かせになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, they were too sour to eat and not welcomed in the market, which hampered a shift of production from Ubai to edible plums.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, they were too sour to eat and not welcomed in the market, which hampered the shift of production from Ubai to edible plums.</e>
<cmt>冠詞を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, they were too sour to eat and not welcomed in the market, which hampered the shift of production from Ubai to edible plums.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>結果的に多くの梅樹が伐採され、桑畑や茶畑に転作されていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, many plum trees were cut down and the lands were transformed into mulberry- or tea-plantation fields.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, many plum trees were cut down and the land was transformed into mulberry or tea plantation fields.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。landを単数形にしました。ハイフンを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, many plum trees were cut down and the land was transformed into mulberry or tea plantation fields.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>政府・自治体の保護</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Protection by Government and Local Community</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Government and Local Community Protection</e>
<cmt>順序を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Government and Local Community Protection</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="28">
<j>名勝「月瀬梅林」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A Place of Scenic Beauty &apos;Tsukigase Bairin&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsukigase Bairin,&apos; a Place of Scenic Beauty</e>
<cmt>順序を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsukigase Bairin,&apos; a Place of Scenic Beauty</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="29">
<j>1922年3月8日 - 史蹟名勝天然紀念物保存法により指定。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 8, 1922 - designated as scenic beauty based on The Historical Spot, Scenic Beauty and Natural Monument Preservation Law.</e>
<cmt>訳文に説明語追加：as scenic beauty</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 8, 1922 - designated as a place of scenic beauty based on the Historical Spot, Scenic Beauty and Natural Monument Preservation Law.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。A placeを追加しました。theを小文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 8, 1922 - designated as a place of scenic beauty based on the Historical Spot, Scenic Beauty and Natural Monument Preservation Law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>内務省告示第49号。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">No. 49 Ministry of Interior Notification.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ministry of Interior Notification No. 49.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。順序を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ministry of Interior Notification No. 49.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>日本政府が初めて指定した名勝の一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is one of the first scenic beauty places designated by the Japanese government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is one of the first places of scenic beauty designated by the Japanese government.</e>
<cmt>placesを移動しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is one of the first places of scenic beauty designated by the Japanese government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="32">
<j>1950年 - 文化財保護法施行により指定更新。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1950 - renewed the designation after the enforcement of The Law for the Protection of Cultural Properties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1950 - renewed the designation after the enforcement of the Law for the Protection of Cultural Properties.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。theを小文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1950 - renewed the designation after the enforcement of the Law for the Protection of Cultural Properties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="33">
<j>奈良県立月ヶ瀬神野山自然公園</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nara Prefectural Tsukigase-Konoyama Natural Park</e>
<cmt>用語集ではKoyasanですが、Konoyamaのようです。自然公園は、nature parkではなくnatural parkと訳出しています。http://www.vill.yamazoe.nara.jp/kankou/k-foresuto.htm</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nara Prefectural Tsukigase-Konoyama Natural Park</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nara Prefectural Tsukigase-Konoyama Natural Park</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="34">
<j>1975年7月1日 - 指定。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">July 1, 1975 - designated as Nara Prefectural Tsukigase-Konoyama Natural Park.</e>
<cmt>訳文に説明語追加：as Nara Prefectural Tsukigase-Konoyama Natural Park</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">July 1, 1975 - designated as Nara Prefectural Tsukigase-Konoyama Natural Park.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">July 1, 1975 - designated as Nara Prefectural Tsukigase-Konoyama Natural Park.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>奈良県告示第178号。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">No. 178 Nara Prefectural Notification.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nara Prefectural Notification No. 178.</e>
<cmt>順序を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nara Prefectural Notification No. 178.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="36">
<j>月ヶ瀬桃香野のウメの古木</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ancient Plum Tree in Momogano, Tsukigase</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ancient Plum Tree in Momogano, Tsukigase</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ancient Plum Tree in Momogano, Tsukigase</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="37">
<j>19xx年 - 月ヶ瀬村指定文化財に指定。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">19xx - designated as a cultural property by Tsukigase Village</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">19xx - designated as a cultural property by Tsukigase Village.</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">19xx - designated as a cultural property by Tsukigase Village.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="38">
<j>2006年3月6日 - 奈良市指定文化財に指定。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 6, 2006 - designated as a cultural property by Nara City</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 6, 2006 - designated as a cultural property by Nara City.</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 6, 2006 - designated as a cultural property by Nara City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>表記</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanji Description</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanji Description</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanji Description</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="39">
<j>月ヶ瀬梅林の所在地、月ヶ瀬は「月ヶ瀬」「月ノ瀬」「月瀬」と複数の呼称・表記を持っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsukigase where Tsukigase Bairin is located is described in several different kanjis, &apos;月ヶ瀬&apos; (Tsukigase), &apos;月ノ瀬&apos; (Tsukinose) and &apos;月瀬&apos; (Tsukinose).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsukigase where Tsukigase Bairin is located is described in several different kanji combinations, &apos;月ヶ瀬&apos; (Tsukigase), &apos;月ノ瀬&apos; (Tsukinose) and &apos;月瀬&apos; (Tsukise).</e>
<cmt>combinationsを追加しました。wikiでは月瀬（つきせ）と表記されいます。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsukigase where Tsukigase Bairin is located is described in several different kanji combinations, &apos;月ヶ瀬&apos; (Tsukigase), &apos;月ノ瀬&apos; (Tsukinose) and &apos;月瀬&apos; (Tsukise).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>2007年現在においても「奈良市月ヶ瀬月瀬（ならしつきがせつきのせ）」という地名が現存している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As of 2007, there still exists a place, &apos;奈良市月ヶ瀬月瀬&apos; (Tsukigase Tsukinose, Nara City).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As of 2007, there still exists a place called &apos;奈良市月ヶ瀬月瀬&apos; (Tsukigase Tsukise, Nara City).</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。calledを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As of 2007, there still exists a place called &apos;奈良市月ヶ瀬月瀬&apos; (Tsukigase Tsukise, Nara City).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>この複数存在する呼称・表記の統一を図るため、1968年に当時の「月瀬村」は村名を「月ヶ瀬村」に変更した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order to unify these fluctuated descriptions, the village name was changed from &apos;月瀬村&apos; to &apos;月ヶ瀬村&apos; in 1968.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to unify these multiple names and descriptions, the village name was changed from &apos;Tsukise Village&apos; to &apos;Tsukigase Village&apos; in 1968.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。漢字表記を英語にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to unify these multiple names and descriptions, the village name was changed from &apos;Tsukise Village&apos; to &apos;Tsukigase Village&apos; in 1968.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="42">
<j>よって、「月ヶ瀬梅林」の表記は村名変更の前後で異なる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, the kanji description of &apos;Tsukigase Bairin&apos; varies before and after the change of the village name.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the kanji descriptions of &apos;Tsukigase Bairin&apos; before and after the change of the village name are different.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。descriptionを複数形にしました。Varyをdifferentにして移動しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the kanji descriptions of &apos;Tsukigase Bairin&apos; before and after the change of the village name are different.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>村名変更後は「月ヶ瀬梅林」の表記が一般的であり、『月ヶ瀬村史』においても「月ヶ瀬梅林」「月ヶ瀬梅渓」の表記で統一されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the village name change, &apos;月ヶ瀬梅林&apos; (Tsukigase Bairin) became a common term, and &quot;Tsukigase Sonshi&quot; (Tsukigase Village History) also uses the unified terms, &apos;月ヶ瀬梅林&apos; and &apos;月ヶ瀬梅渓&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the village name change, &apos;Tsukigase Bairin&apos; became the common term, and the names are unified as &apos;Tsukigase Bairin&apos; and &apos;Tsukigase Baikei&apos; in &quot;Tsukigase Sonshi&quot; (Tsukigase Village History).</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。冠詞を修正しました。順序を変えました。漢字表記を英語にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the village name change, &apos;Tsukigase Bairin&apos; became the common term, and the names are unified as &apos;Tsukigase Bairin&apos; and &apos;Tsukigase Baikei&apos; in &quot;Tsukigase Sonshi&quot; (Tsukigase Village History).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>しかし、名勝の登録名には登録当時の「月瀬梅林」の表記が残っており、2007年現在「月瀬梅林」の表記は変更されていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the description used for the scenic-beauty registration is still &apos;月瀬梅林&apos;, and no correction has been made to it as of 2007.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the description used for the registered name as the place of scenic beauty is still &apos;Tsukise Bairin,&apos; the name used at the time of original registration, and no correction has been made to it as of 2007.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。前半を訳し直しました。コンマを移動しました。漢字表記を英語にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the description used for the registered name as the place of scenic beauty is still &apos;Tsukise Bairin,&apos; the name used at the time of original registration, and no correction has been made to it as of 2007.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="45">
<j>※本記事では特に必要のある場合を除き、「月ヶ瀬村史」に従い「月ヶ瀬梅林」に統一して表記しました。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this article, &apos;月ヶ瀬梅林&apos; is used to describe the Bairin in accordance with the &apos;Tsukigase Village History&apos;, unless otherwise required.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this article, &apos;Tsukigase Bairin&apos; is used to describe the plum groves in accordance with the &apos;Tsukigase Village History,&apos; unless otherwise required.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。漢字表記を英語にしました。Bairinをplum grovesにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this article, &apos;Tsukigase Bairin&apos; is used to describe the plum groves in accordance with the &apos;Tsukigase Village History,&apos; unless otherwise required.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>みどころ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sightseeing Spot</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sightseeing</e>
<cmt>Spotを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sightseeing</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="46">
<j>月ヶ瀬梅林は月ヶ瀬尾山とその周辺に広がる梅林の総称で、実際には複数の梅林が存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsukigase Bairin is a collective term to call the Bairins stretching from Mt. Tsukigaseoyama to its surrounding areas, and in fact, the area has several different Bairins.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsukigase Bairin refers collectively to the plum groves stretching from Mt. Tsukigaseoyama to its surrounding areas, and actually, the area has several independent plum groves.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。bairinをplum grovesにし、より自然な表現に変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsukigase Bairin refers collectively to the plum groves stretching from Mt. Tsukigaseoyama to its surrounding areas, and actually, the area has several independent plum groves.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>ここでは「月ヶ瀬ウォーキングマップ」より梅林に関わりの深いみどころを抜粋して紹介する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this section, sightseeing spots closely related to the Bairin are introduced from the &apos;Map of Tsukigase for Walking&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this section, sightseeing spots from the &apos;Walking Map of Tsukigase&apos; which are closely related to the plum groves are introduced.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。訳し直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this section, sightseeing spots from the &apos;Walking Map of Tsukigase&apos; which are closely related to the plum groves are introduced.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="48">
<j>園生姫の碑 月ヶ瀬の地に烏梅を伝えたとされる園生姫（そのおひめ）を記念する石碑である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Monument of Princess Sonoohime: a stone monument to commemorate Prince Sonoohime who is believed to be the first person to bring Ubai to the Tsukigase area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Monument of Princess Sonohime: a stone monument to commemorate Prince Sonohime who is believed to be the first person to bring Ubai to the Tsukigase area.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。園生姫のローマ字表記を規定通りにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Monument of Princess Sonohime: a stone monument to commemorate Prince Sonohime who is believed to be the first person to bring Ubai to the Tsukigase area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="49">
<j>「名勝月瀬梅林」の石柱 日本国指定名勝に指定された際に建立された石柱である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Stone Pillar of &apos;Scenic Beauty Tsukigase Bairin&apos;: a stone pillar erected when the Bairin was designated as National Site of Scenic Beauty by the Japanese government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Stone Pillar of &apos;Scenic Beauty Tsukigase Bairin&apos;: a stone pillar erected when the Bairin was designated as National Site of Scenic Beauty by the Japanese government.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Stone Pillar of &apos;Scenic Beauty Tsukigase Bairin&apos;: a stone pillar erected when the Bairin was designated as National Site of Scenic Beauty by the Japanese government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="50">
<j>真福寺・一目八景 五月川と梅林が織り成す景観が美しい場所である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinpuku-ji Temple/Hitome Hakkei (eight different views at a glance): beautiful scenery consisting of the Satsuki River and Bairins.</e>
<cmt>一目八景→Hitome Hakkei (eight different views at a glance)と訳出しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinpuku-ji Temple/Hitome Hakkei (eight different views at a glance): beautiful scenery consisting of the Satsuki River and plum groves.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。Bairinをplum groveにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinpuku-ji Temple/Hitome Hakkei (eight different views at a glance): beautiful scenery consisting of the Satsuki River and plum groves.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="51">
<j>帆浦梅林 一目八景と天神梅林との間にある梅林である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Houra Bairin: a Bairin located between Hitome Hakkei and Tenjin Bairin.</e>
<cmt>帆浦梅林→語録ではHoura Japanese apricot gardenとありますが、他所でplumを使っている点と、gardenでは規模・ニュアンスがずれるため、そのままBairinで訳出しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Houra Bairin: a plum grove located between Hitome Hakkei and Tenjin Bairin.</e>
<cmt>Bairinをplum groveにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Houra Bairin: a plum grove located between Hitome Hakkei and Tenjin Bairin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="52">
<j>天神神社・天神梅林 天神神社は真福寺境内に建立された天神社である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tenjin-jinja Shrine/Tenjin Bairin - The Tenjin-jinja Shrine is situated on the grounds of Shinpuku-ji Temple, honoring the god of academic achievements, Michizane SUGAWARA.</e>
<cmt>天神梅林→語録ではTenjin Japanese apricot gardenとありますが、他所でplumを使っている点と、gardenでは規模・ニュアンスがずれるため、そのままBairinで訳出しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tenjin-jinja Shrine/Tenjin Bairin - Tenjin-jinja Shrine is situated on the grounds of Shinpuku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。冠詞を削除しました。originalに記載されていない内容を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tenjin-jinja Shrine/Tenjin Bairin - Tenjin-jinja Shrine is situated on the grounds of Shinpuku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>記録上、月ヶ瀬で最古に梅を植樹した場所と言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This place is believed to be the first place to have plum trees in Tsukigase, according to records.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to records, this place is believed to be the first place in Tsukigase to have plum trees planted.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。順序を置き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to records, this place is believed to be the first place in Tsukigase to have plum trees planted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="54">
<j>月瀬橋 旧月ヶ瀬村の中央で五月川を渡る橋で1893年に初めて架橋された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsukigase Bridge: built in 1893 across Satsuki River and located in the center of former Tsukigase Village.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsukigase Bridge: built in 1893 across Satsuki River and located in the center of former Tsukigase Village.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsukigase Bridge: built in 1893 across Satsuki River and located in the center of former Tsukigase Village.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>初代月瀬橋は木造であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The original Tsukigase Bridge was made of wood.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The original Tsukigase Bridge was made of wood.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The original Tsukigase Bridge was made of wood.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>現在の橋は高山ダム完成前に架橋された4代目の橋である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The current bridge is the 4th one built before the completion of Takayama Dam.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The current bridge is the 4th one, built before the completion of Takayama Dam.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。コンマを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The current bridge is the 4th one, built before the completion of Takayama Dam.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="57">
<j>鶯谷梅林 月瀬橋北岸の梅林である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Uguisudani Bairin: located in the north side of the Tsukigase Bridge.</e>
<cmt>鶯谷梅林→語録ではUguisudani Japanese apricot gardenとありますが、他所でplumを使っている点と、gardenでは規模・ニュアンスがずれるため、そのままBairinで訳出しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Uguisudani Bairin: located on the north side of the Tsukigase Bridge.</e>
<cmt>inをonにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Uguisudani Bairin: located on the north side of the Tsukigase Bridge.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="58">
<j>こけいし梅林・一目万本・芭蕉句碑 「春もやゝけしきとのふ月と梅」と刻まれているが、松尾芭蕉が月ヶ瀬の地に来た事実を実証する資料は存在せず、本当に芭蕉の句であるか否かははっきりしない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kokeishi Bairin/Hitome Manbon (ten thousands of plum trees at a glance)/Basho&apos;s Poem Monument: the monument is inscribed with Basho&apos;s poem that reads &apos;I feel spring has finally come to see beautiful moon and plum flowers&apos;, but there is no record of Basho MATSUO visiting Tsukigase and it is also not clear whether or not the poem was truly created by Basho.</e>
<cmt>こけいし梅林→語録ではKokeishi Japanese apricot gardenとありますが、他所でplumを使っている点と、gardenでは規模・ニュアンスがずれるため、そのままBairinで訳出しています。一目万本→Hitome Manbon (ten thousands of plum trees at a glance)と訳出しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokeishi Bairin/Hitome Manbon (ten thousand trees at a glance)/Basho&apos;s Poem Monument: the monument is inscribed with Basho&apos;s poem that reads &apos;I feel spring has finally come to see beautiful moon and plum flowers,&apos; but there is no record of Basho MATSUO visiting Tsukigase and it is also not clear whether or not the poem was truly created by Basho.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。コンマを移動しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kokeishi Bairin/Hitome Manbon (ten thousand trees at a glance)/Basho&apos;s Poem Monument: the monument is inscribed with Basho&apos;s poem that reads &apos;I feel spring has finally come to see beautiful moon and plum flowers,&apos; but there is no record of Basho MATSUO visiting Tsukigase and it is also not clear whether or not the poem was truly created by Basho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="59">
<j>龍王梅林・龍王の滝 龍王の滝は役行者の修行の地であったと伝わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryuo Bairin/Ryuo no taki (Dragon King Waterfall): Ryuo no taki is believed to be the training place for EN no Gyoja (A semi-legendary holy man noted for his practice of mountain asceticism during the second half of the 7 century).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryuo Bairin/Ryuo no taki (Dragon King Waterfall): Ryuo no taki is believed to have been the training place for EN no Gyoja (a semi-legendary holy man noted for his practice of mountain asceticism during the latter half of the 7th century).</e>
<cmt>aを小文字にしました。secondをlatterにしました。thを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryuo Bairin/Ryuo no taki (Dragon King Waterfall): Ryuo no taki is believed to have been the training place for EN no Gyoja (a semi-legendary holy man noted for his practice of mountain asceticism during the latter half of the 7th century).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="60">
<j>桃仙の梅 月ヶ瀬梅林で一番の古木であり、旧月ヶ瀬村指定文化財である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tosen no Ume (Plum Tree of Tosen): the oldest plum tree in Tsukigase Bairin and designated as a cultural property by former Tsukigase Village.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tosen no Ume (Plum Tree of Tosen): the oldest plum tree in Tsukigase Bairin and designated as a cultural property by the former Tsukigase Village.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。冠詞を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tosen no Ume (Plum Tree of Tosen): the oldest plum tree in Tsukigase Bairin and designated as a cultural property by the former Tsukigase Village.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>奈良女子大学教授の菅沼孝之により樹齢600年と査定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The tree is estimated to be 600 years old by Professor Takayuki SUGANUMA of Nara Women&apos;s University.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The tree is estimated to be 600 years old by Professor Takayuki SUGANUMA of Nara Women&apos;s University.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The tree is estimated to be 600 years old by Professor Takayuki SUGANUMA of Nara Women&apos;s University.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="62">
<j>雲景山梅林 月ヶ瀬桃香野に位置する梅林である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Unkeizan Bairin: situated in Momogano, Tsukigase.</e>
<cmt>雲景山梅林→Unkeizan Japanese apricot gardenとありますが、他所でplumを使っている点と、gardenでは規模・ニュアンスがずれるため、そのままBairinで訳出しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unkeizan Bairin: situated in Momogano, Tsukigase.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unkeizan Bairin: situated in Momogano, Tsukigase.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="63">
<j>起源</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Origin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Origin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Origin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="64">
<j>月ヶ瀬梅林の起源は古く、1205年（文久2年）に真福寺境内に天神社を建立する際、菅原道真の好んだ梅を植樹したとの口伝が残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A story has been handed down for generations that the origin of Tsukigase Bairin dates back to 1205 when plum trees were first planted to pay respect to Michizane SUGAWARA when his Ten-jinja Shrine was erected on the grounds of Shinpuku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A story has been handed down verbally for generations that the origin of Tsukigase Bairin dates back to 1205 when plum trees were first planted to pay respect to Michizane SUGAWARA when his Ten-jinja Shrine was erected on the grounds of Shinpuku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。verballyを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A story has been handed down verbally for generations that the origin of Tsukigase Bairin dates back to 1205 when plum trees were first planted to pay respect to Michizane SUGAWARA when his Ten-jinja Shrine was erected on the grounds of Shinpuku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>この記録の真偽は定かではないが、「桃仙の梅」が樹齢600年と推定されることから、月ヶ瀬梅林の起源は少なくとも600年前にさかのぼるのではないかと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the authenticity of this oral record has not be verified, it is believed that the origin of the Tsukigase Bairin goes back at least 600 years, as &apos;Tosen no Ume&apos; is estimated to have lived 600 years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the authenticity of this record has not been verified, it is believed that the origin of the Tsukigase Bairin goes back at least 600 years, as &apos;Tosen no Ume&apos; is estimated to have lived 600 years.</e>
<cmt>oralを削除しました。beをbeenにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the authenticity of this record has not been verified, it is believed that the origin of the Tsukigase Bairin goes back at least 600 years, as &apos;Tosen no Ume&apos; is estimated to have lived 600 years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>烏梅伝来</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Introduction of Ubai</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Introduction of Ubai</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Introduction of Ubai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="66">
<j>1331年に起こった元弘の乱で大敗を喫した後醍醐天皇が笠置山から撤退する際、一緒に逃げてきた女官の一人が月瀬に滞在した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A court lady, who fled from Mt. Kasagi with Emperor Godaigo in face of a crushing defeat in Onin War of 1331, came to Tsukigase to stay.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of the court ladies who had fled from Mt. Kasagi with Emperor Godaigo in the face of a crushing defeat in the Onin War of 1331 came to Tsukigase to stay.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of the court ladies who had fled from Mt. Kasagi with Emperor Godaigo in the face of a crushing defeat in the Onin War of 1331 came to Tsukigase to stay.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>その女官が熟れた梅の実を見て月瀬の民に京都で使用される紅花染め用の烏梅の製法を教えたという伝承が残る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has been told that the lady looked at ripe plums and decided to introduce to the people of Tsukigase the production method of Ubai, an ingredient for safflower dyes which was popularly used in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has been told that the lady looked at ripe plums and decided to introduce the production method of Ubai, an ingredient for safflower dyes which was popularly used in Kyoto to the people of Tsukigase.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。順序を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has been told that the lady looked at ripe plums and decided to introduce the production method of Ubai, an ingredient for safflower dyes which was popularly used in Kyoto to the people of Tsukigase.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>その約100年後の15世紀ごろには五月川流域一帯は烏梅を作るための梅林で埋め尽くされたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that about 100 years later by the 15th century, the areas across Satsuki River were filled with plum trees to produce Ubai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that around the 15th century, about 100 years later, the entire area around Satsuki River was completely covered with plum trees to produce Ubai.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。自然な表現に変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that around the 15th century, about 100 years later, the entire area around Satsuki River was completely covered with plum trees to produce Ubai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="69">
<j>深い渓谷にある月瀬の村々には耕作地として利用できる土地に乏しく、厳しく取り立てられる上納米を納める余裕がなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the villages in Tsukigase which were situated alongside the deep valleys did not have enough cultivated fields, they could not afford paying to the government the tribute rice which were collected without mercy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the villages in Tsukigase which were situated in deep valleys did not have enough land to grow crops, villagers could not afford to provide the government with the tribute rice which was strictly collected.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。訳し直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the villages in Tsukigase which were situated in deep valleys did not have enough land to grow crops, villagers could not afford to provide the government with the tribute rice which was strictly collected.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>そこで換金作物である烏梅を生産し、烏梅の販売金を銀納した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, they produced a cash crop, Ubai, to receive cash and paid its proceeds in silver to the government instead.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, they produced a cash crop, Ubai, in order to pay the equivalent in cash from the sale of Ubai.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。訳し直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, they produced a cash crop, Ubai, in order to pay the equivalent in cash from the sale of Ubai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>耕作地として利用できない斜面で烏梅に用いる梅を栽培し、限られた耕作地では自給食料を生産することで自らの生活を守ったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They protected their life by cultivating plum trees for Ubai on barren hillsides which were not suitable to cultivate foods, while producing food for themselves on limited fertile lands.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They protected their livlihoods by cultivating plum trees for Ubai on barren hillsides which were not suitable to grow crops, while producing food for themselves on the limited fertile lands.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。lifeをlivelihoodsに変えました。Cultivate foodsをgrow cropsにしました。冠詞を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They protected their livlihoods by cultivating plum trees for Ubai on barren hillsides which were not suitable to grow crops, while producing food for themselves on the limited fertile lands.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>最盛期</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Golden Age</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Golden Age</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Golden Age</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="72">
<j>月ヶ瀬梅林が文献上はじめて紹介されるのは江戸時代に入ってからである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was not until in the Edo period that Tsukigase Bairin was introduced in literature.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was not until in the Edo period that Tsukigase Bairin was introduced in literature.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was not until in the Edo period that Tsukigase Bairin was introduced in literature.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>1772年に神沢其蜩が著した『翁草』において月ヶ瀬梅林が紹介された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsukigase Bairin was first mentioned in &quot;Okina gusa&quot;, which was written by Kicho KANZAWA in 1772.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsukigase Bairin was first mentioned in &quot;Okina gusa,&quot; which was written by Kicho KANZAWA in 1772.</e>
<cmt>コンマを移動しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsukigase Bairin was first mentioned in &quot;Okina gusa,&quot; which was written by Kicho KANZAWA in 1772.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>続いて、1803年に大坂の儒学者である田宮仲宜が著した『東&amp;ampx7256子』では挿絵を添えて紹介している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was followed by the publication of &quot;Toyushi&quot; in 1803 written by 田宮仲宜, a Confucian scholar from Osaka, in which the Bairin was introduced with illustrations.</e>
<cmt>田宮仲宜-読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was followed by the publication of &quot;Toyushi&quot; in 1803 written by Nakanobu TAMIYA, a Confucian scholar from Osaka, in which the plum groves were introduced with illustrations.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。bairinをplum grovesに変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was followed by the publication of &quot;Toyushi&quot; in 1803 written by Nakanobu TAMIYA, a Confucian scholar from Osaka, in which the plum groves were introduced with illustrations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="75">
<j>当時の烏梅は収益率がよく、年によっては米や麦の数倍の値段となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In those days, Ubai was highly profitable and priced several-fold higher than rice and wheat in some years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In those days, Ubai was highly profitable and depending on the year was valued several times higher than rice or wheat.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。訳し直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In those days, Ubai was highly profitable and depending on the year was valued several times higher than rice or wheat.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>このため月ヶ瀬の住民は競って梅の植栽を行い、烏梅を生産した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This brought a competition among Tsukigase villagers in planting plum trees to produce Ubai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This brought competition among Tsukigase villagers in planting plum trees to produce Ubai.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。aを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This brought competition among Tsukigase villagers in planting plum trees to produce Ubai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>享和、文化、文政年代の月瀬周辺に関わる借用書には梅木畑の入質記録が散見され、この時代には畑一面にまで梅が植えられていたことが窺える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the IOUs of Tsukigase areas created during the eras of Kyowa, Bunka and Bunsei show, plum-tree fields frequently appear on a pawn list, indicating that plum trees were planted on entire cultivated fields as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the IOUs of the Tsukigase region created during the Kyowa, Bunka and Bunsei eras (1801-1830) plum-tree fields frequently appear on a pawn lists, indicating that plum trees were planted on entire crop fields as well.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。areasをregionに変えました。eraを名前の後に付けました。コンマを削除しました。listを複数形にしました。cultivatedをcropにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the IOUs of the Tsukigase region created during the Kyowa, Bunka and Bunsei eras (1801-1830) plum-tree fields frequently appear on a pawn lists, indicating that plum trees were planted on entire crop fields as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>1810年～1830年ごろ（文化、文政年間）の最盛期には、月ヶ瀬梅林には10万本近くの梅の木が栽培されていたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At its peak around 1810 to 1830 (Bunka and Bunsei eras), it is believed that nearly 100,000 plum trees were grown in Tsukigase Bairin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At its peak around 1810 to 1830 (Bunka and Bunsei eras), it is believed that nearly 100,000 plum trees were grown in Tsukigase Bairin.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At its peak around 1810 to 1830 (Bunka and Bunsei eras), it is believed that nearly 100,000 plum trees were grown in Tsukigase Bairin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="79">
<j>1819年、山田 (伊勢市)の学者であった韓聯玉が記した『遊月瀬記』では月ヶ瀬の光景を以下のように記している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1819, Rengyoku Kan, a scholar from Yamada (Ise City), described the scenery of Tsukigase in his writing, &quot;Yu Tsukigase Ki&quot;, as follows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1819, Rengyoku Kan, a scholar from Yamada (Ise City), described the scenery of Tsukigase in his writing, &quot;Yu Tsukigase Ki&quot;, as below.</e>
<cmt>followsをbelowにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1819, Rengyoku Kan, a scholar from Yamada (Ise City), described the scenery of Tsukigase in his writing, &quot;Yu Tsukigase Ki&quot;, as below.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="80">
<j>梅花層出、山に溢れ谷を&amp;ampx5861め、霏々族々朝陽と廉を競う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">梅花層出、山に溢れ谷を塡め、霏々族々朝陽と廉を競う。</e>
<cmt>意味解釈が困難なため訳出できず。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Plum flowers bloom, filling the mountains and valleys, competing with the morning sun falling down.</e>
<cmt>訳出は推測です。日本語ネイティブの方にチェックをお願いします。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Plum flowers bloom, filling the mountains and valleys, competing with the morning sun falling down.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>（中略）一大石苔あり湿灌綴り老梅之を掩ふ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(中略)一大石苔あり湿灌綴り老梅之を掩ふ。</e>
<cmt>意味解釈が困難なため訳出できず。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(snip) There is a large mossy stone, humidity closes in on the old plum trees.</e>
<cmt>訳出は推測です。日本語ネイティブの方にチェックをお願いします。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(snip) There is a large mossy stone, humidity closes in on the old plum trees.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>天然の巧置人をして&amp;ampx5ed4々眷みて去る能はざらむ、既に村に入れば岸壁籬落の際芳雪和霧之を尾山に較ぶれば尤も絶勝たり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">天然の巧置人をして廔々眷みて去る能はざらむ、既に村に入れば岸壁籬落の際芳雪和霧之を尾山に較ぶれば尤も絶勝たり。</e>
<cmt>意味解釈が困難なため訳出できず。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">天然の巧置人をして廔々眷みて去る能はざらむ、既に村に入れば岸壁籬落の際芳雪和霧之を尾山に較ぶれば尤も絶勝たり。</e>
<cmt>訳出できませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">天然の巧置人をして廔々眷みて去る能はざらむ、既に村に入れば岸壁籬落の際芳雪和霧之を尾山に較ぶれば尤も絶勝たり。</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="83">
<j>五月川の深い渓谷と万本の梅が織り成す絶景は次第に遠方にまで知れ渡るようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A magnificent landscape with deep valleys across Satsuki River coupled with ten thousands of plum trees was gradually known far and wide.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The magnificent scenery of the deep valleys surrounding Satsuki River and ten thousand plum trees gradually became known far and wide.</e>
<cmt>訳し直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The magnificent scenery of the deep valleys surrounding Satsuki River and ten thousand plum trees gradually became known far and wide.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="84">
<j>月ヶ瀬梅林の名勝としての地位を不動にしたのは津藩の儒学者であった斉藤拙堂が1830年に著した書物『月瀬記勝（つきがせきしょう／げつらいきしょう）』の影響が大きい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The biggest influence was &quot;Tsukigase Kisho or Getsurai Kisho&quot; written in 1830 by Setsudo SAITO, a Confucian scholar of Tsu Clan, which helped Tsukigase Bairin receive an unwavering reputation as a place of scenic beauty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was &quot;Tsukigase Kisho or Getsurai Kisho&quot; written in 1830 by Setsudo SAITO, a Confucian scholar of Tsu Clan, which had the largest effect in garnering Tsukigase Bairin its unwavering reputation as a site of scenic beauty.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。順序を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was &quot;Tsukigase Kisho or Getsurai Kisho&quot; written in 1830 by Setsudo SAITO, a Confucian scholar of Tsu Clan, which had the largest effect in garnering Tsukigase Bairin its unwavering reputation as a site of scenic beauty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>拙堂やその同行者が月ヶ瀬を訪れて20年後に発刊された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The book was published 20 years after Setsudo and his accompanying men first visited Tsukigase.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The book was published 20 years after Setsudo and his accompanying men first visited Tsukigase.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The book was published 20 years after Setsudo and his accompanying men first visited Tsukigase.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>「乾」「坤」の2巻からなる書物で全巻漢文・漢詩であり、要所に挿絵が入っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The book consists of two versions, &apos;Ken&apos; and &apos;Kon&apos;, which are written in the form of Chinese classics and Chinese poetry dotted with illustrations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The book consists of two volumes, &apos;Ken&apos; and &apos;Kon,&apos; which are written in the form of Chinese classics and Chinese poetry dotted with illustrations.</e>
<cmt>versionをvolumeにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The book consists of two volumes, &apos;Ken&apos; and &apos;Kon,&apos; which are written in the form of Chinese classics and Chinese poetry dotted with illustrations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>拙堂やその同行者はこの書物の中で月ヶ瀬を激賞している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Setsudo and his followers highly admired Tsukigase in the book.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the book, Setsudo and his followers highly praised Tsukigase.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。順序を変えました。admireをpraiseにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the book, Setsudo and his followers highly praised Tsukigase.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>『月瀬記勝』は明治時代・大正時代に至るまで土産物店で手軽に購入できるガイドブックとして多くの人々にもてはやされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The &quot;Tsukigase Kisho&quot; had been a very popular guidebook which was readily available at souvenir shops, until as recently as Meiji and Taisho periods.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Tsukigase Kisho&quot; was a very popular guidebook which was readily available at souvenir shops until as recently as Meiji and Taisho periods.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。冠詞を修正しました。コンマを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Tsukigase Kisho&quot; was a very popular guidebook which was readily available at souvenir shops until as recently as Meiji and Taisho periods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>また、1932年発刊の『師範漢文改制版・巻二』（明治書院）と題する師範学校の教科書に『月瀬記勝』の一部が使用された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, some parts of &quot;Tsukigase Kisho&quot; were used in the textbook for Normal School (a school for teacher training), titled &quot;Revised Chinese Classics for Teachers. Vol. 2&quot; (Meiji-Shoin Publications) published in 1932.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, a section from &quot;Tsukigase Kisho&quot; was used in a teachers&apos; college textbook titled &quot;Revised Chinese Classics for Teachers. Vol. 2&quot; (Meiji-Shoin Publications), published in 1932.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。訳し直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, a section from &quot;Tsukigase Kisho&quot; was used in a teachers&apos; college textbook titled &quot;Revised Chinese Classics for Teachers. Vol. 2&quot; (Meiji-Shoin Publications), published in 1932.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>衰退と保護</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Decline and Protection</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Decline and Protection</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Decline and Protection</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="90">
<j>明治時代に入り合成染料が伝来すると、烏梅を用いた手間のかかる紅花染めは徐々に行われなくなり、烏梅の価格は暴落した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Meiji period when synthesized dyes were introduced, time-consuming safflower dyes made from Ubai were phased out, resulting in the price of Ubai to nosedive.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Meiji period when synthesized dyes were introduced, time-consuming safflower dyes made from Ubai were phased out, causing the price of Ubai to nosedive.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。Resulting inをcausingに変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Meiji period when synthesized dyes were introduced, time-consuming safflower dyes made from Ubai were phased out, causing the price of Ubai to nosedive.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>梅樹の手入れはおろそかになり、畑地に植えられていた梅は伐採されて他の作物に植え替えられていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Plum trees were left unattended and those planted on the cultivated lands were cut down to be replaced by other crops.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Plum trees were left unattended and those planted on crop fields were cut down to be replaced by other crops.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。Cultivated landsをcrop fieldsに変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Plum trees were left unattended and those planted on crop fields were cut down to be replaced by other crops.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>最盛期に10万本を誇った梅林は徐々に衰退してゆく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The once-flourished Bairin which hosted 100,000 plum trees at its peak was on the wane.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The plum groves which boasted 100,000 plum trees at its peak slowly deteoriated.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。訳し直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The plum groves which boasted 100,000 plum trees at its peak slowly deteoriated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>しかし、風光明媚な風景を求めて観光客はむしろ増えていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the number of tourists who sought for beautiful scenery increased to the contrary.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the number of tourists who came seeking the beautiful scenery increased.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。Sought forをcame seeking theにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the number of tourists who came seeking the beautiful scenery increased.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>月ヶ瀬梅林は徐々に一般の人々の観光地に変化していく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsukigase Bairin was slowly changed into a tourist site for people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsukigase Bairin slowly changed into a tourist destination.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。wasを削除しました。Site for peopleをdestinationに変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsukigase Bairin slowly changed into a tourist destination.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="95">
<j>一方、朽ちてゆく月ヶ瀬梅林を守るための保存活動が行われるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, activities to protect rotting Tsukigase Bairin was begun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, people began to take action to protect the rotting Tsukigase Bairin.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。訳し直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, people began to take action to protect the rotting Tsukigase Bairin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>上野市を務めたことのある伊賀上野の事業家、田中善助は隣村の梅林を守るために「月瀬保勝会」を発足させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zensuke TANAKA, an entrepreneur of Iga Ueno and the former mayor of Ueno City, established &apos;Tsukigase Hoshokai&apos; (Tsukigase Conservation Association) to protect Bairin in the neighboring village.</e>
<cmt>上野市→上野市長 the former mayor of Ueno Cityと訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zensuke TANAKA, an entrepreneur of Iga Ueno and the former mayor of Ueno City, established &apos;Tsukigase Hoshokai&apos; (Tsukigase Conservation Association) to protect the plum groves in the neighboring village.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。Bairinをthe plum grovesに変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zensuke TANAKA, an entrepreneur of Iga Ueno and the former mayor of Ueno City, established &apos;Tsukigase Hoshokai&apos; (Tsukigase Conservation Association) to protect the plum groves in the neighboring village.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>しかし村民の意識の低さからか、梅林の伐採はおさまらず、月瀬保勝会の事業は頓挫した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, due to low awareness among villagers, cut-down of plum trees continued and the conservation efforts of Tsukigase Hoshokai was stalled.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, possibly due to the lack of awareness among villagers, plum trees continued to be cut down, stalling the conservation efforts of Tsukigase Hoshokai.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。自然な順序に置き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, possibly due to the lack of awareness among villagers, plum trees continued to be cut down, stalling the conservation efforts of Tsukigase Hoshokai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="98">
<j>1889年、町村制施行により月瀬村が発足すると、奈良県知事税所篤や月瀬村長奥田源吉らは梅林の衰退を憂い、租税減免など、梅林保護の政策を実施した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the establishment of Tsukigase Village in 1889 in accordance with the enforcement of The Municipal Government Act turned the tide; the governor of Nara Prefecture, Atsushi SAISHO, and the mayor of Tsukigase Village, Genkichi OKUDA, lamented the waning state of the Bairin and decided to protect it through measures including tax reduction or tax exemption.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the establishment of Tsukigase Village in 1889 in accordance with the enforcement of The Municipal Government Act turned the tide; the governor of Nara Prefecture, Atsushi SAISHO, and the mayor of Tsukigase Village, Genkichi OKUDA, lamented the waning state of the plum groves and implemented tax reductions and exemptions as well as plum grove protection measures.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。bairinをplum grovesにしました。最終部分を訳し直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the establishment of Tsukigase Village in 1889 in accordance with the enforcement of The Municipal Government Act turned the tide; the governor of Nara Prefecture, Atsushi SAISHO, and the mayor of Tsukigase Village, Genkichi OKUDA, lamented the waning state of the plum groves and implemented tax reductions and exemptions as well as plum grove protection measures.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>熱意が功を奏し、月瀬村民は自主的に「月瀬保勝会」の運営を行うようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Their dedicated efforts finally paid off, and Tsukigase villagers became involved in the management of &apos;Tsukigase Hoshokai&apos; voluntarily.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their dedicated efforts paid off, and Tsukigase villagers voluntarily became involved in the management of &apos;Tsukigase Hoshokai.&apos;</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。finallyを削除しました。voluntarilyを移動しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Their dedicated efforts paid off, and Tsukigase villagers voluntarily became involved in the management of &apos;Tsukigase Hoshokai.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>資金難から活発な事業を行えずにいたが、活動強化を目指し、1919年には「財団法人月瀬保勝会」として法人改組している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although financial difficulties kept the association from taking active measures, it was incorporated as &apos;Tsukigase Hoshokai Foundation&apos; in 1919 in an effort to reinforce its activities.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although financial difficulties kept the association from taking active measures, it was incorporated as &apos;Tsukigase Hoshokai Foundation&apos; in 1919 in an effort to reinforce its activities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although financial difficulties kept the association from taking active measures, it was incorporated as &apos;Tsukigase Hoshokai Foundation&apos; in 1919 in an effort to reinforce its activities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>「財団法人月瀬保勝会」の設立と時を同じくして、月瀬村当局も梅林の保護に関心を持ち始め、政府に対して名勝指定への陳情を続けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To coincide with the establishment of &apos;Tsukigase Hoshokai Foundation&apos;, the municipal government of Tsukigase Village itself begun to be involved in the protection of the Bairin, which led to the continued plea to the government to designate the Bairin as National Site of Scenic Beauty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To coincide with the establishment of &apos;Tsukigase Hoshokai Foundation,&apos; the municipal government of Tsukigase Village itself began to be involved in the protection of the plum groves, which led to the continued plea to the government to designate Tsukigase Bairin as a National Site of Scenic Beauty.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。コンマを移動しました。bairinをplum grovesに変えました。aを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To coincide with the establishment of &apos;Tsukigase Hoshokai Foundation,&apos; the municipal government of Tsukigase Village itself began to be involved in the protection of the plum groves, which led to the continued plea to the government to designate Tsukigase Bairin as a National Site of Scenic Beauty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="102">
<j>以上の努力の結果により、1922年、当時の内務省 (日本)は日本国が指定する初めての名勝に奈良公園、兼六園とともに「月瀬梅林」を指定した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These efforts paid off in 1922 when prewar Ministry of Home Affairs designated &apos;Tsukigase Bairin&apos; as its first National Site of Scenic Beauty along with Nara Park and Kenroku-en Garden.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These efforts paid off in 1922 when the pre-war Ministry of Home Affairs designated &apos;Tsukigase Bairin&apos; as its first National Site of Scenic Beauty along with Nara Park and Kenroku-en Garden.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。ハイフンを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These efforts paid off in 1922 when the pre-war Ministry of Home Affairs designated &apos;Tsukigase Bairin&apos; as its first National Site of Scenic Beauty along with Nara Park and Kenroku-en Garden.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="103">
<j>梅林の保護は軌道に乗り始めたかに見えたが、1937年ごろからの戦時統制の時代に突入すると食糧増産のために梅の木畑は半ば強制的に伐採され、耕作地に姿を変えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It seemed the protection efforts of the Bairin got on a right track, but the plum fields begun to be cut down again almost forcibly and transformed into farm lands to increase food production, when the wartime controls was imposed around 1937.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It seemed the protection efforts of the plum groves had gotten on the right track, but with wartime control being introduced from around 1937, plum trees were almost forcibly cut down and fields were transformed into farmland to increase food production.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。順序を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It seemed the protection efforts of the plum groves had gotten on the right track, but with wartime control being introduced from around 1937, plum trees were almost forcibly cut down and fields were transformed into farmland to increase food production.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>そして、戦前は2万本といわれた梅の木は戦後は半分以下まで減少した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">200,000 plum trees grown before the war were reduced to less than half that number after the war.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fewer than half of the 200,000 plum trees that existed before the war remained afterwards.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。意訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fewer than half of the 200,000 plum trees that existed before the war remained afterwards.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>高山ダム建設と新生月ヶ瀬梅林</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Construction of Takayama Dam and New Tsukigase Bairin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Construction of Takayama Dam and New Tsukigase Bairin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Construction of Takayama Dam and New Tsukigase Bairin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="105">
<j>1953年に当時の建設省から木津川総合開発計画が発表された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1953, Ministry of Construction announced Comprehensive Development of the Upstream Area of Kizu-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>木津川総合開発計画は、木津川上流総合開発事業と同義であり、加えて、前者は正式名称ではないようなので、後者で訳出しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1953, the Ministry of Construction of the time announced the Comprehensive Development Plan of the Upstream Area of Kizu-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。theを追加しました。Planを追加しました。Of the timeを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1953, the Ministry of Construction of the time announced the Comprehensive Development Plan of the Upstream Area of Kizu-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>大阪平野を洪水から守るため、木津川 (京都府)支流に水量調節用のダムを建設する計画であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The aim of the project was to construct a dam in the branch of Kizu-gawa River (Kyoto Prefecture) to adjust water volume to protect Osaka plains from flooding.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The aim of the project was to construct a dam in the branch of Kizu-gawa River (Kyoto Prefecture) to adjust water volume to protect the Osaka Plains from flooding.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。Osaka plainsを固定名詞扱いにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The aim of the project was to construct a dam in the branch of Kizu-gawa River (Kyoto Prefecture) to adjust water volume to protect the Osaka Plains from flooding.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>この計画には名張川の高山ダムが含まれており、計画の実現は月ヶ瀬梅渓の水没を意味した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This project included the construction of Takayama Dam on Nabari-gawa River, which meant that if it was completed, Tsukigase Baikei would be swallowed by the Dam.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This project included the construction of Takayama Dam on Nabari-gawa River, which meant that if it was completed, Tsukigase Baikei would be swallowed up by the Dam.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。upを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This project included the construction of Takayama Dam on Nabari-gawa River, which meant that if it was completed, Tsukigase Baikei would be swallowed up by the Dam.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>月ヶ瀬村では村を挙げての反対運動が行われ、奈良県やマスコミも声を上げたが、下流域の安全確保の大義の前にしてついに水没を回避することはできなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsukigase Village carried out official protests and Nara City and mass media also voiced opposition, but the construction could not be stopped for the cause of safety in the lower stream area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsukigase Village carried out official protests and Nara City and mass media also voiced opposition, but the construction could not be stopped for the cause of securing safety in the downstream area.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。securingを追加しました。Lower streamをdownstreamにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsukigase Village carried out official protests and Nara City and mass media also voiced opposition, but the construction could not be stopped for the cause of securing safety in the downstream area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="109">
<j>約10年間の交渉により梅林の復元と新生月ヶ瀬の再建を条件に高山ダムの建設工事は開始された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After about 10 years of negotiation, the construction work of Takayama Dam started on condition that the Bairin is restored and a new Tsukigase area is created.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After about 10 years of negotiation, the construction work of Takayama Dam started with the conditions that the plum groves would be restored and a new Tsukigase area would be created.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。bairinをplum grovesに変えました。On conditionをwith the contidionsに変えました。isをwould beに変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After about 10 years of negotiation, the construction work of Takayama Dam started with the conditions that the plum groves would be restored and a new Tsukigase area would be created.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="110">
<j>高山ダムが完成すると約3800本の梅がダムの底に水没することになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Completion of Takayama Dam meant about 3,800 plum trees would be swallowed by the dam.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Completion of Takayama Dam meant about 3,800 plum trees would be swallowed up by the water.</e>
<cmt>Upを追加しました。damをwaterにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Completion of Takayama Dam meant about 3,800 plum trees would be swallowed up by the water.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>水没する梅林を補償するため、移植可能な古木を現在の月ヶ瀬尾山天神の森付近や月ヶ瀬嵩三山付近に移植した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order to save the submerging Bairin, some transplantable old trees were moved to the area around Mt. Tsukigaseoyama Tenjin-no Mori Forest and Mt. Tsukigasedake miyama.</e>
<cmt>三山→読み方不明(miyama)と訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to save the submerging plum groves, some transplantable old trees were moved to the area around Mt. Tsukigaseoyama Tenjin-no Mori Forest and the three mountains surrounding Mt. Tsukigasedake.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。三山は「大和三山」と解釈しました。bairinをplum grovesに変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to save the submerging plum groves, some transplantable old trees were moved to the area around Mt. Tsukigaseoyama Tenjin-no Mori Forest and the three mountains surrounding Mt. Tsukigasedake.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>また、月瀬村内各所に新たな梅林が設けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, new Bairins were created in various places of Tsukigase Village.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, new plum groves were planted in various places around Tsukigase Village.</e>
<cmt>bairinをplum groveにしました。createdをplantedにしました。ofをaroundにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, new plum groves were planted in various places around Tsukigase Village.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="113">
<j>また、梅林を保護する立場である月ヶ瀬保勝会は戦中戦後の混乱から休眠状態に陥っていたが、新生月ヶ瀬梅林を盛り立てるために活動を再開した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emerged from the dormant state during the wartime and postwar turmoil, Tsukigase Hoshokai resumed its operation to support the new Tsukigase Bairin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emerging from the dormant state it had fallen into during the war and postwar turmoil, Tsukigase Hoshokai resumed its operation to support the new Tsukigase Bairin.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。It had fallen intoを追加しました。warをwartimeにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emerging from the dormant state it had fallen into during the war and postwar turmoil, Tsukigase Hoshokai resumed its operation to support the new Tsukigase Bairin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="114">
<j>高山ダム工事中には、水没する前の月ヶ瀬の姿を一目見るために多くの観光客が押し寄せた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the construction of Takayama Dam, many tourists visited the site to have one last look at the landscape of Tsukigase before being gulped by water.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the construction of Takayama Dam, many tourists visited the site to take one last look at the landscape of Tsukigase before being swallowed up by water.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。haveをtakeにしました。gulpedをswallowed upにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the construction of Takayama Dam, many tourists visited the site to take one last look at the landscape of Tsukigase before being swallowed up by water.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>最盛期には1日当たり2 - 3万人の観光客で賑わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">20,000 to 30,000 tourists visited the village a day at its peak.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At its peak, 20,000 to 30,000 tourists visited each day.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。順序を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At its peak, 20,000 to 30,000 tourists visited each day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="116">
<j>ちょうど自家用車が普及し始めた時代であり、駐車場不足により中学校の校庭を駐車場に開放せざるを得ない状況であったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was the time when people started owning a car, the village had to use the playground of a junior high school as an extra parking space to compensate the lack of parking lot.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was the time when people had started owning their own cars, and the village had to use the playground of a local junior high school to compensate for the lack of parking.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。時制を修正しました。後半を訳し直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was the time when people had started owning their own cars, and the village had to use the playground of a local junior high school to compensate for the lack of parking.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="117">
<j>高山ダムは1969年に完成し、五月川の渓谷は月ヶ瀬湖に変貌した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takayama Dam was completed in 1969, and the Satsuki River Valley was replaced by Lake Tsukigase.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takayama Dam was completed in 1969, and the Satsuki River Valley was replaced by Lake Tsukigase.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takayama Dam was completed in 1969, and the Satsuki River Valley was replaced by Lake Tsukigase.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="118">
<j>渓谷が沈んだ後も月ヶ瀬梅林では月ヶ瀬梅渓保勝会や観光協会による梅林の管理保全、移植梅樹や幼木梅の育成が続けられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even after the Valley was submerged under water, Tsukigase Baikei hoshokai and tourist associations continue their efforts to manage and protect Tsukigase Bairin and foster transplanted or young plum trees.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even though the valley has gone under water, Tsukigase Baikei Hoshokai and tourist associations continue their efforts to manage and protect Tsukigase Bairin and foster transplanted or young plum trees.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。Hoshokaiを大文字にしました。時制を修正しました。Valleyを小文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even though the valley has gone under water, Tsukigase Baikei Hoshokai and tourist associations continue their efforts to manage and protect Tsukigase Bairin and foster transplanted or young plum trees.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="119">
<j>また、月ヶ瀬梅林は1975年には奈良県立月ヶ瀬神野山自然公園の一部に指定された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, Tsukigase Bairin was designated a part of Nara Prefectural Tsukigase Konoyama Natural Park in 1975.</e>
<cmt>神野山→Konoyamaで訳出しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsukigase Bairin was designated a part of Nara Prefectural Tsukigase Konosan Natural Park in 1975.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。神野山はKonosanです。（google maps参照）alsoを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsukigase Bairin was designated a part of Nara Prefectural Tsukigase Konosan Natural Park in 1975.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="120">
<j>名阪国道の開通や都道府県道・広域農道の整備などにより交通事情が改善したこともあり、1988年には推定観光客10万人以上を見込める観光地となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As opening of Meihan National Rout and improved prefectural roads and wide-area farm road contributed to the better traffic conditions, Tsukigase has grown to be the tourist spot which expects more than 100,000 tourists in 1988.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The opening of the Meihan Expressway and improved prefectural roads and wide farm roads have contributed to better traffic conditions, Tsukigase has grown to be a tourist destination which expected more than 100,000 tourists in 1988.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。Meihan Expressway（http://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E5%90%8D%E9%98%AA%E5%9B%BD%E9%81%93参照）時制を修正しました。spotをdestinationに変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The opening of the Meihan Expressway and improved prefectural roads and wide farm roads have contributed to better traffic conditions, Tsukigase has grown to be a tourist destination which expected more than 100,000 tourists in 1988.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="121">
<j>今では月ヶ瀬湖の湖水と育成した梅樹が調和し、新生月ヶ瀬梅林が観光客の目を楽しませている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today, the lake water of Lake Tsukigase and grown plum trees coexist in harmony, and the newborn Tsukigase Bairin provides beautiful landscape to tourists.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, Lake Tsukigase and grown plum trees compliment each other perfectly, and tourists enjoy the amazing beauty of the newborn Tsukigase Bairin.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。originalが英語ではあまり自然ではなかったので意訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, Lake Tsukigase and grown plum trees compliment each other perfectly, and tourists enjoy the amazing beauty of the newborn Tsukigase Bairin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 ミッキーマウスのぬいぐるみ(id:80103), Rusk(id:9895), Fievarsty(id:201483), N yotarou(id:60870), Excl-zoo(id:47086), Tawashi2006(id:95112), Complex01(id:10454), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>