<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>金烏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kinu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>金烏（きんう）は、太陽に三本足の烏がいるという伝説であり、すなわちその烏（火烏）、ないし太陽の異称である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinu is a story of a bird with three legs in the sun; it refers to the bird (kau) and the sun.</e>
<cmt>読み方不明のため、火鳥→Kau と訳出しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kinu is a story of a bird with three legs in the sun; it refers to the bird (kau) and the sun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinu is a story of a bird with three legs in the sun; it refers to the bird (kau) and the sun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>対称に玉兎。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The opposite story was gyokuto (jade rabbit).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The opposite story was gyokuto (jade rabbit).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The opposite story was gyokuto (jade rabbit).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>八咫烏は金烏伝説と少なからず関連しており、太陽にトリ（主にカラス）のモチーフは世界中で散見される伝説である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yatagarasu (Japanese mythological big crow) is related to Kinu story, and it is a story whose motif; a crow in the sun (mainly a crow), was seen around the world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yatagarasu (a big Japanese mythological crow) is related to the Kinu story, and it is a story with the motif of a crow in the sun (mainly a crow), that was seen around the world.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yatagarasu (a big Japanese mythological crow) is related to the Kinu story, and it is a story with the motif of a crow in the sun (mainly a crow), that was seen around the world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>太陽信仰の象徴とされることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It may be regarded as a symbol of sun worship.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It may be regarded as a symbol of sun worship.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It may be regarded as a symbol of sun worship.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>日本では出雲に関連する神社に多く伝承が遺っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan, many tales have been succeeded to shrines that are related to Izumo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan, many tales have been told at shrines that are related to Izumo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan, many tales have been told at shrines that are related to Izumo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>下鴨神社の祭神賀茂建角身命は八咫烏の化身であり、神武東征に際し太陽神天照大神とタカミムスビの令をうけ、金鵄（金色のトビ。八咫烏とも）に化身して神武天皇を先導したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The enshrined deity, Kamo Taketsunumi no mikoto in Shimogamo-jinja Shrine is a incarnation of yatagarasu, and he guided Emperor Jinmu turning himself into a golden kite (also called yatagarasu) under the ordinance of Amaterasu Omikami (the Sun Goddess) and Takamimusubi at the time of Jimmu tosei (the first generation of the Imperial family).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The enshrined deity, Kamo Taketsunumi no mikoto in Shimogamo-jinja Shrine is an incarnation of yatagarasu, and he guided Emperor Jinmu by turning himself into a golden kite (also called yatagarasu) under the ordinance of Amaterasu Omikami (the Sun Goddess) and Takamimusubi at the time of Jimmu tosei (the first generation of the Imperial family).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The enshrined deity, Kamo Taketsunumi no mikoto in Shimogamo-jinja Shrine is an incarnation of yatagarasu, and he guided the Emperor Jinmu by turning himself into a golden kite (also called yatagarasu) under the ordinance of Amaterasu Omikami (the Sun Goddess) and Takamimusubi at the time of Jimmu tosei (the first generation of the Imperial family).</e>
<cmt>&quot;the&quot; を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>神代よりあるという有馬温泉は、日本書紀に大巳貴命と少彦名命が傷ついた3鳥が水に浸かり傷が治る姿をみて温泉を発見したとある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan), Arima-Onsen Hot Spring that is said to have been existed since the age of the gods, was discovered when Onamuchi no mikoto and Sukunahikona no Mikoto saw three injured birds were cured after those birds went into the water.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan), Arima-Onsen Hot Spring that is said to have existed since the age of the gods, was discovered when Onamuchi no mikoto and Sukunahikona no Mikoto saw that three injured birds were cured after those birds went into the water.</e>
<cmt>grammar, word spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan), Arima-Onsen Hot Spring that is said to have existed since the age of the gods, was discovered when Onamuchi no mikoto and Sukunahikona no Mikoto saw that three injured birds were cured after those birds went into the water.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>3羽とあるがこれは足の数と類似し、本来は八咫烏であった可能性がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the story the number of birds was similar to the number of yatagarasu, therefore three birds might have been yasogarasu.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the story the number of birds was similar to the number of yatagarasu, therefore the three birds might have been yasogarasu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the story the number of birds was similar to the number of yatagarasu, therefore the three birds might have been yatagarasu.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>中国長江文明では、三星堆遺跡から出土した青銅器（青銅神樹と呼ばれる）には木に止まる太陽を模した9羽の鳥があり、上古神話では鳥は8羽が既に死んでおり現在の太陽は最後の1羽だが既に瀕死であるという（故に供物を捧げた）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bronze ware (called seidoshinju) unearthed from Sanseitai-iseki Remains in the region of Chinese Chang Jiang Culture has nine birds representing suns perching a tree, and according to ancient myth, the eight birds were already dead and the last bird which represented the current sun was almost dead (offerings were already made).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bronze ware (called seidoshinju) unearthed from Sanseitai-iseki Remains in the region of Chinese Chang Jiang Culture has nine birds representing suns perching on a tree, and according to ancient mythology, the eight birds were already dead and the last bird which represented the current sun was almost dead (offerings were already made).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bronze ware (called seidoshinju) unearthed from Sanseitai-iseki Remains in the region of Chinese Chang Jiang Culture has nine birds representing suns perching on a tree, and according to ancient mythology, the eight birds were already dead and the last bird which represented the current sun was almost dead (offerings were already made).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>『山海経』には鳥の止まるこずえは「扶桑」と、木は「神樹」として登場するが、下の枝は9の太陽が留まるところとされ上の枝は1つの太陽が今まさに出んとするものであるとあり、若干のズレがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Sengaikyo&quot; (oldest topography of China), the tree top the birds were perching was `fusang&apos; (pictorial motifs), and the tree was `god tree&apos;, and the upper branch is where the ninth sun is to perch while the lower branch was for the first sun which was about to come out, which identified inconsistency between them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;Sengaikyo&quot; (oldest topography of China), the tree top the birds were perching on was `fusang&apos; (pictorial motifs), and the tree was the `god tree&apos;, and the upper branch is where the ninth sun is to perch while the lower branch was for the first sun which was about to come out, which identified an inconsistency between them.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;Sengaikyo&quot; (oldest topography of China), the tree top the birds were perching on was `fusang&apos; (pictorial motifs), and the tree was the `god tree&apos;, and the upper branch is where the ninth sun is to perch while the lower branch was for the first sun which was about to come out, which identified an inconsistency between them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>出土した青銅器には復元できなかった幹があるので、そこにもう一羽の鳥があるのかもしれないという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since some trunks in the unearthed bronze ware were not restored, another bird might have been there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since some trunks in the unearthed bronze ware were not restored, another bird might have been there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since some trunks in the unearthed bronze ware were not restored, another bird might have been there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Tenko(id:102318), Championship2006(id:38664), Jade0416(id:104181), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>