<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>町並み保存</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Townscape preservation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Townscape preservation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Townscape preservation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>町並み保存（まちなみほぞん）とは、伝統的な建築等が残る町並みを保存することによって、その町ならではの個性や魅力を再生させ、あわせて住民の生活環境を整備すること。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Machinami hozon (Townscape preservation) is the activities to bring out distinctive characteristics and attractiveness of the towns and to improve living conditions of the residents by preserving townscape in which traditional architecture and the like remain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Townscape preservation refers to activities intended to renew distinctive characteristics and attractiveness of towns and to improve living conditions of the residents by preserving townscapes that retain traditional architecture and so on.</e>
<cmt>&quot;is the changed&quot; to &quot;refers to,&quot; sentence reworded</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Townscape preservation refers to activities intended to renew distinctive characteristics and attractiveness of towns and to improve living conditions of the residents by preserving townscapes that retain traditional architecture and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>通常は江戸時代に町の骨格が形成され、幕末から明治・大正時代に建てられた建築がある程度残っている町並みを「歴史的町並み」という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The townscape in which a structure of the town was formed in the Edo period, and the buildings constructed from the end of the Edo period to the Meiji and Taisho period still remain to some extent is usually called &apos;historical townscape&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Normally, &quot;historical townscape&quot; is used for towns that had their structures formed during the Edo period, and for those that still retain some of the buildings that were constructed during the period between the end of the Edo period to the Meiji and Taisho periods.</e>
<cmt>sentence reworded</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Normally, &quot;historical townscape&quot; is used for towns that had their structures formed during the Edo period, and for those that still retain some of the buildings that were constructed during the period between the end of the Edo period to the Meiji and Taisho periods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>しかし、明治期に西洋化する中で生まれた神戸や函館などの町並みも保存の対象とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, such townscapes as those in Kobe and Hakodate, which were generated in the middle of westernization during the Meiji period, are also covered for preservation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the term also applies to towns that developed during westernization in the Meiji period, such as Kobe and Hakodate.</e>
<cmt>sentence reworded</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the term also applies to towns that developed during westernization in the Meiji period, such as Kobe and Hakodate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>保有の方法には町並み保存地区を指定する、国の重要伝統的建造物群保存地区によるもの、県や市の景観条例などによるものがあるほか、町並み保存会を結成してや町並み保存運動を展開するなどがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are several ways of preservation such as to designate townscape preservation districts, to develop townscape preservation movements by setting up townscape conservation societies, and to follow the regulations on preservation districts for groups of important national historical buildings and prefectural and city landscape ordinances.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Townscape preservation can be done by several ways, for example, by designating townscape preservation districts, by following the regulations on preservation districts for groups of important national historical buildings, by following prefectural and city landscape ordinances, and by forming townscape preservation movements by setting up townscape conservation societies.</e>
<cmt>sentence reworded</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Townscape preservation can be done by several ways, for example, by designating townscape preservation districts, by following the regulations on preservation districts for groups of important national historical buildings, by following prefectural and city landscape ordinances, and by forming townscape preservation movements by setting up townscape conservation societies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 HidE(id:14357), かぼ(id:79147), Tribot(id:186681), Mishika(id:276), D.h(id:79056), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>