<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>火箸</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hibashi chopstick</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hibashi chopstick</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hibashi chopstick</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>火箸（ひばし）とは、日本の道具のひとつ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hibashi chopstick is one of Japanese tools.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hibashi chopstick is a Japanese tool.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hibashi chopstick is a Japanese tool.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>多くは鉄で作られ、火鉢や火箱の炭を扱うことを目的とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most of them are made of iron, and are designed to handle charcoal in a brazier or fire box.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most of them are made of iron, and are designed to handle charcoal in a brazier or fire box.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most of them are made of iron, and are designed to handle charcoal in a brazier or fire box.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>かつて火鉢や囲炉裏が普及していた時代には、どこの家庭にもある一般的な道具だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When a brazier or an irori fire place was widely used, a Hibashi chopstick was a common tool you could see in any home in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When braziers or irori fire places were widely used, Hibashi chopsticks were common tools you could see in any home in Japan.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When braziers or irori fire places were widely used, Hibashi chopsticks were common tools you could see in any home in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>2本の、先に行くにつれて細くなる鉄の棒で構成され、長さは25センチから40センチ程度。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hibashi chopstick consists of two iron sticks narrow to a point, and it is about 25 centimeters to 40 centimeters long.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A Hibashi chopstick consists of two iron sticks narrow at the points, and is about 25 centimeters to 40 centimeters long.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A Hibashi chopstick consists of two iron sticks narrow at the points, and is about 25 centimeters to 40 centimeters long.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>炭を継ぎ足したり、熾っている火を調整したりするときに使用する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is used to add some charcoal to a fire or to control a fire.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is used to add some charcoal to a fire or to control a fire.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is used to add some charcoal to a fire or to control a fire.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>後端は丸いもの、瓦釘のようになっているもの、割ったり巻いたりして輪をつけたものなど様々である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The back end of Hibashi chopstick comes in a variety of forms: rounded shape; copper nail-like shape; one fitted with a ring by splitting or wrapping.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The back end of the Hibashi chopstick comes in a variety of forms: rounded shape; copper nail-like shape; one fitted with a ring by splitting or wrapping.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The back end of the Hibashi chopstick comes in a variety of forms: rounded shape; copper nail-like shape; one fitted with a ring by splitting or wrapping.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペースを除去しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>火鉢の火を灰を被せて消した後、火箸を十文字に刺しておくという習慣があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was a custom of thrusting two Hibashi chopsticks into ash crossing them each other when covering brazier fire with ash to put out.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was a custom of thrusting two Hibashi chopsticks into ash crossing them over each other when covering a brazier fire with ash to put it out.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was a custom of thrusting two Hibashi chopsticks into ash crossing them over each other when covering a brazier fire with ash to put it out.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>一種の火伏せのまじないである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a kind of a charm for preventing fire.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a kind of a charm for preventing fires.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a kind of a charm for preventing fires.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>家庭で炭火を扱うことが少なくなるにつれ、茶道の席などを除き次第にその姿を消していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the chance of using charcoal fire was getting less and less, a Hibashi chopstic gradually disappeared from daily life except on occasions like Japanese tea ceremony.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the chances of using charcoal fires decreased, Hibashi chopsticks gradually disappeared from daily life except for occasions like Japanese tea ceremony.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the chances of using charcoal fires decreased, Hibashi chopsticks gradually disappeared from daily life except for occasions like Japanese tea ceremony.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>しかし、何本かを吊るして風鈴にするという風流な用途があり、この目的で生き残っているのを見かけることができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, you could see some of them still survive for elegant pursuits as a wind chime, which consists of several Hibashi chopsticks hanging.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, you can still see some for elegant pursuits as wind chimes, which consist of several Hibashi chopsticks hanging.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, you can still see some for elegant pursuits as wind chimes, which consist of several Hibashi chopsticks hanging.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>戦国時代 (日本)から甲冑師として鉄の加工技術を守ってきた姫路市の明珍（みょうちん）家では、この材料に日本刀の材料である玉鋼を用い、さらに美しい音色のものを現在も製作している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MYOCHIN family in Himeji City has been keeping up the iron-processing technique as an armorer since the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States in Japan) and makes a wind chime with better sound by using Tamahagane (gem steel) which is the original material of Japanese sword.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The MYOCHIN family in Himeji City has been keeping up the iron-processing technique as an armorer since the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States in Japan) and makes wind chimes with better sound by using Tamahagane (gem steel) which is the original material of Japanese swords.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The MYOCHIN family in Himeji City has been keeping up the iron-processing technique as an armorer since the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States in Japan) and makes wind chimes with better sound by using Tamahagane (gem steel) which is the original material of Japanese swords.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>この音色は冨田勲の楽曲にサンプリングされたり、ソニーの音響機器の試験にも使用されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The sound is sampled for the music by Isao TOMITA, or used for testing audio equipment made by SONY.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sound is sampled for music by Isao TOMITA, or used for testing audio equipment made by SONY.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sound is sampled for music by Isao TOMITA, or used for testing audio equipment made by SONY.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Lupinoid(id:68), Point136(id:211299), 竃馬(id:102733), U.S.S.Momotaro(id:646), Mzaki(id:61977), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>