<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>観光ボランティアガイド</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tourism Volunteer Guide</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tourism Volunteer Guide</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sightseeing Volunteer Guide</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>観光ボランティアガイド（かんこうぼらんてぃあがいど）とは、地域を訪れる観光客に対し、無料若しくは低廉な料金で、自発的に、継続して、自分なりのやり方で案内・ガイドする人のことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A tourism volunteer guide is individual who voluntarily assists and guides tourists for free or a nominal fee on a continual basis.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A tourism volunteer guide is an individual who voluntarily assists and guides tourists for free or a nominal fee on a continual basis.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A sightseeing volunteer guide is an individual who voluntarily assists and guides tourists for free or a nominal fee on a continual basis.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>全国の多くの観光地で観光ボランティア組織が誕生しており、観光協会等を窓口としてガイドを受け付けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are tourism volunteer guide organizations associated with sightseeing areas throughout Japan, and these accept guide requests via groups such as tourism associations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are tourism volunteer guide organizations associated with sightseeing areas throughout Japan, and these accept guide requests via groups such as tourism associations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are sightseeing volunteer guide organizations associated with sightseeing areas throughout Japan, and these accept guide requests via groups such as tourist associations.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>昔からある観光ガイドとは、個人が主体という点で異なり、（これまでの概念の）観光のプロではない人たちが担っているという点でエコツアー、ネイチャーツアーなどでみられるほぼシステム化された専門の有料ガイドとも区別される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The role differs from traditional tourist guides as the focus is on the individual, and tours are conducted by those who are differentiated from tourism industry professionals such as those organized specialist fee-charging guides who conduct excursions such as eco tours and nature tours.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The role differs from traditional tourist guides as the focus is on the individual, and tours are conducted by those who are differentiated from tourism industry professionals such as those that organize specialist fee-charging guides who conduct eco and nature excursions.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The role differs from traditional tourist guides as the focus is on the individual, and tours are conducted by those who are differentiated from tourism industry professionals such as those organize specialist fee-charging guides who conduct eco and nature excursions.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>仕組み</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Structure</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Structure</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Structure</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>観光ボランティアは個人ベースではなく、組織化され行動している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tourism volunteer guides do not operate individually but as part of an organization.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tourism volunteer guides do not operate individually but as part of an organization.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sightseeing volunteer guides do not operate individually but as part of an organization.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>その大半は、地方自治体行政や商工会議所・旅館組合等の関係団体の音頭取りで作られたものといえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The majority of such organizations were assembled under the leadership of groups related to local public bodies, chambers of commerce and industry as well as hotels associations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The majority of such organizations were assembled under the leadership of groups related to local public bodies, chambers of commerce and industry as well as hotels associations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The majority of such organizations were assembled under the leadership of groups related to local public governments, chambers of commerce and industry, as well as hotel associations.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>観光協会等の団体を通じた事前申込制としているボランティア組織が多いが、別府温泉の「別府八湯ウォーク」 のように、決まった日時に集合すれば誰でも参加できる形態を採るところも最近ではある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are many volunteer organizations that accept advance bookings through touism associations but there recently are also those such as the &apos;Beppu Hatto Walk&apos; of the Beppu-onsen Hot Spring area that allow anyone who assembles at a given point at a certain date and time to participate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are many volunteer organizations that accept advance bookings through touism associations but there recently are also those such as the &apos;Beppu Hatto Walk&apos; of the Beppu-onsen Hot Spring area that allow anyone who assembles at a given point at a certain date and time to participate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are many volunteer organizations that accept advance bookings through tourism associations, but there recently are also those such as the &apos;Beppu Hatto Walk&apos; of the Beppu-onsen Hot Spring area that allow anyone who assembles at a given place at a certain date and time to participate.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>先の定義で示した「自発性」、「継続性」、「個人性」がポイントである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The main points that define the role are the fact that it is voluntary, undertaken on a continual basis and conducted personally.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The main points that define the role are the fact that it is voluntary, undertaken on a continual basis and conducted personally.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The main conditions that define the role are the fact that it is voluntary, undertaken on a continual basis and conducted personally.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>観光ガイド社の従業員としてではなく、文字どおり一個人として自発的にその組織に参加し、ガイドを行う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tourism volunteer guides are not employees of tour guide companies but are, as the name suggests, individuals who voluntarily join groups and serve as guides.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tourism volunteer guides are not employees of tour guide companies but are, as the name suggests, individuals who voluntarily join groups and serve as guides.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tourism volunteer guides are not employees of tour guide companies but are, as the name suggests, individuals who voluntarily join groups and serve as guides.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>また、単発ではなく、継続的に実施する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is done not only once or twice but on a continual basis.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is done not only once or twice but on a continual basis.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is done not on a one-off basis but on a continual basis.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>そして、組織でありながら、組織のルールに従うものの、ガイドの内容については実質的に個人個人の個性が許されており、自分なりの言葉で案内・ガイドしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, although they are part of an organization and obey its rules, the itinerary of tours can effectively be determined by the guide and may be conducted in one&apos;s own words.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, although they are part of an organization and obey its rules, the itinerary of tours can effectively be determined by the guide and may be conducted in one&apos;s own words.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, although they are part of an organization and obey its rules, the itinerary of tours can effectively be determined by the guide and may be conducted in one&apos;s own words.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>なかには自分でガイドマニュアルや手引きをつくったり、専用の衣装を誂えたりする熱心な人も居る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some such guides are so enthusiastic that they create their own guide manuals and guidelines and even order specialist clothing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some such guides are so enthusiastic that they create their own guide manuals and guidelines and even order specialist clothing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some such guides are so enthusiastic that they create their own guide manuals and guidelines and even order special clothing.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>誕生と成長の経緯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Origin and Development</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Origin and Development</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Origin and development</e>
<cmt>小タイトル用に小文字にしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="12">
<j>以前から郷土史家と呼ばれる人が地域の住民もしくは社会見学の一環として訪れた学童・生徒等を対象に説明を行っていたということはありえるが、これは「観光」の要素は乏しい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Local historians have long conducted talks for local residents as well as schoolchildren and pupils during field trips but this phenomenon does not fall under the definition of tourism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Local historians have long conducted talks for local residents as well as schoolchildren and pupils during field trips but this phenomenon does not fall under the definition of tourism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Local historians have long conducted talks for local residents as well as schoolchildren and pupils during field trips but this phenomenon does not fall under the definition of tourism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>観光ボランティアガイドは、1990年代の前半に注目され始め、1995年以降各地で急増した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tourism volunteer guides began to come to attention during the 1990s and their numbers rapidly increased throughout the country from 1995.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tourism volunteer guides began to come to attention during the 1990s and their numbers rapidly increased throughout the country from 1995.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tourism volunteer guides began to come to attention in the first half of 1990s and their numbers rapidly increased throughout the country from 1995.</e>
<cmt>前半に　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>観光ボランティアガイドの成長の背景には、ありきたりの観光地の説明ではなく、ディープな知識を吸収したい、新しい発見をしたいという観光客のニーズも見逃せない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tourism volunteer guides arose to meet the needs of those tourists who were not satisfied with talks about the usual sightseeing spots and wanted to acquire a deep knowledge and discover something new.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tourism volunteer guides arose to meet the needs of those tourists who were not satisfied with talks about the usual sightseeing spots and wanted to acquire a deep knowledge and discover something new.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tourism volunteer guides arose to meet the needs of those tourists who were not satisfied with talks about the usual sightseeing spots and wanted to acquire a deep knowledge and discover something new.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>何よりも生涯学習時代の到来を踏まえ、自己の知識を活かして訪れる観光客のお役に立ちたい、それが自己実現につながる、そして自分の街を誇りに思い、他の地域の人々との新たな出会いが楽しいという、ボランティアの成り手自身の意識の成熟が大きな要因として挙げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Major reasons for choosing to become a tourism volunteer guide include the desire to use one&apos;s knowledge acquired through lifelong study to educate visiting tourists to attain a feeling of self-fulfillment, a sense of pride in the area in which one lives, and taking pleasure in meeting new people from different places.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Major reasons for choosing to become a tourism volunteer guide include the desire to use one&apos;s knowledge acquired through lifelong study to educate visiting tourists to attain a feeling of self-fulfillment, a sense of pride in the area in which one lives, and taking pleasure in meeting new people from different places.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Major reasons for choosing to become a tourism volunteer guide include the desire to use one&apos;s knowledge acquired through lifelong study to educate visiting tourists to attain a feeling of self-fulfillment, a sense of pride in the area in which one lives, and taking pleasure in meeting new people from different places.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="16">
<j>加えて、観光客・交流人口を増やしたい地元自治体や、観光客の滞在時間を少しでも伸ばしたい関連事業者、新たな魅力を注入したい旅行社などのニーズも見逃せない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, one cannot overlook the needs of regional governments hoping to increase the numbers of tourists and visitors, those in related industries in whose interests it is to increase the length of tourist stays, and travel agencies aiming to promote new attractions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, one cannot overlook the needs of regional governments hoping to increase the numbers of tourists and visitors, those in related industries in whose interests it is to increase the length of tourist stays, and travel agencies aiming to promote new attractions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, one cannot overlook the needs of regional governments hoping to increase the numbers of tourists and visitors, related industries whose interest is to increase the length of tourist stays, and travel agencies aiming to promote new attractions.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>観光行政サイドとしては、ボランティアガイドを利用して、少しでも訪れる人を増やすとともに、じっくりと見て回ってもらって滞在時間を伸ばし、観光消費に結び付けたいと考える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tourism administration bodies find it desirable to use volunteers to increase income by increasing the numbers of visitors while ensuring that they see as much as possible and stay for as long as possible.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tourism administration bodies find it desirable to use volunteers to increase income by increasing the numbers of visitors while ensuring that they see as much as possible and stay for as long as possible.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tourism administration bodies find it desirable to use volunteers to increase income by increasing the numbers of visitors while ensuring that they see as much as possible and stay for as long as possible.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="18">
<j>ガイドと称する中には客引きに等しい悪質な人が居る恐れもあり、「質」を確保するために、一定の「認定」「認証」の仕組みが必要である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are fears that some disreputable touts will attempt to use the label of &apos;guide&apos;, so in order for legitimate guides to maintain their reputation, a certain level of certification is necessary.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are fears that some disreputable touts will attempt to use the label of &apos;guide&apos;, so in order for legitimate guides to maintain their reputation, a certain level of certification is required.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are fears that some disreputable solicitor will attempt to use the label of &apos;guide,&apos; so in order for legitimate guides to maintain their reputation, a certain level of certification is required.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>観光ボランティアガイドが今日の地位を確保しえたのも、一つには「ボランティア」つまり「無料」であるという安心感、わかりやすさ、つまりブランド構築における「安心」「保証」である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tourism volunteer guides have been able to maintain their current status due to the sense of security that comes from the fact that they are volunteers and therefore free as well as the security and guarantees that come with an established brand.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tourism volunteer guides have been able to maintain their current status due to the sense of security that comes from the fact that they are volunteers and therefore free as well as the security and guarantees that come with an established brand.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sightseeing volunteer guides have been able to maintain their current status due to the sense of security and clearness that comes from the fact that they are volunteers and therefore free as well as the security and guarantees that come with an established brand.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>もう一つは、公的機関の窓口で紹介する等の事実上の「保証」（これもブランドの構成要素の一つ）であろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another reason is the actual assurances (also an element of a brand) that come from their connections to public organizations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another reason is the actual assurances (also an element of a brand) that come from their connections to public organizations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another reason is the actual assurances (also an element of a brand) that come from their connections to public organizations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>最近の傾向</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Recent Trends</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Recent Trends</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Recent trends</e>
<cmt>小タイトル用に小文字にしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="21">
<j>行政の取り組み</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Administrative System</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Administrative System</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Administrative system</e>
<cmt>小タイトル用に小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>各地でボランティアガイドの養成講座が行われており、一定の課程を修了すると認定書等がもらえる仕組みになっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A system exists in which volunteer guide courses are conducted throughout the country and a certificate is awarded to those who complete a certain curriculum.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A system exists in which volunteer guide courses are conducted throughout the country and a certificate is awarded to those who complete a certain curriculum.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A system exists in which volunteer guide courses are conducted throughout the country and a certificate is awarded to those who complete a certain curriculum.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="23">
<j>有償化</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Remuneration</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Remuneration</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Remuneration</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>次第に有償とする例が増えてきている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The number of such guides who receive financial compensation is gradually increasing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The number of such guides who receive financial compensation is gradually increasing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The number of such guides who receive financial compensation is gradually increasing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>その意味ではビジネス化しつつあるといえよう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It can therefore be said that the sector is becoming commercialized.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It can therefore be said that the sector is becoming commercialized.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It can therefore be said that the sector is becoming commercialized.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="26">
<j>旅行業者とのタイアップ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tie-ups with Travel Agents</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tie-ups with Travel Agents</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Affiliation with travel agents</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>問題点</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Problems</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Problems</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Problems</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="27">
<j>ボランティア仲間同士での人間関係</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Relationships Between Volunteers</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Relationships Between Volunteers</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Relationships between volunteers</e>
<cmt>小タイトル用に小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>志を同じくする人たちが集まって発足した当初は良いが、やがてメンバーが多くなっていくと、「ボランティア」そのものに対する取組意識の差やそれまでの社会的地位や経験、ボランティア経験等によって微妙に人間関係が難しくなっていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When a group of people with the same intentions come together, things often begin well but as the number of members increase, human relationships can become strained due to differences in levels of commitment and issues arising from social status as well as differing levels of experience.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When a group of people with the same intentions come together, things often begin well but as the number of members increase, human relationships can become strained due to differences in levels of commitment and issues arising from social status as well as differing levels of experience.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When a group of people with the same intentions come together, things often begin well but as the number of members increase, human relationships can become strained due to differences in levels of commitment and issues arising from social status as well as differing levels of experience.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>もっと言えば仲間同士の個人的な「好き嫌い」が発生する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In other words, likes and dislikes between individuals emerge within the group.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In other words, likes and dislikes between individuals emerge within the group.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In other words, likes and dislikes between individuals emerge within the group.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>観光ボランティアガイド組織は、企業や行政のように、ある一つの目的（ミッション）とそれを達成するためのルール・執行組織が明確でない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As they differ from business or administrative bodies, tourism volunteer guide organizations do not have a definite objective (mission) or rules and procedures in place to achieve this mission.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As they differ from business or administrative bodies, tourism volunteer guide organizations do not have a definite objective (mission) or rules and procedures in place to achieve this mission.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As they differ from business or administrative bodies, tourism volunteer guide organizations do not have a definite objective (mission) or rules and procedures in place to achieve this mission.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>このため、こうした人間関係の調整が難しい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is for this reason that such human relationship issues are difficult to manage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is for this reason that such human relationship issues are difficult to manage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is for this reason that such human relationship issues are difficult to manage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>ルール違反者に「退出」願うルールも確立されていないところがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are even such groups in which there is no rule stating that those who violate regulations will be forced to leave.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are even such groups in which there is no rule stating that those who violate regulations will be forced to leave.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are even such groups in which there is no rule stating that those who violate regulations will be forced to leave.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>こうした問題については、窓口の行政組織もなかなか手を突っ込みたがらず及び腰になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Administrative organizations that have contact with these volunteer groups are reluctant about intervening in such matters.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Administrative organizations that have contact with these volunteer groups are reluctant about intervening in such matters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Administrative organizations that have contact with these volunteer groups are reluctant about intervening in such matters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>極言すればリーダーの人間性いかんにかかっているといえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One could go so far as to say that the presence or absence of such problems is dependent on the nature of the group leader.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One could go so far as to say that the presence or absence of such problems is dependent on the nature of the group leader.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One could go so far as to say that the presence or absence of such problems is dependent on the nature of the group leader.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="35">
<j>行政との関係、「してやっている」という意識の拡がり？</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Relationships with Administration</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Relationships with Administration</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Relationships with administration</e>
<cmt>小タイトル用に小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>行政の要請に基づき組織化され、事業している場合、行政の観光政策の一環を担っているという使命感のあるうちはいいが、それが変質し、行政施策に「協力してやっている」という意識に変質していく恐れがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Where volunteer groups are organized and operated based on the demands of administrative bodies, there are few problems as long as there is a sense of duty as being part of a tourism policy but there is a fear that this can change to an attitude of merely cooperating with the tourism policy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Where volunteer groups are organized and operated based on the demands of administrative bodies, there are few problems as long as there is a sense of duty as being part of a tourism policy but there is a fear that this can change to an attitude of merely cooperating with the tourism policy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Where volunteer groups are organized and operated based on the demands of administrative bodies, there are few problems as long as there is a sense of duty as being part of a tourism policy but there is a fear that this can change to an attitude of merely cooperating with the tourism policy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="37">
<j>ツアーの下請け化</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tour Subcontracting</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tour Subcontracting</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tour subcontracting</e>
<cmt>小タイトル用に小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>観光ボランティアガイドは個人・グループ客を主な対象としているが、最近では新しいツアー商品開発とパック価格引下げを図りたい旅行会社が、施設入場料やガイド料がそれほどかからず一定時間を過ごせる便利な立寄り先として観光ボランティアガイドに着目し、活用しはじめている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tourism volunteer guides mainly handle individuals and groups but recently, travel agencies that are aiming to develop new your products and cut package costs have begun to pay attention to and use tourism volunteer guides in order to cut back on entrance and guide fees while conveniently providing customers with a way to spend time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tourism volunteer guides mainly handle individuals and groups but recently, travel agencies that are aiming to develop new your products and cut package costs have begun to pay attention to and use tourism volunteer guides in order to cut back on entrance and guide fees while conveniently providing customers with a way to spend time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sightseeing volunteer guides mainly handle individuals and groups but recently, travel agencies that are aiming to develop new products and cut package costs have begun to pay attention to and use sightseeing volunteer guides in order to cut back on entrance and guide fees while conveniently providing customers with a way to spend time.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="39">
<j>なかには、ガイドをまるで下請のように扱い、あれこれ命令したり、ツアースケジュールの都合から本来説明に2時間かかるところを「1時間で説明しろ」と要請する旅行社も出てきたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This has meant that guides have become treated like subcontractors, are given various instructions and it is said that travel agencies have emerged that order guides to condense two hour talks into one hour due to tour scheduling.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This has meant that guides have become treated like subcontractors, are given various instructions and it is said that travel agencies have emerged that order guides to condense two hour talks into one hour due to tour scheduling.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This has meant that guides have become treated like subcontractors, are given various instructions and it is said that travel agencies have emerged that order guides to condense two hour talks into one hour due to tour scheduling.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>ツアー参加客もガイドに興味を持つ人ばかりとは限らないので、ガイドの話を聞こうともしない、あるいはわずらわしいという表情をあからさまにする場合も出てきているという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Not all of those who participate in tours are interested in the guides, so some participants may either not listen to what the guide is saying or appear clearly bored.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Not all of those who participate in tours are interested in the guides, so some participants may either not listen to what the guide is saying or appear clearly bored.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Not all of those who participate in tours are interested in the guides, so some participants may either not listen to what the guide is saying or appear apparently bored.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="41">
<j>本職ガイドとのすみわけ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Separation from Professional Guides</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Separation from Professional Guides</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Separation from professional guides</e>
<cmt>小タイトル用に小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>本職ガイドが居る地域ではそれとのすみわけが必要になってくる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The need arises to separate tourism volunteer guides from professional guides in areas where both are active.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The need to separate tourism volunteer guides from professional guides arises in areas where both are active.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The need to separate tourism volunteer guides from professional guides arises in areas where both are active.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>「本職」の領域に近づけば近づくほど、本職の本分を侵すことになり、「無償」ないし「低額」が正当な市場形成を阻害することになりかねないという心配がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As volunteer guides operate ever more closely to the areas worked by professional guides, they may encroach on their areas of operation and there is the concern that the volunteer or low-fee sector will impede the fee-charging market.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As volunteer guides operate ever more closely to areas worked by professional guides, they may encroach on their areas of operation and there is concern that the volunteer or low-fee sector will impede the fee-charging market.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As volunteer guides operate ever more closely to areas worked by professional guides, they may encroach on their areas of operation and there is concern that the volunteer or low-fee sector will impede the fee-charging market.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>（今日、ボランティアガイドが組織されている地域で「本職」が成り立つかいささか疑問であるが。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is now the slight problem that it is difficult for professional guides to become established in areas in which volunteer guides are organized.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is now a slight problem that it is difficult for professional guides to become established in areas in which volunteer guides are organized.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(There is now a slight problem that it is difficult for professional guides to become established in areas in which volunteer guides are organized.)</e>
<cmt>括弧を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="45">
<j>無償の限界</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Limitations of Volunteering</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Limitations of Volunteering</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The limitations of volunteering</e>
<cmt>小タイトル用に小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>先のような、旅行社のツアーに対して一定の費用負担を求めようと考える組織も出てきている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Volunteer organizations are emerging that are considering claiming certain expenses when conducting travel agency tours such as those mentioned above.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Volunteer organizations are emerging that are considering claiming certain expenses when conducting travel agency tours such as those mentioned above.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Volunteer organizations are emerging that are considering claiming certain expenses when conducting travel agency tours such as those mentioned above.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>観光ボランティア組織では、あくまでも無料で行いたいと考えているが、ツアーの一部に組み込まれつつある状況にあっては、「ボランティア」の文字が次第に重荷になってきつつある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tourism volunteer groups would like to be able to operate free of charge but as they become part of tour itineraries, the label of &apos;volunteer&apos; is becoming gradually more difficult to justify.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tourism volunteer groups would like to be able to operate free of charge but as they become part of tour itineraries, the label of &apos;volunteer&apos; is becoming gradually more difficult to justify.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tourism volunteer groups would like to be able to operate free of charge but as they become part of tour itineraries, the label of &apos;volunteer&apos; is becoming gradually more difficult to justify.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="48">
<j>一方で、先にみたように自治体のニーズはますます高まっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, the needs of local public bodies are becoming ever more as described above.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, the needs of local public bodies are increasing as described above.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, the needs of local public bodies are increasing as described above.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>また、地域の観光事業者としても、ガイドが有料になれば価格競争の激しい旅行会社のツアーから外される恐れがあるため、できれば無料若しくは極めて低廉であり続けてもらいたいと考える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, if these guides were to charge fees, there is the fear that they may be withdrawn from tour itineraries in a market in which competitiveness is so dependent on price, so it is desirable that they remain free or very inexpensive.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, if these guides were to charge fees, there is the fear that they may be withdrawn from tour itineraries in a market in which competitiveness is so dependent on price, so it is desirable that they remain free or very inexpensive.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, if these guides were to charge fees, there is the fear that they may be withdrawn from tour itineraries in a market in which competitiveness is so dependent on price, so it is desirable that they remain free or very inexpensive.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="50">
<j>このように、いわば「善意」を基本に成り立つボランティアガイド組織と、ビジネスの論理で行動する旅行社や観光事業者とのギャップが拡大しつつある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is due to such factors that the gap is widening between the volunteer guide organizations that are built on good will and the travel agencies and tourism industry workers that operate according to business principles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is due to such factors that the gap is widening between the volunteer guide organizations that are built on good will and the travel agencies and tourism industry workers that operate according to business principles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is due to such factors that the gap is widening between the volunteer guide organizations that are built on good will and the travel agencies and tourism industry workers that operate according to business principles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>今後の方向</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Future</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Future</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The future</e>
<cmt>小タイトル用に小文字にしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="51">
<j>先の問題点を克服する一つの方法として、ガイド組織をボランティアからNPO法人化することが考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One way that the above problems can be overcome is by guide organizations becoming non-profit organizations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One way that the above problems can be overcome is by guide organizations becoming non-profit organizations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One way that the above problems can be overcome is by guide organizations becoming non-profit organizations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="52">
<j>正当な「対価」を払うべき</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Payment of a Fair Price</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Payment of a Fair Price</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Payment of a reasonable price</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>そのガイド組織が地域活性化のために価値ある存在で、かつ利用客や旅行会社の経済的負担を仰げないのならば、地元自治体や観光事業者及びその団体が当該組織に対価を支払うべきであり、ガイド組織自身もその受け皿としての機能を有した組織に生まれ変わる必要があるのではなかろうか。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As guide volunteer organizations are valuable entities for local revitalization and also do not require the financial support of customers and travel agencies, local public bodies as well as tourism industry workers and related groups should be expected make the appropriate payments while it is also necessary for guide organizations to transform themselves into the recipients of such payment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As guide volunteer organizations are valuable entities for local revitalization and also do not require the financial support of customers and travel agencies, local public bodies as well as tourism industry workers and related groups should be expected make the appropriate payments while it is also necessary for guide organizations to transform themselves into the recipients of such payment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A volunteer guide organizations are valuable entities for local revitalization and also do not require the financial support of customers and travel agencies, local public bodies as well as tourism industry workers and related groups should be expected to make the appropriate payments while it is also necessary for guide organizations to transform themselves into the recipients of such payment.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="54">
<j>システマチックに行う必要性</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Necessity for Systematic Operation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Necessity for Systematic Operation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The necessity for systematic operation</e>
<cmt>小タイトル用に小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>ガイド事業をシステマチックに継続して行うには、組織として統率が取れ、構成メンバーも絶えず学習を続けるという仕組み（程度の差こそあれ民間企業には当然存在する）がビルトインされていることが望ましいのではなかろうか。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order to for guide operations to be continued in a systematic manner, it is desirable to have a built-in mechanism (that would be similar to a public company with the exception of certain differences) which provides leadership as well as encourages the continuous study of members.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to for guide operations to be continued in a systematic manner, it is desirable to have a built-in mechanism (that would be similar to a public company with the exception of certain differences) which provides leadership as well as encouraging the continuous study of members.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order for guide operations to be continued in a systematic manner, it is desirable to have a built-in mechanism (that would be similar to a public company with the exception of certain differences) which provides leadership as well as encouraging the continuous study of members.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Hsz(id:42256), MD242(id:11277), 伏儀(id:142093), Bsx(id:38434), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>