<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>御所解</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gosyodoki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gosyodoki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gosyodoki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>御所解（ごしょどき）は、和服の文様の一種。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gosyodoki is a pattern of traditional Japanese clothes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gosyodoki is a pattern of traditional Japanese clothes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gosyodoki is a pattern of traditional Japanese clothes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>四季の草花を細かく密に表し、その間に御所車や扇、垣など『源氏物語』等の王朝文学や能に頻出する事物を配するのが特徴。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The features of Gosyodoki are that things often appeared in dynastic style literature including &quot;Tale of Genji&quot; or Noh such as an ox-drawn coach, a fan, a fence are laid out in seasonal flowers that are delicately described to detail.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gosyodoki often appeared in dynastic style literature including &quot;The Tale of Genji&quot; or in Noh where an ox-drawn coach, a fan, a fence are laid out in seasonal flowers that are delicately described in detail.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The features of Gosyodoki are that things often appeared in dynastic style literature including &quot;Tale of Genji&quot; or Noh such as an ox-drawn coach, a fan, a fence are laid out in seasonal flowers that are delicately described in detail.</e>
<cmt>訳を戻しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>「御所解文様」とも言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also referred to as `goshodoki monyo&apos; (goshodoki pattern).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also referred to as `goshodoki monyo&apos; (goshodoki pattern).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also referred to as `goshodoki monyo&apos; (goshodoki pattern).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>語源</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The origin of a word (an etymology)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The origin of a word (etymology)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The origin of a word (etymology)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>上記のように柄行きが平安時代の文学を思い浮かべさせるような物になっていたことから、明治時代以降に名付けられた物である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the pattern mentioned above reminds us of the literature in Heian period, it can be determined as the one named after Meiji period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the pattern mentioned above reminds us of Heian period literature, it can be determined to be named after Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the pattern mentioned above reminds us of Heian period literature, it can be determined to be named after Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>名前からよく誤解されるが公家の女性が着用していた着物の文様ではない（歴史にて詳述）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of its name, it is often taken as the pattern of Kimono which court noble ladies were wearing (to be described in History), in fact it is not.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of its name, it is often mistaken as Kimono that court noble ladies wore (as described in History), in fact it is not.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of its name, it is often mistaken as Kimono that court noble ladies wore (as described in History), in fact it is not.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>ところが、和服を解説した書籍や雑誌によっては、公家女性が着用した着物を「御所解」、武家女性が着用した着物（本来の「御所解」）を「江戸解」と説明しているため、未だに呼称は混乱している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in some books or magazines that explain on traditional Japanese clothes, the clothes worn by a court noble lady was described as `Goshodoki,&apos; while clothes worn by a lady from Samurai society (original `Goshodoki&apos;) was described as `Edodoki-pattern&apos;; thus, the definition of Goshodoki is still confused.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in some books or magazines that describe traditional Japanese clothing, clothes worn by a court noble lady was described as `Goshodoki,&apos; while clothes worn by a lady from Samurai society (original `Goshodoki&apos;) was described as `Edodoki-pattern&apos;; thus, the definition of Goshodoki is still confusing.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in some books or magazines that describe traditional Japanese clothing, clothes worn by a court noble lady was described as `Goshodoki,&apos; while clothes worn by a lady from Samurai society (original `Goshodoki&apos;) was described as `Edodoki-pattern&apos;; thus, the definition of Goshodoki is still confusing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>（公家女性と武家女性の着物の差異については「小袖小袖の身分差」の項目を参照。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(As for the difference between Kimono for a court noble lady and Kimono for a lady from Samurai society, refer to the section of `Social position shown in sleeve length.&apos;</e>
<cmt>項目→section と訳出しています。「小袖小袖の身分差」の文意が不明なため→`social position shown in sleeve length&apos;と暫定的に訳出しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(As for the difference between Kimono for a court noble lady and Kimono for a lady from Samurai society, refer to the section of `Social position shown in sleeve length.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(As for the difference between Kimono for a court noble lady and Kimono for a lady from Samurai society, refer to the section of `Social position shown in sleeve length.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>江戸時代後期に武家婦人の衣服制度が定まったときに、特に高位の御殿女中の着物の文様として好まれた物である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When a system of clothes for ladies from Samurai society was established in the latter half of Edo period, Gosyodoki was favored by goten jochu (palace maids) especially in high grade for their Kimono.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When a wardrobe for ladies for Samurai society was established in the latter half of the Edo period, Gosyodoki was favored by goten jochu (palace maids) especially the high grade Kimono.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When a wardrobe system for ladies for Samurai society was established in the latter half of the Edo period, Gosyodoki was especially favored by goten jochu (palace maids) that held a high rank.</e>
<cmt>変更しました。構文等チェックお願いします。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>柄行きの選定には先述のように平安文学や能に関する素養が要求されたため、「武家女性の品格の高さを表す物」として特に好まれた物と思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As previously prescribed, the education about Heian literature or Noh was required to select a pattern of Kimono; Gosyodoki was especially favored as `A thing to represent dignity of a lady from Samurai society.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As previously mentioned in Heian literature or in Noh it was required to select a pattern for Kimono; and Gosyodoki was especially favored as it represented dignity among women in Samurai society.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As previously prescribed, the education about Heian literature or Noh was required to select a pattern of Kimono; Gosyodoki was especially favored as `A thing to represent dignity of a lady from Samurai society.&apos;</e>
<cmt>元に戻しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>当時は主な文様は刺繍、補助的に友禅等の染めで文様を表していたため、身分制度で刺繍技法の着物が着用できなかった庶民にはとても手の届く物ではなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, main patterns were embroidered, and additional patterns were dyed by means of Yuzen (dying technique), therefore, it can&apos;t be available for common women who were not allowed to wear Kimono with an embroidery technique.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, the main patterns were embroidered, and additional patterns were dyed by means of Yuzen (a dying technique), therefore, it wasn&apos;t available for common women who were not allowed to wear elaborate embroidered Kimono.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, the main patterns were embroidered, and additional patterns were dyed by means of Yuzen (a dying technique), therefore, it wasn&apos;t available for common women who were not allowed to wear elaborate embroidered Kimono.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>この頃はこれら武家女性の好みの着物は「御屋敷風」といわれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kimono favored by ladies from Samurai society at that time was said to be `Oyashiki fu&apos; (Buke style).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kimono favored by ladies from Samurai society at that time was said to be `Oyashiki fu&apos; (Buke style).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kimono favored by ladies from Samurai society at that time was said to be `Oyashiki fu&apos; (Buke style).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="12">
<j>これらの着物の文様は、厳格に決まりがあったとはいえ、武家女性は教養の限りを尽くして文様の位置を微妙に変えたりなどの工夫をしていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The patterns of those Kimono were controlled under strict rules, ladies from Samurai society utilized full of their education and added some flavors on the Kimono such as slightly changing the position of patterns of Kimono, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The patterns of those Kimono were controlled under strict rules, ladies from Samurai society fully utilized their education and added some flavors of their own to the Kimono such as slightly changing the position of patterns, etc.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The patterns of those Kimono were controlled under strict rules, ladies from Samurai society fully utilized their education and added some flavors of their own to the Kimono such as slightly changing the position of patterns, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>その柄行きから着物がどの物語を主題としているのを当てるのも教養の内だったからである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because guessing which story was described as a theme in the patterns of Kimono tested one&apos;s education.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because guessing which story was described as a theme in the patterns of the Kimono tested one&apos;s education.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is because guessing which story was described as a theme in the patterns of the Kimono tested one&apos;s education.</e>
<cmt>1文にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>が、幕末になると完全に形式化してしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it turned to be completely formalized after the end of Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It became completely formalized after the end of Edo period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It became completely formalized after the end of Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="15">
<j>明治維新で幕藩体制が崩壊すると、貧窮した武家階級からこれらの着物が質屋等を介して市中に出回るようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the feudal system characteristic of the shogunate collapsed through Meiji Restoration, impoverished bushi classa sold their Kimono at pawn shops, and they became available around the town.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the feudal system, characteristic of the shogunate, collapsed through the Meiji Restoration, the impoverished bushi clasa sold their Kimono at pawn shops, and they became available around town.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the feudal system, characteristic of the shogunate, collapsed through the Meiji Restoration, the impoverished bushi class sold their Kimono at pawn shops, and they became available around town.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>この時、これらの着物を見た庶民によって「御所解」という誤解の多い呼称が生まれたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term of `Gosyodoki&apos;, causing a lot of misunderstandings, were created by the common people who had seen those Kimono at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term of `Gosyodoki&apos;, caused a lot of misunderstandings by common people who had come into contact with such Kimono during that time.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term of `Gosyodoki&apos;, caused a lot of misunderstandings by common people who had come into contact with such Kimono during that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="17">
<j>現在では格式の高さから振袖、留袖、訪問着などに使われることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nowadays, it is often used for furisode (a long sleeved type of kimono), tomesode, formal dress patterned only below the waistline worn by a married woman, and semi-formal kimono for women due to its formality,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nowadays, it is often used for furisode (a long sleeved type of kimono), tomesode, formal dress patterned only below the waistline worn by a married woman, and semi-formal kimono for women, due to its formality,</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nowadays, it is often used for furisode (a long sleeved type of kimono), tomesode, formal dress patterned only below the waistline worn by a married woman, and semi-formal kimono for women, due to its formality,</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 こぶまき(id:38278), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>