<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>扇子</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sensu/Ogi (folding fan)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sensu/Ogi (folding fan)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sensu/Ogi (folding fan)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>扇子（せんす）・扇（おうぎ）とは、うちわと同じく自分の手で風を送るのに用いる道具であり、数本から数十本の細長い骨組みを束ねて端の一点（要＝かなめ）で固定し、使用時には開いて可動できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A Sensu or Ogi (folding fan) is an implement used to induce an airflow by moving it by hand as well as Uchiwa fans, and its frame is several to several dozens strips tied together with thread at its end (kaname referred to as pivot), and when used, a Sensu or Ogi is widely unfolded and waved back and forth to create an airflow.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A Sensu or Ogi (folding fan) is an implement used to imove air by hand like Uchiwa fans, and its frame is several dozens of wooden strips tied together with thread at their ends (kaname referred to as pivot), and when used, a Sensu or Ogi is widely unfolded and waved back and forth to create a cooling airflow.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A Sensu or Ogi (folding fan) is an implement used to move air by hand like Uchiwa fans, and its frame is several dozens of wooden strips tied together with thread at their ends (kaname referred to as pivot), and when used, a Sensu or Ogi is widely unfolded and waved back and forth to create a cooling airflow.</e>
<cmt>スペルスペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>骨には大抵和紙が貼られており、展開すると紙を貼られた部分が段々の扇面となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are made out of accordion folded Washi (Japanese paper) pasted to movable strips, and when a Sensu or Ogi is unfolded, it shows accordion folded paper attached to movable strips.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are made out of accordion folded Washi (Japanese paper) pasted to movable strips of wood, and when a Sensu or Ogi is unfolded, it shows the accordion folded paper attached to the movable wooden strips.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are made out of accordion folded Washi (Japanese paper) pasted to movable strips of wood, and when a Sensu or Ogi is unfolded, it shows the accordion folded paper attached to the movable wooden strips.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>折り畳むことでコンパクトに納めることができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sensu is compact in shape by when folded.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sensu is compact in shape when folded.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sensu is compact in shape when folded.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>いわば折り畳みのできるうちわである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is, so to speak, an uchiwa available to be folded.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is, so to speak, an uchiwa that can be folded.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is, so to speak, an uchiwa that can be folded.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>扇子を開く角度は、大体90度から180度の間であり、円を三等分した中心角120度前後のものが主流である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The angle a Sensu or Ogi is unfolded to varies from between 90 -180 degrees, with around 120 degrees being the norm.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The angle a Sensu or Ogi when unfolded varies from 90 -180 degrees, with around 120 degrees being the norm.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The angle a Sensu or Ogi when unfolded varies from 90 - 180 degrees, with around 120 degrees being the norm.</e>
<cmt>スペース補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>扇子を開いた形は、「扇形（おうぎがた、せんけい）」と言い、幾何学の用語にもなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The shape of the unfolded fan is called &apos;Ogigata or Senkei&apos; and is used as a term in geometry.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shape of the unfolded fan is called &apos;Ogigata or Senkei&apos; and is used as a term in geometry.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The shape of the unfolded fan is called &apos;Ogigata or Senkei&apos; and is used as a term in geometry.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>このような扇子の形状は、「末広」に通ずるので縁起のよいものとされてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The shape of an unfolded Sensu is known as &quot;Suehiro&quot; in Japanese, and has been considered lucky.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shape of an unfolded Sensu is known as &quot;Suehiro&quot; in Japanese, and has been considered lucky.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The shape of an unfolded Sensu is known as &apos;Suehiro&apos; in Japanese, and has been considered lucky.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>そのため、めでたい席での引出物としても用いられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, it is available for a gift given to people on special or happy occasions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, it makes a nice gift on special or happy occasions.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, it makes a nice gift on special or happy occasions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>「おうぎ」は、語源は「あふぐ」（扇ぐ）の派生形の「あふぎ」であるが、日本語の変化により関聨がわかりにくくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The word &apos;Ogi&apos; has its origin in afugi (あふぎ)(something which creates wind) which had derived from &apos;afugu (あふぐ)&apos;, and it has been hard to ascertain the association between the words.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The word &apos;Ogi&apos; has its origin in afugi (あふぎ)(something which creates wind) which had derived from &apos;afugu (あふぐ)&apos;, and it has been hard to ascertain the association between the words.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The word &apos;Ogi&apos; has its origin in &apos;afugi (あふぎ)&apos; (something which creates wind) which had derived from &apos;afugu (あふぐ)&apos;, and it has been hard to ascertain the association between the words.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&apos;を補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>扇子とうちわでは、うちわの方が遙かに成立が早く、紀元前の中国で用いられたという記録がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Uchiwa was made much earlier than Sensu, and there is a record that an Uchiwa was being used in China in the era B.C.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Uchiwa were made much earlier than Sensu, and it is recorded that Uchiwa were being used in China in B.C.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Uchiwa were made much earlier than Sensu, and it is recorded that Uchiwa were being used in China in B.C.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>また、古代エジプトの壁画にも、王の脇に巨大な羽根うちわを掲げた従者が侍っている図がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among ancient Egyptian wall paintings, there is one describing the scene that a King was attended by servants holding a huge Hane-uchiwa (feathered fan.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among ancient Egyptian wall paintings, there is one showing a scene where a King was being attended by servants holding a huge Hane-uchiwa (feathered fan.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among ancient Egyptian wall paintings, there is one showing a scene where a King was being attended by servants holding a huge Hane-uchiwa (feathered fan.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="12">
<j>このようにうちわは文明発祥時から存在する古い物であり、日本へは7世紀頃に伝来したが、うちわを折り畳んで携帯に便利な扇子にするというアイデアは、ずっと時代が下り、8世紀頃の日本で発明された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the history tells, an uchiwa is an old thing which has existed since the appearance of the civilization on the earth, and was taken to Japan in around the 7th century, and the idea of developing it to a folding fan Sensu available to carry around was invented as late as in around the 8th century in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History shows that uchiwa has existed since the appearance of civilization, and was adopted in Japan during the 7th century, the idea of developing it into a folding fan, Sensu, to make it easy to carry around was invented around the 8th century.</e>
<cmt>revised for wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History shows that uchiwa has existed since the appearance of civilization, and was adopted in Japan during the 7th century, the idea of developing it into a folding fan, Sensu, to make it easy to carry around was invented around the 8th century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>扇子の着想は、一説には、木簡（今で言うメモ帳のような物）を束ねて一端に穴を開け、紐などで繋いだ物が起源であるとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The idea of developing an Uchiwa to a Sensu originated from a thing which was made by tying wood strips (currently, like a memopad) together with a thread at a hole created at the end.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The idea of developing an Uchiwa into Sensu was inspired from a things that were made by tying wooden strips together (like a present day memopad) with thread through holes in the end of the wooden strips.</e>
<cmt>revised for wordiness, clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The idea of developing an Uchiwa into Sensu was inspired from a things that were made by tying wooden strips together (like a present day memo pad) with thread through holes in the end of the wooden strips.</e>
<cmt>スペース補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>平安時代頃から、扇子（扇）はあおぐという役割だけでなく、儀礼や贈答、コミュニケーションの道具としても用いられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A Sensu has been used for the expression of respect and good wishes and as a gift and communication tools since the Heian period as well as the function to create airflows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A Sensu has been used as an expression of respect and good wishes and as a gift and as a communication tool since the Heian period, besides its function to create an airflow.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A Sensu has been used as an expression of respect and good wishes and as a gift and as a communication tool since the Heian period, besides its function to create an airflow.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>具体的には和歌を書いて贈ったり、花を載せて贈ったりしたことが、源氏物語など、多くの文学作品や歴史書に書かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In fact, many literatures and historical books including the Tale of Genji tell that a Sensu was gifted with a Waka (poem) written on it or some flowers on it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In fact, a lot of literature and historical books, including the Tale of Genji, say that a Sensu had Waka (poem) written on it or were decorated with some flowers.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity, wordiness, redundancy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact, a lot of literature and historical books, including the Tale of Genji, say that a Sensu had Waka (poem) written on it or were decorated with some flowers.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="16">
<j>武士階級では刀と同じ物と解釈され尊ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were appreciated by warriors as a form of weapons in the Samurai society.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were appreciated by warriors as a form of a weapon in the Samurai society.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were appreciated by warriors as a form of a weapon in the Samurai society.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="17">
<j>大陸には北宋の時代に輸出された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Folding fans were exported to China in the Baisong Era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Folding fans were exported to China in the Baisong Era.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Folding fans were exported to China in the Baisong Era.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="18">
<j>日本で発明された扇子は、コンパクトに折り畳めるという利点が高く評価され、大航海時代には中国を経由して西洋にまで輸出されて独自の発展を遂げ、17世紀のパリには扇を扱う店が150軒を数えるほど、上流階級の女性のコミュニケーションの道具として大流行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A Sensu invented in Japan was exported through China to the West in the age of geographical discovery due to the appreciated advantages to fold it into compact size, and developed in a unique way, and became very popular among the high-class women of the era as a communication tool when there were about 150 shops handling a Sensu in Paris in the 17th century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sensu invented in Japan were exported through China to the West in the age of discovery, and because of its convenient folding into a compact size it developed in a unique way, becoming very popular among high-class women of the times, as a communication tool when there were about 150 shops handling Sensu in Paris during the 17th century.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sensu invented in Japan were exported through China to the West in the age of discovery, and because of its convenient folding into a compact size it developed in a unique way, becoming very popular among high-class women of the times, as a communication tool when there were about 150 shops handling Sensu in Paris during the 17th century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="19">
<j>ヨーロッパで発展したものには、羽根扇やレース (手芸)を編みこんだ洋扇などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the folding fans which were developed in Europe, there are the ones called Hane-ogi (feathered folding fan) and Yo-sen made of lace (for handicraft) knit onto the strips.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among folding fans developed in Europe, there were some called Hane-ogi (feathered folding fan) and Yo-sen made of lace (for handicraft) knitted onto the strips.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among folding fans developed in Europe, there were some called Hane-ogi (feathered folding fan) and Yo-sen made of lace (for handicraft) knitted onto the strips.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="20">
<j>トーマス・エジソンが、白熱電球のフィラメントに竹製の扇子の骨を使って成功したという有名な話がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has been popularly known that Thomas Edison was successful about using the bamboo ribs of Sensu for filaments of an incandescent bulb.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has been popularly known that Thomas Edison was successful using bamboo ribs of Sensu for filaments for his invention the incandescent bulb.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has been popularly known that Thomas Edison was successful using bamboo ribs of Sensu for filaments for his invention the incandescent bulb.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>構成</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Frame</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Frame</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Frame</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="21">
<j>骨</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ribs</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ribs</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ribs</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="22">
<j>骨の材質は、一般的には竹製または木製の物が多く、先端部ほど薄く細くなるテーパ構造になっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Generally, ribs are made of bamboo or wood, and in tapered structure that ribs get thinner toward the end.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Generally, ribs are made of bamboo or wood, in a tapered shape that become thinner towards the end.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Generally, ribs are made of bamboo or wood, in a tapered shape that become thinner towards the end.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>大抵の扇子の骨は細長く、折り畳んだ和紙を張って開くと段になるように展開する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most ribs of Sensu products are thin and long, and the accordion folded Washi is glued to ribs to show accordion folded surface of a Sensu when unfolded.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most ribs of Sensu products are thin and long, and the accordion like folded Washi is glued to the ribs that show the accordion like folds of a Sensu when unfolded.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most ribs of Sensu products are thin and long, and the accordion like folded Washi is glued to the ribs that show the accordion like folds of a Sensu when unfolded.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>骨組みのうち一番外側の部分（親骨）はとくに太く、内側の骨とは逆に先端部ほど太くなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ribs constituting the most end of the frame (Oyabone, ribs at both ends of a folding fan) are the thickest, and unlike inside ribs, get thicker toward the end.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ribs constituting the most ends of the frame (Oyabone, ribs at both ends of a folding fan) are the thickest, and unlike inside ribs, become thicker toward the end.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ribs constituting the most ends of the frame (Oyabone, ribs at both ends of a folding fan) are the thickest, and unlike inside ribs, become thicker toward the end.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>高級な物では、親骨に装飾として漆塗りや蒔絵などの細工が施されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oyabone of expensive or fancy products is decorated with lacquering or gold-lacquer craft.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oyabone of expensive or fancy products are decorated with lacquer or gold-lacquer craft.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oyabone of expensive or fancy products are decorated with lacquer or gold-lacquer craft.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="26">
<j>骨のみの扇子は、香木白檀などの香木を平たく削って作られることがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A Sensu with only frame is usually made from a Koboku (fragrant wood) such as Koboku-byakudan (wood sandal of fragrant wood) by whittling it to get flat.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A Sensu made with only a frame is usually made from a Koboku (fragrant wood) such as Koboku-byakudan (wood sandal of fragrant wood) by whittling them flat.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A Sensu made with only a frame is usually made from a Koboku (fragrant wood) such as Koboku-byakudan (wood sandal of fragrant wood) by whittling them flat.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>ヒノキの薄板を束ねた物は、「檜扇」と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A Sensu made of tied thin stripes of hinoki (Japanese cypress) was called Hi-ogi wooden fan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A Sensu made of tied thin stripes of hinoki (Japanese cypress) was called a Hi-ogi wooden fan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A Sensu made of tied thin stripes of hinoki (Japanese cypress) was called a &apos;Hi-ogi&apos; wooden fan.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&apos;を補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>この形式の扇子はすたれ気味であり、和紙などを貼った紙扇が主流である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such type of Sensu is now losing popularity, and paper folding fans using the Washi are gaining more popularity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such type of Sensu is now losing popularity, and paper folding fans using Washi are gaining more popularity.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such type of Sensu is now losing popularity, and paper folding fans using Washi are gaining more popularity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="29">
<j>木や竹のほかに象牙、鼈甲などもしばしば骨の素材となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ivory and tortoise shell are often used for ribs as well as wood and bamboo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ivory and tortoise shell are often used for ribs as well as wood and bamboo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ivory and tortoise shell are often used for ribs as well as wood and bamboo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="30">
<j>また、武術に用いられる物として、鉄扇（てっせん）がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sensu called Tessen (iron-ribbed fan) is used for martial art.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sensu called Tessen (iron-ribbed fans) is used for martial arts.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sensu called Tessen (iron-ribbed fans) is used for martial arts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>骨だけが鉄製で紙や布などを張ったもの、鉄の短冊を重ねたもの、また扇子の形を模しただけで開かない鉄扇も存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are Tessen products which are made of paper- or cloth-pasted iron ribs, made of stacked iron pieces like Tanzaku (small card on which Japanese poems are usually written vertically), and which don&apos;t open though its appearance is a Sensu&apos;s shape.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are Tessen products which are made of paper- or cloth-pasted on iron ribs, made of stacked iron pieces like Tanzaku (small card on which Japanese poems are usually written vertically), and which don&apos;t open though its appearance is like a Sensu&apos;s shape.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are Tessen products which are made of paper- or cloth-pasted on iron ribs, made of stacked iron pieces like Tanzaku (small card on which Japanese poems are usually written vertically), and which don&apos;t open although its appearance is like a Sensu&apos;s shape.</e>
<cmt>though →althoughに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>携帯用の護身具、または鍛錬具として用いられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are also used as a portable Goshingu (self-defense tool) or training tool.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are also used as a portable Goshingu (self-defense weapon) or a training tool.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are also used as a portable Goshingu (self-defense weapon) or a training tool.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="33">
<j>扇面</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Surface of fan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fan suface</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fan surface</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>あおぐ時に風を送る部位。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It&apos;s a part available to create a small airflow by waving back and forth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It can create a small airflow by waving back and forth.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It can create a small airflow by waving back and forth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>骨が完全に開ききらないように固定する働きもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It also functions to prevent the rib frame from extremely unfolding.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It also functions to prevent the rib frame from extreme unfolding.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It also functions to prevent the rib frame from extreme unfolding.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>伝統的な扇子では和紙を張るが、合成繊維や布を貼ったものもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Surface of a traditional type of Sensu gets Washi glued, while some other type of Sensu has synthetics- or cloth-glued surface.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The surface of a traditional type Sensu has Washi, while some other type of Sensu use synthetics- or cloth-glued to the ribs.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The surface of a traditional type Sensu has Washi, while some other type of Sensu use synthetics- or cloth-glued to the ribs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>この扇面に絵を描く必要から、湾曲した形状（いわゆる扇形）の紙に描く、扇絵と呼ばれる日本画の形式が発展した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the need for painting curved area, fan painting available to draw pictures on a curved place (ogigata- or senkei-shaped place) was developed and is called as a Japanese painting style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the need for painting on a curved area, fan painting progressed in drawing pictures on a curved shape (ogigata- or senkei-shaped place) was developed and is known as a Japanese painting style.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the need for painting on a curved area, fan painting progressed in drawing pictures on a curved shape (ogigata- or senkei-shaped place) was developed and is known as a Japanese painting style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>この形式を発展させたのが、俵屋宗達と尾形光琳だといわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Persons who contributed to the development of this painting style were believed to be Sotatsu TAWARAYA and Korin OGATA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">People who contributed to developing this style of painting were believed to be Sotatsu TAWARAYA and Korin OGATA.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">People who contributed to developing this style of painting were believed to be Sotatsu TAWARAYA and Korin OGATA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="39">
<j>扇子のアイデアがヨーロッパに輸出された時は、絹やレースを貼った洋扇に発展した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the concept of Sensu was spread to Europe, it was developed to make silk- or lace-glued Yo-sen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the concept of Sensu spread to Europe, it developed into silk- or lace-glued Yo-sen.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the concept of Sensu spread to Europe, it developed into silk- or lace-glued Yo-sen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>クジャクの羽根を用いた扇子もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are Sensu products using peacock feathers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are Sensu products using peacock feathers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are Sensu products using peacock feathers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="41">
<j>また、沖縄では扇面にヤシ科のビロウ（クバ）の葉を使ったクバ扇（くばおーじ）というものがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Okinawa, there are products called Kuba-ogi with surface made of leaves of a Biro (Kuba) (Livistona chinensis.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Okinawa, there are products called Kuba-ogi with surface made of leaves of a Biro (Kuba) (Livistona chinensis.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Okinawa, there are products called Kuba-ogi with surface made of leaves of a Biro (Kuba) (Livistona chinensis.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaname (Pivot)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaname (Pivot)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaname (Pivot)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="43">
<j>かなめ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaname (Pivot)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaname (Pivot)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaname (Pivot)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>扇を開く際に根本で止めるもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It&apos;s an elementary part to control the folding of a fan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An elementary part to allow the folding of the fan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An elementary part to allow the folding of the fan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>扇子の要は、金属やプラスチック、鯨ひげなどで骨を束ねている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A pivot of Sensu is made by tying the ribs with metal or plastic thread or baleens.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A pivot for the Sensu is made by tying the ribs with metal or plastic thread or baleen.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A pivot for the Sensu is made by tying the ribs with metal or plastic thread or baleen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>この部位が壊れると扇子としての用を為さなくなるため、最も重要な部分である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If it&apos;s broken, the Sensu doesn&apos;t fulfill its primary functions, so this is the most important point</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If it&apos;s brakes, the Sensu won&apos;t be able to fulfill its primary function, so this is the most important point</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If it&apos;s brakes, the Sensu won&apos;t be able to fulfill its primary function, so this is the most important point</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>ここから、「肝心要」の語源となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A term &apos;Kanjin-kaname (the main point) originated from the above.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term &apos;Kanjin-kaname&apos; (the main point) originated from the above idea.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term &apos;Kanjin-kaname&apos; (the main point) originated from the above idea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>責</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seme</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seme</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seme</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="49">
<j>せめ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seme</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seme</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seme</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>扇を止める帯状の輪。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It&apos;s a ring to keep a Sensu closed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is a ring to keep a Sensu closed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is a ring to keep a Sensu closed.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>開閉の方法</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The way to fold and unfold a Sensu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The way to fold and unfold a Sensu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The way to fold and unfold a Sensu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="51">
<j>骨を右手親指でずらすように押すことで開く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A Sensu can be opened by pushing the ribs away with a thumb of the right hand.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A Sensu can be opened by separating the ribs by pushing them away with the thumb of the right hand.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A Sensu can be opened by separating the ribs by pushing them away with the thumb of the right hand.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>一般的には利き手用であるが、左利き用も販売されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most Sensu products are right-handed, but left-handed Sensu is on sale, too.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most Sensu products are right-handed, but left-handed Sensu are also sold as well.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most Sensu products are right-handed, but left-handed Sensu are also sold as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="53">
<j>また、扇子そのものを振ることで開く方法もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shaking is another way to unfold a Sensu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shaking is another way to unfold a Sensu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shaking is another way to unfold a Sensu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="54">
<j>分類</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Classifications</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Classifications</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Classifications</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>飾り扇子、檜扇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kazari-sensu (decorated folding fan)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kazari-sensu (decorated folding fan)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kazari-sensu (decorated folding fan)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>夏扇子</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Natsu-sensu (summer fan)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Natsu-sensu (summer fan)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Natsu-sensu (summer fan)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>舞扇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mai-ogi (fan for Japanese dance)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mai-ogi (fan for Japanese dance)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mai-ogi (fan for Japanese dance)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>祝儀扇子</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shugi-sensu (folding fan for formal dress)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shugi-sensu (folding fan for formal dress)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shugi-sensu (folding fan for formal dress)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>用途</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Purpose of use</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Purpose of use</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Purpose of use</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="59">
<j>風を送る</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To send air.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To move air.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To move air.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>扇子の主用途。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Principal purpose of a Sensu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Principal purpose of a Sensu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Principal purpose of a Sensu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>暑いときに、手元で扇子を開いて自ら風を送ることで涼しさを得ることを目的に扇ぐ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The purpose of a Sensu is to induce an airflow for cooling down by waving it by hand on a hot day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The purpose of a Sensu is to induce an airflow for cooling by waving it by hand on a hot day.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The purpose of a Sensu is to induce an airflow for cooling by waving it by hand on a hot day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>繊細な構造であるため、強い風を送るのには向いていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A Sensu is not appropriate to create a strong airflow due to its delicate structure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A Sensu is not appropriate for creating a strong airflow due to its delicate structure.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A Sensu is not appropriate for creating a strong airflow due to its delicate structure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>炭火をおこす場合に扇ぐ用途には向いていない、渋うちわか火吹き竹が妥当であろう、成田山等の寺社で護摩を焚く場合には、点火後、扇子を広げて火を扇ぐ所作が見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When making a fire using charcoal, a Shibu-uchiwa (fan coated with persimmon tannin) or a Hifuki-dake (bamboo blowpipe used to stimulate a fire) will be perfect rather than a Sensu, but when making a holy fire at temples and shrines in Naritasan, it is observed for people to stimulate the fire by waving a unfolded Sensu back and forth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When making a fire using charcoal, a Shibu-uchiwa (fan coated with persimmon tannin) or a Hifuki-dake (bamboo blowpipe used to stimulate a fire) will be perfect rather than a Sensu, but when making a holy fire at temples and shrines in Naritasan, it is observed for people to stimulate the fire by waving a unfolded Sensu back and forth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When making a fire using charcoal, a Shibu-uchiwa (fan coated with persimmon tannin) or a Hifuki-dake (bamboo blowpipe used to stimulate a fire) will be perfect rather than a Sensu, but when making a holy fire at temples and shrines in Naritasan, it is observed for people to stimulate the fire by waving a unfolded Sensu back and forth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>実質的な着火の用途でないのであれば扇子のほうが美しく見える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If a substantial purpose is not making a fire, a Sensu looks more beautiful.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If a substantial purpose is not for making a fire, a Sensu is beautiful as an accessory.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If a substantial purpose is not for making a fire, a Sensu is beautiful as an accessory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="65">
<j>落語の見立て</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitate likening of Rakugo (Japanese sit-down comedy)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitate likening of Rakugo (Japanese sit-down comedy)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitate likening of Rakugo (Japanese sit-down comedy)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>落語でのうどんなどを食べる場面で、畳んだ状態での扇子を箸に見立てて用いる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a scene where noodle like udon (Japanese wheat noodle) is eaten in a Rakugo, a folded Sensu is often used to substitute for chopsticks.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In a scene where noodle like udon (Japanese wheat noodle) is eaten in a Rakugo, a folded Sensu is often used to substitute for chopsticks.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In a scene where noodle like udon (Japanese wheat noodle) is eaten in a Rakugo, a folded Sensu is often used to substitute for chopsticks.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>場面に応じて、刀や望遠鏡など様々な見立てがなされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the scenes, a folded Sensu is used to substitute for various items such as a sword and a telescope.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the scene, a folded Sensu is used to substitute for various items such as a sword or a telescope.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the scene, a folded Sensu is used to substitute for various items such as a sword or a telescope.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>手拭と並んで重要な落語の小道具。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A Sensu is an indispensable property for Rakugo as well as a Tenugui towel.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A Sensu is an indispensable prop for Rakugo and serves also as a Tenugui towel.</e>
<cmt>revised for clairity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A Sensu is an indispensable prop for Rakugo and serves also as a Tenugui towel.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>噺家の隠語では扇子は風（かぜ）と呼ばれる（ちなみに手拭はマンダラ）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hanashika (professional Rakugo storyteller) calls the Sensu as Kaze (wind) for a slang (a Tenugui towel is called Mandala for a slang.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hanashika (professional Rakugo storyteller) calls it Kaze (wind) as slang (a Tenugui towel is called Mandala as slang.)</e>
<cmt>revised for clairity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hanashika (professional Rakugo storyteller) calls it Kaze (wind) as slang (a Tenugui towel is called Mandala as slang.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="70">
<j>挨拶の境</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Greeting border line</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Greeting border line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Greeting border line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>座って挨拶をするときに、胸元から畳んだ状態の扇子を自らの膝前に置き、それを境にするように相手に礼を行う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When a person sits on a floor to say greeting, the person takes out a folded Sensu from the front collars of a kimono (usually) and puts it in front of his or her knees, and says greeting or thank-you words, considering the folded Sensu as a border line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When a person sits on the floor as a greeting, he takes out a folded Sensu from within the front overlap of his kimono (usually) and places it in front of his knees, before saying his greeting or thank-yous, considering the folded Sensu as a border line.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When a person sits on the floor as a greeting, he takes out a folded Sensu from within the front overlap of his kimono (usually) and places it in front of his knees, before saying his greeting or thank-yous, considering the folded Sensu as a border line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>これは扇子に自他のさかいをつくる結界としての役割をもたせたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This gives a role for a folded Sensu to work as kekkai barrier in order to constitute a border line with the other person.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus the folded Sensu to work as kekkai barrier in order to constitute a border line between himself and another person.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus the folded Sensu to work as kekkai barrier in order to constitute a border line between himself and another person.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>葬儀の際に喪主に挨拶する場合なども同様に行う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A folded Sensu is used in the same way when someone extends a condolence to a host of the funeral.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A folded Sensu is used in the same way when someone extends a condolence to a host at a uneral.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A folded Sensu is used in the same way when someone extends a condolence to a host at a funeral.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="74">
<j>胸に挿す</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Put a Sense into the two front collars of a kimono.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Put a Sensu into the two front overlaps of a kimono.</e>
<cmt>spelling, terminology</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Put a Sensu into the two front overlaps of a kimono.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>女性が和装の際に、懐剣の代用として帯に扇子を挿す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Women dressed in kimono wear a Sensu in a obi belt for a substitute of a Futokoro-gatana (pocket tagger.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Women dressed in kimono wear a Sensu in their obi belt as a substitute for a Futokoro-gatana (pocket dagger.)</e>
<cmt>&quot;tagger&quot; is probably &quot;dagger&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Women dressed in kimono wear a Sensu in their obi belt as a substitute for a Futokoro-gatana (pocket dagger.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="76">
<j>弓矢の的</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Aim for bow and arrow</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Target for bow and arrow</e>
<cmt>terminology revised</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Target for bow and arrow</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>かつては、日の丸の扇子（白地に赤い丸が描かれている）を開いて、弓の的にした事例がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the past, there were cases that a Hinomaru (national flag of Japan) designed Sensu was opened to work for a target for bow and arrow.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the past, there were cases where a Hinomaru (national flag of Japan) designed Sensu was opened to be used for a target for bow and arrow.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the past, there were cases where a Hinomaru (national flag of Japan) designed Sensu was opened to be used for a target for bow and arrow.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>源平合戦で弓矢の達人と言われた那須与一が、平氏の船の上に掲げられた扇の的を射抜いた故事は有名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a famous historical event that NASU no Yoichi shot into a Sensu placed at the top of a Taira clan&apos;s boat in the Gappei-Kassen Battle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a famous story about NASU no Yoichi shooting an arrow into a Sensu placed at the top of a Taira clan&apos;s boat in the Gappei-Kassen Battle.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a famous story about NASU no Yoichi shooting an arrow into a Sensu placed at the top of a Taira clan&apos;s boat in the Genpei War.</e>
<cmt>the Gappei-Kassen Battle→the Genpei War</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="79">
<j>棋士の思考の際の手すさび</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hand game for a Kishi (professional go/shogi player) while thinking.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Stress reliever for a Kishi (professional go/shogi player) while thinking.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Stress reliever for a Kishi (professional go/shogi player) while thinking.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>将棋や囲碁の対局時、棋士 (将棋)や棋士 (囲碁)が考える際に手で開け閉めしていることがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When playing Shogi (Japanese chess) or Igo (game of Igo), a Kishi (player) is likely to unfold or fold a Sensu while thinking of the strategy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When playing Shogi (Japanese chess) or Igo (game of Igo), a Kishi (player) is likely to unfold or fold a Sensu while thinking about his strategy.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When playing Shogi (Japanese chess) or Igo (game of Igo), a Kishi (player) is likely to unfold or fold a Sensu while thinking about his strategy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>これは数十手先の着手を読む際に、開閉の単調なリズムが思考へ好影響をもたらすためである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is because repeated same motions to only fold and unfold a Sensu give good effects to the thinking when trying to read the coming development.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is because habitual motions to fold and unfold a Sensu has a soothing effect on thinking when anticipating the coming moves.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is because habitual motions to fold and unfold a Sensu has a soothing effect on thinking when anticipating the coming moves.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>なお扇子の開け閉めは相手にとって雑音として受け取られる場合もあることから、極力自分の考慮時間中に行う事が相手に対する礼節とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A sound arising from fan folding and unfolding is sometimes likely to be a noise to other parson, so it is considered a good manner for the player to do the same during his or her considering time as much as possible.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sound folding and unfolding is sometimes likely to be annoying to the other parson, so it is considered good manners for the player to reciprocate the motion during his or her turn, as much as possible.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sound folding and unfolding is sometimes likely to be annoying to the other parson, so it is considered good manners for the player to reciprocate the motion during his or her turn, as much as possible.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="83">
<j>舞踊の小道具</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Property for dance</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prop for dance</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prop for dance</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>日本舞踊や能楽における小道具として、また仕舞・素踊などの際に本来の舞台において用いられる小道具の代りとして用いられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A Sensu is used as a property in classical Japanese dance or Nogaku, or for a substitute of a property used in Shimai (No dance in plain clothes) or Su-odori Japanese dance played on a stage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A Sensu is used as a prop in classical Japanese dance or Nogaku, or for a substitute of a prop used in Shimai (No dance in plain clothes) or Su-odori Japanese dance on stage.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A Sensu is used as a prop in classical Japanese dance or Nogaku, or for a substitute of a prop used in Shimai (No dance in plain clothes) or Su-odori Japanese dance on stage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>（舞扇の項も参照）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(See the Mai-ogi section, too.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(See the Mai-ogi section, too.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(See the Mai-ogi section, too.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="86">
<j>口を隠す</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cover a mouth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Covering the mouth.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Covering the mouth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>礼儀として、笑うときに歯が見えないように口の前を覆う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a polite way to cover the mouth showing the teeth by Sensu when laughing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a polite way to cover the mouth hiding the teeth with a Sensu when laughing.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a polite way to cover the mouth hiding the teeth with a Sensu when laughing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="88">
<j>張り扇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hari-ogi paper fan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hari-ogi paper fan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hari-ogi paper fan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>講談師が講談の最中に、調子取りと音を出すために、釈台を叩く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A kodanshi (professional storyteller) slaps the a shakudai pedestal (table) with a Sensu to keep rhythm and make a sound in the course of a kodan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A kodanshi (professional storyteller) slaps the a shakudai pedestal (table) with a Sensu to keep rhythm and make a sound in the course of a kodan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A kodanshi (professional storyteller) slaps the a shakudai pedestal (table) with a Sensu to keep rhythm and make a sound in the course of a kodan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="90">
<j>人を叩く</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hit a person.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To hit a person with.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To hit a person with.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>落語で自分の頭を叩いたり、踊りの師匠が弟子をたしなめるのに、手ではなく扇子を使って頭を叩く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To discipline in a rakugo, a kodanshi pats his/her own head with a Sensu and a master pats his apprentice on his/her head with a Sensu rather than a hand.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To discipline in a rakugo, a kodanshi pats his/her own head with a Sensu or a master pats his apprentice on his/her head with a Sensu rather than with the hand.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To discipline in a rakugo, a kodanshi pats his/her own head with a Sensu or a master pats his apprentice on his/her head with a Sensu rather than with the hand.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>空中で叩く所作をもって叩いたことにすることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An action of slapping something in the air substitutes for a real slap.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An action of slapping something in the air substitutes for a real slap.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An action of slapping something in the air substitutes for a real slap.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>（但し、武士階級では扇子で頭を叩かれる（叩く）行為は非常に屈辱を与える（あるいは受ける）物とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(In Samurai society, an act to slap someone&apos;s head with a Sensu was believed to insult the person or get the person insulted extremely.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(In Samurai society, the act of slapping someone&apos;s head with a Sensu was an extreme insult.</e>
<cmt>revised for wordiness and clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(In Samurai society, the act of slapping someone&apos;s head with a Sensu was an extreme insult.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>扇子で頭や手足を叩く行為は明治以降に行われる様になったと思われる。)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that an act to slap someone&apos;s head, hand or leg with a Sensu began in the Meiji era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that the act to slap someone&apos;s head, hand, or leg with a Sensu began in the Meiji era.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that the act to slap someone&apos;s head, hand, or leg with a Sensu began in the Meiji era.)</e>
<cmt>次行の)を統合</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="95">
<j>ツッコミ用ハリセン</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Harisen (paper fan used as a slapstick) for feeding.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Harisen (a paper fan used by the straight man for slapstick) for a straight man (tsukkomi) in manzai.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Harisen (a paper fan used by the straight man for slapstick) for a straight man (tsukkomi) in manzai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>大きな紙を折り畳んで一方をテープで止めたものは、「ハリセン」と呼ばれ、ドツキ漫才などでツッコミ用に使われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A large sheet of paper folded with an edge glued is called Harisen, and is used for feeding in a Dotsuki Manzai (comic backchat with using a tap as an interjection.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The harisen is a giant folding fan which is usually made to appear closed, and is used by a straight man (tsukkomi) in a Dotsuki manzai (comic backchat using a tap as an interjection.)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &apos;harisen&apos; is a giant folding fan which is usually made to appear closed, and is used by a straight man (tsukkomi) in a Dotsuki manzai (comic backchat using a tap as an interjection.)</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&apos;を補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="97">
<j>投扇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tosen</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tosen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tosen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>投扇興（とうせんきょう）といい、扇子を的に向かって投げ、的を落とす遊びに用いる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tosenkyo Japanese game is to thrown a Sensu to the target and drop it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tosenkyo Japanese game, is throwing a Sensu at a target and knocking it down..</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tosenkyo Japanese game, is throwing a Sensu at a target and knocking it down..</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>技の名前に源氏物語の帖名や百人一首などが用いられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Techniques had a name taken from book title such as The Tale of Genji or Hyakunin-Isshu (one hundred waka poems.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The technique used a name taken from book title such as The Tale of Genji or Hyakunin-Isshu (one hundred waka poems.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The technique used a name taken from book title such as The Tale of Genji or Hyakunin-Isshu (one hundred waka poems.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="100">
<j>装飾</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Decoration</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Decoration</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Decoration</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>置物として飾るためだけの扇子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A Sensu only to be displayed as a decoration item.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A Sensu can be displayed as a decoration or an art object.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A Sensu can be displayed as a decoration or an art object.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>扇子を美しい工芸品として評価したもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A Sensu appreciated to be a beautiful art craft.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A Sensu appreciated to be a beautiful art craft.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A Sensu appreciated to be a beautiful art craft.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>差し渡し1メートルに達する巨大なものもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a big Sensu with a one meter distance across the both edges.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A large Sensu, a one meter across.</e>
<cmt>grammar. Assuming this is a caption for a photo.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A large Sensu, a one meter across.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>和歌を書いて贈る場合の白地の扇子も装飾あるいは次の贈答の意味だといえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A white-surfaced Sensu available to write a waka poem on it for a gift will be a decoration item and a gift item which will be described below.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A white-surfaced Sensu available for writing a waka poem on to be presented as a gift can be a decoration and a gift, which will be described below:</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A white-surfaced Sensu available for writing a waka poem on to be presented as a gift can be a decoration and a gift, which will be described below:</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="105">
<j>贈答</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gift</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gift</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gift</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>能楽で節目の舞台をする時に、出演者や贔屓の方に配る（被き扇）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A Sensu is delivered to the players and the Hiiki (illegitimate favor) persons (a Kazuki-ogi) when a Nogaku milestone stage is planned.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A Sensu is given to the actors, actresses and Hiiki persons (patrons) when a milestone stage of Nogaku is performed (a Kazuki-ogi).</e>
<cmt>Questions: by &quot;players&quot; do you mean &quot;actors?&quot; By &quot;illegitimate favor&quot; do you mean &quot;illegal favor&quot; and if so, can you provide an example of an &quot;illegal favor?&quot; What is a &quot;milestone stage?&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A Sensu is given to the actors and patrons when Nohgaku is performed in spcial occations (a Kazuki-ogi).</e>
<cmt>エディタのコメントをふまえて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>落語などでも行われる慣習である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The above practice is performed in Rakugo society.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The above practice is performed in the Rakugo society.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The above practice is performed in the Rakugo society.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>かつては販売促進の物品に使われていたこともあったようだが、うちわにその座を追われた格好である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A Sensu seemed to be popular sales promotion item in the past, but an Uchiwa looks to take the place.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A Sensu seemed to be popular sales promotion item in the past, but an Uchiwa seems to have taken its place.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A Sensu seemed to be popular sales promotion item in the past, but an Uchiwa seems to have taken its place.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="109">
<j>この他、平安時代などに於ける貴族階級で上位の階級の者が親しい階級の者に下賜するときの贈答品としても用いられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, in the noble society in the Heian era, a senior-ranked person in a noble class used to give a Sensu to a lower-ranked person as a gift.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among nobles in society, during the Heian era, a senior-ranked person, from a noble class, used to give a Sensu to a lower-ranked person as a gift.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among nobles in society, during the Heian period, a senior-ranked person, from a noble class, used to give a Sensu to a lower-ranked person as a gift.</e>
<cmt>Heian era→Heian periodに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="110">
<j>武器、護身用</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Weapon, tool for self-protection</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Weapon, for self-protection</e>
<cmt>redundancy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Weapon, for self-protection</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>骨に鉄を用いた「鉄扇」はほとんど鉄棒と変らないため、殴打用の武器となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A &apos;Tessen&apos; made of iron ribs is hardly different from iron bar, and can be a weapon to slap or beat.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A &apos;Tessen&apos; made of iron ribs is hardly different from an iron bar, and can be a weapon used to slap or beat.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A &apos;Tessen&apos; made of iron ribs is hardly different from an iron bar, and can be a weapon used to slap or beat.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>かつては刀剣などの武器を持込むことが禁じられた場所において、護身用の暗器として多く用いられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In places where a weapon such as swords was not allowed to bring in, a Sensu was often used as an Anki (small concealed weapon) for self-protection purposes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In places where a weapon, such as a sword, was not allowed, a Sensu was often used as an Anki (small concealed weapon) for self-protection.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In places where a weapon, such as a sword, was not allowed, a Sensu was often used as an Anki (small concealed weapon) for self-protection.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="113">
<j>扇子の紙の弧の部分に刃や針を仕込んだものの他、骨組みが稼動しない物に短刀クラスの刀身を仕込んだ物などが考案されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are newly developed Sensu with features such as concealing a blade or needle in arc-shaped paper surface, and concealing a blade of a short-typed knife in an immovable frame.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are newly developed Sensu that conceal a blade or needle in the arc-shaped paper surface, and concealing a blade of a short-typed knife in the frame.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are newly developed Sensu that conceal a blade or needle in the arc-shaped paper surface, and concealing a blade of a short-typed knife in the frame.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="114">
<j>密書</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Secret letter</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Secret letter</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Secret letter</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>鉄扇と同じく、軍事的・武器的用途としての「仕込み」のひとつである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Likely Tessen, a Sensu is a kind of &apos;Shikomi (Anki)&apos; intended to be used for military purposes or as a weapon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Like Tessen, a Sensu is a kind of &apos;Shikomi (Anki)&apos; intended to be used for military purposes or as a weapon.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Like Tessen, a Sensu is a kind of &apos;Shikomi (Anki)&apos; intended to be used for military purposes or as a weapon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="116">
<j>和紙を貼って作られるという点を利用して、裏側に文書を記録しておく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taking advantage of the use of the Washi, words or statement can be recorded on a reverse side of the Sensu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taking advantage of the use of the Washi, words or statements can be written on a reverse side of the Sensu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taking advantage of the use of the Washi, words or statements can be written on a reverse side of the Sensu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="117">
<j>侍にとって印籠や扇子を持つことは一種のファッションであった為、取調べを逃れることが容易であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since for a samurai warrior to carry an Inro (pill case) or a Sensu with him is a fashion, it was easy to flee from investigations.</e>
<cmt>次の文章は、make no senseです。&quot;取調べを逃れることが容易であった”</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since, for a samurai warrior to carry an Inro (pill case) or a Sensu with him was fashionable, it was easy to flee from investigations.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since, for a samurai warrior to carry an Inro (pill case) or a Sensu with him was fashionable, it was easy to flee from investigations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="118">
<j>応援</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Support</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Support</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Support</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="119">
<j>応援団が和装で声援を送る時、手に「必勝」などの文字が描かれた扇子を振って調子を取る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When supporters dressed in Japanese clothes cheer, they keep rhythm moving a Sensu on which a word &apos;victory&apos; is written.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When supporters dressed in Japanese clothes are cheering, they keep rhythm by moving a Sensu on which the word &apos;victory&apos; is written.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When supporters dressed in Japanese clothes are cheering, they keep rhythm by moving a Sensu on which the word &apos;victory&apos; is written.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="120">
<j>鉢巻に挿す場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A Sensu may be put in a Hachimaki head band.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A Sensu may be put in a Hachimaki head band.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A Sensu may be put in a Hachimaki head band.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="121">
<j>羽根扇子・ジュリ扇（ジュリせん）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hane-sensu (feathered folding fan) and Juli-sen</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hane-sensu (feathered folding fan) and Juli-sen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hane-sensu (feathered folding fan) and Juli-sen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="122">
<j>日本で羽根扇子を用いた舞踊は宝塚歌劇に見る事ができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan, dancing featuring a Hane-sensu can be enjoyed in Takarazuka Revue.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan, dancing featuring a Hane-sensu can be enjoyed in the Takarazuka Revue.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan, dancing featuring a Hane-sensu can be enjoyed in the Takarazuka Revue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="123">
<j>主に歌劇中の女性貴族の持ち物として用いられ、劇中の華やかさを彩る物となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mostly, a Hane-sensu is employed as an item carried by a noblewoman appearing in a musical and adds more opulence to the play.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mostly, a Hane-sensu is employed as an item carried by a noblewoman appearing in a musical and adds more opulence to the play.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mostly, a Hane-sensu is employed as an item carried by a noblewoman appearing in a musical and adds more opulence to the play.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="124">
<j>1990年代にはディスコで踊ることが流行し、ジュリアナ東京でも多く用いられたことからジュリ扇とも呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dancing in a disco was popular in the 1990s and many people danced with a Hane-sensu in JULIANA&apos;S TOKYO British discotheque in Shibaura, so that&apos;s why it was called Juli-sen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dancing in a disco was popular in the 1990s and many people danced with a Hane-sensu in JULIANA&apos;S TOKYO British discotheque in Shibaura, so that&apos;s why it was called Juli-sen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dancing in a disco was popular in the 1990s and many people danced with a Hane-sensu in JULIANA&apos;S TOKYO British discotheque in Shibaura, so that&apos;s why it was called Juli-sen.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="125">
<j>またこの羽根扇子はストリップ劇場などの舞台でも小道具として使われることがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A Hane-sensu can be used for a prop in strip theaters.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A Hane-sensu can be used for a prop in strip theaters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A Hane-sensu can be used for a prop in strip theaters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="126">
<j>盆の代用として（贈答時）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Substitute of a tray</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Substitute for a tray</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Substitute for a tray</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="127">
<j>扇子に金封をのせてさしだすこともある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A Kimpu (envelope with gift money) can be put on a Sensu when offered.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A Kimpu (envelope with gift money) can be put on a Sensu when offered.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A Kimpu (envelope with gift money) can be put on a Sensu when offered.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="128">
<j>このとき要を手前にして、金封をのせ、相手の膝前に要がむくように、転回してさしだす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this case, after a Kimpu is put on a Sensu with a Kaname closer to the giver, the Sensu with a Kimpu on is turned with the Kaname closer to the receiver and offered.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this case, after a Kimpu is put on a Sensu with a Kaname closer to the giver, the Sensu with a Kimpu on it is turned with the Kaname closer to the receiver and offered.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this case, after a Kimpu is put on a Sensu with a Kaname closer to the giver, the Sensu with a Kimpu on it is turned with the Kaname closer to the receiver and offered.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="129">
<j>これは本来盆にのせてさしだすところを扇子で代用するという意味をもつ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It means that a Sensu substitutes for a tray though originally, a tray should be used to offer a Kimpu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It means that a Sensu substitutes for a tray though originally, a tray should be used to offer a Kimpu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It means that a Sensu substitutes for a tray although originally, a tray should be used to offer a Kimpu.</e>
<cmt>though→althoughに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="130">
<j>扇子腹</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sensu-bara</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sensu-bara</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sensu-bara</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="131">
<j>切腹の際、本来は実際に短刀で腹を切るのであるが、次第に形式化して切る形だけとなり、後には小刀が扇子で代用されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When committing a Seppuku (suicide by disembowelment), a short knife should be actually plunged into the abdomen, but it has gradually become a ritual thing, and eventually, a Sensu substituted for a short knife for a Seppuku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When committing Seppuku (suicide by disembowelment), a short knife should be actually plunged into the abdomen, but it has gradually become a ritualistic thing, and eventually, a Sensu substituted as a short knife for Seppuku.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When committing Seppuku (suicide by disembowelment), a short knife should be in fact plunged into the abdomen, but it has gradually become a ritualistic thing, and eventually, a Sensu substituted as a short knife for Seppuku.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除actually →in factに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="132">
<j>（介錯は行われたため、この場合斬首と大差ない。)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Kaisaku (to assist someone in committing hara-kiri by beheading him/her) was performed, and there was no big difference between a Zanshu (beheading) and the Seppuku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Kaisaku (to assist someone in committing hara-kiri by beheading him/her) was performed, and there was no big difference between a Zanshu (beheading) and Seppuku.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Kaisaku (to assist someone in committing hara-kiri by beheading him/her) was performed, and there was no big difference between a Zanshu (beheading) and Seppuku.)</e>
<cmt>次行の)を統合</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="133">
<j>扇合わせ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ogi-awase (a fan matching game)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ogi-awase (a fan matching game)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ogi-awase (a fan matching game)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="134">
<j>平安時代の宮中において2組に分かれて、扇を持ち合い、その描かれた絵画や材質の優劣を競い合う行事である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It&apos;s an event to compete the quality of a Sensu held by the two groups of people in the Imperial court in the Heian Era and pictures painted on the surface of the Sensu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is a competition where the quality of a Sensu held by the two groups of people in the Imperial court in the Heian Era, and pictures were painted on the surface of the Sensu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is a competition where the quality of a Sensu held by the two groups of people in the Imperial court in the Heian period, and pictures were painted on the surface of the Sensu.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除Era→periodに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="135">
<j>円融天皇の天禄四年（973年）に行われた記録がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a record that an Ogi-awase was performed in 973 of the Emperor Enyu era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a story about an Ogi-awase that was performed in 973 during the Emperor Enyu era.</e>
<cmt>revisedfor clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a story about an Ogi-awase that was performed in 973 during the Emperor Enyu era.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="136">
<j>宮中行事の小道具</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gadgets for court events</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gadgets for court events</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gadgets for court events</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="137">
<j>毎月一日、天皇が三種の神器が安置されている内侍所へ参拝する為に御月扇として月毎に扇が新調されたほか、毎年、絵所から賢聖御末広として、表面に古代中国の賢聖、裏面に金銀砂子に草花を描いた扇が献上された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A Sensu was made every month for an On-tsuki-ogi (御月扇) because the Emperor carried it with him for a visit at the Naishidokoro (a place where sacred mirror was enshrined) storing the three sacred imperial treasures on the 1st day of the month, and also the Edokoro government office made a present of a fan with pictures of Kenjo sage in the ancient China on its surface and pictures of plants and flowers on Kin-gin Sunago (gold and silver leaf reduced to powder) on the reverse side as a Kenjo-Onsuehiro fan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A Sensu was made every month for an On-tsuki-ogi (御月扇) because the Emperor carried it with him for a visit at the Naishidokoro (a place where the sacred mirror was enshrined) storing the three sacred imperial treasures on the 1st day of the month, and also the Edokoro government office presented a fan with pictures of Kenjo sage in ancient China on its surface and pictures of plants and flowers on Kin-gin Sunago (gold and silver leaf reduced to powder) on the reverse side as a Kenjo-Onsuehiro fan.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A Sensu was made every month for an On-tsuki-ogi (御月扇) because the Emperor carried it with him for a visit at the Naishidokoro (a place where the sacred mirror was enshrined) storing the three sacred imperial treasures on the 1st day of the month, and also the Edokoro government office presented a fan with pictures of Kenjo sage in ancient China on its surface and pictures of plants and flowers on Kin-gin Sunago (gold and silver leaf reduced to powder) on the reverse side as a Kenjo-Onsuehiro fan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>派生したもの</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Offshoots</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Offshoots</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Offshoots</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="138">
<j>ヒオウギアヤメ（檜扇菖蒲）－葉が檜扇に似ていることから名付けられた</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hiogiayama named because its leaves resembled a Hiogi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hiogiayama came from the idea that its leaves resembled a Hiogi.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hiogiayama came from the idea that its leaves resembled a Hiogi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="139">
<j>ヒオウギガイ－貝の形が檜扇に似ていることから名付けられた</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hiogigai chlamys nobilis named because the shells resembled a Hiogi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Was called Hiogigai chlamys nobilis because the shells resembled a Hiogi.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Was called Hiogigai chlamys nobilis because the shells resembled a Hiogi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="140">
<j>オウギバショウ－葉の付き方が扇に似ていることから名付けられた</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ogibasho traveler&apos;s-tree named because the way of growing the leaves resembled a fan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ogibasho traveler&apos;s-tree was named because of the way the leaves grew resembled a fan.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ogibasho traveler&apos;s-tree was named because of the way the leaves grew resembled a fan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>家紋</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Family crest</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Family crest</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Family crest</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="141">
<j>家紋の意匠としても用いられ、摺り畳扇を図案化した扇紋（おうぎもん）と板扇を図案化した檜扇紋（ひおうぎもん）がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are an Ogi-mon crest designed based on a Suridatami-ogi (摺り畳扇) and a Hi-ogi-mon crest designed based on an Ita-ogi (a fan with thin wooden board) which are used for a design of family crests.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are an Ogi-mon crest designed based upon a Suridatami-ogi (摺り畳扇) and a Hi-ogi-mon crest designed based upon an Ita-ogi (a fan with thin wooden board) which are used for designing family crests.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are an Ogi-mon crest designed based upon a Suridatami-ogi (摺り畳扇) and a Hi-ogi-mon crest designed based upon an Ita-ogi (a fan with thin wooden board) which are used for designing family crests.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除摺り畳扇→Suridatami-ogi (摺り畳扇)[定訳不明,読み方が見つからなかったため、仮訳です。]</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="142">
<j>扇紋には五本骨扇等の骨の数によって表されるものや・より写実的な図案の雁木扇や反り返りの付けられた反り扇、また、扇の部位を用いた扇骨（おうぎぼね）や地紙（じがみ）といったものもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ogi-mon crests include a five-ribs-fan crest representing the number of ribs, a Gangi-ogi crest showing realistic designs, a Sori-ogi crest with a portion of sori-kaeri (leaning backward) and an Ogi-bone (ogi-ribs) and a Jigami using parts of a fan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ogi-mon crests include a five-ribs-fan crest representing the number of ribs, a Gangi-ogi crest showing realistic designs, a Sori-ogi crest with a portion of sori-kaeri (leaning backward) and an Ogi-bone (ogi-ribs) and a Jigami using parts of a fan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ogi-mon crests include a five-ribs-fan crest representing the number of ribs, a Gangi-ogi crest showing realistic designs, a Sori-ogi crest with a portion of sori-kaeri (leaning backward) and an Ogi-bone (ogi-ribs) and a Jigami using parts of a fan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="143">
<j>佐竹氏の佐竹扇、島原藩の島原扇や浅野氏の浅野扇等があり、高崎藩や三遊亭の紋である「高崎扇（三つ雁木扇）」は小説などにも出てくる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are the Satake-ogi crest for the Satake clan, the Shimabara-ogi crest for the domain of Shimabara and the Asano-ogi crest for the Asano clan, and the &apos;Takasaki-ogi crest (Mitsu-Gangi-ogi)&apos; for the domain of Takasaki and Sanyutei appears in novels.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are the Satake-ogi crest for the Satake clan, the Shimabara-ogi crest for the domain of Shimabara and the Asano-ogi crest for the Asano clan, and the &apos;Takasaki-ogi crest (Mitsu-Gangi-ogi)&apos; for the domain of Takasaki and Sanyutei appears in novels.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are the Satake-ogi crest for the Satake clan, the Shimabara-ogi crest for the domain of Shimabara and the Asano-ogi crest for the Asano clan, and the &apos;Takasaki-ogi crest (Mitsu-Gangi-ogi)&apos; for the domain of Takasaki and Sanyutei appears in novels.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="144">
<j>檜扇紋では、山崎扇や秋田扇などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for the Hi-ogi-mon crest, there are the Yamazaki-ogi crest and the Akita-ogi crest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for the Hi-ogi-mon crest, there are the Yamazaki-ogi crest and the Akita-ogi crest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for the Hi-ogi-mon crest, there are the Yamazaki-ogi crest and the Akita-ogi crest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>調度品</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furnishing goods</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furnished goods</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furnished goods</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="145">
<j>文箱や屏風の意匠としても用いられ、「扇面源氏蒔絵文庫」には文庫の蓋表から側面にかけて、『源氏物語』の一場面が描かれた扇を二面描いているほか、俵屋宗達の「扇面散屏風」も作成されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Crests are used for a design of letter boxes and folding screens, and there is a picture of two fans with a painting of a scene from the Tale of Genji in the area from the front cover of Senmen Genji Makie Bunko and its side as well as an art of Senmen-chirashi byobu folding screen produced by Sotatsu TAWARAYA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Crests are used for a design of letter boxes and folding screens, and there is a picture of two fans with a painting of a scene from the Tale of Genji in the area from the front cover of Senmen Genji Makie Bunko and its side as well as an artistic Senmen-chirashi byobu folding screen produced by Sotatsu TAWARAYA.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Crests are used for a design of letter boxes and folding screens, and there is a picture of two fans with a painting of a scene from &quot;the Tale of Genji&quot; in the area from the front cover of &apos;Senmen Genji Makie Bunko&apos; and its side as well as an artistic &apos;Senmen-chirashi byobu&apos; folding screen produced by Sotatsu TAWARAYA.</e>
<cmt>原文の『』に合わせ&quot;を補足原文の「」に合わせ&apos;を補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Suguri F(id:11127), Ypacaraí(id:11031), Nnh(id:474), MIsogi(id:20599), Kstigarbha(id:13376), Tgmsito(id:15714), おすぽん(id:16560), Sina(id:10021), Ftaka(id:141046), Charon(id:9162), Halfd(id:145364), Mishika(id:276), ムカイ(id:72972), Toto-tarou(id:16648), Fxcxt(id:21803), Tomomarusan(id:17060), NoriBeat(id:2074), Blad(id:104439), 日本一弱い男(id:92046), Bit(id:2197), 竹麦魚(id:11012), Aska27(id:9690), Nopira(id:29335), 白糸(id:47025), Kzhr(id:131), Toki-ho(id:10691), Sin-man(id:18399), GENMEI(id:31879), 拳王(id:22115), Zzzwik(id:144215), Ro-(id:36890), Soramine(id:15940), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), Crystaltear(id:72425), Chikumaya(id:26499), U.S.S.Momotaro(id:646), けんち(id:5147), Corwin(id:973), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>