<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>床の間</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokonoma (alcove in a traditional Japanese room where art or flowers are displayed)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokonoma (alcove in a traditional Japanese room where art or flowers are displayed)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokonoma (alcove in a traditional Japanese room where art or flowers are displayed)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>床の間（とこのま）とは、日本の住宅の畳の部屋に見られる座敷飾りの一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokonoma is a kind of Zashikikazari (a set of decorative features), which is seen in the tatami room of the Japanese house.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A tokonoma is a kind of Zashikikazari (a set of decorative features), seen in a tatami room of a Japanese house.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A tokonoma is a kind of Zashikikazari (a set of decorative features), seen in a tatami room of a Japanese house.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>ハレとケの空間である客間の一角に造られ、床柱、床框などで構成されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokonoma is installed at a corner in a guest room, i.e., a space of Hare (noticeably cheerful and formal situations or such places) and Ke (informal and daily situations), and it is composed of tokobashira (the pillar closest to the corner of the tea ceremony room and the second of two pillars dictate the width of the alcove), tokogamachi (an ornamental wooden bar in the front part of tokonoma), and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokonoma is installed at a corner in a guest room, i.e., a space of Hare (noticeably cheerful and formal situations or such places) and Ke (informal and daily situations), and it is composed of tokobashira (the pillar closest to the corner of the tea ceremony room and the second of two pillars dictate the width of the alcove), tokogamachi (an ornamental wooden bar in the front part of tokonoma), and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokonoma is installed at a corner in a guest room, i.e., a space of Hare (noticeably cheerful and formal situations or such places) and Ke (informal and daily situations), and it is composed of tokobashira (the pillar closest to the corner of the tea ceremony room and the second of two pillars dictate the width of the alcove), tokogamachi (an ornamental wooden bar in the front part of tokonoma), and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>掛け軸や活けた花を飾る場所である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is the spot to decorate kakejiku (hanging scroll) or ikebana (flower arrangement).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is the spot to decorate kakejiku (hanging scroll) or ikebana (flower arrangement).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is the spot to decorate kakejiku (hanging scroll) or ikebana (flower arrangement).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>中世の押し板が起源であり、典型的には近世初期の書院造、数寄屋風書院において完成した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The origin of tokonoma is oshiita (a zashiki kazari of a thick wooden board settled at the bottom of the wall in the Medieval Period) in the Medieval period, and tokonoma has been accomplished in Shoin-zukuri style (a traditional Japanese style of residential architecture that includes a tokonoma), and in Shoin-zukuri in the style of sukiya (traditional style of Japanese residential architecture building in the style of a tea-ceremony house), in the early modern period, in a quintessential way.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The origin of tokonoma is oshiita (a zashiki kazari of a thick wooden board settled at the bottom of the wall in the Medieval Period) in the Medieval period, and the tokonoma had been accomplished in the Shoin-zukuri style (a traditional Japanese style of residential architecture that includes a tokonoma), and in Shoin-zukuri in the style of sukiya (traditional style of Japanese residential architecture building in the style of a tea-ceremony house), in the early modern period, in a quintessential way.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The origin of tokonoma is oshiita (a zashiki kazari of a thick wooden board settled at the bottom of the wall in the Medieval Period) in the Medieval period, and the tokonoma had been accomplished in the Shoin-zukuri Sukiya (a house built in the style of a tea-ceremony hut), and in Shoin-zukuri in the style of sukiya (traditional style of Japanese residential architecture building in the style of a tea-ceremony house), in the early modern period, in a quintessential way.</e>
<cmt>数奇屋の定訳</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>書院造においては、上座に座る人物の格式を示すものであったが、その後の和風住宅では、客人をもてなすために季節に合わせた掛け軸や花を飾り、住まい手の心配りを示す存在であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Shoin-zukuri style, tokonoma represented the social status of the person seated at Kamiza (seat of honour), but afterwards, in the Japanese-style house, it has represented the consideration and attention of the resident, who decorates seasonable kakejiku or flowers at tokonoma.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Shoin-zukuri style, the tokonoma represented the social status of the person seated at Kamiza (seat of honour), but afterwards, in the Japanese-style house, it has represented the consideration and attention of the resident, who decorates the tokonoma with seasonable kakejiku or flowers.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Shoin-zukuri style, the tokonoma represented the social status of the person seated at Kamiza (seat of honour), but afterwards, in the Japanese-style house, it has represented the consideration and attention of the resident, who decorates the tokonoma with seasonable kakejiku or flowers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>（もっぱら家族が使う茶の間などでは床の間を造る必要はない）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(There is no need to install tokonoma in a living room that is usually used by the family members.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(There is no need to install tokonoma in a living room that is usually used by the family members.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(There is no need to install tokonoma in a living room that is usually used by the family members.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>床の間のある部屋においては、床の間側を上座とし、その部屋の中心となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the room having tokonoma, the side close to tokonoma is regarded as Kamiza, and it is regarded as the center of the room.</e>
<cmt>部屋の中心とされるのが「床の間」か「上座」か不明でした（従って、itを主語として置いています。）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In a room having a tokonoma, the side close to tokonoma is regarded as Kamiza, and it is regarded as the center of the room.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In a room having a tokonoma, the side close to tokonoma is regarded as Kamiza, and it is regarded as the center of the room.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>（室内空間に方向性を与えるという点では、洋間のマントルピースに相当するともいえる）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(In the sense that tokonoma gives the directionality to the indoor space, it can be said that tokonoma is equivalent to the mantelpiece in the Western-style room.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(In the sense that the tokonoma gives direction to the indoor space, the tokonoma can be said to be equivalent to the mantelpiece of a Western-style room.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(In the sense that the tokonoma gives direction to the indoor space, the tokonoma can be said to be equivalent to the mantelpiece of a Western-style room.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>江戸時代には、庶民が床の間を造るのは贅沢だとして規制されていたが、明治時代以降になると客間に床の間を造るのが一般的になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Edo period, having tokonoma was restricted because tokonoma was regarded to be too luxury for ordinary people, but after the Meiji period, installing tokonoma in a guest room became general.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Edo period, having a tokonoma was restricted because tokonoma was regarded as too luxurious for ordinary people, but after the Meiji period, installing tokonoma in a guest room became common.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Edo period, having a tokonoma was restricted because tokonoma was regarded as too luxurious for ordinary people, but after the Meiji period, installing tokonoma in a guest room became common.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>現在では掛け軸をかける習慣が衰え、畳の部屋でも床の間を省略することも多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nowadays, the custom to decorate kakejiku has been faded, and even in a tatami room, tokonoma is often excluded.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nowadays, the custom to decorate kakejiku has faded, and even in a tatami room, tokonoma is often excluded.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nowadays, the custom to decorate kakejiku has faded, and even in a tatami room, tokonoma is often excluded.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>既に床の間がある部屋も、最近は床の間を潰してクローゼットにすることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even in a room where there is tokonoma already, in these days, tokonoma is often taken down and remodeled into the closet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even today in a room where there is already tokonoma, it is often remodeled into a closet.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, even in a room where there is already tokonoma, it is often remodeled into a closet.</e>
<cmt>Even が文頭にあると意味が違うと考え、変更しました。ご確認願います。NR: I agree that the position of &quot;even&quot; in the revised sentence makes more sense.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>和風旅館では床の間がテレビやセーフティボックス（要は金庫）を置くスペースになり下がっていることもよく見受けられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Japanese-style inn, it is often seen that tokonoma falls to the level of a space to set a TV or a safety box (i.e., cashbox).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japanese-style inns, it is often seen that tokonoma falls to the level of a space to set a TV or a safety box (i.e., cashbox).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japanese-style inns, it is often seen that tokonoma falls to the level of a space to set a TV or a safety box (i.e., cashbox).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>床の間の構成</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Composition of tokonoma</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Composition of tokonoma</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Composition of tokonoma</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>床の構成</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Composition of toko (alcove)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Composition of toko (alcove)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Composition of toko (alcove)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="13">
<j>床柱</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokobashira</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokobashira</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokobashira</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>- 床の間で最も目立つ部材である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">-Tokobashira is the most appealing material in tokonoma.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">-Tokobashira is the most appealing material in tokonoma.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">-Tokobashira is the most appealing material in tokonoma.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>書院造では角柱が基本であるが、私邸などでは数寄屋造りの影響から、節つきの丸木等、珍しい銘木を用いることも多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Shoin-zukuri style, tokobashira is basically kakubashira (a corner post or pillar that is square or rectangular), but at a private residence, for example, because of the influence of Sukiya-zukuri style, an uncommon precious wood, such as a log with knots, is often used.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Shoin-zukuri style, tokobashira is basically kakubashira (a corner post or pillar that is square or rectangular), but at a private residence, for example, because of the influence of Sukiya-zukuri style, an uncommon precious wood, such as a log with knots, is often used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Shoin-zukuri style, tokobashira is basically kakubashira (a corner post or pillar that is square or rectangular), but at a private residence, for example, because of the influence of Sukiya-zukuri style, an uncommon precious wood, such as a log with knots, is often used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="16">
<j>落し掛け</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Otoshikake (a bar placed across the upper part of tokonoma)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Otoshikake (a bar placed across the upper part of the tokonoma)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Otoshikake (a bar placed across the upper part of the tokonoma)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>-　床の間上部の横材で、小壁を受ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">-It is a cross piece located at the upper part of tokonoma, and it holds the wall between the kamoi and the ceiling.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">-It is a cross piece located at the upper part of the tokonoma, and it holds the wall between the kamoi and the ceiling.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">- It is a cross piece located at the upper part of the tokonoma, and it holds the wall between the kamoi (door header) and the ceiling.</e>
<cmt>kamoi の説明追記　([英辞郎 on the WEB]より）</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="18">
<j>床框（かまち）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokogamachi (kamachi: an ornamental wooden bar in the front part of tokonoma)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokogamachi (kamachi: an ornamental wooden bar in the front part of tokonoma)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokogamachi (kamachi: an ornamental wooden bar in the front part of tokonoma)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>-　畳の面より一段上げるようにして、漆塗りの横材（床框）と畳を置く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">- a lacquered cross piece (tokogamachi) and a tatami mat put on the raised place above the tatami floor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">- a lacquered cross piece (tokogamachi) and a tatami mat on the raised place above the tatami floor.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">- a lacquered cross piece (tokogamachi) and a tatami mat on the raised place above the tatami floor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="20">
<j>壁</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wall</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wall</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wall</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>-　一般的な床の間では左官仕上げの壁とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">- In the general tokonoma, the wall is finished by a plasterer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">- In general the tokonoma wall is finished by a plasterer.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">- In general the tokonoma wall is finished by a plasterer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="22">
<j>近世初期の園城寺光浄院客殿、二条城二の丸書院、本願寺書院などは床框を用いず、一枚板（押板）を置く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In buildings in the early modern period, such as Reception Hall of Kojoin of Onjo-ji Temple, Ninomaru Shoin of Nijo Castle, Shoin of Hongan-ji Temple, tokogamachi is not used, but a solid timber (oshi-ita (a shallow decorative alcove)) is placed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In buildings during the early modern period, such as the Reception Hall of Kojoin of Onjo-ji Temple, Ninomaru Shoin of Nijo Castle, Shoin of Hongan-ji Temple, tokogamachi is not used, but a solid timber (oshi-ita or a shallow decorative alcove) is placed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In buildings during the early modern period, such as the Reception Hall of Kojoin of Onjo-ji Temple, Ninomaru Shoin of Nijo-jo Castle, Shoin of Hongan-ji Temple, tokogamachi is not used, but a solid timber (oshi-ita or a shallow decorative alcove) is placed.</e>
<cmt>Nijo→Nijo-jo書院の定訳</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>また、これらは張付け壁に障壁画を描いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, in these buildings, pictures on partitions are painted on the pasted walls.</e>
<cmt>「これら＝上段に挙げられた建物」として訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, in these buildings, pictures on partitions are painted on the plastered walls.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, in these buildings, pictures on partitions are painted on the plastered walls.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>本床の間</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hon-tokonoma (a full tokonoma)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hon-tokonoma (a full tokonoma)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hon-tokonoma (a full tokonoma)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="24">
<j>床の間は、床を単独で配置するだけではなく、書院造の伝統を受け継ぎ廊下（採光）側に付書院、反対側に脇棚を備える事が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In tokonoma, toko is not only placed alone, but also frequently accompanied by tsukeshoin (a built-in table) at the corridor (daylighting) side, and by wakidana (shelves next to tokonoma) at the opposite side, in accordance with the tradition of Shoin-zukuri style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In tokonoma, toko is not only placed alone, but also frequently accompanied by tsukeshoin (a built-in table) at the corridor (daylighting) side, and by wakidana (shelves next to tokonoma) at the opposite side, in accordance with the tradition of Shoin-zukuri style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In tokonoma, toko is not only placed alone, but also frequently accompanied by tsukeshoin (a built-in table) at the corridor (daylighting) side, and by wakidana (shelves next to tokonoma) at the opposite side, in accordance with the tradition of Shoin-zukuri style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>これを本床の間という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is called hon-tokonoma.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is called hon-tokonoma.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is called hon-tokonoma.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="26">
<j>付書院　単に「書院」とも言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsukeshoin (a built-in table); this is also simply called &apos;shoin.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsukeshoin (a built-in table); this is also simply called &apos;shoin.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsukeshoin (a built-in table); this is also simply called &apos;shoin.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>出窓状に奥行きを持たせ、その奥に書院欄間、障子が配される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Depth is created in the style of bay window, and shoin ranma and shoji are placed in the back.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Depth is created by the style of bay window, and shoin ranma and shoji are placed in the back.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Depth is created by the style of bay window, and shoin ranma (transom) and shoji (a paper sliding door) are placed in the back.</e>
<cmt>欄間、障子の説明補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="28">
<j>床脇　床を挟んで付書院と反対側に配される空間。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokowaki; a space created at the opposite side of tsukishoin across toko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokowaki; a space created at the opposite side of tsukishoin across toko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokowaki: a space created at the opposite side of tsukeshoin across toko.</e>
<cmt>;→:tsukishoin→tsukeshoin</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>床脇棚と袋戸棚（襖付の棚）が設えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokowakidana (decorative shelve arranged in the recess next to the decorative alcove) and fukurotodana (a small cupboard on the wall of a tokonoma) (shelve with fusuma) are placed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokowakidana (decorative shelve arranged in the recess next to the decorative alcove) and fukurotodana (a small cupboard on the wall of a tokonoma) (shelve with fusuma) are placed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokowakidana (decorative shelve arranged in the recess next to the decorative alcove) and fukurotodana (a small cupboard on the wall of a tokonoma) (shelve with fusuma, a sliding door) are placed.</e>
<cmt>and の後のスペース短縮襖の説明補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>床脇棚は、二段の棚を組合わせた「違い棚」代表的だが、施主の好みにより「釣り棚」等他の様式が採られることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The representative tokowakidana is &apos;chigai-dana&apos; (shelves built into the wall), which is made by combining double-stage shelves, but depending on the owner&apos;s taste, other styles including &apos;tsuridana&apos; (a three small shelves hung from a large shelf) are also employed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The representative tokowakidana is &apos;chigai-dana&apos; (shelves built into the wall), which is made by combining double-stage shelves, but depending on the owner&apos;s taste, other styles including &apos;tsuridana&apos; (a three small shelves hung from a large shelf) are also employed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The representative tokowakidana is &apos;chigai-dana&apos; (shelves built into the wall), which is made by combining double-stage shelves, but depending on the owner&apos;s taste, other styles including &apos;tsuridana&apos; (a three small shelves hung from a large shelf) are also employed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 文姫(id:66661), ととりん(id:31982), Nighthawks(id:36125), PixelBot(id:166734), ＲＪＡＮＫＡ(id:118019), Yas(id:739), Yiuchan(id:28580), けんち(id:5147), 伊集院聖(id:53199), Zwobot(id:23873), Chuta(id:10457), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>