<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>くちこ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kuchiko</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kuchiko</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kuchiko (the ovaries of sea cucumbers)</e>
<cmt>説明を加えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>くちこ（海鼠子、口子）は、ナマコの卵巣である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kuchiko (written in Japanese as 海鼠子, 口子) is the ovary of a sea cucumber.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kuchiko are the ovaries of sea cucumbers.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity - I don&apos;t think the kanji are necessary for English speakers</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kuchiko are the ovaries of sea cucumbers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>このことも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called &quot;konoko&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are also called &quot;konoko&quot;.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are also called &quot;konoko&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>ナマコは厳冬の1月から3月になると産卵期を迎えて発達肥大した卵巣を持つようになり、それが口先にあることから「くちこ」と呼ばれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the harsh winter between January and March, the sea cucumbers enter the breeding season and their ovaries grow enlarged; since the ovary is found at the tip of the mouth (&quot;kuchi&quot; in Japanese) of a sea cucumber, it is called &quot;kuchiko&quot; (literally, &quot;child in the mouth&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the harsh winter between January and March, the sea cucumbers enter the breeding season and their ovaries grow enlarged; the name &quot;kuchiko&quot; (literally, &quot;mouth child&quot;), comes from the fact that the ovary is found near the mouth.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the harsh winter between January and March, the sea cucumbers enter the breeding season and their ovaries grow enlarged; the name &apos;kuchiko&apos; (literally, &apos;mouth child&apos;), comes from the fact that the ovary is found near the mouth.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>主な産地は能登半島周辺。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kuchiko is mainly produced in and around the Noto Peninsular.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kuchiko is mainly produced in and around the Noto Peninsular.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kuchiko is mainly produced in and around the Noto Peninsular.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>一般的に三角形に平たく干したものが能登の高級珍味として親しまれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Generally the kuchiko is dried in a flat triangle form and known as Noto&apos;s high-quality food with a delicate flavor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Generally the kuchiko is dried in a flat triangle form and is known as &apos;Noto&apos;s premium delicacy&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Generally the kuchiko is dried in a flat triangle form and is known as Noto&apos;s premium delicacy.</e>
<cmt>原文には「」がありませんので&apos;を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>干した姿が、三味線のばちに似ていることから、ばちことも呼ばれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since it resembles the plectrum of shamisen (a three-stringed Japanese banjo) when dried, it is also called &quot;bachiko&quot; (literally, &quot;plectrum child&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since it resembles the plectrum of a shamisen (a three-stringed Japanese banjo) when dried, it is also called &quot;bachiko&quot; (literally, &quot;plectrum child&quot;).</e>
<cmt>Article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since it resembles the plectrum of a shamisen (a three-stringed Japanese banjo) when dried, it is also called &apos;bachiko&apos; (literally, &apos;plectrum child&apos;).</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>何枚も重ねて干し上げるが、一枚作るのに十数キロのナマコが必要であるため、大変高価なものとなる（2008年現在、一枚数千円）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ovaries are dried in layers, and over a dozen ovaries are required to produce a single sheet of kuchiko; thus the food is very expensive (several thousand yen per sheet, as of 2008).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ovaries are dried in layers, and over a dozen kilograms of sea cucmbers are required to produce a single sheet;, making it very expensive (several thousand yen per sheet, as of 2008).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ovaries are dried in layers, and over a dozen kilograms of sea cucmbers are required to produce a single sheet, making it very expensive (several thousand yen per sheet, as of 2008).</e>
<cmt>;, →,</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>そのまま食べるか、炙ってから、お吸い物・熱燗に入れても良い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kuchiko can be eaten by itself, or also by being placed in soup or warmed sake after being roasted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kuchiko can be eaten by itself, or toasted and placed in soup or warmed sake.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kuchiko can be eaten by itself, or toasted and placed in soup or warmed sake.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="9">
<j>生のものは、塩漬けされた塩辛として出回ることが多いが、取り出して瓶などに詰めただけの「生」のものもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Usually, raw kuchiko is sold well as salted kuchiko that have been preserved in salt, but sometimes, the ovaries taken out of sea urchins are simply bottled and sold &quot;raw&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Usually, raw kuchiko is pickled and sold as salted kuchiko, but sometimes, the ovaries are simply removed from the sea cucumbers, bottled and sold &quot;raw&quot;.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Usually, raw kuchiko is pickled and sold as salted kuchiko, but sometimes, the ovaries are simply removed from the sea cucumbers, bottled and sold &apos;raw&apos;.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="10">
<j>酒の肴として好適である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is ideal as a side dish for sake.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is ideal as a side dish for sake.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is ideal as a side dish for sake.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 あにり(id:199303), Tom-spring(id:42457), Oneuchi(id:70845), 円口類(id:186088), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>