<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>三曲合奏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Sankyoku Gassou&quot; (The Ensemble Made Up Of &quot;Sankyoku&quot; [Instrumental Trio])</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Sankyoku Gassou&quot; (The Ensemble Made Up of &quot;Sankyoku&quot; [Instrumental Trio])</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sankyoku Gasso</e>
<cmt>タイトルなので説明括弧を削除しました。Sankyoku Gasso に訂正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>三曲合奏とは、三曲の楽器である地歌三味線（三弦）、箏、胡弓の三種の楽器による合奏編成、及びそれにより演奏される音楽をいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Sankyoku gassou&quot; means the ensemble made up of &quot;sankyoku&quot; (instrumental trio) - originally, the trio was &quot;shamisen&quot; (also called &quot;sangen,&quot; the three-stringed Japanese banjo) for accompanying &quot;Jiuta&quot; (songs of the country), &quot;koto&quot; (the long Japanese zither with thirteen strings) and &quot;kokyu&quot; (the Chinese fiddle) - and also means the ensemble music itself.</e>
<cmt>・訳文2行目の&quot;originally&quot;は、セル6との関係で補ったものです。　　　　　　　　　　　　 ・「地歌」の訳については以下のホームページを参照しました。[http://jtrad.columbia.jp/eng/u_jiuta.html]　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Sankyoku gassou&quot; means the ensemble made up of &quot;sankyoku (instrumental trio)&quot;; originally, the trio was &quot;shamisen&quot; (also called &quot;sangen,&quot; the three-string Japanese banjo) for accompanying &quot;Jiuta&quot; (songs of the country), &quot;koto&quot; (the long Japanese zither with thirteen strings) and &quot;kokyu&quot; (the Chinese fiddle), but it also means the ensemble music itself.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Sankyoku gasso&quot; means the ensemble made up of &quot;sankyoku&quot; (instrumental trio); originally, the trio was &quot;shamisen&quot; (also called &quot;sangen,&quot; the three-string Japanese banjo) for accompanying &quot;Jiuta&quot; (songs of the country), &quot;koto&quot; (the long Japanese zither with thirteen strings) and &quot;kokyu&quot; (the Chinese fiddle), but it also means the ensemble music itself.</e>
<cmt>Sankyoku gasso に訂正しました。原文にはありませんが、ここでは読み易くする為用語に&quot; &quot;をつけた表記になっているのを採用します。括弧位置を訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>古くは「三曲合わせ」などとも呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the past, sankyoku gassou was also called &quot;sankyoku awase.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the past, sankyoku gassou was also called &quot;sankyoku awase.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the past, sankyoku gassou was also called &apos;sankyoku awase.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>後に尺八が参入し、三味線、箏、尺八による編成が多くなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, &quot;shakuhachi&quot; (the bamboo flute) participated in the ensemble, and thereafter the instrumental trio was mostly shamisen, koto and shakuhachi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, &quot;shakuhachi&quot; (the bamboo flute) participated in the ensemble, and thereafter the instrumental trio was mostly shamisen, koto and shakuhachi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, &quot;shakuhachi&quot; (the bamboo flute) participated in the ensemble, and thereafter the instrumental trio was mostly shamisen, koto and shakuhachi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>概説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>今日的な「三曲」とは「三つの曲」ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Sankyoku&quot; today does not mean &quot;three tunes&quot;; in literal Japanese, &quot;san&quot; means &quot;three&quot; and &quot;kyoku&quot; means &quot;tune.&quot;</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処　・訳者がセミコロンの後に「もっとも字面からいえば&quot;san&quot;は『三つ』、&quot;kyoku&quot;は『曲』を意味するのだが。」と補っているのには理由があります。第一に、「三曲」は「三つの曲」でない、とわざわざ説明していることの意味を海外の人が読んでわかるようにすること、第二に、セル46の一行目における「三という数字にこだわらず」の部分とつなげるため、です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term &quot;Sankyoku&quot; today doesn&apos;t mean &quot;three tunes&quot;; in literal Japanese, &quot;san&quot; means &quot;three&quot; and &quot;kyoku&quot; means &quot;tune.&quot;</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term &apos;Sankyoku&apos; today doesn&apos;t mean &apos;three tunes;&apos; in literal Japanese, &quot;san&quot; means &quot;three&quot; and &quot;kyoku&quot; means &quot;tune.&quot;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>これはおそらく当道座の音楽家たちの本来の専門音楽である「平曲」（平家琵琶の音楽）に対しての名称である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This sankyoku must have been the name used in contrast with &quot;heikyoku&quot; (the music of &quot;heike biwa&quot; [the Japanese lute for playing the Tale of Heike]), in which the musicians of Todo-za (the traditional guild for the blind) originally engaged as a profession.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This sankyoku must have been the name used in contrast with &quot;heikyoku&quot; (the music of &quot;heike biwa&quot; [the Japanese lute for playing the Tale of Heike]), in which the musicians of Todo-za (the traditional guild for the blind) originally engaged as a profession.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This sankyoku must have been the name used in contrast with ￥&apos;heikyoku&apos; (the music of &quot;heike biwa&quot; (the Japanese lute for playing the Tale of Heike)), in which the musicians of Todo-za (the traditional guild for the blind) originally engaged as a profession.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。[を（に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>つまり、同じく彼らが専門とする新しい三種の楽器（三味線（主として地歌の三味線）、箏、胡弓）」とその音楽である地歌、箏曲、胡弓楽を区別するために使われ始めたのではないかと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In other words, they must have begun to use the name sankyoku to distinguish heikyoku from their new, professionally-engaged three instruments (shamisen [mainly for Jiuta], koto and kokyu) &amp; their tunes (Jiuta, &quot;Sokyoku&quot; [the koto music] and &quot;Kokyu-gaku&quot; [the kokyu music]).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In other words, they must have begun using the name sankyoku to distinguish heikyoku from their new, professionally engaged three instruments (shamisen [mainly for Jiuta], koto and kokyu) and their tunes (Jiuta, &quot;Sokyoku&quot; [koto music] and &quot;Kokyu-gaku&quot; [kokyu music]).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In other words, they must have begun using the name sankyoku to distinguish heikyoku from their new, professionally engaged three instruments (shamisen (mainly for Jiuta), koto and kokyu) and their tunes (Jiuta, Sokyoku (koto music) and Kokyu-gaku (kokyu music)).</e>
<cmt>[を（に訂正しました。原文に合せて&quot; &quot;削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>しかし厳密なものではなく、18世紀後半には箏、胡弓に尺八が加わった合奏を「三曲」と呼んだ記録もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But the usage of the name was not so strict, and the ensemble of koto, kokyu and shakuhachi was also called &quot;sankyoku&quot; in a record of the later 18th century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the usage of the name wasn&apos;t strict, and the ensemble of koto, kokyu and shakuhachi was also called &quot;sankyoku&quot; in a record from the late eighteenth century.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the usage of the name wasn&apos;t strict, and the ensemble of koto, kokyu and shakuhachi was also called &apos;sankyoku&apos; in a record from the late 18th century.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。数字に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>実際、江戸時代末期からそこに尺八が参入したので、現在三曲と呼ぶ場合は地歌・箏曲・胡弓楽・尺八楽を総合する名称と言え、邦楽分類上不可分な一ジャンルの呼称となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In fact, shakuhachi participated in the ensemble from the end of the Edo period, so sankyoku today can be said the general term for Jiuta, Sokyoku, Kokyu-gaku and &quot;Shakuhachi-gaku&quot; (the shakuhachi music), which becomes the name of an inseparable genre in Japanese music.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In fact, shakuhachi participated in the ensemble from the end of the Edo period, so sankyoku today can be thought of as the general term for Jiuta, Sokyoku, Kokyu-gaku and &quot;Shakuhachi-gaku (shakuhachi music),&quot; which becomes the name of an inseparable genre in Japanese music.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact, shakuhachi participated in the ensemble from the end of the Edo period, so sankyoku today can be thought of as the general term for Jiuta, Sokyoku, Kokyu-gaku and Shakuhachi-gaku (shakuhachi music), which becomes the name of an inseparable genre in Japanese music.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>これらの四種の音楽のうちで、三種の楽器編成で合奏されるのが現在言われる「三曲合奏」であるが、それと「三曲」の概念との前後関係は不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">What we call &quot;sankyoku gassou&quot; today is the ensemble made up of the three kinds of instruments out of above-mentioned four, but it is unclear which concept comes first, &quot;sankyoku gassou&quot; or &quot;sankyoku.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">What we call sankyoku gassou today is the ensemble made up of the three kinds of instruments out of the above-mentioned four, but it isn&apos;t clear which concept came first, sankyoku gassou or sankyoku.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">What we call sankyoku gassou today is the ensemble made up of the three kinds of instruments out of the above-mentioned four, but it isn&apos;t clear which concept came first, &apos;sankyoku gasso&apos; or &apos;sankyoku.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文に合せて&apos; &apos;補足しました。sankyoku gassoに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>言えることは「三曲合奏」とは三種の楽器を合奏させる意味であって、「三」種の楽器を合わせて奏する「曲」という意味ではないということである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At least, it can be said that the meaning of &quot;sankyoku gassou&quot; is not &quot;tunes&quot; played with &quot;three&quot; kinds of instruments but the ensemble with three kinds of instruments.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At least, it can be said that the meaning of &quot;sankyoku gassou&quot; is not &quot;tunes&quot; played with &quot;three&quot; kinds of instruments but the ensemble with three kinds of instruments.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At least, it can be said that the meaning of &apos;sankyoku gasso&apos; is not &apos;tunes&apos; played with &apos;three&apos; kinds of instruments but the ensemble with three kinds of instruments.</e>
<cmt>原文に合せて&apos; &apos;補足しました。sankyoku gassoに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>ただし三曲においてすべての楽曲が三曲合奏されるわけではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In sankyoku, however, not every tune is performed in the style of sankyoku gassou.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In sankyoku, however, not every tune is performed in the style of sankyoku gassou.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In sankyoku, however, not every tune is performed in the style of sankyoku gasso.</e>
<cmt>sankyoku gassoに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>大学のサークルで、邦楽部が存在する場合にはこの三曲を構成する楽器を行っている場合が殆どである（ただし、主に伝統的な曲を行っているサークルと、主に現代的な曲を行っているサークルとがある)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If there is a Japanese music club in a college, the club activities are the performances of the sankyoku instruments in most cases; there are two types of clubs, and one is mainly about the traditional tunes while another is about the contemporary ones.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If there is a Japanese music club at a college, in most cases the club activities are the performances of the sankyoku instruments; there are two types of clubs, and one is mainly about the traditional tunes while another is about the contemporary ones.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If there is a Japanese music club at a college, in most cases the club activities are the performances of the sankyoku instruments; there are two types of clubs, and one is mainly about the traditional tunes while another is about the contemporary ones.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>このほか「三曲萬歳」では三味線、胡弓、鼓をいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides, in &quot;sankyoku manzai&quot; (a comic dialogue accompanied by sankyoku), the instruments used are shamisen, kokyu and &quot;tsuzumi&quot; (hand drum).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides, in &quot;sankyoku manzai&quot; (a comic dialogue accompanied by sankyoku), the instruments used are shamisen, kokyu and &quot;tsuzumi&quot; (hand drum).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides, in &apos;sankyoku manzai&apos; (a comic dialogue accompanied by sankyoku), the instruments used are shamisen, kokyu and tsuzumi (hand drum).</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。&quot; &quot;削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="15">
<j>三曲合奏の範囲</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Range of sankyoku gassou</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The range of sankyoku gassou</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The range of sankyoku gasso</e>
<cmt>sankyoku gassoに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>三曲合奏が行なわれる曲は「三曲」の中でも地歌曲（三味線組歌を除く）が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Of all tunes of &quot;sankyoku,&quot; those performed in the style of sankyoku gassou are mostly the music of Jiuta (except for &quot;Kumiuta&quot; [assembled songs] accompanied by the shamisen).</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　・「組歌」の訳については下記ホームページを参照しました。[http://www.textfiles.com/apple/DOCUMENTATION/danmono](＊）　</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Of all the tunes of sankyoku, those performed in the style of sankyoku gassou are mostly the music of Jiuta (except for &quot;Kumiuta&quot; [assembled songs] accompanied by the shamisen).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Of all the tunes of &apos;sankyoku,&apos; those performed in the style of sankyoku gasso are mostly the music of Jiuta (except for Kumiuta (assembled songs) accompanied by the shamisen).</e>
<cmt>sankyoku gassoに訂正しました。原文に合せて&apos; &apos;補足しました。&quot; &quot;削除しました。[]を（）に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>他に箏曲（段もの、及び山田流箏曲の歌もの、段もの）、まれに胡弓本曲（「岡康砧」など）も三曲合奏される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, the koto music (e.g. &quot;Danmono&quot; [leveled pieces], Yamada school&apos;s &quot;Utamono&quot; [accompanied singing in which the singing is emphasized over the instrumental part], and Yamada school&apos;s Danmono) and - in a rare case - &quot;kokyu honkyoku&quot; (kokyu pieces composed in the early days), such as &quot;Okayasu-ginuta&quot; (a piece for koto composed by Kosaburo OKAYASU, but originally a kokyu piece), are also performed in sankyoku gassou.</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処 ・「本曲」の訳についてセル60を参照しました。　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　・「段もの」の訳は上記（＊）のホームページを、「歌もの」の訳は下記ホームページを参照しました。（原文一行目の「段もの」の重複記載は訳していてやや不自然に思いましたが敢えてそのまま訳しています。）[http//tangorin.com/words/singing%20and%20%20music]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, the koto music (e.g. &quot;Danmono&quot; [leveled pieces], Yamada school&apos;s &quot;Utamono&quot; [accompanied singing in which the singing is emphasized over the instrumental part], and Yamada school&apos;s Danmono) and--in rare cases--&quot;kokyu honkyoku&quot; (kokyu pieces composed in the early days), such as &quot;Okayasu-ginuta&quot; (a piece for koto composed by Kosaburo OKAYASU but originally a kokyu piece), are also performed in sankyoku gassou.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, the koto music (e.g. Danmono (leveled pieces), Yamada school&apos;s Utamono (accompanied singing in which the singing is emphasized over the instrumental part), and Yamada school&apos;s Danmono) and, in rare cases, kokyu honkyoku (kokyu pieces composed in the early days), such as &apos;Okayasu-ginuta&apos; (a piece for koto composed by Kosaburo OKAYASU but originally a kokyu piece), are also performed in sankyoku gasso.</e>
<cmt>原文に合せて&apos; &apos;補足しました。&quot; &quot;削除しました。[]を（）に訂正しました。ハイフン削除し、コンマを補足しました。sankyoku gassoに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>当然「三曲」の範囲内で行なわれるので、地歌以外の三味線音楽では、三曲合奏はまずほとんど行なわない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Of course, sankyoku gassou is performed within &quot;sankyoku,&quot; and so, when shamisen is performed for the music other than Jiuta, the music is rarely performed in sankyoku gassou.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Of course, sankyoku gassou is performed within sankyoku; therefore, when shamisen is performed for the music other than Jiuta, the music is rarely performed in sankyoku gassou.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Of course, sankyoku gasso is performed within &apos;sankyoku;&apos; therefore, when shamisen is performed for the music other than Jiuta, the music is rarely performed in sankyoku gasso.</e>
<cmt>sankyoku gassoに訂正しました。原文に合せて&apos; &apos;補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>長唄曲に「三曲糸の調」や「三曲松竹梅」があるが、これは三曲を指し、つまり三種の楽器を詠んだもので、三曲合奏の意味ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Nagauta&quot; (ballads sung to shamisen accompaniment), there exist some tunes whose titles include &quot;sankyoku,&quot; such as &quot;Sankyoku Ito no Shirabe&quot; (The Melody of Sankyoku Strings) and &quot;Sankyoku Sho-chiku-bai&quot; (literally, Sankyoku Made Up of Pine, Bamboo and Plum Blossom), to be sure, but the &quot;sankyoku&quot; embedded in their titles indicates not sankyoku gassou, but the very three kinds of instruments themselves.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;Nagauta&quot; (ballads sung to shamisen accompaniment), there are certainly tunes whose titles include &quot;sankyoku,&quot; such as &quot;Sankyoku Ito no Shirabe (The Melody of Sankyoku Strings)&quot; and &quot;Sankyoku Sho-chiku-bai&quot; (literally, Sankyoku Made Up of Pine, Bamboo and Plum Blossom), but the &quot;sankyoku&quot; embedded in their titles indicates not sankyoku gassou but the three kinds of instruments themselves.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Nagauta (ballads sung to shamisen accompaniment), there are certainly tunes whose titles include sankyoku, such as &quot;Sankyoku Ito no Shirabe&quot; (The Melody of Sankyoku Strings) and &quot;Sankyoku Sho-chiku-bai&quot; (literally, Sankyoku Made Up of Pine, Bamboo and Plum Blossom), but the sankyoku embedded in their titles indicates not sankyoku gasso but the three kinds of instruments themselves.</e>
<cmt>原文に合せて&quot; &quot;削除しました。原文に合せて&apos; &apos;削除しました。原文に合せて&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に訂正しました。括弧の位置を訂正しました。sankyoku gassoに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>また三曲合奏が行なわれるわけでもない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And so, sankyoku gassou is not performed about these tunes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequently, sankyoku gassou is not performed in regard to these tunes.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently, sankyoku gasso is not performed in regard to these tunes.</e>
<cmt>sankyoku gassoに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>地歌曲の「三つ恋慕」も同様な趣向の曲であるが、こちらは地歌なので三曲合奏が行なわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Jiuta music &quot;Mitsu-renbo&quot; (a tune expressing love for the instruments themselves, shamisen, koto and kokyu) has the same idea as the above-mentioned Nagauta, however, as this tune is for Jiuta, it is performed in sankyoku gassou.</e>
<cmt>・「三つ恋慕」は「三味線、箏、胡弓そのものについて詠んだ曲」と解説しています。　</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Jiuta music &quot;Mitsu-renbo&quot; (a tune expressing love for the instruments themselves, meaning the shamisen, koto and kokyu) has the same idea as the above-mentioned Nagauta, but since this tune is for Jiuta, it&apos;s performed in sankyoku gassou.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Jiuta music &apos;Mitsu-renbo&apos; (a tune expressing love for the instruments themselves, meaning the shamisen, koto and kokyu) has the same idea as the above-mentioned Nagauta, but since this tune is for Jiuta, it&apos;s performed in sankyoku gasso.</e>
<cmt>原文に合せて&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に訂正しました。sankyoku gassoに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>また三曲に属する箏曲の中でも、筑紫箏、及び八橋流箏曲は三曲合奏以前の音楽を伝えているので、まったく他楽器との合奏を行なわない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And of all pieces of &quot;Sokyoku&quot; (the koto music), both of &quot;Tsukushi-goto&quot; (the refined and elegant Sokyoku composed in the Azuchi-Momoyama period, which became the origin of Sokyoku in the early modern ages) &amp; Yatsuhashi school of Sokyoku perform the music before sankyoku gassou, so they are not be played with other instruments at all.</e>
<cmt>・「筑紫箏」は「近世筝曲の起源として安土桃山時代に創られた高尚で雅な筝曲のこと」と解説しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Of all the pieces of &quot;Sokyoku&quot; (koto music), both of &quot;Tsukushi-goto&quot; (the refined and elegant Sokyoku composed during the Azuchi-Momoyama period, which became the origin of Sokyoku in the early modern age) and the Yatsuhashi school of Sokyoku perform the music before sankyoku gassou, so they aren&apos;t to be played with other instruments.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Of all the pieces of Sokyoku (koto music), both of Tsukushi-goto (the refined and elegant Sokyoku composed during the Azuchi-Momoyama period, which became the origin of Sokyoku in the early modern age) and the Yatsuhashi school of Sokyoku perform the music before sankyoku gasso, so they aren&apos;t to be played with other instruments.</e>
<cmt>原文に合せて&quot; &quot;削除しました。sankyoku gassoに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="23">
<j>地歌曲の場合は、多くは元の三味線パートに後に箏や胡弓のパートが付けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In most Jiuta tunes, the parts of koto &amp; kokyu were added to the original shamisen part afterward.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In most Jiuta tunes, the parts for koto and kokyu were later added to the original shamisen part.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In most Jiuta tunes, the parts for koto and kokyu were later added to the original shamisen part.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>後から付けられるパートは流派によって異なっている場合が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The added parts often differ from school to school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The added parts often differ from school to school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The added parts often differ from school to school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>楽器編成は古くは三弦、箏、胡弓の組み合わせが一般的であったが、箏、胡弓、尺八といった組み合わせの三曲合奏も行なわれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The common instrumental trio was sangen (shamisen), koto and kokyu, but occasionally, it was koto, kokyu and shakuhachi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The common instrumental trio was sangen (shamisen), koto and kokyu, but occasionally it was koto, kokyu and shakuhachi.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The common instrumental trio was sangen (shamisen), koto and kokyu, but occasionally it was koto, kokyu and shakuhachi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>胡弓の代わりに尺八が加わることも江戸時代後半から行なわれていたが、明治初年に虚無僧制度が廃止されて以降、尺八が積極的に三曲合奏に進出し、今日では胡弓よりも尺八が加わる方が圧倒的に多くなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the later Edo period, shakuhachi began to participate in sankyoku gassou instead of kokyu, and from the first year of the Meiji period, when the governmental protection of &quot;komuso&quot; (a mendicant Zen priest of the Fuke sect) was ended, shakuhachi performers actively went into the world of sankyoku gassou, and therefore, shakuhachi overwhelms kokyu in sankyoku gassou today.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later in the Edo period, shakuhachi began to participate in sankyoku gassou instead of kokyu, and from the first year of the Meiji period, when the governmental protection of &quot;komuso&quot; (a mendicant Zen priest of the Fuke sect) was ended, shakuhachi performers actively entered the world of sankyoku gassou, and therefore shakuhachi predominates over kokyu in sankyoku gassou today.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later in the Edo period, shakuhachi began to participate in sankyoku gasso instead of kokyu, and from the first year of the Meiji period, when the governmental protection of &quot;komuso&quot; (a mendicant Zen priest of the Fuke sect) was ended, shakuhachi performers actively entered the world of sankyoku gasso, and therefore shakuhachi predominates over kokyu in sankyoku gasso today.</e>
<cmt>sankyoku gassoに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>ただし胡弓入りの三曲合奏がなくなったわけではなく、現在でも各地で行なわれ、特に名古屋では比較的盛んであるし、また山田流箏曲に藤植流の胡弓が加わり三曲合奏されることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, kokyu&apos;s participation into sankyoku gassou is still seen nationwide, such as the relatively active one in Nagoya, and sometimes, the participation of Fujiue school&apos;s kokyu music into Yamada school&apos;s koto music is seen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, kokyu&apos;s participation in sankyoku gassou is still seen nationwide, such as the relatively active one in Nagoya, and sometimes the participation of the Fujiue school&apos;s kokyu music in the Yamada school&apos;s koto music is seen.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, kokyu&apos;s participation in sankyoku gasso is still seen nationwide, such as the relatively active one in Nagoya, and sometimes the participation of the Fujiue school&apos;s kokyu music in the Yamada school&apos;s koto music is seen.</e>
<cmt>sankyoku gassoに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>歌のある曲の場合は、三味線，箏の奏者が弾きながら唄う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If a tune has its song, the performers of shamisen &amp; koto sing the song while picking their instruments.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If a tune has its song, the performers of shamisen and koto sing the song while plucking their instruments.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If a tune has its song, the performers of shamisen and koto sing the song while plucking their instruments.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="29">
<j>三曲合奏の音楽的特徴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Musical characteristics of sankyoku gassou</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The musical characteristics of sankyoku gassou</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The musical characteristics of sankyoku gasso</e>
<cmt>sankyoku gassoに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>三曲合奏を人体になぞらえて、三味線は骨、箏は肉、胡弓、尺八は皮にたとえられることがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sankyoku gassou is sometimes likened to a human body, such as the bone for shamisen, the flesh for koto, and the skin for kokyu &amp; shakuhachi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sankyoku gassou is sometimes likened to a human body, such as the bone for shamisen, the flesh for koto, and the skin for kokyu &amp; shakuhachi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sankyoku gasso is sometimes likened to a human body, such as the bone for shamisen, the flesh for koto, and the skin for kokyu and shakuhachi.</e>
<cmt>sankyoku gassoに訂正しました。&amp;をandに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>通常、胡弓と尺八は持続音楽器として同じ働きをするので互換性が強い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Generally, kokyu and shakuhachi are interchangeable with each other, because both of them similarly serve as an instrument to make continuous sounds.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Generally, kokyu and shakuhachi are interchangeable with each other, because both of them similarly serve as instruments to make continuous sounds.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Generally, kokyu and shakuhachi are interchangeable with each other, because both of them similarly serve as instruments to make continuous sounds.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>それゆえ、三味線、箏、胡弓か、三味線、箏、尺八の編成が普通である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, the common instrumental trio is either shamisen, koto and kokyu, or shamisen, koto and shakuhachi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the common instrumental trio is either shamisen, koto and kokyu or shamisen, koto and shakuhachi.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the common instrumental trio is either shamisen, koto and kokyu or shamisen, koto and shakuhachi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>ただし、一般的ではないが箏、胡弓、尺八と言った組み合わせも可能である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The trio of koto, kokyu and shakuhachi is also possible, though it is not a common one.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The trio of koto, kokyu and shakuhachi is also possible, though it isn&apos;t common.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The trio of koto, kokyu and shakuhachi is also possible, though it isn&apos;t common.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>楽器間の関係は、曲によってほとんどユニゾンのものもあれば（歌がある場合はその方が良いことも多い）、器楽的要素が強い曲では各楽器が複雑にからみ合うよう作られているものが多い（特に三味線と箏）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In some tunes, all instruments are performed almost in unison - this will be better in most cases if the instruments accompany a song - and in other tunes, different melodies of the instruments are interwoven with each other when the tune has an instrumental flavor - especially when the tune is an ensemble of shamisen &amp; koto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In some tunes, all instruments are performed nearly in unison--this is better in most cases, if the instruments accompany a song--and in other tunes the different melodies of the instruments are interwoven when the tune has an instrumental flavor, especially when the tune is an ensemble of shamisen and koto.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In some tunes, all instruments are performed nearly in unison; This is better in most cases, if the instruments accompany a song, and in other tunes the different melodies of the instruments are interwoven when the tune has an instrumental flavor, especially when the tune is an ensemble of shamisen and koto.</e>
<cmt>ハイフン削除し、;補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>これはきわめて精緻に作られた合奏音楽と言え、雅楽の管絃やガムランなどと共に、西洋音楽のポリフォニー（多音性）とは異なるヘテロフォニー（異音性）の端的な例として挙げることができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This sankyoku gassou can be said a very scrupulously made ensemble, and along with other music, such as the wind &amp; string music of &quot;Gagaku&quot; (ancient Japanese court music), or Gamelan (Indonesian music), it is typical heterophony, different from polyphony of the Western music.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This sankyoku gassou can be called a very scrupulously made ensemble, and along with other music, such as the wind and string music of &quot;Gagaku&quot; (ancient Japanese court music), or Gamelan (Indonesian music), it&apos;s typical heterophony, being different from the polyphony of Western music.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This sankyoku gasso can be called a very scrupulously made ensemble, and along with other music, such as the wind and string music of Gagaku (ancient Japanese court music), or Gamelan (Indonesian music), it&apos;s typical heterophony, being different from the polyphony of Western music.</e>
<cmt>sankyoku gassoに訂正しました。原文に合せて&quot; &quot;削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>また例えば地歌のある曲でも、流派によって違う箏の手、胡弓の手、尺八の手がつけられていることが多く、それもユニゾンに近いものから多音的なものまで、流派によっても傾向が異なっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And, even when one and the same jiuta is sung, its accompaniment melody of koto, kokyu and shakuhachi often differs from school to school, and the performance style also differs from school to school, ranging from unison-like ensemble to polyphonic one.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even when one and the same jiuta is sung, its accompaniment melody of koto, kokyu and shakuhachi often varies from school to school, and the performance style varies from school to school, ranging from a unison-like ensemble to polyphonic one.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even when one and the same jiuta is sung, its accompaniment melody of koto, kokyu and shakuhachi often varies from school to school, and the performance style varies from school to school, ranging from a unison-like ensemble to polyphonic one.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>西洋音楽で言えば弦楽四重奏の各パートは緊密な重層的構造を成していて、絶対的に固定され一パートでも欠かせない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the case of the Western music, each part of a string quartet is linked tightly with another one in a polyphonic melody, and so no part is ever movable and dispensable.</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処　</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the case of Western music, each part of a string quartet is linked tightly with another one in a polyphonic melody, so no single part is ever movable or dispensable.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the case of Western music, each part of a string quartet is linked tightly with another one in a polyphonic melody, so no single part is ever movable or dispensable.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>これと違い、三曲合奏は本来独奏曲に後から他のパートを付けたものであり、どちらかと言えば流動的、並列的、装飾的であって、その編成にはバロック音楽のように自由さがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Contrastingly, in the case of sankyoku gassou, some parts are added to a tune that is originally a solo, and so the music is rather fluid, heterophonic and ornamental, and in its orchestration, it is as flexible as baroque music.</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Contrastingly, in the case of sankyoku gassou some parts are added to a tune that is originally a solo, so the music is somewhat fluid, heterophonic and ornamental, and in its orchestration it&apos;s as flexible as baroque music.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Contrastingly, in the case of sankyoku gasso some parts are added to a tune that is originally a solo, so the music is somewhat fluid, heterophonic and ornamental, and in its orchestration it&apos;s as flexible as baroque music.</e>
<cmt>sankyoku gassoに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>それゆえ、三という数にこだわらず、たとえば三味線と尺八だけ、箏と胡弓だけ、三味線と箏、あるいは三味線の本手と替手だけといった編成での演奏も行なわれるし、独奏や四種の楽器での合奏すら可能である（ただしそれらのような場合は三曲合奏とは言わない）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, in spite of the number &quot;three&quot; embedded in the name &quot;sankyoku,&quot; various kinds of performances are possible, such as an ensemble of just shamisen &amp; shakuhachi, an ensemble of just koto &amp; kokyu, an ensemble of just shamisen &amp; koto, an ensemble of just the leading shamisen &amp; the second shamisen, a solo performance, or even an ensemble of four instruments; these performances are not called sankyoku gassou.</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　・「本手」「替手」の訳については以下のホームページを参照しました。[www.komuso.com/albums/Traditional_Music_of_Japan_The_-03.html]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, despite the number &quot;three&quot; being embedded in the name &quot;sankyoku,&quot; various kinds of performances are possible, such as an ensemble of just shamisen and shakuhachi, an ensemble of just koto and kokyu, an ensemble of just shamisen and koto, an ensemble of just the leading shamisen and the second shamisen, a solo performance or even an ensemble of four instruments; however, these performances aren&apos;t called sankyoku gassou.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, despite the number &quot;three&quot; being embedded in the name &quot;sankyoku,&quot; various kinds of performances are possible, such as an ensemble of just shamisen and shakuhachi, an ensemble of just koto and kokyu, an ensemble of just shamisen and koto, an ensemble of just the leading shamisen and the second shamisen, a solo performance or even an ensemble of four instruments; however, these performances aren&apos;t called sankyoku gasso.</e>
<cmt>sankyoku gassoに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>あるいは三曲合奏の中に箏、または三味線の替手や地を加えたり（つまり4パート以上の編成）することも珍しくない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And it is not rare for sankyoku gassou to be joined by the second and third koto, or by the second and third shamisen, which means the ensemble consists of not less than four parts.</e>
<cmt>・「地」の訳は研究社和英によると&quot;accompaniment&quot;(伴奏）です。ただ、ここでは「替手」の訳（the second koto [shamisen])との統一性を考え&quot;the third shamisen (koto)&quot; と訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It&apos;s fairly common for sankyoku gassou to be joined by the second and third koto or by the second and third shamisen, which means the ensemble consists of at least four parts.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It&apos;s fairly common for sankyoku gasso to be joined by the second and third koto or by the second and third shamisen, which means the ensemble consists of at least four parts.</e>
<cmt>sankyoku gassoに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>それぞれの編成に面白みがあり、また流派によって後で付けられたパートの旋律が違っていたりするので、同一曲でも様々な編成の演奏を楽しむことができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Each ensemble has fun of its own, and each school of the music adds a different melody part to the original tune, so that you can enjoy various styles of ensembles for even a single tune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Each ensemble has fun of its own, and each school of the music adds a different melody part to the original tune, so that one can enjoy various styles of ensembles for even a single tune.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Each ensemble has fun of its own, and each school of the music adds a different melody part to the original tune, so that one can enjoy various styles of ensembles for even a single tune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>このような融通性が特徴と言える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such flexibility is characteristic of sankyoku gassou.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such flexibility is characteristic of sankyoku gassou.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such flexibility is characteristic of sankyoku gasso.</e>
<cmt>sankyoku gassoに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>ただ、幕末になるほど、特に光崎、幾山、吉沢の各検校らの作品の多くは2～3パートが一人で作られており、各パート間の関連が緊密になる傾向がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as the last days of the Edo period drew near, each part of a tune became closely linked with another, and this was true especially when Mitsuzaki Kengyo, Ikuyama Kengyo and Yoshizawa Kengyo - &quot;Kengyo&quot; was the highest rank of Todo-za - were active, because, in most cases, they themselves made two or three parts of their own pieces.</e>
<cmt>・「検校」は「当道座の最高位」を意味するものの、「光崎検校」のように個人を指して用いられる場合、信頼に足るホームページ、例えば[http://www.komuso.com/people/Mitsuzaki_Kengyo.html]の表記は&quot;Mtsuzaki Kengyo&quot;となっており、ここでもそれに従っています。　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　なお、これは「姓」と「名」ではないので、「検校」の部分（あるいは「光崎」の部分）をすべて大文字にする、というお約束は妥当しないものとして処理しています。　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　また、検校が何者であるか示しておいた方が親切であろう、とも思うので「当道座の最高位であった」と補っておきました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as the Edo period drew to a close, each part of a tune became closely linked with another, and this was particularly true when Mitsuzaki Kengyo, Ikuyama Kengyo and Yoshizawa Kengyo--&quot;Kengyo&quot; being the highest rank of Todo-za--were active, because in most cases they would create two or three parts for their own pieces.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as the Edo period drew to a close, each part of a tune became closely linked with another, and this was particularly true when Mitsuzaki Kengyo, Ikuyama Kengyo and Yoshizawa Kengyo (being the highest rank of Todo-za) were active, because in most cases they would create two or three parts for their own pieces.</e>
<cmt>ハイフン削除し、（）補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>さらに下って宮城道雄の作品においては、各パートは完全に固定され、西洋音楽のポリフォニーの概念も導入されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the times came closer to ours, Michio MIYAGI completely fixed each part of his tunes, and introduced the concept of polyphony from the Western music into them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the modern age approached, Michio MIYAGI completely fixed all the parts in his tunes, and into them he introduced the Western concept of polyphony.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the modern age approached, Michio MIYAGI completely fixed all the parts in his tunes, and into them he introduced the Western concept of polyphony.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>こうして、三曲合奏は日本の伝統音楽の中でも合奏音楽として重要な位置を占めており、明治以降、西洋音楽にももっとも早くから対応することにもなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this way, of all kinds of traditional Japanese music, sankyoku gassou came to occupy an important position as the ensemble music, and it could catch up with the Western music in and after the Meiji period earlier than any other music in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this way, of all kinds of traditional Japanese music, sankyoku gassou came to occupy an important position as ensemble music, and it was able to catch up with Western music in and after the Meiji period sooner than any other music in Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this way, of all kinds of traditional Japanese music, sankyoku gasso came to occupy an important position as ensemble music, and it was able to catch up with Western music in and after the Meiji period sooner than any other music in Japan.</e>
<cmt>sankyoku gassoに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>このように三曲合奏が多音的な展開を見せたのも、地歌の手事もの、箏曲の段もの、胡弓本曲など器楽的な発展が著しかったからであろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sankyoku gassou developed in such a polyphonic way probably because there was much development in instrumental works, such as Jiuta&apos;s &quot;tegotomono&quot; (pieces with long instrumental interludes called &quot;tegoto&quot;), the koto music&apos;s &quot;danmono&quot; (leveled pieces), and the kokyu music&apos;s &quot;honkyoku&quot; (pieces composed in the early days).</e>
<cmt>・「手事（てごと）もの」の訳については以下のpdfを参照しました。[http://wwwsoc.nii.ac.jp/msj4/publish/v50/fukuda-e.pdf]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sankyoku gassou developed in such a polyphonic way probably because there was much development in instrumental works, such as Jiuta&apos;s &quot;tegotomono&quot; (pieces with long instrumental interludes called &quot;tegoto&quot;), koto music&apos;s &quot;danmono&quot; (leveled pieces) and kokyu music&apos;s &quot;honkyoku&quot; (pieces composed in the early days).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sankyoku gasso developed in such a polyphonic way probably because there was much development in instrumental works, such as Jiuta&apos;s &quot;tegotomono&quot; (pieces with long instrumental interludes called &quot;tegoto&quot;), koto music&apos;s &quot;danmono&quot; (leveled pieces) and kokyu music&apos;s &quot;honkyoku&quot; (pieces composed in the early days).</e>
<cmt>sankyoku gassoに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>ただしあくまでも声楽を基本とする山田流箏曲では、基本的にほとんどすべてユニゾンで三曲合奏が行なわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in Yamada school of koto music which is completely based on vocal music, all instruments of sankyoku gassou are performed almost in unison.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in the Yamada school of koto music, which is completely based on vocal music, all the instruments of sankyoku gassou are performed nearly in unison.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in the Yamada school of koto music, which is completely based on vocal music, all the instruments of sankyoku gasso are performed nearly in unison.</e>
<cmt>sankyoku gassoに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="48">
<j>三曲合奏の由来</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Origin of sankyoku gassou</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The origin of sankyoku gassou</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The origin of sankyoku gasso</e>
<cmt>sankyoku gassoに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>三種の楽器（地歌三味線、箏、胡弓）が合奏される由来は、もともとこれらがすべて当道座に属する盲人音楽家が扱う楽器であったからである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ensembles of three types of instruments (shamisen, koto and kokyu) began to be played because all these instruments were originally played by the blind musicians who belonged to &quot;Todo-za&quot; (the traditional guild for the blind).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ensembles of three types of instruments (shamisen, koto and kokyu) began to be played, because all these instruments were originally played by the blind musicians who belonged to &quot;Todo-za,&quot; the traditional guild for the blind.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ensembles of three types of instruments (shamisen, koto and kokyu) began to be played, because all these instruments were originally played by the blind musicians who belonged to Todo-za, the traditional guild for the blind.</e>
<cmt>原文に合せて&quot; &quot;削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>しかし演奏者は同じでも本来、三味線は地歌、箏は箏曲、胡弓は胡弓楽という、それぞれ別個の音楽として成立、存在していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, each instrument established and kept music of its own - Jiuta for shamisen, Sokyoku for koto, and Kokyu-gaku for kokyu - although their performers overlapped with each other.</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処　</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, each instrument established and kept music of its own--Jiuta for shamisen, Sokyoku for koto, and Kokyu-gaku for kokyu--although their performers overlapped with one another.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, each instrument established and kept music of its own, Jiuta for shamisen, Sokyoku for koto, and Kokyu-gaku for kokyu, although their performers overlapped with one another.</e>
<cmt>ハイフン削除し、コンマ補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>それゆえ、江戸時代初期の芸術音楽の範囲において、異種の楽器が合奏されることはほとんどなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, in the early Edo period, ensembles of the different kinds of instruments were rarely played in the world of art music.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, in the early Edo period ensembles of the different kinds of instruments were rarely conducted in the world of art music.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, in the early Edo period ensembles of the different kinds of instruments were rarely conducted in the world of art music.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>実際に現在でも、初期に作られた楽曲（本曲、または本手組ともいう）は、他の楽器を加えないことがほとんどである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even today, the tunes composed in the early days, called &quot;honkyoku,&quot; or &quot;honte-gumi,&quot; are mostly played solo actually.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even today, the tunes composed in the early days, called &quot;honkyoku&quot; or &quot;honte-gumi,&quot; are generally played solo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even today, the tunes composed in the early days, called &quot;honkyoku&quot; or &quot;honte-gumi,&quot; are generally played solo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>ただしそれらの中で箏曲の「段もの」は後世三曲合奏が行なわれるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Of these tunes, however, &quot;Danmono&quot; (leveled pieces) of Sokyoku (koto music) began to be played in sankyoku gassou in later years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Of these tunes, however, the Danmono (leveled pieces) of Sokyoku (koto music) began to be played in sankyoku gassou in later years.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Of these tunes, however, the &apos;Danmono&apos; (leveled pieces) of Sokyoku (koto music) began to be played in sankyoku gasso in later years.</e>
<cmt>原文に合せて&apos; &apos;補足しました。sankyoku gassoに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="54">
<j>三曲合奏に地歌曲が多い理由については、次のように考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Why so many tunes of Jiuta are found in sankyoku gassou are explained as follows:</e>
<cmt>・セル64から71までは、ここに言う「理由」の説明がなされているものとしてセミコロンでつなげています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reasons that so many tunes of Jiuta are found in sankyoku gassou are explained as follows:</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reasons that so many tunes of Jiuta are found in sankyoku gasso are explained as follows:</e>
<cmt>sankyoku gassoに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>上方における三曲の音楽の中では、江戸時代中期になると箏曲が停滞し、旧作の演奏のみで新作は非常に少なくなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Of the music of sankyoku (instrumental trio), Sokyoku became stagnant in Kamigata (Kyoto and Osaka area) in the middle of the Edo period, and so they just performed tunes composed earlier and rarely performed new ones;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Of the music of sankyoku (instrumental trio), Sokyoku became stagnant in Kamigata (the area of Kyoto and Osaka) in the middle of the Edo period, so they simply performed tunes composed earlier and rarely performed new ones;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Of the music of sankyoku (instrumental trio), Sokyoku became stagnant in Kamigata (the area of Kyoto and Osaka) in the middle of the Edo period, so they simply performed tunes composed earlier and rarely performed new ones.</e>
<cmt>不要なスペースを削除しました。;をピリオドに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>その一方で、三味線はその音楽がますます発展し、次々と新しい形式が生み出され、後期にかけて日本音楽の主導権を握る楽器となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">meanwhile, shamisen developed its music more and more, and produced its new styles one after another, so it took the lead in Japanese musical instruments until the later Edo period;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, shamisen music continued to develop and new styles were introduced one after another, so it took the lead among Japanese musical instruments until the later Edo period;</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, shamisen music continued to develop and new styles were introduced one after another, so it took the lead among Japanese musical instruments until the later Edo period.</e>
<cmt>;をピリオドに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>こうして江戸時代中期以降、厖大な数の地歌三味線の新曲が次々と作られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">in this way, from the middle of the Edo period, huge amounts of new Jiuta accompanied by shamisen were composed one after another;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this way, from the middle of the Edo period, large numbers of Jiuta accompanied by shamisen were composed, one after another;</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this way, from the middle of the Edo period, large numbers of Jiuta accompanied by shamisen were composed, one after another.</e>
<cmt>;をピリオドに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>天保頃までの箏の発展も、主にそこに便乗し合奏する形で進んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">and Sokyoku developed until around Tenpo era mainly by jumping on the shamisen bandwagon, in other words, by participating in Jiuta;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, Sokyoku developed until around Tenpo era, mainly by jumping on the shamisen bandwagon or, in other words, by participating in Jiuta;</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, Sokyoku developed until around Tenpo era, mainly by jumping on the shamisen bandwagon or, in other words, by participating in Jiuta.</e>
<cmt>;をピリオドに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>胡弓は中期に興隆していくつか流派も生まれ、新作も作られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the kokyu music also prospered in the middle of the Edo period, so it produced some schools and new pieces;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokyu music also prospered in the middle of the Edo period, so it produced its own schools and new pieces;</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kokyu music also prospered in the middle of the Edo period, so it produced its own schools and new pieces.</e>
<cmt>;をピリオドに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>特に尺八や笛から影響を受けた曲が生まれ、それが更に三味線(地歌)に取り入れられたりすることもあったが、江戸時代後期に入るとやはり地歌に便乗する面が強くなったといえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">occasionally, the kokyu music, which was influenced mainly by the music of the shakuhachi &amp; other Japanese flutes, further influenced the music of the shamisen (Jiuta), but from the later Edo period, the kokyu music also had a tendency to participate in Jiuta;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Occasionally, kokyu music, which was influenced mainly by the music of the shakuhachi and other Japanese flutes, further influenced the music of the shamisen (Jiuta), but from the later Edo period kokyu music also had a tendency to participate in Jiuta;</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Occasionally, kokyu music, which was influenced mainly by the music of the shakuhachi and other Japanese flutes, further influenced the music of the shamisen (Jiuta), but from the later Edo period kokyu music also had a tendency to participate in Jiuta.</e>
<cmt>;をピリオドに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>なお尺八も中期に興隆したが、これは当道座の外の楽器であり、その音楽に三味線や箏が直接合奏することはなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">incidentally, the shakuhachi music also prospered in the middle of the Edo period, but neither shamisen nor koto participated in the shakuhachi music because the shakuhachi was not the instrument performed by those in Todo-za;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Incidentally, shakuhachi music also prospered in the middle of the Edo period, but neither the shamisen nor the koto participated in shakuhachi music because the shakuhachi wasn&apos;t an instrument performed by those in the Todo-za;</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Incidentally, shakuhachi music also prospered in the middle of the Edo period, but neither the shamisen nor the koto participated in shakuhachi music because the shakuhachi wasn&apos;t an instrument performed by those in the Todo-za.</e>
<cmt>;をピリオドに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>三曲合奏に参入する時も結局尺八が地歌、箏曲に便乗する形になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">when sankyoku gassou was orchestrated, it was the side of the shakuhachi that participated in Jiuta &amp; Sokyoku in the end.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When sankyoku gassou was orchestrated, ultimately it was the side of the shakuhachi that participated in Jiuta and Sokyoku.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When sankyoku gasso was orchestrated, ultimately it was the side of the shakuhachi that participated in Jiuta and Sokyoku.</e>
<cmt>sankyoku gassoに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="63">
<j>ただし江戸時代初期には、大衆的な曲では色々な合奏が行なわれていたことが絵画などで知られるが、そのような曲は現在ほとんど伝えられていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some pictures and other historical materials show us that various ensembles of popular tunes were performed in the early Edo period, but few of them are handed down to us today.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some pictures and other historical materials show us that various ensembles of popular tunes were performed in the early Edo period, but few have been handed down to the present day.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some pictures and other historical materials show us that various ensembles of popular tunes were performed in the early Edo period, but few have been handed down to the present day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="64">
<j>箏の参入</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Participation of the koto into the shamisen music</e>
<cmt>・セル76以下の内容から、「箏の三味線の曲への参入」と訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Participation of the koto in shamisen music</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Participation of the koto in shamisen music</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>芸術曲における箏と三味線の本格的な合奏は、元禄期の生田検校により始められたと言われ（異説もあり）、三味線の曲（地歌）に箏のパートを作り合わせるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A theory says the genuine ensemble of koto &amp; shamisen in the world of art music was started by Ikuta Kengyo in the Genroku era - though some oppose to this theory - when he started to add the part of the koto music to the shamisen music (Jiuta).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A theory asserts that the genuine ensemble of koto and shamisen in the world of art music was started by Ikuta Kengyo in the Genroku era--though some disagree with that theory--when he began to add the part of koto music to shamisen music (Jiuta).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A theory asserts that the genuine ensemble of koto and shamisen in the world of art music was started by Ikuta Kengyo in the Genroku era, though some disagree with that theory, when he began to add the part of koto music to shamisen music (Jiuta).</e>
<cmt>ハイフンを削除し、コンマを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>当時は両パートをほとんどユニゾンに合わせるだけであったが、文化 (元号)頃に至って大阪の市浦検校により、元の三味線パートに対して異なった旋律を持つ箏のパートが作られるようになり、合奏効果が高まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, both of these instruments were simply performed in unison-like style, but around the Bunka era, Ichiura Kengyo living in Osaka started to add the melody part of the koto different from that of the shamisen, and this enhanced the effect of the ensemble.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, both these instruments were simply performed in unison-like style, but in or around the Bunka era, Ichiura Kengyo, a resident of Osaka, started to add the melody part of the koto, which was different from that of the shamisen, and this enhanced the effect of the ensemble.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, both these instruments were simply performed in unison-like style, but in or around the Bunka era, Ichiura Kengyo, a resident of Osaka, started to add the melody part of the koto, which was different from that of the shamisen, and this enhanced the effect of the ensemble.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>これを「替手式」と呼び、京都の八重崎検校らによりいっそう洗練された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was called &quot;kaedeshiki&quot; (the accompaniment style), and Yaezaki Kengyo living in Kyoto refined the style more.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処　</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was called &quot;kaedeshiki&quot; (the accompaniment style), and Yaezaki Kengyo, who lived in Kyoto, further refined the style.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was called &apos;kaedeshiki&apos; (the accompaniment style), and Yaezaki Kengyo, who lived in Kyoto, further refined the style.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>三味線と箏の両パートを一人の作曲家が作るようになったのは八重崎の弟子の光崎検校からである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was Mitsuzaki Kengyo (Yaezaki Kengyo&apos;s pupil) who began to compose both of the shamisen melody part &amp; the koto one.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was Mitsuzaki Kengyo (Yaezaki Kengyo&apos;s pupil) who began to compose both the shamisen melody part and the koto part.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was Mitsuzaki Kengyo (Yaezaki Kengyo&apos;s pupil) who began to compose both the shamisen melody part and the koto part.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="69">
<j>いっぽう江戸では、1777年に山田検校が新しい箏曲山田流を創始する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, in Edo, Yamada Kengyo founded his new Yamada school of Sokyoku in 1777.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, in Edo, Yamada Kengyo founded his new Yamada school of Sokyoku in 1777.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, in Edo, Yamada Kengyo founded his new Yamada school of Sokyoku in 1777.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>これは地歌ではなく一中節、河東節など浄瑠璃の音楽スタイルを取り入れたもので、はじめから箏と三味線を合奏させていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He introduced not the music style of Jiuta but that of Icchu-bushi or Kato-bushi in &quot;Joruri&quot; (dramatic narrative chanted to a shamisen accompaniment), in which koto and shamisen played a tune together from the start.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He introduced not the music style of Jiuta but that of Icchu-bushi or Kato-bushi in &quot;Joruri&quot; (a dramatic narrative chanted to shamisen accompaniment), in which the koto and shamisen played a tune together from the start.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He introduced not the music style of Jiuta but that of Icchu-bushi or Kato-bushi in &quot;Joruri&quot; (a dramatic narrative chanted to shamisen accompaniment), in which the koto and shamisen played a tune together from the start.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="71">
<j>胡弓の参入</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Participation of the kokyu into Jiuta or Sokyoku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Participation of the kokyu in Jiuta or Sokyoku</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Participation of the kokyu in Jiuta or Sokyoku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>胡弓も独自の楽曲である胡弓本曲を持つ一方、江戸中期からしばしば地歌や箏曲の合奏に加わっていたが、やはり即興的にユニゾンに近い状態で合わせられていたらしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Having its own music &quot;kokyu honkyoku&quot; (pieces of kokyu composed in the early days), kokyu often participated in the ensemble of Jiuta or Sokyoku from the middle of the Edo period, and this improvised performance also seems to have been an unison-like style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The kokyu, having its own music &quot;kokyu honkyoku&quot; (pieces for kokyu composed in the early days), woul often participate in the ensemble of Jiuta or Sokyoku from the middle of the Edo period, and this improvised performance also seems to have been in a unison-like style.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The kokyu, having its own music &quot;kokyu honkyoku&quot; (pieces for kokyu composed in the early days), would often participate in the ensemble of Jiuta or Sokyoku from the middle of the Edo period, and this improvised performance also seems to have been in a unison-like style.</e>
<cmt>would スペル訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>胡弓本曲に三味線または箏を合わせることはあったが、これは主に「地」で伴奏する形であり、普通二重奏までで三曲合奏にはしない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Occasionally, shamisen or koto joined kokyu honkyoku, but both of them did so merely as &quot;an accompaniment,&quot; and the ensemble was usually a duet, not a trio.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Occasionally, shamisen or koto would join in kokyu honkyoku, but both of them did so merely as an accompaniment and the ensemble was usually a duet instead of a trio.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Occasionally, shamisen or koto would join in kokyu honkyoku, but both of them did so merely as an accompaniment and the ensemble was usually a duet instead of a trio.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>ただ、胡弓楽から「巣籠」や「獅子」といった器楽的要素が地歌に取り入れられ、地歌の器楽的発展のひとつの要素となった点は重要である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But it was important for Jiuta to learn the instrumental factor from kokyu pieces, such as &quot;Tsuru no sugomori&quot; (The Cranes Nesting) &amp; &quot;Yachiyojishi&quot; (Lion of Eight Thousand Generations from the 16th century), because this became one of the basic factors of Jiuta&apos;s instrumental development.</e>
<cmt>・原文に言う「巣籠」は「鶴の巣籠」（①）、「獅子」は「八千代獅子」（②）のことと解され、その英訳は以下のホームページを参照しています(ただし下記ホームページでは「八千代」が&quot;Yachio&quot;になっており、これは&quot;Yachiyo&quot;の誤りと解されますので、そう訂正して訳しています。）[http:www.komuso.com/pieces/Tsuru_no_Sugomori_(Dokyu).html](①）　[http:www.komuso.com/pieces/Yachio_Jishi.html](②）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it was important that Jiuta should acquire the instrumental facet of kokyu pieces, such as &quot;Tsuru no sugomori (The Cranes Nesting)&quot; and &quot;Yachiyojishi&quot; (&quot;Lion of Eight Thousand Generations,&quot; from the sixteenth century), because this became a basic factor in Jiuta&apos;s instrumental development.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it was important that Jiuta should acquire the instrumental facet of kokyu pieces, such as &apos;Tsuru no sugomori&apos; (The Cranes Nesting) and &apos;Yachiyojishi&apos; (Lion of Eight Thousand Generations, from the 16th century), because this became a basic factor in Jiuta&apos;s instrumental development.</e>
<cmt>原文に合せて&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に訂正しました。&quot; &quot;削除しました。数字に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>地歌や箏曲での合奏の中で、胡弓に独自の旋律を持たせたのは光崎の後輩にあたる名古屋の吉沢検校である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was Yoshizawa Kengyo (Mitsuzaki Kengyo&apos;s junior) living in Nagoya who made the kokyu melody distinctive in the Jiuta (or Sokyoku) ensemble.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was Yoshizawa Kengyo (Mitsuzaki Kengyo&apos;s junior), a resident of Nagoya, who made the kokyu melody distinctive in the Jiuta (or Sokyoku) ensemble.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was Yoshizawa Kengyo (Mitsuzaki Kengyo&apos;s junior), a resident of Nagoya, who made the kokyu melody distinctive in the Jiuta (or Sokyoku) ensemble.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>また同一曲において胡弓のパートも含め三パートすべてが一人の作曲家により作られるようになったのも吉沢からであり、以後二パート、三パートを一人で作曲することが多くなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was also Yoshizawa Kengyo who composed all three parts of a tune, including the part of kokyu, all by himself for the first time in history, and thereafter, many musicians came to compose two or three parts all by themselves.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was also Yoshizawa Kengyo who composed all three parts of a tune, including the part for kokyu, all by himself for the first time in history, and thereafter many musicians came to compose two or three parts by themselves.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was also Yoshizawa Kengyo who composed all three parts of a tune, including the part for kokyu, all by himself for the first time in history, and thereafter many musicians came to compose two or three parts by themselves.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="77">
<j>江戸では、18世紀中頃に藤植検校により藤植流胡弓が成立していたが、山田検校により山田流箏曲が興ると、それに加わり合奏されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Edo, Fujiue school of the kokyu music was founded by Fujiue Kengyo around the middle of the 18th century, and when Yamada school of the koto music was founded by Yamada Kengyo, Fujiue&apos;s kokyu music participated in Yamada&apos;s koto music, and they began to play a tune together.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Edo, the Fujiue school of kokyu music was founded by Fujiue Kengyo around the middle of the eighteenth century, and when the Yamada school of koto music was founded by Yamada Kengyo, Fujiue&apos;s kokyu music participated in Yamada&apos;s koto music and they began to play tunes together.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Edo, the Fujiue school of kokyu music was founded by Fujiue Kengyo around the middle of the 18th century, and when the Yamada school of koto music was founded by Yamada Kengyo, Fujiue&apos;s kokyu music participated in Yamada&apos;s koto music and they began to play tunes together.</e>
<cmt>数字に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>また尾張から松翁流胡弓が伝えられ、山田流箏曲との合奏専用に特化して伝えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And Shoo school of the kokyu music, which was introduced from Owari Province, is handed down to us in an exclusively specialized form of the ensemble with Yamada school of the koto music.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, the Shoo school of kokyu music, which was introduced from Owari Province, has been handed down to us in an exclusively specialized form of the ensemble with the Yamada school of koto music.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, the Shoo school of kokyu music, which was introduced from Owari Province, has been handed down to us in an exclusively specialized form of the ensemble with the Yamada school of koto music.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="79">
<j>尺八の参入</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Participation of the shakuhachi into other instruments&apos; music</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Participation of the shakuhachi in music for other instruments</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Participation of the shakuhachi in music for other instruments</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>尺八は本来虚無僧の占有楽器であり、娯楽よりは宗教行為のひとつとして演奏されてきたが、江戸時代中期に黒沢琴古が出て、宗教音楽から世俗音楽への道が開かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally, the shakuhachi was exclusively owned by &quot;komuso&quot; (a mendicant Zen priest of the Fuke sect), and its performance was deemed part of religious activities rather than entertainment, but in the middle of the Edo period, Kinko KUROSAWA changed it from the instrument for religious music to that for secular music.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally, the shakuhachi was exclusively owned by &quot;komuso&quot; (a mendicant Zen priest of the Fuke sect), and its performance was deemed part of religious activities instead of entertainment, but in the middle of the Edo period Kinko KUROSAWA changed it from an instrument for religious music to one for secular music.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally, the shakuhachi was exclusively owned by &quot;komuso&quot; (a mendicant Zen priest of the Fuke sect), and its performance was deemed part of religious activities instead of entertainment, but in the middle of the Edo period Kinko KUROSAWA changed it from an instrument for religious music to one for secular music.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>しかし他の楽器との演奏は法令により表向き禁止されていたらしいが、実際にはすでに18世紀末に尺八が加わった三曲合奏図が見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though the ensemble of shakuhachi &amp; other instruments seemed to be officially prohibited by law, a picture in those days shows us that in fact the shakuhachi already participated in sankyoku gassou at the end of the 18th century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though it seemed the ensemble of shakuhachi and other instruments was officially prohibited by law, a picture in those days shows us that in fact the shakuhachi was already participating in sankyoku gassou at the end of the eighteenth century.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though it seemed the ensemble of shakuhachi and other instruments was officially prohibited by law, a picture in those days shows us that in fact the shakuhachi was already participating in sankyoku gasso at the end of the 18th century.</e>
<cmt>sankyoku gassoに訂正しました。数字に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>ただし本格的な三曲への参入は幕末に大阪で始まる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But the genuine participation of the shakuhachi into sankyoku began in the last days of the Tokugawa shogunate in Osaka.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the genuine participation of the shakuhachi in sankyoku began in the last days of the Tokugawa shogunate in Osaka.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the genuine participation of the shakuhachi in sankyoku began in the last days of the Tokugawa shogunate in Osaka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>特に明治になって、普化宗廃止により虚無僧という生業を断たれた尺八奏者たちが、新たな仕事の場として積極的に進出したのが大きなきっかけである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This participation was particularly accelerated when shakuhachi performers actively went into the sankyoku world for their workplace after losing their occupation of komuso owing to the government&apos;s abolition of Fuke sect in the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This kind of participation was particularly accelerated when shakuhachi performers actively entered the sankyoku world for their workplace after losing their occupations as komuso, owing to the government&apos;s abolition of the Fuke sect in the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This kind of participation was particularly accelerated when shakuhachi performers actively entered the sankyoku world for their workplace after losing their occupations as komuso, owing to the government&apos;s abolition of the Fuke sect in the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>今日伝えられている琴古流系尺八のパートは、明治のごく初期に吉田一調、荒木古童らによって手付けされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The shakuhachi part of some tunes added by a school descendent from Kinko KUROSAWA is still existent today, and the part was arranged by the school musicians, including Iccho YOSHIDA and Kodo ARAKI, in the quite early days of the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shakuhachi parts of some tunes, having been added by a school descendent of Kinko KUROSAWA, still exist today, and the part was arranged by the school musicians--including Iccho YOSHIDA and Kodo ARAKI--in the very early Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The shakuhachi parts of some tunes, having been added by a school descendent of Kinko KUROSAWA, still exist today, and the part was arranged by the school musicians, including Iccho YOSHIDA and Kodo ARAKI, in the very early Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>ハイフンを削除し、コンマを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>その後都山流の創始者である初代中尾都山がより手の込んだ手付を行ない、ほかにも竹保流、上田流、西園流など各流が独自の手付を行なっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, Tozan NAKAO Ⅰ, the founder of Tozan school of the shakuhachi music, added a more elaborate arrangement to the shakuhachi melody, and other schools of shakuhachi, such as Chikuho school, Ueda school and Seien school, also added the arrangements of their own.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, Tozan NAKAO I, the founder of the Tozan school of shakuhachi music, added a more elaborate arrangement to the shakuhachi melody, and other schools of shakuhachi, such as the Chikuho school, Ueda school and Seien school, added arrangements of their own.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, Tozan NAKAO, the founder of the Tozan school of shakuhachi music, added a more elaborate arrangement to the shakuhachi melody, and other schools of shakuhachi, such as the Chikuho school, Ueda school and Seien school, added arrangements of their own.</e>
<cmt>Iは不要と考え削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>はじめて同一曲内において尺八のパートまで作曲したのは宮城道雄であり、西洋音楽の合奏法を取り入れて作曲されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was Michio MIYAGI who composed not only the koto part but also the shakuhachi part of a tune for the first time in history, and he introduced the ensemble method of the Western music into his tunes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was Michio MIYAGI who composed not only the koto part but also the shakuhachi part of a tune for the first time in history, and he introduced the ensemble method of Western music into his tunes.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was Michio MIYAGI who composed not only the koto part but also the shakuhachi part of a tune for the first time in history, and he introduced the ensemble method of Western music into his tunes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), Carkuni(id:79281), Yas(id:739), Hermes(id:21387), 0null0(id:582), 詠狸庵(id:41048), TS(id:481), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>