<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>雅楽</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gagaku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gagaku</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gagaku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>雅楽（ががく）は、日本、中国、朝鮮半島、ベトナムの伝統的な音楽の一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gagaku is one of the traditional music in Japan, China, the Korean Peninsula and Vietnam.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gagaku is one of the traditional forms of music in Japan, China, the Korean Peninsula and Vietnam.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gagaku is one of the traditional forms of music in Japan, China, the Korean Peninsula and Vietnam.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>以下、宮内庁式部職楽部に伝わる日本の雅楽（重要無形文化財）を中心に述べる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Japanese Gagaku (Important intangible cultural heritage) passed down in Gakubu section, Shikibu-shoku department of the Imperial Household Agency is mainly described here as follows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Japanese Gagaku (an important intangible cultural heritage) passed down in the Gakubu Section, Shikibu-shoku Department, of the Imperial Household Agency, is mainly described here as follows:</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japanese Gagaku (an important intangible cultural heritage) passed down in the Gakubu Section, Shikibu-shoku Department, of the Imperial Household Agency, is mainly described here as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Overview</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Overview</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>統一</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>雅楽の原義は「雅正の楽舞」で、「俗楽」の対。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The original meaning of Gagaku is &quot;Gasei-no-Gakubu,&quot; and its antonym is &quot;Zokugaku (worldly music).&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The original meaning of Gagaku is &quot;Gasei-no-Gakubu,&quot; and its antonym is &quot;Zokugaku (worldly music).&quot;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The original meaning of Gagaku is &apos;Gasei-no-Gakubu,&apos; and its antonym is &apos;Zokugaku (worldly music).&apos;</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>国内の宮内庁式部職楽部による定義では、宮内庁式部職楽部が演奏する曲目の内、洋楽を除くもの、とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gakubu section, Shikibu-shoku department of Imperial Household Agency in Japan defines it as the numbers played by Gakubu section, Shikibu-shoku department of Imperial Household Agency except Western music.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Gakubu Section, Shikibu-shoku Department of the Imperial Household Agency, defines it as the numbers played by the Gakubu Section, Shikibu-shoku Department of the Imperial Household Agency (except for Western music).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Gakubu Section, Shikibu-shoku Department of the Imperial Household Agency, defines it as the numbers played by the Gakubu Section, Shikibu-shoku Department of the Imperial Household Agency (except for Western music).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>多くは器楽曲で宮廷音楽として継承されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most of them are instrumental music and inherited as court music.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most consist of instrumental music that has been inherited as court music.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most consist of instrumental music that has been inherited as court music.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>現在でも大規模な合奏形態で演奏される伝統音楽としては世界最古の様式である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has the world&apos;s oldest style as traditional music played in a large-scale ensemble form now.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is the world&apos;s oldest extant style of traditional music played in a large-scale ensemble.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is the world&apos;s oldest extant style of traditional music played in a large-scale ensemble.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>ただし、雅楽本来の合奏形態としては、応仁の乱以降、徳川幕府が楽師の末裔（楽家）をあつめて再編するまでは、100年以上断絶していたので、平安時代の形態をどこまで継承しているかは疑問である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the original ensemble form of Gagaku was discontinued for more than a hundred years until the Tokugawa Shogunate gathered the descendants of the musicians (Gaku families) and rebuilt it after the turmoil of the Onin war, and it is doubtful how precise the style in the Heian era is inherited.</e>
<cmt>楽家http://100.yahoo.co.jp/detail/楽人（がくにん）/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the original ensemble form of Gagaku was discontinued for more than 100 years until the Tokugawa shogunate gathered the descendants of the musicians (Gaku families) and rebuilt it after the turmoil of the Onin War, and it is doubtful how precise the style from the Heian period has been inherited.</e>
<cmt>grammaratructure</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the original ensemble form of Gagaku was discontinued for more than 100 years until the Tokugawa shogunate gathered the descendants of the musicians (Raku families) and rebuilt it after the turmoil of the Onin War, and it is doubtful how faithfully the style from the Heian period has been inherited.</e>
<cmt>Gaku→ Raku</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>篳篥のカタカナで記されている譜面を唱歌（しょうが メロディーを暗謡するために楽譜の文字に節をつけて歌う事）として歌うときにハ行の発音をファフィフフェフォと発音するなど16世紀以前の日本語の発音の特徴もそのまま伝えられており、全体的にもかなり忠実に再現されているのではないかということが推測される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The features of pronunciation of the Japanese language before the 16th century are passed on without change - the line of Ha is pronounced as fa, fi, fu, fe, fo, when singing the musical score of Hichiriki instrument written in katakana as Shoga (chanting the letters of the music note to recite the melody) for example, which implies that the whole style can be quite faithfully recreated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The features of pronunciation of the Japanese language before the sixteenth century are passed on without change: the line of Ha is pronounced as fa, fi, fu, fe, fo, when singing the musical score of the Hichiriki instrumentation written in katakana as &quot;Shoga,&quot; by chanting the letters of the music note to recite the melody for example, which implies that the whole style can be quite faithfully recreated.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The features of pronunciation of the Japanese language before the sixteenth century are passed on without change: the line of Ha is pronounced as fa, fi, fu, fe, fo, when singing the musical score of the Hichiriki instrument written in katakana as Shoga, for example by chanting the letters of the musical note to recite the melody, which implies that the whole style can be quite faithfully recreated.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot; 削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>楽琵琶の譜面のように漢字で記されるものは、中国の敦煌で発見された琵琶譜とも類似点が多く、さらに古い大陸から伝わった様式が多く継承されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The musical score written in Chinese characters such as that of Gakubiwa instrument has a lot of similarities to Biwa musical score discovered in Dun Huang in China, and a lot of older forms introduced from the continent are inherited.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The musical score written in Chinese characters, such as that of the Gakubiwa instrument, has many similarities to a biwa musical score discovered in Dun Huang, China, and several older forms introduced from the Asian continent have been inherited.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The musical score written in Chinese characters, such as that of the Gakubiwa instrument, has many similarities to a biwa musical score discovered in Dun Huang, China, and several older forms introduced from the Asian continent have been inherited.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>最も重要な史料としては、豊原統秋(1450~1512)が応仁の乱により雅楽等の記録が散逸することを憂えて著した『體源抄』（たいげんしょう）があげられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the most important historical data, &quot;Taigen-sho&quot; written by TOYOHARA no Muneaki (1450-1512), worrying about dissipation of the records of Gagaku and others due to the turmoil of the Onin war, can be cited.</e>
<cmt>http://100.yahoo.co.jp/detail/体源抄/http://dic.yahoo.co.jp/dsearch?enc=UTF-8&amp;p=體源抄&amp;dtype=0&amp;dname=0na&amp;stype=0&amp;pagenum=1&amp;index=12687611135500</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the most important historical data, &quot;Taigen-sho,&quot; written by Toyohara no Muneaki (1450-1512), which expresses concern about the dissipation of the records of Gagaku and others due to the turmoil of the Onin War, can be cited.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the most important historical data, &quot;Taigen-sho,&quot; written by TOYOHARA no Muneaki (1450-1512), which expresses concern about the dissipation of the records of Gagaku and others due to the turmoil of the Onin War, can be cited.</e>
<cmt>苗字を大文字に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>笙の楽家の統秋が、笙を中心とした雅楽、舞楽についての記録をまとめたもので、古い時代の雅楽についての貴重な記録である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is a valuable record of Gagaku in old days, which Muneaki from a Gaku family of Sho flute compiled the records of Gagaku mainly about Sho flute and Bugaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is a valuable record of Gagaku in the old days, in which Muneaki from a Gaku family of Sho flute compiled the records of Gagaku, mainly about the Sho flute and Bugaku.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is a valuable record of Gagaku in the old days, in which Muneaki from a Raku family of Sho flute compiled the records of Gagaku, mainly about the Sho flute and Bugaku (gagaku piece with dance).</e>
<cmt>Gaku→ Raku舞楽に (gagaku piece with dance)と補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>日本三大楽書の一。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It&apos;s one of the three biggest Gakusho books.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is one of the three largest Gakusho books.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is one of the three largest Gakusho (records on Gagaku and Bugaku) books.</e>
<cmt>楽書の補足として (records on Gagaku and Bugaku)　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>13巻22冊。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It consists of 13 volumes in 22 books.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It consists of 13 volumes in 22 books.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It consists of 13 volumes in 22 books.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>永正9年成立。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was completed in 1512.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was completed in 1512.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was completed in 1512.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="15">
<j>10世紀以前に中国、朝鮮半島、南アジアから伝わった儀式用の音楽がもとになっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is based on the music for ceremonies introduced from China, the Korean Peninsula and South Asia before the 10th century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is based on the ceremonial music introduced from China, the Korean Peninsula and South Asia prior to the tenth century.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is based on the ceremonial music introduced from China, the Korean Peninsula and South Asia prior to the tenth century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>中国において雅楽ya-yüeといえば儀式に催される音楽であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In China, Gagaku (ya-yüe) meant the music played in ceremonies, and Togaku music that is said to have been introduced from China and is presently played as Japanese Gagaku is believed to be based on the music played at a party called Engaku in Tang.</e>
<cmt>http://100.yahoo.co.jp/detail/唐楽/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In China, Gagaku (ya-yüe) meant the music played in ceremonies, while Togaku music, which is said to have been introduced from China and is presently played as Japanese Gagaku, is believed to have been based on the music played in Tang at a party called the Engaku.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In China, Gagaku (ya-y?e) meant the music played in ceremonies.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>しかしながら、現在日本の雅楽で演奏されている曲目のなかで中国から伝わったとされる唐楽は、唐の燕楽という宴会で演奏されていた音楽がもとになっているとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Togaku music, however, which is said to have been introduced from China and is presently played as Japanese Gagaku, is believed to be based on the music played in the Tang period at a party called the Engaku.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>日本と同様に中国の伝統音楽をとりいれたベトナムの雅楽（nhã nhạc）や大韓民国に伝わる国楽とは兄弟関係にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its relation of Vietnamese Gagaku (nhã nhạc) taking in Chinese traditional music as Japan did and National traditional music in South Korea is equivalent to brotherly relationship.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its relationship to the Vietnamese Gagaku (nhã nhạc), which assimilated Chinese traditional music as Japan did, as well as the national traditional music in South Korea, is equivalent to a brotherly relationship.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its relationship to the Vietnamese Gagaku (nhã nhạc), which assimilated Chinese traditional music as Japan did, as well as the national traditional music in South Korea, is equivalent to a brotherly relationship.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>楽曲のカテゴリーとしても、唐楽、高麗楽、林邑楽（チャンパの音楽）等、国際色豊かな名前が伝わっており、大陸の音楽伝来以前からの日本古来の音楽の要素も含まれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for categories of numbers, international names including Togaku, Komagaku and Rin&apos;yugaku (music of Champa) are brought over, and the elements of Japanese ancient music before introduction of the music from the continent are also included.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for the categories of numbers, international names including Togaku, Komagaku and Rin&apos;yugaku (music of Champa) have been brought over, and the elements of Japanese ancient music before the introduction of the music from the continent were included.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for the categories of numbers, international names including Togaku, Komagaku and Rinyugaku (music of Champa) have been brought over, and the elements of Japanese ancient music before the introduction of the music from the continent were included.</e>
<cmt>Rin&apos;yugaku→Rin&apos;yugaku</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="20">
<j>近代以前においては、最古の様式を伝える四天王寺の天王寺楽所（がくそ）（大阪市）、宮中の大内楽所（京都）、春日大社の南都楽所（奈良市）が三方楽所とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before the modern age, Tennoji gakuso Theater (Osaka City) with the oldest style, Ouchi gakuso Theater in the Imperial court (Kyoto) and Nanto gakuso Theater in Kasugataisha Shrine (Nara City) were called Sampo gakuso Theaters.</e>
<cmt>http://www.kasugataisha.or.jp/http://www.nantogakuso.jp/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before the modern age, the Tennoji gakuso Theater (Osaka City) with the oldest style, the Ouchi gakuso Theater in the Imperial Court (Kyoto) and the Nanto gakuso Theater in Kasugataisha Shrine (Nara City) were called Sampo gakuso theaters.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before the modern age, the Tennoji gakuso Theater in Shitenno-ji Temple (Osaka City) with the oldest style, the Ouchi gakuso Theater in the Imperial Court (Kyoto) and the Nanto gakuso Theater in Kasugataisha Shrine (Nara City) were called Sanpo gakuso theaters.</e>
<cmt>「四天王寺」を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>これらの楽所は近代になると東京に呼ばれ、現在の宮内庁の楽部の基礎となるが、それぞれの楽所の伝統はそれぞれの地で続いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These gakuso Theaters were called to Tokyo in the modern age and became the basis for the current Gakubu section of the Imperial Household Agency, but the tradition of each gakuso Theater has continued in each place.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These gakuso theater companies were called to Tokyo during the modern age and became the basis for the current Gakubu section of the Imperial Household Agency, but the tradition of each gakuso theater company has continued in each place.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These gakuso theater companies were called to Tokyo during the modern age and became the basis for the current Gakubu section of the Imperial Household Agency, but the tradition of each gakuso theater company has continued in each place.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="22">
<j>その他にも民謡や声明とも相互に影響がみられ、日本独自の様式が作られてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides, it has mutually affected Min&apos;yo and Shomyo, and Japanese original style has been made.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, it has mutually affected Min&apos;yo and Shomyo, and the Japanese original style has been created.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, it has mutually affected Minyo and Shomyo, and the Japanese original style has been created.</e>
<cmt>Min&apos;yo →Minyo に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>現在、100曲ほどが宮内庁式部職楽部に継承されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Presently, about 100 numbers are inherited in in Gakubu section, Shikibu-shoku department of the Imperial Household Agency.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Presently, about 100 numbers are inherited in the Gakubu section, Shikibu-shoku Department, of the Imperial Household Agency.</e>
<cmt>uppercase</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Presently, about 100 numbers are inherited in the Gakubu section, Shikibu-shoku Department, of the Imperial Household Agency.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>雅楽の曲の分類と演目</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Classification and Numbers of Gagaku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Classifications and Numbers of Gagaku</e>
<cmt>plural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Classifications and Numbers of Gagaku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="24">
<j>日本に古くから伝わるもの（国風歌舞 くにぶりのうたまい）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese traditional numbers (Kuniburi-no-utamai Dance)</e>
<cmt>http://www.gagaku.net/Gagaku/bugaku.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese traditional numbers (Kuniburi-no-utamai Dance)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese traditional numbers (Kuniburi-no-utamai Dance)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="25">
<j>神楽歌</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kagurauta song</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kagurauta song</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kagurauta song</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="26">
<j>人長舞（にんじょうまい）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ninjomai dance</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ninjomai dance</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ninjomai dance</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="27">
<j>東遊（あずまあそび）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Azuma-asobi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Azuma-asobi</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Azuma-asobi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="28">
<j>駿河舞</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Surugamai dance</e>
<cmt>http://www.gagaku.net/Gagaku/kuniburi.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Surugamai dance</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Surugamai dance</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="29">
<j>求子舞（もとめごまい）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Motomegomai dance</e>
<cmt>http://dic.yahoo.co.jp/dsearch?enc=UTF-8&amp;p=求&amp;dtype=0&amp;stype=0&amp;dname=0na&amp;pagenum=31&amp;index=20975618288900</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Motomegomai dance</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Motomegomai dance</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="30">
<j>大和歌（倭歌とも）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamatouta song (Waka)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yamatouta song (Waka)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamatouta song (Waka)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="31">
<j>大和舞（倭舞とも）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamatomai dace (Wabu)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yamatomai dace (Wabu)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamatomai dace (Wabu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="32">
<j>久米歌</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kumeuta song</e>
<cmt>http://www.amazon.co.jp/雅楽への招待/dp/B00005ELCA</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kumeuta song</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kumeuta song</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="33">
<j>久米舞</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kumemai dance</e>
<cmt>http://dic.yahoo.co.jp/dsearch?enc=UTF-8&amp;p=久米舞&amp;stype=0&amp;dtype=0</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kumemai dance</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kumemai dance</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="34">
<j>大歌（おおうた）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Outa song</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Outa song</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Outa song</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="35">
<j>五節舞（ごせちのまい）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gosechi-no-mai dance</e>
<cmt>http://100.yahoo.co.jp/detail/五節舞/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gosechi-no-mai dance</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gosechi-no-mai dance</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="36">
<j>誄歌（るいか）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ruika song</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ruika song</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ruika song</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="37">
<j>悠紀・主基（ゆき・すき）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yuki and Suki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yuki and Suki</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yuki and Suki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="38">
<j>歌詞はs国風歌舞を参照</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">See s; Kuniburi-no-utamai Dance for the lyrics</e>
<cmt>原文のsはWikisourceへのリンクを表しているようです。そのままにしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">See the section on Kuniburi-no-utamai Dance for the lyrics.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For the lyrics, see the section on Kuniburi-no-utamai dance.</e>
<cmt>s:を追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="39">
<j>日本国外から伝来したもの（これのみを雅楽とする見解もある。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Introduced numbers from abroad (there is an opinion to take only them as Gagaku.)</e>
<cmt>72の）をこちらにまとめました</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Introduced numbers from abroad (there is an opinion that they should be taken only as Gagaku)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Introduced numbers from abroad (there is an opinion that they should be taken only as Gagaku)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="40">
<j>左方舞・唐楽　………中国、天竺（インド）、林邑（南ベトナム）系のもの</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sahomai dance and Togaku music - from China, Tenjiku (India), Rin&apos;yu (South Vietnam)</e>
<cmt>http://www.gagaku.net/Gagaku/bugaku.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sahomai dance and Togaku music, from China, Tenjiku (India), Rin&apos;yu (South Vietnam)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sahomai dance and Togaku music, from China, Tenjiku (India), Rinyu (South Vietnam)</e>
<cmt>Rin&apos;yu→Rin&apos;yu</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="41">
<j>右方舞・高麗楽………朝鮮、渤海（中国の東北地方）系のもの</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Uhomai dance and Komagaku music - from Korea and Bokkai (Northeast region in China)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Uhomai dance and Komagaku music from Korea and Bokkai (northeastern region of China)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Uhomai dance and Komagaku music from Korea and Bokkai (northeastern region of China)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="42">
<j>これらには上記の作風を真似て日本で制作された曲（本邦楽）も含む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These include the numbers created in Japan (Japanese music) imitating these tunes above.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These include the numbers created in Japan (Japanese music) imitating the above tunes.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These include the numbers created in Japan (Japanese music) imitating the above tunes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="43">
<j>平安時代にできた歌曲（謡物 うたいもの）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Songs made in the Heian era (Utaimono)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Songs made during the Heian period (Utaimono)</e>
<cmt>usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Songs made during the Heian period (Utaimono)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="44">
<j>催馬楽（さいばら）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saibara</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saibara</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saibara</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="45">
<j>朗詠（ろうえい）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Roei</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Roei</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Roei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="46">
<j>今様（いまよう）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imayo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imayo</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imayo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="47">
<j>歌詞はs謡物を参照</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">See s: Utaimono for the lyrics</e>
<cmt>原文のsはWikisourceへのリンクを表しているようです。そのままにしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">See the section on Utaimono for the lyrics.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">See the section on Utaimono for the lyrics.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="25">
<sen id="48">
<j>※国風歌舞と謡物を古代歌謡と総称する場合がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">*Kuniburi-no-utamai dance and Utaimono may be generically called ancient songs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">*Kuniburi-no-utamai dance and Utaimono may be generically called ancient songs.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">*Kuniburi-no-utamai dance and Utaimono may be generically called ancient songs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>唐楽・高麗楽</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Togaku Music and Komagaku Music</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Togaku Music and Komagaku Music</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Togaku Music and Komagaku Music</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>演奏形態</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Performance Style</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Performance Style</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Performance Style</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="49">
<j>楽器のみの演奏を管絃と言い、主として屋内で演奏され、舞を伴う演奏を舞楽と言い、主として屋外で演奏される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Performance only with instruments is called Kangen music, which is mainly performed indoors, and performance with dance is called Bugaku, which is mainly performed outdoors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Performance exclusively with instruments is called Kangen music, which is mainly performed indoors, and performance with dance is called Bugaku, which is mainly performed outdoors.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Performance exclusively with instruments is called Kangen music, which is mainly performed indoors, and performance with dance is called Bugaku, which is mainly performed outdoors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>楽曲の様式</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Style of Music</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Style of Music</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Style of Music</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="50">
<j>曲には序（じょ）・破（は）・急（きゅう）があり、西洋音楽で言う第一楽章、第二楽章、第三楽章を言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A piece of music has Jo, Ha and Kyu, and they are equivalent to the first movement, the second movement and the third movement in the Western music.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A piece of music has Jo, Ha and Kyu, and respectively they are equivalent to the first, second and third movements in Western music.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A piece of music has Jo, Ha and Kyu, and respectively they are equivalent to the first, second and third movements in Western music.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="51">
<j>序は一番ゆったりした流れで、自由な緩急で旋律を演奏する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jo has the slowest rhythm, and its melody is played with free pace.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jo has the slowest rhythm, and its melody is played with a free pace.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jo has the slowest rhythm, and its melody is played with a free pace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="52">
<j>破はゆったりした流れだが、拍子が決められていて一小節を八拍として演奏する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ha has slow rhythm, but the tempo is fixed and eight beats to a bar.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ha has a slow rhythm, but the tempo is fixed and there are eight beats to a bar.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ha has a slow rhythm, but the tempo is fixed and there are eight beats to a bar.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="53">
<j>急はさっくりした流れとなり、拍子は一小節を四拍として演奏する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyu has faster rhythm, and four beats to a bar as its tempo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyu has a faster rhythm, and its temp is based on four beats to a bar.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyu has a faster rhythm, and its tempo is based on four beats to a bar.</e>
<cmt>tempoとしました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="54">
<j>ただし、演目によっては必ずしも急が速いテンポとはならないので、あくまでも一組の曲の3番目ぐらいの意味である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, some numbers don&apos;t necessarily have fast tempo in Kyu, so this means it is the third tempo of a piece of music.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, some numbers don&apos;t necessarily have a fast tempo in Kyu, so this means it is the third tempo of a piece of music.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, some numbers don&apos;t necessarily have a fast tempo in Kyu, so this means it is the third tempo of a piece of music.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="55">
<j>多くの場合、破のみあるいは急のみの演奏となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In most cases, Only Ha or Kyu is played.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In most cases, only Ha or Kyu is played.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In most cases, only Ha or Kyu is played.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>序・破・急を通しで演奏することを「一具」と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Playing Jo, Ha and Kyu through is called &quot;Ichigu.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Playing Jo, Ha and Kyu all the way through is called &quot;Ichigu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Playing Jo, Ha and Kyu all the way through is called &apos;Ichigu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>曲の調子</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tone of Music</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tone of Music</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tone of Music</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="57">
<j>曲の調子には何種類か有ったが、現在は、唐楽に6種類、高麗楽に3種類が残る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although there used to be several kinds as tones of music, there remains 6 kinds in Togaku music and 3 kinds in Komagaku music today.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although there used to be several kinds as tones of music, today there remain six kinds in Togaku music and three kinds in Komagaku music.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although there used to be several kinds as tones of music, today there remain six kinds in Togaku music and three kinds in Komagaku music.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="58">
<j>G呂旋双調（そうじょう）（春）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">G Ryosen Sojo tone (Spring)</e>
<cmt>http://100.yahoo.co.jp/detail/六調子/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">G Ryosen Sojo tone (Spring)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">G Ryosen Sojo tone (Spring)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="59">
<j>D呂旋壱越調（いちこつちょう）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">D Ryosen Ichikotsucho tone</e>
<cmt>http://100.yahoo.co.jp/detail/六調子/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">D Ryosen Ichikotsucho tone</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">D Ryosen Ichikotsucho tone</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="60">
<j>Am律旋黄鐘調（おうしきちょう）（夏）、高麗雙調（こまそうじょう）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Am Rissen Oshikicho tone (Summer) and Koma-sojo tone</e>
<cmt>http://100.yahoo.co.jp/detail/六調子/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Am Rissen Oshikicho tone (Summer) and Koma-sojo tone</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Am Rissen Oshikicho tone (Summer) and Koma-sojo tone</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="61">
<j>E呂旋太食調（たいしきちょう）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">E Ryosen Taishikicho tone</e>
<cmt>http://100.yahoo.co.jp/detail/六調子/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">E Ryosen Taishikicho tone</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">E Ryosen Taishikicho tone</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="62">
<j>Em律旋平調（ひょうじょう）（秋）、高麗壱越調（こまいちこつちょう）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Em Rissen Hyojo tone (Fall) and Koma-ichikotsucho tone</e>
<cmt>http://100.yahoo.co.jp/detail/六調子/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Em Rissen Hyojo tone (Fall) and Koma-ichikotsucho tone</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Em Rissen Hyojo tone (Fall) and Koma-ichikotsucho tone</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="63">
<j>Bm律旋盤渉調（ばんしきちょう）（冬）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bm Rissen Banshikicho tone (Winter)</e>
<cmt>http://100.yahoo.co.jp/detail/六調子/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bm Rissen Banshikicho tone (Winter)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bm Rissen Banshikicho tone (Winter)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="64">
<j>Fm律旋高麗平調（こまひょうじょう）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fm Rissen Koma-hyojo tone</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fm Rissen Koma-hyojo tone</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fm Rissen Koma-hyojo tone</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="65">
<j>（双調、壱越調、太食調は対応する洋音階の長音階と比べてシに相当する音が半音低い（ミクソリディア旋法と同様））</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(The note of Ti in Sojo, Ichikotsucho and Taishikicho tone is a half tone lower than the equivalent major scale of the Western musical scale. (Same as Mixolydian mode))</e>
<cmt>シhttp://www.esl-lounge.com/songs/song-do-re-mi.shtml</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(The note of Ti in Sojo, Ichikotsucho and Taishikicho tone is half a tone lower than the equivalent major scale of the Western musical scale (same as the Mixolydian mode).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(The note of the Ti in Sojo, Ichikotsucho and Taishikicho tone is a semi-tone lower than the equivalent major scale of the Western system (being equivalent to the Mixolydian mode)).</e>
<cmt>閉じ括弧追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="66">
<j>（黄鐘調、平調、盤渉調は対応する洋音階の自然短音階と比べてラに相当する音が半音高い（ドリア旋法と同様）、高麗平調は洋音階と同じ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(The note of La in Oshikicho, Hyojo and Banshikicho tone is a half tone higher than the equivalent natural minor scale of the Western musical scale. (Same as Dorian mode) The note of Koma-hyojo tone is same as the Western musical scale.)</e>
<cmt>ラhttp://www.esl-lounge.com/songs/song-do-re-mi.shtml</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(The note of La in Oshikicho, Hyojo and Banshikicho tone is half a tone higher than the equivalent natural minor scale of the Western musical scale (the same as the Dorian mode); the note of the Koma-hyojo tone is same as the Western musical scale.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(The note of La in the Oshikicho, Hyojo and Banshikicho tone is half a tone higher than the equivalent natural-minor scale of the Western musical scale (equivalent to the Dorian mode); the note of the Koma-hyojo tone is the same as the Western musical scale.)</e>
<cmt>閉じ括弧追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>渡し物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Watashimono</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Watashimono</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Watashimono</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="67">
<j>雅楽のレパートリーで親しまれている調子とは別の調子に乗っ取って演奏する事も可能である（「渡し物」と称する）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also possible to play Gagaku with another tone different form the familiar repertoire (this is called &quot;Watashimono&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also possible to play Gagaku with another tone that differs from the familiar repertoire (being called &quot;Watashimono&quot;).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also possible to play Gagaku with another tone that differs from the familiar repertoire (being called &apos;Watashimono&apos;).</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>その場合は西洋音楽の移調とは異なり、その調子に含まれる音階に沿って演奏されるため、メロディラインが若干変化する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this case, different from the transposition of the Western music, the melody line varies a little because of playing along with the musical scale included the tone.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this case, being different from the transposition of Western music, the melody line varies slightly because it is played along with the musical scale that constitutes the tune.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this case, being different from the transposition of Western music, the melody line varies slightly because it is played along with the musical scale that constitutes the tune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="69">
<j>『越天楽』を平調と盤渉調で聴き比べて例に挙げると、平調では「D-EEBBABEEEDE」となるが、これを西洋音楽の論理に乗っ取って完全5度下に移調すると「G-AAEEDEAAAGA」となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, when comparing &quot;Etenraku&quot; in Hyojo tone and Banshikicho tone, the Hyojo tone has &quot;D-EEBBABEEEDE,&quot; which would become &quot;G-AAEEDEAAAGA&quot; after transposing perfect fifth below on the principle of the Western music.</e>
<cmt>http://www.amazon.co.jp/雅楽への招待/dp/B00005ELCA</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, when comparing &quot;Etenraku&quot; in Hyojo tone and Banshikicho tone, the Hyojo tone has &quot;D-EEBBABEEEDE,&quot; which would become &quot;G-AAEEDEAAAGA&quot; after transposing a perfect fifth below on the principle of Western music.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, when comparing &quot;Etenraku&quot; in the Hyojo tone and Banshikicho tone, the Hyojo tone has &apos;D-EEBBABEEEDE,&apos; which would become &apos;G-AAEEDEAAAGA&apos; after transposing a perfect fifth below, based on the principle of Western music.</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>それに対して盤渉調では「G-AAFFEFBBBAB」となり、途中から完全4度下の移調になっている事が判る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Whereas, the Banshikicho tone has &quot;G-AAFFEFBBBAB,&quot; which shows its transposing perfect forth below from the middle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Whereas, the Banshikicho tone has &quot;G-AAFFEFBBBAB,&quot; which shows its transposing perfect fourth below, from the middle.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Whereas, the Banshikicho tone has &apos;G-AAFFEFBBBAB,&apos; which shows its transposition of a perfect fourth below, from the middle.</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>これは、一つには現代使用されている楽器が平調のためのもので、特に、主旋律を奏する篳篥の音域が狭いため、他の調子を演奏するときに、部分的に変えて演奏せざるを得ないためである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is partly because the instrumentals used today have Hyojo tone, and especially the Hichiriki instrument playing the main theme has a narrow range, which has no choice but to play by changing partly when playing in another tone.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is partly because the instruments used today have the Hyojo tone; particularly, the Hichiriki instrument playing the main theme has a narrow range, which has no choice but to play by changing partly when playing in another key.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is partly because the instruments used today have Hyojo tone; particularly, the Hichiriki instrument playing the main theme has a narrow range, which has no choice but to play by changing partly when playing in another tone.</e>
<cmt>instrumentals→instruments</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>このような部分で龍笛が補足的に本来の音に近いメロディーを吹くことになり、その部分がヘテロフォニーと呼ばれる、ずれの現象を伴って演奏されることにより、独特の味わいがでることとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In such a part, the melody close to the original sound is played collaterally by Ryuteki flute, and playing the part with the gap called heterophony creates unique taste.</e>
<cmt>龍笛http://100.yahoo.co.jp/detail/竜笛/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In such a part, the melody close to the original sound is played collaterally on the Ryuteki flute, and playing the part with the gap (called heterophony) creates a unique flavor.</e>
<cmt>usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In such a part, the melody close to the original sound is played collaterally on the Ryuteki flute, and playing the part with the gap (called heterophony) creates a unique flavor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="73">
<j>実際は、更に複雑で、黄鐘調や盤渉調の『越天楽』を、聞き慣れた平調と聞き比べると、同じ曲とは思えないほど、全く違う雰囲気になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is actually more complicated, and if you compare &quot;Etenraku&quot; with Oshikicho tone or Banshikicho tone with the familiar Hyojo tone, it has totally different atmosphere and no one could think it was the same number.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is actually more complicated, and if one compares &quot;Etenraku&quot; with the Oshikicho tone or compares Banshikicho tone with the familiar Hyojo tone, it has a totally different atmosphere and no one could think it was the same number.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is in fact more complicated, and if one compares &quot;Etenraku&quot; of the Oshikicho tone or of the Banshikicho tone with that of the familiar Hyojo tone, it has a totally different atmosphere and no one could think it was the same number.</e>
<cmt>一部修正actually →in factに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>譜面も別に作成され、唱歌も変わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The musical score is created separately and Shoga is also changed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The musical score is created separately, and Shoga is also changed.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The musical score is created separately, and Shoga is also changed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>『迦陵頻』に於いては、渡し物では曲名も『鳥』に変わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Karyobin,&quot; the name of the number is changed to &quot;Tori&quot; in Watashimono.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;Karyobin,&quot; the name of the number is changed to &quot;Tori&quot; in Watashimono.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;Karyobin,&quot; the name of the number is changed to &quot;Tori&quot; in Watashimono.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="76">
<j>実は、リズムも渡し物において変化することがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In fact, the rhythm may be also changed in Watashimono.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In fact, the rhythm may be also changed in Watashimono.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact, the rhythm may be also changed in Watashimono.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>管弦では只拍子（6拍子）で演奏される曲が舞楽になると夜多羅拍子（5拍子）となって変わってしまうものがいくつかある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kangen music, the some numbers played with Tada-byoshi beat (sextuple measure) are changed to Yatara-byoshi beat (quintuple measure) in Bugaku.</e>
<cmt>「管絃」となっているものと「管弦」となっているものがあるのですが、同じ意味として訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Kangen music, the some numbers played with Tada-byoshi beat (sextuple measure) are changed to Yatara-byoshi beat (quintuple measure) in Bugaku.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some numbers played with the Tada-byoshi beat (sextuple measure) in Kangen music are changed to the Yatara-byoshi beat (quintuple measure) in Bugaku music.</e>
<cmt>一部修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>一つの曲に使用される音列が変わったり、リズムが変わったりするところはインドの古典音楽のラーガマーリカ（ラーガを変えながら演奏）やターラマーリカ（リズムを変えながら演奏）等と共通するものがあり、特に雅楽で言う拍の概念はインドのターラの概念に近いものがあることは、小泉文夫の指摘するところである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Changing the tone row or rhythm used in a number is a feature in common with Ragamalika (playing with changing Raga) and Talamalika (playing with changing rhythm) in Indian ancient music, and especially the concept of Haku beat in Gagaku is close to that of Tala in India, which Fumio KOIZUMI points out.</e>
<cmt>ラーガマーリカhttp://www.ragamalika.net/ターラマーリカhttp://asgardprod.com/talamalika.htm</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Changing the tone row or rhythm used in a number is a feature in common with Ragamalika (playing with changing Raga) and Talamalika (playing with changing rhythm) in Indian ancient music; particularly, the concept of Haku beat in Gagaku is close to that of the Tala in India, which Fumio Koizumi points out.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Changing the tone row or the rhythm used in a number is a feature in common with Ragamalika (playing with changing ragas) and Talamalika (playing with changing rhythm) in Indian ancient music; particularly, the concept of Haku beat in Gagaku is close to that of the Tala in India, as noted by Fumio KOIZUMI.</e>
<cmt>苗字を大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>舞楽の種類</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinds of Bugaku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kinds of Bugaku</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinds of Bugaku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="79">
<j>広義には国風歌舞も含まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kuniburi-no-utamai Dance is included in a broad sense.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kuniburi-no-utamai Dance is included in a broad sense.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kuniburi-no-utamai Dance is included in a broad sense.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>以下の分類には例外や異論もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The classification below has exceptions and there are also different opinions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The classification below has exceptions, but there are also different opinions.</e>
<cmt>syntax</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The classification below has exceptions, but there are also different opinions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>左方と右方</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saho and Uho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saho and Uho</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saho and Uho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="81">
<j>唐を経由して伝来したものを左方舞（左舞）と言い、伴奏音楽を唐楽と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Bugaku introduced via Tang is called Sahomai dance (Samai dance), and its accompanying music is called Togaku music.</e>
<cmt>http://www.gagaku.net/Gagaku/bugaku.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Bugaku introduced via Tang is called Sahomai dance (Samai dance), and its accompanying music is called Togaku music.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Bugaku introduced via Tang is called Sahomai dance (Samai dance), and its accompanying music is called Togaku music.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="82">
<j>朝鮮半島（高麗）を経由して伝来したものを右方舞（右舞）と言い、伴奏音楽を高麗楽と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Bugaku introduced via the Korean Peninsula (Goryeo) is called Uhomai dance (Umai dance), and its accompanying music is called Komagaku music.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Bugaku introduced via the Korean Peninsula (Goryeo) is called Uhomai dance (Umai dance), and its accompanying music is called Komagaku music.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Bugaku introduced via the Korean Peninsula (Goryeo) is called Uhomai dance (Umai dance), and its accompanying music is called Komagaku music.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>平舞</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hiramai Dance</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hiramai Dance</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hiramai Dance</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="83">
<j>平舞（ひらまい）は、文舞（ぶんのまい）ともよばれ、武器などを持たずに舞う、穏やかな感じの舞。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hiramai Dance is also called Bunnomai dance, which is a gentle dance without having any arms.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hiramai dance is also called Bunnomai dance, which is a gentle dance that doesn&apos;t incorporate the arms.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hiramai dance is also called Bunnomai dance, which is a gentle dance that doesn&apos;t incorporate the arms.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="84">
<j>仮面を付けずに、常装束（襲装束・蛮絵装束）で、4人で舞う曲が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is danced with Tsune-Shozoku costume (Kasane-shozoku costume, Ban&apos;e-shozoku costume) and no mask, and most of them are performed by 4 dancers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is danced with Tsune-Shozoku costume (Kasane-shozoku costume, Ban&apos;e-shozoku costume) and no mask, and most often it is performed by four dancers.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is danced with Tsune-Shozoku costume (Kasane-shozoku costume, Bane-shozoku costume) and no mask, and most often it is performed by four dancers.</e>
<cmt>Ban&apos;e→Bane</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="85">
<j>例外として、『振鉾（えんぶ）』は鉾を持つ1人舞、『青海波』『迦陵頻』『胡蝶』は別装束、『安摩』『二ノ舞』は仮面を着け笏や桴を持つなど。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As exceptions, &quot;Embu&quot; is performed by 1 dancer with a pike, &quot;Seigaiha,&quot; &quot;Karyobin&quot; and &quot;Kocho&quot; are danced with Betsu-shozoku costume, and &quot;Ama&quot; and &quot;Ninomai&quot; are danced with wearing a mask and having Shaku and Bachi beater.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As exceptions, &quot;Embu&quot; is performed by one dancer with a pike, &quot;Seigaiha,&quot; &quot;Karyobin&quot; and &quot;Kocho&quot; are danced with Betsu-shozoku costume, and &quot;Ama&quot; and &quot;Ninomai&quot; are danced while wearing a mask and having Shaku and Bachi beaters.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As exceptions, &quot;Enbu&quot; is performed by one dancer with a pike, &quot;Seigaiha,&quot; &quot;Karyobin&quot; and &quot;Kocho&quot; are danced with Betsu-shozoku costume, and &quot;Ama&quot; and &quot;Ninomai&quot; are danced while wearing a mask and having Shaku and Bachi beaters.</e>
<cmt>Embu→Enbu</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>走舞</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hashirimai Dance</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hashirimai Dance</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hashirimai Dance</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="86">
<j>走舞（はしりまい）は勇猛な仮面を付け、桴や鉾を持ち、平舞に比して活発な動きで舞う勇壮な舞。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hashirimai Dance is a heroic dance with a valiant mask, Bachi beater and pike, having active movement compared to Hiramai dance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hashirimai dance is a heroic dance with a valiant mask, Bachi beater and pike, and it has active movement compared to Hiramai dance.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hashirimai dance is a heroic dance with a valiant mask, Bachi beater and pike, and it has active movement compared to Hiramai dance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="87">
<j>別装束（裲襠装束）で1名（『納曽利』は2名、又は1名）で舞う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is danced with Betsu-shozoku costume by 1 dancer (2 or 1 dancer for &quot;Nasori&quot;).</e>
<cmt>http://www.kyoto-ap.ne.jp/gagaku/bugaku/bu-top.htm</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is danced in the Betsu-shozoku costume by one dancer (either two dancers or one for &quot;Nasori&quot;).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is danced in the Betsu-shozoku costume by one dancer (either two dancers or one for &quot;Nasori&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>武舞</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bumai (Bunnomai) Dance</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bumai (Bunnomai) Dance</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bumai (Bunomai) Dance</e>
<cmt>(Bunomai)としました</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="88">
<j>武舞（ぶまい、ぶのまい）は、太刀・剣や鉾を持って舞う勇猛な舞。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bumai (Bunnomai) Dance is a valiant dance with a sword or pike.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bumai (Bunnomai) Dance is a valiant dance performed with a sword or a pike.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bumai (Bunomai) Dance is a valiant dance performed with a sword or a pike.</e>
<cmt>(Bunomai)としました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>「文舞」に対する言葉。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It&apos;s the word opposed to &quot;Bunnomai Dance.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It&apos;s the word opposed to &quot;Bunnomai Dance.&quot;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is the word opposed to &apos;Bunnomai Dance.&apos;</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="90">
<j>2名、又は4名で舞う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It&apos;s performed by 2 or 4 dancers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It&apos;s performed by either two or four dancers.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It&apos;s performed by either two or four dancers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="14">
<tit>
<j>童舞</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dobu (Warawamai) Dance</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dobu (Warawamai) Dance</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dobu (Warawamai) Dance</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="91">
<j>童舞（どうぶ、わらわまい）とは、元服前の男子が舞う舞楽のことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dobu (Warawamai) Dance is Bugaku performed by a boy before coming of age.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dobu (Warawamai) Dance is Bugaku performed by a boy who has not yet come of age.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dobu (Warawamai) Dance is Bugaku performed by a boy who has not yet come of age.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>近代以降は女子あるいは成人女性が舞う場合も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the modern age, it is performed by a girl or an adult woman in many cases.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the modern age it has in many cases been performed by a girl or an adult woman.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the modern age it has in many cases been performed by a girl or an adult woman.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>装束、仮面、化粧から童舞は特に関東地方においては希少価値がきわめて高い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dobu Dance has scarcity value especially in Kanto region due to its costume, mask and makeup.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Dobu dance has value as a rarity, particularly in the Kanto region, due to its costume, mask and makeup.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Dobu dance has value as a rarity, particularly in the Kanto region, due to its costume, mask and makeup.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="94">
<j>『迦陵頻』と『胡蝶』は童舞専用の曲であり、その他にも『蘭陵王 (雅楽)』や『納曽利』等、童舞のバージョンがある曲が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Karyobin&quot; and &quot;Kocho&quot; are only for Dobu Dance, and besides them, lots of numbers including &quot;Ranryo-o (Gagaku)&quot; and &quot;Nasori&quot; have the Dobu Dance version.</e>
<cmt>http://www.kyoto-ap.ne.jp/gagaku/bugaku/bu-ranryouou.htm</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Karyobin&quot; and &quot;Kocho&quot; are only for Dobu dance, and in addition many numbers, including &quot;Ranryo-o (Gagaku)&quot; and &quot;Nasori&quot; have the Dobu dance version.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Karyobin&quot; and &quot;Kocho&quot; are only for Dobu dance, and in addition many numbers, including &quot;Ranryo-o (Gagaku)&quot; and &quot;Nasori&quot; have the Dobu dance version.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>仮面を付けずに白塗りの厚化粧をするのが原則であるが、素顔のままや薄化粧の場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In principle, dancers wear heavy white makeup without a mask, but it may be a natural face or light makeup.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Principally, dancers wear heavy white makeup but no masks, insteading having a natural face or light makeup.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Principally, dancers wear heavy white makeup but no masks, insteading having a natural face or light makeup.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="15">
<tit>
<j>女舞</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Onnamai Dance</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Onnamai Dance</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Onnamai Dance</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="96">
<j>女舞（おんなまい）とは、妙齢の女性が舞う舞楽のことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Onnamai Dance is Bugaku performed by a woman of marriageable age.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Onnamai dance is Bugaku performed by a woman of marriageable age.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Onnamai dance is Bugaku performed by a woman of marriageable age.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>平安末期には中絶し、文献上のみの存在となってたが、1970年代に一部の団体が復活させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though this was interrupted in the end of the Heian era and existed only on documents, some groups brought it back in the 1970s.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though this was interrupted at the end of the Heian period and existed only in documents, some groups brought it back in the 1970s.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although this was interrupted at the end of the Heian period and existed only in documents, some groups brought it back in the 1970s.</e>
<cmt>Though →Although に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="98">
<j>『柳花苑』は元々は女舞専用の曲だったが長年管弦のみだった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Ryukaen&quot; was originally only for Onnamai Dance and had only Kangen music for years.</e>
<cmt>http://www.kyoto-ap.ne.jp/gagaku/bugaku/bu-top.htm</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Ryukaen&quot; was originally only for Onnamai dance and had only Kangen music for years.</e>
<cmt>lowercase</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Ryukaen&quot; was originally only for Onnamai dance and had only Kangen music for years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>その他にも『桃李花』や『五常楽』等に、女舞のバージョンがあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides this, some numbers including &quot;Torika&quot; and &quot;Gojoraku&quot; had the Onnamai Dance version.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides this, some numbers including &quot;Torika&quot; and &quot;Gojoraku&quot; had the Onnamai dance version.</e>
<cmt>lowercase</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides this, some numbers including &quot;Torika&quot; and &quot;Gojoraku&quot; had the Onnamai dance version.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>仮面を付けずに白塗りの厚化粧をするのが原則であるが、素顔のままや薄化粧の場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In principle, dancers wear heavy white makeup without a mask, but it may be a natural face or light makeup.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Principally, dancers wear heavy white makeup but no masks, insteading having a natural face or light makeup.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Principally, dancers wear heavy white makeup but no masks, insteading having a natural face or light makeup.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="16">
<tit>
<j>有名曲</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Famous Numbers</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Famous Numbers</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Famous Numbers</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="101">
<j>※は林邑八楽、及び、その番舞</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">* shows Rin&apos;yu hachigaku and its Tsugaimai Dance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">* shows Rin&apos;yu hachigaku and its Tsugaimai dance.</e>
<cmt>lowercase</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">* shows Rinyu hachigaku and its Tsugaimai dance.</e>
<cmt>Rin&apos;yu →Rinyu に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="17">
<tit>
<j>唐楽（左方）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Togaku Music (Saho)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Togaku Music (Saho)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Togaku Music (Saho)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="102">
<j>※太字は舞楽曲</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">*The boldface shows Bugaku music.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">*The boldface shows Bugaku music.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">*The boldface shows Bugaku music.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="103">
<j>双調　春庭楽、柳花苑（女人舞楽近年復活）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sojo tone: Shundeiraku, Ryukaen (recently restored female Bugaku)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sojo tone: Shundeiraku, Ryukaen (recently restored female Bugaku)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sojo tone: Shundeiraku, Ryukaen (recently restored female Bugaku)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="104">
<j>壱越調　春鶯囀、賀殿、酒胡子、武徳楽、新羅陵王、北庭楽、承和楽、迦陵頻※、蘭陵王 (雅楽)※、胡飲酒※、菩薩 (雅楽)※、安摩（二ノ舞）※</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ichikotsucho tone: Shunnoden, Katen, Shukoshi, Butoraku, Shinraryo-o, Hokuteiraku, Showaraku, Karyobin*, Ranryo-o (Gagaku)*, Konju*, Bosatsu (Gagaku)*, Ama (Ninomai)*</e>
<cmt>http://www.amazon.co.jp/雅楽への招待/dp/B00005ELCAhttp://www.kyoto-ap.ne.jp/gagaku/bugaku/bu-top.htm</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ichikotsucho tone: Shunnoden, Katen, Shukoshi, Butoraku, Shinraryo-o, Hokuteiraku, Showaraku, Karyobin*, Ranryo-o (Gagaku)*, Konju*, Bosatsu (Gagaku)*, Ama (Ninomai)*</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ichikotsucho tone: Shunnoden, Katen, Shukoshi, Butoraku, Shinraryo-o, Hokuteiraku, Showaraku, Karyobin*, Ranryo-o (Gagaku)*, Konju*, Bosatsu (Gagaku)*, Ama (Ninomai)*</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="105">
<j>黄鐘調　喜春楽、桃李花、央宮楽、感城楽、西王楽、河南浦</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oshikicho tone: Kishunraku, Torika, Oguraku, Kanjoraku, Seioraku, Kanampu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oshikicho tone: Kishunraku, Torika, Oguraku, Kanjoraku, Seioraku, Kanampu</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oshikicho tone: Kishunraku, Torika, Oguraku, Kanjoraku, Seioraku, Kanampu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="106">
<j>太食調　抜頭※（舞は左右双方にあり）、散手、太平楽（朝小子、武昌楽、合歓塩）、傾盃楽、賀王恩、打毬楽、還城楽（左右双方にあり）、庶人三台、輪鼓褌脱、長慶子</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taishikicho tone: Bato* (having dance both in Saho and Uho), Sanju, Taiheiraku (Chokoshi, Bushoraku, Gakkaen), Keibaraku, Kao-on, Dakyuraku, Genjoraku (both in Saho and Uho), Soninsandai, Rinkokotatsu, Chogeishi</e>
<cmt>http://www.amazon.co.jp/雅楽への招待/dp/B00005ELCAhttp://gagaku-dvd.net/vol3.htmhttp://www.kyoto-ap.ne.jp/gagaku/bugaku/bu-dakyuu.htm</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taishikicho tone: Bato* (having dance both in Saho and Uho), Sanju, Taiheiraku (Chokoshi, Bushoraku, Gakkaen), Keibaraku, Kao-on, Dakyuraku, Genjoraku (both in Saho and Uho), Soninsandai, Rinkokotatsu, Chogeishi</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taishikicho tone: Bato* (having dance both in Saho and Uho), Sanju, Taiheiraku (Chokoshi, Bushoraku, Gakkaen), Keibaraku, Kao-on, Dakyuraku, Genjoraku (both in Saho and Uho), Soninsandai, Rinkokotatsu, Chogeishi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="107">
<j>平調　万歳楽、三台塩、裹頭楽、甘州 (雅楽)、五常楽、越天楽、勇勝、慶徳 (雅楽)、王昭君 (雅楽)、老君子、小娘子、皇麞、夜半楽、扶南 (雅楽)、春楊柳、想夫恋 (雅楽)（相府蓮）、陪臚※（唐楽だが舞は右方）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hyojo tone: Manzairaku, Sandaien, Katoraku, Kanshu (Gagaku), Gojoraku, Etenraku, Yojo, Keitoku (Gagaku), Oshokun (Gagaku), Rokunshi, Koroji, Ojo, Yahanraku, Funan (Gagaku), Shunyoryu, Sofuren (Gagaku) (Soburen), Bairo* (Togaku music with dance in Uho)</e>
<cmt>http://www.terakoya.com/gonshiki/gagaku/kaisetsu2.htmlhttp://www.kyoto-ap.ne.jp/gagaku/bugaku/bu-katouraku.htmhttp://www.amazon.co.jp/雅楽への招待/dp/B00005ELCA</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hyojo tone: Manzairaku, Sandaien, Katoraku, Kanshu (Gagaku), Gojoraku, Etenraku, Yojo, Keitoku (Gagaku), Oshokun (Gagaku), Rokunshi, Koroji, Ojo, Yahanraku, Funan (Gagaku), Shunyoryu, Sofuren (Gagaku) (Soburen), Bairo* (Togaku music with dance in Uho)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hyojo tone: Manzairaku, Sandaien, Katoraku, Kanshu (Gagaku), Gojoraku, Etenraku, Yojo, Keitoku (Gagaku), Oshokun (Gagaku), Rokunshi, Koroji, Ojo, Yahanraku, Funan (Gagaku), Shunyoryu, Sofuren (Gagaku) (Soburen), Bairo* (Togaku music with dance in Uho)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="108">
<j>盤渉調　蘇合香 (雅楽)、万秋楽※、秋風楽、輪台、青海波、採桑老、剣気褌脱、蘇莫者、白柱、千秋楽 (雅楽)、竹林楽</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Banshikicho tone: Soko (Gagaku), Manjuraku*, Shufuraku, Rindai, Seigaiha, Saisoro, Kenkikotatsu, Somakusha, Hakuchu, Senshuraku (Gagaku), Chikuringaku</e>
<cmt>http://www.amazon.co.jp/雅楽への招待/dp/B00005ELCA</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Banshikicho tone: Soko (Gagaku), Manjuraku*, Shufuraku, Rindai, Seigaiha, Saisoro, Kenkikotatsu, Somakusha, Hakuchu, Senshuraku (Gagaku), Chikuringaku</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Banshikicho tone: Soko (Gagaku), Manjuraku*, Shufuraku, Rindai, Seigaiha, Saisoro, Kenkikotatsu, Somakusha, Hakuchu, Senshuraku (Gagaku), Chikuringaku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="18">
<tit>
<j>高麗楽（右方）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Komagaku music (Uho)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Komagaku music (Uho)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Komagaku music (Uho)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="109">
<j>※全曲が舞楽曲</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">*All the numbers are Bugaku music.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">*All the numbers are Bugaku music.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">*All the numbers are Bugaku music.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="110">
<j>高麗双調　地久、白浜 (雅楽)、登天楽、蘇志摩利</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koma-sojo tone: Chikyu, Hohin (Gagaku), Totenraku, Soshimari</e>
<cmt>http://www.kyoto-ap.ne.jp/gagaku/bugaku/bu-top.htmhttp://www.kyoto-ap.ne.jp/gagaku/bugaku/bu-sosimari.htm</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koma-sojo tone: Chikyu, Hohin (Gagaku), Totenraku, Soshimari</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koma-sojo tone: Chikyu, Hohin (Gagaku), Totenraku, Soshimari</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="111">
<j>高麗壱越調　新鳥蘇、古鳥蘇、進走禿（進宿徳）、退走禿（退宿徳）、納曽利※、胡蝶※、長保楽、延喜楽、蘇利古※、綾切、新靺鞨、敷手、皇仁庭、貴徳、狛鉾、八仙 (雅楽)、仁和楽、胡徳楽、埴破、進蘇利古</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koma-ichikotsucho tone: Shintoriso, Shinsotoku, Taisotoku, Nasori*, Kocho*, Choboraku, Engiraku, Soriko*, Ayakiri, Shinmaka, Shikite, Onnintei, Kitoku, Komaboko, Hassen (Gagaku), Ninnaraku, Kotokuraku, Hannari, Shinsoriko</e>
<cmt>進走禿（進宿徳）、退走禿（退宿徳）の（）内は同じ読みのため、訳出せず。http://www.terakoya.com/gonshiki/gagaku/gakkyoku.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koma-ichikotsucho tone: Shintoriso, Shinsotoku, Taisotoku, Nasori*, Kocho*, Choboraku, Engiraku, Soriko*, Ayakiri, Shinmaka, Shikite, Onnintei, Kitoku, Komaboko, Hassen (Gagaku), Ninnaraku, Kotokuraku, Hannari, Shinsoriko</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koma-ichikotsucho tone: Shintoriso, Shinsotoku, Taisotoku, Nasori*, Kocho*, Choboraku, Engiraku, Soriko*, Ayakiri, Shinmaka, Shikite, Onnintei, Kitoku, Komaboko, Hassen (Gagaku), Ninnaraku, Kotokuraku, Hannari, Shinsoriko</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="112">
<j>高麗平調　林歌</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koma-hyojo tone: Ringa</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koma-hyojo tone: Ringa</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koma-hyojo tone: Ringa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="19">
<tit>
<j>雑楽</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zogaku Music</e>
<cmt>雑楽http://www.d2.dion.ne.jp/~kaz/gagaku/zougaku/index.htm</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zogaku Music</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zogaku Music</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="113">
<j>振鉾（新楽乱声（唐楽）と高麗乱声（高麗楽）を同時に演奏、左方と右方の舞人が登場）、壹鼓、一曲</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Empu (Shingakuranjo (Togaku music) and Komaranjo (Komagaku music) are played simultaneously with dancers both in Saho and Uho), Ikko, Ikkyoku</e>
<cmt>振鉾、壹鼓、一曲http://www.d2.dion.ne.jp/~kaz/gagaku/zougaku/index.htm</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Empu (Shingakuranjo (Togaku music) and Komaranjo (Komagaku music) are played simultaneously with dancers both in Saho and Uho), Ikko, Ikkyoku</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Empu (Shingakuranjo (Togaku music) and Komaranjo (Komagaku music) are played simultaneously with dancers both in Saho and Uho), Ikko, Ikkyoku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="20">
<tit>
<j>番舞一覧</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">List of Tsugaimai Dance</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">List of Tsugaimai Dance</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">List of Tsugaimai Dance</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="114">
<j>平安以降、唐楽の曲目と高麗楽の曲目が番舞（つがいまい）としてセットで上演される場合が多くなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Heian era, a Togaku music number and a Komagaku music number are played by the set as a Tsugaimai Dance in many cases.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Heian period, a Togaku music number and a Komagaku music number were in many cases played in a set as a Tsugaimai dance.</e>
<cmt>lowercase</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Heian period, a Togaku music number and a Komagaku music number were in many cases played in a set as a Tsugaimai dance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>その一覧を示す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The list is shown below.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The list is shown below.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The list is shown below.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="21">
<tit>
<j>雅楽に使われる楽器</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Instruments Played in Gagaku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Instruments Played in Gagaku</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Instruments Played in Gagaku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="116">
<j>管絃の合奏の中心となる楽器は、一般的に三管、三鼓、両絃の8種類といわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The major instruments of Kangen music played in concert are generally 8 kinds including Three Winds, Three Drums and Two Strings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The major instruments of Kangen music played in concert generally consisted of eight kinds, including three winds, three drums and two strings.</e>
<cmt>lowercase</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The major instruments of Kangen music played in concert generally consisted of eight kinds, including three winds, three drums and two strings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="117">
<j>笙（鳳笙）、篳篥（ひちりき）、龍笛（横笛、おうてき）または高麗笛（こまぶえ）または神楽笛</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sho flute (Hosho), Hichiriki instrument, Ryuteki flute (Oteki) or Komabue flute or Kagurabue flute</e>
<cmt>http://www.gagaku.net/Gakki/kan.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sho flute (Hosho), Hichiriki instrument, Ryuteki flute (Oteki) or Komabue flute or Kagurabue flute</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sho flute (Hosho), Hichiriki instrument, Ryuteki flute (Oteki) or Komabue flute or Kagurabue flute</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="118">
<j>楽太鼓または和太鼓（鼉太鼓、だだいこ）、鉦鼓または大鉦鼓、羯鼓（鞨鼓）または三ノ鼓</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gakudaiko drum or Wadaiko drum (Dadaiko), Shoko drum or Oshoko drum, Kakko drum or Santsuzumi drum</e>
<cmt>http://dic.yahoo.co.jp/dsearch?enc=UTF-8&amp;p=大鉦鼓&amp;dtype=0&amp;dname=0na&amp;stype=0&amp;pagenum=1&amp;index=02711502190000</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gakudaiko drum or Wadaiko drum (Dadaiko), Shoko drum or Oshoko drum, Kakko drum or Santsuzumi drum</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gakudaiko drum or Wadaiko drum (Dadaiko), Shoko drum or Oshoko drum, Kakko drum or Santsuzumi drum</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="119">
<j>楽琵琶、楽箏または和琴（倭琴）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gakubiwa instrument, Gakuso koto or Wagon koto.</e>
<cmt>楽筝http://100.yahoo.co.jp/detail/唐楽/和琴http://100.yahoo.co.jp/detail/和琴/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gakubiwa instrument, Gakuso koto or Wagon koto</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gakubiwa instrument, Gakuso koto or Wagon koto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="120">
<j>これらの楽器は大変高価であるが、練習用に、やや安価な楽器（プラスチック製）もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These instruments are very expensive, but there are also less expensive ones (made of plastic) for practices.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These instruments are very expensive, but there are less expensive ones (made of plastic) available for practice.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These instruments are very expensive, but there are less expensive ones (made of plastic) available for practice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="121">
<j>その他に笏拍子などが使われることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides these, other instruments such as Shaku byoshi drum may be used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides these, other instruments such as the Shaku byoshi drum may be used.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides these, other instruments such as the Shaku byoshi drum may be used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="122">
<j>笙は簧（リード）に結露すると音程が狂うので、演奏の合間に必ず暖めておく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since a Sho flute would be out of tune if the reed built up condensation, it is always warmed up between performances.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because a Sho flute would be out of tune if the reed were to build up condensation, it is always warmed up between performances.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because a Sho flute would be out of tune if the reed were to build up condensation, it is always warmed up between performances.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="123">
<j>このため夏でも火鉢や電熱器をそばに置く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, even in the summer, a brazier or an electric heater is put beside it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, even in the summer a brazier or an electric heater is placed beside it.</e>
<cmt>usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, even in the summer a brazier or an electric heater is placed beside it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="124">
<j>篳篥は舌（リード）を柔らかくするため、緑茶に浸ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A Hichiriki instrument is put into green tea so that the reed gets soft.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A Hichiriki instrument is put into green tea so that the reed gets soft.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A Hichiriki instrument is put into green tea so that the reed gets soft.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="22">
<tit>
<j>三管の説明</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">About Three Winds</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">About Three Winds</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">About Three Winds</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="125">
<j>三管については次のような説明がなされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Three Winds are described as follows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Three Winds are described as follows:</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Three Winds are described as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="126">
<j>「天から差し込む光」を表す笙。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sho flute to express &quot;light thrown from the sky.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sho flute to express &quot;light thrown from the sky.&quot;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sho flute to express &apos;the light thrown from the sky.&apos;</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="127">
<j>「天と地の間を縦横無尽に駆け巡る龍」を表す龍笛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryuteki flute to express &quot;a dragon running around freely between the sky and the earth.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryuteki flute to express &quot;a dragon running around freely between the sky and the earth.&quot;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryuteki flute to express &apos;a dragon running around freely between the sky and the earth.&apos;</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="128">
<j>「地上にこだまする人々の声」を表す篳篥。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hichiriki instrument to express &quot;people&apos;s voices echoing on the earth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hichiriki instrument to express &quot;people&apos;s voices echoing on the earth.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hichiriki instrument to express &apos;people&apos;s voices echoing on the earth.&apos;</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="129">
<j>この3つの管楽器をあわせて「三管」と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These three wind instruments are collectively called &quot;Three Winds.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These three wind instruments are collectively called &quot;Three Winds.&quot;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These three wind instruments are collectively called the &apos;Three Winds.&apos;</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="130">
<j>合奏時の主な役割は、主メロディを篳篥が担当する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for the major roles when playing in concert, a Hichiriki instrument takes charge of the main melody.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for the major roles when playing in concert, a Hichiriki instrument takes charge of the main melody.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for the major roles when playing in concert, a Hichiriki instrument takes charge of the main melody.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="131">
<j>篳篥は音程が不安定な楽器である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A Hichiriki instrument is an instrument with unstable musical intervals, and the difference of a major second with the same finger position can be changed by the way of closing the lips.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A Hichiriki instrument is an instrument with unstable musical intervals, and the difference of a major second with the same finger position can change based on the way one closes the lips.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A Hichiriki instrument is an instrument with unstable musical intervals.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="132">
<j>同じ指のポジションで長2度くらいの差は唇の締め方で変わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Differences can be made to a major second with the same finger positions by tightening ones lips.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="133">
<j>演奏者は、本来の音程より少し下から探るように演奏を始めるため、その独特な雰囲気が醸しだされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A player starts to play as if searching from a little below the original musical interval, which creates its unique atmosphere.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A player starts to play as if searching from just below the original musical interval, which creates a unique atmosphere.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A player starts to play as if searching from just below the original musical interval, which creates a unique atmosphere.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="134">
<j>また、その特徴を生かして、「塩梅」といわれる、いわゆるこぶしのような装飾的な演奏法が行われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Using the feature allows the decorative style of play such as tremolo called &quot;Embai.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The use of this feature facilitates a decorative style of play, such as the tremolo called &apos;Embai.&apos;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The use of this feature facilitates a decorative style of play, such as the tremolo called &apos;Enbai.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Embai→Enbaiに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="135">
<j>龍笛は篳篥が出ない音をカバーしたりして、旋律をより豊かにする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A Ryuteki flute enriches the melody by covering the sound a Hichiriki instrument cannot make.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A Ryuteki flute enriches the melody by covering the sound a Hichiriki instrument isn&apos;t capable of producing.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A Ryuteki flute enriches the melody by covering the sound a Hichiriki instrument isn&apos;t capable of producing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="136">
<j>笙は独特の神々しい音色で楽曲を引き締める役割もあるが、篳篥や龍笛の演奏者にとっては、息継ぎのタイミングを示したり、テンポを決めたりといった役割もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A Sho flute has a role to spice up the tune with its unique divine sound, and also roles to show the timing of breathing or to decide the tempo for players of a Hichiriki instrument and a Ryuteki flute.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A Sho flute has the role of spicing up the tune with its uniquely divine sound, and it has the role of showing the timing of breathing or deciding the tempo for the players of the Hichiriki instrument and Ryuteki flute.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A Sho flute has the role of spicing up the tune with its uniquely divine sound, and it has the role of showing the timing of breathing or deciding the tempo for the players of the Hichiriki instrument and Ryuteki flute.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="137">
<j>笙は日本の音楽の中ではめずらしく和声（ハーモニー）を醸成する楽器である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A Sho flute is an instrument to create harmony, unusual for a Japanese music.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A Sho flute is an instrument used to create harmony, which is unusual for Japanese music.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A Sho flute is an instrument used to create harmony, which is unusual for Japanese music.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="138">
<j>基本的には6つの音（左手の親指、人差し指、中指、薬指と右手の親指と人差し指を使用）から構成され、4度と5度音程を組み合わせた20世紀以降の西欧音楽に使用されるような複雑なものであるが、調律法が平均律ではないので協和音と不協和音というより、むしろ澄んだ音色に聞こえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Basically, it is composed of 6 sounds (using the left thumb, index finger, middle finger, ring finger and the right thumb and index finger), which is complicated with the mixture of the fourth and fifth interval used in the Western music after the 20th century, but it sounds clear rather than consonance and dissonance because the musical tuning is not equal temperament.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Basically, it is composed of six sounds (using the left thumb, index finger, middle finger, ring finger and the right thumb and index finger), which is complicated by the mixture of the fourth and fifth intervals used in Western music since the twentieth century, but it sounds clear as opposed to consonant or dissonant because the musical tuning is not equal temperament.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Basically, it is composed of six sounds (using the left thumb, index finger, middle finger, ring finger and the right thumb and index finger), which is complicated by the mixture of the fourth and fifth intervals used in Western music since the twentieth century, but it sounds clear as opposed to consonant or dissonant because the musical tuning is not equal temperament.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="139">
<j>クロード・ドビュッシーの和音は笙の影響がみられるという説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The harmony of Claude Debussy is said to be influenced by Sho flute.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The harmony of Claude Debussy is said to be influenced by the Sho flute.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The harmony of Claude DEBUSSY is said to have been influenced by the Sho flute.</e>
<cmt>苗字を大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="23">
<tit>
<j>三鼓の説明</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">About Three Drums</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">About Three Drums</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">About Three Drums</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="140">
<j>「三鼓」とは、羯鼓（又は三ノ鼓）、鉦鼓、和太鼓であるが、羯鼓の演奏者が洋楽の指揮者の役割を担い、全体のテンポを決めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Three Drums&quot; refer to Kakko drum (or Santsuzumi drum), Shoko drum and Wadaiko drum, and the player of Kakko drum takes a role equivalent to a conductor in the Western music and decides the overall tempo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Three Drums&quot; refer to Kakko drum (or Santsuzumi drum), Shoko drum and Wadaiko drum; the player of Kakko drum takes a role equivalent to a conductor in Western music and decides the overall tempo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &apos;Three Drums&apos; refers to the Kakko drum (or Santsuzumi drum), Shoko drum and Wadaiko drum; the player of the Kakko drum takes a role equivalent to a conductor in Western music, deciding the overall tempo.</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="24">
<tit>
<j>使われる楽器</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Instruments to Use</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Instruments to Be Used</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Instruments to Be Used</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="141">
<j>国風歌舞</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kuniburi-no-utamai Dance</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kuniburi-no-utamai Dance</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kuniburi-no-utamai Dance</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="142">
<j>笏拍子、和琴、篳篥、神楽笛（倭舞、神楽）、高麗笛（東遊）、龍笛（五節舞）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shaku byoshi drum, Wagon koto, Hichiriki instrument, Kagurabue flute (Wabu, Kagura), Komabue flute (Azuma-asobi), Ryuteki flute (Gosechi-no-mai Dance)</e>
<cmt>http://100.yahoo.co.jp/detail/五節舞/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shaku byoshi drum, Wagon koto, Hichiriki instrument, Kagurabue flute (Wabu, Kagura), Komabue flute (Azuma-asobi), Ryuteki flute (Gosechi-no-mai Dance)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shaku byoshi drum, Wagon koto, Hichiriki instrument, Kagurabue flute (Wabu, Kagura), Komabue flute (Azuma-asobi), Ryuteki flute (Gosechi-no-mai Dance)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="143">
<j>管弦（管絃舞楽）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kangen music (Kangen Bugaku)</e>
<cmt>http://dic.yahoo.co.jp/dsearch?enc=UTF-8&amp;p=%00管&amp;dtype=0&amp;stype=0&amp;dname=0ss&amp;pagenum=11&amp;index=104122100000</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kangen music (Kangen Bugaku)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kangen music (Kangen Bugaku)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="144">
<j>羯鼓、楽太鼓、鉦鼓、笙、篳篥、龍笛、楽琵琶、楽箏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kakko drum, Gakudaiko drum, Shoko drum, Sho flute, Hichiriki instrument, Ryuteki flute, Gakubiwa instrument, Gakuso koto</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kakko drum, Gakudaiko drum, Shoko drum, Sho flute, Hichiriki instrument, Ryuteki flute, Gakubiwa instrument, Gakuso koto</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kakko drum, Gakudaiko drum, Shoko drum, Sho flute, Hichiriki instrument, Ryuteki flute, Gakubiwa instrument, Gakuso koto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="145">
<j>唐楽（左方）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Togaku music (Saho)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Togaku music (Saho)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Togaku music (Saho)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="146">
<j>羯鼓、和太鼓、大鉦鼓、笙、篳篥、龍笛</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kakko drum, Wadaiko drum, Oshoko drum, Sho flute, Hichiriki instrument, Ryuteki flute</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kakko drum, Wadaiko drum, Oshoko drum, Sho flute, Hichiriki instrument, Ryuteki flute</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kakko drum, Wadaiko drum, Oshoko drum, Sho flute, Hichiriki instrument, Ryuteki flute</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="147">
<j>高麗楽（右方）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Komagaku music (Uho)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Komagaku music (Uho)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Komagaku music (Uho)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="148">
<j>三ノ鼓、和太鼓、大鉦鼓、篳篥、高麗笛</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Santsuzumi drum, Wadaiko drum, Oshoko drum, Hichiriki instrument, Komabue flute</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Santsuzumi drum, Wadaiko drum, Oshoko drum, Hichiriki instrument, Komabue flute</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Santsuzumi drum, Wadaiko drum, Oshoko drum, Hichiriki instrument, Komabue flute</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="149">
<j>催馬楽、今様</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saibara, Imayo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saibara, Imayo</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saibara, Imayo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="150">
<j>笏拍子、笙、篳篥、龍笛、楽琵琶、楽箏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shaku byoshi drum, Sho flute, Hichiriki instrument, Ryuteki flute, Gakubiwa instrument, Gakuso koto</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shaku byoshi drum, Sho flute, Hichiriki instrument, Ryuteki flute, Gakubiwa instrument, Gakuso koto</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shaku byoshi drum, Sho flute, Hichiriki instrument, Ryuteki flute, Gakubiwa instrument, Gakuso koto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="151">
<j>朗詠</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Roei</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Roei</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Roei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="152">
<j>笏拍子、笙、篳篥、龍笛</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shaku byoshi drum, Sho flute, Hichiriki instrument, Ryuteki flute</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shaku byoshi drum, Sho flute, Hichiriki instrument, Ryuteki flute</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shaku byoshi drum, Sho flute, Hichiriki instrument, Ryuteki flute</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="153">
<j>浦安の舞（参考）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Urayasu-no-mai Dance (Reference)</e>
<cmt>http://dic.yahoo.co.jp/dsearch?enc=UTF-8&amp;p=浦安の舞&amp;dtype=0&amp;dname=0ss&amp;stype=0&amp;pagenum=1&amp;index=101779400000</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Urayasu-no-mai Dance (Reference)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Urayasu-no-mai Dance (Reference)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="154">
<j>笏拍子、又は楽太鼓（一般の和太鼓もok）、和琴、又は楽箏（生田流等の箏もok）、篳篥、神楽笛</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shaku byoshi drum or Gakudaiko drum (general Wadaiko drum is also ok), Wagon koto or Gakuso koto (So instrument of Ikutaryu or other schools is ok), Hichiriki instrument, Kagurabue flute</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shaku byoshi drum or Gakudaiko drum (general Wadaiko drum is also ok), Wagon koto or Gakuso koto (the So instrument of Ikutaryu or other schools is ok), Hichiriki instrument, Kagurabue flute</e>
<cmt>grammar, article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shaku byoshi drum or Gakudaiko drum (general Wadaiko drum is also ok), Wagon koto or Gakuso koto (the So instrument of Ikutaryu or other schools is ok), Hichiriki instrument, Kagurabue flute</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="25">
<tit>
<j>装束、仮面、化粧</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Costume, Mask and Makeup</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Costume, Mask and Makeup</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Costume, Mask and Makeup</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="155">
<j>楽人の正式な装束は衣冠、又は狩衣が原則であるが、明治以降に楽部が直垂を制定して以降は神社仏閣や民間の伝承団体でも直垂を着用する場合が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though the official costume of a player is Ikan or Kariginu in principle, shrines and temples, and private tradition groups mostly use Hitatare, after the Gakubu section assigned Hitatare after the Meiji era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the official costume of a player is principally Ikan or Kariginu, shrines and temples, as well as private tradition groups mostly use Hitatare, in keeping with the Gakubu section assigned to Hitatare after the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the official costume of a player is principally Ikan (costume worn by court nobles and officers when they are on duty at the Imperial Palace) or Kariginu (informal clothes worn by court nobles and officers), shrines and temples, as well as private tradition groups mostly use Hitatare (a kind of traditional Japanese clothes), in keeping with the Gakubu section assigned to Hitatare after the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>衣冠 (costume worn by court nobles and officers when they are on duty at the Imperial Palace)、　狩衣 (informal clothes worn by court nobles and officers)、　直垂 (a kind of traditional Japanese clothes)　以上の説明を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="156">
<j>直垂の場合、生地は海松色（みるいろ）と呼ばれる、見る角度によって色彩が変わる美しいものが使われる場合が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for Hitatare, beautiful fabric called Miruiro color, which changes its colors when looked at from different angles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for Hitatare, a beautiful fabric called Miruiro is used, which changes its colors when seen from different angles.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for Hitatare, a beautiful fabric called Miruiro is used, which changes its colors when seen from different angles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="157">
<j>略式では比較的安価な白衣に差袴（神職の普段着と同様）、稀に夏には統一の浴衣（俗楽の浴衣ざらいに倣う）となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On informal occasions, relatively reasonable Byakue and Sashiko (same as ordinary clothes of a Shinto priest) are used, and unified Yukata, Japanese summer kimono (following Zokugaku&apos;s run-through in Yukata) are used in the Summer in rare cases.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On informal occasions, relatively reasonable Byakue and Sashiko (equivalent to the ordinary clothes of a Shinto priest) are used, but in rare cases unified Yukata (Japanese summer kimono, following Zokugaku&apos;s run-through in Yukata) are used in the summer.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On informal occasions, relatively reasonable Byakue and Sashiko (equivalent to the ordinary clothes of a Shinto priest) are used, but in rare cases unified Yukata (Japanese summer kimono, following Zokugaku&apos;s run-through in Yukata) are used in the summer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="158">
<j>装束を統一しない場合、僧職は法衣、女性は女性神職装束や巫女装束、一般的な和服の場合がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When not unifying the costumes, a clerical robe may be used for priesthood, and woman&apos;s Shinto priest costume, mediumistic costume, or general kimono may be used for a woman.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When not unifying the costumes, a clerical robe may be used for priesthood, and a woman&apos;s Shinto priest costume, mediumistic costume or general kimono may be used for a woman.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When not unifying the costumes, a clerical robe may be used for priesthood, and a woman&apos;s Shinto priest costume, mediumistic costume or general kimono may be used for a woman.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="159">
<j>通常、化粧しない（女性は薄化粧の場合有り、三管の場合は口紅を塗らない）が、舞人と兼任の場合や、祭り等によっては厚化粧の場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Generally, makeup is not applied (women may have light makeup, but no lipstick in case of Three Winds), but heavy makeup may be applied in case of also dancing or for some festivities.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Generally, makeup is not applied (women may have light makeup, but no lipstick in the case of the Three Winds), but heavy makeup may be applied in the event there will be dancing or certain festivities.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Generally, makeup is not applied (women may have light makeup, but no lipstick in the case of the Three Winds), but heavy makeup may be applied in the event there will be dancing or certain festivities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="160">
<j>舞人の装束は国風歌舞や謡物では白系、唐楽では赤系、高麗楽では緑、茶、黄褐色系が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The costumes of dancers are mostly white for Kuniburi-no-utamai and Utaimono, red for Togaku music, and green, brown and brownish-yellow for Komagaku music.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The costumes of dancers are mostly white for Kuniburi-no-utamai and Utaimono, red for Togaku music, and green, brown and brownish-yellow for Komagaku music.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The costumes of dancers are mostly white for Kuniburi-no-utamai and Utaimono, red for Togaku music, and green, brown and brownish-yellow for Komagaku music.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="161">
<j>それぞれに、特定の曲目専用の装束（常装束）と、複数の曲目で共通に使う装束（常装束、等）がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Respectively, there are costumes only for a certain number (Betsu-shozoku costumes） and ones commonly used for more than one number (Tsune-Shozoku costumes, etc.).</e>
<cmt>常装束が2回出てきますが、Wikiを見るとはじめは「別装束」で次は「襲装束」（常装束と同じ）となっています。意味合いから考え、はじめを「別装束」で訳しました。原文は未訂正のまま。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Respectively, there are costumes only for a certain number (Betsu-shozoku costumes) and ones commonly used for more than one number (Tsune-Shozoku costumes, etc.).</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Respectively, there are costumes only for a certain number (Betsu-shozoku costumes) and those commonly used for more than one number (Tsune-shozoku costumes, etc.).</e>
<cmt>shozokuは小文字で統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="162">
<j>曲によっては指定の仮面を着用する場合がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Specified masks may be worn depending on numbers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Specified masks may be worn, depending on the numbers.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Specified masks may be worn, depending on the numbers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="163">
<j>仮面を付けない曲の場合や、仮面が指定された曲を女性や少年少女が舞う場合は仮面を付けずに素顔のままか、化粧（団体によっては歌舞伎舞踊と同様の舞台化粧）をする場合がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In case of numbers without masks, or numbers with masks assigned and played by a woman, or boy or girl, they may be performed with natural face without masks, or with makeup (stage makeup same as Kabuki Buyo Dance depending on groups).</e>
<cmt>http://www.nihonjiten.com/monogatari/data_4.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the case of numbers without masks, or numbers with masks assigned and played by a woman, or a boy or girl, they may be performed with a natural, unmasked face or with makeup (the same stage makeup as for Kabuki Buyo dance, depending on the group).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the case of numbers without masks, or numbers with masks assigned and played by a woman, or a boy or girl, they may be performed with a natural, unmasked face or with makeup (the same stage makeup as for Kabuki Buyo dance, depending on the group).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="164">
<j>尚、これらの正式な装束、仮面（特に別装束、とりわけ、童舞の装束）は大変高価であるため、これらを購入できる神社仏閣、団体は大規模な神社、寺院や財政に余裕がある団体に限定される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In fact, these official costumes and masks (especially Betsu-shozoku costumes, and costumes for Dobu Dance above all) are very expensive, so the shrines and temples, and groups that can afford to buy them are limited to big temples and shrines, and financially well-of groups.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In fact, these official costumes and masks (especially Betsu-shozoku costumes, and costumes for Dobu Dance above all) are very expensive, so the shrines, temples and groups that can afford to buy them are limited to large temples and shrines, or to groups that are financially prosperous.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact, these official costumes and masks (especially Betsu-shozoku costumes, and costumes for Dobu Dance above all) are very expensive, so the shrines, temples and groups that can afford to buy them are limited to large temples and shrines, or to groups that are financially prosperous.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="165">
<j>又、童舞以外の殆どの装束は成人男性、又は女性用に仕立てられ、又、重量があること、仮面を付けた場合に視野が制約されること、長く伸びてる部分（裾、裳、等）があるため、振り付けに関しても伸びてる部分の捌き方等の難易度が高いこと、又、東日本においては伝承団体のメンバーの殆どが成人であることと財政に余裕がない場合が多いことから少年少女の育成に消極的な場合が多く、育成してる場合でも略式なら安価な装束で済む管弦と『浦安の舞』等にとどまり、舞楽は行わないか、行う場合でも成人に限られる場合が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, most costumes except for Dobu Dance are made for adult men or women, they are heavy, the eyesight is limited when wearing a mask, the difficulty level in choreography such as handling the long part of the costume (hem, ancient skirt, etc.) is high, and the tradition groups in East Japan have mostly adult members and cannot afford, so the development of children is not active enough, even when developing them, it is limited to Kangen music or &quot;Urayasu-no-mai Dance&quot; for which reasonable costumes can be used in an informal style, and Bugaku is not performed or limited to adults in most cases.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, most costumes except for Dobu dance are made for adult men or women: they are heavy, the eyesight is limited when wearing a mask, the difficulty level in choreography such as handling the long part of the costume (hem, ancient skirt, etc.) is high, and the tradition groups in East Japan have mostly adult members and cannot afford, so the development of children is not active enough, even when developing them; it is limited to Kangen music or &quot;Urayasu-no-mai Dance&quot; for which reasonable costumes can be used in an informal style, and Bugaku is not performed or limited to adults in most cases.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, most costumes except for those of Dobu dance are made for adult men or women: they are heavy, the eyesight is limited when wearing a mask, the difficulty level in choreography such as handling the long part of the costume (hem, ancient skirt, etc.) is high; however, the traditional groups in East Japan have mostly adult members and cannot afford, so the development of children&apos;s participation is not active enough; even when developing them, it is limited to Kangen music or &quot;Urayasu-no-mai Dance&quot; for which reasonable costumes can be used in an informal style, and in most cases Bugaku is not performed or is limited to adults.</e>
<cmt>;の場所を変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="166">
<j>従って、童舞は特に関東地方においては希少価値がきわめて高い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, Dobu Dance has scarcity value especially in Kanto region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the Dobu dance has value as a rarity, particularly in the Kanto region.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the Dobu dance has value as a rarity, particularly in the Kanto region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="26">
<tit>
<j>伶楽 （一度廃絶し、近年復元された雅楽）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reigaku (Gagaku eliminated once and restored in recent years)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reigaku (Gagaku, which was once eliminated but has been restored in recent years)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reigaku (Gagaku, which was once eliminated but has been restored in recent years)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="167">
<j>現在、国立劇場の企画の一環として、廃絶された楽器や楽曲を復元する試みが行われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Presently, as one of the projects of the National Theater, there are attempts to restore eliminated instruments and numbers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Currently, as one of the projects of the National Theater, there are attempts to restore the instruments and numbers that had been eliminated.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Currently, as one of the projects of the National Theater, there are attempts to restore the instruments and numbers that had been eliminated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="168">
<j>これを総称して、「伶楽」（れいがく）ないし「遠楽」（えんがく）と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is generically called &quot;Reigaku&quot; or &quot;Engaku.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is generically called &quot;Reigaku&quot; or &quot;Engaku.&quot;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Generically, this is called &apos;Reigaku&apos; or &apos;Engaku.&apos;</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="169">
<j>芝祐靖が音楽監督を務める伶楽舎が演奏活動を行っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reigakusha of which Sukeyasu SHIBA is the musical director has performance activities.</e>
<cmt>http://reigakusha.com/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reigakusha, of which Sukeyasu Shiba is the musical director, has performance activities.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reigakusha, of which Sukeyasu SHIBA is the musical director, has performance activities.</e>
<cmt>苗字を大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="27">
<tit>
<j>復元された楽器</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Instruments Restored</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Instruments Restored</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Instruments Restored</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="170">
<j>箜篌、五弦琵琶、阮咸、排簫、尺八（近世邦楽の尺八と異なる）、竽、方響など</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kugo instrument, Gogenbiwa instrument, Genkan instrument, Haisho flute, Shakuhachi flute (different from Shakuhachi in modern time Japanese music), Sho flute, Hokyo percussion, etc.</e>
<cmt>http://hibiki.shinnyo-en.or.jp/hokyo.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kugo instrument, Gogenbiwa instrument, Genkan instrument, Haisho flute, Shakuhachi flute (different from Shakuhachi in modern time Japanese music), Sho flute, Hokyo percussion, etc.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kugo instrument, Gogenbiwa instrument, Genkan instrument, Haisho flute, Shakuhachi flute (different from Shakuhachi in modern time Japanese music), Sho flute, Hokyo percussion, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="171">
<j>明治時代にも正倉院にのこる残欠を参考に箜篌や五弦琵琶などを復元したことがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Meiji era, Kugo instruments and Gogenbiwa instruments were also restored, referring to the remains kept in Shosoin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Meiji period, Kugo instruments and Gogenbiwa instruments were also restored, with reference to the remaining pieces kept in Shosoin.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Meiji period, Kugo instruments and Gogenbiwa instruments were also restored, with reference to the remaining pieces kept in Shosoin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="172">
<j>江戸時代からとだえることなくつたわる漆工芸や螺鈿の技術等により工芸品としては高度なものであるが、弦の張力は演奏に耐えるものではなく、演奏のための楽器としての復元は昭和になってからである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though they were sophisticated as craftworks thanks to the techniques of lacquer craftworks and mother-of-pearl works continually handed down from the Edo era, the tension of the strings cannot withstand performance, and the restoration of instruments for performance was done after the Showa era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though they were sophisticated as craftworks thanks to the techniques of lacquer craftworks and mother-of-pearl works successively handed down from the Edo period, the tension of the strings cannot withstand performance, and the restoration of instruments for performance was done after the Showa era.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although they were sophisticated as craftworks thanks to the techniques of lacquer craftworks and mother-of-pearl works successively handed down from the Edo period, the tension of the strings cannot withstand performance, and the restoration of instruments for performance was done after the Showa period.</e>
<cmt>periodThough →Althoughに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="28">
<tit>
<j>近代における雅楽の派生</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Derivation of Gagaku in the Modern Age</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Derivation of Gagaku in the Modern Age</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Derivation of Gagaku in the Modern Age</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="173">
<j>雅楽器を用いた宗教音楽、祭典楽などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are religious music and festivity music using Gagaku instruments.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gagaku instruments are used in the music of religious rites and festivities.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gagaku instruments are used in the music of religious rites and festivities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="174">
<j>「浦安の舞」「悠久の舞」「豊栄の舞」「朝日舞」など近代に作られた神楽（s近代に作られた神楽）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kagura made after the modern age including &quot;Urayasu-no-mai Dance,&quot; &quot;Yukyu-no-mai Dance,&quot; &quot;Toyosaka-no-mai Dance&quot; and &quot;Asahimai Dance&quot; (s: Kagura made after the modern age)</e>
<cmt>原文のsはWikisourceへのリンクを表しているようです。そのままにしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kagura made after the modern age including &quot;Urayasu-no-mai Dance,&quot; &quot;Yukyu-no-mai Dance,&quot; &quot;Toyosaka-no-mai Dance&quot; and &quot;Asahimai Dance&quot; (s: Kagura made after the modern age)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kagura made after the modern age, including &apos;Urayasu-no-mai Dance,&apos; &apos;Yukyu-no-mai Dance,&apos; &apos;Toyosaka-no-mai Dance&apos; and &apos;Asahimai Dance&apos; (Kagura made after the modern age)</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="175">
<j>真如苑の古楽器復元し仏教声明と融合した「千年の響き」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Sennen-no-hibiki&quot; mixed with Buddhism Shomyo after restoring ancient instruments of Shinnyo-en</e>
<cmt>真如苑http://www.shinnyo-en.or.jp/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Sennen-no-hibiki&quot; mixed with Buddhism Shomyo after restoring the ancient instruments of Shinnyo-en</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sennen-no-hibiki&apos; mixed with Buddhism Shomyo after restoring the ancient instruments of Shinnyo-en</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="176">
<j>岡山県（黒住教、金光教）発祥の、雅楽と能楽・俗楽の要素が合わさった「吉備楽」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kibigaku&quot; born in Okayama Prefecture (Kurozumikyo sect and Konkokyo sect), with the elements of Gagaku, and Nogaku and Zokugaku mixed</e>
<cmt>http://www.kurozumikyo.com/http://www.konkokyo.or.jp/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kibigaku,&quot; born in Okayama Prefecture (Kurozumikyo sect and Konkokyo sect), with the elements of Gagaku, and Nogaku and Zokugaku mixed</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kibigaku,&apos; born in Okayama Prefecture (Kurozumikyo sect and Konkokyo sect), with the elements of Gagaku, and Nogaku and Zokugaku mixed</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="177">
<j>金光教楽長尾原音人によって創始された金光教祭典楽の「中正楽」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Chuseigaku&quot; as festivity music of Konkokyo sect created by Otondo OHARA, master of the music section of Konkokyo sect</e>
<cmt>http://tengaku.konko.jp/item/chusei/chusei.htmhttp://www.konkokyo.or.jp/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Chuseigaku&quot; as festivity music of Konkokyo sect created by Otondo Ohara, master of the music section of the Konkokyo sect</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chuseigaku&apos; as festivity music of Konkokyo sect created by Otondo OHARA, master of the music section of the Konkokyo sect</e>
<cmt>I have added a single quotation mark at the start of the sentence but because of the way that Excel works, you cannot see it on the sheet itself, only in the formula bar at the top of the page. To make this visible, you have to add a second single quotation mark but this might cause problems later so I have not done this.</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="29">
<tit>
<j>現代雅楽</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Modern Gagaku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Modern Gagaku</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Modern Gagaku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="178">
<j>国立劇場では、雅楽の編成のための新しい作品を現代の国内外の作曲家に委嘱し、演奏している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The National Theater asks new works for organizing Gagaku to composers of the day from home and abroad, and performs them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The National Theater requests new works from domestic and foreign composers of the day for the organization of Gagaku, and performs them.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The National Theater requests new works from domestic and foreign composers of the day for the organization of Gagaku, and performs them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="179">
<j>国立劇場以外の民間でも同様の試みが行われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Private sectors other than the National Theater also make similar attempts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Private sectors other than the National Theater make similar efforts.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Private sectors other than the National Theater make similar efforts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="180">
<j>特に武満徹の「秋庭歌一具」（1973年 - 1979年）は優秀な解釈により頻繁に演奏され、現代雅楽の欠かせないレパートリーとなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially &quot;Shuteiga-ichigu&quot; (1973-1979) by Toru TAKEMITSU is frequently played due to its excellent interpretation, and this is an essential number for modern Gagaku.</e>
<cmt>http://100.yahoo.co.jp/detail/武満徹/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Particularly, &quot;Shuteiga-ichigu&quot; (1973-1979), by Toru Takemitsu, is frequently played due to its excellent interpretation, and this is an essential number for modern Gagaku.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Particularly, &apos;Shuteiga-ichigu&apos; (1973-1979), by Toru TAKEMITSU, is frequently played due to its excellent interpretation, and this is an essential number for modern Gagaku.</e>
<cmt>括弧修正 苗字を大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="181">
<j>ポップスの分野では篳篥の東儀秀樹が、篳篥の音色を生かしたポピュラー音楽の編曲および自作を演奏し、メディアにも頻繁に出演するなど、雅楽のイメージを一新し一般に紹介している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the field of pops, Hideki TOGI, a Hichiriki player plays arranged and original popular music using Hichiriki sound and frequently comes out in the media, and he has renewed the image of Gagaku and introduced it to the public.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the field of pops, Hideki Togi, a Hichiriki player plays arranged and original popular music using the Hichiriki sound and frequently comes out in the media; he has renewed the image of Gagaku and introduced it to the public.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the field of pops, Hideki TOGI, a Hichiriki player, plays arranged and original popular music using the Hichiriki sound and frequently comes out in the media; he has renewed the image of Gagaku and introduced it to the public.</e>
<cmt>苗字を大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="182">
<j>また東儀の他に、雅楽器も用いた演奏集団、音楽理論の分析・研究に重点を置き現代的雅楽曲を創作する、芸術団体などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other than TOGI, there exist a performance group using Gagaku instruments as well, and an art group that creates modern Gagaku music focusing analysis and study of musical theories.</e>
<cmt>ひとつの文なので、次の370とあわせて訳出。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other than Togi, there exists a performance group using Gagaku instruments as well, and there is an art group that creates modern Gagaku music focusing on the analysis and study of musical theories.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other than TOGI, there is also a performance group that uses Gagaku instruments and an art group that creates modern Gagaku music with a focus on the analysis and study of music theory, etc.</e>
<cmt>there exists---と and there is を,(コンマ）で羅列するのではなく、一つの文にまとめた方が分りやすい。「など」 が訳されていない。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="183">
<j>詳しくは現代雅楽の項を参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">See further details in the section of Modern Gagaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">See further details in the &quot;Modern Gagaku&quot; section.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">See further details in the &quot;Modern Gagaku&quot; section.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="30">
<tit>
<j>雅楽にまつわる言葉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Expressions Related to Gagaku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Expressions Related to Gagaku</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Expressions Related to Gagaku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="184">
<j>塩梅（あんばい）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ambai</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ambai</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Anbai</e>
<cmt>Ambai→Anbai</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="185">
<j>西洋音楽で言うところのメリスマ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is equivalent to melisma in the Western music.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is equivalent to melisma in Western music.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is equivalent to melisma in Western music.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="186">
<j>近似する音程へ徐々に移行する一種のポルタメント。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a kind of portamento, which gradually moves to a close interval.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a kind of portamento that gradually moves to a close interval.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a kind of portamento that gradually moves to a closer interval.</e>
<cmt>close→closer</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="187">
<j>ゆっくりと慎重に音程を変更するところから、具合を測りつつ物事を進めるさまを表す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the state of changing the intervals slowly and carefully, it is used to mean a state of doing things with checking doneness.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the state of changing the intervals slowly and carefully, it is used to mean a state of doing things with checking the degree of completion.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the state of changing the intervals slowly and carefully, it is used to mean a state of doing things with checking the degree of completion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="188">
<j>八多羅（やたら）、八多羅滅多羅（やたらめったら）、滅多（めった）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yatara, Yataramettara and Metta</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yatara, Yataramettara and Metta</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yatara, Yataramettara and Metta</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="189">
<j>現在は矢鱈と書くがこれは明治時代に夏目漱石によって作られた当て字で、本来は雅楽の拍子を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is written as 矢鱈 in Chinese character today, which is a phonetic equivalent Soseki NATSUME made, but this originally indicates a beat of Gagaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is written as 矢鱈 in Chinese character today, which is a phonetic equivalent Soseki Natsume made, but this originally indicates a beat of Gagaku.</e>
<cmt>lowercase</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is written as 矢鱈 in Chinese characters today, which is a phonetic equivalent Soseki NATSUME made, but this originally indicates a beat of Gagaku.</e>
<cmt>苗字を大文字に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="190">
<j>2拍子と3拍子のリズム細胞を繋げる変拍子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is an irregular meter connecting rhythm cells of binary measure and triple measure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is an irregular meter connecting the rhythmic cells of binary and triple measures.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is an irregular meter connecting the rhythmic cells of binary and triple measures.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="191">
<j>転じて、リズムが合わずめちゃくちゃで大袈裟な身振りや様を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Accordingly, it indicates an exaggerated gesture or state, that is out of rhythm and insane.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Accordingly, it indicates an exaggerated gesture or state that is out of rhythm and therefore insane.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Accordingly, it indicates an exaggerated gesture or state that is out of rhythm and therefore insane.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="192">
<j>多羅（たら）はサンスクリットのターラ（リズム）に由来する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tara derives from Tala (rhythm) of Sanskrit.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tara is derived from Tala (rhythm) of Sanskrit.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tara is derived from Tala (rhythm) of Sanskrit.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="193">
<j>打ち合わせ（うちあわせ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Uchiawase (meeting)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Uchiawase (meeting)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Uchiawase (meeting)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="194">
<j>管楽器同士で練習をした後、打楽器を交えて、最終的なリハーサルをしたことから。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It stems from the final rehearsal with percussions after a practice of wind instruments.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It stems from the final rehearsal with percussion, after the practice of wind instruments.</e>
<cmt>comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It stems from the final rehearsal with percussion, after the practice of wind instruments.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="195">
<j>野暮（やぼ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yabo (rudeness)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yabo (rudeness)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yabo (rudeness)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="196">
<j>笙の17本の管のうち「也」と「毛」の音が使用されないことから。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It stems from not using the sound of &quot;Ya&quot; and &quot;Bo&quot; out of 17 tubes of a Sho flute.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It stems from not using the sound of &quot;Ya&quot; and &quot;Bo&quot; out of 17 tubes of a Sho flute.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It stems from not using the sound of &apos;Ya&apos; and &apos;Bo&apos; out of the 17 tubes of a Sho flute.</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="197">
<j>様になる（さま-）／左舞なる（さまい-）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Samaninaru/Samainaru (looking good)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Samaninaru/Samainaru (looking good)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Samaninaru/Samainaru (looking good)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="198">
<j>左舞（さまい）が上達することから。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By extension of proficiency of Samai Dance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By extension of proficiency of the Samai dance</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By extension of proficiency of the Samai dance</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="199">
<j>上手い（うまい）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Umai (skillful)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Umai (skillful)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Umai (skillful)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="200">
<j>右舞（うまい）から。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By extension of Umai Dance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By extension of the Umai dance</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By extension of the Umai dance</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="201">
<j>二の舞を舞う（にのまいをまう）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ninomai-wo-mau</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ninomai-wo-mau</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ninomai-wo-mau</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="202">
<j>「二ノ舞」は「安摩」とセットの番舞一覧、ただし例外的にどちらも左方に属し、装束のみ二ノ舞は右方の装束。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Ninomai&quot; is a Tsugaimai Dance performed together with &quot;Ama,&quot; but exceptionally, both of them belong to Saho, and only for costumes, Uho costumes are used in Ninomai.</e>
<cmt>原文にある「一覧」というのはWikiページにはなく、訳出しませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Ninomai&quot; is a Tsugaimai dance performed together with &quot;Ama,&quot; but exceptionally both of them belong to Saho, and only for costumes; however, Uho costumes are used in Ninomai.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ninomai&apos; is a Tsugaimai dance performed together with &apos;Ama,&apos;; exceptionally, both of them belong to Saho but only for costumes, while Uho costumes are used in Ninomai.</e>
<cmt>括弧修正一部修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="203">
<j>安摩が上手に舞った後、二ノ舞は真似て舞おうとするが、上手に出来ずに滑稽な動きになるという設定。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The situation is, after Ama is performed well, Ninomai dancers try to imitate the performance, but they cannot perform well and make a funny movement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The situation is, after Ama is performed well, Ninomai dancers try to imitate the performance, but they cannot perform well and make funny movements.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The situation is, after Ama is performed well, Ninomai dancers try to imitate the performance, but they cannot perform well and make funny movements.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="204">
<j>転じて他人の成功 を真似て失敗すること。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Accordingly, it indicates failure after imitating somebody else&apos;s success.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Accordingly, it indicates failure after imitating somebody else&apos;s success.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Accordingly, it indicates failure after imitating somebody else&apos;s success.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="205">
<j>他人の失敗 を繰り返す例に使われるのは本来は誤用。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is principally incorrect to mean repeating somebody else&apos;s mistake.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is principally incorrect to mean repeating somebody else&apos;s mistake.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is principally incorrect to mean repeating somebody else&apos;s mistake.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="206">
<j>呂律（ろれつ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Roretsu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Roretsu</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Roretsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="207">
<j>古くは「りょりつ」とも読んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was also read as &quot;Ryoritsu&quot; in old times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was also read as &quot;Ryoritsu&quot; in old times.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was also read as &apos;Ryoritsu&apos; in old times.</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="208">
<j>呂と律は雅楽における曲調の大分類であり（上述の曲の調子を参照）、呂律は広い意味での曲の調子を意味する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryo and Ritsu are large classifications of Music tones in Gagaku (See Tone of Music described above), Roretsu means tone of music in a broad sense.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryo and Ritsu are large classifications of Music tones in Gagaku (See &quot;Tone of Music&quot; as described above), Roretsu means the tone of music in a broad sense.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryo and Ritsu are large classifications of musical tones in Gagaku (See &quot;Tone of Music&quot; as described above), Roretsu means the tone of music in a broad sense.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="209">
<j>呂旋法を前提に作られた曲を律旋法で詠おうとすると調子がおかしくなることから、音の調子が合わない（転じて詠唱や講演でうまく言葉が続けて発音できない）ことを「呂律が回らない」と表現するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The expression &quot;Roretsu-ga-mawaranai&quot; has been used when trying to perform a number made for Ryosenpo with Rissenpo, the tone becomes strange, and the notes become off key (accordingly, when words cannot be continuously pronounced well at a speech or a chant.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The expression &quot;Roretsu-ga-mawaranai&quot; has been used when trying to perform a number made for Ryosenpo with Rissenpo, the tone becomes strange and the notes become off-key (accordingly, when words cannot be continuously pronounced well at a speech or a chant).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The expression &apos;Roretsu-ga-mawaranai&apos; has been used when trying to perform a number made for Ryosenpo with Rissenpo; the tone becomes strange and the notes become off-key (accordingly, when words cannot be continuously pronounced well in the context of a speech or a chant).</e>
<cmt>括弧修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="210">
<j>二の句を継げない（にのくをつげない）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ninoku-wo-tsugenai (to be struck dumb）</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ninoku-wo-tsugenai (to be dumbstruck）</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ninoku-wo-tsugenai (to be dumbstruck）</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="211">
<j>朗詠で、一の句から二の句に移る時、急に高音となるため歌うのが難しいことから。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It stems from the difficulty to sing when moving from the first phrase to the second in Roei, where the notes become suddenly high.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It stems from the difficulty of singing when moving from the first phrase to the second in Roei, when suddenly the notes become high.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It stems from the difficulty of singing when moving from the first phrase to the second in Roei, when suddenly the notes become high.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="31">
<tit>
<j>雅楽を鑑賞する機会</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Opportunities to Appreciate Gagaku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Opportunities to Appreciate Gagaku</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Opportunities to Appreciate Gagaku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="212">
<j>神社等で行われ、録音、撮影可能なもの　※は童舞（厚化粧の少年、又は少女）が登場</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gagaku performed at shrines or other places and allowing recording or shooting. * has Dobu Dance (with a boy or girl with heavy makeup).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gagaku performed at shrines or other places and allowing recording or shooting. * has the Dobu dance (with a boy or girl in heavy makeup).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gagaku performed at shrines or other places and allowing recording or shooting. * has the Dobu dance (with a boy or girl in heavy makeup).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="213">
<j>北海道</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hokkaido</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hokkaido</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hokkaido</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="214">
<j>東北地方</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tohoku Region</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Tohoku Region</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tohoku Region</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="215">
<j>北関東</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kita-Kanto</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kita-Kanto</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kita-Kanto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="216">
<j>5月上旬：雅楽鑑賞の夕べ - 群馬県護国神社（高崎市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Early May: An Evening of Gagaku viewing - Gunma Prefecture Gokoku-jinja Shrine (Takasaki City)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Early May: An Evening of Gagaku viewing - Gunma Prefecture Gokoku-jinja Shrine (Takasaki City)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Early May: An Evening of Gagaku - Gunma Prefecture Gokoku-jinja Shrine (Takasaki City)</e>
<cmt>次の「雅楽の夕べ」と統一し、evening削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="217">
<j>10月上旬：雅楽秋の演奏会 - 貫前神社（富岡市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Early October: Fall Concert of Gagaku - Nukisaki-jinja Shrine (Tomioka City)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Early October: Fall Concert of Gagaku - Nukisaki-jinja Shrine (Tomioka City)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Early October: Fall Concert of Gagaku - Nukisaki-jinja Shrine (Tomioka City)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="218">
<j>11月中旬：舞楽祭 - 笠間稲荷神社（笠間市）※</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mid-November: Bugaku Festival - Kasamainari-jinja Shrine (Kasama City) *</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mid-November: Bugaku Festival - Kasamainari-jinja Shrine (Kasama City) *</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mid-November: Bugaku Festival - Kasamainari-jinja Shrine (Kasama City) *</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="219">
<j>南関東</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Minami-Kanto</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Minami-Kanto</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Minami-Kanto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="220">
<j>7月上旬：雅楽の夕べ - 大宮八幡宮 (杉並区)（杉並区）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Early July: An Evening of Gagaku - Omiya Hachimangu (Suginami Ward)</e>
<cmt>（杉並区）が二回あるのは間違いだと思い訳出せず。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Early July: An Evening of Gagaku - Omiya Hachimangu (Suginami ward)</e>
<cmt>lowercase</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Early July: An Evening of Gagaku - Omiya Hachimangu (Suginami Ward)</e>
<cmt>ward→Wardに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="221">
<j>甲信越地方</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koshin&apos;etsu Region</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Koshin&apos;etsu Region</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Koshinetsu Region</e>
<cmt>Koshin&apos;etsu→ Koshinetsuに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="222">
<j>東海地方</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokai Region</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Tokai Region</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tokai Region</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="223">
<j>4月16日：東照宮祭 - 名古屋東照宮（名古屋市中区 (名古屋市)）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April 16th: Toshogu Festival - Nagoya Toshogu (Naka Ward, Nagoya City)</e>
<cmt>最後の「名古屋市」は不要と判断、訳出せず。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April 16th: Toshogu Festival - Nagoya Toshogu (Naka Ward, Nagoya City)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 16: Toshogu Festival - Nagoya Toshogu (Naka Ward, Nagoya City)</e>
<cmt>lowercaseward→Wardに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="224">
<j>4月29日：春季神楽祭 - 伊勢神宮（伊勢市）※</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April 29th: Spring Kagura Festival - Ise Jingu (Ise City) *</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April 29th: Spring Kagura Festival - Ise Jingu (Ise City) *</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 29: Spring Kagura Festival - Ise Jingu (Ise City) *</e>
<cmt>th削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="225">
<j>5月1日：舞楽神事 - 熱田神宮（名古屋市熱田区）※</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">May 1st: Bugaku Shinji Ritual - Atsuta Jingu (Atsuta Ward, Nagoya City) *</e>
<cmt>http://www.atsutajingu.or.jp/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">May 1st: Bugaku Shinji Ritual - Atsuta Jingu (Atsuta Ward, Nagoya City) *</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">May 1: Bugaku Shinji Ritual - Atsuta Jingu (Atsuta Ward, Nagoya City) *</e>
<cmt>lowercaseward→Wardに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="226">
<j>北陸地方</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hokuriku Region</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hokuriku Region</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hokuriku Region</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="227">
<j>京都府</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="228">
<j>4月上旬：お花祭 - 観音寺(山崎聖天)（大山崎町）※</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Early April: Flower Festival - Kannon-ji Temple (Yamazaki Shoten Temple) (Oyamazaki-cho) *</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Early April: Flower Festival - Kannon-ji Temple (Yamazaki Shoten Temple) (Oyamazaki-cho) *</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Early April: Flower Festival - Kannon-ji Temple (Yamazaki Shoten Temple) (Oyamazaki-cho) *</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="229">
<j>5月中旬：三船祭（京都市右京区）※</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mid-May: Mifune Festival (Ukyo Ward, Kyoto City) *</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mid-May: Mifune Festival (Ukyo ward, Kyoto City) *</e>
<cmt>lowercase</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mid-May: Mifune Festival (Ukyo Ward, Kyoto City) *</e>
<cmt>ward→Wardに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="230">
<j>7月7日：水祭り - 貴船神社（京都市左京区）※</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">July 7th: Water Festival - Kibune-jinja Shrine (Sakyo Ward, Kyoto City) *</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">July 7th: Water Festival - Kibune-jinja Shrine (Sakyo Ward, Kyoto City) *</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">July 7: Water Festival - Kibune-jinja Shrine (Sakyo ward, Kyoto City) *</e>
<cmt>lowercase</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="231">
<j>9月15日未明：石清水祭 - 石清水八幡宮（八幡市）※</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">September 15th, before dawn : Iwashimizu Festival - Iwashimizu Hachimangu (Yawata City) *</e>
<cmt>http://www.iwashimizu.or.jp/7/s/tyo/index.htmlhttp://www.iwashimizu.or.jp/index/toppageh2002.htm</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">September 15th, before dawn : Iwashimizu Festival - Iwashimizu Hachimangu (Yawata City) *</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September 15, before dawn : Iwashimizu Festival - Iwashimizu Hachimangu (Yawata City) *</e>
<cmt>th削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="232">
<j>11月中旬：嵐山もみじ祭（京都市右京区）※</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mid-November: Arashiyama Momiji Festival (Ukyo Ward, Kyoto City) *</e>
<cmt>http://kaiwai.city.kyoto.jp/search/view_sight.php?lang=ja&amp;InforKindCode=2&amp;ManageCode=1000008</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mid-November: Arashiyama Momiji Festival (Ukyo Ward, Kyoto City) *</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mid-November: Arashiyama Momiji Festival (Ukyo Ward, Kyoto City) *</e>
<cmt>lowercaseward→Wardに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="233">
<j>その他の近畿地方</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other areas in Kinki Region</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other areas in the Kinki Region</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other areas in the Kinki Region</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="234">
<j>4月22日：聖霊会 - 四天王寺（大阪市天王寺区）※</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April 22nd: Shoryoe - Shitenno-ji Temple (Tennoji Ward, Osaka City) *</e>
<cmt>聖霊会http://www.shitennoji.or.jp/gyouji2/geturei/shigatu/4gatsu.htm</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April 22nd: Shoryoe - Shitenno-ji Temple (Tennoji Ward, Osaka City) *</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 22: Shoryoe - Shitenno-ji Temple (Tennoji Ward, Osaka City) *</e>
<cmt>lowercaseward→Wardに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="235">
<j>5月5日：こどもの日舞楽演奏会 - 春日大社（奈良市）※</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">May 5th: Children&apos;s Day Bugaku Concert - Kasugataisha Shrine (Nara City) *</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">May 5: Children&apos;s Day Bugaku Concert - Kasugataisha Shrine (Nara City) *</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">May 5: Children&apos;s Day Bugaku Concert - Kasugataisha Shrine (Nara City) *</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="25">
<sen id="236">
<j>5月上卯日：卯之葉神事奉納舞楽 - 住吉大社（大阪市住吉区）※</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">May, Kaminou Day: Unoha Shinji Ritual Bugaku Dedication - Sumiyoshitaisha Shrine (Sumiyoshi Ward, Osaka City) *</e>
<cmt>http://www.sumiyoshitaisha.net/calender/index.htmlhttp://www.sumiyoshitaisha.net/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">May, Kaminou Day: Unoha Shinji Ritual Bugaku Dedication - Sumiyoshitaisha Shrine (Sumiyoshi ward, Osaka City) *</e>
<cmt>lowercase</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">May, Kaminou Day: Unoha Shinji Ritual Bugaku Dedication - Sumiyoshitaisha Shrine (Sumiyoshi Ward, Osaka City) *</e>
<cmt>ward→Wardに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="26">
<sen id="237">
<j>6月10日：漏刻祭 - 近江神宮（大津市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">June 10th: Rokokusai Festival - Omijingu (Otsu City)</e>
<cmt>http://www.ct-net.com/nishioumi/97-06.shtml</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">June 10: Rokokusai Festival - Omijingu (Otsu City)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">June 10: Rokokusai Festival - Omijingu (Otsu City)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="27">
<sen id="238">
<j>中秋の名月：観月祭 - 住吉大社（大阪市住吉区）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Harvest moon: Full Moon Festival - Sumiyoshitaisha Shrine (Sumiyoshi Ward, Osaka City)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Harvest moon: Full Moon Festival - Sumiyoshitaisha Shrine (Sumiyoshi ward, Osaka City)</e>
<cmt>lowercase</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Harvest moon: Full Moon Festival - Sumiyoshitaisha Shrine (Sumiyoshi Ward, Osaka City)</e>
<cmt>ward→Wardに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="28">
<sen id="239">
<j>9月下旬：雅楽の夕べ - 生田神社（神戸市中央区 (神戸市)）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Late September: An Evening of Gagaku - Ikuta-jinja Shrine (Chuo Ward, Kobe City)</e>
<cmt>最後の「神戸市」は不要と判断、訳出せず。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Late September: An Evening of Gagaku - Ikuta-jinja Shrine (Chuo ward, Kobe City)</e>
<cmt>lowercase</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Late September: An Evening of Gagaku - Ikuta-jinja Shrine (Chuo Ward, Kobe City)</e>
<cmt>ward→Wardに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="29">
<sen id="240">
<j>11月3日：文化の日舞楽演奏会 - 春日大社（奈良市）※</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">November 3rd: Culture Day Bugaku Concert - Kasugataisha Shrine (Nara City) *</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">November 3: Culture Day Bugaku Concert - Kasugataisha Shrine (Nara City) *</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November 3: Culture Day Bugaku Concert - Kasugataisha Shrine (Nara City) *</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="30">
<sen id="241">
<j>中国地方</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chugoku Region</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Chugoku Region</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Chugoku Region</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="31">
<sen id="242">
<j>四国</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shikoku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shikoku</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shikoku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="32">
<sen id="243">
<j>九州</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyushu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyushu</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyushu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Novo(id:87875), MIsogi(id:20599), 30rKs56MaE(id:11801), Urania(id:7213), Sina(id:10021), おはぐろ蜻蛉(id:8405), Im224(id:57113), Kliment.A.K.(id:161714), 沢田(id:40580), Nakaoka7675(id:39645), Dream100(id:41924), らりた(id:1327), さららゆら(id:12274), A. J. Kuonji(id:68661), Hy sonic(id:63550), TY(id:1386), Ticky(id:620), Tamago915(id:11009), Hukidera(id:87796), Yas(id:739), Aloha-vodka(id:22493), Mikomaid(id:56139), 詠狸庵(id:41048), Izayohi(id:13095), HikaruFukushima(id:89838), K.F.(id:18171), Youtetsu(id:7844), TS(id:481), Sat.K(id:3751), Wikindexan(id:10060), 伊集院聖(id:53199), Rusk(id:9895), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), ウィキ太郎(id:81560), こいつぅ(id:2105), Seelee(id:149131), Junger(id:10282), Ha～Ha(id:36403), Snufkin(id:184), Suisui(id:69), 10cm(id:147838), Jade0416(id:104181), 弥(id:61590), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>