<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>速水流</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hayami-ryu School</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hayami-ryu School</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hayami-ryu School</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>速水流（はやみりゅう）は、速水宗達に始まる茶道の流派。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hayami-ryu is a school of the tea ceremony, originated by Sotatsu HAYAMI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hayami-ryu is a school of the tea ceremony, originated by Sotatsu HAYAMI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hayami-ryu is a school of the tea ceremony, originated by Sotatsu HAYAMI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>家元は滌源居（てきげんきょ）と称して京都市北区 (京都市)にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The head family of the school, named Tekigenkyo, is located in Kita Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The head family of the school, named Tekigenkyo, is located in Kita Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The head family of the school, named Tekigenkyo, is located in Kita Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>同門組織として滌源会がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has an organization of fellow students called Tekigenkai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has an organization of fellow students called Tekigenkai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has an organization of fellow students called Tekigenkai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>特徴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Features</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Features</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Features</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>裏千家から分かれた流派であるものの、聖護院門跡との密接な関わりにより公家文化を基調とした流儀となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Hayami-ryu school stemmed from Urasenke school of the tea ceremony, it is based on the culture of court nobles since it has maintained close relationships with Shogoin-monzeki (the temple originally built in 1090 in Kyoto as a temple of Tendai-shu sect and has been continuaously used as a residence of various priests retired from nobilities including imperial house members.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Hayami-ryu school stemmed from the Urasenke school of tea ceremony, it is based upon the culture of court nobles since it has maintained close relationships with Shogoin-monzeki (the temple originally built in 1090 in Kyoto as a temple of Tendai-shu sect and has been continuaously used as a residence of various priests retired from nobilities including imperial household members.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Hayami-ryu school stemmed from the Urasenke school of tea ceremony, it is based upon the culture of court nobles since it has maintained close relationships with Shogoin Monzeki Temple (originally built in 1090 in Kyoto as a temple of Tendai Sect and has been continuaously used as a residence of various priests retired from nobilities including imperial household members).</e>
<cmt>Shogoin-monzeki→Shogoin Monzeki Templeとし、補足を一部修正、ピリオドの位置を移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>わかりやすいところでは十二単の色目を参考にした斜め二色の袱紗を使用することがあげられ、また畳紙（たとう）と浅香の懸盤を参考にした小掛台とを使った貴人点前も公家文化をよく反映したものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some prominent examples of the influence of court culture are the use of fukusa (a small cloth for wiping tea utensils) in two colors on a skew which refers to the color pattern of juni-hitoe (twelve-layered ceremonial kimono wear) as well as the Kinin-date (the tea ceremony procedure for nobilities) using tato (a folding paper-case) and kokakedai (a small table) which refers to Senko no Kakeban (a small low table made of subtle fragrant wood to place dishes.)</e>
<cmt>浅香の懸盤→Senko no Kakeban (a small low table made of subtle fragrant wood to place dishes)[浅香を「浅い香りの木でできた食膳台」と解釈して仮訳しました]: 小掛台→kokakedai (a small table)　[定訳不明,読み方が見つからず、仮訳です。]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some prominent examples of the influence of court culture are the use of fukusa (a small cloth for wiping tea utensils) in two colors on a skew which refers to the color pattern of juni-hitoe (twelve-layered ceremonial kimono wear) as well as the Kinin-date (the tea ceremony procedure for nobilities) using tato (a folding paper-case) and kokakedai (a small table) which refers to Senko no Kakeban (a small low table made of subtle fragrant wood to place dishes.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some prominent examples of the influence of court culture are the use of fukusa (a small cloth for wiping tea utensils) in two colors on a skew which refers to the color pattern of juni-hitoe (twelve-layered ceremonial kimono wear) as well as the Kinin-date (the tea ceremony procedure for nobilities) using tato (a folding paper-case) and kokakedai (a small table) which refers to Senko no Kakeban (a small low table made of subtle fragrant wood to place dishes).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>その他、三千家で江戸中期に制定された七事式は三式を追加して肄業式（いぎょうしき）となっており、さらに特殊な点前として茶杓を使わない脱杓点法がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of the other features of Hayami-ryu school is the &quot;igyoshiki exercises&quot; (a series of officially established ten methods to exercise the tea ceremony) developed from the &quot;shichijishiki exercises&quot; (a series of officially established seven methods) which was officially established in the middle of Edo Period by Sansenke (three Senke schools,) and another feature is the shool&apos;s unique procedure called the &quot;dasshaku tenho&quot; which is a special procedure of the tea ceremony using no chashaku or excluding bamboo tea spoon for making Japanese tea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of the other features of Hayami-ryu school is the &quot;igyoshiki exercises&quot; (a series of officially established ten methods to exercise the tea ceremony) developed from the &quot;shichijishiki exercises&quot; (a series of officially established seven methods) which was officially established in the middle of Edo Period by Sansenke (three Senke schools,) and another feature is the shool&apos;s unique procedure called the &quot;dasshaku tenho&quot; which is a special procedure of the tea ceremony using no chashaku or excluding the bamboo tea spoon for making Japanese tea.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of the other features of Hayami-ryu school is the igyoshiki exercises (a series of officially established ten methods to exercise the tea ceremony) developed from the shichijishiki exercises (a series of officially established seven methods) which was officially established in the middle of Edo period by Sansenke (three Senke schools,) and another feature is the shool&apos;s unique procedure called the dasshaku tenho which is a special procedure of the tea ceremony using no chashaku or excluding the bamboo tea spoon for making Japanese tea.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション削除、Periodの頭文字を小文字に変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>速水宗達は、代々御典医を務めて速水彦達と呼ばれた家に生まれたが、古義堂に学んで漢学や国学に深く通じた学者となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sotatsu HAYAMI who was born in the family of Hikotatsu HAYAMI, a successor of the job as goten-i (a doctor hired by a family of shogun or other feudal lord,) became acquainted with kangaku (the study of Chinese classics) and kokugaku (study of ancient Japanese literature and culture) by studying them at Kogido (a private tutoring shoool to teach Confucianism by Jinsai ITO in Kyoto.)</e>
<cmt>速水彦達→Hikotatsu HAYAMI (速水彦達)[定訳不明,読み方が見つからず、仮訳です。]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sotatsu HAYAMI who was born in the family of Hikotatsu HAYAMI, a successor of the job as goten-i (a doctor hired by a family of shogun or other feudal lord,) became acquainted with kangaku (the study of Chinese classics) and kokugaku (study of ancient Japanese literature and culture) by studying them at Kogido (a private tutoring shoool to teach Confucianism by Jinsai ITO in Kyoto.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sotatsu HAYAMI who was born in the family of Hikotatsu HAYAMI, a successor of the job as goten-i (a doctor hired by a family of shogun or other feudal lord,) became acquainted with kangaku (the study of Chinese classics) and kokugaku (study of ancient Japanese literature and culture) by studying them at Kogido (a private tutoring shoool to teach Confucianism by Jinsai ITO in Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>茶道は裏千家8代又玄斎一燈宗室の門に学び、早くから奥義をきわめ学究肌の茶風であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sotatsu HAYAMI learned the tea ceremony under Itto Soshitsu, Yugensai, the eighth head of Urasenke school, and mastered its secrets early on assuming his own scholarly style of the tea ceremony.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sotatsu HAYAMI learned tea ceremony under Itto Soshitsu, Yugensai, the eighth head of Urasenke school, and mastered its secrets early on assuming his own scholarly style of tea ceremony.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sotatsu HAYAMI learned tea ceremony under Itto Soshitsu, Yugensai, the eighth head of Urasenke school, and mastered its secrets early on assuming his own scholarly style of tea ceremony.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>速水家が医者として名家であったこと、宗達の学者としての高い見識と茶の湯に対する学究的態度が評価されたこともあり、一燈の門人では随一の人とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sotatsu was respected as a prominent disciple of Itto Soshitsu, because of his deep insight as a scholar and his academic approach to the tea ceremony, beside the pedigree of his Hayami family as distinguished doctors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sotatsu was respected as a prominent disciple of Itto Soshitsu, because of his deep insight as a scholar and his academic approach to the tea ceremony, beside the pedigree of his Hayami family as distinguished doctors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sotatsu was respected as a prominent disciple of Itto Soshitsu, because of his deep insight as a scholar and his academic approach to the tea ceremony, beside the pedigree of his Hayami family as distinguished doctors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>光格天皇の弟である聖護院宮盈仁親王の茶道指南を努め、次第に御所風の流儀に改めるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a coach of the tea ceremony, he served Imperial Prince Einin, Shogoinnomiya, a younger brother of Emperor Kokaku, and gradually changed his style of the tea ceremony to goshofu (imperial palace style.)</e>
<cmt>「指南を努め」→「指南を勤め」と読み替えました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a coach of the tea ceremony, he served Imperial Prince Einin, Shogoinnomiya, a younger brother of Emperor Kokaku, and gradually changed his style of the tea ceremony to goshofu (imperial palace style.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a coach of the tea ceremony, he served Imperial Prince Shogoinnomiya Einin, a younger brother of the Emperor Kokaku, and gradually changed his style of the tea ceremony to goshofu (imperial palace style).</e>
<cmt>Imperial Prince Shogoinnomiya Einin　で統一し、ピリオドの位置を移動 &quot;the&quot; を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>備前国岡山藩池田家や大和国郡山藩柳沢家の茶道指南を務めたことでも知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sotatsu is also known to have coached on the tea ceremony the Ikeda family of Okayama domain, Bizen Province, and the Yanagisawa family of Koriyama domain, Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sotatsu is also known to have coached the tea ceremony to the Ikeda family of Okayama domain, Bizen Province, and the Yanagisawa family of Koriyama domain, Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sotatsu is also known to have coached the tea ceremony to the Ikeda family of Okayama Domain, Bizen Province, and the Yanagisawa family of Koriyama Domain, Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt>domainの頭文字を大文字に変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="14">
<j>速水流の起源については、一燈宗室が岡山藩池田家から出仕の要請を受けた際に、分派を許した上で代理に宗達を遣わしたという説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a way, the Hayami-ryu school is believed to have originated in the event that Sotatsu was allowed to establish a branch school in order to be delegated to Okayama on behalf of Soshitsu when Soshitsu received a request for outside services of the tea ceremony at Ikeda family&apos;s residence in the domain of Okayama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In a way, the Hayami-ryu school is believed to have originated in the event that Sotatsu was allowed to establish a branch school in order to be delegated to Okayama on behalf of Soshitsu when Soshitsu received a request for outside services of the tea ceremony at Ikeda family&apos;s residence in the domain of Okayama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In a way, the Hayami-ryu school is believed to have originated in the event that Sotatsu was allowed to establish a branch school in order to be delegated to Okayama on behalf of Soshitsu when Soshitsu received a request for outside services of the tea ceremony at Ikeda family&apos;s residence in the domain of Okayama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>一燈在世中の岡山藩主は文化人としても知られる5代池田治政だが、岡山藩池田家が文治主義になるのは治政隠居後とされており、このときすでに一燈は世を去っているため整合しない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But, this explanation is contradictory to the fact that the Okayama domain assumed its policy of civilian control only after the retirement of the fifth lord, Harumasa IKEDA, known as an intellectual lord who had lived contemporary with Itto Soshitsu, and that Soshitsu had then already passed away at the time of Harumasa&apos;s retirement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But, this explanation is contradictory to the fact that the Okayama domain assumed its policy of civilian control only after the retirement of the fifth lord, Harumasa IKEDA, known as an intellectual lord who had lived with Itto Soshitsu, and that Soshitsu had then already passed away at the time of Harumasa&apos;s retirement.</e>
<cmt>grammar, word spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But, this explanation is contradictory to the fact that the Okayama Domain assumed its policy of civilian control only after the retirement of the fifth lord, Harumasa IKEDA, known as an intellectual lord who had lived with Itto Soshitsu, and that Soshitsu had then already passed away at the time of Harumasa&apos;s retirement.</e>
<cmt>domainの頭文字を大文字に変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>一方で一燈亡き後に聖護院宮盈仁親王のお声掛かりで別派を許されたとする説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, there is another explanation that Sotatsu HAYAMI was allowed to establish an offshoot of Itto Soshitsu, when accosted and asked by Imperial Prince Einin, Shogoinnomiya, after Itto&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, there is another explanation that Sotatsu HAYAMI was allowed to establish an offshoot of Itto Soshitsu, when accosted and asked by Imperial Prince Einin, Shogoinnomiya, after Itto&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, there is another explanation that Sotatsu HAYAMI was allowed to establish an offshoot of Itto Soshitsu, when accosted and asked by Imperial Prince Shogoinnomiya Einin, after Itto&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>Imperial Prince Shogoinnomiya Eininとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>これらは早くても天保期、おそらく文久以降に成立した伝承だろうと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Stories of these traditions are considered to have been formed in the Tenpo period at the earliest, most probably after the Bunkyu era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Stories of these traditions are considered to have been formed in the Tenpo period at the earliest, most probably after the Bunkyu era.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Stories of these traditions are considered to have been formed in the Tenpo era at the earliest, most probably after the Bunkyu era.</e>
<cmt>Tenpo period→Tenpo eraとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="18">
<j>宗達は流派に拠らない学術的な茶道の教授体系を考案しようとしたらしく、莫大な量の草稿を残している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sotatsu left a huge vokume of scripts showing that he had apparently intended to create an academic teaching system of the tea ceremony regardless of whatever school or sect it may concern.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sotatsu left a huge vokume of scripts showing that he had apparently intended to create an academic teaching system of the tea ceremony regardless of whatever school or sect it may concern.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sotatsu left a huge vokume of scripts showing that he had apparently intended to create an academic teaching system of the tea ceremony regardless of whatever school or sect it may concern.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>その一部は宗達の死後、2代宗曄によって整理されて『茶旨略』『喫茶指掌篇』などとして、また3代宗筧により『茶則』として刊行されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Sotatsu died, his scripts were partly compiled by the second head of the school, Soyo, into such books as &quot;Chashiryaku,&quot; &quot;Kissa-shisho-hen&quot; and others, and further they were published by the third head, Soken, as a book titled &quot;Chasoku.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Sotatsu died, his scripts were partly compiled by the second head of the school, Soyo, into such books as &quot;Chashiryaku,&quot; &quot;Kissa-shisho-hen&quot; and others, and further they were published by the third head, Soken, as a book titled &quot;Chasoku.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Sotatsu died, his scripts were partly compiled by the second head of the school, Soyo, into such books as &quot;Chashiryaku,&quot; &quot;Kissa-shisho-hen&quot; and others, and further they were published by the third head, Soken, as a book titled &quot;Chasoku.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>滌源居は流勢盛んであった3代宗筧のときに幕府の命により釜座出水から立ち退き、北野の現在地へ移った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the generation of the third head, Soken, Dekigenkyo, the head family of Haymi-ryu school, reached a new height of prosperity and shifted its location from Kamaza Demizu to the current address of Kitano under the order from the Shogunate (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the generation of the third head, Soken, Dekigenkyo, the head family of Haymi-ryu school, reached a new height of prosperity and shifted its location from Kamaza Demizu to the current address of Kitano under the order from the Shogunate (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the generation of the third head, Soken, Dekigenkyo, the head family of Hayami-ryu school, reached a new height of prosperity and shifted its location from Kamaza Demizu to the current address of Kitano under the order from the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>Haymi-ryu→Hayami-ryu、Shogunate→bakufuとし、ピリオドの位置を移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>6代宗仁は早稲田大学出身で宗教や哲学に通じた学者でもあり、全国日本学士会よりアカデミア賞を授与された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The sixth head, Sojin, a graduate of Waseda University, was awarded with Academia prize of Zenkoku Nihon Gakushikai (the Academic Society of Japan) as a scholar adept in religions and philosophy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sixth head, Sojin, a graduate of Waseda University, was awarded with Academia prize of Zenkoku Nihon Gakushikai (the Academic Society of Japan) as a scholar adept in religion and philosophy.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sixth head, Sojin, a graduate of Waseda University, was awarded with Academia prize of Zenkoku Nihon Gakushikai (the Academic Society of Japan) as a scholar adept in religion and philosophy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="22">
<j>歴代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Succession</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Succession</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Succession</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>速水流</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hayami-ryu School</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hayami-ryu School</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hayami-ryu School</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Mzaki(id:61977), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>