<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>京焼</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyo-yaki (Kyoto pottery)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyo-yaki (Kyoto pottery)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyo-yaki (Kyoto pottery)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>京焼（きょうやき）は日本の陶磁器の一種。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyo-yaki is a type of Japanese ceramics.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyo-yaki is a type of Japanese pottery.</e>
<cmt>ceramics &gt; pottery</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyo-yaki is a type of Japanese pottery.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>粟田口焼、御室焼など京都で作られる作品の総称となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is a generic name given to pottery made in Kyoto such as Awataguchi-yaki (Awataguchi pottery) and Omuro-yaki (Omuro pottery).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a generic name given to pottery made in Kyoto, such as Awataguchi-yaki (Awataguchi pottery) and Omuro-yaki (Omuro pottery).</e>
<cmt>added comma after &quot;Kyoto&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a generic name given to pottery made in Kyoto, such as Awataguchi-yaki (Awataguchi pottery) and Omuro-yaki (Omuro pottery).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>一度焼成した後に上絵付けを施す上絵付けの技法を用いた陶器が多く、作家ごとの個性が強いのが特徴。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most Kyo-yaki ceramics are made in an overglaze painting technique in which figures are painted on burned pottery, and one of the characteristics of Kyo-yaki is that the originality of each ceramist comes across clearly in his or her work.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most Kyo-yaki ceramics are made with an overglaze painting technique in which figures are painted on burned pottery, resulting in special characteristics that make the originality of each ceramist come across clearly in his or her work.</e>
<cmt>in &gt; with; fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most Kyo-yaki ceramics are made with an overglaze painting technique in which figures are painted on burned pottery, resulting in special characteristics that make the originality of each ceramist come across clearly in his or her work.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>京焼の始まり</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The origin of Kyo-yaki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The origin of Kyo-yaki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The origin of Kyo-yaki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>近年の研究では、慶長初頭の1590年代末には京焼の生産が始まっていたと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Recent research insists that the Kyo-yaki production had already begun in the early Keicho era, at the end of the 1590s.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Recent research insists that Kyo-yaki had already began being produce during the early Keicho era at the end of the 1590s.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Recent research insists that Kyo-yaki had already began being produce during the early Keicho era at the end of the 1590s.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>この頃の作品については不明な点が多いが、低温で焼成し、鉛を含む釉薬が使用されていて、技法やデザインが多様なことが特徴である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although there are still many questions left about Kyo-yaki ceramics produced around that time, it is notable that most pieces of such pottery were burned at moderate temperature with lead glaze, and were made with various techniques and designs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although there are still many questions left unanswered about Kyo-yaki ceramics produced around that time, it is notable that most pieces of such pottery were burned at a moderate temperature with lead glaze and made with various techniques and designs.</e>
<cmt>left about &gt; left unanswered about; eliminated period after &quot;glaze&quot;; added &quot;a&quot; after &quot;burned at&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although there are still many questions left unanswered about Kyo-yaki ceramics produced around that time, it is notable that most pieces of such pottery were burned at a moderate temperature with lead glaze and made with various techniques and designs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>この時期以前の京都は三条付近に陶磁器の問屋が集中していたものの、本格的な生産は行われていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before that period, many pottery wholesalers were around Sanjo, Kyoto, but the amount of pottery production was not so large.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before this period, there were many pottery wholesalers around Sanjo, Kyoto, but they produced only a small amount.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before this period, there were many pottery wholesalers around Sanjo, Kyoto, but they produced only a small amount.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>ただし、天正以前の16世紀中頃には三彩や交趾焼などの技術を持った中国人陶工およびその後継者達が製陶を開始していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before the Tensho era, however, Chinese potters who had some techniques such as sansai (three-color glazed pottery technique) and the Cochin ware technique and their successors had already started pottery manufacture in the middle of the 16th century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before the Tensho era, however, Chinese potters and their successors, who had techniques such as sansai (a three-color glazed pottery technique) and the Cochin ware technique, had already started manufacturing pottery during the middle of the 16th century.</e>
<cmt>added comma after &quot;technique&quot;; changed location of &quot;and their successors&quot; to earlier in the sentence; fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before the Tensho era, however, Chinese potters and their successors, who had techniques such as sansai (a three-color glazed pottery technique) and the Cochin ware technique, had already started manufacturing pottery during the middle of the 16th century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>緑、紫、紺、黄など寒色系の釉薬が特徴で、押小路焼のルーツとなったと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The distinguishing feature of their pottery was cold colored glaze such as green, purple, navy-blue, and yellow, and it is thought that Oshikoji-yaki (Oshikoji pottery) was derived from this.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The distinguishing feature of their pottery was a cold colored glaze, such as green, purple, navy-blue, and yellow, and it is thought that this is where Oshikoji-yaki (Oshikoji pottery) was derived from.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;a&quot; before &quot;cold&quot;; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The distinguishing feature of their pottery was a cold colored glaze, such as green, purple, navy-blue, and yellow, and it is thought that this is where Oshikoji-yaki (Oshikoji pottery) was derived from.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>色絵陶器の成立</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Beginning of polychrome pottery</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The beginning of polychrome pottery</e>
<cmt>added &quot;The&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The beginning of polychrome pottery</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>17世紀に入ると、茶道の興隆に伴って茶碗、茶入など茶陶の製造が盛んになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Once the 17th century began, the production of tea pottery such as tea bowls and tea leaf containers increased as the art of the tea ceremony became more popular.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the beginning of the 17th century, the production of tea pottery, such as tea bowls and tea leaf containers, increased as the art of the tea ceremony became more popular.</e>
<cmt>added comma after &quot;pottery&quot; and &quot;containers&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the beginning of the 17th century, the production of tea pottery, such as tea bowls and tea leaf containers, increased as the art of the tea ceremony became more popular.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>具体的には、瀬戸焼、美濃焼や唐津焼の職人とその技法をベースとして高麗茶碗の写しなどが作られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Specifically, Seto-yaki (Seto pottery), Mino-yaki (Mino pottery), and Karatsu-yaki (Karatsu pottery) craftsmen made copies of Goryeo tea bowls, taking advantage of their techniques.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Specifically, Seto-yaki (Seto pottery), Mino-yaki (Mino pottery), and Karatsu-yaki (Karatsu pottery) craftsmen made copies of Goryeo tea bowls, taking advantage of their techniques.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Specifically, Seto-yaki (Seto pottery), Mino-yaki (Mino pottery), and Karatsu-yaki (Karatsu pottery) craftsmen made copies of Goryeo tea bowls, taking advantage of their techniques.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>また、この頃に黒谷土と呼ばれる製陶に適した原料土が地元の山城国で発見されたことも陶磁器の生産の助けとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, good clay for pottery called Korodani-tsuchi (Korodani clay) was found in Yamashiro Province, and this discovery accelerated the manufacture of ceramics.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The discovery of clay that was good for pottery called Korodani-tsuchi (Korodani clay) was found in Yamashiro Province, accelerating the manufacture of ceramics.</e>
<cmt>eliminated &quot;In addition&quot;; moved &quot;discovery&quot; toward the beginning of the sentence; good clay &gt; clay good</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The discovery of clay that was good for pottery called Korodani-tsuchi (Korodani clay) was found in Yamashiro Province, accelerating the manufacture of ceramics.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="14">
<j>京焼の中で最古の部類に入る粟田口焼（粟田焼）は、寛永には粟田口で生産を行なっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of the oldest Kyo-yaki series called Awataguchi-yaki (also known as Awata-yaki) had already begun in the Awataguchi district in the Kanei era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of the oldest categories of Kyo-yaki called Awataguchi-yaki (also known as Awata-yaki) had already began being produced in the Awataguchi district in the Kanei era.</e>
<cmt>series &gt; categories; had already begun &gt; had already began being produced</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of the oldest categories of Kyo-yaki called Awataguchi-yaki (also known as Awata-yaki) had already began being produced in the Awataguchi district in the Kanei era.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>ここでは中国の茶器の写しや天目茶碗が作られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this area, they manufactured copies of Chinese tea bowls and Tenmoku tea bowls (bowls with a wide brim and a narrow base used in the tea ceremony).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this area, they manufactured copies of Chinese tea bowls and Tenmoku tea bowls (bowls with a wide brim and a narrow base used during tea ceremonies).</e>
<cmt>used in the tea ceremony &gt; used during tea ceremonies</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this area, they manufactured copies of Chinese tea bowls and Tenmoku tea bowls (bowls with a wide brim and a narrow base used during tea ceremonies).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>同時期では、八坂焼は1640年、清水焼は1643年までには存在が確認されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasaka-yaki (Yasaka pottery) and Kiyomizu-yaki (Kiyomizu pottery) are almost as old as such pottery, and it is confirmed that Yasaka-yaki existed in 1649 and Kiyomizu-yaki appeared no later than 1643.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasaka-yaki (Yasaka pottery) and Kiyomizu-yaki (Kiyomizu pottery) are almost as old, and it has been confirmed that Yasaka-yaki existed in 1649 and Kiyomizu-yaki appeared no later than 1643.</e>
<cmt>eliminated &quot;as such pottery&quot;; it is confirmed &gt; it has been confirmed</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasaka-yaki (Yasaka pottery) and Kiyomizu-yaki (Kiyomizu pottery) are almost as old, and it has been confirmed that Yasaka-yaki existed in 1640 and Kiyomizu-yaki appeared no later than 1643.</e>
<cmt>1649→1640</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>これに続いて御室焼、御菩薩池焼、修学院焼なども作られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After these types of pottery, Mimuro-yaki, Mizorogaike-yaki (Mizorogaike pottery), and Shugakuin-yaki (Shugakuin pottery) began.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After these types of pottery came Mimuro-yaki (Mimuro pottery), Mizorogaike-yaki (Mizorogaike pottery) and Shugakuin-yaki (Shugakuin pottery).</e>
<cmt>changed comma after pottery to &quot;came&quot;; eliminated &quot;began&quot;; added (Mimuro pottery) for consistency</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After these types of pottery came Mimuro-yaki (Mimuro pottery), Mizorogaike-yaki (Mizorogaike pottery) and Shugakuin-yaki (Shugakuin pottery).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="18">
<j>このような中、慶安3年（1650年）5月25日_(旧暦)に金森宗和が参加した茶会に関する記述の中で、絵付を施した御室焼の登場が確認されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, the description about a tea party in which Sowa KANAMORI participated on June 23, 1650, mentioned painted Mimuro-yaki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In a description about a tea party in which Sowa KANAMORI participated in on June 23, 1650, painted Mimuro-yaki is mentioned.</e>
<cmt>eliminated &quot;In addition&quot;; changed &quot;the&quot; to &quot;In a&quot;; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In a description about a tea party in which Sowa KANAMORI participated in on June 23, 1650, painted Mimuro-yaki is mentioned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>さらに翌年か翌々年には赤色系の上絵付を施した御室焼が野々村仁清によって初めて作られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the following year or the year after that, Ninsei NONOMURA made the first Mimuro-yaki with reddish color paint.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Within the next two years, Ninsei NONOMURA made the first Mimuro-yaki with a reddish color paint.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;In the following year or the year after that&quot; to &quot;Within the next two years&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Within the next two years, Ninsei NONOMURA made the first Mimuro-yaki with a reddish color paint.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>調合・焼成の困難な赤色系の絵付を17世紀に成功させたのは、磁器を国内で初めて製作した有田焼以外ではこれが唯一の例であり、かつ陶器では国内初であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was the only example of successful ceramics with reddish color paint of the 17th century except for Arita-yaki (Arita pottery), which was the first Japanese porcelain, because the reddish color paint requires delicate glaze compounding and burning, and this was the first example among earthenware.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was the first and only example of a successful piece of earthen pottery with a reddish color paint in the 17th century aside from Arita-yaki (Arita pottery), which was the first Japanese porcelain, since reddish color paint requires a delicate glaze compound and burning.</e>
<cmt>successful ceramics &gt; a successful piece of pottery; eliminated &quot;and this was the first example among earthware.&quot; and added &quot;the first&quot; before &quot;only&quot; and &quot;earthen&quot; before &quot;pottery&quot;; compounding &gt; compound</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was the first and only example of a successful piece of earthen pottery with a reddish color paint in the 17th century aside from Arita-yaki (Arita pottery), which was the first Japanese porcelain, since reddish color paint requires a delicate glaze compound and burning.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>18世紀以降</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In and after the 18th century</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In and after the 18th century</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In and after the 18th century</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="21">
<j>野々村仁清の死後、跡を継いだ息子は技量が及ばず製陶から手を引いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Ninsei NONOMURA passed away, his son took over his work but he eventually withdrew from the pottery work because his skill was not good enough.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although his son took over his work after Ninsei NONOMURA passed away, he eventually withdrew from ceramics due to a lack of skill.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although his son took over his work after Ninsei NONOMURA passed away, he eventually withdrew from ceramics due to a lack of skill.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>しかし仁清から直接技法を学んだ尾形乾山は優れた作品を多く残した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Kanzan OGATA, who learned pottery techniques directly from Ninsei, produced a good many of excellent pieces of pottery.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Kanzan OGATA, who learned pottery techniques directly from Ninsei, produced many excellent pieces of pottery.</e>
<cmt>a good many of excellent &gt; many excellent</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Kanzan OGATA, who learned pottery techniques directly from Ninsei, produced many excellent pieces of pottery.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>また、永樂了全より後の永樂家は永樂保全、永樂和全など優れた陶工を輩出し、千家に作品を納めて今日に至る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, many skilled potters such as Hozen EIRAKU and Wazen EIRAKU appeared from the Eiraku family after Ryozen EIRAKU, and this family has been making tea equipment for the Senke (House of Sen) since then.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, many skilled potters such as Hozen EIRAKU and Wazen EIRAKU appeared from the Eiraku family after Ryozen EIRAKU, and this family has been making tea equipment for the Senke (House of Sen) ever since.</e>
<cmt>since then &gt; ever since</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, many skilled potters such as Hozen EIRAKU and Wazen EIRAKU appeared from the Eiraku family after Ryozen EIRAKU, and this family has been making tea equipment for the Senke (House of Sen) ever since.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="24">
<j>技術的にも重要な存在としては奥田頴川が挙げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eisen OKUDA is a very significant person in terms of pottery production techniques.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eisen OKUDA is a very significant person in terms of pottery production techniques.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eisen OKUDA is a very significant person in terms of pottery production techniques.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>頴川は京焼として初めて磁器を製作し、この後を受けて青木木米や仁阿弥道八らも磁器の作品を多く残した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eisen made the first Kyo-yaki porcelain, and Mokubei AOKI and Dohachi NINNAMI followed him and made many porcelain pieces.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He made the first Kyo-yaki porcelain, and Mokubei AOKI and Dohachi NINNAMI continued his legacy, making many porcelain pieces.</e>
<cmt>followed him &gt; continued his legacy; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He made the first Kyo-yaki porcelain, and Mokubei AOKI and Dohachi NINNAMI continued his legacy, making many porcelain pieces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="26">
<j>明治維新後は体制や文化の変化に伴って茶陶の需要が激減し、廃業した者も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Meiji Restoration, the demand for tea pottery rapidly dropped as the Japanese society and culture changed, and many potters gave up their professions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Meiji Restoration, the demand for tea pottery rapidly dropped as Japanese society and culture changed, leading to many potters giving up their professions.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Meiji Restoration, the demand for tea pottery rapidly dropped as Japanese society and culture changed, leading to many potters giving up their professions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>また、陶工の一部は日本陶器（現・ノリタケカンパニーリミテド）のような企業組織に入っていき、その技術を支えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, some potters participated in business organizations such as Nippon Toki Gomei Kaisha (Nippon Toki Co., Ltd.), which is known as Noritake Co., Ltd. at present, and supported and developed Kyo-yaki techniques.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A number of potters participated in business organizations, such as Nippon Toki Gomei Kaisha (Nippon Toki Co., Ltd.), currently known as Noritake Co., Ltd., supporting developed Kyo-yaki techniques.</e>
<cmt>added comma after &quot;organizations&quot;; at present &gt; currently known; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A number of potters participated in business organizations, such as Nippon Toki Gomei Kaisha (Nippon Toki Co., Ltd.), currently known as Noritake Co., Ltd., supporting development of techniques of the company.</e>
<cmt>「その技術」と京焼の技術ではなく、会社の技術ということだと解釈しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Okapia2(id:98589), Nopira(id:29335), Surfstar(id:94919), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>