<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>清楽</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Shingaku&quot; (Qing-era Chinese music)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Shingaku&quot; (Qing-era Chinese music)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Shingaku&quot; (Qing-era Chinese music)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>清楽（しんがく）とは、清国から伝来した、民謡、俗曲を中心とする音楽群の名称である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Shingaku&quot; is a group of music that is centered on &quot;minyo&quot; (traditional folk songs) &amp; &quot;zokkyoku&quot; (folk songs), introduced from Qing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Shingaku&quot; is a group of music that is centered on &quot;minyo&quot; (traditional folk songs) &amp; &quot;zokkyoku&quot; (folk songs), introduced from Qing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Shingaku&quot; is a group of music that is centered on &quot;minyo&quot; (traditional folk songs) and &quot;zokkyoku&quot; (folk songs), introduced from Qing.</e>
<cmt>&amp;→ and　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>明楽とあわせて明清楽(みんしんがく)とも称される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Combined with &quot;Mingaku&quot; (Ming-era Chinese music), it is also called &quot;Minshingaku&quot; (Ming &amp; Qing-era Chinese music).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Combined with &quot;Mingaku&quot; (Ming-era Chinese music), it is also called &quot;Minshingaku&quot; (Ming &amp; Qing-era Chinese music).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Combined with &quot;Mingaku&quot; (Ming-era Chinese music), it is also called &quot;Minshingaku&quot; (Ming and Qing-era Chinese music).</e>
<cmt>&amp;→ and　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>明楽は江戸時代の中期には衰退したため、明清楽と称しても、事実上、清楽だけを指すことも多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mingaku was on the decline in the middle of the Edo period, so Minshingaku substantially means - in many cases - Shingaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mingaku was on the decline in the middle of the Edo period, so Minshingaku substantially means - in many cases - Shingaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mingaku was on the decline in the middle of the Edo period, so Minshingaku substantially means - in many cases - Shingaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>清楽の伝来は享保年間（1716年-1735年）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shingaku was introduced to Japan in the Kyoho era (1716 - 1735).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shingaku was introduced to Japan in the Kyoho era (1716 - 1735).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shingaku was introduced to Japan in the Kyoho era (1716 - 1735).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>清の中国支配が始まり、清国との貿易で長崎には多くの清国商人が渡来し、彼らが清国の戯曲や民謡といった民間音楽を伝えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Qing dynasty began to rule China, many Qing merchants came to Nagasaki for trade and they introduced the people&apos;s music, such as Qing plays &amp; minyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Qing dynasty began in China, many Qing merchants came to Nagasaki for trade and they introduced the people&apos;s music, such as Qing plays &amp; minyo.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Qing dynasty began in China, many Qing merchants came to Nagasaki for trade and they introduced the people&apos;s music, such as Qing plays and minyo.</e>
<cmt>&amp;→ and　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>唐人屋敷に出入りを許された唐通事（中国語通訳）、地下役人や奉行所役人、さらに丸山の遊女等を介して普及した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These music spread via &quot;totsuji&quot; (Chinese translators), &quot;jige yakunin&quot; (lower-ranking officers of the Tokugawa shogunate) and officers of Nagasaki Magistrate&apos;s Office - they were permitted to go in and out the Chinese premises in Nagasaki - and in addition, via &quot;yujo&quot; (prostitutes) in Maruyama.</e>
<cmt>※「地下役人」は、ここでは朝廷ではなく江戸幕府の役人を指します。また「奉行所」は、「長崎奉行所」のことです。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These music spread via &quot;totsuji&quot; (Chinese translators), &quot;jige yakunin&quot; (lower-ranking officers of the Tokugawa shogunate) and officers of Nagasaki Magistrate&apos;s Office - they were permitted to go in and out the Chinese premises in Nagasaki - and in addition, via &quot;yujo&quot; (prostitutes) in Maruyama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These music spread via &quot;totsuji&quot; (Chinese translators), &quot;jige yakunin&quot; (lower-ranking officers of the Tokugawa shogunate) and officers of Nagasaki Magistrate&apos;s Office, and in addition, via &quot;yujo&quot; (prostitutes) in Maruyama.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>幕末までには、薩摩や琉球などを除く全国各地に広まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By the last days of the Tokugawa shogunate, Shingaku spread nationwide, except for some areas including Satsuma Domain and Ryukyu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By the last days of the Tokugawa shogunate, Shingaku spread nationwide, except for some areas including Satsuma Domain and Ryukyu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By the final years of the Tokugawa shogunate, Shingaku spread nationwide, except for some areas including Satsuma Domain and Ryukyu.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>また江戸や大坂を中心に、清楽の歌詞と楽譜(工尺譜)を書いた清楽譜も盛んに刊行された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And &quot;Shingaku-fu,&quot; on which the words &amp; score of Shingaku (called &quot;gongchepu&quot;) were written, was often issued mainly in Edo and Osaka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And &quot;Shingaku-fu,&quot; on which the words &amp; score of Shingaku (called &quot;gongchepu&quot;) were written, was often issued mainly in Edo and Osaka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further, &quot;Shingaku-fu,&quot; on which the words and score of Shingaku (called &quot;gongchepu&quot;) were written, was often issued mainly in Edo and Osaka.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>現存最古の清楽譜は、天保3年(1831)ごろ刊行された亀齢軒斗遠(葛生斗遠)編『花月琴譜』である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The existent oldest Shingaku-fu is &quot;Kagetsu Kinpu&quot; that was issued around 1831, and it was compiled by &quot;Toen KIREIKEN&quot; (also called &quot;Toen KUZUO&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The existent oldest Shingaku-fu is &quot;Kagetsu Kinpu&quot; that was issued around 1831, and it was compiled by &quot;Toen KIREIKEN&quot; (also called &quot;Toen KUZUO&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The oldest extent Shingaku-fu is &quot;Kagetsu Kinpu&quot; that was issued around 1831, and it was compiled by Toen KIREIKEN (also called Toen KUZUO).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>明清楽奏者の家元としては、平井連山（女性。明治19年5月に88歳で没）などが有名であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were some known &quot;iemoto&quot; (the head of a school) of Minshingaku player, including &quot;Renzan HIRAI,&quot; a female player who died in May 1886 at the age of 88.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were some known &quot;iemoto&quot; (the head of a school) of Minshingaku player, including &quot;Renzan HIRAI,&quot; a female player who died in May 1886 at the age of 88.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were some known &quot;iemoto&quot; (the head of a school) of Minshingaku musician, including Renzan HIRAI, a female player who died in May 1886 at the age of eighty-eight.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>坂本龍馬(坂本竜馬)とその妻の「楢崎龍」も、清楽の月琴の名手であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Ryoma SAKAMOTO&quot; and his wife &quot;Ryo NARASAKI&quot; were both experts of &quot;gekkin&quot; (a moon harp), an instrument of Shingaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Ryoma SAKAMOTO&quot; and his wife &quot;Ryo NARASAKI&quot; were both experts of &quot;gekkin&quot; (a moon harp), an instrument of Shingaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryoma SAKAMOTO and his wife &apos;Ryo NARASAKI&apos; were both experts of &quot;gekkin&quot; (a moon harp) used in Shingaku.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>清楽は江戸から明治にかけて大人気を博したが、日清戦争を境に急速に衰えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The popularity of Shingaku was quite high from the Edo period to the Meiji period, but after Sino-Japanese War, it was lost rapidly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The popularity of Shingaku was quite high from the Edo period to the Meiji period, but after the Sino-Japanese War, it&apos;s popularity declined rapidly.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The popularity of Shingaku was overwhelmingly high from the Edo period to the Meiji period, but after the Sino-Japanese War, its popularity declined rapidly.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>だが、日本の大衆音楽に残した影響は極めて大きい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Shingaku gave a great impact on Japanese popular music.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Shingaku had a huge impact on Japanese popular music.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Shingaku made a huge impact on Japanese popular music.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>「かんかんのう（看々踊り）」や、「法界節（ほうかいぶし）」や「演歌」も、清楽から発展したものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kankan no&quot; (Kankan dance), &quot;Hokaibushi&quot; and &quot;Enka&quot; (Japanese ballad) all derived from Shingaku.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kankan no&quot; (Kankan dance), &quot;Hokaibushi&quot; and &quot;Enka&quot; (Japanese ballad) all derived from Shingaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kankan no&apos; (Kankan dance), &apos;Hokaibushi&apos; and &apos;Enka&apos; (Japanese ballad) all derived from Shingaku.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>ちなみに「かんかんのう」は江戸から明治にかけて流行した曲で、「法界節」は明治の自由民権の壮士たちが月琴を弾きながら唱った曲である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Incidentally, &quot;Kankan no&quot; was a popular tune from the Edo period to the Meiji period, and &quot;Hokaibushi&quot; was the tune that Freedom and People&apos;s Rights Movement&apos;s desperadoes and others in the Meiji period sang to their own accompaniment of gekkin.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Incidentally, &quot;Kankan no&quot; was a popular tune from the Edo period to the Meiji period, and &quot;Hokaibushi&quot; was the tune that Freedom and People&apos;s Rights Movement&apos;s desperadoes and others in the Meiji period sang to accompany their gekkin.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Incidentally, &apos;Kankan no&apos; was a popular tune from the Edo period to the Meiji period, and &apos;Hokaibushi&apos; was the tune that Freedom and People&apos;s Rights Movement&apos;s desperadoes and others in the Meiji period sang to accompany their gekkin.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>また清楽のメロディーに乗せたさまざまな替え歌は、清楽そのものが衰退したあとも、昭和の初め頃まで歌い継がれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And various parodies, tuned in to the same melody as the original Shingaku song, continued to be sung even after Shingaku itself went into decline until around the early Showa period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And various parodies, tuned in to the same melody as the original Shingaku song, continued to be sung even after Shingaku itself went into decline until around the early Showa period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And various parodies, changed versions of the same melody as the original Shingaku song, continued to be sung by the early Showa period even after Shingaku itself went into decline.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>特徴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Characteristics</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Characteristics</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Characteristics</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="17">
<j>同じ中国伝来の音楽でも、明楽は、宮廷音楽的、雅楽的要素が強かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mingaku had the factors of the court music more than any other music introduced from China.</e>
<cmt>※ここでは「雅楽」も「宮廷音楽」の意味であり、同義反復的に使われています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mingaku contained elements of court music more than any other music introduced from China.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mingaku contained much more elements of the Chinese court music and gagaku than any other music introduced from China.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>これに対して清楽は、俗曲の色彩が強く、歌詞(中国語)の内容も市井に受け入れやすかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In contrast, the important factor of Shingaku was &quot;zokkyoku&quot; (folk songs) and the content of the song&apos;s words (in Chinese) was also accessible for ordinary people in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In contrast, the important factor of Shingaku was &quot;zokkyoku&quot; (folk songs) and the content of the song&apos;s words (in Chinese) was also accessible for ordinary people in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In contrast, the important factor of Shingaku was folk songs and the content of the song&apos;s words (in Chinese) was also accessible for ordinary people in Japan.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>清楽の歌詞は中国語で、江戸時代の日本人は、南方の中国語の発音をカタカナで写し(当時、これを「唐音」と言った)、そのまま唱った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The song&apos;s words were written in Chinese, so Japanese in the Edo period noted the pronunciation of the southern Chinese in &quot;Katakana&quot; (a square form of &quot;kana&quot; [Japanese syllabaries]) - the notes were called &quot;toon&quot; at that time - and they sang with these notes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The song&apos;s words were written in Chinese, so Japanese in the Edo period noted the pronunciation of the southern Chinese in &quot;Katakana&quot; (a square form of &quot;kana&quot; [Japanese syllabaries]) - the notes were called &quot;toon&quot; at that time - and they sang with these notes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The song&apos;s words were written in Chinese, so Japanese during the Edo period noted down the pronunciation of the southern Chinese in &quot;Katakana&quot; (a square form of &quot;kana&quot; [Japanese syllabaries]) - the notes were called &quot;toon&quot; at that time - and they sang according to these notes.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>現代の日本人が、ウクレレやギターを弾きつつ英語の歌を唄うように、江戸から明治にかけての日本人も、清楽の楽器(主として月琴)をかなでつつ唐音で中国語の歌詞を唄ったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As today&apos;s Japanese sing an English song to their own accompaniment of a ukulele or a guitar, so Japanese from the Edo period to the Meiji period sang Chinese words in toon while playing the instrument of Shingaku (mainly, gekkin).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As today&apos;s Japanese sing an English song to their own accompaniment of a ukulele or a guitar, so did Japanese from the Edo period to the Meiji period sang Chinese words in toon while playing the instrument of Shingaku (mainly, gekkin).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As modern Japanese sing an English song to their own accompaniment of a ukulele or a guitar, so did Japanese from the Edo period to the Meiji period, singing Chinese words in &apos;toon&apos; while playing the instrument of Shingaku (mainly, gekkin).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="21">
<j>江戸時代の音楽文化は、概して、身分制や家元制に縛られた窮屈なものだった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The music culture in the Edo period was, as a whole, an inflexible one, which was bound to the class system and to the monopolized system of licensing the teaching of the art.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The music culture in the Edo period was, as a whole, an inflexible one, which was bound to the class system and to the monopolized system of licensing the teaching of the art.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The music culture in the Edo period was, as a whole, rigid as it was bound to the class system and to the monopolized system of licensing of teaching art.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>庶民の楽器であった三味線を武士が弾いたり、虚無僧の法器とされた尺八を百姓町人が吹くことは、江戸時代には許されなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Edo period, warriors could not play &quot;shamisen&quot; (a three-stringed Japanese banjo), which was the instrument for ordinary people, and peasants &amp; merchants could not play &quot;shakuhachi&quot; (a vertical bamboo flute), which was a Buddhist ritual vessel of &quot;komuso&quot; (a mendicant Zen priest of the Fuke sect).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Edo period, warriors could not play &quot;shamisen&quot; (a three-stringed Japanese banjo), which was the instrument for ordinary people, and peasants &amp; merchants could not play &quot;shakuhachi&quot; (a vertical bamboo flute), which was a Buddhist ritual vessel of &quot;komuso&quot; (a mendicant Zen priest of the Fuke sect).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Edo period, warriors were not allowed to play &quot;shamisen&quot; (a three-stringed Japanese banjo), which was the instrument for ordinary people, and peasants and merchants were not allowed to play &quot;shakuhachi&quot; (a vertical bamboo flute), which was a Buddhist ritual vessel of &quot;komuso&quot; (a mendicant Zen priest of the Fuke sect).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>しかし中国伝来の現代音楽(当時として)であった清楽は、例外的に、江戸時代の身分制度から自由であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But Shingaku, the modern music (at that time) introduced from China, was exceptionally free from the class system in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But Shingaku, the modern music (at that time) introduced from China, was exceptionally free from the class system in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But Shingaku, contemporary music introduced from China, was exclusively free from the class system in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>町人も武士も、男も女も、身分の上下や性別を超えて、いっしょになって合奏や合唱を楽しむことができた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Merchants &amp; warriors, and men &amp; women could enjoy an ensemble and a chorus together beyond the wall of the class and gender.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Merchants &amp; warriors, and men &amp; women could enjoy an ensemble and a chorus together beyond the walls of class and gender.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Merchants and warriors, and men and women could enjoy an ensemble and a chorus together without regard of class and gender.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="25">
<j>清楽の代表的な曲には、「算命曲」「九連環（右上の写真の楽譜参照)」「茉莉花 (民謡)」「四季」「紗窓」「売脚魚」「哈哈調」「満江紅」「将軍令」などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Typical Shingaku songs are &quot;Sanminkyo,&quot; &quot;Kyurenkan&quot; (cf. the upper right photograph of the score), &quot;Matsurika&quot; (Jasmine) [minyo], &quot;Shiki&quot; (Four Seasons), &quot;Saso,&quot; &quot;Baikyakugyo,&quot; &quot;Hahacho,&quot; &quot;Man Jiang Hong&quot; and &quot;Jiang Jun Ling.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Typical Shingaku songs are &quot;Sanminkyo,&quot; &quot;Kyurenkan&quot; (cf. the upper right photograph of the score), &quot;Matsurika&quot; (Jasmine) [minyo], &quot;Shiki&quot; (Four Seasons), &quot;Saso,&quot; &quot;Baikyakugyo,&quot; &quot;Hahacho,&quot; &quot;Man Jiang Hong&quot; and &quot;Jiang Jun Ling.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Typical Shingaku songs are &apos;Sanminkyo,&apos; &apos;Kyurenkan&apos; (cf. the upper right photograph of the score), &apos;Matsurika&apos; (folk song), &apos;Shiki&apos;, &apos;Saso,&apos; &apos;Baikyakugyo,&apos; &apos;Hahacho,&apos; &apos;Man Jiang Hong&apos; and &apos;Jiang Jun Ling.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>これらの曲の多くは、現在の中国でも古典的な軽音楽としての生命を保っている(ただし歌詞の字句や編曲などは、日本の清楽のものとかなり違うことが多い)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most of these songs keep their vitality as classical light music even in today&apos;s China; the words, the style of arrangement and others are, in many cases, quite different from those of Shingaku in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most of these songs keep their vitality as classical light music even in today&apos;s China; the words, the style of arrangement and others are, in many cases, quite different from those of Shingaku in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most of these songs keep their vitality as classical popular music even in today&apos;s China; the words, the style of arrangement and others are, in many cases, quite different from those of Shingaku in Japan.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="27">
<j>清楽で使う楽器は、月琴、唐琵琶、清笛、吶(チャルメラ)、三弦子、胡琴など各種の「擦絃楽器」、などであった(右の写真を参照)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The instruments used in Shingaku included various kinds of string instruments, such as &quot;gekkin&quot; (a moon harp), &quot;karabiwa,&quot; &quot;shinteki,&quot; &quot;charamela,&quot; &quot;sangenshi&quot; and &quot;kokin&quot; (cf. the right photograph).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The instruments used in Shingaku included various kinds of string instruments, such as &quot;gekkin&quot; (a moon harp), &quot;karabiwa,&quot; &quot;shinteki,&quot; &quot;charamela,&quot; &quot;sangenshi&quot; and &quot;kokin&quot; (cf. the right photograph).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The instruments used in Shingaku included various kinds of string instruments, such as &quot;gekkin&quot; (Moon guitar), &quot;karabiwa&quot; (Chinese lute), &quot;shinteki&quot; (Qing flute), &quot;charamela&quot; (Suona), &quot;sangenshi&quot; (three-stringed Chinese instrument played with fingers) and &quot;kokin&quot; (Chinese string instrument played with a bow) (cf. the right photograph).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>これらの楽器は、日本人のアマチュア愛好家でも、わりあい簡単に習得できた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These instruments were relatively easy for Japanese amateurs to learn to perform.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These instruments were relatively easy for Japanese amateurs to learn to perform.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These instruments were relatively easy for Japanese amateurs to learn.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>また清楽の旋律は歯切れがよくシンプルなものが多く、覚えるのも簡単だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And most Shingaku melodies were so clear and simple that they were easy to learn by heart, too.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And most Shingaku melodies were so clear and simple that they were easy to learn by heart, too.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides, most Shingaku melodies were so clear and simple that they were easy to learn by heart.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>演奏形式も自由で、同一の曲でも、月琴や胡琴だけの2～3名のアンサンブルや、あるいは月琴を弾き語りするソロなど、適宜、演奏形式を選ぶことができた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, the performance style of Shingaku music was so flexible that players could choose their own style to taste, such as the two or three people&apos;s ensemble with using just gekkin &amp; kokin, and a solo performance of singing to its own accompaniment of gekkin - even when the tune was just the same.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, the performance style of Shingaku music was so flexible that players could choose their own style to taste, such as the two or three people&apos;s ensemble with using just gekkin &amp; kokin, and a solo performance of singing to its own accompaniment of gekkin - even when the tune was just the same.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, the performance style of Shingaku music was so flexible that players could choose their own style to their tastes, such as the two or three people&apos;s ensemble with using just gekkin and kokin, and a solo performance of singing to its own accompaniment of gekkin - even when the tune was just the same.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>明治以降は、清楽の曲を邦楽器や洋楽器でも演奏するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In and after the Meiji period, Shingaku music was performed also by Japanese instruments and by Western instruments.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In and after the Meiji period, Shingaku music was performed also by Japanese instruments and by Western instruments.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In and after the Meiji period, Shingaku music was performed by Japanese instruments and by Western instruments as well.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>明治に刊行された明笛や尺八、手風琴(アコーディオン)、ハーモニカなどの教則本には、当時の日本の曲に混じって、「九連環」「算明曲」「茉莉花」なども収録されていることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Meiji period, instruction books were issued about &quot;minteki,&quot; shakuhachi, accordion and harmonica, and these books often include not only the Japanese songs at that time but also the Shingaku songs, such as &quot;Kyurenkan,&quot; &quot;Sanminkyo&quot; and &quot;Matsurika.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Meiji period, instruction books were issued about &quot;minteki,&quot; shakuhachi, accordion and harmonica, and these books often include not only the Japanese songs at that time but also the Shingaku songs, such as &quot;Kyurenkan,&quot; &quot;Sanminkyo&quot; and &quot;Matsurika.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Meiji period, instruction books were issued about &quot;minteki&quot; (Ming flute), shakuhachi, accordion and harmonica, and these books often include the Japanese songs at that time as well as the Shingaku songs, such as &apos;Kyurenkan,&apos; &apos;Sanminkyo&apos; and &apos;Matsurika.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>現状</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Present situation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Present situation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Present situation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="33">
<j>江戸から明治にかけて、日本でも、清楽の楽譜集の和刻本が多数、出版された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the Edo period to the Meiji period, many music collections of Shingaku, written in Chinese with Japanese leading marks, were issued in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the Edo period to the Meiji period, many music collections of Shingaku, written in Chinese with Japanese leading marks, were issued in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the Edo period to the Meiji period, many music collections of Shingaku, written in Chinese with Japanese leading marks, were issued in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>また、清楽の演奏で使う中国楽器も、長崎経由で輸入されたり、日本で模倣して作られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And Chinese instruments used in performances of Shingaku were imported via Nagasaki, and they were also made in Japan in imitation of the imports.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And Chinese instruments used in performances of Shingaku were imported via Nagasaki, and they were also made in Japan in imitation of the imports.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And Chinese instruments used in performances of Shingaku were imported via Nagasaki, and they were also made in Japan in imitation of the Chinese imports.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>そのため今日でも、古書店や骨董品店で、清楽の楽譜集(たいてい工尺譜で書かれている)や月琴などの楽器を、よく見かける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, music collections of Shingaku, which are written in gongchepu in many cases, and Chinese instruments such as gekkin are often seen at an used bookstore and an antique shop.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, music collections of Shingaku, which are written in gongchepu in many cases, and Chinese instruments such as gekkin are often seen at an used bookstore and an antique shop.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, music collections of Shingaku, which are written in gongchepu in general, and Chinese instruments such as gekkin are often seen at an used bookstore and an antique shop.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="36">
<j>現在の日本で清楽を演奏する団体としては、東京の明清音楽研究会、長崎市の長崎明清楽保存会、神奈川県横須賀市のよこすか龍馬会・月琴部などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the present Japan, there exist some groups that perform Shingaku music, such as the Association of the Study of Ming &amp; Qing-era Chinese Music (in Tokyo), Nagasaki Association of the Preservation of the Ming &amp; Qing-era Chinese Music (in Nagasaki City) and the gekkin section of Yokosuka Association of Ryoma (in Yokosuka City, Kanagawa Prefeture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In present-day Japan, there exist some groups that perform Shingaku music, such as the Association of the Study of Ming &amp; Qing-era Chinese Music (in Tokyo), Nagasaki Association of the Preservation of the Ming &amp; Qing-era Chinese Music (in Nagasaki City) and the gekkin section of Yokosuka Association of Ryoma (in Yokosuka City, Kanagawa Prefeture).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In present-day Japan, there are some groups that perform Shingaku music, such as the Association of the Study of Ming and Qing-era Chinese Music (in Tokyo), Nagasaki Association of the Preservation of the Ming and Qing-era Chinese Music (in Nagasaki City) and the gekkin section of Yokosuka Association of Ryoma (in Yokosuka City, Kanagawa Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>このほか、清楽の演奏を録音したレコードやＣＤなども若干ある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides, there exist some records &amp; CDs in Japan that record the performances of Shingaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides, there exist some records &amp; CDs in Japan that record the performances of Shingaku.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides, there exist some record albums and CDs in Japan that contain the performances of Shingaku.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Camelia(id:112815), 軽功(id:40602), S02944ty(id:36412), ととりん(id:31982), Takavoid(id:120830), ウィキ太郎(id:81560), Nighthawks(id:36125), TS(id:481), Nate(id:165259), BitBucket(id:30999), K. Takeda(id:119013), Kaznov17(id:68122), Nakaoka7675(id:39645), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>