<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>舞鶴かまぼこ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Maizuru Kamaboko (Fish Minced and Steamed)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Maizuru Kamaboko (Fish Minced and Steamed)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Maizuru Kamaboko (Fish Minced and Steamed)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>舞鶴かまぼこ（まいづるかまぼこ）は、京都府舞鶴市で製造・販売されている蒲鉾のブランド。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Maizuru Kamaboko&quot; is a brand of kamaboko (fish minced and steamed) made and sold in Maizuru City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Maizuru Kamaboko&quot; is a brand of kamaboko (fish minced and steamed) made and sold in Maizuru City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Maizuru Kamaboko&quot; is a brand of kamaboko (fish minced and steamed) made and sold in Maizuru City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>2006年10月27日には地域団体商標制度（地域ブランド）の認定第一弾として認定された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 27, 2006, it was certified as the first certification of Regional Organizations&apos; Trademark System (Regional Brand).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 27, 2006, it was certified as the first certification of Regional Organizations&apos; Trademark System (Regional Brand).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On October 27, 2006, it was certified as the first certification of Regional Organizations&apos; Trademark System (Regional Brand).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>舞鶴かまぼこは近畿北部の海の玄関口である舞鶴港を擁する舞鶴市の名産品で、舞鶴近海の日本海沿岸で獲れた魚（シログチ等）をすり身にし伝統製法で作られている蒲鉾で、贈答品として人気がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Maizuru Kamaboko is a specialty of Maizuru City, having Maizuru Port, as the sea gateway in the northern part of Kinki region, which is kamaboko made by traditional methods, mincing the fish (including white croakers) caught along the coast of the Japan Sea near Maizuru, and it is popular as a gift item.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Maizuru Kamaboko is a specialty of Maizuru City, having Maizuru Port, as the sea gateway in the northern part of the Kinki region, kamaboko is made by traditional methods, mincing fish (including white croakers) caught along the coast of the Japan Sea near Maizuru, and it is popular as a gift item.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Maizuru Kamaboko is a specialty of Maizuru City, having Maizuru Port, as the sea gateway in the northern part of the Kinki region, and the kamaboko is made by traditional methods, mincing fish (including white croakers) caught along the coast of the Japan Sea near Maizuru, and it is popular as a gift item.</e>
<cmt>文章の接続に　andを挿入。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 フェロもん(id:96171), ぱむ(id:24323), ととりん(id:31982), 満月(id:82772), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>