<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>竹紙</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chikushi</e>
<cmt>下記で竹紙についての2つの意味を説明しているので、ここでの補足は省きます。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chikushi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chikushi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>竹紙（ちくし）とは；</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chikushi;</e>
<cmt>ウェブでは、ここは箇条書きのタイトルとなるところなので、originalの「、」終わりを、「；」終わりに変更し、1文としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chikushi;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chikushi;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>竹を原料として作った紙。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Paper made from bamboo.</e>
<cmt>文というより、箇条書きスタイルなので、そのように訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Paper made from bamboo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Paper made from bamboo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="3">
<j>竹の内側から取れる薄皮。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Inner thin skin of a bamboo tree.</e>
<cmt>文というより、箇条書きスタイルなので、そのように訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Inner thin skin of a bamboo tree.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Inner thin skin of a bamboo tree.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>竹紙（紙）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chikushi (bamboo paper)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chikushi (bamboo paper)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chikushi (bamboo paper)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>竹紙は、竹の表皮や竹の子の繊維を原料として作った紙。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chikushi is a paper made from bark of bamboo and fiber of bamboo shoot.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chikushi is paper made from bark of bamboo and fiber of bamboo shoot.</e>
<cmt>a 削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chikushi is paper made from bark of bamboo and fiber of bamboo shoot.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>主として中国・江南で作られていたが、日本でも和紙の一種として一部において作られていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has been made as a type of Japanese paper in some part of Japan, but mainly it has been manufactured in Konan region, China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It had been mainly manufactured in Konan region, China, and also in Japan as a type of Japanese paper.</e>
<cmt>修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It had been mainly manufactured in Konan region, China, and also in Japan as a type of Japanese paper.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>薄く破れやすいが墨引が良く、虫に対して丈夫なために書画に用いる紙として文人達に愛された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although it is very thin, its spread of sumi ink is good and is strong against insect, so that many literati loved it, as a paper used for calligraphic works and paintings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although it is very thin, its spread of sumi ink is good and is strong against insect, so that many literati loved it, as paper used for calligraphic works and paintings.</e>
<cmt>a 削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it is very thin, its spread of sumi ink is good and is strong against insect, so that many literati loved it, as paper used for calligraphic works and paintings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>古くは東晋において竹の産地として知られていた会稽郡の竹紙が著名であったが、脆弱性と耐久性の無さから長く下質な紙として扱われてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Formerly, chikushi made in the Province of Hui Ji, which was famous bamboo production area, was well known in Eastern Jin Dynasty, but for long time it was treated as poor quality paper from its weakness and lack of durability.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Formerly, chikushi made in the Province of Hui Ji, which was famous bamboo production area and was well known in Eastern Jin Dynasty, but for long time it had been treated as poor quality paper due to its weakness and lack of durability.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Formerly, chikushi made in the Province of Hui Ji, which was famous bamboo production area and was well known in Eastern Jin Dynasty, but for long time it had been treated as poor quality paper due to its weakness and lack of durability.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>だが、北宋時代に改良が加えられてより丈夫になり、また王安石や蘇軾がその光沢や墨の発色ぶりと保色性を高く評価してこれを寵愛した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However the paper became stronger with improvement made in the Northern Song Dynasty Period, and Wang Anshi and Su Shi (Chinese poet) favored its gloss, color development of sumi ink and color retention.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, with improvement made in the Northern Song Dynasty Period, chikushi paper became stronger, which Wang Anshi and Su Shi (Chinese poet) favored because of its gloss, color development of sumi ink and color retention.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, with improvement made in the Northern Song Dynasty Period, chikushi paper became stronger, which Wang Anshi and Su Shi (Chinese poet) favored because of its gloss, color development of sumi ink and color retention.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>この事から、従来の高級紙であった藤紙や麻紙に代わって、書簡や書画に用いられるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of these, chikushi had replaced wisteria paper and mashi (paper made of hemp), the former high quality papers, and used for letter and calligraphic work and paintings.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of these, chikushi had replaced wisteria paper and mashi (paper made of hemp), the former high quality papers, and had become used for letter and calligraphic work and paintings.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of these, chikushi had replaced wisteria paper and mashi (paper made of hemp), the former high quality papers, and had become used for letter and calligraphic work and paintings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>竹紙（竹の内側の皮）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chikushi (inner skin of a bamboo tree)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chikushi (inner skin of a bamboo tree)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chikushi (inner skin of a bamboo tree)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>竹紙は、竹の内側から採れる薄皮。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chikushi is an inner thin skin of a bamboo tree.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chikushi is an inner thin skin of a bamboo tree.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chikushi is an inner thin skin of a bamboo tree.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="11">
<j>笛の一種民笛にはこの竹紙を張るための響穴があり、吹いた際に竹紙が振動することにより独特の音が出、より音が響く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Minteki, a type of flute, has acoustic bore to stick chikushi, which vibrate to give out unique sound and the sound reverberate better when the flute is played.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Minteki, a type of flute, has acoustic bore to stick chikushi, which vibrate to give out unique sound and the sound reverberates better when the flute is played.</e>
<cmt>reverberate →reverberates</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Minteki, a type of flute, has acoustic bore to stick chikushi, which vibrate to give out unique sound and the sound reverberates better when the flute is played.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>竹紙の薄く、また空気を通さず、唾で容易に張り付くといった性質を利用したものであり、淡竹や黒竹のものが使用されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is a utilization of thin, airtight, and easily sticking with saliva properties of chikushi, and chikushi from henon bamboo and kurochiku (black bamboo) are used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This applies the characteristic of chikushi, which is thin, airtight, and easily sticking with saliva, and chikushi made of henon bamboo and kurochiku (black bamboo) are used.</e>
<cmt>修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chikushi made from henon bamboo or black bamboo is used for the flute because it is thin, provides an airtight seal, and can easily be pasted onto the flute with saliva.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせて修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>特に有用な代用品は無く、手に入らない場合苦肉の策としてセロハンテープを張る者もいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are no serviceable substitutes, but some people uses cellophane tape if they cannot obtain one, as a desperate resort.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are no serviceable substitutes, but some people use a cellophane tape if they cannot obtain one, as a desperate resort.</e>
<cmt>uses →　usea追加 修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are no serviceable substitutes, but some people use a cellophane tape if they cannot obtain one, as a desperate resort.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>しかし、十分な振動が得られないため音が悪く、笛の表面を傷めることもあるため、好ましくない行為である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However it is not a favorable choice, as it will damage surface of a flute, and the sound is bad, because cellophane tape cannot produce enough vibration.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However it is not a favorable choice, as it damages the surface of flute, and the sound is bad because the cellophane tape cannot produce enough vibration.</e>
<cmt>修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However it is not a favorable choice, as it damages the surface of flute, and the sound is bad because the cellophane tape cannot produce enough vibration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>こういった笛は、竹紙を採取しなければならないこと、うまく調整して張る技術が必要とされること、破れやすいこと、乾湿により響きが変わることなど、手間がかかるものであるため現在は広く使用されているものではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Presently such flute is not widely used because of much effort required, such as gathering of chikushi, technique to stick chikushi with correct adjustment, and its easy to break and change a sound with humidity properties.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Presently, such flute is not widely used because it requires much efforts, such as collection of chikushi, techniques to stick chikushi with correct adjustment, and its easy-to-break nature, and changeable sound with humidity.</e>
<cmt>修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Presently, such flutes are not widely used because they require too much effort in that chikushi has to be collected, techniques for pasting chikushi to the flute by making appropriate adjustments have to be employed, chikushi breaks easily, and the sound produced by these flutes varies depending on the level of humidity.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせて修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>しかし、長崎の竹ん芸、日田祇園祭、唐津くんち、浜崎祇園山笠などの祭囃子で聴くことができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However such flute can be heard in matsuri-bayashi, (Japanese music) of Takenge festival in Nagasaki, Hita Gion Matsuri Festival, Karatsu Kunchi Festival and Hamasaki Gion Yamagasa Festival.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, such flutes can still be heard in matsuri-bayashi (Japanese music), of Takenge festival in Nagasaki, Hita Gion Matsuri Festival, Karatsu Kunchi Festival and Hamasaki Gion Yamagasa Festival.</e>
<cmt>修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, such flutes can still be heard in matsuri-bayashi (Japanese music), of Takenge festival in Nagasaki, Hita Gion Matsuri Festival, Karatsu Kunchi Festival and Hamasaki Gion Yamagasa Festival.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>張り加減の好みについては、地域や地区により異なる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A liking for tension of chikushi is different in each region and area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Preference on the grade of tension when putting on chikushi differs according to each region and area.</e>
<cmt>修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Preferences with regard to the degree of tension desired when pasting chikushi onto the flute vary according to the region and area.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせて修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="18">
<j>そのほか、漢方においては強壮剤としても使用されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, chikushi is also used as a stimulant in traditional Chinese medicine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, chikushi is also used as a stimulant in traditional Chinese medicine.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, chikushi is also used as a stimulant in traditional Chinese medicine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Mooko(id:36162), Hamasaki gion higashi(id:144985), Tatsujin28(id:9300), Vvawavv(id:82129), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>