<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>日置流</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Heki-ryu school</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Heki-ryu school</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Heki School</e>
<cmt>タイトルなのでSchoolとしました。-ryu削除</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>日置流（へきりゅう）とは、古流の逸見流を学んだ日置弾正政次（へきだんじょうまさつぐ）（正次とも）が確立した、和弓の流派の一つである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Heki-ryu school established by Masatsugu Danjo HEKI, who learnt the ancient Henmi-ryu school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Heki-ryu school was established by Masatsugu Danjo HEKI, who learned in the ancient Henmi-ryu school.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Heki school was established by Masatsugu Danjo HEKI, who learned in the ancient Henmi school.</e>
<cmt>-ryu削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>日置弾正正次は室町時代（15世紀後半）の人といわれているが諸説あり、神仏の化身と称されたり、日置吉田流初代・吉田上野介重賢であるとされたり（同一人物説）する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masatsugu Danjo HEKI is said to be a person of Muromachi Era (the latter half of the 15th century). However, there are various opinions. Some says he was god or Buddha&apos; incarnation. Some says he was the same person as the first representative of Heki-yoshida-ryu school Shigetaka Kozukenosuke YOSHIDA. After all, the theory that he was a fictitious character is persuasive.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masatsugu Danjo HEKI is said to be a person of the Muromachi Era (latter half of the 15th century). However, there are various opinions. Some say he was god or Buddha&apos; incarnated. Some say he was the same person as the first representative of Heki-yoshida-ryu school Shigetaka Kozukenosuke YOSHIDA.. Finally, the theory that he was a fictitious character is persuasive.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masatsugu Danjo HEKI is said to be a person of the Muromachi period (latter half of the 15th century), however, there are various opinions: some say he was god or Buddha&apos; incarnated; some say he was the same person as the first representative of Heki-Yoshida school Shigetaka Kozukenosuke YOSHIDA.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理eraに訂正しました。一文にしました。Yoshidaに訂正しました。-ryu削除era→periodに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>架空の人物との説が有力である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Finally, the theory that he was a fictitious character is persuasive.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>特徴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Features</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Features</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Features</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>日本の弓道は、主に戦場における徒歩による弓射から発展した「歩射」と、馬上から射る弓射から発展した「騎射」、三十三間堂における通し矢の弓射から発展した「堂射」に分類することが出来る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Archery in Japan can be classified mainly into &quot;Busha/Kachiyumi (walking archery)&quot;, which was developed from bow shooting on foot in a battlefield, &quot;Kisha (riding archery)&quot;, which was developed from bow shooting while riding horse, and &quot;Dosha (long-range archery)&quot;, which was developed from Toshiya (long-range archery) passing through the Sanjusangendo Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Archery in Japan can be classified mainly into &quot;Busha/Kachiyumi (walking archery),&quot; developed from bow shooting on foot on the battlefield, &quot;Kisha (riding archery),&quot; developed from bow shooting while riding horseback, and &quot;Dosha (long-range archery),&quot; developed from Toshiya (long-range archery) passing through the Sanjusangendo Temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Archery in Japan can be classified mainly into &apos;Busha/Kachiyumi&apos; (walking archery), developed from bow shooting on foot on the battlefield, &apos;Kisha&apos; (riding archery), developed from bow shooting while riding horseback, and &apos;Dosha&apos; (long-range archery), developed from Toshiya (long-range archery) passing through the Sanjusangen-do Temple.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;にスペース削除-補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>今日的な分類では、弓道を武射と礼射に分ける考え方が主流となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a modern classification, the idea that divided archery into busha (archery for battle) and reisha (archery for ceremony) has become the main common practice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In a modern classification, the idea that divided archery into busha (archery for battle) and reisha (archery for ceremony) has become the main common practice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In a modern classification, the idea that divided archery into busha (archery for battle) and reisha (archery for ceremony) has become the main common practice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>武射系と言えば日置流系統の射を指し（この場合は歩射・堂射が含まれている）、礼射系と言えば、小笠原流騎射・歩射から儀礼・儀式的なものを加味されつつ発展した射の系統を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When it comes to busha group, it refers to Heki school system. (In this case, it includes walking archery and long-range archery). When it comes to reisha group, it refers to the shooting system developed from Ogasawara-ryu school&apos;s riding archery and walking archery but gradually implemented with ceremonial elements.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When it comes to the busha group, it refers to the Heki school system. (In this case, it includes walking archery and long-range archery). When it comes to the reisha group, it refers to the shooting system developed from Ogasawara-ryu school&apos;s riding archery and walking archery, but gradually implemented with ceremonial elements.</e>
<cmt>grammar, spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When it comes to the busha group, it refers to the Heki school system (in this case, it includes walking archery and long-range archery), and when it comes to the reisha group, it refers to the shooting system developed from Ogasawara school&apos;s riding archery and walking archery, but gradually implemented with ceremonial elements.</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。-ryu削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>900年近く続く小笠原流と比べると日置流の歴史は新しく500年程である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Compared with Ogasawara-ryu school with a history of about 900 years, Heki school is new with a history of about 500 years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Compared with Ogasawara-ryu school with a history of about 900 years, Heki school is new with a history of about 500 years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Compared with Ogasawara school with a history of about 900 years, Heki school is new with a history of about 500 years.</e>
<cmt>-ryu削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>ただ、戦国時代の一時期、没落した小笠原家に変わり、日置吉田流一門が宮中で射礼を行った事もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, for a certain period of time in the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States), instead of the declined Ogasawara family, Heki-yoshida-ryu school group did the ceremonial shootings in the Imperial court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, for a certain period of time during the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States), instead of the declining Ogasawara family, the Heki-yoshida-ryu school group performed the ceremonial shootings in the Imperial court.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, for a certain period of time during the Sengoku period (period of Warring States), instead of the declining Ogasawara family, the Heki-Yoshida school group performed the ceremonial shootings in the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>periodに訂正しました。Yoshidaに訂正しました。-ryu削除Courtに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>なお、弓の引き方を儀礼的に行うことを一般に「礼射」というが、その際に小笠原流が「礼射」と称するところのものを日置流では「体配（たいはい）」と呼び、区別している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Pulling the bow in a ceremonial way is in general referred as &quot;ceremonial shooting&quot;. However in that case, Heki school called this &quot;ceremonial shooting&quot; of Ogasawara-ryu school &quot;Taihai (posture and manner of the martial art)&quot; in order to distinguish.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Pulling the bow in a ceremonial way is generally referred to as &quot;ceremonial shooting.&quot; However, the Heki school called this &quot;ceremonial shooting&quot; of the Ogasawara-ryu school &quot;Taihai (posture and manner of the martial art)&quot; in order to distinguish it.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Pulling the bow in a ceremonial way is generally referred to as &apos;Reisha&apos; (ceremonial shooting), however, the Heki school called this &apos;Reisha&apos; of the Ogasawara school &apos;Taihai&apos; (posture and manner of the martial art) in order to distinguish it.</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。&apos;Reisha&apos; (ceremonial shooting)としました。原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に-ryu削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>日置流の体配は、簡略な動作から生まれる武士らしい気合の充実が特徴である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taihai of the Heki school is characterized by enhanced spirit born from simple gestures resembling that of a samurai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taihai of the Heki school is characterized by enhanced spirit born from simple gestures resembling those of a samurai.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taihai of the Heki school is characterized by enhanced spirit born from simple gestures resembling those of a samurai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>小笠原流が騎射を出発点とし、主に見た目の美しさや品位を重視するものであったのに対して、日置流は的中や矢の貫通力に重点を置いた実利的な歩兵用弓術であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ogasawara-ryu school originated from riding shoot emphasizes chiefly beauty and elegance of externals. On the contrary, the Heki school is a practical archery for infantrymen which put its emphasis on the targeting accuracy and the penetrating power of arrow.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ogasawara-ryu school originated from shooting while riding and emphasizes chiefly beauty and elegance. On the contrary, the Heki school is practical archery for infantrymen which places emphasis on target accuracy and the penetrating power of an arrow.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ogasawara school originated from shooting while riding and emphasizes chiefly beauty and elegance, on the contrary, the Heki school is practical archery for infantrymen which places emphasis on target accuracy and the penetrating power of an arrow.</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。-ryu削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>現在では、同じ「弓道」という競技において、本来は目的の異なる別のものである「歩射」「騎射」「堂射」の違いを深く理解している射手は少数となってしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nowadays, they are under the same category as the competitive game &quot;Archery&quot;. There are a small number of archers who understand thoroughly the difference between &quot;walking archery&quot;, &quot;riding archery&quot; and long-range archery&quot;, whose purposes are originally different.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nowadays, they are both categorized as competitive game &quot;Archery.&quot; There are a small number of archers who thoroughly understand the difference between &quot;walking archery,&quot; &quot;riding archery,&quot; and long-range archery,&quot; the purposes of which were originally different.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nowadays, they are both categorized as competitive game &apos;Archery,&apos; though, there are a small number of archers who thoroughly understand the difference between &apos;walking archery,&apos; &apos;riding archery,&apos; and &apos;long-range archery,&apos; the purposes of which were originally different.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に一文にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>また、今日では日置流や小笠原流、日置流堂射流派の垣根が低くなってきている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, today, the fence of Heki-ryu school, Ogasawara-ryu school, and Dosha-ryu group of Heki-ryu school has become lowered.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, today, the fence separating the Heki-ryu school, the Ogasawara-ryu school, and the Dosha-ryu group of the Heki-ryu school, has owered.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, today, the fence separating the Heki school, the Ogasawara school, and the Dosha group of the Heki school, has lowered.</e>
<cmt>loweredスペル-ryu削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>しかし、発展過程がそれぞれ異なる、日置流（武射系）や小笠原流（礼射系）の文化的・歴史的な背景に敬意を払い、よく理解して弓道を学ぶことが望ましい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the processes of development are respectively different. It is hoped that learners of archery should pay respect to and understand well the cultural and historic backgrounds of Heki school (busha group) and Ogasawara-ryu school (reisha group).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the development processes are respectively different. It is hoped that students of archery will pay respect to and understand well the cultural and historical backgrounds of the Heki school (busha group) and the Ogasawara-ryu school (reisha group).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, because the development processes are respectively different, it is hoped that students of archery will pay respect to and understand well the cultural and historical backgrounds of the Heki school (busha group) and the Ogasawara school (reisha group).</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。-ryu削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="16">
<j>日置流には、途切れたものや現存するものを含めると多くの派が存在するが、古来の「派」の位置付けは「教えを受けた～家・～師匠の流れを組むもの」程度の意味合いであったと考えられ、伝承してきた教えの解釈等の違いから生ずる小さな違いはあるが、根幹となる教えはどの派でも同一である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For Heki school, there are a lot of sects, including both the discontinued ones and the existing ones. Traditionally, &quot;school&quot; has been referring to &quot;a system of unified style from a family or master with handed-down teachings&quot;. There may be minor differences caused from the discrepancies in interpretation of handed-down teachings. However, the teaching that forms the foundation of any sect is the same.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For the Heki school, there are a lot of sects, including both the discontinued ones and the existing ones. Traditionally, the &quot;school&quot; has been referring to &quot;a system of unified styles from a family or master who passed down their teachings.&quot; There may be minor differences caused from discrepancies in interpretation of the teachings. However, teaching that forms the foundation of any sect is basically the same.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For the Heki school, there are a lot of sects, including both the discontinued ones and the existing ones; traditionally, the &apos;school&apos; has been referring to &apos;a system of unified styles from a family or master who passed down their teachings,&apos; that is, there may be minor differences caused from discrepancies in interpretation of the teachings, however teaching that forms the foundation of any sect is basically the same.</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="17">
<j>射法</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shooting method</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shooting method</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shooting method</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="18">
<j>小笠原流が多くの場合、射の行程における打起しと呼ばれる動作において身体の正面で構える形、いわゆる「正面打起し」をとるのに対し、日置流では「斜面打起し」をとる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In many cases of Ogasawara-ryu school, there are facing postures of shooting at distance. That is, the so-called &quot;Shomen-uchiokoshi (anchoring in front facing posture)&quot; is taken. On the contrary, Heki-ryu school takes &quot;Shamen-uchiokoshi (anchoring in slanting position)&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In many cases of Ogasawara-ryu school, there are facing postures for shooting at a distance. That is, the so-called &quot;Shomen-uchiokoshi (anchoring in front facing posture)&quot; is taught. On the contrary, the Heki-ryu school teaches &quot;Shamen-uchiokoshi (anchoring in a slanted position)&quot;.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In many cases of Ogasawara school, there are facing postures for shooting at a distance, that is, the so-called &apos;Shomen-uchiokoshi&apos; (anchoring in front facing posture) is taught; on the contrary, the Heki school teaches &apos;Shamen-uchiokoshi&apos; (anchoring in a slanted position).</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に-ryu削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>（本多流を除く）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Except for the Honda-ryu school)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Except for the Honda-ryu school)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Except for the Honda school)</e>
<cmt>-ryu削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="20">
<j>日置流が斜面打ち起こしの射法であるのは、弓の握り方に独特の教えがあるからであり、矢を放つ際に的中率・貫通率を高める事等を目的としている為である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Heki-ryu school takes the shooting method of &quot;Shamen-uchiokoshi (anchoring in slanting position)&quot; because it has peculiar teachings to how to grip the bow. Also, the purpose is to increase the hitting chance and the penetrating rate when the arrow is shot.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Heki-ryu school teaches the shooting method of &quot;Shamen-uchiokoshi (anchoring in a slantied position)&quot; because it has peculiar teaching about how to grip the bow. Also, the purpose is to increase the chance of hitting the target and the penetrating rate when the arrow is shot.</e>
<cmt>grammar,</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Heki school teaches the shooting method of &apos;Shamen-uchiokoshi&apos; (anchoring in a slanted position) because it has peculiar teaching about how to grip the bow, also the purpose is to increase the chance of hitting the target and the penetrating rate when the arrow is shot.</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。前の文章にならい&quot;を&apos;に-ryu削除slanted スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>例えば、印西派ではこの握り方を「紅葉重（もみじがさ）ね」といい、古来から秘伝とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For instance, in Insai-ha school, this way to grasp is called &quot;Momiji-gasane&quot;. It was a way how to grip the bow with left hand secretly handed down from the old days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For instance, in the Insai-ha school, the way to grip the bow is called &quot;Momiji-gasane.&quot; a method of gripping the bow with the left hand secretly handed down from the old days.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For instance, in the Insai school, the way to grip the bow is called &apos;Momiji-gasane;&apos; a method of gripping the bow with the left hand secretly handed down from the old days.</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に-ha削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>また戦場での体勢で即座に敵を射る為に、矢を番えた弓を体の左斜め前方で構える事が有利であるのも理由である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, since this way can shoot the enemy immediately by a body pose in a battlefield, it is advantageous for the shooter anchoring in front facing posture to set up the bow.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, since this way allows the archer to shoot the enemy immediately by employing this body pose on the battlefield, it is advantageous for the archer anchored in the frontal facing posture, to set up the bow.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, since this way allows the archer to shoot the enemy immediately by employing this body pose on the battlefield, it is advantageous for the archer anchored in the frontal facing posture, to set up the bow.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="23">
<j>なお、和弓では利き手にかかわらず、弓は左手で押し、弦は右手で引くのが通常である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Usually in the Japanese bow, regardless of the dominant hand, the bow is pushed by the left hand and the bowstring is pulled by the right hand.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Usually in the Japanese bow, regardless of the archer&apos;s dominant hand, is pushed by the left hand and the bowstring is pulled by the right hand.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Usually in the Japanese bow, regardless of the archer&apos;s dominant hand, is pushed by the left hand and the bowstring is pulled by the right hand.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="24">
<j>これは、弓兵を集団で訓練し運用する事を容易にし、また規格を統一する事で弓具を大量生産する為の名残であると考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is thought that, this facilitates the training of bow soldiers in group. And because of the unification of standards, bow, arrows, etc. could be mass-produced.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is thought that, this facilitates the training of archers in group. And because of the unifide standards, bow, arrows, etc. could be mass-produced.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is thought that, this facilitates the training of archers in group, and because of the unified standards, bow and arrows, could be mass-produced.</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。unifiedスペル、を,に訂正しました。etc.は不要と考えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="25">
<j>武士が戦場での実戦を出発点として磨き上げてきた弓術、それが日置流である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the starting point of a samurai actually combat in a battlefield, Heki-ryu school has contributed much to the polishing up of archery.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a starting point for samurai who actually engage in combat on the battlefield, the Heki-ryu school has contributed much to the refining archery techniques.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a starting point for samurai who in fact engage in combat on the battlefield, the Heki school has contributed much to the refining archery techniques.</e>
<cmt>-ryu削除actually →in factに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="26">
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>日置流は、「吾国弓術中興始祖也」（『本朝武芸小伝』）と称される日置弾正正次（生没年不詳）を祖とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The founder of Heki-ryu school is said to be Masatsugu Danjo HEKI(date of birth and death unknown), who is described as &quot;he is a founder of restored archery in my country Japan&quot; in &quot;Honcho Bugei Shoden (a survey of traditional Japanese martial arts)&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The founder of the Heki-ryu school is said to be Masatsugu Danjo HEKI (date of birth and death unknown), who is described as &quot;the founder of restored archery in my country Japan&quot; in &quot;Honcho Bugei Shoden (a survey of traditional Japanese martial arts)&quot;.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The founder of the Heki school is said to be Masatsugu Danjo HEKI (date of birth and death unknown), who is described as &apos;the founder of restored archery in my country Japan&apos; in &quot;Honcho Bugei Shoden&quot; (a survey of traditional Japanese martial arts).</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に&quot;の位置を訂正。-ryu削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>日置弾正は室町時代中期（15世紀後半）の大和の人といわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Danjo HEKI is said to be a person of Yamato during mid Muromachi Era (latter half of the 15th century). There are many uncertainties about him. Some says he is a real existing person. Some says he is a fictitious person. Some says he is the same person as Shigekata YOSHIDA of Yoshida-ryu school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Danjo HEKI is said to be a person of Yamato during the mid Muromachi Era (latter half of the 15th century). There are many uncertainties about him. Some says he was a real existing person. Some says he is fictitious. Some say he is the same person as Shigekata YOSHIDA of the Yoshida-ryu school.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Danjo HEKI is said to be a person of Yamato during the mid Muromachi period (latter half of the 15th century).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理eraに訂正しました。era→periodに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>しかし、その経歴については不明な点も多く、実在説、架空人物説、吉田流初代・吉田重賢と同一人物とする説などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are many uncertainties about him: some says he was a real existing person; some says he is fictitious; some say he is the same person as Shigekata YOSHIDA of the Yoshida school.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理一文にしました。-ryu削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>神仏の化身とも称された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was called gods and Buddha&apos; incarnations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was called god and Buddha&apos; incarnations.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was called god and Buddha&apos; incarnations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>日置弾正の高弟の一人に吉田重賢がおり、以後主に吉田氏により継承されたので吉田流ともいうが、現在では一部を除き日置流と呼ぶ場合が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of the best pupils of Danjo HEKI is Shigekata YOSHIDA. Thereafter, the teachings were chiefly succeeded to the Yoshida clan. Thus, it was also called the Yoshida style. However now, except for a part, it is often called the Heki-ryu school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of the best pupils of Danjo HEKI was Shigekata YOSHIDA. Thereafter, the teachings were chiefly succeeded to the Yoshida clan. It was also known as the Yoshida style. However now, except for a certain segment, it is often called the Heki-ryu school.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of the best pupils of Danjo HEKI was Shigekata YOSHIDA; thereafter, the teachings were chiefly succeeded to the Yoshida clan, and it was also known as the Yoshida style, however now, except for a certain segment, it is often called the Heki school.</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。-ryu削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="32">
<j>吉田重賢（太郎左衛門・上野介・出雲守など、号：道宝）（寛正4年（1463） - 天文 (元号)12年（1543））は南近江の戦国大名六角氏家臣で、川守城（現竜王町川守）を本拠としていたと伝わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that, Shigekata YOSHIDA (also called Tarozaemon, Kozukenosuke, Izumo-no-kami (chief of Izumo-no-kuni), title: Doho)(1463 - 1543) was a retainer of the Rokkaku clan which is a daimyo of the region Minami Omi during the Sengoku Period. It is also said that Shigekata YOSHIDA based his activities around Kawamori Castle (present&apos;s Kawamori, Ryuo-cho).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that, Shigekata YOSHIDA (also called Tarozaemon, Kozukenosuke, Izumo-no-kami (chief of Izumo-no-kuni), title: Doho)(1463 - 1543) was a retainer of the Rokkaku clan which was a daimyo of the Minami Omi region during the Sengoku Period. It is also said that Shigekata YOSHIDA based his activities around Kawamori Castle (present day Kawamori, Ryuo-cho).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that, Shigekata YOSHIDA (also called Tarozaemon, Kozukenosuke, Izumo no kami (chief of Izumo Province), his title was Doho)(1463 - 1543) was a retainer of the Rokkaku clan which was a daimyo of the Minami Omi region during the Sengoku Period, and it is also said that Shigekata YOSHIDA based his activities around Kawamori Castle (present day Kawamori, Ryuo-cho).</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。-ryu削除Izumo Provinceに訂正しました。-削除his title wasに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="33">
<j>吉田氏は主家の六角氏と同じ近江源氏（佐々木氏）の一族で、源頼朝に従って活躍した佐々木定綱らの弟厳秀に始まる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Like the Rokkaku clan, which is the main family, the Yoshida clan is a clan of Omi-Genji (the Minamoto clan) (the Sasaki clan). It starts from Genshu, the younger brother of Sadatsuna SASAKI, who was following MINAMOTO no Yoritomo and taking an active part.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Like the Rokkaku clan, which is the main family, the Yoshida clan is a clan of Omi-Genji (the Minamoto clan) (the Sasaki clan). It starts from Genshu, the younger brother of Sadatsuna SASAKI, who was following MINAMOTO no Yoritomo taking an active part.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Like the Rokkaku clan, which is the main family, the Yoshida clan is a clan of Omi-Genji (the Minamoto clan) (the Sasaki clan); it starts from Genshu, the younger brother of Sadatsuna SASAKI, who was following MINAMOTO no Yoritomo taking an active part.</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>近江吉田荘、または出雲吉田村を名字としたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omi-yoshida-sho. Or, it is said that the family name is Izumo-yoshida-mura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omi-yoshida-sho. Or, it is said that the family name is Izumo-yoshida-mura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omi-Yoshida-sho, or, it is said that the family name is Izumo-Yoshida-mura.</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。Yoshidaに訂正しました。スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>山陰の戦国大名尼子氏（佐々木氏支族）配下にも吉田氏がおり、同族ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Yoshida clan was also under the Amago clan (branch family of Sasaki clan), which was a feudal lord (daimyo) of Sanin during the provincial wars. It is said to be the same clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Yoshida clan was also under the Amago clan (branch family of the Sasaki clan), which was a feudal lord (daimyo) of Sanin during the provincial wars. It is said to be the same clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Yoshida clan was also under the Amago clan (branch family of the Sasaki clan), which was a feudal lord (daimyo) of Sanin during the provincial wars; it is said to be the same clan.</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="36">
<j>江戸時代後期に編纂された寛政重修諸家譜の吉田氏系図（印西派宗家の旗本吉田氏が提出したもの）には、出自について「宇多源氏　佐々木庶流　今の呈譜に吉田厳秀より出るといふ。」とある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In family tree of the Yoshida clan (submitted by a direct retainer of the shogun Insai-ha Soke (head of Insai-ha school)) of Kansei-Choshu-Shokafu (genealogies of vassals in Edo Bakufu) edited during late Edo Era, concerning the origin, it written, &quot;Uda-Genji (Minamoto clan), illegitimate family lineage of the Sasaki family. According to present&apos;s accepted genealogy, it is said to be from Genshu YOSHIDA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the family tree of the Yoshida clan (submitted by a direct retainer of the shogun Insai-ha Soke - head of the Insai-ha school) of Kansei-Choshu-Shokafu (genealogies of vassals in the Edo Bakufu) edited during late Edo Era, concerning the origin, it was written, &quot;Uda-Genji&quot; (Minamoto clan), an illegitimate family lineage of the Sasaki family. According to present&apos;s accepted genealogy, it is said to be from Genshu YOSHIDA..</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the family tree of the Yoshida clan (submitted by a direct retainer of the shogun Insai school soke - head of the Insai school) of Kansei-Choshu-Shokafu (genealogies of vassals in the Edo Bakufu) edited during late Edo period, concerning the origin, it was written, &apos;Uda-Genji (Minamoto clan), an illegitimate family lineage of the Sasaki family. According to present&apos;s accepted genealogy, it is said to be from Genshu YOSHIDA.&apos;</e>
<cmt>下の行の」を統合しました。原文の「」に合わせ&apos;を補足。-ha削除、school補足eraに訂正しました。&quot;削除スペース削除era→periodに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>重賢については「某（註：諱不明の意）　出雲守　今の呈譜、太郎左衛門下野守重政〔ママ〕につくる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;. Concerning Shigetaka, it is written, &quot; A certain Izumo-no-kami (chief of Izumo-no-kuni). According to present&apos;s accepted genealogy, Tarozaemon, Shimotsuke-no-kami, Shigemasa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Concerning Shigetaka, it is written, &quot;A certain Izumo-no-kami&quot; (chief of Izumo-no-kuni). According to present&apos;s accepted genealogy, Tarozaemon, Shimotsuke-no-kami, Shigemasa.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Concerning Shigetaka, it is written, &apos;A certain Izumo no kami (chief of Izumo Province). According to present&apos;s accepted genealogy, Tarozaemon Shimotsuke no kami Shigemasa.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;にIzumo Provinceに訂正しました。-削除,削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>佐々木家に属し、旗下七人のうちたり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He belongs to the Sasaki family and is one of the Kika Nananin (seven major influencing disciples))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He belongs to the Sasaki family and is one of the Kika Nananin (seven major influencing disciples))</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He belongs to the Sasaki family and is one of the Kika Nananin (seven major influencing disciples)</e>
<cmt>)削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>日置弾正豊秀にしたがひて射芸を学ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He followed Toyohide Danjo HEKI and studied Shagei (technique of archery).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He followed Toyohide Danjo HEKI and studied the Shagei (technique of archery).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He followed Toyohide Danjo HEKI and studied the Shagei (technique of archery).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>豊秀が門人多しといへども、出雲守ひとりその妙をうるがゆへに、豊秀家伝をつがしむ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although there were many disciples of Toyohide, only Izumonokami succeeded the private hand-down techniques of Toyohide&apos;s family because of his excellence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although there were many disciples of Toyohide, only Izumonokami succeeded the private handed-down techniques of Toyohide&apos;s family because of his excellence.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although there were many disciples of Toyohide, only Izumo no kami succeeded the private handed-down techniques of Toyohide&apos;s family because of his excellence.</e>
<cmt>スペース補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>これより世こぞりて吉田流と称す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, people called them Yoshida-ryu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, people called them Yoshida-ryu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, people called them Yoshida school.</e>
<cmt>-ryu削除、school補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>子孫にいたるまで代々相伝てその術を教授す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The techniques are taught from generation to generation to the descendants.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The techniques are taught from generation to generation to the descendants.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The techniques are taught from generation to generation to the descendants.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>法名道宝。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Buddhist name is Doho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Buddhist name is Doho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Buddhist name is Doho.&apos;</e>
<cmt>下の行の」を統合しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>」と記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot; It is recorded like this.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot; It was recorded like this.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was recorded like this.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>（豊秀は日置弾正の別名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Toyohide is another name of Masatsugu Danjo HEKI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Toyohide is another name of Masatsugu Danjo HEKI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Toyohide is another name of Masatsugu Danjo HEKI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>重政は重賢の誤りか。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Is Shigemasa a misprint of Shigetaka?</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Is Shigemasa a misprint of Shigetaka?</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Is Shigemasa a misprint of Shigetaka?</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>重賢ら吉田氏の人物には別名が多く伝わっている。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">People of the Yoshida clan like Shigetaka have a lot of other names.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">People of the Yoshida clan like Shigetaka have a lot of other names.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">People of the Yoshida clan like Shigetaka have a lot of other names.)</e>
<cmt>下の行の)を統合しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="48">
<j>重賢の後は嫡子重政（助左衛門・出雲守、号 一鴎）（文明 (日本) 16年（1484） - 永禄12年（1569））が継承した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His only son Shigemasa (1484-1569) (Sukezaemon, Izumo-no-kami, title: Ichio) succeeded after Shigetaka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His the only son Shigemasa (1484-1569) (Sukezaemon, Izumo-no-kami, title: Ichio) who succeeded after Shigetaka.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His the only son Shigemasa (1484 - 1569) (Sukezaemon, Izumo no kami (chief of Izumo Province), his title was Ichio) who succeeded after Shigetaka.</e>
<cmt>スペース補足-削除(chief of Izumo Province), his title was Ichio に補足訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="49">
<j>天文 (元号)年間頃、重政は主君の六角義賢から家伝の伝受を求められるが、これを拒み、一時越前の朝倉氏の下に身を寄せた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the years of Emperor Tembun, Shigemasa was requested to teach his family secret techniques by Yoshikata ROKKAKU. He once refused and turned him under the protection of the Asakura clan of Echizen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the years of Emperor Tembun, Shigemasa was requested by Yoshikata ROKKAKU to teach his family secret techniques. He refused and put him under the protection of the Asakura clan of Echizen.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the years of Emperor Tenbun, Shigemasa was requested by Yoshikata ROKKAKU to teach his family secret techniques, but he refused and put him under the protection of the Asakura clan of Echizen.</e>
<cmt>Tenbunに訂正しました。一文にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>その後和解して近江に帰還し、義賢と養子縁組をして家伝を伝授した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They settled peacefully then and he returned to Omi. He adopted Yoshikata as his son and taught him the family secret techniques.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They settled peacefully then and he returned to Omi. He adopted Yoshikata as his son and taught him the family secret techniques.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They settled peacefully then and he returned to Omi, and Shigemasa adopted Yoshikata as his son and taught him the family secret techniques.</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="51">
<j>この騒動時に、家伝が絶えることを危惧した重政は、四男の重勝に家伝を授け京都に移らせたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that at this period of trouble, Shigemasa was afraid that his family secret techniques might get discontinued. So, he taught them to their fourth son Shigekatsu and sent him to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that at this period of trouble, Shigemasa was afraid that his family secret techniques might be lost. So, he taught them to their fourth son Shigekatsu and sent him to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that at this period of trouble, Shigemasa was afraid that his family secret techniques might be lost, so he taught them to their fourth son Shigekatsu and sent him to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>この重勝の系統は後に雪荷派と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This system of Shigekatsu was called Sekka-ha school (Snow Lotus Sect).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This system of Shigekatsu was called the Sekka-ha school (Snow Lotus Sect).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This system of Shigekatsu was called the Sekka school (Snow Lotus sect).</e>
<cmt>sectに訂正しました。-ha削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>重政の嫡子重高には義賢から返伝がなされ、家伝は再び吉田氏で継承された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The manual of secret techniques were returned back to Shigemasa&apos;s only son Shigetaka by Yoshikata. So, the family manual was handed down back to the Yoshida clan again.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The manual of secret techniques was returned to Shigemasa&apos;s only son Shigetaka by Yoshikata. So, the family manual was again being handed down in the Yoshida clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The manual of secret techniques was returned to Shigemasa&apos;s only son Shigetaka by Yoshikata, so the family manual was again being handed down in the Yoshida clan.</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>この系統は出雲派と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This system is called Izumo-ha school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This system is called Izumo-ha school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This system is called Izumo school.</e>
<cmt>-ha削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="55">
<j>以後、出雲派からは分派が多く生じ、雪荷派分派の道雪派などともに九流十派などと呼ばれるほど多くの分派が生じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, the Izumo-ha school spun off a lot of sub-schools. The spun-off sects are so numerous that, together with Dosetsu-ha school (which is a spun-off from Sekka-ha school), they are called Kyu-ryu Juppa (nine schools ten sects).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, the Izumo-ha school spun off a lot of sub-schools. The spin-off sects were so numerous that, together with Dosetsu-ha school (which is a spin-off from the Sekka-ha school), they were called Kyu-ryu Juppa (nine schools, ten sects).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, the Izumo school spun off a lot of sub-schools; the spin-off sects were so numerous that, together with Dosetsu school (which is a spin-off from the Sekka school), they were called Kyu-ryu Juppa (nine schools, ten sects).</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。-ha削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>またこの時期に石堂竹林坊如成を祖とする竹林派も成立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, at this time, Chikurin-ha school (Bamboo Forest School), whose founder is Josei Chikurinbo ISHIDO, was established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, at this time, the Chikurin-ha school (Bamboo Forest School), whose founder was Josei Chikurinbo ISHIDO, was established.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, at this time, the Chikurin school (Bamboo Forest school), whose founder was Josei Chikurinbo ISHIDO, was established.</e>
<cmt>schoolに訂正しました。-ha削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>如成は重政の弟子とも、日置弾正とは別の日置弥左衛門範次（伊賀の人と伝わる）を祖とする流れを汲むともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also said that Josei, a student of Shigemasa and Masatsugu Danjo HEKI were related to the origin of another Noritsugu Yazaemon HEKI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also said that Josei, a student of Shigemasa and Masatsugu Danjo HEKI were related to the origin of another Noritsugu Yazaemon HEKI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also said that Josei, a student of Shigemasa and Masatsugu Danjo HEKI were related to the origin of another Noritsugu Yazaemon HEKI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>以降の日置流の歴史については諸派を見よ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The history of Heki-ryu school and various sects is as follows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The history of Heki-ryu school and various sects</e>
<cmt>grammar, wordy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The history of Heki school and various sects is as follows.</e>
<cmt>-ryu削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="59">
<j>日置流の影響は非常に強く、以降の弓術はほとんど日置流に依ったと言っても過言ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The influence of Heki-ryu school has been tremendous. It is not exaggerated to say that almost all the archery thereafter depended on it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The influence of the Heki-ryu school has been tremendous. Thereafter almost all the archery depended on it.</e>
<cmt>grammar, wordy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The influence of the Heki school has been tremendous, thereafter almost all the archery depended on it.</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。-ryu削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>また日置流後に成立した弓術流派も様々な名称のものがあったが、多くは日置流の系譜に連なるものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, though there were many archery sects with various namesestablished after the Heki-ryu school, most of these are related to the system of the Heki-ryu school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, though there were many archery sects with various names established after the Heki-ryu school, most of these are related to the system of the Heki-ryu school.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, although there were many archery sects with various names established after the Heki school, most of these are related to the system of the Heki school.</e>
<cmt>-ryu削除though→althoughに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>江戸時代、各藩は弓術師範を召し抱えたが、それらのほとんどは日置流の射手であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During Edo Era, each domain employed its own grand master of archery. However, they were mostly archers of Heki-ryu school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Edo Era, each domain employed its own grand master of archery. However, they were mostly archers from the Heki-ryu school.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Edo period, each domain employed its own grand master of archery, however, they were mostly archers from the Heki school.</e>
<cmt>eraに訂正しました。一文にしました。-ryu削除era→periodに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="62">
<j>諸派</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Various sects</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Various sects</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Various sects</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>分派については諸説あるが、代表的な説に基づいていくつかの派を挙げる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are various opinions about how the sects were spun off. However, according to some representative theories, some sects are as follows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are various opinions about how the sects were spun off. However, according to some representative theories, some sects are as follows:</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are various opinions about how the sects were spun off, according to some representative theories, some sects are as follows:</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。However削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="64">
<j>大和日置系統　(吉田流)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamato-heki-ryu school group</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yamato-heki-ryu school group</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamato-Heki school group</e>
<cmt>Hekiに訂正しました。-ryu削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>日置弾正政次の弟子、吉田重賢を祖とする流れ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a sect founded by Shigekata YOSHIDA, a student of Masatsugu Danjo HEKI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A sect founded by Shigekata YOSHIDA, a student of Masatsugu Danjo HEKI.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A sect founded by Shigekata YOSHIDA, a student of Masatsugu Danjo HEKI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>吉田家が代々伝えた事から、吉田流とも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since it has been handed down in the Yoshida family from generation to generation, it is also called the Yoshida-ryu school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since it had been handed down in the Yoshida family from generation to generation, it is also called the Yoshida-ryu school.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since it had been handed down in the Yoshida family from generation to generation, it is also called the Yoshida school.</e>
<cmt>-ryu削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="67">
<j>出雲派</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Izumo-ha school</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Izumo-ha school</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Izumo school</e>
<cmt>-ha削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>吉田重政の嫡子、吉田重高（助左衛門・出雲守、号：露滴）（永正5年（1508） - 天正13年（1585））を祖とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The only son of Shigemasa YOSHIDA, Shigetaka YOSHIDA (Sukezaemon, Izumo-no-kami (chief of Izumo-no-kuni), title: Roteki)(1508 -1585) was the founder.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The only son of Shigemasa YOSHIDA, Shigetaka YOSHIDA (Sukezaemon, Izumo-no-kami - chief of Izumo-no-kuni), title: Roteki) (1508 -1585) was the founder.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The only son of Shigemasa YOSHIDA, Shigetaka YOSHIDA (Sukezaemon, Izumo no kami (chief of Izumo Province), his title was Roteki) (1508 - 1585) was the founder.</e>
<cmt>(chief of Izumo Province), his title was Roteki に補足訂正しました。-削除スペース補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="69">
<j>上述の経緯で、吉田氏の家伝は主君六角義賢が継承していたが、重高は義賢から返伝を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the above-mentioned details, the family secret manual of the Yoshida clan was handed down to the master Yoshikata ROKKAKU. But Yoshikata returned it back to Shigetaka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for the above-mentioned details, the family secret manual of the Yoshida clan was handed down to master Yoshikata ROKKAKU. But Yoshikata returned it to Shigetaka.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for the above-mentioned details, the family secret manual of the Yoshida clan was handed down to master Yoshikata ROKKAKU, but Yoshikata returned it to Shigetaka.</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>重高以後は子孫の助左衛門家で継承され、重賢ら代々の受領名から出雲派と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Yoshikata, it was succeeded to descendants of the Sukezaemon family. From the generations of juryomei (acceptance name) after Shigekata, it was called Izumo-ha school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Yoshikata, it was succeeded to descendants of the Sukezaemon family. From the generations of juryomei (acceptance name) after Shigekata, it was called the Izumo-ha school.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Yoshikata, it was succeeded to descendants of the Sukezaemon family, from the generations of juryomei (acceptance name) after Shigekata, it was called the Izumo school.</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。-ha削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>この系統は吉田家の嫡流ではあるが、技術的には雪荷派が本流とする見解もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though this system is legitimacy of the Yoshida family, there are also opinions that it is mainly Sekka-ha school technically.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though this is the legitimate system of the Yoshida family, there are also opinions that technically, it is mainly a Sekka-ha school.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although this is the legitimate system of the Yoshida family, there are also opinions that technically, it is mainly a Sekka school.</e>
<cmt>-ha削除Though →Althoughに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="25">
<sen id="72">
<j>重高の嫡男重綱（助左右衛門、号 華翁・花翁・道春）（天文 (元号)23年（1554） - 天正10（1582））は父に先立ち28歳で没する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigetaka&apos;s only son Shigetsuna (Sukezaemon, titles: Kao, Kao or Doshun) (1554 - 1582) passed away (before his father) at the age of 28.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigetaka&apos;s only son Shigetsuna (Sukezaemon, titles: Kao, Kao or Doshun) (1554 - 1582) passed away (before his father) at the age of 28.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigetaka&apos;s only son Shigetsuna (Sukezaemon, his title was Kao, Kao or Doshun) (1554 - 1582) passed away (before his father) at the age of 28.</e>
<cmt>titles:をhis title wasに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>『明良洪範』によれば、重綱の嫡子豊隆は幼少であったため、婿の吉田重氏（印西派祖）に伝書類が預けられていたが、豊隆成長後に返伝がなされず騒動になったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Meiryo-kohan historical records&quot;, because Shigetsuna&apos;s only son Toyotaka was too young, the information documents had been entrusted by the son-in-law Shigeuji YOSHIDA (Insai-ha-so (founder of Insai-ha school)). However, it is said that a quarrel was resulted because the manual was not returned to Toyotaka after he grew up.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Meiryo-kohan historical records,&quot; because Shigetsuna&apos;s only son Toyotaka was too young, the information had been entrusted to the son-in-law Shigeuji YOSHIDA (Insai-ha-so - founder of Insai-ha school). However, it is said there was a quarrel because the manual was not returned to Toyotaka after he grew up.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Meiryo-kohan historical records,&quot; because Shigetsuna&apos;s only son Toyotaka was too young, the information had been entrusted to the son-in-law Shigeuji YOSHIDA (Insai school so - founder of Insai school). However, it is said there was a quarrel because the manual was not returned to Toyotaka after he grew up.</e>
<cmt>-ha削除、school補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="26">
<sen id="74">
<j>豊隆は後に岩槻藩主阿部正次に仕えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toyotaka later served Masatsugu ABE, who was the lord of Iwatsuki domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toyotaka later served Masatsugu ABE, who was the lord of the Iwatsuki domain.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toyotaka later served Masatsugu ABE, who was the lord of the Iwatsuki Domain.</e>
<cmt>Domainに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>子孫も代々阿部氏に仕え、転封により備後福山藩に移り、家老職も務めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The descendants also served the Abe clan from generation to generation. With the changing the territory, they were transferred to the domain of Bigo-fukuyama. They even served as Karo (chief retainers).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The descendants also served the Abe clan from generation to generation. With the changing the territory, they were transferred to the domain of Bigo-fukuyama. They even served as Karo (chief retainers).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The descendants also served the Abe clan from generation to generation, with the changing the territory, they were transferred to the domain of Bingo-Fukuyama, and they even served as Karo (chief retainers).</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。Bingo-Fukuyamaに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>道統は明治まで継承され、幕末の当主豊辰は阿部正弘以降の藩主の師範を務めたほか、執政・藩校誠之館文武総裁を務めた（『三百藩家臣人名事典』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The system of techniques was passed down until Meiji Era. The clan chief Toyotoki at the late Edo Era Period, besides serving the clan chiefs after Masahiro ABE as a teacher, he also served as administrator, and Seishikan Monbu Sosai (literary and military arts president of Seishikan, school of the Fukuyama domain) of schools of the feudal domains.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The system of techniques was passed down until the Meiji Era. The clan chief Toyotoki during the late Edo Era, besides serving the clan chiefs after Masahiro ABE as a teacher, he also served as administrator, and Seishikan Monbu Sosai (literary and military arts president of Seishikan, school of the Fukuyama domain) of schools in the feudal domains.</e>
<cmt>redundancy, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The system of techniques was passed down until the Meiji era; the clan chief Toyotoki during the late Edo era, besides serving the clan chiefs after Masahiro ABE as a teacher, he also served as administrator, and Seishikan Monbu Sosai (literary and military arts president of Seishikan, school of the Fukuyama domain) of schools in the feudal domains.</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。Eraに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="27">
<sen id="77">
<j>福山以外には阿部氏分家（刈谷藩のち佐貫藩主）、米沢藩などにも伝わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides Fukuyama, it was also spread to the branch family of the Abe clan (domain of Kariya, domain of Sanuki) and domain of Yonezawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides Fukuyama, it also spread to the branch family of the Abe clan (domain of Kariya, domain of Sanuki) and domain of Yonezawa.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides Fukuyama, it also spread to the branch family of the Abe clan (domain of Kariya, domain of Sanuki) and domain of Yonezawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="28">
<sen id="78">
<j>重高門下から山科派、左近衛門、大心派、重綱門下から寿徳派、印西派が分派した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the students of Shigetaka, it ramified to Yamashina-ha school, Sakonemon, and Daishin-ha school. From the students of Shigetsuna, it ramified to Jutoku-ha school, and Insai-ha school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the students of Shigetaka, it ramified to the Yamashina-ha school, Sakonemon, and Daishin-ha school. From the students of Shigetsuna, it ramified to Jutoku-ha school, and Insai-ha school.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the students of Shigetaka, it ramified to the Yamashina school, Sakonemon, and Daishin school, and from the students of Shigetsuna, it ramified to Jutoku school, and Insai school.</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。-ha削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="29">
<sen id="79">
<j>山科派</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamashina-ha school</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yamashina-ha school</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamashina school</e>
<cmt>-ha削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>吉田重高の弟子、片岡家次（平右衛門）またはその孫の家清（助右衛門）を祖とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigetaka YOSHIDA&apos;s student Ietsugu KATAOKA (Heiemon) and his grandson Iekiyo KATAOKA(Sukemon) are assumed to be the originators.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigetaka YOSHIDA&apos;s student Ietsugu KATAOKA (Heiemon) and his grandson Iekiyo KATAOKA(Sukemon) are assumed to be the originators.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigetaka YOSHIDA&apos;s student Ietsugu KATAOKA (Heiemon) and his grandson Iekiyo KATAOKA(Sukemon) are assumed to be the originators.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="30">
<sen id="81">
<j>家次は重高の死後、その三男業茂（左近衛門派祖）を輔佐した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Shigetaka&apos;s death, Ietsugu assisted his third son Narishige (founder of Sakonemon School).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Shigetaka&apos;s death, Ietsugu assisted his third son Narishige (founder of Sakonemon School).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Shigetaka&apos;s death, Ietsugu assisted his third son Narishige (founder of Sakonemon school).</e>
<cmt>schoolに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>子の家延（平右衛門）も茂氏（大蔵派祖）らに師事し技術を伝えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His son Ienobu (Heiemon) also studied the techniques under Shigeuji (Okura-ha school) et al. The second son Ienkiyo, who was the son-in-law of Narishige&apos;s only son Shigetake, studied under Shigeuji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His son Ienobu (Heiemon) also studied the techniques under Shigeuji (Okura-ha school) et al. The second son Ienkiyo, who was the son-in-law of Narishige&apos;s only son Shigetake, studied under Shigeuji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His son Ienobu (Heiemon) also studied the techniques under Shigeuji (Okura school) and others.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理-ha削除et aliaをand othersに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>その次男家清は業茂の嫡子茂武の女婿で、茂氏に師事した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The second son Ienkiyo, who was the son-in-law of Narishige&apos;s only son Shigetake, studied under Shigeuji.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>このように片岡家は業茂の子孫と縁が深く、伝書も山科・大蔵各派で類似するという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Like this, the Kataoka family was closely associated with the descendants of Narishige. It is said that the documents handed-down were also similar in that they were Yamashina-ha school Okura-ha school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Like this, the Kataoka family was closely associated with the descendants of Narishige. It is said that the documents handed-down were also similar in that they were from the Yamashina-ha school Okura-ha school.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Like this, the Kataoka family was closely associated with the descendants of Narishige, and it is said that the documents handed-down were also similar in that they were from the Yamashina school and Okura school.</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。-ha削除and補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>『本朝武芸小伝』は家清を山科派祖としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Honcho Bugei Shoden (a survey of traditional Japanese martial arts)&quot; regards Iekiyo as the originator of Yamashina-ha school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Honcho Bugei Shoden (a survey of traditional Japanese martial arts)&quot; regards Iekiyo as the originator of the Yamashina-ha school.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Honcho Bugei Shoden&quot; (a survey of traditional Japanese martial arts) regards Iekiyo as the originator of the Yamashina school.</e>
<cmt>“を&quot;に訂正しました。位置も訂正。スペース削除-ha削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="31">
<sen id="86">
<j>左近右衛門派</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sakonemon-ha school</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sakonemon-ha school</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sakonemon school</e>
<cmt>-ha削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>吉田重高の三男、吉田業茂（左近（右）衛門）を祖とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigetaka YOSHIDA&apos;s third son Narishige YOSHIDA (Sakonemon) was regarded as the originator.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigetaka YOSHIDA&apos;s third son Narishige YOSHIDA (Sakonemon) was regarded as the originator.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigetaka YOSHIDA&apos;s third son Narishige YOSHIDA (Sakonemon) was regarded as the originator.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="32">
<sen id="88">
<j>業茂は父および片岡家次に師事し、後に叔父重勝（雪荷）にも師事したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Narishige studied under father and Ietsugu KATAOKA, and afterwards under Shigekatsu (Sekka).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Narishige studied under his father and Ietsugu KATAOKA, and afterwards under Shigekatsu (Sekka).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Narishige studied under his father and Ietsugu KATAOKA, and afterwards under Shigekatsu (Sekka).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>始め豊臣秀次、後に前田利家に仕えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He first served Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI, and then served Toshiie MAEDA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He first served Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI, and then served Toshiie MAEDA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He first served Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI, and then served Toshiie MAEDA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>子孫も技術を伝え、加賀藩、富山藩に仕えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His descendants also handed down the techniques and served domains of Kaga and Toyama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His descendants also handed down the techniques and served the domains of Kaga and Toyama.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His descendants also handed down the techniques and served the domains of Kaga and Toyama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>この系統は後に左近派とも呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This system was later called Sakon-ha school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This system was later called Sakon-ha school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This system was later called Sakon school.</e>
<cmt>-ha削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="33">
<sen id="92">
<j>大蔵派</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Okura-ha school</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Okura-ha school</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Okura school</e>
<cmt>-ha削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>吉田業茂の三男、吉田茂氏（大蔵）（天正6年（1578年）- 正保元年（1644））を祖とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Narishige Yoshida&apos;s third son Shigeuji (Okura) YOSHIDA (1578 - 1644) is regarded as the originator.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Narishige Yoshida&apos;s third son Shigeuji (Okura) YOSHIDA (1578 - 1644) is regarded as the originator.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Narishige YOSHIDA&apos;s third son Shigeuji (Okura) YOSHIDA (1578 - 1644) is regarded as the originator.</e>
<cmt>YOSHIDAに訂正。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="34">
<sen id="94">
<j>茂氏は父に師事し、始め富田信高、後に前田利常に仕えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigeuji studied under father, first served Nobutaka TOMITA and then Toshitsune MAEDA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigeuji studied under his father, first served Nobutaka TOMITA and then Toshitsune MAEDA.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigeuji studied under his father, first served Nobutaka TOMITA and then Toshitsune MAEDA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>大坂の陣で武功を立て、1,400石に加増される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He established distinguished credit during Osaka-no-Jin War and was granted 1400 Goku (crop yields).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He established distinguished credit during the Osaka-no-Jin War and was granted 1400 Goku (crop yields).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He established distinguished credit during the Osaka no Jin (The Siege of Osaka) and was granted 1400 Goku (crop yields).</e>
<cmt>Osaka no Jin　（The Siege of Osaka)に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>三十三間堂の通し矢を7回試み、6回の天下一を記録した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He tried seven times of arrows in Sanjusangen-do Temple, and won six times tenkaichi (Japan&apos;s No. 1).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He tried seven arrows at the Sanjusangen-do Temple, and won six times tenkaichi (Japan&apos;s No. 1).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He tried seven arrows at the Sanjusangen-do Temple, and won six times tenkaichi (Japan&apos;s No. 1).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>加賀藩を中心に栄えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He brought honor and glory to Kaga Domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He brought honor and glory to the Kaga Domain.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He brought honor and glory to the Kaga Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="35">
<sen id="98">
<j>印西派（いんさいは）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Insai-ha school</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Insai-ha school</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Insai school</e>
<cmt>-ha削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>吉田重綱・業茂の弟子、吉田重氏（源八郎、旧姓：葛巻、号：一水、法名：印西、一水軒印西）（永禄 5年（1562年） - 寛永15年（1638年）3月4日）を祖とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigetsuna YOSHIDA (Narishige&apos;s student), Shigeuji YOSHIDA (Genpachiro, former surname: Kuzumaki, title: Issui/Isumi, Buddhist name: Insai, Issui/Isumi ken Insai) (1562 to 1638 March 4) are regarded as originators.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigetsuna YOSHIDA (Narishige&apos;s student), Shigeuji YOSHIDA (Genpachiro, former surname: Kuzumaki, title: Issui/Isumi, Buddhist name: Insai, Issui/Isumi ken Insai) (1562 to 1638 March 4) are regarded as the originators.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigetsuna YOSHIDA (Narishige&apos;s student), Shigeuji YOSHIDA (Genpachiro, former surname: Kuzumaki, his title was Issui/Isumi, his Buddhist name was Insai, Issui/Isumi ken Insai) (1562 - April 17, 1638) are regarded as the originators.</e>
<cmt>his、was補足スペース削除年号表記訂正。新暦に訂正。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>重氏は近江国蒲生郡葛巻村（現滋賀県東近江市）に生まれる（吉田氏本拠の川守は近隣）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigeuji was born in Kuzumaki-mura, Gamo-gun, Omi-no-kuni (present&apos;s Higashiomi City, Shiga Prefecture). Kawamori, which was the base of the Yoshida clan, was in the neighborhood.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigeuji was born in Kuzumaki-mura, Gamo-gun, Omi-no-kuni (present&apos;s Higashiomi City, Shiga Prefecture). Kawamori, the base of the Yoshida clan, was in the neighborhood.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigeuji was born in Kuzumaki-mura, Gamo-gun, Omi Province (present&apos;s Higashiomi City, Shiga Prefecture) (Kawamori, the base of the Yoshida clan, was in the neighborhood).</e>
<cmt>Omi Provinceに訂正しました。原文に合わせて（）に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>もと葛巻氏（吉田氏の近親であるとも伝わる）で、吉田重綱（出雲派）の養子となりその娘を妻としたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that he was from the Kuzumaki clan, became Shigetsuna YOSHIDA (Izumo-ha school)&apos;s adopted son, and married with his daughter. (Rumors also says he was a close relative of the Yoshida clan)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that he was from the Kuzumaki clan, became Shigetsuna YOSHIDA (Izumo-ha school)&apos;s adopted son, and married his daughter. (Rumors also says he was a close relative of the Yoshida clan)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that he was from the Kuzumaki clan, became Shigetsuna YOSHIDA (Izumo school)&apos;s adopted son, and married his daughter (rumors also says he was a close relative of the Yoshida clan).</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。-ha削除原文に合わせて（）に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>後に養父と不仲になり、吉田業茂（左近右衛門派）に師事した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterwards, he had bad terms with his foster father and he studied under Narishige YOSHIDA (Sakonemon-ha school).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Afterwards, he was on bad terms with his foster father and he studied under Narishige YOSHIDA (Sakonemon-ha school).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Afterwards, he was on bad terms with his foster father and he studied under Narishige YOSHIDA (Sakonemon school).</e>
<cmt>-ha削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>豊臣秀次、結城秀康、松平忠昌らにつかえ、後に徳川家康、徳川秀忠、徳川家光に拝謁した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He served Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI, Hideyasu YUKI, Tadamasa MATSUDAIRA etc. Then he paid visits to Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, Hidetada TOKUGAWA, and Iemitsu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He served Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI, Hideyasu YUKI, Tadamasa MATSUDAIRA etc. Then he paid visits to Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, Hidetada TOKUGAWA, and Iemitsu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He served Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI, Hideyasu YUKI and Tadamasa MATSUDAIRA, then he paid visits to Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, Hidetada TOKUGAWA and Iemitsu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="36">
<sen id="104">
<j>嫡子重信（久馬助）が旗本となり、家光ら将軍家弓術指南役となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His only son Shigenobu (Kyu-umanosuke) became a direct retainer of the shogun and the family archery instructor for Iemitsu et al.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His only son Shigenobu (Kyu-umanosuke) became a direct retainer of the shogun and the family archery instructor for Iemitsu et al.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His only son Shigenobu (Kyumanosuke) became a direct retainer of the shogun and the family archery instructor for Iemitsu and others.</e>
<cmt>et aliaをand othersに訂正しました。Kyumanosukeに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>江戸、岡山藩、薩摩藩、遠州地方、福井藩など各地に広まる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His archery school became well-spread to various places such as Edo, Okayama domain, Satsuma domain, Enshu region, and Fukui domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His archery school became well-spread to various places such as Edo, Okayama domain, the Satsuma domain, the Enshu region, and Fukui domain.</e>
<cmt>punctuation, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His archery school became well-spread to various places such as Edo, Okayama Domain, Satsuma Domain, the Enshu region, and Fukui Domain.</e>
<cmt>Domainに訂正しました。the削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>江戸と岡山藩の印西派のみ「日置当流」と称される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Only the Insai-ha school in Edo and the Okayama domain is called &quot;Heki-to-ryu school&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Only the Insai-ha school in Edo and the Okayama domain are called the &quot;Heki-to-ryu school&quot;.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Only the Insai school in Edo and the Okayama Domain are called the &quot;Heki-to school&quot;.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に-ha削除Domainに訂正しました。-ryu削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>日置弾正正次からの教義を血族には唯授一人、血縁関係の無い弟子には免許皆伝を与え、日置弾正の教義を次世代次世代へと伝えてきた射法。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, Masatsugu Danjo HEKI&apos;s doctrine of archery was handed down from generation to generation by the only one blood-linked successor of Masatsugu Danjo HEKI, or one student without any blood relation who was granted with Menkyo-kaiden (full proficiency).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, Masatsugu Danjo HEKI&apos;s doctrine of archery was handed down from generation to generation by the only one blood-linked successor of Masatsugu Danjo HEKI, or one student without any blood relationship who was granted Menkyo-kaiden (full proficiency).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, Masatsugu Danjo HEKI&apos;s doctrine of archery was handed down from generation to generation by the only one blood-linked successor of Masatsugu Danjo HEKI, or one student without any blood relationship who was granted Menkyo-kaiden (full proficiency).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>その土地の印西派の伝承者（つまり宗家）は、その世代にただ一人しか存在しない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The successor (in other words, Soke or grand master) of the Insai-ha school in a certain region of a certain generation could only be one person.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The successor (in other words, Soke or grand master) of the Insai-ha school in a certain region of a certain generation could only be one person.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The successor (in other words, Soke or grand master) of the Insai school in a certain region of a certain generation could only be one person.</e>
<cmt>-ha削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="109">
<j>免許皆伝者は複数居る場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there were sometimes more than one person who could receive Menkyo-kaiden (full proficiency).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there were sometimes more than one person who could receive Menkyo-kaiden (full proficiency).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there were sometimes more than one person who could receive Menkyo-kaiden (full proficiency).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="37">
<sen id="110">
<j>一部の印西派を当流と呼ぶのは、江戸印西派の宗家が徳川将軍家の弓術指南役だった事からで、将軍家の流派という意味。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A part of the Insai-ha school was called &quot;Toryu (meaning sect for the Shogunate family) because the grant master of Edo-Insai-ha school was teaching archery for Tokugawa Shogunate family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A part of the Insai-ha school was called &quot;Toryu (meaning sect for the Shogunate family) because the grant master of Edo-Insai-ha school was teaching archery for Tokugawa Shogunate family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A part of the Insai school was called &quot;Toryu&quot; (meaning sect for the Shogunate family) because the grant master of Edo-Insai school was teaching archery for Tokugawa Shogunate family.</e>
<cmt>&quot;補足-ha削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>また、岡山藩の印西派が当流と呼ばれる所以は、池田侯と当時の将軍が弓の勝負をした際に池田侯が勝利し、池田侯が当家でも「当流」と称させて欲しいと願い出たところ、将軍が褒美の意味で当流と称すことを許可した事から。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, the reason why the Insai-ha school of Okayama domain was called &quot;Toryu&quot; is that, when the shogun at that time competed with Ikeda-ko (daimyo IKEDA) in an archery match, Ikeda-ko won. Ikeda-ko requested to be also called &quot;Toryu&quot; and the shogun allowed it for praising.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, the reason why the Insai-ha school of Okayama domain was called &quot;Toryu&quot; is that, when the shogun at that time competed with Ikeda-ko (daimyo IKEDA) in an archery match, Ikeda-ko won. Ikeda-ko requested to be also called &quot;Toryu&quot; and the shogun allowed his request.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, the reason why the Insai school of Okayama Domain was called &quot;Toryu&quot; is that, when the shogun at that time competed with Ikeda-ko (daimyo IKEDA) in an archery match, Ikeda-ko won, then Ikeda-ko requested to be also called &quot;Toryu&quot; and the shogun allowed his request.</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。-ha削除Domainに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="38">
<sen id="112">
<j>印西派は戦場で徒歩武者（かちむしゃ）(歩兵の意）が用いる射法である「歩射」であり、本来は馬上で弓を引く「騎射」の射法である小笠原流とは根本的にその土台が異なる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Insai-ha school is &quot;walking archery&quot;, shooting method for walking troops (walking warriors) in battle field. Originally, it was different from Ogasawara-ryu school, which is a &quot;riding archery&quot;, shooting method while riding a horse&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Insai-ha school is &quot;walking archery,&quot; shooting method for walking troops (walking warriors) on the battle field. Originally, it was different from the Ogasawara-ryu school, which is &quot;horseback riding archery,&quot; shooting from horseback.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Insai school is &apos;walking archery,&apos; shooting method for walking troops (walking warriors) on the battle field; originally, it was different from the Ogasawara school, which is &apos;horseback riding archery,&apos; shooting from horseback.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に-ha削除スペース削除-ryu削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="113">
<j>印西派の本来の射法は「割膝（わりひざ）」という膝立ちの体勢で弓を引くものであり、戦場で敵方から放たれる矢を避けて身を隠しながら、瞬間的に身を起こし敵を射るのに非常に適している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For Insai-ha school&apos;s original shooting method, a body pose of &quot;opening knees&quot; with one knee standing was adopted to pull the bow. While the body is hidden to avoid the arrow shot by the enemy in the battlefield, the body can readily be raised momentarily to shoot an enemy. So, it is very practical.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For the Insai-ha school&apos;s original shooting method, a body pose of &quot;opening knees&quot; with one knee standing was adopted to pull the bow. While the body is hidden to avoid the arrow shot by the enemy on the battlefield, the body can readily be raised momentarily to shoot an enemy. So, it is very practical.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For the Insai school&apos;s original shooting method, a body pose of &apos;opening knees&apos; with one knee standing was adopted to pull the bow, while the body is hidden to avoid the arrow shot by the enemy on the battlefield, the body can readily be raised momentarily to shoot an enemy, so, it is very practical.</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に-ha削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="39">
<sen id="114">
<j>現代では、その割膝の練習段階とされる、立ったまま弓を引く「立射」の体勢が一般的である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In modern days, &quot;opening knees&quot; is assumed to be the practice stage, and the body pose of &quot;Rissha (standing shoot)&quot;, that pulls the bow while standing, is general.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In modern days, &quot;open knees&quot; is assumed to be the practice stage, and the body pose of &quot;Rissha (standing shoot),&quot; that pulls the bow while standing, is the general position.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In modern days, &apos;open knees&apos; is assumed to be the practice stage, and the body pose of &apos;Rissha&apos; (standing shoot), that pulls the bow while standing, is the general position.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="40">
<sen id="115">
<j>印西派の教えでは「貫（かん）・中（ちゅう）・久（きゅう）」の実践を最高とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the doctrine of the Insai-ha school, the highest levels of practice are Kan, Chu, and Kyu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the doctrine of the Insai-ha school, the highest levels of practice are Kan, Chu, and Kyu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the doctrine of the Insai school, the highest levels of practice are Kan, Chu, and Kyu.</e>
<cmt>-ha削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="41">
<sen id="116">
<j>「貫」は敵兵の鎧まで貫く強力な貫通力、「中」は百射百中の命中率、「久」は貫・中を永久に実践できることを意味する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kan (Penetration)&quot; is a strong penetrating power that can pass through enemy&apos;s armor. &quot;Chu (Precision)&quot; is a hit rate of 100 hits out of 100 shoots. &quot;Kyu (Persistence)&quot; means &quot;Kan&quot; and &quot;Chu&quot; can be persistently maintained.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kan (Penetration)&quot; is a strong penetrating power that can pass through enemy&apos;s armor. &quot;Chu (Precision)&quot; is a hit rate of 100 hits out of 100 shots. &quot;Kyu (Persistence)&quot; means &quot;Kan&quot; and &quot;Chu&quot; can be persistently maintained.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kan&apos; (Penetration) is a strong penetrating power that can pass through enemy&apos;s armor; &apos;Chu&apos; (Precision) is a hit rate of 100 hits out of 100 shots; &apos;Kyu&apos; (Persistence) means &apos;Kan&apos; and &apos;Chu&apos; can be persistently maintained.</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="117">
<j>つまり印西派は、弓矢が強力な武器であった時代において、戦場で戦う徒歩武者が如何に敵を射殺できるか、その鍛錬と戦場での実践のために編み出された射法であり、文字通り極めて実戦的かつ合理的なものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In other words, the Insai-ha school is a shooting method designed in an era with powerful bow and arrow as to how a walking warrior who fights in the battlefield shoots an enemy dead. As the name suggests, it is extremely practical and reasonable.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In other words, the Insai-ha school teaches a shooting method conceived during an era when powerful bows and arrows were used and by walking warriors who fight on the battlefield to kill the enemy. As the name suggests, it is extremely practical and reasonable.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In other words, the Insai school teaches a shooting method conceived during an era when powerful bows and arrows were used and by walking warriors who fight on the battlefield to kill the enemy, as the name suggests, it is extremely practical and reasonable.</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。-ha削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="42">
<sen id="118">
<j>現代の弓道においては通常の競技において的中主義であるため、貫通力の相対的価値が下がっていることもあり、今日では「中・貫・久」の実践を最高としているが、本来は「貫・中・久」である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In modern archery, for a usual game, emphasis is put on Tekichu-shugi (hitting the target). Because of this, penetration is relatively less valued. Nowadays, the praising order is &quot;Precision, Penetration, and Persistence&quot;. Originally, the praising order should be &quot;Penetration, Precision, and Persistence&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In modern archery, emphasis is put on Tekichu-shugi (hitting the target). Penetration is valued less. Nowadays, the praising order is &quot;Precision, Penetration, and Persistenc.&quot; Originally, the praising order should be &quot;Penetration, Precision, and Persistence&quot;.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In modern archery, since emphasis is put on Tekichu-shugi (hitting the target), penetration is valued less; nowadays, the praising order is &apos;Precision, Penetration and Persistenc&apos;, however, the praising order should be &apos;Penetration, Precision and Persistence&apos; originally.</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="43">
<sen id="119">
<j>印西派における射法の教えについて、物理学的・医学的等の見地からの研究が筑波大（旧東京教育大）で行われているが、その伝承されてきた事項について科学的な見地から否定されるものが一切発見されておらず、古来からの教えが戦場での経験に基づいた極めて合理的・科学的なことが裏付けられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">About doctrine of the shooting method in the Insai-ha school, University of Tsukuba (former Tokyo University of Education) is conducting a research of it from a medical and physical viewpoint. Concerning the contents in the doctrine, there has been nothing discovered at all that can be denied from a scientific viewpoint. Rather, it is proven that this ancient doctrine based on experiences in battlefields is extremely reasonable and scientific.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">About doctrine of the shooting method in the Insai-ha school, the University of Tsukuba (formerly Tokyo University of Education) is conducting research about it from a medical and physical viewpoint. Concerning the contents of the doctrine, there has been nothing discovered at all that can be denied from a scientific viewpoint. Rather, it has been proven that this ancient doctrine based on battlefield experiences is extremely reasonable and scientific.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">About doctrine of the shooting method in the Insai school, the University of Tsukuba (formerly Tokyo University of Education) is conducting research about it from a medical and physical viewpoint; concerning the contents of the doctrine, there has been nothing discovered at all that can be denied from a scientific viewpoint, rather, it has been proven that this ancient doctrine based on battlefield experiences is extremely reasonable and scientific.</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。-ha削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="44">
<sen id="120">
<j>的は日置霞（へきがすみ）と呼ばれる独特の模様の物を用い、多人数で射る場合も一つの的を全員で射るのが本来正式である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The target, called &quot;Hekigasumi&quot;, has a peculiar pattern (supposed to be like a human body). Even in the case when there are multiple players shooting, originally only one target is set formally.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The target, called &quot;Hekigasumi,&quot; has a peculiar pattern (supposed to be like a human body). Even in the case when there are multiple players shooting, originally only one target is formally set.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The target, called &quot;Hekigasumi,&quot; has a peculiar pattern (supposed to be like a human body), and even in the case when there are multiple players shooting, originally only one target is formally set.</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="121">
<j>これは、集団で向かってくる敵兵の先頭の者を確実に射倒す事で、敵兵の戦意を削ぐ為である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The purpose is to shoot down for sure the person standing out first in the confronting enemy group, in order to destroy the enemy&apos;s fighting spirit.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The purpose is to shoot down for sure the person standing out first when confronting an enemy group, in order to destroy the enemy&apos;s fighting spirit.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The purpose is to shoot down for sure the person standing out first when confronting an enemy group, in order to destroy the enemy&apos;s fighting spirit.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="45">
<sen id="122">
<j>また、もし敵兵を射損じた場合でも、外れた矢が足元に突き刺さる方が、頭上を飛び越えて行くよりもより敵に恐怖感を与える事が出来るため、的は地面すれすれの低い場所に立てて稽古した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, even if you miss shooting the enemy, a missed arrow that pierces in front of one&apos;s feet appears more scaring to the enemy than a missed arrow that flies over one&apos;s head. Thus, the target was set up in a low place on ground for practice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, even if you miss, a missed arrow that hit in front of one&apos;s feet appears more frightening to the enemy than a missed arrow that flies over one&apos;s head. Thus, the target was set up in a low place on the ground for practice.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, even if you miss, a missed arrow that hit in front of one&apos;s feet appears more frightening to the enemy than a missed arrow that flies over one&apos;s head, thus, the target was set up in a low place on the ground for practice.</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="46">
<sen id="123">
<j>近的用の的の大きさは人間の胴体の幅を想定しているとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is assumed that the size of a short distance target is the width of a human body.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is assumed that the size of a short distance target is the width of a human body.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is assumed that the size of a short distance target is the width of a human body.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="124">
<j>それ故、上や下に外す事よりも、的の左や右に外す事の方が良くない事だとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, it is assumed that rather than missing the target vertically, missing the target horizontally is not recommended.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, it is assumed that rather than missing the target vertically, missing the target horizontally is to be avoided.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, it is assumed that rather than missing the target vertically, missing the target horizontally is to be avoided.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="47">
<sen id="125">
<j>また、的は約15間（けん）(28m)先に設置するが、これは戦場での敵の位置を想定したものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, the target is set up about 28m away, which is assumed to be the enemy&apos;s position in a battlefield.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, the target is set up about 28m away, which is assumed to be the enemy&apos;s position on the battlefield.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, the target is set up about 28m away, which is assumed to be the enemy&apos;s position on the battlefield.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="126">
<j>これは、直接攻撃用の武器の中で最も攻撃距離の長い槍が届かず、かつ遠すぎない距離である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is about the shortest distance not reachable by the spear with long attack distance for a direct attack.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is about the shortest distance unreachable by a spear for a direct long distance attack.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is about the shortest distance unreachable by a spear for a direct long distance attack.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="48">
<sen id="127">
<j>現在もこれらに習い、近的の場合は流派を問わず、直径一尺二寸(36cm)の的を15間(28m)先の低い位置に設置するのが一般的である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even nowadays, we learn from these. For a short distance target, regardless of the sect, a target of diameter 36cm is set up in general at a low position of 28m away.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even nowadays, we learn from these. For a short distance target, regardless of the sect, a target 36cm in diameter is generally set up at a low position 28m away.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even nowadays, we learn from these, for a short distance target, regardless of the sect, a target 36cm in diameter is generally set up at a low position 28m away.</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="49">
<sen id="128">
<j>徳山文右衛門から明治初期に免許を受けた浦上直置（なおおき）が創始した、「三分の二」とよばれる動作をとる浦上一派が現在関東を中心に活動している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Urakami group was founded by Naoki URAKAMI who received mastership in early Meiji Period from Bunemon TOKUYAMA. It adopted a move called Sambun-no-ni (a gesture of archery with the string two-third drawn). Now, it bases its activities around Kanto area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Urakami group was founded by Naoki URAKAMI who received his masters during the early Meiji Period from Bunemon TOKUYAMA. It adopted a move called Sambun-no-ni (the string two-thirds drawn). Now, it bases its activities around Kanto area.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Urakami group, founded by Naoki URAKAMI who received his masters during the early Meiji period from Bunemon TOKUYAMA, adopted a move called &apos;Sambun-no-ni&apos; (the string two-thirds drawn), and now, it bases its activities around Kanto area.</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。periodに訂正しました。原文の「」に合わせ&apos;を補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="129">
<j>「三分の二」とは、「打起し」から「引分け」てくる間、矢の高さが眉毛のあたりになった時に一度動きを止める動作である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The so-called &quot;Sambun-no-ni (2/3)&quot; is a move of holding the arrow without moving momentarily when the height of the arrow is around the level of the eyebrow from the move of &quot;Uchiokoshi (anchoring)&quot; to the move of &quot;Hikiwake (drawing)&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When executing &quot;Sambun-no-ni&quot; (2/3) the arrow is held without moving momentarily when the arrow is positioned around the level of the eyebrow during &quot;Uchiokoshi (anchoring)&quot; to the move of &quot;Hikiwake&quot; (drawing).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When executing &apos;Sambun-no-ni&apos; the arrow is held without moving momentarily when the arrow is positioned around the level of the eyebrow during &apos;Uchiokoshi&apos; (anchoring) to the move of &apos;Hikiwake&apos; (drawing).</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に(2/3)削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="130">
<j>しかしまた、「三分の二」を取らない昔ながらの印西派も各地に数多く残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there are still remaining various places where it is like the ancient Insai-ha school which doesn&apos;t take &quot;2/3&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there are still examples of situations where the ancient Insai-ha school doesn&apos;t employ &quot;2/3.&quot;</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity, wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there are still examples of situations where the ancient Insai school doesn&apos;t employ &apos;Sambun-no-ni.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;(2/3)&quot;削除、補足&apos;Sambun-no-ni&apos;-ha削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="50">
<sen id="131">
<j>印西派の中でも薩摩日置、備前日置、遠州系等の系統は詳しく系譜をさかのぼる事が出来る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even within the Insai-ha school, the systems such as Satsuma-heki, Bizen-heki and Enshu group can be traced back in detail genealogically.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even within the Insai-ha school, the teachings of Satsuma-heki, Bizen-heki, and the Enshu group can be traced back in detail genealogically.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even within the Insai school, the teachings of Satsuma-Heki, Bizen-Heki, and the Enshu group can be traced back in detail genealogically.</e>
<cmt>Hekiに訂正しました。-ha削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="51">
<sen id="132">
<j>有名な射手としては、弓道教本編集に関わり射法制定委員であった浦上榮（うらかみさかえ）範士十段、全日本弓道連盟副会長を務めた村上久範士十段、東京教育大学教授でドイツ武道連盟師範であった稲垣源四郎範士九段がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Famous archers are include Sakae URAKAMI (Hanshi Judan (tenth grade of the highest ranked archers)), who is shaho-seitei-iin (Archery Constitution Committee) and an editor of textbooks of archery; Hisashi MURAKAMI (Hanshi Judan (tenth grade of the highest ranked archers)), who is vice-president of All Nippon Kyudo Federation; Genshiro INAGAKI (Hanshi Kyudan (ninth grade of the highest ranked archers)), who is a professor for Tokyo University of Education and an instructor for Budo Federation Germany.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Famous archers include Sakae URAKAMI (Hanshi Judan - tenth grade of the highest ranked archers), who is shaho-seitei-iin (Archery Constitution Committee Member) and an editor of textbooks on archery; Hisashi MURAKAMI (Hanshi Judan - tenth grade of the highest ranked archers, who is vice-president of All Nippon Kyudo Federation; Genshiro INAGAKI (Hanshi Kyudan - ninth grade of the highest ranked archers), who is a professor at Tokyo University of Education and an instructor for the Budo Federation of Germany.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Famous archers include Sakae URAKAMI (Hanshi Judan - tenth grade of the highest ranked archers), who is shaho-seitei-iin (Archery Constitution Committee Member) and an editor of textbooks on archery; Hisashi MURAKAMI (Hanshi Judan - tenth grade of the highest ranked archers), who is vice-president of All Nippon Kyudo Federation; Genshiro INAGAKI (Hanshi Kyudan - ninth grade of the highest ranked archers), who is a professor at Tokyo University of Education and an instructor for the Budo Federation of Germany.</e>
<cmt>)補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="52">
<sen id="133">
<j>大心派</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daishin-ha school</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daishin-ha school</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daishin school</e>
<cmt>-ha削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="134">
<j>吉田重高の弟子、田中秀次（号：大心）を祖とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigetaka YOSHIDA&apos;s student Hidetsugu TANAKA (title: Daishin) is regarded as the originator.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigetaka YOSHIDA&apos;s student Hidetsugu TANAKA (title: Daishin) is regarded as the originator.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigetaka YOSHIDA&apos;s student Hidetsugu TANAKA (title: Daishin) is regarded as the originator.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="135">
<j>秀次は京都の人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hidetsugu is a person of Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hidetsugu is a person from Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hidetsugu is a person from Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="53">
<sen id="136">
<j>寿徳派</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jutoku-ha school</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jutoku-ha school</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jutoku school</e>
<cmt>-ha削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="137">
<j>吉田重綱の弟子、木村寿徳を祖とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigetsuna YOSHIDA&apos;s student Jutoku KIMURA is regarded as the originator.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigetsuna YOSHIDA&apos;s student Jutoku KIMURA is regarded as the originator.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigetsuna YOSHIDA&apos;s student Jutoku KIMURA is regarded as the originator.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="54">
<sen id="138">
<j>寿徳は近江国堅田の出身で、もと猪飼氏を称していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jutoku was from Katata, Omi-no-kuni. He was originally claiming to come from the Ikai clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jutoku was from Katata, Omi-no-kuni. He originally claimed to have come from the Ikai clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jutoku was from Katata, Omi Province and originally claimed to have come from the Ikai clan.</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。Omi Provinceに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="55">
<sen id="139">
<j>雪荷派（せっかは）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sekka-ha school (Snow Lotus Sect).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sekka-ha school (Snow Lotus Sect).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sekka school (Snow Lotus sect)</e>
<cmt>ピリオド削除-ha削除sectに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="140">
<j>吉田重政の四男（異説あり）、吉田重勝（六左衛門、号：雪荷）（永正11年（1514年）- 天正18年（1590年））を祖とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigemasa YOSHIDA&apos;s fourth son (controversial) Shigekatsu YOSHIDA (Rokuzaemon, title: Sekka) (1514 - 1590) is regarded as the originator.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigemasa YOSHIDA&apos;s fourth son (controversial) Shigekatsu YOSHIDA (Rokuzaemon, title: Sekka) (1514 - 1590) is regarded as the originator.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigemasa YOSHIDA&apos;s fourth son (controversial) Shigekatsu YOSHIDA (Rokuzaemon, title: Sekka) (1514 - 1590) is regarded as the originator.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="56">
<sen id="141">
<j>上述のように吉田家と主君の六角義賢の間で家伝をめぐって争いが生じた折、家伝が絶えることを危惧した重政らが雪荷に奥義を授けて京都に移らせたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As mentioned above, there were trouble about the family secret techniques between the Yoshida clan and the lord Yoshikata ROKKAKU. Shigemasa was afraid that his family secret techniques might get discontinued. So, he taught the doctrines to Sekka and sent him to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As mentioned above, there was trouble concerning the family secret techniques between the Yoshida clan and the lord Yoshikata ROKKAKU. Shigemasa was afraid that his family secret techniques might become lost. So, he taught the doctrines to Sekka and sent him to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As mentioned above, since there was trouble concerning the family secret techniques between the Yoshida clan and the lord Yoshikata ROKKAKU, Shigemasa was afraid that his family secret techniques might become lost, so he taught the doctrines to Sekka and sent him to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="57">
<sen id="142">
<j>雪荷は仕官しなかったものの、多くの武将との交際が伝えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though Sekka did not enter the government service, it is said that he was associated with a lot of warlords.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though Sekka did not enter government service, it is said that he was associated with many warlords.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Sekka did not enter government service, it is said that he was associated with many warlords.</e>
<cmt>Though →Although に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="143">
<j>特に細川幽斎とは親しく、弓術を教授したほか、幽斎配下の故実家小笠原秀清（少斎）から故実・礼法を学んだという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially, he was an intimate friend of Yusai HOSOKAWA. Besides teaching him archery, it is said that he learnt Kojitsu (ancient practices of customs) and rules of decorum from Yusai&apos;s follower Hidekiyo (Shosai) OGASAWARA, who was an authority of ancient custom practice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was an intimate friend of Yusai HOSOKAWA. Besides teaching him archery, it is said that he learnt Kojitsu (ancient customs) and rules of decorum from Yusai&apos;s follower Hidekiyo (Shosai) OGASAWARA, who was an authority of ancient customs.</e>
<cmt>wordiness, redundancy,</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was an intimate friend of Yusai HOSOKAWA; besides teaching him archery, it is said that he learnt Kojitsu (ancient customs) and rules of decorum from Yusai&apos;s follower Hidekiyo (Shosai) OGASAWARA, who was an authority of ancient customs.</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="144">
<j>天正18年（1590年）に77歳で没した地も細川氏領国の丹後国田辺であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When he passed away in 1590 at the age of 77, the place was Tanabe, Tango-no-kuni country, which was within the territory of the Hosokawa clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He passed away in 1590 at the age of 77, in Tanabe, Tango-no-kuni country, which was within the territory of the Hosokawa clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar, wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He passed away in 1590 at the age of 77, in Tanabe, Tango Province, which was within the territory of the Hosokawa clan.</e>
<cmt>Tango Provinceに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="58">
<sen id="145">
<j>子孫は津藩主の藤堂氏に仕え（扶持600石）、代々六左衛門を称し唯授一人の相伝を受け継いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His descendants served the Todo clan (chief of domain of Tsu) (salary was 600 Koku of rice). From generation to generation, they claimed to be Rokuzaemon and handed down their techniques by only one student (Yuiju Ichinin, to succeed everything that the master knows about the art to only one excellent disciple).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His descendants served the Todo clan (chief of the Tsu domain) (his salary was 600 Koku of rice). From generation to generation, they claimed to be Rokuzaemon and handed down their techniques through only one student (Yuiju Ichinin, to succeed everything that the master knows about the art to only one excellent disciple).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His descendants served the Todo clan (chief of the Tsu Domain) (his salary was 600 Koku of rice); from generation to generation, they claimed to be Rokuzaemon and handed down their techniques through only one student (Yuiju Ichinin, to succeed everything that the master knows about the art to only one excellent disciple).</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。Domainに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="146">
<j>津藩で手厚く保護され、近年まで道統が伝えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was cordially protected in domain of Tsu that its traditions have been handed down and spread until recent years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was cordially protected in the domain of Tsu and its traditions have been handed down and spread until recent years.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was cordially protected in the domain of Tsu and its traditions have been handed down and spread until recent years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="147">
<j>仙台藩、会津藩等にも伝わったほか、道雪派が分派した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides spreading to the domain of Sendai and the domain of Aizu, etc., it spun off Dosetsu-ha school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides spreading to the domain of Sendai and the domain of Aizu, etc., it spun off the Dosetsu-ha school.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides spreading to the domain of Sendai and the domain of Aizu, etc., it spun off the Dosetsu school.</e>
<cmt>-ha削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="148">
<j>雪荷から免許を受けた人物には、細川幽斎、蒲生氏郷、豊臣秀長・豊臣秀次、宇喜多秀家らの武将もいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the persons who had received mastership from Sekka, there were warlords such as Yusai HOSOKAWA, Ujisato GAMO, Hidenaga TOYOTOMI and Hideie UKITA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among those who had received their masters from Sekka, there were warlords such as Yusai HOSOKAWA, Ujisato GAMO, Hidenaga TOYOTOMI, and Hideie UKITA.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among those who had received their masters from Sekka, there were warlords such as Yusai HOSOKAWA, Ujisato GAMO, Hidenaga TOYOTOMI, and Hideie UKITA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="59">
<sen id="149">
<j>道雪派</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dosetsu-ha school</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dosetsu-ha school</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dosetsu school</e>
<cmt>-ha削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="150">
<j>吉田重勝（雪荷）の弟子、伴一安（喜左衛門、号：道雪）（元和7年（1621）没）を祖とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigekatsu YOSHIDA (Sekka)&apos;s student Ichian BAN (Kizaemon, title: Dosetsu) (passed away in 1621) is regarded as the originator.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigekatsu YOSHIDA (Sekka)&apos;s student Ichian BAN (Kizaemon, title: Dosetsu) (passed away in 1621) is regarded as the originator.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigekatsu YOSHIDA (Sekka)&apos;s student Ichian BAN (Kizaemon, title: Dosetsu) (passed away in 1621) is regarded as the originator.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="60">
<sen id="151">
<j>道雪はもと建仁寺の下級僧侶で、後に細川幽斎に出仕した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dosetsu was originally a low-ranked monk in Kennin-ji Temple. Later, he served Yusai HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dosetsu was originally a low-ranked monk in Kennin-ji Temple. Later, he served Yusai HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>word spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dosetsu was originally a low-ranked monk in Kennin-ji Temple, later he served Yusai HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="152">
<j>雪荷は、門下で道雪が最も優れていたので道統を継がせようとしたが、道雪は固辞し、別に一派を立てることを願い許されたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Dosetsu was the most excellent disciple, Sekka tried to have him succeeded the doctrines. But Dosetsu refused firmly, wished to establish another sect and got permitted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Dosetsu was the most excellent disciple, Sekka tried to have him succeeded the doctrines. But Dosetsu firmly refused, wished to establish another sect and got permission to do so.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Dosetsu was the most excellent disciple, Sekka tried to have him succeeded the doctrines, but Dosetsu firmly refused, wished to establish another sect and got permission to do so.</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="153">
<j>道雪の子孫が郡山藩に仕えたほか、高槻藩、会津藩、広島藩、熊本藩などに伝わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides serving the Koriyama domain, descendants of Dosetsu, they also taught for the Takatsuki domain, the Aizu domain, the Hiroshima domain, and the Kumamoto domain, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides serving the Koriyama domain, the descendants of Dosetsu, they also taught for the Takatsuki domain, the Aizu domain, the Hiroshima domain, and the Kumamoto domain, etc.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides serving the Koriyama Domain, the descendants of Dosetsu, they also taught for the Takatsuki Domain, the Aizu Domain, the Hiroshima Domain, and the Kumamoto Domain, etc.</e>
<cmt>Domainに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="61">
<sen id="154">
<j>道雪は天正年間に根矢（鏃の付いた実戦用の矢。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dosetsu did the long-range archery of Sanjusangen-do Temple with a neya</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dosetsu practiced the long-range archery of Sanjusangen-do Temple with a neya</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dosetsu practiced the long-range archery of Sanjusangen-do Temple with a neya (arrow having a heavy arrowhead that is in fact used on the battlefield. Doesn&apos;t fly far because it is heavy) during the rule of Emperor Tensho.</e>
<cmt>下の行と統合しました。actually →in factに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="155">
<j>重いので遠くに飛ばすには不利）で三十三間堂の通し矢を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(arrow attached with a heavy arrowhead used actually in battlefields. It is difficult to fly far away because it is heavy) in the period under the rule of Emperor Tensho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(arrow having a heavy arrowhead that is actually used on the battlefield. Doesn&apos;t fly far because it is heavy) during the rule of Emperor Tensho.</e>
<cmt>grammar, wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(arrow having a heavy arrowhead that is actually used on the battlefield. Doesn&apos;t fly far because it is heavy) during the rule of Emperor Tensho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="156">
<j>これが後の「根矢数」の起源となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This became the origin of the following &quot;Neyasuu&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This became the origin of the following &quot;Neyasuu&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This became the origin of the following &apos;Neyasuu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="157">
<j>初期の通し矢では道雪派の門人が多くの記録を残している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dosetsu&apos;s disciples left a lot of records in the initial long-range archery.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dosetsu&apos;s disciples left a lot of records on the initial long-range archery.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dosetsu&apos;s disciples left a lot of records on the initial long-range archery.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="62">
<sen id="158">
<j>伊賀日置系統</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">group under Iga-heki school</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">group under the Iga-heki school</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Group under the Iga-Heki school</e>
<cmt>文頭を大文字にしました。Hekiに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="159">
<j>日置弾正政次と同じ血統であるか、もしくは教えを受けたとされる、日置弥左衛門範次を祖とする流れ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Noritsugu Yazaemon HEKI, who was blood-related to Masatsugu Danjo HEKI or received the doctrines, is regarded as the originator.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Noritsugu Yazaemon HEKI, who was blood-related to Masatsugu Danjo HEKI and received the doctrines, is regarded as the originator.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Noritsugu Yazaemon HEKI, who was blood-related to Masatsugu Danjo HEKI and received the doctrines, is regarded as the originator.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="63">
<sen id="160">
<j>竹林派（ちくりんは）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chikurin-ha school (Bamboo Forest School)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chikurin-ha school (Bamboo Forest School)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chikurin school (Bamboo Forest School)</e>
<cmt>-ha削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="161">
<j>石堂竹林坊如成を祖とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Josei Chikurinbo ISHIDO is regarded as the originator.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Josei Chikurinbo ISHIDO is regarded as the originator.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Josei Chikurinbo ISHIDO is regarded as the originator.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="162">
<j>姓は北村・喜多村・石塔とも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family name is said to be Kitamura (2 kanji characters), Kitamura (3 kanji characters), or Sekito.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family name is said to be Kitamura (2 kanji characters), Kitamura (3 kanji characters), or Sekito.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family name is said to be Kitamura (北村), Kitamura (喜多村) or Sekito.</e>
<cmt>表記の違いのため漢字を併記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="163">
<j>竹林流と称する場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sometimes, it is also called the Chikurin-ryu school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sometimes, it is also called the Chikurin-ryu school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sometimes, it is also called the Chikurin school.</e>
<cmt>-ryu削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="164">
<j>如成ははじめ僧侶になり、竹林坊と号して近江に居住した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Josei first became a monk, he lived in Omi with a title of Chikurinbo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Josei first became a monk, he lived in Omi with the title of Chikurinbo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Josei first became a monk, he lived in Omi with the title of Chikurinbo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="165">
<j>この時期に吉田重政の技を伝え聞いたとも、吉田家の祈願僧となって弓術修行に没頭したとも伝えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time, he heard Shigemasa YOSHIDA&apos;s techniques and became the private prayer monk of the Yoshida family. It is said he was absorbed in archery training.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He heard about Shigemasa YOSHIDA&apos;s techniques and became the private prayer monk of the Yoshida family. It is said he was absorbed in archery training.</e>
<cmt>wordy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He heard about Shigemasa YOSHIDA&apos;s techniques and became the private prayer monk of the Yoshida family, and he was absorbed in archery training.</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="166">
<j>一方竹林派の伝書では</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, in some documentary records of the Chikurin-ha school (Bamboo Forest School)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, in some documentary records of the Chikurin-ha school (Bamboo Forest School)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, in some documentary records of the Chikurin school (Bamboo Forest School):</e>
<cmt>-ha削除:補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="64">
<sen id="167">
<j>日置弥左衛門範次 - 安松左近吉次 - 同新三郎良清 - 弓削甚左衛門正次 - 同弥六郎繁次 - 石堂竹林坊如成　（氏名には異説あり）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Noritsugu Yazaemon HEKI - Yoshitsugu, Sakon, YASUMATSU - Yoshikiyo Shinzaburo - Masatsugu, Jinzaemon, YUGE - Shitetsugu, Yarokuro - Josei Chikurinbo ISHIDO (it is controversial about the names).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Noritsugu Yazaemon HEKI - Yoshitsugu, Sakon, YASUMATSU - Yoshikiyo Shinzaburo - Masatsugu, Jinzaemon, YUGE - Shitetsugu, Yarokuro - Josei Chikurinbo ISHIDO (the names are controversial).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Noritsugu Yazaemon HEKI - Yoshitsugu Sakon YASUMATSU - Yoshikiyo Shinzaburo YASUMATSU - Masatsugu Jinzaemon YUGE - Shitetsugu Yarokuro YUGE - Josei Chikurinbo ISHIDO (the names are controversial).</e>
<cmt>,削除YASUMATSU、YUGE補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="168">
<j>という系譜が記載されるが、如成以前は不明な点が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This genealogy is written. However, there are a lot of uncertainties before Josei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This genealogy is written. However, there are a lot of uncertainties before Josei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This genealogy is written, however, there are a lot of uncertainties before Josei.</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="169">
<j>如成は後に清洲藩主松平忠吉に仕え藩士らを指導したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Josei later served Tadayoshi MATSUDAIRA (the lord of Kiyosu domain) and taught the feudal soldiers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Josei later served Tadayoshi MATSUDAIRA (the lord of Kiyosu domain) and taught the feudal soldiers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Josei later served Tadayoshi MATSUDAIRA (the lord of Kiyosu Domain) and taught the feudal soldiers.</e>
<cmt>Domainに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="170">
<j>次男の貞次（弥蔵）が技術を伝え、尾張藩成立後も引き続き栄えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His second son&apos;s Sadatsugu (Yazo) taught the techniques and continued to prosper even after the Owari domain formed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His second son Sadatsugu (Yazo) taught the techniques and continued to prosper even after the Owari domain formed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His second son Sadatsugu (Yazo) taught the techniques and continued to prosper even after the Owari Domain formed.</e>
<cmt>Domainに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="171">
<j>子孫は郡山藩に仕えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The descendants served the Koriyama domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His descendants served the Koriyama domain.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His descendants served the Koriyama Domain.</e>
<cmt>Domainに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="172">
<j>（正統竹林派）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Seito-chikurin-ha school)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Seito-chikurin-ha school)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Seito-Chikurin school)</e>
<cmt>Chikurinに訂正しました。-ha削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="65">
<sen id="173">
<j>貞次門下から尾張藩士の岡部忠次（藤左衛門）、長屋忠久（忠左衛門）、同忠重（六左衛門）らが、さらに忠重門下からは京都三十三間堂の通し矢で名高い星野茂則（勘左衛門）が輩出し、各家は代々技術を伝えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the famous disciples of Sadatsugu, there were Tadatsugu OKABE (Tozaemon) (feudal soldier of Owari domain), Tadahisa NAGAYA (Tadazaemon) and Tadashige (Rokuzaemon). Moreover, among the famous disciples of Tadashige, there was Shigenori HOSHINO (Kanzaemon), who was highly reputed for his long-range archery in the Kyoto Sanjusangen-do Temple. They handed down the techniques from generation to generation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the famous disciples of Sadatsugu, were Tadatsugu OKABE (Tozaemon) (feudal soldier of Owari domain), Tadahisa NAGAYA (Tadazaemon) and Tadashige (Rokuzaemon). Moreover, among the famous disciples of Tadashige, there was Shigenori HOSHINO (Kanzaemon), who was highly reputed for his long-range archery skills in the Kyoto Sanjusangen-do Temple. They handed down the techniques from generation to generation.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the famous disciples of Sadatsugu, were Tadatsugu OKABE (Tozaemon) (feudal soldier of Owari domain), Tadahisa NAGAYA (Tadazaemon) and Tadashige (Rokuzaemon), moreover, among the famous disciples of Tadashige, there was Shigenori HOSHINO (Kanzaemon), who was highly reputed for his long-range archery skills in the Kyoto Sanjusangen-do Temple; they handed down the techniques from generation to generation.</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="174">
<j>これら尾張の系統が尾州竹林派である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These schools in Owari is the Bishu-Chikurin-ha group.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These schools in Owari belong to the Bishu-Chikurin-ha group.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These schools in Owari belong to the Bishu-Chikurin group.</e>
<cmt>-ha削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="66">
<sen id="175">
<j>また貞次門下の野村勝吉（喜左衛門）、瓦林（尾林）成直（与次右衛門）は紀伊藩に竹林派を伝えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, Sadatsugu&apos;s disciples Katsukichi (Kizaemon) NOMURA and Shigenao (Yojiemon/Yojiuemon) KAWARABAYASHI (OBAYASHI) taught Chikurin-ha school to the Kishu domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, Sadatsugu&apos;s disciples Katsukichi (Kizaemon) NOMURA and Shigenao (Yojiemon/Yojiuemon) KAWARABAYASHI (OBAYASHI) taught Chikurin-ha school techniques to the Kishu domain.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, Sadatsugu&apos;s disciples Katsukichi (Kizaemon) NOMURA and Shigenao (Yojiemon/Yojiuemon) KAWARABAYASHI (OBAYASHI) taught Chikurin school techniques to the Kishu Domain.</e>
<cmt>Domainに訂正しました。-ha削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="176">
<j>射法訓作者の吉見経武（台右衛門、法名：順正）、通し矢天下一の和佐範遠（大八郎）らが輩出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were famous masters such as Noritake YOSHIMI (Daiemon, posthumous Buddhist name: Junsei), who was the author of &quot;Shahokun (textbook how to shoot an arrow)&quot;, and Norito WASA (Daihachiro), who was Toshiya-tenkaichi (Japan No. 1 of long-range archery).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were famous masters such as Noritake YOSHIMI (Daiemon, posthumous Buddhist name: Junsei), who was the author of &quot;Shahokun (textbook how to shoot an arrow),&quot; and Norito WASA (Daihachiro), who was Toshiya-tenkaichi (No. 1 in Japan for long-range archery).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were famous masters such as Noritake YOSHIMI (Daiemon, posthumous Buddhist name: Junsei), who was the author of &quot;Shahokun&quot; (textbook how to shoot an arrow), and Norito WASA (Daihachiro), who was Toshiya-tenkaichi (No. 1 in Japan for long-range archery).</e>
<cmt>&quot;の位置を訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="177">
<j>これが紀州竹林派である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is the Kishu-chikurin-ha group of schools.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is the Kishu-chikurin-ha group of schools.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is the Kishu-Chikurin group of schools.</e>
<cmt>Chikurinに訂正しました。-ha削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="67">
<sen id="178">
<j>他に高松藩、熊本藩など多くの藩に伝わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides, it spread to a lot of domains such as Takamatsu domain and Kumamoto domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides, it spread to a lot of domains such as Takamatsu domain and Kumamoto domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It spread to a lot of domains such as the Takamatsu and Kumamoto Domains.</e>
<cmt>Domainsに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="179">
<j>星野茂則から江戸に伝わった系統は旗本により伝承され（江戸竹林派）、後に本多流となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The school spread to Edo from Shigenori HOSHINO was handed down to direct retainers of shoguns as Edo Chikurin-ha school. Later, it became Honda-ryu school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The school spread to Edo from Shigenori HOSHINO and was handed down to direct retainers of shoguns as the Edo Chikurin-ha school. Later, it became the Honda-ryu school.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The school spread to Edo from Shigenori HOSHINO and was handed down to direct retainers of shoguns as the Edo Chikurin school, later, it became the Honda school.</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。-ha削除-ryu削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="68">
<sen id="180">
<j>通し矢は堂射ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Long-range archery is also called Dosha.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Long-range archery is also called Dosha.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Long-range archery is also called Dosha.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="181">
<j>江戸時代前期に流行し、特に尾張藩と紀伊藩が鎬を削ったことから両藩の竹林派も栄えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It became popular in early Edo Era. Especially after the Owari domain and the Kii domain engaged in fierce competition, Chikurin-ha school in both domains became prosperous.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It became popular in early Edo Era. Especially after the Owari domain and the Kii domain engaged in fierce competition, Chikurin-ha school in both domains became prosperous.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It became popular in early Edo period; especially after the Owari Domain and the Kii Domain engaged in fierce competition, Chikurin school in both domains became prosperous.</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。eraに訂正しました。Domainに訂正しました。-ha削除era→periodに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="182">
<j>また記録更新のため射法・用具の研究・改良が進んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, in order to break the record, researches on the shooting method and tools, and improvements were going on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, in order to break the record, research on shooting methods and tools, and improvements were continuing.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, in order to break the record, research on shooting methods and tools, and improvements were continuing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="183">
<j>このように竹林派は堂射と縁の深い系統ではあるが、的前射法も存在し、また通し矢を禁じた系もあることから通し矢専門の流派ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Like this, Chikurin-ha school is a school closely related to Dosha. Since it has Matomae-shaho (the action to shoot an arrow to the target) and a sub-sect that forbids long range archery, it is not a sect of long range archery.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Likewise, the Chikurin-ha school is closely related to Dosha. Since it has Matomae-shaho (the action to shoot an arrow to the target) and is a sub-sect that forbids long range archery.</e>
<cmt>redundancy, wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Likewise, the Chikurin school is closely related to Dosha, since it has Matomae-shaho (the action to shoot an arrow to the target) and is a sub-sect that forbids long range archery.</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。-ha削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="184">
<j>如成は僧侶であったため、竹林派の思想・用語には仏教の影響がみられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because Josei was a monk, the influence of the Buddhism can be seen in the thought and the terminologies of Chikurin-ha school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because Josei was a monk, the influence of the Buddhism can be seen in the thought and terminologies of the Chikurin-ha school.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because Josei was a monk, the influence of the Buddhism can be seen in the thought and terminologies of the Chikurin school.</e>
<cmt>-ha削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="185">
<j>例えば現在の弓道射法八節にも採用されている「会」「離」は、仏教語の会者定離にちなむ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For instance, even in the present&apos;s Kyudo-shaho Hassetsu (eight arts of shooting an arrow), the adopted terms such as &quot;E (concentration at full draw)&quot; and &quot;Ri (release)&quot; are related to the Buddhist expression &quot;Esha-Jori&quot; (meaning that those who meet must part).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For instance, even in the presence Kyudo-shaho Hassetsu the eight arts of shooting an arrow), the adopted terms such as &quot;E (concentration at full draw)&quot; and &quot;Ri (release)&quot; are related to the Buddhist expression &quot;Esha-Jori&quot; (meaning that those who meet must part).</e>
<cmt>spelling, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For instance, even in the presence Kyudo-shaho Hassetsu (the eight arts of shooting an arrow), the adopted terms such as &apos;E&apos; (concentration at full draw) and &apos;Ri&apos; (release) are related to the Buddhist expression &quot;Esha-Jori&quot; (meaning that those who meet must part).</e>
<cmt>(補足原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="69">
<sen id="186">
<j>一貫流</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ikkan-ryu school</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ikkan-ryu school</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ikkan school</e>
<cmt>-ryu削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="187">
<j>大野又兵衛一貫（文化 (元号)13年没、63歳）を祖とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ikkan Matabe ONO (passed away at the age of 63 in year 13 under the rule of Emperor Bunka) is regarded as the originator.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ikkan Matabe ONO (passed away at the age of 63 in the year 13 under the rule of Emperor Bunka) is regarded as the originator.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ikkan Matabe ONO (passed away at the age of 63 in 1816) is regarded as the originator.</e>
<cmt>元号を新暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="188">
<j>一貫は鳥取藩若桜藩（鳥取藩支藩、鳥取西館新田藩）藩士（130石）で、竹林派系統の大口流大口子積に師事した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ikkan was a warrior of Wakasa domain of Tottori domain (branch domain of Tottori, domain of Tottori Nishikan Nitta) (salary 130 koku of rice). He studied under Shiseki OGUCHI of Oguchi-ryu school, which belongs to the Chikurin-ha school group.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ikkan was a warrior of the Wakasa domain of the Tottori domain (branch domain of Tottori, domain of Tottori Nishikan Nitta) (his salary was 130 koku of rice). He studied under Shiseki OGUCHI of the Oguchi-ryu school, belonging to the Chikurin-ha school group.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ikkan was a warrior of the Wakasa Domain of the Tottori Domain (branch domain of Tottori, domain of Tottori Nishikan Nitta) (his salary was 130 koku of rice), and he studied under Shiseki OGUCHI of the Oguchi school, belonging to the Chikurin school group.</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。Domainに訂正しました。-ha削除-ryu削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="189">
<j>寛政年間に剣・槍・居合術も含む一貫流を創始した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He established Ikkan-ryu school, which contains also the sword, the spear, and Iai-jutsu (technique of drawing real swords).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He established the Ikkan-ryu school, which teaches also sword, spear, and Iai-jutsu (technique of drawing real swords).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He established the Ikkan school, which teaches also sword, spear, and Iai-jutsu (technique of drawing real swords).</e>
<cmt>-ryu削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="70">
<sen id="190">
<j>本多流</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Honda-ryu school</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Honda-ryu school</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Honda school</e>
<cmt>-ryu削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="71">
<sen id="191">
<j>竹林派の本多利実（天保7年（1836） - 大正6（1917））を祖とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toshizane HONDA (1836 - 1917) of the Chikurin-ha school is regarded as the originator.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toshizane HONDA (1836 - 1917) of the Chikurin-ha school is regarded as the originator.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toshizane HONDA (1836 - 1917) of the Chikurin school is regarded as the originator.</e>
<cmt>-ha削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="192">
<j>明治大正期に成立。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was established during the Meiji and Taisho Eras.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was established during the Meiji and Taisho Eras.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was established during the Meiji and Taisho eras.</e>
<cmt>erasに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="193">
<j>日置流の系統ながら正面で打起すのが特徴。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since it belongs to the group of Heki-ryu schools, Shomen-uchiokoshi (anchoring in front facing posture) is a characteristic.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since it belongs to the group of Heki-ryu schools, Shomen-uchiokoshi (anchoring in front facing posture) is a characteristic.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since it belongs to the group of Heki schools, Shomen-uchiokoshi (anchoring in front facing posture) is a characteristic.</e>
<cmt>-ryu削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="194">
<j>利実は、斜面打起しであった竹林派に正面打起しを導入するなど射法に改良を加え、現代の射法に強い影響を与えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By introducing various modifications such as Shamen-uchiokoshi (anchoring in slanting position) into Chikurin-ha, which is Shomen-uchiokoshi (anchoring in front facing posture), Toshizane improved the shooting method. He brought about major impacts to modern archery.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By introducing various modifications such as Shamen-uchiokoshi (anchoring in a slanting position) into Chikurin-ha, which is Shomen-uchiokoshi (anchoring in front facing posture), Toshizane improved the shooting method. He brought about a major impact to modern archery.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By introducing various modifications such as Shamen-uchiokoshi (anchoring in a slanting position) into Chikurin school, which is Shomen-uchiokoshi (anchoring in front facing posture), Toshizane improved the shooting method and brought about a major impact to modern archery.</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。-ha削除、school補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="72">
<sen id="195">
<j>日置流の現在</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Heki-ryu school nowadays</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Heki-ryu school nowadays</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Heki school nowadays</e>
<cmt>-ryu削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="196">
<j>山科派、大蔵派</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamashina-ha school, Okura-ha school</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yamashina-ha school, Okura-ha school</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamashina school, Okura school</e>
<cmt>-ha削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="197">
<j>吉田大蔵・片岡家延・家清の流れを汲む流派が「日置流吉田派」として熊本県で活動している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshida-ha group of Heki-ryu school popular in Kumamoto Prefecture is a sect related to the schools of Okura YOSHIDA, Ienobu KATAOKA and Iekiyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshida-ha group of Heki-ryu school popular in Kumamoto Prefecture is a sect related to the schools of Okura YOSHIDA, Ienobu KATAOKA and Iekiyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshida group of Heki school popular in Kumamoto Prefecture is a sect related to the schools of Okura YOSHIDA, Ienobu KATAOKA and Iekiyo.</e>
<cmt>-ha削除-ryu削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="73">
<sen id="198">
<j>左近右衛門派、大心派、寿徳派</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sakonemon-ha school, Daishin-ha school, and Jutoku-ha school</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sakonemon-ha school, Daishin-ha school, and the Jutoku-ha school</e>
<cmt>grammar, cell alignment</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sakonemon school, Daishin school, and the Jutoku school</e>
<cmt>-ha削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="199">
<j>現在は伝わらない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">do not have any activity now.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">No activity at present.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">No activity at present.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="74">
<sen id="200">
<j>印西派</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Insai-ha school</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Insai-ha school</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Insai school</e>
<cmt>-ha削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="201">
<j>鹿児島県に薩摩日置、岡山県には江戸時代・日置当流師家であった徳山家に備前日置が伝わっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kagoshima Prefecture, Satsuma-heki was popular. In Okayama Prefecture during Edo Era, Bizen Hioki was taught to the Tokuyama family in the teachers&apos; house of Hekito-ryu school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Kagoshima Prefecture, Satsuma-heki was popular. In Okayama Prefecture during the Edo Era, Bizen Hioki was taught to the Tokuyama family iat the teachers&apos; house of the Hekito-ryu school.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Kagoshima Prefecture, Satsuma-Heki was popular; in Okayama Prefecture during the Edo period, Bizen-Heki was taught to the Tokuyama family iat the teachers&apos; house of the Hekito school.</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。-ryu削除’を&apos;に訂正しました。Hekiに訂正しました。eraに訂正しました。Bizen-Hekiに訂正しました。era→periodに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="202">
<j>備前日置の流れである浦上一派は関東を中心として活動している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Urakami group, which belongs to schoolof Bizen-heki, is popular mainly in Kanto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Urakami group, which belongs to schoolof Bizen-heki, is popular mainly in Kanto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Urakami group, which belongs to schoolof Bizen-Heki, is popular mainly in Kanto.</e>
<cmt>Bizen-Hekiに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="203">
<j>静岡県には印西派遠州系の流れの2系統が伝わりそれぞれ宗家が存在する（奥村家→河合治明系と上村清兵衛系）、近年になって、上村清兵衛系の遠州系から摂津系が分派した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Shizuoka Prefecture, two schools (each with originator respectively) belonging to the Enshu group of Insai-ha school are popular (Okumura family =&gt; Haruaki KAWAI group and Seibe KAMIMURA group). In recent years, the Enshu group of Seibe KAMIMURA group spun off Settsu group.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Shizuoka Prefecture, two schools belonging to the Enshu group of the Insai-ha school are popular (Okumura family =&gt; Haruaki KAWAI group and Seibe KAMIMURA group). In recent years, the Enshu group of Seibe KAMIMURA group spun off the Settsu group.</e>
<cmt>wordy, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Urakami group, which belongs to schoolof Bizen-Heki, is popular mainly in Kanto.</e>
<cmt>Bizen-Hekiに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="204">
<j>主な活動団体としては、徳山師家道場・徳山正射会、浦上同門会、筑波大学弓道研究室、桜一射会、一水会、薩摩日置流腰矢保存会などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The main active groups include Tokuyama Shika Dojo (training hall of Tokuyama, teachers&apos; house), Tokuyama Seishakai, Urakami Domonkai, archery laboratory of University of Tsukuba, Sakura-isshakai (archery circle), Issuikai, Satsuma Heki-ryu Koshiya Hozonkai (Preservation Society of Koshiya (the archery for battle that a group of archers shoot under the command of a general) of Heki-ryu school in Satsuma).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The main active groups include Tokuyama Shika Dojo (training hall of Tokuyama, teachers&apos; house), Tokuyama Seishakai, Urakami Domonkai, archery laboratory of the University of Tsukuba, Sakura-isshakai (archery circle), Issuikai, Satsuma Heki-ryu Koshiya Hozonkai (Preservation Society of Koshiya - archery for battle where a group of archers shoot under the command of a general -of the Heki-ryu school in Satsuma).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The main active groups include Tokuyama Shika Dojo (training hall of Tokuyama, teachers&apos; house), Tokuyama Seishakai, Urakami Domonkai, archery laboratory of the University of Tsukuba, Sakura-isshakai (archery circle), Issuikai, Satsuma Heki-ryu Koshiya Hozonkai (Preservation Society of Koshiya - archery for battle where a group of archers shoot under the command of a general - of the Heki school in Satsuma).</e>
<cmt>スペース補足-ryu削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="205">
<j>他に、日置流印西派塩崎御弓保存会（一水軒の弟子・稲葉吉重が始まり）が福島県南相馬市で、上村清兵衛系の遠州系が静岡草薙神社境内の道場で、摂津系同門会が兵庫県川西市で活動している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, the Heki-ryu Insai-ha Shionosaki Onkyu Hozonkai (Preservation Society of archery in Shionosaki, founded by Issuiken&apos;s student Yoshishige INABA) is active in Minami-soma City, Fukushima Prefecture. Enshu group of Seibe KAMIMURA group is active in the training hall within the premises of Kusanagi-jinja Shrine, Shizuoka. And Settsu-kei Domonkai (Fellow Association of Settsu group) is active in Kawanishi City, Hyogo Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, the Heki-ryu Insai-ha Shionosaki Onkyu Hozonkai (Preservation Society of archery in Shionosaki, founded by Issuiken&apos;s student Yoshishige INABA) is active in Minami-soma City, Fukushima Prefecture. The Enshu group of Seibe KAMIMURA group is active in the training hall within the premises of Kusanagi-jinja Shrine, Shizuoka. And Settsu-kei Domonkai (Fellow Association of Settsu group) is active in Kawanishi City, Hyogo Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, the Heki-ryu Insai-ha Shionosaki Onkyu Hozonkai (Preservation Society of archery in Shionosaki, founded by Issuiken&apos;s student Yoshishige INABA) is active in Minamisoma City, Fukushima Prefecture, and the Enshu group of Seibe KAMIMURA group is active in the training hall within the premises of Kusanagi-jinja Shrine, Shizuoka, and Settsu-kei Domonkai (Fellow Association of Settsu group) is active in Kawanishi City, Hyogo Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>Minamisomaに訂正しました。一文にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="206">
<j>流れを汲む大学弓道部は、早稲田大学、法政大学、筑波大学、東京工業大学、お茶の水女子大学、関西大学、岡山大学、京都大学、大阪市立大学、大阪産業大学、東北学院大学工学部など。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The university archery clubs related to the archery schools include Waseda University, Hosei University, Tsukuba University, Tokyo Institute of Technology, Ochanomizu University, Kansai University, Okayama University, Kyoto University, Osaka City University, Osaka Sangyo University, Department of Engineering at Tohoku Gakuin University, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">University archery clubs related to archery schools include Waseda University, Hosei University, Tsukuba University, Tokyo Institute of Technology, Ochanomizu University, Kansai University, Okayama University, Kyoto University, Osaka City University, Osaka Sangyo University, Department of Engineering at Tohoku Gakuin University, etc.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">University archery clubs related to archery schools include Waseda University, Hosei University, Tsukuba University, Tokyo Institute of Technology, Ochanomizu University, Kansai University, Okayama University, Kyoto University, Osaka City University, Osaka Sangyo University, Department of Engineering at Tohoku Gakuin University, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="75">
<sen id="207">
<j>雪荷派</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sekka-ha school</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sekka-ha school</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sekka school</e>
<cmt>-ha削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="208">
<j>東海地方などに伝わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It spreads to the Tokai region etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It spread to the Tokai region etc.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It spread to the Tokai region etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="209">
<j>東海地方では武士以外に庄屋・名主層にも弓術が普及し、現在でも「お祭り弓」と称して神社において祭礼と結びついた形で保存されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Tokai region, besides among samurais, archery is popular also in Shoya (village headman) and Nanushi hierarchy (village headman). Even now, it is preserved in the form of the so-called &quot;Omatsuri-yumi (archery for the festival)&quot;, which is related to the festival in the Shinto shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Tokai region, besides being popular among the samurai, archery is also popular among Shoya (village headman) and in the Nanushi hierarchy (village headman). Even now, it is preserved in the form of the so-called &quot;Omatsuri-yumi (archery for the festival),&quot; which is related to festivals in the Shinto shrine.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Tokai region, besides being popular among the samurai, archery is also popular among Shoya (village headman) and in the Nanushi hierarchy (village headman); even now, it is preserved in the form of the so-called &apos;Omatsuri-yumi&apos; (archery for the festival), which is related to festivals in the Shinto shrine.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に一文にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="76">
<sen id="210">
<j>道雪派</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dosetsu-ha school</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dosetsu-ha school</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dosetsu school</e>
<cmt>-ha削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="211">
<j>熊本県に熊本系の宗家が存在し、継承されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kumamoto Prefecture, a Kumamoto group with an existing originator is handing down its doctrines.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Kumamoto Prefecture, a group with an existing originator is handing down its doctrines.</e>
<cmt>redundant</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Kumamoto Prefecture, a group with an existing originator is handing down its doctrines.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="212">
<j>藤崎八旛宮で射去祭を奉仕するなどの活動をしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Fujisaki Hachimangu, there are events such as Shasaru-matsuri (Shooting Festival).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Fujisaki Hachimangu, there are events such as theShasaru-matsuri (Shooting Festival).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Fujisakihachiman-gu Shrine, there are events such as the Shasaru-matsuri (Shooting Festival).</e>
<cmt>Fujisakihachiman-gu Shrineに訂正しました。スペース補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="77">
<sen id="213">
<j>竹林派</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chikurin-ha school</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chikurin-ha school</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chikurin school</e>
<cmt>-ha削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="214">
<j>愛知県に尾州竹林派の星野系・岡部系などが、熊本県に肥後竹林派が継承されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Aichi Prefecture, there are schools such as Hoshino group of Bishu-Chikurin-ha group, and Okabe group. In Kumamoto Prefecture, Higo-chikurin-ha school is being succeeded.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Aichi Prefecture, there are schools such as Hoshino group of Bishu-Chikurin-ha group, and Okabe group. In Kumamoto Prefecture, Higo-chikurin-ha school is being succeeded.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Aichi Prefecture, there are schools such as Hoshino group of Bishu-Chikurin group, and Okabe group, and in Kumamoto Prefecture, Higo-Chikurin school is being succeeded.</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。Chikurinに訂正しました。-ha削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="215">
<j>肥後竹林派は維新後一時絶えたが、その後旧熊本藩家老家で八代城主であった松井氏に相伝され、現在まで代々受け継がれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Higo-chikurin-ha school was temporarily discontinued after the Imperial restoration. However, it was later inherited in the family of karo (chief retainer of daimyo (Japanese territorial lord)) of the former Kumamoto domain by the Matsui clan, which was the eighth owner of the castle. It is succeeded from generation to generation up to the present time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Higo-chikurin-ha school was temporarily discontinued after the Imperial restoration. However, it was later inherited by the family of karo (chief retainer of daimyo - Japanese territorial lord) of the former Kumamoto domain by the Matsui clan, which was the eighth owner of the castle. It has succeeded from generation to generation up to the present time.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Higo-Chikurin school was temporarily discontinued after the Imperial restoration, however, it was later inherited by the family of karo (chief retainer of daimyo - Japanese territorial lord) of the former Kumamoto Domain by the Matsui clan, which was the eighth owner of the castle, and it has succeeded from generation to generation up to the present time.</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。Chikurinに訂正しました。-ha削除Domainに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="216">
<j>流れを汲む大学弓道部は、龍谷大学、同志社大学、名古屋大学、香川大学など。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The university archery clubs related to the archery schools include Ryukoku University, Doshisha University, Nagoya University, Kagawa University, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">University archery clubs related to the archery schools include Ryukoku University, Doshisha University, Nagoya University, Kagawa University, etc.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">University archery clubs related to the archery schools include Ryukoku University, Doshisha University, Nagoya University, Kagawa University, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="217">
<j>本多流の関西学院大学は石堂竹林派（高松藩系）の伝統も伝えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kwansei Gakuin University of Honda-ryu school also teaches the traditional doctrines of Ishido-Chikurin-ryu school (group of the Takamatsu domain).</e>
<cmt>関西学院大学の英名はKwansei Gakuin University だと思います。http://www.kwansei.ac.jp/index.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kwansei Gakuin University of Honda-ryu school also teaches the traditional doctrines of Ishido-Chikurin-ryu school (group of the Takamatsu domain).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kwansei Gakuin University of Honda school also teaches the traditional doctrines of Ishido-Chikurin school (group of the Takamatsu Domain).</e>
<cmt>Domainに訂正しました。-ryu削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="78">
<sen id="218">
<j>一貫流</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ikkan-ryu school</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ikkan-ryu school</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ikkan school</e>
<cmt>-ryu削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="219">
<j>宗家は絶えたものの、鳥取県で一貫流保存会が活動。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Soke or grand master no longer exists. However, in Tottori Prefecture, Ikkan-ryu hozon kai (Preservation society of Ikkan-ryu school) is still active.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Soke or grand master no longer exists. However, in Tottori Prefecture, Ikkan-ryu hozon kai (Preservation society of Ikkan-ryu school) is still active.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Soke or grand master no longer exists, however, in Tottori Prefecture, Ikkan-ryu hozon kai (Preservation society of Ikkan school) is still active.</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。-ryu削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="79">
<sen id="220">
<j>本多流</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Honda-ryu school</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Honda-ryu school</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Honda school</e>
<cmt>-ryu削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="221">
<j>財団法人生弓会として各地の支部で活動している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seikyukai Foundation has active branch associations in various places.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Seikyukai Foundation has active branch associations in various places.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Seikyukai Foundation has active branch associations in various places.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="222">
<j>関東で特に盛んである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is particularly active in Kanto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is particularly active in Kanto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is particularly active in Kanto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="223">
<j>現在本多利永氏が四世宗家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At present, Toshinaga HONDA is the fourth soke (grand master).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At present, Toshinaga HONDA is the fourth soke (grand master).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At present, Toshinaga HONDA is the fourth soke (grand master).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="224">
<j>流れを汲む大学弓道部は、東京大学、國學院大學、学習院大学、東京理科大学、関西学院大学など。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The university archery clubs related to the archery schools include the University of Tokyo, Kokugakuin University, Gakushuin University, Tokyo University of Science, and Kwansei Gakuin University, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">University archery clubs related to the archery schools include the University of Tokyo, Kokugakuin University, Gakushuin University, Tokyo University of Science, and Kwansei Gakuin University, etc.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">University archery clubs related to the archery schools include the University of Tokyo, Kokugakuin University, Gakushuin University, Tokyo University of Science, and Kwansei Gakuin University, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Oxhop(id:2551), Carkuni(id:79281), Tomomarusan(id:17060), Izayohi(id:13095), 赤井彗星(id:18381), 月下薄氷(id:47743), ゐ(id:795), 経済準学士(id:22656), ぼびん(id:108524), MizunoH(id:112470), 福太郎(id:132415), Himazin(id:22034), Kumatora(id:16941), Shigekata(id:72788), Ticks(id:17577), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>