<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>門松</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kadomatsu (New Year&apos;s pine decoration)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kadomatsu (New Year&apos;s pine decoration)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kadomatsu (New Year&apos;s pine decoration)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>門松（かどまつ）とは、正月に家の門の前などに立てられる一対になった松や竹の飾りのこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The kadomatsu (literally, gate pine) is a pair of displays made of pine and bamboo set up in places such as in front of houses during the New Year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The kadomatsu (literally, gate pine) is a pair of displays made of pine and bamboo set up in places such as in front of houses during the New Year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The kadomatsu (literally, gate pine) is a pair of displays made of pine and bamboo set up in places such as in front of houses during the New Year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>松飾りとも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also referred to as matsukazari (literally, pine decoration).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also referred to as matsukazari (literally, pine decoration).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also referred to as matsukazari (literally, pine decoration).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>古くは、木のこずえに神が宿ると考えられていたことから、門松は年神を家に迎え入れるための依代という意味合いがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The kadomatsu has an implication of the yorishiro (an object where the gods reside) for welcoming Toshigami (god of the incoming year) home because the gods were believed to reside in treetops.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The significance of the kadomatsu is that it is a yorishiro (an object where the gods reside) for welcoming Toshigami (god of the incoming year) home because the gods were believed to reside in treetops.</e>
<cmt>「The kadomatsu has an implication of the」→「The significance of the kadomatsu is that is is a」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The significance of the kadomatsu is that it is an object where the gods reside for welcoming the god of the incoming year home because the gods were believed to reside in treetops.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>地域の言い伝えにより松を使わない所もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Pine is not used in some areas according to their traditions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Pine is not used in some areas, depending on local traditions.</e>
<cmt>「according to their」→「, depending on local」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Pine is not used in some areas, depending on the local traditions.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>飾り付け</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Decoration</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Decoration</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Decoration</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>現在の門松は中心の竹が目立つが、その本体は名前で解るとおり松である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The present-day kadomatsu seems to feature bamboo in the middle, but the main part of it is pine as indicated in the name.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The present-day kadomatsu features bamboo in the middle, but the main part of it is pine as indicated in the name.</e>
<cmt>「seems to feature」→「features」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The present-day kadomatsu features bamboo in the middle, but its main part is pine as indicated in the name.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>もと、平安の貴族達が好んだ小松引きと言う行事で持ち帰った「子の日の松」を長寿祈願のため愛好する習慣から変遷したものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The kadomatsu was originally transformed from the custom of adoring the &apos;Pine on the Day of the Rat,&apos; which nobles in the Heian period took home from their favorite event called the Komatsu-hiki (pulling out small pine trees on the first day of the Rat), to pray for longevity.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The kadomatsu stems originally from the popular custom of the &apos;Pine on the Day of the Rat,&apos; in which nobles in the Heian period took pines home during the fondly-held event called the Komatsu-hiki (pulling out small pine trees on the first day of the Rat), and used them to pray for longevity.</e>
<cmt>再構成しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The kadomatsu stems originally from the popular custom of the &apos;Pine on the Day of the Rat,&apos; in which nobles in the Heian period took pines home during the fondly-held event called the Komatsu-hiki (pulling out small pine trees on the first day of the Rat), and used them to pray for longevity.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>現在も関西の旧家などでは門松の代わりに、玄関の両側に白い和紙で包んだ根が付いたままの小松（松の折枝は略式）が飾られているのはその流れを汲むものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even today, families such as old families in the Kansai region partly follow the old custom, displaying, in stead of the kadomatsu, small pines (simplified design of pine branches) with roots wrapped in Japanese paper on the both sides of the entrance.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even today, families of ancient lineage in the Kansai region partly follow the old custom, displaying small pines (with a simplified design of pine branches) with roots wrapped in Japanese paper on both sides of the house entrance, instead of the standard kadomatsu.</e>
<cmt>「such as old families」→「of ancient lineage」, 「with a」挿入, 「the」削除,「standard」挿入,「instead of the kadomatsu」箇所異動,</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even today, families of ancient lineage in the Kansai region partly follow the old custom, displaying small pines (with a simplified design of pine branches) with roots wrapped in Japanese paper on both sides of the house entrance, instead of the standard kadomatsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>地方により門松の様式に差がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are regional differences in the style of the kadomatsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are regional differences in the style of the kadomatsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are regional differences in the style of the kadomatsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>関西では3本組の竹を中心に、前面にハボタン（紅白）後方に長めの若松を添え、下部を竹で巻く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Kansai region, a set of the three bamboo stalks is placed in the middle with the decoration of (red and white) ornamental cabbage on the front and young pine on the back, all tied with bamboo strips around the bottom.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Kansai region, a set of three bamboo stalks is placed in the middle with a decoration of (red and white) ornamental cabbages at the front and young pine at the back, all tied with bamboo strips around the bottom.</e>
<cmt>「the」削除, 「the」→「a」, 「()」削除, 「cabbage on」→「cabbages at」, 「on」→「at」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Kansai region, a set of three bamboo stalks is placed in the middle with a decoration of (red and white) ornamental cabbages at the front and young pine at the back, all tied with bamboo strips around the bottom.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>豪華になるとウメ老木やナンテン、クマザサやユズリハなどを添える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A luxurious kadomatsu includes trees such as old plum, nandina (heavenly bamboo), low striped bamboo called kumazasa, and yuzuriha (Daphniphyllum macropodum).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The more luxurious kadomatsu include trees such as old plum, nandina (heavenly bamboo), low striped bamboo called kumazasa, and yuzuriha (Daphniphyllum macropodum).</e>
<cmt>「A」→「The more」, 「includes」→「include」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The more luxurious kadomatsu include trees such as old plum, nandina (heavenly bamboo), low striped bamboo called kumazasa, and yuzuriha (Daphniphyllum macropodum).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>関東では、3本組の竹を中心に、周囲に短めの若松を配置し、下部をわらで巻くという形態が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For the common kadomatsu in the Kanto region, relatively short young pine is placed around a set of the three bamboo stalks in the middle, the bottom of which is tied with straw ropes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For the standard kadomatsu in the Kanto region, relatively short young pine branches are placed around a set of three bamboo stalks in the middle, the bottom of which is tied with straw ropes.</e>
<cmt>「common」→「standard」, 「pine is」→「pine branches are」,「the」削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For the standard kadomatsu in the Kanto region, relatively short young pine branches are placed around a set of three bamboo stalks in the middle, the bottom of which is tied with straw ropes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="13">
<j>竹の先端部の形状は、斜めに切った「そぎ」と、真横に切った「寸胴（ずんどう）」の2種類がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are two forms of the tip of the bamboo stalk: the diagonally sliced &apos;sogi&apos; and the horizontally sliced &apos;zundo.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are two styles for the tip of the bamboo stalks: the diagonally sliced &apos;sogi&apos; and the horizontally sliced &apos;zundo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「forms of」→「styles for」, 「stalk」→「stalks」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are two styles for the tip of the bamboo stalks: the diagonally sliced &apos;sogi&apos; and the horizontally sliced &apos;zundo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="14">
<j>「そぎ」は徳川家康が始めたもので、徳川家康の生涯唯一の敗北として知られる「三方ヶ原の戦い」（1572年）のあと、対戦相手の武田信玄に対して、次は斬るぞという念を込めたのが始まりという俗説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to popular belief, it was Ieyasu TOKUGAWA who started the &apos;sogi&apos; after the Battle of Mikatagahara (1572), a battle known as his only defeat ever, swearing that he would slash his enemy Shingen TAKEDA next time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to popular belief, it was Ieyasu TOKUGAWA who created the &apos;sogi&apos; after the Battle of Mikatagahara (1572), a battle known as his only ever defeat, swearing that he would slash his enemy Shingen TAKEDA next time.</e>
<cmt>「started」→「created」, 「defeat ever」→「ever defeat」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to popular belief, it was Ieyasu TOKUGAWA who created the &apos;sogi&apos; after the Battle of Mikatagahara (1572), a battle known as his only ever defeat, swearing that he would slash his enemy Shingen TAKEDA next time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="15">
<j>実際は武家が昔ながらの寸胴、庶民がそこから発展させた派手なそぎを好んだのが基らしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The two forms, as a matter of fact, seem to have originated from the facts that samurai families favored the old-fashioned zundo while ordinary people preferred the showy sogi that they had developed from the zundo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In reality, the two forms seem to have originated from the fact that samurai families favored the old-fashioned zundo while ordinary people preferred the showy sogi that they had developed from the zundo.</e>
<cmt>「The two forms, as a matter of fact,」→「In reality, the two forms」, 「facts」→「fact」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In reality, the two forms seem to have originated from the fact that samurai families favored the old-fashioned zundo while ordinary people preferred the showy sogi that they had developed from the zundo.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="16">
<j>関西だけかもしれないが切り口に節が現れる様に斜めに切る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although this might be the case for the Kansai region only, a bamboo stalk is diagonally cut so that the section includes the joint.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although generally the case for the Kansai region only, a bamboo stalk is diagonally cut so that the section includes the joint.</e>
<cmt>「this might be」→「genarally」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although generally the case for the Kansai region only, a bamboo stalk is diagonally cut so that the section includes the joint.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="17">
<j>これは笑った口を意味するものらしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The shape is said to embody a smiling mouth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shape is said to embody a smiling mouth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The shape is said to embody a smiling mouth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="18">
<j>設置期間</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Display period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Display period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Display Period</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>12月の10日ごろに、山から松の木（枝）を取ってくる「松迎え」をおこなう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The event called &apos;Matsu-mukae&apos; (literally, pine welcome) in which people climb mountains to collect pine trees (branches) is held around December 10,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The event called &apos;Matsu-mukae&apos; (literally, welcoming the pines) in which people climb mountains to collect pine trees (branches) is held around December 10,</e>
<cmt>「pine welcome」→「welcoming the pines」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The event called &apos;Matsu-mukae&apos; (literally, welcoming the pines) in which people climb mountains to collect pine trees (branches) is held around December 10.</e>
<cmt>ピリオドにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>これで、山から歳神様（歳徳神）を家に迎えるという説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One theory holds that this invites Toshigami-sama (Toshitokujin) home from the mountains.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One theory holds that this invites Toshigami-sama (Toshitokujin) home from the mountains.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One theory holds that this invites Toshigami-sama (Toshitokujin) home from the mountains.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="21">
<j>早いところでは20日ごろから飾る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In some regions, they display the kadomatsu from as early as December 20.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In some regions, they display the kadomatsu from as early as December 20.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In some regions, they display the kadomatsu from as early as December 20.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>しかし、現代ではクリスマスなどのイベントもあるため、25日以降に設置される場合が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In most cases, however, the kadomatsu is placed after December 25 because people today celebrate events such as Christmas.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In most cases, however, the kadomatsu is placed outside after December 25 because people today celebrate events such as Christmas.</e>
<cmt>「outside」挿入</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In most cases, however, the kadomatsu is placed outside after December 25 because people today celebrate events such as Christmas.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>12月29日に飾るのは「二重苦」、また9の末日でもあるので｢苦待つ」に通じ、12月30日12月31日に飾るのは「一夜飾り」「一日飾り」といって神をおろそかにするということから、12月28日までに飾るのが良い、とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that the kadomatsu should be placed before December 28 because to place the kadomatsu on December 29 means niju-ku (meaning double pain with the identical pronunciation as the number 29) or ku-matsu (waiting for pain) as the last (matsu) day ending 9 (ku) and also because to place it on December 30 or 31 is called the &apos;ichiya-kazari&apos; (one-night display) or the &apos;ichinichi-kazari&apos; (one-day display), meaning to treat the gods lightly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that the kadomatsu should be placed before December 28 because to place the kadomatsu on December 29 means niju-ku (meaning double pain with the identical pronunciation as the number 29) or ku-matsu (waiting for pain) as the last (matsu) day ending 9 (ku) and also because to place it on December 30 or 31 is called &apos;ichiya-kazari&apos; (one-night display) or &apos;ichinichi-kazari&apos; (one-day display), meaning to treat the gods lightly.</e>
<cmt>「the」削除x2</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that the kadomatsu should be placed before December 28 because to place the kadomatsu on December 29 means niju-ku (meaning double pain with the identical pronunciation as the number 29) or ku-matsu (waiting for pain) as the last (matsu) day ending 9 (ku) and also because to place it on December 30 or 31 is called &apos;ichiya-kazari&apos; (one-night display) or &apos;ichinichi-kazari&apos; (one-day display), meaning to treat the gods lightly.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="24">
<j>飾る期間は、1月6日の夕方に片付けて、翌1月7日の「七日正月」を併せて7日までを「松の内」と呼ぶことが多いが、地域により1月15日の小正月まで飾るなど、さまざまである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In many regions, the display of the kadomatsu is cleared in the evening of January 6 and the display period until January 7 of the next day named the &apos;Nanuka-shogatsu&apos; (celebration of the seventh day of the New Year) is called the &apos;Matsu no Uchi;&apos; the display period varies in regions, however, as some regions display the kadomatsu until the Little New Year of January 15.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In many regions the display of the kadomatsu ends on the evening of January 6 and a display period until January 7 to match with the &apos;Nanuka-shogatsu&apos; (celebration of the seventh day of the New Year) is called the &apos;Matsu no Uchi&apos;; the display period varies from region to region, however, as some regions display the kadomatsu until the Little New Year of January 15.</e>
<cmt>「is cleared in」→「ends on」, 「the」→「a」,「of the next day named」→「to match with」, 「;&apos;」→「&apos;;」,「in regions」→「from region to region」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In many regions the display of the kadomatsu ends on the evening of January 6 and a display period until January 7 to match with the &apos;Nanuka-shogatsu&apos; (celebration of the seventh day of the New Year) is called the &apos;Matsu no Uchi;&apos; but the display period varies from region to region, as some regions display the kadomatsu until the Little New Year of January 15.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="25">
<j>入手</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">How to obtain</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">How to obtain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">How to Obtain</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>生花店やホームセンター、造園業や工務店などで作られ、設置・撤去まで一括でおこなうサービスもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Flower shops, hardware stores, gardening companies and builders create the kadomatsu, and some of them even offer a full service of setting and removing it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Flower shops, hardware stores, gardening companies and builders create the kadomatsu, and some of them even offer a full service of setting and removing it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Flower shops, hardware stores, gardening companies and builders create the kadomatsu, and some of them even offer a full service of setting and removing it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="27">
<j>これらのサービスでは、1対あたり1万～5万円が相場であることが多い（本式になるほどさらに値が張る）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The average cost of receiving these services per a pair of the kadomatsu ranges from ten to fifty thousand yen (the more formal the kadomatsu is, the more expensive it will be).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The average cost of receiving these services per pair of kadomatsu ranges from ten to fifty thousand yen (the more formal the kadomatsu is, the more expensive it will be).</e>
<cmt>「a pair of the」→「pair of」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The average cost of receiving these services per pair of kadomatsu ranges from ten to fifty thousand yen (the more formal the kadomatsu is, the more expensive it will be).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="28">
<j>ちなみに、生花を利用するので、翌年に使い回しはできない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Incidentally, the kadomatsu can not be reused in the following year since it uses fresh flowers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Incidentally, the kadomatsu can not be reused the following year since it requires fresh flowers.</e>
<cmt>「in」削除, 「uses」→「requires」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Incidentally, the kadomatsu can not be reused the following year since it requires fresh flowers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="29">
<j>現況</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Current state</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Current state</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Current State</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>自然破壊や、設置期間の終了後にゴミになるなど環境問題などの関係や、藁など材料の入手難、集合住宅の発達など社会環境の変化などからか、画像の様な本格的な門松が設置されることは少なくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Less people place full-scale kadomatsu such as those in the pictures probably due to the destruction of nature, the environmental issues such as waste of the kadomatsu after the display period, the difficulty in obtaining straws, and/or the change in the social environment such as the development of apartment buildings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fewer people put up full-scale kadomatsu such as those seen in pictures probably due to a combination of concerns regarding the destruction of nature, environmental issues such as waste of the kadomatsu after the display period, the difficulty in obtaining straws, and the change in the social environment such as in the development of apartment buildings.</e>
<cmt>「Less」→「Fewer」, 「place」→「put up」,「in the」→「seen in」,「a combination of concerns regarding」挿入, 「the」削除, 「in」挿入</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fewer people put up full-scale kadomatsu such as those seen in pictures probably due to a combination of concerns regarding the destruction of nature, environmental issues such as the used kadomatsu after the display period, the difficulty in obtaining straws and other materials, and the change in the social environment such as in the development of apartment buildings.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="31">
<j>また、一般家庭用に小さな寄せ植え風の門松などが年末に店頭に並ぶようになったため、このタイプの門松を置く場合がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As small kadomatsu of group planting style for the average family hit the store shelves at the end of the year, some people place this type of kadomatsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As small kadomatsu of group planting style aimed at the average family hit the store shelves at the end of the year, some people put up this type of kadomatsu.</e>
<cmt>「for」→「aimed at」, 「place」→「put up」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As small kadomatsu of group planting style aimed at the average families hit the store shelves at the end of the year, some people put up this type of kadomatsu.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>さらに省略版として、枝振りのいい若松に、紅白や金銀の水引を蝶結びにし、門柱などに付ける方法もあり、手軽なことから多く使われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For a simplified version of kadomatsu, a well-formed young pine, around which a bow of the mizuhiki (decorative Japanese cord made from twisted paper) in red and white or in gold and silver is tied, is attached on places such as gateposts, becoming popular for its ease of use.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For a simplified version of kadomatsu, a well-formed young pine, around which a bow of the mizuhiki (decorative Japanese cord made from twisted paper) in red and white or in gold and silver is tied, is attached on places such as gateposts, and has become popular for its ease of use.</e>
<cmt>「becoming」→「and has become」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For a simplified version of kadomatsu, a well-formed young pine, around which a bow of the decorative Japanese cord made from twisted paper in red and white or in gold and silver is tied, is attached to places such as gateposts, and has become popular for its ease of use.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="33">
<j>商店でも、現状では1月2日に初売りを行う場合が多いためか、本格的な門松が置かれるのは大型百貨店やパチンコなど一部の業種か、正月は無人に近くなる都心のオフィスビルなどに限られることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the commercial district, full scale kadomatsu are usually placed only by certain business such as large-scaled department stores or pachinko (Japanese pinball) parlors probably because many store open on January 2 for the New Year sales; additionally, they are also often placed in front of office buildings that are almost deserted during the New Year holidays.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the commercial sector, full scale kadomatsu are usually put up only by certain business such as large-scaled department stores or pachinko (Japanese pinball) parlors probably because many stores open on January 2 for the New Year sales; additionally, they are also often placed in front of office buildings that are almost deserted during the New Year holidays.</e>
<cmt>「district」→「sector」, 「placed」→「put up」,「store」→「stores」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the commercial sector, full-scale kadomatsu are usually put up only by certain businesses such as large-scaled department stores or pachinko (Japanese pinball) parlors probably because many stores open on January 2 for the New Year sales; additionally, they are also often placed in front of office buildings that are almost deserted during the New Year holidays.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>スーパーマーケットなど多くの商店では「賀正」「謹賀新年」といった語と、新年のあいさつ文、門松や鶴、亀、日の出などの絵を印刷したポスターを張って済まされることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many stores such as grocery stores only display posters which include the words &apos;Gasho&apos; (Happy New Year!) or &apos;Kinga-shinnen&apos; (I wish you a happy New Year), New Year&apos;s greetings, and pictures such as a kadomatsu, a crane, a tortoise and a sunrise.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many stores such as grocery stores only display posters with New Year&apos;s greetings which include the words &apos;Gasho&apos; (Happy New Year!) or &apos;Kinga-shinnen&apos; (I wish you a happy New Year) and pictures such as a kadomatsu, a crane, a tortoise or a sunrise.</e>
<cmt>「with」挿入,「New Year&apos;s greetings」箇所異動,「and」→「or」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A lot of stores such as grocery stores only display posters with New Year&apos;s greetings which include the words &apos;Gasho&apos; (Happy New Year!) or &apos;Kinga-shinnen&apos; (I wish you a happy New Year) and pictures such as a kadomatsu, a crane, a tortoise, a sunrise, or the like.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>元日も営業する場合、ポスターの貼付も省略されることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some stores do not even display those posters if they are open on New Year&apos;s Day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some stores do not even display these posters if they are open on New Year&apos;s Day.</e>
<cmt>「those」→「these」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some of the stores which open on New Year&apos;s Day do not even display these posters.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="36">
<j>和歌</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Waka (traditional Japanese poetry)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Waka (traditional Japanese poetry)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Waka (traditional Japanese poetry)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>「門松は冥途の旅の一里塚めでたくもありめでたくもなし」の歌は一休宗純の作とされているが、一休と親交のあった遊女、地獄太夫が一休のために詠んだものとの説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The waka &apos;the kadomatsu is a milestone for the trip to the world of the dead, so it may or may not be happy&apos; is said to have been written by Ikkyu Sojun, but some people maintain that his close yujo (courtesan) Jigoku Dayu wrote it for him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The waka &apos;the kadomatsu is a milestone for the trip to the world of the dead, so it may or may not be happy&apos; is said to have been written by Ikkyu Sojun, but some people maintain that his close yujo (courtesan) Jigoku Dayu wrote it for him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The waka &apos;the kadomatsu is a milestone for the trip to the world of the dead, so it may or may not be happy&apos; is said to have been written by Ikkyu Sojun, but some people maintain that his close courtesan Jigoku Dayu wrote it for him.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="38">
<j>起源説等</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Theory on the origin and others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Theories of the origin of kadomatsu.</e>
<cmt>再構成しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Theories of the Origin of Kadomatsu</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="39">
<j>新年に松を家に持ち帰る習慣は平安時代に始まり、室町時代に現在のように玄関の飾りとする様式が決まったという説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to a theory, the custom of bringing pine home for the new year started during the Heian period and the present-day style of displaying the kadomatsu at the entrance was adopted during the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to a theory, the custom of bringing pine home for the new year started during the Heian Period and the present-day style of displaying the kadomatsu at the entrance was adopted during the Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt>「period」→「Period」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to a theory, the custom of bringing pine home in the new year days started during the Heian period and the present-day style of displaying the kadomatsu at the entrance was adopted during the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Ligar(id:12623), Starbacks(id:1018), ととりん(id:31982), Ceridwen(id:36889), Nnh(id:474), 0null0(id:582), T.Yama(id:40416), Yiuchan(id:28580), Sh(id:2707), Eveningmist(id:28648), 桜井悠士(id:72420), らりた(id:1327), A.s(id:48856), Nnn(id:26535), ABnormal(id:254617), Ntoshi(id:97089), 水平芳(id:203583), Hamasaki gion higashi(id:144985), Louperibot(id:128971), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>