<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>織部流</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oribe School (Tea Ceremony)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oribe School (Tea Ceremony)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oribe School (Tea Ceremony)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>織部流（おりべりゅう）は茶道流派の一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Oribe School is one of the schools of the tea ceremony.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Oribe School is one of the schools of the tea ceremony.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Oribe School is one of the schools of the tea ceremony.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>古田重然の創始による流儀で、侘茶法と式正茶法の両伝があると織部流十七世を称した浅野牧仙が提唱した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was founded by Shigenari Furuta, and the 17th Master of the Oribe School, Bokusen Asano, proposed that there are two traditions, Wabi-cha and Shikisei Oribe.</e>
<cmt>浅野牧仙 Bokusen Asano</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was founded by Shigenari Furuta, and the seventeenth Master of the Oribe School, Bokusen Asano, proposed that there were two traditions, Wabi-cha and Shikisei Oribe.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was founded by Shigenari FURUTA, and the seventeenth Master of the Oribe School, Bokusen ASANO, proposed that there were two traditions, Wabi-cha and Shikisei Oribe.</e>
<cmt>Furuta→FURUTAAsano→ASANO</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>式正茶法は秋元瑞阿弥が体系化し、式正織部流（しきせい おりべりゅう）と称して千葉県市川市国府台の織部桔梗会が教授にあたっており、千葉県指定文化財一覧に指定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shikisei Tea Ceremony was systemized by Zuiami Akimoto and called Shikisei Oribe School, and the Oribe Kikyokai Association in Konodai, Ichikawa City, Chiba Prefecture provides instruction, and is designated an Intangible Cultural Asset by Chiba Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>秋元瑞阿弥 Zuiami Akimoto, 織部桔梗会 Oribe Kikyokai Association</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Shikisei tea ceremony was systemized by Zuiami Akimoto and referred to as the Shikisei Oribe School, and the Oribe Kikyokai Association in Konodai, Ichikawa City, Chiba Prefecture provides instruction and is designated as an Intangible Cultural Asset by Chiba Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Shikisei tea ceremony was systemized by Zuiami AKIMOTO and referred to as the Shikisei Oribe School, and the Oribe Kikyokai Association in Konodai, Ichikawa City, Chiba Prefecture provides instruction and is designated as an Intangible Cultural Asset by Chiba Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>Akimoto→AKIMOTO</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>特徴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Characteristics</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Characteristics</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Characteristics</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>織部の茶は「織部百ヶ条」にみられるように、利休の茶を遵守したものだったが、現代では大きく二つにわかれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As can be seen in the &apos;Oribe Hyakkajo&apos; (One Hundred Rules for Oribe Tea Ceremony), the Oribe school of tea ceremony strictly observed the Rikyu way of tea ceremony, however now there are two branches.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As can be seen in the &apos;Oribe Hyakkajo&apos; (A Hundred Rules for Oribe Tea Ceremony), the Oribe school of tea ceremony strictly observed the Rikyu way of tea ceremony, but now there are two branches.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As can be seen in the &apos;Oribe Hyakkajo&apos; (A Hundred Rules for Oribe Tea Ceremony), the Oribe school of tea ceremony strictly observed the Rikyu way of tea ceremony, but now there are two branches.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>侘茶法は千利休ゆずりの草庵の茶といい、これに対して式正茶法は書院および広間の茶で、室町以来の書院茶に武家の礼儀作法と侘茶の精神とを取り入れた秋元瑞阿弥独自の流儀である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Wabi-cha school is said to be that of a simple thatched cottage (soan)of Sen Rikyu Yuzuri, while in comparison Shikisei school is the way of tea of a study (&apos;Shoincha&apos;) or grand hall, and this is the original way of Zuiam Akimoto who incorporated the philosophy called Reigi Sahou (civilties) of the Samurai and the spirit of Wabi-cha into the post-Muromachi period Shoincha way of tea.</e>
<cmt>千利休ゆずり Sen Rikyu Yuzuri, 草庵 thatched cottage,</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Wabi-cha school is said to be that of a simple thatched cottage (soan) of Sen Rikyu Yuzuri, while in comparison the Shikisei school is the way of tea of a study (&apos;Shoincha&apos;) or grand hall, and this is the original way of Zuiam Akimoto, who incorporated the philosophy called Reigi Sahou (civilities) of the samurai and the spirit of Wabi-cha into the Shoincha way of tea from the post-Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Wabi-cha school is said to favor a style of tea ceremony performed in a simple thatched cottage (soan) that is derived from SEN no Rikyu; the Shikisei school, on the other hand, is a style of tea ceremony performed in a study (Shoincha) or grand hall, and this is the original way developed by Zuiami AKIMOTO, who incorporated the philosophy of the samurai called Reigi Saho (civilities) and the spirit of Wabi-cha into the Shoincha way of tea ceremony from the post-Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>千利休ゆずり→is derived from SEN no Rikyu としました。&apos; &apos;削除Zuiam Akimoto→Zuiami AKIMOTOSahou→Saho</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>式正茶法の特色として、畳の上に直接道具を置くことがなく、「茶碗台」というものが考案され、居前で手を清めたり、帛紗を使い分けるなど清潔を旨としていることが挙げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The characteristics of Shikisei Way of Tea are that the tea implements are not placed directly on the tatami mat, but on a tea bowl stand and purification is emphasized by washing hands when sitting in the Imae position, and separating the used &apos;fukusa&apos; cloths.</e>
<cmt>茶碗台 a tea bowl stand, 居前 Imae position</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The characteristics of the Shikisei way of tea are that the tea implements aren&apos;t placed directly on the tatami mat but on a tea-bowl stand, and purification is emphasized by washing hands when sitting in the Imae position and separating the used &apos;fukusa&apos; cloths.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The characteristics of the Shikisei way of tea are that the tea implements aren&apos;t placed directly on the tatami mat but on a &apos;tea-bowl stand&apos;, and purification is emphasized by washing hands when sitting in the Imae position and separating the used fukusa cloths.</e>
<cmt>原文に「」がないので&apos; &apos;を削除原文の「」に合わせ&apos; &apos;を補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>太閤点、六天目点など、面白い点前があることが特徴である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Shikisei Way of Tea is characterized by interesting ways of making tea including the &apos;taikoten&apos; and &apos;roku-tenmoku-tate&apos;.</e>
<cmt>太閤点 taikoten, 六天目点 &apos;roku-tenmoku-tate&apos;</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Shikisei way of tea is characterized by interesting ways of making tea, including the &apos;taikoten&apos; and &apos;roku-tenmoku-tate.&apos;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Shikisei way of tea is characterized by interesting ways of making tea, including the &apos;taikoten&apos; and &apos;roku-tenmoku-tate.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>流祖の古田織部は美濃の古田重定の子で、字は左介、諱を重然といい、伯父重安の養子となり、中川清秀の妹を娶った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The founder Furuta Oribe was the son of Shigesada Furuta of Mino (his usual name was Sasuke and his posthumous name was Shigenari), and he was adopted by his uncle Shigeyasu, and married the sister of Kiyohide Nakagawa.</e>
<cmt>字 usual name, 諱 posthumous name</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The founder, Furuta Oribe, was the son of Shigesada Furuta of Mino (his usual name was Sasuke and his posthumous name was Shigenari), but he was adopted by his uncle Shigeyasu and married the sister of Kiyohide Nakagawa.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The founder, Oribe FURUTA, was the son of Shigesada FURUTA of Mino (his usual name was Sasuke and his posthumous name was Shigenari), but he was adopted by his uncle Shigeyasu and married the sister of Kiyohide NAKAGAWA.</e>
<cmt>Furuta Oribe→Oribe FURUTAFuruta→FURUTANakagawa→NAKAGAWA</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>武将として織田信長・豊臣秀吉に仕え、茶人としては千利休に学び利休七哲の一人に数えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a shogun he served Nobunaga Oda and Hideyoshi Toyotomi, and as a master of the tea ceremony he studied under Sen Rikyu and numbered among one of the &apos;Rikyu Shichitetsu&apos; (seven sages of Rikyu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a shogun he served Nobunaga Oda and Hideyoshi Toyotomi, and as a master of the tea ceremony he studied under Sen Rikyu and numbered among the &apos;Rikyu Shichitetsu&apos; (seven sages of Rikyu).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a shogun he served Nobunaga ODA and Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, and as a master of the tea ceremony he studied under SEN no Rikyu and numbered among the Rikyu Shichitetsu (seven sages of Rikyu).</e>
<cmt>Oda→ODAToyotomi→TOYOTOMISen Rikyu→SEN no Rikyu原文に「」がないので&apos; &apos;を削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>利休切腹の後に、徳川2代将軍徳川秀忠の茶湯の師範を勤め、小堀政一をはじめとする諸大名にも茶の湯を伝授した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Rikyu&apos;s death by ritual suicide, Furuta Oribe was appointed master of the tea ceremony for Hidetada Tokugawa, the second Tokugawa shogun, and he gave instruction to various Daimyo (feudal lords) including Masakazu Kobori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Rikyu&apos;s death by ritual suicide, Furuta Oribe was appointed master of the tea ceremony for the second Tokugawa shogun, Hidetada Tokugawa, and instructed various daimyo (feudal lords), including Masakazu Kobori.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Rikyu&apos;s death by ritual suicide, Oribe FURUTA was appointed master of the tea ceremony for the second Tokugawa shogun, Hidetada TOKUGAWA, and instructed various daimyo (feudal lords), including Masakazu KOBORI.</e>
<cmt>Furuta Oribe→Oribe FURUTATokugawa→TOKUGAWAKobori→KOBORI</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>作意趣向を凝らしたことで知られ、造園、建築、諸道具から料理に至るまで「織部好み」と呼ばれるものが伝わっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was known for his innovative approach and many things from gardens, architecture and various tools to cooking have been labeled &apos;Oribe Konomi&apos; (Oribe taste).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was known for his innovative approach, and many things--from gardens, architecture and various tools to cooking--have been labeled &apos;Oribe Konomi&apos; (Oribe taste).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was known for his innovative approach, and many things--from gardens, architecture and various tools to cooking--have been labeled &apos;Oribe Konomi&apos; (Oribe taste).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>元和 (日本)元年（1615年）、大坂夏の陣で茶堂木村宗喜が豊臣方に内通したため、嫡男とともに自刃させられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1615, at the Osaka Summer War (Osaka Natsu-no-jin) between forces of Tokugawa and Toyotomi, because tea master Muneyoshi Kimura collaborated with Toyotomi&apos;s side, Furuta was implicated in a conspiracy against Tokugawa and forced to commit suicide with his eldest son.</e>
<cmt>茶堂 chado はここでは　茶人tea masterのことと解釈しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1615, at the Osaka Summer War (Osaka Natsu-no-jin) between the forces of Tokugawa and Toyotomi, because the tea master Muneyoshi Kimura collaborated at Toyotomi&apos;s side, Furuta was implicated in a conspiracy against Tokugawa and forced to commit suicide along with his eldest son.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1615, at the Osaka Natsu no Jin (Summer Siege of Osaka) between the forces of Tokugawa and Toyotomi, because the tea master Muneyoshi KIMURA collaborated at Toyotomi&apos;s side, Furuta was implicated in a conspiracy against Tokugawa and forced to commit suicide along with his eldest son.</e>
<cmt>Osaka Summer War (Osaka Natsu-no-jin)→Osaka Natsu no Jin (Summer Siege of Osaka)Kimura→KIMURA</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>遺骸は大徳寺三玄院に葬られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His remains were interred in the Sangenin in Daitokuji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His remains were interred in the Sangenin, in Daitokuji Temple.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His remains were interred in the Sangenin, in Daitoku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>-補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="16">
<j>さて織部の養父重安には後に実子重続が生まれたので、織部は娘を妻の実家中川家の養女として義弟である重続に嫁がせていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oribe&apos;s adopted father, Shigeyasu, subsequently had his own son Shigetsugu, so Oribe had his daughter adopted into his wife&apos;s family, the Nakagawa family, and had her marry his adoptive brother Shigetsugu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oribe&apos;s adopted father, Shigeyasu, subsequently had his own son, Shigetsugu, so Oribe had his daughter adopted into his wife&apos;s Nakagawa family and had her marry his adoptive brother, Shigetsugu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oribe&apos;s adopted father, Shigeyasu, subsequently had his own son, Shigetsugu, so Oribe had his daughter adopted into his wife&apos;s Nakagawa family and had her marry his adoptive brother, Shigetsugu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>重続の一族は織部の罪が及ぶべき所を特に赦されて、豊後岡藩中川家の家老として存続した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigetsugu&apos;s family was absolved of Oribe&apos;s crime and continued as chief retainer to the Nakagawa household in the Oka Clan in Bungo Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigetsugu&apos;s family was absolved of Oribe&apos;s crime and continued as chief retainer to the Nakagawa household in the Oka Clan, in Bungo Province.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigetsugu&apos;s family was absolved of Oribe&apos;s crime and continued as chief retainer to the Nakagawa household in the Oka Clan, in Bungo Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>しかし、織部の茶法は特に伝わらなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However Oribe&apos;s way of tea was not passed on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Oribe&apos;s way of tea wasn&apos;t passed on.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Oribe&apos;s way of tea wasn&apos;t passed on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>14世淵黙（広計）は福岡藩に伝わっていた織部流を習い、自家の茶法としたため、古田家に伝えられることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The 14th Enari (Hiroe) learnt Oribe style tea ceremony that had been passed on to the Fukuoka Clan, and adopted it as his own style of tea ceremony, so it was passed on to the Furuta household.</e>
<cmt>淵黙 Enari (Hiroe)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fourteenth Enari (Hiroe) learned the Oribe style of tea ceremony that had been passed on to the Fukuoka clan, and adopted it as his own style of tea ceremony, so it was passed on to the Furuta household.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fourteenth Enari (Hiroe) learned the Oribe style of tea ceremony that had been passed on to the Fukuoka clan, and adopted it as his own style of tea ceremony, so it was passed on to the Furuta household.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>そして14世古田宗関（重名）は維新に際して豊後から東京へ移り、明治31年（1898年）に茶道温知会を起こして弟子に織部流を教授した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Subsequently, the 14th Furuta Sokan (Shigena) moved from Bungo Province to Tokyo during the Meiji Restoration and in 1898 he started up a tea ceremony association and taught his students the Oribe style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently, the fourteenth Furuta Sokan (Shigena) moved from Bungo Province to Tokyo during the Meiji Restoration, and in 1898 he started a tea-ceremony association and taught his students the Oribe style.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently, the fourteenth Sokan FURUTA (Shigena) moved from Bungo Province to Tokyo during the Meiji Restoration, and in 1898 he started a tea-ceremony association and taught his students the Oribe style.</e>
<cmt>Furuta Sokan→Sokan FURUTA</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>宗関の高弟に岡崎淵冲と原宗改（鉄石）がいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sokan&apos;s best students included Enchu Okazaki and Sokai Hara (Tesseki).</e>
<cmt>原宗改（鉄石）Sokai Hara(Tesseki)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sokan&apos;s best students included Enchu Okazaki and Sokai Hara (Tesseki).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sokan&apos;s best students included Enchu OKAZAKI and Sokai HARA (Tesseki).</e>
<cmt>Okazaki→OKAZAKIHara→HARA</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>宗改は正式織部本流を立ち上げ、秋元瑞阿弥にそれを伝授した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sokai started up a formal Oribe style and taught this to Zuiami Akimoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sokai started up a formal Oribe style and taught it to Zuiami Akimoto.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sokai started up a formal Oribe style and taught it to Zuiami AKIMOTO.</e>
<cmt>Akimoto→AKIMOTO</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>瑞阿弥は16世を称し、千葉県指定無形文化財保持者に認定された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zuiami was named the 16th successor and recognized as a Preserver of Intangible Cultural Properties by Chiba Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zuiami was named the sixteenth successor and was recognized by Chiba Prefecture as a Preserver of Intangible Cultural Properties.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zuiami was named the sixteenth successor and was recognized by Chiba Prefecture as a Preserver of Intangible Cultural Properties.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>瑞阿弥は京都興聖寺の住職浅野牧仙に式正茶法を伝え、以後、同寺の住職が世襲することになったため、茶法が伝わりづらくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zuiami taught the Shikisei tea ceremony to Bokusen Asano, Chief Priest of Koshoji Temple, Kyoto, and subsequently the Chief Priests of this temple followed a hereditary succession so the tea ceremony was difficult to pass on.</e>
<cmt>住職が世襲すること種hereditary succession</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zuiami taught the Shikisei tea ceremony to Bokusen Asano, the chief priest of Koshoji Temple in Kyoto, and subsequently the chief priests of this temple followed a hereditary succession; as a result, the tea ceremony was difficult to pass on.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zuiami taught the Shikisei tea ceremony to Bokusen ASANO, the chief priest of Kosho-ji Temple in Kyoto, and subsequently the chief priests of this temple followed a hereditary succession; as a result, the tea ceremony was difficult to pass on.</e>
<cmt>Asano→ASANO-補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="25">
<j>一方、国府台の織部桔梗会では、瑞阿弥没後も引き続き式正茶法を教授している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, at the Kikyokai Association in Konodai, the Shikisei tea ceremony continued to be taught after Zuiami&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, at the Kikyokai Association in Konodai, the Shikisei tea ceremony continued to be taught after Zuiami&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, at the Kikyokai Association in Konodai, the Shikisei tea ceremony continued to be taught after Zuiami&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>ほかに織部流を称す流派に扶桑派があり、明治時代に日種譲山とともに京都興聖寺を復興させた表千家の見中斎米山により創始されたもので、やはり式正茶法を伝えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Elsewhere there are schools of tea ceremony using the name Oribe including the Fusoha school which was established by Kenchusaibeisan of Omotosenke who refurbished Koshoji Temple in Kyoto together with Nishugosan in the Meiji Era, and it is passing on the Shikisei way of tea.</e>
<cmt>日譲山 Nishugosan, 見中斎米山Kenchusaibeisan</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Elsewhere are schools of tea ceremony using the Oribe name, including the Fusoha school, which was established by Kenchusaibeisan of Omotosenke, who refurbished Koshoji Temple in Kyoto together with Nishugosan in the Meiji Era, and which continues in the Shikisei way of tea.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Elsewhere are schools of tea ceremony using the Oribe name, including the Fusoha school, which was established by Kenchusai Beisan of Omotesenke (the house of Omotesen), who refurbished Kosho-ji Temple in Kyoto together with Nishugosan in the Meiji Era, and which continues in the Shikisei way of tea.</e>
<cmt>見中斎米山→Kenchusai Beisan表千家→Omotesenke (the house of Omotesen)[用語集]-補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>北九州にも織部流（石橋家）が伝わっており、貴重なものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In North Kyushu the Oribe style is being passed on (by the Ishibashi family) and is a valuable tradition.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In north Kyushu, the Oribe style is being passed on (by the Ishibashi family) and is a valuable tradition.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In north Kyushu, the Oribe style is being passed on (by the Ishibashi family) and is a valuable tradition.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="28">
<j>歴代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Atysn(id:53369), 超プロ住民(id:279825), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), Khhy(id:13490), Mzaki(id:61977), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>