<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>蘇民将来</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Somin Shorai (a Japanese old story and the folk religion originated in the story)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Somin Shorai (a Japanese old story about a folk religion)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Somin Shorai (a Japanese old story about a folk religion)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>蘇民将来（そみんしょうらい　蘇民將來）とは近畿地方を中心に日本各地に伝わる説話、およびそれを起源とする民間信仰である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Somin shorai refers to a folk tale that have been legendarily told throughout Japan mainly including Kinki region, and also refers to folk beliefs which originated in the folk tale.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Somin shorai refers to a folk tale that has been told as a legend in Japan in mainly the Kinki region, referring to folk beliefs that originated in the folk tale.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Somin shorai refers to a folk tale that has been told as a legend in Japan in mainly the Kinki region, referring to folk beliefs that originated in the folk tale.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>古くは『釈日本紀』（卜部兼方　鎌倉時代中期）に引用された『備後国風土記』逸文の素盞嗚神社 (福山市) に見える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Looking back the past, Somin Shorai is found in Susano-jinja Shrine (Fukuyama city) in itsubun (a composition previously existed but doesn&apos;t exist now) of &quot;Bingo-koku Fudoki&quot; (regional gazetteers of Bingo Province) quoted in &quot;Shaku Nihongi&quot;; an annotated text of the Nihon Shoki, (Kanekata URABE, in the middle of the Kamakura period).</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Looking at the past, Somin Shorai was founded in Susano-jinja Shrine (Fukuyama city) in itsubun (a composition previously existed but doesn&apos;t exist now) of &quot;Bingo-koku Fudoki&quot; (regional gazetteers of Bingo Province) quoted in &quot;Shaku Nihongi;&quot; an annotated text of the Nihon Shoki, (Kanekata URABE, during the middle of the Kamakura period).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Looking at the past, Somin Shorai was founded in Susano-jinja Shrine (Fukuyama city) in itsubun (a composition previously existed but doesn&apos;t exist now) of &quot;Bingo-koku Fudoki&quot; (regional gazetteers of Bingo Province) quoted in &quot;Shaku Nihongi;&quot; an annotated text of the Nihon Shoki, (Kanekata URABE, during the middle of the Kamakura period).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>祭祀起源譚としておおむね似た形で広く伝わっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It also has been widely spread as Saishi kigen tan (story of ritual origin) almost in a similar way.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has also been widely spread as Saishi kigen tan (story of ritual origin) almost in a similar way.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has also been widely spread as Saishi kigen tan (story of ritual origin) almost in a similar way.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>すなわち、旅の途中で宿を乞うた武塔神（むとうしん）を裕福な弟の将来（『備後国風土記』では「或本作巨旦將來也」とあり、巨旦将来　こたんしょうらいとされる）は断り、貧しい兄・蘇民将来は粗末ながらもてなした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the tale, Muto shin (deity with clear roots in the Korean peninsula) had asked his wealthy younger brother, Shorai, for the place to sleep in during his journey and had been refused; Muto shin asked his poor brother, Somin shorai as well, and Sonin Shorai treated him in a poor way.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the tale, Muto shin (deity with clear roots in the Korean peninsula) had asked his wealthy younger brother, Shorai, for the place to sleep during his journey and had been refused; Muto shin asked his poor brother, Somin shorai as well, and Sonin Shorai treated him in a poor way.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the tale, Muto shin (deity with clear roots in the Korean peninsula) had asked his wealthy younger brother, Shorai, for the place to sleep during his journey and had been refused; Muto shin asked his poor brother, Somin shorai as well, and Somin Shorai treated him even in a poor way.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>後に再訪した武塔神は、弟将来の妻となっていた蘇民の娘には茅の輪を付けさせ、それを目印として娘を除く弟将来の一族を滅ぼした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Muto shin who revisited his younger brother, Shorai, put a ring of Chigaya (Japanese blood grass) as a mark on Somin&apos;s daughter who became a wife of his younger brother, Shorai, and destroyed Shorai&apos;s family members other than her.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Muto shin who revisited his younger brother, Shorai, put a ring of Chigaya (Japanese blood grass) as a mark on Somin&apos;s daughter who became the wife of his younger brother, Shorai, and destroyed Shorai&apos;s family members except for her.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Muto shin who revisited his younger brother, Shorai, put a ring of Chigaya (Japanese blood grass) as a mark on Somin&apos;s daughter who became the wife of his younger brother, Shorai, and destroyed Shorai&apos;s family members except for her.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>武塔神は速須佐雄能神（スサノオ）を名乗り、以後、茅の輪を付けていれば疫病を避けることができると教えたとする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Muto shin called himself as Susano no Mikoto (Susano), and taught that putting a ring of Chigaya (Japanese blood grass) enables to avoid diseases.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Muto shin called himself Susano no Mikoto (Susano), and taught that putting a ring of Chigaya (Japanese blood grass) enables us to avoid diseases.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Muto shin called himself Susano no Mikoto (Susano), and taught that putting a ring of Chigaya (Japanese blood grass) enables us to avoid diseases.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>この逸話を基に岩手県内を始め各地に伝わる蘇民祭を始め、京都の八坂神社や伊勢・志摩地方の年中行事で厄除け祈願として、茅の輪潜りや蘇民将来護符の頒布、注連飾りなどの祭祀が盛んに行われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Based on this episode, rituals such as Chinowa kuguri; going through a ring of Chigaya, distribution of talisman of Somin shorai, and shimekazari (sacred Shinto rope with festoons), are actively performed as a prayer for protection from evil in Somin-sai Festival that takes place in various places including within Iwate prefecture in Yasaka-jinja Shrine in Kyoto and in Ise and shima regions as an annual event.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based on this episode, rituals such as Chinowa kuguri; going through a ring of Chigaya, distribution of talisman of Somin shorai, and shimekazari (sacred Shinto rope with festoons), are actively performed as a prayer for protection from evil in Somin-sai Festival that takes place in various places including within Iwate prefecture in the Yasaka-jinja Shrine in Kyoto and in Ise and Shima regions as an annual event.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based on this episode, rituals such as Chinowa kuguri; going through a ring of Chigaya, distribution of talisman of Somin shorai, and shimekazari (sacred Shinto rope with festoons), are actively performed as a prayer for protection from evil in Somin-sai Festival that takes place in various places including within Iwate prefecture in the Yasaka-jinja Shrine in Kyoto and in Ise and Shima regions as an annual event.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Izayohi(id:13095), 蒼海牧菜(id:78923), Ks8823(id:130146), Greenland4(id:114494), KAMUI(id:9330), 弥(id:61590), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>