<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>江戸千家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Edosenke</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Edosenke</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Edosenke</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>江戸千家 （えどせんけ）は、川上不白に始まる茶道の流派。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Edosenke is a school of tea ceremony that was originated by Fuhaku Kawakami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Edosenke is a school of tea ceremony that was originated by Fuhaku Kawakami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Edosenke is a school of tea ceremony that was originated by Fuhaku KAWAKAMI.</e>
<cmt>名字を大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>不白流とも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also called Fuhaku school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called the Fuhaku school.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called the Fuhaku school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>家元は台東区池之端にあり、同門組織として不白会、関連機関の江戸千家茶の湯研究所がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The headquarters are in Ikenohata, Taito Ward, and fellow organizations include the Fuhaku Association, and a related institution is the Edosenke Chanoyu (tea ceremony) Research Association.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The headquarters are in Ikenohata, Taito Ward, and fellow organizations include the Fuhaku Association, but a related institution is the Edosenke Chanoyu (tea ceremony) Research Association.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The headquarters are in Ikenohata, Taito Ward; its fellow organization is the Fuhaku Association, and a related institution is the Edosenke Chanoyu (tea ceremony) Research Association.</e>
<cmt>一部変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>また川上不白を祖と仰ぐ流派として、文京区弥生 (文京区)に家元がある江戸千家宗家蓮華庵や杉並区高円寺に家元がある表千家不白流などいくつかの分派がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are also several branches of the Edosenke school which count Fuhaku Kawakami as their founder, including Edosenke Soke Renkean which is headquartered in Yayoi, Bunkyo Ward (Bunkyo Ward) and the Omotesenke Fuhaku school which is headquartered in Koenji, Suginami Ward.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are also several branches of the Edosenke school that count Fuhaku Kawakami as their founder, including Edosenke Soke Renkean, which is headquartered in Yayoi, Bunkyo Ward (Bunkyo Ward), and the Omotesenke Fuhaku school, which is headquartered in Koenji, Suginami Ward.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are also several branches of the Edosenke school that count Fuhaku KAWAKAMI as their founder, including Edosenke Soke Renge-an, which is headquartered in Yayoi (Bunkyo Ward), Bunkyo Ward, and the Omotesenke Fuhaku school, which is headquartered in Koenji, Suginami Ward.</e>
<cmt>名字を大文字にしました。蓮華庵 →Renge-anとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>川上不白は元は紀州紀伊新宮藩水野家に仕える藩士の次男で、当主水野忠昭の勧めにより表千家7代如心斎の門に入り茶道で身を立てることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fuhaku Kawakami was the second son of a retainer of the Daimyo who served the Mizuno family in the Shingu Clan of Kii Province (Kishu) and under the recommendation of the head of the family at the time, Tadaaki Mizuno, he was able to enter the school of the 7th master of Omotesenke, Joshinsai, and establish himself in chado (the way of tea).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fuhaku Kawakami was the second son of a retainer of the daimyo who served the Mizuno family in the Shingu clan of Kii Province (Kishu) and under the recommendation of Tadaaki Mizuno, then the head of the family, he was able to enter the school of Joshinsai, the seventh master of Omotesenke, and establish himself in chado (the way of tea).</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fuhaku KAWAKAMI was the second son of a retainer of the daimyo who served the Mizuno family in the Shingu clan of Kii Province (Kishu); under the recommendation of Tadaaki Mizuno, then the head of the family, he was able to enter the school of Joshinsai, the seventh master of Omotesenke, and establish himself in chado (the way of tea).</e>
<cmt>名字を大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>折しも京都の三千家では如心斎を中心に一大改革期を迎えており、それを担う高弟の一人として七事式の制定などで活躍することになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, the Sansenke (three schools associated with Sen Rikyu) in Kyoto entered a significant period of reform with Joshinsai at the forefront, and as one of the leading disciples to take on the reformation, Fuhaku was active in the establishment of the Shichijishiki (seven training exercises).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, the Sansenke (three schools associated with Sen Rikyu) in Kyoto entered a significant period of reform with Joshinsai at the forefront, and as one of the leading disciples in taking on the reformation, Fuhaku was active in the establishment of the Shichijishiki (seven training exercises).</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, the Sansenke (three schools associated with Sen Rikyu) in Kyoto entered a significant period of reform with Joshinsai at the forefront, and as one of the leading disciples in taking on the reformation, Fuhaku was active in the establishment of the Shichijishiki (seven training exercises).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>真台子ならびに長盆の伝授を受けた後の寛延3年（1750年）に、不白は江戸に戻ってまず神田駿河台で黙雷庵を営んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1750, after receiving instruction in the Shindaisu (tea shelf) and Nagabon (long tray), Fuhaku returned to Edo and first of all established a branch of the Omotosenke school called 黙雷庵 in Surugadai, Kanda.</e>
<cmt>黙雷庵</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1750, after receiving instruction in the Shindaisu (tea shelf) and Nagabon (long tray), Fuhaku returned to Edo and first established a branch of the Omotosenke school called 黙雷庵 in Surugadai, Kanda.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1750, after receiving instruction in the Shindaisu (tea shelf) and Nagabon (long tray), Fuhaku returned to Edo and first established a branch of the Omotosenke school called Mokurai-an in Surugadai, Kanda.</e>
<cmt>Mokurai-an を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>この折りに深川_(江東区)の豪商冬木家に千利休の遺偈が秘蔵されていることがわかり、不白の交渉により表千家に返納された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Right at that time, he found out that the last writings of Sen Rikyu were being kept by the Fuyuki family, wealthy merchants in Fukagawa (Koto Ward), and he negotiated for their return to Omotosenke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was then he learned that the last writings of Sen Rikyu were being kept by the Fuyuki family, who were wealthy merchants in Fukagawa (Koto Ward), and he negotiated for their return to Omotosenke.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was then he learned that the last writings of Sen Rikyu were being kept by the Fuyuki family, who were wealthy merchants in Fukagawa (Koto Ward), and he negotiated for their return to Omotesenke.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>翌年（1751年）に如心斎が亡くなると、上京して4年にわたって後事にあたった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the following year, 1751, upon the death of Joshinsai, Fuhaku returned to Kyoto and looked after Joshinsai&apos;s affairs for four years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the following year, 1751, upon the death of Joshinsai, Fuhaku returned to Kyoto and looked after Joshinsai&apos;s affairs for four years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the following year, 1751, upon the death of Joshinsai, Fuhaku returned to Kyoto and looked after Joshinsai&apos;s affairs for four years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>宝暦5年（1755年）再び江戸に帰ると神田明神境内に蓮華庵を営み、大名・豪商から町人や職人に至るまで幅広い層に茶道の手ほどきをしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1755, Fuhaku again returned to Edo and established the Renkean inside the Kanda Shrine, and gave instruction in the tea ceremony to a wide strata of society from Daimyo and wealthy merchants to townspeople and artisans.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1755, Fuhaku again returned to Edo and established the Renkean within the Kanda Shrine, whereupon he gave instruction in the tea ceremony to a wide strata of society, from daimyo and wealthy merchants to townspeople and artisans.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1755, Fuhaku again returned to Edo and established the Renge-an within the Kanda-Myojin Shrine, whereupon he gave instruction in the tea ceremony to a wide strata of society, from daimyo and wealthy merchants to townspeople and artisans.</e>
<cmt>神田明神→Kanda-Myojin Shrine としました。蓮華庵 →Renge-anとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>安永2年（1773年）に水野家下組屋敷に隠居したが、その後も30年以上にわたって活発に活動を続け文化 (日本)4年（1807年）に世を去った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1773 he retired to the kumi-yashiki (residence for general samurai) of the Mizuno family, however he remained active in the tea ceremony for over 30 years until his death in 1807.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1773 he retired to the kumi-yashiki (residence for general samurai) of the Mizuno family, however he remained active in the tea ceremony for more than 30 years until his death in 1807.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1773 he retired to the kumi-yashiki (residence for general samurai) of the Mizuno family, however he remained active in the tea ceremony for more than thirty years until his death in 1807.</e>
<cmt>数字をスペルアウトしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>その後代々江戸で新宮藩の茶頭や水戸徳川家の茶道師範などを務めていたが、幕末の4代蓮華庵（新柳斎）のときに新宮へ帰った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Subsequent generations served as tea masters for the Shingu clan in Edo or as tea instructors to the Tokugawa family in Mito, however, at the end of the Edo period, during the time of the 4th master of the Renkean (Shingosai), they returned to Shingu (Wakayama Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>新柳斎 Shingosai</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequent generations served as tea masters for the Shingu clan in Edo or as tea instructors to the Tokugawa family in Mito&apos; however, at the end of the Edo period, during the time of the fourth master of the Renkean (Shingosai), they returned to Shingu (Wakayama Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequent generations served as tea masters for the Shingu clan in Edo or as tea instructors to the Tokugawa family in Mito; however, at the end of the Edo period, during the time of the fourth master of the Renge-an (Shinryu-sai), they returned to Shingu (Wakayama Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>新柳斎→Shinryu-sai　としました。蓮華庵 →Renge-anとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>明治の初めに7代蓮々斎が再び東京に出て池之端に茶家を再興し、江戸千家の中興と称せられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the beginning of the Meiji Era the 7th master of the Renkean again returned to Tokyo and restored the chado in Ikenohata, and was known as the restorer of Edosenke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the beginning of the Meiji period, the seventh master of the Renkean again returned to Tokyo and restored the chado in Ikenohata, and he was known as the restorer of Edosenke.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the beginning of the Meiji period, the seventh master of the Renge-an again returned to Tokyo and restored the chado in Ikenohata, and he was known as the restorer of Edosenke.</e>
<cmt>蓮華庵 →Renge-anとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>9代名元庵は病身で、家族や社中も家元を補佐して支えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The 9th master Motoan was an invalid and his family and friends provided support to the master.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ninth master, Motoan, was an invalid, so his family and friends provided support to the master.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ninth master, Myogen-an, was an invalid, so his family and friends provided support to the master.</e>
<cmt>名元庵→Myogen-an　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>このため、名元庵は生前に家元の座を長男に譲り、名心庵宗雪が10代として家元を継承した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, Motoan passed on the role of master to his eldest son while Motoan was still alive, and his son Soyuki Kokoroan succeeded to the position of 10th master.</e>
<cmt>心庵宗雪 Soyuki Shinan 心庵宗雪Soyuki Kokoroan</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, Motoan, while he was still living, passed on the role of master to his eldest son, Soyuki Kokoroan, who succeeded to the position of tenth master.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, Myogen-an, while he was still living, passed on the role of master to his eldest son, Myoshin-an Sosetsu, who succeeded to the position of tenth master.</e>
<cmt>名心庵宗雪→Myoshin-an Sosetsu　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>しかし、3年後に名元庵が没すると、名元庵の弟不式庵閑雪も10代家元を名乗り、江戸千家宗家蓮華庵を称して独立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, three years later upon the death of Motoan, Motoan&apos;s younger brother Kansetsu Geshikian also took the title of 10th master and independently started the Edosenke Soke Renkean.</e>
<cmt>不式庵閑雪 Kansetsu Geshikian</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, three years later, upon the death of Motoan, Motoan&apos;s younger brother Kansetsu Geshikian also took the title of tenth master and independently started the Edosenke Soke Renkean.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, three years later, upon the death of Myogen-an, Myogen-an&apos;s younger brother, Fushiki-an (不式庵) Kansetsu, also took the title of tenth master and independently started the Edosenke Soke Renge-an.</e>
<cmt>蓮華庵 →Renge-anとしました。不式庵の読み方が不明だったため、不式庵閑雪→Fushiki-an (不式庵) Kansetsu としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>両者を区別するために便宜上、江戸千家を「江戸千家（池之端）」、江戸千家宗家蓮華庵を「江戸千家（弥生町）」と呼ぶこともある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order to distinguish between the two, for the sake of convenience, Edosenke is called Edosenke (Ikenohata) and Edosenke Soke Renke-an is called Edosenke (Yayoi-cho).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to distinguish between the two, and for the sake of convenience, Edosenke is called Edosenke (Ikenohata) and Edosenke Soke Renke-an is called Edosenke (Yayoi-cho).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to distinguish between the two, and for the sake of convenience, Edosenke is called Edosenke (Ikenohata) and Edosenke Soke Renge-an is called Edosenke (Yayoi-cho).</e>
<cmt>蓮華庵 →Renge-anとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>江戸千家宗家蓮華庵には財団法人として江戸千家茶道会、同門組織として不白会がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Edosenke Soke Renke-an has foundations called Edosenke Chado Association and its fellow organization called Fuhaku Association.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Edosenke Soke Renke-an has foundations called the Edosenke Chado Association and its fellow organization, the Fuhaku Association.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Edosenke Soke Renge-an has foundations called the Edosenke Chado Association and its fellow organization, the Fuhaku Association.</e>
<cmt>蓮華庵 →Renge-anとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="20">
<j>川上家浜町派は不白の高弟の川上宗什が浜町に居を構えたのに始まり、代々久留米藩有馬家の茶道役を務めていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kawakami Hamacho school was originated by Soten Kawakami who was a leading student of Fuhaku, and who established himself in Hamacho; and successive generations served as tea masters to the Arima household in the Kurume clan.</e>
<cmt>川上宗什 Soten Kawakami</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kawakami Hamacho school was originated by Soten Kawakami, a leading student of Fuhaku who established himself in Hamacho; and successive generations served as tea masters to the Arima household in the Kurume clan.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kawakami Hamacho school was originated by Soju KAWAKAMI, a leading student of Fuhaku who established himself in Hamacho, and successive generations served as tea masters to the Arima family in the Kurume clan.</e>
<cmt>名字を大文字にしました。人名を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>この流れでは維新後5代蓮心宗順の時の門人に益田鈍翁・馬越恭平ら当時の数奇者が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this line, during the time of the 5th master Sojun Keshin after the Meiji Restoration, there were many ardent students of the tea ceremony including Donno Masuda and Kyodaira Umakoshi.</e>
<cmt>蓮心宗順Sojun Keshin, 馬越恭平ら Kyodaira Umakoshi</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this line, during the time of the fifth master Sojun Keshin after the Meiji Restoration, there were many ardent students of tea ceremony, including Donno Masuda and Kyodaira Umakoshi.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this line, during the time of the fifth master Renshin Sojun (蓮心宗順) after the Meiji Restoration, there were many ardent students of tea ceremony, including Donno Masuda and Kyohei MAGOSHI.</e>
<cmt>蓮心宗順の読み方が不明なため、Renshin Sojun (蓮心宗順)としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>しかし6代素蓮宗順のとき関東大震災によって浜町の住居を焼失してしまい、家元としては一時断絶という形になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, during the time of the 6th tea master Sojun Soken, the house in Hamacho was burnt to the ground in the Great Kanto Earthquake, and the position of tea master was temporarily discontinued.</e>
<cmt>蓮舟宗順 Kefune Sojun</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, during the time of the sixth tea master Sojun Soken, the house in Hamacho burned to the ground as a result of the Great Kanto Earthquake, and the position of tea master was temporarily discontinued.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, during the time of the sixth tea master Suren Sojun (素蓮宗順), the house in Hamacho burned to the ground as a result of the Great Kanto Earthquake, and the position of tea master was temporarily discontinued.</e>
<cmt>素蓮宗順の読み方が不明なため、Suren Sojun (素蓮宗順)としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>7代蓮舟宗順は東京大学法科大学を卒業後しばらく実業界にあったが、戦後になって高円寺で家元を再興し、このときから表千家不白流と称するようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The 7th master Kefune Sojun was engaged in business for a while after graduating from the Faculty of Law of Tokyo University, however after the war he restored the lineage in Koenji and it henceforth came to be called Omotesenke Fuhaku school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The seventh master, Kefune Sojun, was engaged in business for a while after graduating from the Tokyo University School of Law; however, after the war he restored the lineage in Koenji and it henceforth became known as the Omotesenke Fuhaku school.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The seventh master, Renshu Sojun (蓮舟宗順), was engaged in business for a while after graduating from the Tokyo University School of Law; however, after the war he restored the lineage in Koenji and it henceforth became known as the Omotesenke Fuhaku school.</e>
<cmt>蓮心宗順の読み方が不明なため、Renshin Sojun (蓮心宗順)としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>財団法人として不白流白和会がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has a foundation called Fuhaku-ryu Hakuwa-kai (Fuhaku School Hakuwa Association).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has a foundation called Fuhaku-ryu Hakuwa-kai (Fuhaku School Hakuwa Association).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has a foundation called Fuhaku-ryu Hakuwa-kai (Fuhaku School Hakuwa Association).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="25">
<j>このほか、不白の門人の石塚宗通が代々伝えた流れでは明治になって岡倉天心と交流があったことで有名であり、また同じく不白の門人で川上渭白が伝えた流れには岸田劉生夫人の岸田蓁（しげる）がいて、6代川上渭白と称して江戸千家渭白流を再興した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Elsewhere, in the tea ceremony passed on from Sotsu Ishizuka, a student of Fuhaku, masters in the Meiji Era were famous for their exchanges with Tenshin Okakura, and again, in the tea ceremony passed on by another student of Fuhaku&apos;s, Ihaku Kawakami, one of the masters was the wife of Ryusei Kishida, Shigeru Kishida, who was named the 6th master Ihaku Kawakami and restored the Edosenke Ihaku school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Elsewhere, in the tea ceremony passed on from Sotsu Ishizuka, a student of Fuhaku, masters in the Meiji period were famous for their exchanges with Tenshin Okakura, and again, in the tea ceremony passed on by Ihaku Kawakami, another student of Fuhaku, one of the masters was Shigeru Kishida, the wife of Ryusei Kishida, who was designated as the sixth master of Ihaku Kawakami and then restored the Edosenke Ihaku school.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Elsewhere, in the tea ceremony passed on from Sotsu ISHIZUKA, a student of Fuhaku, masters in the Meiji period were famous for their exchanges with Tenshin OKAKURA, and again, in the tea ceremony passed on by Ihaku KAWAKAMI, another student of Fuhaku, one of the masters was Shigeru KISHIDA, the wife of Ryusei KISHIDA, who was designated as the sixth master of Ihaku KAWAKAMI and then restored the Edosenke Ihaku school.</e>
<cmt>名字を大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="26">
<j>歴代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>江戸千家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Edosenke</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Edosenke</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Edosenke</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>江戸千家宗家蓮華庵</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Edosenke Soke Renke-an</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Edosenke Soke Renke-an</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Edosenke Soke Renge-an</e>
<cmt>蓮華庵 →Renge-anとしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="27">
<j>1〜9代は、江戸千家と同人物であるが、一部で異なった名や称号を使っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Generations one through nine were the same masters as the Edosenke, however some masters used different names or titles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first through ninth generations were the same masters as the Edosenke, but some masters used different names or titles.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first through ninth generations were the same masters as the Edosenke, but some masters used different names or titles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>表千家不白流（浜町川上家）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omotesenke Fuhaku School (Kawakami family in Hamacho).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Omotesenke Fuhaku School (the Kawakami family of Hamacho)</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Omotesenke Fuhaku School (the Kawakami family of Hamacho)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 つきみ(id:91808), YukkeBot2(id:251491), Tawashi2006(id:95112), Dabofish(id:239582), Mzaki(id:61977), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>