<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>土用の丑の日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Doyo No Ushi No Hi&quot; (The Ox Day During &quot;Doyo&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Doyo No Ushi No Hi&quot; (The Ox Day During &quot;Doyo&quot;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Doyo no Ushi no Hi (The Ox Day During &apos;Doyo&apos;)</e>
<cmt>クォーツを削除、修正しました。No→no</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>土用の丑の日（どようのうしのひ）は、土用の間で日の十二支が丑である日のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Doyo no ushi no hi&quot; is the Ox day (by the twelve signs of the Chinese zodiac) during &quot;doyo&quot; (the period of about 18 days at each end of four seasons).</e>
<cmt>・「土用」については「各季節の終わりの約18日間のこと」と解説しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Doyo no ushi no hi&quot; is the Ox day (based on the twelve signs of the Chinese zodiac) during the &quot;doyo&quot; (the period of about 18 days at each end of four seasons).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Doyo no ushi no hi&apos; is the Ox day (based on the twelve signs of the Chinese zodiac) during the &quot;doyo&quot; (the period of about 18 days at each end of four seasons).</e>
<cmt>クォーツを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>夏の土用の丑の日は、暑い時期を乗り切る栄養をつける為に、ウナギを食べる習慣がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There exists a custom for Japanese to eat an eel on the Ox day during doyo of summer in order to take nourishment for overcoming the heat.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is customary for Japanese to eat an eel on the Ox day during doyo of summer in order to take nourishment and overcome the heat.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is customary for Japanese to eat an eel on the Ox day during doyo of summer, in order to take nourishment and overcome the heat.</e>
<cmt>カンマを挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="3">
<j>土用の間に丑の日が2回ある場合があり、2回目を二の丑という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Occasionally, the Ox day comes around twice during each doyo, and the second Ox day is called &quot;ni no ushi.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Occasionally, the Ox day comes around twice during each doyo, and the second Ox day is called &quot;ni no ushi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Occasionally, the Ox day comes around twice during each doyo, and the second Ox day is called &apos;ni no ushi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーツを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="4">
<j>一般には土用の丑の日といえば夏を指すが、土用は春、夏、秋、冬の年4回あり、土用の丑の日は年に数回ある事になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Generally speaking, the Ox day during doyo indicates the summer one, but as doyo comes around four times in a year, the day also comes around several times in a year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Generally speaking, the Ox day during the doyo indicates the summer one, but as the doyo comes around four times in a year, the day also comes around several times in a year.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Generally speaking, the Ox day during the doyo indicates the summer one, but as the doyo comes around four times in a year, the day also comes around several times in a year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="5">
<j>近年、ウナギの人口当たり消費量上位に位置する長野県岡谷市を中心として寒の土用の丑の日にも鰻を食べようというキャンペーンが展開されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Recently, an advertising campaign for the eel to be eaten on winter one has been carried on mainly by the municipal office of Okaya City, Nagano Prefecture, which ranks high in per capita eel consumption.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Recently, an advertising campaign for the eel to be eaten in the winter one has been carried on mainly by the municipal office of Okaya City, Nagano Prefecture, which ranks high in per-capita eel consumption.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Recently, a campaign to eat eel on doyo in winter has been run in mainly Okaya City, Nagano Prefecture, which ranks high in per-capita eel consumption.</e>
<cmt>by the municipal office of を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>2004年～2011年の夏の土用の丑の日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ox day during doyo of summer from 2004 to 2011</e>
<cmt>（注）年号の部分につき、数字だけを入力するとエクセルの挙動が乱れます（原因は不明）ので括弧の中に入れさせて頂きました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ox day during the summer doyo, 2004 to 2011</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ox day during the summer doyo, 2004 to 2011</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>2004年</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">[2004]</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">[2004]</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">[2004]</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>- 7月21日 8月2日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">- July 21, August 2</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">- July 21, August 2</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">- July 21, August 2</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>2005年</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">[2005]</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">[2005]</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">[2005]</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>- 7月28日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">- July 28</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">- July 28</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">- July 28</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>2006年</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">[2006]</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">[2006]</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">[2006]</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>- 7月23日 8月4日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">- July 23, August 4</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">- July 23, August 4</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">- July 23, August 4</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>2007年</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">[2007]</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">[2007]</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">[2007]</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>- 7月30日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">- July 30</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">- July 30</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">- July 30</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>2008年</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">[2008]</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">[2008]</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">[2008]</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>- 7月24日 8月5日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">- July 24, August 5</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">- July 24, August 5</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">- July 24, August 5</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>2009年</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">[2009]</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">[2009]</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">[2009]</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>- 7月19日 7月31日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">- July 19, July 31</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">- July 19, July 31</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">- July 19, July 31</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>2010年</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">[2010]</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">[2010]</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">[2010]</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>- 7月26日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">- July 26</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">- July 26</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">- July 26</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>2011年</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">[2011]</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">[2011]</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">[2011]</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>- 7月21日 8月2日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">- July 21, August 2</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">- July 21, August 2</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">- July 21, August 2</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>二の丑</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Ni no ushi&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Ni no ushi&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ni no Ushi</e>
<cmt>クォーツを削除し、大文字にしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="22">
<j>前節でもわかるとおり、土用の丑の日が2回となる場合が多々ある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As mentioned above, the day often comes around twice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As mentioned above, the day often comes around twice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As mentioned above, the day often comes around twice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>夏の土用は平気法では立秋の前の18日間、近年用いられている定気法では黄道座標が117度から135度までと定義され、約18日間ということになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With &quot;Heiki-ho&quot; (the method to place the 24 traditional seasonal divisions of a year by making equal time intervals), the doyo days of summer are figured out the 18 days before &quot;risshu&quot; (the first day of autumn), and with recent popular &quot;Teiki-ho&quot; (the method to place the 24 traditional seasonal divisions of a year by equally dividing the ecliptic into 24 parts, calculating the date when the sun passes each of those parts, and setting the seasonal divisions into the date), the doyo days of summer fall on the dates that the sun passes the the obliquity of 117°- 135°, and they are figured out about 18 days around risshu.</e>
<cmt>・「平気法」「定気法」の定訳は見当たらなかったので、やむを得ず拙訳による解説を付しています。　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　前者は、「二十四節気の日付を、一年の暦の上で時間的に均等な間隔を空けて割りつけることで配置する方法」、後者は「黄道を24等分し、導き出される特定の度を太陽が通過する日に二十四節気を配置する方法」と解説したつもりです。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With &quot;Heiki-ho&quot; (the method of placing the 24 traditional seasonal divisions of a year by making equal time intervals), the doyo days of summer are calculated as the 18 days before &quot;risshu&quot; (the first day of autumn), and with the recently popular &quot;Teiki-ho&quot; (the method of placing the 24 traditional seasonal divisions of a year by equally dividing the ecliptic into 24 parts, calculating the date when the sun passes each of those parts and setting the seasonal divisions into the date), the doyo days of summer fall on the dates the sun passes the obliquity of 117°- 135°, and they are calculated as approximately 18 days around risshu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With &apos;Heiki-ho&apos; (the method of placing the 24 traditional seasonal divisions of a year by making equal time intervals), the doyo days of summer are calculated as the 18 days before &apos;risshu&apos; (the first day of autumn), and with the recently popular &apos;Teiki-ho&apos; (the method of placing the 24 traditional seasonal divisions of a year by equally dividing the ecliptic into 24 parts, calculating the date when the sun passes each of those parts and setting the seasonal divisions into the date), the doyo days of summer fall on the dates the sun passes the obliquity of 117°to 135°, and they are calculated as approximately 18 days around risshu.</e>
<cmt>スペースの修正、-→to,クォーツの修正をしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>18日間として考えると土用入りの日から6日以内に丑の日があると（すなわち土用入りの日が申から丑の間の場合）もう一度丑の日が巡って来る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Provided that doyo has 18 days, the Ox day comes around twice when the first Ox day comes within 6 days from the first day of doyo, in other words, when the first day of doyo falls on the day of the Monkey, Cock, Dog, Boar, Rat, or Ox (by the twelve signs of the Chinese zodiac).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Provided that the doyo has 18 days, the Ox day comes around twice when the first Ox day comes within six days from the first day of the doyo, in other words, when the first day of the doyo falls on the day of the Monkey, Cock, Dog, Boar, Rat or Ox (based on the twelve signs of the Chinese zodiac).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Provided that the doyo has 18 days, the Ox day comes around twice when the first Ox day comes within 6 days from the first day of the doyo, in other words, when the first day of the doyo falls on the day of the Monkey, Cock, Dog, Boar, Rat or Ox (based on the twelve signs of the Chinese zodiac).</e>
<cmt>six→6</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>これが二の丑であり、約2年に1回の割合である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This second Ox day is ni no ushi, and it comes around almost every other year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This second Ox day is ni no ushi, and it comes around almost every other year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This second Ox day is ni no ushi, and it comes around almost every other year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>鰻を食べる由来</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Origin of the custom to eat eel on the Ox day during doyo of summer</e>
<cmt>・セル46-49から、「夏の土用の丑の日に」という話であることが明確であり、そこを補って訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Origin of the custom of eating eel on the Ox day during the summer doyo</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Origin of the custom of eating eel on the Ox day during the summer doyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="26">
<j>鰻を食べる習慣についての由来には諸説あり、讃岐国出身の平賀源内が発案したという説が最もよく知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There exist some theories about the origin to eat eel on the Ox day during doyo of summer, and the most famous one is that the idea was devised by Gennai HIRAGA who came from Sanuki Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are various theories regarding the origin of the custom of eating eel on the Ox day during the summer doyo, but the best known of them is that the idea was devised by Gennai HIRAGA, who came from Sanuki Province.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are various theories regarding the origin of the custom of eating eel on the Ox day during the summer doyo, but the best known of them is that the idea was devised by Gennai HIRAGA, who came from Sanuki Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>これは文政5年（1822年）の、当時の話題を集めた『明和誌』（青山白峰著）に収められている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This story is included in &quot;Meiwa-shi&quot; (The Book about Food Customs around the Meiwa era), which was written by Hakuho AOYAMA in 1822.</e>
<cmt>・「明和誌」の定訳は見つかりませんでしたので訳者の拙訳（「明和年間前後の食風俗に関する本」）を付しています（この内容については、以下のホームページを参照しています。）[http://www.ndl.go.jp/jp/gallery/permanent/jousetsu145.html#02] の「２）鼠璞十種２」より。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This story is included in &quot;Meiwa-shi&quot; (a book about food customs in the time around the Meiwa era), which was written by Hakuho AOYAMA in 1822.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This story is included in &quot;Meiwa-shi&quot; (a book about food customs in the time around the Meiwa era), which was written by Hakuho AOYAMA in 1822.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="28">
<j>それによると、こういう話だ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It says as follows:</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It states as follows:</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It states as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>商売がうまく行かない鰻屋が、夏に売れない鰻を何とか売るため源内の所に相談に行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Having few customers, an eel shop owner went to Gennai&apos;s home to consult about how to sell eels during summer, the sluggish season for its business:</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処　 ・以下セル46から49までは一連の話としてセミコロンでつないでいます。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The owner of an eel shop, having few customers, went to Gennai&apos;s home to consult about how to sell eel during summer, the sluggish season for his business:</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The owner of an eel restaurant, having few customers, went to Gennai&apos;s home to consult about how to sell eel during summer, the sluggish season for his business.</e>
<cmt>鰻屋：eel restaurant として修正しました。コロンを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>源内は、「丑の日に『う』の字が附く物を食べると夏負けしない」という民間伝承からヒントを得て、「本日丑の日」と書いて店先に貼ることを勧めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Getting a hint from the folklore that one could overcome the summer heat by eating something that had the Japanese syllable of &quot;u&quot; at the head of its name - such as an eel (in Japanese, &quot;unagi&quot;) - on the Ox day, Gennai recommended the owner to stick a poster on its shop&apos;s door saying, &quot;Today is the Ox day&quot;;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Getting a hint from the folklore that one could overcome the summer heat by eating something that had the Japanese syllable of &quot;u&quot; at the head of its name--such as an eel (in Japanese, &quot;unagi&quot;)--on the Ox day, Gennai recommended that the owner attach a poster to the shop door stating, &quot;Today is the Ox day&quot;;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Getting a hint from the folklore that &quot;one could overcome the summer heat by eating something that had the Japanese syllable of &apos;u&apos; at the head of its name, such as an eel (in Japanese, &apos;unagi&apos;) on the Ox day,&quot; Gennai recommended that the owner attach a poster to the shop door stating, &quot;Today is the Ox day.&quot;</e>
<cmt>クォーツと、クォーツ内の修正をしました。セミコロンを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>すると、物知りとして有名な源内の言うことならということで、その鰻屋は大変繁盛した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">so the owner followed Gennai&apos;s advice and greatly prospered, because people bought eels from the shop trusting Gennai, who was a well-known person for his knowledge;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">so the owner followed Gennai&apos;s advice and greatly prospered, because people bought eel from the shop trusting Gennai, who was well known for being knowledgeable;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">So the owner followed Gennai&apos;s advice, and greatly prospered, because people came to eat trusting Gennai, who was well known for being knowledgeable.</e>
<cmt>so→So,bought eel from the shop →came to eat,セミコロンを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>その後、他の鰻屋もそれを真似るようになり、土用の丑の日に鰻を食べる風習が定着したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">and so, other eel shop owners followed suit, and the custom took root.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">and so, other eel shop owners followed suit, and the custom took root.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And so, other eel restaurants followed suit, and the custom took root.</e>
<cmt>and so→And so,eel shop owners→eel restaurants</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="33">
<j>この民間伝承を根拠とするならば、土用の丑の日に食べるものは鰻でなく「う」の付くものでいいのだから、うどんでもうどでもいいことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If the folklore is the rationale for the custom, the food to eat on the Ox day during doyo could be &quot;udon&quot; (Japanese wheat noodle) or &quot;udo&quot; (Aralia cordata), since every food other than an eel is possible when it has the Japanese syllable &quot;u&quot; at the head of its name.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If the folklore is the rationale for the custom, the food to eat on the Ox day during the doyo could be &quot;udon&quot; (Japanese wheat noodle) or &quot;udo&quot; (Aralia cordata), since every food other than eel is possible when it has the Japanese syllable &quot;u&quot; at the head of its name.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If the folklore is the rationale for the custom, the food to eat on the Ox day during the doyo could be &apos;udon&apos; (Japanese wheat noodle) or &apos;udo&apos; (Aralia cordata), since every food other than eel is possible when it has the Japanese syllable &quot;u&quot; at the head of its name.</e>
<cmt>クォートを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="34">
<j>鰻を食べるのが主流となったのは確固とした由緒由来が有るわけではなく、バレンタインデーのチョコレートや節分の恵方巻きなどと同様、現代でいうコマーシャリズムの産物といえよう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The custom became popular, but it has no certain history or origin, and it could be said the product of what we call commercialism today, just like the chocolate on St. Valentine&apos;s Day, or &quot;eho-maki&quot; (rolled sushi that is said to bring you luck when you eat in &quot;eho&quot; [the lucky direction]) on &quot;Setsubun&quot; (February 3).</e>
<cmt>・「恵方巻き」は「恵方（縁起が良いとされる方向）を向いて食べると良いと言われる巻きずし」と解説しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The custom became popular, but it has no certain history or origin and could be called the product of what we now call commercialism, like chocolate on St. Valentine&apos;s Day, or &quot;eho-maki&quot; (rolled sushi that is said to bring luck when eaten in &quot;eho&quot; [the lucky direction]) on &quot;Setsubun&quot; (February 3).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The custom became popular, but it has no certain history or origin and could be called the product of what we now call commercialism; like chocolate on St. Valentine&apos;s Day, or &apos;eho-maki&apos; (rolled sushi that is said to bring luck when eaten in &apos;eho&apos; [the lucky direction]) on &apos;Setsubun&apos; (February 3).</e>
<cmt>セミコロンを挿入しました。クォートを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="35">
<j>ただし鰻にはビタミンB類が豊富に含まれているため、夏バテ、食欲減退防止の効果が期待できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But an eel is rich in Vitamin Bs, so you can prevent your summer fatigue and loss of appetite by eating it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eel, however, is rich in Vitamin B, so one can prevent summer fatigue and loss of appetite by eating it.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eel, however, is rich in Vitamin B, so one can prevent summer fatigue and loss of appetite by eating it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>そういった面から鑑みると、当時夏の時期に鰻を食べたのは理に適った習慣であるともいえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Considering this, the then custom of eating an eel in summer can be said to have made sense.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Considering this, the old custom of eating eel in summer can be said to make sense.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Considering this, the old custom of eating eel in summer can be said to make sense.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>その他の説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other theories</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other theories</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other theories</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="37">
<j>春木屋善兵衛説 - 同じ文政年間（1818 - 1829）の『江戸買物独案内』によると、土用に大量の蒲焼の注文を受けた鰻屋、春木屋善兵衛が、子の日、丑の日、寅の日の3日間で作って土甕に入れて保存しておいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The &quot;Zenbei HARUKIYA&quot; origin theory: According to &quot;Edo kaimono hitori annai&quot; (the shopping guide of Edo) compiled in the same Bunsei era (1818-1829) as the above, Zenbei HARUKIYA, an eel shop owner, received a large order for &quot;kabayaki&quot; (eel split, grilled and basted with a sweet sauce) during doyo, so he grilled eels on the day of Rat, Ox and Tiger consecutively and kept them in earthenware pots;</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処　・「江戸買物独案内」は定訳が見つからず、翻訳者の拙訳を付しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Zenbei HARUKIYA&quot; origin theory: According to &quot;Edo kaimono hitori annai&quot; (the shopping guide of Edo) compiled in the same Bunsei era (1818-1829) as the above, Zenbei HARUKIYA, an eel-shop owner received a large order for &quot;kabayaki&quot; (eel split, grilled and basted with a sweet sauce) during the doyo, so he grilled eel on the day of the Rat, Ox and Tiger consecutively and kept it in earthenware pots;</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Zenbei HARUKIYA origin theory: According to &quot;Edo kaimono hitori annai&quot; (the shopping guide of Edo) compiled in the same Bunsei era (1818-1829) as the above, Zenbei HARUKIYA, an eel restaurant owner received a large order for &apos;kabayaki&apos; (eel split, grilled and basted with a sweet sauce) during the doyo, so he grilled eel on the day of the Rat, Ox and Tiger consecutively and kept it in earthenware pots;</e>
<cmt>クォートの修正をしました。eel-shop→eel restaurant,</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>そのうち、丑の日に作った物だけが悪くなっていなかったから、という説。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">of these eels, only the ones grilled on the Ox day kept the good taste, so this became the custom&apos;s origin, the guide says.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">of these eels, only the ones grilled on the Ox day retained their good flavor, so this gave rise to the custom, the guide states.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">of these eels, only the ones grilled on the Ox day retained their good flavor, so this gave rise to the custom, the guide states.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="39">
<j>蜀山人説 - やや時代が下がった天保10年（1839年）の『天保佳話』（劉会山大辺甫篇）では、やはり鰻屋に相談をもちかけられた蜀山人こと太田南畝が、「丑の日に鰻を食べると薬になる」という内容の狂歌をキャッチコピーとして考え出したという話が載せられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The &quot;Shokusanjin&quot; origin theory: According to &quot;Tenpo kawa&quot; (Good Stories in the Tenpo era) compiled by Daihenho RYUKAISAN a little later in 1839, Nanbo OTA (also known as Shokusanjin) was consulted - like Gennai - by an eel shop owner, so Nanbo thought out a tag line in the style of &quot;kyoka&quot; (a comic &quot;tanka&quot; [Japanese poem]) saying that eating the eel on the Ox day was good for health.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Shokusanjin&quot; origin theory: According to &quot;Tenpo kawa (Good Stories in the Tenpo era),&quot; compiled by Daihenho RYUKAISAN a bit later in 1839, Nanbo OTA (also known as Shokusanjin) was consulted--like Gennai--by an eel-shop owner, so Nanbo devised a tag line in the style of &quot;kyoka&quot; (a comic &quot;tanka&quot; [Japanese poem]) saying that eating eel on the Ox day was good for one&apos;s health.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Shokusanjin origin theory: According to &quot;Tenpo kawa (Good Stories in the Tenpo era),&quot; compiled by Daihenho RYUKAISAN a bit later in 1839, Nanbo OTA (also known as Shokusanjin) was consulted also by an eel restaurant owner, Nanbo devised a tag line in the style of kyoka (a comic tanka [Japanese poem]) saying that &quot;eating eel on the Ox day was good for one&apos;s health.&quot;</e>
<cmt>クォートの修正をしました。 alsoを挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="40">
<j>丑＝鰻二匹説 - 平仮名で墨汁を使って毛筆で書いた「うし」と言う文字が、まるで二匹の鰻のように見えたからと言う説。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;An ox = two eels&quot; theory: The Japanese syllabary characters meaning an ox (&quot;うし&quot;), which were written on something with a brush &amp; India ink, looked like two eels, so they became the origin of the custom, this theory says.</e>
<cmt>・「うし」という平仮名を直接文章に入れることで、海外の人にも「形がウナギに似てる」と分かってもらえると考えました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;An ox = two eels&quot; theory: The Japanese syllabary characters meaning an ox (&quot;うし&quot;), which were written on something with a brush and India ink, looked like two eels, so they became the origin of the custom, this theory states.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An ox = two eels theory: The Japanese syllabary characters meaning an ox (&quot;うし&quot;), which were written on something with a brush and India ink, looked like two eels, so they became the origin of the custom, this theory states.</e>
<cmt>クォートの修正をしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>最近の動き</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Recent campaigns</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Recent campaigns</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Recent campaigns</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="41">
<j>鰻の養殖業者らが中心となって、夏以外の土用の丑の日にも鰻を食べる習慣を普及させようという動きがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There has been an advertising campaign for the eel to be eaten on the Ox days other than the summer one, which has been carried on mainly by eel mariculturists.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There has been an advertising campaign to promote the consumption of eel on the Ox days other than the summer one, which has been carried out mainly by eel mariculturists.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There has been an advertising campaign to promote the consumption of eel on the Ox days other than the summer one, which has been carried out mainly by eel mariculturists.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>スーパーやコンビニでもこの動きが見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Similar campaigns have been done by supermarkets &amp; convenience stores.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Similar campaigns have been carried out by supermarkets and convenience stores.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Similar campaigns have been carried out by supermarkets and convenience stores.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>土用は季節の変わり目でもあるため、栄養価の高いウナギを食べて精を付けようという趣旨に一応の妥当性はある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Doyo is at the change of seasons, so it is reasonable to some extent to eat the eel, which has high nutritional value, for gaining strength.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Doyo is at the change of seasons, so to some extent it&apos;s reasonable to eat eel, which has high nutritional value and benefits one&apos;s strength.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Doyo is at the change of seasons, so to some extent it&apos;s reasonable to eat eel, which has high nutritional value and benefits one&apos;s strength.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="44">
<j>中国産ウナギの安全性が問題視され、2007年はウナギの売上が激減した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 2007, the sales of eels fell sharply in Japan, because consumers were concerned about the safety of eels imported from China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 2007, eel sales fell sharply in Japan because consumers were concerned about the safety of eel imported from China.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 2007, eel sales fell sharply in Japan because consumers were concerned about the safety of eel imported from China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="45">
<j>（中国産食品の安全性も参照のこと）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Please refer to the article of &quot;the safety of Chinese foods.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Please refer to the article on &quot;the safety of Chinese foods.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Please refer to the article on &apos;the safety of Chinese foods&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォートの修正、ピリオドを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Su-jack(id:228917), TRIBESMAN(id:4735), Hoge-(id:158), 銀色しっぽ(id:197919), Ypacaraí(id:11031), Locahunt(id:18828), Nnh(id:474), 0null0(id:582), Chinamie(id:213556), Charenji(id:7908), 久太郎(id:188054), Araisyohei(id:378), 久米っち(id:24975), Tagaru(id:30411), 舞神楽(id:229495), Ohura(id:5986), MBP(id:93853), Syulan(id:142532), Shota(id:10854), NouvelleNatBlvd(id:98672), Mochi(id:9489), Pacusi(id:70460), Poo-T(id:10118), Point136(id:211299), U1p(id:48290), S-yamada(id:60097), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>