<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>黄丹袍</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oni-no-ho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oni no ho</e>
<cmt>ハイフンを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oni no ho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>黄丹袍（おうにのほう）とは皇太子が儀式の際に着用する束帯装束の袍のことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oni-no-ho is a term of wafuku (traditional Japanese clothes) that means a costume, called sokutai shozoku, which a crown prince puts on in a ritual.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Oni no ho&quot; is a ho (round-necked robe worn by members of nobility and the imperial court) of sokutai (traditional ceremonial court dress) costume, worn by a crown prince in the rituals.</e>
<cmt>原文「和服用語集」を「袍」に修正しました。英文全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Oni no ho&quot; is a ho (round-necked robe worn by members of nobility and the imperial court) of sokutai (traditional ceremonial court dress) costume, worn by a crown prince in the rituals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>この名前はクチナシ（くちなし）とベニバナ（べにばな）で染めた色名「黄丹」からである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was named after the color &quot;Oni&quot;, which is obtained by dying a cloth with gardenia and safflower</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was named after the color &apos;oni,&apos; which is obtained by dying a cloth with gardenia and safflower.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Oni&quot;, を &apos;oni,&apos; に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was named after the color &apos;oni,&apos; which is obtained by dying a cloth with gardenia and safflower.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>沿革</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Brief history</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>Brief history を History に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>黄丹は、『養老律令』の「衣服令」において皇太子の礼服（朝賀と即位に使う正装）・朝服（のちの束帯の原型）の「衣」の色と規定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;The Garment Code&quot; of &quot;Yoro Ritsuryo Code&quot;, oni was determined as the color of &quot;koromo&quot; (robe) of crown prince&apos;s reifuku (full dress to be used for choga (retainers&apos; New Year greeting to the emperor) and the enthronement ceremony) and chofuku (the original model of sokutai).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &apos;The Garment Code&apos; of &quot;Yoro Ritsuryo Code,&quot; oni was determined as the color of &apos;koromo&apos; (robe) of crown prince&apos;s reifuku (formal dress used for choga [retainers&apos; New Year&apos;s greeting to the emperor] and the enthronement ceremony) and chofuku (the original model of sokutai).</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &apos;The Garment Code&apos; of &quot;Yoro Ritsuryo Code,&quot; oni was determined as the color of &apos;koromo&apos; (robe) of crown prince&apos;s reifuku (formal dress used for choga [retainers&apos; New Year&apos;s greeting to the emperor] and the enthronement ceremony) and chofuku (the original model of sokutai).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>それ以前の「朱華色」（はねずいろ）の系統を引くものと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is thought that this color might have originated from &quot;hanezu-iro&quot; (hanezu red), a color which had been used before then.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is thought that this color might have originated from &apos;hanezu-iro&apos; (hanezu red), a color which had been used before then.</e>
<cmt>ダブルコーテーションをシングルコーテーションに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is thought that this color might have originated from &apos;hanezu-iro&apos; (hanezu red), a color which had been used before then.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>天皇の黄櫨染御袍が中国の赭黄袍を起源として平安時代初期に導入された（それ以前の天皇の袍は白色であったと推定されている）のに対し、黄丹色の日本での起源は、より古い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While korozen-no-goho (a costume which an emperor puts on when he performs an important ritual), whose origin was shakoho of China, was imported in the early Heian period, oni-no-ho came to be in use in Japan earlier than that.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While korozen no goho (a costume which an emperor puts on when he performs an important ritual), whose origin was shakoho (apricot-yellow robe made for the exclusive use of an emperor) of China, was imported in the early Heian period, the origin of oni no ho is earlier than that.</e>
<cmt>korozen-no-goho 及び oni-no-ho のハイフンを削除しました。shakoho に (apricot-yellow robe made for the exclusive use of an emperor)　を追記しました。oni no ho came to be in use in Japan を the origin of oni no ho に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While korozen no goho (a costume which an emperor puts on when he performs an important ritual), whose origin was shakoho (apricot-yellow robe made for the exclusive use of an emperor) of China, was imported in the early Heian period, the origin of oni no ho is earlier than that.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>平安時代前期には皇太子の礼服は赤色の九章服になったが（さらに朝賀の廃止された平安中期以降は、皇太子の礼服の着装例がない）、朝服においてはその後も使用され、文様も鴛鴦丸（えんおうまる）が使われることが一般化した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although crown prince&apos;s reifuku was replaced by red-colored kushofuku in the early Heian period (after choga was abolished in the middle of Heian period, crown prince&apos;s reifuku fell into disuse), oni-no-ho was continuously used for chofuku and eno-maru (the design of mandarin duck making a circle) came to be in use for its pattern.</e>
<cmt>九章服→読み不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although crown prince&apos;s reifuku was replaced by red-colored kushofuku in the early Heian period (after choga was abolished in the middle of Heian period, crown prince&apos;s reifuku fell into disuse), oni no ho was continuously used for chofuku and the use of eno-maru (the design of mandarin duck making a circle) pattern was generalized.</e>
<cmt>oni-no-ho のハイフンを削除しました。came to be in use for its pattern をpattern became popular に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the crown prince&apos;s reifuku was replaced by a red kushofuku in the early Heian period (after choga was abolished in the middle of the Heian period, the crown prince&apos;s reifuku fell into disuse), oni no ho was continuously used for chofuku and the use of the eno-maru (a design in which mandarin ducks form a circle) pattern became common practice.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせて修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>室町時代に至り、立太子が中絶し、皇位継承者は親王のままで即位することが一般化すると、黄丹袍は中絶した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The use of oni-no-ho was suspended in the Muromachi period when the investiture ceremony of the Crown Prince was suspended and the heir to the Imperial Throne asscended the throne from the status of imperial prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The use of oni no ho was suspended in the Muromachi period when the investiture ceremony of the Crown Prince was suspended and the heir to the Imperial Throne ascended the throne from the status of imperial prince.</e>
<cmt>oni-no-ho のハイフンを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The use of oni no ho was suspended in the Muromachi period when the investiture ceremony of the Crown Prince was suspended and the heir to the Imperial Throne ascended the throne from the status of imperial prince.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="8">
<j>江戸時代に至り、朝仁親王（東山天皇）の立太子以降皇太子の制度が復活する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The investiture ceremony of the Crown Prince was revived in the Edo period, starting with that of Imperial Prince Tomohito (the Emperor Higashiyama).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The investiture ceremony of the Crown Prince was revived in the Edo period, starting with that of Imperial Prince Tomohito (the Emperor Higashiyama).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The investiture ceremony of the Crown Prince was revived in the Edo period, starting with that of Imperial Prince Tomohito (the Emperor Higashiyama).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>しかし、当初は赤色袍と称して、赤茶色の袍をもちいることがあったらしく、裂が各所に現存している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it seems that a costume of reddish-brown color, called akairo-no-ho, was used in the beginning and its fabrics are existent at various places.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理　　赤色袍→読み不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in the beginning, it seems that a costume of reddish-brown color called &quot;akairo no ho&quot; was used, and its fabrics still exist in some places.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in the beginning, it seems that a costume of reddish-brown color called &quot;akairo no ho&quot; was used, and its fabrics still exist in some places.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="10">
<j>なお皇太子の「赤色袍」は『台記』などにみえるが、黄丹の異名であったものか（黄丹に似たオレンジ色の検非違使の朱紱も平安中期以降は「赤衣」とよばれたという事実がある）、別のものであったものか不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Akairo-no-ho&quot; of crown prince is seen in &quot;Daiki&quot;, but it is unknown whether it was the another name of oni-no-ho or another thing (in fact, shufutu costume of kebiishi (officials with judicial and police power), whose color was orange similar to oni, was called &quot;aka-ginu&quot;(red robe)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akairo no ho&apos; of the crown prince is seen in &quot;Daiki&quot;and so on, but it is unknown whether it was the another name of oni no ho or another thing (in fact, shufutsu costume of kebiishi [officials with judicial and police power], whose color was orange similar to oni, was called &apos;aka ginu&apos; [red robe]).</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akairo no ho&apos; of the crown prince is seen in &quot;Daiki&quot;and so on, but it is unknown whether it was the another name of oni no ho or another thing (in fact, shufutsu costume of kebiishi [officials with judicial and police power], whose color was orange similar to oni, was called &apos;aka ginu&apos; [red robe]).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>形状</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Design</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shape</e>
<cmt>Design を Shape に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shape</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>朝仁親王以来、紋は花形の枠に下向きになった鴛鴦（おしどり）一羽を収めた（鴛鴦とはいっても雄のみ）もので、定型化して現在まで変わっていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The crest of a mandarin duck (only male) sitting inside the flower-shaped frame has been used since the time of Imperial Prince Tomohito.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the time of Imperial Prince Tomohito, the crest of a mandarin duck (only male) sitting inside the flower-shaped frame has been stylized and never changed till now.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the time of Imperial Prince Tomohito, the crest of a mandarin duck (only male) sitting inside the flower-shaped frame has been stylized and never changed till now.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="12">
<j>近世後期の規定では、衣紋道（えもんどう）の山科家・高倉家ともに冬の場合、元服後の縫腋袍の仕立てのときは裏を黄平絹、元服前の闕腋袍の仕立てのときは裏を黄丹平絹の表裏同色とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For winter-use ones, according to the regulations established in the late early-modern times by Yamashina family and Takakura family, families of emon-do (traditional technique for dressing up ceremonial costume), yellow hiraginu silk was used for lining in the case of hoeki-no-ho, the one that was used by an adult, while yellow tanpei silk was used for ketteki-no-ho, the one that was used by a minor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the regulations in the late early-modern times, in winter, both Yamashina and Takakura families of emon-do (traditional technique for dressing up ceremonial costume) tailor a hoeki no ho (robe with a round collar, stitched sides and a ran, worn by the emperor and high-ranking officials) after coming of age with yellow hiraginu silk for lining, while tailoring a ketteki no ho (open sleeve seams outer robe) before coming of age with oni silk, same color as lining.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the regulations in the late early-modern times, in winter, both Yamashina and Takakura families of emon-do (traditional technique for dressing up ceremonial costume) tailor a hoeki no ho (robe with a round collar, stitched sides and a ran, worn by the emperor and high-ranking officials) after coming of age with yellow hiraginu silk for lining, while tailoring a ketteki no ho (open sleeve seams outer robe) before coming of age with oni silk, same color as lining.</e>
<cmt>スペース調整</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>紋の配置は升目状に縦横一列に配して、普通の装束地のように一段ごとに紋の位置をずらすことはしない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The crests were lined up vertically and horizontally, and they were not staggered stepwise as the case of ordinary cloth of shozoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The crests were lined up vertically and horizontally, and they were not staggered stepwise as the case of ordinary cloth of shozoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The crests were lined up vertically and horizontally, and they were not staggered stepwise as the case of ordinary cloth of shozoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>これは黄櫨染も同じである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The above was same in the case of korozen-no-ho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The above was same in the case of Koro zen (yellowish brown color for emperors).</e>
<cmt>korozen-no-ho をKoro zen (yellowish brown color for emperors) に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The above was same in the case of Koro zen (yellowish brown color for emperors).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="15">
<j>また闕腋のときは、未成年のゆえをもって鴛鴦丸が間を詰めて織られ（総じて装束では、若年ほど紋が小さく密である）る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the case of ketteki, crests of eno-maru were placed closely on the ground that it is the one for a minor (the size of crests were generally small and they were closely placed in the case of shozoku for the young).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the case of ketteki, crests of eno-maru are placed closely on the ground that it is the one for a minor (the size of crests were generally small and they were closely placed in the case of shozoku for the young).</e>
<cmt>were を are に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the case of ketteki, crests of eno-maru are placed closely on the ground that it is the one for a minor (the size of crests were generally small and they were closely placed in the case of shozoku for the young).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>また冬の生地は、未成年の闕腋であっても浮織にはせずに、三枚綾地に六枚綾で紋をあらわしたいわゆる固地綾である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A kataji-aya fabric, a sanmai-aya fabric on which crests are arranged by a rokumai-aya fabric, was used as the material of ketteki for winter-use.</e>
<cmt>禾→系→読み、定訳不明 一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A kataji-aya fabric, a sanmai-aya fabric on which crests are arranged by a rokumai-aya fabric, was used as the material of ketteki for winter-use.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A kataji-aya fabric, a sanmai-aya fabric on which crests are arranged by a rokumai-aya fabric, was used as the material of ketteki for winter-use.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>夏は穀（禾→系）という紗で裏をつけない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the case of ketteki for summer-use, a kind of sha (silk gauze) called koku (禾=&gt;系) was used as material and a lining was not attached.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the case of ketteki for summer-use, a kind of sha (silk gauze) called &quot;koku&quot; (禾=&gt;系) is used without lining.</e>
<cmt>called koku 以下を全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the case of ketteki for summer-use, a kind of sha (silk gauze) called &quot;koku&quot; (禾=&gt;系) is used without lining.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="18">
<j>近代においてもほぼこの制度を継承するが、紋の配置については、闕腋のときも近世ほど間を詰めていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The above system basically continued to exist up to the recent times, but the crests were not placed so closely as in the early-modern times even in the case of ketteki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The above system basically continued to exist up to the recent times, but the crests were not placed so closely as in the early-modern times even in the case of ketteki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The above system basically continued to exist up to the recent times, but the crests were not placed so closely as in the early-modern times even in the case of ketteki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>また裕仁親王（昭和天皇）立太子に先立ち、鴛鴦丸を鶴丸に代える案が生じたが、却下されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A proposal to change eno-maru for tsuru-maru (the design of crane) was made before the investiture ceremony of Imperial Prince Hirohito (the Emperor Showa), but it was dismissed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A proposal to change eno-maru for tsuru-maru (the design of crane) was made before the investiture ceremony of Imperial Prince Hirohito (the Emperor Showa), but it was dismissed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A proposal to change eno-maru for tsuru-maru (the design of crane) was made before the investiture ceremony of Imperial Prince Hirohito (the Emperor Showa), but it was dismissed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 翰林硯士(id:99377), Blue-comet(id:192801), Ktr(id:30468), Takranke(id:23355), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>