<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>直垂</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hitatare</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hitatare</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hitatare</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>直垂（ひたたれ）は日本の和服の種類の一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hitatare (the large square-cut coat with cord laced sleeve edges of samurai) is one type of Japanese traditional kimono.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hitatare (the large square-cut coat with cord laced sleeve edges of samurai) is one type of Japanese traditional kimono.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hitatare (the large square-cut coat with cord laced sleeve edges of samurai) is one type of Japanese traditional kimono.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>男性用。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is for males.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is worn by males.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is worn by males.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>なお、平安時代の貴族社会で「直垂」といえば、普通「直垂衾」（着物の形をした絹綿入りの布団。今のかいまき布団のようなもの）をさす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Whenever the &quot;hitatare&quot; is mentioned in the noble society of the Heian period, it usually referred to &quot;hitatare-fusuma&quot; (a futon (blanket) shaped like a kimono and stuffed with silk and cottons).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Whenever the &quot;hitatare&quot; was mentioned in the noble society of the Heian period, it usually referred to &quot;hitatare-fusuma&quot; (a futon (blanket) shaped like a kimono and stuffed with silk and cotton).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Whenever the &apos;hitatare&apos; was mentioned in the noble society of the Heian period, it usually referred to &apos;hitatare-fusuma&apos; (a futon (blanket) shaped like a kimono and stuffed with silk and cotton), similar to present day kaimaki futon (a comforter with sleeves)).</e>
<cmt>次セルと統合し、クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>発祥</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Birthplace</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Birthplace</e>
<cmt>title</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Origin</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>古墳時代の頃から着られていた、前で打ち合わせるタイプの衣料が基である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The clothing that overlapped in front used from the Tumulus period was the origin of this.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Clothing that overlapped in front used from the Tumulus period was the origin of hitatare.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Clothing that overlapped in front used from the Tumulus period was the origin of hitatare.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>つまり、束帯、直衣などより古くから日本に存在した着物が起源である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In another words, it originated from kimono that existed in Japan before sokutai (formal court dress) or nosi (casual wear of nobles).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In another words, it originated from kimono that existed in Japan before sokutai (formal court dress) or nosi (casual wear of nobles).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In another words, it originated from kimono that existed in Japan before sokutai (formal court dress) or noshi (casual wear of nobles).</e>
<cmt>スペルを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>形態</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shape</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shape</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shape</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>時代によって変動が激しいが</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It changed greatly depending on the time period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It changed greatly depending upon the time period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It changed greatly depending upon the time period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>上半身の衣料は詰め襟でなく、前合わせであり、打ち合わせを紐で結ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The top was not a stand-up collar, but was open in front and tied together with a string at the overlap.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The top was not a stand-up collar, but was open in front and tied together with a string at the overlap.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The top was not a stand-up collar, but was open in front and tied together with a string at the overlap.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>下半身の衣料はズボンと同じ形式である</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bottom part of this clothing was shaped like pants.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bottom part was shaped like trousers.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bottom part was shaped like trousers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>という2点は古くから変わらない特徴といえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These two parts did not change from a long time ago.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These two parts have not changed since long ago.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These two parts have not changed since long ago.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>平安時代以前</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prior to the Heian Period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prior to the Heian Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prior to the Heian Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>古墳時代、男子をかたどった埴輪は上半身には前合わせの着物、下半身には別仕立てのズボンのような物を着用している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The haniwa (ancient burial clay figurine) shaped like a boy wore a top kimono that overlapped in front and a separate pants-like object for the bottom.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The haniwa (ancient burial clay figurines) shaped like a boy wore a top kimono that overlapped in front and had separate trouser-like clothing for the bottom.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Kofun period (tumulus period), the haniwa (ancient burial clay figurines) shaped like a boy wore a top kimono that overlapped in front and had separate trouser-like clothing for the bottom.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>これが直垂の起源と思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is said to be the origin of hitatare.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is said to be the origin of hitatare.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is said to be the origin of hitatare.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="12">
<j>しかし飛鳥時代以降、律令制の導入により、衣料も大陸伝来の物が正統とされるようになっていき、束帯に位置を取って代わられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, clothing that was introduced from a continent became formal with the introduction of the political system based on the ritsuryo codes after the Asuka period, and its position was replaced by sokutai (formal male court clothing).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, clothing introduced from the continent became formal with the introduction of the political system based on the ritsuryo codes after the Asuka period, and were replaced by sokutai (formal male court clothing).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, clothing introduced from the continent became formal with the introduction of the political system based on the ritsuryo codes after the Asuka period, and were replaced by sokutai (formal male court clothing).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>その後は一般庶民の着物として、束帯など大陸からの着物の影響も受けて変化をしながら着られていた物と思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that it was used as a kimono for the commoner and changed its shape while being influenced by kimono from the continent such as sokutai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed it was used as a kimono for commoners and its shape changed while being influenced by kimono from the continent such as sokutai.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed it was used as a kimono for commoners and its shape changed while being influenced by kimono from the continent such as sokutai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>鎌倉時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kamakura Period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kamakura Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kamakura Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="14">
<j>院政の頃から武士が政治の表舞台に立つようになっていったが、この武士の平服であった直垂も武士の地位の上昇と共に正装として認められるようになっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The informal clothing of bushi (warrior class) started to be accepted as the formal dress as the bushi class rose from the period of insei (the government of the cloistered emperor) by openly taking a role in politics.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The informal clothing of the bushi (warrior class) started to be accepted as formal dress as the bushi class rose from the period of insei (the government of the cloistered emperor) by openly taking a role in politics.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The informal clothing of samurai (warrior class) started to be accepted as formal dress as the samurai class rose from the period of insei (the government of the cloistered emperor) by openly taking a role in politics.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>正装化と共に威儀を正すために袖は次第に大きくなり、袴もくるぶし丈まで長くなっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the hitatare became formal and corrected in a dignified manner, the sleeve became bigger and hakama (pleated and divided skirt made in fine stripes) went down to the height of an ankle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the hitatare became formal and corrected in a dignified manner, the sleeve became bigger and hakama (pleated and divided skirt made in fine strips) reached down to the height of the ankle.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the hitatare became formal and corrected in a dignified manner, the sleeve became bigger and hakama (pleated and divided skirt made in fine strips) reached down to the height of the ankle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>大きくなった袖は、いざ戦闘の際には邪魔になるため袖口に袖を絞る紐を通す慣例が始まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It became a custom to put the cord through the opening of the sleeve, which became bigger, to tie it up since it was in the way during a time of battle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It became customary to put the cord through the opening of the sleeve, which became bigger, to tie it up since it was in the way during a time of battle.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It became customary to put the cord through the opening of the sleeve, which became bigger, to tie it up since it was in the way during a time of battle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>また、古墳時代の男子着物や、大陸の影響を受けた束帯、直衣などは上半身の着物を下半身の着物の外に出して着るのが通例であったが、直垂は活動の便宜を図るため上半身の着物を下半身の着物の中に納めて着るようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, it became a norm to wear sokutai and nosi, which were the male kimono during the Tumulus period and affected by the influence from the continent, with its top over the bottom kimono, but hitatare was worn tucking in the top into the bottom kimono for it to be useful.</e>
<cmt>束帯→sokutai, formal court dress</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, it became the norm to wear sokutai and nosi, which were the male kimono during the Tumulus period and affected by the influence from the continent, with its top over the bottom kimono, but hitatare was worn tucking the top into the bottom kimono for it to be useful.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, it became the norm to wear sokutai and noshi, which were the male kimono during the Kofun period and affected by the influence from the continent, with its top over the bottom kimono, but hitatare was worn tucking the top into the bottom kimono for it to be useful.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="18">
<j>ただし、将軍など高位の武士は直垂ではなく水干を正装として着用していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, high class bushi such as a shogun did not wear hitatare but wore suikan (the less formal dress of upper class children) as a formal wear.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, high class bushi such as a shogun did not wear hitatare, but wore suikan (the less formal dress of upper class children) as a formal wear.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, high class samurai such as a shogun did not wear hitatare, but wore suikan (everyday garment worn by commoners in ancient Japan) as a formal wear.</e>
<cmt>補足などしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>中級以下の公家貴族もまた鎌倉後期には直垂を平服として着用するようになっていたことが、文献資料により知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is known from documents that court nobles below the middle class also wore hitatare as an informal dress at the end of Kamakura Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is known from documents that court nobles below the middle class also wore hitatare as an informal dress at the end of Kamakura Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is known from documents that court nobles below the middle class also wore hitatare as an informal dress at the end of Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>室町時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Muromachi Period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Muromachi Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Muromachi Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="20">
<j>南北朝時代 (日本)の動乱による貴族社会の地位の低下により、直垂は公家貴族の平服として着用されるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hitatare began to be used as the informal dress of court nobles from the lowering of the aristocratic social status due to disturbance of the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hitatare began to be used as the informal dress of court nobles influenced by the lowering of the aristocratic social status due to disturbance of the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hitatare began to be used as the informal dress of court nobles influenced by the lowering of the aristocratic social status due to disturbance of the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>束帯・直衣・狩衣などは、儀式などの必要に応じて着用するものになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The sokutai, nosi, and kariginu (clothing worn originally for hunting) began to be worn depending on the need of performing events such as rituals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sokutai, nosi, and kariginu (clothing worn originally for hunting) began to be worn depending on the need of performing events such as rituals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sokutai, noshi, and kariginu (clothing worn originally for hunting) began to be worn depending on the need of performing events such as rituals.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>参内には束帯・衣冠・直衣に限られたが、室町時代には直垂を「下姿」と称して参内に使用した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was limited to wear just sokutai, ikan (clothes and a crown or hat), and nosi for the Sandai (court visit), but they referred to hitatare as &quot;shitasugata&quot; (informally dressed) and incorporated it into the Sandai during the Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was limited to wearing just sokutai, ikan (clothes and a crown or hat), and nosi for the Sandai (court visit), but they referred to hitatare as &quot;shitasugata&quot; (informally dressed) and incorporated it into the Sandai during the Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was limited to wearing just sokutai, ikan (clothes and a crown or hat), and noshi for the Sandai (court visit), but they referred to hitatare as &apos;shitasugata&apos; (informally dressed) and incorporated it into the Sandai during the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>特に応仁の乱で室町殿に一時天皇が移ると、この習慣は広まったが、摂家などを除き、下姿の時は天皇の御殿に昇殿することは許されなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This custom spread especially after the emperor temporarily moved to the Muromachi Palace due to the Onin War, but it was not permitted to enter to court of the emperor&apos;s palace in shitasugata, except for the Sekke (the family of Regent).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This custom spread especially after the emperor temporarily moved to the Muromachi Palace due to the Onin War, but it was not permitted to enter the court of the emperor&apos;s palace in shitasugata, except for the Sekke (the family of Regent).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This custom spread especially after the emperor temporarily moved to the Muromachi Palace due to the Onin War, but it was not permitted to enter the court of the emperor&apos;s palace in shitasugata, except for the Sekke (the family of Regent).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>江戸時代に入ると復古的風潮から公家社会では狩衣が再び盛行し、下姿での参内もなくなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to the restoration trend with the start of Edo Period, kariginu became popular once more and the custom of performing Sandai while wearing shitasugata disappeared.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to the restoration trend with the start of the Edo Period, kariginu became popular once more and the custom of performing Sandai while wearing shitasugata disappeared.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to the restoration trend with the start of the Edo period, kariginu became popular once more and the custom of performing Sandai while wearing shitasugata disappeared.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="25">
<j>一方で武士の中での階級差に対応するように直垂から大紋、素襖などが派生していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, daimon (formal costume of daimyo consisting of wide sleeved jacket with family crests) and suo (formal middle rank dress, usually including jacket and hakama) started to derive in response to social class differences within bushi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, daimon (formal costume of daimyo consisting of a wide sleeved jacket with family crests) and suo (formal middle rank dress, usually including a jacket and hakama) started to appear in response to social class differences within bushi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, daimon (formal costume of daimyo consisting of a wide sleeved jacket with family crests) and suo (formal middle rank dress, usually including a jacket and hakama) started to appear in response to social class differences within samurai.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>特に直垂は幕府より屋形を許された足利一門や守護や国人の家臣に限り、侍烏帽子と直垂の着用が許されており、直垂の着用に制限が出来たのもこの頃である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially for hitatare, only Ashikaga clan, military governors, and retainers of provincial lords granted yakata (an honorific title) by bakufu were permitted to wear, and they were allowed to wear the lacquered hat of samurai with hitatare, and this was the period when a restriction on the wearing of hitatare appeared.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Especially for hitatare, only the Ashikaga clan, military governors, and retainers of provincial lords granted yakata (an honorific title) by bakufu were permitted to wear it, and they were allowed to wear the lacquered hat of samurai with hitatare, and this was the period when there were restrictions on the wearing of hitatare.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Especially for hitatare, only the Ashikaga clan, military governors, and retainers of provincial lords granted yakata (an honorific title) by bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) were permitted to wear it, and they were allowed to wear the lacquered hat of samurai with hitatare, and this was the period when there were restrictions on the wearing of hitatare.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="27">
<j>直垂の素材は一定しないが、室町幕府将軍は白の無紋の絹を多く用いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The texture used in hitatare was not consistent, but shogun of the Muromachi Bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) wore white silk with no family crest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The texture used in hitatare was not consistent, but shogun of the Muromachi Bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) wore white silk with no family crest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The texture used in hitatare was not consistent, but shogun of the Muromachi bakufu wore white silk with no family crest.</e>
<cmt>前出用語の補足をのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="28">
<j>鎌倉時代の直垂は袴の裾をくくっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hitatare of the Kamakura period tied up the hem of a hakama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When wearing hitatare of the Kamakura period the hem of the hakama was tied up.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When wearing hitatare of the Kamakura period the hem of the hakama was tied up.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>くくりの袴は丈に余裕を持たす例であったが、室町後期頃にはくくりをせず、丈に余裕のある袴の裾を踏んで歩くことが起こり、近世の長袴につながった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The hem sewn hakama was the example to give more room for the height, but they did not sew it at the end of Muromachi period, and walked by stepping on a hem of the hakama with more room for height, and this led to the modern naga-hakama (extra long hakama).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The hem sewn hakama was an example to give more room for height, but they did not sew it at the end of Muromachi period, and walked by stepping on a hem of the hakama, and this led to the modern naga-hakama (extra long hakama).</e>
<cmt>wordy and redundant</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The hem sewn hakama was an example to give more room for height, but they did not sew it at the end of Muromachi period, and walked by stepping on a hem of the hakama, and this led to the modern naga-hakama (extra long hakama).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>なお、直垂・大紋の腰紐は白とし、素襖は共生地を用いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They made hitatare and the waist cord of daimon as white and used the cloth of the same material for the suo (one type of kimono for the Japanese male).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They made hitatare and the waist cord of daimon white and used the cloth of the same material for the suo (one type of kimono for the Japanese male).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They made hitatare and the waist cord of daimon white and used the cloth of the same material for the suo.</e>
<cmt>前出用語の補足をのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="31">
<j>戦国時代 (日本)にはいると、直垂の袖すら邪魔となり肩衣という物が生まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even the sleeve of hitatare came in the way once entering the Warring States period (Japan), and something called kataginu (short sleevless garment made of hemp) was born.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even the sleeves of hitatare got in the way once entering the Warring States period (Japan), and something called kataginu (short sleevless garment made of hemp) was born.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even the sleeves of hitatare got in the way once entering the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States) (Japan), and something called kataginu (short sleevless garment made of hemp) was born.</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>これは後に裃となっていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This eventually became a kamishimo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This eventually became kamishimo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This eventually became kamishimo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>江戸時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Edo Period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Edo Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Edo Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="33">
<j>江戸幕府により、直垂、大紋、素襖は高位の武家しか着られない着物とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to the Edo bakufu, hitatare, daimyo, and suo became a kimono which could be only worn by high class bushi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to the Edo bakufu, hitatare, daimyo, and suo became a kimono which could only be worn by high class bushi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to the Edo bakufu, hitatare, daimyo, and suo became a kimono which could only be worn by high class bushi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>直垂の着用が許されたのは四位以上の武士に限られたが、これはほぼ幕閣を輩出する有力譜代大名、国持大名、御三家、将軍に重なる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The hitatare was allowed to be worn by bushi above the Fourth Court Rank, but this applied to those where the high officials of bakufu appeared in great numbers, such as the powerful daimyo in hereditary vassal to the Tokugawa family, daimyo having domain of one province or more, the Three families of shogun, and the shogun himself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The hitatare was allowed to be worn by bushi above the Fourth Court Rank, but this applied to those where the high officials of bakufu appeared in great numbers, such as the powerful daimyo in hereditary vassals to the Tokugawa family, daimyo having a domain of one province or more, the Three families of the shogun, and the shogun himself.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The hitatare was allowed to be worn by samurai ranked at Shii (Fourth Rank) and above, but this applied to those where the high officials of bakufu appeared in great numbers, such as the powerful daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) in hereditary vassals to the Tokugawa family, daimyo having a domain of one province or more, the Three families of the shogun, and the shogun himself.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>また色も葡萄色（えびいろ）は将軍のみ使用、緋色は大納言以上のみ使用、浅黄色、萌黄色は使用禁止の禁色（きんじき）とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for colors, only shogun was permitted to wear wine color, scarlet was worn by those above the rank of the Major Councillor, and light yellow and light green were considered to be kinjiki (prohibited colors) not permitted for usage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for colors, only the shogun was permitted to wear wine color, scarlet was worn by those above the rank of the Major Councillor, and light yellow and light green were considered to be kinjiki (prohibited colors) not permitted.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for colors, only the shogun was permitted to wear wine color, scarlet was worn by those above the rank of the Major Councillor, and light yellow and light green were considered to be kinjiki (prohibited colors) not permitted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>また着用できるシーンも元服や将軍に年始の挨拶をするときなど、事細かに限定された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, its usage was restricted down into the detail of which occasion to wear, as ganpuku or when performing new year greetings to the shogun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, there were restrictions covering the details on which occasion and what to wear, as ganpuku or when performing new year greetings to the shogun.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, there were restrictions covering the details on which occasion and what to wear, as genpuku (celebrate one&apos;s coming of age) or when performing new year greetings to the shogun.</e>
<cmt>用語を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>また、袴の長さが著しく長くなり（長袴）、引きずるほどとなって活動には適さない様式となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The length of hakama became remarkably long (naga-hakama) enough to the point of dragging and was not suited for activities.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The length of hakama became remarkably long (naga-hakama) enough to the point of dragging and was not suited for activities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The length of hakama became remarkably long (naga-hakama) enough to the point of dragging and was not suited for activities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="38">
<j>近世の武家の直垂は絹無地である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The modern hitatare of bushi is made from a single color silk.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The modern hitatare of bushi is made from silk of a single color.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The modern hitatare of samurai is made from silk of a single color.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>将軍家は精好紗（透精好）という横糸の太い紗、諸大名は精好という羽二重の厚いような生地を用いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They used a thick gauze of woof called seigosha (sheer seigo (type of weaving)) and various daimyo used a cloth called seigo that was as thick as habutae (a smooth, glossy silk cloth with a fine weave).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They used a thick gauze of woof called seigosha (sheer seigo - type of weaving) and various daimyo used cloth called seigo that was as thick as habutae (a smooth, glossy silk cloth with a fine weave).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They used a thick gauze of woof called seigosha (sheer seigo - type of weaving) and various daimyo used cloth called seigo that was as thick as habutae (a smooth, glossy silk cloth with a fine weave).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>いずれも裏は無い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They both lacked unlined parts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They both lacked lining.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They both lacked lining.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>また袖くくりは狩衣のように全体に通すのでなく、袖下に小さな輪のようにつけて「露」と称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The sodekukuri (cord to tie up the sleeve) was not laced up entirely like kariginu but was attached in the form of a small ring underneath the sleeve and called it &quot;tsuyu&quot; (dew).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sodekukuri (cord used to tie up the sleeve) was not laced up entirely like kariginu, but was attached in the form of a small ring underneath the sleeve and called it &quot;tsuyu&quot; (dew).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sodekukuri (cord used to tie up the sleeve) was not laced up entirely like kariginu, but was attached in the form of a small ring underneath the sleeve and called it &apos;tsuyu&apos; (dew).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>諸大名は禁じられた色を避けるために経緯（たてよこの糸）の色を変えた織色（玉虫）を好み、紫と緑の糸で織った松重、紫と黄色で織った木蘭地など、渋く上品な「織色」に趣味を競った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The various daimyo favored the woven color (a jewel beetle) which had different colored keii (length and breath threads) in order to avoid the usage of prohibited colors, and competed for astringent and elegant &quot;woven color,&quot; such as matsushige, which wove with purple and green strings, mokuranji (lily magnolia) which was woven with purple and yellow strings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The various daimyo favored the woven color (a jewel beetle) which had different colored keii (length and breath threads) in order to avoid the usage of prohibited colors, and competed for astringent and elegant &quot;woven colors,&quot; such as matsushige, woven with purple and green strings, mokuranji (lily magnolia) woven with purple and yellow strings.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The various daimyo favored the woven color (a jewel beetle) which had different colored keii (length and breath threads) in order to avoid the usage of prohibited colors, and competed for astringent and elegant &apos;woven colors,&apos; such as matsushige, woven with purple and green strings, mokuranji (lily magnolia) woven with purple and yellow strings.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>袴は先述のように長袴で、裾のくくりはない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The hakama was naga-hakama, as written previously, and had no tied up sleeve.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The hakama was naga-hakama, as written previously, and the sleeves were not tied up.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The hakama was naga-hakama, as written previously, and the sleeves were not tied up.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>上級武家のなかには内々に短い袴の直垂も用いたようで、遺品もあるが、公的な制度にもとづくものではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some high class bushi used hitatare with short hakama informally and belongings left by the dead were present, but it was not according to the publically enforced system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some high class bushi used hitatare with short hakama informally and belongings left by the dead were present, but it was not according to a publically enforced system.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some high class samurai used hitatare with short hakama informally and belongings left by the dead were present, but it was not according to a publically enforced system.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="45">
<j>近世の公家社会での直垂着用は著しく限られたが、用いるときは綾や固織物など、狩衣地に準じた紋織物を使用し、袴も切袴で（形式的なくくりをつけたものもある）、袖にも狩衣のようなくくりを通したものが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The current kuge (court noble) society extremely limited the usage of hitatare, but it accompanied aya and kata-orimono (types of Japanese textile), which followed the pattern woven fabrics such as kariginu-ji (hunting outfit) when used, and hakama was kiri-hakama (short fringe hakama) (there is a tie up cord just as a formality), and has a stringed sleeve just like kariginu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The current kuge (court noble) society extremely limited the usage of hitatare, but it accompanied aya and kata-orimono (types of Japanese textile), which followed the pattern woven fabrics such as kariginu-ji (hunting outfit) when used, and hakama was kiri-hakama (short fringe hakama) (there is a tie up cord just as a formality), and it has a stringed sleeve just like kariginu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The current kuge (court noble) society extremely limited the usage of hitatare, but it accompanied aya and kata-orimono (types of Japanese textile), which followed the pattern woven fabrics such as kariginu-ji (hunting outfit) when used, and hakama was kiri-hakama (short fringe hakama) (there is a tie up cord just as a formality), and it has a stringed sleeve just like kariginu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>特に明治維新の頃は服制の緩和により公家社会でも一時さかんに使用され、そのころの遺品は少なくない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The court noble society temporarily used hitatare frequently with the relaxation on laws of clothing at the time of the Meiji Restoration, and there were many belongs left by the dead at that period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The court noble society temporarily used hitatare frequently with the relaxation on laws for clothing at the time of the Meiji Restoration, and there were many belongings left by the dead during that period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The court noble society temporarily used hitatare frequently with the relaxation on laws for clothing at the time of the Meiji Restoration, and there were many belongings left by the dead during that period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>現代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Present</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Present</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Present</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="47">
<j>雅楽の演奏者や相撲の行司などが着用している姿を見ることが出来る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One could see it being worn by gagaku (court music) players and sumo referees.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One could see it being worn by gagaku (court musicians) players and sumo referees.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One could see it being worn by gagaku (ancient Japanese court dance and music) players and sumo referees.</e>
<cmt>補足を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>また狂言や歌舞伎の舞台衣装として残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, it remained as stage costumes for kyogen (a Noh farce) and the kabuki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, it remained as a stage costume for kyogen (a Noh farce) and the kabuki.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, it remained as a stage costume for kyogen (a Noh farce) and the kabuki (traditional drama performed by male actors).</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>このように伝統芸能の世界でしか着用している姿を見ることが出来なかったが、ここ最近の結婚式における花嫁の十二単にたいし花婿が着用する和装として再び脚光をあびている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One could see it being worn only within the world of traditional performing arts, but it came again into spotlight as the Japanese kimono worn by the groom in opposite to a bride, who wore juni-hitoe (sumptuous, many-layered kimono), in current day weddings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One could see it being worn only within the world of traditional performing arts, but it came again into spotlight as the Japanese kimono worn by the groom opposite the bride, who wore juni-hitoe (sumptuous, many-layered kimono), in present day weddings.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One could see it being worn only within the world of traditional performing arts, but it came again into spotlight as the Japanese kimono worn by the groom opposite the bride, who wore juni-hitoe (traditional multi-layer court costume, literally, twelve-layered ceremonial kimono), in present day weddings.</e>
<cmt>補足を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 APQ13(id:165006), こぶまき(id:38278), Mintleaf(id:2216), Nevylax(id:38464), 海衛士(id:19229), 堀五郎右衛門(id:84263), 樒(id:35770), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>