<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>粥占</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kayuura</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kayuura (Porridge Fortunetelling)</e>
<cmt>Added term explanation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kayuura (Porridge Fortunetelling)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>粥占（かゆうら）とは、粥を用いて1年の吉凶を占う年占である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kayuura is an annual fortune telling to read people&apos;s fortunes of a year using Kayu (porridge).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kayuura is an annual fortune-telling, where people&apos;s fortunes for the year are read using Kayu (porridge).</e>
<cmt>Hyphenated &quot;fortune-telling&quot;, inserted comma, changed &quot;to read people&apos;s fortunes of a year&quot; to &quot;where people&apos;s fortunes for the year are read&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kayuura is an annual fortune-telling, where people&apos;s fortunes for the year are read using Kayu (porridge).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>各地の神社で祭礼として行われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was taken place as a festival in shrines around the country.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is conducted as a festival in shrines around the country.</e>
<cmt>Changed &quot;was taken place&quot; to &quot;is conducted&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is conducted as a festival in shrines around the country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>多くは小正月に神にあずき粥を献ずるときに行われ、占われる内容はその年の天候や作物の豊凶などである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mostly in the Little New Year of January 15 when people offer Azuki beans Kayu to God, the futures of climate of the year, good or bad harvest etc. were told.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is mainly conducted on the Lunar New Year, when red bean Kayu is offered to the gods, and the fortunes told include information about the year&apos;s weather and whether the harvest will be good or bad.</e>
<cmt>Rewrote.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is mainly conducted on the Lunar New Year, when red bean Kayu is offered to the gods, and the fortunes told include information about the year&apos;s weather and whether the harvest will be good or bad.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>起源は、『年中行事秘抄』によれば、中国からつたえられたので、この日にあずき粥を蚩尤もしくは高辛氏の女の怨霊に供し、これを食すればその祟りをのがれ、年中の邪気をはらうという伝説に由来するという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Nenjugyojihisyo (descriptions of annual events)&quot; it came from China and originated in a legend that by offering Azuki beans Kayu to Chihyu (a God of Chinese myth) or a woman ghost of the Koshin clan and eating it, people can avoid the curse and evil spirits through the year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the &quot;Nenjugyojihisyo (descriptions of annual events)&quot; the custom came from China and originated in a legend that, by offering red bean Kayu to Chihyu (a god of Chinese myth) or a woman ghost of the Koshin clan, then eating it, people could escape their curses and avoid evil spirits throughout the year.</e>
<cmt>Inserted &quot;the&quot;, changed &quot;it&quot; to &quot;the custom&quot;, inserted comma, changed &quot;Azuki beans Kayu&quot; to &quot;red bean Kayu&quot;, inserted comma, changed &quot;and&quot; to &quot;then&quot;, changed &quot;people can avoid the curse and evil spirits through&quot; to &quot;people could escape their curses and avoid evil spirits throughout&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the &quot;Nenjugyojihisyo (descriptions of annual events)&quot; the custom came from China and originated in a legend that, by offering red bean Kayu to Chihyu (a god of Chinese myth) or a woman ghost of the Koshin clan, then eating it, people could escape their curses and avoid evil spirits throughout the year.</e>
<cmt>” ”を&quot; &quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>方法にはいくつかあるが、多くは、煮え上がった粥の中に棒を入れてかき回し、棒についた米粒の数で占うものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are some ways of Kayuura and the major one is to read the future by seeing how many rice grains are adhering to the stick after the stick was used to stir up boiling Kayu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are several methods of Kayuura, but the major one involves using a stick to stir up boiling Kayu, then reading the future by seeing how many rice grains adhere to the stick.</e>
<cmt>Changed &quot;some ways&quot; to &quot;several methods&quot;, changed &quot;and&quot; to &quot;,but&quot;, changed &quot;is to read the future by seeing how many rice grains are adhering to the stick after the stick was used to stir up boiling Kayu&quot; to &quot;involves using a stick to stir up boiling Kayu, then reading the future by seeing how many rice grains adhere to the stick&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are several methods of Kayuura, but the major one involves using a stick to stir up boiling Kayu, then reading the future by seeing how many rice grains adhere to the stick.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>他に、細い竹管などを米などとともに鍋釜で煮て、炊き上げた後に管を割いて中に入った粒の数を数えるもの（この場合、12本の管を入れて1か月ごとの天候を判断したり、その地域で作られる作物の数だけ管を入れて作物別の豊凶を判断したりする）や、粥を数日間放置して、カビの生え具合で占うものもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The other ways are to simmer small bamboo tubes and rice in a pan and later cut the tubes and see how many rice grains enters in it after boiled up (in this way putting 12 tubes to see the climate of each month or same numbers of tubes as the kinds of crops in the area to see the future of each crop) or just to leave Kayu for a few days and tell the future by seeing how much it becomes moldy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other methods include simmering small bamboo tubes and rice in a pan and, after the rice is boiled, cutting the tubes to see how many rice grains entered them (in this method, twelve tubes are used to see the climate of each month, or the same number of tubes as the kinds of crops in the area to see the future of each crop), or simply leaving the Kayu for a few days and telling the future by how the mold grows on it.</e>
<cmt>Rewrote.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other methods include simmering small bamboo tubes and rice in a pan and, after the rice is boiled, cutting the tubes to see how many rice grains entered them (in this method, twelve tubes are used to see the climate of each month, or the same number of tubes as the kinds of crops in the area to see the future of each crop), or simply leaving the Kayu for a few days and telling the future by how the mold grows on it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>かつては全国的に、神社ではなく村落や一族の本家などで共同で行われていたと見られるが、そのほとんどは行われなくなり、神社で神事として行われるものが残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It used to be done in village communities or main branches of families and not in shrines in all over the country, but most of them were not done any more and only some are still done as a shrine ritual.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This used to be done, not in shrines, but in village communities or the main branches of families all over the country; however, most of these ceremonies are no longer performed, and only those performed as shrine rituals remain.</e>
<cmt>Rewrote.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This used to be done, not in shrines, but in village communities or the main branches of families all over the country; however, most of these ceremonies are no longer performed, and only those performed as shrine rituals remain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="8">
<j>諏訪大社下社春宮のものについて述べれば、 1月14日夜から粥炊舎にもうけられた大釜のあずきがゆのなかに、葭の筒をいれ、終夜煮たて、翌15日朝、神前にそなえ、祭典をおこなったのち葭筒を割り、筒内の粥の分量を量って農作物のうちさだめられた種の豊凶を判定する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Suwa Taisha Shrine Shimosha Harumiya form the evening of January 14 reed tubes are put in Azuki beans Kayu in a big pan at Kayu boiling house and simmered through the night and offered to God in the morning on the 15th and the tubes are broke after the festival to see good or bad harvest of predetermined kinds of crops by measuring the amount of Kayu in the tubes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Suwa Taisha Shrine Shimosha Harumiya, reed tubes are put into a big pan of red bean Kayu at the Kayu boiling house on the evening of January 14th, simmered through the night, and offered to the gods on the morning of the 15th; after the festival, the tubes are broken open, and the amount of Kayu in the tubes is measured to see whether predetermined kinds of crops will have a good or bad harvest.</e>
<cmt>Rewrote.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Suwa Taisha Shrine Shimosha Harumiya, reed tubes are put into a big pan of red bean Kayu at the Kayu boiling house on the evening of January 14th, simmered through the night, and offered to the gods on the morning of the 15th; after the festival, the tubes are broken open, and the amount of Kayu in the tubes is measured to see whether predetermined kinds of crops will have a good or bad harvest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="9">
<j>葭筒のながさは5寸5分で、これを42本（本数はとしによってことなる）麻で簾状に編みつらねて、巻いたものをいれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The length of a reed tube is about 16cm and total 42 tubes (different numbers of tubes every year) are braided by hemp like a blind and rolled up and put in the pan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reed tubes are about 16cm in length, and a total of 42 tubes (although the number of tubes changes every year) are braided together like a blind with hemp, rolled up and put in the pan.</e>
<cmt>Rewrote.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reed tubes are about 16cm in length, and a total of 42 tubes (although the number of tubes changes every year) are braided together like a blind with hemp, rolled up and put in the pan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="10">
<j>それぞれの筒はそれぞれの穀種にかたどり、神殿大床で1筒わり、穀菜の種類上下の品位を神占にしたがってとなえ、社丁がこれにおうじて大声でとなえかえして神前にむれあつまったひとびとに聞かせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Each tube is modeled after each crop kind and one of the tubes are broke on the shrine floor and the ranking of crops is called following the fortune telling of God and Shatei (lower-rank Shinto priest) repeats it loudly to the audience in front of the alter and after all the 42 kinds is called and the ceremony is finished, the list is hung in front of the shrine.</e>
<cmt>社丁は社人として訳出しました。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Each tube is modeled after a type of crop; one of the tubes is broken on the shrine floor, after which the ranking of crops is called in accordance with the gods&apos; fortune telling, and the Shatei (lower-rank Shinto priest) repeats it loudly to the audience gathered in front of the alter.</e>
<cmt>Rewrote.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Each tube is modeled after a type of crop; one of the tubes is broken on the shrine floor, after which the ranking of crops is called in accordance with the gods&apos; fortune telling, and the Shatei (lower-rank Shinto priest) repeats it loudly to the audience gathered in front of the alter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>42種のすべてをおわって式を終了し、等級を記入した目録を社前に掲示した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After all 42 kinds are called and the ceremony is finished, the list is hung in front of the shrine.</e>
<cmt>Rewrote.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After all 42 kinds are called and the ceremony is finished, the list is hung in front of the shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Nnh(id:474), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>