<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>海人 (能)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ama (Noh) (traditional masked dance-drama)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ama (Noh play)</e>
<cmt>他のファイルと統一しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ama (Noh play)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>海人（あま、別表記海士）は、能作品のひとつ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ama (otherwise written as &apos;海士&apos;) is one of the plays of Noh.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ama (&apos;海人&apos; otherwise written as &apos;海士&apos;) is a Noh play (classical Japanese dance theater).</e>
<cmt>他のファイルと統一しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ama (&apos;海人&apos; otherwise written as &apos;海士&apos;) is a Noh play (classical Japanese dance theater).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>旧来世阿弥作ともいわれてきたが、世阿弥自身がこの能の一部について「金春の節である（申楽談儀）」と書いているところから、世阿弥の時代にはすでにこの主題の能があったことが推測される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was said to be the work of Zeami, but as Zeami himself wrote on a part of this play to be &apos;the tune of Konparu (&quot;Sarugaku Dangi&quot;, which is Zeami&apos;s talk on his own art)&apos;, it is conjectured that there was already a Noh with this title at the time of Zeami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although it has been said to be a work of Zeami, due to the fact that Zeami himself has written that a part of the play was &apos;the tune of Konparu (&quot;Sarugaku Dangi,&quot; Zeami&apos;s talk on his own art),&apos; there is speculation that a Noh piece with this title already existed at his time.</e>
<cmt>コンマを移動しました。conjectureをspeculationにしました。文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it has been said to be a work of Zeami, due to the fact that Zeami himself has written that a part of the play was &apos;the tune of Konparu (&quot;Sarugaku Dangi,&quot; Zeami&apos;s talk on his own art),&apos; there is speculation that a Noh piece with this title already existed at his time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>讃岐国志度寺の縁起、藤原氏にまつわる伝説を素材に、ドラマチックに作り上げられた作品。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a play dramatically written based on the history of Shido-ji Temple of Sanuki Province and the legend of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a play dramatically written based on the history of Shido-ji Temple in Sanuki Province and the legend of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>Ofをinにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a play dramatically written based on the history of Shido-ji Temple in Sanuki Province and the legend of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>藤原房前の出生譚や、藤原氏の女性が唐の后になったという伝説、海底に奪われた宝物をとりかえす海人の伝承、房前が志度寺に寄進したことなどを題材としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Materials for this play include the story of the birth of FUJIWARA no Fusasaki, a legend that a lady from Fujiwara clan became the empress of Tang, folklore about a diver retrieving a stolen treasure from the bottom of the sea, and Fusasaki&apos;s donation to Shido-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Materials for this play include the story of the birth of FUJIWARA no Fusasaki, a legend that a lady from Fujiwara clan became the empress of Tang (China), the folklore about a diver retrieving a stolen treasure from the bottom of the sea and Fusasaki&apos;s donation to Shido-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>唐の説明を追加しました。冠詞を追加しました。コンマを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Materials for this play include the story of the birth of FUJIWARA no Fusasaki, a legend that a lady from Fujiwara clan became the empress of Tang (China), the folklore about a diver retrieving a stolen treasure from the bottom of the sea and Fusasaki&apos;s donation to Shido-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>わが命を犠牲にしてまで子の栄達を願う母の行動を主筋に、法華経による女人成仏などの宗教性も加味した人気のある能のひとつである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is one of the popular Noh plays with the main plot about a mother who wishes for her son&apos;s success even at the cost of her own life, and an addition of religious features such as Nyonin Jobutsu (Attainment of Buddha hood by Women) through Hokke-kyo Sutra (the Lotus Sutra).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is one of the more popular Noh plays with the main plot about a mother who wishes for her son&apos;s success even at the cost of her own life, with added religious elements such as Nyonin Jobutsu (attainment of enlightenment by a woman) through Hokke-kyo Sutra (the Lotus Sutra).</e>
<cmt>Moreを追加しました。大文字を小文字にしました。buddhahoodをより一般的なenlightenmentにしました。And an addition ofをwith addedにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is one of the more popular Noh plays with the main plot about a mother who wishes for her son&apos;s success even at the cost of her own life, with added religious elements such as Nyonin Jobutsu (attainment of enlightenment by a woman) through Hokke-kyo Sutra (the Lotus Sutra).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="6">
<j>この曲のクライマックス部分「玉ノ段」は、写実性にとみ、独立した仕舞としてもよく上演される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tama no dan&apos; (column of Tama) which is the climax of this play is filled with realism, and is frequently performed as an independent Shimai (Noh dance in plain cloths).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tama no dan&apos; (column of Tama), the climax of this play, is filled with realism and is frequently performed as an independent shimai (Noh dance in plain costume).</e>
<cmt>Clothsをcostumeにしました。構成を変えました。大文字を小文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tama no dan&apos; (column of Tama), the climax of this play, is filled with realism and is frequently performed as an independent shimai (Noh dance in plain costume).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>特殊演出である小書も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are also many Kogaki (variant performance) which are special effects performances.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are also many Kogaki which are variant performances with special effects.</e>
<cmt>originalにより近いよう訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are also many Kogaki which are variant performances with special effects.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="8">
<j>幸若舞『大職冠』とも共通性がみられ、結末に縁起物語にみられるような詞章があるなど、能と他の芸能の関連性を考えるうえでも、貴重な作である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In terms of considering relations of Noh with other performing arts, Ama is a valuable play, since common features are seen with &quot;Taishokukan&quot; which is Kowaka-mai (story-telling with a simple dance), and there is existence of shi-sho (context of a poem or a book with musical components) at the end which is seen in historical stories.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In terms of considering how Noh relates to other performing arts Ama is a valuable play, due to the commonalities that can be seen with the Kowaka-mai (story-telling with a simple dance) &quot;Taishokukan&quot; and the shi-sho (context of a poem or a book with musical components) at the end which is seen in historical stories.</e>
<cmt>自然な表現にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In terms of considering how Noh relates to other performing arts Ama is a valuable play, due to the commonalities that can be seen with the Kowaka-mai (story-telling with a simple dance) &quot;Taishokukan&quot; and the shi-sho (context of a poem or a book with musical components) at the end which is seen in historical stories.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>またこの曲をモチーフとした他分野の作品（地歌『珠取海人』など）も少なくない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are other plays in other genre (such as &quot;Tamatori ama&quot; (Pearl fisherman), a jiuta (a genre of traditional songs with samisen accompaniment)) that have motifs from this play.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are quite a few other works in other genres (such as the jiuta [traditional songs with shamisen accompaniment] &quot;Tamatori ama&quot; [Pearl Fisherman]) based on this play.</e>
<cmt>genreを複数形にしました。originalにより近いよう訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are quite a few other works in other genres (such as the jiuta [traditional songs with shamisen accompaniment] &quot;Tamatori ama&quot; [Pearl Fisherman]) based on this play.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>作品構成</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Structure of the play</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Structure of the play</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Structure of the play</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>房前大臣（藤原房前）が、幼少のころに亡くした母は讃岐国志度津の人と聞かされ、菩提を弔うためその地をたずねると、その浦の海女が登場、自分が房前の母であり、龍宮に奪われた「面向不背の珠」をとりかえした経緯を物語る前段、その土地の住人が前段のストーリーを改めて語る間狂言部分、房前が妙法蓮華経で母の追善供養をしていると、龍女に姿をかえた母があらわれ供養を謝す後段からなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first part tells about the story of Fusasaki no Otodo (FUJIWARA no Fusasaki) who, on hearing his mother he had lost during childhood to have come from Shidotsu, Sanuki Province, visits there to perform religious rites for the repose of his mother&apos;s departed soul and meets a woman diver in the area who tells him that she is his mother and how she retrieved &apos;Menko huhai no tama&apos; (an oval treasure that is aesthetic from any angle) which was stolen by the Palace of the Dragon King; and there is aikyogen (comic interlude in Noh) where an inhabitant of Shidotsu recounts the story that was told in the first part; and the latter part is where Fusasaki&apos;s mother appears as Ryunyo (a form that a woman must turn into in order to rest in peace) and thanks Fusasaki for holding a mass while Fusasaki was performing a memorial service in honor of her mother with Myohorenge-kyo Sutra (the Lotus Sutra).</e>
<cmt>「龍女」の読み方や説明については、『能楽鑑賞百一番』（淡交社）や『能楽ハンドブック』（三省堂）などを参考に致しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first part tells the story of Fusasaki no Otodo (FUJIWARA no Fusasaki) who, on hearing that his mother he had lost during childhood had come from Shidotsu, Sanuki Province, visits there to perform religious rites for the repose of her departed soul; there, he meets a female diver from the area who tells him that she is his mother and how she had retrieved &apos;Menko huhai no tama&apos; (an oval treasure that shows the frontal figure from any angle) which was stolen by the Palace of the Dragon King; this is followed by the aikyogen (comic interlude) where an inhabitant of Shidotsu recounts the story that was told in the first part; and in the latter part Fusasaki&apos;s mother appears as Ryunyo (a form that a woman must turn into in order to rest in peace) and thanks Fusasaki for the memorial service featuring the Myohorenge-kyo Sutra (the Lotus Sutra) he is performing in honor of her.</e>
<cmt>区切りを変えました。womanをfemaleにしました。宝の説明を変えました。最終部分の構成を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first part tells the story of Fusasaki no Otodo (FUJIWARA no Fusasaki) who, on hearing that his mother he had lost during childhood had come from Shidotsu, Sanuki Province, visits there to perform religious rites for the repose of her departed soul; there, he meets a female diver from the area who tells him that she is his mother and how she had retrieved &apos;Menko huhai no tama&apos; (an oval treasure that shows the frontal figure from any angle) which was stolen by the Palace of the Dragon King; this is followed by the aikyogen (comic interlude) where an inhabitant of Shidotsu recounts the story that was told in the first part; and in the latter part Fusasaki&apos;s mother appears as Ryunyo (a form that a woman must turn into in order to rest in peace) and thanks Fusasaki for the memorial service featuring the Myohorenge-kyo Sutra (the Lotus Sutra) he is performing in honor of her.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>前段</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first part</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">First Half</e>
<cmt>他のファイルと統一しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">First Half</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>【登場人物】</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Characters&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Characters&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Characters&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>能シテ　海人</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Noh shite (main role) A diver</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Noh shite (main role): Diver</e>
<cmt>他のファイルと統一しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Noh shite (main role): Diver</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>能シテ　房前大臣</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Noh shite Fusasaki no Otodo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Noh shite: Fusasaki no Otodo</e>
<cmt>他のファイルと統一しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Noh shite: Fusasaki no Otodo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>能ワキ　房前の従者</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">No waki (supporting role) Fusasaki&apos;s retainer</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">No waki (supporting role): Fusasaki&apos;s retainer</e>
<cmt>他のファイルと統一しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">No waki (supporting role): Fusasaki&apos;s retainer</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>能ワキ　房前の従者二人</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">No waki Fusasaki&apos;s two retainers</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">No waki: Fusasaki&apos;s two retainers</e>
<cmt>他のファイルと統一しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">No waki: Fusasaki&apos;s two retainers</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="16">
<j>13歳の房前大臣は母が亡くなった地、讃岐国房前の地におもむく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thirteen year old Fusasaki no Otodo visits the land of Fusasaki, Sanuki Province, where his mother died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thirteen-year-old Fusasaki no Otodo visits the land of Fusasaki, Sanuki Province, where his mother died.</e>
<cmt>-を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thirteen-year-old Fusasaki no Otodo visits the land of Fusasaki, Sanuki Province, where his mother died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>従者（ワキ、ワキヅレ）による奈良、摂津国、淡路国、鳴門の道行きが謡われ、志度の浦に到着。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His pilgrim with his retainers (Waki (supporting actor) and Wakitsure (companion who appears with the supporting actor in a Noh play)) through Nara, Settsu Province, Awaji Province, and Naruto are recited, and they reach Shido no ura (Shido Bay).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His pilgrim with his retainers (Waki and Wakizure [companion appearing with the supporting actor]) through Nara, Settsu Province, Awaji Province and Naruto are recited, and they reach Shido no ura (Shido Bay).</e>
<cmt>ワキ等の説明を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His pilgrim with his retainers (Waki and Wakizure [companion appearing with the supporting actor]) through Nara, Settsu Province, Awaji Province and Naruto are recited, and they reach Shido no ura (Shido Bay).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>従者がこの地のいわれを聞きたいというと、そこにひとりの海女が登場する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the retainer says he wants to know the history of this land, a woman diver appears in the scene.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the retainer says he wants to know the history of this land, a female diver appears.</e>
<cmt>womanをfemaleにしました。In the sceneを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the retainer says he wants to know the history of this land, a female diver appears.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>海女は「志度寺の近くに住むけれども、仏道に反する殺生をしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The woman diver says in a soliloquy, &apos;I live near Shido-ji Temple, but destructs life which is against the teachings of Buddha.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The diver says in a soliloquy, &apos;I live near Shido-ji Temple, but I destruct life, which is against the teachings of Buddha.</e>
<cmt>womanを削除しました。（以下同様）主語を追加し、動詞を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The diver says in a soliloquy, &apos;I live near Shido-ji Temple, but I destruct life, which is against the teachings of Buddha.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>伊勢や須磨のように風流の心をはぐくむような土地柄でもない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This land is not fit to cultivate furyu (splendor) to the mind like in Ise and Suma.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And this land is not fit to cultivate furyu (splendor) to the mind like Ise and Suma.</e>
<cmt>Andを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And this land is not fit to cultivate furyu (splendor) to the mind like Ise and Suma.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>しかし、そんなことをいってもいられない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But I cannot keep on saying such things.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But I cannot keep on saying such things.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But I cannot keep on saying such things.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>仕事をしよう」と独白する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">I must work.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">I must work.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">I must work.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="23">
<j>従者が彼女に「海底の藻をとってきてください」と頼むと海女は「空腹でいらっしゃるなら、ここに持っている藻をおあがりください」と応える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the retainer says &apos;Could you please pick seaweed from the bottom of the sea?&apos;, she replies &apos;If you are hungry, please have the seaweed I have in my hands.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the retainer says &apos;Could you please pick seaweed from the bottom of the sea?&quot; she replies, &apos;If you are hungry, please have the seaweed I have in my hands.&apos;</e>
<cmt>コンマを移動しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the retainer says &apos;Could you please pick seaweed from the bottom of the sea?&quot; she replies, &apos;If you are hungry, please have the seaweed I have in my hands.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>従者は「そうではないのだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The retainer says, &apos;That is not what I meant.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The retainer says, &apos;That is not what I meant.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The retainer says, &apos;That is not what I meant.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>海に映る月をご覧になるのに、藻がじゃまになるのだ」という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The seaweed gets in the way when my master wants to see the moon reflecting on the ocean.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The seaweed gets in the way when my master wants to see the moon reflecting on the ocean.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The seaweed gets in the way when my master wants to see the moon reflecting on the ocean.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>それを聞いた海女は「昔もそのようなことがあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On hearing this, the woman diver says with deep emotion, &apos;Something like this happened, too, a long time ago.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On hearing this, the diver says with deep emotion, &apos;Something like this happened, a long time ago.</e>
<cmt>tooを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On hearing this, the diver says with deep emotion, &apos;Something like this happened, a long time ago.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>海底の珠をとってこいとのことだった」と感慨深かげに言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">I was told to go fetch an orb from the bottom of the ocean.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">I was told to go fetch an orb from the bottom of the ocean.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">I was told to go fetch an orb from the bottom of the ocean.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>その折のことを語ってほしいという従者の頼みに海女は次のように語り始める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The retainer requests her to tell the story about that occasion, and she begins to tell the story as follows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The retainer asks her to tell the story of that occasion, and she begins to tell the following story.</e>
<cmt>aboutをofにしました。The story as followsをthe following storyにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The retainer asks her to tell the story of that occasion, and she begins to tell the following story.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="29">
<j>「今の大臣淡海公（藤原不比等）の妹君が唐の妃になられるにあたって、唐の高宗 (唐)皇帝から興福寺に三つの宝物が贈られました。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the younger sister of the present Otodo Tankaiko (FUJIWARA no Fuhito) was to become the empress of Tung, three treasures were sent to Koufuku-ji temple from Emperor Gojong (Tang).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the younger sister of the present Otodo Tankaiko (FUJIWARA no Fuhito) was to become the empress of Tang, three treasures were sent to Koufuku-ji Temple from Emperor Gao Zong (Tang).</e>
<cmt>「&apos;」を追加しました。綴りを修正しました。templeを大文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the younger sister of the present Otodo Tankaiko (FUJIWARA no Fuhito) was to become the empress of Tang, three treasures were sent to Koufuku-ji Temple from Emperor Gao Zong (Tang).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>そのうちのひとつ『面向不背の珠（釈迦の像が必ず正面にみえる不思議な宝珠）』をこの地で竜宮にとられてしまいました。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among them, &quot;Menko huhai no tama (a strange oval treasure that always reflects the full face image of Shaka from every angle)&quot; was stolen in this land by the Palace of the Dragon King.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among them, the &quot;Menko huhai no tama (a strange oval treasure that always reflects the frontal image of Shaka from every angle)&quot; was stolen in this land by the Palace of the Dragon King.</e>
<cmt>冠詞を追加しました。Full faceをfrontalにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among them, the &quot;Menko huhai no tama (a strange oval treasure that always reflects the frontal image of Shaka from every angle)&quot; was stolen in this land by the Palace of the Dragon King.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>大臣はその珠を奪い返すため身をやつしてこの地に来られ、海人乙女と契りを結ばれました。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Otodo disguised himself and came to this land to retrieve the treasure, and he married an amaotome (a woman diver).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Otodo disguised himself and came to this land to retrieve the treasure, and he married an amaotome (a female diver).</e>
<cmt>womanをfemaleにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Otodo disguised himself and came to this land to retrieve the treasure, and he married an amaotome (a female diver).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>そのとき生まれたのが房前の大臣です」と。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The baby born on this occasion was Fusasaki no Otodo.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The baby born on this occasion was Fusasaki no Otodo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The baby born on this occasion was Fusasaki no Otodo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>房前はそれを聞き「われこそ房前大臣である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On hearing this, Fusasaki answers, &apos;I am that very Fusasaki no Otodo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On hearing this, Fusasaki answers, &apos;I am that very Fusasaki no Otodo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On hearing this, Fusasaki answers, &apos;I am that very Fusasaki no Otodo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>わが母は志度の浦の海女ときかされてここに来たのだ」と名告る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">I came here because I was told my mother was a woman diver in Shido no ura.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">I came here because I was told my mother was a diver in Shido no ura.&apos;</e>
<cmt>womanを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">I came here because I was told my mother was a diver in Shido no ura.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>海女はさらに、珠を取り返したときのことを語る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The woman diver continues to tell the story of how the orb was retrieved.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The diver continues to tell the story of how the orb was retrieved.</e>
<cmt>womanを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The diver continues to tell the story of how the orb was retrieved.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="36">
<j>「もし珠をとってきたら、この子を世継ぎとしてくださるという約束に、海女は命を惜しまず海中に飛び入ったのです」という語りから能地謡にあわせての所作になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moves and steps according to Noh-jiutai (Noh chorus) begin with the words, &apos; Given a promise that my son would be made a successor if the treasure was retrieved, I jumped into the ocean without holding onto my life.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moves and steps according to Noh-jiutai (Noh chorus) begin with the words, &apos;Given a promise that her son would be made a successor if the treasure was retrieved, she jumped into the ocean without a care for her own life.&apos;</e>
<cmt>my等を全てsheにしました。Holding onto lifeをa care for lifeにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moves and steps according to Noh-jiutai (Noh chorus) begin with the words, &apos;Given a promise that her son would be made a successor if the treasure was retrieved, she jumped into the ocean without a care for her own life.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>玉ノ段</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tama no dan (column of Tama)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tama no Dan (Column of Tama)</e>
<cmt>タイトルなので大文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tama no Dan (Column of Tama)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="37">
<j>「空はひとつに雲の波、煙の波を凌ぎつつ、海漫々と分け入りて」やっと竜宮につくと、三十丈の宝塔の頂にその珠がまつられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The sky was nothing but waves of clouds, and overcoming the smoky waves, going deeper in to the sea&apos; and finally reaching the Palace of the Dragon King, the oval treasure is mounted on the top of a pagoda which was about 90 meters tall.</e>
<cmt>「空はひとつに雲の波、煙の波を凌ぎつつ、海漫々と分け入りて」は、可能な範囲で訳出致しましたが、意味解釈が困難なため正確ではありません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was but one sky, she weaved through clouds of wavese and smoke of waves, deeper and deeper into the sea,&apos; until finally reaching the Palace of the Dragon King, where the oval treasure was mounted on top of a 90-meter-tall pagoda.</e>
<cmt>訳し直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was but one sky, she weaved through clouds of wavese and smoke of waves, deeper and deeper into the sea,&apos; until finally reaching the Palace of the Dragon King, where the oval treasure was mounted on top of a 90-meter-tall pagoda.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>まわりには八大竜王や悪魚、鰐(わに)がとりまいている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around the pagoda are Hachidai Ryuo (Eight Dragon Kings), evil fishes, and alligators.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around the pagoda are Hachidai Ryuo (Eight Dragon Kings), evil fish and alligators.</e>
<cmt>Fishを単数形にしました。コンマを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around the pagoda are Hachidai Ryuo (Eight Dragon Kings), evil fish and alligators.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>志度の観音菩薩たすけたまえと、剣を手に竜宮に飛び入ると、竜たちはぱっと退いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jumping into the palace with a dagger in one hand and prayers to Kannon Bosatsu (Kannon Buddhisattva) in Shido to please help her, the dragons retreat in an instant.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When she jumped into the palace with a dagger in one hand and dedicating prayers to Kannon Bosatsu (Kannon Buddhisattva) in Shido to please help her, the dragons retreated in an instant.</e>
<cmt>時制を修正しました。dedicatingを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When she jumped into the palace with a dagger in one hand and dedicating prayers to Kannon Bosatsu (Kannon Buddhisattva) in Shido to please help her, the dragons retreated in an instant.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>その隙に宝珠を盗み取って逃げようとするのを竜が追ってくる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When she steals the oval treasure in that moment, the dragons chase her running away.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She took the opportunity to steal the oval treasure and made her escape, the dragons in pursuit.</e>
<cmt>訳し直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She took the opportunity to steal the oval treasure and made her escape, the dragons in pursuit.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>竜宮では死人を忌むということなので、海女は自分の乳の下を掻き切って、珠を押し込め海底に倒れると、近づくものもない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the dead are abhorred in the palace, the woman diver cuts the bottom of her breast, hides the treasure, and collapses to the bottom of the sea; not one being comes near.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the dead are abhorred in the palace, the diver cut the bottom of her breast, hid the treasure, and collapsed at the bottom of the sea; not one being came near.</e>
<cmt>womanを削除しました。時制を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the dead are abhorred in the palace, the diver cut the bottom of her breast, hid the treasure, and collapsed at the bottom of the sea; not one being came near.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>そのとき力をこめて命綱をひけば、海上の人々によって命綱がひきあげられ、海女は海上に浮かび上がった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She pulls the lifeline, and those above the sea pull up the rope, and the woman diver floats to the surface.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She tugged hard at her lifeline and those above the sea pulled up the rope, and the diver floated to the surface.</e>
<cmt>pullをtug hardにしました。時制を修正しました。womanを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She tugged hard at her lifeline and those above the sea pulled up the rope, and the diver floated to the surface.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>大臣は傷つき息もたえだえになった海女をみて嘆き悲しむが、海女の「わが乳のあたりを御覧ぜ」との末期の言葉に傷跡をみると面向不背の珠がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Otodo grieves and mourns on seeing the wounded and breathless woman diver, but by her last word &apos;Look around my breast&apos;, he finds the Menko huhai no tama in her wound.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Otodo grieved and mourned on seeing the wounded and breathless diver, but with her dying words, &apos;look around my breast,&apos; he found the Menko huhai no tama in her wound.</e>
<cmt>womanを削除しました。時制を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Otodo grieved and mourned on seeing the wounded and breathless diver, but with her dying words, &apos;look around my breast,&apos; he found the Menko huhai no tama in her wound.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>こうして海女は命を落としたが、その子は房前の大臣となったのだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The woman diver dies in this way, but her son becomes Fusasaki no Otodo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The diver died in this way, but her son became Fusasaki no Otodo.</e>
<cmt>womanを削除しました。時制を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The diver died in this way, but her son became Fusasaki no Otodo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="45">
<j>こう語った海女は「われこそあなたの母、海人の幽霊です。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The woman diver that told the story says, &apos;I am your mother, the ghost of that diver.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On finishing her story the diver says, &apos;I am your mother, the ghost of that diver.</e>
<cmt>前半を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On finishing her story the diver says, &apos;I am your mother, the ghost of that diver.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>この手紙を御覧になってわが菩提を弔ってください」と、房前に手紙をわたし朝の海に消えていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Please read this letter and perform religious rites to repose my departed soul&apos;, and handed him a letter and disappeared in to the morning sea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Please read this letter and perform religious rites to repose my departed soul,&apos; and hands him a letter and disappears into the morning sea.</e>
<cmt>コンマを移動しました。時制を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Please read this letter and perform religious rites to repose my departed soul,&apos; and hands him a letter and disappears into the morning sea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>間狂言</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Aikyogen</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Aikyogen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Aikyogen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="47">
<j>【登場人物】</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Characters&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Characters&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Characters&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>ワキ　房前の従者</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Waki Fusasaki&apos;s retainer</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Waki: Fusasaki&apos;s retainer</e>
<cmt>他のファイルと統一しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Waki: Fusasaki&apos;s retainer</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>狂言間狂言　所の者（その土地の住人）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyogen aikyogen (comic interlude in Noh) (An inhabitant of the land)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyogen aikyogen (comic interlude in Noh): A local (inhabitant of the land)</e>
<cmt>他のファイルと統一しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyogen aikyogen (comic interlude in Noh): A local (inhabitant of the land)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="50">
<j>そこへ通りかかったこの土地の住人に、従者が「海中より珠をとってきた海人のことを知っていたら語ってくれ」というと、「奈良の大織冠の娘で淡海公の妹にあたる光伯女は、大変な美人で高宗皇帝の后となられました。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the retainer says to the inhabitant of the land who was passing by, &apos;Tell us if you know the story of the diver who retrieved an orb from the sea&apos;, the inhabitant answers &apos;She was 光伯女, the daughter of Taishokkan (Holder of the Grand Crown) from Nara and a younger sister of Tankaiko; she was very beautiful and became the empress of Emperor Gojong.</e>
<cmt>「光伯女」の正しい読み方が不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the retainer says to an inhabitant of the land who was passing by, &apos;Tell us if you know the story of the diver who retrieved an orb from the sea,&apos; the inhabitant answers, &apos;The daughter of Mitsunori, the Taishokkan (Holder of the Grand Crown) from Nara who was Lord Tankai&apos;s younger sister, was very beautiful and became the empress of Emperor Gojong.</e>
<cmt>光伯女を光白の娘と訳出しました。後半を海女と光伯女を誤解しないようにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the retainer says to an inhabitant of the land who was passing by, &apos;Tell us if you know the story of the diver who retrieved an orb from the sea,&apos; the inhabitant answers, &apos;The daughter of Mitsunori, the Taishokkan (Holder of the Grand Crown) from Nara who was Lord Tankai&apos;s younger sister, was very beautiful and became the empress of Emperor Gojong.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>奈良の興福寺は光伯女の氏寺なので、三種の宝物を唐から渡されたのです。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The three treasures were sent from Tang, since Koufuku-ji Temple of Nara was 光伯女&apos;s Uji-dera Temple (temple built for praying clan&apos;s glory).</e>
<cmt>「光伯女」の正しい読み方が不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The three treasures were sent from Tang, since Koufuku-ji Temple of Nara was Mitsunori&apos;s daughter&apos;s Uji-dera Temple (temple built for praying clan&apos;s glory).</e>
<cmt>光伯女を光白の娘と訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The three treasures were sent from Tang, since Koufuku-ji Temple of Nara was Mitsunori&apos;s daughter&apos;s Uji-dera Temple (temple built for praying clan&apos;s glory).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>そのひとつ、面向不背の珠を竜宮の住人は奪い取りたく思ったのですが、船頭が優秀で取ることができません。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among them, the inhabitants of the Palace of the Dragon King wanted to steal Menko huhai no tama, but they were unable to do so because the boatmen were smart.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among them, the inhabitants of the Palace of the Dragon King wanted to steal Menko huhai no tama, but they were unable to do so because the boatmen were very capable.</e>
<cmt>Smartをcapableにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among them, the inhabitants of the Palace of the Dragon King wanted to steal Menko huhai no tama, but they were unable to do so because the boatmen were very capable.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>しかし、とうとうこの浦の近くで取ってしまいました。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But, they have finally stolen it near this bay.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But, they finally stole it near this bay.</e>
<cmt>時制を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But, they finally stole it near this bay.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>淡海大臣は残念に思って、身をやつしてこの浦に来られ、海人乙女と契り一子をもうけ、色々のお約束をされて、海女のおかげでその珠を取りかえすことができました。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tankai no Otodo was disappointed, and came to this land in disguise; he married an amaotome and had a son, and through many promises, he was able to retrieve the orb owing to the woman diver.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tankai no Otodo was disappointed, and came to this land in disguise; he married an amaotome and had a son, and through many promises, he was able to retrieve the orb owing to the diver.</e>
<cmt>womanを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tankai no Otodo was disappointed, and came to this land in disguise; he married an amaotome and had a son, and through many promises, he was able to retrieve the orb owing to the diver.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>その珠をはじめて御覧になった島は新珠島という名がつきました。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The island where he first saw the orb was named Shinju-jima Island.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The island where he first saw the orb was named Shinju-jima Island.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The island where he first saw the orb was named Shinju-jima Island.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>またその時生まれたお子はこの浦の名から房前の大臣といわれるそうです」と語り「しかし、どうしてそうようなことをお尋ねになるのですか」と問う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, the baby born on this occasion was referred to as Fusasaki no Otodo from the name of this bay&apos;, and the inhabitant says, &apos; Why do you ask such a thing?&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, the baby born on this occasion was referred to as Fusasaki no Otodo from the name of this bay,&apos; and the inhabitant says, &apos;Why do you ask such a thing?&apos;</e>
<cmt>コンマを移動しました。スペースを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, the baby born on this occasion was referred to as Fusasaki no Otodo from the name of this bay,&apos; and the inhabitant says, &apos;Why do you ask such a thing?&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="57">
<j>従者は「ここにおられるのがその房前の大臣です。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The retainer answers &apos;The person here is the very Fusasaki no Otodo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The retainer answers &apos;The person here is the very Fusasaki no Otodo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The retainer answers &apos;The person here is the very Fusasaki no Otodo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>御母のお弔いのためにこれから管弦講という法要を催されるので、管弦の役者は集まるように言ってください。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is going to hold Buddhist memorial service known as kangenko (pipes, strings, and preaching) to mourn for his mother, so please gather those who perform kangen (gagaku piece without dance).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is going to hold Buddhist memorial service known as kangenko (pipes, strings, and preaching) to mourn for his mother, so please gather those who perform kangen (gagaku piece without dance).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is going to hold Buddhist memorial service known as kangenko (pipes, strings, and preaching) to mourn for his mother, so please gather those who perform kangen (gagaku piece without dance).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>また七日の間、殺生はやめるように」と告げる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And, for seven days, stop the destruction of life.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And, for seven days, stop the destruction of life.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And, for seven days, stop the destruction of life.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>そのことを触れ回ることを約束して土地の住人は去る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The inhabitant of the land leaves by promising to spread his words to the people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The inhabitant of the land leaves, promising to spread the word.</e>
<cmt>後半を簡潔にまとめました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The inhabitant of the land leaves, promising to spread the word.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>後段</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The latter part</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Second Half</e>
<cmt>他のファイルと統一しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Second Half</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="61">
<j>【登場人物】</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Characters&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Characters&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Characters&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>能シテ　龍女</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Noh shite Ryunyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Noh shite: Ryunyo</e>
<cmt>他のファイルと統一しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Noh shite: Ryunyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>能シテ　房前大臣</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Noh shite Fusasaki no Otodo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Noh shite: Fusasaki no Otodo</e>
<cmt>他のファイルと統一しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Noh shite: Fusasaki no Otodo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>能ワキ　房前の従者</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">No waki Fusasaki&apos;s retainer</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">No waki: Fusasaki&apos;s retainer</e>
<cmt>他のファイルと統一しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">No waki: Fusasaki&apos;s retainer</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>能ワキ　房前の従者二人</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">No waki Fusasaki&apos;s two retainers</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">No waki: Fusasaki&apos;s two retainers</e>
<cmt>他のファイルと統一しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">No waki: Fusasaki&apos;s two retainers</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="66">
<j>従者は房前にさきほど海女から渡された手紙を読むように勧める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The retainer advises Fusasaki to read the letter which was handed to him by the woman diver.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The retainer advises Fusasaki to read the letter which was handed to him by the female diver.</e>
<cmt>womanをfemaleにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The retainer advises Fusasaki to read the letter which was handed to him by the female diver.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>房前はその手紙をひらく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fusasaki opens the letter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fusasaki opens the letter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fusasaki opens the letter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>そこには「十三年の間わたしを弔う人とてなく冥土の暗闇におります。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It says: &apos;For thirteen years, I am in the darkness of the world of the dead without anyone to mourn me.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It says: &apos;For thirteen years, I have been in the darkness of the world of the dead without anyone to mourn me.</e>
<cmt>時制を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It says: &apos;For thirteen years, I have been in the darkness of the world of the dead without anyone to mourn me.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>あなたが孝行ならわが闇を助けてください」とある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If you are thoughtful, please help me out of this darkness.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If you are thoughtful, please help me out of this darkness.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If you are thoughtful, please help me out of this darkness.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>地謡によって「妙法蓮華経の読誦やさまざまな法要をして善をなそう」と謡われると、龍女に姿をかえた先ほどの海女が登場する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Jiutai sings &apos;Perform good deeds by reading the Myohorenge-kyo Sutra and through various Buddhist memorial services&apos;, the woman diver disguised as ryunyo appears in the scene.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Jiutai sings &apos;Perform good deeds by reading the Myohorenge-kyo Sutra and through various Buddhist memorial services,&apos; the diver from the previous half appears as ryunyo.</e>
<cmt>コンマを移動しました。後半を訳し直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Jiutai sings &apos;Perform good deeds by reading the Myohorenge-kyo Sutra and through various Buddhist memorial services,&apos; the diver from the previous half appears as ryunyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>「ありがたいお弔い、なおなお法華経をお誦みください」といって、経にあわせて舞いはじめる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She starts to dance along the sutra saying, &apos;A gracious mourning, please continue reading the Lotus sutra.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She starts to dance along the sutra saying, &apos;A gracious mourning, please continue reading the Lotus sutra.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She starts to dance along the sutra saying, &apos;A gracious mourning, please continue reading the Lotus sutra.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>やがて「舞事」になり、「今この経の功徳にて」成仏した礼をのべ、地謡の「龍女成仏、さてこそ讃州志度寺と号し、毎年八講、朝暮の勤行、仏法繁昌の霊地となるも、この孝養と承る（龍女は成仏しました。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soon it becomes &apos;mai-goto&apos; (instrumental dances) and she thanks for her jobutsu (die peacefully) through &apos;merit of the sutra&apos;, and with the dance along Jiutai singing, &apos;今この経の功徳にて&apos;成仏した礼をのべ、地謡の&apos;龍女成仏、さてこそ讃州志度寺と号し、毎年八講、朝暮の勤行、仏法繁昌の霊地となるも、この孝養と承る (Ryunyo has died peacefully.</e>
<cmt>「龍女成仏、さてこそ讃州志度寺と号し、毎年八講、朝暮の勤行、仏法繁昌の霊地となるも、この孝養と承る・・・は、下に訳があるため原文のままと致しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soon it becomes &apos;mai-goto&apos; (instrumental dance) and she gives thanks for her jobutsu (die peacefully) through &apos;the merit of the sutra,&apos; and with the dance to the Jiutai singing, &apos;Ryunyo has died peacefully.</e>
<cmt>唄の意訳のみを残しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soon it becomes &apos;mai-goto&apos; (instrumental dance) and she gives thanks for her jobutsu (die peacefully) through &apos;the merit of the sutra,&apos; and with the dance to the Jiutai singing, &apos;Ryunyo has died peacefully.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>このように志度寺と号して、毎年の法華経読誦の法要や朝夕の勤行をする仏教の盛んな地となったのも、この房前大臣の親孝行のおかげなのです）」で舞い納め能は終わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is because of the filial deeds of Fusasaki no Otodo that this temple is named Shido-ji, and that this land a place flourishing in Buddhism with the annual Buddhist memorial services by hailing Lotus Sutra and devotional exercises performed in mornings and evenings&apos;, the play ends.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is because of the filial deeds of Fusasaki no Otodo that this temple is named Shido-ji, and this land a place flourishing in Buddhism with the annual Buddhist memorial services by hailing the Lotus Sutra and devotional exercises performed in mornings and evenings,&apos; the play ends.</e>
<cmt>コンマを移動しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is because of the filial deeds of Fusasaki no Otodo that this temple is named Shido-ji, and this land a place flourishing in Buddhism with the annual Buddhist memorial services by hailing the Lotus Sutra and devotional exercises performed in mornings and evenings,&apos; the play ends.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Fryed-peach(id:63402), Sat666(id:127263), Mymelo(id:122034), Dr jimmy(id:111486), Miya(id:1881), R28Bot(id:177951), Charenji(id:7908), ささがに(id:228586), Toki-ho(id:10691), Toto-tarou(id:16648), 樒(id:35770), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>