<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>親子丼</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oyako-don</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oyako-don</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oyakodon (bowl of rice with chicken and egg)</e>
<cmt>補足を追加しました。他の丼ものの表現と合わせ（カツ丼など）、ハイフンを削除してOyakodon としました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>親子丼（おやこどん、おやこどんぶり）とは、鶏肉、玉ねぎなどを割り下で煮て鶏卵でとじ、ご飯の上に乗せた料理で丼物の一種。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oyako-don is one of rice bowl dishes that boils chicken and onion in warishita (stock mixed with soy sauce, mirin and sugar) and put it on the rice with egg.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oyako-don is a rice bowl dish that uses boiled chicken and onion in warishita (stock mixed with soy sauce, mirin and sugar) over rice with egg.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oyakodon is a rice bowl dish that uses boiled chicken and onion in warishita (stock mixed with soy sauce, mirin and sugar) over rice with egg.</e>
<cmt>親子丼→Oyakodon としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>「親子丼」という名前は鶏の肉と鶏の卵を使うことに由来する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name &apos;Oyako-don&apos; is derived from the fact that both chicken meat and chicken egg are used for the dish.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name &apos;Oyako-don&apos; (&quot;oya&quot; meaning parent and &quot;ko&quot; meaning child) is derived from the fact that both chicken meat and chicken egg are used for the dish.</e>
<cmt>added information</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name &apos;oyakodon&apos; (&quot;oya&quot; meaning parent and &quot;ko&quot; meaning child) is derived from the fact that both chicken meat and chicken egg are used for the dish.</e>
<cmt>親子丼→Oyakodon としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>親子どんがよく使われる呼称であるが、地方によっては親子どんぶりと言うこともある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oyako-don is most common name, but some regions call it Oyako-donburi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oyako-don is the most common name, but some regions call it Oyako-donburi.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oyakodon is the most common name, but some regions call it Oyako-donburi.</e>
<cmt>親子丼→Oyakodon としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>東京都中央区日本橋にある鳥料理専門店「玉ひで」の五代目当主の妻「山田とく」が1891年に考案したのがはじめである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toku YAMADA,&apos; the wife of the fifth family head of spatchcock restaurant &apos;Tamahide&apos; in Nihonbashi, Chuo Ward, Tokyo Prefecture first invented the dish.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toku YAMADA,&apos; the wife of the fifth family head of the spatchcock restaurant &apos;Tamahide&apos; in Nihonbashi, Chuo Ward, Tokyo Prefecture first invented the dish.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toku YAMADA, the wife of the fifth family head of the spatchcock restaurant &apos;Tamahide&apos; in Nihonbashi, Chuo Ward, Tokyo, first invented the dish in 1891.</e>
<cmt>文頭のシングルクォーテーションを削除しました。1891年を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>元祖親子丼は、割り下で鶏肉のみを煮て卵とじにしたもので、現在のように玉ねぎやミツバ等の材料は使われていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The originator of Oyako-don only used chicken boiled in warishita and served with egg, so ingredients such as onion and Japanese honewort were not used as it is today.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The original Oyako-don only used chicken boiled in warishita and served with egg, ingredients such as onion and Japanese honewort were not used as they are today.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The original oyakodon only used chicken boiled in warishita and served with egg, ingredients such as onion and Japanese honewort were not used as they are today.</e>
<cmt>親子丼→Oyakodon としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="6">
<j>また、派生としてサケの刺身または鮭フレークとイクラをのせたものを指すこともある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, as its derivative, it sometimes indicate the dish with raw salmon or salmon flake and salmon caviar</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, as it is a derivative of oyako-don, the term is sometimes used to refer to a dish with raw salmon or salmon flake and salmon caviar</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, as it is a derivative of oyakodon, the term is sometimes used to refer to a dish with raw salmon or salmon flake and salmon caviar.</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>この場合、区別するために海鮮親子丼などともよばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this occasion, it is called Kaisen Oyako-don (Seafood Oyako-don) to distinguish it from Oyako-don.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this case, it may be called Kaisen Oyako-don (Seafood Oyako-don) to distinguish it from Oyako-don.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this case, it may be called Kaisen oyakodon (Seafood oyakodon) to distinguish it from oyakodon.</e>
<cmt>親子丼→Oyakodon としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="8">
<j>親子丼の具材をかけうどんに乗せた親子うどんというのもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is Oyako-udon (noodle) that is served with the ingredients of Oyako-don on udon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is another variation, Oyako-udon (noodle) which is served with the ingredients of Oyako-don with udon noodles.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is another variation, oyako-udon (noodle) which is served with the ingredients of oyakodon with udon noodles.</e>
<cmt>親子丼→Oyakodon としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Arufu(id:733), Zoominshiodome(id:149045), 霧木諒二(id:9795), マクガイア(id:33346), Eskimbot(id:29676), Roger(id:9883), Seibuabina(id:37532), LaaknorBot(id:220851), ShikiH(id:181574), Hykw-a4(id:14184), Baldanders(id:81163), Goch(id:17164), Opponent(id:720), Rusk(id:9895), 準急三条(id:25072), Tanuki Z(id:612), Michey.M(id:906), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), Mochi(id:9489), Nevylax(id:38464), GURAX(id:107578), Nogyer(id:57650), Shikai shaw(id:14306), Iburi(id:48097), 扇風機のせんちゃん(id:161810), Yas(id:739), Ｋｓ(id:15319), Nekojikonn(id:182106), 1029man(id:93235), Hotei(id:7664), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>