<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>松花堂弁当</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shokado bento (meal box).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shokado bento (meal box).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shokado bento</e>
<cmt>弁当箱ではなく弁当のことなので括弧書き削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>松花堂弁当（しょうかどうべんとう）は、中に十字形の仕切りがあり、縁の高いかぶせ蓋のある弁当箱を用いた弁当。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Shokado bento (meal box) container is divided internally into parts in a cross shape and hashigh sides suitable for a lunch box.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Shokado bento (meal box) container is divided internally into parts in a cross shape and hashigh sides suitable for a lunch box.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shokado bento is a meal in a box, whose inside is divided into sections in a cross pattern and has a lid with high sides.</e>
<cmt>全体を書き換えましたのでご確認願います。</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>仕切りのそれぞれに刺身、焼き物、煮物、飯などを見栄え良く配置する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sashimi (sliced raw fish), grilled food, boiled food, rice etc are arranged into separate compartment divisions within the meal box to be visually appealing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sashimi (sliced raw fish), grilled food, boiled food, rice, etc. are arranged into separate compartments within the meal box to be visually appealing.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sashimi (sliced raw fish), grilled food, boiled food, rice, etc. are arranged into separate compartments within the meal box to be visually appealing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>盛り分様式としては、ごはんと数種類のおかずを組み合わせたものであり、幕の内弁当に似ているとも言える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ultimate arrangement is an assortment of rice and various dishes, and said to be somewhat similar to the Makunouchi bento (boxed meal).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ultimate arrangement is an assortment of rice and various dishes, and said to be somewhat similar to the Makunouchi bento (boxed meal).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ultimate arrangement is an assortment of rice and various dishes, and said to be somewhat similar to the Makunouchi bento (boxed meal).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>しかし源流は、幕の内弁当が本膳料理の流れを汲むものであるのに対し、松花堂弁当は懐石料理の流れを汲むものであり、歴史は大きく異なる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the history of Shokado and Makunouchi boxed meals differ substantially:, Shokado bento (boxed meals) have their origins in stylized Kaiseski tea ceremony foods, rather than the claim the origins rest with the high-grade Makunouchi boxed meals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the history of Shokado and Makunouchi boxed meals differ substantially:, Shokado bento (boxed meals) have their origins in stylized Kaiseski tea ceremony foods, rather than the claiming the origin is from high-grade Makunouchi boxed meals.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the history of Shokado and Makunouchi boxed meals differ substantially: Makunouchi bento has its origin in honzen ryori (formally arranged dinner), while Shokado bento has its origin in Kaiseski tea ceremony dishes.</e>
<cmt>全体を書き換えましたのでご確認願います。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>「松花堂」の名は、江戸時代初期の石清水八幡宮（京都府八幡市）の社僧であった松花堂昭乗（1584年 - 1639年）に因むものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name &quot;Shokado&quot; is associated with Shojo SHOKADO (1584 - 1639), a priest attached to Iwashimizu Hachimangu Shrine (Hachimangu City, Kyoto Prefecture) in the early part of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name &quot;Shokado&quot; is associated with Shojo SHOKADO (1584 - 1639), a priest attached to Iwashimizu Hachimangu Shrine (Hachimangu City, Kyoto Prefecture) in the early part of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name &apos;Shokado&apos; is associated with Shojo SHOKADO (1584 - 1639), a priest attached to Iwashimizu Hachimangu Shrine (Yawata City, Kyoto Prefecture) in the early part of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;Hachimangu City→Yawata City</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>昭乗は、農家が種入れとして使っていた器をヒントにこの形の器を作り、絵の具箱や煙草盆として使用していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shojo made the container inspired by a container used by farmers to hold seeds: a box like container with sides and used to hold tobacco.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shojo made the box inspired by a container used by farmers to hold seeds: a box like container with sides and used to hold tobacco.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shojo made the box inspired by a container used by farmers to hold seeds: a box like container with sides and used it as a paint box or a tobacco tray.</e>
<cmt>「絵の具箱」を追記し「煙草盆」も変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>その入れ物が松花堂弁当に発展したのは、それから数百年たってからである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The development of this container from these origins into the Shokado meal box took several hundred years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The development of this container from the origin into the Shokado meal box took several hundred years.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The development of this container from the origin into the Shokado meal box took several hundred years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>昭和の始め（昭和8年（1933年）頃とされている）、日本屈指の名料亭である大阪の「吉兆」の創始者である湯木貞一が八幡でこの器の話を聞き、弁当の器にすることを思いついた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the early 1930&apos;s, &quot;Kitcho&quot; Japan&apos;s preeminent restaurant in Osaka was established by Teiichi YUKI who heard about the container while at Hachiman and thought about using the container to hold food.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the early 1930&apos;s, &quot;Kitcho&quot; Japan&apos;s preeminent restaurant in Osaka was established by Teiichi YUKI who heard about the container while at Hachiman and thought about using the container to hold food.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the early 1930&apos;s, &apos;Kitcho&apos; Japan&apos;s preeminent restaurant in Osaka was established by Teiichi YUKI who heard about the container while at Yawata and thought about using the container to hold food.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;&apos;Kitcho&apos;, was の前のスペース短縮Hachiman→Yawata</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>十字形の仕切りがあることで、互いに味や匂いが移らないと考えたためである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the container was divided into sections in a cross pattern, he thought the flavors and aromas of the foods would not meld into each other.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the container was divided into sections in a cross pattern, he thought the flavors and aromas of the foods would not melt into each other.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the container was divided into sections in a cross pattern, he thought the flavors and aromas of the foods would not melt into each other.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>異説として「松花堂昭乗が、上記の十字の仕切りがはいった箱に料理を盛って、来客をもてなした」とするものもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another view is that; Shojo SHOKADO served up food in the partitioned container noted above which amused the customers. However, perhaps this is a story made up by later generations or based on a misunderstanding.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another view is that; Shojo SHOKADO served up food in the partitioned container noted above which amused his customers. However, perhaps this is a story made up by later generations or based on a misunderstanding.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another view is that; Shojo SHOKADO served up food in the partitioned container noted above which amused his customers.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>しかしながら、おそらくこれは後世の創作あるいは誤解に基づくものである</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, perhaps this is a story made up by later generations or based on a misunderstanding.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>ノートPCのThinkPadは、松花堂弁当の弁当箱をコンセプトにしてデザインされたと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has been said that the ThinkPad notebook PC owes its concept design to the Shokado bento meal box container.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has been said that the ThinkPad notebook PC owes its concept design to the Shokado bento meal box container.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has been said that the ThinkPad notebook PC owes its concept design to the Shokado bento meal box.</e>
<cmt>「bento meal box」で十分と考え container は削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 しーりん(id:176393), ととりん(id:31982), Nnh(id:474), マクガイア(id:33346), 663highland(id:18755), Kansai explorer(id:48975), Nekosuki600(id:21263), 沢田(id:40580), Comyu(id:58135), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>