<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>高麗楽</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Komagaku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Komagaku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Komagaku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>高麗楽（こまがく）は、朝鮮から日本に伝わった雅楽の一種である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Komagaku is a form of Gagaku (traditional Japanese court music), which was introduced into Japan from Korea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Komagaku is a form of Gagaku (traditional Japanese court music) that was introduced into Japan from Korea.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Komagaku is a form of Gagaku (traditional Japanese court music) that was introduced into Japan from Korea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>高麗笛、篳篥、三鼓、鉦鼓、太鼓が使われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Komagaku uses komabue (a transverse flute with six finger-holes), hichiriki (an oboe), san-no-tsuzumi (an hourglass-shaped drum), shoko (a small gong), and taiko (an ornately decorated drum).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Komagaku uses komabue (a transverse flute with six finger holes), hichiriki (an oboe), san-no-tsuzumi (an hourglass-shaped drum), shoko (a small gong) and taiko (an ornately decorated drum).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Komagaku uses komabue (a transverse flute with six finger holes), hichiriki (an oboe), san-no-tsuzumi (an hourglass-shaped drum), shoko (a small gong) and taiko (an ornately decorated drum).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>高麗楽には 高麗一越調、高麗平調、高麗小調の三種類が使われ、高麗平調など高麗楽で使われる調は道楽に使われるものより2度高い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Komagaku, there are three types of modes: Koma Ichikotsucho (E), Koma Hyojo (F#), and Koma Shocho (A); and the notes of Koma Hyojo used in Komagaku are two tones higher than the ones used in Michigaku (Gagaku music performed in marches).</e>
<cmt>原文の「高麗小調｣は「高麗双調」のことであると思われます。訳は原文通り&quot;koma shocho&quot;としましたが、正しくは&quot;koma sojo&quot;であると思われます。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Komagaku, there are three types of modes--Koma Ichikotsucho (E), Koma Hyojo (F#), and Koma Shocho (A)--and the notes of Koma Hyojo used in Komagaku are two tones higher than the ones used in Michigaku (Gagaku music performed in marches).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Komagaku, there are three types of modes--Koma Ichikotsucho (E), Koma Hyojo (F#), and Koma Shocho (A)--and the notes of Koma Hyojo used in Komagaku are two tones higher than the ones used in Michigaku (Gagaku music performed in marches).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>高麗楽の拍子には4拍子、揚拍子、唐拍子の三種類がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Komagaku has three types of rhythms: Yon-byoshi (quadruple time), Age-byoshi (a faster tempo), and Kara-byoshi (a Chinese beat).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Komagaku has three types of rhythms: Yon-byoshi (quadruple time), Age-byoshi (a faster tempo) and Kara-byoshi (a Chinese beat).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Komagaku has three types of rhythms: Yon-byoshi (quadruple time), Age-byoshi (a faster tempo) and Kara-byoshi (a Chinese beat).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>高麗楽は道楽のように来を使わず、付点のリズムを持つのが特異である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Unlike Michigaku, Komagaku uses no rai and is characterized by dotted rhythm.</e>
<cmt>来：意味解釈が困難なため訳出できず</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unlike Michigaku, Komagaku uses no rai and is characterized by dotted rhythm.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unlike Michigaku, Komagaku uses no rai and is characterized by dotted rhythm.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>高麗楽の古楽譜は三五要録と仁智要録に記録されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The classical scores of Komagaku are contained in the collections of musical notation, Sango Yoroku (score of lute biwa) and Jinchi Yoroku (score of zither koto).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The classical scores of Komagaku are contained in the collections of musical notation, Sango Yoroku (score for biwa lute) and Jinchi Yoroku (score for koto zither).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The classical scores of Komagaku are contained in the collections of musical notation, Sango Yoroku (score for biwa lute) and Jinchi Yoroku (score for koto zither).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Whdoc(id:270502), Hyolee2(id:16439), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>