<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>二陪織物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Futaeorimono (二陪織物)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Futaeorimono (double technique brocade)</e>
<cmt>二陪織物 を double technique brocade に修正しました。出典：http://www.takata-courtrobe.co.jp/enco2.htm</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Futaeorimono (double technique brocade)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>二陪織物（ふたえおりもの、ふたべおりもの）は全面に亀甲や唐草などの連続紋を織り出して地紋とし、その上に「上紋（うわもん）」と称して丸文や花鳥文などを地とは別の色糸で飛び飛びに織り出したもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Futaeorimono (or futabeorimono) is a fabric on which two kinds of patterns are arranged; the one is called jimon, running patterns of of kikko (hexagonal pattern) and karakusa (arabesque) that spread over a fablic, and the another one is called &quot;uwamon&quot;, patterns of marubumi (round pattern) and kachobumi (patterns of flowers and birds) which are woven with colored threads different from those of jimon and are arranged at random.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Futaeorimono&quot; (or &quot;Futabeorimono&quot;) is a fabric on which two kinds of patterns are arranged; the one is called &apos;jimon&apos; (textile pattern), running patterns such as kikko (hexagonal pattern) and karakusa (arabesque) that spread over a fabric, and the other called &apos;uwamon,&apos; patterns of marumon (round pattern) and kachomon (pattern of flowers and birds) which are woven with colored threads different from those of jimon and arranged at random.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Futaeorimono&quot; (or &quot;Futabeorimono&quot;) is a fabric on which two kinds of patterns are arranged; the one is called &apos;jimon&apos; (textile pattern), running patterns such as kikko (hexagonal pattern) and karakusa (arabesque) that spread over a fabric, and the other called &apos;uwamon,&apos; patterns of marumon (round pattern) and kachomon (pattern of flowers and birds) which are woven with colored threads different from those of jimon and arranged at random.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>二重織物とも書く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also written as &quot;二重織物&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also written as &quot;二重織物.&quot;</e>
<cmt>ピリオドをダブルコーテーションの中に移動しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also written as &quot;二重織物.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>普通は、横糸を刺繍糸のように浮かせた浮織物の地紋に、絵緯（えぬき。織の組織に必要な経緯《たてよこ糸》とは無関係な、紋をあらわすだけに使う色糸）を使って上紋を浮織にする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Usually, uwamon is woven with enuki (threads that are used solely for making patterns and are irrevant to keii (the warp and the weft) used for weaving a fabric) on the jimon of ukiorimono, a fabric with raised patterns that are woven by raising the weft like embroidery thread.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Usually, uwamon is woven with enuki (threads only used for making patterns and irrelevant to keii [the warp and the weft] for weaving a fabric) on the jimon of ukiorimono, a fabric with raised patterns that are woven by raising the weft like embroidery thread.</e>
<cmt>threads that are used solely for making patterns and are irrevant to keii (the warp and the weft) used for weaving a fabric を threads only used for making patterns and irrelevant to keii [the warp and the weft] for weaving a fabric に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Usually, uwamon is woven with enuki (threads only used for making patterns and irrelevant to keii [the warp and the weft] for weaving a fabric) on the jimon of ukiorimono, a fabric with raised patterns that are woven by raising the weft like embroidery thread.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>まれに地紋を堅織物にすることがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In rare cases, Kataorimono (tight-woven fabric) is also used for jimon.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In rare cases, jimon is made with Kataorimono (hard woven) style.</e>
<cmt>Kataorimono 以降を全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In rare cases, jimon is made with Kataorimono (hard woven) style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>地紋上紋ともに堅織物にしたものは「沈め織」といって区別することもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The one which uses kataorimono both for jimon and uwamon is called &quot;shizumeori&quot; and is sometimes distinguished from futaeorimono.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A fabric whose jimon and uwamon are both hard woven is called &apos;shizumeori&apos; and distinguished from futaeorimono.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A fabric whose jimon and uwamon are both hard woven is called &apos;shizumeori&apos; and distinguished from futaeorimono.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>また地紋がなく、絵緯による紋だけをあらわしたものを鎌倉時代以降唐織物と呼んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, the one which has no jimon and has only patterns woven with enuki was called karaorimono in the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, the one without jimon and has only patterns woven with enuki was called &quot;karaorimono&quot; after the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>which has no を without に修正しました。karaorimono in を &quot;karaorimono&quot; after に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, the one without jimon and has only patterns woven with enuki was called &quot;karaorimono&quot; after the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>これが能装束の唐織につながってゆく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The above is the origin of the karaori (Chinese weaving) of Noh costume.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The above is the origin of the karaori (Chinese weaving) of Noh costume.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The above is the origin of the karaori (Chinese weaving) of Noh costume.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>平安時代以降の文献に見え、特に高貴な女性が用いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term &quot;futaeorimono&quot; is seen in the documents written in the Heian period as well as in the subsequent times, and it was used by the ladies of noble family in particular.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term &quot;futaeorimono&quot; is seen in the documents written in the Heian period as well as in the subsequent times, and it was particularly used by noble women.</e>
<cmt>it was used by the ladies of noble family in particular をit was particularly used by noble women に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term &quot;futaeorimono&quot; is seen in the documents written in the Heian period as well as in the subsequent times, and it was particularly used by noble women.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>その他、主人のお仕着せで女房たちがそろって着用することもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, nyobo (a court ladies) sometimes wore futaeorimono-made clothes en masse as livery imposed by their masters.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, nyobo (court ladies) sometimes wore futaeorimono-made clothes en masse as livery imposed by their masters.</e>
<cmt>a court ladies を court ladies に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, nyobo (court ladies) sometimes wore futaeorimono-made clothes en masse as livery imposed by their masters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>しかし、たびたび奢侈（しゃし）禁制の対象とされ、女房はもちろん、高貴な女性まで一切禁止という法令が出たこともあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, futaeorimono often became the target of the ban of luxury goods, and not only nyobo but also the ladies of noble family were once banned from using it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, futaeorimono was often the target of sumptuary laws, and even regulations were issued to ban its use by not only nyobo but also the noble women.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, futaeorimono was often the target of sumptuary laws, and even regulations were issued to ban its use by not only nyobo but also the noble women.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>女性の唐衣や表着、小袿などのほか、元服前の男子の袴などに用いられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Futae orimono was used for female&apos;s karaginu (a waist length Chinese style jacket), omotegi (outer garment) and kouchigi as well as for hakama (men&apos;s formal divided skirt) for males who have not yet celebrated genpuku (coming of age ceremony).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Futaeorimono was used for women&apos;s karaginu (a waist length Chinese style jacket), omotegi (outer garment) and kouchigi (informal outer robe) as well as for boys&apos; hakama (men&apos;s formal divided skirt) before genpuku (coming of age).</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Futaeorimono was used for women&apos;s karaginu (a waist length Chinese style jacket), omotegi (outer garment) and kouchigi (informal outer robe) as well as for boys&apos; hakama (men&apos;s formal divided skirt) before genpuku (coming of age).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Takranke(id:23355), 草薙(id:23262), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>