<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>応声虫</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ousei-chu (responding worm)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Osei-chu</e>
<cmt>ヘボン式ローマ字長音表記の誤解。括弧内の解説は、後段に移動。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Osei-chu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>応声虫（おうせいちゅう）または応声は、中国や日本の『新著聞集』や『閑田次筆』などの江戸時代の随筆集にある奇病、及びその病気を引き起こす怪虫。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ousei-chu&apos; or &apos;Ousei&apos; is s a strange disease and a strange worm which causes the disease recorded in collected essays of the Edo period such as Chinese or Japanese &quot;Shin Chomonju&quot;or &quot;Kandenjihitsu&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An &apos;Osei-chu&apos; (mimicking roundworm) or &apos;Osei&apos; (literally, mimicking or parroting the host&apos;s words) is a weird disease or a ghostly roundworm which causes the disease known in China and Japan, as described in collected essays written in the Edo period, such as &quot;Shin Chomonju&quot; (literally, a new collection of famous tales) and &quot;Kanden jihitsu&quot; (literally, fallow-field essays, continued; miscellaneous essays).</e>
<cmt>応声虫の訳語ですが、responding wormというよりは、後段解説「宿主の言葉を口まねする回虫のような寄生虫」に忠実に訳し直しました。また、原文にある２冊の書物は明らかに日本人によって日本で書かれたものと分かっている為、「中国や日本の」は直後の書名に係るのではなく、「奇病、及びその病気を･･･」に係るものと思われます。或いは、「中国や日本の怪談について書かれた（書名）」という意味の可能性があります。その他、不要文字の削除、用語選択、パンクチュエーション、英文の流れ調整を修正。書名英訳追加（参考：http://www.google.co.jp/search?hl=ja&amp;prmdo=1&amp;tbs=bks:1&amp;q=Kanden+jihitsu&amp;aq=f&amp;aqi=&amp;aql=&amp;oq=&amp;gs_rfai=）。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An &apos;Osei-chu&apos; (mimicking roundworm) or &apos;Osei&apos; (literally, mimicking or parroting the host&apos;s words) is a weird disease or a ghostly roundworm which causes the disease known in China and Japan, as described in collected essays written in the Edo period, such as &quot;Shin Chomonju&quot; (literally, a new collection of famous tales) and &quot;Kanden jihitsu&quot; (literally, fallow-field essays, continued; miscellaneous essays).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>人間がこの病気に侵されると、高熱が10日間ほど続いて苦しんだ後、腹に出来物ができ、次第にそれが口のような形になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When people get the disease, they have a high fever for about 10 days and after that, they get a boil which developed gradually in the shape of mouth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When a human is affected with this disease, he or she suffers a high fever for about 10 days, which is followed by getting a skin boil which gradually develops into the mouth shape.</e>
<cmt>用語選択、パンクチュエーション、表現調整</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When a human is affected with this disease, he or she suffers a high fever for about 10 days, which is followed by getting a skin boil which gradually develops into the mouth shape.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>この口は病気になった者の喋ったことを口真似するため、応声虫の名がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This mouth is named &apos;Ousei-chu (responding worm), because it parrots the word of the host who suffers from this disease.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The mouth-shape boil thus formed is named &apos;Osei-chu (mimicking worm), because it mimics the words of the host who suffers from this disease.</e>
<cmt>用語選択</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The mouth-shaped boil thus formed is named Osei-chu (mimicking worm), because it mimics the words of the host who suffers from this disease.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>喋るだけでなく食べ物も食べる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Not only does it speak, but aloso it eats food.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Not only does it speak, but also it eats food.</e>
<cmt>スペルミス</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Not only does it speak, but also it eats food.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>自ら食べ物を要求し、これを拒むと患者を高熱で苦しめたり、大声で悪口を叫んだりもする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It demand food itself and when it is rejected, it tortures the host with a high fever or hurls verbal abuse.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It demands food itself, and when it is rejected, it tortures the host with a high fever or hurls verbal abuse in a loud voice.</e>
<cmt>主語・動詞の数量不一致、パンクチュエーション、訳抜け</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It demands food itself, and when it is rejected, it tortures the host with a high fever or hurls verbal abuse in a loud voice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>『新著聞集』では、回虫などの寄生虫のように人間の体内に棲む怪虫によって引き起こされる病気とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Shin Chomonju&quot;, the disease is caused by a parasite worm such as a roundworm living on human&apos;s body.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the &quot;Shin Chomonju,&quot; the disease is caused by a parasitic worm such as a roundworm living in the human body.</e>
<cmt>パンクチュエーション、文法調整</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the &quot;Shin Chomonju,&quot; the disease is caused by a parasitic worm such as a roundworm living in the human body.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>以下のような記述がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is described as follows;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is described as follows:</e>
<cmt>パンクチュエーション</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is described as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>元禄16年（1703年）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1703,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1703.</e>
<cmt>パンクチュエーション</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1703.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>油小路通に住むある男の腹に応声虫による出来物ができ、高熱や罵詈雑言に苦しみ続けていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">a man living in Aburanokoji Street got a boil in the stomach and continued suffering from it with a high fever and verbal attacks.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A man living in Abura no-koji Alley got an Osei-chu boil on the surface of the stomach and continued suffering a high fever and verbal abuse.</e>
<cmt>文頭大文字、用語選択、英文の流れ調整。なお、「腹に･･･出来物ができ」たのは内部ではなく表面であるという理解で訳し直してあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A man living in Abura no-koji Alley got an Osei-chu boil on the surface of the stomach and continued suffering a high fever and verbal abuse.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>様々な種類の薬や祈祷を試したが、一向に効果がない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He tried various kind of drugs and theotherapy, but they did not work at all.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He tried out various drugs and theotherapy, but they did not work at all.</e>
<cmt>英文の簡潔化。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He tried out various drugs and theotherapy, but they did not work at all.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>ある名医が診察し、様々な種類の薬を出来物の口に飲ませた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A skilled doctor saw him and gave various kinds of drugs to the mouth of the boil.</e>
<cmt>＜一原文一翻訳文の原則例外処理＞</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A skilled doctor saw him and gave various drugs to the mouth of the boil.</e>
<cmt>英文の簡潔化。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A skilled doctor saw him and gave various drugs to the mouth of the boil.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>そして、その中でも嫌がって飲まないものを選び、それらを調合したものを飲ませることにした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He chose some drugs that the mouth rejected to take from these drugs and then, mixed them, gave it to the patient.</e>
<cmt>＜一原文一翻訳文の原則例外処理＞</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He selected some drugs that the mouth had rejected to take from among those drugs, and gave a mixture of them to the patient.</e>
<cmt>原文で「飲ませることにした」の対象が「出来物」なのか「患者」なのか不明ですが、「患者」として訳出してあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He selected some drugs from those that the mouth had rejected, and gave a mixture of them to the patient.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせて修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>出来物は次第に弱り始め、10日ほど経つと肛門から怪虫が出てきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The boil gradually became weak and 10 days later, a strange worm came out from the anus of the patient,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The boil gradually became weak and 10 days later, a grotesque worm came out of the anus of the patient,</e>
<cmt>用語選択、文法調整</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The boil gradually became weak and 10 days later, a grotesque worm came out of the anus of the patient.</e>
<cmt>カンマをピリオドに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>それは体長が35センチメートルほどのトカゲのようなもので、頭には1本の角があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was about 35 centimeters long, like a lizard and had an antenna in the head.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was an about 35 centimeter-long lizard-like roundworm, having an antenna in the head.</e>
<cmt>表現調整</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was an about 35 centimeter-long lizard-like roundworm, having an antenna in the head.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>逃げ出そうとしたところを滅多打ちにして殺し、患者は元気を取り戻したということである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the worm came out and ran away, it was beaten out and killed, and then, the patient recovered.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the worm came out and tried to run away, it was beaten up to be killed, and the patient recovered thereafter.</e>
<cmt>文法、表現調整</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the worm came out and tried to run away, it was beaten up to be killed, and the patient recovered thereafter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="16">
<j>この逸話は、前述の実在の寄生虫である回虫を綴ったものであるとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This anecdote is said to be a description of a real parasite roundworm previously described.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This anecdote is reportedly based on a true story of a real parasitic roundworm as described above.</e>
<cmt>表現調整</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This anecdote is reportedly based on a true story of a real parasitic roundworm as described above.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>回虫が腹にいることによる異常な空腹感や、虫下しを飲んで肛門から排泄された回虫の死骸を妖怪視したものとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An abnormal feeling of hunger or a dead roundworm coming from an anus with vermifuge is considered to be an imaginary weird creature.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Abnormal hunger caused by a roundworm inside, and the body of a dead roundworm excreted from anus with vermifuge were allegedly attributed to a yokai (an imaginary weird creature).</e>
<cmt>表現調整</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Abnormal hunger caused by a roundworm inside, and the body of a dead roundworm excreted from anus with vermifuge were allegedly attributed to a yokai (an imaginary weird creature).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>本来は応声虫は中国のものであり、日本の逸話は中国の文献を翻訳・脚色したものとする説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another legend says that &apos;Ousei-chu&apos; originated in China and Chinese literature was translated or dramatized into Japanese anecdotes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One theory has it that the story of Osei-chu has its origin in China and that the Japanese Osei-chu was created based on translation and dramatization of the Chinese original.</e>
<cmt>表現調整</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One theory has it that the story of Osei-chu has its origin in China and that the Japanese Osei-chu was created based on translation and dramatization of the Chinese original.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="19">
<j>また、『閑田随筆』には以下のような話がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, in &apos;Kanden zuihitsu&apos; (essay), the following story was described.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, in &quot;Kanden zuihitsu&quot; (literally, fallow-field essays; miscellaneous essays), the following story was described.</e>
<cmt>書名訳修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, in &quot;Kanden zuihitsu&quot; (literally, fallow-field essays; miscellaneous essays), the following story was described.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>元文3年、油小路の見世物小屋の業者が、応声虫に取り憑かれているという女性の話を聞き、見世物に出そうと商談に訪れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1738, a staffer of a tent show in Aburanokoji heard about a woman who seemed to be caught by &apos;Ousei-chu&apos; and visited her to talk business because they wanted her to be in their show.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1738, a sideshow manager doing business in the Abura no-koji Alley heard about a woman who seemed to be caught by the Osei-chu and visited her to recruit her into their show.</e>
<cmt>表現調整</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1738, a sideshow manager doing business in the Abura no-koji Alley heard about a woman who seemed to be caught by the Osei-chu and visited her to recruit her into their show.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>その女性の家を訪ねたところ、女性は確かに応声虫の病気を患っているらしく、腹から声を出していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When they saw her, they noticed that she was caught by &apos;Ousei-chu&apos; because they heard the voice from her stomach.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the manager saw the woman, he noticed that surely she suffered from the Osei-chu because they heard the voice from her stomach.</e>
<cmt>表現調整</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the manager saw the woman, he noticed that surely she suffered from the Osei-chu because they heard the voice from her stomach.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>女性の夫が言うには、寺へ参拝に行った際、腹から出る声を周囲の人々が怪しみ、とても恥かしい思いをした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her husband said, &apos;When she went to a temple, she was very embarrassed because people around her were suspicious of the voice coming from her stomach.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her husband disclosed that when they went to worship at a temple, people around her were suspicious of the voice coming from her stomach, which was so embarrassing.</e>
<cmt>表現調整</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her husband disclosed that when they went to worship at a temple, people around her were suspicious of the voice coming from her stomach, which was so embarrassing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>そのため、見世物など到底無理とのことだった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, she would not be caught dead being in the show&apos;.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The husband continued that she would therefore not be caught dead being in the show.</e>
<cmt>表現調整、パンクチュエーション</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The husband continued that she would therefore not be caught dead being in the show.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>こうして業者の思惑は外れてしまったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After all, their expectations were disappointed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this way, the manager&apos;s expectations were disappointed.</e>
<cmt>表現調整</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this way, the manager&apos;s expectations were disappointed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 逃亡者(id:14864), Toroia(id:31889), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>