<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>日本映画プロダクション連盟</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan Movie Production Federation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan Movie Production Federation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan Movie Production Federation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>日本映画プロダクション連盟（にほんえいが-れんめい、1928年5月 - 1929年2月）は、かつて京都に存在した日本のインディペンデント系映画会社の集合組織である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan Movie Production Federation (May 1928-February 1929) was a association of film companies focusing on independent film genre that once existed in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan Movie Production Federation (May 1928 - February 1929) was an association in Kyoto made up of film companies focused on independent films.</e>
<cmt>fixed to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan Movie Production Federation (May 1928 - February 1929) was an association in Kyoto made up of film companies focused on independent films.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>マキノ・プロダクションを退社したスター俳優の製作会社5社を中心に設立された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was established centering around five production companies of popular actors that quit Makino Production.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its establishment was centered around five production companies owned by popular actors who had quit Makino Productions.</e>
<cmt>&quot;It was established centering around&quot; &gt; &quot;Its establishment was centered around&quot;; Production &gt; Productions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its establishment was centered around five production companies owned by popular actors who had quit Makino Productions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>略歴・概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Personal History and Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History and Summary</e>
<cmt>eliminated &quot;Personal&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History and Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>1928年（昭和3年）4月、牧野省三率いるマキノ・プロダクションの四国ブロック配給会社・三共社の山崎徳次郎は、阪東妻三郎プロダクションの経営者・立花良介とともに、以前から映画作家系インディーズの興行に熱心であった神戸市の菊水キネマ商会の大島菊松らを中心とした全国150館の独立系映画館主に呼びかけ、「日本活動常設館館主連盟映画配給本社」を設立、配給会社の中間マージンを排除し、独立プロダクションへの製作費のダイレクトな出資および興行の方針を打ち出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokujiro YAMAZAKI of Sankyo Company that provided Makino Production in Shikoku Region led by Shozo MAKINO along with Ryosuke TACHIBANA of Bando Tsumasaburo Production manager called out in April 1928 to Kikumatsu OSHIMA of Kikusui Kinema Firm in Kobe city, who was greatly interested in Indies films from previously, and 150 independent film theater owners around Japan and established &apos;Nihon Katsudo Josetsukan Kanshu Renmei Eiga Haikyu Honsha&apos; (Headquarters of Eiga Haikyu for association of masters of movie theaters in Japan) to eradicate the intervening contracting company and introduced the performance policy that provided direct production fee to independent film productions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April of 1928 Tokujiro YAMAZAKI of Sankyo, the company led by Shozo MAKINO that had been distributing Makino films in the Shikoku area, conspired with the top execute of Bando Tsumasaburo Productions named Ryosuke TACHIBANA to get in contact with 150 independent theater owners throughout Japan, such as Kikumatsu OSHIMA of Kikusui Kinema in Kobe who was greatly interested in Indies films, to cooperate in establishing &quot;Nihon Katsudo Josetsukan Kanshu Renmei Eiga Haikyu Honsha&quot; (Distribution Company Headquarters for Movie Theater Owners in Japan; also known as &quot;Kanshu Renmei&quot; [the Theater Owner&apos;s Association]) to eradicate the intervening contracting company and introduce policies that would provide direct production fees to independent film productions.</e>
<cmt>moved date to the beginning of the sentence; changed description for &quot;Nihon Katsudo…&quot;; fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April of 1928 Tokujiro YAMAZAKI of Sankyo, the company led by Shozo MAKINO that had been distributing Makino films in the Shikoku area, conspired with the top execute of Bando Tsumasaburo Productions named Ryosuke TACHIBANA to get in contact with 150 independent theater owners throughout Japan, such as Kikumatsu OSHIMA of Kikusui Kinema in Kobe who was greatly interested in Indies films, to cooperate in establishing &apos;Nihon Katsudo Josetsukan Kanshu Renmei Eiga Haikyu Honsha&apos; (Distribution Company Headquarters for Movie Theater Owners in Japan; also known as &quot;Kanshu Renmei&quot; [the Theater Owner&apos;s Association]) to eradicate the intervening contracting company and introduce policies that would provide direct production fees to independent film productions.</e>
<cmt>原文「」の部分を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>同時期、片岡千恵蔵が先陣を切って退社し、嵐長三郎が牧野にかつて命名された名を返上して退社して嵐寛寿郎を名乗り、また山口俊雄 (新派俳優)、中根龍太郎、市川小文治、山本礼三郎、武井龍三、中村梅太郎（「マキノ梅太郎」名返上）ら50数名のスターを中心とした俳優が大挙してマキノ・プロダクションを退社した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chiezo KATAOKA became the forerunner in quitting the company, Chozaburo ARASHI returned the acting name when quitting Makino and called himself Kanjuro ARASHI, Toshio YAMAGUCHI (New School Actor), Ryutaro NAKANE, Kobunji ICHIKAWA, Reizaburo YAMAMOTO, Ryuzo TAKEI, and Umetaro NAKAMURA (&apos;Makino Umetaro&apos;), and approximately fifty popular actors quit Makino Production.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chiezo KATAOKA was the first to quit the company, Chozaburo ARASHI, who went back to using his acting name after quitting Makino and called himself Kanjuro ARASHI, Toshio YAMAGUCHI (New School Actor), Ryutaro NAKANE, Kobunji ICHIKAWA, Reizaburo YAMAMOTO, Ryuzo TAKEI, and Umetaro NAKAMURA (Makino Umetaro), and approximately fifty popular actors quit Makino Productions.</e>
<cmt>became the forerunner in quitting the company &gt; was the first to quit the company; fixed grammar to read more smoothly; eliminated quotations around &quot;Makino Umetaro&quot;; Production &gt; Productions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chiezo KATAOKA was the first to quit the company, Chozaburo ARASHI, who went back to using his acting name after quitting Makino and called himself Kanjuro ARASHI, Toshio YAMAGUCHI (New School Actor), Ryutaro NAKANE, Kobunji ICHIKAWA, Reizaburo YAMAMOTO, Ryuzo TAKEI, and Umetaro NAKAMURA (sending back to using his acting name &apos;Makino Umetaro&apos;), and approximately fifty popular actors quit Makino Productions.</e>
<cmt>Makino Umetaroに&apos; &apos;を付加し、名返上の訳を加えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>同年5月10日、片岡が「片岡千恵蔵プロダクション」（千恵プロ）を設立、嵐、山口、中根、小文治、山本もそれぞれプロダクションを設立、「千恵プロ」、嵐の「嵐寛寿郎プロダクション」（第1次寛プロ）を中心としたスタープロダクション5社が結成したのがこの「日本映画プロダクション連盟」である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kataoka established &apos;Kataoka Chiezo Production&apos; (Chie Pro) on May 10 of the same year, and Arashi, Yamaguchi, Nakane, Kobunji, Yamamoto also established their own production company, and this &apos;Japan Movie Production Federation&apos; was formed by five star production companies that centered around &apos;Chie Pro&apos; and &apos;Arashi Kanjuro Production&apos; (The First Period Kan Pro).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kataoka established &quot;Kataoka Chiezo Productions&quot; (Chie Pro) on May 10 of the same year, while Arashi, Yamaguchi, Nakane, Kobunji, and Yamamoto also established their own production companies, thus forming the &apos;Japan Movie Production Federation&apos; with five, star production companies centered around &apos;Chie Pro&apos; and &apos;Arashi Kanjuro Productions&apos; (The First Period Kan Pro).</e>
<cmt>Production &gt; Productions; and this &gt; thus; fixed awkward wording and grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kataoka established &apos;Kataoka Chiezo Productions&apos; (Chie Pro) on May 10 of the same year, while Arashi, Yamaguchi, Nakane, Kobunji, and Yamamoto also established their own production companies, thus forming the &apos;Japan Movie Production Federation&apos; with five, star production companies centered around &apos;Chie Pro&apos; and &apos;Arashi Kanjuro Productions&apos; (The First Period Kan Pro).</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>またこのとき、山崎に共鳴したマキノの大道具主任河合広始と撮影技師の田中十三もマキノを退社、京都・双ヶ丘に貸しスタジオ「日本キネマ撮影所」（双ヶ丘撮影所）を設立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, Hiroshi KAWAI responsible for big equipments in Makino was moved by Yamazaki and camera technician Juzo TANAKA quit Makino and founded a rental studio called &apos;Japan Cinema Studio&apos; (Narabigaoka Studio) in Narabigaoka, Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Inspired by Yamazaki, Makino&apos;s chief stagehand Hiroshi KAWAI and camera technician Juzo TANAKA quit Makino and founded a rental studio called &quot;Japan Cinema Studio&quot; (Narabigaoka Studio) in Narabigaoka, Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>moved &gt; inspired; rearranged sentence to read more smoothly; big equipements &gt; heavy equipment;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Inspired by Yamazaki, Makino&apos;s chief stagehand Hiroshi KAWAI and camera technician Juzo TANAKA quit Makino and founded a rental studio called &apos;Japan Cinema Studio&apos; (Narabigaoka Studio) in Narabigaoka, Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>同撮影所は「日本映画プロダクション連盟の撮影所」と呼ばれることもあり、同連盟がもっぱらこれをレンタルし、スタッフ・キャストを共有し、協力して映画製作を行なった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The same shooting studio was also called as &apos;Studio for Japan Movie Production Federation&apos; and the same association rented this place, used the same staff and cast and collaborated for a film production.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This studio was also called the &quot;Studio for the Japan Movie Production Federation&quot; and the assocation rented it, using the same staff and cast and collaborated in producing films.</e>
<cmt>&gt; &quot;; fixed awkward wording and grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This studio was also called the &apos;Studio for the Japan Movie Production Federation&apos; and the association rented it, using the same staff and cast and collaborated in producing films.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。assocationをassociationに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>しかし、製作費の出資と興行をになう山崎の「館主連盟」が同年7月末には早くも瓦解、「千恵プロ」と「寛プロ」以外は解散を余儀なくされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, &apos;association of movie theaters&apos; of Yamazaki that gave out the production fee and performance collapsed early in end of July of the same year and film companies other than &apos;Chie Pro&apos; and &apos;Kan Pro&apos; had to disband.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Yamazaki&apos;s assocation that had been shouldering production investment costs and promotions collapsed early at the end of July of the same year and every film company except &quot;Chie Pro&quot; and &quot;Kan Pro&quot; were forced to liquidate.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;gave out the production fee and performance&quot; to &quot;that had been shouldering production investment costs and promotions&quot; for &quot;製作費の出資と興行をになう&quot;; disband &gt; liquidate;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Yamazaki&apos;s association that had been shouldering production investment costs and promotions collapsed early at the end of July of the same year and every film company except &apos;Chie Pro&apos; and &apos;Kan Pro&apos; were forced to liquidate.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。assocationをassociationに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>大島菊松が神戸に経営する「菊水館」を中心に興行に協力する映画館は残ったが、寛プロも翌1929年（昭和4年）2月には解散、嵐は東亜キネマ京都撮影所（等持院撮影所）に入社した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The movie theaters cooperating with the show such as the &apos;Kikusuikan Theater&apos; managed by Kikumatsu OSHIMA in Kobe City remained, but Kan Pro disbanded in the following February 1929 and Arashi entered Toa Kinema Kyoto Studio (Tojiin Studio).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Movie theaters that cooperated with promotions such as Kikumatsu OSHIMA&apos;s &quot;Kikusuikan Theater&quot; in Kobe remained, but Kan Pro disbanded the following February in 1929 and Arashi joined Toa Kinema Kyoto Studio (Tojin Studio).</e>
<cmt>cooperating with the show &gt; cooperated with promotions; &apos; &gt; &quot;; fixed awkward wording and grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Movie theaters that cooperated with promotions such as Kikumatsu OSHIMA&apos;s &apos;Kikusuikan Theater&apos; in Kobe remained, but Kan Pro disbanded the following February in 1929 and Arashi joined Toa Kinema Kyoto Studio (Tojin Studio).</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="10">
<j>「千恵プロ」は同年1月に嵯峨野に自前の撮影所「千恵蔵映画撮影所」をオープン、双ヶ丘撮影所を離れて映画製作を続行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chie Pro&apos; opened its own shooting studio &apos;Chiezo Movie Studio&apos; in Sagano in January of the same year and continued film production after leaving Narabigaoka Studio.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Chie Pro&quot; opened its own shooting studio called &quot;Chiezo Movie Studio&quot; in Sagano in January of the same year and continued film production after leaving Narabigaoka Studio.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;called&quot; before &quot;Chiezo Movie Studio&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chie Pro&apos; opened its own shooting studio called &apos;Chiezo Movie Studio&apos; in Sagano in January of the same year and continued film production after leaving Narabigaoka Studio.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>武井龍三は「千恵プロ」から独立、双ヶ丘撮影所に「武井龍三プロダクション」を設立し、3本の映画を製作したが、失敗に終り解散した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryuzo TAKEI became independent from &apos;Chie Pro&apos; and established &apos;Takei Ryuzo Production&apos; in Narabigaoka Studio to make three films, but failed and disbanded.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryuzo TAKEI became independent from &apos;Chie Pro&apos; and established &apos;Takei Ryuzo Productions&apos; in Narabigaoka Studio to make three films, but then went under and disbanded.</e>
<cmt>Production &gt; Productions; failed &gt; went under;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryuzo TAKEI became independent from &apos;Chie Pro&apos; and established &apos;Takei Ryuzo Productions&apos; in Narabigaoka Studio to make three films, but then went under and disbanded.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>解散後のスターを含めたキャスト、スタッフのほとんどは、マキノ以外のメジャー系撮影所に移籍、あるいは舞台出身の者は舞台に戻った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most of the cast, including the popular actors and staff, moved to a major film shooting studio other than Makino or those that came from theatrical performances returned to the stage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most of the cast, including the popular actors and staff, moved to major film shooting studios other than Makino, and those that came from theatrical performances returned to the stage.</e>
<cmt>moved to a major film shooting studio &gt; moved to major film shooting studios; added comma after &quot;Makino&quot;; or &gt; and</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most of the cast, including the popular actors and staff, moved to major film shooting studios other than Makino, and those that came from theatrical performances returned to the stage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>メンバー</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Members</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Members</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Members</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="13">
<j>片岡千恵蔵プロダクション （片岡千恵蔵）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kataoka Chiezo Production (Chiezo KATAOKA)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kataoka Chiezo Productions (Chiezo KATAOKA)</e>
<cmt>Production &gt; Productions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kataoka Chiezo Productions (Chiezo KATAOKA)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="14">
<j>嵐寛寿郎プロダクション （嵐寛寿郎）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Arashi Kanjuro Production (Kanjuro ARASHI)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Arashi Kanjuro Productions (Kanjuro ARASHI)</e>
<cmt>Production &gt; Productions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Arashi Kanjuro Productions (Kanjuro ARASHI)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="15">
<j>中根龍太郎喜劇プロダクション （中根龍太郎）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nakane Ryutaro Comedy Production (Ryutaro NAKANE)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nakane Ryutaro Comedy Productions (Ryutaro NAKANE)</e>
<cmt>Production &gt; Productions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nakane Ryutaro Comedy Productions (Ryutaro NAKANE)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="16">
<j>山口俊雄プロダクション （山口俊雄 (新派俳優)）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamaguchi Toshio Production (Toshio YAMAGUCHI (the new school actor))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yamaguchi Toshio Productions (Toshio YAMAGUCHI (the new school actor))</e>
<cmt>Production &gt; Productions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamaguchi Toshio Productions (Toshio YAMAGUCHI (the new school actor))</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="17">
<j>市川小文治歌舞伎映画プロダクション （市川小文治）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ichikawa Kobunji Kabuki Eiga Production (Kobunji ICHIKAWA)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ichikawa Kobunji Kabuki Eiga Productions (Kobunji ICHIKAWA)</e>
<cmt>Production &gt; Productions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ichikawa Kobunji Kabuki Eiga Productions (Kobunji ICHIKAWA)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="18">
<j>山本礼三郎プロダクション （山本礼三郎）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamamoto Reizaburo Production (Reizaburo YAMAMOTO)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yamamoto Reizaburo Productions (Reizaburo YAMAMOTO)</e>
<cmt>Production &gt; Productions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamamoto Reizaburo Productions (Reizaburo YAMAMOTO)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="19">
<j>武井龍三プロダクション （武井龍三、千恵プロからの独立）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takei Ryuzo Production (Ryuzo TAKEI, became independent from Chie Pro)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takei Ryuzo Productions (Ryuzo TAKEI, became independent from Chie Pro)</e>
<cmt>Production &gt; Productions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takei Ryuzo Productions (Ryuzo TAKEI, became independent from Chie Pro)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>参加者</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Participants</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Participants</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Participants</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="20">
<j>俳優　中村梅太郎 （「マキノ梅太郎」改め）、林誠之助、香川良介、成松和一、沢田清</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Actors such as Umetaro NAKAMURA (revised as &apos;Makino Umetaro&apos;), Seinosuke HAYASHI, Ryosuke KAGAWA, Kazuichi NARIMATSU, and Kiyoshi SAWADA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Actors such as Umetaro NAKAMURA (changed his name to &quot;Makino Umetaro&quot;), Seinosuke HAYASHI, Ryosuke KAGAWA, Kazuichi NARIMATSU and Kiyoshi SAWADA</e>
<cmt>eliminated comma after NARIMATSU; eliminated period; revised as &gt; changed his name to; &apos; &gt; &quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Actors such as Umetaro NAKAMURA (changed his name from &apos;Makino Umetaro&apos;), Seinosuke HAYASHI, Ryosuke KAGAWA, Kazuichi NARIMATSU and Kiyoshi SAWADA</e>
<cmt>toをfromに変更しました。&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="21">
<j>監督　稲垣浩、伊丹万作、富沢進郎</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Directors such as Hiroshi INAGAKI, Mansaku ITAMI, and Shinro TOMIZAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Directors such as Hiroshi INAGAKI, Mansaku ITAMI and Shinro TOMIZAWA</e>
<cmt>eliminated comma after ITAMI; eliminated period</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Directors such as Hiroshi INAGAKI, Mansaku ITAMI and Shinro TOMIZAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="22">
<j>撮影　石本秀雄、田中十三</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shooting members such as Hideo ISHIMOTO and Juzo TANAKA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Film photographers such as Hideo ISHIMOTO and Juzo TANAKA.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;shooting members&quot; to &quot;Film photographers&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Film photographers such as Hideo ISHIMOTO and Juzo TANAKA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kmrt(id:101778), IwaimBot(id:190695), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>