<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>天下一品</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tenka-ippin (second to none)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tenka-ippin (second to none)</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;(second to none)&quot; - as the name of the shop, I don&apos;t think it needs a translation here</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tenka-ippin</e>
<cmt>(second to none)削除</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>天下一品（てんかいっぴん）は京都府京都市が発祥のラーメンチェーン店である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tenka-ippin (that means second to none in the world), the chain stores of ramen (Chinese-style noodles served in a hot soup) was born in Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tenka-ippin (which means the best in the world), is a chain of ramen (Chinese-style noodles served in a hot soup) stores founded in Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>&quot;that means second to none&quot;→&quot;which means the best&quot;Added &quot;is&quot;&quot;the&quot;→&quot;a&quot;Moved &quot;stores&quot;&quot;was born&quot;→&quot;founded&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tenka-ippin (which means the best in the world), is a chain of ramen (Chinese-style noodles served in a hot soup) stores founded in Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>天一（てんいち）と省略して呼ばれることも多いが、「天一」と言う名前のラーメン店もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name is sometimes abbreviated and called &quot;Tenichi&quot;, however, there is other ramen shop named &quot;Tenichi&quot; different from &quot;Tenka-ippin.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name is sometimes abbreviated to &quot;Tenichi&quot;, although there is another ramen shop named &quot;Tenichi&quot; different from &quot;Tenka-ippin.&quot;</e>
<cmt>&quot;and called&quot;→&quot;to&quot;&quot;however,&quot;→&quot;although&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name is sometimes abbreviated to &quot;Tenichi,&quot; although there is another ramen shop named &apos;Tenichi&apos; different from Tenka-ippin.</e>
<cmt>コンマの位置移動原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>京都のラーメンの一つである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is one of the ramen shops in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is one of the ramen shops in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is one of the ramen shops in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>創業者は木村勉。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The founder is Tsutomu KIMURA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The founder is Tsutomu KIMURA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The founder is Tsutomu KIMURA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>1971年頃に屋台を開業したのがはじまりで、試行錯誤の末作られた独特のラーメンが京都の学生に愛され人気店に成長していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He started the business with a street stall in around 1971 and the unique taste ramen he developed through a trial and error process was loved by the students of Kyoto, and the shop grew popular.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He started the business with a street stall in around 1971 and by developing through a trial and error process a unique tasting ramen that was loved by the students of Kyoto, the shop grew popular.</e>
<cmt>&quot;he developed through a trial and error process&quot;→&quot;by developing through a trial and error process&quot; and moved&quot;the&quot;→&quot;a&quot;&quot;tastre&quot;→&quot;tasting&quot;Added &quot;that&quot;Deleted &quot;and&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He started the business with a street stall in around 1971 and by developing through a trial and error process a unique tasting ramen that was loved by the students of Kyoto, the shop grew popular.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>現在では全国に店舗が広がった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today, they deployed shops nation wide.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, they operate shops nation wide.</e>
<cmt>&quot;deployed&quot;→&quot;operate&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, they operate shops nation wide.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>滋賀には自社工場をもつ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They have captive factory in Shiga Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They have their own factory in Shiga Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>&quot;captive&quot;→&quot;their own&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They have their own factory in Shiga Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>本店は京都市左京区一乗寺築田町94にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Their head shop is at 94, Ichijoji Tsukuda Cho, Sakyo Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their head shop is at 94, Ichijoji Tsukuda-cho, Sakyo Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Cho&quot;→&quot;-cho&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Their head shop is at 94, Ichijoji Tsukuda-cho, Sakyo Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>() 叡山電鉄茶山駅 (京都府)から徒歩10分ほど。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is about 10 minutes walk from Chayama Station of Eizan Electric Railway (Kyoto Prefecture.)</e>
<cmt>冒頭の()は無視しております。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is about 10 minutes walk from Eizan Electric Railway&apos;s Chayama Station (Kyoto Prefecture.)</e>
<cmt>Moved &quot;Eizan Electric Railway&quot; and made possessivedeleted &quot;of&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is about 10 minutes walk from Eizan Electric Railway&apos;s Chayama Station (Kyoto Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>観光ガイドにも掲載され全国各地からファンが訪れている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is on the sightseeing guidebooks and enthusiasts who want to taste it visit the shop from every region of the country.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is in sightseeing guidebooks and fans visit the shop from every region of the country.</e>
<cmt>&quot;on the&quot;→&quot;in&quot;&quot;enthusiasts who want to taste it&quot;→&quot;fans&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is in sightseeing guidebooks and fans visit the shop from every region of the country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>メニュー</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Menu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Menu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Menu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>独特のラーメン</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Unique Ramen</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unique Ramen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unique Ramen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>木村が当初屋台で始めたラーメンは、京都では珍しくない鶏ガラ白湯ラーメン（京都で言うところのこってり系ラーメン）であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the time when Kimura sold his ramen at the street stall, it was &apos;Torigara Baitan Ramen&apos; (a ramen with a whitish chicken-bone soup) common in Kyoto (what people of Kyoto call thick type ramen.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Kimura first opened his ramen stall, he sold &apos;Torigara Baitan Ramen&apos; (ramen with a whitish chicken-bone soup) common in Kyoto (what Kyoto people call kotteri, or thick type, ramen.)</e>
<cmt>&quot;At the time when Kimura sold his ramen at the street stall, it was&quot;→&quot;When Kimura first opened his ramen stall, he sold&quot;Deleted &quot;a&quot;&quot;people of Kyoto&quot;→&quot;Kyoto people&quot;Added &quot;kotteri, or&quot; and comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Kimura first opened his ramen stall, he sold Torigara Baitan Ramen (ramen with a whitish chicken-bone soup) common in Kyoto (what Kyoto people call kotteri, or thick type, ramen).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置&apos;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>しかし、彼は屋台仲間からスープを教わったり、自らの家財を次々と質に入れ費用を捻出して研究を重ね、それまでに無いスープを作り出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he asked the fellow street stall ramen sellers about different recipe of soup and managed to raise money by putting his household articles in pawn one after another and continued researches to finally make a new recipe of soup that had never been.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, he asked his fellow street stall ramen sellers about different recipes for the soup and by pawning his belongings one after another, he managed to raise enough money to continue experimenting, finally inventing a totally new kind of soup.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the&quot;→&quot;his&quot;&quot;recipe of&quot;→&quot;recipes for the&quot;Reworded last part of sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, he asked his fellow street stall ramen sellers about different recipes for the soup and by pawning his belongings one after another, he managed to raise enough money to continue experimenting, finally inventing a totally new kind of soup.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>通常は注文時にニンニクの有無を聞かれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Usually, the cook asks the visitor if he wants garlic or not when ordered.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In most shops, the cook asks customers if they want garlic or not when ordering.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Usually&quot;→&quot;In most shops&quot;&quot;the visitor&quot;→&quot;customers&quot;&quot;he wants&quot;→&quot;they want&quot; &quot;ordered&quot;→&quot;ordering&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In most shops, the cook asks customers if they want garlic or not when ordering.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>店舗によっては特にニンニク無しを希望しない場合に自動的にニンニク入りが提供されることがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Depends on the shop, ramen with garlic is served automatically unless orderer specified garlic-less ramen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, depending on the shop, ramen with garlic is served automatically unless the customer specifically orders it without garlic.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;However&quot;&quot;Depends&quot;→&quot;depending&quot;&quot;orderer specified garlic-less ramen&quot;→&quot;the customer specifically orders it without garlic&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, depending on the shop, ramen with garlic is served automatically unless the customer specifically orders it without garlic.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>また、ラーメンの注文自体も、特に指定しないと後述の「こってり」が出てくる場合もあるので注意が必要。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Orderer must take care at the time of order as there are cases that sometimes after-mentioned &quot;thick type&quot; ramen is served automatically unless he specifically orders not.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The customer must take when ordering, as in some cases the &quot;thick type&quot; kotteri ramen (described below) is served automatically unless another type is specifically ordered.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Orderer&quot;→&quot;The customer&quot;&quot;at the time of order&quot;→&quot;when ordering&quot;&quot;as there are cases that sometimes&quot;→&quot;, as in some cases&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;&quot;after-mentioned&quot;→&quot;(described below)&quot; and movedAdded &quot;kotteri&quot;&quot;he specifically orders not&quot;→&quot;another type is specifically ordered&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The customer must take care when ordering, as in some cases the &apos;thick type&apos; kotteri ramen (described below) is served automatically unless another type is specifically ordered.</e>
<cmt>care補足&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>ここで言う、「ニンニク」は、いわゆる「ニントン」（ニンニク唐辛子）のことであり、「おろしニンニク」のことではない（「おろしニンニク」は置いている店舗もあるが、通常は置いてない）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The &quot;garlic&quot; mentioned above does not mean ordinary &quot;grated garlic&quot; but so-called &quot;ninton&quot; (garlic pepper.) (Some shops have &quot;grated garlic,&quot; however, basically they do not serve it in the shops.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;garlic&quot; mentioned above does not mean ordinary &quot;grated garlic&quot; but so-called &quot;ninton&quot; (garlic pepper) (Some shops have &quot;grated garlic,&quot; but it is not available in most shops.).</e>
<cmt>Moved full stop&quot;however, basically they do not serve it in the shops&quot;→&quot;but it is not available in most shops&quot;&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &apos;garlic&apos; mentioned above does not mean ordinary &apos;grated garlic&apos; but so-called &apos;ninton (garlic pepper)&apos; (Some shops have &apos;grated garlic,&apos; but it is not available in most shops.).</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;一文にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>「こってり」と「あっさり」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Thick Type&quot; and &quot;Plain Type&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Thick Type&quot; and &quot;Plain Type&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thick type&apos; and &apos;plain type&apos;</e>
<cmt>文頭以外小文字</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="17">
<j>基本的には天下一品のラーメンスープは「こってり」（名古屋等「スタミナ」と呼ぶ店もあり）と「あっさり」の二種類から選ぶことができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Basically, diners at Tenka-ippin shops are able to choose ramen soup from two types, &quot;thick&quot; (they sometimes call it &apos;stamina&apos; at the shops in Nagoya region and so on) and &quot;plain.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Basically, diners at Tenka-ippin shops are able to choose between two types of ramen soup, &quot;kotteri&quot; or&quot;thick&quot; (they sometimes call it &apos;stamina&apos; at shops in Nagoya and other places) and &quot;assari&quot; or &quot;plain.&quot;</e>
<cmt>&quot;ramen soup from two types&quot;→&quot;between two types of ramen soup&quot;Added &quot;&quot;kotteri&quot; or&quot;Deleted &quot;the&quot;&quot;region and so on&quot;→&quot;and other places&quot;Added &quot;&quot;assari&quot; or&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Basically, diners at Tenka-ippin shops are able to choose between two types of ramen soup, &apos;kotteri&apos; or &apos;thick&apos; (they sometimes call it &apos;stamina&apos; at shops in Nagoya and other places) and &apos;assari&apos; or &apos;plain.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>（その他のメニューについては後述。)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Other dishes listed on the menu is to be described.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Other dishes on the menu are described below.)</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;listed&quot;&quot;is to be described&quot;→&quot;are described below&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Other dishes on the menu are described below.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>ニワトリと野菜から作ったこってりのスープはコラーゲンでドロドロでポタージュのようなスープと称される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thick type soup made of chicken and vegetables is thick with collagen and it is said to be potage-like soup.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;kotteri&quot; soup, made from chicken and vegetables, is thick with collagen and is often likened to a potage.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Thick type&quot;→&quot;The &quot;kotteri&quot;&quot; &quot;of&quot;→&quot;from&quot;Added commas&quot;it is said to be potage-like soup&quot;→&quot;is often likened to a potage&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &apos;kotteri&apos; soup, made from chicken and vegetables, is thick with collagen and is often likened to a potage.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>「ドロドロ」の正体については、コラーゲンだけでなく、持ち帰り用のスープパックの成分表記から米粉ではないかといわれているが、定かではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although it is not certain, however, the &quot;thickness&quot; of the soup is said to be made not only by collagen but also by powdered rice due to the ingredients label on the soup bag for takeout ramen set.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said, though not proven, that this thickness comes not only from collagen but also from rice flour, which is known to be added from the ingredients label on the soup bag for takeout ramen.</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentenceAdded &quot;which is known to be added&quot; which is not in the original bujt makes the sentence read better</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said, though not proven, that this thickness comes not only from collagen but also from rice flour, which is known to be added from the ingredients label on the soup bag for takeout ramen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>店内には鍋に入ったスープと「健康食品」と描かれたポスターが貼られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the shops, there are pictorial posters of soup in a pot with the logo, &quot;health food.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the shops, there are posters of soup in a pot with the logo, &quot;health food.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;pictorial&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the shops, there are posters of soup in a pot with the logo, &apos;health food.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="22">
<j>鶏ガラ清湯スープ（いわゆる「中華そば」）である「あっさり」は、「こってり」に合わない人には普通のラーメンとして楽しむことができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For those who do not like &quot;thick&quot; type soup, ordinary ramen with &quot;plain&quot; type of Torigara Chintan Soup (a soup with transparent chicken-bone broth) (so-called ordinary Chuka Soba, Chinese noodles) is also available.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For those who do not like the &quot;kotteri&quot; soup, ordinary ramen with &quot;plain&quot; type of Torigara Chintan Soup (a soup with transparent chicken-bone broth), so-called Chuka Soba, Chinese noodles, is also available.</e>
<cmt>&quot;&quot;thick&quot; type&quot;→&quot;the &quot;kotteri&quot;&quot;brackets→commasDeleted &quot;ordinary&quot;Added &quot;or&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For those who do not like the &apos;kotteri&apos; soup, ordinary ramen with &apos;plain&apos; type of Torigara Chintan Soup (a soup with transparent chicken-bone broth), so-called Chuka Soba, Chinese noodles, is also available.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>また、「こってり」は、敬遠する者も多く、『天一はラーメンとは別種の麺類である』と認識する者もいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Not a small number of people avoid &quot;thick&quot; type and some regard it as a different sort of noodles from ramen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many people avoid the &quot;kotteri&quot; type and some regard it as a different sort of noodles from ramen.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Not a small number of&quot;→&quot;Many&quot;&quot;&quot;thick&quot;&quot;→&quot;the &quot;kotteri&quot;&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many people avoid the &apos;kotteri&apos; type and some regard it as a different sort of noodles from ramen.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>「あっさり」と言う名は天一基準であり、店舗によっては一般的な京都ラーメン並に油が浮いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">What they call &quot;plain&quot; at Tenichi is the standard of their own of &quot;Tenichi&quot;, and depends on shops, their ramen with &quot;plain&quot; soup has oil on its surface just the same as common (thick) Kyoto ramen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;assari&quot; ramen are Tenichi&apos;s standard and, depending on the shop, may have oil on the surface, similar to ordinary Kyoto ramen.</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &apos;assari&apos; ramen are Tenichi&apos;s standard and, depending on the shop, may have oil on the surface, similar to ordinary Kyoto ramen.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>ここでの「油」はこってりしたラーメンとしてよくイメージされる固形の背脂（ラード）ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The &quot;oil&quot; mentioned above does not mean that made of solid lard often gives impression of ramen with thick soup.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This &quot;oil&quot; is not the lard that is often associated with thick soup.</e>
<cmt>&quot;The&quot;→&quot;This&quot; &quot;mentioned above does not mean that made of solid lard often gives impression of ramen&quot;→&quot;is not the lard that is often associated&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This &apos;oil&apos; is not the lard that is often associated with thick soup.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="26">
<j>初期は「こってり」のみの商品構成であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At Tenichi, they only serve &quot;thick type&quot; ramen at first.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the restaurant first opened, they only served &quot;kotteri&quot; ramen.</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the restaurant first opened, they only served &apos;kotteri&apos; ramen.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>その他のメニュー</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other Food on the Menu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other Food on the Menu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other food on the menu</e>
<cmt>文頭以外小文字</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="27">
<j>2004年1月に新メニューとして、「味がさね」という自分で濃度を調整できる野菜入り味噌ラーメンが加わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January 2004, they add a sort of &apos;Miso ramen&apos; (ramen with soup made of soy bean paste) with vegetables, &quot;Aji gasane&quot; (a noodle with mixed flavor) on their menu. For &quot;Aji gasane,&quot; diners are able to adjust the thickness of flavor themselves.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In January 2004, they introduced a sort of &apos;miso ramen&apos; (ramen with soup made of soy bean paste) with vegetables, called &quot;Aji gasane,&quot; where diners are able to adjust the thickness themselves.</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。&quot;add&quot;→&quot;introduced&quot;Made &apos;M&apos; lower caseAdded &quot;called&quot;Deleted &quot;(a noodle with mixed flavor) on their menu.&quot;&quot;For &quot;Aji gasane,&quot;→&quot;where&quot;Deleted &quot;of flavor&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In January 2004, they introduced a sort of &apos;miso ramen&apos; (ramen with soup made of soy bean paste) with vegetables, called &apos;Aji gasane,&apos; where diners are able to adjust the thickness themselves..</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>それまで存在した「4号」と呼ばれる味噌ラーメンは、味がさねの登場により販売終了となった）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the introduction of &quot;Aji gasane&quot;, miso ramen called &quot;Number 4&quot; was discontinued.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the introduction of &quot;Aji gasane&quot;, the miso ramen called &quot;Number 4&quot; was discontinued.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the introduction of &apos;Aji gasane,&apos; the miso ramen called &apos;Number 4&apos; was discontinued.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;コンマの位置</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>なお、「味がさね」は定食に組み込むことが出来ない店舗がほとんどである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, &quot;Aji gasane&quot; are not permitted to set within a combination meal at most shops.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, &quot;Aji gasane&quot; cannot be ordered as part of a combination meal at most shops.</e>
<cmt>&quot;not permitted to set within a&quot;→&quot;cannot be ordered as part of&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, &apos;Aji gasane&apos; cannot be ordered as part of a combination meal at most shops.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="30">
<j>また、「こってり」と「あっさり」のスープを半々に混ぜた「2号」（別名「屋台ラーメン」、「こっさり」あるいは「マイルド」）というのもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is also a ramen called &quot;Number 2&quot; with mixed soup of &quot;thick type&quot; and &quot;plain type&quot; in halves of which bynames are, &quot;Street stall ramen&quot;, &quot;Mild&quot; or &quot;Kossari&quot; (a complex word of &apos;kotteri&apos; that means thick and &apos;assari&apos; that means plain.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is also a ramen called &quot;Number 2&quot;, which is half kotteri soup and half assari soup mixed together (it is also known as &quot;Street stall ramen&quot;, &quot;Mild&quot; or &quot;Kossari&quot;).</e>
<cmt>&quot;with mixed soup of &quot;thick type&quot; and &quot;plain type&quot; in halves&quot;→&quot;which is half kotteri soup and half assari soup mixed together&quot;&quot;bynames are, &quot;Street stall ramen&quot;, &quot;Mild&quot; or &quot;Kossari&quot; (a complex word of &apos;kotteri&apos; that means thick and &apos;assari&apos; that means plain.)&quot;→&quot;(it is also known as &quot;Street stall ramen&quot;, &quot;Mild&quot; or &quot;Kossari&quot;).&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is also a ramen called &apos;Number 2,&apos; which is half kotteri soup and half assari soup mixed together (it is also known as &apos;Street stall ramen,&apos; &apos;Mild&apos; or &apos;Kossari&apos;).</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;コンマの位置</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>もともとは、裏メニューだったが（「こってり」が「1号」、「あっさり」が「3号」という厨房の符丁が有り、そこから来ている）、最近、多くの店でメニューに記載されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although it was not a formally served foodstuff listed on the menu (#2 came from the kitchen secret language, I.e. #1 for thick type and #3 for plain type and #2 for the mixed,) recently, it becomes to be listed on the menu at many shops.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although it was not officially on the menu (the name comes from the kitchen code with &quot;Number 1&quot; meaning &quot;kotteri&quot;, &quot;Number 3&quot;, &quot;assari&quot; and &quot;Number 2&quot;, mixed), many shops have recently started including it.</e>
<cmt>&quot;a formally served foodstuff listed&quot;→&quot;officially on the menu&quot;Changed section in brackets&quot;recently, it becomes to be listed on the menu at many shops&quot;→&quot;, many shops have recently started including it&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it was not officially on the menu (the name comes from the kitchen code with &apos;Number 1&apos; meaning &apos;kotteri,&apos; &apos;Number 3,&apos; &apos;assari&apos; and &apos;Number 2,&apos; mixed), many shops have recently started including it.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>メニューに記載がない店でも、「中間」あるいは「二番」と言えば、大抵は作ってくれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even in a case when it is not on the menu, usually they serve it when a diner orders &quot;intermediate&quot; or &quot;Number 2.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even in cases when it is not on the menu, it is served if a customer orders an &quot;intermediate&quot; or &quot;Number 2.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Made &quot;case&quot; plural&quot;&quot;it is served if a customer&quot;→&quot;head office&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even in cases when it is not on the menu, it is served if a customer orders an &apos;intermediate&apos; or &apos;Number 2.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="33">
<j>店によっては裏メニューとして「超こってり」を出す店もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A few shops serve ramen with &quot;super thick&quot; soup which is not listed on the formal menu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A few shops serve ramen with &quot;super thick&quot; soup which is not included on the official menu.</e>
<cmt>&quot;listed&quot;&quot;included&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A few shops serve ramen with &apos;super thick&apos; soup which is not included on the official menu.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>製法はこってり用のスープを小鍋に取り煮詰める、というもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The recipe is to pour thick type soup in small pan and boil it down.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is made by boiling down &quot;kotteri&quot; soup in a small pan.</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is made by boiling down kotteri soup in a small pan.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>ただ、これは天下一品本部未公認であり、数店舗しか対応していないようだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it is not officially permitted by the headquarter of Tenka-ippin and only a few shops cope with this.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is not officially permitted by Tenka-ippin head office and only a few shops serve it.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the headquarter of&quot;→&quot;head office&quot; and moved&quot;cope with this&quot;→&quot;serve it&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is not officially permitted by Tenka-ippin head office and only a few shops serve it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>サービスとその変遷</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Service and Its Transition</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Changes in Service</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Changes in service</e>
<cmt>文頭以外小文字</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="36">
<j>カウンターにはスープのタレが置かれており、味の微調整をすることができる（置いてない店舗もあり）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the bar of the shops are &apos;tare&apos; (in this case, condensed soup or soup stock) and diners are able to adjust the flavor themselves (it is not available in some shops.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some shops have &apos;tare&apos; (in this case, condensed soup or soup stock) on the counter so that diners are able to adjust the flavor themselves.</e>
<cmt>&quot;On the bar&quot;→&quot;on the counter&quot; and moved&quot;of the shops are&quot;→&quot;Some shops have&quot;&quot;and&quot;→&quot;so that&quot;Deletefd &quot;(it is not available in some shops.)&quot;Added full stop</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some shops have &apos;tare&apos; (in this case, condensed soup or soup stock) on the counter so that diners are able to adjust the flavor themselves.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>また、前述の唐辛子入りのおろしニンニクや、発酵した芳香のあるからし味噌（唐辛子入りの味噌）が備えられているのも特徴である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, diners are able to add aforementioned grated garlic with chili pepper (ninton) and aromatic fermented &apos;karashi-miso&apos; (miso with chili pepper) to served ramen according to taste at these shops.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, diners are able to add the aforementioned grated garlic with chili pepper (ninton) as well as aromatic fermented &apos;karashi-miso&apos; (miso with chili pepper).</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;&quot;and&quot;→&quot;as well as&quot;Deleted &quot; to served ramen according to taste at these shops&quot; - not in the original</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, diners are able to add the aforementioned grated garlic with chili pepper (ninton) as well as aromatic fermented &apos;karashi-miso&apos; (miso with chili pepper).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="38">
<j>1985年頃までは基本的に各店舗でスープを仕込んでいたため、チェーンといえども各店舗ごとに、および同じ店舗でも日により、さらに同じ日でも時間帯により味のばらつきがあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Tenichi are chain stores, as the soup was basically prepared by each shop until around 1985, the flavor of soup varied depends on the shop, the day and even the time of the day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Tenichi are chain stores, as the soup was basically prepared by each shop until around 1985, the flavor of the soup varied depends on the shop, the day and even the time of the day.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;&quot;depends&quot;→&quot;depending&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Tenichi are chain stores, as the soup was basically prepared by each shop until around 1985, the flavor of the soup varied depends on the shop, the day and even the time of the day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>仕込鍋の中のスープにはスープを煮出す材料がふんだんに投入されており、そのまま丼に入れると、元が何かわからない細かいものが浮いていたが、後に、丼投入時には笊で漉すようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The soup pot was filled with full of ingredients and when it was directly poured into ramen bowl, minute scum of ingredients were used to be on the surface of the soup, however, later they began to infilter when pouring soup into a bowl.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When making the soup, the pot was filled with ingredients and then the soup was poured directly into the ramen bowl, resulting in minute bits of ingredients floating on the surface, although they later began to filter the soup.</e>
<cmt>&quot;The soup&quot;→&quot;When making the soup, the&quot;Deleted &quot;full of&quot;&quot;when it&quot;→&quot;then the soup&quot;Moved &quot;directly&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;&quot;minute scum&quot;→&quot;resulting in minute bits&quot;&quot;were used to be&quot;→&quot;floating&quot;Deleted &quot;of the soup&quot;&quot;however, later they&quot;→&quot;although they later&quot;&quot;infilter when pouring soup into a bowl&quot;→&quot;filter the soup&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When making the soup, the pot was filled with ingredients and then the soup was poured directly into the ramen bowl, resulting in minute bits of ingredients floating on the surface, although they later began to filter the soup.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>現在のスープは関連会社「株式会社タック・フーズ」のセントラルキッチンで仕込んだスープを真空パックで各店舗に配送し、各店舗ではこの真空パックのスープを元に濃度や味の調整を行った上で提供している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today, the soup is prepared by the central kitchen of &quot;Takku Foods, Ltd&quot;, an affiliate company of Tenka-ippin, and it is vacuum-packed and delivered to the shops, and each shop adjusts flavor and taste of the vacuum-packed soup and serves it at the shop.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, the soup is prepared at the central kitchen of &quot;Takku Foods, Ltd&quot;, an affiliate company of Tenka-ippin, before being vacuum-packed and delivered to the shops, where they adjust the thickness and flavor before serving.</e>
<cmt>&quot;by&quot;→&quot;at&quot;&quot;and it is&quot;→&quot;before being&quot;&quot;and each shop adjusts flavor and taste of the vacuum-packed soup and serves it at the shop&quot;→&quot;where they adjust the thickness and flavor before serving&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, the soup is prepared at the central kitchen of &apos;Takku Foods, Ltd,&apos; an affiliate company of Tenka-ippin, before being vacuum-packed and delivered to the shops, where they adjust the thickness and flavor before serving.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;コンマの位置</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>セントラルキッチン方式にも関わらず店舗によって（以前に比べれば統一されているとは言え）味にバラつきがあるのは、この調整（具体的には元ダレの量や、加温方法など）について店の裁量に任されている部分が大きい為である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reason why the flavor varies depends on shops (even though its degree is lowered than before) although they adopted central kitchen system is that this adjustment of the flavor (more precisely, volume of soup stock used and the way to heat) is up to the discretion of shop&apos;s cook at large.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This adjustment of the flavor (or more precisely, the volume of soup stock used and the method of heating) is up to the discretion of shop&apos;s cook, which is a big reason why the flavor varies depending on shops (although to a lesser extent than before) even with the central kitchen system.</e>
<cmt>&quot;The&quot;→&quot;A big&quot;&quot;depends&quot;→&quot;depending&quot;&quot;even though its degree is lowered&quot;→&quot;although to a lesser extent&quot;&quot;although they adopted&quot;→&quot;even with the&quot;Added &quot;or&quot;, &quot;the&quot;&quot;way to heat&quot;→&quot;method of heating&quot;Deleted &quot;at large&quot;Changed word orderAdded &quot;which is&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This adjustment of the flavor (or more precisely, the volume of soup stock used and the method of heating) is up to the discretion of shop&apos;s cook, which is a big reason why the flavor varies depending on shops (although to a lesser extent than before) even with the central kitchen system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>現在は経営が大きく分けて直営店・フランチャイズ店の2系統の店舗があり、価格設定が異なる場合がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today, the management of the shops generally belong to two systems: one is company shop and another is franchised shop and pricing of the two sometimes differ.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, shops are either directly managed or run as a franchise and prices can differ between the two.</e>
<cmt>Rerworded sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, shops are either directly managed or run as a franchise and prices can differ between the two.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>提供されるメニューもフランチャイズ店などにおいては、サブメニューが多かったり、またランチビュッフェを行っている店舗もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Served food also differ by the line and there are more dishes on the submenu at franchised shops and some of them provide so-called lunch buffet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The food at franchises also differs, with more dishes on the submenu and some of them offering a lunch buffet.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Served food also differ by the line and there are&quot;→&quot;The food at franchises also differs, with&quot;Deleted &quot;franchised shops&quot;&quot;provide so-called&quot;→&quot;offering a&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The food at franchises also differs, with more dishes on the submenu and some of them offering a lunch buffet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="44">
<j>当初、北白川総本店をはじめとした直営店においては青ネギは青いプラスチック製のザルに入れて供され、自由に入れることができた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At first, green onion was served in a plastic-made colander and diners were able to take it freely at the company shops such as the central head shop in Kitashirakawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At first, at directly-managed shops such as the central head shop in Kitashirakawa, green onion was served in a plastic colander and customers were able to help themselves.</e>
<cmt>Moved &quot;at the company shops such as the central head shop in Kitashirakawa&quot;&quot;the company&quot;→&quot;directly-managed&quot;Deleted &quot;-made&quot;&quot;diners&quot;→&quot;customers&quot;&quot;take it freely&quot;→&quot;help themselves&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At first, at directly-managed shops such as the central head shop in Kitashirakawa, green onion was served in a blue plastic colander and customers were able to help themselves.</e>
<cmt>blue補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>最近は北白川総本店においてもこのネギの入ったザルは姿を消し、一部の直営店でしか見ることはできない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Recently, this service is discontinued even in the central head shop in Kitashirakawa, and available at only a few company shops.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Recently, this service has been discontinued, even at the central head shop in Kitashirakawa, and available at only a few directly-managed shops.</e>
<cmt>&quot;is&quot;→&quot;has been&quot;Added comma&quot;in&quot;→&quot;at&quot;Added &quot;is&quot;&quot;company&quot;→&quot;directly-managed&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Recently, this service has been discontinued, even at the central head shop in Kitashirakawa, and available at only a few directly-managed shops.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>また、ゆで卵を食べ放題とする店舗もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some shops provide the diners with all-you-can-eat soft-boiled eggs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some shops provide the diners with all-you-can-eat soft-boiled eggs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some shops provide the diners with all-you-can-eat soft-boiled eggs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="47">
<j>2007年より約1年間、従来のストレート麺の他に、縮れ麺が選択できるようになっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">About one year from 2007, diners were able to choose wavy noodles other than basic straight noodles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For about one year from 2007, diners were able to choose wavy noodles as well as the basic straight noodles.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;For&quot;&quot;other&quot;→&quot;as well as&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For about one year from 2007, diners were able to choose wavy noodles as well as the basic straight noodles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>また、2009年現在は細麺が選択できるようになっている（これらは数量限定であったり、置いていない店舗もあったりする）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, today in 2009, visitors are able to choose thin noodles (although it is limited in quantity or it is not available at some shops.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, as of 2009, visitors are able to choose thin noodles (although they are limited in quantity and are not available at some shops).</e>
<cmt>&quot;today in&quot;→&quot;as of&quot;&quot;it is&quot;→&quot;they are&quot;&quot;or it is&quot;→&quot;and are&quot;Moved full stop</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, as of 2009, visitors are able to choose thin noodles (although they are limited in quantity and are not available at some shops).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>なお、味がさねおよび冷麺は専用麺のため、細麺は注文できないことになっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Noodles used for &apos;Aji gasane&apos; and &apos;Reimen&apos; (cold noodles) are specific for them and thin noodle is not available.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The noodles used for &apos;Aji gasane&apos; and &apos;Reimen&apos; (cold noodles) are specific to them and thin noodles are not available.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;The&quot;&quot;for&quot;→&quot;to&quot;&quot;noodle is&quot;→&quot;noodles are&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The noodles used for &apos;Aji gasane&apos; and &apos;Reimen&apos; (cold noodles) are specific to them and thin noodles are not available.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>CM</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Commercial Messages</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TV Commercials</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;TV&quot;Deleted &quot;Messages&quot;Made &quot;Commercial&quot; plural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TV Commercials</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="50">
<j>コマーシャルメッセージには、過去に河内家菊水丸や筒井康隆が出演しており、現在はベッキー（「味がさね」のイメージキャラクターだったが、以降も継続してCMに出演）が出演したバージョンが放送されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Kikusuimaru KAWACHIYA and Yasutaka TSUTSUI appeared in the commercial message in the past, Becky&apos;s version is now on the air (she once was a poster child for &apos;Aji gasane&apos; and continued to appear in the CM of Tenka-ippin.)</e>
<cmt>「河内家菊水丸」の読みはこの様にしています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While Kikusuimaru KAWACHIYA and Yasutaka TSUTSUI have appeared in commercials in the past, Becky&apos;s version is now on the air (after being the poster child for &apos;Aji gasane&apos;, she continued by starring in the commercials.)</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;have&quot;Deleted &quot;the&quot;Made &quot;commercial&quot; pluralDeleted &quot;messages&quot;&quot;she once was a&quot;→&quot;after being the&quot;Added comma&quot;and continued to appear in the CM of Tenka-ippin&quot;→&quot;she continued by starring in the commercials&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While Kikusuimaru KAWACHIYA and Yasutaka TSUTSUI have appeared in commercials in the past, Becky&apos;s version is now on the air (after being the poster child for &apos;Aji gasane,&apos; she continued by starring in the commercials).</e>
<cmt>コンマ、ピリオドの位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>CMには、しばしば、創業社長の木村勉も出演している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The founder and president of Tenka-ippin Tsutomu KIMURA also often appeared in the CM.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The founder and president of Tenka-ippin Tsutomu KIMURA also often appears in the commercials.</e>
<cmt>&quot;appeared&quot;→&quot;appears&quot;&quot;CM&quot;→&quot;commercials&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The founder and president of Tenka-ippin Tsutomu KIMURA also often appears in the commercials.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>またハワイで放送されているローカルCMには、元横綱の武蔵丸光洋が出演している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ex-Grand Sumo wrestling champion, Koyo MUSASHIMARU appears in the local CM aired in the Hawaiian islands.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ex-Grand Sumo wrestling champion, Koyo MUSASHIMARU appears in the local commercials aired in the Hawaiian islands.</e>
<cmt>&quot;CM&quot;→&quot;commercials&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ex-Grand Sumo wrestling champion, Koyo MUSASHIMARU appears in the local commercials aired in the Hawaiian islands.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>天一の日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tenichi Day</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tenichi Day</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tenichi Day</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="53">
<j>毎年10月1日は天一の日として各店舗でキャンペーンが行われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They wage campaign at each shop on every October 1 named the day as Tenichi Day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They hold a campaign at each shop on every October 1, known as Tenichi Day.</e>
<cmt>&quot;wage&quot;→&quot;hold a&quot;&quot;named the day&quot;→&quot;, known&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They hold a campaign at each shop on every October 1, known as Tenichi Day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>麺類や麺類を含む定食を注文すると、1ヶ月間有効のラーメン1杯無料券が貰えるというもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A voucher for one bowl of free ramen good for one month is given to a visitor when he orders noodles or set menu including noodles on the day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A voucher for one bowl of free ramen good for one month is given to customers when they order noodles or a set menu including noodles.</e>
<cmt>&quot;a visitor&quot;→&quot;customers&quot;&quot;he orders&quot;→&quot;they order&quot;Added &quot;a&quot;Deleted &quot;on the day&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A voucher for one bowl of free ramen good for one month is given to customers when they order noodles or a set menu including noodles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>翌日からの1週間はスピードくじが配布される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For one week from the next day of Tenichi Day, instant lottery is provided.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For one week from the day after Tenichi Day, there is an instant lottery.</e>
<cmt>&quot;next day of&quot;→&quot;the day after&quot;&quot;instant lottery is provided&quot;→&quot;there is an instant lottery&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For one week from the day after Tenichi Day, there is an instant lottery.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>2005年はストラップや100円割引券などが景品だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Free gift in 2005 was a strap for cell-phone or 100 Yen discount voucher.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The prizes in 2005 included cell-phone straps and 100-yen discount vouchers.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Free gift&quot;→&quot;The prizes&quot;&quot;was&quot;→&quot;included&quot;&quot;a strap for cell-phone&quot;→&quot;cell-phone straps&quot;&quot;or 100 Yen discount voucher&quot;→&quot;and 100-yen discount vouchers&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The prizes in 2005 included cell-phone straps and 100-yen discount vouchers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>過去には店の丼を模した小型の丼などの景品もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Small bowls modeled shop bowl were provided as free gifts in the past.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other gifts in the past included small models of the bowls used in the shops.</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other gifts in the past included small models of the bowls used in the shops.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 青井岳(id:82630), Whity(id:13629), Chinamie(id:213556), 春野秋葉(id:36725), Immortal(id:16871), Yanahan(id:2437), Frame(id:95820), Arumakan(id:18779), Martin(id:6394), MikimaruGT(id:84553), Naru-W(id:17852), Freedonian(id:110955), Guchi(id:119384), Yasu2006(id:93004), MCHC(id:208548), Kenpei(id:11349), Mochi(id:9489), ＮｉＫｅ(id:7512), Happy(id:24511), 竹やり(id:243021), Point136(id:211299), こぶまき(id:38278), Tmatsu(id:10583), Calvero(id:38360), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>