<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>京漆器</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyo-shikki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyo-shikki (Kyoto lacquerware)</e>
<cmt>(Kyoto lacquerware) を追記しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyo-shikki (Kyoto lacquerware)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>京漆器（きょうしっき）とは、京都市内で生産される工芸品的な漆器のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyo-shikki (Kyo-lacquered ware) is a handicraft of lacquerware produced in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kyo-shikki&quot; is a handicraft of lacquerware produced in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>Kyo-shikki にダブルコーテーションを追記しました。 (Kyo-lacquered ware) を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Kyo-shikki&quot; is a handicraft of lacquerware produced in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>実用性も併せ持ち、日本を代表する漆器となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Being of practical use as well, it has become the best lacquerware in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Being of practical use as well, it is one of Japan&apos;s best-known lacquerware in Japan.</e>
<cmt>has become the best をis one of Japan&apos;s best-known に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Being of practical use as well, it is one of Japan&apos;s best-known lacquerware in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>京漆器は全国の漆器産地の中でも、とりわけ薄い木地を用い、入念な下地を施し、洗練された優美な蒔絵が施された、日常的に使う器というよりも「美術工芸品」としての価値観に基づいてつくられる漆器である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyo-shikki is a lacquerware produced on the basis of values as &quot;works of arts and crafts&quot; rather than as serving dishes for daily use, being made from thinner wood grain, treated with foundation more carefully and given more sophisticated and elegant makie (Japanese lacquer sprinkled with gold or silver powder) on it than lacquerwares produced in any other area of Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyo-shikki is a lacquerware produced on the basis of values as &apos;arts and crafts&apos; rather than as serving dishes for daily use, being made from thinner wood grain, treated with foundation more carefully and given more sophisticated and elegant makie (Japanese lacquer sprinkled with gold or silver powder) on it than lacquerware produced in any other area of Japan.</e>
<cmt>&quot;works of arts and crafts&quot; を &apos;arts and crafts&apos; に修正しました。lacquerwares を lacquerware に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyo-shikki is a lacquerware produced on the basis of values as &apos;arts and crafts&apos; rather than as serving dishes for daily use, being made from thinner wood grain, treated with foundation more carefully and given more sophisticated and elegant makie (Japanese lacquer sprinkled with gold or silver powder) on it than lacquerware produced in any other area of Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>京都は平安遷都以後現在に至るまで、政治・文化と同様に日本の漆工芸の中心地として王朝貴族の祭祀装飾品から茶道具まで特に手間隙をかけた完成度の高い漆器を送り出してきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto has been the center of production of lacquer craftworks in Japan as well as of politics and culture since the transfer of national capital to the city of Heian-kyo, supplying high-quality lacquerware made with a great deal of time and care, from religious service accessories to tea utensils of the royalty and nobility.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto has been the center of production of lacquer craftworks in Japan as well as of politics and culture since the transfer of national capital to the city of Heian-kyo, supplying high-quality lacquerware made with a great deal of time and care, from religious service accessories to tea utensils of the royalty and nobility.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto has been the center of production of lacquer craftworks in Japan as well as of politics and culture since the transfer of national capital to the city of Heian-kyo, supplying high-quality lacquerware made with a great deal of time and care, from religious service accessories to tea utensils of the royalty and nobility.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>顧客である公家や商家と隣接し発達した京漆器は薄く繊細で気品高いデザインをもち、他産地の漆器に比して極端に高価である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Having developed side-by-side with court nobles and mercantile houses who are its customers, Kyo-shikki is extremely expensive compared with lacquerwares produced in the other areas, with a design which is thin, delicate and elegant.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Having developed side-by-side with court nobles and mercantile houses who are its customers, Kyo-shikki is extremely expensive compared with lacquerware produced in the other areas, with a design which is thin, delicate and elegant.</e>
<cmt>lacquerwares を lacquerware に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Having developed side-by-side with court nobles and mercantile houses who are its customers, Kyo-shikki is extremely expensive compared with lacquerware produced in the other areas, with a design which is thin, delicate and elegant.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>こうした京漆器の工芸品は大名同士の贈答品にも用いられ全国に伝播したことから、地方漆器の起源や生産工程に影響を与えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As these handicrafts of Kyo-shikki were used as presents between daimyos (Japanese territorial lords) and spread all over Japan, they have influenced the origin and manufacture process of the other local lacquerwares.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As these handicrafts of Kyo-shikki were used as presents between daimyos (Japanese territorial lords) and spread all over Japan, they have influenced the origin and manufacture process of the other local lacquerware.</e>
<cmt>lacquerwares を lacquerware に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As these handicrafts of Kyo-shikki were used as presents between daimyos (Japanese territorial lords) and spread all over Japan, they have influenced the origin and manufacture process of the other local lacquerware.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="8">
<j>特徴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Characteristics</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Characteristics</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Characteristics</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>京漆器の特徴は薄手の木地に漆と澱粉糊で麻布を貼って補強し、その上に京都市山科区から産出する「山科地之粉」「山科砥之粉」等を漆で練り合わせてペースト状にした「地錆漆」「錆漆」という下地材を何層にもわたって塗り重ね、さらに器の角の部分をより鋭角を際立たせ、丈夫にするために補強する「くくり錆」という工程をはさみ、黒や赤のうるしを塗り重ねていくという「本堅地」という漆工芸において最も基本的な製作工程にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The characteristics of Kyo-shikki is &quot;Honkataji,&quot; the most basic process of manufacturing lacquer craftworks in which thin wood grain is reinforced with hemp attached to it by using lacquer and starch glue, layers of foundation called &quot;Jisabiurushi&quot; and &quot;Sabiurushi,&quot; which is a kind of paste made from &quot;Yamashina Jinoko&quot; and &quot;Yamashina Tonoko&quot;(both are produced in Yamashina Ward, Kyoto City) mixed together with lacquer, are applied onto the reinforced wood grain, and, after a process called &quot;Kukurisabi&quot; in which the corners of the artifact are reinforced for the purpose of strengthening and making the sharp edge sharper, black and red lacquer is applied onto it layer by layer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The characteristics of Kyo-shikki is &quot;Honkataji,&quot; the most basic process of manufacturing lacquer craftworks in which thin wood grain is reinforced with hemp attached to it by using lacquer and starch glue, layers of foundation called &quot;Jisabiurushi&quot; and &quot;Sabiurushi,&quot; which is a kind of paste made from &quot;Yamashina Jinoko&quot; and &quot;Yamashina Tonoko&quot;both produced in Yamashina Ward, Kyoto City and mixed together with lacquer, are applied onto the reinforced wood grain, and, after a process called &quot;Kukurisabi&quot; in which the corners of the artifact are reinforced for the purpose of strengthening and making the sharp edge sharper, black and red lacquer is applied onto it layer by layer.</e>
<cmt>(both are produced in Yamashina Ward, Kyoto City) を both produced in Yamashina Ward, Kyoto City and に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The characteristics of Kyo-shikki is &quot;Honkataji,&quot; the most basic process of manufacturing lacquer craftworks in which thin wood grain is reinforced with hemp attached to it by using lacquer and starch glue, layers of foundation called &quot;Jisabiurushi&quot; and &quot;Sabiurushi,&quot; which is a kind of paste made from &quot;Yamashina Jinoko&quot; and &quot;Yamashina Tonoko&quot;both produced in Yamashina Ward, Kyoto City and mixed together with lacquer, are applied onto the reinforced wood grain, and, after a process called &quot;Kukurisabi&quot; in which the corners of the artifact are reinforced for the purpose of strengthening and making the sharp edge sharper, black and red lacquer is applied onto it layer by layer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="10">
<j>「本堅地」の工程は漆器製作の技術が地方に広まり、地方産地が形成されていくと共に越前漆器、山中塗、輪島塗などの製作工程にも受けつかがれていくが、それらの産地では生産量に見合った作業効率が必要になるために下地材に米糊などを混合することが一般的である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the manufacturing technique of lacquerware spread across provincial areas and local lacquerware was created, the process of &quot;Honkataji&quot; was passed on to manufacturing processes of Echizen lacquerware, Yamanaka-nuri and Wajima-nuri lacquerware, but it is common practice to mix rice glue into foundation in Echizen, Yamanaka and Wajima because work efficiency concomitant with production volume is required.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the manufacturing technique of lacquerware spread across provincial areas and local lacquerware was created, the process of &quot;Honkataji&quot; was passed on to manufacturing processes of Echizen lacquerware, Yamanaka-nuri and Wajima-nuri lacquerware, but it is common practice to mix rice glue into foundation in Echizen, Yamanaka and Wajima because work efficiency concomitant with production volume is required.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the manufacturing technique of lacquerware spread across provincial areas and local lacquerware was created, the process of &quot;Honkataji&quot; was passed on to manufacturing processes of Echizen lacquerware, Yamanaka-nuri and Wajima-nuri lacquerware, but it is common practice to mix rice glue into foundation in Echizen, Yamanaka and Wajima because work efficiency concomitant with production volume is required.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>米糊の添加は、器物に下地を付ける作業とその硬化管理を容易にすることができ、作業性をあげるメリットがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is beneficial to add rice glue because application of foundation to the artifact and its cure control are made easier and as a result workability is improved.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is beneficial to add rice glue because application of foundation to the artifact and its cure control are made easier and as a result workability is improved.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is beneficial to add rice glue because application of foundation to the artifact and its cure control are made easier and as a result workability is improved.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>しかし樹脂分の漆、地之粉や砥之粉等のフィラーの他に、耐水性に乏しい澱粉を配合することで下地の耐久性は低下する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, durability is lowered by blending resin (lacquer), fillers such as Jinoko and Taonoko, and starch, which has less resistance to water.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, durability is lowered by blending resin (lacquer), fillers such as Jinoko and Taonoko, and starch, which has less resistance to water.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, durability is lowered by blending resin (lacquer), fillers such as Jinoko and Taonoko, and starch, which has less resistance to water.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="13">
<j>一方、単価の高い小ロット品の生産を得意とする京漆器では米糊などを添加しないため、下地材全体に対する漆の割合が50重量％程度（wet重量、固形分では60重量％程度）と、樹脂分の高い下地を施すためコストはかかるが堅牢な器ができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, in the case of Kyo-shikki good at production of small lots with a high unit price, percentage of lacquer in the whole foundation is about 50 percent by weight (wet)/60 percent by weight (dry) because rice glue is not added, so the artifacts are costly but durable thanks to foundation which contains much resin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, in the case of Kyo-shikki good at production of small lots with a high unit price, percentage of lacquer in the whole foundation is about 50 percent by weight (wet)/60 percent by weight (dry) because rice glue is not added, so the artifacts are costly but durable thanks to foundation which contains much resin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, in the case of Kyo-shikki good at production of small lots with a high unit price, percentage of lacquer in the whole foundation is about 50 percent by weight (wet)/60 percent by weight (dry) because rice glue is not added, so the artifacts are costly but durable thanks to foundation which contains much resin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="14">
<j>経済産業大臣より『伝統的工芸品』の指定を受けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyo-shikki is designated as &quot;Traditional Crafts&quot; by the Minister for Economy, Trade and Industry.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyo-shikki is designated as &quot;Traditional Crafts&quot; by the Minister for Economy, Trade and Industry.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyo-shikki is designated as &quot;Traditional Crafts&quot; by the Minister for Economy, Trade and Industry.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Mois(id:30596), 新茶(id:157775), 橄欖岩(id:24996), 藤原朝臣太政大臣忠宣公(id:48007), 徒労筆(id:160300), 小太刀(id:18154), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>