<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>お歯黒</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ohaguro (Tooth black)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ohaguro (Tooth black)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ohaguro (Tooth black)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>お歯黒（おはぐろ）は明治時代以前の日本や中国南東部・東南アジアの主として既婚女性、まれに男性などの歯を黒く染める化粧法である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ohaguro (tooth blackening) is the cosmetic treatment of dyeing teeth to black used chiefly by married women (or occasionally men) in Japan, southeast China or Southeast Asia, before the Meiji Era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ohaguro (tooth blackening) is the cosmetic treatment of dyeing teeth black used chiefly by married women (or occasionally men) in Japan, southeast China or Southeast Asia, before the Meiji Era.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ohaguro (tooth blackening) is the cosmetic treatment of dyeing teeth black used chiefly by married women (or occasionally men) in Japan, southeast China or Southeast Asia, before the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>eraに訂正しました。era→periodに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>日本</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>日本では古代から存在したとされ、民間には明治時代末期まで見られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is assumed to exist from ancient Japan, and could be seen among the common people until the late Meiji Era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was assumed to exist from ancient Japan, and could be seen among the common people until the late Meiji Era.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was assumed to exist from ancient Japan, and could be seen among the common people until the late Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>eraに訂正しました。era→periodに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>漆のような艶のある真っ黒が美しいとされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was considered that the jet-black with the gloss like the Japanese lacquer is beautiful.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was considered that jet-black with a gloss like Japanese lacquer was beautiful.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was considered that jet-black with a gloss like Japanese lacquer was beautiful.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>名称</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Name</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Name</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Name</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>「お歯黒」というのは日本の貴族の用語である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Tooth black&quot; is a term used by the aristocracy in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Tooth black&quot; is a term used by the aristocracy in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Ogaguro&quot; (tooth black) is a term used by the aristocracy in Japan.</e>
<cmt>読みを補足、訳は（）に入れました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>「おはぐろ」の読みに鉄漿の字を当てることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The kanji characters of Ohaguro (tooth black) are sometimes written as &quot;iron paste&quot;, and thus pronounced as Kane.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The kanji characters of Ohaguro (tooth black) are sometimes written as &quot;iron paste,&quot; and thus is pronounced as Kane.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The kanji characters of Ohaguro (tooth black) are sometimes written as &quot;iron paste (鉄漿),&quot; and thus is pronounced as Kane.</e>
<cmt>漢字補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>御所では五倍子水（ふしみず）という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Imperial Palace, it is called fushimizu (gallnut water).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Imperial Palace, it is called fushimizu (gallnut water).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Imperial Palace, it is called fushimizu (gallnut water).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>民間では鉄漿付け（かねつけ）、つけがね、歯黒め（はぐろめ）はなどとも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among common people, it was also called something like Kanetsuke (Iron Paste attachment), Tsukegane (attached Iron Paste), or Hagurome (Tooth Black).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the common people, it was also called something like Kanetsuke (Iron Paste attachment), Tsukegane (attached Iron Paste), or Hagurome (Tooth Black).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the common people, it was also called something like Kanetsuke (Iron Paste attachment), Tsukegane (attached Iron Paste), or Hagurome (Tooth Black).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>古墳に埋葬されていた人骨や埴輪にはお歯黒の跡が見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The remains of the tooth black were discovered among human bones and clay figures buried in ancient burial mounds.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The remains of the tooth black were discovered among human bones and clay figures buried in ancient burial mounds.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The remains of the tooth black were discovered among human bones and clay figures buried in ancient burial mounds.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>山海経に黒歯国（『三国志 (歴史書)』魏志倭人伝では倭国東方）があると記述がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Sengaikyo (oldest topography of China)&quot;, it was written that there is Kokushi-koku (literally, &quot;&quot;black-teeth country&quot;&quot;). In &apos;Gishi-wajin-den (the first written record of Japan&apos;s commerce)&apos; of the history book &quot;Sangokushi (Three Kingdom Saga)&quot;, it was written as Wakoku Toho (eastern country, Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;Sengaikyo (oldest topography of China)&quot;, it was written that there is Kokushi-koku (literally, &quot;&quot;black-teeth country&quot;&quot;). In &apos;Gishi-wajin-den (the first written record of Japan&apos;s commerce)&apos; of the history book &quot;Sangokushi (Three Kingdoms of Saga),&quot; it was written as Wakoku Toho (eastern country, Japan).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;Sengaikyo&quot; (oldest topography of China), it was written that there is Kokushi-koku (literally, &quot;black-teeth country&quot;); in Gishi-wajin-den (the first written record of Japan&apos;s commerce) of the history book &quot;Sangokushi&quot; (Three Kingdoms of Saga), it was written as Wakoku Toho (eastern country, Japan).</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。&quot;の位置を訂正。スペース削除原文に「」がないので&apos; &apos;を削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>（『源氏物語』末摘花の注では「歯黒 山海経云東海有黒歯国其俗婦人歯志黒染」とある。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(In the explanatory note of the chapter Suetsumuhana in &quot;The Tale of Genji&quot;, it was written that, Sengaikyo says there is a black-teeth country in which the women have the customs of dyeing their teeth black.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(In the explanatory note of the chapter Suetsumuhana in &quot;The Tale of Genji,&quot; it was written that, Sengaikyo says there is a black-teeth country in which the women practice the custom of dyeing their teeth black.)</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(In the explanatory note of the chapter Suetsumuhana in &quot;The Tale of Genji,&quot; it was written that, Sengaikyo says there is a black-teeth country in which the women practice the custom of dyeing their teeth black.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>753年に鑑真が持参した製法が東大寺の正倉院に現存する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The making method that Jianzhen used in 753 still remains now in Shoso-in House of Todai-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The method that Jianzhen used in 753 still remains now in Shoso-in House of Todai-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The method that Jianzhen used in 753 still remains now in Shoso-in House of Todai-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>お歯黒に関する言及は『源氏物語』、『堤中納言物語』にもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;The Tale of Genji&quot; and &quot;Tsutsumi-Chunagon Monogatari (Ten shorter stories collection after later Heian Era)&quot; also mentioned about tooth blackening.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;The Tale of Genji&quot; and &quot;Tsutsumi-Chunagon Monogatari (Ten shorter stories collection after later Heian Era)&quot; also mentioned tooth blackening.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;The Tale of Genji&quot; and &quot;Tsutsumi-Chunagon Monogatari&quot; (Ten shorter stories collection after later Heian period) also mentioned tooth blackening.</e>
<cmt>&quot;の位置を訂正。Era→periodに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>平安時代の末期には、第二次性徴に達し元服・裳着を迎えるにあたって女性のみならず男性貴族、平氏などの武士、大規模寺院における稚児も行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In late Heian Era, not only did girls who had shown secondary sex characteristic or who had attended coming-of-age ceremony, but male nobles, Samurais in the Taira clan, and children in a festival procession in big temples or shrines also did the tooth blackening.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the late Heian Era, not only did girls who had shown secondary sex characteristics or who had attended coming-of-age ceremony, but male nobles, Samurai in the Taira clan, and children in a festival procession in big temples or shrines also practiced tooth blackening.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the late Heian period, not only did girls who had shown secondary sex characteristics or who had attended coming-of-age ceremony, but male nobles, Samurai in the Taira clan, and children in a festival procession in big temples or shrines also practiced tooth blackening.</e>
<cmt>eraに訂正しました。era→periodに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>特に皇族や上級貴族は袴着を済ませた少年少女も化粧やお歯黒、引眉を行うようになり、皇室では幕末まで続いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially for the royal families and high-ranked aristocracy, the boys and girls were dresses up in Hakamagi (ceremony fitting child with a hakama (Japanese skirt)) with make-up, blacken teeth and Hikimayu (painted eyebrows).. The Imperial family lasted until the end of Tokugawa shogunate Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Especially for the royal families and high-ranked aristocracy, the boys and girls were dressed up in Hakamagi (ceremony fitting child with a hakama - Japanese skirt) with make-up, blackened teeth and Hikimayu (painted eyebrows). This lasted until the end of Tokugawa shogunate Period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Especially for the royal families and high-ranked aristocracy, the boys and girls were dressed up in Hakamagi (ceremony fitting child with a hakama - Japanese skirt) with make-up, blackened teeth and Hikimayu (painted eyebrows), this lasted until the end of Tokugawa Shogunate period.</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。Tokugawa Shogunate periodに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>室町時代には一般の大人にも浸透したが、戦国時代 (日本)に入ると政略結婚に備えて8～10歳前後の戦国武将の息女へ成年の印として鉄漿付けを行ない、このとき鉄漿付けする後見の親族の夫人を鉄漿親(かねおや)といった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Muromachi Era, this custom was even diffused among adults in the common people. During the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States) of Japan, it was done as a symbol of being adult for bushos (Japanese military commanders)&apos; daughters of age around 8 to 10. At that time, the wife of a guardian relative was called kaneoya (godmother of kanetsuke).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Muromachi Era, this custom was even diffused among adults amongst the common people. During the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States) of Japan, it was done as a symbol of being an adult for bushos (Japanese military commanders)&apos; daughters at the age around 8 to 10. At that time, the wife of a guardian relative was called kaneoya (godmother of kanetsuke).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Muromachi period, this custom was even diffused among adults amongst the common people, moreover, during the Sengoku period (period of Warring States) of Japan, it was done as a symbol of being an adult for bushos&apos; (Japanese military commanders) daughters at the age around 8 to 10, at that time, the wife of a guardian relative was called kaneoya (godmother of kanetsuke).</e>
<cmt>eraに訂正しました。一文にしました。periodに訂正しました。’を&apos;に訂正しました。era→periodに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>又、一部の戦国武将(主に小田原北条家をはじめとする平家系)は戦場に赴くにあたり首を打たれても見苦しくないように、ということから女性並みの化粧をし、お歯黒まで付けた、という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, it is said that some of the commanders (mainly the Taira family series including the Odawara-hokujo family) during the Age of Provincial Wars had make up as intense as a woman to the extent of even blackening their teeth when they proceeded to battlefield in order that they did not look bad even if they were struck in the head.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, it is said that some of the commanders (mainly the Taira family series including the Odawara-hokujo family) during the Age of Provincial Wars had make up as intense as a woman to the extent of even blackening their teeth when they proceeded to the battlefield in order that they did not look bad even if they were struck in the head.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, it is said that some of the commanders (mainly the Taira family series including the Odawara-Hojo family) during the Sengoku period (period of warring states) had make up as intense as a woman to the extent of even blackening their teeth when they proceeded to the battlefield in order that they did not look bad even if they were struck in the head.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除Odawara-Hojoに訂正しました。the Sengoku period (period of warring states)に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>これらの顔が能面の女面、少年面、青年面に写された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These faces were drawn on Onnamen (women&apos;s mask), Shonenmen (boy&apos;s mask), Seinenmen (man&apos;s mask) in Noh plays.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These faces were drawn on Onnamen (women&apos;s mask), Shonenmen (boy&apos;s mask), Seinenmen (man&apos;s mask) in Noh plays.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These faces were drawn on Onnamen (women&apos;s mask), Shonenmen (boy&apos;s mask), Seinenmen (man&apos;s mask) in Noh plays.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="18">
<j>江戸時代以降は皇族・貴族以外の男性の間では殆ど廃絶、又、悪臭や手間、そして老けた感じになることが若い女性から敬遠されたこともあって既婚女性、未婚でも18～20才以上の女性、及び、遊女、芸妓の化粧として定着した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Edo Era, it was almost abolished among men other than the royalty and the aristocrat. Moreover, young women refrained from this practice because it was stinky, time-consuming, and feeling aged. It became a make-up exclusively used by married women, single women above 18 or 20, prostitutes or geishas.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the Edo Era, it was almost abolished among men other than the royalty and the aristocrats. Moreover, young women refrained from this practice because it was stinky, time-consuming, and made them feel aged. It became a form of make-up exclusively used by married women, single women above 18 or 20, prostitutes or geishas.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the Edo period, it was almost abolished among men other than the royalty and the aristocrats, moreover, young women refrained from this practice because it was stinky, time-consuming, and made them feel aged, therefore it became a form of make-up exclusively used by married women, single women above 18 or 20, prostitutes or geishas.</e>
<cmt>eraに訂正しました。一文にしました。era→periodに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>農家においては祭り、結婚式、葬式、等特別な場合のみお歯黒を付けた（童話ごんぎつねにもその描写がある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Farmers blacken their teeth only on special occasions such as festivals, weddings, funerals and so on (this is also depicted in the children&apos;s tale called &quot;Gon the Fox&quot;).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="20">
<j>1870年2月5日、政府から皇族・貴族に対してお歯黒禁止令が出され、それに伴い民間でも徐々に廃れ(明治以降農村では一時的に普及したが)、大正時代にはほぼ完全に消えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 5, 1870, government put a ban on tooth black among the royalty and the aristocrat. Consequently, this practice also faded gradually among the common people. (After the Meiji Era, it was once popular among farm villages). In Taisho Era, it almost completely disappeared.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 5, 1870, government put a ban on tooth black among the royalty and aristocrats. Consequently, this practice also faded gradually among the common people. (After the Meiji Era, it was once popular among farm villages). In the Taisho Era, it almost completely disappeared.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 5, 1870, government put a ban on tooth black among the royalty and aristocrats; consequently, this practice also faded gradually among the common people (after the Meiji period, it was once popular among farm villages), and in the Taisho period, it almost completely disappeared.</e>
<cmt>eraに訂正しました。一文にしました。era→periodに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="21">
<j>現代においては、演劇、花街、一部の祭り、1960年代頃までの時代劇映画(大映、等)のDVD、等で見ることが出来るだけである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nowadays, it can only be seen in dramas, fleshpots, certain festivals, some Jidaigeki-eiga (period movies) until the 1960s (by some movie companies such as Daiei).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nowadays, it can only be seen in dramas, fleshpots, certain festivals, some Jidaigeki-eiga (period movies) until the 1960s (by some movie companies such as Daiei).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nowadays, it can only be seen in dramas, fleshpots, certain festivals, some Jidaigeki-eiga (period movies) until the 1960s (by some movie companies such as Daiei).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="22">
<j>尚、お歯黒は引眉とセットになる場合が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, there were often set of tooth black with penciled eyebrows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, there were often sets of tooth black with penciled eyebrows.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, there were often sets of tooth black with penciled eyebrows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="23">
<j>以上をまとめると、以下の通りである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The above can be summarized as follows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The above can be summarized as follows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following people engaged in the practice of Ohaguro.</e>
<cmt>文脈に基づき、&quot;The above can be summarized as follows.&quot; から表現を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="24">
<j>平安時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Heian Era</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Heian Era</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Heian period</e>
<cmt>eraに訂正しました。Era→periodに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>皇族・平安貴族(元服・裳着後(袴着後の少年少女もする場合あり)、男女、未既婚を問わず)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Royalty and Heian aristocrats (in Genpuku and Mogi (coming-of-age ceremony) (for both boys and girls after putting on the hakama (Japanese skirt for formal wear), regardless of gender and whether he/she is married or not).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Royalty and Heian aristocrats (in Genpuku and Mogi (coming-of-age ceremony) (for both boys and girls after putting on the hakama (Japanese skirt for formal wear), regardless of gender and whether he/she is married or not).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Royalty and Heian aristocrats (in Genpuku and Mogi (coming-of-age ceremony) (for both boys and girls after putting on the hakama (Japanese skirt for formal wear), regardless of gender and whether he/she is married or not).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>主に平家の武将(源氏は付けない場合が多かった)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mainly warlords of the Taira family (it was uncommon for the Minamoto clan)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>大規模寺院における稚児</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ritual children in big Buddhist temples</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ritual children in big Buddhist temples</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ritual children in big Buddhist temples</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>戦国時代 (日本)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the Age of Provincial Wars (Japan)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">the Age of Provincial Wars (Japan)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sengoku period (period of warring states) (Japan)</e>
<cmt>the Sengoku period (period of warring states)に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>政略結婚させられた、又はさせられそうな幼い姫君</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Young princess who entered into, or were likely to enter into, a marriage of convenience</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>一部の戦国武将(以上は何れも眉を剃り、殿上眉を描く)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some commanders during the age of provincial wars (both eyebrows were shaved off and tenjo-mayu (false eyebrows) were drawn.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some commanders during the age of provincial wars (both eyebrows were shaved off and tenjo-mayu (false eyebrows - were drawn.)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some commanders during the Sengoku period (both eyebrows were shaved off and tenjo-mayu (false eyebrows - were drawn.)</e>
<cmt>the Sengoku periodに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>江戸時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Edo Era</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Edo Era</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Edo period</e>
<cmt>eraに訂正しました。Era→periodに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>都市部の既婚女性全般(引眉する、但し武家では出産後に引眉する)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">All married women in the city (with penciled eyebrows). (However, those from samurai families penciled their eyebrows after giving birth)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">All married women in the city (with penciled eyebrows). (However, those from samurai families penciled their eyebrows after giving birth)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">All married women in the city (With penciled eyebrows, however, those from samurai families penciled their eyebrows after giving birth.)</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>18～20才以上の未婚女性(引眉する場合としない場合有り)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Single women of 18 to 20 years old or more. (Their eyebrows may either be penciled or not.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Single women of 18 to 20 years old or more. (Their eyebrows may either be penciled or not.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Single women of 18 to 20 years old or more (Their eyebrows may either be penciled or not.)</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。ピリオド削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>遊女(江戸、上方、共、一人前、引眉しない)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prostitute (Edo, Kamigata, matured, and without penciled eyebrows)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prostitute (Edo, Kamigata, matured, and without penciled eyebrows)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prostitute (Edo, Kamigata, matured, and without penciled eyebrows)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>芸妓(上方のみ、一人前、引眉しない／江戸は付けない)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Geisha (only Kamigata, matured, without penciled eyebrows/ not adopted in Edo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Geisha (only Kamigata, matured, without penciled eyebrows/ not adopted in Edo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Geisha (only Kamigata, matured, without penciled eyebrows/ not adopted in Edo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>現代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nowadays</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nowadays</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nowadays</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>演劇、花柳界、一部の祭り、等</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dramas, demimonde, certain festivals, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dramas, demimonde, certain festivals, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dramas, demimonde, certain festivals, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>染料</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">dyes</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">dyes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">dyes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="38">
<j>鉄漿を「かね」と読むと、染めるのに使う液を表す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the kanji characters &quot;Iron Paste&quot; are pronounced as &quot;Kane&quot;, it refers to the liquid for dyeing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the kanji characters &quot;Iron Paste&quot; are pronounced as &quot;Kane,&quot; it refers to the liquid for dyeing.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the kanji characters &quot;Iron Paste&quot; are pronounced as &apos;Kane,&apos; it refers to the liquid for dyeing.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="39">
<j>主成分は鉄漿水（かねみず）と呼ばれる酢酸に鉄を溶かした茶褐色・悪臭の溶液で、これに五倍子粉（ふしこ）と呼ばれる、タンニンを多く含む粉を混ぜて非水溶性にする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The main component is a tea-brown extremely stinky solution of dissolved iron in acetic acid (vinegar) that is called &quot;Kanemizu (Iron Paste Water&quot;. To this, the so-called fushiko or gallnut powder is added and mixed. A hydrophobic solution is resulted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The main component is a tea-brown extremely stinky solution of dissolved iron in acetic acid (vinegar) that is called &quot;Kanemizu (Iron Paste Water&quot;. To this, the so-called fushiko or gallnut powder is added and mixed. A hydrophobic solution is the result.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The main component is a tea-brown extremely stinky solution of dissolved iron in acetic acid (vinegar) that is called &quot;Kanemizu&quot; (Iron Paste Water), to this, the so-called fushiko or gallnut powder is added and mixed, then a hydrophobic solution is the result.</e>
<cmt>)補足、&quot;位置訂正一文にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>主成分は、酢酸第一鉄でそれがタンニン酸と結合して黒くなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The main component, ferrous acetate combines with tannic acid and changes to black.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The main component, ferrous acetate combines with tannic acid and changes to black.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The main component, ferrous acetate combines with tannic acid and changes to black.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>歯を被膜することによる虫歯予防や、成分がエナメル質に浸透することにより浸食に強くなる、などの実用的効果もあったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered to have practicable effects such as prevention of tooth decay by forming a film on the teeth&apos;s surface, and strengthening of teeth against erosion by infiltrating into the enamel.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered to have practicable effects such as the prevention of tooth decay by forming a film on the teeth&apos;s surface, and strengthening of teeth against erosion by infiltrating into the enamel.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered to have practicable effects such as the prevention of tooth decay by forming a film on the teeth&apos;s surface, and strengthening of teeth against erosion by infiltrating into the enamel.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>毎日から数日に一度、染め直す必要があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was necessary to dye once every day or every several days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was necessary to dye once every day or every several days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was necessary to dye once every day or every several days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="43">
<j>又、簡便にした処方として、五倍子粉、硫酸鉄、蠣殻を合わせた粉末を歯に塗るだけのものもあったが、あまり普及しなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, as a handy treatment, some teeth were blackened by painting with a powder mixture of fushiko (gallnut powder), iron sulfate, and oyster shell. However, this way was not so popular.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, as a handy treatment, some teeth were blackened by painting with a powder mixture of fushiko (gallnut powder), iron sulfate, and oyster shell. However, this method was not so popular.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, as a handy treatment, some teeth were blackened by painting with a powder mixture of fushiko (gallnut powder), iron sulfate, and oyster shell, however, this method was not so popular.</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="44">
<j>演劇用には松脂に墨を混ぜたものが使われ、現代ではトゥースワックス(蝋に墨を混ぜたもの)が使われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For dramas, pine resin mixed with ink is used. Nowadays, tooth wax (wax mixed with ink) is used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For dramas, pine resin mixed with ink is used. Nowadays, tooth wax (wax mixed with ink) is used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For dramas, pine resin mixed with ink is used, nowadays, tooth wax (wax mixed with ink) is used.</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="45">
<j>現在お歯黒を見ることが出来る場所等</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Places where tooth black can be seen nowadays</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Places where tooth black can be seen nowadays</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Places where tooth black can be seen nowadays</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>これらは全て演劇用の一時的なお歯黒となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These all become once teeth black for dramas.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These all become teeth black for dramas.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These all become teeth black for dramas.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="47">
<j>演劇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dramas</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dramas</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dramas</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>歌舞伎(既婚女性、平安貴族、遊女、芸者役)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kabuki (Roles of married women, aristocrats of Heian Era, prostitute, or geisha)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kabuki (Roles of married women, aristocrats of Heian Era, prostitute, or geisha)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kabuki (Roles of married women, aristocrats of Heian era, prostitute, or geisha)</e>
<cmt>eraに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>歌舞伎舞踊</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kabuki dance</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kabuki dance</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kabuki dance</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>年増(常磐津)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Middle-aged woman (Tokiwazu (a Japanese-type puppet play))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Middle-aged woman (Tokiwazu - a Japanese-type puppet play)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Middle-aged woman (Tokiwazu - a Japanese-type puppet play)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>文売り(清元)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fumiuri (letter seller) (Kiyomoto (a type of Japanese-type puppet play))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fumiuri (letter seller) (Kiyomoto - a type of Japanese-type puppet play)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fumiuri (letter seller) (Kiyomoto - a type of Japanese-type puppet play)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>花柳界</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">karyu-kai (world of the Geisha)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">karyu-kai (world of the Geisha)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">karyu-kai (world of the Geisha)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>太夫（嶋原、京都市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tayu (top ranked Geisha) (Shimabara, Kyoto City)</e>
<cmt>「太夫」の読み方は「たゆう」或るいは「たいふ」だと思います。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tayu (top ranked Geisha) (Shimabara, Kyoto City)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tayu (top ranked Geisha) (Shimabara, Kyoto City)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>芸妓、舞妓(京都市、舞妓は芸妓になる1～4週間前)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Geisha and maiko (in Kyoto City, when a maiko is 1 to 4 weeks before she becomes a geisha)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Geisha and maiko (in Kyoto City, when a maiko is 1 to 4 weeks before she becomes a geisha)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Geigi and maiko (in Kyoto City, when a maiko is 1 to 4 weeks before she becomes a geisha)</e>
<cmt>Geigiに訂正しました。京都の話題なので「芸妓」→Geigiとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>祭り</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Festivals</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Festivals</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Festivals</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>斎王代（葵祭、京都市）（年によってはお歯黒を付けない場合もある）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saiodai (the heroine of Aoi-matsuri Festival, Kyoto City) (Depending on the age, there are also cases where tooth blackening is not practiced.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saiodai (the heroine of Aoi-matsuri Festival, Kyoto City) (Depending on the age, there are also cases where tooth blackening is not practiced.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saiodai (the heroine of Aoi-matsuri Festival, Kyoto City) (Depending on the age, there are also cases where tooth blackening is not practiced.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>曳山歌舞伎（長浜曳山祭、長浜市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hikiyama-kabuki (Kabuki drama on a Hikiyama festival float) (Nagahama Hikiyama Matsuri (Nagahama Parade Float Festival), Nagahama City)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hikiyama-kabuki (Kabuki drama on a Hikiyama festival float) (Nagahama Hikiyama Matsuri (Nagahama Parade Float Festival), Nagahama City)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hikiyama-kabuki (Kabuki drama on a Hikiyama festival float) (Nagahama Hikiyama Matsuri (Nagahama Parade Float Festival), Nagahama City)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>曳山歌舞伎（米原まつり、米原市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hikiyama-kabuki (Kabuki drama on a Hikiyama festival float) (Maibara Festival, Maibara City)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hikiyama-kabuki (Kabuki drama on a Hikiyama festival float) (Maibara Festival, Maibara City)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hikiyama-kabuki (Kabuki drama on a Hikiyama festival float) (Maibara Festival, Maibara City)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>その他全国各地の素人歌舞伎（但しお歯黒を付けない場合もある）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amateur kabuki in various places in Japan (However, tooth black may not be put.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amateur kabuki in various places in Japan (However, tooth black may not be used.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amateur kabuki in various places in Japan (However, tooth black may not be used.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>迷信・都市伝説・等</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Superstition, urban legend, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Superstition, urban legend, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Superstition, urban legend, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>妖怪一反木綿は刀では切れないが一度でもお歯黒をした歯なら噛み切れる、という伝承がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a legend saying that, though the specter Ittan-momen (a ghostly phenomenon formed as one-tenth hectare of cotton) cannot be cut, but it can be cut by teeth once blackened before. Therefore, in a region where people thought Ittan-momen appeared, even men there had their teeth blackened.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a legend saying that, though the specter Ittan-momen (a ghostly phenomenon formed as one-tenth hectare of cotton) cannot be cut, but it can be cut by teeth once blackened before. Therefore, in a region where people thought Ittan-momen appeared, even men there had their teeth blackened.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a legend saying that, although the specter Ittan-momen (a ghostly phenomenon formed as one-tenth hectare of cotton) cannot be cut, but it can be cut by teeth once blackened before.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処though→althoughに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>一反木綿が現れるとされる地域では男でもお歯黒をするという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, in a region where people thought Ittan-momen appeared, even men there had their teeth blackened.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="63">
<j>明治時代に一部地域で「電線に処女の生き血を塗る」という噂が広まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Meiji Era, in certain regions, there were well-spread rumors that &quot;Virgin&apos;s lifeblood is painted on electric wires&quot;. Thus, women of marriageable age in those regions often blackened their teeth, penciled their eyebrows and dressed in plain clothes as married women so that their blood was not taken.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Meiji Era, in certain regions, there were well-spread rumors that &quot;Virgin&apos;s lifeblood is painted on electric wires,. Thus, women of marriageable age in those regions often blackened their teeth, penciled their eyebrows and dressed in plain clothes as married women so that their blood would not be taken.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Meiji period, in certain regions, there were well-spread rumors that &apos;Virgin&apos;s lifeblood is painted on electric wires.&apos;</e>
<cmt>eraに訂正しました。原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に一原文一訳文例外対処Era→periodに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>これにより、その地域の妙齢の女性の多くが生き血を取られないようにお歯黒・引眉・地味な着物・等の既婚女性と同様の容姿となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, women of marriageable age in those regions often blackened their teeth, penciled their eyebrows and dressed in plain clothes as married women so that their blood would not be taken.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="65">
<j>山田野理夫『東北怪談の旅』に福島県の話として妖怪お歯黒べったりのことと思われるものが記述されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Norio YAMADA&apos;s &quot;Tohoku Kaidan no Tabi (Trip to scary stories in Tohoku Region)&quot;, a rumor of the specter Ohaguro-bettari in Fukui Prefecture was described.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Norio YAMADA&apos;s &quot;Tohoku Kaidan no Tabi (Trip to scary stories in Tohoku Region),&quot; a rumor of the specter Ohaguro-bettari in Fukui Prefecture was described.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Norio YAMADA&apos;s &quot;Tohoku Kaidan no Tabi&quot; (Trip to scary stories in Tohoku Region), a rumor of the specter Ohaguro-bettari in Fukui Prefecture was described.</e>
<cmt>&quot;の位置を訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="66">
<j>中国・東南アジア・等</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">China, Southeast Asia, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">China, Southeast Asia, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">China, Southeast Asia, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>現代においても、以下の少数民族地域において、本式のお歯黒が見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even nowadays, regular tooth blackening can be seen in the following regions of minority races.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even nowadays, regular tooth blackening can be seen in the following regions of minority races.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even nowadays, regular tooth blackening can be seen in the following regions of minority races.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>主に、年配の女性に限られ、既婚でも若い女性が、お歯黒をすることは稀である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chiefly, it is limited to elderly women. It is rare for a young woman to have her teeth blackened even if she is married.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chiefly, it is limited to elderly women. It is rare for a young woman to have her teeth blackened even if she is married.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chiefly, since it is limited to elderly women, it is rare for a young woman to have her teeth blackened even if she is married.</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>この地域向けに、お歯黒の義歯が作られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Black artificial teeth are made for these regions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Black artificial teeth are made for these regions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Black artificial teeth are made for these regions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>照葉樹林文化圏も参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Refer also to cultural region of evergreen broadleaf forest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Refer also to cultural region of evergreen broadleaf forest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Refer also to cultural region of evergreen broadleaf forest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="71">
<j>中華人民共和国雲南省</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yunnan (People&apos;s Republic of China)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yunnan (People&apos;s Republic of China)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yunnan (People&apos;s Republic of China)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>ミャオ族</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hmong ethnic group</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hmong ethnic group</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hmong ethnic group</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>ラフ族</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Lahu ethnic group</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Lahu ethnic group</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Lahu ethnic group</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>ヤオ族</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yao (Dao) ethnic group</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yao (Dao) ethnic group</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yao (Dao) ethnic group</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>ベトナム(ハノイ、及び中国に接する地域)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Vietnam (Hanoi, and the region adjacent to China)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Vietnam (Hanoi, and the region adjacent to China)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Vietnam (Hanoi, and the region adjacent to China)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>ザオテン族</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dao Tien ethnic group</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dao Tien ethnic group</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dao Tien ethnic group</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>ルー族</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Lu ethnic group</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Lu ethnic group</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Lu ethnic group</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>黒ザオ族</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Black Dao ethnic group</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Black Dao ethnic group</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Black Dao ethnic group</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>ヌン族</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nung ethnic group</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nung ethnic group</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nung ethnic group</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>ラオス(現代では付けない場合が多い)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Laos (nowadays, it is often not put on)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Laos (nowadays, it is often not used)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Laos (nowadays, it is often not used)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>ハニ族</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hani ethnic group</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hani ethnic group</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hani ethnic group</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>カトゥ族</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Katu (Co Tu) ethnic group</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Katu (Co Tu) ethnic group</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Katu (Co Tu) ethnic group</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>プーノイ族</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Phounoy ethnic group</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Phounoy ethnic group</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Phounoy ethnic group</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>タイ王国(キンマとビンロウを一緒に噛む習慣と関連あり)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kingdom of Thailand (It is related to the custom of biting betel plant and betel palm together.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kingdom of Thailand (It is related to the custom of biting betel plant and betel palm together.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kingdom of Thailand (It is related to the custom of biting betel plant and betel palm together.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>アカ族</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Aka (Akha) ethnic group</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Aka (Akha) ethnic group</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Aka (Akha) ethnic group</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>リス族</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Lisu ethnic group</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Lisu ethnic group</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Lisu ethnic group</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Izayohi(id:13095), Kkkdc(id:32227), Papamaruchan22(id:71152), VolkovBot(id:105371), 朝彦(id:9407), 釣本直紀(id:85142), SuisuiBot(id:10165), 経済準学士(id:22656), Nevylax(id:38464), 葉月(id:25674), けんち(id:5147), Zunda(id:57280), Mikomaid(id:56139), Kurokani(id:86838), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>