<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>神社建築</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jinja Architecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jinja Architecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jinja Architecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>神社建築（じんじゃけんちく）は、神社の建築。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jinja architecture refers to the architecture associated with jinja, or Shinto shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jinja architecture refers to the architecture associated with jinja, or Shinto shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jinja architecture refers to the architecture associated with jinja, or Shinto shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>社殿建築(しゃでんけんちく)ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called shaden (shrine pavillions) architecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called shaden (shrine pavillions) architecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called shaden (shrine pavillions) architecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Overview</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Overview</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>統一用語</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>今日一般的に見られる神社建築は本殿・幣殿・拝殿からなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Structures of Jinja typically seen today consist of honden (main sanctuary hall), heiden (offering hall), and haiden (worship hall)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Structures of Jinja typically seen today consist of honden (main sanctuary hall), heiden (offering hall), and haiden (worship hall)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Structures of Jinja typically seen today consist of honden (main sanctuary hall), heiden (offering hall), and haiden (worship hall).</e>
<cmt>ピリオド追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>神社を訪れると、本殿の手前に礼拝用の建物である拝殿が建っており、賽銭箱が置いてある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When you visit a shrine, you see the worship hall haiden building situated on the same axis as the main sanctuary honden toward the front with a saisen (offertory) box being placed at the front.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When you visit a shrine, you see the worship hall haiden building situated on the same axis as the main sanctuary honden toward the front with a saisen (offertory) box being placed at the front.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When you visit a shrine, you see the worship hall haiden building situated on the same axis as the main sanctuary honden toward the front with a saisen (offertory) box being placed at the front.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>拝殿は修祓や祈祷などを受ける場所になっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Haiden is a place to have ceremonies for purification rite or prayer services.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Haiden is a place where ceremonies like purification rites or prayer services are held.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Haiden is a place where ceremonies like purification rites or prayer services are held.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>拝殿の奥の方に神体を収める本殿がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The honden, a main sanctuary hall which is located at the rear of the haiden, contains shintai, or an object believed to contain the spirit of the deity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The honden, a main sanctuary hall which is located in the rear of the haiden, contains shintai, or an object believed to contain the spirit of a deity.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The honden, a main sanctuary hall which is located in the rear of the haiden, contains shintai, or an object believed to contain the spirit of a deity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>本殿は奥にあるため、一般の参拝者は拝殿を中心的建物と考えがちである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The haiden is considered to be the main building to see by most visitors because it is situated at the rear of the shrine building complex.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The haiden is considered to be the main building to see, by most visitors, because it is situated at the rear of the shrine building complex.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The haiden is considered to be the main building to see, by most visitors, because Honden is situated at the rear of the shrine building complex.</e>
<cmt>it→ Honden</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>本殿は流造、春日造が一般的で、小型の本殿では、風雨から守るために覆屋をかける場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for architectural styles, nagare-zukuri and kasuga-zukuri are the most typical; in some cases, an oiya, or a covering roof is constructed over a small-sized honden as a protection.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for architectural styles, nagare-zukuri and kasuga-zukuri are the most typical; in some cases, an oiya, or a covering roof is constructed over a small-sized honden as a protection from the elements.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for architectural styles, nagare-zukuri and kasuga-zukuri are the most typical; in some cases, an oiya, or a covering roof is constructed over a small-sized honden as a protection from the elements.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>拝殿と本殿をつなぐ部分に幣殿が造られることも多く、これらを一続きに建てる場合も少なくない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A heiden is typically build between the haiden and honden on the same axis as them; it is not uncommon for these buildings to be joined to each other.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A heiden is typically built between the haiden and honden on the same axis; it is not uncommon for these buildings to be joinedr.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A heiden is typically built between the haiden and honden on the same axis; it is not uncommon for these buildings to be joinder.</e>
<cmt>joinedr→joinder</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>建物の横に回ってみると、拝殿の奥に幣殿や本殿を確認することができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If you walk to the side of the building structure, you see the heiden and honden at the rear of haiden.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If you walk to the side of the building, you&apos;ll see the heiden and honden at the rear of haiden.</e>
<cmt>redundancy, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If you walk to the side of the building, you&apos;ll see the heiden and honden at the rear of haiden.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>本殿は神がいるとされる神聖な場所であるため、瑞垣などで囲われたり、覆屋が造られ、普段は見ることができなくなっていることも多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a honden is regarded as the sacred place where a spirit of kami or deity dwells, it is often enclosed by wooden fences, or protected by the oiya structure built over it, keeping the honden from being seen by public at ordinary times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the honden is regarded as the sacred place where a spirit of kami or deity dwells, it is often enclosed by wooden fences, or protected by the oiya structure built over it, keeping the honden from being seen by public during ordinary times.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the honden is regarded as the sacred place where a spirit of kami or deity dwells, it is often enclosed by wooden fences, or protected by the oiya structure built over it, keeping the honden from being seen by public during ordinary times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>一部の神社では本殿を持たず、神体の前に直接拝殿が建てられているところ（大神神社・金鑚神社など）もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In some shrines, a haiden is located directly at the front of shintai, or objects believed to contain the spirit of deity, instead of having a honden in the middle, such as Omiwa-jinja Shrine and Kanasana-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In some shrines, a haiden is located directly at the front of shintai, or objects believed to contain the spirit of the deity, instead of having a honden in the middle, such as in Omiwa-jinja Shrine and Kanasana-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In some shrines, a haiden is located directly at the front of shintai, or objects believed to contain the spirit of the deity, instead of having a honden in the middle, such as in Omiwa-jinja Shrine and Kanasana-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>本来は社殿を持たない神社が古風な形式であったと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered that shrines without shaden or pavillions are of more archaic style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered that shrines without shaden or pavillions are of a more archaic style.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered that shrines without shaden or pavillions are of a more archaic style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="14">
<j>神社建築は寺院建築の影響のもとで発生し、日本の上古の建築を復古的に採用し、仏教建築のデザインを意識的に排除しつつ成立したと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Architecture of shrine is believed to have been emerged under the influence of that of ji-in, or buddhist pagoda, adopting ancient architecture by revivalism, and in the course of subsequent development process, design elements of buddhist nature were conisdered to be intentionally eliminated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Architecture of shrine is believed to have emerged under the influence of ji-in, or Buddhist pagoda, reviving ancient architecture, and in the course of subsequent developments, design elements of Buddhist nature were conisdered to be intentionally eliminated.</e>
<cmt>grammar, wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Architecture of shrine is believed to have emerged under the influence of ji-in, or Buddhist pagoda, reviving ancient architecture, and in the course of subsequent developments, design elements of Buddhist nature were considered to be intentionally eliminated.</e>
<cmt>consideredのスペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>神社建築の特徴の一つとしては、その形式の尊重がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The shrine architecture is characterized by the strong emphasis on the forms.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shrine architecture is characterized by a strong emphasis on form.</e>
<cmt>grammar, wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shrine architecture is characterized by a strong emphasis on form.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>神社建築は、一宮などの各有力神社において固有の形式を採っているので、各神社で固有の伝統的な形式を保っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The major shinto shrines including those designated as Ichinomiya shrines adopted and retained distinctive architectural styles, contributing to the preservation of unique traditional styles.</e>
<cmt>原文の前半と後半の意味のつながりがはっきりわかりませんでした。Major shrineが固有のStyleを採り、保っているので、各神社にさなざまな伝統形式が残されることとなっているということだと解釈しました</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The major Shinto shrines including those designated as Ichinomiya shrines adopted and retained distinctive architecture, contributing to the preservation of unique traditional styles.</e>
<cmt>redundancy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The major Shinto shrines including those designated as Ichinomiya shrines adopted and retained distinctive architecture, contributing to the preservation of unique traditional styles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>そのため、神社建築の様式を解明することは、その神社の祭神の性格を知る上で重要な手がかりの一つとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Understanding of the architectural style of a shrine gives important clues to the characteristics of saishin, or deity, of the shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Understanding architectural style of a shrine gives important clues about the characteristics of saishin, or the deity of a shrine.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Understanding architectural style of a shrine gives important clues about the characteristics of saishin, or the deity of a shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>後にできた神社においても、建立当初の形式を保つものが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A shrine is built often with a style of the root of the particular shrine that it had at the time of the establishment.</e>
<cmt>原文の意味がはっきりわからなかったのですが、新しく建てられた神社であってもその源となる神社の確立当時の形式を保っていることが多い、ということと解釈しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A shrine is often built in a style based upon the roots of a particular shrine from when it was first established</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A shrine is often built in a style based upon the roots of a particular shrine from when it was first established</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="19">
<j>本殿（ほんでん） - 神が宿るとされる神体を安置する社殿のことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Honden: a pavillion which houses shintai, or objects believed to contain the spirit of kami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Honden: a pavillion which houses shintai, or objects believed to contain the spirit of kami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Honden: a pavillion which houses shintai, or objects believed to contain the spirit of kami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>本殿は人が内部に入ることを前提としていないため、拝殿より小さいことが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Honden is not intended to be built for people to enter and stay inside; therefore, it tends to be smaller than haiden.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Honden is not intended to be built for people to enter and stay inside; therefore, it tends to be smaller than haiden.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Honden is not intended to be built for people to enter and stay inside; therefore, it tends to be smaller than haiden.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>古くは一社殿に一柱の神が祀られたが、現在では一つの社殿に多数の神が祀られることも多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It used to be in a way that only one deity was enshrined in one pavillion; today, it is not uncommon to have many deities enshrined in one pavillion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It used to be that only one deity was enshrined in one pavillion; today, it is not uncommon to have many deities enshrined in one pavillion.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It used to be that only one deity was enshrined in one pavillion; today, it is not uncommon to have many deities enshrined in one pavillion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>内部には御神体（鏡など）がおさめられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A honden may house Goshintai, which is an object of worship and believed to contain the spirit of a deity (e.g., a mirror).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A honden may house Goshintai, which is an object of worship believed to contain the spirit of a deity (e.g., a mirror).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A honden may house Goshintai, which is an object of worship believed to contain the spirit of a deity (e.g., a mirror).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="23">
<j>拝殿（はいでん） - 祭祀・拝礼を行なうための社殿である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Haiden: a pavillion for worship and prayer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Haiden: a pavillion for worship and prayer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Haiden: a pavillion for worship and prayer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>通常、神社を訪れた際に見るのはこの拝殿である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The building which visitors typically see when they visit a shrine is the haiden.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The building which visitors typically see when they visit a shrine is the haiden.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The building which visitors typically see when they visit a shrine is the haiden.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>一般の参拝は拝殿の手前で拍手を打って行なうが、お祓いなどのため拝殿に入ることがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In most cases, worship takes place by clapping hands at the front of haiden; in some cases, such as for purification ceremonies, people may enter into the building of haiden.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In most cases, worship takes place by clapping hands at the front of haiden; in some cases, such as for purification ceremonies, people may enter the haiden building.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In most cases, worship takes place by clapping hands at the front of haiden; in some cases, such as for purification ceremonies, people may enter the haiden building.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>祭祀のときに神職などが着座するところでもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also a place for shinto priests and priestesses to sit during worship.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also a place for Shinto priests and priestesses to sit during worship.</e>
<cmt>captialization</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also a place for Shinto priests and priestesses to sit during worship.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>一般に本殿よりも大きく建てられ、床を張るのが一般的であるが、建物の中央が吹き抜けの土間となっており、通り抜けることができる「割拝殿」もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Haiden is typically built larger than honden and have raised floors of timber; in some cases, however, the center of the building has earthen floors with vaulted ceilings, a structure called wari-haiden, to allow people to pass through.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Haiden is typically built larger than honden and have raised floors of timber; in some cases, however, the center of the building has earthen floors with vaulted ceilings, a structure called wari-haiden, to allow people to pass through.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Haiden is typically built larger than honden and have raised floors of timber; in some cases, however, the center of the building has earthen floors with vaulted ceilings, a structure called wari-haiden, to allow people to pass through.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>（国宝となっている桜井神社 (堺市)のものが著名）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A well known example can be found in Sakurai-jinja Shrine, Sakai City, which is designated as a national treasure.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A well known example can be found in Sakurai-jinja Shrine, Sakai City, which is designated as a national treasure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A well known example can be found in Sakurai-jinja Shrine, Sakai City, which is designated as a national treasure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>舞殿、神楽殿、社務所などを兼ねていることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In some shrines, haiden serves also as a structure for mai-den or kagura-den, a place for floor dancing performance, or shamusho, a shrine office.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In some shrines, haiden serves also as a place for mai-den or kagura-den, a place for floor dancing performance, or shamusho, a shrine office.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In some shrines, haiden serves also as a place for mai-den or kagura-den, a place for floor dancing performance, or shamusho, a shrine office.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>神社によっては拝殿を持たないところ（春日大社・伊勢神宮など）や、二つ持つところ（伏見稲荷大社・明治神宮など）もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some shrines including Kasuga-taisha Shrine and Ise-jingu Shrine do not have haiden; others including Fushimi Inari-taisha and Meiji-jingu have two haiden halls.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some shrines including Kasuga-taisha Shrine and Ise-jingu Shrine do not have haiden; others including Fushimi Inari-taisha and Meiji-jingu have two haiden halls.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some shrines including Kasuga-taisha Shrine and Ise-jingu Shrine do not have haiden; others including Fushimi Inari-taisha and Meiji-jingu Shrine have two haiden halls.</e>
<cmt>Shrineを追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>二つある場合は、手前を外拝殿（げ はいでん）と呼び、奥のものを内拝殿（ない はいでん）と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When there are two haiden halls, the one toward you is called ge-haiden, or outer haiden, and the one at the back nai-haiden, or inner haiden.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When there are two haiden halls, the one toward you is called ge-haiden, or outer haiden, and the one at the back nai-haiden, or inner haiden.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When there are two haiden halls, the one toward you is called ge-haiden, or outer haiden, and the one at the back nai-haiden, or inner haiden.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>鰐口、鈴（鈴の緒）がある場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There may be waniguchi, or a medal shape steel drum, or suzu, a bell with a string.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There may be waniguchi, or a medal shape steel drum, or suzu, a bell with a cord.</e>
<cmt>terminology</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There may be waniguchi, or a medal shape steel drum, or suzu, a bell with a cord.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="33">
<j>幣殿（へいでん） - 祭儀を行い、幣帛を奉る社殿である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Heiden: a pavillion for having ceremonies and presenting offerings made of paper or silk cuttings, called heihaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Heiden: a pavillion for having ceremonies and presenting offerings made of paper or silk cuttings, called heihaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Heiden: a pavillion for having ceremonies and presenting offerings made of paper or silk cuttings, called heihaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>独立していることもあるが、拝殿と一体になっていることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In some shrines, heiden is built as an independent structure; more commonly, however, heiden shares the building structure with haiden.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In some shrines, heiden is built as an independent structure; more commonly, however, heiden shares the building structure with haiden.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In some shrines, heiden is built as an independent structure; more commonly, however, heiden shares the building structure with haiden.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>幣殿を持たない神社もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some shrines do not have a heiden structure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some shrines do not have a heiden structure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some shrines do not have a heiden structure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="36">
<j>また、神楽殿、手水鉢、灯籠、狛犬などもある場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Heiden may have additional features including: kaguraden, or kagura hall, chozubachi, a basin for water to purify before entring a shrine, toro, a lantern, and komainu, guardian dogs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Heiden may have additional features including: kaguraden, or kagura hall, chozubachi, a basin for water to purify before entring a shrine, toro, a lantern, and komainu, guardian dogs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Heiden may have additional features including: kaguraden, or kagura hall, chozubachi, a basin for water to purify before entering a shrine, toro, a lantern, and komainu, guardian dogs.</e>
<cmt>entring→entering</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>神社建築（本殿）の特徴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Characteristics of shrine architecture: honden</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Characteristics of shrine architecture: honden</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Characteristics of shrine architecture: honden</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="37">
<j>神社建築（本殿）の特徴として以下の点が指摘されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following characteristics have been pointed out as features of the honden architecture:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following characteristics have been pointed out as features of honden architecture:</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following characteristics have been pointed out as features of honden architecture:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="38">
<j>屋根に妻を持つこと</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gabled roofs</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gabled roofs</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gabled roofs</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>床を高く張ること</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">High raised timber floors</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Highly raised timbered floors</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Highly raised timbered floors</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>瓦を用いないこと</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Absence of tile use for roofing</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Absence of tile used for roofing</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Absence of tile used for roofing</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>土壁を用いないこと</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Absence of earthen walls</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Absence of earthen walls</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Absence of earthen walls</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>装飾の質素なこと</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Simple and not decorative</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Simple and not decorative</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Simple and not decorative</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="43">
<j>まず「屋根に妻を持つこと」についてだが、これは神社建築の屋根はほとんどが切妻造で、一部に入母屋造が見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Having tsuma, or a gable pediment, at each end of the roof, is a feature of kirizuma-zukuri, or gable style, which is the domnant style of shrine architecture with other style being irimoya-zukuri, a gable roof style with hip.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Having tsuma, or a gable pediment, at each end of the roof, is a feature of kirizuma-zukuri, or gable style, which is the domnant style of shrine architecture with the other style being irimoya-zukuri, a gabled hipped roof style.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Having tsuma, or a gable pediment, at each end of the roof, is a feature of kirizuma-zukuri, or gable style, which is the dominant style of shrine architecture with the other style being irimoya-zukuri, a gabled hipped roof style.</e>
<cmt>domnant→dominant</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>入母屋造は仏教建築に由来する様式である</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Irimoya-zukuri is a style derived from buddhist construction style.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Irimoya-zukuri is derived from Buddhist style of construction.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Irimoya-zukuri is derived from Buddhist style of construction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>入母屋造が神社建築に採用されたことに付いて、仏教建築からの一方的な影響のみがあったのではなく、神社建築としての価値観に基づいて、受身的ではなく主体的に採用したことが、同じ仏教建築の様式であるが妻のない寄棟造や方形造を採用しなかったことから分かる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As can be noticed from not applying non-gabled styles such as yosemune-zukuri or hougyo-zukuri, the irimoya-zukuri is considered to have been adopted as an architectural style of shrines willingly while maintaining the values of shinto shrine architecture, rather than passively influenced by buddhist styles.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外処理。主体的に→「進んで」　Willinglyと意訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As can be seen from the lack of non-gabled styles such as yosemune-zukuri or hougyo-zukuri, the irimoya-zukuri is considered to have been willingly adopted as an architectural style maintaining the values of Shinto shrine architecture, over passively influenced Buddhist styles.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As can be seen from the lack of non-gabled styles such as yosemune-zukuri or hougyo-zukuri, the irimoya-zukuri is considered to have been willingly adopted as an architectural style maintaining the values of Shinto shrine architecture, over passively influenced Buddhist styles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="46">
<j>妻が神社建築においてどのような意味を持つのかははっきりしないが、信仰上の重要な要素であったことは間違いないらしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Whereas the meaning of gabled roof on shrine architecture is not clear; there seems to be little doubt that it was of great religious importance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Whereas the meaning of gabled roof in shrine architecture is not clear; there seems to be little doubt that it was of great religious significance.</e>
<cmt>terminology</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Whereas the meaning of gabled roof in shrine architecture is not clear; there seems to be little doubt that it was of great religious significance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>例えば、伊勢神宮正殿において妻の部分の金具が特別視され、式年遷宮の際にそれを装着する儀礼が秘伝とされていたことや、流造の社殿を横にいくつも連結した社殿において、ひとつの社殿ごとに正面に千鳥破風（妻）が設けられて、ひとつひとつの社殿が分かるようにしていることからも分かる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The religious importance is evident from the fact that for instances, the hardware parts of tsuma, or gable pediment, are treated special, and mounting them at occasions of periodical moving of shintai to a new shrine was carried out as a secret ceremonies at the Shoden of Ise Jingu, and in nagare-zukuri pavillions jointed side by side in rows, each apvillion has chidori-hafu, a dormer bargeboard at the front side to differentiate pavillions from one another.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The religious importance is evident, for instance, in the hardware parts of tsuma, or gabled pediment, which are specially treated, and mounting them during periodical occasions when moving shintai to a new shrine was carried out as a secret ceremony at the Shoden of Ise Jingu, and in nagare-zukuri pavillions jointed side by side in rows, each pavillion has chidori-hafu, a dormer bargeboard at the front side to differentiate the pavillions from each other.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity, spelling, wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The religious importance is evident, for instance, in the hardware parts of tsuma, or gabled pediment, which are specially treated, and mounting them during periodical occasions when moving shintai to a new shrine was carried out as a secret ceremony at the Shoden of Ise Jingu, and in nagare-zukuri pavillions jointed side by side in rows, each pavillion has chidori-hafu, a dormer bargeboard at the front side to differentiate the pavillions from each other.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="48">
<j>床を高く張ることについては、土間を基本とする寺院建築と対照的である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">High raised floor presents sharp contrast to doma, or earthen floor, which is a basic element of buddhist architecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A highly raised floor presents a sharp contrast to doma, or earthen floor, a basic element of Buddhist architecture.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A highly raised floor presents a sharp contrast to doma, or earthen floor, a basic element of Buddhist architecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="49">
<j>ただ古代の神社建築においても一部の住吉造など、床を張らずに土間とする様式もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, some shrine structures of ancient times, such as some of the sumiyoshi-zukuri structures, have earthen floors instead of using timber floors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, some ancient shrines, like sumiyoshi-zukuri structures, have earthen instead of timbered floors.</e>
<cmt>redundancy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, some ancient shrines, like sumiyoshi-zukuri structures, have earthen instead of timbered floors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="50">
<j>瓦を用いないことについては、明らかに瓦葺きの仏教建築との差異を意識し、もしくは仏教建築を忌避したものであるといえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered that tile roofing was not used apaprently to distinguish shinto architecture itself from buddhist architecture, or even to avoid it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered that tile roofing was not used appropriately to distinguish Shinto architecture itself from Buddhist architecture, or even to avoid it.</e>
<cmt>capitalization</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered that tile roofing was not used appropriately to distinguish Shinto architecture itself from Buddhist architecture, or even to avoid it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>神社は基本的に木の屋根（杮葺、檜皮葺）とするが、近世になると銅板葺きも用いられるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In principle, roofing material of shrine construction is wood (wood strip roofing or cedar bark roofing); later on, in modern era, copper plate roofing became a material of choice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In principle, roofing material in shrine construction is wood (wood strip roofing or cedar bark roofing); later on, in the modern era, copper sheeting became a material of choice.</e>
<cmt>terminology</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In principle, roofing material in shrine construction is wood (wood strip roofing or cedar bark roofing); later on, in the modern era, copper sheeting became a material of choice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>ただし例外的に、本殿に瓦葺を用いる場合もなくはない(たとえば、沖縄の神社は伝統的な赤瓦を用いる)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there are exceptions to the rule of roofing of honden; in Okinawa, for instance, shrine buildings are commonly roofed with traditional red tiles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there are exceptions to the rule in honden roofing; in Okinawa, for instance, shrine buildings are commonly roofed with traditional red tiles.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there are exceptions to the rule in honden roofing; in Okinawa, for instance, shrine buildings are commonly roofed with traditional red tiles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>土壁を用いないことについても同様である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is the same for the non-use of earthen walls.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">similarly, earthen walls are not used.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Similarly, earthen walls are not used.</e>
<cmt>大文字に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="54">
<j>装飾が質素なことは、原始的な段階の日本建築の様式を固定化した結果であるといえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Simple decoration can be interpreted as the resut that shrine architecture conserved the styles of ancient Japanese architecture.</e>
<cmt>「固定化した結果である」の意味が明確でありません。「原始的な段階の日本建築の様式を保存した」というニュアンスと解釈しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Simplicity in decoration can be interpreted as a result of shrines preserving the styles of ancient Japanese architecture.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Simplicity in decoration can be interpreted as a result of shrines preserving the styles of ancient Japanese architecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>日本固有の神の住まいであるので、仏教とは異なることを意識し、日本に伝統的な建築の意匠を取り入れている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Traditional Japanese design elements were incorporated to distinguish itself from buddhist architecture because shrine is a place for Japanese deities.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Traditional Japanese design elements were incorporated to distinguish itself from Buddhist architecture because a shrine is a place for Japanese deities.</e>
<cmt>captialization, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Traditional Japanese design elements were incorporated to distinguish itself from Buddhist architecture because a shrine is a place for Japanese deities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="56">
<j>もちろん以上のことは全ての神社建築に当てはまるわけではなく、時代によっても変遷がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These characteristics however do not always apply to all structures of shrine architecture, which also changes from times to times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These characteristics however do not always apply to all structures of shrine architecture, which also changes from time to time.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These characteristics however do not always apply to all structures of shrine architecture, which also changes from time to time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>本殿の起源</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Origin of honden</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Origin of honden</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Origin of honden</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="57">
<j>古くは神社には社殿がなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was no shaden, or pavillion structures in the ancient days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were no shaden, or pavillion structures in the ancient days.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were no shaden, or pavillion structures in the ancient days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>神は社殿にいるのではなく、山や森などにいると考えられ、それも特定の一箇所に常在するとは考えられていなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kami or deities were believed to dwell not in shaden, but in mountains and forest, and not in single, definite location.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kami or deities were believed to dwell not in shaden, but in mountains and forest, and not in any single, definite location.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kami or deities were believed to dwell not in shaden, but in mountains and forest, and not in any single, definite location.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>しかし、神は特殊な形をした特定の岩や木に来臨すると考えられ、神への祭祀は、そこで行なわれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kami was believed to visit specific rocks and trees with special shapes, and therefore worship to kami was conducted at such places.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kami were believed to visit specific rocks and trees with special shapes, and therefore worship to kami was conducted at such places.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kami were believed to visit specific rocks and trees with special shapes, and therefore worship to kami was conducted at such places.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>この祭場が磐境（いわさか）・磐座（いわくら）などと呼ばれるものであり、現在でも各地に残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These places are called iwasaka or iwakura, both of which refer to an area a deity sits, and are found all over Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These places are called iwasaka or iwakura, both of which refer to an area a deity sits, and are found all over Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These places are called iwasaka or iwakura, both of which refer to an area a deity sits, and are found all over Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>ただ、やはり常にその祭場に神がいるのだとは考えられず、祭祀を行なうときのみ、神がその場に招かれたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Deities, however, were not believed to live there; rather, deities were invited to the place only when worship took place.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Deities, however, were not believed to live there; rather, deities were invited to the place only when worship took place.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Deities, however, were not believed to live there; rather, deities were invited to the place only when worship took place.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="62">
<j>やがて、祭場には仮設の祭壇が設けられるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, people started to set up temporary alters at the ceremony sites.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, people started to set up temporary alters at ceremony sites.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, people started to set up temporary alters at ceremony sites.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>いわゆる「神籬」（ひもろぎ）とよばれるものがこれに当たると考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The alters are considered to be so called himorogi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The alters are considered to be so called himorogi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The alters are considered to be so called himorogi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>神籬は祭祀の際に祭場の上に設置されて、祭祀が行なわれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Himorogi was placed above the worship site at the time of ritual.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Himorogi were placed above the worship site at the time of the ritual.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Himorogi were placed above the worship site at the time of the ritual.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>やがて、この神籬が発展して本格的な建築物をなすようになり、社殿になったと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, himorogi is considered to have developed into a substantial structure and subsequently became shaden, a shrine pavillion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, himorogi is considered to have developed into a substantial structure and subsequently became shaden, a shrine pavillion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, himorogi is considered to have developed into a substantial structure and subsequently became shaden, a shrine pavillion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="66">
<j>仮設の祭壇が常設の社殿になるとき、既にある建築物がそれとして採用されたと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is the process of temporary alter developed into permanent structure of shaden in which then existing construction style was incorporated into the pavillion structure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is the process of a temporary alter developing into a permanent structure called shaden and then the existing construction style was later incorporated into the pavillion structure.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is the process of a temporary alter developing into a permanent structure called shaden and then the existing construction style was later incorporated into the pavillion structure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>ただ建築様式が示す年代とその建築様式が神社建築として使われ始めた年代はおそらく一致しない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there are probably inconsistencies beween the beginning date of an architecture style and the beginning date that particular style started to be used for shrine construction.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there are probably inconsistencies beween the beginning date of an architecture style and the beginning date that particular style started to be used for shrine construction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there are probably inconsistencies between the beginning date of an architecture style and the beginning date that particular style started to be used for shrine construction.</e>
<cmt>beween→between</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>神社に社殿を建てたときに、過去の技法と様式を復古的に採用した可能性が強いのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is because it is likely that the traditional techniques and styles, which were archaic in those days, were adopted in a revivalist manner when the pavillions were built in shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is because it is likely that traditional techniques and styles, which were archaic in those days, were adopted in a revivalist manner when the pavillions were built as shrines.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is because it is likely that traditional techniques and styles, which were archaic in those days, were adopted in a revivalist manner when the pavillions were built as shrines.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>また神社に社殿が登場した時代は仏教建築全盛の時代であり、その影響を受けなかったとはいえない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, the time pavillion construction emerged saw a culmination of buddhism architecture, suggesting that it is likely that the pavillion construction may have affected by buddhism architecture styles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, the time pavillion construction emerged saw a culmination of Buddhism architecture, suggesting that it is likely that pavillion construction may have been affected by Buddhist architectural styles.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, the time pavillion construction emerged saw a culmination of Buddhism architecture, suggesting that it is likely that pavillion construction may have been affected by Buddhist architectural styles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>そもそも建築物を礼拝の対象とするという発想自体が仏教に由来するものかもしれない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The idea of an architectural structure being the object of worship per se may have been originated in buddhism influence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The idea of an architectural structure being the object of worship per se may have originated in Buddhist influence.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The idea of an architectural structure being the object of worship per se may have originated in Buddhist influence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="71">
<j>神社建築の成立に影響を与えたと考えられるのが神宮寺の建立である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered that construction of the jinguji affected the establishment of shrine architecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered that construction of the jinguji affected the establishment of shrine architecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered that construction of the jinguji affected the establishment of shrine architecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>神宮寺は神社に建てられた寺院のことで、神仏習合の初期段階で登場した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jinguji are temples which were built within a shrine; it emerged at an early phase of syncretic process of shinto and buddhism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jinguji are temples which were built within a shrine; it emerged at an early phase of the syncretic process of Shinto and Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>captialization</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jinguji are temples which were built within a shrine; it emerged at an early phase of the syncretic process of Shinto and Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>神宮寺の建立により、神社は仏教建築の直接の影響にさらされたが、隣接するためにかえって神社建築と寺院建築の差異を求めるようになったと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After jinguji temples had started being built, shinto shrines were exposed to the influence of buddhist architecture; however, having been built side by side, differentiation of shrine architecture and buddhist architecture from each other became rather desirable.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After jinguji temples had started being built, Shinto Shrines were exposed to the influence of Buddhist architecture; however, having been built side by side, differentiation of shrine and Buddhist architecture from each other became rather desirable.</e>
<cmt>redundancy, capitalization</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After jinguji temples had started being built, Shinto Shrines were exposed to the influence of Buddhist architecture; however, having been built side by side, differentiation of shrine and Buddhist architecture from each other became rather desirable.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>拝殿の起源</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Origin of haiden</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Origin of haiden</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Origin of haiden</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="74">
<j>拝殿の成立は本殿よりものちである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Establishment of haiden postdates that of honden.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Establishment of haiden postdates that of honden.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Establishment of haiden postdates that of honden.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>現在でも伊勢神宮・春日大社・宇佐神宮・松尾大社など拝殿を持たない古社は多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today there are many old shrines that do not have a haiden, such as Ise Jingu, Kasuga Taisha, Usa Jingu, and Matsuo Taisha.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today there are many old shrines that do not have a haiden, such as Ise Jingu, Kasuga Taisha, Usa Jingu, and Matsuo Taisha.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today there are many old shrines that do not have a haiden, such as Ise Jingu, Kasuga Taisha, Usa Jingu, and Matsuo Taisha.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="76">
<j>拝殿は祭神の祭祀のための施設であるが、本来、祭祀は露天で行なわれるものだった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Haiden is now a place for ceremonies for kami worshiped at a specific shrine; however, originally, ceremonies were performed outdoor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Haiden is now a place for ceremonies for kami that are worshiped at a specific shrine; however, originally, the ceremonies were performed outdoors.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Haiden is now a place for ceremonies for kami that are worshiped at a specific shrine; however, originally, the ceremonies were performed outdoors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>本殿は、その起源を祭壇に求められるように、祭祀の対象であって、祭祀を行なう場ではなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Honden, which was originated in alter, used to be an object of ceremonies intead of a place for having ceremonies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Honden, which was originated as an alter, used to be an object of ceremonies intead of a place for having ceremonies.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Honden, which was originated as an alter, used to be an object of ceremonies instead of a place for having ceremonies.</e>
<cmt>intead→instead</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>拝殿が登場する以前、神社の祭祀は本殿の正面の露天の祭場で行なわれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prior to the establishment of haiden, shrine ceremonies were held outdoor ceremonial place at the front of honden.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prior to the establishment of haiden, shrine ceremonies were held at outdoor ceremonial places in the front of a honden.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prior to the establishment of haiden, shrine ceremonies were held at outdoor ceremonial places in the front of a honden.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>神職らは祭場の左右に着座し、そこから中央の祭場に赴いて祭儀を行なった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Priests and priestesses were seated on the left and right sides of the ceremonial place, from which they moved to the center of the place to perform a ceremony.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Priests and priestesses were seated on the left and right sides of the ceremonial place, from which they moved to the center of the place to perform a ceremony.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Priests and priestesses were seated on the left and right sides of the ceremonial place, from which they moved to the center of the place to perform a ceremony.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="80">
<j>これが祭場が屋内になると、中心の祭場が幣殿となり、神職着座の場が回廊となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later on, when ceremonies started taking place indoor, the central part of the ceremonial place became haiden; the places which used to be the seats for priests and priestesses became kairou or corridors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later on, when ceremonies began taking place indoors, the central part of the ceremonial place became haiden; the places which used to be the seats for priests and priestesses became kairou or corridors.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later on, when ceremonies began taking place indoors, the central part of the ceremonial place became haiden; the places which used to be the seats for priests and priestesses became kairou or corridors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>回廊の入口には楼門が建てられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A two-storied gate or romon was built at the entrance of a corridor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A two-storied gate or romon was built at the entrance of a corridor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A two-storied gate or romon was built at the entrance of a corridor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="82">
<j>このように祭祀の形式にあわせて、楼門と回廊と幣殿が建てられたが、これらを持つに至らない小規模な神社は、やがてその機能を圧縮して、ひとつの社殿にその機能を備えさせることにした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As we have seen, the original forms of ceremonies were developed into the structures of romon, corridor, and heiden; on the other hand, a small size shrine, which was not big enough to have all the sucturets, subsequently consolidated all the features into a single pavillion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As we have seen, the original forms of ceremonies were developed into the structures of romon, corridor, and heiden; on the other hand, a small size shrine, which was not big enough to have all the sections, subsequently consolidated all the features into a single pavillion.</e>
<cmt>spelling; &quot;sucturets&quot; substituted &quot;sections&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As we have seen, the original forms of ceremonies were developed into the structures of romon, corridor, and heiden; on the other hand, a small size shrine, which was not big enough to have all the sections, subsequently consolidated all the features into a single pavillion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>これが拝殿である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is haiden.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Haiden.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is haiden.</e>
<cmt>最初の翻訳の表現が適切と判断し戻しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>楼門・回廊・幣殿の機能を圧縮する形で拝殿が成立したのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Haiden was therefore established by squeezing all the functions of romon, corridor, and heiden.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Haiden was therefore established by squeezing together all the functions of romon, corridor, and heiden.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Haiden was therefore established by squeezing together all the functions of romon, corridor, and heiden.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>建築様式</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Architectural styles</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Architectural styles</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Architectural styles</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>古典的神社建築（本殿）の類型</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Types of classic shrine architecture (honden)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Types of classic shrine architecture (honden)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Types of classic shrine architecture (honden)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="85">
<j>古典的な神社建築（本殿建築）は、以下のように分類することができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Classic shrine architecture (honden) can be categorized as follows:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Classic shrine architecture (honden) can be categorized as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Classic shrine architecture (honden) can be categorized as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="86">
<j>柱の下に土台を持つもの</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Structures that have sills under posts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Structures that have sills under posts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Structures that have sills under posts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>心御柱を持つもの</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Structures that have shin-no-mihashira, or non-structural symbolic post.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Structures that have shin-no-mihashira, or non-structural symbolic post.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Structures that have shin-no-mihashira, or non-structural symbolic post.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>内部が2室に分かれるもの</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Structures that have two divided rooms.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Structures that have two divided rooms.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Structures that have two divided rooms.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>柱の下に土台を持つものは流造・春日造に代表されるものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first type of structures with sills under posts is represented by nagare-zukuri and kasuga-zukuri architectural styles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first type of structures with sills under posts is represented by nagare-zukuri and kasuga-zukuri architectural styles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first type of structures with sills under posts is represented by nagare-zukuri and kasuga-zukuri architectural styles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>柱を地面に直接建てたり、礎石などの基礎を設置したりせずに、社殿の最下部に井桁を組み、その上に柱を建てる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this type of structure, a timber grid is formed on the bottom of the pavillion, on top of which posts are placed, instead of placing posts directly onto the ground or building a foundation such as a foundation stone.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this type of structure, a timber grid is formed on the bottom of the pavillion, on top of which posts are placed, instead of placing posts directly onto the ground or building a foundation with stone.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this type of structure, a timber grid is formed on the bottom of the pavillion, on top of which posts are placed, instead of placing posts directly onto the ground or building a foundation with stone.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>これは社殿を移動させることを前提とした様式で、祭祀のときのみ社殿を設置し、祭祀を行なわないときには社殿を設置していなかったという、上古の祭祀方法の名残ではないかと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The structure assumes the pavillion to be mobile; which is considered to be the traces of ceremony practice in ancient times when a pavillion was placed only at the time of ceremony and the rest of the time it was not set up.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The structure assumes the pavillion to be mobile; which is considered to be atrace of ceremonies practiced in ancient times when a pavillion was placed only at the time of ceremony and the rest of the time it was not set up.</e>
<cmt>revised for grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The structure assumes the pavillion to be mobile; which is considered to be a trace of ceremonies practiced in ancient times when a pavillion was placed only at the time of ceremony and the rest of the time it was not set up.</e>
<cmt>スペース</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>「神籬」と呼ばれる上古の仮設の祭壇が発展して、常設の社殿となったのではないかといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has been suggested that a temporaty alter in ancient times called himorogi was developed into a permanent parillion structure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has been suggested that a temporaty alter in ancient times called himorogi was developed into a permanent pavillion structure.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has been suggested that a temporary alter in ancient times called himorogi was developed into a permanent pavillion structure.</e>
<cmt>tempraty→temporary</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="93">
<j>流造・春日造のいずれも床下を壁で隠蔽している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Both in the nagarezukuri and kasugazukuri styles, the under floor space is covered by a wall.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Both in the nagarezukuri and kasugazukuri styles, the space under the floor is arroundedby a wall.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Both in the nagarezukuri and kasugazukuri styles, the space under the floor is surrounded by a wall.</e>
<cmt>スペース, スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>これは神社建築一般の特徴でもあるが、社殿と設置された地面とのつながりに神聖性を求めることによる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The feature, which is common in shrine architecture in general, is based on the idea that the point of connection between the pavillion and the ground is sacred.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Generally, the feature which is common in shrine architecture is the idea that the point of connection between the pavillion and the ground is sacred.</e>
<cmt>revised wordiness for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Generally, the feature which is common in shrine architecture is the idea that the point of connection between the pavillion and the ground is sacred.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>いいかえると、社殿の神聖性の根源は置かれている場所に求めることができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In other words, the sacredness of a pavillion stems from the place where it is located.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In other words, the sacredness of a pavillion stems from the place where it is located.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In other words, the sacredness of a pavillion stems from the place where it is located.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>すなわち、神体とされる領域や磐座などの上に仮設の祭壇を置いて祀った神籬の形式を受け継いだものではないかということが、ここからも指摘できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This supports the view that pavillions originate in himorogi, in which a temporary alter was placed in the sacred area or on the large rock to invite kami to descend.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This supports the view that pavillions originate in himorogi, in which a temporary alter was placed in a sacred area or on the large rock to invite kami to descend.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This supports the view that pavillions originate in himorogi, in which a temporary alter was placed in a sacred area or on the large rock to invite kami to descend.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="97">
<j>境内社や小祠に用いられる様式で、流造や春日造の階を省略して棚を付けた見世棚造という小型社殿形式があるが、これは省略形というよりはむしろ神社建築の原形に近いともいえるかもしれない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Misedana-zukuri, a small pavillion style, which is characterized by the absence of steps that are present in nagare-zukuri and kasuga-zukuri, and by the presence of a shelf istead; the misedana-zukuri probably is closer to the original form of shrine architecture rather than being a simplified version of a normal size shrine building.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Misedana-zukuri, a small pavillion style, which is characterized by the absence of steps that are present in nagare-zukuri and kasuga-zukuri, and by the presence of a shelf istead; the misedana-zukuri probably is closer to the original form of shrine architecture rather than being a simplified version of a normal size shrine building.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Misedana-zukuri, a small pavillion style, which is characterized by the absence of steps that are present in nagare-zukuri and kasuga-zukuri, and by the presence of a shelf instead; the misedana-zukuri probably is closer to the original form of shrine architecture rather than being a simplified version of a normal size shrine building.</e>
<cmt>intead→instead</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="98">
<j>このように、起源を上古に求めることができ、「柱の下に土台を持つもの」は神社建築の中でも古い形式と考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As we have seen, the origin of these styles go back to the ancient times, and the structure having sills under the posts are considered to be one of the oldest shrine architecture forms.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As we have seen, the origin of these styles go back to ancient times, and the structure having sills under the posts are considered to be one of the oldest shrine architectural forms.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As we have seen, the origin of these styles go back to ancient times, and the structure having sills under the posts are considered to be one of the oldest shrine architectural forms.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="99">
<j>心御柱を持つものは神明造と大社造である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Structures that have shin-no-mihashira, or non-structural symbolic post are shinmei-zukuri style and taisha-zukuri style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Structures that have shin-no-mihashira, or non-structural symbolic post are shinmei-zukuri style and taisha-zukuri style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Structures that have shin-no-mihashira, or non-structural symbolic post are shinmei-zukuri style and taisha-zukuri style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>この様式の特徴は、心御柱・棟持柱を持ち、掘立柱であることである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These styles are characterized by having hottate-bashira, or earthfast posts, such as shin-no-mihashira and munamochi-bashira.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These styles are characterized by having hottate-bashira, or earthfast posts, such as shin-no-mihashira and munamochi-bashira.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These styles are characterized by having hottate-bashira, or earthfast posts, such as shin-no-mihashira and munamochi-bashira.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>心御柱は、社殿の中央にある柱のことであるが、建築構造上、意味をなさない柱であり、本来は神の依代であったと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shin-no-mihashira, which is in the center of a pavillion structure, is a non-structural post, and is considered to have been yorishiro, an object capable of attracting kami originally.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shin-no-mihashira, which is in the center of a pavillion structure, is a non-structural post, and is considered to have been yorishiro, an object originally capable of attracting kami.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shin-no-mihashira, which is in the center of a pavillion structure, is a non-structural post, and is considered to have been yorishiro, an object originally capable of attracting kami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>神明造では社殿本体と完全に分離している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In shinmei-zukuri, shin-no-mihashira is completely separated from the body of the structure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In shinmei-zukuri, shin-no-mihashira is completely separated from the body of the structure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In shinmei-zukuri, shin-no-mihashira is completely separated from the body of the structure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>棟持柱は母屋の梁を支える他の柱と違って棟に届く柱のことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Munamochi-bashira is a post which directly supports the ridge, unlike other posts that support the beam in the main part of the building.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Munamochi-bashira is a post which directly supports the ridge, unlike other posts that support the beam in the main part of the building.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Munamochi-bashira is a post which directly supports the ridge, unlike other posts that support the beam in the main part of the building.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="104">
<j>そして棟持柱を含めて、全ての柱が礎石を使わず地面に穴を掘って建てる掘立柱である（現在の出雲大社は土台の上に建つ）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">All the posts, including munamochi-bashira, are hottate-bashira, which are erected by excavating a hole to insert and being secured without using a foundation stone. (Note: Today&apos;s Izumo-taisha Shrine is built on a sill.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">All the posts, including munamochi-bashira, are hottate-bashira, which are erected by excavating a posthole to insert secure the post without using any foundation stones. (Note: Today&apos;s Izumo-taisha Shrine is built on a sill.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">All the posts, including munamochi-bashira, are hottate-bashira, which are erected by excavating a posthole to insert and secure the post without using any foundation stones. (Note: Today&apos;s Izumo-taisha Shrine is built on a sill.)</e>
<cmt>and を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>掘立柱は原始住居以来の建築に使われるものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hottate-bashira was used in structures for a long time in the history since prehistoric times when it was used in primitive dwellings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hottate-bashira was used in structures throughout history since prehistoric times when it was used in primitive dwellings.</e>
<cmt>grammar, wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hottate-bashira was used in structures throughout history since prehistoric times when it was used in primitive dwellings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="106">
<j>内部が2室に分かれるものは住吉造と八幡造である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Structures that are divided into two buildings are sumiyosi-zukuri and hachiman-zukuri styles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Structures that are divided into two buildings are sumiyosi-zukuri and hachiman-zukuri styles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Structures that are divided into two buildings are sumiyosi-zukuri and hachiman-zukuri styles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>どちらも本殿内部に前後2室もっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In both styels, the honden structure consists of two buildings, one in front of the other.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In both styles, the honden structure consists of two buildings, one in front of the other.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In both styles, the honden structure consists of two buildings, one in front of the other.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>住吉造は後室に神座があり、八幡造は前後の室にそれぞれ神座（昼の神座と夜の神座）があるのであって、両者を簡単にひとくくりにすることは出来ないが、もともと1室の本殿が分化して2室になったものではないという意味で共通である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sumiyosi-zukuri differs from hachiman-zukuri in that in former the building situated in the back has kamiza, or a place of the deity, and in the latter, the front and back buildings have daytime and nighttime places for the deity, respectively; however, sumiyoshi-zukuri and hachiman-zukuri share a commonality in that the two buildings were not developed into from one building.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sumiyosi-zukuri differs from hachiman-zukuri in that in the former, the building situated in the back has kamiza, or a place for the deity, and in the latter, the front and back buildings have daytime and nighttime places for the deity, respectively; however, sumiyoshi-zukuri and hachiman-zukuri share a commonality in that the two buildings were not developed from one building.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sumiyosi-zukuri differs from hachiman-zukuri in that in the former, the building situated in the back has kamiza, or a place for the deity, and in the latter, the front and back buildings have daytime and nighttime places for the deity, respectively; however, sumiyoshi-zukuri and hachiman-zukuri share a commonality in that the two buildings were not developed from one building.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="109">
<j>大鳥造や天皇が大嘗祭のときに祭儀を行なう大嘗宮もこれに含まれると考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered that these styles include otori-zukuri style structures and daijo-gu, a temporary shrine prepared at the palace for Daijo-sai festival, which is held only once in an emperor&apos;s lifetime after his succession, or his first &quot;niiname-sai.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered that these styles include otori-zukuri style structures and daijo-gu, a temporary shrine prepared at the palace for Daijo-sai festival, which is held only once in an emperor&apos;s lifetime after his succession, or his first &quot;niiname-sai.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered that these styles include otori-zukuri style structures and daijo-gu, a temporary shrine prepared at the palace for Daijo-sai festival, which is held only once in an emperor&apos;s lifetime after his succession, or his first &quot;niiname-sai.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>本殿の建築形式</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Architectural styles of honden</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Architectural styles of honden</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Architectural styles of honden</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="110">
<j>神社の建築形式は、様々な種類があるが、最古の形式は、神明造、大社造、住吉造とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are varieties of architectural styles for shrine; shinmei-zukuri, taisha-zukuri, and sumiyosi-zukuri are considered to be the oldest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are various architectural styles for shrines; shinmei-zukuri, taisha-zukuri, and sumiyosi-zukuri are considered to be the oldest.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are various architectural styles for shrines; shinmei-zukuri, taisha-zukuri, and sumiyosi-zukuri are considered to be the oldest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>一般の神社に、よく見られる形式は流造、次いで春日造である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The styles commonly seen in general shrines is nagare-zukuri, which is followed by kasuga-zukuri.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The styles commonly seen in general shrines are nagare-zukuri, followed by kasuga-zukuri.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The styles commonly seen in general shrines are nagare-zukuri, followed by kasuga-zukuri.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>そのほか、建築形式名称がついたものがあるが、神社は固有な形式を持つものが多く、それぞれ別のものとすると膨大な数となり、分類不能であまり意味がなく、屋根形式で分類することが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While there are varieties of architectural style names, each shrine has a distinctive style, which creates a huge number of styles, thus making the classification rather meaningless; shrine architecture is therefore simply classified by the forms of roof.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While there are varieties of architectural style names, each shrine has a distinctive style, which creates a huge number of styles, thus making the classification rather meaningless; shrine architecture is therefore simply classified by the varous forms of the roof.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While there are varieties of architectural style names, each shrine has a distinctive style, which creates a huge number of styles, thus making the classification rather meaningless; shrine architecture is therefore simply classified by the various forms of the roof.</e>
<cmt>varous→various</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="113">
<j>なお、神社建築形式は、複合社殿形式とは同一に扱うことはできない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The shrine architecture styles should be treated separately from the shrine pavillion complex styles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The architectural styles for shrines should be treated separately from the complex styles of shrine pavillions.</e>
<cmt>restructured for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The architectural styles for shrines should be treated separately from the complex styles of shrine pavillions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="114">
<j>神明造（伊勢神宮・三重県伊勢市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinmei-zukuri (Ise City, Mie Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinmei-zukuri (Ise City, Mie Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinmei-zukuri (Ise-jingu Shrine, Ise City, Mie Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>Ise-jingu Shrineを追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="115">
<j>切妻造、平入。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kirizuma-zukuri, hirairi (i.e., a style in which an entry is located in one of the side parallele to the ridge of the roof)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kirizuma-zukuri, hirairi (i.e., a style in which the entrance is located in one of the sides parallel to the ridge of the roof)</e>
<cmt>terminology, spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kirizuma-zukuri, hirairi (i.e., a style in which the entrance is located in one of the sides parallel to the ridge of the roof)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="116">
<j>本来、柱は地面に穴をあけて直接柱を立てた掘立柱とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In principle, kirizuma-zukuri uses hottate-bashira posts, which were erected by excavating a hole in the ground and being secured directly on the ground.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In principle, kirizuma-zukuri uses hottate-bashira posts, which were erected by excavating a hole in the ground and being secured directly in the ground.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In principle, kirizuma-zukuri uses hottate-bashira posts, which were erected by excavating a hole in the ground and being secured directly in the ground.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="117">
<j>屋根の棟に届く棟持柱という柱を持つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kirizuma-zukuri has munamochi-bashira, posts which directly support the ridge.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kirizuma-zukuri have munamochi-bashira, posts which directly support the ridge.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kirizuma-zukuri have munamochi-bashira, posts which directly support the ridge.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="118">
<j>破風板はそのまま延びて千木となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hafu-ita, which are gable boards, extend to become chigi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hafu-ita, which are gable boards, extend to become chigi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hafu-ita, which are gable boards, extend to become chigi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="119">
<j>明治時代以降に建てられた神社は神明造が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many shrines build in Meiji era and beyond have a shinmei-zukuri style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many shrines built in Meiji era and later have a shinmei-zukuri style.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many shrines built in Meiji period and later have a shinmei-zukuri style.</e>
<cmt>era→periodに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="120">
<j>特に伊勢の神宮の本殿は唯一神明造と言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The honden of Ise-jingu Shrine, in particular, is called yuitsu-jinmei-zukuri, literally, the unique shinmei-zukuri style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The honden of Ise-jingu Shrine, in particular, is called yuitsu-jinmei-zukuri, literally, the unique shinmei-zukuri style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The honden of Ise-jingu Shrine, in particular, is called yuitsu-jinmei-zukuri, literally, the unique shinmei-zukuri style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="121">
<j>相撲の吊り屋根は神明造に分類される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsuriyane, or a hanging roof above the dohyo (sumo wresling ring) is classified as shinmei-zukuri style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsuriyane, or a hanging roof above the dohyo (sumo wrestling ring) is classified as shinmei-zukuri style.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsuriyane, or a hanging roof above the dohyo (sumo wrestling ring) is classified as shinmei-zukuri style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="122">
<j>大社造（神魂神社、出雲大社・島根県）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taisha-zukuri (Kamosu-jinja Shrine and Izumo-taisha Shrine, in Shimane Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taisha-zukuri (Kamosu-jinja Shrine and Izumo-taisha Shrine, in Shimane Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taisha-zukuri (Kamosu-jinja Shrine and Izumo-taisha Shrine, in Shimane Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="123">
<j>切妻造、妻入。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kirizuma-zukuri, tsumairi (i.e., a style in which an entry is located in one of the gable side of the building.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kirizuma-zukuri, tsumairi (i.e., a style in which the entrance is located in one of the gabled sides of the building.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kirizuma-zukuri, tsumairi (i.e., a style in which the entrance is located in one of the gabled sides of the building.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="124">
<j>屋根の棟に届く棟持柱を持つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The kirizuma-zukuri structures have munamochi-bashira, or posts which hold the ridge.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The kirizuma-zukuri structures have munamochi-bashira, or posts which hold the ridge.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The kirizuma-zukuri structures have munamochi-bashira, or posts which hold the ridge.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="125">
<j>正面二間のため入口が左右のどちらかに寄る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The entrance is located either in the rightward or leftward instead of in the middle because the front side is two-bay wide.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The entrance is located either on the right or left side instead of in the middle because the front is two-bays wide.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The entrance is located either on the right or left side instead of in the middle because the front is two-bays wide.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="126">
<j>住吉造（住吉大社・大阪府大阪市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sumiyosi-zukuri style (Sumiyosi taisha, Osaka City, Osaka Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sumiyosi-zukuri style (Sumiyosi taisha, Osaka City, Osaka Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sumiyosi-zukuri style (Sumiyosi taisha, Osaka City, Osaka Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="127">
<j>切妻造、妻入。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kirizuma-zukuri style, tsumairi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kirizuma-zukuri style, tsumairi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kirizuma-zukuri style, tsumairi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="128">
<j>関西の住吉大社に関係する一部神社に見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some shrines that are related to Sumiyoshi-jinja in Kansai Region have the style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some shrines that are related to Sumiyoshi-jinja in Kansai Region have this style.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some shrines that are related to Sumiyoshi-jinja in Kansai Region have this style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="129">
<j>内部は前後2室に分かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Internally, the structure is divided into two buildings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Internally, the structure is divided into two buildings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Internally, the structure is divided into two buildings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="130">
<j>大嘗祭の際に造られる建物と似ていることが指摘されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The structural similarity with the buildings which are built at the time of Daijo sai has been suggested.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The structural similarity with the buildings which were built at the time of Daijo sai has been suggested.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The structural similarity with the buildings which were built at the time of Daijo sai has been suggested.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="131">
<j>大鳥造（大鳥大社・大阪府堺市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Otori-zukuri style (Otori-taisha shrine, Sakai City, Osaka Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Otori-zukuri style (Otori-taisha shrine, Sakai City, Osaka Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Otori-zukuri style (Otori-taisha Shrine, Sakai City, Osaka Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>大文字に（Shrine)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="132">
<j>切妻造、妻入。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kirizuma-zukuri style, tsumairi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kirizuma-zukuri style, tsumairi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kirizuma-zukuri style, tsumairi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="133">
<j>住吉造を簡略化したもので奥行きが半分になっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A simplified version of the sumiyoshi zukuri-style with half the standard depth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A simplified version of the sumiyoshi zukuri-style with half the standard depth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A simplified version of the sumiyoshi zukuri-style with half the standard depth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="134">
<j>春日造（春日大社・奈良県奈良市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kasuga-zukuri style (Kasuga-taisha Shrine, Nara City, Nara Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kasuga-zukuri style (Kasuga-taisha Shrine, Nara City, Nara Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kasuga-zukuri style (Kasuga-taisha Shrine, Nara City, Nara Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="135">
<j>妻入。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsumairi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsumairi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsumairi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="136">
<j>身舎の前方に庇を付けた形式。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A style in which an eave is added to the main building.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A style in which an eave is added to the main building.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A style in which an eave is added at the front of the main building.</e>
<cmt>前方＝frontを追加。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="137">
<j>関西を中心に広く見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This style is widely seen over Kansai Region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This style is widely seen all over the Kansai Region.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This style is widely seen all over the Kansai Region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="138">
<j>バリエーションとして王子造(熊野造、皇子造)がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oji-zukuri style (or alternatively called Kumano-zukuri style) is a variation of kasuga-zukuri tsumairi style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oji-zukuri style (or alternatively called Kumano-zukuri style) is a variation of kasuga-zukuri tsumairi style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oji-zukuri style (or alternatively called Kumano-zukuri style) is a variation of kasuga-zukuri tsumairi style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="139">
<j>流造（賀茂神社上賀茂神社、下鴨神社・京都府京都市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagare-zukuri style (Kamo-jinja Shrines, encompassing Kamigamo-jinja and Shimogamo-jinja in Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>「賀茂神社上賀茂神社、下鴨神社」の意味が正確にわかりませんでした。賀茂神社：「賀茂社」は上賀茂神社と下鴨神社の総称であるとのことでここでその意味で使われていると仮定し、すなわちここで示されているのは上賀茂神社と下鴨神社の2つの神社であると解釈しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagare-zukuri style (Kamo-jinja Shrines, encompassing Kamigamo-jinja and Shimogamo-jinja in Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagare-zukuri style (Kamo-jinja Shrines, encompassing Kamigamo-jinja and Shimogamo-jinja in Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="140">
<j>切妻造、平入。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiritsuma-zukuri style, hirairi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiritsuma-zukuri style, hirairi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiritsuma-zukuri style, hirairi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="141">
<j>身舎の前方に庇を付けた形式。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A style in which an eave is added to the main building.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A style in which an eave is added to the main building.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A style in which an eave is added at the front of the main building.</e>
<cmt>前方＝frontを追加。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="142">
<j>全国に多く見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This style is seen all over Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This style is seen all over Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This style is seen all over Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="143">
<j>バリエーションとして両流造（厳島神社）がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryonagare zukuri (Itsukushima-jinja Shrine) is a variation of kasuga-zukuri hirairi style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryonagare zukuri (Itsukushima-jinja Shrine) is a variation of kasuga-zukuri hirairi style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryonagare zukuri (Itsukushima-jinja Shrine) is a variation of kasuga-zukuri hirairi style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="144">
<j>八幡造（宇佐神宮・大分県、石清水八幡宮・京都府八幡市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hachiman-zukuri (Usa-jingu Shrine, Oita Prefecture; Iwashimizu hachimangu, Hachiman City, Kyoto Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hachiman-zukuri (Usa-jingu Shrine, Oita Prefecture; Iwashimizu hachimangu, Hachiman City, Kyoto Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hachiman-zukuri (Usa-jingu Shrine, Oita Prefecture; Iwashimizu hachimangu, Hachiman City, Kyoto Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="145">
<j>本殿の内部が前後2室に分かれ、それぞれの上に屋根が乗っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Internally, the honden structure is divided into two buildings, in the front and back, and each building has a roof independently from each other.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Internally, the honden structure is divided into two buildings, in the front and back, and each building has a roof independent from the other.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Internally, the honden structure is divided into two buildings, in the front and back, and each building has a roof independent from the other.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="146">
<j>入母屋造（御上神社など）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Irimoya-zukuri style (Mikami-jinja Shrine, etc.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Irimoya-zukuri style (Mikami-jinja Shrine, etc.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Irimoya-zukuri style (Mikami-jinja Shrine, etc.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="147">
<j>仏教建築の影響を受けて中世に成立した形式と考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Irimoya-zukuri style is considered to have been established in medieval times under buddhism influence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Irimoya-zukuri style is considered to have been established in medieval times under Buddhist influence.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Irimoya-zukuri style is considered to have been established in medieval times under Buddhist influence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="148">
<j>バリエーションとして日吉造(聖帝造、山王造)がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hie-zukuri style (or alternatively called shotei-zukuri style or san&apos;no-zukuri style) is a variation of irimoya-zukuri</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hie-zukuri style (or alternatively called shotei-zukuri style or san&apos;no-zukuri style) is a variation of irimoya-zukuri</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hie-zukuri style (or alternatively called shotei-zukuri style or sanno-zukuri style) is a variation of irimoya-zukuri</e>
<cmt>ｓan&apos;no→sannoに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="149">
<j>隠岐造（水若酢神社）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oki-zukuri style (Mizuwakasu-jinja Shrine)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oki-zukuri style (Mizuwakasu-jinja Shrine)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oki-zukuri style (Mizuwakasu-jinja Shrine)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="150">
<j>吉備津造、別名：比翼入母屋造り（吉備津神社 (岡山市)）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kibitsu-zukuri style, other name: hiyoku-irimoya-zukuri (Kibitsu-jinja Shrine, Okayama City)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kibitsu-zukuri style, other name: hiyoku-irimoya-zukuri (Kibitsu-jinja Shrine, Okayama City)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kibitsu-zukuri style, other name: hiyoku-irimoya-zukuri (Kibitsu-jinja Shrine, Okayama City)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="151">
<j>織田造（劔神社・福井県越前町)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oda-zukuri style (Tsurugi-jinja Shrine, Echizen Cho, Fukui Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oda-zukuri style (Tsurugi-jinja Shrine, Echizen Cho, Fukui Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oda-zukuri style (Tsurugi-jinja Shrine, Echizen Cho, Fukui Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="152">
<j>尾張造（真清田神社、津島神社、尾張大国霊神社など）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Owari-zukuri style (Masumida-jinja Shrine, Tsushima-jinja Shrine, and Owari Okuninotama-jinja Shrine)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Owari-zukuri style (Masumida-jinja Shrine, Tsushima-jinja Shrine, and Owari Okuninotama-jinja Shrine)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Owari-zukuri style (Masumida-jinja Shrine, Tsushima-jinja Shrine, and Owari Okuninotama-jinja Shrine)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="153">
<j>特に大県神社は特殊で、大縣造、三棟造とも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Of particular unique shrine is Oagata-jinja Shrine, which is specifically called ogata-zukuri, or mitsumune-zukuri.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A particular unique shrine is Oagata-jinja Shrine, which is specifically called ogata-zukuri, or mitsumune-zukuri.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A particular unique shrine is Oagata-jinja Shrine, which is specifically called ogata-zukuri, or mitsumune-zukuri.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="154">
<j>水分造（建水分神社・千早赤阪村など）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mikumari zukuri (Takemikumari-jinja Shrine, Chihaya Akasaka Village, and others)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mikumari zukuri (Takemikumari-jinja Shrine, Chihaya Akasaka Village, and others)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mikumari zukuri (Takemikumari-jinja Shrine, Chihaya Akasaka Village, and others)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="155">
<j>春日造の本殿と流造の左右両殿を渡廊で連結する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The style, in which a roofed passage connects the honden in the middle, which is kasuga-zukuri style, and the two buildings, which are nagare-zukuri style, located one on the right and the other on the left.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A style, in which a roofed passage connects the honden in the middle, which is kasuga-zukuri style, and the two buildings, which are nagare-zukuri style, located one on the right and the other on the left.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A style, in which a roofed passage connects the honden in the middle, which is kasuga-zukuri style, and the two buildings, which are nagare-zukuri style, located one on the right and the other on the left.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="156">
<j>天水分神を祀る神社に見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The style is typically seen in shrines which enshrine Ameno mikumarinokami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This style is typically seen in shrines which enshrine Ameno mikumarinokami.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This style is typically seen in shrines which enshrine Ameno mikumarinokami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>複合社殿形式</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shrine pavillion complex styles</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shrine pavillion complex styles</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shrine pavillion complex styles</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="157">
<j>祇園造（八坂神社）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gion-zukuri style (Yasaka-jinja Shrine)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gion-zukuri style (Yasaka-jinja Shrine)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gion-zukuri style (Yasaka-jinja Shrine)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="158">
<j>本殿と拝殿の双方をまとめて巨大な屋根が覆っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The honden and haiden buildings are under one large roof.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The honden and haiden buildings are under one large roof.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The honden and haiden buildings are under one large roof.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="159">
<j>権現造（北野神社、日光東照宮など）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gongen zukuri (Kitano-jinja Shrine, Nikko Toshogu, etc)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gongen zukuri (Kitano-jinja Shrine, Nikko Toshogu, etc)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gongen zukuri (Kitano-jinja Shrine, Nikko Toshogu, etc)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="160">
<j>本殿と幣殿と拝殿を繋いで建てている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The honden, heiden, and haiden buildings are connected together.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The honden, heiden, and haiden buildings are connected together.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The honden, heiden, and haiden buildings are connected together.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="161">
<j>浅間造（富士山本宮浅間大社）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sengen-zukuri (Fujisan Hongu Sengen-taisha Shrine).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sengen-zukuri (Fujisan Hongu Sengen-taisha Shrine).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sengen-zukuri (Fujisan Hongu Sengen-taisha Shrine).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="162">
<j>社殿の上（2階）に流造の本殿を設置している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Upper story is the honden, which is nagare-zukuri style, situated on top of the pavillion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Upper story is the honden, which is nagare-zukuri style, situated on top of the pavillion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Upper story is the honden, which is nagare-zukuri style, situated on top of the pavillion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>拝殿の建築様式</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Architectural styles of haiden</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Architectural styles of haiden</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Architectural styles of haiden</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="163">
<j>拝殿は3種類に分類できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Haiden can be classified into three types:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Haiden can be classified into three types:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Haiden can be classified into three types:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="164">
<j>横拝殿</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoko-haiden (literally, a wide rectangular prayer hall)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoko-haiden (literally, a wide rectangular prayer hall)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoko-haiden (literally, a wide rectangular prayer hall)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="165">
<j>棟が横に通っているものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A structure in which a beam runs parallel to the front and rear sides.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A structure in which a beam runs parallel to the front and rear sides.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A structure in which a beam runs parallel to the front and rear sides.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="166">
<j>最も一般的な様式といえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoko-haiden is one of the most typical styles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoko-haiden is one of the most typical styles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoko-haiden is one of the most typical styles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="167">
<j>着座する人々が本殿に対面するようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoko-haiden is structured in the way that prayers seated face at the honden.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoko-haiden is structured in the way that those who pray are seated to face the honden.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoko-haiden is structured in the way that those who pray are seated to face the honden.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="168">
<j>切妻造・入母屋造などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The styles can be kirizuma-zukuri, irimoya-zukuri</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The styles can be kirizuma-zukuri, irimoya-zukuri</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The styles can be kirizuma-zukuri, irimoya-zukuri</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="169">
<j>縦拝殿</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tate-haiden (literally, a deep breath rectangular prayer hall)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tate-haiden (literally, a deep breadth rectangular prayer hall)</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tate-haiden (literally, a deep breadth rectangular prayer hall)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="170">
<j>棟が縦に通っているものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A structure in which a beam runs parallel to the right and left sides.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A structure in which a beam runs parallel to the right and left sides.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A structure in which a beam runs parallel to the right and left sides.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="171">
<j>本殿への通路としての性格を持ち、縦長となる奥の部分は幣殿も兼ねている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tate-haiden serves as a passageway to the honden, and the space toward the end of the long axis of the haiden serves as heiden, or offering hall.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tate-haiden serves as a passageway to the honden, and the space toward the end of the long axis of the haiden serves as heiden, or offering hall.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tate-haiden serves as a passageway to the honden, and the space toward the end of the long axis of the haiden serves as heiden, or offering hall.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="172">
<j>拝殿が成立する以前の回廊形式だったころの幣殿が変化したものとも考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The corridor style heiden, which had been common in old times before haiden was established, is believed to have been developed into tate-haiden.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The corridor style heiden, which had been common in olden times before haiden was established, is believed to have been developed into tate-haiden.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The corridor style heiden, which had been common in olden times before haiden was established, is believed to have been developed into tate-haiden.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="173">
<j>割拝殿</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wari-haiden (literally, a divided prayer hall)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wari-haiden (literally, a divided prayer hall)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wari-haiden (literally, a divided prayer hall)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="174">
<j>中央が吹き抜けになっていて、左右に床間がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A structure in which there is a passageway in the center with vaulted ceilings, and there are raised timber floor rooms in both sides separated by the passageway.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A structure in which there is a passageway in the center with vaulted ceilings, and there are raised timber floored rooms in both sides separated by the passageway.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A structure in which there is a passageway in the center with vaulted ceilings, and there are raised timber floored rooms in both sides separated by the passageway.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="175">
<j>これは回廊形式の中門と左右の回廊が変形した結果だと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered that the chumon, or middle gate and the corridors on the right and left in the corridor style structure were developed into the form of wari-haiden.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered that the chumon, or middle gate and the corridors on the right and left in the corridor style structure were developed into the form of wari-haiden.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered that the chumon, or middle gate and the corridors on the right and left in the corridor style structure were developed into the form of wari-haiden.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="176">
<j>遺構は少なく大神神社・石上神宮摂社出雲建男神社・大崎八幡宮に見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today there are only few structures that retain the form of warihaiden style, such as: Omiwa-jinja Shrine, Isonokami Jingu Sessha Izumo Takeo-jinja Shrine, and Osaki Hachimangu Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today there are only few structures that retain the form of warihaiden style, such as: Omiwa-jinja Shrine, Isonokami Jingu Sessha Izumo Takeo-jinja Shrine, and Osaki Hachimangu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today there are only few structures that retain the form of warihaiden style, such as: Omiwa-jinja Shrine, Isonokami Jingu Sessha Izumo Takeo-jinja Shrine, and Osaki Hachimangu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 JAnDbot(id:66507), 浩(id:70121), Mobnoboka(id:35218), Nnh(id:474), Reggaeman(id:6214), Kstigarbha(id:13376), Stanislaus(id:1806), Kansai explorer(id:48975), Tast(id:29478), Koba-chan(id:860), Mega(id:34550), Tantal(id:74335), Wiiii(id:59641), 桔梗Store(id:58881), Fryed-peach(id:63402), Tomomarusan(id:17060), Kenpei(id:11349), Kinori(id:443), N yotarou(id:60870), Deapy(id:191082), Alay(id:37659), Wakkubox(id:30396), 663highland(id:18755), ChibaRagi(id:68046), NDR(id:5500), Junger(id:10282), SieBot(id:126695), Chuta(id:10457), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>