<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>上代特殊仮名遣</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jodai Tokushu Kanazukai (ancient Japanese phonetic orthography)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jodai Tokushu Kanazukai (ancient Japanese phonetic orthography)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jodai Tokushu Kanazukai (ancient Japanese phonetic orthography)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>上代特殊仮名遣（じょうだいとくしゅかなづかい）とは上代日本語における『古事記』・『日本書紀』・『万葉集』など上代（奈良時代頃）の万葉仮名文献に用いられた表音的仮名遣である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jodai Tokushu Kanazukai is Japanese phonetic orthography used in ancient Japan (around the Nara period), which can be observed in the documents written in Manyo-gana (Chinese characters used as phonetic characters) such as &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters), &quot;Nihon Shoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan) and &quot;Manyoshu&quot; (Collection of Ten Thousand Leaves).</e>
<cmt>「万葉仮名」→音を表記するために用いた漢字（yahoo辞書）。&quot;Chinese characters used as phonetic characters&quot;と説明を入れました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jodai Tokushu Kanazukai is Japanese phonetic orthography used in ancient Japan (around the Nara period), which can be observed in the documents written in Manyo-gana (Chinese characters used as phonetic characters) such as &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters), &quot;Nihon Shoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan) and &quot;Manyoshu&quot; (Collection of Ten Thousand Leaves).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jodai Tokushu Kanazukai is Japanese phonetic orthography used in ancient Japan (around the Nara period), which can be observed in the documents written in Manyo-gana (Chinese characters used as phonetic characters) such as &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters), &quot;Nihon Shoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan) and &quot;Manyoshu&quot; (Collection of Ten Thousand Leaves).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>定家仮名遣に先立つ古い時代の歴史的仮名遣ともされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is recognized as a historical phonetic orthography in ancient times, preceding to Teika Kanazukai (phonetic orthography established by FUJIWARA no Teika in the Kamakura period).</e>
<cmt>「定家仮名遣」→鎌倉時代に藤原定家が定めた仮名遣（kotobank）。そのように説明を入れました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is recognized as a historical phonetic orthography in ancient times, preceding Teika Kanazukai (phonetic orthography established by FUJIWARA no Teika in the Kamakura period).</e>
<cmt>precedeは他動詞ですので、toは不要と思われます。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is recognized as a historical phonetic orthography in ancient times, preceding Teika Kanazukai (phonetic orthography established by FUJIWARA no Teika in the Kamakura period).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>名称は国語学者橋本進吉の論文「上代の文献に存する特殊の仮名遣と当時の語法」に由来する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its name has been derived from the article called &apos;Special Phonetic Orthography and Usage in the Documents Written in Ancient Japanese&apos; written by a Japanese linguist Shinkichi HASHIMOTO.</e>
<cmt>「上代の文献に存する特殊の仮名遣と当時の語法」→定訳不明。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its name has been derived from the article called &apos;Special Phonetic Orthography and Usage in the Documents Written in Ancient Japanese&apos; written by a Japanese linguist Shinkichi HASHIMOTO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its name has been derived from the article called &apos;Special Phonetic Orthography and Usage in the Documents Written in Ancient Japanese&apos; written by a Japanese linguist Shinkichi HASHIMOTO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>単に「上代仮名」とも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called simply &quot;Jodai-gana.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called simply &quot;Jodai-gana.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called simply &quot;Jodai-gana.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>現代日本語の50音のうち、イ段のキ・ヒ・ミ、エ段のケ・へ・メ、オ段のコ・ソ・ト・ノ・（モ）・ヨ・ロ及びエの14音について奈良時代以前の上代には甲類と乙類の万葉仮名の書き分けが見られ、両者は厳格に区別されていたことがわかっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is known that among the 50-character syllabary used today, 14 sounds were written in two types of Manyo-gana, A-type and B-type, in ancient Japan before the Nara period, and this distinction of the types was strictly maintained; these 14 sounds were &quot;キ, ヒ, ミ&quot; (ki, hi, mi) with the vowel of イ (i), &quot;ケ, へ, メ&quot; (ke, he, me) with the vowel of エ (e), &quot;コ, ソ, ト, ノ, (モ), ヨ, ロ&quot; (ko, so, to, no, [mo], yo, ro) with the vowel of オ (o), and the vowel &quot;エ&quot; (e).</e>
<cmt>「イ段」「エ段」「オ段」→それぞれ「イ、エ、オの母音を伴う音」と解釈して訳しました。「甲類」「乙類」→定訳不明。&quot;A-type, B-type&quot;と訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is known that among the 50-character syllabary used today, 14 sounds were written in two types of Manyo-gana, namely A-type and B-type, in ancient Japan before the Nara period, and this distinction of the types was strictly maintained; these 14 sounds were &quot;キ, ヒ, ミ&quot; (ki, hi, mi) with the vowel of イ (i), &quot;ケ, へ, メ&quot; (ke, he, me) with the vowel of エ (e), &quot;コ, ソ, ト, ノ, (モ), ヨ, ロ&quot; (ko, so, to, no, [mo], yo, ro) with the vowel of オ (o), and the vowel &quot;エ&quot; (e).</e>
<cmt>A-typeの前にnamelyを挿入しました。（Manyo-ganaと一続きの羅列とみなされないように。）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is known that among the 50-character syllabary used today, 14 sounds were written in two types of Manyo-gana, namely A-type and B-type, in ancient Japan before the Nara period, and this distinction of the types was strictly maintained; these 14 sounds were &quot;キ, ヒ, ミ&quot; (ki, hi, mi) with the vowel of イ (i), &quot;ケ, へ, メ&quot; (ke, he, me) with the vowel of エ (e), &quot;コ, ソ, ト, ノ, (モ), ヨ, ロ&quot; (ko, so, to, no, [mo], yo, ro) with the vowel of オ (o), and the vowel &quot;エ&quot; (e).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>ただし、モの区別は『古事記』のみに見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the distinction of モ (mo) is only observed in &quot;Kojiki.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the distinction of モ (mo) is observed only in &quot;Kojiki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>onlyの位置を「in &quot;Kojiki&quot;｣の直前にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the distinction of モ (mo) is observed only in &quot;Kojiki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>またエはア行とヤ行に分けられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;エ&quot; was divided into two sounds: one of vowel (e) and the other of a consonant and vowel (ye).</e>
<cmt>「ア行」「ヤ行」→「母音の&quot;e&quot;」と「子音と母音の&quot;ye&quot;」と訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;エ&quot; appeared in two sounds: one of vowel (e) and the other of a consonant and vowel (ye).</e>
<cmt>「分けられていた」は「エがア行、ヤ行の2箇所に登場する」ことを意味しているものと判断し、&quot;appeared in&quot;と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;エ&quot; appeared in two sounds: one of vowel (e) and the other of a consonant and vowel (ye).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>なお、甲乙の区別は濁音のギ・ビ・ゲ・ベ・ゴ・ゾ・ドにもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The distinction between A-type and B-type also existed in the dull sounds of ギ, ビ, ゲ, ベ, ゴ, ゾ and ド (gi, bi, ge, be, go, zo and do).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The distinction between A-type and B-type also existed in the dull sounds of ギ, ビ, ゲ, ベ, ゴ, ゾ and ド (gi, bi, ge, be, go, zo and do).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The distinction between A-type and B-type also existed in the dull sounds of ギ, ビ, ゲ, ベ, ゴ, ゾ and ド (gi, bi, ge, be, go, zo and do).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>甲乙の差異については、例えば「き」を表す万葉仮名は支・吉・峡・来・棄などの漢字が甲類の「き」とされ、「秋」や「君」「時」「聞く」の「き」を表していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for the distinction between A-type and B-type, for example, Manyo-gana representing the sound of &quot;き&quot; (ki) included Chinese characters of 支, 吉, 峡, 来 and 棄, which were A-type characters and used to write &quot;き&quot; (ki) of &quot;aki&quot; (autumn), &quot;kimi&quot; (you), &quot;toki&quot; (time) or &quot;kiku&quot; (listen).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for the distinction between A-type and B-type, for example, Manyo-gana representing the sound of &quot;き&quot; (ki) included in the Chinese characters of 支, 吉, 峡, 来 and 棄 were A-type characters and used to write &quot;き&quot; (ki) of &quot;aki&quot; (autumn), &quot;kimi&quot; (you), &quot;toki&quot; (time) or &quot;kiku&quot; (listen).</e>
<cmt>whichにより文が複雑になっていると思われましたので、whichを除き、wereを主動詞にしました。Includedの後にinを入れました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for the distinction between A-type and B-type, for example, Manyo-gana representing the sound of &quot;き&quot; (ki) included in the Chinese characters of 支, 吉, 峡, 来 and 棄 were A-type characters and used to write &quot;き&quot; (ki) of &quot;aki&quot; (autumn), &quot;kimi&quot; (you), &quot;toki&quot; (time) or &quot;kiku&quot; (listen).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>そして己・紀・記・忌・氣などが乙類の「き」とされ、「霧」「岸」「月」「木」などの「き」を表している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, characters like 己, 紀, 記, 忌 and 氣 were B-type, and used to write &quot;き&quot; (ki) of &quot;kiri&quot; (mist), &quot;kishi&quot; (shore), &quot;tsuki&quot; (moon) or &quot;ki&quot; (tree).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, characters like 己, 紀, 記, 忌 and 氣 were B-type, and used to write &quot;き&quot; (ki) of &quot;kiri&quot; (mist), &quot;kishi&quot; (shore), &quot;tsuki&quot; (moon) or &quot;ki&quot; (tree).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, characters like 己, 紀, 記, 忌 and 氣 were B-type, and used to write &quot;き&quot; (ki) of &quot;kiri&quot; (mist), &quot;kishi&quot; (shore), &quot;tsuki&quot; (moon) or &quot;ki&quot; (tree).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>上代の文献では全体にわたってこのように整然たる仮名の使い分けが見られ、一部の例外を除いて甲乙の混同は見られず両者は厳然と区別されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">We can see such a methodical usage of phonetic characters throughout the documents written in ancient Japanese, and with some exceptions, A-type and B-type were strictly distinguished and there was no confusion about it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">We can see such a methodical usage of phonetic characters throughout the documents written in ancient Japanese, and with some exceptions, A-type and B-type were strictly distinguished and there was no confusion between them.</e>
<cmt>confusionの後の「about it」を「between them｣にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">We can see such a methodical usage of phonetic characters throughout the documents written in ancient Japanese, and with some exceptions, A-type and B-type were strictly distinguished and there was no confusion between them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>こうした甲乙の区別は、上代においては母音がアイウエオの5音の他にイエオのみ甲乙の2種類に分かれ、8母音であったことから生じたという音韻による区別の説が立てられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A theory has been developed about this distinction of A-type and B-type that it was caused by the distinction of sounds; in ancient times, there were eight vowels, which were five vowels of アイウエオ (a, i, u, e, o) and each of イエオ (i, e, o) having two types, A-type and B-type.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A theory has been developed about this distinction between A-type and B-type, saying the distinction stemed from sounds; in ancient times, there were eight vowels, which were five vowels of アイウエオ (a, i, u, e, o) with each of イエオ (i, e, o) having two types, A-type and B-type.</e>
<cmt>最初のdistionctionの後のofをbetweenにしました。&quot;that it was&quot;のitはdistinctionを指すと思われるので、簡潔にし、動詞もそれに伴って変更しました。Having two typesは付帯状況を示すと思われたので、andをwithにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A theory has been developed about this distinction between A-type and B-type, saying the distinction stemed from sounds; in ancient times, there were eight vowels, which were five vowels of アイウエオ (a, i, u, e, o) with each of イエオ (i, e, o) having two types, A-type and B-type.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>すなわち、上代日本語は50音でなく87音（あるいは88音）あったと考えられたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, it has been considered that ancient Japanese syllabary had 87 sounds (or 88), not 50.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, it has been considered that ancient Japanese syllabary had 87 sounds (or 88), not 50.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, it has been considered that ancient Japanese syllabary had 87 sounds (or 88), not 50.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>そして、平安時代以降になってそのような区別が薄れたため、一つに統合されていったと考えるのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It says that the distinction of such types gradually died down after the Heian period and they were unified.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It says that the distinction of such types gradually died down after the Heian period and they were unified.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It says that the distinction of such types gradually faded away after the Heian period and they were unified.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>ただし、実際の音価については不明な点も多く、また音素として別だったかについても異論がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, actual sounds for characters are largely unknown, and there are also different opinions whether their phonemes were different.</e>
<cmt>「音価」→ひとつの文字に該当すると認められる音声。「音素」→phoneme（kotobank）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, actual sounds for characters are largely unknown, and there are also different opinions whether they had different phonemes or not.</e>
<cmt>原文「音素として別」ですが、実際「別の音素を有する」のではないかと思われたので「had different phoneme」としました。また、「or　not」を文末に追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, actual sounds for characters are largely unknown, and there are also different opinions whether they had different phonemes or not.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="17">
<j>上代特殊仮名遣が用いられていた当時はまだ「かな」が発達していなかったため、これを表現する仮名文字はヤ行のエを除いて存在しない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the time Jodai Tokushu Kanazukai was used, &quot;Kana&quot; (Hiragana and Katakana, phonetic Japanese syllabaries) had not been developed yet so that only Kana character representing Jodai Tokushu Kanazukai was エ with the consonant y (ye).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the time Jodai Tokushu Kanazukai was used, &quot;Kana&quot; (Hiragana and Katakana, phonetic Japanese syllabaries) had not been developed yet so that only Kana character representing Jodai Tokushu Kanazukai is エ with the consonant y (ye).</e>
<cmt>｢上代特殊仮名遣を表現する仮名文字が・・・存在しない」のは現在であると思われるので、後半wasを現在形にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the time Jodai Tokushu Kanazukai was used, &quot;Kana&quot; (Hiragana and Katakana, phonetic Japanese syllabaries) had not been developed yet so that only Kana character representing Jodai Tokushu Kanazukai is エ with the consonant y (ye).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>そのため、文字上で甲乙の区別をする必要がある時は傍線や片仮名化、ローマ字のウムラウトなどで対応している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, when it is necessary to distinguish between A-type and B-type, characters are written with underlines, in Katakana or alphabet letters with umlauts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, when it is necessary to distinguish between A-type and B-type, characters are written with underlines, in Katakana or alphabet letters with umlauts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, when it is necessary to distinguish between A-type and B-type, characters are written with underlines, in Katakana or alphabet letters with umlauts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="19">
<j>特殊仮名遣の発見</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Discovery of Jodai Tokushu Kanazukai</e>
<cmt>「特殊仮名遣」→「上代特殊仮名遣」と補足して訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Discovery of Jodai Tokushu Kanazukai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Discovery of Jodai Tokushu Kanazukai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>本居宣長・石塚龍麿</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Norinaga MOTOORI and Tatsumaro ISHIZUKA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Norinaga MOTOORI and Tatsumaro ISHIZUKA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Norinaga MOTOORI and Tatsumaro ISHIZUKA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>上代特殊仮名遣はまず本居宣長によって研究の端緒が開かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The study of Jodai Tokushu Kanazukai was initiated by Norinaga MOTOORI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The study of Jodai Tokushu Kanazukai was initiated by Norinaga MOTOORI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The study of Jodai Tokushu Kanazukai was initiated by Norinaga MOTOORI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>宣長の浩瀚な『古事記』の註釈書、『古事記伝』には、第一巻の「仮字の事」ですでに「同じ音の中でも、言葉に応じてそれぞれに当てる仮字が使い分けられている」ことが指摘されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Kojiki-den&quot; (Commentary on the Kojiki), Norinaga&apos;s extensive commentary book on &quot;Kojiki,&quot; he already pointed out in the section &apos;matters concerning Kana&apos; of the first volume, &quot;even for the same sound, it uses different phonetic characters depending on the words.&quot;</e>
<cmt>「浩瀚」→広大。書物の巻数が多いこと（yahoo辞書）「仮字」→仮名のこと。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;Kojiki-den&quot; (Commentary on the Kojiki), Norinaga&apos;s extensive commentary book on &quot;Kojiki,&quot; he already pointed out in the section &apos;matters concerning Kana&apos; of the first volume, that &apos;even for the same sound, it uses different phonetic characters depending on the words.&apos;</e>
<cmt>後半、ダブルクオーテーションを普通のクオーテーションに直しました。クオーテーションの前にthatを入れました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;Kojiki-den&quot; (Commentary on the Kojiki), Norinaga&apos;s extensive commentary book on &quot;Kojiki,&quot; he already pointed out in the section &apos;matters concerning Kana&apos; of the first volume, that &apos;even for the same sound, it uses different phonetic characters depending on the words.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>ただしその指摘はまだ一部に限られており、この宣長の着想をさらに発展させたのが彼の門弟・石塚龍麿による『仮名遣奥山路』（1798年頃発表）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it was only a limited comment, and this idea of Motoori was further developed by his disciple Tatsumaro ISHIZUKA who wrote &quot;Kanazukai Oku no Yamamichi&quot; (The Mountain Road into the Secrets of Kana Usage) (published around 1798).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it was only a limited comment, and this idea of Motoori was further developed by his disciple Tatsumaro ISHIZUKA who wrote &quot;Kanazukai Oku no Yamamichi&quot; (The Mountain Road into the Secrets of Kana Usage) (published around 1798).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it was only a limited comment, and this idea of Motoori was further developed by his disciple Tatsumaro ISHIZUKA who wrote &quot;Kanazukai Oku no Yamamichi&quot; (The Mountain Road into the Secrets of Kana Usage) (published around 1798).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>これは万葉仮名の使われた『古事記』・『日本書紀』・『万葉集』について、その用字を調査したものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This book investigated the usage of characters in &quot;Kojiki,&quot; &quot;Nihon Shoki&quot; and &quot;Manyoshu&quot; in which Manyo-gana was used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this book investigation was carried out on the usage of characters in &quot;Kojiki,&quot; &quot;Nihon Shoki&quot; and &quot;Manyoshu&quot; in which Manyo-gana was used.</e>
<cmt>「本が、～に対する調査をした」という形になっていましたので、「本の中で、～に対する調査が行われた」の形にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this book investigation was carried out on the usage of characters in &quot;Kojiki,&quot; &quot;Nihon Shoki&quot; and &quot;Manyoshu&quot; in which Manyo-gana was used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>この中で石塚は万葉仮名においてはエ・キ・ケ・コ・ソ・ト・ノ・ヒ・ヘ・ミ・メ・ヨ・ロ・チ・モの15種について用字に使い分けがあると結論づけた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ishizuka here concluded that there was a distinction in Manyo-gana, of the types of characters used for fifteen sounds, エ, キ, ケ, コ, ソ, ト, ノ, ヒ, ヘ, ミ, メ, ヨ, ロ, チ and モ (e, ki, ke, ko, so, to, no, hi, he, mi, me, yo, ro, chi, and mo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ishizuka, in this book, concluded that there was a distinction in Manyo-gana, of the types of characters used for fifteen sounds, エ, キ, ケ, コ, ソ, ト, ノ, ヒ, ヘ, ミ, メ, ヨ, ロ, チ and モ (e, ki, ke, ko, so, to, no, hi, he, mi, me, yo, ro, chi, and mo).</e>
<cmt>hereでは不明瞭なのでin this bookにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ishizuka, in this book, concluded that there was a distinction in Manyo-gana, of the types of characters used for fifteen sounds, エ, キ, ケ, コ, ソ, ト, ノ, ヒ, ヘ, ミ, メ, ヨ, ロ, チ and モ (e, ki, ke, ko, so, to, no, hi, he, mi, me, yo, ro, chi, and mo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>しかし、当時は本文の信憑性に関する批評が盛んでなく、調査に使われたテキストに誤記が含まれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the texts used for the investigation contained some errors because then there was not much criticism on the credibility of the materials.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the texts used for the investigation contained some errors because there was not much criticism on the credibility of the materials at that time.</e>
<cmt>thenでは不明瞭なのでat that timeにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the texts used for the investigation contained some errors because there was not much criticism on the credibility of the materials at that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>また、仮名 (文字)の使い分けが音韻の違いに結びつくという結論付けがなされていなかったこともあり、注目を集めることはなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It also did not reach any conclusion to connect the distinction of the types of phonetic characters with the difference of phonemes, and thus did not draw much attention.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore it did not reach any conclusion to connect the distinction of the types of phonetic characters with the difference of phonemes, and thus did not draw much attention.</e>
<cmt>「また」に相当するalsoは、文頭にして全体の文にかけたほうが良いと思われたので、Futhermoreに形を変えて文頭にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore it did not reach any conclusion to connect the distinction of the types of phonetic characters with the difference of phonemes, and thus did not draw much attention.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="28">
<j>8母音説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Theory of Eight Vowels</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Theory of Eight Vowels</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Theory of Eight Vowels</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>橋本進吉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinkichi HASHIMOTO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinkichi HASHIMOTO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinkichi HASHIMOTO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>宣長・石塚によるこの研究は長く評価されずに埋もれていたが橋本進吉によって再発見され、1917年、「帝国文学」に発表された論文「国語仮名遣研究史の一発見――石塚龍麿の仮名遣奥山路について――」で学会に評価されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the studies by Norinaga and Ishizuka had been unrecognized for long time, Shinkichi HASHIMOTO rediscovered them and published an article called &apos;A Discovery in the Field of Japanese Kana Usage Research Concerning Kanazukai Oku no Yamamichi by Tatsumaro Ishizuka&apos; for &apos;Teikoku Bungaku&apos; (Literature of the Empire) and it made the studies recognized by the academic community.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the studies by Norinaga and Ishizuka had not been evaluated for long time, Shinkichi HASHIMOTO rediscovered them and published an article called &apos;A Discovery in the Field of Japanese Kana Usage Research Concerning Kanazukai Oku no Yamamichi by Tatsumaro Ishizuka&apos; for &apos;Teikoku Bungaku&apos; (Literature of the Empire) and it made the studies recognized by the academic community.</e>
<cmt>｢評価されず｣→「unrecognized｣→「not evaluated」「for long time｣→「for a long time」「学会」→「academic community｣→「academic society」にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the studies by Norinaga and Ishizuka had not been evaluated for long time, Shinkichi HASHIMOTO rediscovered them and published an article called &apos;A Discovery in the Field of Japanese Kana Usage Research Concerning Kanazukai Oku no Yamamichi by Tatsumaro Ishizuka&apos; for &apos;Teikoku Bungaku&apos; (Literature of the Empire) and it made the studies recognized by the academic community.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>なお橋本以後の研究では石塚竜麿が指摘したチの使い分けを認めていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The studies after Hashimoto have not accepted the distinction of the types of characters used for &quot;チ&quot; (chi) as Tatsumaro ISHIZUKA pointed out.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The studies conducted after Hashimoto have not accepted the distinction of the types of characters used for &quot;チ&quot; (chi), the distinction which was pointed out by Tatsumaro ISHIZUKA</e>
<cmt>studiesの後にconductedを入れました。as以下が文章全体を指すものと解釈される可能性があったので、「, the distinction which」にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The studies conducted after Hashimoto have not accepted the distinction of the types of characters used for &quot;チ&quot; (chi), the distinction which was pointed out by Tatsumaro ISHIZUKA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>エ・キ・ケ・コ・ソ・ト・ノ・ヒ・ヘ・ミ・メ・ヨ・ロ・モの14種および濁音がある場合はその濁音を古代特有の使い分けと見なしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has been considered that in ancient times there was a special distinction of the types of characters used for 14 sounds of エ, キ, ケ, コ, ソ, ト, ノ, ヒ, ヘ, ミ, メ, ヨ, ロ and モ (e, ki, ke, ko, so, to, no, hi, he, mi, me, yo, ro and mo) and their dull sounds if any.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has been considered that in ancient times there was a special distinction of the types of characters used for 14 sounds of エ, キ, ケ, コ, ソ, ト, ノ, ヒ, ヘ, ミ, メ, ヨ, ロ and モ (e, ki, ke, ko, so, to, no, hi, he, mi, me, yo, ro and mo) and their dull sounds if any.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has been considered that in ancient times there was a special distinction of the types of characters used for 14 sounds of エ, キ, ケ, コ, ソ, ト, ノ, ヒ, ヘ, ミ, メ, ヨ, ロ and モ (e, ki, ke, ko, so, to, no, hi, he, mi, me, yo, ro and mo) and their dull sounds if any.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>この使い分けに橋本は「上代特殊仮名遣」と命名した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hashimoto named this distinction of the types of characters &quot;Jodai Tokushu Kanazukai.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hashimoto called this distinction of the types of characters &quot;Jodai Tokushu Kanazukai.&quot;</e>
<cmt>「named」を「called」にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hashimoto called this distinction of the types of characters &quot;Jodai Tokushu Kanazukai.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>なお、モの使い分けは古事記にのみ見られるものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for モ (mo), such distinction is only observed in Kojiki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for モ (mo), such distinction is only observed in Kojiki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for モ (mo), such distinction is only observed in Kojiki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>橋本は甲乙の音価の違いについて、甲音は現在のものと同じ音i, e, oとし、乙音をï, ë, öと推定した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for the difference of sounds between A-type and B-type, Hashimoto presumed that A-type characters had the sounds of i, e, and o, same as the current ones, while B-type had the sounds of ï, ë and ö.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for the difference of sounds between A-type and B-type, Hashimoto presumed that A-type characters had the sounds of i, e, and o, same as the current ones, while B-type had the sounds of ï, ë and ö.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for the difference of sounds between A-type and B-type, Hashimoto presumed that A-type characters had the sounds of i, e, and o, same as the current ones, while B-type had the sounds of ï, ë and ö.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="36">
<j>有坂秀世と「有坂の法則」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hideyo ARISAKA and &quot;Arisaka&apos;s Law&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hideyo ARISAKA and &apos;Arisaka&apos;s Law&apos;</e>
<cmt>ダブルクオーテーションをクオーテーションにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hideyo ARISAKA and &apos;Arisaka&apos;s Law&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>有坂秀世は1934年の論文「古代日本語における音節結合の法則」で、上代特殊仮名遣いに関する次のような法則を発表した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hideyo ARISAKA published in 1934 an article called &apos;The Laws for the Combination of Syllables in Ancient Japanese&apos;, in which he pointed out the following laws concerning Jodai Tokushu Kanazukai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hideyo ARISAKA published in 1934 an article called &apos;The Laws of the Combination of Syllables in Ancient Japanese&apos;, in which he pointed out the following laws concerning Jodai Tokushu Kanazukai.</e>
<cmt>クオーテーション中、Lawsの後のforをofにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hideyo ARISAKA published in 1934 an article called &apos;The Laws of the Combination of Syllables in Ancient Japanese&apos;, in which he pointed out the following laws concerning Jodai Tokushu Kanazukai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="38">
<j>オ列甲類音とオ列乙類音とは、同一結合単位内に共存することはない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A-type syllables with the vowel of オ (o) and B-type syllables with the vowel of オ (o) are not combined into one unit.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A-type syllables with the vowel of オ (o) and B-type syllables with the vowel of オ (o) are not combined into one unit.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A-type syllables with the vowel of オ (o) and B-type syllables with the vowel of オ (o) are not combined into one unit.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="39">
<j>ウ列音とオ列乙類音とは、同一結合単位内に共存することが少ない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Syllables with the vowel of ウ (u) and B-type syllables with the vowel of オ (o) are rarely combined into one unit.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Syllables with the vowel of ウ (u) and B-type syllables with the vowel of オ (o) are rarely combined into one unit.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Syllables with the vowel of ウ (u) and B-type syllables with the vowel of オ (o) are rarely combined into one unit.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>特に2音節の結合単位については例外がない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Particularly, when the unit consists of two syllables, they are never combined.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Particularly, when the unit consists of two syllables, they are never combined.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Particularly, when the unit consists of two syllables, they are never combined.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="41">
<j>ア列音とオ列乙類音とは、同一結合単位内に共存することが少ない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Syllables with the vowel of ア (a) and B-type syllables with the vowel of オ (o) are rarely combined into one unit.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Syllables with the vowel of ア (a) and B-type syllables with the vowel of オ (o) are rarely combined into one unit.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Syllables with the vowel of ア (a) and B-type syllables with the vowel of オ (o) are rarely combined into one unit.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="42">
<j>実際にこの法則が発表されたのは1932年の論文「古事記におけるモの仮名の用法について」であるが、彼がこれに強い確信を持って発表したのは前述の論文である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In fact these laws had already been mentioned in 1932 in his article &apos;Concerning the Usage of Kana for mo in Kojiki,&apos; but he pointed them out with firm conviction in the aforementioned article.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In fact these laws had already been mentioned in 1932 in his article &apos;Concerning the Usage of Kana for mo in Kojiki,&apos; but he pointed them out with firm conviction in the aforementioned article.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact these laws had already been mentioned in 1932 in his article &apos;Concerning the Usage of Kana for mo in Kojiki,&apos; but he pointed them out with firm conviction in the aforementioned article.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>これは有坂の法則と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was called Arisaka&apos;s Laws.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was called Arisaka&apos;s Laws.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was called Arisaka&apos;s Laws.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>母音同士が共存しやすいグループを作り、互いに同グループの母音と共存しやすく他グループの母音とは共存しにくいという傾向はトルコ語などに見られる「母音調和」現象の名残とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This tendency that vowels were divided into groups and often combined with other vowels in the same group and rarely with the ones in other groups was considered as a trace of vowel harmony observed in Turkish for example.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This tendency that vowels were divided into groups and often combined with other vowels of the same group and rarely with the ones of other groups was considered as a trace of &apos;vowel harmony&apos; observed in Turkish for example.</e>
<cmt>「同グループの母音」を意味するのに、inの代わりにofを用い「vowels of the same group」としました。vowel harmonyにクオーテーションをつけました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This tendency that vowels were divided into groups and often combined with other vowels of the same group and rarely with the ones of other groups was considered as a trace of &apos;vowel harmony&apos; observed in Turkish for example.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>また、有坂の法則は日本語がアルタイ語族であることの一つの証左であるとされたりした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Arisaka&apos;s Laws were also considered as evidence for Japanese being an Altaic language.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Arisaka&apos;s Laws were also considered as evidence for Japanese belonging to an Altaic language family.</e>
<cmt>「Japanese being an Altaic language」→「Japanese belonging to an Altaic language family」としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Arisaka&apos;s Laws were also considered as evidence for Japanese belonging to an Altaic language family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="46">
<j>橋本・有坂によるこれらの研究により上代特殊仮名遣は国語学における定説となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jodai Tokushu Kanazukai became an established theory in Japanese linguistics by these studies of Hashimoto and Arisaka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jodai Tokushu Kanazukai became an established theory in Japanese linguistics by these studies of Hashimoto and Arisaka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jodai Tokushu Kanazukai became an established theory in Japanese linguistics by these studies of Hashimoto and Arisaka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>いわゆる古史古伝の竹内文書などに使用されている神代文字も「上代には8母音あったはずなのに、なぜか5母音のままで上代の仮名遣いに配慮していない」ということから、そうした仮名遣いの区別がなくなった後世の偽書として否定した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They criticized Jindai-moji (written language claimed to have existed before the introduction of Chinese characters) used in so-called Koshi Koden (unofficial ancient documents) including Takeuchi-monjo (alleged record of the lineage of ancient gods and a dynasty preceding Emperor Jinmu) for &quot;having only five vowels and not adopting the ancient Kana usage of eight vowels&quot; and denied it as having been forged in a later era when such distinction of Kana usage had disappeared.</e>
<cmt>「古史古伝」→定訳不明。古事記以前の公式ではない書物を指し、一般に偽書とされているようです。&quot;unofficial ancient documents&quot;と説明を入れました。「竹内文書」「神代文字」→http://www2.kokugakuin.ac.jp/ijcc/wp/glossary/index2.html参考にしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They criticized Jindai-moji (written language claimed to have existed before the introduction of Chinese characters) used in the so-called Koshi Koden (unofficial ancient documents) including Takeuchi-monjo (alleged record of the lineage of ancient gods and a dynasty preceding Emperor Jinmu) for &apos;having only five vowels and not adopting the ancient Kana usage of eight vowels&apos; and denied it as having been forged in a later era when such distinction of Kana usage had disappeared.</e>
<cmt>so-calledの前にtheを補いました。ダブルクオーテーションをクオーテーションにしました。クオーテーション中、「上代には･･･あったはず」のニュアンスが反映されていないように思われます。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They criticized Jindai-moji (written language claimed to have existed before the introduction of Chinese characters) used in the so-called Koshi Koden (unofficial ancient documents) including Takeuchi-monjo (alleged record of the lineage of ancient gods and a dynasty preceding Emperor Jinmu) for &apos;having only five vowels and not adopting the ancient Kana usage of eight vowels&apos; and denied it as having been forged in a later era when such distinction of Kana usage had disappeared.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>これに関連し橋本は1942年、竹内文書第二次天津教弾圧事件裁判の際検察側の証人として出廷した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Concerning this dispute, in 1942, Hashimoto appeared as a witness for the prosecution in the trial of Takeuchi-monjo, the second oppression against Amatsukyo sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Concerning this dispute, in 1942, Hashimoto appeared as a witness for the prosecution in the trial of Takeuchi-monjo, the second oppression against Amatsukyo sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Concerning this dispute, in 1942, Hashimoto appeared as a witness for the prosecution in the trial of Takeuchi-monjo, the second oppression against Amatsukyo sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="49">
<j>8母音説への反論</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Criticism on the Theory of Eight Vowels</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Criticisms on the Theory of Eight Vowels</e>
<cmt>｢反論」は一つではないようですので、複数形にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Criticisms on the Theory of Eight Vowels</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>松本克己</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Katsumi MATSUMOTO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Katsumi MATSUMOTO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Katsumi MATSUMOTO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>古代日本語8母音説は広く受け入れられ半ば定説となっていたが、昭和50年代に入りこれに異を唱える学説が相次いで登場する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The theory that ancient Japanese had eight vowels had been widely accepted and became almost an established theory, however after 1975, different theories appeared.</e>
<cmt>「昭和50年代に入り」→after 1975（昭和50年）と訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The theory that ancient Japanese had eight vowels had been widely accepted and had become almost an established theory, however after 1975, several opposing theories appeared.</e>
<cmt>becameも、過去の過去に入るので、過去完了形にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The theory that ancient Japanese had eight vowels had been widely accepted and had become almost an established theory, however after 1975, several opposing theories appeared.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>その端緒が松本克己の「古代日本語母音組織考 －内的再建の試み－」である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first one was &apos;A Study on Ancient Japanese Vowel Structure - Attempt for Internal Reconstruction&apos; by Katsumi MATSUMOTO.</e>
<cmt>「古代日本語母音組織考 －内的再建の試み－」→定訳不明。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first one was &apos;A Study on Ancient Japanese Vowel Structure - Attempt for Internal Reconstruction&apos; by Katsumi MATSUMOTO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first one was &apos;A Study on Ancient Japanese Vowel Structure - Attempt for Internal Reconstruction&apos; by Katsumi MATSUMOTO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>内的再構とは、一つの言語の言語史を他言語との比較からのみ考えるのではなく、その言語内の共時態の研究を通じて求めていこうとするアプローチである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The internal reconstruction is an approach to the history of certain language through not only comparison with other languages but also a study on the synchrony of the language.</e>
<cmt>「共時態」→ある言語の特定時点における状態（yahoo辞書）&quot;synchrony&quot;</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The internal reconstruction is an approach to the history of certain language through not only comparison with other languages but also a study on the synchrony of the language.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The internal reconstruction is an approach to the history of certain language through not only comparison with other languages but also a study on the synchrony of the language.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="54">
<j>松本は有坂の音節結合の法則について、「同一結合単位」という概念の曖昧さを指摘した上で甲乙2種の使い分けがある母音だけではなく全ての母音について結合の法則性を追求すべきだとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Matsumoto criticized Arisaka&apos;s Laws for the combination of syllables that the idea of &quot;combined into one unit&quot; was ambiguous, and insisted that the laws for the combination should be investigated in relation to all vowels, not only the vowels that had the distinction of A-type and B-type.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Matsumoto criticized Arisaka&apos;s Laws for the combination of syllables that the idea of &apos;combined into one unit&apos; was ambiguous, and insisted that the laws for the combination should be investigated in relation to all vowels, not only the vowels that had the distinction between A-type and B-type.</e>
<cmt>ダブルクオーテーションをクオーテーションに直しました。Distinctionの後のofをbetweenにしました（この場合はofも可能かと思いましたが）。Criticizedに相当するニュアンスは原文には見当たりません。（｢曖昧さを指摘した」だけで、批判はしていないのではないかと思われます。）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Matsumoto criticized Arisaka&apos;s Laws for the combination of syllables that the idea of &apos;combined into one unit&apos; was ambiguous, and insisted that the laws for the combination should be investigated in relation to all vowels, not only the vowels that had the distinction between A-type and B-type.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>そして、1965年の福田良輔の研究をもとに母音を3グループに分けて検証を行なった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then he carried out the investigation, grouping the vowels into three types based on the study of Yoshisuke FUKUDA in 1965.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then he carried out the investigation, grouping the vowels into three types based on the study of Yoshisuke FUKUDA in 1965.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then he carried out the investigation, grouping the vowels into three types based on the study of Yoshisuke FUKUDA in 1965.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>その結果、従来甲乙2種の使い分けがあるとされてきた母音は相補的な分布を示すなどしており、母音の使い分けを行なっていたわけではなく音韻的には同一であったとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, he concluded that the vowels that were previously considered to have the distinction of A-type and B-type indicated complementary distribution and thus these vowels were not distinguished from each other as their phonemes were identical.</e>
<cmt>「相補的な分布」→相補分布。複数の音が互いに生じる環境が違う場合、それらを同一の音素に属するものとみなす（goo辞書）定訳は&quot;complementary distribution&quot;</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, he concluded that the vowels that were previously considered to have the distinction between A-type and B-type indicated complementary distribution and thus these vowels were not distinguished from each other but their phonemes were identical.</e>
<cmt>distinctionの後のofをbetweenにしました。最後のasをbutとしました。（｢音韻的に同一」は理由ではなく、彼がconcludeした要素の１つであると思われるので。）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, he concluded that the vowels that were previously considered to have the distinction between A-type and B-type indicated complementary distribution and thus these vowels were not distinguished from each other but their phonemes were identical.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>松本はギリシア語での/k/の表記を引き合いに出し、/k/についてkとqの二種類の文字が使われていたからと言ってそれがギリシア語で2種の子音が意図的に使い分けられていたという事実を示すわけではないことを挙げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Matsumoto took Greek letters for/k/ for example and explained that the existence of two types of letters, k and q, for/k/ did not indicate the fact that these two consonants were distinguished when used.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Matsumoto took Greek letters for/k/ for example and explained that the existence of two types of letters, k and q, for/k/ did not necessarily indicate the fact that these two consonants were distinguished when used.</e>
<cmt>後半「事実を示すわけではない」であって「事実を示さない」ではないので、necessarilyを挿入しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Matsumoto took Greek letters for/k/ for example and explained that the existence of two types of letters, k and q, for/k/ did not necessarily indicate the fact that these two consonants were distinguished when used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>同様に上代特殊仮名遣いについても使い分けがそのまま当時の母音体系を正確に表したものではないことを指摘した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Similarly, he pointed out that the distinction of usage in Jodai Tokushu Kanazukai did not precisely represent the vowel system of the time.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Similarly, he pointed out that the distinction of usage in Jodai Tokushu Kanazukai did not precisely represent the vowel system of the time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Similarly, he pointed out that the distinction of usage in Jodai Tokushu Kanazukai did not precisely represent the vowel system of the time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>その上で松本は日本語の母音の変遷について、下記のような変遷を辿ったとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, Matsumoto argued that Japanese vowels had developed as follows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, Matsumoto argued that Japanese vowels had developed as follows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, Matsumoto argued that Japanese vowels had developed as follows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="60">
<j>i, a, u の3母音</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Three vowels of i, a, u</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Three vowels of i, a, u</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Three vowels of i, a, u</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="61">
<j>i, a ～ o, u の4母音</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Four vowels of i, a, o, u</e>
<cmt>「～」はコンマ(,)の間違いだと思われます。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Four vowels of i, a, o, u</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Four vowels of i, a, o, u</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="62">
<j>i, e, Ï, a, o, u の6母音</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Six vowels of i, e, Ï, a, o, u</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Six vowels of i, e, Ï, a, o, u</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Six vowels of i, e, Ï, a, o, u</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="63">
<j>現在の5母音</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Current five vowels</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Current five vowels</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Current five vowels</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="64">
<j>そして、上代日本語の母音体系は現代と同じ5母音であったと結論づけた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He then concluded that ancient Japanese vowel system had five vowels as same as current system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He then concluded that ancient Japanese vowel system had five vowels same as the current system.</e>
<cmt>「as same as current system」を「same as the current system」としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He then concluded that ancient Japanese vowel system had five vowels same as the current system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="65">
<j>森重敏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Satoshi MORISHIGE</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Satoshi MORISHIGE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Satoshi MORISHIGE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>松本克己の論文の発表は1975年3月であるが、それと時を同じくして同年9月、森重敏は「上代特殊仮名遣とは何か」を発表し、松本とは別の観点から上代特殊仮名遣の8母音説に異議を唱えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The article by Katsumi MATSUMOTO was published in March 1975, and in September of the same year, Satoshi MORISHIGE almost coincidentally published &apos;What is Jodai Tokushu Kanazukai&apos; and criticized the theory of eight vowels of Jodai Tokushu Kanazukai from a different point of view from Matsumoto&apos;s.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The article by Katsumi MATSUMOTO was published in March 1975, and in September of the same year, Satoshi MORISHIGE almost coincidentally published &apos;What is Jodai Tokushu Kanazukai&apos; and criticized the theory of eight vowels of Jodai Tokushu Kanazukai from a different point of view from Matsumoto&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The article by Katsumi MATSUMOTO was published in March 1975, and in September of the same year, Satoshi MORISHIGE almost coincidentally published &apos;What is Jodai Tokushu Kanazukai&apos; and criticized the theory of eight vowels of Jodai Tokushu Kanazukai from a different point of view from Matsumoto&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>発表は9月であるがこれが執筆されたのは同年2月であり、「定説」であった8母音説に対する反論がほぼ同じ時期に執筆されたことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was published in September but written in February of the same year, and thus the criticisms on the &quot;established theory,&quot; the theory of eight vowels, were written almost in the same period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was published in September but written in February of the same year, and thus the criticisms on the &apos;established theory&apos;, the theory of eight vowels, were written almost in the same period.</e>
<cmt>ダブルクオーテーションをクオーテーションにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was published in September but written in February of the same year, and thus the criticisms on the &apos;established theory&apos;, the theory of eight vowels, were written almost in the same period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="68">
<j>まず森重は、体言において感嘆の際にいかなる助詞も付けないで単語がそのままで使われる時、助詞の代わりのような役目で単語の音韻そのものを「イ」音を加重させることがあると説いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Morishige firstly explained that when indeclinable words were used as exclamation without particles, the sound of &quot;イ&quot; (i) might be added to the words as a substitute for particles.</e>
<cmt>「体言」→主語になることができる単語（kotobank）&quot;indeclinable words&quot;</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Morishige firstly explained that when indeclinable words were used as exclamation without particles, the sound of &quot;イ&quot; (i) might be added to the words as a substitute for particles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Morishige firstly explained that when indeclinable words were used as exclamation without particles, the sound of &quot;イ&quot; (i) might be added to the words as a substitute for particles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>すなわち、「花」であればそれが「花よ」という形を取るのではなく「ハナィ」あるいは「ハィナ」「ハィナィ」と、母音そのものに「イ」を付け加えることによって表現することがあるというのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It meant that the exclamation of &quot;Hana&quot; (flower) might not be expressed as &quot;Hana-yo&quot; (with a particle) but &quot;Hanai,&quot; &quot;Haina&quot; or &quot;Hainai&quot; by adding &quot;イ&quot; (i) to the vowels.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It meant that the exclamation of &quot;Hana&quot; (flower) might not be expressed as &quot;Hana-yo&quot; (with a particle) but &quot;Hanai,&quot; &quot;Haina&quot; or &quot;Hainai&quot; by adding &quot;イ&quot; (i) to the vowels.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It meant that the exclamation of &quot;Hana&quot; (flower) might not be expressed as &quot;Hana-yo&quot; (with a particle) but &quot;Hanai,&quot; &quot;Haina&quot; or &quot;Hainai&quot; by adding &quot;イ&quot; (i) to the vowels.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>ここからア段音にイを加重させたものがエに、ウ段音にイを加重させたものがイに、オ段音にイを加重させたものがオになり、それぞれ乙類と呼ばれる音になったというのが森重説の要旨である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The summary of Morishige&apos;s theory was that B-type sounds with the vowels of エ (e), イ (i) and オ (o) were formed by adding イ (i) to the sounds with the vowels of ア (a), ウ (u) and オ (o) respectively.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The summary of Morishige&apos;s theory was that B-type sounds with the vowels of エ (e), イ (i) and オ (o) were formed by adding イ (i) to the sounds with the vowels of ア (a), ウ (u) and オ (o) respectively.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The summary of Morishige&apos;s theory was that B-type sounds with the vowels of エ (e), イ (i) and オ (o) were formed by adding イ (i) to the sounds with the vowels of ア (a), ウ (u) and オ (o) respectively.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="71">
<j>森重説でも最終的に日本語の母音体系は5母音であったとしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Morishige also concluded that Japanese vowel system had been consisted of five vowels.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Morishige also concluded that Japanese vowel system had been consisted of five vowels.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Morishige also concluded that Japanese vowel system had been consisted of five vowels.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>すなわち、万葉仮名に見られる用字の使い分けは渡来人が日本語にとって不必要であった音声の違いを音韻として読み取ってしまったものだとするものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to his theory, the distinction of characters observed in Manyo-gana was caused by Toraijin (people from overseas, especially from China and Korea, who settled in early Japan and introduced Continental culture) who had distinguished the difference of the sounds that were not distinguishable for Japanese.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to his theory, the distinction of characters observed in Manyo-gana was caused by Toraijin (people from overseas, especially from China and Korea, who settled in early Japan and introduced Continental culture) who had distinguished the difference of the sounds that were not unimportant for Japanese.</e>
<cmt>最後のdistinguishableは、原文が「(日本語にとって）不必要」であったので「unimportant」にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to his theory, the distinction of characters observed in Manyo-gana was caused by Toraijin (people from overseas, especially from China and Korea, who settled in early Japan and introduced Continental culture) who had distinguished the difference of the sounds that were not unimportant for Japanese.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>森重はそれをあたかもヘボン式ローマ字が日本語にとって必ずしも必要な聞き分けでないsh, ch, ts, fなどを聞き取ったことになぞらえた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Morishige explained it taking the Hepburn system of romanization for example, which distinguished the sounds not distinguishable for Japanese such as sh, ch, ts or f.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Morishige explained it taking the Hepburn system of romanization for example, which distinguished the sounds not necessarily important for Japanese such as sh, ch, ts or f.</e>
<cmt>前列に関連してnot distinguishableをnot importantとし、「必ずしも」を反映させるためnecessarilyを入れました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Morishige explained it taking the Hepburn system of romanization for example, which distinguished the sounds not necessarily important for Japanese such as sh, ch, ts or f.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>また、上代特殊仮名遣い中「コ」音のみが平安初期にまで残ったにもかかわらず、ひらがなにその使い分けが存在しなかったことなどを傍証として挙げている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also pointed out as evidence that although only the sound of &quot;コ&quot; (ko) among Jodai Tokushu Kanazukai had survived until the beginning of the Heian period, no such distinction had existed in Hiragana.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also pointed out as evidence that although only the sound of &quot;コ&quot; (ko) among Jodai Tokushu Kanazukai had survived until the beginning of the Heian period, no such distinction had existed in Hiragana.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also pointed out as evidence that although only the sound of &quot;コ&quot; (ko) among Jodai Tokushu Kanazukai had survived until the beginning of the Heian period, no such distinction had existed in Hiragana.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="75">
<j>新説を巡る論争</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Arguments over New Theories</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Arguments over New Theories</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Arguments over New Theories</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>この時期を同じくした新しい論に対しては多数の反論が展開され、1970年(?)12月から翌年1月にかけては毎日新聞紙上においてこの説を巡って4回にわたって議論が繰り広げられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were many criticisms on these new theories published in the same period, and from December 1970 (?) to November of the following year, the discussions about the theories were held four times in Mainichi Newspapers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many criticisms developed against these new theories published in the same period, and from December 1970 (?) to November of the following year, the discussions about the theories were held four times in Mainichi Newspapers.</e>
<cmt>「展開され」に対応する「developed」を挿入し、onをagainstとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many criticisms developed against these new theories published in the same period, and from December 1970 (?) to November of the following year, the discussions about the theories were held four times in Mainichi Newspapers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>中でも激しい論争が繰り広げられたのは『言語』誌上である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Particularly discussions held in a magazine &quot;Gengo&quot; (Language) were intense.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Particularly discussions held in a magazine &quot;Gengo&quot; (Language) were intense.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Particularly discussions held in a magazine &quot;Gengo&quot; (Language) were intense.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>1976年の6号の特集「母音調和を探る」には六母音説を主張する服部四郎の「上代日本語の母音体系と母音調和」と松本の「日本語の母音組織」が並んで掲載され、互いの説を批判し合うという体裁が採られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The June issue of 1976 featured &apos;investigation of vowel harmony,&apos; with Shiro HATTORI&apos;s article &apos;Old Japanese Vowel System and Harmony&apos; that advocated for the theory of six vowels and Matsumoto&apos;s &apos;Japanese Vowel Structure&apos; appearing next to and criticizing each other.</e>
<cmt>「6号」→次の文に「8月号」とありますので、こちらも「6月号」の間違いだと思われます。&quot;June issue&quot;と訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The June issue of 1976 featured &apos;investigation of vowel harmony,&apos; with Shiro HATTORI&apos;s article &apos;Ancient Japanese Vowel System and Harmony&apos; that advocated for the theory of six vowels and Matsumoto&apos;s &apos;Japanese Vowel Structure&apos; appearing next to and criticizing each other.</e>
<cmt>「上代」は他では「ancient」が用いられているので、Oldをancientにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The June issue of 1976 featured &apos;investigation of vowel harmony,&apos; with Shiro HATTORI&apos;s article &apos;Ancient Japanese Vowel System and Harmony&apos; that advocated for the theory of six vowels and Matsumoto&apos;s &apos;Japanese Vowel Structure&apos; appearing next to and criticizing each other.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>さらに8月号では大野晋が「上代日本語の母音体系」で両論を紹介し、持論を展開した他、11月号では松本が「万葉仮名のオ列甲乙について」で、12月には服部が「上代日本語の母音音素は六つであって八つではない」で互いに再反論した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, in the August issue Susumu ONO criticized both theories and presented his own view in &apos;Old Japanese Vowel System,&apos; and both Matsumoto and Hattori countered respectively in &apos;Concerning A-type and B-type Manyo-gana Characters with the Vowel of オ (o)&apos; in the November issue and &apos;Old Japanese Vowel Phonemes were Six, not Eight&apos; in the December issue.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further, in the August issue Susumu ONO introduced both theories and presented his own view in &apos;Old Japanese Vowel System,&apos; which was, in turn, countered by Matsumoto, in &apos;Concerning A-type and B-type Manyo-gana Characters with the Vowel of オ (o)&apos; in the November issue, and by Hattori, saying &apos;Old Japanese Vowel Phonemes were Six, not Eight&apos; in the December issue.</e>
<cmt>大野晋は「紹介した」のでcriticizedをintroducedにしました。再反論の内容を、それぞれの反論者とくっつけて（respectivelyを用いずに）表記しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further, in the August issue Susumu ONO introduced both theories and presented his own view in &apos;Old Japanese Vowel System,&apos; which was, in turn, countered by Matsumoto, in &apos;Concerning A-type and B-type Manyo-gana Characters with the Vowel of オ (o)&apos; in the November issue, and by Hattori, saying &apos;Old Japanese Vowel Phonemes were Six, not Eight&apos; in the December issue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="80">
<j>1981年には森博達が「唐代北方音と上代日本語の母音評価」でエ段以外の甲乙に差があることを認める7母音説を発表するとともに、唐代北方音と切韻を利用した具体的音価の推定を試みた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1981 Hiromichi MORI published an article &apos;The Northern Dialect of the Tang Dynasty and the Phonetic Value of the Vowels in Old Japanese&apos; in which he advocated for the theory of seven vowels, recognizing the distinction of the types in characters other than those with the vowel of エ (e), and tried to presume concrete sounds using the northern dialect of the Tang dynasty and phonetically arranged dictionary of ancient Chinese characters.</e>
<cmt>「切韻」→中国最古の韻書。定訳不明。&quot;phonetically arranged dictionary of ancient Chinese characters&quot;と訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1981 Hiromichi MORI, in his &apos;The Northern Dialect of the Tang Dynasty and the Phonetic Value of the Vowels in Old Japanese&apos;, published a theory of seven vowels, recognizing the distinction between the A- and B-types other than those with the vowel of エ (e), and tried to presume concrete sounds using the northern dialect of the Tang dynasty and phonetically arranged dictionary of ancient Chinese characters.</e>
<cmt>「advocate｣に対応する語は原文にないので、MORIを主語にして簡潔にしました。Types in charactersは、A-typeとB-ｔｙpeとしたほうが文脈に沿うのではないかと考え、そのようにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1981 Hiromichi MORI, in his &apos;The Northern Dialect of the Tang Dynasty and the Phonetic Value of the Vowels in Old Japanese&apos;, published a theory of seven vowels, recognizing the distinction between the A- and B-types other than those with the vowel of エ (e), and tried to presume concrete sounds using the northern dialect of the Tang dynasty and phonetically arranged dictionary of ancient Chinese characters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>これに対しては『国語学』誌上で平山久雄との間で「森博達氏の日本書紀α群原音依拠説について」「平山久雄氏に答え再び日本書紀α群原音依拠説を論証す」「森博達氏の日本書紀α群原音依拠説について、再論」という論争が行われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In response to it, Hisao HIRAYAMA had discussions with him in a magazine &quot;Kokugogaku&quot; (Studies in Japanese Linguistics) through a series of articles called &apos;Concerning Mr. Hiromichi Mori&apos;s Theory that Nihon Shoki α Group Was Written Based on Original Chinese Sounds,&apos; &apos;In Response to Mr. Hisao Hirayama, I Argue Again for the Theory that Nihon Shoki α Group Was Written Based on Original Chinese Sounds&apos; and &apos;Discussing Again Concerning Mr. Hiromichi Mori&apos;s Theory that Nihon Shoki α Group Was Written Based on Original Chinese Sounds.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「日本書紀α群原音依拠説」→日本書紀をα群とβ群に分け、α群が中国語原音に基づいて書かれたとする説。定訳不明。http://plaza.taishukan.co.jp/shop/Product/Detail/30036?p=0&amp;shelf=%E6%97%A5%E6%9C%AC%E5%8F%B2など参照。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In response to it, Hisao HIRAYAMA had discussions with him in a magazine &quot;Kokugogaku&quot; (Studies in Japanese Linguistics) through a series of articles called &apos;Concerning Mr. Hiromichi Mori&apos;s Theory that Nihon Shoki α Group Was Written Based on Original Chinese Sounds,&apos; &apos;In Response to Mr. Hisao Hirayama, I Argue Again for the Theory that Nihon Shoki α Group Was Written Based on Original Chinese Sounds&apos; and &apos;Discussing Again Concerning Mr. Hiromichi Mori&apos;s Theory that Nihon Shoki α Group Was Written Based on Original Chinese Sounds.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In response to it, Hisao HIRAYAMA had discussions with him in a magazine &quot;Kokugogaku&quot; (Studies in Japanese Linguistics) through a series of articles called &apos;Concerning Mr. Hiromichi Mori&apos;s Theory that Nihon Shoki α Group Was Written Based on Original Chinese Sounds,&apos; &apos;In Response to Mr. Hisao Hirayama, Further Argument for the Theory that Nihon Shoki α Group Was Written Based on Original Chinese Sounds&apos; and &apos;Discussing Again Concerning Mr. Hiromichi Mori&apos;s Theory that Nihon Shoki α Group Was Written Based on Original Chinese Sounds.&apos;</e>
<cmt>チェッカーコメントを受けて I Argue Again→Further Argumentとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="25">
<sen id="82">
<j>最近は従来の説を根本から覆すような論は発表されていないが、だからといって上代母音についての結論が出たわけではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Recently no theory has appeared to deny the basis of previous theories, but no conclusion has been reached yet concerning ancient Japanese vowels.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Recently no study has been published in which the previous theories were denied fundamentally, but it does not necessarily mean we have reached conclusion concerning ancient Japanese vowels.</e>
<cmt>実際には「論が説を覆す」のではなく、「論文を書いた人が説を覆す｣と思われるので、受身にしました。｢根本から」に対応する語を、fundamentallyにしました。「だからといって･･･わけではない」のニュアンスをだすために、butの後を「it does not necessarily mean」とし「結論に達する」をweを主語にした能動態にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Recently no study has been published in which the previous theories were denied fundamentally, but it does not necessarily mean we have reached conclusion concerning ancient Japanese vowels.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>上代にはいくつの母音が実際に存在したのか、その具体的な音価は何か、なぜイ段・エ段・オ段の一部のみに使い分けが見られるのかなどについて、今後も様々な分野からのアプローチが待たれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is to be solved in future, and approaches from various fields are expected concerning the matters like how many vowels in fact existed in ancient Japanese or why only a part of characters with the vowels of イ (i), エ (e) and オ (o) had the distinction of the types.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the future approaches from various fields are expected concerning the matters like how many vowels actually existed in ancient Japanese or why only a part of characters with the vowels of イ (i), エ (e) and オ (o) had the distinction of the types.</e>
<cmt>「in fact」を「actually」にしました。「It is to be solved」は原文にないので、削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the future approaches from various fields are expected concerning the matters like how many vowels actually existed in ancient Japanese or why only a part of characters with the vowels of イ (i), エ (e) and オ (o) had the distinction of the types.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Izayohi(id:13095), Sheynhertz-Unbayg(id:15456), 江口磐世☆(id:168037), Skalar nicol tiestar(id:23765), Tomaaru(id:127835), Aga(id:269393), Kahusi(id:1523), Charon(id:9162), Island(id:15610), Sketch(id:102), Anu(id:271616), Fryed-peach(id:63402), Jihi(id:261170), ぎゅうひ(id:9206), Bendono(id:85524), Bit(id:2197), Point136(id:211299), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>