<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>粉河寺縁起絵巻</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kokawadera Engiemaki (a picture scroll of legends of Kokawadera Temple)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokawadera Engiemaki (a picture scroll of the legends of Kokawadera Temple)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kokawadera Engiemaki (a picture scroll of the legends of Kokawadera Temple)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>粉河寺縁起絵巻（こかわでら えんぎ えまき）は、日本の代表的な絵巻物の一つであり、国宝に指定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kokawadera Engiemaki (a picture scroll of legends of Kokawadera Temple), one of representative picture scrolls in Japan, is designated as a national treasure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokawadera Engiemaki (a picture scroll of the legends of Kokawadera Temple), one of representative picture scrolls in Japan, is designated as a national treasure.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kokawadera Engiemaki (a picture scroll of the legends of Kokawadera Temple), one of representative picture scrolls in Japan, is designated as a national treasure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>所有者は和歌山県・粉河寺。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kokawadera Engiemaki is owned by Kokawa-dera Temple, Wakayama Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokawadera Engiemaki is owned by Kokawa-dera Temple, Wakayama Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kokawadera Engiemaki is owned by Kokawa-dera Temple, Wakayama Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>京都国立博物館に寄託されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is deposited in Kyoto National Museum.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is on display at the Kyoto National Museum.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is on display at the Kyoto National Museum.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>紙本著色、1巻、縦30.8cm、横1984.2cm。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shihon-Chakushoku (paper-based colored picture), one roll, 30.8cm long, 1984.2 cm wide.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shihon-Chakushoku (paper-based colored picture), one roll, 30.8cm long, 1984.2 cm wide.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shihon-Chakushoku (paper-based colored picture), one roll, 30.8cm long, 1984.2 cm wide.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>成立は、平安時代の後半、12世紀頃とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is assumed that it was completed around the twelfth century, in the latter half of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is assumed to have been completed around the twelfth century, during the latter half of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is assumed to have been completed around the twelfth century, during the latter half of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>天正年間に兵火に遭って罹災し、巻首部分と、全巻にわたる上下に甚だしい焼損が見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Tensho era during; 1573-1592, it caught a fire from the war; great damages are seen at the beginning of and at the top and bottom of the scroll.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Tensho era during; 1573-1592, it caught fire from the war; it was badly damaged at the beginning of and at the top and bottom of parts of the scroll.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Tensho era (1573-1592), it caught fire from the war; it was badly damaged at the beginning of and at the top and bottom of parts of the scroll.</e>
<cmt>年号表記</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>舞台は、奈良時代最末期の宝亀年間（770年 - 780年）、紀伊国那賀郡 (和歌山県)に住していた山人の大伴孔子古（くじこ）なる人物を主人公とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The story is set during the very end of Nara period, Hoki period (770-780,) the central character of the story is OTOMO no Kujiko, a mountain man, who lived in Naga District, Ki Province (Wakayama prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The story is set during the very end of Nara period, Hoki period (770-780,) the central character of the story is OTOMO no Kujiko, a mountain man, who lived in Naga District, Ki Province (Wakayama prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The story is set during the very end of the Nara period, Hoki period (770-780,) and the central character of the story is OTOMO no Kujiko, a mountain man, who lived in Naga District, Ki Province (Wakayama prefecture).</e>
<cmt>冠詞</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>孔子古は、ある時、山中に奇瑞の地を発見し、そこに精舎を建立し、仏像を安置したいと発願する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One time, Kujiko found an auspicious place in the mountains, and desired to build Shoja (a hall where priests practice asceticism, like a temple) to install a Buddhist stature in.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One time, Kujiko found an auspicious place in the mountains, and wanted to build a Shoja (a hall where priests practice asceticism, like a temple) to install a Buddhist stature in.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One time, Kujiko found an auspicious place in the mountains, and wanted to build a Shoja (a hall where priests practice asceticism, like a temple) to install a Buddhist stature in.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>そうすると、一人の遊行の行者が現われ、仏師であると名乗り、仏像の建立を申し出る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, a wandering pilgrim appeared, and he offered to build a Buddhist statue referring to himself as busshi (sculptor of Buddhist Statues).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, a wandering pilgrim appeared, and he offered to build a Buddhist statue referring to himself as busshi (sculptor of Buddhist Statues).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, a wandering pilgrim appeared, and he offered to build a Buddhist statue referring to himself as busshi (sculptor of Buddhist Statues).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>行者は山中の庵に入って扉に鍵をかけ、7日経てば、見に来るように、と告げる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The pilgrim entered into the hermitage in mountains, locked the door, and then the pilgrim told him to come back to see him after seven days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The pilgrim entered into the hermitage in mountains, locked the door, and then the pilgrim told him to come back to see him after seven days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The pilgrim entered into the hermitage in mountains, locked the door, and then the pilgrim told him to come back to see him after seven days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>孔子古が8日目に扉を開けると、庵内には千手観音立像が安置されており、行者の姿は見えなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Kujiko opened the door on the eighth day, Senju Kannon ryuzo (standing statue of Thousand Armed Avalokiteshwara) was installed in the hermitage, and found that the pilgrim was gone.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Kujiko opened the door on the eighth day, Senju Kannon ryuzo (standing statue of Thousand Armed Avalokiteshwara) was installed in the hermitage, and he found that the pilgrim was gone.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Kujiko opened the door on the eighth day, Senju Kannon ryuzo (standing statue of Thousand Armed Avalokiteshwara) was installed in the hermitage, and he found that the pilgrim was gone.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>その後、河内国渋河郡馬馳市に住していた佐太夫という長者の二人の娘が重篤な病いに倒れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, two daughters of a wealthy man named Satayu who lived in Mabase City, Shibukawa District, Kawachi Province had a serious illness.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, two daughters of a wealthy man named Satayu who lived in Mabase City, Shibukawa District, Kawachi Province came down with a serious illness.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, two daughters of a wealthy man named Satayu who lived in Mabase City, Shibukawa District, Kawachi Province came down with a serious illness.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>医師に診せても、手の施しようがない、と見放される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Doctors gave up them saying that they wouldn&apos;t be cured.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Doctors gave up on them saying that they couldn&apos;t be cured.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Doctors gave up on them saying that they couldn&apos;t be cured.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>そこへ、行者が現われ、千手観音の陀羅尼によって加持祈祷を行なう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, a pilgrim appeared, and performed incantation and prayer making Darani of Senju Kannon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, a pilgrim appeared, and performed incantation and a prayer making Darani of Senju Kannon.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, a pilgrim appeared, and performed incantation and a prayer making Darani of Senju Kannon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>そうすると、俄かに二人の娘の病いは快癒する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That fixed up two daughters immediately.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That two daughters got over their illness immediately.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That two daughters got over their illness immediately.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>佐太夫は、たいそう喜び、お礼として帯鞘の山刀を行者に布施する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Satayu was overjoyed, and offered the pilgrim an obisaya (obi scabbard) woodman&apos;s hatchet as a gift.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Satayu was overjoyed, and offered the pilgrim an obisaya (obi scabbard) woodman&apos;s hatchet as a gift.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Satayu was overjoyed, and offered the pilgrim an obisaya (obi scabbard) woodman&apos;s hatchet as a gift.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>去ろうとする行者に、佐太夫が在所を尋ねると、紀伊国那賀郡風市村にある粉河寺である、という返答がかえってくる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Satayu asked the leaving pilgrim about the place where he lived, the pilgrim replied that he lived in Kokawa-dera Temple in Kazeichi Village, Naga District, Ki Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Satayu asked the pilgrim where he lived, the pilgrim replied that he lived in Kokawa-dera Temple in Kazeichi Village, Naga District, Ki Province.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Satayu asked the pilgrim where he lived, and the pilgrim replied that he lived in Kokawa-dera Temple in Kazeichi Village, Naga District, Ki Province.</e>
<cmt>and を追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="18">
<j>そこで、佐太夫が一族あげて風市村へ赴くと、草庵の中に金色の千手観音像が立っており、その施無畏印を結んだ手に、佐太夫が喜捨した刀がかかっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Satayu led the entire family and went to Kazeichi Village, then they saw a golden Senju Kannon ryuzo stood with the hatchet Sadayu offered in its hands posing of Semui-in (mudra for bestowing fearlessness) in a thatched hut.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Satayu led the entire family to Kazeichi Village, and they saw a golden Senju Kannon ryuzo standing with the hatchet that Sadayu offered, in its hands posing as Semui-in (mudra for bestowing fearlessness) in a thatched hut.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Satayu led the entire family to Kazeichi Village, and they saw a golden Senju Kannon ryuzo standing with the hatchet that Sadayu offered, in its hands posing as Semui-in (mudra for bestowing fearlessness) in a thatched hut.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 663highland(id:18755), ととりん(id:31982), Mooko(id:36162), Urania(id:7213), Charenji(id:7908), D.h(id:79056), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>