<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>石焼き芋</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ishiyaki imo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ishiyaki imo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ishiyaki Imo</e>
<cmt>タイトルなので大文字にしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>石焼き芋（いしやきいも）は、サツマイモを使った料理のひとつである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ishiyaki imo (stone-roasted sweet potato) is one of dishes that use sweet potatoes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ishiyaki imo (stone-roasted sweet potato) is a dish using sweet potatoes.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ishiyaki imo (stone-roasted sweet potato) is a dish using sweet potatoes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>サツマイモを熱した小石の中に埋めて、間接加熱によって焼いたもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fill up sweet potatoes with heated pebbles and cook them by indirect heating.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Place the sweet potatoes onto heated pebbles and cook them by indirect heating.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Place the sweet potatoes onto heated pebbles and cook them by indirect heating.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>間接的にゆっくり加熱することで、アミラーゼ（デンプン分解酵素）が、デンプンをグルコースに変える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By heating them slowly and indirectly, amylase (amylolytic enzyme) changes starch into glucose.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By heating them slowly and indirectly, amylase (amylolytic enzyme) changes starch into glucose.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By heating them slowly and indirectly, amylase (amylolytic enzyme) changes starch into glucose.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>そのため、通常の焼き方よりも甘く仕上がる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, it turns sweeter than the one cooked normally.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore they turn sweeter than ones cooked normally.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore they turn sweeter than ones cooked normally.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>甘みの強さから女性や子供に人気がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since it has strong sweetness, it is popular among women and children.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since they are sweet they are popular among women and children.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since they are sweet, they are popular among women and children.</e>
<cmt>コンマ補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>ただし芋は屁が出やすい・太りやすいなどといわれるため、女性が買うのをためらうことも多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it is said that potatoes make you fart or fat, so women often hesitate to buy it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is said that potatoes make you pass wind or make you fat, so women often hesitate before buying it.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is said that potatoes make you pass wind or make you fat, so women often hesitate before buying it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>屋台や軽トラックに専用の釜を積み売り歩く姿は、日本の冬の風物詩のひとつである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The hawking image with a special kettle on a stall and a lightweight truck is one of winter traditions in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The image of a special kettle on a stall and a lightweight truck is one of the winter traditions in Japan.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The image of a special kettle on a stall and a lightweight truck is one of the winter traditions in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>売り歩く際は、「いーしやぁーきいもー、おいもー」といった独特の節回しで呼びかけるのが定番である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When hawking it, it is typical to call &apos;Ishiyaki imo, oimo&apos; with unique melody.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When hawking it, it is typical to sing &apos;Ishiyaki imo, oimo&apos; to a tune with a unique melody.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When hawking it, it is typical to sing &apos;Ishiyaki imo, oimo&apos; to a tune with a unique melody.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>寒冷地では芋焼き釜の排気圧で「ポー」という音が鳴る機器を代わりに用いる場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The machine that makes &apos;po&apos; sound of exhaust pressure of stone roast kettle is sometimes used in cold climates.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A machine that makes a &apos;po&apos; sound from the steam coming out of a stone roast kettle is sometimes used instead in cold climates.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A machine that makes a &apos;po&apos; sound from the steam coming out of a stone roast kettle is sometimes used instead in cold climates.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>最近では家庭用の「石焼き芋器」も市販されており、家庭でも手軽に石焼き芋が楽しめるようになってきている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Recently, &apos;ishiyaki imo equipment&apos; for household use is on the market, so everyone can easily enjoy ishiyaki imo at home.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Recently, &apos;ishiyaki imo equipment&apos; for household use is on the market, so everyone can easily enjoy ishiyaki imo at home.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Recently, &apos;ishiyaki imo equipment&apos; for household use is on the market, so everyone can easily enjoy ishiyaki imo at home.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>屋台が減少した今はスーパー軒先での路上販売やコンビニなどで売られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Currently with decreasing number of stalls, it is sold on the street under eaves of supermarkets and at convenience stores.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Currently, with a decreasing number of travelling stalls it is also sold on the street at the entrance to supermarkets and at convenience stores.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Currently, with a decreasing number of travelling stalls it is also sold on the street at the entrance to supermarkets and at convenience stores.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>石焼きに適した品種としては「紅あずま」、「鳴門金時」や「ベニオトメ」があげられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The varieties of sweet potatoes suitable for ishiyaki (baking in hot pebbles) are &apos;beni-azuma,&apos; &apos;naruto-kintoki,&apos; and &apos;beni-otome.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The varieties of sweet potato suitable for ishiyaki (baking in hot pebbles) are &apos;beni-azuma,&apos; &apos;naruto-kintoki,&apos; and &apos;beni-otome.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The varieties of sweet potato suitable for ishiyaki (baking in hot pebbles) are &apos;beni-azuma,&apos; &apos;naruto-kintoki,&apos; and &apos;beni-otome.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="14">
<j>焼き芋</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yaki imo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yaki imo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yaki imo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>石焼き釜を使わず焼いたものは、単に焼き芋と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is simply called yaki imo (baked sweet potato) cooked without a ishiyaki kettle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cooking sweet potato without an ishiyaki kettle is simply called yaki imo (baked sweet potato).</e>
<cmt>Word order.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cooking sweet potato without an ishiyaki kettle is simply called yaki imo (baked sweet potato).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="16">
<j>昭和やそれ以前の時代において、冬の時期に道路や庭に積った葉落葉を集め、焚き火として燃やす際に、一緒にサツマイモを入れて焼く光景は、冬を物語るものとして扱われ、冬を表す季語ともなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Showa period or before that, the scenes to collect falling leaves on the road or the garden during winter season and to put sweet potatoes inside the leaves when burning them as bonfires are treated as the scenes to speak for winter, and ishiyaki imo is the season word to describe winter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Showa Period or before, pictures of people collecting falling leaves on the road or the garden during the winter season, and of putting sweet potatoes inside the leaves when burning them on the bonfire, were considered scenes which speak for winter, and ishiyaki imo is a season word to describe winter.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Showa period or before, pictures of people collecting falling leaves on the road or the garden during the winter season, and of putting sweet potatoes inside the leaves when burning them on the bonfire, were considered scenes which speak for winter, and ishiyaki imo is a season word to describe winter.</e>
<cmt>period 小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>その際、焦がさないようにアルミホイルに包んで焼く事もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On this occasion, the sweet potatoes should be wrapped with aluminum foil to avoid scorching them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cooking in this way, the sweet potatoes should be wrapped in aluminum foil to avoid scorching them.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cooking in this way, the sweet potatoes should be wrapped in aluminum foil to avoid scorching them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="18">
<j>こちらは石焼き釜とは違い裸火を使うことから火加減が難しいなどの問題もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since it uses naked flame, different from ishiyaki kettle, it is difficult to control the flame.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since a naked flame is used, different from an ishiyaki kettle, it is difficult to control the flame.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since a naked flame is used, different from an ishiyaki kettle, it is difficult to control the flame.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>しかし、上手に焼ければ甘くホコホコした風味を味わえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But you can enjoy sweet and steaming flavor when it is baked well.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But you can enjoy a sweet fragrance from the steam when it is baked well.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But you can enjoy a sweet fragrance from the steam when it is baked well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="20">
<j>ただ、日本では2002年12月に施行された改正廃棄物の処理及び清掃に関する法律にもより家庭から排出されるごみ類を野焼きすることに制限が加えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, due to Revised Waste Disposal and Public Cleaning Law that was enforced in December 2002, the limitation was added not to burn off trash from households in a field.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, due to the Revised Waste Disposal and Public Cleaning Law that came into force in December 2002, the regulation came into effect not to burn household trash in fields.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, due to the Revised Waste Disposal and Public Cleaning Law that came into force in December 2002, the regulation came into effect not to burn household trash in fields.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>そのため、落ち葉であっても住宅地で燃やして処分しにくくなったこと、庭付きの持ち家率低下、都市開発による森林の伐採などの事情もあり、21世紀に於いて一般ではごく一部でしか見られない風景となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, by the situations where it became difficult to dispose even falling leaves by burning them in residential district, the rate of having a house with a garden declined, and the forests were cut down due to the urban development, the scene can be seen only in a small part of areas in twenty first century.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, as it became more difficult to dispose of even falling leaves by burning them within a residential district, and as the rate of having a house with a garden declined, and the forests were cut down due to urban development, the sight can be seen only in a few areas in the twenty first century.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, as it became more difficult to dispose of even falling leaves by burning them within a residential district, and as the rate of having a house with a garden declined, and the forests were cut down due to urban development, the sight can be seen only in a few areas in the 21st century.</e>
<cmt>数字に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>多くの地方自治体では落ち葉やせん定した枝葉は燃やせるゴミとして排出するか、堆肥化して処分するよう指導している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many local governments instruct to evacuate falling leaves and pruned branches and leaves as burnable garbage or to dispose after composting.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many local governments instruct people to remove fallen leaves and branches and use them as burnable garbage or to dispose with in composting.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many local governments instruct people to remove fallen leaves and branches and use them as burnable garbage or to dispose with in composting.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>詳細は地元自治体の清掃局などに問い合わせして欲しい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For more details, you should contact cleansing department of the local governments.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For more details, you should contact the cleansing department of your local government.</e>
<cmt>This line is only appropriate for those living in Japan.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For more details, you should contact the cleansing department of your local government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="24">
<j>なお、サツマイモ自体は栽培が簡単で収穫量が見込めることから、焼き芋を含むサツマイモを使った芋料理は通年食べられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, since sweet potatoes are easy to cultivate and yield amount can be expected, potato dishes that use sweet potatoes including ishiyaki imo are eaten all year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, since sweet potatoes are easy to cultivate and the yield amount can be predicted, potato dishes that use sweet potatoes including ishiyaki imo are eaten all year.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, since sweet potatoes are easy to cultivate and the yield amount can be predicted, potato dishes that use sweet potatoes including ishiyaki imo are eaten all year.</e>
<cmt>不要なスペース削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>焼く他に蒸すたり煮るといった加熱調理が行われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other than baking, it is also cooked by steaming and boiling.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to baking, it can also be cooked by steaming or boiling.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to baking, it can also be cooked by steaming or boiling.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 田英(id:85936), 陳炬燵(id:253965), 竃馬(id:102733), DIO(id:21528), Nighthawks(id:36125), 日本一弱い男(id:92046), U-kondo(id:150542), Revth(id:12179), 曼珠沙華(id:26417), Yas(id:739), MEDITATE(id:168298), Corwin(id:973), Calvero(id:38360), Yatobi(id:9686), HayaKuwa(id:177119), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>