<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>輪入道</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wanyudo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wanyudo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wanyudo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>輪入道（わにゅうどう）は、鳥山石燕の妖怪画集『今昔画図続百鬼』にある日本の妖怪。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wanyudo is a Japanese specter described in Konjaku Gazu Zoku Hyakki (Continued Illustrations of the Many Demons Past and Present), a collection of illustrations of specters by Sekien TORIYAMA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wanyudo is a Japanese specter described in Konjaku Gazu Zoku Hyakki (Continued Illustrations of the Many Demons Past and Present), a collection of illustrations of specters by Sekien TORIYAMA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wanyudo is a Japanese specter described in Konjaku Gazu Zoku Hyakki (Continued Illustrations of the Many Demons Past and Present), a collection of illustrations of specters by Sekien TORIYAMA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>炎に包まれた牛車の車輪の中央に男の顔が付いた姿をしており、その姿を見た者の魂を抜いていくとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has the appearance of a wheel of an ox-drawn carriage, with a man&apos;s face positioned in the center, and is said to take out the soul of the person who looks at it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has the appearance of a wheel of an ox-drawn carriage, with a man&apos;s face positioned in the center, and is said to take out the soul of the person who looks at it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has the appearance of a wheel of an ox-drawn carriage, with a man&apos;s face positioned in the center, and is said to take out the soul of the person who looks at it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>「此所勝母の里」と書いた紙を呪符として家の戸に貼ると、輪入道が近づくことができないといい、これは中国の儒家の始祖・孔子の門人である曾子が「母に勝つ」の名を嫌って勝母の里に足を踏み入れなかったという『史記』「鄒陽列伝」での逸話が由来とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that when one places a piece of paper indicating &quot;Koko-wa Shobo-no Sato&quot; on the door as a talisman, Wanyudo cannot go near the house; this derives from the anecdote in Shuyo Retsuden (a series of biographies of Shuyo) of Shiki (the Chinese Historical Records), according to which So-shi, a disciple of Koshi, the founder of Confucianist in China, disliked Shobo-no Sato and did not set his foot in the place because of the name suggesting &quot;to win against mother&quot;.</e>
<cmt>【儒家】は【儒教】の誤りだと思いますが、Webでも【儒家】となっていたので（リンク先は【儒教】でしたが）そのままにしました。【儒教】の場合は【Confucianism】になります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that when one places a piece of paper indicating &quot;Koko-wa Shobo-no Sato&quot; on the door as a talisman, Wanyudo cannot go near the house; this derives from the anecdote in Shuyo Retsuden (a series of biographies of Shuyo) of Shiki (the Chinese Historical Records), according to which So-shi, a disciple of Koshi, the founder of Confucianist in China, disliked Shobo-no Sato and did not set his foot in the place because of the name suggesting &quot;to win against mother&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that when one places a piece of paper indicating &quot;Koko-wa Shobo-no Sato&quot; on the door as a talisman, Wanyudo cannot go near the house; this derives from the anecdote in Shuyo Retsuden (a series of biographies of Shuyo) of Shiki (the Chinese Historical Records), according to which So-shi, a disciple of Koshi, the founder of Confucianist in China, disliked Shobo-no Sato and did not set his foot in the place because of the name suggesting &quot;to win against mother&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>石燕の輪入道は、延宝5年刊行の怪談集『諸国百物語』巻一「京東洞院かたわ車の事」で、京都の東洞院通に現れたという車輪の妖怪「かたわ車」のことを描いたものとされており、『今昔画図続百鬼』で別々の妖怪として描かれている片輪車と輪入道を同一のものとする解釈もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wanyudo by Sekien is said to be the specter called &quot;Katawa-Guruma&quot; which looks like a wheel and is said to have appeared in Higashinotoin-dori Street in Kyoto, according to &quot;Regarding Katawa-Guruma in Higashi-no-toin, Kyoto&quot;, Vol. 1 of &quot;A hundred stories from the provinces&quot; which is a collection of ghost stories published in 1677; according to the interpretation by some, Wanyudo and Katawa-Guruma are the same although the two specters are described as different specters in Konjaku Gazu Zoku Hyakki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wanyudo by Sekien is said to be the specter called &quot;Katawa-Guruma&quot; which looks like a wheel and is said to have appeared in Higashinotoin-dori Street in Kyoto, according to &quot;Regarding Katawa-Guruma in Higashi-no-toin, Kyoto&quot;, Vol. 1 of &quot;A hundred stories from the provinces&quot; which is a collection of ghost stories published in 1677; according to the interpretation by some, Wanyudo and Katawa-Guruma are the same although the two specters are described as different specters in Konjaku Gazu Zoku Hyakki.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wanyudo by Sekien is said to be a specter called &quot;Katawa-Guruma&quot;, which looks like a wheel and is said to have appeared in Kyoto&apos;s Higashinotoin-dori Street according to &quot;Regarding Katawa-Guruma in Higashi-no-toin, Kyoto&quot; (from Vol. 1 of &quot;A hundred stories from the provinces&quot;, which is a collection of ghost stories published in 1677); therefore, one possible interpretation is that Wanyudo and Katawa-Gurumaare, which were depicted as different specters in &quot;Konjaku Gazu Zoku Hyakki&quot;, are actually one and the same.</e>
<cmt>Konjaku Gazu Zoku Hyakkiをダブルクォーテーションで囲みました。；以降を書き換えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>『今昔画図続百鬼』の輪入道は男性、片輪車は女性として描かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Althoug Wanyudo is described as a male and Katawa-Guruma as a female in Konjaku Gazu Zoku Hyakki, Katawa-Guruma came to be depicted as a female since the publication of a book with mixed topics titled &quot;Shokoku satobitodan&quot; (Talks on people of all countries) in 1743; as such, one theory has it that 1677, the year of publication of &quot;A hundred stories from the provinces&quot; being the starting point, Katawa-Guruma, which was the same as Wanyudo, diverged into two specters, Katawa-Guruma and Wanyudo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Althoug Wanyudo is described as a male and Katawa-Guruma as a female in Konjaku Gazu Zoku Hyakki, Katawa-Guruma came to be depicted as a female since the publication of a book with mixed topics titled &quot;Shokoku satobitodan&quot; (Talks on people of all countries) in 1743; as such, one theory has it that 1677, the year of publication of &quot;A hundred stories from the provinces&quot; being the starting point, Katawa-Guruma, which was the same as Wanyudo, diverged into two specters, Katawa-Guruma and Wanyudo.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wanyudo is depicted as a male and Katawa-Guruma as a female in &quot;Konjaku Gazu Zoku Hyakki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Konjaku Gazu Zoku Hyakkiをダブルクォーテーションで囲みました。一原文一訳文の例外処理1743年から片輪車は女性として描かれているのに、1677年 から分岐した、とあります。原文どおりに訳しています。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>寛保3年の雑書『諸国里人談』の刊行から片輪車が女性として描かれ始めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Katawa-Guruma was depicted as a female following the publication of a book covering a wide range of topics entitled &quot;Shokoku Rijin Dan&quot; (literally, &quot;tales of villagers from various provinces) in 1743.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>『諸国百物語』の刊行年である延宝5年を起点として、同一のものである片輪車が、片輪車と輪入道という2つの妖怪に分岐したとの説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a theory that in 1677, the year in which &quot;A hundred stories from the provinces&quot; was published, Katawa-Guruma was separated into the two different specters of Kagawa-Guruma and Wanyudo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Meteo Light(id:41515), Watatti(id:98053), Nnh(id:474), Gottokutyo(id:34549), 88(id:28711), 猫道楽(id:49600), 逃亡者(id:14864), Scaxksky(id:266784), Yas(id:739), Uraios(id:72687), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>