<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>煮しめ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nishime (煮しめ)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nishime (煮しめ)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nishime (the traditional Japanese simmered dish)</e>
<cmt>漢字を削除しました。補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>煮しめ（にしめ）とは、煮る調理法のひとつを用いて調理された料理。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Nishime&quot; is a dish cooked by one of simmering cooking techniques.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Nishime&quot; is a dish in which a simmering cooking technique is used.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nishime (煮しめ) is a dish in which a simmering cooking technique is used.</e>
<cmt>ダブルクォーテーションを削除しました。後に漢字表記に言及していますので、ここでも漢字を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>日本の代表的な家庭料理の一つでもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is one of typical Japanese home cooked dishes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a typical Japanese home cooked dish.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a typical Japanese home cooked dish.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>根菜類や芋類、こんにゃく、コンブ、油揚げなどを甘辛く煮たものをこう呼ぶことが多いが、煮しめにされる具材はその地方や季節でさまざまであり、肉類、ちくわやかまぼこなどの水産練り製品（いわゆる練り物）、地域によっては魚も用いられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dishes of root crops, potatoes, konjac, konbu kelp, abura-age (deep-fried bean curd), etc. simmered to taste sweet-salty are often called nishime. Ingredients of nishime, however, differ by regions or seasons in which nishime is cooked, and meats or fish sausages (so-called &quot;nerimono&quot;) such as chikuwa and kamaboko or in some regions, fish, are also included in the ingredients.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dishes containing root crops, potatoes, konjac, konbu kelp, abura-age (deep-fried bean curd) among other ingredients, and simmered to taste salty-sweet are often called nishime; the ingredients of nishime, however, differ by region and the season in which nishime is cooked, and meats or fish sausages (so-called &quot;nerimono&quot;) such as chikuwa and kamaboko or in some regions, fish, also appear as ingredients.</e>
<cmt>Grammar. Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dishes containing root crops, potatoes, konjac, konbu kelp, abura-age (deep-fried bean curd) among other ingredients, and simmered to taste salty-sweet are often called nishime; the ingredients of nishime, however, differ by region and the season in which nishime is cooked, and meats or fish sausages (so-called &quot;nerimono&quot;) such as chikuwa and kamaboko or in some regions, fish, also appear as ingredients.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>味付けもさまざまである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seasoning also differs from region to region.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seasoning also differs from region to region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seasoning also differs from region to region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>日常の食事において供されるほか、盆や正月、節句や祭りなどの、人が多く参集する際のふるまい・もてなし料理としても供される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nishime is served not only for daily meals but for feasts served at occasions such as the Obon festival (a Festival of the Dead or Buddhist All Soul&apos;s Day), New Year&apos;s holidays, seasonal festivals and other festivals where many people are assembled and for welcoming guests with cooking.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nishime is served not only as an everyday meal but also for feasts served at occasions such as the Obon festival (Festival of the Dead or Buddhist All Soul&apos;s Day), New Year&apos;s holidays, seasonal festivals and other festivals where many people are assembled and guests are welcomed with food.</e>
<cmt>Grammar. Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nishime is served not only as an everyday meal but also for feasts served at occasions such as the Obon festival (Festival of the Dead or Buddhist All Soul&apos;s Day), New Year&apos;s holidays, seasonal festivals and other festivals where many people are assembled and guests are welcomed with food.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>こういったことからいわゆる「お袋の味」のひとつとされることも多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For such backgrounds, nishime is generally regarded as one of &quot;Mom&apos;s dishes&quot;, i.e., good old home cooking.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus nishime is generally regarded as one of &quot;Mom&apos;s dishes&quot;, or an example of good old home cooking.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus nishime is generally regarded as one of &apos;Mom&apos;s dishes,&apos; or an example of good old home cooking.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>煮汁が残らないように時間をかけてじっくり煮る調理法を「煮しめる」というが、これが転じてそのように料理されるものを「煮しめ」と称する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The cooking technique of taking time to simmer the contents so as to leave no broth left is called &quot;nishimeru&quot; and in turn, dishes so cooked are collectively called &quot;nishime&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The cooking technique of taking time to simmer the contents so as to leave no broth left is called &quot;nishimeru&quot;, and dishes so cooked are collectively called &quot;nishime&quot;.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The cooking technique of taking time to simmer the contents so as to leave no broth left is called &apos;nishimeru,&apos; and dishes so cooked are collectively called &apos;nishime.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>「煮染め（にしめ）」「煮締め」「お煮しめ」などとも言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nishime is also written as &quot;煮染め&quot; or &quot;煮締め&quot; and is also called &quot;onishime&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nishime is also written as &quot;煮染め&quot; or &quot;煮締め&quot; and is also called &quot;onishime&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nishime is also written as &apos;煮染め&apos; or &apos;煮締め&apos; and is also called &apos;onishime.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>なお、染物にも「煮染め」といわれる技法があるが、こちらは「にぞめ」と読むことが多く、染色液が残らないほど煮るわけではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Here, although there is a dyeing method called &quot;煮染め&quot;, this is usually pronounced as &quot;nizome&quot;and liquid dye is not simmered out in this method.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although there is a dyeing method called &quot;煮染め&quot;, this is usually pronounced as &quot;nizome&quot;and the liquid dye is not simmered in this method.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although there is a dyeing method called &apos;煮染め,&apos; this is usually pronounced as &apos;nizome&apos; and the liquid dye is not simmered in this method.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>煮しめの作り方(小煮しめ)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Recipe of nishime (konishime)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nishime (konishime) recipe</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nishime (konishime) recipe</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>一例として、福井県の郷土料理である「小煮しめ（こにしめ）」を挙げる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As one example, the following is the recipe of konishime.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As ane example, the following is the recipe for konishime (a dish coming from Fukui Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>Added for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As an example, the following is the recipe for konishime (a dish coming from Fukui Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="11">
<j>冬場はやや日持ちするので、大なべで多めに作るのが通例。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In winter when nishime stays good for more days than in the other seasons, it is usually prepared in a relatively large quantity by using a large pot.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In winter, when nishime stays good for more days than in other seasons, it is usually prepared in a relatively large quantity, using a large pot.</e>
<cmt>Grammar. Punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In winter, when nishime stays good for more days than in other seasons, it is usually prepared in a relatively large quantity, using a large pot.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>時間が経つと最後には具が多少溶けて、汁と絡まってどろどろになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some of the ingredients gradually melt down over time to make the broth liquid thick.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some of the ingredients gradually break down over time to make the broth liquid thick.</e>
<cmt>Word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some of the ingredients gradually break down over time to make the broth liquid thick.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>ご飯の上に掛けて食べることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nishime is sometimes eaten as a topping on rice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nishime is sometimes eaten as a topping on rice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nishime is sometimes eaten as a topping on rice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>厚揚げ、干し椎茸、にんじん、こんにゃく、たけのこ、結んだコンブ、サトイモ、ダイコンなどを煮ても壊れない程度でサイコロ状に切る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ingredients suh as atsuage (thick fried tofu), dried shiitake(mushroom), carrots, konjac, bamboo shoots, knotted konbu kelp, Japanese taros and daikon (Japanese raddish) are cut into small cubues yet large enough not to become mushy when simmered.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ingredients suh as atsuage (thick fried tofu), dried shiitake mushrooms, carrots, konjac, bamboo shoots, knotted konbu kelp, Japanese taro and daikon (Japanese giant radish) are cut into small cubes yet large enough not to become mushy when simmered.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, spelling, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ingredients such as atsuage (thick fried tofu), dried shiitake mushrooms, carrots, konjac, bamboo shoots, knotted konbu kelp, Japanese taro and daikon (Japanese giant radish) are cut into small cubes yet large enough not to become mushy when simmered.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>たっぷりの出汁に具を入れ、味付けに醤油、砂糖、みりん、日本酒などで味付けをする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ingredients are put in sufficient dashi broth liquid and seasoned with soy sauce, sugar, mirin (sweet cooking rice wine), and sake.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ingredients are put in a substantial amount of dashi broth and seasoned with soy sauce, sugar, mirin (sweet cooking rice wine), and sake.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ingredients are put in a substantial amount of dashi broth and seasoned with soy sauce, sugar, mirin (sweet cooking rice wine), and sake.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 かなべえコバトン(id:15491), Kentin(id:6768), PeachLover(id:56909), Nnh(id:474), Beagle(id:45036), 草薙(id:23262), R28Bot(id:177951), Point136(id:211299), Yfuruhata(id:20926), Qazzx(id:8772), Corwin(id:973), Mishika(id:276), 1029man(id:93235), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>