<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>煎餅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Senbei (煎餅)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Senbei (煎餅)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Senbei (rice cracker)</e>
<cmt>（煎餅）→(rice cracker)</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>煎餅（せんべい）とは、穀物の粉を使って作る食べ物の一つである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Senbei is a kind of food made from flour.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Senbei is a kind of food made from flour.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Senbei (煎餅) is a kind of food made from flour.</e>
<cmt>後で漢字の説明があるため、ここで（煎餅）を入れました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>多くは薄い形状をしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It often has a thin shape.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It often has a thin shape.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It often has a thin shape.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>日本では焼き菓子の一種で、概して平たい形状のものをいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan, a senbei is usually a kind of baked pastry in a thin form.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan, a senbei is usually a kind of baked pastry in a thin form.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan, a senbei is usually a kind of baked pastry in a thin form.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>中華人民共和国では、小麦粉、アワ、リョクトウなどの粉を水で溶いて、鉄板上に広げて焼いた一銭洋食に似た食品をいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the People&apos;s Republic of China, it means a kind of food made by mixing flour (of wheat, millet, mung bean, etc) with water, then spreading and baking the batter on a hot iron plate, which resembles Japanese &apos;issen-yoshoku&apos; (一銭洋食; an old type Japanese snack resembling a crepe, which is often seasoned by Worcester sauce and topped with finely chopped spring onion - 一銭: one sen, i.e. a hundredth of a yen, and 洋食: literally a Western food).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the People&apos;s Republic of China, it means a kind of food made by mixing flour (of wheat, millet, mung beans, etc) with water, then spreading and baking the batter on a hot iron plate, which resembles Japanese &apos;issen-yoshoku&apos; (an old type Japanese snack resembling a crepe, which is often seasoned by Worcester sauce and topped with finely chopped spring onion).</e>
<cmt>Mung beans. Deleted kanji and part of unnecessarily long explanation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the People&apos;s Republic of China, it means a kind of food made by mixing flour (of wheat, millet, mung beans, etc) with water, then spreading and baking the batter on a hot iron plate, which resembles Japanese &apos;issen-yoshoku&apos; (an old type Japanese snack resembling a crepe, which is often seasoned by Worcester sauce and topped with finely chopped spring onion).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="5">
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Outline</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Outline</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Outline</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>「餅」という字は、もともと中華人民共和国では主に小麦粉、アワ、リョクトウなどの粉を水で練って、平たく成形した食品全般を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The original meaning in the People&apos;s Republic of China of the letter &apos;餅&apos; (which, in Japan, is read as &apos;mochi&apos; or &apos;hei&apos; or &apos;bei&apos; depending on use and means a rice cake) is the whole range of foods made by mixing with water the flour of wheat, millet, mung bean and the like, then being kneaded and formed into a flat shape.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The original meaning in the People&apos;s Republic of China of the character &apos;餅&apos; (which, in Japan, is read as &apos;mochi&apos; or &apos;hei&apos; or &apos;bei&apos; depending on use and means a rice cake) is the whole range of foods made by mixing with water the flour of wheat, millet, mung beans and the like, then being kneaded and formed into a flat shape.</e>
<cmt>Replaced &apos;letter&apos; with &apos;character&apos;. Mung beans.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The original meaning in the People&apos;s Republic of China of the character &apos;餅&apos; (which, in Japan, is read as &apos;mochi&apos; or &apos;hei&apos; or &apos;bei&apos; depending on use and means a rice cake) is the whole range of foods made by mixing with water the flour of wheat, millet, mung beans and the like, then being kneaded and formed into a flat shape.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>そのため、煎餅は餅米を撞いて作る餅（もち）を基本的に使っていないが、「餅」という字が入っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That is why the kanji expression of &apos;senbei&apos; contains the letter &apos;餅&apos; despite that mochi which is a cake of pounded glutinous rice is not used for making senbei in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That is why the kanji form of &apos;senbei&apos; contains the character &apos;餅&apos; despite the fact that mochi, which is a cake of pounded glutinous rice, is not used for making senbei in Japan.</e>
<cmt>Replaced &apos;letter&apos; with &apos;character&apos; and &apos;character&apos; with &apos;form&apos;. Added &apos;the fact&apos; for more natural expression. Added commas.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That is why the kanji form of &apos;senbei&apos; contains the character &apos;餅&apos; despite the fact that mochi, which is a cake of pounded glutinous rice, is not used for making senbei in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="8">
<j>また、「煎」も、中国では薬を煎じるという意味ではなく、鉄板で焼くことを指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Similarly, &apos;煎&apos; (sen) in China means to grill something on a hot iron plate, and does not mean to decoct medicinal herbs (as it does in Japan as in &apos;煎じる&apos; [senjiru]).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Similarly, &apos;煎&apos; (sen) in China means to grill something on a hot iron plate, and does not mean to decoct medicinal herbs as it does in Japan.</e>
<cmt>Deleted part of explanation as felt it was too long.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Similarly, &apos;煎&apos; (sen) in China means to grill something on a hot iron plate, and does not mean to decoct medicinal herbs as it does in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>つまり、中国の「煎餅（ジエンピン jiānbǐng）」は小麦粉などの粉を水で練って、鉄板で焼いたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, &apos;煎餅&apos; (jianbing) in China is a food made by baking the batter of flour (such as of wheat) and water on a hot iron plate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, &apos;煎餅&apos; (jianbing) in China is a food made by baking the batter of flour (such as of wheat) and water on a hot iron plate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, &apos;煎餅&apos; (jianbing) in China is a food made by baking the batter of flour (such as of wheat) and water on a hot iron plate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>別名「薫火」とも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another name for jianbing in China is 薫火.</e>
<cmt>薫火は中国での呼び名ということはインターネット等で確認できるのですが、読みが不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another name for jianbing in China is 薫火.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another name for jianbing in China is 薫火.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>中国においては、現在も山東煎餅、天津煎餅など、一銭洋食に似た作り方の軽食が作られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the present time still, a snack, which is prepared in a method similar to that of issen-yoshoku, is made in China such as Shandong jianbing and Tianjin jianbing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These days snacks such as Shandong jianbing and Tianjin jianbing which are prepared in a method similar to that of issen-yoshoku, are still made in China.</e>
<cmt>Changed word order for more natural expression and replaced &apos;At the present time&apos; with &apos;these days&apos;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These days snacks such as Shandong jianbing and Tianjin jianbing which are prepared in a method similar to that of issen-yoshoku, are still made in China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>日本のお好み焼きもこれらの「煎餅」の一種として「日式雜菜煎餅」などと呼ばれることがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese okonomiyaki (savory pancake with various ingredients) is regarded as one of these &apos;jianbing&apos; type foods, and is sometimes called &apos;日式雜菜煎餅&apos; (Japanese-style chap chai jianbing).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese okonomiyaki (savory pancake with various ingredients) is regarded as one of these &apos;jianbing&apos; type foods, and is sometimes called &apos;日式雜菜煎餅&apos; (Japanese-style chap chai jianbing).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese okonomiyaki (savory pancake with various ingredients) is regarded as one of these &apos;jianbing&apos; type foods, and is sometimes called &apos;日式雜菜煎餅&apos; (Japanese-style chap chai jianbing).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>逆に、日本の揚げ煎餅の類を「仙貝 シエンベイ xiānbèi」と音訳で呼ぶ場合がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the contrary, there is such a case as the Japanese fried senbei and similar snacks are phonetically transliterated as &apos;xianbei&apos; (仙貝).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In contrast, there is such a case as the Japanese fried senbei and similar snacks which are phonetically transliterated as &apos;xianbei&apos; (仙貝).</e>
<cmt>Replaced &apos;on the contrary&apos; with &apos;in contrast&apos; for more naturl expression.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In contrast, there is such a case as the Japanese fried senbei and similar snacks which are phonetically transliterated as &apos;xianbei&apos; (仙貝).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>中国の煎餅は、いずれも軟らかくて、巻いたり、曲げたりして食べることが可能なものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chinese senbei of whatever sort is soft in texture, which can be rolled or bent when eaten.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chinese senbei, of whatever sort, is soft in texture and can be rolled or bent when eaten.</e>
<cmt>Added commas and deleted comma after texture and replaced &apos;which&apos; with &apos;and&apos; for natural expression.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chinese senbei, of whatever sort, is soft in texture and can be rolled or bent when eaten.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="15">
<j>一方、日本では、薄くて、パリッとしたおり、力を加えると割れるような固い菓子の一部を指して煎餅と呼んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for Japanese senbei, it refers to a part of such snacks as are thin, crisp and are breakable when force is applied to.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese senbei are a type of snack which are thin, crispy and are breakable when force is applied to them.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten into natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese senbei are a type of snack which are thin, crispy and are breakable when force is applied to them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>煎餅は日本を代表するスナック菓子（間食）のひとつであるが、近年はポテトチップスなどに人気を奪われる傾向にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Senbei is one of the typical Japanese snacks (eaten between meals), but is in a declining trend in public favor in recent years, being replaced by other snacks such as potato chips</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Senbei are one of the typical Japanese snacks eaten between meals, but are declining in popularity in recent years and are being replaced by other snacks such as potato chips</e>
<cmt>Rewritten into natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Senbei are one of the typical Japanese snacks eaten between meals, but are declining in popularity in recent years and are being replaced by other snacks such as potato chips</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>種類</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Types</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Types</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Types</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="17">
<j>日本における煎餅には、大きく分けて小麦粉、鶏卵などを原料にするもの、米を原料とするもの、ジャガイモなどのデンプンを用いるものの3種類がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are three main types of senbei in Japan, namely one made from wheat flour and eggs, one made from rice and one made from starch such as that of potatoes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are three main types of senbei in Japan; namely one made from wheat flour and eggs, one made from rice and one made from starch such as that of potatoes.</e>
<cmt>Replaced comma with semicolon</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are three main types of senbei in Japan; namely one made from wheat flour and eggs, one made from rice and one made from starch such as that of potatoes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>さらに、焼かずに揚げたり、別の材料を用いたり等の、類似の外観や食感を持つものも煎餅と呼ぶ場合がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, some foods which have a similar appearance or feel in the mouth being, for instance, deep-fried instead of baked or made from different materials, are called senbei.</e>
<cmt>similar feel in the mouth</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, some foods which have a similar appearance or feel in the mouth being, for instance, deep-fried instead of baked or made from different materials, are also called senbei.</e>
<cmt>Addition of &apos;also&apos;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, some foods which have a similar appearance or texture, for instance, deep-fried instead of baked or made from different materials, are also called senbei.</e>
<cmt>feel in the mouth being→texture</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="19">
<j>小麦粉を原料とするものは、主に近畿地方で古くから作られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wheat flour senbei has been made mainly in the Kinki region since old days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wheat flour senbei has been made mainly in the Kinki region since olden days.</e>
<cmt>Replaced old with olden - olden days is a common expression.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wheat flour senbei has been made mainly in the Kinki region since olden days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>材料は主に小麦粉、砂糖、鶏卵などで、カステラやビスケットに近く、味は甘めのものが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Main ingredients include wheat flour, sugar and eggs, and this type of senbei is often sweet in taste and is close to biscuits and &apos;kasutera&apos; (a Japanese-style sponge cake originally imitated from that of Castella in the 16th century).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The main ingredients include wheat flour, sugar and eggs, and this type of senbei is often sweet in taste and is close to biscuits and &apos;kasutera&apos; (a Japanese-style sponge cake originally imitated from that of Castella in the 16th century).</e>
<cmt>Addition of &apos;the&apos;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The main ingredients include wheat flour, sugar and eggs, and this type of senbei is often sweet in taste and is close to biscuits and &apos;kasutera&apos; (a Japanese-style sponge cake originally imitated from that of Castella in the 16th century).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>そのため甘味煎餅（あまみせんべい）とも言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, it is sometimes called amami-senbei (sweet senbei).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, it is sometimes called amami-senbei (sweet senbei).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, it is sometimes called amami-senbei (sweet senbei).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>瓦せんべいなどが代表的なものであり、八ツ橋のように米を材料とするものもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of the best known of this type is kawara-senbei (senbei shaped like a Japanese traditional roof tile), and there are other types made from rice powder such as Yatsuhashi (a specialty confectionery in Kyoto).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of the best known of this type is kawara-senbei (senbei shaped like a Japanese traditional roof tile), and there are other types made from rice powder such as Yatsuhashi (a specialty confectionery in Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of the best known of this type is kawara-senbei (senbei shaped like a Japanese traditional roof tile), and there are other types made from rice powder such as Yatsuhashi (a specialty confectionery in Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>甘味煎餅は唐菓子の伝統を受け継いでおり、こちらが煎餅の原型とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amami-senbei inherits a tradition of To-gashi (唐菓子: Chinese sweets), and this is said to be the origin of senbei.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amami-senbei is part of the tradition of To-gashi (唐菓子: Chinese sweets), and this is said to be the origin of senbei.</e>
<cmt>Replaced inherit with is part of the.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amami-senbei is part of the tradition of To-gashi (唐菓子: Chinese sweets), and this is said to be the origin of senbei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>京都には「唐板」もしくは「唐板煎餅」といわれる、小麦粉・卵（後年に加わった？）・砂糖から作られる煎餅がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kyoto, there is a senbei which is made from wheat flour, eggs (which may have been added in later years) and sugar and is called &apos;karaita&apos; (唐板) or &apos;karaita-senbei.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Kyoto, there is a senbei which is made from wheat flour, eggs (which may have been added in later years) and sugar and is called &apos;karaita&apos; (唐板) or &apos;karaita-senbei.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Kyoto, there is a senbei which is made from wheat flour, eggs (which may have been added in later years) and sugar and is called &apos;karaita&apos; (唐板) or &apos;karaita-senbei.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="25">
<j>米を原料とするものは、米菓煎餅（べいかせんべい）ともいい、主に関東地方で古くから煎餅と呼ばれて作られてきたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Senbei made from rice is also called beika-senbei (米菓煎餅), which has been made in the Kanto region from old days under the name of senbei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Senbei made from rice is also called beika-senbei (米菓煎餅), which has been made in the Kanto region since olden days under the name of senbei.</e>
<cmt>From old days&apos; replaced with &apos;since olden days&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Senbei made from rice is also called beika-senbei (米菓煎餅), which has been made in the Kanto region since olden days under the name of senbei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>醤油や塩による塩辛い味付けのものが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Often it is savory, being seasoned with soy sauce or salt.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Often it is savory, being seasoned with soy sauce or salt.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Often it is savory, being seasoned with soy sauce or salt.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>主に粳米（うるちまい）をつぶしたり搗（つ）いたりして延ばしたものを焼いてつくる米菓である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a rice snack made from uruchimai (ordinary cooking rice) - by crushing or pounding cooked uruchimai, forming it flat into individual pieces and then grilling them.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a rice snack made from uruchimai (ordinary cooking rice) - by crushing or pounding cooked uruchimai, forming it flat into individual pieces and then grilling them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a rice snack made from uruchimai (ordinary cooking rice) - by crushing or pounding cooked uruchimai, forming it flat into individual pieces and then grilling them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>関西では、餅米を利用したかきもち（薄焼き）やあられ（粒状のもの）等の仲間として、おかきなど総称される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Kansai region, this type of senbei is often called by such a collective name as &apos;okaki&apos;, grouping it with kakimochi (thin cracker type) and arare (small cube type) both being made using glutinous rice.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Kansai region, this type of senbei is often called by such a collective name as &apos;okaki&apos;, grouping it with kakimochi (thin cracker type) and arare (small cube type) both of which are made using glutinous rice.</e>
<cmt>Replaced &apos;being&apos; with &apos;of which are&apos;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Kansai region, this type of senbei is often called by such a collective name as &apos;okaki&apos;, grouping it with kakimochi (thin cracker type) and arare (small cube type) both of which are made using glutinous rice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>餅米を使い、油で揚げて作る米菓を揚げ煎餅（あげせんべい）と呼ぶように、現在では必ずしもうるち米だけが原料ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As illustrated by the name age-senbei which refers to deep-fried senbei made from glutinous rice, it is not that uruchimai is the only material for making senbei at present.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As illustrated by the name age-senbei which refers to deep-fried senbei made from glutinous rice, it is evident that uruchimai is not the only material for making senbei at present.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten in natural English.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As illustrated by the name age-senbei which refers to deep-fried senbei made from glutinous rice, it is evident that uruchimai is not the only material for making senbei at present.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="30">
<j>馬鈴薯などのでん粉を用いるものとしては、愛知県の知多半島の名物となっている海老煎餅などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ebi-senbei (shrimp senbei), which is a local specialty of the Chita peninsula in Aichi Prefecture, is one of the examples of senbei made from starch such as that of potato.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ebi-senbei (shrimp senbei), which is a local specialty of the Chita peninsula in Aichi Prefecture, is one of the examples of senbei made from starch such as that of potato.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ebi-senbei (shrimp senbei), which is a local specialty of the Chita peninsula in Aichi Prefecture, is one of the examples of senbei made from starch such as that of potato.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>これは、でん粉に魚や海老の乾燥品を混ぜて焼いたもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is made by grilling the mixture of potato starch and dried seafood such as fish and shrimps.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is made by grilling the mixture of potato starch and dried seafood such as fish and shrimps.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is made by grilling the mixture of potato starch and dried seafood such as fish and shrimps.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>塩辛い味が基本だが、現在ではワサビ味、カレー味、キムチ味など、さまざまな味の物が作られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Basically it has been a savory food, but at present, there is a number of variations in flavors such as wasabi, curry and kimchee.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Basically it has been a savory food, but at present, there is a number of variations in flavors such as wasabi, curry and kimchee.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Basically it has been a savory food, but at present, there is a number of variations in flavors such as wasabi, curry and kimchee.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="33">
<j>関東では、米菓煎餅を焼いて売る煎餅屋も多くみられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Kanto region, there is a number of senbei shops which are specializing in making and selling beika-senbei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Kanto region, there is a number of senbei shops which specialize in making and selling beika-senbei.</e>
<cmt>Replaced &apos;are specializing&apos; with &apos;specialize&apos;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Kanto region, there is a number of senbei shops which specialize in making and selling beika-senbei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>関西では煎餅屋というもの自体が少なく、主におかきやあられ屋で販売しているなど販売形態なども東西で大きく異なる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Not many such senbei shops, however, are found in the Kansai region, where senbei is mainly sold in the shops (confectionery shops) where okaki and arare are the main selling items, which illustrates a major difference in the selling style between eastern and western Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Not many such senbei shops, however, are found in the Kansai region, where senbei is mainly sold in the shops (confectionery shops) where okaki and arare are the main items sold, which illustrates a major difference in the selling style between eastern and western Japan.</e>
<cmt>Replaced &apos;selling items&apos; with &apos;items sold&apos;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Not many such senbei shops, however, are found in the Kansai region, where senbei is mainly sold in the shops where okaki and arare are the main items sold, which illustrates a major difference in the selling style between eastern and western Japan.</e>
<cmt>ウェブで確認し、原文訳文ともに、（菓子）を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="35">
<j>九州などでは煎餅を「せんべい」でなく「せんぺい」と半濁音で発音する人もいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the area such as Kyushu, &apos;煎餅&apos; is sometimes pronounced &apos;senpei&apos; using a p-sound instead of &apos;senbei&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In areas such as Kyushu, &apos;煎餅&apos; is sometimes pronounced &apos;senpei&apos; using a p-sound instead of &apos;senbei&apos;.</e>
<cmt>In the area such as&apos; replaced with &apos;In areas such as&apos;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In areas such as Kyushu, &apos;senbei&apos; is sometimes pronounced &apos;senpei&apos; using a p-sound.</e>
<cmt>煎餅→senbei とし、instead 以下を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>にわかせんぺい（二○加煎餅）、九十九島せんぺい、湯せんぺいといった例がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some such examples include Niwaka-senpei (二O加煎餅), Kujukushima-senpei (九十九島せんぺい) and Yu-senpei (湯せんぺい).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some such examples include Niwaka-senpei (二O加煎餅), Kujukushima-senpei (九十九島せんぺい) and Yu-senpei (湯せんぺい).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some such examples include Niwaka-senpei, Kujukushima-senpei and Yu-senpei.</e>
<cmt>ここでは漢字表記は不要と考え、削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>場合によっては醤油味・塩味を「せんべい」、甘いものを「せんぺい」と呼び分ける例もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In some cases, &apos;senbei&apos; means those seasoned with soy sauce or salt and &apos;senpei&apos; refers to sweet ones.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In some cases, &apos;senbei&apos; means those seasoned with soy sauce or salt and &apos;senpei&apos; refers to sweet ones.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In some cases, &apos;senbei&apos; means those seasoned with soy sauce or salt and &apos;senpei&apos; refers to sweet ones.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="38">
<j>日本で「煎餅」の記述がでてきたのは正倉院所蔵の737年頃の文書である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan, the word &apos;煎餅&apos; first appeared in the literature of around 737 in the collection of Shoso-in Treasure House.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan, the word &apos;煎餅&apos; first appeared in the literature of around 737 in the collection of Shoso-in Treasure House.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan, the word &apos;煎餅&apos; first appeared in the literature of around 737 in the collection of Shoso-in Treasure House.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>ただし、ここに登場する「煎餅」は現在のものと違い、小麦粉を油で固めたいりもち（煎餅）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this case, however, &apos;煎餅&apos;, which can be pronounced senbei, is actually read as &apos;irimochi&apos; meaning a snack made by caking wheat flour with oil, which is different from the present-day senbei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this case, however, &apos;煎餅&apos;, which can be pronounced senbei, is actually read as &apos;irimochi&apos; meaning a snack made by caking wheat flour with oil, which is different from the present-day senbei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this case, however, &apos;煎餅&apos;, which can be pronounced senbei, is actually read as &apos;irimochi&apos; meaning a snack made by caking wheat flour with oil, which is different from the present-day senbei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="40">
<j>もっと現在に近いものでは、日光街道の2番目の宿場町だった草加宿（現在の草加市）で団子屋を営んでいた「おせん」という老婆が、ある日、侍に「団子を平らにして焼いたらどうか」と言われて始めたのが名前の由来、というよく知られた挿話がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a well known story of a time being much closer to the present that &apos;senbei&apos; is derived from an incidence that an old woman named &apos;Osen&apos;, who was running a dumpling shop in Soka-juku (草加宿: present Soka City), the second relay station from Nihonbashi, Edo on the Nikko Highway, started to make and sell a different form of dumplings taking an advice she received one day from a samurai who told her, &quot;How about making those dumplings flat and grill them?&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a well known story of a time much closer to the present in which &apos;senbei&apos; is derived from an incident in which an old woman named &apos;Osen&apos;, who was running a dumpling shop in Soka-juku (草加宿: present Soka City), the second relay station from Nihonbashi, Edo on the Nikko Highway, started to make and sell a different form of dumpling taking advice she received one day from a samurai who told her, &quot;How about making those dumplings flat and grilling them?&quot;</e>
<cmt>Many changes for more natural English.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a well known story of a time much closer to the present in which &apos;senbei&apos; is derived from an incident in which an old woman named &apos;Osen&apos;, who was running a dumpling shop in Soka-juku (present Soka City), the second relay station from Nihonbashi, Edo on the Nikko-kaido Road, started to make and sell a different form of dumpling taking advice she received one day from a samurai who told her, &apos;How about making those dumplings flat and grilling them?&apos;</e>
<cmt>Nikko Highway→Nikko-kaido Road&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;草加宿: 削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="41">
<j>しかし、これは草加市出身の全国紙記者が「草加煎餅」を広めようと創作したものとも言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This story, however, is also said to have been created by a reporter of a national newspaper in order to make Soka-senbei (草加煎餅) better known.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This story, however, is also said to have been created by a reporter of a national newspaper in order to make Soka-senbei (草加煎餅) better known.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This story, however, is also said to have been created by a reporter of a national newspaper in order to make Soka-senbei better known.</e>
<cmt>(草加煎餅)　削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="42">
<j>草加宿一帯の農家では、蒸した米をつぶして丸め、干したもの（「堅餅」という）に塩をまぶして焼き、おやつとして食べていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Farmers living in and around Soka-juku used to make a kind of snack eaten between meals - making balls of crushed cooked rice, which were then dried, sprinkled with salt and grilled (which they called &apos;katamochi&apos;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Farmers living in and around Soka-juku used to make a kind of snack eaten between meals - making balls of crushed cooked rice, which were then dried, sprinkled with salt and grilled, which they called &apos;katamochi&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Added comma, deleted brackets.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Farmers living in and around Soka-juku used to make a kind of snack eaten between meals - making balls of crushed cooked rice, which were then dried, sprinkled with salt and grilled, which they called &apos;katamochi&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>草加宿が日光街道の宿場町として発展したことに伴い、この塩味の煎餅が旅人向けの商品として売り出され、各地に広まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Soka-juku developed as a relay station on the Nikko Kaido, this saline taste senbei sold more to travelers and became widely known everywhere.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Soka-juku developed as a relay station on the Nikko Kaido, this salty senbei was sold more to travelers and became widely known everywhere.</e>
<cmt>Replaced &apos;saline taste&apos; with &apos;salty&apos;. Added was.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Soka-juku developed as a relay station on the Nikko-kaido Road, this salty senbei was sold more to travelers and became widely known everywhere.</e>
<cmt>Nikko Kaido→Nikko-kaido Road</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>その後、利根川沿岸（千葉県野田市）で生産された醤油で味をつけるようになり、現在の草加煎餅の原型となった、というのが実際のところのようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, people started to flavor senbei with soy sauce which was produced in an area alongside the Tone River (Noda City, Chiba Prefecture), and this indeed seems to have become the origin of today&apos;s Soka-senbei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, people started to flavor senbei with soy sauce which was produced in an area alongside the Tone River (Noda City, Chiba Prefecture), and this indeed seems to be the origin of today&apos;s Soka-senbei.</e>
<cmt>Replaced &apos;have become&apos; with &apos;be&apos;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, people started to flavor senbei with soy sauce which was produced in an area alongside the Tone-gawa River (Noda City, Chiba Prefecture), and this indeed seems to be the origin of today&apos;s Soka-senbei.</e>
<cmt>Tone→Tone-gawa</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Zoominshiodome(id:149045), Bakkai(id:7233), Miyuki Meinaka(id:251638), Hhaithait(id:37092), 経済準学士(id:22656), Charenji(id:7908), Eskimbot(id:29676), 笹船団子(id:178738), 4B3(id:14217), CommonsDelinker(id:84593), Roger(id:9883), ラララウルウル(id:10047), Johncapistrano(id:969), ＋－(id:17104), Natunohi(id:6550), たぬき(id:27723), サニードレッシング(id:15736), All way(id:17593), Parayan(id:214526), IwaimBot(id:190695), ロロ(id:104252), Yas(id:739), Takranke(id:23355), 赤鉛筆(id:2434), Wataseakira(id:197134), Poo(id:3277), Izayohi(id:13095), 雪風(id:30818), Lonicera(id:20638), マクガイア(id:33346), 078(id:28534), Nighthawks(id:36125), Dancing fool(id:90442), ネプチューン(id:117766), Aney(id:10520), Yanahan(id:2437), Clarin(id:60278), Mt3(id:118081), ウェルワィ(id:15692), MegMilk(id:87329), VolkovBot(id:105371), Kropsoq(id:10072), ゆすてぃん(id:761), Chiether(id:77421), Alexbot(id:157199), Cpro(id:28341), Ete(id:28565), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>