<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>久田流</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hisada school</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hisada school</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hisada school</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>久田家（ひさだけ）は茶家の一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The HISADA family are a &quot;chake&quot; (a family known as traditional masters of the tea ceremony).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The HISADA family are a &quot;chake&quot; (a family known as traditional masters of the tea ceremony).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hisada family are a &quot;chake&quot; (a family known as traditional masters of the tea ceremony).</e>
<cmt>HISADA →Hisada 　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>三千家の縁戚として表千家の茶を業とする高倉久田家と、久田流（ひさだりゅう）を称する両替町久田家とがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are the Takakura Hisada family, who were tea masters under the Omote Sen-ke branch of the three Sen-ke families, and the Ryogae-machi Hisada family, called the Hisada school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are the Takakura Hisada family, who were tea masters under the Omote Sen-ke branch of the three Sen-ke families, and the Ryogae-machi Hisada family, called the Hisada school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are the Takakura Hisada family, who were tea masters of the Omotesenke school under the Sansenke (three houses of Sen, [Omotesenke, Urasenke and Mushakojisenke]), and the Ryogae-machi Hisada family, called the Hisada school.</e>
<cmt>表千家、三千家　補足を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>久田家の庵号は半床庵（はんしょうあん）といい、3代宗全による二畳中板の茶室を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ango (name of a temple, pen name ending with the character &apos;an&apos;) of the Hisada family is Hanshouan, which is the name of the ??? tea house of the third generation Sozen.</e>
<cmt>Some of these terms have not been searched, so this may need to be revised.</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ango (name of a temple, pen name ending with the character &apos;an&apos;) of the Hisada family is Hanshouan, which is the name of the ??? tea house of the third generation Sozen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ango (pen name ending with the character &apos;an&apos;) of the Hisada family is Hanshoan, which is the name of the tea house called Nijo nakaita-no-seki (two tatami mats with a board in between) of the third generation Sozen.</e>
<cmt>二畳中板→Nijo nakaita-no-seki (two tatami mats with a board in between) としました。（定訳は不明です）（参考：http://www7a.biglobe.ne.jp/~ikka/sinagawaiti.htm）</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>歴代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Lineage</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Lineage</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Lineage</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>元禄期まで</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Through to the Genroku era</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Through to the Genroku era</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Through to the Genroku era</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>久田家の家祖は清和源氏源満季流御園氏末裔といわれ、室町末期の佐々木義実の家臣で久田実房という武人が元祖だとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the founder of the Hisada family wasSanefusa Hisada, a samurai retainer of Yoshizane SASAKI, who was a later Muromachi Period descendant of the Misono clan of the MINAMOTO no Mitsusue line of Seiwa-Genji (Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the founder of the Hisada family wasSanefusa Hisada, a samurai retainer of Yoshizane SASAKI, who was a later Muromachi Period descendant of the Misono clan of the MINAMOTO no Mitsusue line of Seiwa-Genji (Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the founder of the Hisada family was Sanefusa HISADA, a samurai retainer of Yoshizane SASAKI, who was a later Muromachi period descendant of the Misono clan of the MINAMOTO no Mitsusue line of Seiwa-Genji (Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt>HISADA と苗字を大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>口伝により実房は千利休の妹宗円の夫であるとされ、資料はないながらも表千家と高倉久田家の間では了解されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The story passed down in the oral tradition holds that Sanefusa was the husband of SEN no Rikyu&apos;s daughter Soen, and that even though there is no supporting documentation, this account is recognized by the Omotesenke and the Hisada families.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The story passed down in the oral tradition holds that Sanefusa was the husband of SEN no Rikyu&apos;s daughter Soen, and that even though there is no supporting documentation, this account is recognized by the Omotesenke and the Hisada families.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The story passed down in the oral tradition holds that Sanefusa was the husband of SEN no Rikyu&apos;s younger sister Soen, and that even though there is no supporting documentation, this account is recognized by the Omotesenke school and the Takakura Hisada family.</e>
<cmt>daughter→ younger siter に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>それによれば、このとき利休は茶杓を削って「大振袖」と名づけ「婦人シツケ点前一巻」と共に宗円に与えたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the story, at the time of the marriage, Rikyu gave Soen a tea spoon he had carved for the occassion, which he called &quot;large furisode&quot;, along with a scroll called &quot;Fujinshitsuketemae&quot; (tea ceremony procedures for women).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the story, at the time of the marriage, Rikyu gave Soen a tea spoon he had carved for the occassion, which he called &quot;large furisode&quot;, along with a scroll called &quot;Fujinshitsuketemae&quot; (tea ceremony procedures for women).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the story, at the time of the marriage, Rikyu gave Soen a chashaku (bamboo tea spoon for making Japanese tea) he had carved for the occasion, which he called &apos;large furisode,&apos; along with a scroll called &apos;Fujin shitsuke temae&apos; (tea ceremony procedures for women).</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに修正しました。「婦人シツケ点前一巻」の「一巻」ですが、「巻物」（scroll） の意味なのか、1巻、2巻　などの「本」の意味なのか調査できませんでした。翻訳者の方の翻訳のとおり、scroll　としてあります。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>この婦人点前が、今日表千家や久田流に伝わる女点前の源流であるとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This Fujin temae is thought to be the origins of the tea ceremony procedures taught by the Omotesenke and Hisada families today.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This Fujin temae is thought to be the origins of the tea ceremony procedures taught by the Omotesenke and Hisada families today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This Fujin temae is thought to be the origins of the tea ceremony procedures taught by the Omotesenke school and Hisada family today.</e>
<cmt>omotesenke school としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>実房の子は房政といい、剃髪して宗栄と名乗り、茶人であったと考えられており、これを久田家の初代としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanefusa&apos;s child, ???, took the tonsure and became a monk, assuming the name Soei, and it is assumed that he was a tea master, the first in the Hisada family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanefusa&apos;s child, ???, took the tonsure and became a monk, assuming the name Soei, and it is assumed that he was a tea master, the first in the Hisada family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanefusa&apos;s child, Fusamasa, took the tonsure and became a monk, assuming the name Soei, and it is assumed that he was a tea master, the first in the Hisada family.</e>
<cmt>房政→Fusamasa としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>3代久田宗全は手工に秀で、宗全籠に名を残す他、茶碗茶杓などに優品が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The third generation Hisada family head, who excelled at handicrafts, assumed the artistic name Sozenryu, and there are many fine examples of his tea bowls, spoons and other the like.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The third generation Hisada family head, who excelled at handicrafts, assumed the artistic name Sozenryu, and there are many fine examples of his tea bowls, spoons and other the like.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The third generation head of the family, Sozen HISADA, who excelled at handicrafts, was not only famous for his Sozen wicker baskets, but also left many fine works such as tea bowls, spoons and the like.</e>
<cmt>宗全籠→Sozen wicker baskets としました（定訳不明です）。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>久田家歴代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hisada family lineage</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hisada family lineage</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hisada family lineage</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>高倉久田家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takakura Hisada family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takakura Hisada family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takakura Hisada family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>4代不及斎には二男あり、理由は不明ながら次男の宗悦が半床庵を継嗣した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fourth generation head of the family, Sai FUKYU had two sons, and for unkown reasons the second son became the successor to the Hanshouan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fourth generation head of the family, Sai FUKYU had two sons, and for unkown reasons the second son became the successor to the Hanshouan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fourth generation head of the family, Fukyusai (不及斎) had two sons, and for unknown reasons the second son became the successor to the Hanshoan.</e>
<cmt>Fukyusai 読み方が不明なため、漢字を追記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>その後の久田家の継承は表千家の継承の影響を受けて波乱が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Subsequent successions within the Hisada family were influenced by the successions within the Omotesenke, and there are many instances of troubled successions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequent successions within the Hisada family were influenced by the successions within the Omotesenke, and there are many instances of troubled successions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequent successions within the Hisada family were influenced by the successions within the Omotesenke, and there are many instances of troubled successions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>7代皓々斎宗也が没した際に次男達蔵が残されていたが、前年生まれたばかりのため後見人として関宗厳を養子に迎え8代宗利とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the seventh generation head of the Hisada family, Soya KOUKOUSAI, passed away, he was survided by his second son, Tatsuzo; however, because his son had been born only the previous year, Muneyoshi SEKI was adopted as his gaurdian, and became the eight generation Munetoshi.</e>
<cmt>None of these names have been searched.</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the seventh generation head of the Hisada family, Soya KOUKOUSAI, passed away, he was survided by his second son, Tatsuzo; however, because his son had been born only the previous year, Muneyoshi SEKI was adopted as his gaurdian, and became the eight generation Munetoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the seventh generation head of the Hisada family, Kokosai Soya, passed away, he was survived by his second son, Tatsuzo; however, because his son had been born only the previous year, Muneyoshi SEKI (関宗厳) was adopted as his guardian, and became the eighth generation Munetoshi.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。関宗厳 　読みが不明のため、漢字を追記しました。皓々斎宗也 「皓々斎」は名字ではなく、号名ですので、Kokosai Soya とそのまま表記しています（以下同様）。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>その後表千家9代了々斎（皓々斎宗也の兄）が没したため、達蔵が表千家10代を継承した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, the ninth generation head of the Omotesenke, Ryoryosai, Tatsuzo successed him as the tenth generation head of the family.</e>
<cmt>should these all read &quot;grandmaster&quot;?</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, the ninth generation head of the Omotesenke, Ryoryosai, Tatsuzo successed him as the tenth generation head of the family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, since the ninth generation head of the Omotesenke, Ryoryosai (an older brother of Kokosai Soya) passed away, Tatsuzo succeeded him as the tenth generation head of the Omotesenke school.</e>
<cmt>一部翻訳を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>宗利は性行不良で大阪にて客死し、久田家は一時中絶となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Upon the death of Munetoshi while he was staying in Osaka due to a sexual indiscretion, the Hisada family line was temporarily broken.</e>
<cmt>unclear</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Upon the death of Munetoshi while he was staying in Osaka due to a sexual indiscretion, the Hisada family line was temporarily broken.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Upon the death of Munetoshi while he was staying in Osaka due to a delinquent behavior, the Hisada family line was temporarily broken.</e>
<cmt>性行不良→delinquent behavior　としました（定訳不明です）。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>改めて表千家7代如心斎の姻戚である住山家より、住山家8代云々斎楊甫の孫を養子に迎え9代宗与とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, the Hisada-ke adopted the grandson of Denden Saiyoho, the eighth generation head of the Sumiyama-ke, who were in-laws of the seventh generation Nyoshinzai of the Omotesenke, who became the 9th head of the Hisada family, known as Souyo.</e>
<cmt>読み方不明、意味不明な処もあり。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, the Hisada-ke adopted the grandson of Denden Saiyoho, the eighth generation head of the Sumiyama-ke, who were in-laws of the seventh generation Nyoshinzai of the Omotesenke, who became the 9th head of the Hisada family, known as Souyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, the family adopted the grandson of Unnunsai Yoho (云々斎楊甫), the eighth generation head of the Sumiyama family, who were in-laws of the seventh generation Joshinsai of the Omotesenke school, who became the ninth head of the Hisada family, known as Soyo.</e>
<cmt>人名など修正しました。云々斎楊甫 読みが不明のため、漢字を追記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>しかし宗与は夭逝し、改めて表千家10代吸江斎の子を養子に迎え10代宗悦とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Souyo died prematurely, so the Hisada-ke adopted a child of Gyuukosai, the tenth generation head of the Omotosenke, who became the tenth generation head of the Hisada family, known as Souetsu.</e>
<cmt>読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Souyo died prematurely, so the Hisada-ke adopted a child of Gyuukosai, the tenth generation head of the Omotosenke, who became the tenth generation head of the Hisada family, known as Souetsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Soyo died prematurely, so the Hisada family adopted a child of Kyukosai, the tenth generation head of the Omotesenke, who became the tenth generation head of the Hisada family, known as Soetsu.</e>
<cmt>人名、スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>宗悦も1895年に40歳で夭逝したため、11代無適斎宗也は表千家に引き取られ再び一時中絶となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because Souetsu also died an early death at 40 years of age in 1895, the eleventh generation head of the Omotesenke, ??? assumed the leadership of the Hisada-ke, and the line was therefore again temporarily disrupted.</e>
<cmt>読み方不明、意味不明な処もあり。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because Souetsu also died an early death at 40 years of age in 1895, the eleventh generation head of the Omotesenke, ??? assumed the leadership of the Hisada-ke, and the line was therefore again temporarily disrupted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because Soetsu also died an early death at 40 years of age in 1895, the 11th generation head, Mutekisai Soya, was taken in by Omotesenke school, the family line was therefore again temporarily disrupted.</e>
<cmt>人名、スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>無適斎宗也は1917年に表千家12代惺斎の援助を得て再興し、現在に至る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">??? received the support of the 12th generation head of the Omotosenke, Seisai, and restored the line, which persists to this day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">??? received the support of the 12th generation head of the Omotosenke, Seisai, and restored the line, which persists to this day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mutekisai Soya received the support of the 12th generation head of the Omotesenke, Seisai, and restored the line in 1917, which persists to this day.</e>
<cmt>人名など修正しました。1917年を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="20">
<j>高倉久田家歴代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History of the Hisada family of Takakura</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History of the Hisada family of Takakura</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History of the Takakura Hisada family</e>
<cmt>Takakura Hisada family としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>両替町久田家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Hisada family of Ryougae-machi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hisada family of Ryougae-machi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ryogae-machi Hisada family</e>
<cmt>Ryogae-machi Hisada family としました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="21">
<j>4代不及斎の長男の宗玄は両替町に移り両替町久田家を起こした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sougen, the eldest son of Fukyuusai, the fourth grandmaster of the Hisada-ke, relocated to Ryougaecho, and established the Ryougae-machi Hisada family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sougen, the eldest son of Fukyuusai, the fourth grandmaster of the Hisada-ke, relocated to Ryougaecho, and established the Ryougae-machi Hisada family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sogen, the eldest son of Fukyusai, the fourth grandmaster of the Hisada family, relocated to Ryogae-machi, and established the Ryogae-machi Hisada family.</e>
<cmt>人名など修正しました。Ryogae-machi としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>久田流を称して主に東海地方に広まるが、その一方両替町住邸は元治元年（1864年）の兵火により焼失して現在に至る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He named his school the Hisada school, and actively spread his teachings throughout the Tokai region; however, in 1864 the residence in Ryougaecho was consumed in a fire caused by a war, and has not been rebuilt to this day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He named his school the Hisada school, and actively spread his teachings throughout the Tokai region; however, in 1864 the residence in Ryougaecho was consumed in a fire caused by a war, and has not been rebuilt to this day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He named his school the Hisada school, and actively spread his teachings throughout the Tokai region; however, in 1864 the residence in Ryogae-machi was consumed in a fire caused by a war, and has not been rebuilt to this day.</e>
<cmt>Ryogae-machi としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>東海地方には他に尾州久田流があり、大高（現在名古屋市緑区 (名古屋市)）の下村実栗が6代宗参の弟子の栄甫から久田流を習得した後、独自発案を含めて創流したもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Tokai region, there was also the Bishu Hisada school, and in Otaka (Midori district in present day Nagoya City), and after Mikuri SHIMOMURA studied the teachings of the Hisada school under Eiho, a student of the sixth generation grandmaster Sousan, he established his own independent school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Tokai region, there was also the Bishu Hisada school, and in Otaka (Midori district in present day Nagoya City), and after Mikuri SHIMOMURA studied the teachings of the Hisada school under Eiho, a student of the sixth generation grandmaster Sousan, he established his own independent school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Tokai region, there was also the Bishu Hisada school, and after Mitsuyoshi SHIMOMURA in Otaka (Midori Ward in present day Nagoya City) studied the teachings of the Hisada school under Eiho, a student of the sixth generation grandmaster Sosan, he established his own independent school.</e>
<cmt>人名、地名などを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="24">
<j>両替町久田家歴代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History of the Ryogae-machi Hisada family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History of the Ryogae-machi Hisada family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History of the Ryogae-machi Hisada family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Tawashi2006(id:95112), Mzaki(id:61977), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>