<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>堺祭</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sakai Festival</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sakai Festival</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sakai Festival</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>堺祭（さかいのまつり）は、古代・中世日本の王都・令制国郡の堺（境）で行われた祭。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sakai Festival (Sakai no Matsuri) is a festival that was held at corner points in Oto (imperial capital) and Koku-gun in the governing system in the ancient and medieval period of Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sakai Festival (Sakai no Matsuri) is a festival that was held at corner points and boundaries in Oto (imperial capital) and Koku-gun in the governing system in the ancient and medieval period of Japan.</e>
<cmt>corner points →corner points and boundaries</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sakai Festival (Sakai no Matsuri) is a festival that was held at corner points and boundaries in Oto (imperial capital) and Koku-gun in the governing system in the ancient and medieval period of Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>元は村の出入口や坂・峠などで疫病や災厄を防ぎ、道の安全を祈るために堺（境）の神を祀ったのが由来とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The festival is considered originally derived from honoring to the god in Sakai to prevent plagues or disasters at doorways in a village, slope, or peak, and to pray for safety on a way.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The festival is considered originally derived from honoring to the deity of cornor points and boundaries in Sakai to prevent plagues or disasters at gateways to villages, on slopes or peaks, and to pray for safety on the way.</e>
<cmt>the god →deity of cornor points and boundariesdoorways → gateways その他表現変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The festival is considered originally derived from honoring to the deity of cornor points and boundaries in Sakai to prevent plagues or disasters at gateways to villages, on slopes or peaks, and to pray for safety on the way.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>『古事記』の黄泉比良坂を守る道反之大神の説話もこれと関連性があると言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The narrative in &quot;Kojiki&quot; about Chigaeshi no Okami, who protects Yomotsu Hirasaka, is said to have some relation with this derivation.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The narrative in &quot;Kojiki&quot; about Chigaeshi no Okami, who protects Yomotsu Hirasaka, is said to have some relation with this derivation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The narrative in &quot;Kojiki&quot; about Chigaeshi no Okami, who protects Yomotsu Hirasaka, is said to have some relation with this derivation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>後に中国から陰陽道が伝来すると両者が融合されて祭としての体裁が整えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Onmyodo was transmitted later from China, and then both were united for formation as a festival.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Onmyodo was conveyed later from China, and then both were united to form a festival.</e>
<cmt>表現変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Onmyodo was conveyed later from China, and then both were united to form a festival.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>律令政治の元では、神祇官が王都の境界を守る「道饗祭」を掌った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under the government according to the Ritsuryo codes, Jingikan (department of workship) managed &quot;Dokyo-sai Festival&quot; held to protect the borders of the capital.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the government according to the Ritsuryo codes, Jingikan (department of workship) managed &quot;Dokyo-sai Festival&quot; held to protect the borders of the capital.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the government according to the Ritsuryo codes, Jingikan (department of workship) managed &quot;Dokyo-sai Festival&quot; held to protect the borders of the capital.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>だが、天平7年（735年）の疫病で大宰府管内続いて平城京で多数の死者が発生すると、諸国においても同様の祭事を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, many people died in the area of Dazaifu and then subsequently in Heijokyo due to the plagues in 735, and as a result, similar festivals were held in various countries.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 735, however, many people died due to the plagues in the area of Dazaifu and then subsequently in Heijo-kyo, the ancient capital of Japan in current Nara, and as a result, similar festivals were held in various countries.</e>
<cmt>平城京説明追加、語順変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 735, however, many people died due to the plagues in the area of Dazaifu and then subsequently in Heijo-kyo, the ancient capital of Japan in current Nara, and as a result, similar festivals were held in various countries.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>平安京遷都後も同様に道饗祭が行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dokyo-sai Festival was held likewise after removal of the capital to Heiankyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After relocation of national capital to the city of Heiankyo, Dokyo-sai Festival continued to be held</e>
<cmt>遷都の訳、語順変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After relocation of national capital to the city of Heiankyo, Dokyo-sai Festival continued to be held</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>以後、疫病や災厄対策のために同様の祭事が増やされ、『延喜式』では内裏の外周で行う「宮城四隅疫神祭」をはじめ、外国からの賓客の入京・帰国時、行幸や斎宮下向など様々な堺祭が行われたことが記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterward, similar festivals have increased for prevention of plagues or disasters. &quot;The Engisiki&quot; describes that, when guests from foreign countries entered the capital and went back to their countries, various Sakai Festivals were held such as for gyoko (Emperor&apos;s going out) or for leaving the capital for Saigu, including &quot;Kyujo Yosumi Ekijin-sai Festival&quot; performed around the periphery of the dairi (Imperial Palace.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Afterward, similar festivals have increased for prevention of plagues or disasters. &quot;The Engisiki&quot; describes that, when guests from foreign countries entered the capital and went back to their countries, various Sakai Festivals were held such as for gyoko (Emperor&apos;s going out) or for leaving the capital for Saigu, including &quot;Kyujo Yosumi Ekijin-sai Festival&quot; performed around the periphery of the dairi (Imperial Palace.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Afterward, similar festivals have increased for prevention of plagues or disasters. &quot;The Engisiki&quot; describes that, when guests from foreign countries entered the capital and went back to their countries, various Sakai Festivals were held such as for gyoko (Emperor&apos;s going out) or for leaving the capital for Saigu, including &quot;Kyujo Yosumi Ekijin-sai Festival&quot; performed around the periphery of the dairi (Imperial Palace.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>以後、疫病や災厄対策のために同様の祭事が増やされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterward, similar festivals have increased for prevention of plagues or disasters.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Afterward, similar festivals have increased for prevention of plagues or disasters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Afterward, similar festivals have increased for prevention of plagues or disasters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>『延喜式』では内裏の外周で行う「宮城四隅疫神祭」をはじめ、外国からの賓客の入京・帰国時、行幸や斎宮下向など様々な堺祭が行われたことが記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;The Engisiki&quot; describes that, when guests from foreign countries entered the capital and went back to their countries, various Sakai Festivals were held such as for gyoko (Emperor&apos;s going out) or for leaving the capital for Saigu, including &quot;Kyujo Yosumi Ekijin-sai Festival&quot; performed around the periphery of the dairi (Imperial Palace.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処　　　　用語集では「宮城四隅疫神祭」を&quot;Miyagi osumi Ekijin-sai Festival&quot;で登録されておりましたが、宮殿で行われるということから&quot;Miyagi&quot;ではなく&quot;Kyujo&quot;と読むと思われますので、そのように訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;The Engisiki&quot; (an ancient book for codes and procedures on national rites and prayers) describes that, when guests from foreign countries entered the capital and went back to their countries, various Sakai Festivals were held such as for gyoko (Emperor&apos;s going out) or for leaving the capital for Saigu, including &quot;Kyujo Yosumi Ekijin-sai Festival&quot; performed around the periphery of the dairi (Imperial Palace.)</e>
<cmt>延喜式説明追加</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;The Engisiki&quot; (an ancient book for codes and procedures on national rites and prayers) describes that, when guests from foreign countries entered the capital and went back to their countries, various Sakai Festivals were held such as for gyoko (Emperor&apos;s going out) or for leaving the capital for Saigu, including &quot;Kyujo Yosumi Ekijin-sai Festival&quot; performed around the periphery of the dairi (Imperial Palace.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>後に宮城四隅疫神祭と平安京の道饗祭が統合され、平安京の四堺における「四境四堺祭」へと発展していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyujo Yosumi Ekijin-sai Festival was later united with Dokyo-sai Festival in Heiankyo to be developed into &quot;Shikyo Shisakai Matsuri (Festival of Four Borders and Four-corner Points&quot; at four corner points in Heiankyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyujo Yosumi Ekijin-sai Festival was later united with Dokyo-sai Festival in Heiankyo to be developed into &quot;Shikyo Shisakai Matsuri &quot; (Festival of Four Borders and Four-corner Points) at four corner points in Heiankyo.</e>
<cmt>&quot;　)　の位置変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyujo Yosumi Ekijin-sai Festival was later united with Dokyo-sai Festival in Heiankyo to be developed into &quot;Shikyo Shisakai Matsuri &quot; (Festival of Four Borders and Four-corner Points) at four corner points in Heiankyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Basedview(id:182448), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>