<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>京都ラーメン</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Ramen</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">OK</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">OK</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>京都ラーメン（きょうとラーメン）とは、日本の京都府（主に京都市以南）で販売され食べられているラーメンを雑誌や書籍で紹介する場合に用いられる総称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto ramen is a generic name of ramen sold and eaten in Kyoto Prefecture, Japan (mainly in Kyoto City and southern areas) when introduced in Magazines and books.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto ramen is a generic name given to ramen sold and eaten in Kyoto Prefecture, Japan (mainly in Kyoto City and areas to its south) when it is mentioned in magazines and books.</e>
<cmt>Grammar/flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto ramen is a generic name given to ramen sold and eaten in Kyoto Prefecture, Japan (mainly in Kyoto City and areas to its south) when it is mentioned in magazines and books.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>主に京都以外で販売され食べられている、京都をイメージして作り出された京風ラーメン及び、京都発祥ではない京都風ラーメンも存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are Kyo-style ramen produced based on an image of Kyoto and Kyoto-style ramen not deriving from Kyoto, which are mainly sold and eaten in other area than Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyo-style ramen, which is a style of ramen that has been created based on the image of Kyoto, and Kyoto-style ramen, which does not have its origins in Kyoto, are two styles of ramen that share a similar name to Kyoto ramen but are mainly sold and eaten in areas other than Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>The Japanese does not mention that these two styles of ramen have a similar name to Kyoto ramen (because this is obvious to a Japanese speaker from the kanji), but I don&apos;t think this would necessarily be clear to a native speaker of English with little knowledge of Japan/Japanese so I added this.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyo-style ramen, which is a style of ramen that has been created based on the image of Kyoto, and Kyoto-style ramen, which does not have its origins in Kyoto, are two styles of ramen that share a similar name to Kyoto ramen but are mainly sold and eaten in areas other than Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="3">
<j>この2つと前述の京都ラーメン（きょうとラーメン）とは明確に区別される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These two are clearly distinguished from the above-described Kyoto ramen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are clearly distinct from the above-mentioned Kyoto ramen.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are clearly distinct from the above-mentioned Kyoto ramen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>京都のラーメン事情</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Fact of Kyoto Ramen</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Facts about Kyoto Ramen</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Facts about Kyoto Ramen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Outline</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>味付けは濃厚で、ボリュームがあるラーメンが主流である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ramen with heavy seasoning and volume is a mainstream.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto ramen is usually heavily seasoned and served in large portions.</e>
<cmt>This is very chokuyaku. Please make sure you translate the meaning rather than just the words.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto ramen is usually heavily seasoned and served in large portions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>麺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Noodle</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Noodle</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Noodle</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>麺は、細めのストレート角麺（第一旭本店では、1. 8mmの麺を使っており、ほとんどの京都のラーメン店では、同じ太さの麺か、やや細めの麺を使っている。ちなみに、京都ラーメンの一大源流といわれる新福菜館本店では、2. 0mmの麺を使っているが、現在の京都ラーメンの店で、この太さの麺を使っている店は少ない）で、比較的柔らかめに茹でる店が多い（スープに絡みやすいからと言われる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most stores use narrow straight square noodles (Daiichi-Asahi main store uses 1.8mm-thick noodles, and most of other ramen stores in Kyoto use noodles with the same or less thickness. By comparison, Shinpuku-saikan main store, which is called a big origin of Kyoto ramen, uses 2.0mm-thick noodles, but currently very few Kyoto ramen stores use the noodles with this thickness.), and cook them until relatively soft (allegedly because they easily capture the soup).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most stores use straight narrow square noodles (the Daiichi-Asahi main store uses 1.8mm-thick noodles, and most other ramen stores in Kyoto use noodles which are the same thickness or thinner. In comparison, the Shinpuku-saikan main store, which is a giant source of Kyoto ramen, uses 2.0mm-thick noodles (but currently very few Kyoto ramen stores use noodles with this thickness), and cook them until relatively soft (allegedly because they more easily absorbe the soup).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most stores use straight narrow square noodles (the Daiichi-Asahi main store uses 1.8mm-thick noodles, and most other ramen stores in Kyoto use noodles which are the same thickness or thinner. In comparison, the Shinpuku-saikan main store, which is a giant source of Kyoto ramen, uses 2.0mm-thick noodles but currently very few Kyoto ramen stores use noodles with this thickness), and cook them until relatively soft (allegedly because they more easily absorbe the soup).</e>
<cmt>不要なカッコ削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>また、京都では、ラーメンに限らず麺類は出汁を楽しむという意識が強いのか、麺はどうも後回しになってる感が強く、ラーメンでも、名店、老舗、人気店と呼ばれるラーメン専門店の大半が製麺所の麺を使っており、自家製麺の店はほとんど無いという、他府県のラーメン専門店ではあまり見られない傾向がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Probably because an idea of enjoying soup when eating not only ramen but also other noodles is strong, noodles do not seem emphasized, and majority of well-established stores, long-established stores, and popular stores purchase noodles from noodle-making factories instead of making noodles in the store, which trend is seldom seen in stores specializing in ramen in other prefectures.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Noodles are not overly emphasized in due to the fact that enjoying the soup is strongly emphasized with ramen as well as other noodles, and a majority of well-established, long-established, and popular stores purchase noodles from noodle-making factories instead of making noodles in the store, a trend which is seldom seen in stores specializing in ramen in other prefectures.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Noodles are not overly emphasized in due to the fact that enjoying the soup is strongly emphasized with ramen as well as other noodles, and a majority of well-established, long-established, and popular stores purchase noodles from noodle-making factories instead of making noodles in the store, a trend which is seldom seen in stores specializing in ramen in other prefectures.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>具材</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ingredients</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ingredients</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ingredients</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>具材は、モヤシ、メンマ（シナチク）、叉焼（焼豚）、ネギが基本形とされ、俗に「もやしなちゃー」と呼ばれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The basic ingredients are bean sprout, sungan (Chinese bamboo), roasted pork fillet, and green onion, which is commonly called &quot;Moyashinacha.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The basic ingredients are bean sprout, sungan (Chinese bamboo), roasted pork fillet, and green onion, which is commonly called &quot;Moyashinacha.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The basic ingredients are bean sprout, sungan (Chinese bamboo), roasted pork fillet, and green onion, which is commonly called &quot;Moyashinacha.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>ただし、モヤシに関しては、現在は入れない店も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, these days some stored do not use the bean sprout.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, these days some stores do not use bean sprouts.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, these days some stores do not use bean sprouts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>ネギは、京野菜である甘味の強い九条葱を多めに盛る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for the green onion, a generous amount of leek from Kujo with rather strong sweetness, which is vegetable from Kyoto, is arranged.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for green onions, a generous amount of leek from Kujo which has a rather strong sweetness to it, and is a vegetable of Kyoto, is arranged is placed on top.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for green onions, a generous amount of leek from Kujo which has a rather strong sweetness to it, and is a vegetable of Kyoto, is arranged is placed on top.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>ただ、最近はコストダウンのためか、他の青ネギで代用する店も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, probably for the purpose of cost cutting, recently many stores use other green onions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, recently many stores use other green onions most likely to cut costs.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, recently many stores use other green onions most likely to cut costs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>また、最近では、他府県のラーメンの影響か、煮卵、海苔などを載せる店も増えつつある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, increasing number of stores arrange a boiled egg seasoned in soy sauce, dried laver seaweed, and the like, presumably affected by ramen in other prefectures.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, an increasing number of stores place a boiled egg seasoned in soy sauce, dried laver seaweed, and the like, presumably due to an influence by ramen from other prefectures.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, an increasing number of stores place a boiled egg seasoned in soy sauce, dried laver seaweed, and the like, presumably due to an influence by ramen from other prefectures.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>スープ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soup</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soup</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soup</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="13">
<j>スープに関しては大きく分けて3つの系統がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are roughly three types of soup.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are roughly three types of soup.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are roughly three types of soup.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="14">
<j>あっさり系。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Plain type.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Plain type.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Plain type.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="15">
<j>豚骨、豚肉をベースにした、清湯スープ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Clear soup based on pork bone and pork meat.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Clear soup based on pork bone and pork meat.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Clear soup based on pork bone and pork meat.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>ただし、京都以外で言うところの「あっさり系」とは異なる（通常、あっさり系ラーメンとは中華料理店などで出される汎用鶏ガラスープを使った、いわゆる「中華そば」、もしくは鶏ガラ+魚介系の東京風ラーメンを指す）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it is different from the &quot;plain type&quot; in other areas than Kyoto (normally, the plain type ramen means what is called &quot;Chinese noodle&quot; using chicken bone broth for general use as served in a Chinese restaurant or the like, or Tokyo-style ramen using the chicken broth + seafood broth).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is different from the &quot;plain type&quot; in other areas than Kyoto (normally, a plain type ramen means what is called &quot;Chinese noodle&quot; using a general chicken bone broth as served in a Chinese restaurant or the like, or Tokyo-style ramen using chicken broth + seafood broth).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is different from the &apos;plain type&apos; in other areas than Kyoto (normally, a plain type ramen means what is called &apos;Chinese noodle&apos; using a general chicken bone broth as served in a Chinese restaurant or the like, or Tokyo-style ramen using chicken broth + seafood broth).</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>京都のラーメン店のなかでも、元祖的存在である新福菜館が、このスープを採用している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among ramen stores in Kyoto, Shinpuku-saikan, which is virtually an origin, employs this type of soup.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among ramen stores in Kyoto, Shinpuku-saikan, which is a large source of Kyoto rame, employs this type of soup.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among ramen stores in Kyoto, Shinpuku-saikan, which is a large source of Kyoto ramen, employs this type of soup.</e>
<cmt>Kyoto rame→Kyoto ramenに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>その他、第一旭、ラーメン藤、大栄、萬福などがこの系統に属する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, Ramen Fuji, Daiei, Manbuku, and others belong to this type.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, Ramen Fuji, Daiei, Manbuku, and others belong to this type.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, Daiichi-Asahi, Ramen Fuji, Daiei, Manbuku, and others belong to this type.</e>
<cmt>「第一旭」を訳出</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>後述のように、語源は、天下一品の（あっさり）から来ているのだが、天下一品の（あっさり）は鶏ガラスープのため、現在はこのカテゴリーに含めない場合が多い（京都では、中華料理店などで出される汎用鶏ガラスープを使ったラーメンに関しては、「中華そば」と呼ぶことが多く、一般のラーメンとは別物扱いする傾向がある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As described later, the term derives from &quot;plain type&quot; of Tenka-ippin, but the &apos;plain type&apos; of Tenka-ippin is not usually included in this category because it is based on the chicken bone broth (in Kyoto, the ramen using the chicken bone broth for general use as served in a Chinese restaurant or the like is usually called &quot;Chinese noodle,&quot; which tends to be distinguished from general ramen).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As described later, the term derives from &quot;plain type&quot; of Tenka-ippin, but the &apos;plain type&apos; of Tenka-ippin is not usually included in this category because it is based on the chicken bone broth (in Kyoto, ramen which uses general chicken bone broth as served in Chinese restaurants or the like is usually called &quot;Chinese noodle,&quot; which tends to be distinguished from general ramen).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As described later, the term derives from &quot;plain type&quot; of Tenka-ippin, but the &quot;plain type&quot; of Tenka-ippin is not usually included in this category because it is based on the chicken bone broth (in Kyoto, ramen which uses general chicken bone broth as served in Chinese restaurants or the like is usually called &apos;Chinese noodle,&apos; which tends to be distinguished from general ramen).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="20">
<j>背脂醤油系</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soy Sauce with Backfat Type</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soup made of Soy Sauce with Backfat</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soup made of Soy Sauce with Backfat</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="21">
<j>甘みの強い鶏ガラスープに背脂を載せたもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chicken broth with strong sweetness topped with backfat.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chicken broth having a strong sweetness and topped with backfat.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chicken broth having a strong sweetness and topped with backfat.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>ますたにが元祖とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masutani is believed to be its origin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed to have originated in Masutani.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed to have originated in Masutani.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>その他、ほそかわ、来来亭、杉千代などがこの系統に属する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hosokawa, Miraitei, Sugichiyo, and others belong to this type.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hosokawa, Miraitei, Sugichiyo, and others belong to this type.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hosokawa, Miraitei, Sugichiyo, and others belong to this type.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="24">
<j>こってり系。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thick type.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thick type.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thick type.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="25">
<j>鶏ガラがドロドロになるまで煮込んで作る、とろみの強い白湯スープ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thick white broth prepared by boiling chicken bone until melt.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thick white broth prepared by boiling chicken bone until melted.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thick white broth prepared by boiling chicken bone until melted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>元祖は、今は亡き山科の東洋とする説が有力だが、京都駅近くで営業していた屋台御池ラーメン（現在の御池ラーメンさまたとは別の店）とする説もあり、はっきりしない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While it is widely accepted that its origin was Toyo in Yamashina, which is already closed, the origin is not clear as there is another possibility that the origin was Oike-ramen, which was a street stall open near Kyoto station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While it is widely accepted that its origin was Toyo in Yamashina, which is already closed, the origin is not clear as there is another possibility that its origin lies in Oike-ramen, which was a street stall near Kyoto station.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While it is widely accepted that its origin was Toyo in Yamashina, which is already closed, the origin is not clear as there is another possibility that its origin lies in Oike-ramen, which was a street stall near Kyoto station (it is different from present Oike-ramen Samata).</e>
<cmt>&quot;（現在の御池ラーメンさまたとは別の店）&quot;を訳出</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>名門、悟空、天天有などがこの系統に属する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meimon, Goku, Tentenyu, and others belong to this type.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meimon, Goku, Tentenyu, and others belong to this type.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meimon, Goku, Tentenyu, and others belong to this type.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>また、天下一品（こってり）はこの系統の発展系と考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Thick type&quot; of Tenka-ippin is believed to have been developed from this type.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;thick type&quot; of Tenka-ippin is believed to have been developed from this type.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &quot;thick type&quot; of Tenka-ippin is believed to have been developed from this type.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="29">
<j>あっさり系、こってり系の呼称については、天下一品が自店の鶏ガラ白湯をこってり、鶏ガラ清湯をあっさりとメニューに記載したことから始まる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Use of the terms of plain type and thick type started when Tenka-ippin put the chicken bone broth based white broth as the &quot;thick type&quot; and the chicken bone broth based clear broth as &quot;plain type&quot; on a menu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Use of the terms of plain and thick type started with Tenka-ippin, when they referred to the chicken bone broth based white broth as the &quot;thick type&quot; and the chicken bone broth based clear broth as &quot;plain type&quot; on their menu.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Use of the terms of plain and thick type started with Tenka-ippin, when they referred to the chicken bone broth based white broth as the &quot;thick type&quot; and the chicken bone broth based clear broth as the &quot;plain type&quot; on their menu.</e>
<cmt>the &quot;thick type&quot;と同様、&quot;plain type&quot;の前にtheを追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>現在では、鶏ガラに限らず清湯系をあっさり、白湯系をこってりと呼ぶのが京都では一般的である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nowadays, it is common in Kyoto to call clear broth &quot;plain type&quot; and white broth &quot;thick type,&quot; regardless of Chicken bone broth or not.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nowadays, it is common in Kyoto to call the clear broth &quot;plain type&quot; and the white broth the &quot;thick type,&quot; regardless of whether it is chicken bone broth or not.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nowadays, it is common in Kyoto to call the clear broth the &quot;plain type&quot; and the white broth the &quot;thick type,&quot; regardless of whether it is chicken bone broth or not.</e>
<cmt>the &quot;thick type&quot;と同様、&quot;plain type&quot;の前にtheを追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>ただし、背脂醤油系のことをこってりと呼ぶ人も多く、それほど厳密に使われている訳ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, many people still call the soy sauce with backfat type &quot;thick type&quot;, and the definition is not very strict.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, its meaning is not concerete as many people still call the soy sauce with backfat type &quot;thick type.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, its meaning is not concerete as many people still call the soy sauce with backfat type the &quot;thick type.&quot;</e>
<cmt>&quot;thick type&quot;の前にtheを追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="32">
<j>何れの系統も昆布（あるいは化学調味料）や野菜などを副材料として加える場合が多いが、魚介類出汁を使う店はほとんど無い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sub ingredients such as kelp (or chemical condiments) and vegetables are seafood broth often added to any type of the soup, but few stores use seafood broth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While ingredients such as kelp (or chemical condiments) and vegetables are added as sub ingredients to all types of soup, very few stores use seafood broth.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While ingredients such as kelp (or chemical condiments) and vegetables are added as sub ingredients to all types of soup, very few stores use seafood broth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="33">
<j>これは京都が地理的な条件により、昔から生鮮海産物を食べる習慣があまりなく、海産物の生臭さに非常に敏感なためと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is because people in Kyoto are very sensitive to a fishy smell of seafoods, as they have not had a custom to eat fresh seafoods due to the geographical conditions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is due to the fact that the people of Kyoto are especially sensitive to the fishy smell of seafood, and are not accustomed to eating seafood mainly because of their geographical conditions.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is due to the fact that the people of Kyoto are especially sensitive to the fishy smell of seafood, and are not accustomed to eating seafood mainly because of their geographical conditions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="34">
<j>スープの味付け（ラーメンダレ）は、何れも醤油が主流だが、最近は塩を売りにする店も増えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the main stream of the soup seasonings (ramen condiments) of any type is soy sauce, an increasing number of stores feature salt.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although soup is mainly season seasoned with soy sauce, an increasing number of stores also feature salt.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although soup is mainly season seasoned with soy sauce, an increasing number of stores also feature salt.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース消去</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>他地域では一般的な、味噌を売りにする店はほとんどない（味噌ラーメンがメニューにあるラーメン店は京都でも少なくないが、通常は添え物的な扱いである）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Very few stores feature soy bean paste, which is popular in other areas (though soy bean paste ramen is put on a menu in many stores in Kyoto, it is usually treated as an appendage).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Very few stores feature soy bean paste, which is popular in other areas (though soy bean paste ramen is available on menus in many stores in Kyoto, but is often available as an extra)</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Very few stores feature soy bean paste, which is popular in other areas (although soy bean paste ramen is available on menus in many stores in Kyoto, but is often available as an extra).</e>
<cmt>ピリオド追加 &quot;though&quot; -&gt; &quot;although&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>これに関しては、京都がもともと、いわゆる「味噌文化圏」ではないためではないか、といわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is assumedly because Kyoto has not been a so-called &quot;soy bean paste culture region.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is most likely due to the fact that Kyoto was never a so-called &quot;soy bean paste culture region.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is most likely due to the fact that Kyoto was never a so-called &apos;soy bean paste culture region.&apos;</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="37">
<j>その他、これら以外のスープを提供する店も存在するが（博多風の豚骨ラーメンや、東京風の醤油ラーメンなどの他、極めて少数だが、どの分類にも当てはまらない独自のラーメンを出す店もある）、数は少ない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are stores that serve soup of other tastes (pork bone broth of Hakata type, soy sauce soup of Tokyo type, and very few stores serve original ramen that does not belong to any category), but its number is small.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are stores that serve different kinds of soup (Hakata pork bone broth,Tokyo soy sauce soup, with a few stores serving original ramen that does not belong to any category), but their numbers are small.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are stores that serve different kinds of soup (Hakata pork bone broth, Tokyo soy sauce soup, with a few stores serving original ramen that does not belong to any category), but their numbers are small.</e>
<cmt>スペース追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="38">
<j>また、上記のように、中華料理店などで出される汎用鶏ガラスープを使った、いわゆる「中華そば」をメニューに取り入れている店もあるが、その場合、他地域とは違い、別にラーメンというものが存在し、そちらが中心に添えられていることがほとんどであり、いわゆる「中華そば」を売りにしているラーメン専門店は、ほとんど存在しない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As described above, some stores put so-called &quot;Chinese noodle&quot; using the chicken bone broth for general use as served in a Chinese restaurant or the like on a menu, in which case, unlike in other areas, ramen is put on the menu separately and focused more; very few store features the so-called &quot;Chinese noodle.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As described above, some stores feature the so-called &quot;Chinese noodles&quot; and use general chicken bone broth as served in a Chinese restaurant or the like on their menu, in which case, unlike in other areas, the ramen is placed on a separate menu; very few stores feature the so-called &quot;Chinese noodle.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As described above, some stores feature the so-called &apos;Chinese noodles&apos; and use general chicken bone broth as served in a Chinese restaurant or the like on their menu, in which case, unlike in other areas, the ramen is placed on a separate menu; very few stores feature the so-called &apos;Chinese noodle.&apos;</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>もっとも、京都でもラーメン専門店ではなく、中華料理店の場合は、いわゆる「中華そば」を中心にしている店が大半である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nevertheless, even in Kyoto, besides stores specializing in ramen, most of Chinese restaurants feature the so-called &quot;Chinese noodle.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nevertheless, even in Kyoto, most Chinese restarants feature the so-called &quot;Chinese noodle,&quot; besides those stores that specialize in ramen.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nevertheless, even in Kyoto, most Chinese restarants feature the so-called &apos;Chinese noodle,&apos; besides those stores that specialize in ramen.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>薬味</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seasoning</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seasoning</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seasoning</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="40">
<j>定番のコショウの他、一味唐辛子、ごま、おろしニンニク、にんにくチップ、ニントン（ニンニク唐辛子）、ラーメンダレ、酢、豆板醤などの唐辛子味噌、ニラ漬け、各種キムチなどの薬味が一般的である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to pepper as the standard, ground red pepper, sesame, grated garlic, garlic chips, garlic pepper, ramen condiments, vinegar, bean paste with red pepper such as tobanchan, green chive pickles, and various types of Kimchi are popular as the seasonings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to the typical pepper seasoning, ground red pepper, sesame, grated garlic, garlic chips, garlic pepper, ramen condiments, vinegar, bean paste with red pepper such as tobanchan, green chive pickles, and various types of Kimchi are popular as seasonings.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to the typical pepper seasoning, ground red pepper, sesame, grated garlic, garlic chips, garlic pepper, ramen condiments, vinegar, bean paste with red pepper such as tobanchan, green chive pickles, and various types of Kimchi are popular as seasonings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>大抵の店では、前記の内、数種類を常備しており、薬味の豊富さも京都ラーメンの特徴の一つと言える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most stores keep several of the above, and the variety of the seasonings may be one of the features of Kyoto ramen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most stores keep several of the above, and the variety of seasonings available may be considered one of the features of Kyoto ramen.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most stores keep several of the above, and the variety of seasonings available may be considered one of the features of Kyoto ramen.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース消去</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="42">
<j>2008年3月現在、京都でのラーメンの並は600円前後。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As of March 2008, the average price of ramen is around 600 yen in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As of March 2008, the average price of ramen is around 600 yen in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As of March 2008, the average price of ramen is around 600 yen in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>650円を超えると高いといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They say it is expensive if the price exceeds 650 yen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said to be expensive if the price exceeds 650 yen.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said to be expensive if the price exceeds 650 yen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>ただし、小麦の高騰や原油高の影響などもあり、値上げする店が増えている（値上げ幅は50円前後が多い）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, due to an effect of sharp rise of wheat price and high price of crude oil, increasing number of stores rise the ramen price (the markup is about 50 yen in most stores).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, due to a sharp rise in the price of wheat and the high price of crude oil, an increasing number of stores have raised ramen prices (a markup of about 50 yen in most stores).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, due to a sharp rise in the price of wheat and the high price of crude oil, an increasing number of stores have raised ramen prices (a markup of about 50 yen in most stores).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="45">
<j>顧客集中地の競合店密度の高さや保守傾向（固定客だけでなく流動客にも根強く見受けられる贔屓性向とも言い替えられる）から、相当な個性を全面に出すか、逆に価格面で勝負を挑まざるをえないことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to high density of competitors in customer-concentrated areas and conservative tendency (which can be rephrased by patronizing tendency strongly seen not only in regular customers but also in floating customers), they have either to highlight their uniqueness or to challenge in the field of pricing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to the high density of competitors in area with a high concentration of customers and a conservative tendency (which can be rephrased by patronizing tendency strongly seen not only in regular customers but also in floating customers), they are forced to either highlight their uniqueness or be competitive in terms of pricing.</e>
<cmt>Robert: (which can be rephrased by patronizing tendency strongly seen not only in regular customers but also in floating customers) makes absolutely no sense.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to the high density of competitors in area with a high concentration of customers and a &quot;conservative tendency&quot; (which can be rephrased as a &quot;patronizing tendency&quot; strongly seen not only in regular customers but also in floating customers), they are forced to either highlight their uniqueness or be competitive in terms of pricing.</e>
<cmt>rephrased by→rephrased asとし、言い換えの対象になっているconservative tendencyとpatronizing tendencyにクォーテーションをつけ、&quot;patronizing tendency&quot;の前に&quot;a&quot;を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>そのため他府県のラーメン店が京都に進出した際に事情を把握せず価格設定し、客が付かず閉店した例も少なくなく、政令指定都市を核に構える人口の割に、シビアといえる（京都における、この種の傾向は、ラーメンだけではなく多岐の商品、サービスに渡る）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this reason, quite a number of ramen stores from other prefectures penetrated into Kyoto closed the business there because they set prices without knowing the circumstances and were not able to gain regular customers, which proves the business is severe for the popularity of the area that includes a government-ordinance-designated city (such a tendency in Kyoto is seen not only in ramen business but also in wide range of articles and services).</e>
<cmt>government-ordinance-designated city [英辞郎 on the WEB ]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this reason, quite a number of ramen stores from other prefectures which penetrated Kyoto failed, bcause they set price-points without conducting market research or were unable to retain regular customers, reinforcing the point that business is difficult despite the population of the area which includes a government-orginance-designated city (this is seen not only in the ramen business, but a wide range of articles and services as well.)</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow. Translation horrible. May want to recompare against Japanese.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For this reason, quite a number of ramen stores from other prefectures which penetrated Kyoto failed, because they set price-points without conducting market research or were unable to retain regular customers, reinforcing the point that business is difficult despite the population of the area which includes a government-orginance-designated city (this is seen not only in the ramen business, but a wide range of articles and services as well).</e>
<cmt>becauseのスペルミス修正、ピリオドの位置を移動</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>主なラーメン店</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Major Ramen Stores</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Major Ramen Stores</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Major Ramen Stores</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="47">
<j>ここではラーメン専門店を中心に紹介する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Stores specializing in ramen are introduced below.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Stores specializing in ramen are introduced below.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Stores specializing in ramen are introduced below.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="48">
<j>人気、行列に関しては、2008年現在の状況。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for the popularity and line-up, the status as of 2008 is referenced.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for the popularity and line-up, information from 2008 is used as a reference.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for the popularity and line-up, information from 2008 is used as a reference.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>チェーンストア店</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chain stores</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chain stores</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chain stores</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="49">
<j>第一旭</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daiichi-Asahi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daiichi-Asahi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daiichi-Asahi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="50">
<j>1953年創業（当初は「旭食堂」という大衆食堂だった。店名を現在の「第一旭」に変更しラーメン専門店になったのは1956年）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Established in 1953 (It was originally a cheap restaurant, &quot;Asahi restaurant.&quot; It was 1956 when it became specializing in ramen with its name changed to the present name &quot;Daiichi-Asahi&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Established in 1953 (It was originally a cheap restaurant, &quot;Asahi restaurant.&quot; In 1956 it started to specialize in ramen, and changed its name to the present &quot;Daiichi-Asahi&quot;).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Established in 1953 (It was originally a cheap restaurant, &apos;Asahi restaurant.&apos; In 1956 it started to specialize in ramen, and changed its name to the present &apos;Daiichi-Asahi&apos;).</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更、余分なスペース消去</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>いわゆる、あっさり系の代表格。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A representative of the so-called plain type.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A representative of the so-called plain type.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A representative of the so-called plain type.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>もっとも、オーソドックスな京都ラーメンと言う人も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nevertheless, many people call it orthodox Kyoto ramen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nevertheless, many people call it orthodox Kyoto ramen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nevertheless, many people call it orthodox Kyoto ramen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>京都駅そばの高倉陸橋本店は午前5時から営業し、閉店は深夜2時である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takakura Rikkyo main store near Kyoto station opens at 5:00 am and closes at 2:00 am.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Takakura Rikkyo main store near Kyoto station opens at 5:00 am and closes at 2:00 am.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Takakura Rikkyo main store near Kyoto station opens at 5:00 am and closes at 2:00 am.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>いわゆるご飯時だけでなく、早朝や深夜でも行列が出来ることは珍しくない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is not unusual that a line-up is seen not only in a so-called meal time but also early in the morning or at midnight.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is not unusual for lines to occur not only during peak meal times, but also early in the morning or late at night.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is not unusual for lines to occur not only during peak meal times, but also early in the morning or late at night.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>現在、直営店は、南インター店、亀岡店の2店のみで、本店、城陽寺田店は直営ブランドの独立採算店、それ以外はFC店である（その他、「第一旭」とは別に、「たかばし」というブランドも有しており、直営で別展開している）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this moment, only two of South-Interchange store and Kameoka store are directly-managed stores, the main store and Joyo-terada store are financially independent stores of the directly-managed brand, and others are franchise stores (besides &quot;Daiichi-Asahi,&quot; another brand called &quot;Takabashi&quot; is also owned, and directly managed separately).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this moment, only the South-Interchange and Kameoka store are directly-managed stores, the main store and Joyo-terada store are financially independent stores of a directly-managed brand, while others are franchise stores (besides &quot;Daiichi-Asahi,&quot; another brand called &quot;Takabashi&quot; is also owned, and directly managed separately).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this moment, only the South-Interchange store and Kameoka store are directly-managed stores, the main store and Joyo-terada store are financially independent stores of a directly-managed brand, while others are franchise stores (besides &apos;Daiichi-Asahi,&apos; another brand called &apos;Takabashi&apos; is also owned, and directly managed separately).</e>
<cmt>South-Interchange storeとし、シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>そのため、本店、城陽寺田店は、厳密にはチェーン店には含まれない（よって、厳密に言えば、本店は旧本店になるのだが、「第一旭」では、1号店であるとの意味も含めて、そのまま本店の呼称を使っている。現在チェーン店の体制として、いわゆる本店機能を有しているのは、南インター店である）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Accordingly, the main store and Joyo-terada store are strictly not included in the chain stores (Therefore, strictly speaking, the main store should be the old main store, but &quot;Daiichi-Asahi&quot; uses the name of the main store as it is, with a meaning of the first store. In the current system of the chain stores, it is South-Interchange store that functions as the main store).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Accordingly, the main store and Joyo-terada store are not included in the chain stores (Therefore, strictly speaking, the main store should be the old main store, but &quot;Daiichi-Asahi&quot; uses the name of the main store as it is to mean the first store. In the current system of chain stores, it is the South-Interchange store that functions as the main store).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Accordingly, the main store and Joyo-terada store are not included in the chain stores (Therefore, strictly speaking, the main store should be the old main store, but &apos;Daiichi-Asahi&apos; uses the name of the main store as it is to mean the first store. In the current system of chain stores, it is the South-Interchange store that functions as the main store).</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>FC店は質にかなりバラツキがあり、「第一旭」に対する評価に幅があるのはそのためと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The quality varies among the franchise stores, which is considered to be the reason why reputations of &quot;Daiichi-Asahi&quot; widely vary.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The quality varies among franchise stores, which is considered to be the reason why the reputation of &quot;Daiichi-Asahi&quot; widely vary.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The quality varies among franchise stores, which is considered to be the reason why the reputation of &apos;Daiichi-Asahi&apos; widely varies.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更、vary→variesに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>また、過去の様々な経緯により、本店の許可を得ずに「第一旭」を名乗っている店も少なからず存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, doe to what happened in the past, quite a number of stores use the name of &quot;Daiichi-Asahi&quot; without permission by the main store.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, due to its past, quite a number of stores use the name &quot;Daiichi-Asahi&quot; without permission from the main store.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, due to its past, quite a number of stores use the name &apos;Daiichi-Asahi&apos; without permission from the main store.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>現在、正式に「第一旭」を名乗ることを許可されているのは、「第一旭」の公式サイトに紹介されている店舗のみである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Stores officially allowed to use the name of &quot;Daiichi-Asahi&quot; are only those introduced in an official website of &quot;Daiichi-Asahi.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Only stores officially allowed to use the name &quot;Daiichi-Asahi&quot; are introduced in an official website of &quot;Daiichi-Asahi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Only stores officially allowed to use the name &apos;Daiichi-Asahi&apos; are introduced in an official website of &apos;Daiichi-Asahi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="60">
<j>新福菜館</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinpuku-saikan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinpuku-saikan</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinpuku-saikan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="61">
<j>1938年創業（当初は屋台。店舗営業は1947年より）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Established in 1938 (Originally a street stall. Established as a store in 1947).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Established in 1938 (Originally a street stall. Started buiness as a store in 1947).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Established in 1938 (Originally a street stall. Started buiness as a store in 1947).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>京都ではもっとも古いラーメン屋の1つで、京都ラーメンの一大源流とも言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinpuku-saikan is one of the oldest ramen stores in Kyoto, and called a big origin of Kyoto ramen</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinpuku-saikan is one of the oldest ramen stores in Kyoto, and is considered a progenitor of Kyoto ramen</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinpuku-saikan is one of the oldest ramen stores in Kyoto, and is considered a progenitor of Kyoto ramen.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>全国的に見ても、現存するラーメン店の中ではかなり古い部類に属する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It belongs a considerably old group among existing ramen stores all over the country.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It belongs to a considerably old group of existing ramen stores all over the country.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It belongs to a considerably old group of existing ramen stores all over the country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>スープはあっさり系の醤油味の清湯スープだが、醤油ダレに煮豚を作ったあとに残る煮汁が加えられているため、スープの色は非常に黒くて、香ばしく、そして、独特の苦味がある（この苦味ゆえに、好き嫌いは結構分かれる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although they use clear soup of soy sauce of the plain type, because liquor of boiled pork is added to the soy-sauce condiments, the soup is dark in the color and fragrant, with unique bitter (it is love it or hate it due to the bitter).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although they use a plain, clear soy sauce soup, the soup is dark in colar and fragrant with a unique bitterness (opinions often split over this taste) due to a boiled pork liquor which is added as a soy-sauce condiment.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although they use a plain, clear soy sauce soup, the soup is dark in colar and fragrant with a unique bitterness (opinions often split over this taste) due to a boiled pork liquor which is added as a soy-sauce condiment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>しかし、見かけと違い、味は意外とあっさりしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, unlike what it looks, the taste is quite plain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, quite contrary to its looks, its taste is quite plain.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, quite contrary to its looks, its taste is quite plain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>本店は京都駅そばの高倉陸橋の「第一旭」本店の隣で、こちらも営業開始は午前7時半と早い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The main store is next to the main store of &quot;Daiichi-Asahi&quot; at Takakura Rikkyo, and it also opens so early as 7:30 am.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The main store is next to the main store for &quot;Daiichi-Asahi&quot; at Takakura Rikkyo, and also opens as early as 7:30 am.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The main store is next to the main store for &apos;Daiichi-Asahi&apos; at Takakura Rikkyo, and also opens as early as 7:30 am.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>もちろん、こちらも行列が出来ることは珍しくない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Of course it is not unusual to see a line-up in front of this store.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is not unusual to see a line in front of this store as well.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is not unusual to see a line in front of this store as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>支店は京都府下だけではなく、他府県にもあるが、直営店は本店と府立医大前店のみである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although there are branches not only in Kyoto Prefecture but also in other prefectures, directly-managed stores are only the main store and Furitsu-Idai-mae store.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although there are branches outside of Kyoto Prefecture, the only directly-managed stores are the main and Furitsu-Idai-mae store.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although there are branches outside of Kyoto Prefecture, the only directly-managed stores are the main and Furitsu-Idai-mae store.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース消去</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="69">
<j>天下一品</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tenka-ippin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tenka-ippin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tenka-ippin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="70">
<j>1971年創業（当初は屋台。店舗営業は1974年より）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Established in 1971 (Originally a street stall. Established as a store in 1974).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Established in 1971 (Originally a street stall. Established as a store in 1974).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Established in 1971 (Originally a street stall. Established as a store in 1974).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>ラーメンは、前述のように、鶏と野菜を煮込んで作られた濃厚なドロドロのスープの「こってり」、中華そば風の鶏ガラ清湯の「あっさり」の2種類がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are two types of ramen as described above, &quot;thick type&quot; using thick soup prepared by boiling chicken and vegetables, and &quot;plain type&quot; using clear chicken bone broth, and &quot;Ten-ichi&quot; usually refers to the &quot;thick type.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are two types of ramen as described above, a &quot;thick type&quot; which uses a thick soup prepared by boiling chicken and vegetables, and a &quot;plain type&quot; which uses a clear chicken bone broth.&quot;Ten-ichi&quot; usually specializes in the &quot;thick type.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are two types of ramen as described above, a &apos;thick type&apos; which uses a thick soup prepared by boiling chicken and vegetables, and a &apos;plain type&apos; which uses a clear chicken bone broth.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>普通、「天一」と言えば、「こってり」のことを指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ten-ichi&apos; usually specializes in the &apos;thick type.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>「天一」の「こってり」はラーメンと言うより独自の食べ物という人もいるが、歴史的な流れや、味の形成過程を見る限り、旧来の京都ラーメンのこってり系の発展系と考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some people say the &quot;thick type&quot; of &quot;Ten-ichi&quot; is one of a dish rather than ramen, but it can be considered to be an evolved from the thick type of the conventional Kyoto ramen in consideration of the historical background and the formation process of the taste.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some people say the &quot;thick type&quot; for &quot;Ten-ichi&quot; is more a unique dish rather than ramen, but it can be considered to be have evolved from the thick type of conventional Kyoto ramen considering the historical background and the way in which the taste was formed.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some people say the &apos;thick type&apos; for &apos;Ten-ichi&apos; is more a unique dish rather than ramen, but it can be considered to be have evolved from the thick type of conventional Kyoto ramen considering the historical background and the way in which the taste was formed.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>最近、縮れ麺が加わり、元々のストレート麺との2種類の麺から好きな方を選択できるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wavy noodle was introduced recently, and now there are two options of the existing straight noodle and the wavy noodle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wavy noodles were introduced recently, and now there are two options: the existing straight noodle or the wavy noodle.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wavy noodles were introduced recently, and now there are two options: the existing straight noodle or the wavy noodle.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース消去</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>「味がさね」という自分で濃度を調整できる味噌ラーメンもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They also serve &quot;added flavor,&quot; soy beans paste ramen that a customer can adjust the density by himself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They also provide &quot;added flavor,&quot; a soy bean paste ramen which allows a customer to adjust the density by themselves.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They also provide &apos;added flavor,&apos; a soy bean paste ramen which allows a customer to adjust the density by themselves.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>京都のラーメン店では、唯一、全国展開に成功している（ハワイにも支店を持つ）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The only one ramen store in Kyoto which successfully expanded in Japan (There is also a branch in Hawaii).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The only one ramen store in Kyoto which successfully expanded in Japan (There is also a branch in Hawaii).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The only one ramen store in Kyoto which successfully expanded in Japan (There is also a branch in Hawaii).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>現在の店舗数は約200店で、ラーメンチェーン店としては、全国的に見てもかなり大きな部類に入る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Having about 200 stores at this point, Tenka-ippin is one of large-scale ramen chain stores all over the country.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With about 200 stores, Tenka-ippin is one of the larger-scale ramen chain stores in the country.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With about 200 stores, Tenka-ippin is one of the larger-scale ramen chain stores in the country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>セントラルキッチン制を取る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Central kitchen system is employed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A central kitchen system is employed.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A central kitchen system is employed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>本店は左京区北白川。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The main store is located in Kita-Shirakawa Sakyo Ward.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The main store is located in the Kita-Shirakawa Sakyo Ward.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The main store is located in the Kita-Shirakawa, Sakyo Ward.</e>
<cmt>カンマ追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="80">
<j>横綱 (ラーメン店)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yokozuna (Ramen store)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yokozuna (Ramen store)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yokozuna (Ramen store)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="81">
<j>1971年創業（当初は屋台。店舗営業は1977年より）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Established in 1971 (Originally a street stall. Established as a store in 1977).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Established in 1971 (Originally a street stall. Established as a store in 1977).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Established in 1971 (Originally a street stall. Established as a store in 1977).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>一時期、京都で流行った豚骨醤油ラーメンを出す店の数少ない生き残り。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of a few survivors of pork bone broth soy sauce ramen store that was once popular in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of a few survivors of pork bone broth soy sauce ramen stores that were once popular in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of a few survivors of pork bone broth soy sauce ramen stores that were once popular in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>ただ、豚骨スープと言っても鶏ガラをミックスしており、 博多ラーメン（あるいは 長浜ラーメン）と違い、甘くてとろみの強い独特のスープで、こってり系の派生系と考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although it is called pork bone broth soy sauce, unlike Hakata ramen (or Nagahama ramen), being distinct sweet and thick soup mixed with chicken bone, it is considered a derivative from the thick type.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although it is called pork bone broth soy sauce, unlike Hakata ramen (or Nagahama ramen), it is considered a derivative of the thick type owing to its distinct sweet and thick soup which is mixed with chicken bone.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it is called pork bone broth soy sauce, unlike Hakata ramen (or Nagahama ramen), it is considered a derivative of the thick type owing to its distinct sweet and thick soup which is mixed with chicken bone.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>九条ネギが巨大なプラスティックケースで（以前は金ザルだった）、テーブルにおかれ、自由に入れ放題である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Leek from Kujo is placed in a huge plastic case (used to be a metallic colander) on a table, which you can eat as much as you want.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Leek from Kujo is placed in a huge plastic case (used to be a metallic colander) on a table, which is available on an all-you-can eat basis.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Leek from Kujo is placed in a huge plastic case (used to be a metallic colander) on a table, which is available on an all-you-can eat basis.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>店舗はこの数年間で全店舗を改装。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">All stores have been renovated in the last few years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">All stores have been renovated in the last few years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">All stores have been renovated in the last few years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>京都のラーメンチェーン店の中では、ずば抜けて明るく、清潔感があり、女性・子供連れを最も意識した店構えである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The appearance of the stores is outstandingly bright and clean among ramen chain stores in Kyoto, mainly targeting women and families with children.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The appearance of the stores is outstandingly bright and clean among ramen chain stores in Kyoto, and mainly target women and families with children.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The appearance of the stores is outstandingly bright and clean among ramen chain stores in Kyoto, and mainly target women and families with children.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>さらに、このリニューアルに併せて、味の方も若干変更され、以前より幾分マイルドになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In parallel with the renewal, the taste was slightly changed to be somewhat milder than before.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Together with the renewal, the taste was slightly changed to be somewhat milder than before.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Together with the renewal, the taste was slightly changed to be somewhat milder than before.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>ただし、この味の変更は古くからのファンには受けが悪く、賛否両論である（食べやすくなったという女性も多い）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the change of the taste is not welcomed by old fans, and divided between pros and cons (Many women say it became easier to eat).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the change of taste was not welcomed by old fans, and opinions became divided (Many women say it became easier to eat).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the change of taste was not welcomed by old fans, and opinions became divided (Many women say it became easier to eat).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>甘みの強いスープなので、備え付けの「うまみ唐がらし」で好みの味にして食べる人が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because the soup is sweet, many people seasons it with complimentary &quot;flavor pepper&quot; to make his favorite taste.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because the soup is sweet, many people season it with a complimentary &quot;flavored pepper&quot; to suit their tastes.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because the soup is sweet, many people season it with a complimentary &apos;flavored pepper&apos; to suit their tastes.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>「うまみ唐がらし」は、いわゆる「ニントン」（ニンニク唐辛子）風の調味料だが、ニンニクは入っていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The &quot;flavor pepper&quot; is a seasoning similar to so-called &quot;garlic pepper,&quot; but it does not include any garlic.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;flavor pepper&quot; is a seasoning similar to the so-called &quot;garlic pepper,&quot; but it does not include any garlic.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &apos;flavor pepper&apos; is a seasoning similar to the so-called &apos;garlic pepper,&apos; but it does not include any garlic.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>勘違いしている人が多いためか、現在は「ニンニクは入ってませんので、匂いを気にせず、お食べ下さい」の但し書きが付けられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Probably because many people take it in a wrong way, there is now a note saying &quot;Please do not mind the smell because no garlic is used.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most likely due to confusion, there is now a note saying &quot;Please do not mind the smell because no garlic is used.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most likely due to confusion, there is now a note saying &apos;Please do not mind the smell because no garlic is used.&apos;</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>「天下一品」の全国制覇には及ばないが、かなり広域にチェーン展開し、成功している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although less than the nationwide coverage of &quot;Tenka-ippin,&quot; Yokozuna is quite successful with its chain stores in a pretty large area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although less prevalent than &quot;Tenka-ippin&quot; in terms of its coverage across Japan, Yokozuna is quite successful and has numerous chain stores spread across a wide area.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although less prevalent than &apos;Tenka-ippin&apos; in terms of its coverage across Japan, Yokozuna is quite successful and has numerous chain stores spread across a wide area.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>また、京都のラーメン店で、最初にセントラルキッチン制を導入した店でもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also the first ramen store in Kyoto that introduced the central kitchen system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also the first ramen store in Kyoto to have introduced the central kitchen system.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also the first ramen store in Kyoto to have introduced the central kitchen system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>旧本店である、吉祥院店が1号店（現在は、特定の店舗を本店とは位置づけていない）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kisshoin store, which used to be the main store, is the first store (Currently, not a specific store is positioned as the main store).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kisshoin store is the first store and used to be the first store (Currently, there is no specific store designated as the main store.).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kisshoin store is the first store and used to be the main store (Currently, there is no specific store designated as the main store).</e>
<cmt>used to be the first store→used to be the main storeに修正、余分なピリオド削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="95">
<j>悟空</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Goku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Goku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Goku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="96">
<j>スープはこってり系。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The soup is the thick type.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Goku uses a thick type soup.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Goku uses a thick type soup.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>ここも九条ネギがザルでテーブルにおかれ、自由に入れ放題である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Leek from Kujo is placed in a colander on a table, which you can eat as much as you want.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">All-you-can-eat Leek from Kujo is placed in a colander on a table.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">All-you-can-eat Leek from Kujo is placed in a colander on a table.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>中華麺の代わりにパスタを使ったラーメンや、化学調味料不使用のラーメンなどがあり、独特のこだわりがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under a unique belief, they serve ramen using pasta instead of Chinese noodle, and ramen without any chemical condiments.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A unique characteristic of this store is their insistence on serving ramen using pasta instead of Chinese noodles, and ramen without any chemical condiments.</e>
<cmt>Grammar/Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A unique characteristic of this store is their insistence on serving ramen using pasta instead of Chinese noodles, and ramen without any chemical condiments.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>2007年10月、経営上のトラブルなどがあり、本社が機能停止し、実質的に経営体制が崩壊した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In October 2007, the main store lost control of the management due to management trouble, and the management system virtually collapsed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In October 2007, the main store lost control of management due to management trouble, and the management system virtually collapsed.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In October 2007, the main store lost control of management due to management trouble, and the management system virtually collapsed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>2008年5月現在、独立採算店だった一部の店のみが営業を継続している状態である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As of May 2008, only a few of financially independent stores remain open.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As of May 2008, only a few financially independent stores remain open.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As of May 2008, only a few financially independent stores remain open.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="101">
<j>ラーメン藤</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ramen Fuji</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ramen Fuji</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ramen Fuji</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="102">
<j>1972年創業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Established in 1972.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Established in 1972.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Established in 1972.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>京都地区のラーメン店広くに麺を卸している近藤製麺プロデュースのお店。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Produced by Kondo noodle that widely sells noodle to ramen stores in Kyoto area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Produced by Kondo noodle, which provides noodles to a wide range of ramen stores in the Kyoto area.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Produced by Kondo noodle, which provides noodles to a wide range of ramen stores in the Kyoto area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>以前は、「第一旭」も近藤製麺の麺を使っており、両者はかなり緊密な関係にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the past, &quot;Daiichi-Asahi&quot; also used Kondo&apos;s noodle, and these two were in a very close relationship.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the past, &quot;Daiichi-Asahi&quot; also used Kondo&apos;s noodles, and these two had a very close relationship.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the past, &apos;Daiichi-Asahi&apos; also used Kondo&apos;s noodles, and these two had a very close relationship.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>そのためか、味は「第一旭」に似ており、スープはあっさり系。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For the closeness or not, the taste is similar to that of &quot;Daiichi-Asahi,&quot; and the soup is the plain type.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But close or not, the taste is similar to that of &quot;Daiichi-Asahi,&quot; and uses a plain type soup.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But close or not, the taste is similar to that of &apos;Daiichi-Asahi,&apos; and uses a plain type soup.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>本店は、南区 (京都市)烏丸久世橋。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The main store is located in Karasuma Kuzebashi, Minami Ward (Kyoto City).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The main store is located in Karasuma Kuzebashi, Minami Ward (Kyoto City).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The main store is located in Karasuma Kuzebashi, Minami Ward (Kyoto City).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>「第一旭」に似ているためか、今一つ目立った存在ではないが、店舗数は意外と多く、実は横綱や第一旭の店舗数を上回っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fuji is not very outstanding probably because it is similar to &quot;Daiichi-Asahi,&quot; but the number of the stores is rather large, in fact exceeding that of Yokozuna or Daiichi-Asahi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fuji is not very outstanding probably because it is similar to &quot;Daiichi-Asahi,&quot; but the number of the stores is rather large, exceeding that of Yokozuna or Daiichi-Asahi.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fuji is not very outstanding probably because it is similar to &apos;Daiichi-Asahi,&apos; but the number of the stores is rather large, exceeding that of Yokozuna or Daiichi-Asahi.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="108">
<j>名門</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meimon</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meimon</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meimon</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="109">
<j>こってり系。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thick type.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thick type.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thick type.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>山科西野の「東洋(ラーメン店)」（既に閉店）の流れを汲む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meimon is of the school of &quot;Toyo (ramen store)&quot; at Yamashina Nishino (already closed).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meimon is of the school of &quot;Toyo (ramen store)&quot; at Yamashina Nishino (already closed).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meimon is of the school of &apos;Toyo&apos; (ramen store) at Yamashina Nishino (already closed).</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更、位置を移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>九条ネギをザルに入れて出し、自由に入れるサービスは東洋が始めたものだと言われており、現在の名門でも同様のサービスが行われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said to be Toyo that started the service of placing leek from Kujo in a colander on a table for free use.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said tha Toyo started the tradition of placing leek from Kujo in a colander on a table on an all you can eat basis.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said tha Toyo started the tradition of placing leek from Kujo in a colander on a table on an all you can eat basis.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>現在は個々の店舗が独立運営しており、厳密にはチェーン店ではない（よって、本店も存在しない）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time, each of the stores runs business independently, and therefore they are not strictly chain stores (accordingly, there is no main store).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this time, each store runs their business independently, and therefore are not strictly considered to be chain stores (accordingly, there is no main store).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this time, each store runs their business independently, and therefore are not strictly considered to be chain stores (accordingly, there is no main store).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="113">
<j>1号店は「東洋」の跡地に有ったが、現在は閉店。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first store was located at the site of &quot;Toyo,&quot; but it is now closed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first store was located at the site of &quot;Toyo,&quot; but is now closed.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first store was located at the site of &apos;Toyo,&apos; but is now closed.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="114">
<j>来来亭</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mirai-tei</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mirai-tei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mirai-tei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="115">
<j>1997年創業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Established in 1997.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Established in 1997.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Established in 1997.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="116">
<j>滋賀県の野州店が本店で1号店とされているため、滋賀のラーメン店と思いこんでいる人が多いが、元々は京都発祥。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many people believe Mirai-tei came from Shiga because Yasu store in Shiga Prefecture is the main store and the first store, but its birthplace is Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many people believe Mirai-tei came from Shiga because the Yasu store in Shiga Prefecture is the main and first store, but it originated in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>Grammar/Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many people believe Mirai-tei came from Shiga because the Yasu store in Shiga Prefecture is the main and first store, but it originated in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="117">
<j>ただし、本当の1号店（深草にあった）は経営がうまく行かず閉店したため、公式記録ではなかったことにされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, because the real first store (used to be in Fukakusa) was closed due to bad business, its existence was deleted from an official record.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, because the first real store (used to be in Fukakusa) closed due to bad business, and its existence was removed from the official record.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, because the first real store (used to be in Fukakusa) closed due to bad business, and its existence was removed from the official record.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="118">
<j>あまり知られてないが、創業者は「ほそかわ」の弟子である（つまり「ますたに」の孫弟子にあたる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although not well known, the founder is a disciple of &quot;Hosokawa&quot; (i.e., third generation of &quot;Masutani&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although not well known, the founder is a disciple of &quot;Hosokawa&quot; (i.e., third generation of &quot;Masutani&quot;).</e>
<cmt>Edited for spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although not well known, the founder is a disciple of &apos;Hosokawa&apos; (i.e., third generation of &apos;Masutani&apos;).</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="119">
<j>そのため、当然、スープは背脂醤油系である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, the soup is naturally the soy sauce with backfat type.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the soup is naturally made from soy sauce using backfat.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the soup is naturally made from soy sauce using backfat.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="120">
<j>現在、飛ぶ鳥を落とすほどの勢いで、チェーン展開を拡大しており、天下一品にはまだ及ばないが、すでに店舗数は100店を超えており、その勢いは留まる気配を見せない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mirai-tei is now blooming energetically as if taking down flying birds to open a far-reaching chain with more than 100 stores, though still less than Tenka-ippin, and its growth knows no limits.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mirai-tei is now rapidly expanding, with more than 100 stores. While still less than Tenka-ippin, its growth knows no limits.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mirai-tei is now rapidly expanding, with more than 100 stores; while still less than Tenka-ippin, its growth knows no limits.</e>
<cmt>二文に分かれているため、一文になるよう修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="121">
<j>宝屋</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takaraya</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takaraya</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takaraya</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="122">
<j>背脂醤油系。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soy sauce with backfat type.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soy sauce with backfat type.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soy sauce with backfat type.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="123">
<j>叉焼のうまさには定評があり、特に、限定メニューである「トロ肉チャーシューメン」の叉焼(トントロではない)は絶品との呼び声も高い（ただし、値段も高めではある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With a good reputation for the taste of roasted pork fillet, the roasted pork fillet in &quot;roasted fatty pork fillet noodle&quot; (not fatty part of pork) is highly recognized to be exquisite (though the price is high).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Having a solid reputation for the taste of its roasted pork fillet, the roasted pork fillet in &quot;roasted fatty pork fillet noodle&quot; (not the fatty part of pork) is recognized as being a delicacy (though the price is high).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Having a solid reputation for the taste of its roasted pork fillet, the roasted pork fillet in &apos;roasted fatty pork fillet noodle&apos; (not the fatty part of pork) is recognized as being a delicacy (although the price is high).</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更 &quot;though&quot; -&gt; &quot;although&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="124">
<j>京都駅ビルにあるラーメンテーマパーク「京都拉麺小路」に京都代表として出店している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takaraya joins a ramen theme park, &quot;Kyoto-Ramen-Koji&quot; in Kyoto Station Building as a representative from Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takaraya joined a ramen theme park, &quot;Kyoto-Ramen-Koji&quot; in Kyoto Station Building as a representative of Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>Grammar/flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takaraya joined a ramen theme park, &apos;Kyoto-Ramen-Koji&apos; in Kyoto Station Building as a representative of Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更、余分なスペース消去</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="125">
<j>チェーン店立ち上げ当初、かなりややこしい事情があったため、本店と呼べる店は存在しない（かいつまんで言うと、もともと本店だった店がチェーン店から離脱したのである）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to quite complicated situations at the start of the chain stores, there is not a virtual main store (In short, a store that used to be the main store withdrew from the chain.).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to complications during the start of its franchise, there is no virtual main store (basically, the store which used to be the main store withdrew from the chain.)</e>
<cmt>Grammar/flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to complications during the start of its franchise, there is no virtual main store (basically, the store which used to be the main store withdrew from the chain).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="126">
<j>現在の体制における1号店に当たる店は、西小路五条店。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first store in the current system is Nishikoji-Gojo store.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first store in the current system is the Nishikoji-Gojo store.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first store in the current system is the Nishikoji-Gojo store.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="127">
<j>大栄</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daiei</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daiei</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daiei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="128">
<j>あっさり系(旨味調味料無添加/但し醤油の旨味調味料は除く)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Plain type (flavor enhancing additive free, except for the flavor enhancing additive in soy sauce).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Plain type (free of flavor enhancing additives, except for some in the soy sauce).</e>
<cmt>Grammar/flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Plain type (free of flavor enhancing additives, except for some in the soy sauce).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="129">
<j>新福菜館の流れを汲む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daiei is of the school of Shinpuku-saikan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daiei is an offshoot of the Shinpuku-saikan school.</e>
<cmt>Grammar/flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daiei is an offshoot of the Shinpuku-saikan school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="130">
<j>しかし、味はどちらかと言えば、第一旭系である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the taste is rather closer to Daiichi-Asahi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, its taste is rather closer to Daiichi-Asahi.</e>
<cmt>Grammar/flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, its taste is rather closer to Daiichi-Asahi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="131">
<j>一時期はかなりの隆盛を誇り、多数の店舗を展開したが、その後、FC展開を止め、チェーン体制は崩壊した（この間の経緯に関しては諸説有るが、ここでは省略する）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daiei once enjoyed its prosperity opening a lot of stores, but it stopped franchising later to collapse the chain system (Although there are many view on how it collapsed, but the explanation is omitted here).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daiei was once prosperous with many stores, but later stopped franchising and the chain system collapsed (while there are many opionions on why this happened, those explanations will not be included here).</e>
<cmt>Grammar/flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daiei was once prosperous with many stores, but later stopped franchising and the chain system collapsed (while there are many opionions on why this happened, those explanations will not be included here).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="132">
<j>現在も、いくつかの店舗が「大栄」を名乗り、営業を続けているが、旧体制の「大栄」とは直接の関係はない（詳細は略するが、「大栄」の創始者が、これらの関わりから手を引いたためである）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some stores are still open under the name of &quot;Daiei,&quot; but they have nothing to do with the old &quot;Daiei&quot; (Although details are omitted, this is because the founder of &quot;Daiei&quot; withdrew from the business).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some stores are still open under the name of &quot;Daiei,&quot; but they have nothing to do with the old &quot;Daiei&quot; (Although details here are omitted, this is because the founder of &quot;Daiei&quot; withdrew from the business).</e>
<cmt>Grammar/flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some stores are still open under the name of &apos;Daiei,&apos; but they have nothing to do with the old &apos;Daiei&apos; (Although details here are omitted, this is because the founder of &apos;Daiei&apos; withdrew from the business).</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="133">
<j>現体制の「大栄」は基本的に独立採算であり、厳密な意味においてのチェーン店ではない（札辻店が本店を名乗るが、これも厳密な意味においてではない）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Existing &quot;Daiei&quot; are on a stand-alone basis and it is not a chain store in the strict meaning (Although Fudanotsuji store identifies itself as the main store, it is not in the strict meaning).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Existing &quot;Daiei&quot; stores today are on a stand-alone basis and are no longer a franchise (although the Fudanotsuji store identifies itself as the main store, this is not strictly the case.)</e>
<cmt>Grammar/flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Existing &apos;Daiei&apos; stores today are on a stand-alone basis and are no longer a franchise (although the Fudanotsuji store identifies itself as the main store, this is not strictly the case).</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更、ピリオドの位置を移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="134">
<j>現在も旧FC店及び、その流れを汲む店は数多くあり（「大輝」及び、その関連店、「ラーメン伸」など）、その影響は、現在の京都ラーメンを語る際に無視できない存在であることは間違いない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Old franchises and many other stores (e.g., &quot;Daiki&quot; and its affiliated store, &quot;Ramen Shin&quot;) are still of the school of &quot;Daiei&quot;, and there is no doubt that its influence cannot be disregarded when talking about the current situation of Kyoto ramen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Old franchises and many other stores (e.g., &quot;Daiki&quot; and its affiliated store, &quot;Ramen Shin&quot;) are still &quot;Daiei&quot; school, and there is no doubt that its influence cannot be disregarded when talking about the current situation of Kyoto ramen.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Old franchises and many other stores (e.g., &apos;Daiki&apos; and its affiliated store, &apos;Ramen Shin&apos;) are still &apos;Daiei&apos; school, and there is no doubt that its influence cannot be disregarded when talking about the current situation of Kyoto ramen.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>左京区一乗寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ichijoji, Sakyo Ward</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ichijoji, Sakyo Ward</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ichijoji, Sakyo Ward</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="135">
<j>多くの大学に囲まれた左京区一乗寺は関西最大のラーメン店集積地帯とされ、雑誌などで京都のラーメン激戦区として紹介されることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ichijoji, Sakyo Ward, surrounded by many colleges is regarded as the largest concentrated district of ramen stores in Kansai, and is often introduced in magazines as a ramen battleground in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ichijoji, Sakyo Ward, surrounded by many colleges is regarded as the largest concentrated district of ramen stores in Kansai, and is often introduced in magazines as a battleground of ramen stores in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ichijoji, Sakyo Ward, surrounded by many colleges is regarded as the largest concentrated district of ramen stores in Kansai, and is often introduced in magazines as a battleground of ramen stores in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="136">
<j>また、ラーメン街道と呼ばれることもある（ただし、実際には東大路通と北泉通の交差点を中心に店舗が点在しており、1つの通り沿いに店舗が連なっている訳ではない）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called Ramen route (However, stores are scattered about an intersection of Higashi-Oji and Kita-Izumi Streets, not located along a single street).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called Ramen route (However, stores are scattered about an intersection of Higashi-Oji and Kita-Izumi Streets, and not located along a single street).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called Ramen route (However, stores are scattered about an intersection of Higashioji-dori and Kitaizumi-dori Streets, and not located along a single street).</e>
<cmt>Higashi-Oji and Kita-Izumi Streets→Higashioji-dori and Kitaizumi-dori Streetsとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="137">
<j>高安 (ラーメン店)（たかやす）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takayasu (Ramen store)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takayasu (Ramen store)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takayasu (Ramen store)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="138">
<j>1999年創業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Established in 1999.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Established in 1999.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Established in 1999.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="139">
<j>こってり系。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thick type.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thick type.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thick type.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="140">
<j>限定メニューのすじ肉の煮込みが載るスジラーメンが特に人気。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fibrous meat ramen topped with fibrous meat stew, which is a limited menu, is especially popular.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their limited specialty, which is a fibrous meat ramen topped with a meat stew, is especially popular.</e>
<cmt>Gramma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Their limited specialty, which is a fibrous meat ramen topped with a meat stew, is especially popular.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="141">
<j>また、サイドメニューの巨大なカレー風味のから揚げも人気がある（食べきれなかった場合、持ち帰りも可能）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A huge curry flavor fried chicken, which is a side dish, is also very popular (remainder is available to go).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A huge curry flavor fried chicken, which is a side dish, is also very popular (remainders can be taken home).</e>
<cmt>Gramma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A huge curry flavor fried chicken, which is a side dish, is also very popular (remainders can be taken home).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="142">
<j>現在、京都で特に人気がある店の1つである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is one of the most popular ramen stores in Kyoto now.</e>
<cmt>訳出しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="143">
<j>天天有（てんてんゆう）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tentenyu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tentenyu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tentenyu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="144">
<j>1974年創業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Established in 1974.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Established in 1974.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Established in 1974.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="145">
<j>鶏ガラ白湯に豚骨をミックスした最初の店と言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Allegedly, the first store that mixed chicken bone white broth with pork bone broth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Allegedly, the first store that mixed chicken bone white broth with pork bone broth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Allegedly, the first store that mixed chicken bone white broth with pork bone broth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="146">
<j>また、叉焼のうまさには定評がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A good reputation for the taste of roasted pork fillet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their roasted pork fillet has a good reputatio</e>
<cmt>Gramma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Their roasted pork fillet has a good reputation.</e>
<cmt>reputatio→reputationに修正、ピリオド追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="147">
<j>こってり系。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thick type.</e>
<cmt>訳出しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="148">
<j>現在、京都で特に人気がある店の1つである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of the most popular stores in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is one of the most popular stores in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>Gramma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is one of the most popular stores in Kyoto now.</e>
<cmt>now追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="149">
<j>珍遊 (ちんゆう)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chinyu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chinyu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chinyu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="150">
<j>もともとは一乗寺にあった屋台。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was originally a street stall in Ichijoji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was originally a street stall in Ichijoji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was originally a street stall in Ichijoji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="151">
<j>現在は三代目になるが、屋号を引き継いだだけで、初代とは直接の関係はない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although it is the third generation now, the present owner only took over the store name and has nothing to do with the founder.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although it is in its third generation now, the present owner only took over the store name and has nothing to do with the founder.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it is in its third generation now, the present owner only took over the store name and has nothing to do with the founder.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="152">
<j>価格が安くボリュームがあるので、固定客は多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chinyu has many regular customers thanks to the low price and the large volume.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chinyu has many regular customers thanks to its low price and large volume.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chinyu has many regular customers thanks to its low price and large volume.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="153">
<j>背脂醤油系。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soy sauce with backfat type.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soy sauce with backfat type.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soy sauce with backfat type.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="154">
<j>鶴はし</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsuruhashi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsuruhashi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsuruhashi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="155">
<j>2001年創業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Established in 2001.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Established in 2001.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Established in 2001.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="156">
<j>大別すれば、あっさり系だが、鴨を使った独特のコクのあるスープ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although roughly categorized in the plain type, Tsuruhashi serves unique well-seasoned soup using duck.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although roughly categorized as using the plain type of soup, Tsuruhashi serves a unique well-seasoned soup using duck.</e>
<cmt>Gramma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although roughly categorized as using the plain type of soup, Tsuruhashi serves a unique well-seasoned soup using duck.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="157">
<j>店主は元フランス料理のシェフ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The owner was a French chef.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The owner was a French chef.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The owner was a French chef.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="158">
<j>基本は鶏ガラと鴨をミックスしたスープなのだが、日によってスープが変わり、店頭のボードにその日のスープに使われた材料が掲示される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the basic soup is a mixture of the chicken bone broth and duck broth, the soup changes every day, and ingredients used in the soup of the day are displayed on a board in front of the store.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the basic soup is a mixture of chicken bone and duck broth, the soup changes every day, and ingredients used in the soup of the day are displayed on a board in front of the store.</e>
<cmt>Gramma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the basic soup is a mixture of chicken bone and duck broth, the soup changes every day, and ingredients used in the soup of the day are displayed on a board in front of the store.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="159">
<j>中でも、時折提供される、鴨100%のスープは、独特の風味を持ち、熱狂的なファンがいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Above all, occasionally served 100% duck broth has a distinctive flavor, and it is supported by enthusiastic fans.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Above all, the 100% duck broth which is served occasionally has a distinctive flavor, and is popular among its enthusiastic fans.</e>
<cmt>Gramma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Above all, the 100% duck broth which is served occasionally has a distinctive flavor, and is popular among its enthusiastic fans.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="160">
<j>化学調味料は一切使わない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Uses no chemical condiments at all.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsuruhashi uses no chemical condiments at all.</e>
<cmt>Gramma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsuruhashi uses no chemical condiments at all.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="161">
<j>亜喜英（あきひで）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akihide</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akihide</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akihide</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="162">
<j>2005年創業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Established in 2005.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Established in 2005.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Established in 2005.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="163">
<j>豚骨と鳥ガラをひたすら煮込んだ濃厚なスープが特徴。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akihide features its thick soup made by patiently boiling pork bones and chicken bones.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akihide features a thick soup which is created through long hours of simmering pork and chicken bones.</e>
<cmt>Gramma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akihide features a thick soup which is created through long hours of simmering pork and chicken bones.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="164">
<j>臨時休業が非常に多いため来店前に電話で営業を確認をする常連客もいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to too many temporary closings, some of regular customers makes a phone call to see if it is open before they come.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to too many temporary closings, some of the regular customers call the establishment to see if it is open before visiting it.</e>
<cmt>Grammar/flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to too many temporary closings, some of the regular customers call the establishment to see if it is open before visiting it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="165">
<j>現在、京都で特に人気がある店の1つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is one of the most popular stores in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is one of the most popular stores in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is one of the most popular stores in Kyoto now.</e>
<cmt>now追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="166">
<j>天宝 (てんほう)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tenho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tenho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tenho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="167">
<j>1992年創業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Established in 1992.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Established in 1992.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Established in 1992.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="168">
<j>豚の角煮と野菜あんが載る独特のラーメンで、非京都ラーメンの代表的な店の1つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tenho serves unique ramen topped with pork square seasoned in soy sauce and vegetable sauce, and it is one of typical non-Kyoto ramen stores.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tenho serves a unique kind of ramen topped with pork squares seasoned in soy and vegetable sauce, and is typical of non-Kyoto ramen stores.</e>
<cmt>Grammar/flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tenho serves a unique kind of ramen topped with pork squares seasoned in soy and vegetable sauce, and is typical of non-Kyoto ramen stores.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="169">
<j>角煮ラーメンが有名ではあるが激辛マニアの間では激辛（現在は大辛、ちょい辛ラーメンなど）ラーメンも評判である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although it is famous for the pork ramen, super-hot ramen (currently very hot ramen, slightly hot ramen, and the like) is of good repute among super-hot lovers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although it is famous for its pork ramen, super-spicy ramen (very spicy ramen, slightly spicy ramen, and the like) has a solid reputation among super-spicey lovers.</e>
<cmt>Grammar/flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it is famous for its pork ramen, super-spicy ramen (presently very spicy ramen, slightly spicy ramen, and the like) has a solid reputation among super-spicey lovers.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース消去、「現在は」を訳出</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="170">
<j>この店のから揚げはオリジナルのタレがかかっていて、こちらも人気。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fried chicken at this store is topped with original sauce, which is also very popular.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fried chicken at this store is topped with its original sauce, which is also very popular.</e>
<cmt>Grammar/flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fried chicken at this store is topped with its original sauce, which is also very popular.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="171">
<j>店内はレゲエがBGMで流れており一風変わった雰囲気を醸し出している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reggae is played in the store as BGM, which creates an eccentric atmosphere.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The store plays reggae music in the background, setting up an eccentric atmosphere.</e>
<cmt>Grammar/flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The store plays reggae music in the background, setting up an eccentric atmosphere.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="172">
<j>営業状況がかなり不安定で（スープが無くなったり、ある程度、客が途絶えたりすると閉店する。また、店長がバイクレースをする為臨時休業も多い）、常連泣かせの店としても有名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Store hours and days being rather irregular (It closes when the soup runs out or the store is slow with customers. Temporary closing is also frequent because the owner enjoys motorbike races), it is notorious for annoying regular customers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Store hours and days being rather irregular (it closes when the soup runs out or when business is slow; it often closes temporarily due to the owner&apos;s passion for motorbike races); it is notorious for annoying regular customers.</e>
<cmt>Grammar/flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Store hours and days being rather irregular (it closes when the soup runs out or when business is slow; it often closes temporarily due to the owner&apos;s passion for motorbike races); it is notorious for annoying regular customers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="173">
<j>ラーメン荘 夢を語れ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ramen-so Talk Your Dream</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ramen-so Talk Your Dream</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ramen-so Talk Your Dream</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="174">
<j>2006年創業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Established in 2006.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Established in 2006.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Established in 2006.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="175">
<j>東京のラーメン二郎赤羽（富士丸）系の店で、この系統の店としては京都初となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Descendant of Ramen-Jiro Akabane (Fujimaru) in Tokyo, and the fist in Kyoto from this lineage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A descendant of Ramen-Jiro Akabane (Fujimaru) in Tokyo, and the first in Kyoto from this lineage.</e>
<cmt>Spelling error</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A descendant of Ramen-Jiro Akabane (Fujimaru) in Tokyo, and the first in Kyoto from this lineage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="176">
<j>現在、京都で特に人気がある店の1つである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is one of the most popular stores in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is one of the most popular stores in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is one of the most popular stores in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="177">
<j>関西で二郎系のラーメンが食せる店が他にないこともあり、県外からの客も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Partly because there is no other store that serves Jiro type ramen in Kansai, many customers come from outside the prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Partly because there is no other store that serves Jiro type ramen in Kansai, many customers are from outside the prefecture.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Partly because there is no other store that serves Jiro type ramen in Kansai, many customers are from outside the prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="178">
<j>現在休業中。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Temporarily closed now.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Temporarily closed now.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Temporarily closed now.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>伏見区</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fushimi Ward</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fushimi Ward</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fushimi Ward</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="179">
<j>伏見区は左京区一乗寺と並ぶ京都のラーメン激戦区といわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fushimi Ward is referred to as the ramen battleground in Kyoto, along with Ichijoji, Sakyo Ward.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fushimi Ward is referred to as a ramen battleground in Kyoto, along with Ichijoji, Sakyo Ward.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fushimi Ward is referred to as a ramen battleground in Kyoto, along with Ichijoji, Sakyo Ward.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="180">
<j>萬福</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Manbuku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Manbuku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Manbuku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="181">
<j>新福菜館の弟子筋にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Disciple of Shinpuku-saikan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Disciple of Shinpuku-saikan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Disciple of Shinpuku-saikan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="182">
<j>あっさり系。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Plain type.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Plain type.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Plain type.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="183">
<j>本店は深草、下鳥羽に支店がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The main store is in Fukakusa, and there is a branch in Shimo-Toba.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The main store is in Fukakusa,with a branch in Shimo-Toba.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The main store is in Fukakusa, with a branch in Shimo-Toba.</e>
<cmt>スペース追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="184">
<j>大中</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daichu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daichu</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daichu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="185">
<j>麺の堅さや、醤油ダレの味付け、叉焼の部位など、細かに注文できる上に、温泉玉子、白菜キムチのトッピングが無料で出来る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hardness of the noodle, seasoning of the soy sauce condiments, part of the roasted pork fillet, and the like can be minutely specified, and toppings including hot spring boiled egg, Napa cabbage kimchi are free to order.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The noodle&apos;s hardness, seasoning of the soy sauce condiments, part of the roasted pork fillet, and the like can be customized, with toppings such as hot spring boiled eggs and napa cabbage kimchi being available free of charge.</e>
<cmt>Grammar/flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The noodle&apos;s hardness, seasoning of the soy sauce condiments, part of the roasted pork fillet, and the like can be customized, with toppings such as hot spring boiled eggs and napa cabbage kimchi being available free of charge.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="186">
<j>こってり系。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thick type.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thick type.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thick type.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="187">
<j>最近、以前よりのスープを元味とし、それに魚介出汁を加えた新味を始めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A new taste of seafood broth added to the base flavor of the conventional soup was started recently.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Recently, seafood broth was added to the soup base, creating a new flavor.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Recently, the shop has started a new flavor created by adding seafood broth to the soup base as a original flavor.</e>
<cmt>「元味」に加え「新味」を始めたという原文の内容をふまえ、文章を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="188">
<j>大黒ラーメン</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daikoku Ramen</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daikoku Ramen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daikoku Ramen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="189">
<j>非常に価格が安い上に、来店すると100円割引券が貰えることで、人気がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Popular for giving a 100-yen coupon at the store, in addition to the very low price.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Popular for passing out 100-yen coupons in store, in addition to its very low prices.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Popular for passing out 100-yen coupons in store, in addition to its very low prices.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="190">
<j>こってり系。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thick type.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thick type.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thick type.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="191">
<j>東福寺に支店がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a branch at Tofuku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a branch at Tofuku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a branch in front of Tofukuji Station.</e>
<cmt>寺にあるのではなく、「東福寺」駅前にあるという意味のため、at Tofuku-ji Temple→in front of Tofukuji Stationとしました。　(参考: http://www.kyoto-town.com/review/yt075227)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="192">
<j>サイドメニューのチャーハンも極めて安く、合わせて頼む人が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fried rice as a side dish is also very inexpensive, and many customers order it alongside.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fried rice as a side dish is also very inexpensive, and is ordered by many a customer.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fried rice as a side dish is also very inexpensive, and is ordered by many a customer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="193">
<j>水は御香宮の水源を利用していて有名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Famous for using water from a water source at Gokonomiya.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Famous for using water sourced from Gokonomiya.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Famous for using water sourced from Gokonomiya-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>Gokonomiya→Gokonomiya-jinja Shrineとしました。(参照: http://www.kyoto.zaq.ne.jp/gokounomiya/)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="194">
<j>一番星</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ichinan-boshi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ichinan-boshi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ichiban-boshi</e>
<cmt>Ichinan-boshi→Ichiban-boshiに修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="195">
<j>岡崎に姉妹店有り。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a sister store in Okazaki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A sister store is located in Okazaki.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A sister store is located in Okazaki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="196">
<j>こってり系。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thick type.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thick type.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thick type.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="197">
<j>柴漬けが添えられるのだが、こってりとしたラーメンの口直しには非常に良く合う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shibazuke is garnished, which matches the thick taste of ramen as refreshment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shibazuke is included as a garnish, and helps to reset one&apos;s tastebuds after eating the ramen which has a rather heavy flavor to it.</e>
<cmt>Grammar/flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shibazuke is included as a garnish, and helps to reset one&apos;s tastebuds after eating the ramen which has a rather heavy flavor to it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="198">
<j>ラーメン銀閣</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ramen Ginkaku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ramen Ginkaku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ramen Ginkaku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="199">
<j>元々は銀閣寺周辺で営業していた屋台なので、この屋号である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The store name derives from the fact that it used to be a street stall opened around Ginkaku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The store name derives from the fact that it used to be a street stall around Ginkaku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>Grammar/flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The store name derives from the fact that it used to be a street stall around Ginkaku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="200">
<j>こってり系。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thick type.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thick type.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thick type.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="201">
<j>現在、京都で人気がある店の1つで、行列が出来ることは珍しくない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of the most popular stores in Kyoto, and it is not rare to see a line-up there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of the most popular stores in Kyoto, and often has people lined up.</e>
<cmt>Grammar/flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of the most popular stores in Kyoto, and often has people lined up.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="202">
<j>サブメニューのチャーハンも美味しいため好評である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fried rice as a submenu is delicious and popular.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fried rice is also available as a side dish, and is considered to be delicious.</e>
<cmt>Grammar/flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fried rice is also available as a side dish, and is considered to be delicious.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="203">
<j>しるそばたか</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shirusoba-Taka</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shirusoba-Taka</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shirusoba-Taka</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="204">
<j>かなり濃厚な背脂醤油系が売りだが、塩ラーメンやこってり系の白湯ラーメンもあり、いずれも人気がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While it features rather thick soy sauce with backfat type, salt ramen and thick white broth ramen are also popular.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While it features rather a soup made of thick soy sauce with backfat, salt and thick white broth ramen are also popular.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While it features rather a soup made of thick soy sauce with backfat, salt and thick white broth ramen are also popular.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース消去</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="205">
<j>太陽軒</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takyoken</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takyoken</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taiyoken</e>
<cmt>Takyoken→Taiyokenに修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="206">
<j>背脂醤油系の「おいしいラーメン」が売り。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Features the soy sauce with backfat type of &quot;Tasty Ramen.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Features the soy sauce with backfat type of &quot;Tasty Ramen.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Features the soy sauce with backfat type of &apos;Tasty Ramen.&apos;</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="207">
<j>価格も安く、地元ではかなり人気がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The price is low, and pretty popular in the local area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its low price make it fairly popular in the local region.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its low price make it fairly popular in the local region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="208">
<j>塩ラーメンや中華そばの「あっさりラーメン」も人気がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Salt ramen and Chinese noodle called &quot;Plain Ramen&quot; are also popular.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Salt ramen and Chinese noodles called &quot;Plain Ramen&quot; are also popular.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Salt ramen and Chinese noodles called &apos;Plain Ramen&apos; are also popular.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="209">
<j>玄屋</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Genya</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Genya</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genya</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="210">
<j>酒粕を使ったラーメンを出す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Serves ramen using sake lees.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Serves ramen using sake lees.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Serves ramen using sake lees.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="211">
<j>観光客に人気だが、地元での評価はそれほどでもない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Popular among tourist, but not so highly regarded by local people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Popular among tourists, but not highly regarded by local people.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Popular among tourists, but not highly regarded by local people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>その他の地区</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other Areas</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other Areas</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other Areas</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="212">
<j>東龍</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toryu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toryu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toryu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="213">
<j>2000年創業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Established in 2000.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Established in 2000.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Established in 2000.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="214">
<j>メインの東龍そばは、野菜を使ったポタージュのようなスープが特徴。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toryu noodle as a featured menu is characterized in the soup like potage using vegetables.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its feature dish, Toryu noodles, is characterized by a soup like potage which uses vegetables.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its feature dish, Toryu noodles, is characterized by a soup like potage which uses vegetables.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="215">
<j>その他に鶏ガラベースの東京風中華そばも有り、こちらも人気が高い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides, Tokyo type Chinese noodle based on the chicken bone broth is also popular.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides, Tokyo type Chinese noodles based on chicken bone broth is also popular.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides, Tokyo type Chinese noodles based on chicken bone broth is also popular.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="216">
<j>東龍そばは、こってり系の発展系と考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toryu noodle is considered as a developed type of the thick type.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toryu noodle is considered to be evolved from the thick soup type.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toryu noodle is considered to be evolved from the thick soup type.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="217">
<j>また、京都のラーメン店では珍しく麺は縮れ麺を使う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Curly noodle is used, which is rare among ramen stores in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Curly noodles are used, and is rare among ramen stores in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Curly noodles are used, and is rare among ramen stores in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="218">
<j>現在、京都で人気がある店の1つで、行列が出来ることは珍しくない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of the most popular stores in Kyoto, and it is not rare to see a line-up.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of the most popular stores in Kyoto, it is rare for it not to have a string of people lining the store.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of the most popular stores in Kyoto, it is rare for it not to have a string of people lining the store.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="219">
<j>ますたに</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masutani</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masutani</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masutani</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="220">
<j>1947年創業で、左京区北白川の今出川通に店を構える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Established in 1947 with a store on Imadegawa street in Kita-Shirakawa, Sakyo Ward.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Established in 1947 with a store on Imadegawa street in Kita-Shirakawa, Sakyo Ward.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Established in 1947 with a store on Imadegawa-dori Street in Kita-Shirakawa, Sakyo Ward.</e>
<cmt>Imadegawa-dori Streetとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="221">
<j>京都の背脂醤油系の元祖の店。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The origin of soy sauce with backfat type in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The originator of soup made out of soy sauce and backfat in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The originator of soup made out of soy sauce and backfat in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="222">
<j>背脂醤油系のラーメンとしては燕三条系ラーメンの方が古いのだが、関連は不明。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsubame-Sanjo line ramen is older as ramen of the soy sauce with backfat type, but the relation between them is not known.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Tsubame-Sanjo line ramen is older in terms of using a soup made out of soy sauce and backfat, but the relation between them is not known.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tsubame-Sanjo line ramen is older in terms of using a soup made out of soy sauce and backfat, but the relation between them is not known.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="223">
<j>また、「ニントン」（ニンニク唐辛子）を考案したのもこの店だと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This store is also said to have invented garlic pepper.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This store is also said to have invented garlic pepper.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This store is also said to have invented garlic pepper.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="224">
<j>非常にリピーターが多いことでも知られ、常に行列が出来ている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is known to have many repeaters, and there is always a line-up.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is known to have many repeat customers, and there is always a line of people.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is known to have many repeat customers, and there is always a line of people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="225">
<j>現在はすぐ近くに支店が出来たため、以前よりは食べやすくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Now that there is a branch nearby, it is easier to eat at Masutani.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With a branch located nearby, it is now easier to eat at Masutani.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With a branch located nearby, it is now easier to eat at Masutani.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="226">
<j>ほそかわ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hosokawa</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hosokawa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hosokawa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="227">
<j>ますたにで修行後、西大路花屋町西入るに店を構える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After training at Masutani, the owner opened a store at Nishiojo Hanayacho, Nishi-iru.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After training at Masutani, the owner opened a store at Nishiojo Hanayacho, Nishi-iru.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After training at Masutani, the owner opened a store at Nishioji Hanayacho, Nishi-iru.</e>
<cmt>Nishiojo→Nishiojiに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="228">
<j>背脂醤油系。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soy sauce with backfat type</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soy sauce with backfat type</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soy sauce with backfat type.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="229">
<j>2006年頃に3倍ほどの広さを持つ隣の店に移転。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moved to a three-times larger next store around 2006.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moved to a store which is three-times larger around 2006.</e>
<cmt>Grammar/flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moved to a store which is three-times larger around 2006.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="230">
<j>西院、城陽にも支店がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are branches in Saiin and Joyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are branches in Saiin and Joyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are branches in Saiin and Joyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="231">
<j>ぴっかり食堂</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Pikkari Shokudo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Pikkari Shokudo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Pikkari Shokudo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="232">
<j>2002年創業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Established in 2002.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Established in 2002.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Established in 2002.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="233">
<j>鶏ガラを使ったあっさりとした塩ラーメンを出す、非京都ラーメンの代表的な店の1つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of the typical non-Kyoto ramen stores, which serves plain salt ramen using chicken bone broth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A typical type of non-Kyoto ramen store, it serves plain salt ramen using chicken bone broth.</e>
<cmt>Grammar/flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A typical type of non-Kyoto ramen store, it serves plain salt ramen using chicken bone broth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="234">
<j>杉千代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sugichiyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sugichiyo</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sugichiyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="235">
<j>1999年創業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Established in 1999.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Established in 1999.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Established in 1999.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="236">
<j>背脂醤油系。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soy sauce with backfat type.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soy sauce with backfat type.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soy sauce with backfat type.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="237">
<j>現在、京都で特に人気がある店の1つで、常時、行列が出来ている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of the most popular stores in Kyoto, with a line-up all the time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of the most popular stores in Kyoto, there is always a line of people waiting to get in.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of the most popular stores in Kyoto, there is always a line of people waiting to get in.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="238">
<j>観光客も訪れるせいか、特に、昼食時の行列は、平日でもかなりのものになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Probably because tourists also visit, especially the line-up at lunch time is pretty long even on weekdays.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The line is especially long during lunch time, even during weekdays, most likely due to tourists.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The line is especially long during lunch time, even during weekdays, most likely due to tourists.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="239">
<j>風花</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fuka</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fuka</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fuka</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="240">
<j>2001年創業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Established in 2001.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Established in 2001.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Established in 2001.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="241">
<j>「新宿ラーメン」を標榜し、濃厚な魚介系塩ラーメンを出す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Calling itself &quot;Shinjuku Ramen,&quot; Fuka serves the thick seafood type of salt ramen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Calling itself &quot;Shinjuku Ramen,&quot; Fuka serves a thick seafood type of salt ramen.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Calling itself &apos;Shinjuku Ramen,&apos; Fuka serves a thick seafood type of salt ramen.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="242">
<j>非京都ラーメンの代表的な店の1つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of the typical non-Kyoto ramen stores.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a typical non-Kyoto ramen store.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a typical non-Kyoto ramen store.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="243">
<j>○竹</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Marutake</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Marutake</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Marutake</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="244">
<j>魚介出汁のスープに焙り叉焼がのる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seafood broth type of soup topped with roasted and grilled pork fillet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It features a seafood broth type of soup topped with roasted and grilled pork fillet.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It features a seafood broth type of soup topped with roasted and grilled pork fillet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="245">
<j>非京都ラーメンの代表的な店の1つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of the typical non-Kyoto ramen stores.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a typical non-Kyoto ramen store.</e>
<cmt>Grammar/flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a typical non-Kyoto ramen store.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="246">
<j>ラーメン日本一</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ramen Nippon-ichi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ramen Nippon-ichi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ramen Nippon-ichi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="247">
<j>大盛りの「ド根性ラーメン」で有名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Famous for a large helping of &quot;Guts Ramen.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Famous for a large helping of &quot;Guts Ramen.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Famous for a large helping of &apos;Guts Ramen.&apos;</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="248">
<j>2. 5玉の麺に大量の具材がのる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Noodle for 2.5 persons topped with a huge amount of ingredients.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They serve 2.5 servings of noodles, topped with an incredible volume of ingredients.</e>
<cmt>Grammar/flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They serve 2.5 servings of noodles, topped with an incredible volume of ingredients.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="249">
<j>40分以内で3杯完食すれば、この店での飲食は永久に無料。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If one finishes three bowls within 40 minutes, he will be allowed to eat and drink for free for ever.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If one finishes three bowls within 40 minutes, he/she is forever allowed to eat and drink there for free.</e>
<cmt>Grammar/flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If one finishes three bowls within 40 minutes, he/she is forever allowed to eat and drink there for free.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="250">
<j>こってり系。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thick type.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thick type.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thick type.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="251">
<j>めん馬鹿一代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Menbaka Ichidai</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Menbaka Ichidai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Menbaka Ichidai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="252">
<j>山盛りのネギに、熱した油をかけるネギラーメンで知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Known for green onion ramen with heaping green onion poured with boiling oil.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Known for their green onion ramen with a heap of green onions poured with boiling oil.</e>
<cmt>Grammar/flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Known for their green onion ramen with a heap of green onions poured with boiling oil.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="253">
<j>熱した油をかける際に、飛沫が飛び散ることで、見た目に派手なせいかマスコミに取り上げられることが多いが、地元での評価はそれほどでもない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is often picked up by mass media probably for its outstanding sight of flying droplets when the boiling oil is poured, but local reputation is not so high.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is often picked up by the mass media for the amazing site of flying droplets when the oil is poured, but its local reputation is not quite so high.</e>
<cmt>Grammar/flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is often picked up by the mass media for the amazing site of flying droplets when the oil is poured, but its local reputation is not quite so high.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="254">
<j>スープそのものは、あっさり系。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The soup itself is the plain type.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The soup itself is the plain type.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The soup itself is the plain type.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="255">
<j>たんぽぽ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tanpopo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tanpopo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tanpopo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="256">
<j>鉢満面に一味が振りかけられ、真っ赤に見えることで有名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Famous for the bowlful of ground red pepper making the bowl look entirely red.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Famous for a bowlful of ground red pepper which makes the bowl look entirely red.</e>
<cmt>Grammar/flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Famous for a bowlful of ground red pepper which makes the bowl look entirely red.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース消去</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="257">
<j>食べるとそれほど辛くはない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is not so hot to eat.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is not actually as spicy as it looks.</e>
<cmt>Grammar/flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is not in fact as spicy as it looks.</e>
<cmt>&quot;actually&quot; -&gt; &quot;in fact&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="258">
<j>背脂醤油系。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soy sauce with backfat type.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soy sauce with backfat type.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soy sauce with backfat type.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="259">
<j>いいちょ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Iicho</e>
<cmt>長音ではないのでｉを重ねて綴りました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Iicho</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Iicho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="260">
<j>1998年創業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Established in 1998.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Established in 1998.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Established in 1998.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="261">
<j>背脂醤油系。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soy sauce with backfat type.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soy sauce with backfat type.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soy sauce with backfat type.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="262">
<j>現在、京都で人気がある店の1つで、行列が出来ることは珍しくない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of the most popular stores in Kyoto, and it is not rare to see a line-up there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of the most popular stores in Kyoto, it is rare for it not to have a line of people waiting in front.</e>
<cmt>Grammar/flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of the most popular stores in Kyoto, it is rare for it not to have a line of people waiting in front.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="263">
<j>夜鳴き屋</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yonaki-ya</e>
<cmt>訳抜け</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="264">
<j>1971年創業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Established in 1971.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Established in 1971.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Established in 1971.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="265">
<j>あっさり系。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Plain type.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Plain type.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Plain type.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="266">
<j>限定メニューの「細切り肉入りそば」は非常に人気があり、開店直後に売り切れることも多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Noodle with thin sliced meat,&quot; which is a limited menu, is so popular that it is often sold out immediately after the store opens.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its dish of &quot;Noodle with thin sliced meat,&quot; is a limited item, and is so popular that it is often sold out immediately after the store opens.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its dish of &apos;Noodle with thin sliced meat,&apos; is a limited item, and is so popular that it is often sold out immediately after the store opens.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="267">
<j>現在、京都で人気がある店の1つで、行列が出来ることは珍しくない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of the most popular stores in Kyoto, and it is not rare to see a line-up there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of the most popular stores in Kyoto, it is rare for it not to have a line of people waiting in front.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of the most popular stores in Kyoto, it is rare for it not to have a line of people waiting in front.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース消去</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="25">
<sen id="268">
<j>みよし</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Miyoshi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Miyoshi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Miyoshi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="26">
<sen id="269">
<j>博多風（長浜風）豚骨ラーメンを出す（ただし、九州の人間に言わせると、かなりアレンジされた物で、本来の博多風豚骨ラーメンではないという人が多い）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Serves Hakata style (Nagahama style) of pork bone broth ramen (However, most of people from Kyushu say it is rather altered and not the Hakata style pork bone broth ramen in a strict meaning).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Serves Hakata style (Nagahama style) pork bone broth ramen (however, most people from Kyushu say it is rather altered and not the traditional kind of Hakata style pork bone broth ramen).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Serves Hakata style (Nagahama style) pork bone broth ramen (however, most people from Kyushu say it is rather altered and not the traditional kind of Hakata style pork bone broth ramen).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="270">
<j>非京都ラーメンの代表的な店の1つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of the typical non-Kyoto ramen stores.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A typical non-Kyoto ramen stores.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A typical non-Kyoto ramen stores.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="271">
<j>繁華街近くで（木屋町）、早朝まで営業していることで知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Known for opening near busy downtown street (Kiyamachi) until early in the morning.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Known for being open near a busy downtown street (Kiyamachi) until early in the morning.</e>
<cmt>Grammar/flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Known for being open near a busy downtown street (Kiyamachi) until early in the morning.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="272">
<j>リピーターが多く、かつて、Gacktが通っていたことでも知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Miyoshi has many repeaters, and known for the fact that Gackt (a popular male singer) used to be a regular customer.</e>
<cmt>Gacktの説明を挿入。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Miyoshi has many repeat customers and is famous for having had Gackt (a popular male singer) as a regular customer.</e>
<cmt>Grammar/flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Miyoshi has many repeat customers and is famous for having had Gackt (a popular male singer) as a regular customer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="27">
<sen id="273">
<j>てんぐ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tengu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tengu</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tengu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="28">
<sen id="274">
<j>2003年創業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Established in 2003.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Established in 2003.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Established in 2003.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="275">
<j>「杉千代」の開店当時のチーフが独立して始めた店なので、ラーメンは「杉千代」とよく似ているが、現在の「杉千代」より美味しいとの声も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ramen is similar to that of &quot;Sugichiyo&quot; as the chief at the opening of &quot;Sugichiyo&quot; opened Tengu independently, and some people say it is even more delicious compared with current &quot;Sugichiyo.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ramen which is similar to that of &quot;Sugichiyo,&quot; as the chief placed in charge of the opening of &quot;Sugichiyo&quot; opened Tengu independently, and some people say it is even better tasting than the current &quot;Sugichiyo.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Grammar/flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ramen which is similar to that of &apos;Sugichiyo,&apos; as the chief placed in charge of the opening of &apos;Sugichiyo&apos; opened Tengu independently, and some people say it is even better tasting than the current &apos;Sugichiyo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="276">
<j>というわけでメインは「杉千代」と同じ背脂醤油系だが、「杉千代」とは違いラーメンの種類は多く、塩ラーメンも人気が高い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Accordingly, though the featured menu is the soy sauce with backfat type like &quot;Sugichiyo,&quot; there are many kinds of ramen unlike &quot;Sugichiyo,&quot; and salt ramen is also popular.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Accordingly, though the featured dish is a ramen which uses soup made out of soy sauce and backfat like &quot;Sugichiyo,&quot; unlike &quot;Sugichiyo,&quot;it features many different kinds of ramen, and its salt ramen is also popular.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Accordingly, though the featured dish is a ramen which uses soup made out of soy sauce and backfat like &apos;Sugichiyo,&apos; unlike &apos;Sugichiyo,&apos; it features many different kinds of ramen, and its salt ramen is also popular.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更、スペース追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="29">
<sen id="277">
<j>無鉄砲</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Muteppo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Muteppo</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Muteppo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="30">
<sen id="278">
<j>1998年創業（創業当初は、奈良。京都に移転したのは2003年）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Established in 1998 (Opened in Nara. Moved to Kyoto in 2003).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Established in 1998 (Opened in Nara. Moved to Kyoto in 2003).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Established in 1998 (Opened in Nara. Moved to Kyoto in 2003).</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース消去</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="279">
<j>メインの「とんこつラーメン」は大量の豚骨を高温で煮込んだ極めて濃厚なスープで、こってり系の発展系と考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Featured &quot;pork bone broth ramen&quot; uses very thick soup made by boiling a huge amount of pork bones at high temperature, and is considered to be a developed type of the thick type.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Features a &quot;pork bone broth ramen&quot; which uses a very thick soup made out of boiling a huge amount of pork bones at high temperature, and is considered to be an evolved form of thick type of soup.</e>
<cmt>Grammar/flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Features a &apos;pork bone broth ramen&apos; which uses a very thick soup made out of boiling a huge amount of pork bones at high temperature, and is considered to be an evolved form of thick type of soup.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="280">
<j>麺の堅さやタレの濃さを始め、かなり細かく注文できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hardness of the noodle, thickness of the condiments, and the likes can be rather minutely specified.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Noodle hardness, the thickness of the condiments, and so on can be customized.</e>
<cmt>Grammar/flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Noodle hardness, the thickness of the condiments, and so on can be customized.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="281">
<j>その他、期間限定メニューなどもあり、多彩なラーメンが楽しめる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Customers can enjoy a variety of ramen including menu for a limited time only.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Customers enjoy a variety of ramen including dishes offered for a limited time.</e>
<cmt>Grammar/flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Customers enjoy a variety of ramen including dishes offered for a limited time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="282">
<j>化学調味料は使用していない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">No chemical condiments are used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">No chemical condiments are used.</e>
<cmt>Grammar/flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">No chemical condiments are used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="283">
<j>現在の本店は木津川市の山の中と、かなり辺鄙な所にあるにも関わらず、車で遠方から来る客も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the current main store is in such an obscure area as mountains in Kizugawa City, many customers drive from far areas making a line-up all the time, and it is one of the most popular stores in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the current main store is located in an obscure area in the mountains of Kizugawa City, many customers drive from far away areas. There is always a line in the front and it is one of the most popular stores in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>Grammar/flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the current main store is located in an obscure area in the mountains of Kizugawa City, many customers drive from far away areas.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="284">
<j>常時、行列が出来ており、現在、京都でもっとも人気がある店の1つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is always a line in the front and it is one of the most popular stores in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="285">
<j>大阪、奈良にも店舗がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are stores in Osaka and Nara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are stores in Osaka and Nara.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are stores in Osaka and Nara.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="31">
<sen id="286">
<j>元町ラーメン</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Motomachi Ramen</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Motomachi Ramen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Motomachi Ramen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="32">
<sen id="287">
<j>油小路下立売に店を構える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The store is located at Aburanokoji, Shimodachiuri.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The store is located at Aburanokoji, Shimodachiuri.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The store is located at Aburanokoji, Shimodachiuri.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="288">
<j>シンプルだが極めて濃厚な豚骨ベースの醤油系スープが特徴で、ネギともやしが程よいアクセントとなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Characterized in its simple but very thick soy sauce type soup based on pork bone broth, with a good accent of green onion and bean sprout.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Characterized by its simple but very thick soy sauce type soup based on pork bone broth, with a healthy accent of green onion and bean sprout.</e>
<cmt>Grammar/flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Characterized by its simple but very thick soy sauce type soup based on pork bone broth, with a healthy accent of green onion and bean sprout.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="289">
<j>京都出身ロックバンドくるりのボーカル岸田繁氏絶賛の店であり、店内にはサインやグッズが飾られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigeru KISHIDA, a vocalist of a rock band from Kyoto, Kururi, gives the store the highest praise, and his autograph and goods are displayed in the store.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigeru KISHIDA, a vocalist for a rock band from Kyoto, Kururi, gave the store his highest praise, and his autograph and goods are displayed in the store.</e>
<cmt>Grammar/flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigeru KISHIDA, a vocalist for a rock band from Kyoto, Kururi, gave the store his highest praise, and his autograph and goods are displayed in the store.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="290">
<j>2007年6月、右京区花屋町通り沿いに支店が出来た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A branch opened on Hanayacho-tori, Ukyo Ward in June 2007.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A branch opened on Hanayacho-tori, Ukyo Ward in June 2007.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A branch opened on Hanayacho-dori Street, Ukyo Ward in June 2007.</e>
<cmt>Hanayacho-tori→Hanayacho-dori Streetに修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="33">
<sen id="291">
<j>東京ラーメン</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokyo Ramen</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokyo Ramen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokyo Ramen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="34">
<sen id="292">
<j>左京区の京都大学のすぐそばにある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Very close to Kyoto University in Sakyo Ward.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is located close to Kyoto University in Sakyo Ward.</e>
<cmt>Grammar/flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is located close to Kyoto University in Sakyo Ward.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="293">
<j>店名通り、東京風のオーソドックスな醤油ラーメンだが、400円と格安であり昼時は学生でにぎわう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is Tokyo style of orthodox soy sauce ramen as the store name goes, but the price is as low as 400 yen, and the store is filled with students at lunch time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It features the Tokyo style of orthodox soy sauce ramen as the store name goes, but the price is as low as 400 yen, and the store is filled with students at lunch time.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It features the Tokyo style of orthodox soy sauce ramen as the store name goes, but the price is as low as 400 yen, and the store is filled with students at lunch time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="294">
<j>メニューにはギョウザもチャーハンもないが、なぜかカレーライスを売っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The menu includes neither dumpling nor fried rice, but it curry rice is available for some reason.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The menu includes neither dumpling nor fried rice, but curry rice is available for some reason.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The menu includes neither dumpling nor fried rice, but curry rice is available for some reason.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="295">
<j>店主の高齢化に伴い、最近の営業状況はやや不安定である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the owner grows older, the recent store hours and days are slightly irregular.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the owner grows older, recent store hours and days have become slightly irregular.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the owner grows older, recent store hours and days have become slightly irregular.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>ご当地ラーメン</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Local Ramen</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Local Ramen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Local Ramen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>ご当地ラーメンとしての「京都ラーメン」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kyoto Ramen&quot; as Local Ramen</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kyoto Ramen&quot; as Local Ramen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Ramen&apos; as Local Ramen</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="296">
<j>ラーメン愛好家など一部の人の間では、京都ラーメンはご当地ラーメンのひとつとして認知されており、雑誌等のラーメン特集でもよく紹介されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among part of people such as ramen lovers, Kyoto ramen is recognized as one of local ramens, and often introduced in feature articles of magazines about ramen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among some, including ramen lovers, Kyoto ramen is recognized as a local ramen, and often introduced in feature magazine articles about ramen.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among some, including ramen lovers, Kyoto ramen is recognized as a local ramen, and often introduced in feature magazine articles about ramen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="297">
<j>一方で、京都ラーメンのご当地ラーメンとしての一般的な認知度はまだ低い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, visibility of Kyoto ramen as the local ramen is still low among common people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, the visibility of Kyoto ramen as a local ramen is still low among common people.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, the visibility of Kyoto ramen as a local ramen is still low among common people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="298">
<j>また、当の京都に住む人も多くは「京都ラーメン」を特に意識していない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, majority of residents in Kyoto are not especially aware of &quot;Kyoto ramen.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, the majority of residents in Kyoto are not especially aware of the existence of &quot;Kyoto ramen.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Grammar/flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, the majority of residents in Kyoto are not especially aware of the existence of &apos;Kyoto ramen.&apos;</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="299">
<j>これは、京都人にとって、ラーメンはあまりに身近な存在であり、特に、それを注視して考えたことがないためと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered because ramen is too close to people in Kyoto and has not been featured for consideration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered because ramen is too much of a daily food for people in Kyoto and as such has not been featured.</e>
<cmt>Grammar/flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered because ramen is too much of a daily food for people in Kyoto and as such has not been featured.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="300">
<j>こうした例は、高山ラーメン、燕三条系ラーメンなど、少なくない（ちなみに高山では「ラーメン」と言う呼称さえ使われず、地元では「そば」と呼ばれている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such an instance is often observed with regard to Takayama ramen, Tsubame-Sanjo ramen, and the like (For comparison, the word &quot;ramen&quot; is not even used in Takayama, and ramen is locally called &quot;soba&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is often observed with regards to Takayama ramen, Tsubame-Sanjo ramen, and the like (for comparison, the word &quot;ramen&quot; is not even used in Takayama, and ramen is locally called &quot;soba&quot;).</e>
<cmt>Grammar/flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is often observed with regards to Takayama ramen, Tsubame-Sanjo ramen, and the like (for comparison, the word &apos;ramen&apos; is not even used in Takayama, and ramen is locally called &apos;soba&apos;).</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="301">
<j>ご当地ラーメンで町おこしをしている場合などはともかく、地元の人間にとっては、日常、普通に食べている「ラーメン」はただの「ラーメン」としてしか認識されていないことが多いのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Setting aside the case of revitalizing the town depending on the local ramen, the &quot;ramen&quot; that people always eat is recognized as just &quot;ramen&quot; most of time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Setting aside the case of revitalizing the town depending on the local ramen, the &quot;ramen&quot; that people always eat is recognized as just &quot;ramen&quot; most of time.</e>
<cmt>Grammar/flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Setting aside the case of revitalizing the town depending on the local ramen, the &apos;ramen&apos; that people always eat is recognized as just &apos;ramen&apos; most of time.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="302">
<j>ただ、2008年3月現在、iタウンページによると、京都府にはラーメン専門店は500軒ほど有りあり、その他、専門店ではないが、ラーメンを提供する店（中華料理店など）を加えると、実に1000軒を超える店がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As of March 2008, according to I town page, there are about 500 stores specializing in ramen in Kyoto Prefecture, and there are more than 1,000 stores that serve ramen including stores not specializing in ramen (i.e., Chinese restaurants).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As of March 2008, according to the itown page, there are about 500 stores specializing in ramen in Kyoto Prefecture, and there are more than 1,000 stores that serve ramen including stores not specializing in ramen (i.e., Chinese restaurants).</e>
<cmt>Grammar/flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As of March 2008, according to the itown page, there are about 500 stores specializing in ramen in Kyoto Prefecture, and there are more than 1,000 stores that serve ramen including stores not specializing in ramen (i.e., Chinese restaurants).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="303">
<j>これは人口比で言えば、47都道府県の中でもっともラーメンを扱う店が多いのではないかと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that there are most ramen stores per capita among 47 prefectures.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Kyoto prefecture features the most ramen stores per capita among the 47 prefectures.</e>
<cmt>Grammar/flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Kyoto prefecture features the most ramen stores per capita among the 47 prefectures.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="304">
<j>また、そうした京都のラーメン店の多くが共通のフォーマットを持っており（麺と具材）、一括りの存在と見てもおかしくはないだろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, most of the ramen stores in Kyoto have common formats (noodle and ingredients), which can be regarded as one category.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, most of ramen stores in Kyoto have common formats (noodle and ingredients), which can be regarded as one category.</e>
<cmt>Grammar/flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, most of ramen stores in Kyoto have common formats (noodle and ingredients), which can be regarded as one category.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="305">
<j>実際、ご当地ラーメンには、神戸ラーメンや浪花ラーメンのように、実体はないのに言葉だけが一人歩きしているものや、札幌ラーメンや函館ラーメンのようにすでに形骸しているものも多くあり、それらと比較すれば、「京都ラーメン」は、確かな実体もあり、はるかにご当地ラーメンの要件を満たしていると言える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In fact, many types of local ramen have wings without entity like Kobe ramen and Naniwa ramen or have lost substance like Sapporo ramen and Hakodate ramen, and compared with them, &quot;Kyoto ramen&quot; has an evident entity and satisfies requirements of the local ramen much more.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In fact, many types of local ramen have wings without entity like Kobe ramen and Naniwa ramen or have lost substance like Sapporo ramen and Hakodate ramen, and compared with them, &quot;Kyoto ramen&quot; has an evident entity and satisfies requirements of the local ramen much more.</e>
<cmt>Robert: This makes no sense at all</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact, not a few local ramen have become famous without actual forms (like Kobe ramen and Naniwa ramen) or have already become a mere name (like Sapporo ramen and Hakodate ramen); compared with them, &apos;Kyoto ramen&apos; has an evident entity and satisfies requirements as the local ramen much more.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更、意味が不明確なため、訳文全体を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="306">
<j>最近の京都を紹介する雑誌では、特別に「ラーメン」を取り扱わない場合でも「京都ラーメン」を記載する例が増えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Increasing number of recent magazines that introduce Kyoto describe &quot;Kyoto ramen&quot; even when &quot;ramen&quot; is not especially featured.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Anincreasing number of recent magazines that introduce Kyoto describe &quot;Kyoto ramen&quot; even when &quot;ramen&quot; is not especially featured.</e>
<cmt>Grammar/flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Anincreasing number of recent magazines that introduce Kyoto describe &apos;Kyoto ramen&apos; even when &apos;ramen&apos; is not especially featured.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="14">
<tit>
<j>京風ラーメン</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyo-style Ramen</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyo-style Ramen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyo-style Ramen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="307">
<j>京風ラーメンとは京懐石を意識して作られた薄味のラーメン。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyo-style ramen is bland ramen created based on an image of Kyo kaiseki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyo-style ramen is a bland ramen created based on Kyo kaiseki.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyo-style ramen is a bland ramen created based Kyo kaiseki (Kyoto&apos;s traditional local cuisine).</e>
<cmt>Kyo kaisekiの補足を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="308">
<j>京都府外ではチェーン展開している店も多くあり、京都発祥のラーメンであるとの誤解を招いているが、京都市内では一部の観光客向けの店で見られるだけで、ほとんど存在しない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are many stores opening a chain in areas except Kyoto leading to misunderstanding that the ramen came from Kyoto, but they are seldom seen in Kyoto City except very few for part of tourists.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are many stores which have opened a chain in areas except Kyoto, leading to a misunderstanding that the ramen came from Kyoto, when in reality they are seldom seen in Kyoto City except for a few stores located in tourist traps.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are many stores which have opened a chain in areas except Kyoto, leading to a misunderstanding that the ramen came from Kyoto, when in reality they are seldom seen in Kyoto City except for a few stores located in tourist traps.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="309">
<j>スープは、魚介系と鶏ガラを使った和風の味付けのラーメンで、他府県の人間が京都を勝手にイメージして作った物であり、実際に、京都で一般に食べられているラーメンとは全く異なった物である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soup of this ramen uses seafood type and chicken bone broth with Japanese taste, which was created by people from other prefectures based on their own image of Kyoto, and it is entirely different from ramen commonly eaten in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This ramen uses a seafood and chicken bone broth soup suited for Japanese taste, and was created by people from other prefectures based on their perception of Kyoto, and is entirely different from ramen commonly eaten in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This ramen uses a seafood and chicken bone broth soup suited for Japanese taste, and was created by people from other prefectures based on their perception of Kyoto, and is entirely different from ramen commonly eaten in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース消去</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="310">
<j>京懐石を模して、コース仕立てになっていることが多く、デザートに和風の甘味（あんみつなど）がつく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is often served in a course in the image of Kyo kaiseki, followed by Japanese style sweets (e.g. Anmitsu) as a dessert.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is often served in a course that mimics Kyo kaiseki, followed by Japanese style sweets (e.g. Anmitsu) as a dessert.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is often served in a course that mimics Kyo kaiseki, followed by Japanese style sweets (e.g. Anmitsu) as a dessert.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="15">
<tit>
<j>京都発祥ではない京都風ラーメン</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto-style Ramen Not Deriving from Kyoto</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto-style Ramen Not Derived from Kyoto</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto-style Ramen Not Derived from Kyoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="311">
<j>近年、京都ラーメンの一般への認知が進み、京都発祥ではないのに京都ラーメンを標榜するラーメン店や京都ラーメンを標榜するカップラーメンが現れるようになった（京都の実在する店とタイアップしたカップラーメンも多い）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With increasing recognition of Kyoto ramen, there appear ramen stores that call themselves Kyoto ramen though not from Kyoto, and cup ramens that call themselves Kyoto ramen (There are also many cup ramens tied up with existing stores in Kyoto).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the increasing recognition of Kyoto ramen, ramen stores have appeared that themselves Kyoto ramen though they are not from Kyoto, and cup ramens that call themselves Kyoto ramen (there are also many cup ramens tied up with existing stores in Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>Grammar/flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the increasing recognition of Kyoto ramen, ramen stores have appeared that themselves Kyoto ramen though they are not from Kyoto, and cup ramens that call themselves Kyoto ramen (there are also many cup ramens tied up with existing stores in Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="312">
<j>よってこや</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yottekoya</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yottekoya</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yottekoya</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="313">
<j>イートアンド（旧大阪王将）が「京都屋台風ラーメン」をコンセプトに立ち上げたチェーン店。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A chain store established by Eat-and (former Osaka-Osho) with the concept of &quot;Kyoto street-stall style ramen.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A chain store established by Eat-and (former Osaka-Osho) based on the concept of &quot;Kyoto street-stall style ramen.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A chain store established by Eat-and (former Osaka-Osho) based on the concept of &apos;Kyoto street-stall style ramen.&apos;</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="314">
<j>本当に京都の屋台が発祥のラーメン店だと誤解している人は意外と多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Unexpectedly many people misunderstands that the ramen store derives from a street stall in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unexpectedly many people misunderstood this and took it to mean that the ramen store derives from a street stall in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unexpectedly many people misunderstood this and took it to mean that the ramen store derives from a street stall in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="315">
<j>全国制覇とまでは行かないが、かなり広域にチェーン展開をしており成功している（海外にも店舗を持つ）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although it may not be a nationwide expansion, it is successful with a chain in rather wide area (There are also branches overseas).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although it may not be expanding nation-wide, it is nevertheless a successful chain that covers a wide area (there are also branches overseas).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it may not be expanding nation-wide, it is nevertheless a successful chain that covers a wide area (there are also branches overseas).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="316">
<j>ただし、本場であるはずの京都は敷居が高いのか、1店舗しか存在しない（2007年11月現在）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there is only one store in Kyoto that must be its origin, probably because of the high entry levels (as of November 2008).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, for some reason, there is only one store located in Kyoto, despite the fact that Kyoto is supposed to be its origin. This is mostly likely due to the fact of its high entry levels (as of November 2008).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, for some reason, there is only one store located in Kyoto, despite the fact that Kyoto is supposed to be its origin; this is mostly likely due to the fact of its high entry levels (as of November 2007).</e>
<cmt>2008→2007に修正、二文に分かれているため一文になるよう修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="317">
<j>日清 行列のできる店のラーメン 京都鶏トロスープ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto thick chicken soup, Ramen of the store with a line-up by Nissin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto thick chicken soup, Ramen of the store with a line-up by Nissin</e>
<cmt>Robert: This doesn&apos;t make sense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Thick Chicken Soup - gyoretsu no dekiru mise no ramen (ramen noodles of a shop crowded with fans) series by Nissin</e>
<cmt>Kyoto Thick Chicken Soupとし、「行列のできる店のラーメン」→シリーズ名のため、&quot;gyoretsu no dekiru mise no ramen (ramen noodles of a shop crowded with fans) series&quot;とし、間にハイフンを入れました。 (参考: http://www.asahi.com/english/business/TKY200501050101.html)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="318">
<j>京都のこってり系スープをイメージしたカップラーメン。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cup noodle based on an image of the thick type soup of Kyoto Ramen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cup noodle based on the concept of a thick type Kyoto Ramen soup.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cup noodles based on the concept of a thick type Kyoto Ramen soup.</e>
<cmt>Cup noodle→Cup noodlesとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Ligar(id:12623), Greenleaf(id:126500), Roger(id:9883), Kansai explorer(id:48975), 春野秋葉(id:36725), Bellcricket(id:37640), やきとり(id:126941), Zz2(id:30288), パの字(id:34188), 暗黒な方(id:44101), An-chan(id:14590), Knua(id:66861), Ogeshi(id:80487), Coleus(id:55336), Calvero(id:38360), Hotei(id:7664), CarsNgirls(id:142507), Clay(id:110480), ポピュラーポプラ(id:157724), S-PAI(id:4705), Icewind(id:137238), Dobidowa(id:66536), Rusk(id:9895), Vantey(id:22521), Jute(id:207429), 竃馬(id:102733), Ichii-ya(id:48912), Mooko(id:36162), Nakadati(id:26815), 健ちゃん(id:60346), Miya(id:1881), Mochi(id:9489), やすとし(id:63220), Tmatsu(id:10583), 1029man(id:93235), Ziksy(id:84091), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>