<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>大祓</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oharae</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oharae</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oharae</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>大祓（おおはらえ）は、6月と12月の晦日（新暦では6月30日と12月31日）に行われる除災行事である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oharae (the great purification) is an event of removing calamity held on June 30 and December 31.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oharae (the great purification) is an event of removing calamity held on June 30 and December 31.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oharae (the great purification) is an event of removing calamity held on June 30 and December 31.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>犯した罪や穢れを除き去るための祓えの行事で、6月の大祓を夏越の祓（なごしのはらえ）、12月の大祓を年越の祓（としこしのはらえ）という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is an event to remove committed sins and stains, and Oharae held in June and Oharae held in December are called Nagoshi-no-Oharae (great purification ceremony) and Toshikoshi no harae (Annual Shinto ritual of purification), respectively.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is an event to remove committed sins and stains, and Oharae held in June and Oharae held in December are called Nagoshi-no-Oharae (great purification ceremony) and Toshikoshi no harae (Annual Shinto ritual of purification), respectively.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is an event to remove committed sins and stains, and Oharae held in June and Oharae held in December are called Nagoshi no Oharae (great purification ceremony) and Toshikoshi no harae (Annual Shinto ritual of purification), respectively.</e>
<cmt>Nagoshi-no-Oharaeのハイフンを消去</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>6月の大祓は夏越神事、六月祓とも呼んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oharae held in June is also called Nagoshi shinji, Minazukibarae (summer purification rites held at shrines on the last day of the sixth lunar month).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oharae held in June is also called Nagoshi shinji, Minazukibarae (summer purification rites held at shrines on the last day of the sixth lunar month).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oharae held in June is also called Nagoshi shinji, Minazukibarae (summer purification rites held at shrines on the last day of the sixth lunar month).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>なお、「夏越」は「名越」とも標記する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;夏越&quot; is also written as &quot;名越.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;夏越&quot; is also written as &quot;名越.&quot;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">夏越&apos; is also written as &apos;名越.&apos;</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>行事としての大祓</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oharae as an event</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oharae as an event</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oharae as an event</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>701年の大宝律令によって正式な宮中の年中行事に定められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oharae was designated by the Taiho Code in 701 as a formal annual court event.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oharae was designated by the Taiho Code in 701 as a formal annual court event.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oharae was designated by the Taiho Code in 701 as a formal annual court event.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>この日には、朱雀門前の広場に親王、大臣（おおおみ）ほか首都（みやこ）にいる官僚が集って大祓詞を読み上げ、国民の罪や穢れを祓った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On this day, imperial princes, ministers, and other governmental officials in the capital (miyako) gathered at the square in front of the Suzaku-mon Gate and read Oharae no kotoba (Words of the Great Purification) to purify people&apos;s sins and stains.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On this day, imperial princes, ministers, and other governmental officials in the capital (miyako) gathered at the square in front of the Suzaku-mon Gate and read Oharae no kotoba (Words of the Great Purification) to purify people&apos;s sins and stains.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On this day, imperial princes, ministers, and other governmental officials in the capital (miyako) gathered at the square in front of the Suzaku-mon Gate and read Oharae no kotoba (Words of the Great Purification) to purify people&apos;s sins and stains.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>衣服を毎日洗濯する習慣や水などのない時代、半年に一度、雑菌の繁殖し易い夏を前に新しい物に替える事で疫病を予防する意味があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When there was no habit of or water available for washing closes everyday, this event had significance for the prevention of plagues by the semiannual replacement before summer when bacteria were likely to be developed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When there was no habit of or water available for washing closes everyday, this event had significance for the prevention of plagues by the semiannual replacement before summer when bacteria were likely to be developed.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When there was no habit of or water available for washing closes everyday, this event had significance for the prevention of plagues by the semiannual replacement before summer when bacteria were likely to be developed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>その後、百年ほどは盛大に行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the next 100 years since then, this event was conducted tremendously.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the next 100 years since then, this event was conducted tremendously.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the next 100 years since then, this event was conducted tremendously.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>そして応仁の乱の頃から行われなくなったが、江戸時代（1691年）に再開され、次第に広まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This event was ceased since the time of the Onin War, but was started again in the Edo period (1691) and gradually spread.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This event was stopped around the time of the Onin War, but was started again in the Edo period (1691) and gradually spread.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This event was stopped around the time of the Onin War, but was started again in the Edo period (1691) and gradually spread.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>1871年（明治4年）の太政官布告にて明治新政府により「夏越神事」「六月祓」の称の禁止と「大宝律令」の「大祓」の旧儀の再興が命じられ、全国の神社で行われるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The edict of Dajokan (Grand Council of state) issued in 1871 by the New Meiji Government prohibited the names &quot;Nagoshi shinji&quot; and &quot;Minazukibarae&quot; and ordered the revival of the traditional ceremony &quot;Oharae&quot; of the &quot;Taiho Code,&quot; and the ceremony was started being conducted by shrines across the country.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The edict of Dajokan (Grand Council of state) issued in 1871 by the New Meiji Government prohibited the names &quot;Nagoshi shinji&quot; and &quot;Minazukibarae&quot; and ordered the revival of the traditional ceremony &quot;Oharae&quot; of the &quot;Taiho Code,&quot; and the ceremony started being conducted by shrines across the country.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The edict of Dajokan (Grand Council of state) issued in 1871 by the New Meiji Government prohibited the names &apos;Nagoshi shinji&apos; and &apos;Minazukibarae&apos; and ordered the revival of the traditional ceremony &apos;Oharae&apos; of the &apos;Taiho Code,&apos; and the ceremony started being conducted by shrines across the country.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>戦後には「夏越神事」「六月祓」の称も一部では復活し、現在に至る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The names &quot;Nagoshi shinji&quot; and &quot;Minazukibarae&quot; were partly revived after the war, up to the present date.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The names &quot;Nagoshi shinji&quot; and &quot;Minazukibarae&quot; were partly revived after the war, up to the present date.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The names &apos;Nagoshi shinji&apos; and &apos;Minazukibarae&apos; were partly revived after the war, up to the present date.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>夏越の祓では多くの神社で「チガヤの輪潜り（ちのわくぐり）」が行われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Nagoshi shinji, &quot;Chigaya no wakuguri&quot; (Chinowa kuguri, passing through a ring of miscanthus) is performed in many shrines.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Nagoshi shinji, &quot;Chigaya no wakuguri&quot; (Chinowa kuguri, passing through a ring of miscanthus) is performed in many shrines.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Nagoshi shinji, &apos;Chigaya no wakuguri&apos; (Chinowa kuguri, passing through a ring of miscanthus) is performed in many shrines.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>これは、氏子が茅草で作られた輪の中を左まわり、右まわり、左まわりと八の字に三回通って穢れを祓うものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shrine parishioners pass three times with a pigeon-toed gait, clockwise, counterclockwise, and clockwise again, through a hoop made of kaya grass (plants of sedge family) to purify stains.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shrine parishioners pass three times with a pigeon-toed gait, clockwise, counterclockwise, and clockwise again, through a hoop made of kaya grass (plants of the sedge family) to purify stains.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shrine parishioners pass three times with a pigeon-toed gait, clockwise, counterclockwise, and clockwise again, through a hoop made of kaya grass (plants of the sedge family) to purify stains.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>『釈日本紀』（卜部兼方　鎌倉時代中期）に引用された『備後国風土記』逸文にある「蘇民将来」神話では茅の輪を腰につけて災厄から免れたとされ、茅の旺盛な生命力が神秘的な除災の力を有すると考えられてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Somin shorai&quot; (Japanese old story and the folk religion originated in the story) in &quot;Bingo no kuni Fudoki&quot; (unknown or lost writing) quoted in &quot;Shaku Nihongi&quot; (annotated text of the Nihon Shoki) (Kanekata URABE, the mid Kamakura period), a kaya grass ring was worn on a waist to avoid disasters, and it was believed that the strong vitality of kaya grass had a mysterious power to prevent disasters.</e>
<cmt>備後国風土記：用語集には複数の訳語が記載されていましたが、一番登録日付の新しいものを用いました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Somin shorai&quot; (Japanese old story and the folk religion originating in the story) in &quot;Bingo no kuni Fudoki&quot; (unknown or lost writing) quoted in &quot;Shaku Nihongi&quot; (annotated text of the Nihon Shoki) (Kanekata URABE, the mid Kamakura period), a kaya grass ring was worn on the waist to avoid disasters, and it was believed that the strong vitality of kaya grass had the mysterious power of preventing disasters.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &apos;Somin Shorai&apos; (Japanese old story and the folk religion originating in the story) in &quot;Bingo no Kuni Fudoki&quot; (unknown or lost writing) quoted in &quot;Shaku Nihongi&quot; (annotated text of the Nihon Shoki) (Kanekata URABE, the mid Kamakura period), a kaya grass ring was worn on the waist to avoid disasters, and it was believed that the strong vitality of kaya grass had the mysterious power of preventing disasters.</e>
<cmt>Somin Shorai、Bingo no Kuni Fudokiとし、原文に合わせクォーテーション変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>また、茅の輪の左右に設置する笹竹に願い事を書いた短冊を振下げ、七夕に河川に流すといった俗信仰は、書初めをどんどん焼きで焚くと筆が上達するといった行事と対応している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The communal worship that tanzaku (long, narrow card) cards on which a wish is written are hung up on small bamboos provided on the right and left sides of the kaya grass hoop and the bamboos are thrown into a river on the Tanabata festival corresponds to the event in which kakizome (New Year&apos;s writing, resolution) is burnt in the Dondon-yaki (a Shinto blessing of objects that have been a part of a celebration but are now debris consuming by fire at the 14th to the 16the of the lunar New Year) to improve writing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The communal worship that tanzaku (long, narrow card) cards on which a wish is written are hung up on small bamboos provided on the right and left sides of the kaya grass hoop and the bamboos are thrown into a river on the Tanabata festival corresponds to the event in which kakizome (New Year&apos;s writing, resolution) is burnt in the Dondon-yaki (a Shinto blessing of objects that have been a part of a celebration but are now debris consuming by fire from the 14th to the 16th of the lunar New Year) to improve writing.</e>
<cmt>Flow, Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The communal worship that tanzaku (long, narrow card) cards on which a wish is written are hung up on small bamboos provided on the right and left sides of the kaya grass hoop and the bamboos are thrown into a river on the Tanabata festival corresponds to the event in which kakizome (New Year&apos;s writing, resolution) is burnt in the Dondon-yaki (a Shinto blessing of objects that have been a part of a celebration but are now debris consuming by fire from the 14th to the 16th of the lunar New Year) to improve writing.</e>
<cmt>&quot;th&quot;の表記を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="17">
<j>京都では夏越祓に「水無月」という和菓子を食べる習慣がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kyoto, there is a habit of eating the Japanese confectionery called &quot;minazuki&quot; in the Nagoshi no harae.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Kyoto, there is a habit of eating the Japanese confectionery called &quot;minazuki&quot; in the Nagoshi no harae.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Kyoto, there is a habit of eating the Japanese confectionery called &apos;Minazuki&apos; in the Nagoshi no harae.</e>
<cmt>他の表記と合わせ、minazuki→Minazukiとし、シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>水無月は白のういろう (菓子)生地に小豆を乗せ、三角形に包丁された菓子である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Minazuki&quot; is the confectionery prepared by placing azuki beans on white Uiro (a sort of sweetened steamed cake made of rice powder) and then cutting it into a triangular shape.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Minazuki&quot; is a confectionery prepared by placing azuki beans on white Uiro (a sort of sweetened steamed cake made of rice powder) and then cutting it into triangular shapes.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Minazuki is a confectionery prepared by placing azuki beans on white Uiro (a sort of sweetened steamed cake made of rice powder) and then cutting it into triangular shapes.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>水無月の上部にある小豆は悪霊ばらいの意味があり、三角の形は暑気を払う氷を表していると云われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that azuki beans on Minazuki have the meaning of warding off evil spirits, and the triangular shape expresses ice beating the heat away.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that azuki beans on Minazuki have the meaning of warding off evil spirits, and the triangular shape expresses ice beating the heat away.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that azuki beans on Minazuki have the meaning of warding off evil spirits, and the triangular shape expresses ice beating the heat away.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="20">
<j>高知県下では、夏越祓のことを「輪抜け様」と呼び、多くの神社でお祭りが開かれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Kochi Prefecture, the Nagoshi no harae is called &quot;wanuke sama,&quot; and festivals are held in many shrines.</e>
<cmt>輪抜け様：定訳不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Kochi Prefecture, the Nagoshi no harae is called &quot;wanuke sama,&quot; and festivals are held in many shrines.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Kochi Prefecture, the Nagoshi no harae is called &apos;wanuke sama,&apos; and festivals are held in many shrines.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>行事として最も重要な茅の輪潜りはもちろん行われるが、それに併せて神社の参道に多くの屋台が並び、まさにお祭りである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chinowa kuguri, which is the most important ceremony, is certainly performed, and Shrine&apos;s approaches are lined with many street stalls to coincide with the ceremony, which is, exactly, a festival.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chinowa kuguri, which is the most important ceremony, is certainly performed, and Shrine&apos;s approaches are lined with many street stalls to coincide with the ceremony, which basically makes it a festival.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chinowa kuguri, which is the most important ceremony, is certainly performed, and Shrine&apos;s approaches are lined with many street stalls to coincide with the ceremony, which basically makes it a festival.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>梅雨時期に当たることから天気がぱっとしないことが良くあるが、「輪抜け様」が終わると夏到来という風物詩でもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since this is held in the rainy season, the weather is generally not so fine, but this is a special feature for the arrival of summer following the end of &quot;wanuke sama.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since this is held in the rainy season, the weather is generally not so fine, but this is a special feature for the arrival of summer following the end of &quot;wanuke sama.&quot;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since this is held in the rainy season, the weather is generally not so fine, but this is a special feature for the arrival of summer following the end of &apos;wanuke sama.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>祓の事例</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cases of Purification Rites</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cases of Purification Rites</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cases of Purification Rites</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 翰林硯士(id:99377), Ligar(id:12623), Izayohi(id:13095), ととりん(id:31982), Nnh(id:474), Stanislaus(id:1806), 短髄彦(id:5555), Memosa(id:131221), Tjan(id:17305), Greenland4(id:114494), Gleam(id:4760), Beagle(id:45036), ABnormal(id:254617), 663highland(id:18755), Bit(id:2197), 竹麦魚(id:11012), 竹田(id:72642), 伏儀(id:142093), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>