<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>八重崎検校</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kengyo (the highest title of the official ranks within the Todo-za (the traditional guild for the blind)) YAEZAKI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kengyo (the highest title of the official ranks within the Todo-za (the traditional guild for the blind)) YAEZAKI</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kengyo (the highest title of the official ranks within the Todo-za (the traditional guild for the blind)) YAEZAKI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>八重崎 検校（やえざき けんぎょう、安永5年（1776年）頃 － 嘉永元年9月11日 (旧暦)（1848年10月7日））は、19世紀前半に京都で活躍した盲人音楽家（地歌三味線、箏曲演奏家、作曲家）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kengyo YAEZAKI (around 1776 – October 7, 1848) was a blind musician who was active during the early nineteenth century in Kyoto (jiuta shamisen (traditional Japanese shamisen music) player, so or koto (a long Japanese zither with thirteen strings) player and composer).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kengyo YAEZAKI (around 1776 – October 7, 1848) was a blind musician who was active during the early nineteenth century in Kyoto (jiuta shamisen (traditional Japanese shamisen music) player, so or koto (a long Japanese zither with thirteen strings) player and composer).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kengyo YAEZAKI (around 1776 – October 7, 1848) was a blind musician who was active during the early nineteenth century in Kyoto (jiuta shamisen (traditional Japanese shamisen music) player, so or koto (a long Japanese zither with thirteen strings) player and composer).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>安永5年（1776年）頃の生まれ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born around 1776.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born around 1776.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born around 1776.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>浦崎検校に箏曲を師事。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He studied under kengyo URASAKI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He studied under kengyo URASAKI.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He studied under kengyo URASAKI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>文化 (元号)12年（1815年）検校となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became a kengyo in1815.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became a kengyo in 1815.</e>
<cmt>Spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became a kengyo in 1815.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>都名（いちな 当道座に所属する盲人が名乗る名前）は三保一、または壱岐一（いきのいち）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His ichina (a by-name for the blind belonging in Todo-za), was Mihoichi or Ikinoichi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His ichina (a by-name for the blind belonging in Todo-za), was Mihoichi or Ikinoichi.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His ichina (a by-name for the blind belonging in Todo-za), was Mihoichi or Ikinoichi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>箏の名手として知られ、三味線の自作曲もあるが、むしろ多くの地歌、特に手事物曲に優れた箏の手付をしたことの方がはるかに有名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was known for a brilliant koto player and composed his own shamisen songs, but he was far more famous for playing lots of jiuta excellently, especially tegotomono (a form of Japanese chamber music) songs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was known as a brilliant koto player and composed his own shamisen songs, but he was far more famous for playing lots of jiuta excellently, especially tegotomono (a form of Japanese chamber music) songs.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was known as a brilliant koto player and composed his own shamisen songs, but he was far more famous for playing lots of jiuta excellently, especially tegotomono (a form of Japanese chamber music) songs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>文化頃に大阪の市浦検校が、地歌曲に箏の手付をする際、原曲の三味線の旋律とは違う旋律を工夫し（これを替手式箏曲と呼ぶ）、合奏の効果を高めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around Bunka era, kengyo ICHIURA exercised his ingenuity in melodizing differently from the shamisen melody of the original song when playing the koto for jiuta song (we call this &quot;kaede shiki sokyoku&quot; (koto music with accompanying melody style)) and enhanced the ensemble effect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around the Bunka era, kengyo ICHIURA exercised his ingenuity in creating melodies differently from the shamisen melody of the original song when playing the koto for jiuta song (we call this &quot;kaede shiki sokyoku&quot; (koto music with accompanying melody style)) and enhanced the ensemble effect.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around the Bunka era, kengyo ICHIURA exercised his ingenuity in creating melodies differently from the shamisen melody of the original song when playing the koto for jiuta song (we call this &quot;kaede shiki sokyoku&quot; (koto music with accompanying melody style)) and enhanced the ensemble effect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>それを師の浦崎検校が受けて発展させたが、更に八重崎がより工夫、洗練させ、松浦検校や菊岡検校が完成させた京流手事物を、合奏音楽として更に音楽的価値の高いものとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His master Kengyo URASAKI took over and developed it, but YAEZAKI himself devised and refined it further and made Kyoto-style tegotomono (a form of Japanese chamber music) which kengyo MATSUURA or kengyo KIKUOKA had completed an ensemble music which had a higher musical value.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His master Kengyo URASAKI took over and developed it, but YAEZAKI himself devised and refined it further and made Kyoto-style tegotomono (a form of Japanese chamber music) which kengyo MATSUURA or kengyo KIKUOKA had completed an ensemble music which had a higher musical value.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His master Kengyo URASAKI took over and developed it, but YAEZAKI himself devised and refined it further and made Kyoto-style tegotomono (a form of Japanese chamber music) which kengyo MATSUURA or kengyo KIKUOKA had completed an ensemble music which had a higher musical value.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>菊岡検校とは名コンビ、良きライバルとして有名で、先に検校へと登官した菊岡から食事の残り物を食べさせられたのを遺恨に思い、菊岡との合奏の際に箏を縦横無尽に弾き菊岡を打ち負かしたが、菊岡も次には八重崎を圧倒するほどの即興演奏を行ない、そうこうする内に互いに打ちとけて良き楽友となったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was famous for being a good combination and rivalry with kengyo KIKUOKA, but he was forced to eat the leftovers of KIKUOKA who had assumed a kengyo on ahead and bore a grudge against KIKUOKA, but when there was an ensemble with KIKUOKA he played the koto freely and beat KIKUOKA down and next time KIKUOKA improvised staggeringly blowing him out and at last they thawed and became good musical friends.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was famous for being a good combination and rivalry with kengyo KIKUOKA, but he was forced to eat the leftovers of KIKUOKA who had assumed a kengyo earlier and bore a grudge against KIKUOKA, but when there was an ensemble with KIKUOKA he played the koto freely and beat KIKUOKA down and next time KIKUOKA improvised staggeringly blowing him out and at last they thawed and became good musical friends.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was famous for being a good combination and rivalry with kengyo KIKUOKA, but he was forced to eat the leftovers of KIKUOKA who had assumed a kengyo earlier and bore a grudge against KIKUOKA, but when there was an ensemble with KIKUOKA he played the koto freely and beat KIKUOKA down and next time KIKUOKA improvised staggeringly blowing him out and at last they thawed and became good musical friends.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>このコンビから生まれた名曲は多く、今日でも広く演奏されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are many great songs by their combination and even now they are played widely.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are many great songs by their combination and even now they are played widely.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are many great songs by their combination and even now they are played widely.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="12">
<j>また、石川勾当の作品『八重衣』が三味線のあまりの難技巧のため、忘れ去られようとしているのを惜しんだ宮原検校が一計を案じ、「世間では箏の手付けの名人と讃えられているが、さすがに『八重衣』に箏の手が付けられないようでは八重崎も大したことはない」と吹聴した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, the work &quot;Yaegoromo&quot; (An Eight-Fold Garment) by koto ISHIKAWA, where the shamisen parts were extremely difficult to play, was being forgotten and kengyo MIYAHARA regretted this and contrived a plot, saying &apos;YAEZAKI is publicly honored for his koto virtuosity, but he&apos;s never played &quot;Yaegoromo&quot; and is not a big deal.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, the work &quot;Yaegoromo&quot; (An Eight-Fold Garment) by koto ISHIKAWA, where the shamisen parts were extremely difficult to play, was being forgotten and kengyo MIYAHARA regretted this and contrived a plot, saying &apos;YAEZAKI is publicly honored for his koto virtuosity, but he&apos;s never played &quot;Yaegoromo&quot; and is not a big deal.&apos;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, the work &quot;Yaegoromo&quot; (An Eight-Fold Garment) by koto ISHIKAWA, where the shamisen parts were extremely difficult to play, was being forgotten and kengyo MIYAHARA regretted this and contrived a plot, saying &apos;YAEZAKI is publicly honored for his koto virtuosity, but he&apos;s never played &quot;Yaegoromo&quot; and is not a big deal.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>それを聞いた八重崎は発奮して『八重衣』に見事な手付けを行ない、以後広く演奏される曲となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hearing this, YAEZAKI roused himself to play &quot;Yaegoromo&quot; excellently and after that this song came to be widely played.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hearing this, YAEZAKI roused himself to play &quot;Yaegoromo&quot; excellently and after that this song came to be widely played.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hearing this, YAEZAKI roused himself to play &quot;Yaegoromo&quot; excellently and after that this song came to be widely played.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>あるいは、松浦検校の作品『玉の台』には一夜で箏の手を付けたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And he completed the koto part for the work &quot;Tama no Utena&quot; by kengyo MATSUURA in just one night.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And he completed the koto part for the work &quot;Tama no Utena&quot; by kengyo MATSUURA in just one night.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And he completed the koto part for the work &quot;Tama no Utena&quot; by kengyo MATSUURA in just one night.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="15">
<j>このように八重崎検校の音楽的功績は多大であるが、金銭には疎く清貧な生涯を送ったことが知られ、質素な生活ぶりで、京都の両替商万屋がパトロンとして八重崎を支えていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The musical achievement of Kengyo YAEZAKI was huge like this, but allegedly he was ignorant of money and led a life of honorable poverty and austerity and was supported by the money changer Yorozuya as a patron in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The musical achievement of Kengyo YAEZAKI was huge like this, but allegedly he was ignorant of money and led a life of honorable poverty and austerity and was supported by the money changer Yorozuya as a patron in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The musical achievement of Kengyo YAEZAKI was huge like this, but allegedly he was ignorant of money and led a life of honorable poverty and austerity and was supported by the money changer Yorozuya as a patron in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>嘉永元年（1848年）9月11日没。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died on September 11, 1848.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died on September 11, 1848.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died on September 11, 1848.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="17">
<j>門人には、『五段砧』、『秋風の曲』、『七小町』などの作曲で知られる光崎検校、後の京都下派（しもは）に続く松崎検校、中国系箏曲、地歌の祖である備後国の葛原勾当、吉沢検校の「古今組」に手事を補作した松坂春栄ら、女性の門人には『おぼこ菊』を作曲した津留らがいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His disciples included kengyo MITSUZAKI who composed &quot;Godanginuda koto music,&quot; &quot;Akikaze no kyoku&quot; (a song for the autumn wind), &quot;Nanakomachi&quot; (Seven Komachi) and so on, kengyo MATSUZAKI who followed later Kyotoshimo school, koto (the title of the official ranks within the Todo-za) KUZUHARA in Bigo province who was the originator of jiuta and sokyoku of Chugoku region style, Shunei MATSUZAKA and so on who revised and improved &quot;Kokin gumi&quot; (Kokin group) by kengyo YOSHIZAWA and TSURU who was a female and composed &quot;Obokogiku&quot; (Kiku, a virgin girl) and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His disciples included kengyo MITSUZAKI who composed &quot;Godanginuda koto music,&quot; &quot;Akikaze no kyoku&quot; (a song for the autumn wind), &quot;Nanakomachi&quot; (Seven Komachi) and so on, kengyo MATSUZAKI who later followed the Kyotoshimo school, koto (the title of the official ranks within the Todo-za) KUZUHARA in Bigo province who was the originator of jiuta and sokyoku of the Chugoku region style, Shunei MATSUZAKA and so on who revised and improved &quot;Kokin gumi&quot; (Kokin group) by kengyo YOSHIZAWA and TSURU who was a female and composed &quot;Obokogiku&quot; (Kiku, a virgin girl) and so on.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His disciples included kengyo MITSUZAKI who composed &quot;Godanginuda koto music,&quot; &quot;Akikaze no kyoku&quot; (a song for the autumn wind), &quot;Nanakomachi&quot; (Seven Komachi) and so on, kengyo MATSUZAKI who later followed the Kyotoshimo school, koto (the title of the official ranks within the Todo-za) KUZUHARA in Bingo province who was the originator of jiuta and sokyoku of the Chugoku region style, Shunei MATSUZAKA and so on who revised and improved &quot;Kokin gumi&quot; (Kokin group) by kengyo YOSHIZAWA and TSURU who was a female and composed &quot;Obokogiku&quot; (Kiku, a virgin girl) and so on.</e>
<cmt>BigoをBingoに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 BitBucket(id:30999), Point136(id:211299), もけけんぬ(id:150821), 松茸(id:27535), 詠狸庵(id:41048), Dabofish(id:239582), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>