<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>坂東三津五郎 (7代目)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitsugoro BANDO VII</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitsugoro BANDO VII</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitsugoro BANDO VII</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>七代目 坂東 三津五郎（しちだいめ　ばんどう　みつごろう、1882年（明治15年）9月21日 - 1961年（昭和36年）11月4日）は、歌舞伎役者。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitsugoro BANDO VII (21st September 1882 - 4th November 1961) was a Japanese kabuki actor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitsugoro BANDO VII (September 21, 1882 - November 4, 1961) was a Japanese kabuki actor.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitsugoro BANDO VII (September 21, 1882 - November 4, 1961) was a Japanese kabuki actor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>本名は守田 壽作（もりた じゅさく）、屋号は大和屋 (歌舞伎)、定紋は三ツ大。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born Jusaku MORITA, his stage family name was Yamatoya (kabuki) and his alternate crest was the mitsudai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born Jusaku MORITA, his stage family name was Yamatoya (kabuki) and his alternate crest was the mitsudai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born Jusaku MORITA, his acting house name was Yamatoya (kabuki) and his alternate crest was the mitsudai.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>俳名に是好がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His stage name was Zeko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His stage name was Zeko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His stage name was Zeko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>妹に坂東玉三郎 (3代目)、弟に守田勘彌 (13代目)がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His younger sister was Tamasaburo BANDO III and his younger brother was Kanya MORITA XIII.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His younger sister was Tamasaburo BANDO III, and his younger brother was Kanya MORITA XIII.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His younger sister was Tamasaburo BANDO III, and his younger brother was Kanya MORITA XIII.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>略歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Brief Biography</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Brief Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>新富座座元の守田勘彌 (12代目)の長男として東京都に生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitsugoro BANDO VII was born in Tokyo as the eldest son of Kanya MORITA XII, the proprietor of Shintomi-za Theater.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitsugoro BANDO VII was born in Tokyo as the eldest son of Kanya MORITA XII, the proprietor of the Shintomi-za Theater.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitsugoro BANDO VII was born in Tokyo as the eldest son of Kanya MORITA XII, the proprietor of the Shintomi-za Theater.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>明治22年 (1889) 10月、桐座『伊達競阿國歌舞伎』の鶴千代で二代目坂東八十助を襲名して初舞台。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He made his debut under the name Yasusuke BANDO II in October of 1889 as Tsuruchiyo in the Kiri-za Theater production of &quot;Date Kurabe Okuni Kabuki&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He made his debut under the name Yasusuke BANDO II in October 1889 as Tsuruchiyo in the Kiri-za Theater production of &quot;Date Kurabe Okuni Kabuki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He made his debut under the name Yasosuke BANDO II in October 1889 as Tsuruchiyo in the Kiri-za Theater production of &quot;Date Kurabe Okuni Kabuki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Yasosuke　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>明治39年 (1906) 4月歌舞伎座『盲長屋梅加賀鳶』（加賀鳶）の兼五郎で七代目坂東三津五郎を襲名する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In April of 1906, he appeared as Kengoro in &quot;Mekuranagaya Umega Kagatobi&quot; (&quot;Kagatobi&quot;) at the Kabuki-za Theater under the name Mitsugoro BANDO VII.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April 1906, he appeared as Kengoro in &quot;Mekuranagaya Umega Kagatobi&quot; (&quot;Kagatobi&quot;) at the Kabuki-za Theater under the name Mitsugoro BANDO VII.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April 1906, he appeared as Kengoro in &quot;Mekuranagaya Umega Kagatobi&quot; (&quot;Kagatobi&quot;) at the Kabuki-za Theater under the name Mitsugoro BANDO VII.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>その後尾上菊五郎 (6代目)、中村吉右衛門 (初代)などの相方を多く勤めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He went on to work prolifically alongside Kikugoro ONOE VI and Kichiemon NAKAMURA I.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He went on to work prolifically alongside Kikugoro ONOE VI and Kichiemon NAKAMURA I.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He went on to work prolifically alongside Kikugoro ONOE VI and Kichiemon NAKAMURA I.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>昭和23年 (1948) 日本芸術院会員に就任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1948, he was made member of the Japan Art Academy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1948, he was made a member of the Japan Art Academy.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1948, he was made a member of the Japan Art Academy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>昭和32年 (1957) 9月、歌舞伎座『寒山拾得』の舞台で倒れ、これが最後の舞台となって4年後に死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September of 1957, he collapsed on stage at the Kabuki-za Theater during a performance of &quot;Kanzan Jittoku&quot; in what was to be his final stage appearance before he passed away four years later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In September 1957, he collapsed on stage at the Kabuki-za Theater during a performance of &quot;Kanzan Jittoku&quot;; this would prove to be his last performance before his death four years later.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September 1957, he collapsed on stage at the Kabuki-za Theater during a performance of &quot;Kanzan Jittoku&quot;; this would prove to be his last performance before his death four years later.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>死の前年の昭和35年 (1960) には文化功労者および人間国宝にも認定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1960, the year before his death, he was designated a Person of Cultural Merit and a Living National Treasure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1960, the year before his death, he was designated a Person of Cultural Merit and a Living National Treasure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1960, the year before his death, he was designated a Person of Cultural Merit and a Living National Treasure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="13">
<j>人物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Personal Life</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Personal Life</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Personal profile</e>
<cmt>統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>実力がありながら小柄な身体と甲高い声が欠点だったが、所作事にかけては名人と呼ばれ、「西の林又一郎、東の坂東三津五郎」と並び称された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Despite his talent, his small frame and high-pitched voice were weaknesses, yet he is considered to have been a master of all that he undertook and was ranked alongside individuals such as Mataichiro HAYASHI II and Mitsugoro BANDO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His small frame and high-pitched voice were weaknesses, but due to his great talent he is considered to have been a master of all that he undertook; in fact, he is ranked alongside individuals such as Mataichiro HAYASHI II and Mitsugoro BANDO.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His small frame and high-pitched voice were weaknesses, but due to his great talent he is considered to have been a master of all that he undertook; in fact, he is referred to as &apos;Mataichiro HAYASHI II of the west and Mitsugoro BANDO of the east.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一部追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>若いころに先人たちの舞台を研究したり、明治の名人中村芝翫 (4代目)に直接仕込まれたりしたこともあり、長年の精進と鍛錬に培われた舞踊の技術と知識はずば抜けていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During his youth, he studied the works of his predecessors and trained directly under the Meiji era master Shikan NAKAMURA IV, while in adulthood he possessed outstanding knowledge and buyo (Japanese traditional dance) skills cultivated through years of devotion and training.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During his youth, he studied the works of his predecessors and trained directly under the Meiji-era master Shikan NAKAMURA IV; in adulthood he possessed outstanding knowledge and buyo (Japanese traditional dance) skills, which he had cultivated through years of devotion and training.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During his youth, he studied the works of his predecessors and trained directly under the Meiji-period master Shikan NAKAMURA IV; in adulthood he possessed outstanding knowledge and buyo (Japanese traditional dance) skills, which he had cultivated through years of devotion and training.</e>
<cmt>era →period　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>それらは今日書物に残された芸談からもうかがい知ることが出来る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today, these details can also be inferred from discussions that remain in the literature.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, these details can also be inferred from discussions that remain in the literature.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, these details can also be inferred from discussions that remain in the literature.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="17">
<j>そうした理由から、配役では比較的軽い役どころが多く恵まれなかったが、それでも『矢の根』の曾我時致、『壷阪霊験記』の澤市、『娘道成寺』の押戻、『傾城反魂香』（吃又）の又平などは優れていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For these reasons, he was cast in many relatively small roles but despite this gave excellent performances as Tokimune SOGA in &quot;Ya no Ne&quot;, Sawaichi in &quot;Tsubosaka Reigenki&quot;, Oshi Modoshi in &quot;Musume Dojoji&quot;, and Matahei in &quot;Keisei Hangonko&quot; (&quot;Domo Mata&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was therefore cast in many relatively small roles, but despite this he gave excellent performances as Tokimune SOGA in &quot;Ya no Ne,&quot; Sawaichi in &quot;Tsubosaka Reigenki,&quot; Oshi Modoshi in &quot;Musume Dojoji&quot; and Matahei in &quot;Keisei Hangonko&quot; (&quot;Domo Mata&quot;).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was therefore cast in many relatively small roles, but despite this he gave excellent performances as Tokimune SOGA in &quot;Ya no Ne,&quot; Sawaichi in &quot;Tsubosaka Reigenki,&quot; Oshi Modoshi in &quot;Musume Dojoji&quot; and Matahei in &quot;Keisei Hangonko&quot; (&quot;Domo Mata&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>本領を発揮した舞踊では、記録映画に残された『遅櫻手爾葉七文字』（越後獅子）のほか、『大和い手向五字』（子守）、『六歌仙容彩・喜撰』、『神楽諷雲井曲毬』（どんつく）、『傀儡師 (舞踊)』、『再春菘種蒔』（舌出し三番）、『深山櫻及兼樹振』（保名）、『三つ面子守』、その他多数に至芸を見せた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to &quot;Osozakura Teniha no Nanamoji&quot; (&quot;Echigo-Jishi&quot;) which can be seen as in a documentary film, buyo dances which perfectly demonstrated his specialty included &quot;Yamato Gana Tamuke no Itsumoji&quot; (&quot;Komori&quot;), the &quot;Kisen&quot; dance of &quot;Rokkasen Sugata no Irodori&quot;, &quot;Kagurauta Kumoi no Kyokumari&quot; (&quot;Dontsuku&quot;), &quot;Kairaishi&quot; (buyo), &quot;Mata Kuru Haru Suzuna no Tanemaki&quot; (&quot;Shitadashi Sanba&quot;), &quot;Miyama no Hana to Dokanu Edaburi&quot; (&quot;Yasuna&quot;), and &quot;Mitsumen Komori&quot; as well as numerous other productions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to &quot;Osozakura Teniha no Nanamoji&quot; (&quot;Echigo-Jishi&quot;), which can be seen as a documentary film, buyo dances that perfectly demonstrated his specialty included &quot;Yamato Gana Tamuke no Itsumoji&quot; (&quot;Komori&quot;), the &quot;Kisen&quot; dance of &quot;Rokkasen Sugata no Irodori,&quot; &quot;Kagurauta Kumoi no Kyokumari&quot; (&quot;Dontsuku&quot;), &quot;Kairaishi&quot; (buyo), &quot;Mata Kuru Haru Suzuna no Tanemaki&quot; (&quot;Shitadashi Sanba&quot;), &quot;Miyama no Hana to Dokanu Edaburi&quot; (&quot;Yasuna&quot;) and &quot;Mitsumen Komori,&quot; among many other productions.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to &quot;Osozakura Teniha no Nanamoji&quot; (&quot;Echigo-Jishi&quot;), which can be seen as a documentary film, buyo dances that perfectly demonstrated his specialty included &quot;Yamato Gana Tamuke no Itsumoji&quot; (&quot;Komori&quot;), the &quot;Kisen&quot; dance of &quot;Rokkasen Sugata no Irodori,&quot; &quot;Kagurauta Kumoi no Kyokumari&quot; (&quot;Dontsuku&quot;), &quot;Kairaishi&quot; (buyo), &quot;Mata Kuru Haru Suzuna no Tanemaki&quot; (&quot;Shitadashi Sanba&quot;), &quot;Miyama no Hana to Dokanu Edaburi&quot; (&quot;Yasuna&quot;) and &quot;Mitsumen Komori,&quot; among many other productions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>また、尾上菊五郎 (6代目)の相方として『棒しばり』や『彌生之花淺草祭』（三社祭）なども好評だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Boshibari&quot; and &quot;Yayoi no Hana Asakusa Matsuri&quot; (&quot;Sanja Matsuri&quot;) in which he performed with Kikugoro ONOE VI were also highly popular.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Boshibari&quot; and &quot;Yayoi no Hana Asakusa Matsuri&quot; (&quot;Sanja Matsuri&quot;), in which he performed with Kikugoro ONOE VI, were also very popular.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Boshibari&quot; and &quot;Yayoi no Hana Asakusa Matsuri&quot; (&quot;Sanja Matsuri&quot;), in which he performed with Kikugoro ONOE VI, were also very popular.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>晩年はすべてを超越した枯淡の味わいを見せ観客を喜ばせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In his last years, he pleased audience members by displaying the essence of elegant simplicity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In his last years, he pleased audience members by displaying the essence of elegant simplicity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In his last years, he pleased audience members by displaying the essence of elegant simplicity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="21">
<j>また歌舞伎舞踊坂東流の家元としてその普及にも努めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also put great effort into the dissemination of the art of kabuki buyo as head of the Bando-ryu School.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also put great effort into the dissemination of the art of kabuki buyo as head of the Bando-ryu School.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also put great effort into the dissemination of the art of kabuki buyo as head of the Bando-ryu School.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>人間国宝に認定されたのは舞踊家としての貢献が評価されたものだといわれ、七代目は今日でも「踊りの神さま」として知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that his designation as a Living National Treasure was for the contributions that he made as a buyo performer and even today Mitsugoro BANDO VII is known as &apos;Odori no Kami-sama&apos; (lit. God of Dance).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that his designation as a Living National Treasure was given for the contributions he had made as a buyo performer, and even today Mitsugoro BANDO VII is known as &apos;Odori no Kami-sama&apos; (literally, the god of dance).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that his designation as a Living National Treasure was given for the contributions he had made as a buyo performer, and even today Mitsugoro BANDO VII is known as &apos;Odori no Kami-sama&apos; (literally, the god of dance).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Hajimari(id:205606), 白拍子花子(id:244805), Nnh(id:474), PANYNJ(id:38638), Charenji(id:7908), Cprobot(id:97843), 松茸(id:27535), Yukoba(id:28895), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>