<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>くノ一</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kunoichi (female ninja)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kunoichi (female ninja)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kunoichi</e>
<cmt>タイトルのため、補足は削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>くノ一（くのいち）は忍者の隠語で女性のことを指し、仕事のしかけに女性を使うことをくのいちの術と呼んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kunoichi indicates female ninja in the jargon of ninja (professional spy in Japan highly trained in stealth and secrecy), and using females as a trick was called kunoichi no jutsu (art of kunoichi).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kunoichi indicates female ninja in the jargon of ninja (professional spies in Japan, highly trained in stealth and secrecy), and the use of females as a trick was called kunoichi no jutsu (art of kunoichi).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kunoichi indicates female ninja in the jargon of ninja (professional spies in Japan, highly trained in stealth and secrecy), and the use of females as a trick was called kunoichi no jutsu (art of kunoichi).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>しかし小説や漫画などで女忍、すなわち女性の忍者を意味する言葉として用いられることが多く、これが普及している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in the world of novels and comics, the word kunoichi is often used to mean nyonin, or female ninja, and this meaning is prevalent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in the world of novels and comics, the word kunoichi is often used to mean nyonin, or female ninja, and this meaning is prevalent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in the world of novels and comics, the word kunoichi is often used to mean nyonin, or female ninja, and this meaning is prevalent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>ちなみに男性を使うことはタヂカラ（タヂカラの術）と言った（これは男の田と力から由来していると思われる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the contrary, to use male ninja was called the art of tajikara. (This is probably because the Chinese character &apos;男&apos; is broken into &apos;田(ta, or rice field)&apos; and &apos;力(chikara, or force).&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the contrary, the use of male ninja was called the art of tajikara (probably because the Chinese character &apos;男&apos; is broken into &apos;田(ta, or rice field)&apos; and &apos;力(chikara, or force).&apos;</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the contrary, the use of male ninja was called the art of tajikara (probably because the Chinese character &apos;男&apos; is broken into &apos;田&apos; (ta, or rice field) and &apos;力&apos; (chikara, or force)).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションマークを括弧の前に移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>一般的なイメージ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Public image</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Public image</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Public image</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>女忍は、主に力一辺倒では太刀打ちできない相手に対して下女などと偽って送り込まれ、機密情報の収集や暗殺などを請け負った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nyonin were sent to the enemy that they could not beat only by their physical strength in disguise of maid servant, and undertook collecting classified information and assassinating.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nyonin were sent to the enemy that they could not beat through physical strength alone, and were disguised as maid servants, whereupon they gathered classified information and committed assassinations.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nyonin were sent to the enemy that they could not beat through physical strength alone, and were disguised as maid servants, whereupon they gathered classified information and committed assassinations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>そのため、全身黒ずくめの忍者装束を着て男忍と同じような任務に就くことは、実際にはほとんどなかったらしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, the chances of nyonin doing the same job as the male ninja (who were dressed all in black) did seemed be rare.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the chances of nyonin doing the same job as the male ninja (who were dressed all in black) seemed rare.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the chances of nyonin doing the same job as the male ninja (who were dressed all in black) seemed rare.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>しかしながら、籠絡する相手に真剣に惚れ込んだり、裏切ったりするなどの危険が付きまとっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there were risks that nyonin would fall in love with the enemy with serious mind that they were supposed to lure and betray their friends.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処　原文が途中で途切れているため、Wikipediaから該当すると思われる部分を次の列に補充して訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there were risks that a nyonin would fall seriously in love with the enemy she was supposed to lure and thus betray her friends.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there were risks that a nyonin would fall seriously in love with the enemy she was supposed to lure and thus betray her friends.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>それを防ぐために連絡役兼監視役の忍者が常に行動を監視し、裏切りの気配を見せたときには容赦無く殺害していたとも言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order to avoid this, it is said that a ninja who acted as a liaison and watchdog was constantly observing kunoichi, and when she showed even a slight sign of betrayal, the ninja killed her mercilessly.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to avoid this, it is said that a ninja who acted as a liaison and watchdog would constantly observe the kunoichi, and if she showed even a slight sign of betrayal the ninja would kill her mercilessly.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to avoid this, it is said that a ninja who acted as a liaison and watchdog would constantly observe the kunoichi, and if she showed even a slight sign of betrayal the ninja would kill her mercilessly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>語源</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The origin of the word</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The origin of the word</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The origin of the word</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>現在一般に「くノ一」と表記され、「女」という字を分解すると「く」と「ノ」と「一」に分けられる事が語源とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nowadays in general kunoichi is described as &apos;くノ一(kunoichi)&apos; and the fact that the Chinese character &apos;女(female)&apos; can be broken into &apos;く(ku)&apos;, &apos;ノ(no)&apos; and &apos;一(ichi)&apos; supposed to be the origin of the term.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nowadays, the kunoichi is generally described as &apos;くノ一(kunoichi),&apos; and the fact that the Chinese character &apos;女(female)&apos; can be broken into &apos;く(ku),&apos; &apos;ノ(no)&apos; and &apos;一(ichi)&apos; is supposed to be the origin of the term.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nowadays, the kunoichi is generally described as &apos;くノ一&apos; (kunoichi), and the fact that the Chinese character &apos;女&apos; (female) can be broken into &apos;く&apos; (ku), &apos;ノ&apos; (no) and &apos;一&apos; (ichi) is supposed to be the origin of the term.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションマークを括弧の前に移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>語源の異説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hersey of the term</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hearsay regarding the term</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hearsay regarding the term</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="9">
<j>「くのいち」は女性のことで、正しくは「九ノ一」と書く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">kunoichi&apos; means females and should be described as &apos;九ノ一(kunoichi, which means nine plus one).&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The word &apos;kunoichi&apos; means females and should be described as &apos;九ノ一(kunoichi, which means nine plus one).&apos;</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The word &apos;kunoichi&apos; means females and should be described as &apos;九ノ一&apos; (kunoichi, which means nine plus one).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションマークを括弧の前に移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>人体には目、鼻、口、耳、へそ、肛門の九つの穴がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A human body has nine holes such as the holes of eyes, nose, mouth, ears, navel and anus.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A human body has nine holes, including those of the eyes, nose, mouth, ears, navel and anus.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A human body has nine holes, including those of the eyes, nose, mouth, ears, navel and anus.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>女性は女性器があり、もう一つ多いことから、九ノ一と呼ばれたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also said that besides those holes a female has an extra hole of vagina, which is why it is called kunoichi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also said that besides those holes a female has the vagina as an extra hole, which is why it is called kunoichi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also said that besides those holes a female has the vagina as an extra hole, which is why it is called kunoichi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>女の字を分解した「くノ一」は、現在では女忍者の俗称として使われるようになった、とする説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The former theory that the character&apos;女&apos; can be broken into &apos;くノ一&apos; came to be used as the familiar name for female ninja.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The former theory that the character&apos;女&apos; can be broken into &apos;くノ一&apos; came to be used as a familiar term for female ninja.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The former theory that the character &apos;女&apos; can be broken into &apos;くノ一&apos; came to be used as a familiar term for female ninja.</e>
<cmt>スペースを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>しかし、穴の数え方が資料によってまちまちのため（例えば、へそではなく尿口を数えるなど）の説もあり、信憑性は今ひとつである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But the latter theory lacks clear credibility because depending the material, how to count the number of human holes is different, including the theory that it includes urinary hole, saving navel.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the latter theory lacks clear credibility because, depending the material, the way of counting the number of human holes is different, including the theory that it includes the urinary hole, saving the navel.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the latter theory lacks clear credibility because, depending the material, the way of counting the number of human holes is different, including the theory that it includes the urinary hole, saving the navel.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="14">
<j>また、「くノ一」という言葉自体が、忍者小説の大家である山田風太郎の手による造語である、という説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, there is another theory that the word &apos;kunoichi&apos; itself was coined by Futaro Yamada, the authority of ninja novels.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, there is another theory that the word &apos;kunoichi&apos; itself was coined by Futaro Yamada, the authority on ninja novels.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, there is another theory that the word &apos;kunoichi&apos; itself was coined by Futaro Yamada, the authority on ninja novels.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="15">
<j>作家の戸部新十郎は、元々は陰陽道における房術を示す「九一ノ道」が本義であり、九の字がたまたま、平仮名のくの字と同じ発音のうえ、一と合すれば、ともに女になることからくノ一というふうになったものである、と著書「忍者と忍術」で述べている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinjuro TOBE, a novelist, said in his book &apos;Ninja To Ninjutsu (ninja and the art of ninja)&apos; that kunoichi originally came from &apos;kuichi no michi&apos; which indicates the art of chamber bed in Onmyodo (way of Yin and Yang, occult deviation system based on the Taoist theory of the five elements), and the Chinese character &apos;九&apos; and hiragana &apos;く&apos; happens to have the same pronunciation and with the combination of &apos;一&apos; it becomes &apos;女.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The novelist Shinjuro TOBE said in his book, &apos;Ninja To Ninjutsu (Ninja and the Art of Ninja),&apos; that kunoichi originally came from &apos;kuichi no michi,&apos; which indicates the art of the chamber bed in Onmyodo (way of Yin and Yang, an occult deviation system based on the Taoist theory of the five elements), and the Chinese character &apos;九&apos; and hiragana, whereby &apos;く&apos; happens to have the same pronunciation and with the combination of &apos;一&apos; it becomes &apos;女.&apos;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The novelist Shinjuro TOBE said in his book, &apos;Ninja To Ninjutsu&apos; (Ninja and the Art of Ninja), that kunoichi originally came from &apos;kuichi no michi,&apos; which indicates the art of the chamber bed in Onmyodo (way of Yin and Yang, an occult deviation system based on the Taoist theory of the five elements), and the Chinese character &apos;九&apos; and hiragana, whereby &apos;く&apos; happen to have the same pronunciation and with the combination of &apos;一&apos; it becomes &apos;女.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションマークを括弧の前に移動しました。Happens →happen としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>歴史上のくノ一</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History of kunoichi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History of kunoichi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History of kunoichi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="16">
<j>史実に登場するくノ一で有名なのは、武田信玄に仕えた歩き巫女の集団である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The famous kunoichi group was Arukimiko (traveling shrine maiden) that served Shingen TAKEDA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The famous kunoichi group was Arukimiko (traveling shrine maidens), which served Shingen TAKEDA.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The famous kunoichi group was Arukimiko (traveling shrine maidens), which served Shingen TAKEDA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>歩き巫女とは各地を回って芸や舞を見せ、時には男性に身を任せることもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Arukimiko toured many places in Japan and performed tricks and traditional Japanese dance, and sometimes provided sex for money.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Arukimiko toured many places in Japan and performed tricks and traditional Japanese dances, and occasionally provided sex for money.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Arukimiko toured many places in Japan and performed tricks and traditional Japanese dances, and occasionally provided sex for money.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>云わば流浪の遊女である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were, so to speak, traveling yujo (prostitutes).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were, so to speak, traveling yujo (prostitutes).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were, so to speak, traveling yujo (prostitutes).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>戦国時代には孤児や捨て子、迷子が大量に発生した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Sengoku period (period of warring states) a large number of children were orphaned, abandoned and deserted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Sengoku (Warring States) period, large numbers of children were orphaned, abandoned and deserted.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Sengoku (Warring States) period, large numbers of children were orphaned, abandoned and deserted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>その中から心身ともに優れた美少女のみを集めて歩き巫女に仕立て、隠密として各地に放ったのがくノ一である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among such children only the ones who were sound in mind and body were selected, and they were made into arukimiko and sent to various places as onmitsu (spy).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among such children, only those who were sound in mind and body were selected, and they were made into arukimiko and sent to various places as onmitsu (spies).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among such children, only those who were sound in mind and body were selected, and they were made into arukimiko and sent to various places as onmitsu (spies).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>信玄がくノ一の養成を命じたのは信州北佐久郡の豪族望月氏当主・望月盛時の若き未亡人・望月千代女であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shingen ordered Chiyojo MOCHIZUKI who was the young widow of Moritoki MOCHIZUKI, the head of Mochizuki clan, the local ruling family in Kitasaku County in Shinshu province, to make the girls into kunoichi.</e>
<cmt>望月盛時の読み方は不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shingen ordered Chiyojo MOCHIZUKI, who was the young widow of Moritoki MOCHIZUKI, the head of the Mochizuki clan--the local ruling family in Kitasaku County, Shinshu Province--to make the girls into kunoichi.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shingen ordered Chiyojo MOCHIZUKI, who was the young widow of Moritoki MOCHIZUKI, the head of the Mochizuki clan--the local ruling family in Kitasaku County, Shinshu Province--to make the girls into kunoichi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>実は千代は甲賀流忍術の流れを汲む名家・望月家の血族であり、豪族望月氏には信玄の甥が入り婿になっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Actually, Chiyojo was a blood relative of the important family Mochizuki, and Moritoki MOCHIZUKI who was a nephew of Shingen became irimuko (man who takes his wife&apos;s name) of Mochizuki family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Actually, Chiyojo was a blood relative of the important family Mochizuki, and Moritoki MOCHIZUKI, who was a nephew of Shingen, became irimuko (a man who takes his wife&apos;s name) of the Mochizuki family.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Actually, Chiyojo was a blood relative of the important family Mochizuki, and Moritoki MOCHIZUKI, who was a nephew of Shingen, became irimuko (a man who takes his wife&apos;s name) of the Mochizuki family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>信玄は彼女を「甲斐信濃二国巫女頭領」に任じ、信州小県郡禰津村（現長野県東御市祢津）の古御館に「甲斐信濃巫女道」の修練道場を開き、200～300人を超える少女達に呪術、祈祷から忍術、護身術、更に相手が男性だった時の為に性技まで教え込んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shingen appointed Chiyojo as &apos;the chieftain of Miko both in the Kai and Shinano provinces&apos; and opened the training hall called &apos;Kai and Shinano Miko do&apos; in Netsumura village, Chiisagatagun County, Shinshu (present Netsu, Tomi City, Nagano Prefecture) in which she taught 200 to 300 girls from jujutsu (an occult art), saying prayer to ninjutu, art of self-defense and even art of sex in case that the enemy was a male.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shingen appointed Chiyojo as &apos;the chieftain of Miko both in the Kai and Shinano provinces&apos; and opened the training hall called &apos;Kai and Shinano Miko do&apos; in Netsumura Village, Chiisagatagun County, Shinshu (the present-day Netsu, Tomi City, Nagano Prefecture) in which she taught 200 to 300 girls from jujutsu (an occult art), saying prayers to ninjutsu, art of self-defense and even an art of sex in case the enemy was a male.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shingen appointed Chiyojo as &apos;the chieftain of Miko both in the Kai and Shinano provinces&apos; and opened the training hall called &apos;Kai and Shinano Miko do&apos; in Netsu Village, Chiisagata County, Shinshu (the present-day Netsu, Tomi City, Nagano Prefecture) in which she taught 200 to 300 girls from jujutsu (an occult art), saying prayers to ninjutsu, art of self-defense and even an art of sex in case the enemy was a male.</e>
<cmt>Netsu Village, Chiisagata County としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>歩き巫女はののうと呼ばれ、禰津村には巫女の家が並んだののう小路や墓が残る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Arukimiko were called &apos;Nono,&apos; and in Netsumura Village Nonokoji street on which miko&apos;s houses used to stand and their graves still exist.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Arukimiko were called &apos;Nono,&apos; and in Netsumura Village, Nonokoji Street on which the miko&apos;s houses used to stand, their graves still exist.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Arukimiko were called &apos;Nono,&apos; and in Netsu Village, Nonokoji Street on which the miko&apos;s houses used to stand, and their graves still exist.</e>
<cmt>Netsu Village　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="25">
<j>歩き巫女に国境は無く、全国何処でも自由に行けたため、関東から畿内を回って口寄せや舞を披露し、時には売春もしながら情報を収集し、ツナギ（連絡役）の者を通じて信玄に逐一報告した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As arukimiko were allowed to freely cross the border and go everywhere, they gathered information, acted as a liaison with and reported everything to Shingen, performing kuchiyose (spiritualism) and dance, and even sometimes prostituting themselves in Kanto region and Kinai region (provinces surrounding the ancient capitals of Nara and Kyoto).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because the arukimiko were allowed to freely cross the border and go everywhere, they gathered information, acted as liaisons with and reported everything to Shingen, performed kuchiyose (spiritualism) and dances, and sometimes prostituted themselves in the Kanto and Kinai regions (provinces surrounding the ancient capitals of Nara and Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because the arukimiko were allowed to freely cross the border and go everywhere, they gathered information, acted as liaisons with and reported everything to Shingen, performed kuchiyose (spiritualism) and dances, and sometimes prostituted themselves in the Kanto and Kinai regions (provinces surrounding the ancient capitals of Nara and Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>反面、信玄は家臣の謀反を恐れて、彼らの自宅に僧、巫女を泊めるのを禁じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand Shingen who was afraid of his vassals&apos; rebellion did not allow them to give Buddhist priests and arukimiko a night&apos;s lodging.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Shingen, who was afraid of his vassals&apos; rebellion, didn&apos;t allow them to give overnight lodging to Buddhist priests and arukimiko.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Shingen, who was afraid of his vassals&apos; rebellion, didn&apos;t allow them to give overnight lodging to Buddhist priests and arukimiko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Bzx(id:96115), Bakkai(id:7233), 固体物性(id:126677), 今井孝輔(id:64438), K66星雲(id:16609), Revth(id:12179), Kamakura(id:472), Satore(id:106335), 枳殻(id:181191), メカラッパー(id:112936), Escarbot(id:59151), 逆Ｌの男(id:8978), PipepBot(id:146181), RoboDick(id:34097), Mocchy(id:146197), YurikBot(id:18605), Fromm(id:71291), ＮｉＫｅ(id:7512), Kadzuwo(id:3701), Chlewbot(id:33904), MS472(id:58603), アスタロト(id:81932), 端くれの錬金術師(id:23040), Yas(id:739), U.S.S.Momotaro(id:646), FlaBot(id:30804), 目蒲東急之介(id:34741), Louperibot(id:128971), 2006年12月14日(id:100181), KH－editor(id:125369), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>