<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>練り切り</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nerikiri (a cake made of white bean jam which is artistically colored or shaped)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nerikiri (a cake made of white bean jam which is artistically colored or shaped)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nerikiri (a cake made of white bean jam which is artistically colored or shaped)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>練り切り（ねりきり）は、白餡に 求肥（ぎゅうひ：蒸すかゆでた白玉粉や餅米の粉に、砂糖や水飴を加えて練ったもの）やツクネイモを混ぜて練った生菓子の和菓子である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nerikiri (literally, made by kneading) is a fresh and moist type of Japanese confectionery made from white bean jam, gyuhi (a kind of rice cake made from glutinous rice or glutinous rice flour) and Chinese yam, and by mixing and kneading them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nerikiri (literally, made by kneading) is a fresh and moist type of Japanese confectionery made from white bean jam, gyuhi (a kind of rice cake made from refined rice flouror or glutinous rice flour with sugar and starch syrup) and Chinese yam, and by mixing and kneading them.</e>
<cmt>「砂糖や水飴を加えて」訳漏れ対応しました。glutinous rice→refined rice flour</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nerikiri (literally, made by kneading) is a Japanese type of unbaked cake that is made by mixing and kneading its ingredients, which are white bean jam, gyuhi (a kind of rice cake made from refined rice flour or glutinous rice flour with sugar and starch syrup) and Chinese yam.</e>
<cmt>a fresh and moist type of Japanese confectionery→a Japanese unbaked cakeflouror→flour</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>適度なやわらかさと粘度があり、これを様々な形を彫刻した木型に押し付けたり、手やへらで整形して細工を施し、着色料やクチナシなどの食用色素で彩色して仕上げる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nerikiri (literally, made by kneading) is a fresh and moist Japanese confectionery made from white bean jam, gyuhi (a kind of rice cake made from glutinous rice or glutinous rice flour) and Chinese yam, and by mixing and kneading them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nerikiri is a fresh and moist Japanese confectionery made from white bean jam, gyuhi (a kind of rice cake made from glutinous rice or glutinous rice flour) and Chinese yam, and by mixing and kneading them.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ上の段と全く同じ訳文が入っています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nerikiri with the appropriate degree of softness and viscosity is made by forcing the mixture into a wooden mold with various carved patterns, elaborating it by hand or with spatulas, and tinting it with food dyes such as artificial colors and gardenias.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れに対応しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="3">
<j>季節に合わせた色、形の物が作られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nerikiri with various color and shape are made depending on the season</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nerikiri with various color and shape are made depending on the season</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nerikiri is tinted with different colors and molded into various shapes according to the season.</e>
<cmt>全体的に書き換えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Tiyoringo(id:70026), Izayohi(id:13095), Tarobo(id:17287), ととりん(id:31982), Corwin(id:973), 午後紅茶(id:14285), 220.(id:7930), Hotei(id:7664), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>