<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>本音と建前</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Honne to Tatemae (one&apos;s personal feelings and the socially accepted view)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Honne to Tatemae (one&apos;s personal feelings and the socially accepted view)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Honne to Tatemae (one&apos;s personal feelings and the socially accepted view)</e>
<cmt>イタリックになっている箇所を変更しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>本音と建前（ほんねとたてまえ）は、社会現象を表す日本語である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Honne to tatemae&quot; is a Japanese expression to explain a social phenomenon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Honne to tatemae is a Japanese expression to explain a social phenomenon.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Honne to tatemae is a Japanese expression to explain a social phenomenon.</e>
<cmt>イタリックになっている箇所を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>まず、本音とは真実の感情・欲求を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">First, &quot;honne&quot; is the term to indicate one&apos;s real feelings and desire.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">First, honne is the term to indicate one&apos;s real feelings and desires.</e>
<cmt>plural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">First, honne is the term to indicate one&apos;s real feelings and desires.</e>
<cmt>イタリックになっている箇所を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>これらは社会・立場から期待・要求されることと違う場合があり、しばしば正直に表現されない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These feelings and desire may sometimes differ from what are expected or demanded by one&apos;s social status, so that it happens often that honne is not expressed honestly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These feelings and desires may sometimes differ from what are expected or demanded by one&apos;s social status, so that it often happens that honne is not expressed honestly.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These feelings and desires may sometimes differ from what are expected or demanded by one&apos;s social status, so that it often happens that honne is not expressed honestly.</e>
<cmt>イタリックになっている箇所を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>また一方、建前とは公に表す行動・意見を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, the term &quot;tatemae&quot; is referred to one&apos;s behaviors and opinions to be expressed officially.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, the term tatemae refers to one&apos;s behaviors and opinions to be expressed officially.</e>
<cmt>verb form</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, the term tatemae refers to one&apos;s behaviors and opinions to be expressed officially.</e>
<cmt>イタリックになっている箇所を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>これらは社会・立場から期待・要求されることで、本音と一致しない場合がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These behaviors and opinions are expected and demanded from one&apos;s social status, and are sometimes at odds with one&apos;s real feelings and desire.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These behaviors and opinions are expected and demanded from one&apos;s social status, and are sometimes at odds with one&apos;s real feelings and desires.</e>
<cmt>plural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These behaviors and opinions are expected and demanded from one&apos;s social status, and are sometimes at odds with one&apos;s real feelings and desires.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>この分離は、人間の成長過程で普遍的な現象である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This discrepancy appears ubiquitously as a phenomenon in the process of growth of human beings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This discrepancy appears ubiquitously as a phenomenon in the process of growth of human beings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This discrepancy appears ubiquitously as a phenomenon in the process of growth of human beings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>日本人論研究者によれば、日本にこれらの意味を表す言葉があるということは、日本の礼儀や文化への厳格さの一要素だと見ている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Researchers on theories of Japanese cultural and racial uniqueness consider that the existence of such wording as to express discrepancy between personal feelings and social view is an element of austerity of Japanese people in their courtesy and culture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Researchers on theories of Japanese cultural and racial uniqueness consider that the existence of such wording to express discrepancy between personal feelings and social view is an element of austerity of Japanese people in their courtesy and culture.</e>
<cmt>omitted &quot;as&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Researchers on theories of Japanese cultural and racial uniqueness consider that the existence of such wording to express discrepancy between personal feelings and social view is an element of austerity of Japanese people in their courtesy and culture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>日本の劇において、歴史的に本音と義理は主な題材である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Personal feelings and social requirements have been historically main subjects of Japanese plays.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Personal feelings and social requirements have historically been main subjects of Japanese plays.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Personal feelings and social requirements have historically been main subjects of Japanese plays.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>典型的な例として、主人公は自分の家族、大名、禁じられた恋愛との選択に迫られた場合に、唯一の窮地からの解決として、心中をする（例：近松もの）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a typical example, a leading character who is forced to select either to take heed of his family and his lord or to fulfil his forbidden love affairs cannot help but commit a suicide with his lover in order to get released from the dilemma (as depicted, for instance, in a series of drama written by Monzaemon CHIKAMATSU.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a typical example, a leading character who is forced to select either to take heed of his family and his lord or to fulfill his forbidden love affairs cannot help but commit suicide with his lover in order to be released from the dilemma (as depicted, for instance, in a series of drama written by Monzaemon CHIKAMATSU.)</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a typical example, a leading character who is forced to select either to take heed of his family and his lord or to fulfill his forbidden love affairs cannot help but commit suicide with his lover in order to be released from the dilemma (as depicted, for instance, in a series of drama written by Monzaemon CHIKAMATSU.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>しかし日本以外の国にこの様な問題が全く無いわけではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, this kind of phenomenon is not always limited to Japan but can be seen in other countries than Japan, too.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, this kind of phenomenon is not always limited to Japan but can also be seen in countries other than Japan.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, this kind of phenomenon is not always limited to Japan but can also be seen in countries other than Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 MikeAz800o(id:58193), Www(id:41430), SatoshiAsh(id:19531), 貿易風(id:85487), VolkovBot(id:105371), Snff(id:156111), おはぐろ蜻蛉(id:8405), Alexbot(id:157199), Clarin(id:60278), Punu(id:195933), -1g(id:67660), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>