<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>朝服</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chofuku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chofuku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chofuku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>朝服（ちょうふく）は、飛鳥時代から平安時代にかけて、官人が朝廷に出仕するときに着用した衣服である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chofuku is the clothes that kanjin (government officials) wore from Aska period to Heian period when they came to work at the court on a regular basis.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chofuku is the clothes that government officials wore from the Aska period to the Heian period when they came to work at the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>冠詞「朝廷」の訳を変更「官人」を英語表記のみに変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chofuku is the clothes that government officials wore from the Aska period to the Heian period when they came to work at the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>上衣である和服用語集には脇の縫われた文官用の縫腋袍と、袖付けから下が縫い合わさせておらず、脇が開いている武官用の闕腋袍とがあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to wafuku (traditional Japanese clothes) glossary, in the ho (robe or jacket) there were hoeki no ho (robe with a round color, stitched sides and a ran) for civil officers, and kettei no ho (robe without sides being stitched) for military officers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to wafuku (traditional Japanese clothes) glossary, there were two types of ho (robe or jacket): hoeki no ho (robe with sides being stitched) for civil officers and ketteki no ho (robe without sides being stitched) for military officers.</e>
<cmt>「闕腋袍」のスペルミスを修正構成を変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to wafuku (traditional Japanese clothes) glossary, there were two types of ho (robe or jacket): hoeki no ho (robe with sides being stitched) for civil officers and ketteki no ho (robe without sides being stitched) for military officers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="3">
<j>唐の服飾に影響されて制定されたが、制定されてからしばらくの間は、唐風の見栄えであったと想像されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the system of chofuku was established from the influence from Tang dynasty, it is estimated that chofuku looked like the ones in Chinese style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the system of chofuku was established under the influence of the Tang dynasty, it is estimated that chofuku looked like the ones in China for some time.</e>
<cmt>前置詞「制定されてからしばらくの間は」を追加</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the system of chofuku was established under the influence of the Tang dynasty, it is estimated that chofuku looked like the ones in China for some time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>後に国風文化の影響を受けて束帯や衣冠・直衣などに変化していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, by the influence of kokufubunka (indigenous Japanese culture), chofuku changed into ikan sokutai (traditional ceremonial court dress) and noshi (everyday clothes for nobles).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, under the influence of the Kokufu Bunka (Japan&apos;s original national culture), chofuku changed into ikan sokutai (traditional ceremonial court dress) and noshi (everyday clothes for nobles).</e>
<cmt>前置詞「国風文化」の表記を変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, under the influence of the Kokufu Bunka (Japan&apos;s original national culture), chofuku changed into ikan sokutai (traditional ceremonial court dress) and noshi (everyday clothes for nobles).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="5">
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>孝徳天皇の時代には既に制定されていたが、天武天皇の時代に一時期廃された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though chofuku had been established by the period of Emperor Kotoku, it was temporarily abolished at the period of Emperor Tenmu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though chofuku had been established by the period of the Emperor Kotoku, it was temporarily abolished at the period of the Emperor Tenmu.</e>
<cmt>冠詞</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though chofuku had been established by the period of the Emperor Kotoku, it was temporarily abolished at the period of the Emperor Tenmu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>文武天皇の時代に大宝令の制定とともに服飾も一新され、新たに礼服 (宮中)（らいふく）・朝服・制服の制が定められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the period of Emperor Monmu, with the establishment of Taihoryo (Taiho Code), the system of raifuku (formal court attire), chofuku and seifuku (uniform) was introduced.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the period of the Emperor Monmu, with the establishment of Taihoryo (Taiho Code), the system of raifuku (formal court attire), chofuku and seifuku (uniform) was introduced.</e>
<cmt>冠詞</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the period of the Emperor Monmu, with the establishment of Taihoryo (Taiho Code), the system of raifuku (formal court attire), chofuku and seifuku (uniform) was introduced.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="8">
<j>奈良時代の『養老律令』の「衣服令」が定めるところによると、文官の袍が「衣」と呼ばれるのに対し、武官の袍は「襖」と呼ばれ、この「襖」が闕腋袍であったとみられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the stipulation by &apos;ebukuryo&apos; (The Garment Code) of &quot;Yoro ritsuryo code (code promulgated in the Yoro period),&quot; the ho (robe) of civil officers was called &apos;e (衣)&apos; while ho of military officers was called &apos;ou (襖),&apos; which seems to have been kettei no ho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the stipulation by &apos;ebukuryo&apos; (The garment code) of &quot;Yoro ritsuryo code (the code promulgated in the Yoro period),&quot; the ho (robe) of civil officers was called &apos;e (衣)&apos; while ho of military officers was called &apos;ou (襖),&apos; which seems to have been ketteki no ho.</e>
<cmt>「闕腋袍」のスペルミスを修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the stipulation by &apos;ebukuryo&apos; (The garment code) of &quot;Yoro ritsuryo code (the code promulgated in the Yoro period),&quot; the ho (robe) of civil officers was called &apos;e (衣)&apos; while ho of military officers was called &apos;ou (襖),&apos; which seems to have been ketteki no ho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="9">
<j>位階と服色・構成</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ikai (court rank) and the color and construction of chofuku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ikai (court rank) and the color and construction of chofuku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ikai (court rank) and the color and construction of chofuku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>令制によれば、一品親王以下、臣下の位階に至るまでは、当色（とうじき＝服の色目）は礼服と同じであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the ritsuryo code, from ippon shinno (the first-ranked Imperial Prince) down to subjects the tojiki (the color corresponding to one&apos;s official rank) of chofuku was the same as the color of raifuku (formal attire).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the ritsuryo code, from Ippon Shinno (the first-ranked Imperial Prince) down to subjects the tojiki (the color corresponding to one&apos;s official rank) of chofuku was the same as that of raifuku (formal attire).</e>
<cmt>「一品親王」の表記を大文字に変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the ritsuryo code, from Ippon Shinno (the first-ranked Imperial Prince) down to subjects the tojiki (the color corresponding to one&apos;s official rank) of chofuku was the same as that of raifuku (formal attire).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>親王は深紫、二位以下五位以上は浅紫。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Prince&apos;s color was deep purple and from nii (second rank) down to goi (fifth rank) was pale purple.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Prince&apos;s color was deep purple and the color for subjects from from nii (second rank) down to goi (fifth rank) was pale purple.</e>
<cmt>構成を少し変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Prince&apos;s color was deep purple and the color for subjects from from nii (second rank) down to goi (fifth rank) was pale purple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>臣下は一位深紫、二位・三位は浅紫、四位は深緋、五位は浅緋、六位は深緑、七位は浅緑、八位は深縹、初位は浅縹と定められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for subjects, it was stipulated that the color of ichii (the first rank) was deep purple, nii and sanmi (the second and third rank) pale purple, shii (the fourth rank) deep scarlet, goi (the fifth rank) pale scarlet, rokui (the sixth rank) deep green, shichii (the seventh rank) pale green, hachii (the eighth rank) dark light indigo blue and shoi (initial rank) pale light indigo blue, respectively.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For subjects, it was stipulated that the color of ichii (first rank) was deep purple, nii and sanmi (second and third rank) pale purple, shii (fourth rank) deep scarlet, goi (fifth rank) pale scarlet, rokui (sixth rank) deep green, shichii (seventh rank) pale green, hachii (eighth rank) dark blue and shoi (initial rank) azure blue, respectively.</e>
<cmt>「深縹」「浅縹」の表記を変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For subjects, it was stipulated that the color of ichii (first rank) was deep purple, nii and sanmi (second and third rank) pale purple, shii (fourth rank) deep scarlet, goi (fifth rank) pale scarlet, rokui (sixth rank) deep green, shichii (seventh rank) pale green, hachii (eighth rank) dark blue and shoi (initial rank) azure blue, respectively.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="13">
<j>五位以上は、皀羅頭巾（くりのうすはたのときん・くりのらのときん）、牙笏、金銀装腰帯、白袴、烏皮履（くろかわのくつ・うひり）を着けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The officials of the fifth rank or higher wore kuri no usuhara skullcap, geshaku (ivory tablet), sash decorated with gold and silver, white hakama (a formal divided and pleated skirt for men) and hiuri (black leather shoes).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The officials of the fifth rank or higher wore kuri no usuhara skullcap, geshaku (ivory tablet), sash decorated with gold and silver, white hakama (a formal divided and pleated skirt for men) and uhiri (black leather shoes).</e>
<cmt>「烏皮履」のスペルミスを修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The officials of the fifth rank or higher wore kuri no usuhara skullcap, geshaku (ivory tablet), sash decorated with gold and silver, white hakama (a formal divided and pleated skirt for men) and uhiri (black leather shoes).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>六位以下は、皀縵頭巾（くりのかとりのときん）、木笏、烏油腰帯、白袴、白襪（しろしとうず）、烏皮履を着けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And the officials of the sixth rank or lower wore kuri no katori skullcap, mokushaku (wooden tablet), kuronuri yotai (black sash), white hakama, shirotozu (white tabi, or socks) and hiuri.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And the officials of the sixth rank or lower wore kuri no katori skullcap, mokushaku (wooden tablet), black sash, white hakama, shirotozu (white tabi, or socks) and uhiri.</e>
<cmt>「烏皮履」のスペルミスを修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And the officials of the sixth rank or lower wore kuri no katori skullcap, mokushaku (wooden tablet), black sash, white hakama, shirotozu (white tabi, or socks) and uhiri.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="15">
<j>袍を締める際には、後の束帯と同様に石帯を用いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order to fasten the ho (the robe), sekitai (leather belt) was used, which was the same as it was used for sokutai (traditional ceremonial court dress).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to fasten the ho (the robe), sekitai (leather belt) was used, which was the same as the one used for sokutai (traditional ceremonial court dress) later.</e>
<cmt>構成を変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to fasten the ho (the robe), sekitai (leather belt) was used, which was the same as the one used for sokutai (traditional ceremonial court dress) later.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>この石帯に付けられていた石が、日本各地の官衙跡地の遺跡から出土している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The stone attached to the sekitai was found at the ruins of kanga (government office) around Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The stone attached to the sekitai was found at the ruins of government offices around Japan.</e>
<cmt>「官衙」の表記を英語のみに変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The stone attached to the sekitai was found at the ruins of government offices around Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="17">
<j>時代の変遷とともに</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The transition of the time</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The transition of the time</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The transition of the time</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>時代を経ると次第に束帯へと変化していき、それに伴い、官人の勤務服から儀式の際の式服や正装へと地位の昇格が起きた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Over time chofuku gradually changed into sokutai, and with the change, chofuku came to be regarded as more important than before as the ones from the normal working clothes for kanjin to ceremonial dress and formal attire</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Over time chofuku gradually changed into sokutai, and with the change, chofuku came to be regarded as more important than before changing its role from the normal working clothes for government officials to the ceremonial dress and formal attire.</e>
<cmt>官人をkanjinからgovernment officialsに変更構成を変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Over time chofuku gradually changed into sokutai, and with the change, chofuku came to be regarded as more important than before changing its role from the normal working clothes for government officials to the ceremonial dress and formal attire.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="19">
<j>当色は宝亀5年正月に大臣で二位は中紫とし、大同 (日本)元年7月には七位を六位と同じく深緑とし、初位を八位と同じく深縹とし、弘仁元年9月に諸王二位以下の浅紫を中紫に、大臣で二位を中紫から深紫に、二位三位の浅紫を中紫に改めるなどのことがあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January, 744, the color of chofuku for Daijin (Minister) was decided as nakamurasaki purple, and in July, 806 the color of shichii (the seventh rank) was changed to deep hanada (light indigo blue), the same as rokui (the sixth rank), and in September, 810 the dress color of shoo (prince who didn&apos;t receive any proclamation to be an Imperial Prince) was changed from nakamurasaki purple to deep purple and the color of nii and sanmi to nakamurasaki purple.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In January, 774, the color of chofuku for the second-rank Ministers was decided as medium purple, and in July, 806 the color for shichii (seventh rank) was changed to deep green, the same as rokui (sixth rank), and the color for shoi (initial rank) was changed to dark blue, the same as hachii (eighth rank), and in September, 810 the dress color for Shoo (prince who didn&apos;t receive any proclamation to be an Imperial Prince) was changed from pale purple to medium purple and the color for the second rank Ministers was changed from medium purple to deep purple and the color for nii and sanmi (second and third ranks) was changed from the pale purple to medium purple.</e>
<cmt>宝亀5年の西暦の誤りを訂正「中紫」の表記ｊｊをnakamurasaki purple→medium purpleに変更七位の色の誤りを訂正初位の部分を追加諸王の色の誤りを訂正大臣で二位の部分を追加</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In January, 774, the color of chofuku for the second-rank Ministers was decided as medium purple, and in July, 806 the color for shichii (seventh rank) was changed to deep green, the same as rokui (sixth rank), and the color for shoi (initial rank) was changed to dark blue, the same as hachii (eighth rank), and in September, 810 the dress color for Shoo (prince who didn&apos;t receive any proclamation to be an Imperial Prince) was changed from pale purple to medium purple and the color for the second rank Ministers was changed from medium purple to deep purple and the color for nii and sanmi (second and third ranks) was changed from the pale purple to medium purple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>染色技術の変遷とあいまって寛弘年間以降は四位以上は黒、五位は蘇芳、六位及び六位以下は縹の3色となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the changing method of dyeing, Kanko era and later the three colors were decided, that is, for shii or higher as black, goi as suo (dark red) and rokui or lower as hanada.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the changing method of dyeing, the Kanko era and later the three colors were decided, that is, for shii (forth-rank) or higher as black, the gou (fifth-rank) as dark red and rokui (sixth-rank) or lower as hanada (light blue).</e>
<cmt>階位と色を英語の表記に変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the changing method of dyeing, the Kanko era and later the three colors were decided, that is, for shii (forth-rank) or higher as black, the gou (fifth-rank) as dark red and rokui (sixth-rank) or lower as hanada (light blue).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>