<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>舞妓</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Maiko (apprentice geisha, dancing girl)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Maiko (apprentice geisha, dancing girl)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Maiko (apprentice geisha, dancing girl)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>舞妓 （まいこ）は年少芸妓、芸子（芸妓）の見習い、修行段階の者を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term &quot;Maiko&quot; refers to a young geisha or an apprentice of geisha.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term &quot;Maiko&quot; refers to a young geisha or a geisha apprentice.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term &quot;Maiko&quot; refers to a young geisha or a geisha apprentice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>舞妓は京都（大阪、奈良などでも）の呼称である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Maiko&quot; is the name used in Kyoto Prefecture (also in Osaka, Nara Prefectures and so on).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Maiko&quot; is the name used in Kyoto Prefecture (also in Osaka, and Nara Prefectures, etc).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Maiko&quot; is the name used in Kyoto Prefecture (also in Osaka, and Nara Prefectures, etc).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>東京など関東地域でいう『半玉』もしくは『おしゃく』に相当する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It corresponds to &quot;Hangyoku (child geisha, apprentice entertainer)&quot; or &quot;Oshaku (person pouring alcohol for guests or customers)&quot; in Kanto region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It corresponds to &quot;Hangyoku (child geisha, apprentice entertainer)&quot; or &quot;Oshaku (person pouring alcohol for guests or customers)&quot; in the Kanto region.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It corresponds to &quot;Hangyoku (child geisha, apprentice entertainer)&quot; or &quot;Oshaku (person pouring alcohol for guests or customers)&quot; in the Kanto region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>芸者は江戸での呼び方なので、区別する必要がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because the term, &quot;Geisha,&quot; is used in Edo (old name of Tokyo), it needs to be distinguished.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because the term, &quot;Geisha,&quot; is used in Edo (old name for Tokyo), it needs to be distinguished.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because the term, &quot;Geisha,&quot; is used in Edo (old name for Tokyo), it needs to be distinguished.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>京都の舞妓</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Maiko in Kyoto</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Maiko in Kyoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Maiko in Kyoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>で舞を披露する舞妓</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Maiko who performs dancing in Kyoto</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Maiko who performs dancing in Kyoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Maiko who performs dancing in Kyoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>古くは『舞子』と書き、かつては9～12歳でお座敷に上がり接客作法を学び、芸能など修業して一人前の芸妓に成長していたが、戦後児童福祉法と労働基準法の改正にともない現在は中学卒業後でないとなれない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The &quot;Maiko (舞妓)&quot; was written as &quot;Maiko (舞子)&quot; in past times, and learned customer service skills at ozashiki (banquets in which guests were attended by geisha) at the age of 9-12 and stood on her feet through the training of entertainment, but now any girl can not become Maiko until she graduates a junior high school in accordance with the revision of the Child Welfare Act and the Labor Standards Law after the war.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Maiko (舞妓)&quot; was written as &quot;Maiko (舞子)&quot; in past times, and she learned customer service skills at ozashiki (banquets in which guests were attended by geisha) at the age of 9-12 and stood on her feet through the training of entertainment, but now no young girls can become Maiko until she graduates junior high school in accordance with the revision of the Child Welfare Act and the Labor Standards Law after the war.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &quot;Maiko (舞妓)&quot; was written as &quot;Maiko (舞子)&quot; in past times, and she learned customer service skills at ozashiki (banquets in which guests were attended by geisha) at the age of 9 - 12 and stood on her feet through the training of entertainment, but now no young girls can become Maiko until she graduates junior high school in accordance with the revision of the Child Welfare Act and the Labor Standards Law after the war.</e>
<cmt>スペース補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>通例、半年から2年ほどの「仕込み」期間を経た後、1か月間「見習い」としてだらりの帯の半分の長さの「半だらり」の帯を締め、姐さん芸妓と共に茶屋で修行する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Usually, after the &apos;training&apos; period from a half to two years, Maiko wears a sash of &apos;Handarari,&apos; which is half long of darari no obi (long draping sash) as &apos;an apprentice&apos; for a month and trains herself with senior geisha at tea house.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Usually, after a &apos;training&apos; period from a half to two years, Maiko wear a sash of &apos;Handarari,&apos; which is half as long as darari no obi (long draping sash) as &apos;an apprentice&apos; for a month and trains herself with senior geisha at a tea house.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Usually, after a &apos;training&apos; period from a half to two years, Maiko wear a sash of &apos;Handarari,&apos; which is half as long as darari no obi (long draping sash) as &apos;an apprentice&apos; for a month and trains herself with senior geisha at a tea house.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>置屋の女将、茶屋組合よりの許しが出れば、晴れて舞妓として「見世出し」が可能となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If admitted by the mistress of geisha dwelling and the association of tea house, she can debut as a new Maiko (&apos;Misedashi&apos;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If admitted by the mistress of the geisha dwelling and the tea house association, she can debut as a new Maiko (&apos;Misedashi&apos;).</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If admitted by the mistress of the geisha dwelling and the tea house association, she can debut as a new Maiko (&apos;Misedashi&apos;).</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>座敷や舞台に上がるときは芸妓も舞妓も白塗りの厚化粧をするが芸妓が通常鬘を付けるのに対し、舞妓は自髪で日本髪を結い、四季の花などをあしらった華やかな簪つまみ簪を挿す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At ozashiki and on the stage both geisha and Maiko are heavily-powdered with Shironuri (white makeup), but while a geisha usually wears a wig, Maiko dresses her hair in traditional Japanese style and puts on gorgeous ornate hairpin, tsumami-kanzashi (a decorative hair pin) featuring something like flowers of each season.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At ozashiki and on the stage both geisha and Maiko are heavily-powdered with Shironuri (white makeup), but while a geisha usually wears a wig, Maiko dresses her hair in traditional Japanese style and wears a gorgeous ornate hairpin, tsumami-kanzashi (a decorative hair pin) featuring something like flowers of each season.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At ozashiki and on the stage both geisha and Maiko are heavily-powdered with Shironuri (white makeup), but while a geisha usually wears a wig, Maiko dresses her hair in traditional Japanese style and wears a gorgeous ornate hairpin, tsumami-kanzashi (a decorative hair pin) featuring something like flowers of each season.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>舞妓の初期は「割れしのぶ」という髪型で、2、3年後に「おふく」となり、芸妓への襟替え1～4週間前には「先笄」を結い、お歯黒を付ける（引眉しないので半元服の習慣が現代に残るものと見てよい）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The hair style of Maiko at the early stage is &apos;wareshinobu,&apos; which turns to be &apos;Ofuku&apos; in a few years later, and 1-4 weeks before erigae (promoted to a full-fledged geisha) she dresses &apos;sakko fashion (Maiko&apos;s hairstyle)&apos; and puts teeth black (she does not paint eyebrows, which can be regarded as the custom of Hangempuku (attaining womanhood informally) continuing still now).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The hair style of Maiko at the early stage is &apos;wareshinobu,&apos; which turns to be &apos;Ofuku&apos; in a few years later, and 1-4 weeks before erigae (promoted to a full-fledged geisha) she dresses &apos;sakko fashion (Maiko&apos;s hairstyle)&apos; and puts teeth black (she does not paint eyebrows, which can be regarded as the custom of Hangempuku (attaining womanhood informally) continuing still now).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The hair style of Maiko at the early stage is &apos;wareshinobu,&apos; which turns to be &apos;Ofuku&apos; in a few years later, and 1 - 4 weeks before erigae (promoted to a full-fledged geisha) she dresses &apos;sakko fashion (Maiko&apos;s hairstyle)&apos; and puts teeth black (she does not paint eyebrows, which can be regarded as the custom of Hangempuku (attaining womanhood informally) continuing still now).</e>
<cmt>スペース補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>襟替えの時期は20歳前後の場合が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many Maiko promote to a full-fledged geisha around the age of 20.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many Maiko are promoted to full-fledged geisha around the age of 20.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many Maiko are promoted to full-fledged geisha around the age of 20.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>年齢が若いために見習いであるという建前から、衣装はかならず肩上げ、袖上げのされた裾を引いた振袖の着物を着る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In accordance with the public stance that she is an apprentice because she is young, Maiko surely wears long-sleeved kimono pulled a tuck at the shoulders and sleeves.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In accordance with the public stance that she is an apprentice because she is young, Maiko surely wears a long-sleeved kimono pulled in a tuck at the shoulders and sleeves.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In accordance with the public stance that she is an apprentice because she is young, Maiko surely wears a long-sleeved kimono pulled in a tuck at the shoulders and sleeves.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>ぽっくり（こっぽりとも、京都では「おこぼ」）の下駄にだらりの帯、という派手な格好もあるせいで、現在ではむしろ芸妓（芸子）よりも舞妓のほうが上方花街の代表的存在であるといえるかもしれない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Maiko puts on gaudy costumes such as Pokkuri (Koppori or &apos;Okobo&apos; in Kyoto, girl&apos;s lacquered wooden clogs) and darari no obi, it could be said that Maiko is a more representative figure at red-light districts in Kyoto and vicinity rather than geisha.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Maiko wear gaudy costumes such as Pokkuri (Koppori or &apos;Okobo&apos; in Kyoto, girl&apos;s lacquered wooden clogs) and darari no obi, it could be said that Maiko is a more representative figure at red-light districts in Kyoto and vicinity, rather than geisha.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Maiko wear gaudy costumes such as Pokkuri (Koppori or &apos;Okobo&apos; in Kyoto, girl&apos;s lacquered wooden clogs) and darari no obi, it could be said that Maiko is a more representative figure at red-light districts in Kyoto and vicinity, rather than geisha.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>座敷では主に立方を勤め、祇園甲部に限って京舞井上流、それ以外では若柳流などの舞踊を披露する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Maiko is mainly in charge of dancing at ozashiki and performs the dancing of Kyomai Inoue-ryu school in Gion Kobu district and other dancing such as Wakayagi Ryu school in other districts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Maiko is mainly in charge of dancing at ozashiki and performs the dancing of Kyomai Inoue-ryu school in Gion Kobu district and other dancing such as the Wakayagi Ryu school in other districts.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Maiko is mainly in charge of dancing at ozashiki and performs the dancing of Kyomai Inoue school in Gion Kobu district and other dancing such as the Wakayagi school in other districts.</e>
<cmt>-ryu削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>いずれの出身地にかかわりなく独特の京ことば（祇園ことば）を使うよう教育されるために、京都の象徴であるがごとくあつかわれることも多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She is trained to use Kyoto dialect without regard to her origin, and consequently, Maiko is often treated as if she is a symbol of Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She is trained to use the Kyoto dialect without regard to her origin, and consequently, Maiko is often treated as if she is a symbol of Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She is trained to use the Kyoto dialect without regard to her origin, and consequently, Maiko is often treated as if she is a symbol of Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="17">
<j>本業は茶屋においての接待であるが、最近はテレビなどのメディアへの露出、養護施設や病院への慰問、海外への派遣の仕事も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The main business is an entertainment at tea house, but recently other business such as TV appearance, visiting care facilities or hospitals and going abroad are increasing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The main business is entertainment at a tea house, but recently other business such as TV appearance, visiting care facilities or hospitals and going abroad are increasing.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The main business is entertainment at a tea house, but recently other business such as TV appearance, visiting care facilities or hospitals and going abroad are increasing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>かつて「一見さんお断り」の閉鎖的空間であった花街も、徐々に外に対して門戸を開いているようだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The red-light district which was a closed space of &apos;No first-time customers&apos; seems to open the doors to outsiders gradually.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The red-light district which was a closed space of &apos;No first-time customers&apos; seemed to have gradually opened its doors to outsiders.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The red-light district which was a closed space of &apos;No first-time customers&apos; seemed to have gradually opened its doors to outsiders.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="19">
<j>事実、舞妓のなり手がいない置屋では、インターネットを通して舞妓志望者を募るところもあるという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In fact, it is said that some geisha dwelling which has no Maiko are recruiting applicants of Maiko through Internet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In fact, it is said that some geisha dwellings which have no Maiko are recruiting applicants for Maiko through the Internet.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact, it is said that some geisha dwellings which have no Maiko are recruiting applicants for Maiko through the Internet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="20">
<j>現在、京都の花街で舞妓がいるのは祇園甲部、宮川町、祇園東、先斗町、上七軒の五花街である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At present it is the five red-light districts of Gion Kobu, Miyagawa-cho, Gion higashi, Ponto cho and Kamishichiken Districts where there are Maiko in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At present it is the five red-light districts of Gion Kobu, Miyagawa-cho, Gion higashi, Ponto cho, and the Kamishichiken Districts, where there are Maiko in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At present it is the five red-light districts of Gion Kobu, Miyagawa-cho, Gion Higashi, Ponto-cho, and the Kamishichiken districts, where there are Maiko in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>higashi→Hgashi-補足Districts→districts</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>最近はブームのせいもあってか、舞妓志望者は増える一方である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The number of applicant for Maiko is increasing, partly because of the recent boom.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The number of applicant for Maiko is increasing, partly because of the recent boom.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The number of applicant for Maiko is increasing, partly because of the recent boom.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>にもかかわらず、憧れだけで入門した妓は封建的かつ前近代的な体質を持つ花街の昔気質のつらい修行に耐え切れず辞めてしまう場合が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, a girl who becomes a disciple of Maiko only by the feeling of yearning often resigns, because she can not bear the old-fashioned severe training of feudalistic red-light district.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, a girl who becomes a disciple of Maiko only because of her yearning feelings often resigns, because she can not bear the old-fashioned severe training of the feudalistic red-light district.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, a girl who becomes a disciple of Maiko only because of her yearning feelings often resigns, because she can not bear the old-fashioned severe training of the feudalistic red-light district.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>そのため、花街ではいかに質の高い芸舞妓を保持するかが今後の問題といえそうだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, it could be said that it is the future task how to keep high qualified Maiko and geisha in red-light districts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, it is future task how to keep highly qualified Maiko and geisha in the red-light districts.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, it is future task how to keep highly qualified Maiko and geisha in the red-light districts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>京都以外の舞妓</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Maiko except Kyoto</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Maiko outside Kyoto</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Maiko outside Kyoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="24">
<j>酒田市（山形県）には舞娘と書いてまいこと読む年少芸妓が居るが、衣装は京都の舞妓とは異なる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Sakata City (Yamagata Prefecture) there are young geisha who are called Maiko, written as &apos;舞娘,&apos; but their costumes are different from those of Maiko in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Sakata City (Yamagata Prefecture) there are young geisha who are called Maiko, written as &apos;舞娘,&apos; but their costumes are different from those of Maiko in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Sakata City (Yamagata Prefecture) there are young geisha who are called Maiko, written as &apos;舞娘,&apos; but their costumes are different from those of Maiko in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="25">
<j>山形市にも上記と同様のやまがた舞妓（舞子）が居る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Yamagata City there are also Yamagata maiko who are the same as above.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Yamagata City there are also Yamagata maiko who are the same as above.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Yamagata City there are also Yamagata maiko who are the same as above.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>花笠祭りにも登場。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They also appear in Hanagasa-matsuri Festival.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They also appear in the Hanagasa-matsuri Festival.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They also appear in the Hanagasa-matsuri Festival.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="27">
<j>あわら市（福井県）の芦原温泉に於いて三年前に38年ぶりの舞妓が誕生。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the area of Awara-Onsen Hot Spring in Awara City, Fukui Prefecture, a Maiko appeared three years ago for the first time in 38 years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the area of Awara-Onsen Hot Spring in Awara City, Fukui Prefecture, a Maiko appeared three years ago for the first time in 38 years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the area of Awara-Onsen Hot Spring in Awara City, Fukui Prefecture, a Maiko appeared three years ago for the first time in 38 years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>現在、二名の舞妓がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At present there are two Maiko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At present there are two Maiko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At present there are two Maiko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>ひきずりの着物にだらりの帯、という京都の舞妓と同じ衣装、但し地毛ではなくかつら（場合により地毛で結っている時もある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They put on the same costumes as those of Maiko in Kyoto with Hikizuri no kimono and darari no obi, but they dress wigs instead of their own hair (sometimes they dress their hair).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They wear the same dress as the Maiko in Kyoto with Hikizuri no kimono and darari no obi, but they have wigs instead of doing their own hair (sometimes they have their hair done up).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They wear the same dress as the Maiko in Kyoto with Hikizuri no kimono and darari no obi, but they have wigs instead of doing their own hair (sometimes they have their hair done up).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="30">
<j>奈良市元林院町の花街は細々と続いている、という状態で、2006年5月28日に舞妓（京都と同じ衣装）が1名誕生したが、これを入れて芸妓は14名のみ、という状態である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The red-light district in Genrinin-cho, Nara City, has continued somehow and there are only 14 geisha including one new Maiko (with the same costume of Maiko in Kyoto) who appeared on May 28, 2006.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The red-light district in Genrinin-cho, Nara City, has continued somehow and there are only 14 geisha including one new Maiko (with the same kimono of Maiko in Kyoto) who appeared on May 28, 2006.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The red-light district in Genrinin-cho, Nara City, has continued somehow and there are only 14 geisha including one new Maiko (with the same kimono of Maiko in Kyoto) who appeared on May 28, 2006.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>舞妓は京都と同じくお引きの振袖にだらりの帯、地毛で結った京風日本髪に花かんざしを挿し、おこぼを履く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Maiko puts on Ohiki no furisode (long-sleeved Kimono), darari no obi, Hana kanzashi (flower featured hair pin) on her hair dressed to Japanese coiffure of Kyoto style and Okobo, which are the same as those of Maiko in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Maiko puts on Ohiki no furisode (long-sleeved Kimono), darari no obi, Hana kanzashi (flower featured hair pin) on her hair dressed to Japanese coiffure of Kyoto style and Okobo, which are the same as those of Maiko in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Maiko puts on Ohiki no furisode (long-sleeved Kimono), darari no obi, Hana kanzashi (flower featured hair pin) on her hair dressed to Japanese coiffure of Kyoto style and Okobo, which are the same as those of Maiko in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="32">
<j>大阪市には戦前には舞妓が居た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Osaka City there were Maiko before the war.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Osaka City there were Maiko before the war.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Osaka City there were Maiko before the war.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>京都とは異なり、帯結びが腰元の様な立て矢であるのが特徴（「やぎっちゃ」という結び方）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its characteristic was that the way of winding sash was Tateya (vertical arrow) like female servant (a winding way called &apos;Yagiccha&apos;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their characteristics were like the way of a winding sash was Tateya (vertical arrow) like female servant (a winding way called &apos;Yagiccha&apos;).</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Their characteristics were like the way of a winding sash was Tateya (vertical arrow) like female servant (a winding way called &apos;Yagiccha&apos;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>また髪型も京風の引き鬢ではなく、江戸風の出し鬢であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, its hair style was not Hikibin (a style of sideburns) of Kyoto style but was Dashibin (a style of sideburns) in Edo style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, their hair style was not Hikibin (a style of sideburns) of the Kyoto style, but was Dashibin (a style of sideburns) from the Edo style.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, their hair style was not Hikibin (a style of sideburns) of the Kyoto style, but was Dashibin (a style of sideburns) from the Edo style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>現在、北の新地で復活を目指している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Kitashinchi district there is a movement to restore Maiko at present.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Kitashinchi district there is presently a movement to restore Maiko.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Kitashinchi district there is presently a movement to restore Maiko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="36">
<j>神戸市の有馬温泉では高卒の新人は舞妓（半玉）と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the area of Arima-Onsen Hot Spring in Kobe City, new recruits after finishing high school are called Maiko (Hangyoku).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the area of Arima-Onsen Hot Spring in Kobe City, new recruits after finishing high school are called Maiko (Hangyoku).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the area of Arima-Onsen Hot Spring in Kobe City, new recruits after finishing high school are called Maiko (Hangyoku).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>詰め袖の着物だが京都と同様の肩上げをし、鬘だが花かんざしを付ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They wear Kimono of Tsume sode (a kind of sewing sleeves) but pull a tuck at the shoulders in the same way of Kyoto and put Hanakanzashi on a wig.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They wear Kimono of Tsume sode (a kind of sewing sleeves) but tucked at the shoulders in the same way as in Kyoto and they wear Hanakanzashi on a wig.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They wear Kimono of Tsume sode (a kind of sewing sleeves) but tucked at the shoulders in the same way as in Kyoto and they wear Hanakanzashi on a wig.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="38">
<j>いずれの花街も京都と違い現在は舞妓として座敷に出るには18歳以上（高校生は不可）であることが定められている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Unlike in Kyoto, in any other red-light districts it is regulated that Maiko should be more than 18 years old (disapproval of high school students) to appear at ozashiki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unlike in Kyoto, in any other red-light district it is regulated that Maiko should be more than 18 years old (high school students are prohibited) to appear at ozashiki.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unlike in Kyoto, in any other red-light district it is regulated that Maiko should be more than 18 years old (high school students are prohibited) to appear at ozashiki.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 WIPE(id:173578), BOTarate(id:185620), ととりん(id:31982), Πrate(id:11329), D.h(id:79056), Ultratomio(id:1090), Toshiya Na(id:101573), Tribot(id:186681), Mishika(id:276), MegMilk(id:87329), Ichikoma1(id:178933), Goki(id:7107), Fromm(id:71291), 怪蘇(id:45514), 石崎せいか(id:161549), Korokoro(id:42329), 竹田(id:72642), 今紫(id:9521), Bankokuya(id:91191), Tomorrow0622(id:26939), Mikomaid(id:56139), Aryarya(id:35365), Jade0416(id:104181), Chuta(id:10457), Komari(id:115776), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>