<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>蚊帳</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaya</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mosquito Net</e>
<cmt>&quot;Kaya&quot; is Japanese. This is called a &quot;mosquito net&quot; in English.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaya</e>
<cmt>日本語読みのタイトルに訂正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>蚊帳（蚊屋、かや）は、カなどの害虫から人などを守るための箱状の網。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaya is a box-shaped net to protect user from harmful insects such as mosquitoes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A mosquito net is a box-shaped net that offers protection against harmful insects such as mosquitoes.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Kaya&quot; &gt; &quot;A mosquito net&quot;&quot;to protect user from&quot; &gt; &quot;that offers protection against&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A kaya (mosquito net) is a box-shaped net that offers protection against harmful insects such as mosquitoes.</e>
<cmt>蚊帳の英語訳を括弧で補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>通常、室内に吊して用いる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Normally, it is used by hanging in a room.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are normally hung indoors.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten to read professionally.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are normally hung indoors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>虫は通さず風は通すため、1mm程度の網目となっており、麻 (繊維)などの繊維、のちに化学繊維でも作られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To block insects and let wind flow, the mesh of net is about 1mm, and is made from fibers of hemp and others, and later is also made from chemical fibers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to exclude insects but allow air to pass, mosquito nets are comprised of a 1mm mesh and were originally made from materials such as hemp and later from synthetic fibers.</e>
<cmt>Poor translation.Completely retranslated.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to exclude insects but allow air to pass, mosquito nets are comprised of a 1mm mesh and were originally made from materials such as hemp and later from synthetic fibers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>日本には中国から伝来した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan, it was introduced from China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The mosquito net arrived in Japan via China.</e>
<cmt>Poor translation.Completely retranslated.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The mosquito net arrived in Japan via China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>当初は貴族などが用いていたが、江戸時代には庶民にも普及した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At first, it was used by nobilities, but was spread through common people in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was initially used by the nobility but its use spread to the common people during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten to read professionally.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was initially used by the nobility but its use spread to the common people during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>「蚊帳ぁ、萌黄の蚊帳ぁ」という独特の掛け声で売り歩く行商人は江戸に初夏を知らせる風物詩となっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Peddler of kaya, shouting unique call, &apos;Kaya, Kaya in moegi (light green)&apos; brung people feelings that early summer has had come.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mosquito net peddlers with their call of &quot;Kaya! Moegi no kaya!&quot; (lit. Mosquito nets! Light green mosquito nets!) were an indication that summer had arrived in Edo.</e>
<cmt>Poor translation.Completely retranslated.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mosquito net peddlers with their call of &quot;Kaya! Moegi no kaya!&quot; (lit. Mosquito nets! Light green mosquito nets!) were an indication that summer had arrived in Edo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>就寝時に用いることが多く、簡単に取り付け、取り外しができるよう長押（なげし）のくぼみが鉤(かぎ、フック）をかけるのに利用された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is usually used at sleeping time, and to put on and off easily, a dent in nageshi (a horizontal piece of timber in the frame of a Japanese-style house) was used to hang the hook.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are often used at bedtime and in order to allow them to be easily mounted and dethatched, a hook would be attached to a depression in the nageshi (beam running between columns) in traditional Japanese rooms.</e>
<cmt>Poor translation.Completely retranslated.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are often used at bedtime and in order to allow them to be easily mounted and dethatched, a hook would be attached to a depression in the nageshi (beam running between columns) in traditional Japanese rooms.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>また、長押に鉤を打ち付けておき、それに輪型の釣具を掛ける方式もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, there is a way to hang by nailing hook to nageshi and hooking up round-shaped hanging tool.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another method was attach a hook to the nageshi from which a to hang a circular frame.</e>
<cmt>Poor translation.Completely retranslated.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another method was attach a hook to the nageshi from which a to hang a circular frame.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>その長押は、今日の日本家屋からは消滅しつつある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That nageshi is rarely seen in Japanese houses in present days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such nageshi are rarely seen in modern Japanese homes.</e>
<cmt>Poor translation.Completely retranslated.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such nageshi are rarely seen in modern Japanese homes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>生活環境の変化、すなわち殺虫剤や下水の普及による蚊の減少および気密性の高いアルミサッシの普及に伴う網戸の採用、さらにエア・コンディショナーの普及により、昭和の後期にはほとんど使われなくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By changes in living environment, such as decrease of number of mosquitoes by spread of insecticides and drainage, adoption of window screen by spread of aluminum sash with high airtightness, and spread of air conditioner, by the latter half of the Showa period, it was rarely used by the people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mosquito nets fell almost completely out of use by the latter half of the Showa period as a result of changes to living conditions including decreased numbers of mosquitoes due to pesticides and drainage, the increased use of screen doors that accompanied the popularity of airtight aluminum frames, as well as the diffusion of air conditioning.</e>
<cmt>Poor translation.Completely retranslated.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mosquito nets fell almost completely out of use by the latter half of the Showa period as a result of changes to living conditions including decreased numbers of mosquitoes due to pesticides and drainage, the increased use of screen doors that accompanied the popularity of airtight aluminum frames, as well as the diffusion of air conditioning.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="11">
<j>電気も薬品も使わない防蚊手段であり、エコロジーの観点や薬品アレルギー対策として見直され始めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a way to block mosquitoes without using electricity and chemicals, so from the view of ecology and protection from chemical allergies, it has been started to be reevaluated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their use has started to become reevaluated from the standpoints of ecology and chemical allergies as they represent a mosquito repellent that uses neither electricity nor chemicals.</e>
<cmt>Poor translation.Completely retranslated.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Their use has started to become reevaluated from the standpoints of ecology and chemical allergies as they represent a mosquito repellent that uses neither electricity nor chemicals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>海外への普及</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Spread to overseas</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Spread Overseas</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;to&quot;Title case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Spread Overseas</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="12">
<j>日本以外では、蚊帳が普及しつつある地域もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are areas out of Japan where kaya is starting to be used commonly..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are also areas outside of Japan where the use of mosquito nets is becoming widespread.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten to read professionally.This sentence is strange because the mosquito net was initially used outside of Japan.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are also areas outside of Japan where the use of mosquito nets is becoming widespread.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>マラリアの被害に悩まされるアフリカ諸国や東南アジアなどで、低コストな蚊対策として注目を浴びている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In various countries in Africa and in Southeast Asia where people are troubles with Malaria, it is being noticed as protection against mosquitoes with low cost.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In various African and Southeast Asian countries afflicted by malaria, mosquito nets have gained attention as a low-cost measure against mosquitoes.</e>
<cmt>Poor translation.Completely retranslated.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In various African and Southeast Asian countries afflicted by malaria, mosquito nets have gained attention as a low-cost measure against mosquitoes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="14">
<j>特に2000年、世界保健機関（WHO）から蚊帳の増産とアフリカへの無償技術移転を依頼された住友化学はタンザニアに工場を二箇所建設している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially in the year 2000, Sumitomo Chemicals Co., Ltd., being requested by World Health Organization (WHO) for increased production of kaya and voluntary export of technology to Africa, constructed two factories in Tanzania.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Following a request by the World Health Organization (WHO) to increase mosquito net production and voluntary export of technology to Africa, Sumitomo Chemicals Co., Ltd. constructed two factories in Tanzania in the year 2000.</e>
<cmt>Poor translation.Completely retranslated.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Following a request by the World Health Organization (WHO) to increase mosquito net production and voluntary export of technology to Africa, Sumitomo Chemicals Co., Ltd. constructed two factories in Tanzania in the year 2000.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="15">
<j>日本では、2003年より政府開発援助やUNICEFを通じた支援を実施、3年間で200万張以上の蚊帳を世界各国に配布している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan, starting in 2003, though Official Development Assistance and UNICEF, support was made to distribute over 2 million kaya throughout countries of the world in 3 years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From 2003 in Japan, support was implemented through official development assistance and UNICEF, and over two million mosquito nets were distributed throughout the world in three years.</e>
<cmt>Poor translation.Completely retranslated.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From 2003 in Japan, support was implemented through official development assistance and UNICEF, and over two million mosquito nets were distributed throughout the world in three years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="16">
<j>ナイジェリアでは、テレビドラマやコマーシャルを通じたPR活動を進めた結果、普及が進んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Nigeria, as a result of publicity activities in TV dramas and commercials, the spread was advanced.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The spread of mosquito nets in Nigeria has advanced as a result of publicity from television drama series and commercials.</e>
<cmt>Poor translation.Completely retranslated.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The spread of mosquito nets in Nigeria has advanced as a result of publicity from television drama series and commercials.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="17">
<j>海外支援用の蚊帳については、ピレスロイド系殺虫剤を練り込んだ蚊帳をWHOが採用している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for kaya for support to overseas, kaya with pyrethroid kneaded into the net is adopted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The WHO provides mosquito nets containing the pyrethroid insecticide as overseas aid.</e>
<cmt>Poor, incomplete translation.Completely retranslated.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The WHO provides mosquito nets containing the pyrethroid insecticide as overseas aid.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>これは、蚊が触れるだけで殺虫効果があり、5年間ほど効果が持続する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This net has an effect to kill mosquito just by touching, and keeps its effect for about 5 years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These have the effect of killing mosquitoes which come into contact with the net and remain effective for a period of five years.</e>
<cmt>Poor translation.Completely retranslated.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These have the effect of killing mosquitoes which come into contact with the net and remain effective for a period of five years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="19">
<j>ピレスロイド系殺虫剤は発がん性物質の危険性があることが指摘されているため、薬剤無しの蚊帳の使用を推奨する意見も出ている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since pyrethroid has been pointed out that it maybe is a carcinogen, so there are opinions recommending to use kaya without the chemicals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of indications that pyrethroid may be carcinogenic, there is an emerging opinion that advocates the use of mosquito nets without chemicals added.</e>
<cmt>Poor, incomplete translation.Completely retranslated.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of indications that pyrethroid may be carcinogenic, there is an emerging opinion that advocates the use of mosquito nets without chemicals added.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="20">
<j>乳幼児や食卓向けの、傘を逆さまにしたような折り畳みの式のタイプもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are upside-down umbrella shaped type of kaya that can be folded, for babies and dining tables.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are upside-down umbrella shaped foldable mosquito nets designed for infants and dining tables.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten to read professionally.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are upside-down umbrella shaped foldable mosquito nets designed for infants and dining tables.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="21">
<j>前項と同様な形状のものでも、害虫から食品を一時的に保護するためのものは蝿帳という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ones with an object to protect food from harmful insects are called Haicho, even though it may have the same shape with kaya mentioned above.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those designed to temporarily protect food, even those with the same dome shape as described above, are called mesh food covers.</e>
<cmt>Poor translation.Completely retranslated.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those designed to temporarily protect food, even those with the same dome shape as described above, are called mesh food covers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="22">
<j>「大事な情報などを知らされない」「仲間はずれ」といった意味合いで、「蚊帳の外」という言い回しがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is an expression &apos;out of kaya&apos; with meaning &apos;not being told important information&apos; and &apos;being left out in a group.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a Japanese expression that goes &quot;kaya no soto&quot; (lit. &quot;outside of the mosquito net&quot;) which refers to the withholding of important information or leaving somebody out of a group.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten to read professionally.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a Japanese expression that goes &apos;kaya no soto&apos; (lit. &apos;outside of the mosquito net&apos;) which refers to the withholding of important information or leaving somebody out of a group.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="23">
<j>小林一茶の俳句に、「新しき蚊屋に寝るなり江戸の馬」というものがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is Haiku by Issa KOBAYASHI, &apos;Horse in Edo, sleeping in new kaya.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A haiku poem by Issa KOBAYASHI readsAtarashikiKaya ni nerunariEdo no umaand translates as &apos;A horse in Edo sleeps under a new mosquito net.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Poor translation.Completely retranslated.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A haiku poem by Issa KOBAYASHI reads, &apos;Atarashiki, Kaya ni nerunari, Edo no uma&apos; and translates as &apos;A horse in Edo sleeps under a new mosquito net.&apos;</e>
<cmt>改行を削除ました。コンマおよび&apos; &apos;補足しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 アレシンロ(id:170344), AlleborgoBot(id:119729), 明日香零(id:40591), ととりん(id:31982), 0null0(id:582), Nighthawks(id:36125), Sina(id:10021), Brevam(id:13479), TXiKiBoT(id:107492), Komatta(id:52309), Motamota(id:39894), ＋－(id:17104), Fryed-peach(id:63402), Tmtm(id:14181), 竃馬(id:102733), 橄欖岩(id:24996), VolkovBot(id:105371), Chlewbot(id:33904), ラッパ食堂(id:255123), Point136(id:211299), やすとし(id:63220), Transition178(id:185544), SieBot(id:126695), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>