<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>元日節会</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ganjitsu no sechie</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ganjitsu no sechie (New Year&apos;s Festival)</e>
<cmt>カッコ部分を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ganjitsu no sechie (New Year&apos;s Festival)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>元日節会（がんじつのせちえ）は、 古来の正月行事の一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Ganjitsu no sechie&quot; is one of the ancient events for the New Year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Ganjitsu no sechie&quot; is one of the ancient events for the New Year.</e>
<cmt>スペースを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Ganjitsu no sechie&quot; is one of the ancient events for the New Year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>1月1日、朝賀の後に天皇が大極殿、豊楽院（後に紫宸殿）、豊明殿などに出御し、臣や公家の皆々に宴をさせる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 1, after Choga (ceremony in which the emperor receives greetings of the New Year from officials), the emperor comes to the Daigokuden (the Council Hall in the Imperial Palace), the Burakuin (a hall for ceremonies) (later the Shishinden, the Throne Hall), and Homeiden (another main hall), and lets his subjects and court nobles hold a banquet.</e>
<cmt>豊楽院、豊明殿の説明が明確にできませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 1, after the Choga (ceremony in which the emperor receives greetings of the New Year from officials), the emperor comes to the Daigokuden (the Council Hall in the Imperial Palace), the Buraku-in (Reception Compound, later the Shishinden, the Throne Hall), and Homeiden State Banquet Hall and so on, and lets his retainers and court nobles hold the banquet.</e>
<cmt>the, to を挿入しました。”豊楽院”、”豊明殿”の箇所を修正し、and so on を挿入しました。subjects→retainers, a banquet→the banquet と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 1, after the Choga (ceremony in which the emperor receives greetings of the New Year from officials), the emperor comes to the Daigokuden (the Council Hall in the Imperial Palace), the Buraku-in (Reception Compound, later the Shishinden, the Throne Hall), and Homeiden State Banquet Hall and so on, and lets his retainers and court nobles hold the banquet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="3">
<j>奈良時代の初期、元正天皇の御代には行われていたとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said to have already taken place at the beginning of the Nara Period, in the reign of the Emperor Gensho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said to have already taken place at the beginning of the Nara period, in the reign of the Emperor Gensho.</e>
<cmt>Period→period と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said to have already taken place at the beginning of the Nara period, in the reign of the Emperor Gensho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>朝廷でも重要な儀式の一つとされ、応仁の乱の開始から延徳二年（1490年）に再興されるまでの約30年間中断された他は、明治維新まで継続して行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was considered one of the important ceremonies, and took place continuously until the Meiji Restoration, except that it was interrupted for about 30 years from the start of Onin no Ran (the Onin War) until 1490, when it was revived.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was considered as one of the important ceremonies in the Imperial Court, and held continuously until the Meiji Restoration, except for about 30 years of the interruption between the start of the Onin War until being revived in 1490.</e>
<cmt>as, in the Imperial Court を挿入しました。took place→held,後半部分の流れをよりスムースにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was considered as one of the important ceremonies in the Imperial Court, and held continuously until the Meiji Restoration, except for about 30 years of the interruption between the start of the Onin War until being revived in 1490.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>明治時代からは1月5日の新年宴会となり、戦後は、1月1日の「新年祝賀の儀」となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It turned into the New Year banquet of January 5 in the Meiji Period, and is &apos;Shinnen shukuga no gi&apos; (the New Year Greeting) of January 1 after World War Ⅱ.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It became the New Year banquet of January 5 in the Meiji period, then changed into &apos;Shinnen shukuga no gi&apos; (the New Year Greeting) of January 1 after World WarⅡ.</e>
<cmt>クォーツ、スペースを修正しました。turned into→became, Period→period,and is→then changed into</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It became the New Year banquet of January 5 in the Meiji period, then changed into &apos;Shinnen shukuga no gi&apos; (the New Year Greeting) of January 1 after World WarⅡ.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>新年祝賀の儀は国事行為の一つである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Shinnen shukuga no gi&quot; is one of the emperor&apos;s duties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Shinnen shukuga no gi&quot; is one of the constitutional functions.</e>
<cmt>”国事行為”の部分を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Shinnen shukuga no gi&quot; is one of the constitutional functions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Ligar(id:12623), Rai koku(id:1661), Y.Sanada(id:36926), Yiuchan(id:28580), Nnh(id:474), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>