<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>成人の日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Coming-of-Age Day</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Coming-of-Age Day</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Coming-of-Age Day</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>成人の日（せいじんのひ）は日本の国民の祝日の1日である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Coming-of-Age Day is one of Japanese national holidays.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Coming-of-Age Day is a national holiday in Japan.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Coming-of-Age Day is a national holiday in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>国民の祝日に関する法律（祝日法）では「おとなになったことを自覚し、みずから生き抜こうとする青年を祝いはげます」ことを趣旨としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Act on National Holidays states the purpose of the holiday is &quot;to celebrate and encourage young people who realize they have grown up and try to live a life by themselves&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Act on National Holidays states that the purpose of the holiday is to celebrate and encourage young people who realize they have grown up and try to live life by themselves.</e>
<cmt>Grammar. Inverted commas removed as not a direct quotation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Act on National Holidays states that the purpose of the holiday is to celebrate and encourage young people who realize they have grown up and try to live life by themselves.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>この日には、各市町村で新成年を招いて成人式が行われる（ただし、豪雪の影響や帰省しやすい時期等を考慮してゴールデンウィークや盆に行われる地方も多い）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On this holiday each city and town invite new grownups to held a Coming of Age ceremony (in some regions it is held during the Golden Week (early-May holiday season) or Bon festival (a festival of the Dear or Buddhist All Souls&apos; Day) considering influence of heavy snow and season when one can return to hometown).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On this holiday each city and town invites those people who have turned twenty in the last year to a Coming of Age ceremony (in some regions it is held during Golden Week, a holiday in early-May, or during the Bon festival, the festival of Buddhist All Souls&apos; Day, in order to avoid heavy snow and for it to be during a time when people can return to their birthplace).</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity, word choice, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On this holiday each city and town invites those people who have turned twenty in the last year to a Coming of Age ceremony (in some regions it is held during Golden Week, a holiday in early-May, or during the Bon festival, the festival of Buddhist All Souls&apos; Day, in order to avoid heavy snow and for it to be during a time when people can return to their birthplace).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>世界的に見ても、このような祝日は珍しいといわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said this kind of holiday is rare in the world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This kind of holiday is rare in the world.</e>
<cmt>Made more concrete.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This kind of holiday is rare in the world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>本来、成人の日は、前年の成人の日の翌日からその年の成人の日までに誕生日を迎える人（例：1998年の新成人の場合は1997年1月16日から1998年1月15日までに20歳になった人）を祝う日となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Essentially Coming-of-Age Day is for those who turn twenty on the next day of the last Coming-of-Age Day to the day of present one (ex. For the Coming-of-Age Day of 1998, those who turn twenty from 16 January 1997 to 15 January 1998).</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Essentially Coming-of-Age Day is for those who turn twenty between the day after the last Coming-of-Age Day to the day of the present one, so that for Coming-of-Age Day 1998, those who turned twenty between 16 January 1997 and 15 January 1998).</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity, word choice, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Essentially, Coming-of-Age Day is for those who turn twenty from the day after the last Coming-of-Age Day to the day of the present one (For example, for Coming-of-Age Day in 1998, those who turned twenty from January 16, 1997 to January 15, 1998).</e>
<cmt>一部、翻訳を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>しかし最近では前年の4月2日からその年の4月1日に成人する人を式典参加の対象にする、いわゆる学齢方式が定着するようになっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However recently they celebrate the ceremony for those who turn twenty from 2 April of the previous year to 1 April of the present year according to academic year.</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However recently the ceremony is for those who turn twenty between 2 April of the previous year and 1 April of the present year, to fit the academic year.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity, word choice, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, recently the ceremony is for those who turn twenty from April 2nd of the previous year to April 1st of the present year, to fit the academic year.</e>
<cmt>一部、翻訳を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>1999年まで</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Up to 1999</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Up to 1999</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Up to 1999</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>1948年公布・施行の祝日法によって制定された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The holiday was established by the Act on National Holidays which was published and enacted in 1948.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The holiday was established by the Act on National Holidays which was published and enacted in 1948.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The holiday was established by the Act on National Holidays which was published and enacted in 1948.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>制定から1999年までは毎年1月15日だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since establishment up to 1999 the holiday was on 15 January every year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Between 1948 and 1999 the holiday was on 15 January every year.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From 1948 to 1999 the holiday was on January 15 every year.</e>
<cmt>一部、翻訳を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>成人の日を1月15日としたのは、この日が小正月であり、かつて元服の儀が小正月に行われていたことによるといわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">15 January was set to be Coming-of-Age Day because this date is small New Year&apos;s festival and ceremony of attaining manhood used to be held during the small New Year.</e>
<cmt>小正月の定訳から本文脈上自明の&quot;around Januay 15th&quot;は省きました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">15 January was set as Coming-of-Age Day because this date is the date of the Little New Year festival and the ceremony of attaining manhood used to be held during the Little New Year.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reason why January 15 was set as Coming-of-Age Day was that this date is the date of the Little New Year festival and the ceremony of attaining manhood used to be held during the Little New Year.</e>
<cmt>一部、翻訳を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>1月15日が成人の日として固定されていた時代、1983年・1984年には大学共通一次試験、及び1994年・1995年は大学入試センター試験がそれぞれ行われていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the period when 15 January was fixed as the Coming-of-Age Day, preliminary standard university entrance examination in 1983 and 1984 and University Testing Center Examination on 1994 and 1995 were carried out on this holiday.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the period when Coming-of-Age Day was fixed on 15 January, the preliminary standard university entrance examinations in 1983 and 1984 and the University Testing Center Examination in 1994 and 1995 were carried out on this holiday.</e>
<cmt>Order changed, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the period when Coming-of-Age Day was fixed on 15 January, the preliminary standard university entrance examinations in 1983 and 1984 and the University Testing Center Examination in 1994 and 1995 were carried out on this holiday.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="12">
<j>2000年から</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From 2000</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From 2000</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From 2000</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>ハッピーマンデー制度導入に伴い、2000年から1月第2月曜日、つまり、その年の1月8日から1月14日までのうち月曜日に該当する日に変更された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Along with introduction of the happy Monday system, from 2000 this holiday was set to be the second Monday of January, or Monday between 8 and 14 January.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Along with introduction of the &apos;happy Monday&apos; system, from 2000 this holiday was set to be on the second Monday of January, in effect a Monday between 8 and 14 January.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Along with introduction of the &apos;happy Monday&apos; system, from 2000 this holiday was set to be on the second Monday of January, in effect a Monday between 8 and 14 January.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>そのため元々の1月15日には法律を改正しない限りやってこなくなってしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore this holiday does not fall on the original date of 15 January.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore this holiday does not now fall on the original date of 15 January.</e>
<cmt>Added for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore this holiday does not now fall on the original date of 15 January.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>移動先が1月第3月曜日でないのは、1月17日が同時に「防災とボランティアの日」でもあるため。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The new date is not the third Monday of January because 17 January is also &quot;Disaster Prevention and Volunteer Day.&quot;</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The new date was not set for the third Monday of January because 17 January is also &quot;Disaster Prevention and Volunteer Day&quot;.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The new date was not set for the third Monday of January because January 17 is also &apos;Disaster Prevention and Volunteer Day.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Januaryと17を入れ替えました。&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に変更し、ピリオドを&apos; &apos;内に収めました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>（阪神・淡路大震災の発生日。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(The Great Hanshin Awaji Earthquake occurred on this day.</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is the anniversary of the Great Hanshin Awaji Earthquake.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity. Parentheses unnecessary.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is the anniversary of the Great Hanshin Awaji Earthquake.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>（2005年頃から歳時記にも季語「阪神忌」が記述されている。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From around 2005 a kigo (season word) &quot;memorial day of Hanshin&quot; is included in Saijiki (literary calendar.)</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From 2005 the kigo (a phrase used to highlight the season) &quot;Hanshin memorial day&quot; began to appear in the Saijiki literary calendar.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From 2005 the kigo (a phrase used to highlight the season) &apos;Hanshin memorial day&apos; began to appear in the Saijiki literary calendar.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>この日に当たらないよう被災者に対して配慮しているためと思われる（改正祝日法施行後の成人の日が1月10日になる年が該当する）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There seems to be consideration for sufferers not to celbrate the holiday on this day (the year when the Coming-of-Age Day falls on 10 January after the revised Act on National Holidays was enacted is an example).</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is generally consideration for those who lost loved ones in the earthquake in not celebrating the holiday on this day (years when Coming-of-Age Day falls on 10 January following the enacting of the revised Act on National Holidays are an example).</e>
<cmt>Spelling, word order, grammar. Explanation added for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is generally consideration for those who lost loved ones in the earthquake in not celebrating the holiday on this day (years when Coming-of-Age Day falls on January 10 following the enacting of the revised Act on National Holidays are an example).</e>
<cmt>Januaryと10を入れ替えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="19">
<j>地方などでは帰郷する成人が参加しやすいように、成人の日の前日の日曜日に成人式を開催する自治体も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In some regions the local government held Coming-of-Age Ceremony on the Sunday before the Coming-of-Age Day so that those who have to return home can participate without difficulty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In some regions of Japan the local government holds the Coming-of-Age Ceremony on the Sunday before Coming-of-Age Day so that those who have to return home can participate without difficulty.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In some regions of Japan the local government holds the Coming-of-Age Ceremony on the Sunday before Coming-of-Age Day so that those who have to return home can participate without difficulty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="20">
<j>ハッピーマンデー制度導入前は、1日のみの休みでは交通事情等の理由から故郷での成人式への出席が困難な成人も多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before Happy Monday System was introduced many people had difficulty in participating the ceremony in their hometown in one holiday due to traffic circumstances.</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before the Happy Monday System was introduced many people had difficulty participating in the one-day ceremony in their hometown due to the traffic.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before the Happy Monday System was introduced many people had difficulty participating in the one-day ceremony in their hometown due to the traffic.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>が、祝日法の改正に伴い、正月中やゴールデンウィーク、お盆等に成人式を開催していた自治体も、1月の成人の日（又はその前日）の開催に戻したところもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But after the Act on National Holidays was revised, some local governments have gone back to hold the Coming-of-Age Ceremony during New Year holidays, Golden Week, of Obon.</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But since the Act on National Holidays was revised some local governments have gone back to hold the Coming-of-Age Ceremony during New Year holidays, Golden Week, or Obon.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But since the Act on National Holidays was revised some local governments have gone back to hold the Coming-of-Age Ceremony during New Year holidays, Golden Week, or Obon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="22">
<j>全国高等学校サッカー選手権大会の決勝戦は2002年度（2003年）以降、成人の日に行われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The final game of the All Japan High School Tournament is held on the Coming-of-Age Day since fiscal year 2002 (calendar year 2003).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The final game of the All Japan High School Tournament has been held on Coming-of-Age Day since fiscal year 2002 (calendar year 2003).</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The final game of the All Japan High School Soccer Tournament has been held on Coming-of-Age Day since fiscal year 2002 (calendar year 2003).</e>
<cmt>Soccerを挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>かつて、日本ラグビーフットボール選手権大会は1月15日の成人の日に行われており、成人を迎える選手が出場していた事例もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Japan Rugby Football Tournament used to be held on the Coming-of-Age Day on 15 January and some players who celebrate the holiday took part in the game.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Japan Rugby Football Tournament used to be held on Coming-of-Age Day on 15 January and some players who had recently turned twenty took part in the game.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, added for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japan Rugby Football Tournament used to be held on Coming-of-Age Day on January 15 and some players who had recently turned twenty took part in the game.</e>
<cmt>Januaryと15を入れ替えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 TRIBESMAN(id:4735), JAnDbot(id:66507), Hossy(id:20100), Haguii(id:1313), Nnh(id:474), Pazuzu(id:103079), MASA(id:2399), なんざいせん(id:154906), 経済準学士(id:22656), Sat.K(id:3751), お口チャック(id:93706), Makeboy(id:53882), Mintleaf(id:2216), OKG(id:112296), Kst01(id:10342), Majide(id:2247), 1A2B(id:294081), TottyBot(id:101680), Genppy(id:43597), DLAD(id:242635), Iokseng(id:92490), U.S.S.Momotaro(id:646), Tatsujin28(id:9300), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>