<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>格子戸</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koshido (lattice door)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koshido (lattice door)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koshido (lattice door)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>格子戸（こうしど）は、格子状の引き戸若しくは扉。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koshido or lattice door can be a sliding door style or a swinging door style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koshido or lattice door can be either a sliding or swinging door style.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koshido or lattice door can be either a sliding or swinging door style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>「格子」は古文書では、「隔子」と書かれていることが多く、元慶七年（884年）河内国観心寺縁起資財帳によると、如法堂の正面に「隔子戸」四具が建てられていたとある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Koshi (格子)&quot; is often written as &quot;隔子&quot; in old documents; there is a description in a document, Kawachi-no-kuni, Kanshin-ji, Engi Shizaicho (Official Register and Inventory for Kanshin-ji Temple, Kawachi Province) that in 884, in front of the Nyohodo four pieces of &quot;koshido (隔子戸)&quot; were being built.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Koshi (格子)&quot; is often written as &quot;隔子&quot; in old documents; there is a description in a document, Kawachi-no-kuni, Kanshin-ji, Engi Shizaicho (Official Register and Inventory for Kanshin-ji Temple, Kawachi Province) that in 884, in front of the Nyohodo four pieces of &quot;koshido (隔子戸)&quot; were being built.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koshi (格子)&apos; is often written as &apos;隔子&apos; in old documents; there is a description in a document, Kawachi-no-kuni, Kanshin-ji, Engi Shizaicho (Official Register and Inventory for Kanshin-ji Temple, Kawachi Province) that in 884, in front of the Nyohodo four pieces of &apos;koshido (隔子戸)&apos; were being built.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="3">
<j>戸とあるから、蔀（しとみ）ではなく大陸様式の扉開き戸であったと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The use of letter &quot;do (or to 戸)&quot; implies that they were the Chinese continental style swinging doors rather than shitomi (a generic term for timber shutters or doors that generally have vertical and horizontal lattice attached to the exterior surface and sometimes to the interior surface as well).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The use of the letter &quot;do (or to 戸)&quot; implies that they were Chinese continental style swinging doors rather than shitomi (a generic term for timber shutters or doors that generally have vertical and horizontal lattice attached to the exterior surface and sometimes to the interior surface as well).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The use of the letter &quot;do (or to 戸)&quot; implies that they were Chinese continental style swinging doors rather than shitomi (a generic term for timber shutters or doors that generally have vertical and horizontal lattice attached to the exterior surface and sometimes to the interior surface as well).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="4">
<j>寺院建築の正面には扉形式の格子戸が多用されるようになり、さらに『多武峰略記』によると、天禄三年に建立された双堂形式の講堂の内陣の正面に格子戸五間を建て込み、内陣と外陣の間仕切りに格子戸三具を建て込んでいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Swinging door type koshido became more common for the front side in the temple architecture; further, according to Tonomine Ryakki (brief sketch of Tonomine), narabido (two temples) style Kodo (lecture hall), which was built in 972, had a 5-ken (about 9 m) width koshido at the front of naijin (inner sanctuary of the hall), and three units of koshido to divide naijin and gejin, or the inner sanctuary and the adjacent area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Swinging door type koshido became more common for the front side in temple architecture; further, according to Tonomine Ryakki (brief sketch of Tonomine), narabido (two temples) style Kodo (lecture hall), which was built in 972, had a 5-ken (about 9 m) width koshido at the front of naijin (inner sanctuary of the hall), and three units of koshido to divide naijin and gejin, or the inner sanctuary and the adjacent area.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Swinging door type koshido became more common for the front side in temple architecture; further, according to &quot;Tonomine Ryakki&quot; (brief sketch of Tonomine), narabido (two temples) style Kodo (lecture hall), which was built in 972, had a 5-ken (about 9 m) width koshido at the front of naijin (inner sanctuary of the hall), and three units of koshido to divide naijin and gejin, or the inner sanctuary and the adjacent area.</e>
<cmt>『　』に&quot; &quot;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="5">
<j>平安時代後期になると、引き違いの格子戸が広く使用されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In late Heian era, sliding style became widespread.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In late Heian era, the sliding style became widespread.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In late Heian period, the sliding style became widespread.</e>
<cmt>era→periodに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="6">
<j>『源氏物語』『年中行事絵巻』などには、黒漆塗りの格子戸を引き違いに使ったり、嵌め込み式に建て込んだ間仕切りの様子が描かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Genji monogatari emaki (the Illustrated Handscroll of the Tale of Genji), and &quot;Nenju Gyoji Emaki&quot;(Picture Scrolls of Annual Functions), depicted black lacquered koshido, being used as sliding doors or built-in dividers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Genji monogatari emaki (the Illustrated Handscroll of the Tale of Genji), and &quot;Nenju Gyoji Emaki&quot;(Picture Scrolls of Annual Functions), depicted black lacquered koshido, being used as sliding doors or built-in dividers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;Genji monogatari emaki&quot; (the Illustrated Handscroll of the Tale of Genji), and &quot;Nenchu-gyoji Emaki&quot; (illustrated handscroll of annual events), depicted black lacquered koshido, being used as sliding doors or built-in dividers.</e>
<cmt>年中行事絵巻の定訳『源氏物語』はここでは「源氏物語絵巻」と解釈して訳しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="7">
<j>天喜元年（1053年）藤原頼通が建立した、平等院鳳凰堂は四周の開口部には扉を設けているが、その内側に格子遣戸もあわせ用いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Hoo-do Hall of Byodoin Temple, which was built by FUJIWARA no Yorimichi in 1053, there is a door on at the opening parts of the peripheral wall, and koshi-yarido (latticed sliding door) was also used on the inner side.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Hoo-do Hall of Byodoin Temple, which was built by FUJIWARA no Yorimichi in 1053, there is a door on the opening areas of the peripheral wall, and koshi-yarido (latticed sliding door) was also used on the inner side.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Hoo-do Hall of Byodoin Temple, which was built by FUJIWARA no Yorimichi in 1053, there is a door on the opening areas of the peripheral wall, and koshi-yarido (latticed sliding door) was also used on the inner side.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="8">
<j>このような格子遣戸の用い方は、隔ての機能を果たしながら、採光や通風を得ることができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this way, koshi-yarido allows utilizing outside natural light and air effectively while functioning as a divider.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this way, koshi-yarido allows utilizing outside natural light and air effectively while functioning as a divider.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this way, koshi-yarido allows utilizing outside natural light and air effectively while functioning as a divider.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>機能としては、明かり障子の前身ともいうべきものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Based on the function, it can be considered as a predecessor of akari-shoji (a translucent screen or sliding door made by pasting single sheets of white Japanese paper on light wooden frames).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based on the function, it can be considered as a predecessor of akari-shoji (a translucent screen or sliding door made by pasting single sheets of white Japanese paper on light wooden frames).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based on the function, it can be considered as a predecessor of akari-shoji (a translucent screen or sliding door made by pasting single sheets of white Japanese paper on light wooden frames).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Mnd(id:15140), Tomomarusan(id:17060), 草薙(id:23262), ムカイ(id:72972), Urania(id:7213), Terotako(id:11853), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>