<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>洋食</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshoku (western food)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshoku (western food)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshoku (western food)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>洋食（ようしょく）とは、日本国内で供される西洋風の料理を指す用語である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term &quot;Yoshoku&quot; refers to western food served in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term &quot;Yoshoku&quot; refers to western food served in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term &quot;Yoshoku&quot; refers to western food served in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>中国や韓国にも、日本の影響から洋食の流れをくむ料理が広まっており、これらを含めて指すこともある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It sometimes includes the western food in China and Korea, which has been spread influenced by Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It sometimes includes the western food in China and Korea, which has been spread and influenced by Japan.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It sometimes includes western food in China and Korea, which has been spread through Japan&apos;s influence.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>フランス料理店やイタリア料理店など欧米各国のレシピに則った料理を供する形態も存在するが、欧米の料理（西洋料理）を日本人向けにしたものも多数ある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although there are also orthodox western restaurants such as French and Italian restaurants which follow the recipe of the Western countries, many restaurants have arranged western food to fit Japanese&apos;s taste.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although there are also orthodox western restaurants including French and Italian which follow recipes from their origins in Western countries, many restaurants have added their own changes in order to fit Japanese people&apos;s taste.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although there are orthodox western restaurants including French and Italian which follow recipes from their origins in Western countries, many restaurants have added their own changes in order to fit Japanese people&apos;s taste.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>エスカロップ（北海道根室市）やトルコライス（長崎県）のような日本の郷土料理と言える洋食さえも存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, there are the Yoshoku which even can be said to be a local food in Japan such as escalope (Nemuro City, Hokkaido Prefecture) and Turkey rice (Nagasaki Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, there are Yoshoku which can be said to be ocal food in Japan such as escalope (Nemuro City, Hokkaido Prefecture) and Turkey rice (Nagasaki Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, Yoshoku such as escalope (Nemuro City, Hokkaido Prefecture) and Turkey rice (Nagasaki Prefecture) could be said to be local to Japan.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>このことから日本料理の一分野であるという見方もできる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, it can be considered as one category of Japanese dishes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, these could be considered to be within the realm of food which is considered Japanese.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, these could be included in the realm of food which is considered Japanese.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>ここでは日本国内において発展を遂げた西洋風の料理を「洋食」として取り上げる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this article, the term &quot;Yoshoku&quot; refers to the dishes in western style which has been developed in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this article, the term &quot;Yoshoku&quot; refers to western style which were developed in Japan.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this article, the term &apos;Yoshoku&apos; refers to western style dishes which were developed in Japan.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>日本における洋食の成立時期は明治時代であり、和食と比較するとそれほど古いものではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan Yoshoku was established during the Meiji period, which was not so far from Japanese food.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshoku was established in Japan during the Meiji period, and was not far removed from Japanese food.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshoku was established in Japan during the Meiji period, and was not so older than Japanese food.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>カツレツ、コロッケ、エビフライに代表されるフライと呼ばれる揚げ物料理やカレーライス、ハンバーグ、グラタン、ハヤシライス、ナポリタンなどが代表的なメニューである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fried dishes such as fried meat, croquette and fried prawns, curry and rice, hamburger, gratin, hashed rice and spaghetti Neapolitan are famous menu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fried dishes such as fried meat, croquette and fried prawns, curry and rice, hamburger, gratin, hashed rice and spaghetti Neapolitan are representative of Yoshoku.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fried dishes called &apos;furai&apos; such as fried meat, croquettes, fried prawns, and dishes such as curry and rice, hamburger, gratin, hashed rice and spaghetti Neapolitan are representative of Yoshoku.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>和食と比較して歴史が短いことから地域差が小さく、全国的に見ても類似したメニューとなることが多いためファミリーレストランなどによる全国展開が比較的容易な分野でもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since it was established later than Japanese food, there are few regional differences, and similar menu is seen all over Japan, which makes it easier for family restaurant to expand throughout all of Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since such dishes have a relatively short history when compared to Japanese food, there are few regional differences, and similar menus can be found all over Japan, which makes it easier for family restaurants to spread throughout all of Japan.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since such dishes have a relatively short history when compared to Japanese food, there are few regional differences, and similar menus can be found all over Japan, which makes it easier for family restaurants to spread those menus throughout all of Japan.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>考察</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Speculation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Speculation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Speculation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>洋食の中には、明治時代以降に西洋料理を習得した料理人が、必ずしも西洋料理のレシピに則らず、日本人消費者の好みに合うよう作り上げた「創作料理」的なものも少なくないため、母体となる欧米には見られないチキンライス、オムライスのような料理も少なからず存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Not a few cooks who learned western food after the Meiji period has established &apos;creative cuisine&apos; such as chicken rice and rice omelet without following the recipe of western dishes, which are suitable for Japanese consumers and unseen in Western countries.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many cooks who learned western cuisine after the Meiji period, established &apos;creative cuisine&apos; such as chicken rice and rice omelets without following the traditional western recipes, making them suitable to Japanese consumers are unseen in Western countries.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many cooks, who learned western cuisine after the Meiji period, established &apos;creative cuisine&apos; such as chicken rice and rice omelets without following the traditional western recipes, matching the tastes to Japanese consumers&apos; preference, which can not be found in Western countries.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="11">
<j>長年にわたり日本人に深く親しまれ、素材、味付け、ソースといったさまざまな部分において和洋折衷が試みられた</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshoku has been popular among Japanese for a long time, and various materials, seasonings and sources have been tried to be arranged into half in Japanese style and half in Western style (in a semi-Western style).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshoku has been popular among Japanese for a long time, and various ingredients, seasonings and sauces have been tried in order to create dishes which are half Japanese style and half Western style (in a semi-Western style).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshoku has been popular among Japanese for a long time, and various ingredients, seasonings and sauces have been tried in order to create dishes in a semi-Western style.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>結果、一部の料理は和食化している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, a part of Yoshoku has become to be categorized into Japanese food</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, a part of Yoshoku has come to be categorized as Japanese food.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, part of Yoshoku has come to be categorized as Japanese food.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>例えば、豚カツは味噌汁・漬物とともに箸を添えて和定食として出されることが多くなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, pork cutlet is served with miso soup, pickles and chopsticks as a Japanese set meal in many restaurants.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, pork cutlets are served with miso soup, pickles and chopsticks as a Japanese set meal in many restaurants.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, pork cutlets are served with a cup of miso soup, pickles and chopsticks as a Japanese set meal in many restaurants.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>西洋料理の特徴であるソース (調味料)を洋食でも用いるが、フランス料理のような複雑多様なソースの体系は持たず、よく使われるソースの種類はある程度限られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The sauce (seasoning), which is a character of western food, is also used in Yoshoku, but it does not use such complicated and various sauces as those in French cuisine and only some specific sauces are often used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sauce (seasoning), which is a character of western food, is also used in Yoshoku, but it does not use the complicated sauces as those used in French cuisine and only some specific sauces are used.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sauces (seasoning), which are a character of western food, are also used in Yoshoku, but it does not use the complicated sauces used in French cuisine, and only specific ones are used.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>トマトケチャップ、ドミグラスソースは定番の調味料である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tomato ketchup and demiglace sauce are common seasonings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tomato ketchup and demiglace sauce are common seasonings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tomato ketchup and demiglace sauce are common seasoning.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>ベシャメルソースを使用するなどフランス料理の影響も強い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bechamel sauce is also used, influenced by French cuisine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bechamel sauce is also used, influenced by French cuisine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshoku is much influenced by French cuisine such that it uses Bechamel sauce.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>揚げ物にウスターソースをかけるスタイルは、この中で生み出されており、その影響でウスターソースを用いるだけで一銭洋食なる名称の食べ物も生み出され、これは後にお好み焼きへと派生していく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The style to put Worcester sauce on fried dishes was established in this stream, which led to the food named issen yoshoku (literally, one cent Western food) which used Worcester sauce and was developed into okonomiyaki (savory pancake with various ingredients) later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The style to put Worcester sauce on fried dishes was established in this stream, which led to a dish named issen yoshoku (literally, one cent Western food) which used Worcester sauce and was later developed into okonomiyaki (savory pancake with various ingredients).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This trend influenced and established the use of Worcester sauce on fried dishes, which led to a dish named issen yoshoku, which used Worcester sauce and was later developed into okonomiyaki (savory pancake with various ingredients).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="18">
<j>また、ハンバーグや鶏肉などの調理法として醤油を利用した照り焼きがしばしば用いられるが、この方法は日本のみならずアメリカ合衆国をはじめとする世界各国へと広がりを見せている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, a cooking method, teriyaki (grilling with soy sauce and sugar), is often used for hamburger and chicken, which has been spread not only in Japan but also in various countries of the world such as the United States of America.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, a cooking method known as teriyaki (grilling with soy sauce and sugar), is often used for hamburger and chicken, which has spread not only in Japan but also to various countries around the world such as the United States of America.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, a cooking method known as teriyaki (grilling with soy sauce and sugar), is often used for hamburger and chicken, which has spread not only in Japan but also in various countries around the world such as the United States of America.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="19">
<j>パンの代わりに飯を皿に盛り、料理をおかずとして交互に食べるという慣習も生まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A custom to serve rice on a dish instead of bread and to eat rice and side dishes one after the other has been created.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The custom to serve rice on a dish instead of bread, and to eat rice and side dishes one after the other was also created.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The custom to serve rice on a dish instead of bread, and to eat rice and the western food as side dishes one after the other was also created.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>従来の日本の食慣習に沿った方式ではあるが、この場合しばしば、ご飯は「ライス」と呼ばれ、茶碗に盛った和食のそれとは別のものとして扱われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is a style followed by the conventional Japanese eating habit, but in this case the rice is often called &apos;raisu&apos; and considered to be a different one served on a bowl in Japanese food.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is a style followed by conventional Japanese eating habits, but in this case the rice is often called &apos;raisu&apos; and considered to be different from that served in a bowl in Japanese food.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is a style following the conventional Japanese eating habits, but in this case the rice is often called &apos;raisu&apos; and treated as different from that served in a bowl in Japanese food.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>同時にフォーク (食器)の背にライスを載せ食べるという独特のテーブルマナーが醸成されていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time, a particular table manner to put rice on the back of the folk and eat it has been created.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the same time, a unique table manner which involved placing rice on the back of the fork was created.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the same time, a unique table manner which involves placing rice on the back of the fork was created.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>近年では誤りであるという認識が広まり、行われることは少ない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This table manner has become to be considered as wrong and does not seen so often.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in recent years this has come to be considered incorrect and is no longer widely seen.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in recent years this has come to be recognized incorrect and is no longer widely seen.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="23">
<j>これら洋食を出す飲食店は洋食屋と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The restaurants which serve these Yoshoku are called yoshokuya.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The restaurants which serve these Yoshoku are called yoshokuya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The restaurants which serve these Yoshoku are called Yoshokuya.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>昭和の高度成長期にはデパートの食堂も洋食を提供する代表であり、近年はファミリーレストランがその役割を一部担っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The restaurants of the department stores were the major places to served Yoshoku in the high-growth period of the Showa period, and recently a part of the family restaurants serve it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Department store restaurants were major places which served Yoshoku during the high-growth period of the Showa period, and has been taken up in part by family restaurants in recent times.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Department store restaurants were major place which served Yoshoku during the high-growth period of the Showa period, and has been taken up in part by family restaurants in recent times.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="25">
<j>文明開化に始まる日本の近代化の過程では洋食はハイカラな存在であり、また、洋食に適した食材を供給する諸産業も成熟していなかったことから戦前・戦中の庶民にとっては高価なご馳走であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the process of modernization which begun from the civilization and enlightenment in the Meiji period, Yoshoku was rakish and expensive for common people in the prewar times and during the war because the industries which supplied food materials for Yoshoku had not developed yet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the process of modernization which began in the civilization and enlightenment age in the Meiji period, up until after the war, Yoshoku was considered rakish and expensive for common people due to the fact that the industries which supplied food materials for Yoshoku had not been developed yet.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the process of modernization, which began in the civilization and enlightenment age in the Meiji period, until after the war, Yoshoku was considered rakish and expensive for common people due to the fact that the industries which supplied food materials for Yoshoku had not been developed yet.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>洋食が庶民の味として定着したのは戦後であり、食糧難もあって連合軍からもたらされた西洋風の食糧を食卓に受け入れざるを得ない事情もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was the postwar period when Yoshoku became popular among common people, which was partly because they had to receive western food from allied forces for the lack of food.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The postwar period saw Yoshoku become more popular among common people, which was partly due to the fact that they received western food from allied forces based on a lack of food.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The postwar period saw Yoshoku become more popular among common people, which was partly due to the fact that they received western food from the allied forces based on a lack of food.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="27">
<j>こうして徐々に定着した西洋風の食習慣が高度経済成長期以降、国民所得の増加及び食文化の変化とともに家庭へと普及し、現在では日本の家庭の食卓をかざる惣菜等として定着するにまで至っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This eating habits of western food has been spread gradually in accordance with the increase of national income and the change of food culture after the high-growth period, and Yoshoku is consequently a kind of daily dish in the households of Japan at present.</e>
<cmt>原文の主述が不自然です（食習慣が惣菜等として定着する）。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Western eating habits began to spread gradually in accordance with an increase in national income and a change in food culture following a high-growth period, and Yoshoku is now a daily dish in Japanese households.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Western eating habits began to spread in Japanese households gradually in accordance with an increase in national income and a change in food culture following a period of high economic growth, and Yoshoku is now a daily dish in Japanese households.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>こうして洋食そのものが家庭の味として定着し、いまや多くの人にとって和食と同様に日本の食文化として位置づけられるに至っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshoku has become popular in the households of Japan and has been considered to be one of the Japanese food culture as well as Japanese food.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshoku has become popular in Japanese households and has been considered to be a part of Japanese food culture as well as Japanese food.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshoku has become popular in Japanese households and has been considered to be a part of Japanese food culture as well as Japanese food.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="29">
<j>一方で洋食で多用される畜産物を生産するためには大量の輸入飼料が必要になり、洋食の普及が食糧の自給率低下をもたらす要因のひとつにもなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, a large amount of imported feed are needed in order to produce animal products which are often used for Yoshoku, which is one of the reasons for the decrease of food self-sufficiency ratio.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, a large amount of imported feed is needed in order to produce animal products which are often used for Yoshoku, which is one of the reasons for the decrease in the food self-sufficiency ratio.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, a large amount of imported feed is needed in order to produce livestock products which are often used for Yoshoku, which is one of the reasons for the decrease in the food self-sufficiency ratio.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>また、和食と比較して乳製品や油などを多用することから高カロリーな料理となる傾向があるため、中高年を中心に洋食を敬遠する傾向も見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, since Yoshoku tends to have a high calorie content because of its heavier usage of dairy products and oil than Japanese food, some people such as middle-aged and older people tend to avoid Yoshoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, since Yoshoku tends to have a high caloric content due to its heavier usage of dairy products and oil when compared to Japanese food, some people, including middle-aged and the elderly tend to avoid Yoshoku.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, since Yoshoku tends to have a high caloric content due to its heavier usage of dairy products and oil when compared to Japanese food, some people, including the middle-aged and the elderly tend to avoid Yoshoku.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>さらに、健康志向の高まりを背景に和食を軸にした日本型食生活へと回帰する動きも大きくなりつつあり、国が推進する「食育」においても洋食的なメニューが軽視されることが度々である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, on the background of rising concern about health, the eating habit of Japanese food tends to be favored again gradually, and in the &apos;dietary education&apos; promoted by the government, Yoshoku is often considered less serious.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese food is gradually being favored again, due to rising health concerns, and Yoshoku is often looked upon lightly by the government when it comes to &quot;dietary education.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese food is gradually being favored again, due to rising health concerns, and Yoshoku is often treated lightly by the government when it comes to &quot;dietary education.&quot;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>今後はこうした食生活の変化に適合していくことが洋食の将来を左右することになるであろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It will decide the future of Yoshoku to adjust such a change of eating habit.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The change occuring in eating habits will most likely decide the fate of Yoshoku.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Whether or not to catch upon the change occurring in eating habits will most likely to decide the fate of Yoshoku.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>洋食の種類</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The menu of Yoshoku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Types of Yoshoku</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Types of Yoshoku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="33">
<j>カレーライス - インド料理のカレーがイギリス経由で日本に来たもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Curry and rice originates from the curry of Indian food, which was introduced to Japan through England.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Curry and rice originate from Indian curry, which was introduced to Japan through England.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Curry and rice originates from Indian curry, which was introduced to Japan through England.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>大日本帝国海軍の糧食として採用され、米飯を主食とする日本の食文化とマッチして定着。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was adopted as a food for Imperial Japanese Navy (IJN) and became popular because it was matched to the Japanese food culture which main food was rice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was adopted as a food to sustain the Imperial Japanese Navy (IJN) and became popular because it matched Japan&apos;s food culture which was based around rice.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was adopted as a food to sustain the Imperial Japanese Navy (IJN) and became popular because it matched Japan&apos;s food culture which was based on rice.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>「ライスカレー」とも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called &apos;rice and curry.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called &apos;rice and curry.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called &apos;rice and curry.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>また、定着の要因としてハウス食品など食品メーカー各社による経営努力があることも見逃せない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, for the reason of popularity, the efforts by food makers such as House Foods Corp. can be raised.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, the efforts by food makers such as House Foods Corp. can not be ignored in terms of explaining its sustained popularity.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, the efforts by food manufacturers such as House Foods Corp. cannot be ignored in terms of explaining its sustained popularity.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="37">
<j>シチュー- 元来、肉類を時間をかけて煮込む高級なものであったが、高度経済成長期以降、簡便なルウを用いる調理方法が普及。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Stew was originally a high-class meal cooked by simmering meats for a long time, but after the high-growth period, an easy cooking method to use roux has been spread.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Stew was originally a high-class meal cooked by simmering meats for a long time, but after a period of high-growth, an easier method involving the use of roux became popular.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Stew was originally a high-class meal cooked by simmering meats for a long time, but after a period of high economic growth, an easier method involving the use of roux became popular.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>現在では秋から冬にかけての定番メニューとなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At present, it is a common menu in autumn and winter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At present, it is a common menu in autumn and winter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At present, stew is a standard item in autumn and winter.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="39">
<j>コロッケ- 原型は欧米で「クロケット」と呼ばれるもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Croquette originates from the &apos;croquette&apos; in Western countries.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Croquette originates from the &apos;croquette&apos; in Western countries.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Korokke originates from the &apos;croquette&apos; in Western countries.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="40">
<j>チキン南蛮 - もともとは宮崎県ローカルの料理だが、現在では全国的に食べられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fried chicken in Japanese sweet and peppery vegetable sauce was originally a local food in the Miyazaki Prefecture, but it is common all over Japan at present.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fried chicken in Japanese sweet and peppery vegetable sauce was originally a local food in Miyazaki Prefecture, but is now common all over Japan.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fried chicken in Japanese sweet and peppery vegetable sauce was originally a local food in Miyazaki Prefecture, but is now eaten all over Japan.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="41">
<j>ロールキャベツ - 日本独自の食べ方として、おでんの具になることがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Stuffed cabbage is sometimes used as an ingredient of oden (a Japanese dish containing all kinds of ingredients cooked in a special broth of soy sauce, sugar, sake, etc.), which is a unique way to eat in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Stuffed cabbage is sometimes used as an ingredient in oden (a Japanese dish containing all kinds of ingredients cooked in a special broth of soy sauce, sugar, sake, etc.), which is unique to Japan.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Stuffed cabbage is sometimes used as an ingredient in oden (a Japanese dish containing all kinds of ingredients cooked in a special broth of soy sauce, sugar, sake, etc.), which is original in Japan.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="42">
<j>フライ (料理) - 下記のエビフライ、カキフライは豚カツ同様、味噌汁に御新香、箸を添えた膳立てで出されるなど、和食のような扱いを受けることもしばしばある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fried dishes are often treated as Japanese food as well as fried prawns and oysters, mentioned below, which are often served with miso soup, pickles and chopsticks in a set meal.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fried dishes are often treated as Japanese food as well as fried prawns and oysters, mentioned below, which are often served with miso soup, pickles and chopsticks in a set meal.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fried dishes are often treated as Japanese food such that fried prawns and oysters, mentioned below, which are often served with a cup of miso soup, pickles and chopsticks in a set meal.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="43">
<j>カキフライ- 日本で開発された創作料理であり、生食を主とする欧米では一般的な調理方法ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fried oysters is a creative cuisine developed in Japan and is not a common cooking method in the Western countries where people usually eat raw oysters.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fried oysters is a creative cuisine developed in Japan and is not a common method of cooking in Western countries where people usually eat raw oysters.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fried oysters is a creative cuisine developed in Japan and is not a general method of cooking in Western countries where people usually eat raw oysters.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="44">
<j>エビフライ- 洋食の定番メニューであるが、これも欧米では一般的な調理方法ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fried prawns is a common menu of Yoshoku, which is not a common cooking method in the Western countries as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fried prawns are a common dish found in Yoshoku, which is not a common method of cooking used in Western countries as well.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fried prawns are a standard item found in Yoshoku, which is not a general method of cooking used in Western countries, either.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>現在では最も一般的なエビの調理方法であり、またエビフライの普及により日本が世界的なエビの輸入国となったことも見逃せない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is the most common cooking method at present, and it should be noted that Japan became the largest importing country of prawn in the world caused by the spread of prawns.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Frying is the most common cooking method at present, and it should be noted that Japan became the largest importer of prawns in the world due to the spread of fried prawns.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Frying is the most prevailing cooking method of prawns at present, and it should be noted that Japan became the largest importer of prawns in the world due to the spread of the fried prawns.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="46">
<j>ムニエル</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meuniere</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meuniere</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meuniere</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="47">
<j>ハヤシライス - ハッシュドビーフまたはビーフストロガノフとご飯との組合せが更に変化したもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hashed rice originates from the combination of hashed beef or beef stroganoff with rice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hashed rice originates from a combination of hashed beef or beef stroganoff with rice.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hashed rice originates from a combination of hashed beef or beef stroganoff with rice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="48">
<j>スパゲッティ - ナポリタンなどの日本独自のものや、タラコ･納豆などの特定調理法のスパゲッティがよく食べられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such unique spaghetti in Japan as spaghetti Neapolitan and other specific spaghetti including salted cod roe and Natto (fermented soybeans) are popular.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unique spaghetti in Japan such as spaghetti Neapolitan and other spaghetti dishes which include salted cod roe and Natto (fermented soybeans) are popular.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unique spaghetti in Japan such as spaghetti Neapolitan and other spaghetti dishes which include salted cod roe or fermented soybeans are popular.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="49">
<j>カツレツ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fried meat</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fried meat</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fried meat</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="50">
<j>豚カツ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Pork cutlet</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Pork cutlet</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Pork cutlet</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="51">
<j>カツ丼</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Pork cutlet on rice</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Pork cutlet on rice</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Pork cutlet on rice</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="52">
<j>チキンカツ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chicken cutlet</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chicken cutlet</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chicken cutlet</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="53">
<j>牛カツ（ビフカツ）- 東日本では一般的ではないが、近畿地方ではよく食べられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Beef cutlet is not common in the East Japan, but popular in the Kinki region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Beef cutlet is not common in East Japan, but popular in the Kinki region.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Beef cutlet is not generally eaten in East Japan, but popular in the Kinki region.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="54">
<j>ハムカツ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ham cutlet</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ham cutlet</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ham cutlet</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="55">
<j>メンチカツ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mince cutlet</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mince cutlet</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Minced meat cutlet</e>
<cmt>ひき肉のカツと解釈し、minced meat cutletとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="56">
<j>トルコライス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Turkey rice</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Turkey rice</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Turkey rice</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="57">
<j>エスカロップ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Escalope</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Escalope</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Escalope</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="58">
<j>オムライス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rice omelet</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rice omelet</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rice omelet</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>ステーキ- 洋食の典型的なメニューだが、専門のステーキ店ではしばしば和風のソースや箸を用いるなど和食的な要素もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Steak is a common menu of Yoshoku, but it is often served as a Japanese food with soy source and chopsticks in some steak restaurants.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Steak is a common menu in Yoshoku, and is often served as Japanese food with soy sauce and chopsticks in some steak restaurants.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Steak is a standard item in Yoshoku, and is often served as Japanese food with Japanese style sauce and chopsticks in some steak restaurants.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>比較的安価で供されるものに「サイコロステーキ」があり、ファミリーレストランの定番メニューとなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dice steak&apos; is comparatively a low-class meal and common in family restaurants.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Diced steak&apos; is a comparatively low-class meal and common in family restaurants.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Diced steak&apos; is served at relatively low price and a standard item in family restaurants.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="61">
<j>ハンバーグ- 肉料理の中では比較的安価なひき肉を用いるため、家庭料理として早くから普及した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hamburger has been spread early as a home cuisine because it uses ground meat which is cheaper than other meats.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hamburger spread early as a home cuisine because it used ground meat which is cheaper than other meats.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hamburger spread early as a home cuisine because it uses ground meat which is cheaper than other meats.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>照り焼き等を用いた和洋折衷の調理方法もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also cooked in half in Japanese style and half in Western style (in a semi-Western style) such as teriyaki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also cooked using a hybrid cooking method that combines both Japanese and Western styles (in a semi-Western style) using teriyaki.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also cooked with a hybrid cooking method that combines both Japanese and Western styles using teriyaki and the like.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="63">
<j>グラタン</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gratin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gratin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gratin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>ドリア</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Doria</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Doria</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Doria</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>ピラフ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Pilaf</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Pilaf</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Pilaf</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Carkuni(id:79281), Otoko2008(id:238382), こたつ狼(id:27622), Julius Caesar(id:181760), Geogie(id:143809), 0null0(id:582), D.h(id:79056), 日本一弱い男(id:92046), Howcheng(id:46282), Sat.K(id:3751), Point136(id:211299), ＲＪＡＮＫＡ(id:118019), 和泉飛鳥(id:208308), Baldanders(id:81163), やきとり(id:126941), Cpro(id:28341), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>