<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>鞍馬の火祭</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kurama Fire Festival</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kurama Fire Festival</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kurama Fire Festival</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>鞍馬の火祭（くらまのひまつり）は、京都府京都市左京区鞍馬にある由岐神社例祭の一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kurama Fire Festival is one of the annual festivals at the Yuki-jinja Shrine at Kurama Sakyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kurama Fire Festival is one of the annual festivals at the Yuki-jinja Shrine at Kurama Sakyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kurama Fire Festival is one of the annual festivals at the Yuki-jinja Shrine at Kurama, Sakyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>カンマ追加</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>集落各所に焚かれたかがり火の中を、氏神が松明を持って練り歩いて神社山門を目指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ujigami (ancient ancestral or tutelary deity of a clan or family) heads for the main gate of the shrine, parading with pine torches and watch fires are made here and there in the town.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ujigami (ancient ancestral or tutelary deity of a clan or family) heads for the main gate of the shrine, parading with pine torches and watch fires are made here and there in the town.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ujigami (ancient ancestral or tutelary deity of a clan or family) heads for the main gate of the shrine, parading with pine torches and watch fires are made here and there in the town.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>京都三大奇祭の一つに数えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is known as one of the three most eccentric festivals of Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is known as one of the three most eccentric festivals of Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is known as one of the three most eccentric festivals of Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>940年（天慶3年）、平安京の内裏に祀られている由岐明神（由岐神社）を都の北方の守護として、また当時頻発した大地震や争いなど相次ぐ世情不安を沈めるために、朱雀天皇の案により鞍馬に遷された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 940, as a guardian deity of the northern capital, Yuki Myojin (a gracious deity) or Yuki Shrine, which had been worshiped at the Imperial palace in Heiankyo (the former capital of Japan), was transferred to Kurama by the Emperor Suzaku in order to appease social uneasiness caused by big earthquakes and conflicts that took place one after another in those days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 940, Yuki Myojin (a gracious deity) or Yuki Shrine, which had been worshiped at the Imperial palace in Heiankyo (the former capital of Japan)s a guardian deity of the northern capital was transferred to Kurama by the Emperor Suzaku in order to appease the social unease caused by big earthquakes and conflicts that took place one after another in those days.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 940, Yuki Myojin (a gracious deity) or Yuki-jinja Shrine, which had been worshiped at the Imperial palace in Heiankyo (the former capital of Japan)s a guardian deity of the northern capital was transferred to Kurama by the Emperor Suzaku in order to appease the social unease caused by big earthquakes and conflicts that took place one after another in those days.</e>
<cmt>Yuki-jinja Shrineとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>この時、鴨川 (淀川水系)に生えていたヨシをかがり火として道々に点灯したほか、遷宮の行列は1kmにも及んだという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time, reeds in the Kamo River (the Yodo River system) were lit as watch fires along with the road, and the procession of the installation of deity in a new shrine reached one kilometer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this time, reeds in the Kamo River (the Yodo River system) were lit as watch fires along with the road, and the procession during the event reached one kilometer.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this time, reeds in the Kamo-gawa River (the Yodo-gawa River system) were lit as watch fires along with the road, and the procession during the event reached one kilometer.</e>
<cmt>Kamo-gawa River, Yodo-gawa Riverとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>これに感激した鞍馬の住民がその出来事と由岐明神の霊験を伝えるために始まったものが起源といわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Impressed with this, residents of Kurama are said to have begun this festival in order to pass down this event and the miraculous efficacy of Yuki Shrine to posterity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Impressed with this, residents of Kurama are said to have begun this festival in order to pass down this event and the miraculous efficacy of Yuki Shrine in posterity.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Impressed with this, residents of Kurama are said to have begun this festival in order to pass down this event and the miraculous efficacy of Yuki Myojin in posterity.</e>
<cmt>Yuki Shrine→Yuki Myojinとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>なお、祭事は毎年10月22日（時代祭と同日）の夜に行われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The festival is held on the night of October 22 every year (the same day as Jidai matsuri (Festival of the Ages)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The festival is held on the night of October 22 every year (the same day as Jidai matsuri (Festival of the Ages)).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The festival is held on the night of October 22 every year (the same day as Jidai matsuri (Festival of the Ages)).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>祭事の流れ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A process of the festival</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The festival procedure</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Festival Procedure</e>
<cmt>頭文字を大文字に変更</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>18時頃より、「神事にまいらっしゃれ」という神事触れの合図により集落の各戸に積まれたたいまつに点火。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since around six o&apos;clock, an announcement that &apos;Come over to a Shinto ritual&apos; has been made, which is a sign of igniting pine torches installed at the entrance of each house in the village.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From six o&apos;clock, an announcement &apos;Welcome to a Shinto ritual&apos; is made, and pine torches installed at the entrance of each house in the village are lit.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From six o&apos;clock, an announcement &apos;Welcome to a Shinto ritual&apos; is made, and pine torches installed at the entrance of each house in the village are lit.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>初めは主に子どもが小さな松明を、その後は青年など大人が比較的大きな松明を持って「サイレイヤ、サイリョウ」（祭礼や、祭礼の意）のかけ声と共に集落内を練り歩き、「仲間」と呼ばれる御旅所へ向かう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At first mainly children carrying small pine torches, and then grown-ups holding rather huge pine torches parade in the village with shouts, &apos;sairei ya, sairyo&apos; (meaning festival), and head for otabisho (a resting place for a portable shrine being moved about on its feast day) called &apos;nakama.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At first mainly children carrying small pine torches, and then grown-ups holding rather huge pine torches parade in the village with shouts, &apos;sairei ya, sairyo&apos; (meaning festival), and head for otabisho (the resting place for a portable shrine being moved about on its feast day) called &apos;nakama.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At first mainly children carrying small pine torches, and then grown-ups holding rather huge pine torches parade in the village with shouts, &apos;sairei ya, sairyo&apos; (meaning festival), and head for otabisho (the resting place for a portable shrine being moved about on its feast day) called &apos;nakama.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>20時頃より、各仲間からの大松明が鞍馬寺山門前に向かう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">People holding giant pine torches from each &apos;nakama&apos; head for the main gate of Kuramadera Temple at around eight o&apos;clock.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">People holding giant pine torches from each &apos;nakama&apos; head for the main gate of Kuramadera Temple around eight o&apos;clock.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">People holding giant pine torches from each &apos;nakama&apos; head for the main gate of Kurama-dera Temple around eight o&apos;clock.</e>
<cmt>Kurama-dera Templeとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>各松明は山門前にひしめき合い、その後石段下の一ヶ所に焼き捨てられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Each pine torches were gathered crowdedly in front of the gate, and later they were burned away at the bottom of the stone steps.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">All the pine toches aqre gathered in front of the gate where theya re later burned away at the bottom of the stone steps.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">All the pine torches aqre gathered in front of the gate where theya re later burned away at the bottom of the stone steps.</e>
<cmt>torchesのスペルミスを修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>石段奥の注連縄が切られて、八所大明神、由岐大明神の順序で神社から神輿が下る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the shimenawa (sacred straw festoon) has been cut at the top of the stone steps, Hassho Daimyojin (great gracious deity) first, and then Yuki Daimyojin appear and mikoshi (portable shrine) go down the steps.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the shimenawa (sacred straw festoon) has been cut at the top of the stone steps, Hassho Daimyojin (great gracious deity) first, and then Yuki Daimyojin appear and mikoshi (portable shrine) go down the steps.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the shimenawa (sacred straw festoon) has been cut at the top of the stone steps, Hassho Daimyojin (great gracious deity) first, and then Yuki Daimyojin appear and mikoshi (portable shrine) go down the steps.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>参道が急なため、スピードが出過ぎないように女性が綱を牽く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The approach is so steep that women pull ropes not to pick up speed that much.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The approach is so steep that women must used ropes so as not to pick up too much speed.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The approach is so steep that women must used ropes so as not to pick up too much speed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>（この綱を牽くと安産になると伝えられるので、若い女性が多く参加している）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(There is a tradition that the woman who pull this rope would have an easy delivery, so many young women participate in this event.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(It is a traditional belief that the woman that pulls this rope would have an easy delivery, so many young women participate in this event.)</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(It is a traditional belief that the woman that pulls this rope would have an easy delivery, so many young women participate in this event.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>神輿が降りる際、ふんどし姿の青年が担ぎ棒にぶら下がり、これを『チョッペン』という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the portable shrine is taken down, young men wearing only loincloths hang from the poles attached to the portable shrine, which is called &quot;choppen.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the portable shrine is taken down, young men wearing only loincloths hang from the poles attached to the portable shrine, which is called &quot;choppen.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the portable shrine is taken down, young men wearing only loincloths hang from the poles attached to the portable shrine, which is called &quot;choppen.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>これは元服の儀式であり、鞍馬の青年にとって、一生に一度の成人の儀式。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is a coming of age ceremony, which is once in a lifetime for the young men in Kurama.</e>
<cmt>「成人の儀式」は「元服の儀式」と同内容なので、以下の用語は省略しました。成人の儀式→coming to adult ceremony</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is a coming of age ceremony, which is once in a lifetime for the young men in Kurama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is a coming of age ceremony, which is once in a lifetime for the young men in Kurama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="17">
<j>神輿が集落内を練り歩き、御旅所に安置される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">People parade in the village carrying the portable shrine, and then it is to be enshrined again in the otabisho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">People parade in the village carry the portable shrine, after which it is enshrined again in the otabisho.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">People parade in the village carry the portable shrine, after which it is enshrined again in the otabisho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="18">
<j>神楽の奉納のあと、神楽松明が境内をまわる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After sacred Shinto music and dancing has been performed, kagura taimatsu (pine torch in the shape of a tea whisk) is carried around in the precincts of the shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After sacred Shinto music and dancing has been performed, kagura taimatsu (pine torch in the shape of a tea whisk) is carried around in the precincts of the shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After sacred Shinto music and dancing has been performed, kagura taimatsu (pine torch in the shape of a tea whisk) is carried around in the precincts of the shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>（24時頃終了）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(The finishing time is around midnight.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(The festival ends around midnight.)</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(The festival ends around midnight.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="20">
<j>翌2時頃、神輿が御旅所から神社に戻る「還幸祭」が行われ、祭事のすべてが終了する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around two o&apos;clock in the morning, &apos;Kanko-sai Festival&apos; is held in which the portable shrine is brought back from otabisho to the shrine, and this is the end of the festival.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around two o&apos;clock in the morning, &apos;Kanko-sai Festival&apos; is held in which the portable shrine is brought back from otabisho to the shrine, which signals the end of the festival.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around two o&apos;clock in the morning, &apos;Kanko-sai Festival&apos; is held in which the portable shrine is brought back from otabisho to the shrine, which signals the end of the festival.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>見学者の状況</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">About visitors</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">About visitors</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">About Visitors</e>
<cmt>頭文字を大文字に変更</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="21">
<j>鞍馬集落が狭隘なため、入山できる人数は物理的に限られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A community of Kurama is so small that the number of people who can enter the area is limited spatially.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The community of Kurama is so small that the number of people who can enter the area is limited.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The community of Kurama is so small that the number of people who can enter the area is limited.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>また、集落内は立ち止まって見学することが難しい場所もあり、特に鞍馬寺山門前は見学者が立ち止まることを禁止されるため、神輿が下るシーンなどをよく見える場所で見学することは難しい（一部の氏子関係者や、集落内の民家で見学する際はこの限りではない）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the village, there are spots where it is difficult to stop and watch the festival, especially in front of the main gate of the Kuramayama Temple visitors are forbidden to stop, therefore it is difficult to get a good sight of the portable shrine coming down the steps (except those who have something to do with ujiko (people under the protection of the local deity) or unless you watch it from a house in the village.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the village, there are spots where it is difficult to stop and watch the festival, especially in front of the main gate of the Kuramayama Temple where visitors are forbidden to stop, therefore it is difficult to get a good view of the portable shrine coming down the steps (except those who have something to do with ujiko (people under the protection of the local deity) or if you can watch the event from a house in the village.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the village, there are spots where it is difficult to stop and watch the festival, especially in front of the main gate of the Kurama-dera Temple where visitors are forbidden to stop, therefore it is difficult to get a good view of the portable shrine coming down the steps (except those who have something to do with ujiko (people under the protection of the local deity) or if you can watch the event from a house in the village.</e>
<cmt>Kuramayama Temple→Kurama-dera Templeに修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="23">
<j>当日は雑踏警備の一環として、鞍馬寺山門周辺の道路は歩行者一方通行規制が敷かれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On this day, as a part of crowd control, traffic on the streets around the main gate of Kuramayama Temple is regulated by making one-way street for pedestrian.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On this day, as a part of crowd control, traffic on the streets around the main gate of Kuramayama Temple is regulated by changing the streets into one-way streets for pedestrians.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On this day, as a part of crowd control, traffic on the streets around the main gate of Kurama-dera Temple is regulated by changing the streets into one-way streets for pedestrians.</e>
<cmt>Kuramayama Temple→Kurama-dera Templeに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>鞍馬駅より石段下を通り鞍馬温泉方面への一方通行で、そこから鞍馬の民家の裏側を流れる川の反対側へ渡り、南へ下る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Visitors go from the Kurama Station, pass the bottom of the stone steps, walk through a one-way street in the direction of Kurama hot spring, across the river running behind the houses at Kurama, and go down to the south.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Visitors proceed from Kurama Station, pass the bottom of the stone steps, walk through a one-way street in the direction of Kurama hot spring, across the river running behind the houses at Kurama, and proceed south.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Visitors proceed from Kurama Station, pass the bottom of the stone steps, walk through a one-way street in the direction of Kurama hot spring, across the river running behind the houses at Kurama, and proceed south.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>そこからまた温泉方面へ徒歩で周回しながらの見学となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And then walk around in the direction of the hot spring to see the festival.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They then walk around in the direction of the hot spring to see the festival.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They then walk around in the direction of the hot spring to see the festival.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="26">
<j>午後3時～翌午前2時までは規制のため、貴船口～鞍馬温泉・百井別れまでの間は一般車両（自転車含む）全面通行禁止となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From three p.m. to two a.m., regular vehicles (including bicycles) are forbidden to go into the street between the Kibune entrance and Kurama spring/Momoiwakare in order to control traffic.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From three p.m. to two a.m., regular vehicles (including bicycles) are forbidden to go into the street between the Kibune entrance and Kurama spring/Momoiwakare in order to control traffic.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From three p.m. to two a.m., regular vehicles (including bicycles) are forbidden to go into the street between the Kibune entrance and Kurama spring/Momoiwakare in order to control traffic.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>なお、駐輪場が貴船口（鞍馬小学校付近）に開設される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A bicycle parking lot is established at the Kibune entrance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A bicycle parking lot is available at the Kibune entrance.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A bicycle parking lot is available at the Kibune entrance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="28">
<j>当日の午後より、鞍馬へ向かう交通機関は叡山電鉄叡山電鉄鞍馬線しか無い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The transportation bound for Kurama is only Kurama Line of the Eizan Electric Railway on the afternoon of the day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The only transportation avaialbe for Kurama during the afternoon of the event is limited to only the Kurama Line Eizan Electric Railway.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The only transportation avaialbe for Kurama during the afternoon of the event is limited to only the Kurama Line Eizan Electric Railway.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>但しこの路線は2両編成の登山鉄道のため輸送力に限りがあり、増発はされるものの当日夕方の鞍馬駅行きなどは乗車するまでに出町柳駅などでかなりの待ち時間が発生する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, this line is a mountain railway and the train is made up of two carriages, so the transportation capacity is limited; though special trains are operated, at Demachiyanagi Station, it takes considerable time to get on the train bound for Kurama Station on the evening of the day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, this line is a mountain railway and the train is made up of two carriages, so capacity is limited; while special trains are operated at Demachiyanagi Station, it takes considerable time to get on the train bound for Kurama Station on the evening of the event.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, this line is a mountain railway and the train is made up of two carriages, so capacity is limited; while special trains are operated at Demachiyanagi Station, it takes considerable time to get on the train bound for Kurama Station on the evening of the event.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>また、夜間の復路の乗車も同様である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">So is an outward trip to Kurama Station at night.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This applies to return trips to Kurama Station at night.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This applies to return trips to Kurama Station at night.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>なお、鞍馬集落内に収容できる人数を超えた時点で、鞍馬行きの乗車券の販売は中止となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, they stop selling a ticket for the Kurama when they have no room for the visitors in the Kurama village.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, they stop selling tickets for Kurama when no more space is available in the village for visitors.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, they stop selling tickets for Kurama when no more space is available in the village for visitors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="32">
<j>太鼓、松明、御輿など祭りに関するすべての物は神が宿ると考えられているので、関係者以外は一切触れることができない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered that a deity dwells in all the things related to the festival such as a drum, a pine torch, and a portable shrine, so nobody can touch them except those who are involved in the festival.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is belived that a deity dwells in all things related to the festival such as drums, pine torches, and portable shrines, so no-one is allowed to touch them except for hose involved in the festival.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is belived that a deity dwells in all things related to the festival such as drums, pine torches, and portable shrines, so no-one is allowed to touch them except for those involved in the festival.</e>
<cmt>hose→thoseに修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Hideyuki(id:9577), Nnh(id:474), Si-take.(id:91094), 味村(id:128437), 京娘(id:166495), 弥(id:61590), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>