<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>池坊</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ikenobo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ikenobo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ikenobo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>池坊（いけのぼう）は、日本の華道家元。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">N/A</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">N/A</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ikenobo is iemoto (the head family of a school) of Kado (flower arrangement) in Japan.</e>
<cmt>ウェブに従い原文補足、訳文と共に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>紫雲山頂法寺（京都市中京区にある天台宗の寺。通称六角堂）のいくつかあった寺内塔頭（たっちゅう）の中の本坊にあたり、頂法寺の本堂である六角堂の執行として代々経営・管理に当たってきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ikenobo was a main hut (bo) of several annexed temples located in Shiunzan Choho-ji Temple (a Tendai Buddhist temple in Nakagyo Ward, Kyoto City) and has managed Rokkakudo Temple, main hall of Choho-ji Temple, for generations in a position of its senior priest for Rokkakudo Temple.</e>
<cmt>このセルと上のセルの文章は、誤った個所で分割されています。このセルに全体の英訳を記載しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ikenobo was the main hut (bo) of several annexed temples located in the Shiunzan Choho-ji Temple (a Tendai Buddhist temple in Nakagyo Ward, Kyoto City) a senior priest at the Rakkakudo Temple has managed the main hall of the Choho-ji Temple for generations.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name refers to the honbo (a priest&apos;s main living quarter) among minor temples in Choho-ji Temple on Mt. Shiun (a temple of Tendai Sect in Nakagyo-ku Ward, Kyoto City, also known as Rokkakudo); a priest in Ikenobo has managed it for generation as regent of Rokkakudo, the main hall of Choho-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>ウェブに従い原文補足、訳文と共に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>池坊の坊名は、聖徳太子が水浴したという池にちなんで名付けられたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ikenobo was named referring to the pond (ike) where Prince Shotoku bathed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ikenobo was named referring to a pond (ike) where Prince Shotoku bathed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ikenobo, the honbo, was named referring to a pond (ike) where Prince Shotoku bathed.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>華道（いけばな）における池坊</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ikenobo in kado (the Way of Ikebana)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ikenobo in kado (the Way of Ikebana)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ikenobo in Kado</e>
<cmt>表記を変え、前出用語の補足をのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>池坊の僧は、頂法寺の住持として六角堂の本尊如意輪観音に花を供えることとなっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A priest in Ikenobo was assinged to place flowers to Honzon Nyoirin Kannon, the Goddess of Mercy in the Rokkaku Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A priest in Ikenobo was assinged to place flowers at Honzon Nyoirin Kannon, the Goddess of Mercy in the Rokkaku Temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A priest in Ikenobo was assigned to place flowers at the principle image, Nyoirin Kannon (the Goddess of Mercy) in the Rokkakudo, as the chief priest of Choho-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>「頂法寺の住持として」を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>文明 (日本)年間（1469年 - 1486年）に池坊12世池坊専慶は立花（たてばな）の名手として知られ、天文 (元号)年間（1532年 - 1555年）には、池坊13世池坊専応が度々宮中に招かれて花を立て、また「池坊専応口伝」を著して立花の理論と技術を体系化した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Bunmei era (1469 - 1486), the 12th Headmaster Senkei IKENOBO was known as a tatebana (standing flowers as a Japanese style) master, and in the Tenbun era (1532 - 1555), the 13th Headmaster Seno IKENOBO was frequently invited to the Imperial court to do flower arrangements and authored &apos;Ikenobo Senno Kuden (the famous manuscript about ikebana)&apos; to organize the tatebana related theories and techniques.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Bunmei era (1469 - 1486), the 12th Headmaster Senkei IKENOBO was known as a tatebana (standing flowers in Japanese style) master, and in the Tenbun era (1532 - 1555), the 13th Headmaster Seno IKENOBO was frequently invited to the Imperial court to create flower arrangements and he authored &apos;Ikenobo Senno Kuden (the famous manuscript about ikebana)&apos; to organize the tatebana related theories and techniques.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From 1469 to 1486, the 12th of Ikenobo, Senkei IKENOBO, had a reputation as a tatebana (the traditional art of arranging flowers, literally meaning &quot;making flowers stand&quot;) master, and from 1532 to 1555, the 13th of Ikenobo, Seno IKENOBO, was frequently invited to the Imperial court to arrange flowers and he authored &apos;Ikenobo Seno Kuden&apos; (the famous manuscript about ikebana) to organize the theories and techniques of tatebana.</e>
<cmt>元号をのぞき、表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>江戸時代初期池坊専好が、色彩本位の豪華な法式をはじめて発展し、華道の家元として江戸時代中期に興った遠州流や古流などの本流となるものとして現在にいたっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the early Edo era, Senko IKENOBO launched a fancy flower arrangement style particularly emphasizing on colors, and that style is thought to be a mainstream for the school of Enshu and the Old school which appeared in the mid Edo era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the early Edo era, Senko IKENOBO launched a fancy flower arrangement style particularly emphasizing colors, thought to be mainstream for the Enshu school and the Old school in the mid Edo era.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the early Edo period, Senko IKENOBO launched a fancy flower arrangement style particularly emphasizing colors, thought to be main school for the Enshu School and the Old School in the mid Edo period.</e>
<cmt>period、schoolを使用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>また、本流から分流した流派は多々存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are many schools which were separated from the mainstream.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are many schools separated from the mainstream.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are many schools separated from the main school.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>45世専永宗匠より国際化の流れを受け、海外での活躍・支部拡大がめざましい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Sen&apos;ei succeeded the 45th Headmaster, Ikenobo has actively worked hard and endeavored to increase overseas branches, influenced by globalization.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Sen&apos;ei succeeded the 45th Headmaster, Ikenobo has actively worked hard endeavoring to increase overseas branches, influenced by globalization.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Senei, the 45th sosho (iemoto), Ikenobo has actively worked hard endeavoring to increase overseas branches, influenced by globalization.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>様式</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Style</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Style</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Style</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>生花（しょうか）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shoka (living flowers)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoka (living flowers)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoka (living flowers)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>生花新風体（しょうかしんぷうたい）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shoka shimputai (a new style of living flowers)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoka shimputai (a new style of living flowers)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoka shinputai (a new style of living flowers)</e>
<cmt>shinputaiとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>立花（りっか）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rikka style (standing flowers)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rikka style (standing flowers)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rikka style (standing flowers)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>立花新風体（りっかしんぷうたい）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rikka shimputai (a new style of standing flowers)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rikka shimputai (a new style of standing flowers)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rikka shinputai (a new style of standing flowers)</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>自由花（じゆうか）　かつての盛花（もりばな）と投入（なげいれ）は、自由花にまとめられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jiyuka (a free style of Ikebana) - the old styles &quot;moribana&quot; and &quot;nageire&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jiyuka (a free style of Ikebana) - the old styles &quot;moribana&quot; and &quot;nageire&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jiyuka (a free style of Ikebana): the former moribana (flower arrangement in a built-up style) and nageire (free style flower arrangement in upright vases (without the use of needle point holders)) were included in the Jiyuka.</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用し表現を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="16">
<j>歴代家元</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Successive school heads</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Successive school heads</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Successive Iemoto</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>略</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omitted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omitted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omitted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="18">
<j>42世 池坊専正宗匠</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Forty-second Headmaster Sensho IKENOBO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Forty-second Headmaster Sensho IKENOBO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Forty-second Sosho, Sensho IKENOBO</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>43世 池坊専啓宗匠</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Forty-third Headmaster Senkei IKENOBO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Forty-third Headmaster Senkei IKENOBO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Forty-third Sosho, Senkei IKENOBO</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>44世 池坊専威宗匠</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Forty-forth Headmaster Seni IKENOBO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Forty-forth Headmaster Seni IKENOBO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Forty-forth Sosho, Seni IKENOBO</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>45世 池坊専永宗匠（現家元）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Forty-fifth Headmaster Sen&apos;ei IKENOBO (current headmaster)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Forty-fifth Headmaster Sen&apos;ei IKENOBO (current headmaster)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Forty-fifth Sosho, Senei IKENOBO (current iemoto)</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>46世 池坊由紀（次期家元、池坊初の女性の家元となる）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Forty-sixth Headmaster Yuki IKENOBO (next generation headmaster and the first female Ikenobo headmaster)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Forty-sixth Headmaster Yuki IKENOBO (next generation headmaster and the first female Ikenobo headmaster)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Forty-sixth Sosho, Yuki IKENOBO (next generation iemoto and the first female Ikenobo iemoto)</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Izayohi(id:13095), Oxhop(id:2551), Lombroso(id:20212), Hadge(id:9555), R28Bot(id:177951), Swindbot(id:151304), 積みゲくずし(id:37925), NDR(id:5500), Laeco(id:47216), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>