<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>京こま</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyo Top</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kyo Top</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kyo Top</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>京こま（きょう-、京独楽）は日本の独楽の一種。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyo top is a kind of Japanese spinning top.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kyo top is a kind of Japanese spinning top.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kyo top is a kind of Japanese spinning top.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>形状・製法</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its Shape and Making Process</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its Shape and Production Process</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its Shape and Production Process</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>一見見た目は通常「独楽」として販売されている物と同じだが、製法が全く異なる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It looks same as an ordinary &quot;spinning top&quot;, but its making process is totally different.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It looks the same as an ordinary &quot;spinning top,&quot; but it&apos;s made in a totally different way.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It looks the same as an ordinary &apos;spinning top,&apos; but it&apos;s made in a totally different way.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>通常の日本独楽は木を削りだして作成されるが、京こまは竹製の心棒に木綿製の幅広のヒモ（高級品では友禅や西陣織等の絹製の細長いテープ状の生地）を巻き付けてある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ordinary Japanese spinning tops are made of wood, but Kyo tops are made of a bamboo stem and around which a long piece of thick cotton string (or a strip of expensive silk such as yuzen-dyed fabrics or nishijin brocade) is wound.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ordinary Japanese spinning tops are made of wood, but Kyo tops are made of a bamboo stem around which a long piece of thick cotton string (or a strip of expensive silk such as yuzen-dyed fabric or nishijin brocade) is wound.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ordinary Japanese spinning tops are made of wood, but Kyo tops are made of a bamboo stem around which a long piece of thick cotton string (or a strip of expensive silk such as yuzen-dyed fabric or nishijin brocade) is wound.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>心棒を中心として平べったい円錐形の形になるように作成される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The latter are flat cone-shaped with stems in the center.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The latter type is flat and cone-shaped with a stem at its center.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The latter type is flat and cone-shaped with a stem at its center.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>このため、独楽の胴体部分にはヒモが作り出す独特の質感があり、また、心棒が他の日本独楽より相対的に長めに作られている（心棒が長いのは回し方の影響もあると見られる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The body of Kyo top has a peculiar texture thanks to its cotton string, and the stem of Kyo top is relatively longer than that of an ordinary spinning top (probably under the influence of the way to spin it).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The body of the Kyo top has a peculiar texture thanks to its cotton string, and the stem of the Kyo top is relatively longer than that of an ordinary spinning top (which is probably influenced by the way it&apos;s spun).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The body of the Kyo top has a peculiar texture thanks to its cotton string, and the stem of the Kyo top is relatively longer than that of an ordinary spinning top (which is probably influenced by the way it&apos;s spun).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>回し方</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Way to Spin It</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Way to Spin It</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Way to Spin It</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>ベーゴマなど通常の日本独楽では胴に紐を巻き付けて回転を加える物が多いが、京こまは心棒に指で直接回転を加えるひねりゴマに分類される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although ordinary spinning tops including beigoma are usually spun with strings wound around their bodies, twist spinning tops including Kyo top are spun by directly spinning their stems.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although an ordinary spinning top, including the beigoma, is usually spun with a string wound around its body, twist spinning tops (including the Kyo top) are spun by directly spinning their stems.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although an ordinary Japanese spinning top, including the beigoma, is usually spun with a string wound around its body, twist spinning tops (including the Kyo top) are spun by directly spinning their stems.</e>
<cmt>「日本」　訳漏れ対応しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>中国より伝来した独楽が宮中の遊びとして残ったものといわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that spinning tops were introduced to Japan from China and became an amusement in the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that spinning tops were introduced to Japan from China and became popular as amusements in the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that spinning tops were introduced to Japan from China and became popular as amusements in the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>女官が着物の端切れを竹の棒を芯にして巻き付け、独楽状にして室内で回して遊んでいたのが京こまの起源といわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The origin of Kyo top is said to be the fact that court ladies wound tag ends of kimono (Japanese traditional clothing) around bamboo sticks to make spinning tops, and amused themselves with spinning them indoors.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The origin of the Kyo top is said to be the fact that court ladies wound tag the ends of kimono (Japanese traditional clothing) around bamboo sticks to make spinning tops, and that they would amuse themselves by spinning them indoors.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The origin of the Kyo top is said to be the fact that court ladies wound twist the ends of kimono (Japanese traditional clothing) around bamboo sticks to make spinning tops, and that they would amuse themselves by spinning them indoors.</e>
<cmt>「巻きつける」は「tag」より「twist」の方が良いと考え変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="11">
<j>その後、市中にもこの独楽が広まり、お座敷遊びの一つとして定着した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterwards, these spinning tops spread among ordinary people and became established as one of Ozashiki-Asobi (playing games with Geisha (Japanese professional female entertainer at drinking party)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eventually, these spinning tops spread among ordinary people and became established as one of Ozashiki-Asobi (playing games with Geisha (Japanese professional female entertainers at drinking parties)).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eventually, these spinning tops spread among ordinary people and became established as one of Ozashiki-Asobi (playing games with Geisha [Japanese professional female entertainers at drinking parties]).</e>
<cmt>括弧内の括弧を[]に変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>昭和末期から日本全体で伝統的な正月遊びが薄れたが、京こまも例外ではなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the end of the Showa era, traditional New Year games including Kyo top faded away from all areas of Japan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the end of the Showa era, traditional New Year&apos;s games--such as the Kyo top--faded away from all areas of Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the end of the Showa period, traditional New Year&apos;s games--such as the Kyo top--faded away from all areas of Japan.</e>
<cmt>era→period</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>一時すべての製造者が廃業し断絶した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, all the manufacturers of Kyo top closed down and disappeared for a time.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, all the manufacturers of Kyo tops closed down and disappeared for a time.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, all the manufacturers of Kyo tops closed down and disappeared for a time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>近年、最後の製造者の縁者によって製作が再開された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In recent years, the last manufacturer&apos; relatives have resumed manufacturing Kyo top.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in recent years the last manufacturers&apos; relatives have resumed manufacturing Kyo tops.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in recent years the last manufacturers&apos; relatives have resumed manufacturing Kyo tops.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 こぶまき(id:38278), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>