<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>重陽</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Choyo (Chrisanthemum Festival)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Choyo (Chrysanthemum Festival)</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Choyo (Chrysanthemum Festival)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>重陽（ちょうよう）とは五節句の一つで、9月9日のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Choyo&quot; means a festival observed every year on September 9 as one of the five seasonal festivals in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Choyo is a festival observed annually on September 9 as one of the five seasonal festivals in Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Choyo is a festival observed annually on September 9 as one of the five seasonal festivals in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>旧暦ではキクが咲く季節であることから菊の節句とも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called &quot;Kiku no Sekku&quot; (&quot;the Chrisanthemum Festival,&quot;) since it is held in the season of chrisanthemum according to the old calendar.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called &quot;Kiku no Sekku&quot; (&quot;the Chrysanthemum Festival,&quot;) since it&apos;s held in the season of the chrysanthemum, according to the old calendar.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called &quot;Kiku no Sekku&quot; (the Chrysanthemum Festival), since it&apos;s held in the season of the chrysanthemum, according to the old calendar.</e>
<cmt>括弧説明の&quot; &quot;を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>陰陽思想では奇数は陽の数であり、陽数の極である9が重なる日であることから「重陽」と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to inyo-shiso (a Chinese ideology of cosmic dual forces, the active and passive,) odd numbers are regarded as active numbers among which the number nine is the ultimate one, so that dual nine (September 9) means the highest of activeness and is written in Chinese characters as &quot;cho&quot; (meaning &quot;doubled&quot;) and &quot;yo&quot; (meaning &quot;activeness.&quot;)</e>
<cmt>用語集では、「陰陽思想」は「cosmic dual forces ideology」となっています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to inyo-shiso (a Chinese ideology of dual cosmic forces, the active and passive), odd numbers are regarded as active numbers, among which the number nine is the ultimate, so that dual nine (September 9) means the highest level of activeness and is written in Chinese characters as &quot;cho&quot; (meaning &quot;doubled&quot;) and &quot;yo&quot; (meaning &quot;activeness&quot;).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to inyo-shiso (a Chinese ideology of dual cosmic forces, the active and passive), odd numbers are regarded as active numbers, among which the number nine is the ultimate, so that dual nine (September 9) means the highest level of activeness and is written in Chinese characters as &quot;cho&quot; (meaning &quot;doubled&quot;) and &quot;yo&quot; (meaning &quot;activeness&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>奇数の重なる月日は陽の気が強すぎるため不吉とされ、それを払う行事として節句が行なわれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Any month and date of dual odd numbers was believed as ominous due to its extraordinary active energy.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Any month and date of dual odd numbers was considered ominous due to its extraordinary active energy.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Any month and date of dual odd numbers was considered ominous due to its extraordinary active energy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>九は一桁の数のうち最大の「陽」であり、特に負担の大きい節句と考えられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order to expel such inauspicious energy, the sekku festival was performed especially with a heavy load caused by the number of nine which is the maximum of the single-digit odd numbers.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処 「負担の大きい」の意味が今一つ明瞭ではありませんが、「with a heavy load」と訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to expel such inauspicious energy, the Sekku Festival was performed especially with a heavy load caused by the number nine, which is the highest single-digit odd number.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to expel such inauspicious energy, the Sekku Festival was performed especially with a heavy load caused by the number nine, which is the highest single-digit odd number.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>後、陽の重なりを吉祥とする考えに転じ、祝い事となったものである</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Subsequently, however, interpretation of the duality of active numbers has been converted to an auspicious omen to be celebrated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently, however, the interpretation of the duality of active numbers has become an auspicious omen to be celebrated.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently, however, the interpretation of the duality of active numbers has become an auspicious omen to be celebrated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>邪気を払い長寿を願って、菊の花を飾ったり、菊の花冠を浮かべた酒を酌み交わして祝ったりしていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the hope of eliminating evils and achieving longevity, people celebrated the choyo festival by decorating their houses with flowers of chrysanthemum, pouring sake drinks for each other with corollas of chrysanthemum floating on it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the hope of eliminating evils and achieving longevity, people celebrated the Choyo Festival by decorating their houses with flowers of chrysanthemum and pouring sake for each other with corollas of chrysanthemum floating on them.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the hope of eliminating evils and achieving longevity, people celebrated the Choyo Festival by decorating their houses with flowers of chrysanthemum and pouring sake for each other with corollas of chrysanthemum floating on them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>また前夜、菊に綿をおいて、露を染ませ、身体をぬぐうなどの習慣があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, people had a custom of cleansing their own bodies with wet cotton which had been put on chrysanthemums to indraw the dew on them during the evening before the choyo festival..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, people had the custom of cleansing their bodies with wet cotton that had been placed on chrysanthemums to draw up the evening dew prior to the day of the Choyo Festival.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, people had the custom of cleansing their bodies with wet cotton that had been placed on chrysanthemums to draw up the evening dew prior to the day of the Choyo Festival.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>しかし、現在では、他の節句と比べてあまり実施されていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But, at present, this custom is practiced in fewer occasions than the other sekku festivals.</e>
<cmt>「他の節句と比べて」の意味不明につき、逐語訳となりました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, however, this custom is practiced in fewer occasions than the other Sekku festivals.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, however, this custom is practiced in fewer occasions than the other Sekku festivals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>中国では、『芸文類聚』に魏 (三国)の曹丕が鍾繇へ菊花を贈った記事が見える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In China, Emperor Sohi (Cao Pi) of Wei dynasty in the Three States Period was reported to have presented chrysanthemum flowers to Shoyo (Zhong Yao) (a Chinese calligrapher and politician of Wei dynasty) according to the &quot;Geimon-ruiju&quot; (a Chinese encyclopedia, literally &quot;Collection of Literature Arranged by Categories.&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In China, Emperor Sohi (Cao Pi) of the Wei Dynasty (during the Three States period) was reported to have presented chrysanthemum flowers to Shoyo (Zhong Yao) (a Chinese calligrapher and politician of the Wei Dynasty) according to the &quot;Geimon-ruiju&quot; (a Chinese encyclopedia, literally &quot;Collection of Literature Arranged by Categories&quot;).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In China, Emperor Cao Pi of the Wei Dynasty (during the Three States period) was reported to have presented chrysanthemum flowers to Zhong Yao (a Chinese calligrapher and politician of the Wei Dynasty) according to the &quot;Yiwenleiju&quot; (a Chinese encyclopedia, literally &quot;Collection of Literature Arranged by Categories&quot;).</e>
<cmt>中国名の日本語読みは不要と考え削除しました。芸文類聚→the Yiwenleiju、としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>上記の菊を使った習慣の他に、茱萸（グミではなくサンショウ）の実を入れた袋を肘に下げたり、郊外の丘など高い場所へピクニックに出掛け遠くを見る（これを登高と呼ぶ）ことが行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Beside the above mentioned custom of using chrysanthemum, people used to dangle a bag contaiing berries of sansho (Japanese pepper) and to go on a picnic to a suburban hill or any other high place to have a distant view, which is called &quot;toko&quot; (literally &quot;climbing to a height.&quot;)</e>
<cmt>「茱萸（グミではなくサンショウ）の実」の意味不明につき、単に「サンショウの実」と訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Along with the above-mentioned custom of using chrysanthemum, people would dangle bags containing berries of sansho (Japanese pepper) and go on picnic to suburban hills or other high places offering distant views, in an activity called &quot;toko&quot; (literally, &quot;climbing to a height&quot;).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Along with the above-mentioned custom of using chrysanthemum, people would dangle bags containing berries of sansho (Japanese pepper) and go on picnic to suburban hills or other high places offering distant views, in an activity called &quot;toko&quot; (literally, &quot;climbing to a height&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>日本における重陽</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Choyo festivals in Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Choyo festivals in Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Choyo festivals in Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="12">
<j>平安時代から菊花酒（菊の酒）を飲む風習があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the Heian Period, people have been accustomed to enjoy drinking of kikuka-shu (literally &quot;sake of chrysanthemun flower&quot; which is the liquor made from chrysanthemum, rice, millet, etc.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the Heian period, people have been accustomed to drinking kikuka-shu (literally, &quot;sake of chrysanthemum flower,&quot; a liquor made from chrysanthemum, rice, millet, etc.).</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the Heian period, people have been accustomed to drinking kikuka-shu (literally, &quot;sake of chrysanthemum flower,&quot; a liquor made from chrysanthemum, rice, millet, etc.).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>松尾芭蕉の二俳句：</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Two haiku poems of Basho MATSUO:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Two haiku poems of Basho MATSUO</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Two haiku poems of Basho MATSUO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>草の戸や　日暮れてくれし　菊の酒</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kusa no to ya, higurete kuresi, kiku no sake (Sunset beyond the grassy doors of my hut, a great spot to sip chrysanthemum&apos;s sake)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kusa no to ya, higurete kuresi, kiku no sake (Sunset beyond the grassy doors of my hut, a great spot to sip chrysanthemum sake)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kusa no to ya, higurete kuresi, kiku no sake (Sunset beyond the grassy doors of my hut, a great spot to sip chrysanthemum sake)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>山中や　菊はたおらぬ　湯の匂　奥の細道、山中温泉の湯を賞賛して</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamanaka ya, kiku wa taoranu, yu no nioi (With chrysanthemum unplucked, breathes smell of a hot spring at Yamanaka spa,) which is a haiku composed by Basho MATSUO in his anthology &quot;Oku no Hosomichi&quot; praising the hot spring at Yamanaka onsen (spa.).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yamanaka ya, kiku wa taoranu, yu no nioi (With chrysanthemum unplucked, breathes fragrance of a hot spring at Yamanaka spa): a haiku composed by Basho MATSUO in his anthology &quot;Oku no Hosomichi,&quot; in praise of the hot spring at the Yamanaka onsen (spa).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamanaka ya, kiku wa taoranu, yu no nioi (With chrysanthemum unplucked, breathes fragrance of a hot spring at Yamanaka spa): a haiku composed by Basho MATSUO in his anthology &quot;Oku no Hosomichi,&quot; in praise of the hot spring at the Yamanaka onsen (spa).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Ligar(id:12623), Nnh(id:474), 江口磐世☆(id:168037), Eskimbot(id:29676), Alecs.bot(id:194707), SuisuiBot(id:10165), 名無し(id:7386), 鏡水蒼月(id:142300), Chobot(id:20846), Loveless(id:129239), Point136(id:211299), Shadow ump(id:112836), Alexbot(id:157199), Namazu-tron(id:135120), Ptbotgourou(id:229657), Hamasaki gion higashi(id:144985), Ajax(id:11202), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>