<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>鵺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nue (a legendary creature)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nue (a legendary creature)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nue (a fabulous creature)</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>鵺、（ぬえ）は日本で伝承される妖怪や物の怪といわれる伝説の生物一覧。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nue is a legendary creature that is called a specter and has been talked about in Japan from ancient times.</e>
<cmt>生物一覧：　”一覧”の意味が理解できませんでしたので、”生物の一種”として訳してあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nue is a legendary creature that is called a specter and has been talked about in Japan from ancient times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nue is a legendary creature that is called a specter and has been talked about in Japan from ancient times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>『平家物語』などに登場している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, it appears in &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; (The tale of the Heike).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, it appears in &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; (The tale of the Heike).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, it appears in &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot;.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>ニホンザルの顔、タヌキの胴体、トラの手足を持ち、尾はヘビで（文献によっては胴体については何も書かれなかったり、胴が虎で描かれることもある）、「ヒョーヒョー」という、鳥のトラツグミの声に似た大変に気味の悪い声で鳴いた、とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the creature had the face of a Japanese monkey, the trunk of a raccoon dog, the hands and legs of a tiger and the tail of a snake (concerning the trunk, no description is made in some documents or that of a tiger is depicted in some other documents), and generated quite eerie &quot;hyo, hyo&quot;sounds similar to the song of golden mountain thrushes.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the creature had the face of a Japanese monkey, the trunk of a raccoon dog, the hands and legs of a tiger and the tail of a snake (concerning the trunk, no description is made in some documents however that of a tiger is depicted in other documents), and generated quite eerie &quot;hyo, hyo&quot;sounds similar to the voice of golden mountain thrushes.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the creature had the face of a Japanese monkey, the trunk of a raccoon dog, the limbs of a tiger, and the tail of a snake (some documents do not mention the trunk, and other documents describe that the creature had the trunk of tiger), and generated quite eerie &apos;hyo, hyo&apos; sounds similar to the voice of golden mountain thrushes.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>一説には雷獣であるともいわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also said that the creature is a specter that appears together with a lightning stroke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also said that the creature is a specter that appears together with lightning.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also said that the creature is a specter that appears together with lightning.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>また、出現したのは一般には平安時代後期とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is generally said that the creature appeared in the latter half of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is generally said that the creature appeared in the latter half of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is generally believed that the creature appeared in the latter half of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>しかしながら、平安時代のいつ頃かは、二条天皇の時代、近衛天皇の時代、後白河天皇の時代、鳥羽天皇の時代など、資料によって諸説ある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, concerning more specific timing, there are many theories depending on the documents as in the following: the era of Emperor Nijo, that of Emperor Konoe, that of Emperor Goshirakawa or that of Emperor Toba.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, concerning more specific timing, there are many theories depending on the documents, as in the following: the era of Emperor Nijo, that of Emperor Konoe, that of Emperor Goshirakawa and that of Emperor Toba.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, concerning more specific timing, there are many theories depending on the documents, as in the following: in the reign of Emperor Nijo, that of Emperor Konoe, that of Emperor Goshirakawa and that of Emperor Toba.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>元来、鵺とは夜に鳴く鳥のことであり、『古事記』『万葉集』にも名が見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally, Nue indicates birds that sing in the night, and the term appears in &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters) and &quot;Manyoshu&quot; (Collection of Ten Thousand Leaves) as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally, Nue indicates birds that sing in the night, and the term appears in &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters) and &quot;Manyoshu&quot; (Collection of Ten Thousand Leaves) as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally, Nue indicates birds that sing in the night, and the term appears in &quot;Kojiki&quot; and &quot;Manyoshu&quot; as well.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>この鳥の正体は、現在ではトラツグミのこととするのが定説である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nowadays, it is an accepted theory that this bird is actually the golden mountain thrush.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nowadays, it is an accepted theory that this bird is actually the golden mountain thrush.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nowadays, it is accepted that this bird is actually the golden mountain thrush.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>この鳥の寂しげな鳴き声は平安時代頃の人々には不吉なものに聞こえたことから凶鳥とされていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The dreary song of this bird sounded ominous to peoples around the Heian period, and the bird was labeled as an ominous bird.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The dreary song of this bird sounded ominous to people around the Heian period, and the bird was labeled as an ominous bird.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The dreary song of this bird sounded ominous to people around the Heian period, so that the bird was labeled as an ominous bird.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>そのため、天皇や貴族たちは鳴き声が聞こえるや、大事が起きないよう祈祷したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, it is said that, as soon as an emperor or nobles heard the song, they prayed so that no grave matter would occur.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, it is said that, as soon as an emperor or nobles heard the song, they prayed so that no grave matter would occur.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, it is said that, as soon as an emperor or nobles heard the song, they prayed so that no grave matter would occur.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>『平家物語』にある怪物はあくまで「鵺の声で鳴く得体の知れないもの」で名前はついていなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The specter appearing in &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; is always described as &quot;a mysterious creature generating Nue-like song&quot; and is given no specific name.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The specter appearing in &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; is always described as &quot;a mysterious creature generating Nue-like song&quot; and is given no specific name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The specter appearing in &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; is always described as &apos;a mysterious creature singing like Nue&apos; and is given no specific name.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>しかし現在ではこの怪物の名前が鵺だと思われ、そちらの方が有名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, nowadays, it is considered that the name of this specter is Nue and the latter term is more widely known.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, nowadays, it is considered that the name of this specter is Nue and the latter term is more widely known.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, nowadays, it is considered that the name of the bird which had been taken for the specter is Nue, and it is more widely accepted.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>映画「悪霊島」（原作・横溝正史）の有名なキャッチ・フレーズ、「鵺の鳴く夜は恐ろしい」とはこの事である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;The night when the song of Nue is heard is dreadful,&quot; the famous catchphrase for &quot;An island possessed by an evil spirit,&quot; a movie (whose original story was written by Masashi YOKOMIZO), originates in such a legend.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;The night when the song of Nue is heard is dreadful,&quot; the famous catchphrase for &quot;An island possessed by an evil spirit,&quot; a movie (whose original story was written by Masashi YOKOMIZO), originates in such a legend.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The night when the song of Nue is heard is dreadful,&apos; the famous catchphrase for a movie (whose original story was written by Seishi YOKOMIZO) &quot;Akuryoto &quot; results from this misinterpretation.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>描写される姿形は北東の寅（虎）、南東の巳（蛇）、南西の申（猿）、北西の戌亥（犬とイノシシ）といった干支を表わす獣の合成という考えもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to another theory, the depicted shape of the creature is a composite of the tiger placed in the northeast, the snake placed in the southeast, the monkey placed in the southwest and the dog and wild boar in the northwest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to another theory, the depicted shape of the creature is a composite of the tiger placed in the northeast, the snake placed in the southeast, the monkey placed in the southwest and the dog and wild boar in the northwest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to another theory, the depicted shape of the creature is a composite of the twelve zodiac animals which represent compass directions: the tiger representing the northeast, the snake representing the southeast, the monkey representing the southwest and the dog and wild boar representing the northwest.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>『平家物語』や摂津国の地誌『摂津名所図会』などによると、鵺退治の話は以下のように述べられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; and &quot;Settsu-meisho-zue&quot; (a book introducing beauty spots in Settsu), a geographical document about Settsu Province, describe Nude was killed in the following way:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; and &quot;Settsu-meisho-zue&quot; (a book introducing beauty spots in Settsu), a geographical document about Settsu Province, describe that Nue was killed in the following way:</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; and a geographical document about Settsu Province &quot;Settsu-meisho-zue&quot; (a book introducing noted places in Settsu) describe that Nue was killed in the following way:</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>平安時代末期、天皇（近衛天皇）の住む御所・清涼殿に、毎晩のように黒煙とともに不気味な鳴き声が響き渡り、二条天皇がこれに恐怖していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Towards the end of the Hein period, a dreadful song of a bird resounded together with black smoke in almost every night in Seiryoden (Literally &quot;Limpid Cool Hall,&quot; an imperial summer palace), the residence of the emperor (Emperor Konoe), frightening Emperor Nijo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Towards the end of the Hein period, the dreadful song of a bird resounded together with black smoke almost every night in Seiryoden (Literally &quot;Limpid Cool Hall,&quot; an Imperial summer palace), the residence of the emperor (Emperor Konoe), frightening Emperor Nijo.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Towards the end of the Heian period, the dreadful song of a bird resounded together with black smoke almost every night in the residence of Emperor Konoe in the Imperial Palace, frightening Emperor Nijo.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>遂に天皇は病の身となってしまい、薬や祈祷をもってしても効果はなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At last, the emperor became ill, and no medicine nor prayer could restore his health.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Finally, the emperor became ill, and no medicine nor prayer could restore his health.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At last, the emperor became ill, and neither medicine nor prayer could not restore his health.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="18">
<j>側近たちはかつて源義家が弓を鳴らして怪事をやませた前例に倣って、弓の達人である源頼政に怪物退治を命じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Following the precedent that MINAMOTO no Yoshiie stopped the occurrence of a mysterious affair by generating sounds by beating the string of a bow, close aides to the emperor instructed MINAMOTO no Yorimasa, who was an expert of using a bow, to kill the mysterious creature.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Following the precedent that MINAMOTO no Yoshiie stopped the occurrence of a mysterious affair by generating sounds by beating the string of a bow, close aides to the emperor instructed MINAMOTO no Yorimasa, who was an expert in using a bow, to kill the mysterious creature.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Following the precedent that MINAMOTO no Yoshiie stopped the occurrence of a mysterious affair by generating sounds by beating the string of a bow, close aides to the emperor instructed MINAMOTO no Yorimasa, who was an expert with a bow and arrow, to kill the mysterious creature.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>頼政はある夜、家来の猪早太（井早太との表記もある）を連れ、先祖の源頼光より受け継いだ弓を手にして怪物退治に出向いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At one night, Yoshimasa, together with I no Hayata (written as 猪早太 or 井早太), one of his retainers, ventured out for killing the mysterious creature with the bow that was inherited from MINAMOTO no Yorimitsu, his ancestor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One night, Yoshimasa, together with I no Hayata (written as 猪早太 or 井早太), one of his retainers, ventured out to kill the mysterious creature with the bow that was inherited from MINAMOTO no Yorimitsu, his ancestor.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One night, Yorimasa, together with his retainer I no Hayata (written as 猪早太 or 井早太), ventured out to kill the mysterious creature with the bow that was inherited from his ancestor MINAMOTO no Yorimitsu.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>すると清涼殿を不気味な黒煙が覆い始めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then eerie black smoke began covering Seiryoden.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then eerie black smoke began covering Seiryoden.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then eerie black smoke began to cover Seiryoden.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>そこで、頼政が山鳥の尾で作った尖り矢を射った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, Yorimasa shot a sharp-edged arrow made of the tail of a copper pheasant.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, Yorimasa shot a sharp-edged arrow made of the tail of a copper pheasant.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, Yorimasa shot a sharp-edged arrow made of the tail of a copper pheasant.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>悲鳴とともに鵺が二条城の北方あたりに落下し、すかさず猪早太が取り押さえてとどめを差した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then a Nue fell down screaming in an area around north of Nijo-jo Castle, and I no Hayata subdued and killed it immediately.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then a Nue fell down screaming in an area around the north of Nijo-jo Castle, and I no Hayata subdued and killed it immediately.</e>
<cmt>slight modification赤い部分はいいか、わからない。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Nue fell down screaming in an area approximately north of Nijo-jo Castle, and I no Hayata subdued and killed it immediately.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>その時宮廷の上空には、カッコウの鳴き声が二声三声聞こえ、静けさが戻ってきたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that, at that time, a cuckoo sang its song twice or thrice over the Imperial court and then silence was restored.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that, at that time, a cuckoo sang its song twice or thrice over the Imperial court and then silence was restored.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that, at that time, a cuckoo sang its song twice or thrice over the Imperial Palace and then silence was restored.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>これにより天皇の体調もたちまちにして回復し、頼政は天皇から褒美に獅子王 (刀)という刀を貰賜した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then the health of the emperor was restored quickly, and Yorimasa was awarded by the emperor a sword called Shishio (literally, a lion king) as the reward.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then the health of the Emperor was restored quickly, and Yorimasa was given a sword by the Emperor, called Shishio (literally, a lion king) as a reward.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then the health of the Emperor was restored quickly, and Yorimasa was given a sword called Shishio (literally, a lion king) by the Emperor as a reward.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="25">
<j>退治された鵺のその後については諸説ある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Concerning how the killed Nue was handled thereafter, there are many theories.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Concerning how the killed Nue was handled thereafter, there are many theories.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are many theories concerning the treatment of the killed Nue.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>『平家物語』などによれば、京の都の人々は鵺の祟りを恐れて、死体を船に乗せて鴨川 (滋賀県)に流した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According, for example, to &quot;Heike Monogatari,&quot; people in Kyoto feared the vengeance of the Nue, and therefore, put the dead Nue on a boat and floated the boat down the Kamo-gawa River (in Shiga Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According, for example, to &quot;Heike Monogatari,&quot; people in Kyoto feared the vengeance of the Nue, and therefore, put the dead Nue on a boat and floated the boat down the Kamo-gawa River (in Shiga Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot;, for example, people in Kyoto feared the vengeance of the Nue, and therefore, put the dead Nue on a boat and floated it down the Kamo-gawa River (in Shiga Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>淀川を下った船は大阪東成郡に一旦漂着した後、海を漂って芦屋川と住吉川 (兵庫県)の間の浜に打ち上げられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The boat, which floated down the Yodo-gawa River, once drifted ashore Higashinari County, Osaka Prefecture, then floated on the sea and was washed up on the shore between Ashiya-gawa River and the Sumiyoshi-gawa River (in Hyogo Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The boat, which floated down the Yodo-gawa River, once drifted ashore in Higashinari County, Osaka Prefecture, then floated on to the sea and was washed up on the shore between Ashiya-gawa River and the Sumiyoshi-gawa River (in Hyogo Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The boat, which floated down the Yodo-gawa River, once drifted ashore in Higashinari-gun County, Osaka, then floated on to the sea and was washed up on the shore between the Ashiya-gawa River and the Sumiyoshi-gawa River (in Hyogo Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>芦屋の人々はこの屍骸をねんごろに葬り、鵺塚を造って弔ったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that people in Ashiya buried the dead body of the Nue cordially and mourned the death by building a Nue-zuka mound.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that people in Ashiya buried the dead body of the Nue cordially and mourned the death by building a Nue-zuka mound.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that people in Ashiya buried the Nue with the due ceremony and mourned over the death of the Nue by building a Nue-zuka mound.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>鵺を葬ったとされる鵺塚は、『摂津名所図会』では「鵺塚 芦屋川住吉川の間にあり」とある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Concerning the Nue-zuka mound, where it is said the Nue was buried, &quot;Settsu-meisho-zue&quot; describes that &quot;The Nue-zua mound is located between between the Ashiya-gawa River and the Sumiyoshi-gawa River.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Concerning the Nue-zuka mound, where it is said the Nue was buried, &quot;Settsu-meisho-zue&quot; describes that &quot;The Nue-zua mound is located between the Ashiya-gawa River and the Sumiyoshi-gawa River.&quot;</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Concerning the Nue-zuka mound, under which the Nue was believed to be buried, &quot;Settsu-meisho-zue&quot; describes that &apos;The Nue-zuka mound is located between the Ashiya-gawa River and the Sumiyoshi-gawa River.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="30">
<j>また江戸初期の地誌『芦分船』によれば、鵺は淀川下流に流れ着いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Ashiwakebune,&quot; a geographical document in the early Edo period, the Nue drifted down to the Yodo-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Ashiwakebune,&quot; a geographical document in the early Edo period, the Nue drifted down to the Yodo-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to a geographical document in the early Edo period &quot;Ashiwakebune,&quot; the Nue drifted down to the Yodo-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>祟りを恐れた村人たちが母恩寺の住職に告げ、ねんごろに弔って土に埋めて塚を建てた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Village people there feared its vengeance, notified the head priest of Boon-ji Temple of it, buried the corpse mourning cordially and built a Nue-zuka mound.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Village people there feared its vengeance, notified the head priest of Boon-ji Temple of it, buried the corpse mourning cordially and built a Nue-zuka mound.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Villagers around the area feared the vengeance of the Nue, notified the head priest of Boon-ji Temple of it, buried the corpse, mourning over the death of the Nue by building a Nue-zuka mound.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>しかし、明治時代に入って塚が取り壊されかけ、鵺の怨霊が近くに住む人々を悩ませ、慌てて塚が修復されたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it is said that, entering the Meiji period, the mound was threatened to be destroyed, tormenting people living around it, and therefore, the Nue-zuka was restored in haste.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is said that, upon entering the Meiji period, the mound was threatened with destruction, tormenting the people living around it, and therefore, the Nue-zuka was restored in haste.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is said that the mound was threatened with destruction during the Meiji period, which tormented the people living around it; therefore, the Nue-zuka was restored in haste.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>一方で『源平盛衰記』『閑田次筆』によれば、鵺は京都府の清水寺に埋められたといい、江戸時代にはそれを掘り起こしたために祟りがあったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, according to &quot;Genpei Seisui ki&quot; (Rise and Fall of the Minamoto and the Taira clans) and &quot;Kandenjihitsu&quot; (a book of essays in the latter half of the Edo period), the Nue was buried in Kiyomizu-dera Temple in Kyoto Prefecture, and in the Edo period, people were cursed because the corpse was dug out.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, according to &quot;Genpei Seisui ki&quot; (Rise and Fall of the Minamoto and Taira clans) and &quot;Kandenjihitsu&quot; (a book of essays in the latter half of the Edo period), the Nue was buried in Kiyomizu-dera Temple in Kyoto Prefecture, and in the Edo period, people were cursed because the corpse was dug out.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, according to &quot;Genpei Seisuiki&quot; (Rise and Fall of the Minamoto and Taira clans) and &quot;Kandenjihitsu&quot; (a book of essays in the latter half of the Edo period), the Nue was buried in Kiyomizu-dera Temple in Kyoto Prefecture, and during the Edo period, people were cursed because the corpse was dug out.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="34">
<j>別説では鵺の死霊は1頭の馬と化し、木下と名づけられて頼政に飼われたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to another theory, the spirit of the dead Nue turned into a horse, and the horse was named Kinoshita and was kept by Yorimasa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to another theory, the spirit of the dead Nue turned into a horse, and the horse was named Kinoshita and was kept by Yorimasa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to another theory, the spirit of the dead Nue turned into a horse, which was named Kinoshita and kept by Yorimasa.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>この馬は良馬であったために平宗盛に取り上げられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Being a good horse, it was taken away by TAIRA no Munemori.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Being a good horse, it was taken away by TAIRA no Munemori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As it was a good horse, it was taken away by TAIRA no Munemori.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>それをきっかけに頼政は反平家のために挙兵してその身を滅ぼすことになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this, Yorimasa took up arms against the Taira clan, ruining himself.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this, Yorimasa took up arms against the Taira clan, ruining himself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For this reason, Yorimasa took up arms against the Taira clan, ruining himself.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>このようにして、鵺は宿縁を晴らしたのだという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that, in this way, the Nue accomplished its revenge.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that, in this way, the Nue accomplished its revenge.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that, in this way, the Nue revenged itself on Yorimasa.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="38">
<j>また静岡県の浜名湖西方に鵺の死体が落ちて来たとも言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also said that the dead body of a Nue fell down in an area in the north of Lake Hamana.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also said that the dead body of a Nue fell down in an area in the north of Lake Hamana.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also said that the dead body of a Nue fell down in an area west of Lake Hamana, Shizuoka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>浜松市北区 (浜松市)の三ヶ日町鵺代、胴崎、羽平、尾奈といった地名はそれぞれ鵺の頭部、胴体、羽、尾が落ちてきたという伝説に由来する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The place names of Nueshiro, Dozaki, Hanehira and Ona originate in the legend that the head, trunk, feathers and tail of a Nue fell down there, respectively.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処胴崎、羽平：　読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The place names of Nueshiro, Dozaki, Hanehira and Ona originate in the legend that the head, trunk, feathers and tail of a Nue fell down there, respectively.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The toponyms of Nueshiro, Dozaki, Hanehira and Ona in Mikkabi-cho, Kita ward, Hamamatsu Prefecture originate in the legend that the head, trunk, feathers, and tail of a Nue fell down these places respectively.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="40">
<j>愛媛県上浮穴郡久万高原町には、鵺の正体は頼政の母だという伝説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kumakogen Town, Kamiukeana County, Ehime Prefecture, there is also a legend that the real identity of the Nue was Yorimasa&apos;s mother.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Kumakogen Town, Kamiukeana County, Ehime Prefecture, there is also a legend that the real identity of the Nue was Yorimasa&apos;s mother.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Kumakogen-cho Town, Kamiukeana-gun County, Ehime Prefecture, there is also a legend that the original form of the Nue was Yorimasa&apos;s mother.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>かつて伊勢平氏全盛の時代、頼政の母が故郷のこの地に隠れ住んでいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the era when Ise-Heishi (Taira clan) was at the peak of its prosperity, Yorimasa&apos;s mother lived secretly in this place where she was born and raised.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the era when Ise-Heishi (Taira clan) was at the peak of its prosperity, Yorimasa&apos;s mother lived secretly in this place where she was born and raised.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the era when Ise-Heishi (Taira clan) was at the peak of its prosperity, Yorimasa&apos;s mother lived secretly here, her birthplace.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>山間部の赤蔵ヶ池という池で、息子の武運と源氏再興をこの池の主の竜に祈った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Beside the pond named Azoga-ike, she prayed to the guardian dragon of the pond for his son&apos;s good fortune in battle and the revival of Genji (Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Beside the pond named Azoga-ike, she prayed to the guardian dragon of the pond for his son&apos;s good fortune in battle and the revival of Genji (Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Beside the pond named Azoga-ike in mountain areas, she prayed to the guardian dragon of the pond for her son&apos;s good fortune in battle and the revival of Genji (Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>すると、祈祷と平家への憎悪により母の体が鵺と化し、京都へ飛んで行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then her body turned into a Nue because of the prayer and hate for the Taira family, and flied to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then her body turned into a Nue because of the prayer and hate for the Taira family, and flew to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then her body turned into a Nue because of the prayer and hate for the Taira family, and the Nue flew to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>母の化身した鵺は天皇を病気にさせた上、自身を息子・頼政に退治させることで手柄を上げさせたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The mother-turned-into Nue made the emperor become ill, and furthermore, made herself killed by his son, Yorimasa, making him accomplish a great achievement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The mother-turned-into Nue made the Emperor become ill, and furthermore, made herself become killed by his son, Yorimasa, making him accomplish a great achievement.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Nue, the reincarnation of his mother, made the Emperor ill, and furthermore, had her son kill herself to make him perform a feat.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>頼政の矢に貫かれた鵺は赤蔵ヶ池に舞い戻って池の主となったものの、矢傷がもとで命を落としたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the Nue shot by an arrow of Yorimasa flied back to Azoga-ike Pond and became the guardian of the pond, but died from the wound due to the arrow.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the Nue shot by an arrow from Yorimasa flew back to Azoga-ike Pond and became the guardian of the pond, but died from the arrow wound.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the Nue shot by the Yorimasa&apos;s arrow flew back to Azoga-ike Pond and became the guardian of the pond, but died from the arrow wound.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>史跡</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Historical sites</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Historical sites</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Historical Sites</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="46">
<j>鵺塚（阪神芦屋駅近く、松浜公園の一画）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nue-zuka Mound (placed near to the Ashiya station of Hanshin Electric Express Railway: in the Hamamatsu-koen park)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nue-zuka Mound (located near to Ashiya station on the Hanshin Electric Express Railway: in Hamamatsu-koen park)</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nue-zuka Mound (located near to Ashiya Station on the Hanshin Electric Express Railway line: in Matsuhama-koen park)</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="47">
<j>『平家物語』で川に流された鵺を葬ったとされる塚。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The mound where, according to &quot;Heike Monogatari,&quot; the Nue washed ashore floating down the Yodo-gawa River was buried.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The mound where, according to &quot;Heike Monogatari,&quot; the Nue that washed ashore floating down the Yodo-gawa River was buried.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The mound where, according to &quot;Heike Monogatari,&quot; the Nue that floated down and washed ashore the Yodo-gawa River was buried.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>付近に掛かっている鵺塚橋の名はこの鵺塚に由来する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name of Nue-zuka-bashi Bridge located nearby originated in this Nue-zuka mound.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name of Nue-zuka-bashi Bridge located nearby originated in this Nue-zuka mound.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name of the Nue-zuka-bashi Bridge located nearby originated in this Nue-zuka mound.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="49">
<j>鵺塚（大阪市都島区）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nue-zuka Mound (located in Miyakojima Ward, Osaka City)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nue-zuka Mound (located in Miyakojima Ward, Osaka City)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nue-zuka Mound (located in Miyakojima-ku Ward, Osaka City)</e>
<cmt>住所表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="50">
<j>『芦分船』で淀川下流に流れ着いた鵺を葬ったとされる塚。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The mound where, according to &quot;Ashiwakebune,&quot; the Nue washed ashore in the lower part of the Yodo-gawa River was buried.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The mound where, according to &quot;Ashiwakebune,&quot; the Nue that washed ashore in the lower part of the Yodo-gawa River, was buried.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The mound where, according to &quot;Ashiwakebune,&quot; the Nue that washed ashore in the downstream part of the Yodo-gawa River was buried.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>現在の塚は前述の通り1870年に大阪府が改修したもので、祠も1957年に地元の人々によって改修されたもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As described above, the present mound is the one that was repaired in 1870 by Osaka Prefecture, and the small shrine was also the one that was repaired in 1957 by local people in that area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As described above, the present mound is the one that was repaired in 1870 by Osaka Prefecture, and the small shrine is also the one that was repaired in 1957 by local people in that area.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As described above, the present mound was repaired in 1870 by Osaka Prefecture, and the small shrine was also repaired in 1957 by local people in that area.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="52">
<j>鵺塚（京都府）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nue-zuka Mound (located in Kyoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nue-zuka Mound (located in Kyoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nue-zuka Mound (located in Kyoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="53">
<j>岡崎公園運動場付近。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Located around the athletic field in the Okazaki-koen park.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Located around the athletic field in Okazaki-koen park.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Located at the athletic field in Okazaki-koen park.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>京都の清水寺に鵺を葬ったという伝承との関連性は不明。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">No relationship between this mound and the legend, in which the dead body of the Nue was buried in Kiyomizu-dera Temple, is known.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">No relationship between this mound and the legend, in which the dead body of the Nue was buried in Kiyomizu-dera Temple, is known.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The relationship between this mound and the legend, in which the dead body of the Nue was buried in Kiyomizu-dera Temple, is unknown.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>発掘調査の結果、古墳時代の墳墓であることが判明している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An investigation based on an excavation revealed that it was a grave in the Kofun period (tumulus period).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An investigation based on an excavation revealed that it was a grave in the Kofun period (tumulus period).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An excavation revealed that it was a grave in the Kofun period (tumulus period).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="56">
<j>鵺池</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nue-ike Pond</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nue-ike Pond</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nue-ike Pond</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="57">
<j>二条城北方の児童公園にある池。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The pond in the children&apos;s park located in the north of Nijo-jo Castle</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The pond in the children&apos;s park located to the north of Nijo-jo Castle</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The pond in the children&apos;s park in the north of Nijo-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>頼政が鵺を射抜いて血塗られた矢を洗ったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Yoshimasa washed the blood-smeared arrow used for shooting the Nue in the pond.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Yoshimasa washed the blood-smeared arrow used for shooting the Nue in the pond.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Yorimasa washed the blood-smeared arrow used for shooting the Nue in the pond.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>現在では池跡が親水施設状に改装されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nowadays, the former pond site has been changed to a place for enabling people to become familiar to water.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nowadays, the former pond site has been changed to a place for enabling people to become familiar with water.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Now, the former pond site has been changed to a water garden.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="60">
<j>神明神社</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinmei-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinmei-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinmei-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="61">
<j>京都市下京区。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Located in Shimogyo Ward, Kyoto City</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Located in Shimogyo Ward, Kyoto City</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Located in Shimogyo-ku Ward, Kyoto City</e>
<cmt>住所表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>頼政が鵺退治の前にここで祈願し、見事退治した礼といって矢尻を奉納したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Yorimasa prayed here before killing the Nue and dedicated the arrow head there to offer his thanks for his successful killing of it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Yorimasa prayed here before killing the Nue and dedicated the arrow head there to offer his thanks for his successful killing of it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Yorimasa prayed here before killing the Nue, and devoted the arrowhead there as token of his thanks for his successful killing of it.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>この矢尻は社宝とされ、普段は写真のみ展示されており、毎年9月の祭礼で実物が公開される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This arrow head was kept as a treasure of the shrine, and only its photograph is exhibited usually, with the real one exhibited publicly at the feast of the shrine in September every year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This arrow head was kept as a treasure of the shrine, and only its photograph is exhibited usually, with the real one exhibited publicly at the feast of the shrine in September every year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This arrowhead was kept as a treasure of the shrine, and its photograph is always exhibited, with the real one exhibited to the public at the annual feast of the shrine in September.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="64">
<j>矢根地蔵</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yanone-jizo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yanone-jizo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yanone-jizo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="65">
<j>京都府亀岡市。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Located in Kameoka City, Kyoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Located in Kameoka City, Kyoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Located in Kameoka City, Kyoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>頼政が鵺退治の際、守り本尊である地蔵菩薩に願をかけた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When going to kill the Nue, Yorimasa offered a prayer with a bow to Jizo Bosatsu (Jizo Bodhisattva), his protective god.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When going to kill the Nue, Yorimasa offered a prayer with a bow to Jizo Bosatsu (Jizo Bodhisattva), his protective god.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When going to kill the Nue, Yorimasa offered a prayer to his protective god Jizo Bodhisattva.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>すると、夢枕に地蔵が現れ、矢田の鶏山の白鳥の羽で矢を作るよう告げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then Jizo appeared in his dream and instructed him to make an arrow with the feathers of swans at Mt. Tori in Yada.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then Jizo appeared in his dream and instructed him to make an arrow with the feathers of swans at Mt. Tori in Yada.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then Jizo appeared in his dream and instructed him to make an arrow with the feathers of swans which were at Mt. Tori in Yada.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>この伝承にちなみ、この地蔵は矢尻を持った姿をしているが、普段は非公開。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Related to this legend, this Jizo statue is provided with an arrow head, but is usually not exhibited publicly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Related to this legend, this Jizo statue is provided with an arrow head, but is usually not exhibited publicly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Related to this legend, this Jizo statue has an arrowhead, but is usually not exhibited to the public.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="69">
<j>長明寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chomyo-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chomyo-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chomyo-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="70">
<j>兵庫県西脇市。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Located in Nishiwaki City, Hyogo Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Located in Nishiwaki City, Hyogo Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Located in Nishiwaki City, Hyogo Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>この地はもとは頼政の所領地であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This area was originally owned by Yorimasa.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This area was originally owned by Yorimasa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This area was originally owned by Yorimasa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>そのため、寺の境内には頼政による鵺退治の像があるほか、寺のそばの矢竹藪という竹薮は、頼政が鵺退治の矢に用いる竹を採取したといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, in the premises of the temple, there is a Yosimasa&apos;s statue that depicts his killing of the Nue, and near to the temple, there is also a bamboo thicket called Yatakeyabu (arrow bamboo grove) where it is said he got the bamboo to be used for the arrows to kill the Nue.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, on the premises of the temple, there is a statue of Yosimasa that depicts his killing of the Nue, and near to the temple, there is also a bamboo thicket called Yatakeyabu (arrow bamboo grove) where it is said he obtained the bamboo used for the arrows used to kill the Nue.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, in the precincts of the temple, there is a statue of Yorimasa that depicts his killing of the Nue, and near to the temple, there is a bamboo thicket called Yatakeyabu (arrow bamboo grove) where it is said he obtained the bamboo used for the arrows used to kill the Nue.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="73">
<j>上記のほか、大分県別府市の別府地獄めぐり現存しない地獄にあったテーマパーク「怪物館」には鵺のミイラがあったといわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to those described above, it is said that the mummy of the Nue existed in the &quot;A specter house,&quot; a theme park that was provided in now extinct Jigoku (hot spring) on the course of Beppu Jizoku-meguri (a tour visiting various hot springs in Beppu) in Beppu, Oita Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to those described above, it is said that the mummy of the Nue existed in the &quot;Specter house,&quot; a theme park that was located at the now extinct Jigoku (hot spring) on the course of the Beppu Jizoku-meguri (a tour visiting various hot springs in Beppu) in Beppu, Oita Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to those described above, it is said that the mummy of the Nue was exhibited at the &apos;Specter house,&apos; a theme park in Hachiman Jigoku on the course of the Beppu Jigoku-meguri (a tour visiting various hot springs in Beppu) in Beppu, Oita Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>ほかにも類のない貴重なものと言われたが、このテーマパークは現存せず、ミイラも行方も判明していない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The mummy was said being unparalleled and very important, but the theme park was now extinct and it is also unknown where the mummy exists now.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The mummy was said to be unparalleled and very important, but the theme park is now extinct and it is also unknown where the mummy exists now.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The mummy was said to be unparalleled and invaluable, but the theme park is now closed and it is also unknown where the mummy exists now.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 MD242(id:11277), Izayohi(id:13095), 桂鷺淵(id:151322), Dummyoscar(id:26399), Nnh(id:474), Ykji1103(id:83710), MIsogi(id:20599), Eskimbot(id:29676), OiOiO(id:94238), Lupinoid(id:68), 逃亡者(id:14864), Ash Crow(id:26765), Escarbot(id:59151), Café au lait(id:30776), 柏木ゆげひ(id:121321), Rusk(id:9895), Riku(id:16088), Sionnach(id:21673), うぃき野郎(id:53567), Yasm(id:66127), けんち(id:5147), Corwin(id:973), FlaBot(id:30804), Dora(id:1122), Suisui(id:69), LeonardoRob0t(id:25875), KH－editor(id:125369), ぽーるべあー(id:152979), 小太刀(id:18154), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>