<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>すぐき</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Suguki Pickles</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Suguki Pickles</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Suguki Pickles</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>すぐきは、漬物のひとつ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Suguki pickles&quot; are one kind of pickles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Suguki pickles&quot; are one kind of Japanese pickles.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;Japanese&quot; - not in original but translation was a bit axiomatic</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Suguki pickles are one kind of Japanese pickles.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>カブの変種である酸茎菜（すぐきな、すぐきかぶらともいう）を原材料とする、現代の日本では数の少ない発酵漬物である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are made from Sugukina/Sugukikabura, a variant of turnip, and they are one of the handful ferment pickles in modern Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are made from Sugukina/Sugukikabura, a variant of turnip, and they are one of the few remaining fermented pickles in Japan.</e>
<cmt>&quot;handful ferment pickles in modern&quot;→&quot;few remaining fermented pickles in&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are made from Sugukina, a variant of turnip, and they are one of the few remaining fermented pickles in Japan.</e>
<cmt>すぐきな、としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>まったく味付けをしない調味なしの日本唯一の自然漬物といわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that they are the only unflavored native pickles without seasoning in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are said to be the only unflavored and unseasoned natural pickles in Japan.</e>
<cmt>&quot;It is said that they are&quot;→&quot;They are said to be&quot;&quot;without seasoning&quot;→&quot;and unseasoned&quot;&quot;native&quot;→&quot;natural&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are said to be the only unflavored and unseasoned natural pickles in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>京都の伝統的な漬物であり、「柴漬」、「千枚漬」と並んで京都の三大漬物と言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are traditional pickles in Kyoto, and called one of the three major pickles along with &apos;Shibazuke (salted chopped pickled vegetables)&apos; and &apos;Senmaizuke (pickled sliced radishes).&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are traditional Kyoto pickles and, along with &apos;Shibazuke (salted chopped pickled vegetables)&apos; and &apos;Senmaizuke (pickled sliced radishes)&apos;, they are known as one of the three major pickles.</e>
<cmt>pickles in KyotoKyoto pickles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are traditional Kyoto pickles and, along with &apos;Shibazuke&apos; (salted chopped pickled vegetables) and &apos;Senmaizuke&apos; (pickled sliced radishes), they are known as one of the three major pickles.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>酸茎菜は、京都市北区 (京都市)の賀茂別雷神社（上賀茂神社）で栽培したのが発祥とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sugukina pickles are said to have originated from cultivation at Kamo-wakeikazuchi-jinja Shrine (Kamigamo-jinja Shrine) in Kita Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sugukina are said to have first been cultivated at Kamo-wakeikazuchi-jinja Shrine (Kamigamo-jinja Shrine) in Kita Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;pickles&quot;&quot;originated from cultivation&quot;→&quot;first been cultivated&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sugukina are said to have first been cultivated at Kamowakeikazuchi-jinja Shrine (Also known as Kamigamo-jinja Shrine) in Kita-ku Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>しかしその歴史についてはいまだに定かにはなっていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, their history is not clear yet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, their history remains unclear.</e>
<cmt>&quot;is not clear yet&quot;→&quot;remains unclear&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, their history remains unclear.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>約300余年前の「日次紀事」（1667年）への記載をはじめ、数々の本草書、詩文などにその名前が載っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name was on numerous honsosyo (herbal works) or poetry, including description on &apos;Hinami-kiji (guidebook of annual events in Kyoto and surrounding area)&apos; (1667) more than three hundred years ago.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were first recorded over three hundred years ago in the &apos;Hinami-kiji (a guidebook of annual events in Kyoto and the surrounding area)&apos; (1667) and also appear in numerous botanical texts and poems.</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were first recorded over three hundred years ago in the &apos;Hinami-kiji&apos; (a guidebook of annual events in Kyoto and the surrounding area) (in 1667) and also appear in numerous botanical texts and poems.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>明治の時代になりその栽培が一般農家にも広がり、販売されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Meiji Period, their cultivation prevailed among conventional farmers, who started to sell them.</e>
<cmt>Meiji era　はMeiji Periodにしました。他の記事と統一。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Meiji Period, their cultivation spread to ordinary farmers, who started to sell them.</e>
<cmt>&quot;prevailed among conventional farmers&quot;→&quot;their cultivation spread to ordinary farmers&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Meiji period, their cultivation spread to ordinary farmers, who started to sell them.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>古来、酸茎菜の栽培と生産は、東西を鴨川 (淀川水系)と高野川 (京都市)にはさまれた三角州の中で、北端を深泥池とする地区に限られ、ここで生育されたものだけが「すぐき」と名が付けられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since ancient times, cultivation and production of Sugukina have been limited to the delta between Kamo-gawa River (Yodo-gawa water system) and Takano-gawa River (Kyoto City) in the east and west, having deep mud pool in the northern end, and only Sugukina grown there was named &apos;Suguki.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since ancient times, the cultivation and production of Sugukina have been limited to the delta between Kamo-gawa River (Yodo-gawa water system) and Takano-gawa River (Kyoto City) to the east and west, with Midorogaike Lake at the northern end, and only Sugukina grown there are called &apos;Suguki.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;&quot;in&quot;→&quot;to&quot;&quot;having deep mud pool in&quot;→&quot;and Midorogaike Lake at&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since ancient times, the cultivation and production of Sugukina have been limited to the delta between the Kamo-gawa River (Yodo-gawa water system) and the Takano-gawa River (Kyoto City) to the east and west, with Midorogaike Pond at the northern end, and only Sugukina grown there are called &apos;Suguki.&apos;</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>酸茎菜の種蒔きは8月末に行われ11月下旬ごろに収穫される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sugukina is planted at the end of August, and harvested in late November.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sugukina are planted at the end of August, and harvested in late November.</e>
<cmt>&quot;is&quot;→&quot;are&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sugukina are planted at the end of August, and harvested in late November.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>収穫した後、皮を剥き下漬をした後本漬を行う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After harvesting, it is peeled and pre-pickled, then has main pickling.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After harvesting, they are peeled and pre-pickled before the main pickling takes place.</e>
<cmt>&quot;it is&quot;→&quot;they are&quot;&quot;, then has main pickling&quot;→&quot;before the main pickling takes place&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After harvesting, they are peeled and pre-pickled before the main pickling takes place.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="12">
<j>本漬時の重石のかけ方は、独特の「天秤押し」というやり方で、長さ4～5mほどの丸太棒の一方を固定させ、もう一方の先に重石を下げて樽のフタを押さえる、「テコの原理」を利用した方法で行う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They way of placing stone weight at the main pickling is a unique one called &apos;Tenbin oshi,&apos; which makes use of &apos;principle of leverage&apos;, to press the cover by fixing the one end of a 4 to 5m long log, and hanging stone weight at the tip of the other end.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the main pickling stage, the pickles are squeezed using a unique method known as &apos;tenbin oshi&apos;, where a 4- to 5-meter-long pole, with one end fixed and a stone weight hung on the other, pushes down on the lid of the barrel containing the pickles.</e>
<cmt>reworded sentence to make it clearer for people unfamiliar with Japanese pickling methods. Also, I presume the &quot;テコの原理&quot; is to give more weight than would be obtained with the stone alone, but seeing as how this isn&apos;t explained in the original, I omitted it for clarity&apos;s sake</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the main pickling stage, the pickles are squeezed using a unique method known as &apos;tenbin oshi,&apos; where a 4- to 5-meter-long pole, with one end fixed and a stone weight hung on the other, pushes down on the lid of the barrel containing the pickles.</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>数日の本漬の後室に入れ加熱し発酵をさせる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After several days of the main pickling, they are put in a cellar, heated and fermented.</e>
<cmt>室→wifeは、cellarに直しました。(正室、側室の室でなく、ここは「むろ」の意味）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After several days of the main pickling, they are put in a cellar, heated and fermented.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After several days of the main pickling, they are put in a cellar, heated and fermented.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="14">
<j>収穫してから約一月程度の期間で乳酸発酵したあめ色のすぐきが完成する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Within about a month after harvesting, yellowish brown Suguki pickles with lactic fermentation become ready.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Within about a month after harvesting, the Suguki pickles, turned yellowish brown by lactic fermentation, are ready.</e>
<cmt>&quot;yellowish brown Suguki pickles with lactic fermentation become&quot;→&quot;the Suguki pickles, turned yellowish brown by lactic fermentation, are ready&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Within about a month after harvesting, the Suguki pickles, turned yellowish brown by lactic fermentation, are ready.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="15">
<j>酸茎菜の収穫は年明けまで続き、2月末ごろにはその年の漬け込みは終了する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Harvest of Sugukina continues until the turn of the year, and the pickling for the year is completed by the end of February.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sugukina harvest continues until the turn of the year, and the year&apos;s pickling is completed by the end of February.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Harvest of Sugukina&quot;→&quot;The Sugukina harvest&quot;&quot;pickling for the year&quot;→&quot;year&apos;s pickling&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sugukina harvest continues until the turn of the year, and the year&apos;s pickling is completed by the end of February.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="16">
<j>冬に息の見える頃が、最もおいしい期間である旬の京つけものの一つである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are one kind of Kyo pickles which are the best in the period when you can see your breath in the winter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are a seasonal Kyoto pickle, best eaten in the cold of winter when you can see your breath.</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence&quot;Kyo pickles&quot;→&quot;a seasonal Kyoto pickle&quot; - I feel it should be either Kyoto pickles or kyotsukemono, but not Kyo pickles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are a seasonal Kyoto pickle, best eaten in the cold of winter when you can see your breath.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="17">
<j>発祥の頃は、時候熟れ（じこうなれ）の技法を用いられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When they originated, the technique of Jikonare was applied.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally, they were produced using a technique known as &apos;jikonare&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally, they were produced using a technique known as &apos;jikonare.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="18">
<j>時候熟れとは、収穫して本漬したすぐきを家の軒下に置き、自然の気温で発酵させる技法である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jikonare&apos; is a technique to ferment with natural temperature by putting Suguki pickles after harvesting and the main pickling under the eaves of a house.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jikonare&apos; is a technique where the pickles, after the main pickling stage, are placed under the eaves of a house and fermented at natural temperatures.</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jikonare&apos; is a technique where the pickles, after the main pickling stage, are placed under the eaves of a house and fermented at natural temperatures.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>この時候熟れの技法で生産すると、すぐきの食べごろは春から初夏になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When producing by this technique of Jikonare, they are ready to eat from spring to early summer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When produced using the jikonare technique, they are ready to eat by spring to early summer.</e>
<cmt>&quot;producing by this technique of Jikonare&quot;→&quot;produced using the jikonare technique&quot;&quot;from&quot;→&quot;by&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When produced using the jikonare technique, they are ready to eat by spring to early summer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>現在は雑菌の繁殖や気温の変化によりこの漬け方をすることはほぼない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Currently, due to developing bacteria and temperature change, this way of pickling is hardly seen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These days, due to the spread of bacteria and temperature changes, this way of pickling is rarely seen.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Currently&quot;→&quot;These days&quot;&quot;developing bacteria&quot;→&quot;the spread of bacteria&quot;Maded &quot;change&quot; plural&quot;&quot;hardly&quot;→&quot;rarely&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These days, due to the spread of bacteria and temperature changes, this way of pickling is rarely seen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Suguki(id:208447), Shimotsuke(id:19741), J o(id:26533), Borracho(id:22592), Takoradee(id:82103), 春野秋葉(id:36725), Komatta(id:52309), 1029man(id:93235), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>