<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>落語</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Rakugo&quot; (Traditional Comic Storytelling [or The Comic Story Itself] In Japan)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rakugo (Japanese Traditional Comic Storytelling, or the Comic Story Itself)</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, parentheses within parentheses removed.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rakugo (Japanese Traditional Comic Storytelling, or the Comic Story Itself)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>落語（らくご）は、近世期の日本において成立し、現在まで伝承されている伝統的な話芸の一種。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Rakugo&quot; refers to a kind of traditional narrative arts, established in the Japanese early modern ages and handed down to the present generation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rakugo is a traditional Japanese narrative art handed down through the generations that was established in early modern times.</e>
<cmt>Word order, grammar, word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rakugo is a traditional Japanese narrative art handed down through the generations that was established in early modern times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>「落し話（おとしばなし）」、略して「はなし」とも言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called &quot;otoshi-banashi&quot; (a story that has a punchline), or in abbreviation &quot;hanashi&quot; (a story).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called otoshi-banashi (a story that has a punchline), or in abbreviation, hanashi (a story).</e>
<cmt>Punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called otoshi-banashi (a story that has a punchline), or in abbreviation, hanashi (a story).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>都市に人口が集積することによって独立した芸能として成立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The concentration of the population in urban areas enabled rakugo to become the independent performing arts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The movement of the population to urban areas enabled rakugo to become an independent performing art.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The movement of the population to urban areas enabled rakugo to become an independent performing art.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>成立当時はさまざまな人が演じたが、現在は通常、それを職業とする人が演じる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When rakugo was established, it was performed by various people having another occupation, but at present it is usually performed by the professional.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the early days of rakugo it was performed by a variety of people having another main occupation, but at present it is usually performed by professionals.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the early days of rakugo it was performed by a variety of people having another main occupation, but at present it is usually performed by professionals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>衣装や道具、音曲に比較的頼らず、身振りと語りのみで物語を進めてゆく独特の演芸であり、高度な技芸を要する伝統芸能でもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is the performance peculiarly expressed in gesture and narration rather than costume, props, and music, so it needs a high-level technique as the traditional performing arts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a unique performance using gesture and narration rather than costume, props, or music, and requires a high degree of skill to perform.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, changed for clarity. Repetition removed.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a unique performance using gesture and narration rather than costume, props, or music, and requires a high degree of skill to perform.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>本来「落語」とは落語家が行う演目（ネタ）のなかでも滑稽を中心とし、落ちを持つ「落とし噺」（おとしばなし）のことを指したが、現在では人情噺・芝居噺をも含めた総称として用いられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally, rakugo meant otoshi-banashi, which is distinguished from other kinds of &quot;neta&quot; (programs) by its comic taste and punchline, but at present, rakugo is used as the general term for otoshi-banashi, &quot;ninjo-banashi&quot; (a story with human interest), and &quot;shibai-banashi&quot; (a story with drama).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally, rakugo referred to otoshi-banashi, performances which were humorous and had a punchline, but at present, rakugo is used as a general term which includes otoshi-banashi, ninjo-banashi (a story with human interest), and shibai-banashi (a story with an element of drama).</e>
<cmt>Rewritten.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally, rakugo referred to otoshi-banashi, performances which were humorous and had a punchline, but at present, rakugo is used as a general term which includes otoshi-banashi, ninjo-banashi (a story with human interest), and shibai-banashi (a story with an element of drama).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>落語は寄席（よせ）と呼ばれる常設館で演じられることが多いが、近年は若手による小さなライブもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mostly, rakugo has been performed at a storytellers&apos; hall called &quot;yose,&quot; and nowadays, a small live performance of rakugo by a young comic storyteller is also seen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mostly, rakugo has been performed at yose (storytellers&apos; halls), but in recent years small live rakugo performances by young comic storytellers have also appeared.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mostly, rakugo has been performed at yose (storytellers&apos; halls), but in recent years small live rakugo performances by young comic storytellers have also appeared.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>落語家の舞台のことを「高座（こうざ）」と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The stage that a comic storyteller goes onto is called &quot;koza&quot; in Japanese.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The stage that a comic storyteller goes on to is called a koza.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, flow.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The stage that a comic storyteller goes on to is called a koza.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>江戸落語と上方落語には小道具や慣習に違いがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Edo rakugo&quot; (the rakugo performed in Edo) and &quot;Kamigata rakugo&quot; (the rakugo performed in &apos;Kamigata&apos; [Kyoto and Osaka area]) differ in props and routines.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Edo rakugo (rakugo performed in Edo) and Kamigata rakugo (that performed in the Kyoto and Osaka region) differ in terms of props and routines.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Edo rakugo (rakugo performed in Edo) and Kamigata rakugo (that performed in the Kyoto and Osaka region) differ in terms of props and routines.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>演目の種類</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Varieties of rakugo programs</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Varieties of Rakugo Performance</e>
<cmt>Word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Varieties of rakugo performance</e>
<cmt>文頭のみ大文字にしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>落語演目の分類にはいくつかの方法があり、それによって立てられる種類や区分も異なってくる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There exist some classification methods of rakugo programs, and each of the methods categorizes and divides the programs in a different way.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are several methods of classifying rakugo, each of the methods categorizing and dividing performances in a different way.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are several methods of classifying rakugo, each of the methods categorizing and dividing performances in a different way.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>成立時期によるもの</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Classification by the production period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Classification by Production Period</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Classification by production period</e>
<cmt>文頭のみ大文字にしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>- 古典落語/新作落語（創作落語）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">: Classical rakugo/New rakugo (Original rakugo)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Categories: Classical Rakugo, New Rakugo (also known as Original Rakugo)</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar. The term &apos;Original Rakugo&apos; does not appear in the explanation below, and is confusing as it appears next to &apos;New Rakugo&apos; when I assume it is an alternate name for &apos;Classical Rakugo&apos;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Categories: Classical rakugo, new rakugo (also known as original rakugo)</e>
<cmt>文頭のみ大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="12">
<j>江戸時代から明治ごろまでに原型が成立し、戦前までの時期に演出が確立した演目を「古典落語」とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Classical rakugo refers to the programs whose prototypes were established from Edo to around Meiji period, and whose staging was established before World War Ⅱ.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Classical rakugo refers to those performances which were established in some form between the Edo and Meiji periods, and which were staged World War Ⅱ.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word choice, changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Classical rakugo refers to those performances which were established in some form between the Edo and Meiji periods, and which were staged World War Ⅱ.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>それ以外の「新作落語」は、多くの場合、作者もしくは初演者以外の噺家がネタにしていることが少なく、斯界全体の共通財産となっていないことが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Programs of new rakugo have rarely been performed by storytellers - other than the creator (or the first performer) of the story - so most of the programs do not constitute the common property of the whole rakugo community.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">New rakugo has mainly been performed either by the authors themselves or young or inexperienced storytellers, and most of the performances do not constitute the common property of the whole rakugo community.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">New rakugo has mainly been performed either by the authors themselves or young or inexperienced storytellers, and most of the performances do not constitute the common property of the whole rakugo community.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>だが、社会の動向に機敏に反応した時事的な作品や風刺性の濃いものが多いのが特徴である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But many of them have been characteristically quick to respond to the social trend by touching on the topical agenda or by sprinkling sarcastic spice on the story.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, many of them have been quick to respond to social trends by including topical references and introducing satirical elements.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, many of them have been quick to respond to social trends by including topical references and introducing satirical elements.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>なお、両者の線引きは必ずしも明確ではなく、多くの演者によって演じられる新作落語（桂米朝 (3代目)作「一文笛」等）のように境界線上にある作品も少なくない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Incidentally, the distinction between classical rakugo and new rakugo is not always clear, so not a few works, such as Little Flute (a new rakugo program made by the third Beicho KATSURA and performed by many storytellers), are deemed to be ambiguous in category.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The distinction between classical rakugo and new rakugo is not always clear, and a number of works such as Little Flute (a new rakugo performance created by the third Beicho KATSURA and performed by many storytellers) are deemed to be ambiguous in terms of which category they belong to.</e>
<cmt>Added for clarity, word choice, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The distinction between classical rakugo and new rakugo is not always clear, and a number of works such as Little Flute (a new rakugo performance created by the third Beicho KATSURA and performed by many storytellers) are deemed to be ambiguous in terms of which category they belong to.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>演出の方法・構成によるもの</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Classification by the method or the constitution of the staging</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Classification by Method or Structure of the Production</e>
<cmt>Rewritten.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Classification by method or structure of the production</e>
<cmt>文頭のみ大文字にしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="16">
<j>落とし噺/人情噺/芝居噺(怪談噺・音曲噺)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">: Otsoshi-banashi/Ninjo-banashi/Shibai-banashi (including &quot;kaidan-banashi&quot; [a ghost story] and &quot;onkyoku-banashi&quot; [a story with background music])</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Categories: Otoshi-banashi, Ninjo-banashi, Shibai-banashi (including Kaidan-banashi ghost stories, and Onkyoku-banashi stories with background music)</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, spelling, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Categories: Otoshi-banashi, ninjo-banashi, shibai-banashi (including kaidan-banashi ghost stories, and onkyoku-banashi stories with background music)</e>
<cmt>文頭のみ大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="17">
<j>古典落語のうち、滑稽を中心とし、噺の最後に落ちまたはサゲのあるものを「落とし噺」という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Of all classical rakugo, the story characterized by its comic taste and punchline (called &quot;ochi&quot; or &quot;sage&quot;) is categorized as otsoshi-banashi.</e>
<cmt>（注）・・・「落ち」の訳に用いた&quot;punchline&quot;の意味は、Longman Dictionary of Contemporary English （以下、LDCEと略記）によれば、&quot;the last few words of a joke or story, which make it funny or surprising&quot; （ジョークや物語の最後に添えて、聞き手を面白がらせる、あるいは意外に思わせる言葉）です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Within classical rakugo, stories characterized by their comic content and punchlines called &quot;ochi&quot; or &quot;sage&quot; are categorized as otoshi-banashi.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, punctuation, spelling, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Within classical rakugo, stories characterized by their comic content and punchlines called &quot;ochi&quot; or &quot;sage&quot; are categorized as otoshi-banashi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="18">
<j>人情の機微を描くことを目的としたものを「人情噺」とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The story which aims to depict subtleties of human nature is categorized as ninjo-banashi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Stories which aim to depict the subtleties of human nature are categorized as ninjo-banashi.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Stories which aim to depict the subtleties of human nature are categorized as ninjo-banashi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>人情噺はたいていの場合続きものによる長大な作品で、かつては主任（トリ）に出た噺家が10日間の興行中連続して演じるものであったが、現在ではその区切りのいい一部分が取出されて演じられることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mostly, ninjo-banashi is a long series of works, so in the past, the feature storyteller (called &quot;tori&quot;) performed ninjo-banashi for 10 consecutive days during the show, but nowadays, only a separable part of the works is performed in many cases.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mostly ninjo-banashi form a long series of connected works, so in the past the central storyteller, or tori, performed a sequence of ninjo-banashi for ten consecutive days, but nowadays only individual sections of the sequence are performed in many cases.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, word choice, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mostly ninjo-banashi form a long series of connected works, so in the past the central storyteller, or tori, performed a sequence of ninjo-banashi for ten consecutive days, but nowadays only individual sections of the sequence are performed in many cases.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>この理由から、サゲはかならずしも必要ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, the performance does not always include &quot;sage.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result an individual performance may not contain a punchline.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result an individual performance may not contain a punchline.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="21">
<j>「落とし噺」や「人情噺」が素で上演されるのに対して、芝居のような書割や音曲を利用し、場合によっては演者が立って芝居のごとき見得をしたりする演目を「芝居噺」という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Otoshi-banashi and ninjo-banashi are both performed simply with talking, but in contrst, shibai-banashi takes the staging like &quot;shibai&quot; (a theatrical performance), in which &quot;kakiwari&quot; (a stage setting) and music are used and occasionally the performer stands up and poses.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Otoshi-banashi and ninjo-banashi are both performed simply by talking, but in contrast shibai-banashi are staged like a shibai (theatrical performance or play), in which a kakiwari (stage setting) and music are used, and occasionally the performer may stands up and pose as part of the performance.</e>
<cmt>Added for clarity, spelling, grammar, punctuation, word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Otoshi-banashi and ninjo-banashi are both performed simply by talking, but in contrast shibai-banashi are staged like a shibai (theatrical performance or play), in which a kakiwari (stage setting) and music are used, and occasionally the performer may stands up and pose as part of the performance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>特に幽霊の出てくるような怪談噺は、途中までが人情噺で、末尾が芝居噺ふうになっている場合が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And kaidan-banashi (a ghost story), which belongs to shibai-banashi, mostly consists of a ninjo-banashi-like story and a shibai-banashi-like ending.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaidan-banashi ghost stories, which come under the category of shibai-banashi, mostly consist of a ninjo-banashi-like story with a shibai-banashi-like ending.</e>
<cmt>Style, punctuation, flow, changed for clarity, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaidan-banashi ghost stories, which come under the category of shibai-banashi, mostly consist of a ninjo-banashi-like story with a shibai-banashi-like ending.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>広義には芝居を題材にしたり、パロディにしたりしている演目を芝居噺とすることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a broad sense, shibai-banashi includes the program whose topic is taken out from shibai, and the program which parodies shibai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In a broad sense, shibai-banashi may also include performances where the central topic is derived from a shibai or performances that parody them.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In a broad sense, shibai-banashi may also include performances where the central topic is derived from a shibai or performances that parody them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>この場合には、全体として「落とし噺」の構造を取り、なかにところどころ歌舞伎ふうの台詞廻しが混じる程度で、立って所作を行うことはない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In these kinds of shibai-banashi, the story is like an otoshi-banashi as a whole, and the dramatic, Kabuki-like elocution is seen only in some parts of it, so the performer does not stand up to pose in the program.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In these kinds of shibai-banashi, the story is similar to an otoshi-banashi as a whole, and some parts contain dramatic, kabuki-like lines and gestures, but the performer does not stand up or pose as part of the performance.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In these kinds of shibai-banashi, the story is similar to an otoshi-banashi as a whole, and some parts contain dramatic, kabuki-like lines and gestures, but the performer does not stand up or pose as part of the performance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="25">
<j>また大げさな所作が加わらなくても、音曲を利用して話をすすめてゆくネタもあり、これらを「音曲噺」と称する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And some programs called onkyoku-banashi unfold with background music, if not with exaggerated gestures.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Performances called onkyoku-banashi unfold with background music but do not use exaggerated gestures.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Performances called onkyoku-banashi unfold with background music but do not use exaggerated gestures.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>上方落語では噺の途中にはめものとして下座の音曲が利用されることがふつうであり、この点が東京とは異なる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Kamigata&quot; (Kyoto and Osaka area), the music of &quot;geza&quot; (a background musician) is used in every genre of rakugo as &quot;hamemono&quot; (the musical accompaniment for stage effect) during the storytelling, but in Tokyo, it is not.</e>
<cmt>（注）・・・次のセルの内容との対比から、原文の意味内容は「上方落語においては（落とし噺や人情噺など）あらゆるジャンルで一般的に音曲が利用された」、という風に解しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Kamigata rakugo (from the Kyoto and Osaka area), it is usual to include the music of a geza (background musician) in every genre of rakugo as the hamemono (musical accompaniment for stage effect) during the storytelling, but in Tokyo (Edo rakugo) it is not.</e>
<cmt>Added for clarity, punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Kamigata rakugo (from the Kyoto and Osaka area), it is usual to include the music of a geza (background musician) in every genre of rakugo as the hamemono (musical accompaniment for stage effect) during the storytelling, but in Tokyo (Edo rakugo) it is not.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>従って音曲噺という項目をわざわざ立てるのは江戸落語に限られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, it is only in Edo rakugo that the category of onkyoku-banashi is set in particular.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, it is only in Edo rakugo that the category of onkyoku-banashi is particularly fixed.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, it is only in Edo rakugo that the category of onkyoku-banashi is particularly fixed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>難易度によるもの</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Classification by the level of the performance difficulty</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Classification by Difficulty of Performance</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Classification by difficulty of performance</e>
<cmt>文頭のみ大文字にしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="28">
<j>- 前座噺（旅のネタ）/大ネタ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">: &quot;Zenza-banashi&quot; (an opening story) related to travel/&quot;Oneta&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Categories: Zenza-banashi (an opening story relating to travel, and Oneta</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Categories: Zenza-banashi (an opening story relating to travel, and Oneta</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="29">
<j>落語家身分が初めに習い覚える話を「前座ばなし」と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The story learned by a beginner &quot;rakugo-ka&quot; (comic storyteller) is called zenza-banashi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first stories learned by comic storytellers when they are new to rakugo are called zenza-banashi.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first stories learned by comic storytellers when they are new to rakugo are called &apos;zenza-banashi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>多くは口慣らしや口捌きを兼ねた単純で短い、しかし基礎的な技術を養うのに適したネタである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most programs of zenza-banashi are simple and short, so they are suitable for acquiring the basic storytelling skills, and they are also used for loosening up the performer&apos;s tongue (in other words, for warming up the talk technique).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most performances of zenza-banashi are simple and short, so they are suitable for acquiring basic storytelling skills, and they are also used for improving a storyteller&apos;s vocal technique and letting a beginner become accustomed to performing.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most performances of zenza-banashi are simple and short, so they are suitable for acquiring basic storytelling skills, and they are also used for improving a storyteller&apos;s vocal technique and letting a beginner become accustomed to performing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>二つ目や真打によって演じられることもあるが、比較的簡単な軽い話とみなされるためにトリの演目になることは無い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Regarded as a relatively brief and light story, zenza-banashi is never played by the feature performer called tori, although played by &quot;hutatsu-me&quot; (the performer situated between &apos;zenza&apos; [a beginner rakugo-ka] and &apos;shin-uchi&apos; [a star rakugo-ka]) and by shin-uchi occasionally.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regarded as a relatively brief and light story, zenza-banashi are never performed by established storytellers called tori, although they may be played by futatsu-me performers, situated between the zenza beginner storytellers and shin-uchi skilled performers, and occasionally by shin-uchi themselves.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, spelling, flow, changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regarded as a relatively brief and light story, zenza-banashi are never performed by established storytellers called tori, although they may be played by futatsu-me performers, situated between the zenza beginner storytellers and shin-uchi skilled performers, and occasionally by shin-uchi themselves.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>逆に大作といわれるネタや人情噺などのうちで特に難易度の高い作品を「大ネタ」と俗称することもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In contrast, there exist some programs that are commonly called &quot;oneta&quot; - the program praised as a masterpiece, and the program which is particularly difficult to perform of all (including ninjo-banashi).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In contrast, within the category ninjo-banashi, or of those performances which are considered masterpieces, works which are particularly difficult to perform are commonly called oneta.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In contrast, within the category ninjo-banashi, or of those performances which are considered masterpieces, works which are particularly difficult to perform are commonly called &apos;oneta.&apos;</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>上方では前座噺として長い続きものの「旅のネタ」を行うことが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kamigata, a serial program related to travel is often performed as zenza-banashi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Kamigata rakugo, a series of performances relating to travel are often performed as zenza-banashi.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity, word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Kamigata rakugo, a series of performances relating to travel are often performed as zenza-banashi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>どこで切って次の演者をあげてもいいようにできているためだといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is because the program is convenient to punctuate for the next performer who is about to appear on stage, they say.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is because it is said that the performance is convenient to punctuate for the next performer who is about to appear on stage.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is because it is said that the performance is convenient to punctuate for the next performer who is about to appear on stage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="35">
<j>サゲの種類によるもの（落とし噺）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Classification by the varieties of &quot;sage&quot; (or &apos;ochi&apos;) within otoshi-banashi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Classification by Type of Sage or Ochi within Otoshi-banashi</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, word choice, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Classification by type of sage or ochi within otoshi-banashi</e>
<cmt>文頭のみ大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="36">
<j>にわか落ち、ひょうし落ち、逆さ落ち、考え落ち、まわり落ち、見立て落ち、まぬけ落ち、とたん落ち、ぶっつけ落ち、しぐさ落ちなどがある（落ちの項参照）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Otoshi-banashi has various kinds of sage (or ochi), such as &quot;niwaka-ochi&quot; (the punchline using a pun), &quot;hyoshi-ochi&quot; (the punchline cracked in a rhythmical story), &quot;sakasa-ochi&quot; (the punchline whose funny points were hinted at to the audience early on), &quot;kangae-ochi&quot; (the punchline whose funny points might be difficult to catch), &quot;mawari-ochi&quot; (the punchline that returns to the beginning of the story), &quot;mitate-ochi&quot; (the punchline that likens something to a different thing), &quot;manuke-ochi&quot; (the punchline that ends with a nonsense or an absurdity), &quot;totan-ochi&quot; (the punchline that makes the whole story plausible), &quot;buttsuke-ochi&quot; (the punchline whose characters&apos; words are at odds with each other), and &quot;shigusa-ochi&quot; (the punchline using gestures) [cf. the section of &quot;Ochi&quot;].</e>
<cmt>（注）・・・それぞれの「落ち」につき下記ブログを参照の上次のように訳しています。①「にわか落ち」・・・「しゃれを使った落ち」②「ひょうし落ち」・・・「リズミカルに進んで最後の一言でオチるもの」③「逆さ落ち」・・・「オチの理屈や内容を（観衆に）先に言っておくもの」④「まわり落ち」・・・「話が回り回って元の所に戻るもの」⑤「見立て落ち」・・・「ある物を別の物に見立てるもの」⑥「まぬけ落ち」・・・「間抜け（論理矛盾）な一言で終わるもの」⑦「とたん落ち」・・・「最後の一言で話の筋がまとまるもの」⑧「ぶっつけ落ち」・・・「（登場人物の）言っていることが互いに食い違うもの」⑨「しぐさ落ち」・・・「しぐさで落ちをつけるもの」[http://kmblog.blog55.fc2.com/blog-entry-154.html]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Otoshi-banashi have various kinds of sage or ochi, such as niwaka-ochi (punchlines using a pun), hyoshi-ochi (forming part of a rhythmical story), sakasa-ochi (which have been hinted at to the audience early on), kangae-ochi (which might make the audience think or may be difficult to understand), mawari-ochi (which link to the beginning of the story), mitate-ochi (which liken something to a different thing), manuke-ochi (ending in nonsense or absurdity), totan-ochi (which add plausibility to the story as a whole), buttsuke-ochi (where characters&apos; words are at odds with each other), and shigusa-ochi (using gestures) [see the article Ochi for details].</e>
<cmt>Made smoother, repetition removed.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Otoshi-banashi have various kinds of sage or ochi, such as niwaka-ochi (punchlines using a pun), hyoshi-ochi (forming part of a rhythmical story), sakasa-ochi (which have been hinted at to the audience early on), kangae-ochi (which might make the audience think or may be difficult to understand), mawari-ochi (which link to the beginning of the story), mitate-ochi (which liken something to a different thing), manuke-ochi (ending in nonsense or absurdity), totan-ochi (which add plausibility to the story as a whole), buttsuke-ochi (where characters&apos; words are at odds with each other), and shigusa-ochi (using gestures) (see the article Ochi for details).</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>必ずしも十分な分類法ではないが、現在もっとも広く用いられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is still incomplete but the most popular classification now.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While incomplete, this is the most popular current classification.</e>
<cmt>Flow.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While incomplete, this is the most popular current classification.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>このほかに桂枝雀 (2代目)による四分類法（ドンデン、謎解き、へん、合わせ）がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides, the second Shijaku KATSURA classifies otoshi-banashi according to the contents of the punchline into four categories : &quot;donden&quot; (the punchline which amuses the audience with its unexpected twist in an ordinary story line); &quot;nazotoki&quot; (the punchline that suggests the answer of a riddle given to the audience in the story); &quot;hen&quot;(the punchline that amuses the audience with its wanders); and &quot;awase&quot; (the punchline that amuses the audience by matching two different things mentioned in the story with each other).</e>
<cmt>（注）・・・「ドンデン」は「話の筋に意外なひねりを加えることで聴衆を楽しませる落ち」、「謎解き」は「話の展開上聴衆が抱くであろう疑問を種明かしするタイプの落ち」、「へん」は「話を脱線させることで聴衆を楽しませるタイプの落ち」、「合わせ」は「話の中で異なる事物を合致させることにより聴衆を楽しませるタイプの落ち」と訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to the classification above, the second Shijaku KATSURA classified otoshi-banashi into four categories according to the type of punchline, namely, donden (punchlines which amuse the audience with an unexpected twist to an ordinary story line), nazotoki (that suggest the answer to a riddle presented to the audience within the story), hen (that amuses the audience by taking the story on a tangent), and awase (punchlines that amuse the audience by bringing together two separate things mentioned earlier in the story).</e>
<cmt>Grammar, changed for clarity, punctuation, wording, flow.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to the classification above, the second Shijaku KATSURA classified otoshi-banashi into four categories according to the type of punchline, namely, donden (punchlines which amuse the audience with an unexpected twist to an ordinary story line), nazotoki (that suggest the answer to a riddle presented to the audience within the story), hen (that amuses the audience by taking the story on a tangent), and awase (punchlines that amuse the audience by bringing together two separate things mentioned earlier in the story).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>表現の要素</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Factors of expression in rakugo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Methods of Expression in Rakugo</e>
<cmt>Word choice, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Methods of expression in rakugo</e>
<cmt>文頭のみ大文字にしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="39">
<j>落語において用いられる表現の要素は、以下の五種に区分することができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Factors of expression in rakugo can be classified into five categories as follows :</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Methods of expression in rakugo can be classified into five categories as follows :</e>
<cmt>Wording.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Methods of expression in rakugo can be classified into five categories as follows :</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="40">
<j>言葉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Words</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Words</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Words</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="41">
<j>音声として発せられる口頭語。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The voice, or the verbal word, is used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The performer&apos;s voice is the primary method.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten. Meaning altered slightly.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The performer&apos;s voice is the primary method.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="42">
<j>仕草</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gestures</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gestures</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gestures</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="43">
<j>最小限のものに限られ、基本的に立上って歩くことはない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gestures are used, but they are minimized, so a storyteller basically does not stand up, nor does he or she wander on stage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gestures are used, but they are minimized, and storytellers basically do not stand up or wander about the stage.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gestures are used, but they are minimized, and storytellers basically do not stand up or wander about the stage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="44">
<j>仕草のための小道具</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Props for the gestures</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Props for the Gestures</e>
<cmt>Punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Props for the gestures</e>
<cmt>文頭のみ大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="45">
<j>扇子、手ぬぐい、上方落語における見台と拍子木、張扇の五種に限定される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Only five props are used, that is, &quot;sensu&quot; (a fan), &quot;tenugui&quot; (a hand towel), &quot;kendai&quot; (a bookrack), &quot;hyoshigi&quot; (a wooden clapper), and &quot;harisen&quot; (a paper used as a slapstick) - the latter three are used merely in Kamigata-rakugo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Only five props may be used, a sensu (fan), tenugui (hand towel), kendai (bookstand), hyoshigi (wooden clapper), and a harisen (a fan used as a stick-shaped object), the latter three being used only in Kamigata rakugo.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar, changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Only five props may be used, a sensu (fan), tenugui (hand towel), kendai (bookstand), hyoshigi (wooden clapper), and a harisen (a fan used as a stick-shaped object), the latter three being used only in Kamigata rakugo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="46">
<j>そのほか特殊な演目における付随的要素</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Accompaniments to a special program</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additional Accompaniments for Special Performances</e>
<cmt>Added for clarity, punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additional accompaniments for special performances</e>
<cmt>文頭のみ大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="47">
<j>上方落語・音曲噺のはめもの、芝居噺の書割・ツケなど。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There exist some accompaniments to a special program, such as &quot;hamemono&quot; used in Kamigata-rakugo and in onkyoku-banashi, and &quot;kakiwari&quot; and &quot;tsuke&quot; (the sound effect produced by striking a wooden board called tsukeita with a clapper) both used in shibai-banashi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Kamigata-rakugo and onkyoku-banashi there are some further accompaniments to performances such as hamemono, and kakiwari and tsuke (sound effects produced by striking a wooden board called a tsukeita with a clapper) are both used in shibai-banashi.</e>
<cmt>Word order, punctuation, wording.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Kamigata-rakugo and onkyoku-banashi there are some further accompaniments to performances such as hamemono, and kakiwari and tsuke (sound effects produced by striking a wooden board called a tsukeita with a clapper) are both used in shibai-banashi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="48">
<j>口演には直接関係ないが、落語の演ぜられる場を構成する要素</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other components of rakugo stage</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other Components of the Rakugo Stage</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other components of the rakugo stage</e>
<cmt>文頭のみ大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="49">
<j>出囃子 (落語)、噺家の衣装（着物）、座布団、高座、めくりなど。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides, there exist other components of rakugo stage as well, such as &quot;debayashi&quot; (the background music played when a storyteller appears on stage), &quot;kimono&quot; (Japanese traditional clothing used by a storyteller), &quot;zabuton&quot; (a traditional square floor cushion for sitting on), &quot;koza&quot; (the stage that a storyteller goes onto) and &quot;mekuri&quot; (paper cards stitched together and stood on stage, and the name of a storyteller is written on the card one by one).</e>
<cmt>（注）「めくり」については「噺家の名前を一人一枚ずつ書いて綴じた紙の札で、舞台の上に置かれる。」と訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Debayashi (background music played when a storyteller appears on stage), kimono (Japanese traditional clothing worn by a storyteller), zabuton (a traditional square floor cushion for sitting on), koza (the stage that a storyteller goes onto) and mekuri (paper cards stitched together and stood up on stage, the name of a storyteller written on each card) are all additional components of the rakugo stage.</e>
<cmt>Word order, punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Debayashi (background music played when a storyteller appears on stage), kimono (Japanese traditional clothing worn by a storyteller), zabuton (a traditional square floor cushion for sitting on), koza (the stage that a storyteller goes onto) and mekuri (paper cards stitched together and stood up on stage, the name of a storyteller written on each card) are all additional components of the rakugo stage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>このうち特に重要なのは言葉と仕草であり、これが落語という芸の根幹を成しているといえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Of all things, words and gestures are most significant, so they can be said the essence of the rakugo performance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Words and gestures are the most significant, and they can be said to be the essence of the rakugo performance.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Words and gestures are the most significant, and they can be said to be the essence of the rakugo performance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>以下、言葉と仕草という要素を中心に説明してゆく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The details, particularly on words and gestures, of rakugo are explained below.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further details regarding the components are given below.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further details regarding the components are given below.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="52">
<j>言葉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Words</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Words</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Words</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>一般的に古典落語には定められた口演台本があり、噺家はこれを記憶して高座で再現する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Generally, classical rakugo has the fixed model of narration, and a storyteller memorizes and reproduces this on stage;</e>
<cmt>（注）「台本」は素直に訳せば&quot;script&quot;でしょうが、この英単語はLDCEによれば、「筆記された形態のもの」(＝the written form of a speech, play etc) のみを指します。次のセルにあるように、ここの「台本」は「筆記されたものとは限らない」のですから、&quot;model&quot;（＝お手本）と訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Generally, classical rakugo has a fixed model of narration, and a storyteller memorizes and reproduces this on stage.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Generally, classical rakugo has a fixed model of narration, and a storyteller memorizes and reproduces this on stage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>（ただし必ずしも筆記されたものとは限らない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the model does not always exist in a form of writing;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The model does not always exist in written form.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, wording.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The model does not always exist in written form.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>多くの場合は口伝えである）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">mostly, the model has been handed down orally.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In most cases, the model has been handed down orally.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, wording.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In most cases, the model has been handed down orally.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>すなわち落語のもっとも基礎的構成要素は、これらの台本を含めた「言葉」であるといえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And the most basic component of rakugo can be said the words, including those expressed in the model.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this reason the most basic component of rakugo can be said to be the spoken words, rather than any physical element.</e>
<cmt>Added for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For this reason the most basic component of rakugo can be said to be the spoken words, rather than any physical element.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>言葉の側面から見た落語には以下のような特徴が指摘できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seen from the perspetive of words, some characteristics can be pointed out for rakugo as follows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the perspective of words, some specific characteristics can be pointed out as follows:</e>
<cmt>Spelling, punctuation, wording.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the perspective of words, some specific characteristics can be pointed out as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="58">
<j>地の文と会話文（対話文）で構成されているが、噺の勘所にくると会話文によってテンポよく話を進めてゆき、説明的な地の文が少なくなる（この点が話芸としての講談との相違である）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The story of rakugo consists of descriptive parts and conversational parts (dialogue parts), and when the story comes to the point, conversations of characters are exchanged in a bouncy rhythm, and descriptive parts become fewer; this characteristic is not seen in another art of narration called &quot;kodan&quot; (vaudeville storytelling).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A rakugo story consists of descriptive parts and dialog, and when the story comes to a point the conversations between the characters are exchanged in an increasingly lively rhythm and the descriptive parts become fewer; this characteristic is not seen in another narrative art called kodan (vaudeville storytelling).</e>
<cmt>Word choice, order, grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A rakugo story consists of descriptive parts and dialog, and when the story comes to a point the conversations between the characters are exchanged in an increasingly lively rhythm and the descriptive parts become fewer; this characteristic is not seen in another narrative art called kodan (vaudeville storytelling).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="59">
<j>地の文の省略によって伝えきれないディテール（登場人物の細かい気持の変化や感情、会話をとりまく情景）は仕草によって補われて表現される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The details of the descriptive parts which are difficult to narrate - a subtle change of feelings of characters, and the background situation of their feelings and conversations - are expressed by gestures as the complement to the words.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The details of the descriptive parts which are difficult to narrate, such as subtle changes in the feelings of the characters and the background to their feelings and conversations, are expressed by gestures as a complement to the spoken words.</e>
<cmt>Added for clarity, grammar, punctuation, word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The details of the descriptive parts which are difficult to narrate, such as subtle changes in the feelings of the characters and the background to their feelings and conversations, are expressed by gestures as a complement to the spoken words.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="60">
<j>登場人物の多寡にかかわらず全てを一人で演じ、役割わけをしない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Regardless the number of characters, the whole story is told merely by one storyteller, not by some.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regardless of the number of characters, the whole story is told by a single storyteller.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regardless of the number of characters, the whole story is told by a single storyteller.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>このため声調、言葉づかい、話しかたなどによって登場人物の個性を印象づける工夫がなされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, the storyteller contrives to impress the personality of the characters each by differentiating their tone of voice, choice of words, way of talking, and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the storyteller contrives to convey the personality of each character by differentiating their tone of voice, choice of words, way of talking, and other factors.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, order.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the storyteller contrives to convey the personality of each character by differentiating their tone of voice, choice of words, way of talking, and other factors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="62">
<j>会話文から地の文への移りやその逆の場面、あるいはその他大勢的な多人数の会話においては、だれの視点から語られているのか判然としない語りが存在したり、気づかない間に語りの担い手が入れ替わったりするが、それが聴衆には不自然に聞こえない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When a conversational part proceeds to a descriptive part in a story - and vice versa - or when the conversations among many minor characters are exchanged, some of the conversations are unclear about which character&apos;s talk it is, and the character is changed before being noticed, but they do not sound unnatural to the audience.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When a conversational part precedes a descriptive part in the story, and vice versa, or when conversations take place among many minor characters, it is unclear sometimes as to which character is speaking, and the storyteller may change character without being noticed, but this does not sound unnatural to the audience.</e>
<cmt>Spelling, punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When a conversational part precedes a descriptive part in the story, and vice versa, or when conversations take place among many minor characters, it is unclear sometimes as to which character is speaking, and the storyteller may change character without being noticed, but this does not sound unnatural to the audience.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="63">
<j>仕草</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gestures</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gestures</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gestures</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>仕草は、落語において言葉の欠を補うための存在である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In rakugo, gestures are the complement to the words.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In rakugo, gestures are an important complement to the words.</e>
<cmt>Added for clarity, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In rakugo, gestures are an important complement to the words.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>すなわち演劇のように話のすべての部分について仕草が伴っているわけではなく、言葉だけでは表現しきれない部分に補足的な意味を持って仕草が付加されているのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In other words, rakugo differs from the theatrical performance that is accompanied by gestures in every part of a story, so gestures in rakugo are added as the complement to words when the words have difficulties in conveying the contents of a story.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In other words, rakugo differs from theatrical performances that are accompanied by gestures in every part of the story, and gestures in rakugo are added to complement the words when it is difficult for them to convey the meaning of the story on their own.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, order.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In other words, rakugo differs from theatrical performances that are accompanied by gestures in every part of the story, and gestures in rakugo are added to complement the words when it is difficult for them to convey the meaning of the story on their own.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>もっとも「言葉だけでは表現しきれない」内容については、言葉では端的に表現できない動作や前述「言葉」の項で述べたような地の文の欠如を補うといった低次のものから、素の芸において聴衆の想像力を刺激するために付加されるきわめて高度のものまで含まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And the contents of a story, which are difficult to convey with words, range from simple ones - an action that words have difficulties in expressing straightforward, and a performance complementary to the descriptive part mentioned above in &quot;words&quot; - to highly artistic ones that are added as improvisations for stimulating the imagination of the audience.</e>
<cmt>（注）原文に言う「素の芸において」は「即興の芸として」の意味に解しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The parts of a story which are difficult to convey with words range from simple ones, such as actions that words cannot express in a straightforward way, or sections of the performance which complement the descriptive parts mentioned above, to highly artistic ones that are added as improvisation to stimulate the imagination of the audience.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, word choice, order, grammar, changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The parts of a story which are difficult to convey with words range from simple ones, such as actions that words cannot express in a straightforward way, or sections of the performance which complement the descriptive parts mentioned above, to highly artistic ones that are added as improvisation to stimulate the imagination of the audience.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>仕草においても言葉同様、一人全役が原則であり、噺家は必要に応じて次々にさまざまな役のさまざまな仕草を仕分ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gestures, as well as words, are all played merely by one storyteller in principle, so he or she should differentiate a gesture of a character from another one if necessary.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Just as a single storyteller uses a variety of verbal communication styles to differentiate between the characters as dictated by the story, an array of gestures are also used to convey the various characters.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Just as a single storyteller uses a variety of verbal communication styles to differentiate between the characters as dictated by the story, an array of gestures are also used to convey the various characters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="68">
<j>仕草の主なものには以下のようなものがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Major gestures are as follows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Major gestures are as follows:</e>
<cmt>Punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Major gestures are as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="69">
<j>表情：登場人物の表情を演じる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A facial expression : A storyteller puts on facial expressions of characters of a story;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Facial expressions: the storyteller uses different facial expressions for each of the characters of a story.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar, word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Facial expressions: the storyteller uses different facial expressions for each of the characters of a story.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>必要に応じてわざと強調した、おもしろい表情をつくることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">occasionally, he or she puts on a funny facial expression in an exaggerated way if necessary.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Occasionally, he or she pulls a funny facial expression in an exaggerated way if necessary.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Occasionally, he or she pulls a funny facial expression in an exaggerated way if necessary.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="71">
<j>視線：上位の人物が下位の人物に話しかける場合には舞台下手を向き、逆の場合には舞台上手を向く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A line of sight : In a scene that an elder character talks to a younger one, the storyteller looks to the left of the stage (seen from the audience), and in a scene that a younger character talks to an elder one, the storyteller looks to the right of the stage (seen from the audience);</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Line of sight: in scenes where an elder character talks to a younger one the storyteller looks to the left of the stage (seen from the audience), and in scenes where a younger character talks to an elder one the storyteller looks to the right of the stage.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar, repetition removed.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Line of sight: in scenes where an elder character talks to a younger one the storyteller looks to the left of the stage (seen from the audience), and in scenes where a younger character talks to an elder one the storyteller looks to the right of the stage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>会話の部分において、こうして視線を切り替えることが、登場人物を仕分けて聴衆に印象付ける効果的な手法となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">in a conversational part, such a switch of the line of sight effectively impresses the audience with the difference of characters.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Within a dialog such a switch of the line of sight effectively conveys to the audience differences between the characters.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, wording, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Within a dialog such a switch of the line of sight effectively conveys to the audience differences between the characters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="73">
<j>ものを食べる：閉じた扇子を箸に見立てて、あるいは手づかみで、さまざまなものを食べる仕草が落語のなかにはある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A gesture of eating something : In rakugo, there exist varieties of gestures of eating something, using a folded fan like &quot;hashi&quot; (a pair of chopsticks, which is a Japanese utensil to eat food), or moving a hand like eating something with bare hands;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eating gestures: in rakugo there are a range of gestures to represent the act of eating something, using a folded fan like a pair of chopsticks, or moving a hand in a way that conveys the image of eating something with bare hands.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, wording. I don&apos;t feel the Japanese word &apos;hashi&apos; adds anything to the word chopstick, and an explanation of &apos;chopstick&apos; is unnecessary as it is a familiar sight.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eating gestures: in rakugo there are a range of gestures to represent the act of eating something, using a folded fan like a pair of chopsticks, or moving a hand in a way that conveys the image of eating something with bare hands.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>食べものや食べる状況によって仕分けるコツがそれぞれにある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">there exists the trick that differentiates a gesture from another one according to the varieties of food and the situation of eating it;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are various tricks or moves to illustrate the eating of a variety of different foods and in a range of situations.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are various tricks or moves to illustrate the eating of a variety of different foods and in a range of situations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>名人桂文楽が甘納豆（「明烏」）・枝豆（「馬のす」）などで見せた至芸が有名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">and the consummate performances of the master Bunraku KATSURA are well-known, such as the gesture of eating sweetened azuki beans (in the program of &quot;Ake-garasu&quot; [A crow nesting at dawn]), and the gesture of eating boiled green soybeans (in &quot;Umanosu&quot; [A hair of a horse&apos;s tail]).</e>
<cmt>（注）「明烏（あけがらす）」については定訳が見つかりませんでしたので翻訳者の創作で「明け方に巣籠りする烏」と意訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As an example, the consummate performances of the master Bunraku KATSURA are well-known, such as his gesture of eating sweetened adzuki beans in the performance of Ake-garasu (A Crow Nesting at Dawn), and the gesture of eating boiled green soybeans in Umanosu (The Hair of a Horse&apos;s Tail).</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, spelling, word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As an example, the consummate performances of the master Bunraku KATSURA are well-known, such as his gesture of eating sweetened adzuki beans in the performance of Ake-garasu (A Crow Nesting at Dawn), and the gesture of eating boiled green soybeans in Umanosu (The Hair of a Horse&apos;s Tail).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="76">
<j>歩く：正座したまま、あるいは軽くひざ立ちぐらいになって、手をぶらぶら動かしながら、両膝を交互に動かす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A gesture of walking : Kneeling formally with the buttocks on the heels (or taking a half-kneeling position), a storyteller swings the arms and moves the knees left and right.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Walking: kneeling formally while resting the buttocks on the heels or being in a half-kneeling position, a storyteller swings the arms and moves the knees left and right.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Walking: kneeling formally while resting the buttocks on the heels or being in a half-kneeling position, a storyteller swings the arms and moves the knees left and right.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>立上って実際に歩くことは基本的にない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Basically, he or she does not stand up to walk for real.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Generally, the storyteller does not get up and walk around the stage in imitation of a character.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Generally, the storyteller does not get up and walk around the stage in imitation of a character.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="78">
<j>書く：もっとも一般的には手ぬぐいを帳面や紙、扇子を筆に見立てて字を書く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A gesture of writing : Most commonly, a storyteller uses &quot;tenugui&quot; like a notebook or a piece of paper, and uses &quot;sensu&quot; like a writing brush;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Writing: most commonly a storyteller uses a tenugui to represent a notebook or a piece of paper, and uses sensu fan like a writing brush.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, changed for clarity, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Writing: most commonly a storyteller uses a tenugui to represent a notebook or a piece of paper, and uses sensu fan like a writing brush.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>上方落語の場合は見台を机に見立てることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">in Kamigata-rakugo, &quot;kendai&quot; is used like a desk.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">in Kamigata rakugo the kendai is used like a desk.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Kamigata rakugo the kendai is used like a desk.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="80">
<j>舟を漕ぐ：落語にはめずらしい大きな動きで、扇子を竿や艪にして演じる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A gesture of rowing a boat : This is an exceptionally showy movement for rakugo, using sensu like a pole or an oar;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rowing a boat: this is an exceptionally showy movement for rakugo, using a sensu like a pole or an oar.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rowing a boat: this is an exceptionally showy movement for rakugo, using a sensu like a pole or an oar.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>力仕事らしい感じを出さなければならない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">a storyteller should make the gesture look like a heavy work.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The storyteller should make the gesture look like heavy work.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The storyteller should make the gesture look like heavy work.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="25">
<sen id="82">
<j>寝る：横になることができないので、腕を添えてひじ枕の感じを出す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A gesture of lying down : A storyteller cannot lie down on stage, so he or she rests its head on its elbow;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Lying down: storytellers cannot lie down on stage so they often use their own arm to represent a pillow.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity, grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Lying down: storytellers cannot lie down on stage so they often use their own arm to represent a pillow.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>演出上の工夫である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">this is a technique for a stage effect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is another technique for stage effect.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is another technique for stage effect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="26">
<sen id="84">
<j>指さす・目をつかう：落語の性質上、噺のなかに登場するモノを実際に高座に持出すことは不可能であるために、虚空を指さしたり、見たりすることで、あたかもそれらがあるかのように演じる工夫がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gestures of pointing a finger, and shifting eyes : Rakugo does not allow a storyteller to bring an object mentioned in a story onto the stage, so he or she skillfully performs as if there were the object on stage by pointing its finger at empty space, or by staring into empty space.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Pointing a finger or staring: rakugo does not allow the storyteller to bring objects mentioned in the story onto the stage, so he or she skillfully acts as if the object were on stage by pointing a finger at an empty space, or by staring at a particular point on the stage.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar, wording.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Pointing a finger or staring: rakugo does not allow the storyteller to bring objects mentioned in the story onto the stage, so he or she skillfully acts as if the object were on stage by pointing a finger at an empty space, or by staring at a particular point on the stage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>例えば「刀を抜く」という仕草の場合、扇子を柄に見立てて抜いた後、鍔元から切先まで視線を動かしながら見ると、刀の長さが観客に伝わるという口伝がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, there exists an oral instruction within rakugo community that the gesture of drawing a sword can be well conveyed to the audience by moving a folded fan like a haft of a sword, and then by shifting eyes from an end of the fan (likened to a sword guard) straight to a point of empty space (likened to the point of a sword).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, there is a tradition within the rakugo community that the gesture of drawing a sword can be well conveyed to the audience by moving a folded fan like the hilt of a sword, and then by shifting the eyes from the end of the fan to a point of empty space representing the point of the sword to indicate the length of the blade.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word choice, changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, there is a tradition within the rakugo community that the gesture of drawing a sword can be well conveyed to the audience by moving a folded fan like the hilt of a sword, and then by shifting the eyes from the end of the fan to a point of empty space representing the point of the sword to indicate the length of the blade.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="27">
<sen id="86">
<j>涙を流す：主に人情噺で多く用いられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A gesture of shedding tears : This gesture is often seen in ninjo-banashi;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Crying: this gesture is often seen in ninjo-banashi.</e>
<cmt>Wording, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Crying: this gesture is often seen in ninjo-banashi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>高座に持参した湯呑みの中の茶や湯に指をつけ、その指で目の下を縦になぞる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">a storyteller dips its finger into tea or hot water of the teacup brought onto the stage, and he or she draws a vertical line under its eyes with the finger.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The storyteller dips a finger into a cup of tea or hot water brought onto the stage, and he or she draws a vertical line under the eyes with the finger.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, order.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The storyteller dips a finger into a cup of tea or hot water brought onto the stage, and he or she draws a vertical line under the eyes with the finger.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="28">
<sen id="88">
<j>厳密には話芸ではないが、食べる、飲む、歩く、走る、着るなど、登場人物の動作を、座布団の上に制限された動きで表現することも、臨場感を出す上で非常に重要な役割を果たす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To make the performance lively, characters&apos; action - eating, drinking, running, dressing, and so on - expressed merely on &quot;zabuton&quot; plays quite a significant role in rakugo, though the action is not the art of storytelling in a strict sense.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To make the performance lively, actions such as eating, drinking, running, dressing, and so on expressed in a defined manner without moving from the zabuton play quite a significant role in rakugo, though the action is not part of the art of storytelling in a strict sense.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, wording, changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To make the performance lively, actions such as eating, drinking, walking, running, dressing, and so on expressed in a defined manner without moving from the zabuton play quite a significant role in rakugo, though the action is not part of the art of storytelling in a strict sense.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>道具</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Props</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Props</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Props</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="89">
<j>使用する道具は、原則として扇子と手ぬぐいに限られる（稀に湯呑みも使われる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In principle, the props used in rakugo are only &quot;sensu&quot; and &quot;tenugui,&quot; but in a rare case, a teacup is also used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In principle, the props to be used in rakugo are limited to sensu and tenugui, but in rare cases a teacup is also used.</e>
<cmt>This sentence conflicts in meaning with the sentence in cell B80 above, where five standard props are outlined. Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In principle, the props to be used in rakugo are limited to sensu and tenugui, but in rare cases a teacup is also used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>扇子と手ぬぐいは、落語の表現上抽象性があらかじめ与えられており、状況に応じて、前者は箸や刀になり、後者は財布や証文になるなど、様々な用途で使用される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sensu and tenugui are given versatility in rakugo, so they are used to symbolize various things - for example, the former becomes &quot;hashi&quot; or a sword, and the latter becomes a wallet or a document.</e>
<cmt>（注）原文に言う「抽象性」は文脈からいって「万能性・融通性」(=versatility)の意味だと解しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sensu and tenugui are given a great deal of versatility in rakugo as they are used to symbolize a range of things, for example, the former may be used to represent a pair of chopsticks or a sword, and the latter a wallet or a document.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, added for clarity, wording.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sensu and tenugui are given a great deal of versatility in rakugo as they are used to symbolize a range of things, for example, the former may be used to represent a pair of chopsticks or a sword, and the latter a wallet or a document.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="91">
<j>扇子は落語家の符牒で「カゼ」と呼ばれ、特に幅が広く作ってある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sensu is called &quot;kaze&quot; within the community of storytellers, and the width is a little wider than a usual sensu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sensu are called kaze within the community of storytellers, and the width is a little wider than a standard sensu.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation, wording.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sensu are called &apos;kaze&apos; within the community of storytellers, and the width is a little wider than a standard sensu.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>刀、槍、箸、筆、キセルなど棒状の物の他に、開いた状態で手紙や提灯に見立てられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When folded, sensu is used like a sword, a pike, &quot;hashi,&quot; a writing brush, &quot;kiseru&quot; (a traditional Japanese cigarette pipe), or other things in a stick shape, and when unfolded, sensu is used like a letter or a paper lantern.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When folded, a sensu is used like a sword, a pike, chopsticks, a writing brush, a kiseru (traditional Japanese cigarette pipe), or other things which are long and thin, and when unfolded, the sensu is used like a letter or paper lantern.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation, wording.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When folded, a sensu is used like a sword, a pike, chopsticks, a writing brush, a kiseru (traditional Japanese cigarette pipe), or other things which are long and thin, and when unfolded, the sensu is used like a letter or paper lantern.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="93">
<j>手ぬぐいは「マンダラ」と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tenugui is called &quot;mandala.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tenugui are called mandala within the rakugo community.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar, changed for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tenugui are called &apos;mandala&apos; within the rakugo community.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>財布や証文、煙草入れ、本、巾着など袋状・布状の物の他に、紐や縄として使われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tenugui is used like a wallet, a document, a cigarette case, a book, a thing of a sac shape (or a thing like cloth) including a drawstring money pouch, a string, or a rope.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A tenugui is used to represent a wallet, a document, a cigarette case, a book, any object made of cloth or in the shape of a bag, such as a drawstring money pouch, and even a string or a rope.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation, wording.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A tenugui is used to represent a wallet, a document, a cigarette case, a book, any object made of cloth or in the shape of a bag, such as a drawstring money pouch, and even a string or a rope.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="95">
<j>上方落語ではこれらの他に見台と呼ばれる簡素な台と膝隠しが演者の前に置かれることがあるなどの特徴がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Peculiarly in Kamigata-rakugo, a simple bookrack (called &quot;kendai&quot;) and &quot;hiza-kakushi&quot; (a low single-leaf screen) are sometimes placed in front of a storyteller.</e>
<cmt>（注）「膝隠し」は「低い衝立（ついたて）」です。[http://www.kamigatarakugo.jp/about.html]参照</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Kamigata rakugo a simple bookrack called a kendai or a low single-leaf screen called a hiza-kakushi are sometimes placed in front of the storyteller.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar, order.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Kamigata rakugo a simple bookrack called a kendai or a low single-leaf screen called a hiza-kakushi are sometimes placed in front of the storyteller.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="96">
<j>服装・効果音</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Costume and sound effects</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Costume and Sound Effects</e>
<cmt>Punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Costume and sound effects</e>
<cmt>文頭のみ大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>落語家は単純な柄か無柄の和服を着用する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A storyteller should wear Japanese clothes with a simple or no pattern on it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A storyteller should wear Japanese clothes with little or no pattern.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A storyteller should wear Japanese clothes with little or no pattern.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>このとき、羽織の脱ぎ方一つをとっても約束事がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And here, there exist some rules - for example, the rules about when a storyteller should take off &quot;haori&quot; (a Japanese half coat) during rakugo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are also some additional rules in relation to when a storyteller should take off their haori (Japanese half coat) during the performance.</e>
<cmt>Wording, changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are also some additional rules in relation to when a storyteller should take off their haori (Japanese half coat) during the performance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>まず、演目のイントロダクションともいうべき関連した話題や背景を紹介していく枕から本題に移行する合図として、羽織を脱ぐ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Firstly, haori is taken off as the sign that the story progresses from &quot;makura&quot; (a related topic, or a background of the story, which serves as the introduction of the program) to the main topic.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Firstly, the haori is taken off to signify that the story is progressing from the makura (a related topic, or the background to the story, which serves as an introduction to the performance) to the main topic.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation, wording.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Firstly, the haori is taken off to signify that the story is progressing from the makura (a related topic, or the background to the story, which serves as an introduction to the performance) to the main topic.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>また大店（おおだな）などの商家を扱った演目では羽織は羽織ったままである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Secondly, haori is not taken off in the program that a merchant house - especially a large one - becomes the stage of the story.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Secondly, the haori is not taken off during performances where a merchant house, especially a large one, forms the focus of the story.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Secondly, the haori is not taken off during performances where a merchant house, especially a large one, forms the focus of the story.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>八つぁん・熊さん等の名で代表される町人や職人が登場するものでは羽織を脱ぐ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thirdly, haori is taken off in the program that an ordinary merchant or artisan, typically named &quot;Hattsuan&quot; and &quot;Kumasan,&quot; appears.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thirdly, the haori is taken off in performances where an ordinary merchant or artisan, typically named Hattsuan or Kumasan, appears.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation, wording.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thirdly, the haori is taken off in performances where an ordinary merchant or artisan, typically named Hattsuan or Kumasan, appears.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>更に、羽織の脱ぎ方も肩から滑らせるようにして一瞬で脱ぐ所作も注目すべき点である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And moreover, the storyteller&apos;s carriage is noteworthy, which slips a haori off its shoulders in a moment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, the ability of the storyteller to slip the haori from the shoulders in a moment is also worty of note.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, the ability of the storyteller to slip the haori from the shoulders in a moment is also worthy of note.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>このような決めごとにより、観衆の耳目を自身の芸そのものに集中させる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Using these rules, the storyteller attracts the attention of the audience to his or her art of narration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By adhering to these rules the storyteller attracts the attention of the audience to his or her art of narration.</e>
<cmt>Wording.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By adhering to these rules the storyteller attracts the attention of the audience to his or her art of narration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>落語は純粋な話芸であり、演じている最中は、音曲や効果音などは制限される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rakugo is a genuine art of narration, so music, sound effects, and the like are not used when a storyteller narrates the story.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In rakugo the focus is on the art of narration, so music, sound effects and the like are not used when the storyteller narrates the story.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation, wording.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In rakugo the focus is on the art of narration, so music, sound effects and the like are not used when the storyteller narrates the story.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>ただし地域や演目などによっては、出し物の最中に音曲や効果音が使用される場合がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in some areas, or in some programs, music and sound effects are used even when a storyteller narrates the story.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in some areas, or in some specific performances, music and sound effects are used when the storyteller narrates the story.</e>
<cmt>Wording.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in some areas, or in some specific performances, music and sound effects are used when the storyteller narrates the story.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>話の構成</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Constitution of the story</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Structure of the Story</e>
<cmt>Wording.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Structure of the story</e>
<cmt>文頭のみ大文字にしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="106">
<j>本筋に入る前に演目に関わりのある小話が語られ、これを「枕」という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before getting into the main topic, a storyteller warms up with the funny little tale that is related to the program, and the tale is called &quot;makura.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before getting into the main topic, a storyteller warms up with a funny little tale that is related to the performance called a makura.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before getting into the main topic, a storyteller warms up with a funny little tale that is related to the performance called a makura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>これの果たす役割は、小話で笑わせて、本題の前に聴衆をリラックスさせる、本題に関連する話題で聴衆の意識を物語の現場に引きつける、落ちへの伏線を張る、などが挙げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Makura has some roles in rakugo - to amuse the audience and make them relax before the start of the main topic, to lead the audience with its topic (related to the main topic) to a scene of the story, to allude to the punchline, and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The makura fills a variety of roles in rakugo, such as to amuse the audience and get them to relax before the start of the main topic, to lead the audience into the main topic of the story using a related scene, or as a tool to set up the final punchline, among others.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation,</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The makura fills a variety of roles in rakugo, such as to amuse the audience and get them to relax before the start of the main topic, to lead the audience into the main topic of the story using a related scene, or as a tool to set up the final punchline, among others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>古典落語の演題の中には、現在では廃れてしまった風習、言葉を扱うものがあり、それらに関する予備知識がないと、話全体や落ちが充分に楽しめないことがあり、枕がこの目的にあてられることも多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some programs of classical rakugo mention the words and customs that are obsolete today, so that the audience occasionally cannot enjoy the whole story or the punchline to their hearts&apos; content without the previous knowledge, so makura often provides the knowledge.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some classical rakugo performances contain words and customs that are obsolete today, and the audience may not be able to enjoy the whole story or the punchline fully without previous knowledge, so the makura is often used to provide the audience with assistance in this regard.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity, grammar, wording, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some classical rakugo performances contain words and customs that are obsolete today, and the audience may not be able to enjoy the whole story or the punchline fully without previous knowledge, so the makura is often used to provide the audience with assistance in this regard.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="109">
<j>本来の筋にはない、演者によって挿入されたおかしみのある部分を「くすぐり」と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And a storyteller sometimes inserts a humorous tale, which is not seen in the original plot, and the tale is called &quot;kusuguri.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The storyteller also sometimes inserts a humorous tale which is not seen in the original plot called a kusuguri.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The storyteller also sometimes inserts a humorous tale which is not seen in the original plot called a &apos;kusuguri.&apos;</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>一般的には話の筋から大きく外れないくすぐりが好まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Generally, the audience prefer the kusuguri that does not go off so far from the plot.</e>
<cmt>（注）「好まれる」とあるのは「観衆から」の意味に解しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Generally, audiences prefer kusuguri that are connected to the plot of the main story.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, added for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Generally, audiences prefer kusuguri that are connected to the plot of the main story.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="111">
<j>本来は落し咄は落ちによって締めくくられるが、最近は口演時間（寄席では概ね一人 15 分見当）の制約や、時代的に判り難い下げが出て来たなどの関係で、本来の下げまで行かずに終ることも多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In principle, otoshi-banashi should conclude with the punchline, but nowadays, it often ends before the punchline because of some snags, such as the time constraint - a storyteller has only about 15 minutes at &quot;yose&quot; - and the situation that some punchlines become difficult for the audience to understand in the present age.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In general, otoshi-banashi should conclude with a punchline, but nowadays they often end before the punchline because of such factors as time constraints (a storyteller generally has only about fifteen minutes on stage) and for the reason that some punchlines are difficult for modern audiences to understand.</e>
<cmt>I understand &apos;yose&apos; to be the building where the performance takes place, but in this sentence it appears that the stage is being indicated. Grammar, wording, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In general, otoshi-banashi should conclude with a punchline, but nowadays they often end before the punchline because of such factors as time constraints (a storyteller generally has only about fifteen minutes on stage) and for the reason that some punchlines are difficult for modern audiences to understand.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="112">
<j>前述のように人情噺、芝居噺などのほとんどには落ちはない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As is mentioned above, most of ninjo-banashi and shibai-banshi have no punchline.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As mentioned above, most ninjo-banashi and shibai-banshi have no punchline.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As mentioned above, most ninjo-banashi and shibai-banshi have no punchline.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="113">
<j>他の芸能との違い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Differences between rakugo and other performing arts</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Differences between Rakugo and Other Performing Arts</e>
<cmt>Punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Differences between rakugo and other performing arts</e>
<cmt>文頭のみ大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="114">
<j>落語が再現芸術でありながら演劇や舞踏と一線を画して考えられるのは、演劇・舞踏といった芸能が通常扮装を伴って演技されるのに対して、落語においては扮装を排し、素のままで芸を見せるためである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Being the art based on a fixed model and reenacted on stage, rakugo is distinguished clearly from other performing arts, such as a theatrical performance and a dance performance, because a storyteller does not dress up as some character and shows himself or herself in its performance, while the theatrical and dance performer commonly dress up as some character.</e>
<cmt>（注）「再現芸術」の意味については「定まったお手本があり、これに基づいて再現される芸術」の意味に解しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Being an art based on a fixed model that is reenacted on stage rakugo can be distinguished clearly from other performing arts such as theatrical and dance performances because storytellers do not dress up as each character but rather appear as themselves, whereas theatrical and dance performers usually dress up as a character.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation, wording.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Being an art based on a fixed model that is reenacted on stage rakugo can be distinguished clearly from other performing arts such as theatrical and dance performances because storytellers do not dress up as each character but rather appear as themselves, whereas theatrical and dance performers usually dress up as a character.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>すなわち落語では、噺家は登場人物や話の流れに相応しい身なりや格好をモノ（衣装・小道具・大道具・書割・照明・効果音）で表現することはなく、主として言葉と仕草によって演出効果をねらう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In rakugo, a storyteller expresses the attire and the clothes - suitable for the character and the plot of the story - in principle, not with various stuff (costume, props, stage setting, &quot;kakiwari,&quot; stage lighting, and sound effects), but with words and gestures.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In rakugo, storytellers convey the the attire and appearance of the characters they portray not with various physical objects such as costume, props, the stage setting, kakiwari, stage lighting, and sound effects, but with words and gestures.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation, wording.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In rakugo, storytellers convey the attire and appearance of the characters they portray not with various physical objects such as costume, props, the stage setting, kakiwari, stage lighting, and sound effects, but with words and gestures.</e>
<cmt>重複削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="116">
<j>そのために、落語の表現要素は (1) 噺家の芸に結びつく基本的な要素（言葉、仕草）と (2) 1 を助けるためにその場に応じて何にでも変化できるようなニュートラルな最低限のモノ（小道具、衣装）とに区分することができるのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Accordingly, factors of expression in rakugo can be classified into two categories, that is, the basic factors (words and gestures) directly linked with the art of a storyteller, and the minimum stuff (props and costume) that complements the basic factors with its versatility.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Accordingly, methods of expression in rakugo can be classified into two categories, basic factors (words and gestures) directly linked with the art of the storyteller, and restricted tools (props and costume) that complement these basic factors through their versatility.</e>
<cmt>Wording, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Accordingly, methods of expression in rakugo can be classified into two categories, basic factors (words and gestures) directly linked with the art of the storyteller, and restricted tools (props and costume) that complement these basic factors through their versatility.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="117">
<j>これは、素の芸であることを前提とする落語の大きな特徴であるといえるだろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These factors can be said the remarkable characteristics of rakugo, which are based on the nature not to dress up as some character.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fact that the art itself, rather than the costume or scenery, is central to the performance is the overriding characteristic of rakugo.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fact that the art itself, rather than the costume or scenery, is central to the performance is the overriding characteristic of rakugo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="118">
<j>一人の話者が聴衆を笑わせる芸としては、ほかに漫談が挙げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to rakugo, there exists another amusing, narrative art called &quot;mandan&quot; (comic chat) performed by one person.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to rakugo there is another amusing, narrative art called mandan (comic chat) which is performed by a single person.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation, wording.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to rakugo there is another amusing, narrative art called mandan (comic chat) which is performed by a single person.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="119">
<j>しかし、漫談が聴衆に語りかける話法を用いるのに対し、落語は主として登場人物同士の対話によって話が進められてゆくことがひとつの大きな特徴といえるであろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mandan takes the style of monologue, while rakugo is mostly occupied with the dialogue between the characters, which could be said a remarkable characteristic of rakugo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mandan is in the style of a monologue, while rakugo is mostly occupied with the dialogue between several characters, which could be said to be the remarkable characteristic of rakugo.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mandan is in the style of a monologue, while rakugo is mostly occupied with the dialogue between several characters, which could be said to be the remarkable characteristic of rakugo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="120">
<j>枕の部分を別とすれば、落語の本筋の部分では、必要最小限の情景の叙述（「地」といわれる部分）と、演出上、話からはなれて緊張を解くなどの目的で、「語りかけ」に戻ることもあるが、主として、物語は対話で成り立っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In rakugo, the main topic is mostly occupied with dialogue, and the rest is the minimum background description (called &quot;ji&quot;) and the monologue that is diverged from the story for relaxing the audience - though the structure of the introductory part (called &quot;makura&quot;) is different.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In rakugo the main topic centers around the dialogue between the characters, and the remainder is minimal background description (called ji) or a monologue which is separate from the main story and has the aim of relaxing the audience, though the structure of the introductory makura is different.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In rakugo the main topic centers around the dialogue between the characters, and the remainder is minimal background description (called ji) or a monologue which is separate from the main story and has the aim of relaxing the audience, though the structure of the introductory makura is different.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="121">
<j>会話が少なく、主にいわゆる「地の文」で展開される話を「地噺（じばなし）」と呼ぶ（『紀州 (落語)』など）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The story made up of so-called descriptive parts (and few dialogues) is called &quot;ji-banashi,&quot; exemplified by &quot;Kishu&quot; (Kishu Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Stories made up of so-called descriptive parts and few dialogues are called ji-banashi, exemplified by Kishu Rakugo.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Stories made up of so-called descriptive parts and few dialogues are called &apos;ji-banashi,&apos; exemplified by &quot;Kishu Rakugo.&quot;</e>
<cmt>記号補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History of rakugo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History of Rakugo</e>
<cmt>Punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History of rakugo</e>
<cmt>文頭のみ大文字にしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="122">
<j>おもしろみのある話の源流は『竹取物語』、または『今昔物語』や『宇治拾遺集』に収められた説話にまでさかのぼる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The origin of comic story traces way back to the tales included in &quot;Taketori Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of the Bamboo Cutter), &quot;Konjaku Monogatari&quot; (Tales of Now and Then), and &quot;Uji Shui-shu&quot; (Collection of Tales from Uji).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The origin of comic story telling can be traced back to the tales included in &quot;Taketori Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of the Bamboo Cutter), &quot;Konjaku Monogatari&quot; (Tales of Now and Then), and &quot;Uji Shui-shu&quot; (Collection of Tales from Uji).</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The origin of comic story telling can be traced back to the tales included in &quot;Taketori Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of the Bamboo Cutter), &quot;Konjaku Monogatari&quot; (Tales of Now and Then), and &quot;Uji Shui-shu&quot; (Collection of Tales from Uji).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="123">
<j>滑稽な話を集めた本の元祖としては、誓願寺の安楽庵策伝が京都所司代の板倉重宗に語った話をもとに作られたという1623年の『醒睡笑』が挙げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The book that collected funny stories for the first time in history was &quot;Seisuisho,&quot; which is said to have been written in A.D. 1623 by Sakuden ANRAKUAN at Seigan-ji Temple, based on the tales he spoke to Shigemune ITAKURA, the Governor-General of Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first collection of amusing stories in Japan was &quot;Seisuisho&quot;, which is said to have been written in 1623 by Sakuden ANRAKUAN at Seigan-ji Temple, based on the tales he told to Shigemune ITAKURA, the Governor-General of Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity, punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first collection of amusing stories in Japan was &quot;Seisuisho,&quot; which is said to have been written in 1623 by Sakuden ANRAKUAN at Seigan-ji Temple, based on the tales he told to Shigemune ITAKURA, the Governor-General of Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>カンマ位置移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="124">
<j>この本を元にして『子ほめ』『牛ほめ』『唐茄子屋政談』『たらちね』など現在でも演じられるはなしが生まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From this book, some stories performed even today were born, such as &quot;Kohome&quot; (A Flattered Baby), &quot;Ushihome&quot; (A Flattered Cow), and &quot;Tonasuya-seidan&quot; (A Pumpkin Vender).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Several stories still performed today are derived from this collection, such as &quot;Kohome&quot; (A Flattered Baby), &quot;Ushihome&quot; (A Flattered Cow), and &quot;Tonasuya-seidan&quot; (A Pumpkin Vendor).</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity, spelling.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Several stories still performed today are derived from this collection, such as &quot;Kohome&quot; (A Flattered Baby), &quot;Ushihome&quot; (A Flattered Cow), &quot;Tonasuya-seidan&quot; (A Pumpkin Vendor) and &quot;Tarachine.&quot;</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="125">
<j>また、豊臣秀吉の茶話相手をつとめる御伽衆の一人、曽呂利新左衛門も落語家の先祖であるといわれるが、架空の人物であるとも言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And some people say Shinzaemon SORORI (a tea-drinking companion and one of entertainers of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI) was the first comic storyteller in Japanese history, but others say Shinzaemon was a mythical figure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some people say Shinzaemon SORORI (a tea-drinking companion and one of entertainers of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI) was the first comic storyteller in Japanese history, but others say Shinzaemon was a mythical figure.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some people say Shinzaemon SORORI (a tea-drinking companion and one of entertainers of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI) was the first comic storyteller in Japanese history, but others say Shinzaemon was a mythical figure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="126">
<j>17世紀後半になると、江戸の町では大坂出身の鹿野武左衛門が芝居小屋や風呂屋で「座敷仕方咄」を始めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the later 17th century, Buzaemon SHIKANO from Osaka began &quot;Zashiki Shikata Hanashi&quot; (theatrical comic storytelling performed inside of a house) at playhouses and bathhouses in Edo towns.</e>
<cmt>（注）「座敷仕方咄」とは「屋内で行われる芝居がかりの咄」です。[http://www.sky-a.co.jp/rakugoblog/rakugo2008091016.html]参照</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the latter half of the seventeenth century, Buzaemon SHIKANO from Osaka began &quot;Zashiki Shikata Hanashi&quot; (theatrical comic storytelling performed inside a house) at playhouses and bathhouses within Edo.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, style, changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the latter half of the seventeenth century, Buzaemon SHIKANO from Osaka began &apos;Zashiki Shikata Hanashi&apos; (theatrical comic storytelling performed inside a house) at playhouses and bathhouses within Edo.</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="127">
<j>同時期に京都では露の五郎兵衛が四条河原で活躍し、後水尾天皇の皇女の御前で演じることもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around the same time at Shijo Gawara in Kyoto, TSUYU no Gorobei (the first) was busily engaged in rakugo, and he sometimes performed in front of an Imperial Princess of Emperor Gomizuo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around the same time at Shijo Gawara in Kyoto, TSUYU no Gorobei (the first) was busily engaged in rakugo, and he sometimes performed in front of the imperial princesses of Emperor Gomizuo.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around the same time at Shijo Gawara in Kyoto, TSUYU no Gorobei (the first) was busily engaged in rakugo, and he sometimes performed in front of the imperial princesses of Emperor Gomizunoo.</e>
<cmt>人名修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="128">
<j>大坂には米沢彦八が現れて人気を博し、名古屋でも公演をした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Osaka, Hikohachi YONEZAWA (the first) appeared and caught fire, so he made a perfomance tour to Nagoya.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Osaka Hikohachi YONEZAWA (the first) became popular and perfomed in Nagoya.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Osaka Hikohachi YONEZAWA (the first) became popular and performed in Nagoya.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="129">
<j>また、『寿限無』の元になる話を作ったのが初代の彦八であると言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said to have been the first Hikohachi who made the original story of &quot;Jugemu&quot; (a well-known rakugo program).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said to have been the first Hikohachi who made the original story of &quot;Jugemu&quot; (a well-known rakugo program).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said to have been the first Hikohachi who made the original story of &quot;Jugemu&quot; (a well-known rakugo program).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="130">
<j>18世紀後半になると、上方では雑俳や仮名草子に関わる人々が「咄（はなし）」を集め始めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the later 18th century, &quot;hanashi&quot; (comic stories) were begun to be collected in Kamigata by people who were related to &quot;zappai&quot; (playful literature originated from &apos;haiku&apos; [a Japanese poem in 17 syllables having a 5-7-5 syllabic form]) and to &quot;kana zoshi&quot; (a story book written in &apos;kana&apos; [Japanese syllabary characters]).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the latter half of the eighteenth century, hanashi (comic stories) began to be collected in Kamigata by people who wrote zappai (a lighthearted form of literature which originated from haiku, a Japanese poem in seventeen syllables having a 5-7-5 syllabic form) and kana zoshi, a story book written in kana characters.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity, wording, punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the latter half of the eighteenth century, hanashi (comic stories) began to be collected in Kamigata by people who wrote zappai (a lighthearted form of literature which originated from haiku, a Japanese poem in seventeen syllables having a 5-7-5 syllabic form) and kana zoshi, a story book written in kana characters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="131">
<j>これが白鯉館卯雲という狂歌師によって江戸に伝えられて江戸小咄が生まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These stories were introduced into Edo by Bouun HAKURIKAN, a maker of comic &quot;tanka&quot; (Japanese poem made up of 31 syllables), who gave birth to Edo-kobanashi (Edo little comic stories).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These stories were introduced to Edo by Bouun HAKURIKAN, a writer of comic tanka (a Japanese poem made up of thirty-one syllables), who gave birth to Edo-kobanashi (short Edo comic stories).</e>
<cmt>Style, grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These stories were introduced to Edo by Bouun HAKURIKAN, a writer of comic tanka (a Japanese poem made up of thirty-one syllables), who gave birth to Edo-kobanashi (short Edo comic stories).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="132">
<j>上方では1770年代に、江戸では1786年に烏亭焉馬らによって咄の会が始められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A gathering of comic storytellers was begun in Kamigata in 1770s, and also begun in Edo in A.D. 1786 by Enba UTEI and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A gathering of comic storytellers was begun in Kamigata in 1770s, and also in Edo in 1786 by Enba UTEI among others.</e>
<cmt>Style, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A gathering of comic storytellers was begun in Kamigata in 1770s, and also in Edo in 1786 by Enba UTEI among others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="133">
<j>やがて1798年に岡本万作と初代三笑亭可楽がそれぞれ江戸で2軒の寄席を開くと、その後寄席の数は急激に増えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before long in A.D. 1798, Mansaku OKAMOTO and Karaku SANSYOTEI (the first) each opened two storytellers&apos; hall in Edo, and thereafter its number increased rapidly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before long, in 1798, Mansaku OKAMOTO and Karaku SANSYOTEI (the first) each opened two storytellers&apos; halls in Edo, and thereafter the number of venues increased rapidly.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, wording.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before long, in 1798, Mansaku OKAMOTO and Karaku SANSHOTEI (the first) each opened two storytellers&apos; halls in Edo, and thereafter the number of venues increased rapidly.</e>
<cmt>人名修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="134">
<j>幕末から明治にかけて活躍した三遊亭圓朝は歴史的な名人として知られ、圓朝の高座を書き記した速記本は当時の文学、特に言文一致の文章の成立に大きな影響を与えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Encho SANYUTEI, a popular storyteller from the last days of Tokugawa shogunate to the Meiji period, was known as a historic master of storytelling, so the book (based on the shorthand notes of his storytelling) gave a great impact on the then literature - particularly, gave birth to the sentences written in a colloquial style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Encho SANYUTEI, a popular storyteller who performed from the last days of the Tokugawa shogunate to the Meiji Period, was known as a historic master of storytelling, and the book based on shorthand notes of his storytelling had a great impact on the literature of the time, particularly in relation to sentences written in a colloquial style.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity, punctuation, grammar, wording.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Encho SANYUTEI, a popular storyteller who performed from the last days of the Tokugawa shogunate to the Meiji period, was known as a historic master of storytelling, and the book based on shorthand notes of his storytelling had a great impact on the literature of the time, particularly in relation to sentences written in a colloquial style.</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="135">
<j>1917年8月には柳派と三遊派が合併し、橘家圓蔵 (4代目)、三遊亭圓右、柳家小さん (3代目)らが中心となって演芸会社「東京寄席演芸株式会社」を、柳亭左楽は「三遊柳連睦会（通称、睦会）」を設立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In August 1917, Yanagi Group and Sanyu Group (both are storyteller groups) converged, and the core members - Enzo TACHIBANAYA (the fourth), Enu SANYUTEI, Kosan YANAGIYA (the third) and others - established Tokyo Vaudeville Co.,Ltd, and Ryutei SARAKU (the fifth) also established &quot;Sanyu-yanagi Friendly Association&quot; (commonly called &apos;Mutsumi-kai&apos; in Japanese).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In August 1917, the Yanagi Group and Sanyu Group (both storyteller groups) merged, and the core members, Enzo TACHIBANAYA (the fourth), Enu SANYUTEI, Kosan YANAGIYA (the third) and others, established Tokyo Vaudeville Co. Ltd, and Ryutei SARAKU (the fifth) also established the Sanyu-yanagi Friendship Association (commonly called &apos;Mutsumi-kai&apos; in Japanese).</e>
<cmt>Grammar, wording, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In August 1917, the Yanagi Group and Sanyu Group (both storyteller groups) merged, and the core members, Enzo TACHIBANAYA (the fourth), Enu SANYUTEI, Kosan YANAGIYA (the third) and others, established Tokyo Vaudeville Co. Ltd, and Ryutei SARAKU (the fifth) also established the Sanyu-yanagi Friendship Association (commonly called &apos;Mutsumi-kai&apos; in Japanese).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="136">
<j>その後前者は翌年に「東京演芸合資会社」と名前を変える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the next year, the former company was renamed into Tokyo Entertainment Limited Partnership (TELP).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the following year the former company was renamed into Tokyo Entertainment Limited Partnership (TELP).</e>
<cmt>Wording, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the following year the former company was renamed into Tokyo Entertainment Limited Partnership (TELP).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="137">
<j>1923年に「睦会」と「会社」が合併し「東京落語協会」（落語協会の前身）を設立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In A.D. 1923, Mutsumi-kai and TELP were combined to form Tokyo Rakugo Association (the predecessor of Rakugo Association).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1923 the Mutsumi-kai and TELP merged to form Tokyo Rakugo Association (the predecessor of the Rakugo Association).</e>
<cmt>Style, wording, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1923 the Mutsumi-kai and TELP merged to form Tokyo Rakugo Association (the predecessor of the Rakugo Association).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="138">
<j>大学のサークルとしての落語研究会 (サークル活動)（通称「落研（おちけん）」）が生まれたのは昭和20年代頃で、東京大学や早稲田大学のものが始まりだと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around Showa 20s (A.D. 1945 - 1954), an association to study rakugo (in an abbreviated Japanese, &quot;ochiken&quot;) was born as a club in an university, and ones in Tokyo University and Waseda University are said to have been the first.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the 1940s and 50s rakugo study associations known as ochiken began to appear in several universities as a form of extra-curricular activity, Tokyo University and Waseda University being among the first.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the 1940s and 50s rakugo study associations known as ochiken began to appear in several universities as a form of extra-curricular activity, Tokyo University and Waseda University being among the first.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="139">
<j>現在、学生落語の全国大会として、「全日本学生落語選手権・策伝大賞」が年1回、岐阜市で開催されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today, the All Japan Students Rakugo Championship (for Sakuden Award) - a nation-wide rakugo event of students, and the award is named after Sakuden ANRAKUAN, who is said to have begun rakugo - is held annually in Gifu City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, the All Japan Students Rakugo Championship (Sakuden Award), a nationwide rakugo competition for students, is held annually in Gifu City.</e>
<cmt>Sentence split for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, the All Japan Students Rakugo Championship (Sakuden Award), a nationwide rakugo competition for students, is held annually in Gifu City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="140">
<j>落語の祖といわれる安楽庵策伝は「策伝大賞」名を冠した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The award is named after Sakuden ANRAKUAN, who is said to have begun rakugo.</e>
<cmt>Sentence split for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The award is named after Sakuden ANRAKUAN, who is said to have begun rakugo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>落語家の所属団体</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Group to which comic storytellers belong</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Groups to which Comic Storytellers Belong</e>
<cmt>Punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Groups to which comic storytellers belong</e>
<cmt>文頭のみ大文字にしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="141">
<j>寄席や演芸場（ホールともいう）の興行で演じるプロを落語家と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The professional who performs rakugo in a show at a storytellers&apos; hall or an entertainment hall is called &quot;rakugo-ka&quot; in Japanese.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Professionals who perform rakugo in a show at a storytellers&apos; hall or an entertainment hall are called rakugo-ka in Japanese.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Professionals who perform rakugo in a show at a storytellers&apos; hall or an entertainment hall are called rakugo-ka in Japanese.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="142">
<j>落語家の同業組合（ギルド）に加入していないとプロとは呼ばれない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A storyteller is not called the professional if he or she does not belong to a guild of rakugo-ka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A storyteller is not called a professional if he or she does not belong to a guild of rakugo-ka.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A storyteller is not called a professional if he or she does not belong to a guild of rakugo-ka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="143">
<j>ギルドである以上、内部では徒弟制度が敷かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Being a guild, it has an apprentice system inside.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Being a guild, it has an apprentice system.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Being a guild, it has an apprentice system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>関東の落語家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Associations or schools to which rakugo-ka in Kanto region belong</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Associations or schools to which rakugo-ka in the Kanto region belong</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Associations or schools to which rakugo-ka in the Kanto region belong</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="144">
<j>落語協会（落協）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rakugo Association (in an abbreviated Japanese, &quot;Rakkyo&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rakugo Association (in abbreviated Japanese, Rakkyo)</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rakugo Association (in abbreviated Japanese, Rakkyo)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="145">
<j>落語芸術協会（芸協）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rakugo Art Association (in an abbreviated Japanese, &quot;Geikyo&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rakugo Art Association (in abbreviated Japanese, Geikyo)</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rakugo Art Association (in abbreviated Japanese, Geikyo)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="146">
<j>円楽一門会</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Enraku School of Storytellers</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Enraku School of Storytellers</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Enraku School of Storytellers</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="147">
<j>落語立川流</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tatekawa School of Storytellers</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tatekawa School of Storytellers</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tatekawa School of Storytellers</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>関西の落語家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Association to which rakugo-ka in Kansai region belong</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Associations to which rakugo-ka in the Kansai region belong</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Associations to which rakugo-ka in the Kansai region belong</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="148">
<j>上方落語協会</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kamigata Rakugo Association</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kamigata Rakugo Association</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kamigata Rakugo Association</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="149">
<j>東方落語民話寄席</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eastern Rakugo Association</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eastern Rakugo Association</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eastern Rakugo Association</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>録音・録画の収集</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Collection of the storage media of rakugo sounds and images</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Collections of rakugo sounds and images</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Collections of rakugo sounds and images</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="150">
<j>高座の模様が収録されたコンパクトディスクやカセットテープが販売されており、ラジオ等で放送される音源をカセットテープやミニディスク等の記録メディアに録音・収集することも行われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Compact discs (CDs) and cassettes recording storytellers&apos; stage performances are on the market, and some people have been recording the rakugo aired on the radio and others on the storage media, such as cassettes and minidiscs, and the media are accumulating.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Compact discs and cassettes of recorded rakugo stage performances are on the market, and some people have recorded rakugo aired on the radio on media such as cassettes and minidiscs.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity, wording, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Compact discs and cassettes of recorded rakugo stage performances are on the market, and some people have recorded rakugo aired on the radio on media such as cassettes and minidiscs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="151">
<j>現在では入手不能な、戦前の落語家たちの名演が聞けるSP盤を集める者もいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And others have been collecting standard-playing records (SP records) of excellent storytelling performed by rakugo-ka before World War Ⅱ, which are unavailable today.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Others have collected standard-playing records (SP records) of famous storytelling performances by rakugo-ka before World War Two, which are unavailable today.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation, wording.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Others have collected standard-playing records (SP records) of famous storytelling performances by rakugo-ka before World War II, which are unavailable today.</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="152">
<j>特に著名な収集家として、レコード(SP)蒐集では 八代目都家歌六と岡田則夫が挙げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among others, the eighth Utaroku MIYAKOYA and Norio OKADA are well-known collectors of SP records.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The eighth Utaroku MIYAKOYA and Norio OKADA are well-known collectors of SP records.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The eighth Utaroku MIYAKOYA and Norio OKADA are well-known collectors of SP records.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="153">
<j>「SPレコード 復刻CD集 昭和戦前面白落語」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;A collection of CDs reproduced from SP records : Excellent Rakugo Performed by Rakugo-ka in the Showa Period before World War Ⅱ&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;A collection of CDs reproduced from SP records : Excellent Rakugo Performed by Rakugo-ka in the Showa Period before World War Two&quot;</e>
<cmt>Style.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;A collection of CDs reproduced from SP records: Excellent Rakugo Performed by Rakugo-ka in the Showa Period before World War II&quot;</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="154">
<j>八代目都家歌六の著書『落語レコード八十年史』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;The 80 Years&apos; Chronicle of the Rakugo SP Records&quot; written by the eighth Utaroku MIYAKOYA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;The 80 Years&apos; Chronicle of the Rakugo SP Records&quot; written by the eighth Utaroku MIYAKOYA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;The 80 Years&apos; Chronicle of the Rakugo SP Records&quot; written by the eighth Utaroku MIYAKOYA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="155">
<j>レコード化されていない音源なら 川戸貞吉が挙げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sadakichi KAWADO accumulated the storage media (other than SP records) recording the rakugo aired on the radio and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sadakichi KAWADO accumulated media (other than SP records) containing recordings of rakugo aired on the radio and other locations.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sadakichi KAWADO accumulated media (other than SP records) containing recordings of rakugo aired on the radio and other locations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="156">
<j>彼は落語テープの収集では日本一。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He accumulated rakugo cassettes more than any other in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He accumulated more rakugo cassettes than any other person in Japan.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He accumulated more rakugo cassettes than any other person in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="157">
<j>放送等に限らず、独自に高座を収録し録音を残し続けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Continuously, he recorded the rakugo aired on the media, and he also went to the storytellers&apos; hall himself to record the stage performances, thereby accumulating the cassettes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He not only recorded performances broadcast on the radio, but also live performances at storytellers&apos; halls.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He not only recorded performances broadcast on the radio, but also live performances at storytellers&apos; halls.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="158">
<j>CDボックスセット 川戸貞吉（撰）『古典落語の巨匠たち・寄席の噺・ホールの噺』第一期・第二期（ゲオ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Great Masters of Classical Rakugo/Storytellig at Storytellers&apos; Halls/Storytelling at Entertainment Halls&quot; (the first term/the second term) : A set of CDs selected by Sadakichi KAWADO (produced by Geo Corporation)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Great Masters of Classical Rakugo/Storytelling at Storytellers&apos; Halls/Storytelling at Entertainment Halls&quot; (the first term/the second term) : A set of CDs selected by Sadakichi KAWADO (produced by Geo Corporation)</e>
<cmt>Spelling.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Great Masters of Classical Rakugo/Storytelling at Storytellers&apos; Halls/Storytelling at Entertainment Halls&quot; (the first term/the second term): A set of CDs selected by Sadakichi KAWADO (produced by Geo Corporation)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="159">
<j>その他、玉置宏は「ラジオ名人寄席」にて収集家であることが放送された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And Hiroshi TAMAOKI acknowledged in &quot;Hall of Masters on Radio&quot; that he was also a collector of the rakugo storage media.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hiroshi TAMAOKI acknowledged in &quot;Hall of Masters on the Radio&quot; that he was also a collector of the rakugo storage media.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hiroshi TAMAOKI acknowledged in &apos;Hall of Masters on the Radio&apos; that he was also a collector of the rakugo storage media.</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="160">
<j>草柳俊一は「日本一落語音源に詳しいレコーディング・エンジニア」で、数多くの落語録音にレコーディング・エンジニアとして参加。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shunichi KUSAYANAGI is a recording engineer who knows better about the sound source of rakugo than any other Japanese, and he participated many times in recording of rakugo as a recording engineer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shunichi KUSAYANAGI is a recording engineer who knows more about the sound source of rakugo than any other person in Japan, and he participated many times in the recording of rakugo as a recording engineer.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, wording. I am not sure what the phrase &apos;sound source&apos; refers to.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shunichi KUSAYANAGI is a recording engineer who knows more about the sound source of rakugo than any other person in Japan, and he participated many times in the recording of rakugo as a recording engineer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="161">
<j>「極楽亭プロジェクト」の発起人でもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is also one of the originators of &quot;Gokuraku-tei Project.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is also one of the originators of the Gokuraku-tei Project.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is also one of the originators of the Gokuraku-tei Project.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="162">
<j>極楽亭プロジェクトとは、過去に放送された落語演芸の音源等を収集、鑑定、保存し、将来的には「寄席演芸の『音の博物館』」を目指しているとされているプロジェクトである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Gokuraku-tei Project&quot; refers to the project that collects, appraises, and conserves the storage media recording the rakugo performances (aired in the past on the radio and others), and this project aims to establish &quot;Sound Museum&quot; in the vaudeville world in the future.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Gokuraku-tei Project is a project that collects, appraises, and conserves media recordings of rakugo performances (aired in the past on the radio and other formats), and this project aims to establish a &quot;Sound Museum&quot; in the vaudeville world in the future.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, wording.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Gokuraku-tei Project is a project that collects, appraises, and conserves media recordings of rakugo performances (aired in the past on the radio and other formats), and this project aims to establish a &quot;Sound Museum&quot; in the vaudeville world in the future.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="163">
<j>矢野誠一・草柳俊一（著）『落語CDDVD名盤案内』ISBN 978-4479300168</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;An Introduction of CDs and DVDs Recording Excellent Rakugo&quot; : cowritten by Seiichi YANO and Shunici KUSAYANAGI (ISBN - 978-4479300168)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;An Introduction of CDs and DVDs Recording Excellent Rakugo&quot; : cowritten by Seiichi YANO and Shunici KUSAYANAGI (ISBN - 978-4479300168)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;An Introduction of CDs and DVDs Recording Excellent Rakugo&quot;: cowritten by Seiichi YANO and Shunichi KUSAYANAGI (ISBN - 978-4479300168)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除しました。スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="164">
<j>落語に関するありとあらゆる資料（書籍・古書・音源・刷物・グッズ・自筆物など）の個人収集家としては次の3氏が挙げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides, there are three collectors who collect every kind of material related to rakugo (books old and new, storage media recording the sound source, prints, goods, things of storytellers&apos; own handwriting, and so on).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides this, there are three collectors who collect every kind of material related to rakugo (books old and new, media containing sound recordings, prints, related merchandise, items signed by storytellers, and so on).</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides this, there are three collectors who collect every kind of material related to rakugo (books old and new, media containing sound recordings, prints, related merchandise, items signed by storytellers, and so on).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="165">
<j>桂文我 (4代目)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bunga KATSURA (the fourth)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bunga KATSURA (the Fourth)</e>
<cmt>Punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bunga KATSURA (the Fourth)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="166">
<j>岡田則夫（前出）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Norio OKADA (mentioned above)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Norio OKADA (mentioned above)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Norio OKADA (mentioned above)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="167">
<j>前田憲司</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kenji MAEDA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenji MAEDA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenji MAEDA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="168">
<j>その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="169">
<j>明治時代から興行収入の歩合（割 (寄席)）だけでは生活が成り立たなくなってきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the Meiji period, some comic storytellers have had a hard time in earning their living merely by receiving their percentage of the box-office revenues.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the Meiji Period some comic storytellers have had a hard time in earning a living only through receiving a percentage of box-office revenues.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the Meiji period some comic storytellers have had a hard time in earning a living only through receiving a percentage of box-office revenues.</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="170">
<j>スポンサー（旦那、お旦）からのお小遣いや、妻の賃労働収入をあてにしたり、落語家自身がお座敷（酒席）での余興から収入を得たりした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And so, they got pocket mony from their sponsors (called &quot;danna&quot; or &quot;odan&quot; in Japanese), relied on the income from wage labor of their wife, and earned money for themselves by putting on an entertaiment in a Japanese-style banquet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some received a stipend from sponsors called danna or odan, relied on their wives&apos; income, or earned money for themselves by putting on entertaiment at Japanese-style banquets.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some received a stipend from sponsors called danna or odan, relied on their wives&apos; income, or earned money for themselves by putting on entertainment at Japanese-style banquets.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="171">
<j>副業・内職・アルバイトの、収入源・額は様々である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">What kind of a side job (an extra job, or a part-time job) is chosen - and how much money is earned - differ from person to person.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The kind of side job and how much was charged deiffered from person to person.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The kind of side job and how much was charged differed from person to person.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Nnh(id:474), 0null0(id:582), Nobuyuki(id:274206), Parchment(id:218757), Hide-sp(id:145562), Tribot(id:186681), Gombe(id:27), Opponent(id:720), ぎゅうひ(id:9206), Janus01(id:69663), Thats-you(id:40059), A-Taul(id:41790), Koegeki(id:46093), TY(id:1386), Point136(id:211299), Bit(id:2197), Ｋｓ(id:15319), FlaBot(id:30804), КОЛЯ(id:59429), Balmung0731(id:99201), PixelBot(id:166734), ＫｏＺ(id:48584), よもすがら(id:212112), Martin(id:6394), Maruno(id:255642), 白拍子花子(id:244805), Petty(id:43013), SuisuiBot(id:10165), Bakase(id:13909), Riden(id:27573), Tmatsu(id:10583), AJC(id:71368), HASIDATE(id:181052), Ziman-JAPAN(id:40303), B612(id:96270), Charlesy(id:137799), Koba-chan(id:860), Dabbler(id:65389), Paseri0924(id:151116), PALNAS, MOSCOW-TASTE(id:140939), ShikiH(id:181574), Soukei(id:41418), Uraios(id:72687), 馬場徳助(id:24090), さららゆら(id:12274), 嫦娥(id:81469), 河端(id:194294), MCHC(id:208548), Y-yuji(id:24048), Goki(id:7107), Kadzuwo(id:3701), Rei-bot(id:94097), Metronome(id:81545), Loveless(id:129239), Noai(id:50359), ちろのけたぼ(id:72760), Samai(id:117), Love(id:266), Dora(id:1122), Mc70334s(id:92157), Bankokuya(id:91191), Camelia(id:112815), Izayohi(id:13095), Kentin(id:6768), Chapati(id:2361), MH(id:1586), Lucas0123(id:130266), Mooko(id:36162), VolkovBot(id:105371), Hitotsukami(id:213558), Ajcxx(id:103602), Rakugo(id:49741), 本屋(id:125948), Corwin(id:973), Icchuu(id:224881), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>