<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>絵巻物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emakimono (illustrated scrolls)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emakimono (illustrated scrolls)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emakimono</e>
<cmt>補足をのぞきました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>絵巻物（えまきもの）は、日本の絵画形式の1つで、横長の紙（または絹）を水平方向につないで長大な画面を作り、情景や物語などを連続して表現したもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emakimono (an illustrated scroll) is a kind of Japanese style paintings composed of series of illustrated scenes or stories on a horizontally long screen made up of multiple sheets of rectangular paper (or silk cloth) connected side by side..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emakimono (an illustrated scroll) is a kind of Japanese style painting composed of series of illustrated scenes or stories on a horizontally long screen made up of multiple sheets of rectangular paper (or silk cloth) connected side by side..</e>
<cmt>word spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emakimono (an illustrated scroll) is a kind of Japanese style painting composed of series of illustrated scenes or stories on a horizontally long screen made up of multiple sheets of rectangular paper (or silk cloth) connected side by side.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペースやピリオドをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>「絵巻」とも言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called &quot;emaki.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called &quot;emaki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called as &apos;emaki.&apos;</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>絵画とそれを説明する詞書が交互に現われるものが多いが、絵画のみのものもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many emakimono have numbers of pictures and captions (narrative texts), alternately arranged for each text to explain what its relevant picture depicts, but there are aslo some emakimono with pictures only.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many emakimono have numbers of pictures and captions (narrative texts), alternately arranged for each text to explain what its relevant picture depicts, but there are aslo some emakimono with pictures only.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many emakimono have numbers of pictures and captions (narrative texts), alternately arranged for each text to explain what its relevant picture depicts, but there are also some emakimono with pictures only.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>中国の画巻が起源であるが、日本で独自の発達をとげた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emakimono is originated in Chinese gakan (illustrated handscrolls,) but has developed independently in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emakimono iwas originated in Chinese gakan (illustrated handscrolls,) but later developed independently in Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emakimono was originated in Chinese gakan (illustrated handscrolls), but later developed independently in Japan.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>最初の絵巻物は、奈良時代に制作された『絵因果経』であると言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first emakimono painted in Japan is reportedly the &quot;E Ingakyo (literally, an illustrated sutra of the past and present causes and effects)&quot; produced in Nara period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first emakimono painted in Japan is reportedly the &quot;E Ingakyo (literally, an illustrated sutra of the past and present causes and effects)&quot; produced in the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first emakimono painted in Japan is reportedly the &quot;E Ingakyo&quot; (literally, an illustrated sutra of the past and present causes and effects) produced in the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>これは巻物の下段に経文、上段にそれを絵解きする絵画を配したものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On this emakimono, sutras are described at lower stand while pictures to explain the sutras are laid out at upper stand above related texts of sutras.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On this emakimono, sutras are described on the lower stand while pictures used to explain the sutras are laid out at upper stand above related texts.</e>
<cmt>wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On this emakimono, sutras are described on the lower stand while pictures used to explain the sutras are laid out at upper stand above related texts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>平安時代になると、王朝文学の物語、説話などを題材とした絵巻が制作されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Heian era, there emerged some emaki which were produced on the subjects of dynastic style literarture and preaching type stories.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Heian era, there emerged some emaki which were produced as subjects of dynastic styled literarture, preaching type stories.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Heian period, there emerged some emaki which were produced as subjects of dynastic styled literature, preaching type stories.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>これらは、金銀箔や野毛、砂子を撒き、花鳥などの下絵をあしらった料紙に連綿体で書かれた詞書と、それに対する絵を交互に配する独特の様式を生み出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These emaki created their own style of alternate arrangement of pictures and uninterrupted texts of relevant captions, on paper materials where flowers and birds are designed and grains, foils or slices of gold or silver foils are dispersed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These emaki created their own style, alternating the arrangement of pictures and uninterrupted texts of relevant captions, on paper materials where flowers and birds were designed and grain, foils or slices of gold or silver foils were dispersed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These emaki created their own style, alternating the arrangement of pictures and uninterrupted texts of relevant captions, on paper materials where flowers and birds were designed and foils, thin and long strip, and fine powder of gold and silver were used for decoration.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>物語絵巻は、『枕草子』『伊勢物語』『源氏物語』『宇治拾遺物語』などを、独特の表現で描写し、特に『源氏物語絵巻』は、濃厚な色彩で貴族の生活を描き、家屋は屋根を省略した吹抜屋台で描かれていて、当時の住居の状況や建具の使用状況などが一望できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These monogatari-emaki (illustrated scrolls of tales) could depict in their own way of expression such stories as of &quot;Makurano Soshi (the Pillow Book,)&quot; &quot;Ise Monogatari (the Tales of Ise,)&quot;&quot;Genji Monogatari (the Tale of Genji,)&quot;&quot;Uji Shui Monogatari (a collection of the Tales from Uji)&quot; and others, and especially &quot;Genji Monogatari Emaki (illustrated scrolls of the Tale of Genji)&quot; was drawn in rich colors to show the lives of noble class people, by using a special compositional technique called &quot;fukinuki-yatai&quot; which is useful to depict a residential interior without a roof and ceiling so that viewers can see overall conditions of the residence and furnitures of that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These monogatari-emaki (illustrated scrolls of tales) could depict in their own way of expression such stories as of &quot;Makurano Soshi (the Pillow Book,)&quot; &quot;Ise Monogatari (the Tales of Ise,)&quot;&quot;Genji Monogatari (the Tale of Genji,)&quot;&quot;Uji Shui Monogatari (a collection of the Tales from Uji)&quot; and others, and especially &quot;Genji Monogatari Emaki (illustrated scrolls of the Tale of Genji)&quot; was drawn in rich colors to show the lives of noble class people, by using a special compositional technique called &quot;fukinuki-yatai&quot; which is useful to depict a residential interior without a roof and ceiling so that viewers can see overall conditions of the residence and furnitures of that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These monogatari-emaki (illustrated scrolls of tales) could depict in their own way of expression such stories as of &quot;Makura no Soshi&quot; (the Pillow Book), &quot;Ise Monogatari&quot; (the Tales of Ise), &quot;Genji Monogatari&quot; (the Tale of Genji), &quot;Uji Shui Monogatari&quot; (a collection of the Tales from Uji) and others, and especially &quot;Genji Monogatari Emaki&quot; (illustrated scrolls of the Tale of Genji) was drawn in rich colors to show the lives of noble class people, by using a special compositional technique called fukinuki-yatai which is useful to depict a residential interior without a roof and ceiling so that viewers can see overall conditions of the residence and furniture of that time.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションの位置を変えスペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="10">
<j>鎌倉時代には、歌仙絵巻、戦記絵巻、そして寺社縁起や高僧の伝記絵巻などが多く制作された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During Kamakura period, many emaki were produced, including kasen emaki (illustrated scrolls of celebrated poets), senki emaki (illustrated scrolls of war tales), jisha engi (illustrated legends of temples and shrines) and denki emaki (scrolls of illustrated biographies of well-known priests.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During Kamakura period, many emaki were produced, including kasen emaki (illustrated scrolls of celebrated poets), senki emaki (illustrated scrolls of war tales), jisha engi (illustrated legends of temples and shrines) and denki emaki (scrolls of illustrated biographies of well-known priests.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Kamakura period, many emaki were produced, including kasen emaki (illustrated scrolls of celebrated poets), senki emaki (illustrated scrolls of war tales), jisha engi (illustrated legends of temples and shrines) and denki emaki (scrolls of illustrated biographies of well-known priests).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を変えました。Kamakura period→the Kamakura periodに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="11">
<j>『源氏物語絵巻』・『信貴山縁起』・『伴大納言絵巻』・『鳥獣人物戯画』を、日本の四大絵巻物と称される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">What are regarded as the best four picture scrolls in Japan are &quot;Genji Monogatari Emaki (illustrated scrolls of the Tale of Genji,)&quot;&quot;Shigisan Engi (legends of Mr. Shigi,)&quot;&quot;Ban Dainagon Emaki (illustrated scrolls of the story of a courtier Ban Dainagon)&quot; and &quot;Choju Jinbutsu Giga (caricatures of frolicking birds, animals and humans.)&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">What are regarded as the best four picture scrolls in Japan are &quot;Genji Monogatari Emaki (illustrated scrolls of the Tale of Genji,)&quot;&quot;Shigisan Engi (legends of Mr. Shigi,)&quot;&quot;Ban Dainagon Emaki (illustrated scrolls of the story of a courtier Ban Dainagon)&quot; and &quot;Choju Jinbutsu Giga (caricatures of frolicking birds, animals and humans.)&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">What are regarded as the best four picture scrolls in Japan are &quot;Genji Monogatari Emaki,&quot; &quot;Shigisan Engi&quot; (legends of Mr. Shigi), &quot;Ban Dainagon Emaki&quot; (illustrated scrolls of the story of a courtier Ban Dainagon) and &quot;Choju Jinbutsu Giga&quot; (scrolls of frolicking animals and humans).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションの位置をかえ、前出補足をのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>定義</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Definitions</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Definitions</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Definitions</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="12">
<j>紙（まれに絹）を横方向に順次つないで、水平方向に長大な紙面を作り、終端に巻き軸をつけ、収納時には軸を中心にして巻き収めることができるようにした装丁形式を「巻子装」（かんすそう）と言い、このような装丁で作られた書物、経典、絵画作品などを「巻子本」、より一般的には「巻物」という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kansuso (a hand scroll or horizontal scroll)&quot; means a binding style of a horizontally long sized scroll of paper (or silk cloths on rare occations) made up of many rectangular sheets connected side by side in lateral direction, and equipped with a roller on one end of the sheet to wind the whole sheet up on it to store the scroll, and we call various documents, Buddhist sutras, and other paintings, which are made up in this &quot;Kansuso&quot; method of binding, as &quot;kansubon&quot; or more generally &quot;makimono.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kansuso (a hand scroll or horizontal scroll)&quot; means a binding style of a horizontally long sized scroll of paper (or silk cloths on rare occations) made up of many rectangular sheets connected side by side in lateral direction, and equipped with a roller on one end of the sheet to wind the whole sheet up on it to store the scroll, and we call various documents, Buddhist sutras, and other paintings, which are made up in this &quot;Kansuso&quot; method of binding, as &quot;kansubon&quot; or more generally &quot;makimono.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kansuso&apos; (a hand scroll or horizontal scroll) means a binding style of a horizontally long sized scroll of paper (or silk cloths on rare occasions) made up of many rectangular sheets connected side by side in lateral direction, and equipped with a roller on one end of the sheet to wind the whole sheet up on it to store the scroll, and we call various documents, Buddhist sutras, and other paintings, which are made up in this kansuso method of binding, as &apos;kansubon&apos; or more generally &apos;makimono.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションなどを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>巻子本は中国、朝鮮半島、日本などの東アジアにおいて盛んに作られたほか、古代エジプトなどにも例がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kansubon were poplularly made and used in China, Korean Peninsula, Japan and other East Asian countries, as well as even in ancient Egypt where some similar examples were reported.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kansubon were poplularly made and used in China, Korean Peninsula, Japan and other East Asian countries, as well as even in ancient Egypt where some similar examples were reported.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kansubon were popularly made and used in China, Korean Peninsula, Japan and other East Asian countries, as well as even in ancient Egypt where some similar examples were reported.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="14">
<j>「絵巻物」ないし「絵巻」とは、巻子装の絵画作品の意であるが、日本美術史用語における「絵巻物」とは、日本で制作された、主として大和絵様式の作品を指すのが通常であり、さらに範囲を限定して、平安時代から室町時代の作品に限って「絵巻物」と呼ぶ場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Emakimono&quot; or &quot;emaki&quot; means whole pictorial works of kansuso style binding, but, when the term &quot;emakimono&quot; is used in the history of Japanese art, it is usually understood to indicate mainly the works of yamatoe style paintings made in Japan (a typical Japanese traditional style of painting,) or in some cases, the term is more limited to the works produced during Heian period through Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Emakimono&quot; or &quot;emaki&quot; means whole pictorial works of kansuso style binding, but, when the term &quot;emakimono&quot; is used in the history of Japanese art, it is usually understood to indicate mainly the works of yamatoe style paintings made in Japan (a typical Japanese traditional style of painting,) or in some cases, the term is more limited to the works produced during the Heian period through to the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emakimono&apos; or &apos;emaki&apos; means whole pictorial works of kansuso style binding, but, when the term &apos;emakimono&apos; is used in the history of Japanese art, it is usually understood to indicate mainly the works of yamato-e style paintings made in Japan (a typical Japanese traditional style of painting), or in some cases, the term is often limited to the works produced during the Heian period through to the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションなどを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>中国で制作された同様の装丁の絵画作品は「画巻」「図巻」等と呼ぶのが普通であり、日本人の作品であっても、水墨画家雪舟の『山水長巻』のような作品については、「絵巻物」とは呼ばないのが普通である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Similar pictorial scrolls of kansuso style painted in China are not called &quot;emakimono&quot; but &quot;gakan&quot; or &quot;zukan,&quot; and also such ink paintings as &quot;Sansui Chokan (literally, long scroll of landscape scenery)&quot; by Japanese ink painter Sesshu are usually not called &quot;emakimono.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Similar pictorial scrolls of kansuso style painted in China are not called &quot;emakimono&quot; but &quot;gakan&quot; or &quot;zukan,&quot; and also such ink paintings as &quot;Sansui Chokan (literally, long scroll of landscape scenery)&quot; by Japanese ink painter Sesshu are usually not called &quot;emakimono.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Similar pictorial scrolls of kansuso style painted in China are not called &apos;emakimono&apos; but &apos;gakan&apos; or &apos;zukan,&apos; and also ink paintings by Japanese, such as &quot;Sansui Chokan&quot; (literally, long scroll of landscape scenery) by Sesshu, a ink painter, are usually not called &apos;emakimono.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションなどを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="16">
<j>日本では、奈良時代に『絵因果経』と通称される絵解き経典が数本制作されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During Nara era in Japan, there were produced some pieces of illustrated scroll of Buddhist sutra, commonly known as &quot;E-Ingakyo.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Nara era in Japan, some pieces of illustrated scrolls of Buddhist sutra, commonly known as &quot;E-Ingakyo&quot; were produced.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Nara period in Japan, some pieces of illustrated scrolls of Buddhist sutras, commonly known as &quot;E Ingakyo&quot; were produced.</e>
<cmt>periodを使用し、前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>これは、巻物の紙面の下半分には釈迦の前世と成仏について述べた経典の本文を書写し、上半分には経典の内容に対応する絵画を描いたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Each scroll of this &quot;E-Ingakyo&quot; has a space divided into two parts, with lower part having text copies of Buddist sutra description about Siddhartha&apos;s previous life and his enlightenment as Buddha, and upper part having pictures corresponding to the descriptions below them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Each scroll of this &quot;E-Ingakyo&quot; has a space divided into two parts, with the lower part having text copies of Buddist sutra descriptions about Siddhartha&apos;s previous life and his enlightenment as Buddha, and the upper part having pictures corresponding to the descriptions below them.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Each scroll of them has a space divided into two parts, with the lower part having text copies of Buddhist sutra descriptions about Shakyamuni&apos;s previous life and his enlightenment as Buddha, and the upper part having pictures corresponding to the descriptions below them.</e>
<cmt>用語などを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>ここに描かれた絵画は非常に素朴な様式のものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">All pictures on these scrolls were drawn in a very simple style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">All pictures on these scrolls were done in a very simple style.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">All pictures on these scrolls were done in a very simple style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>『絵因果経』を日本の絵巻物のルーツだとする見方のある一方で、平安時代以降の絵巻物とは直接の影響関係はないとする見方もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are two opposing opinions that, on the one hand, &quot;E Ingakyo&quot; is to be regarded as a root of Japanese emakimono (illustrated scrolls,) and, on the other hand, it has nothing to do with emakimono produced after Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are two opposing opinions that, on the one hand, &quot;E Ingakyo&quot; is to be regarded as a root of Japanese emakimono (illustrated scrolls,) and, on the other hand, it has nothing to do with emakimono produced after the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are two opposing opinions that, on the one hand, &quot;E Ingakyo&quot; is to be regarded as a root of Japanese emakimono (illustrated scrolls), and, on the other hand, it has nothing to do with emakimono produced after the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="20">
<j>『源氏物語』の「絵合（えあわせ）」の巻などを参照すると、日本では平安時代前期～中期にも多くの物語絵が制作されたことが推測されるが、9世紀～11世紀までの絵巻物作品の現存するものは皆無であり、この間、絵巻物の画風がどのような発展過程を経たのかは定かでない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to such descriptions as written in a volume captioned &quot;Eawase (picture contest)&quot; in &quot;Genji Monogatari (the Tale of Genji),&quot; many scrolls of illustrated tales may be assumed to have been produced during the beginning and middle Heian period in Japan, but, since none of such scrolls is now existing that were produced between 9th and 11th centuries, it is unable for us to trace clearly how the styles of illustrated scrolls of that period had developed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to such descriptions written in a volume captioned &quot;Eawase (picture contest)&quot; in &quot;Genji Monogatari (the Tale of Genji),&quot; many scrolls of illustrated tales may be assumed to have been produced during the beginning and middle Heian period in Japan, but since none of such scrolls are now existing that were produced between the 9th and 11th centuries, we are unable to trace clearly how the styles of illustrated scrolls, of that period, had developed.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to such descriptions written in a volume captioned &apos;Eawase&apos; (picture contest) in &quot;Genji Monogatari,&apos; many scrolls of illustrated tales may be assumed to have been produced during the beginning and middle Heian period in Japan, but since none of such scrolls are now existing that were produced between the 9th and 11th centuries, we are unable to trace clearly how the styles of illustrated scrolls, of that period, had developed.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>一般に「四大絵巻」と称される『源氏物語絵巻』『伴大納言絵詞』『信貴山縁起』『鳥獣人物戯画』はいずれも平安時代末期、12世紀の作と考証されている（『鳥獣人物戯画』4巻のうち2巻の制作時期は鎌倉時代に降る）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">So called &quot;the best four picture scrolls&quot;are now ascertained by historical evidences to be the works of 12th century, or the later Heian period, which are &quot;Genji Monogatari Emaki (illustrated scrolls of the Tale of Genji,)&quot;&quot;Ban Dainagon Emaki (illustrated scroll of the story of a coutier Ban Dainagon,)&quot; &quot;Shigisan Engi (legends of Mt. Shigi)&quot; and &quot;Choju Jinbutsu Giga (carricatures of frolicking birds, animals and humans)&quot;, with exception of two scrolls out of four &quot;Choju Jinbutsu Giga&quot; scrolls that are believed to have been made later in Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The so called &quot;the best four picture scrolls&quot;are now ascertained by historical evidence to be works of the 12th century, or the later Heian period, which are &quot;Genji Monogatari Emaki (illustrated scrolls of the Tale of Genji),&quot;&quot;Ban Dainagon Emaki (illustrated scroll of the story of a coutier Ban Dainagon),&quot; &quot;Shigisan Engi (legends of Mt. Shigi),&quot; and &quot;Choju Jinbutsu Giga (carricatures of frolicking birds, animals and humans),&quot;,with exception of two scrolls out of four &quot;Choju Jinbutsu Giga&quot; scrolls that are believed to have been made later in the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The so called &apos;the best four picture scrolls&apos; are now ascertained by historical evidence to be works of the 12th century, or the later Heian period, which are &quot;Genji Monogatari Emaki,&quot; &quot;Ban Dainagon Ekotoba&quot; (Also known as &quot;Ban Dainagon Emaki&quot;), &quot;Shigisan Engi,&quot; and &quot;Choju Jinbutsu Giga&quot; (the exception of two scrolls out of four &quot;Choju Jinbutsu Giga&quot; scrolls that are believed to have been made later in the Kamakura period).</e>
<cmt>前出補足をのぞきました。(『伴大納言絵詞』は前出『伴大納言絵巻』の別名ですが、原文通りの表記とし、補足しました。）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>これらの作品は、現存する絵巻物の最古の作品群であるとともに、芸術的にももっとも高く評価されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These works are not just the oldest ones of existing illustrated scrolls, but also they are appraised as the most valuable artistic production.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These works are not just the oldest existing illustrated scrolls, but are also appraised as the most valuable works of art.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These works are not just the oldest existing illustrated scrolls, but are also appraised as the most valuable works of art.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>平安時代末期～鎌倉時代が絵巻物の全盛期で、室町時代には作品数は多いものの、前記「四大絵巻」に匹敵するような作品は生まれなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Glory days of illustrated scrolls were from late Heian to Kamakura period, while in Muromachi period there were also lots of illustrated scrolls produced but no one could be compared to the aforesaid &quot;best four picture scrolls.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The glory days of illustrated scrolls were from the late Heian to Kamakura period, while in the Muromachi period there were also lots of illustrated scrolls produced but none could be compared to the aforesaid &quot;best four picture scrolls.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The glory days of illustrated scrolls were from the late Heian period to the Kamakura period, while in the Muromachi period there were also lots of illustrated scrolls produced but none could be compared to the aforesaid &apos;best four picture scrolls.&apos;</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>近世にも巻物形式の絵画は多く制作され、俵屋宗達、狩野探幽、岩佐又兵衛なども巻物形式の作品を残しているが、これらは「絵巻物」の範疇に含めない場合も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also in the modern age, a lot of pictures were painted in the style of emakimono (illustrated scrolls) by such painters as Sotatsu TAWARAYA, Tanyu KANO and Matabei IWASA, but these pictures are now often excluded from the category of &quot;emakimono.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also in the modern age, a lot of pictures were painted in the style of emakimono (illustrated scrolls) by such artists as Sotatsu TAWARAYA, Tanyu KANO and Matabei IWASA, but these pictures are now often excluded from the category of &quot;emakimono.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also in the modern age, a lot of pictures were painted in the style of emakimono by such artists as Sotatsu TAWARAYA, Tanyu KANO and Matabei IWASA, but these pictures are now often excluded from the category of &apos;emakimono.&apos;</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションにし前出補足をのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>名称</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Appellatives</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Appellatives</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Appellatives</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="25">
<j>「絵巻」という語には、『源氏物語絵巻』『紫式部日記絵巻』のように、作品名に「○○絵巻」と付けて巻子装の作品であることを表す用法と、巻子形式の絵画を総称した概念として「絵巻」ないし「絵巻物」と呼ぶ場合とがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The word &quot;emaki&quot; is used in two ways; one is to attach the word at the end of the name of its corresponding mother work, like &quot;Genji Monogatari Emaki (illustrated scroll of the Tale of Genji)&quot; and &quot;Murasakishikibu Nikki Emaki (illustrated scroll of the Lady Murasaki&apos;s Diary)&quot;, and another way is to regard the term of &quot;emaki&quot; or &quot;emakimono&quot; as a concept to collectively refer to the pictures painted in Kansu (a handscroll or horizontal scroll) style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The word &quot;emaki&quot; is used in two ways; one is to attach the word at the end of the name of its corresponding mother work, like &quot;Genji Monogatari Emaki (illustrated scroll of the Tale of Genji)&quot; and &quot;Murasakishikibu Nikki Emaki (illustrated scroll of the Lady Murasaki&apos;s Diary)&quot;, and another way is to regard the term of &quot;emaki&quot; or &quot;emakimono&quot; as a concept to collectively refer to the pictures painted in Kansu (a handscroll or horizontal scroll) style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The word &apos;emaki&apos; is used in two ways; one is to attach the word at the end of the name of its corresponding mother work, like &quot;Genji Monogatari Emaki&quot; and &quot;Murasaki Shikibu Nikki Emaki&quot; (illustrated scroll of the Lady Murasaki&apos;s Diary), and another way is to regard the term of &apos;emaki&apos; or &apos;emakimono&apos; as a concept to collectively refer to the pictures painted in kansu (a handscroll or horizontal scroll) style.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>ただし、これらの「絵巻」「絵巻物」の語は、近世になって使われだしたもので、中世以前の記録では単に「○○絵」と呼ばれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the words of &quot;emaki&quot; and &quot;emakimono&quot; became used only after the modern age, and according to records written before the medieval age, they were simply expressed with the ending of &quot;-e (literally, -&apos;s picture.)&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the words of &quot;emaki&quot; and &quot;emakimono&quot; came to be used only after the modern age, and according to records written before the medieval period, they were simply expressed with the ending of &quot;-e (literally, -&apos;s picture).&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the words of &apos;emaki&apos; and &apos;emakimono&apos; came to be used only after the modern age, and according to records written before the medieval period, they were simply expressed with the ending of &apos;XX-e&apos; (literally, XX&apos;s picture).</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="27">
<j>絵巻物の作品名称としては、「○○絵詞（えことば）」「○○草紙」「○○絵伝」等と称するものも多い（例としては『平治物語絵詞』『地獄草紙』『法然上人絵伝』など）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Illustrated scrolls are often titled with endings of &quot;-ekotoba,&quot; &quot;-soshi,&quot; &quot;-eden&quot; and others, like &quot;Heiji Monogatari Ekotoba (illustrated stories of Heiji Rebellion),&quot; &quot;Jigoku-zoshi (handscrolls depicting Buddhist hell,)&quot; &quot;Honen Shonin Eden (illustrated tales of Honen, a Buddhist saint)&quot; and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Illustrated scrolls are often titled with endings of &quot;-ekotoba,&quot; &quot;-soshi,&quot; &quot;-eden&quot; and others, like &quot;Heiji Monogatari Ekotoba (illustrated stories of Heiji Rebellion),&quot; &quot;Jigoku-zoshi (handscrolls depicting Buddhist hell,)&quot; &quot;Honen Shonin Eden (illustrated tales of Honen, a Buddhist saint)&quot; and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Illustrated scrolls are often titled with endings of &apos;-ekotoba,&apos; &apos;-soshi,&apos; &apos;-eden&apos; and others, like &quot;Heiji Monogatari Ekotoba&quot; (illustrated stories of Heiji Rebellion), &quot;Jigoku Zoshi&quot; (handscrolls depicting Buddhist hell), &quot;Honen Shonin Eden&quot; (illustrated tales of Honen, a Buddhist saint) and so on.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>このうち、「絵詞」とは、「絵の詞」、つまり、ある特定の絵に対応する文章というのが本来の意味であることが指摘されており、「絵詞」よりは「絵巻」の方が作品名として適切であるとの説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among them, the word &quot;ekotoba&quot; is pointed out to have originally meant as &quot;words for pictures,&quot; viz. sentences corresponding to particular pictures, so that some may claim that &quot;-emaki&quot; is more suitablly titled than &quot;-ekotoba.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among them, the word &quot;ekotoba&quot; is pointed out to have originally meant as &quot;words for pictures,&quot; viz. sentences corresponding to particular pictures, so that some may claim that &quot;-emaki&quot; is more suitablly titled than &quot;-ekotoba.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among them, the word &apos;ekotoba&apos; is pointed out to have originally meant as &apos;words for pictures,&apos; namely, sentences corresponding to particular pictures, so that some may claim that &apos;-emaki&apos; is more suitably titled than &apos;-ekotoba.&apos;</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>たとえば、『伴大納言絵巻』は、1951年に国宝に指定された際の名称は『伴大納言絵詞』であったが、現所有者の出光美術館では『伴大納言絵巻』と呼んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, &quot;Ban Dainagon Emaki&quot; was originally named as &quot;Ban Dainagon Ekotoba&quot; in 1951 when it was designated as a national treasure, but now is called &quot;Ban Dainagon Emaki&quot; at Idemitsu Museum of Arts, the current owner of the subject.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, &quot;Ban Dainagon Emaki&quot; was originally named as &quot;Ban Dainagon Ekotoba&quot; in 1951 when it was designated as a national treasure, but now is called &quot;Ban Dainagon Emaki&quot; at Idemitsu Museum of Arts, the current owner of the subject.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, &quot;Ban Dainagon Emaki&quot; was originally named as &quot;Ban Dainagon Ekotoba&quot; in 1951 when it was designated as a national treasure, but now is called &quot;Ban Dainagon Emaki&quot; at Idemitsu Museum of Arts, the current owner of the subject.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>形態</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Patterns</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Patterns</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Patterns</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="30">
<j>絵巻物は、前述のように紙（まれに絹）を横方向につないだ、長大な紙面に描かれたものである（紙でなく絹に描かれた作品としては『一遍上人絵伝』『春日権現験記絵巻』などがある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As already explained, emakimono is a painting drawn on a long paper sheet (or, rarely, a sheet of silk cloths) composed of a number of rectangular sheets connected side by side to horizontal direction, while those painted on silk cloths include &quot;Ippen Shonin Eden (illustrated tales of a Buddhist saint, Ippen) and &quot;Kasuga Gongen Kenki Emaki (illustrated scrolls of miracles of the Kasuga Deity.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As already explained, emakimono is a painting drawn on a long sheet of paper (or, rarely, a sheet of silk cloth) composed of a number of rectangular sheets connected side by side in the horizontal direction, while those painted on silk include &quot;Ippen Shonin Eden&quot; (illustrated tales of a Buddhist saint, Ippen) and &quot;Kasuga Gongen Kenki Emaki&quot; (illustrated scrolls of miracles of the Kasuga Deity.</e>
<cmt>punctuation, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As already explained, emakimono is a painting drawn on a long sheet of paper (or, rarely, a sheet of silk cloth) composed of a number of rectangular sheets connected side by side in the horizontal direction, while those painted on silk include &quot;Ippen Shonin Eden&quot; (illustrated tales of a Buddhist saint, Ippen) and &quot;Kasuga Gongen Kenki Emaki&quot; (illustrated scrolls of miracles of the Kasuga god).</e>
<cmt>カッコを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>1巻の中に「絵」と「詞」とが交互に現れる形式がもっとも多く、通常は「詞」が先に来て、その直後に、その「詞」に対応する｢絵｣が来る（まれに例外もある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The most popular pattern of emakimono is an alternate appearance of &quot;e (picture)&quot; and &quot;kotoba (text or description,)&quot; where preceding text is immediately followed by a corresponding picture in ordinary cases (but with rare exceptional cases.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The most popular pattern of emakimono is an alternate appearance of &quot;e (picture)&quot; and &quot;kotoba: (text or description,) where the preceding text is immediately followed by a corresponding picture in ordinary cases (but with rare exceptional cases.)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The most popular pattern of emakimono is an alternate appearance of &apos;e&apos; (picture) and &apos;kotoba&apos; (text or description), where the preceding &apos;kotoba&apos; is immediately followed by a corresponding &apos;e&apos; in ordinary cases (but with rare exceptional cases).</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>ひと続きの絵、ひと続きの詞を数える単位を「段」といい、絵巻物の説明にたとえば「絵4段、詞4段」とあれば、その絵巻物は絵と詞とが交互に4回ずつ現れるものであることがわかる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A series of pictures or texts in an emakimono is counted as one &quot;dan (section,)&quot;and, if an emakimono is said to have &quot;e 4-dan, kotoba 4-dan (four sections of picture and four sections of text),&quot; it means a picture and text will appear alternately four times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A series of pictures or texts in an emakimono is counted as one &quot;dan (section,)&quot;and, if an emakimono is said to have &quot;e 4-dan, kotoba 4-dan (four sections of picture and four sections of text),&quot; it means the picture and text will appear alternately four times.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A series of pictures or texts in an emakimono is counted as one &apos;dan&apos; (section), and, if an emakimono is said to have &apos;e 4-dan, kotoba 4-dan&apos; (four sections of picture and four sections of text), it means the picture and text will appear alternately four times.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>なお、『鳥獣人物戯画』のように絵のみで詞のない絵巻もあり、『華厳宗祖師絵伝』のように、「詞」とは別に、画中人物のかたわらに「せりふ」を書き込んだものもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time, there were some emakimono created with different patterns than the above, such as &quot;Choju Jinbutsu Giga (caricatures of frolicking birds, animals and humans)&quot; which had no part of text but pictures only, and &quot;Kegonshu Soshi Eden (pictorial biographies of the founders of the Kegon sect)&quot; which contained &quot;spoken lines&quot; beside some characters in a scene in addition to ordinary texts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the same time, there were some emakimono created with different patterns than the above, such as &quot;Choju Jinbutsu Giga&quot; (caricatures of frolicking birds, animals and humans) which had no text, but pictures only, and &quot;Kegonshu Soshi Eden&quot; (pictorial biographies of the founders of the Kegon sect) that contained &quot;spoken lines&quot; beside some characters in a scene in addition to ordinary texts.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the same time, there were some emakimono created with different patterns than the above, such as &quot;Choju Jinbutsu Giga&quot; which had no text, but pictures only, and &quot;Kegonshu Soshi Eden&quot; (pictorial biographies of the founders of the Kegon sect) that contained &apos;spoken lines&apos; beside some characters in a scene in addition to &apos;kotoba.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションなどを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="34">
<j>画面のサイズは天地が30cm前後のものがもっとも多いが、『北野天神縁起』（承久本）のように、天地が50cmを超える大作もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most emakimono have pictures of more or less 30cm high in full vertical length, but some have even larger pictures with vertical length of 50cm or more like the Jokyu version of &quot;Kitano Tenjin Engi Emaki (an illustrated history of Kitano shrine.)&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most emakimono have pictures of more or less 30cm high in full vertical length, but some have even larger pictures with a vertical length of 50cm or more like the Jokyu version of &quot;Kitano Tenjin Engi Emaki&quot; (an illustrated history of Kitano shrine).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most emakimono have pictures of more or less 30cm high in full vertical length, but some have even larger pictures with a vertical length of 50cm or more like the Jokyu version of &quot;Kitano Tenjin Engi Emaki&quot; (an illustrated history of Kitano shrine).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>また、室町時代のお伽草紙のように、天地15cmほどの小品もあり、これらは小絵（こえ）と呼ばれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are also some emakimono with smaller pictures of about 15cm high like otogi-zoshi (illustrated short prose narratives of Japan) which are called koe (small pictures.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are also some emakimono with smaller pictures of about 15cm high like otogi-zoshi (illustrated short prose narratives of Japan) which are called koe (small pictures.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are also some emakimono with smaller pictures of about 15cm high like otogi-zoshi (illustrated short prose narratives of Japan) which are called koe (small pictures).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>左右の長さ、すなわち巻物全体の長さについてはまちまちで、全長10メートル前後のものが多いが、『粉河寺縁起絵巻』のように1巻で20メートル近い長さのものもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Overall length, from left to right ends, of emakimono varies very much, with majority length in the vicinity of 10m, but also with such length as 20m per one scroll like &quot;Kokawadera Engiemaki (a picture scroll of the legends of Kokawadera Temple.)&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Overall length, from left to right ends, of emakimono varies very much, with majority length in the vicinity of 10m, but also with such length as 20m per one scroll like &quot;Kokawadera Engiemaki&quot; (a picture scroll of the legends of Kokawadera Temple).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Overall length, from left to right ends, of emakimono varies very much, with majority length in the vicinity of 10m, but also with such length as 20m per one scroll like &quot;Kokawadera Engi Emaki&quot; (a picture scroll of the legends of Kokawa-dera Temple).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="37">
<j>巻数については、1巻のみで完結している作品と、数巻からなる作品とがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Each emakimono is completed either in one scroll or in multiple scrolls.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Each emakimono is completed either in one scroll or in multiple scrolls.</e>
<cmt>word spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Each emakimono is completed either in one scroll or in multiple scrolls.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>1つの作品でもっとも巻数が多いのは京都・知恩院と奈良・当麻寺奥院の『法然上人絵伝』で、いずれも全48巻の大作である（「48」という数字は阿弥陀如来の「四十八願」にちなんだもの）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Honen Shonin Eden (an illustrated biography of Buddhist saint, Honen)&quot; of both Chion-in Temple in Kyoto and Oku-in of Taima-dera Temples in Nara (deepest located temple house of Taimadera Temples in Nara) have the largest number of scrolls of an emakimono work, namely fourty-eight, which number is compared to &quot;fourty-eight vows&quot; of Amida Nyorai (celestial Amitabha Buddha.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Honen Shonin Eden&quot; (an illustrated biography of Buddhist saint, Honen) of both Chion-in Temple in Kyoto and Oku-in of Taima-dera Temples in Nara (deepest located temple house of Taimadera Temples in Nara) have the largest number of scrolls of an emakimono work, namely fourty-eight, which number is compared to &quot;fourty-eight vows&quot; of Amida Nyorai (celestial Amitabha Buddha.)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Honen Shonin Eden&quot; of both Chionin Temple in Kyoto and Okuin of Taima-dera Temples in Nara (deepest located temple house of Taima-dera Temple) have the largest number of scrolls of an emakimono work, namely &apos;forty-eight,&apos; which number is compared to &apos;forty-eight vows&apos; of Amida Nyorai (Amitabha Tathagata).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションなどを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="39">
<j>なお、「○○絵巻」と呼ばれていても、額装や掛軸仕立てになっている作品もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are some works whose names have the ending of &quot;-emaki&quot; but are nevertheless kept in frames or in vertical hanging scrolls.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are some works whose names have the ending of &quot;-emaki&quot; but are nevertheless kept in frames or in vertical hanging scrolls.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are some works whose names have the ending of &apos;-emaki&apos; but are nevertheless kept in frames or in vertical hanging scrolls.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>これには、元来巻物だったものを保存上の観点から1紙ずつはがして額装にしたものと、分割して譲渡・売却するために、長い巻物を画面ごとに切断したものとがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These works were originally complete in the style of emakimono but later split off into pieces of illustrated paper either to be fixed in frames for the preservation purpose or to be transferred or sold out to others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These works were originally completed in the style of emakimono, but later split off into pieces of illustrated paper either to be fixed in frames for the preservation purpose or to be transferred or sold out to others.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These works were originally completed in the style of emakimono, but later split off into pieces of illustrated paper either to be fixed in frames for the preservation purpose or to be transferred or sold out to others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>前者の典型的な例は『源氏物語絵巻』（五島美術館、徳川美術館蔵）で、厚塗りの絵具が剥落することを恐れて、絵、詞ともに1段ずつ分割して額仕立てになっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Typical example of the former case is &quot;Genji Monogatari Emaki (illustrated scroll of the Tale of Genji) in the possession of Gotoh Art Museum and Tokugawa Art Museum, where the emaki is partitioned into each dan (section) of both pictures and texts and set in frames.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A typical example of the former case is &quot;Genji Monogatari Emaki&quot; (illustrated scroll of the Tale of Genji) in the possession of Gotoh and Tokugawa Art Museums, where emaki is partitioned into each dan (section) of both pictures and texts and set in frames.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A typical example of the former case is &quot;Genji Monogatari Emaki&quot; in the possession of the Gotoh Art Museum and the Tokugawa Art Museum, where emaki is partitioned into each dan (section) of both pictures and texts and set in frames.</e>
<cmt>前出補足をのぞくなどしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>後者、すなわち、譲渡のために分割された例として著名なものは佐竹本『三十六歌仙絵巻』である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One well-known example of the latter case of emakimono, which were split into pieces to be transferred to others, is the Satake version of &quot;Sanju-roku Kasen Emaki (illustrated scroll of the thirty-six celebrated poets.)&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One well-known example of the latter case of emakimono, split into pieces to be transferred, is the Satake version of &quot;Sanju-roku Kasen Emaki (illustrated scroll of the thirty-six celebrated poets).&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One well-known example of the latter case of emakimono, split into pieces to be transferred, is the Satake version of &quot;Sanju-roku Kasen Emaki&quot; (illustrated scroll of the thirty-six celebrated poets).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>この作品は、元来は上下2巻の巻物に三十六歌仙それぞれの肖像画を描き、略歴と代表歌を書いたものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This work was originally composed of two scrolls of emakimono where each poet&apos;s portrait was painted beside his/her profile and representative poem.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This work was originally composed of two scrolls of emakimono where each poet&apos;s portrait was painted beside his/her profile and representative poem.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This work was originally composed of two scrolls of emakimono where each poet&apos;s portrait was painted beside his or her profile and representative poem.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>これが大正年間に売りに出された時に全巻一括で購入できる者がいなかったため、歌仙1名ごとに切り離して、それぞれ別のコレクターに譲渡されたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was in Taisho era when this emaki was offered for sale, but, since no body was able to purchase it in complete sets, it was divided into pieces of each poet and sold out to different individual buyers (collectors.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was in the Taisho era when this emaki was offered for sale, but since no body was able to purchase it in complete sets, it was divided into pieces of each poet and sold out to different individual buyers (collectors.)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was in the Taisho period when this emaki was offered for sale, but since no body was able to purchase it in complete sets, it was divided into pieces of each poet and sold out to different individual buyers (collectors).</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>構図・画法</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Composition and Brushwork</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Composition and Brushwork</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Composition and Brushwork</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="45">
<j>絵画作品は、壁画、襖絵、掛軸、屏風などのように垂直に立てた状態で鑑賞するものが多いが、絵巻物は、机の上などに水平に置いて見下ろす形で鑑賞する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emakimono are viewed by placing it horizontally on a desk or others, although other art works are mostly set up vertically for appreciation, like mural paintings, paintings on sliding-door panels, hanging scrolls, folding screens consisting of multiple, joined panels and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emakimono are viewed horizontally on a desk or other surfaces, although other art works are mostly set up vertically for appreciation, like mural paintings, paintings on sliding-door panels, hanging scrolls, folding screens consisting of multiple joined panels..</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emakimono are viewed horizontally on a desk, and so on, although other art works are mostly set up vertically for appreciation, like wall paintings, fusumae (paintings on sliding-doors panels), kakejiku (hanging scrolls), byobu (folding screens consisting of multiple and joined panels).</e>
<cmt>表現を合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>この点に加え、天地の幅が狭いという画面形式の制約もあり、絵巻物の画面には斜め上方から見下ろしたような構図のものが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to the above way of viewing, emakimono is generally limited to a narrow vertical length so that many of its pictures are composed as if they are looked down from upper side.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to the above way of viewing, emakimono is generally limited to a narrow vertical length so that many pictures are composed as if they are looked down upon from.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to the above way of viewing, emakimono is generally limited to a narrow vertical length so that many pictures are composed as if they are looked down upon from.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>絵巻物で室内の情景を描いたものの中には、建物内部にいる人物が見えるように、建物の屋根と天井を省略して全く描かないという表現法が使われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In some emakimono depicting inner sight of a house, a special composition technique was used to make viewers able to see figures inside the house by eliminating whole roofs and ceilings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In some emakimono depicting the inside of a house, a special composition technique was used to make viewers able to see figures inside the house by eliminating the complete roofs and ceilings.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In some emakimono depicting the inside of a house, a special composition technique was used to make viewers able to see figures inside the house by eliminating the complete roofs and ceilings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>あたかも、建物の屋根と天井を取り払ってしまったようなこうした描写方法は『源氏物語絵巻』などに典型的に見られ、「吹抜屋台（ふきぬきやたい）」と称する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This method of painting, which gives an image of houses deprived of roofs and ceilings, is called &quot;fukinuki-yatai&quot; and can be typically noted in &quot;Genji Monogatari Emaki (illustrated scroll of the Tale of Genji)&quot; and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This method of painting, which gives an image of houses with roofs and ceilings missing, is called &quot;fukinuki-yatai&quot; and can be typically noted in &quot;Genji Monogatari Emaki (illustrated scroll of the Tale of Genji)&quot; and others.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This method of painting, which gives an image of houses with roofs and ceilings missing, is called &apos;fukinuki-yatai&apos; and can be typically noted in &quot;Genji Monogatari Emaki&quot; and others.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションにし、表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>なお、「吹抜屋台」は絵巻物に限らず、画帖などにも見られる描法である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This fukinuki-yatai method was applied not only to emakimono but also to gajo (an album of paintings.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This fukinuki-yatai method was applied not only to emakimono, but also to gajo (an album of paintings.)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This &apos;fukinuki-yatai&apos; method was applied not only to emakimono, but also to gajo (an album of paintings).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>今一つ絵巻物に特徴的な画法としては「異時同図法」がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another characteristic painting method of emakimono is &quot;Iji Dozu Gaho (a composition method used to show successive events within a united background.)&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another characteristic painting method of emakimono is &quot;Iji Dozu Gaho (a composition method used to show successive events within a united background.)&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another characteristic painting method of emakimono is &apos;Iji Dozu Gaho&apos; (a composition method used to show successive events within a united background).</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>これは、同一画面内に同一人物が複数回登場して、その間の時間的推移が示されているもので、『伴大納言絵巻』の「子どもの喧嘩」の場面と、『信貴山縁起絵巻』の東大寺大仏殿の場面がその代表例として知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This method was used to allow repeated appearances of the same figure in the same scene to show passage of time, as may be seen in such typical screen pages as &quot;Kodomono Kenka (boys&apos; fight)&quot; of &quot;Dainagon Emaki&quot; and Todai-ji Temple Daibutsu-den (hall of the Great Statute of the Buddha) of &quot;Shigisan Engi (legends of Mt. Shigi.)&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This method was used to allow repeated appearances of the same figure in the same scene to show passage of time, as may be seen in such typical screen pages as &quot;Kodomono Kenka&quot; (boys&apos; fight) of &quot;Dainagon Emaki&quot; and Todai-ji Temple Daibutsu-den (hall of the Great Statute of the Buddha) of &quot;Shigisan Engi&quot; (legends of Mt. Shigi).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This method was used to allow repeated appearances of the same figure in the same scene to show passage of time, as may be seen in such typical screen pages as &apos;Kodomo no Kenka&apos; (children&apos;s fight) in &quot;Ban Dainagon Emaki&quot; and Daibutsu-den (hall of the Great Statute of the Buddha) of Todai-ji Temple in &quot;Shigisan Engi Emaki&quot; (Also known as &quot;Shigisan Engi&quot;).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションや表現を変えました。（『信貴山縁起絵巻』は前出では『信貴山縁起』ですが、原文通りとし補足しました）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>後者を例にとると、登場人物の尼公（あまぎみ）が1つの画面に計6回描かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the latter case of the above, a character of Amagimi (the nun) appears six times in one scene.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the latter case of the above, a character of Amagimi (the nun) appears six times in one scene.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the latter case of the above, a character of Amagimi (the nun) appears six times in one scene.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>これは尼公が大仏殿に到着し、礼拝し、夜通し参篭し、明け方出発するという一連の時間的経過を1枚の絵で表現したものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This scene is depicting a sequence of events as time goes on in one picture, namely arrival of Amagimi at Daibutsu-den hall, her pray to the Buddha stature, her overnight stay in the hall in seclusion, and her departure at dawn.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This scene is depicting a sequence of events as time goes on in one picture, namely the arrival of Amagimi at Daibutsu-den hall, her pray to the Buddha stature, her overnight stay in the hall in seclusion, and her departure at dawn.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This scene is depicting a sequence of events as time goes on in one picture, namely the arrival of Amagimi at Daibutsu-den hall, her pray to the Buddha statue, her overnight stay in the hall in seclusion, and her departure at dawn.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="54">
<j>絵巻物が襖絵、掛軸、屏風などの形式と根本的に異なるもう1つの点は、作品全体を一度に視野に入れることができないという点である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another fundamental difference of emakimono from fusumae (paintings on sliding-doors panels,) kakejiku (hanging scrolls,) byobu (folding screens consisting of multiple and joined panels) and other forms of traditional paintings is that emakimono is unable to be overviewed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another fundamental difference of emakimono from fusumae (paintings on sliding-doors panels,) kakejiku (hanging scrolls,) byobu (folding screens consisting of multiple and joined panels) and other forms of traditional paintings is that emakimono is unable to be overviewed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another fundamental difference of emakimono from fusumae, kakejiku, byobu, and other forms of traditional paintings is that emakimono is unable to be overviewed.</e>
<cmt>前出補足をのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>絵巻物は、博物館・美術館等においては、ガラスケースの中に、数メートルにわたって広げた状態で展示されるが、本来の鑑賞方法は、作品を机などの上に置き、左手で新しい場面を繰り広げながら、右手ですでに見終わった画面を巻き込んでいくというものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although emakimono is exhibited at a museum or any other place by showing a few meters of unfolded part of it in a glass case, the standard way of appreciation of emakimono is to put it on a desk and unscroll with left hand its left side to see new screens while with right hand rolling up already viewed scenes at right siide of it..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although emakimono is exhibited at a museum or any other place by showing a few meters of unfolded part of it is in a glass case, the standard way of appreciation of emakimono is to put it on a desk and unscroll with the left hand its left side to see new screens while with right hand is rolling up already viewed scenes on the right siide..</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although emakimono is exhibited at a museum or any other place by showing a few meters of unfolded part of it is in a glass case, the standard way of appreciation of emakimono is to put it on a desk and scroll with the left hand its left side to see new screens while with right hand is rolling up already viewed scenes on the right side.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>このような画面形式では、天地の高さには限界があるが、画面の水平方向の長さには制約がなく、物語の展開などを長大な画面に劇的に表現することが可能であり、そこに時間的な推移を盛り込むこともできる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With this style of emakimono pictures, the vertical length of a picture is limited but its horizontal length is not, which makes it possible to depict a drastic development of any long story on a long space of paper and also to show there the passage of time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With this style of emakimono pictures, the vertical length of a picture is limited but its horizontal length is not, which makes it possible to depict a drastic development of any long story on a long space of paper and also to show there the passage of time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With this style of emakimono pictures, the vertical length of a picture is limited but its horizontal length is not, which makes it possible to depict a drastic development of any long story on a long space of paper and also to show there the passage of time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>たとえば、『伴大納言絵巻』上巻の応天門の火災の場面は、炎上する応天門、火事見物の群衆、火災の報を聞いて現場に駆け付ける政府の役人などが、途中に「詞」を挟まず、数メートルにわたって絵のみで描写されており、絵巻の特性を生かした例として著名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a typical example of this feature of emakimono, the first roll of two scrolls of &quot;Ban Dainagon Emaki&quot; has a scenery of fire at Otenmon (the red-painted front gate) which depicts flaring Otenmon, crowds of viewer, government&apos;s officers trotting down on to the site upon information and so on, in a few meter long series of pictures only without any &quot;text.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a typical example of this feature of emakimono, the first roll of two scrolls of &quot;Ban Dainagon Emaki&quot; has a scenery of fire at Otenmon (the red-painted front gate) which depicts flaring Otenmon, crowds of viewers, government&apos;s officers trotting down on to the site upon receiving information and so on, in a few meters long series of pictures only without any &quot;text.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a typical example of this feature of emakimono, the first roll of two scrolls of &quot;Ban Dainagon Emaki&quot; has a scenery of fire at Otenmon (the red-painted front gate) which depicts flaring Otenmon, crowds of viewers, government&apos;s officers trotting down on to the site upon receiving information, and so on, in a few meters long series of pictures only without any &apos;kotoba.&apos;</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>このように、「絵」の部分が長大に続き、巻物を繰り広げるにつれて画面が展開していく構図を「連続式構図」という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This kind of composition of long successive series of pictures to show development of scenes by unrolling a scroll is called &quot;progression style composition.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This kind of composition of long successive series of pictures to show development of scenes by unrolling a scroll is called &quot;progression style composition.&quot;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This kind of composition of long successive series of &apos;e&apos; to show development of scenes by unrolling a scroll is called &apos;progression style composition.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションなどを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>これに対して、巻物を机の上で広げた際に一目で見渡せる程度の大きさ（横幅50 - 60cm程度）を一画面とし、絵と詞が交互に現れる形式を「段落式構図」といい、『源氏物語絵巻』がその典型的な例である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the otherhand, a composition of alternate appearance of a picture and text page of about 50-60cm width to be overviewed by spreading it on a desk is called &quot;section style composition,&quot; typical example of which is &quot;Genji Monogatari Emaki.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the otherhand, a composition of alternating appearance of a picture and text pages of about 50-60cm width to be overviewed by spreading on a desk is called &quot;section style composition,&quot; typical example of which is &quot;Genji Monogatari Emaki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, a composition of alternating appearance of a picture and text pages of about 50 to 60 cm width to be overviewed by spreading on a desk is called &apos;section style composition,&apos; typical example of which is &quot;Genji Monogatari Emaki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションなどを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>現存作品を見ると、「連続式構図」のもの、つまり絵巻の特性を効果的に生かした作品はさほど多くなく、「段落式構図」の作品の方が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In existing works of emakimono, there are not so many &quot;progression style composition&quot; showing effective features of emakimono, but are many &quot;section style composition.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In existing works of emakimono, there are not so many &quot;progression style compositions&quot; showing effective features of emakimono, but there are many &quot;section style compositions.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In existing works of emakimono, there are not so many &apos;progression style compositions&apos; showing effective features of emakimono, but there are many &apos;section style compositions.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションなどを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>資料的価値</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Documentary Value</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Documentary Value</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Documentary Value</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="61">
<j>絵巻物については、美術的価値とともに、ビジュアルな歴史民俗資料(絵画資料)としての価値が注目されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emakimono is attracting attention to its artistic value as well as to its documentary value as visual historical and folklore materials (pitorial materials.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emakimono is attracting attention to its artistic value as well as to its documentary value as visual historical and folklore materials (pictorial material).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emakimono is attracting attention to its artistic value as well as to its documentary value as visual historical and folklore materials (pictorial material).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>絵巻物に描き表された服装、建築、食物、武器武具、調度品等は、それが制作された時代の実態をそのまま反映したものとは必ずしも言えないが、服飾史、武具甲冑史、建築史、民俗学、有職故実などの研究のために貴重な視覚情報を提供している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emakimono represents various items such as clothings, architectures, foods, weapons and armour, furnishing goods and so on, which do not necessarily reflect their real status in the days of production but, nevertheless, provides valuable visual information for various study and research, including history of clothings, history of architecture, folklore and Yusoku-kojitsu (studies in ancient court and military practices and usage.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emakimono represents various items such as clothing, architecture, food, weapons and armour, furnishing goods and so on, which do not necessarily reflect their real status in the days of production but, nevertheless, provides valuable visual information for various studies and research, including history of clothing, history of architecture, folklore, and Yusoku-kojitsu (studies in ancient court and military practices and usage).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emakimono represents various items such as clothing, architecture, food, weapons and armor, furnishing goods, and so on, which do not necessarily reflect their real status in the days of production but, nevertheless, provides valuable visual information for various studies and research, including history of clothing, history of architecture, folklore, and Yusoku-kojitsu (studies in ancient court and military practices and usage).</e>
<cmt>余分なスペースをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>一例として、『信貴山縁起』（12世紀）に登場する東大寺大仏殿の場面は、創建当時の大仏および大仏殿を描いたほとんど唯一の資料である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, the scene of Todai-ji Temple Daibutsu-den (hall of Great Statue of the Buddha) painted in &quot;Shigisan Engi (legends of Mt. Shigi)&quot; produced in 12th century is the only one existing material depicting actual Daibutsu (Great Statue of the Buddha) and its hall in the age of their creation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, the scene of Todai-ji Temple Daibutsu-den (hall of Great Statue of the Buddha) painted in &quot;Shigisan Engi&quot; (legends of Mt. Shigi) produced in 12th century is the only one existing material depicting actual Daibutsu (Great Statue of the Buddha) and its hall in the age of their creation.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, the scene of Daibutsu-den of Todai-ji Temple painted in &quot;Shigisan Engi&quot; produced in 12th century is the only one existing material depicting actual Daibutsu (Great Statue of the Buddha) and its hall in the age of their creation.</e>
<cmt>前出補足をのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>また、『餓鬼草紙』を見ると、文献資料ではわからない、当時のトイレの様子がわかる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also &quot;Gaki Soshi (hungry ghosts scroll)&quot; shows us real current condition of toilet (bath room) of that time, which we can no longer trace in other documentary materials.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also &quot;Gaki Soshi&quot; (hungry ghosts scroll) shows us real conditions of toilet (bath room) of that time, which we can no longer trace in other documentary materials.</e>
<cmt>punctuation, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also &quot;Gaki Soshi&quot; (hungry ghosts scroll) shows us real conditions of toilet of that time, which we can no longer trace in other documentary materials.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>内容による分類</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Classification by Contents</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Classification by Contents</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Classification by Contents</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="65">
<j>絵巻物はその題材によって、物語絵、説話絵、戦記絵、社寺縁起絵、高僧伝絵、歌仙絵などに分類される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emakimono are classified, according to the subjects of painted pictures, into monogatari-e (illustrated tales,) setsuwa-e (didactic pictures,) senki-e (illustrated tales of battles,) shaji-engi-e (illustrated founding stories of shrines and temples,) kosoden-e (illustrated biographies of high rank priests,) kasen-e (illustrated scroll of celebrated poets) and others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emakimono are classified, according to the subjects of painted pictures, into monogatari-e (illustrated tales,) setsuwa-e (didactic pictures,) senki-e (illustrated tales of battles,) shaji-engi-e (illustrated founding stories of shrines and temples,) kosoden-e (illustrated biographies of high rank priests,) kasen-e (illustrated scroll of celebrated poets) and others.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emakimono are classified, according to the subjects of painted pictures, into monogatari-e (illustrated tales), setsuwa-e (didactic pictures), senki-e (illustrated tales of battles), shaji-engi-e (illustrated founding stories of shrines and temples), kosoden-e (illustrated biographies of high rank priests), kasen-e (illustrated scroll of celebrated poets) and so on.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>「物語絵巻」は『源氏物語』のような「王朝物語」系の作品の絵画化したものを指すのが通例であり、ストーリー性のあるものでも『宇治拾遺物語』などに取材したものは『説話絵巻』として別に分類することが普通である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Monogatari-emaki (an illustrated scroll of tales)&quot; is usually understood to cover pictorial works based on the line of &quot;Ocho-monogatari (stories of dynasties)&quot; such as &quot;Genji Monogatari (the Tale of Genji,)&quot; and, therefore, even such illustrated stories as based on &quot;Uji Shui Monogatari (collection of tales from Uji)&quot; are usually classified into &quot;setsuwa emaki (illustrated scroll of preaching stories.)&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Monogatari-emaki&quot; (an illustrated scroll of tales) is usually understood to cover pictorial works based on the line of &quot;Ocho-monogatari&quot; (stories of dynasties&quot; such as &quot;Genji Monogatari&quot; (the Tale of Genji,) and, therefore, even such illustrated stories as those based on &quot;Uji Shui Monogatari&quot; (collection of tales from Uji) are usually classified into &quot;setsuwa emaki&quot; (illustrated scroll of preaching stories).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Monogatari-emaki&apos; (an illustrated scroll of tales) is usually understood to cover pictorial works based on the line of &apos;Ocho-monogatari&apos; (stories of dynasties) such as &quot;Genji Monogatari&quot; (the Tale of Genji), and, therefore, even such illustrated stories as those based on &quot;Uji Shui Monogatari&quot; (collection of tales from Uji) are usually classified into &quot;setsuwa emaki&quot; (illustrated scroll of preaching stories).</e>
<cmt>『説話絵巻』は他と合わせると「説話絵巻」としたほうがいいと思われますが、原文通り『』に対応するダブルクォーテーションにしています。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>絵巻という画面形式から、何らかのストーリー性をもった題材を絵画化したものが多いが、歌仙絵のように、ストーリー性は全くなく、肖像を描き並べた形式の作品もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of its painting form, many emaki are characterized by their visualized subjects based on various tales with plot, but there are also exceptions like kasen-e (illustrated scroll of celebrated poets) with a sequence of poets&apos; portraits without any plot.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of its painted form, many emaki are characterized by their visualized subjects based upon various tales with plot, but there are also exceptions like kasen-e (illustrated scroll of celebrated poets) with a sequence of poets&apos; portraits without any plot.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of its painted form, many emaki are characterized by their visualized subjects based upon various tales with plot, but there are also exceptions like kasen-e with a sequence of poets&apos; portraits without any plot.</e>
<cmt>前出補足をのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 DNCAL(id:120593), AlleborgoBot(id:119729), Mooko(id:36162), Htks(id:24185), Kstigarbha(id:13376), Urania(id:7213), Eskimbot(id:29676), Metronome(id:81545), Yas(id:739), Louperibot(id:128971), TeaServer(id:55403), Greenland4(id:114494), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>