<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>卵焼き</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tamagoyaki (Japanese omelette)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tamagoyaki (Japanese omelette)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tamagoyaki (Japanese omelette)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>卵焼き、玉子焼き（たまごやき）は、卵を溶きほぐしたものを焼き固める料理の総称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tamagoyaki is a general term forJapanese egg dishes in which eggs are beaten and cooked in a pan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tamagoyaki is a general term for Japanese egg dishes in which eggs are beaten and cooked in a pan.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tamagoyaki is a general term for Japanese egg dishes in which eggs are beaten and cooked in a pan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>広義には卵を溶かないで焼くものも含むが、ここでは溶いて焼く狭義の「卵焼き」について記述する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although in a broader definition, eggs may be cooked without beaten, this article describes the egg dishes of narrower definition.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although in a broader definition, eggs may be cooked without being beaten, this article describes the egg dishes of the narrower definition.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although in a broader definition, eggs may be cooked without being beaten, this article describes egg dishes in which the eggs are beaten.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>一般には鶏卵を使用するが、ウズラ、アヒル、ダチョウなどの卵を使用する場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Generally, chicken eggs are used; however, in some cases quail-, duck-, or ostrich- eggs are also used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Generally, chicken eggs are used; however, in some cases quail, duck, or ostrich eggs are also used.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Generally, chicken eggs are used; however, in some cases quail, duck, or ostrich eggs are also used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>調理方法</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">How to cook</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">How to cook</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">How to cook</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>黄身、白身を共に混ぜ（黄身は割りほぐして白身とよく混ぜ合わせる）、油を塗ったフライパンなどを使って焼く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Beat eggs lightly (break the yolks with chopsticks or a fork to ensure that whites and yolks are mixed to each other), and pour a small portion of the mixture in a greased skillet or other types of pan to cook.</e>
<cmt>泡立て器などでまぜるのではないため「フォークや箸で」という部分を足しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Beat eggs lightly (break the yolks with chopsticks or a fork to ensure that whites and yolks mix), and pour a small portion of the mixture into a greased skillet or other type of pan to cook.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Beat eggs lightly (break the yolks with chopsticks or a fork to ensure that whites and yolks mix), and pour a small portion of the mixture into a greased skillet or other type of pan to cook.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>表面をフッ素加工したフライパンでは油を引く必要はない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oil can be omitted if a non-stick pan is used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oil can be omitted if a non-stick pan is used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oil can be omitted if a non-stick pan is used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>家庭でよく作られる卵焼きは、角型のフライパンに溶き卵をいれて薄く延ばし、表面だけを軽く焼いた状態で巻いていったものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Typical types of tamagoyaki are prepared by pouring the beaten eggs in a rectangular frying pan, rolling it from one side of the pan to the other side when the eggs are just set, and pouring another mixture portion to repeat the process.</e>
<cmt>「表面だけを軽く焼いた状態で巻いていったものである。」の「巻いていった」とは,生地を注いで焼くのを繰りかえして巻いていくということであり、巻き簾などで巻くことを指しているのではない、と解釈しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Typically tamagoyaki is prepared by pouring the beaten eggs into a rectangular frying pan, rolling it from one side of the pan to the other side when the eggs are just semi-cooked, and pouring in another portion of the mixture and repeating the process.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Typically tamagoyaki is prepared by pouring the beaten eggs into a rectangular frying pan, rolling it from one side of the pan to the other side when the eggs are just semi-cooked, and pouring in another portion of the mixture and repeating the process.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>味付けには、多くの場合塩、コショウを加えるが、寿司や懐石料理などに用いる場合には砂糖を加えることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While salt and pepper is the common flavor, eggs are sweetened in the case that it is used in sushi or kaiseki ryori (traditional Japanese dinner)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While salt and pepper is the common flavor, the mixture is sweetened when it is used in sushi or kaiseki ryori (traditional Japanese dinner).</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While salt and pepper are the common seasonings, the egg mixture is sweetened when it is used in sushi or kaiseki ryori (traditional Japanese dinner).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>関東地方では、おかずとして食べる場合にも砂糖を加える家庭が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kanto Region, sweetened tamagoyaki is popular also as a side dish on the everyday table.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Kanto Region, sweetened tamagoyaki is popular also as a side dish on the everyday table.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Kanto Region, sweetened tamagoyaki is popular as an everyday side dish.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>近畿地方では、出汁を混入しただし巻き卵の方が主流である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kinki Region, tamagoyaki is typically prepared with dashi (Japanese stock made from kelp and/or bonito shavings) and the egg dish prepared as such is called dashimaki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Kinki Region, tamagoyaki is typically prepared with dashi (Japanese stock made from kelp and/or bonito shavings) and the dish prepared this way is called dashimaki.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Kinki Region, tamagoyaki is typically prepared with dashi (Japanese soup stock made from kelp and/or bonito shavings) and the dish prepared this way is called dashimaki.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>このほか、めんつゆや魚醤ナムプラーを混ぜることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As variations, mentsuyu (Japaneses soba/udon noodle soup made from dashi, soy sauce, mirin, etc.) or fish sauce can be used to impart fravors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As variations, mentsuyu (soup for Japanese soba/udon noodles made from dashi, soy sauce, mirin, etc.) or fish sauce can be used to give different flavors.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mentsuyu (soup for Japanese soba or udon noodles made from dashi, soy sauce, mirin, etc.) or fish sauce can also be used to give different flavors.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>また、刻んだホウレンソウやニンジンといった緑黄色野菜を溶き卵に加えて焼く、ウナギを中に入れて巻く（う巻き）などのものも知られており、いろいろと応用が利く料理である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is easy to create variations by adding spinach and carrot and other colorful vegetables to the egg mixture, or by rolling up filling such as a dish called umaki, in which shredded pieces of broiled eel are rolled in the center of the egg layers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is easy to create variations by adding spinach and carrot and other colorful vegetables to the egg mixture, or by rolling up a filling such as in a dish called umaki, in which shredded pieces of broiled eel are rolled in the center of layers of egg.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is easy to create variations by adding spinach, carrot and other colorful vegetables to the egg mixture; also, it can be used to roll up with a filling such as in a dish called umaki, in which shredded pieces of broiled eel are rolled in the center of layers of egg.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。訳文を1文にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>細片状になる炒り卵については、普通「卵焼き」という呼び方はしない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Usually, iritamago, or Japanese scrambled eggs are not called tamagoyaki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Usually, iritamago, or Japanese scrambled eggs, are not considered tamagoyaki.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Usually, iritamago, or Japanese scrambled eggs, are not considered tamagoyaki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>また、単に薄く延ばしただけの卵焼きとオムレツの相違点は、焦げ目の有無のほか、オムレツには牛乳やバターを入れることが多く、クリーム (食品)やベーコン、ソーセージなどを混ぜることがあるのが卵焼きとの大きな違いである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The diffrences between non-rolled type tamagoyaki and omelette include: whether the egg is browned or not; while butter is sometimes used to cook with omelette, but not with tamagoyaki; while milk, cream, chopped bacon, or chopped sausage is sometimes added to the egg mixture of omelette, but not to that of tamagoyaki.</e>
<cmt>「単に薄く延ばしただけの卵焼き」とは、（WIKIPEDIA日本語の卵焼き参照）における表現では「薄焼き卵」となっていますが、ここではオムレツと比較しているため、単に巻いていないタイプの卵焼きのことと解釈しました。　「焦げ目の有無」について：卵焼きとオムレツのどちらが焦げ目があるのかわかりませんでした。両方ともある場合とない場合があるように思われます。「バターを入れることが多く」：バターは料理するときにフライパンに引くことを指していると解釈しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Differences between non-rolled type tamagoyaki and omelettes include: whether the egg is browned or not; butter is sometimes used to cook omelettes, but not with tamagoyaki; milk, cream, chopped bacon, or chopped sausage is sometimes added to the egg mixture of omelette, but not that of tamagoyaki.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Differences between non-rolled type tamagoyaki and omelettes include: whether the egg is browned or not; butter is sometimes used to cook omelettes, but not with tamagoyaki; and while milk, cream, chopped bacon, or chopped sausage are sometimes added to omelettes, they are not added to tamagoyaki.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="14">
<j>なお、1960年代には、「読売ジャイアンツ・大鵬幸喜・卵焼き」と子供が好きな物の代表として挙げられることが多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1960s, tamagoyaki used to be one of the most favorite food for kids; it is listed as one of three things kids typically love in a popular phrase of that time: &quot;Giants (Japanese baseball team), Taiho (sumo wrestler), and tamagoyaki.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the 1960s, tamagoyaki used to be one of the favorite foods of children; it is listed as one of three things children typically love in a popular phrase of that time: &quot;Giants (a Japanese baseball team), Taiho (a sumo wrestler), and tamagoyaki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the 1960s, tamagoyaki used to be one of the favorite foods of children and it was listed as one of three things children typically love in a popular phrase of that time: &apos;Giants (a Japanese baseball team), Taiho (a sumo wrestler), and tamagoyaki.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>現代においても弁当の惣菜として人気があり、子供たちからの人気は根強い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even today, tamagoyaki is still a popular food among kids, and favorite choise of food constituting a school lunch box.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even today, tamagoyaki is still a popular food among children, and a favorite choice of foods used in school lunch boxes.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tamagoyaki remains a popular food among children even today, and a favorite choice of foods used in school lunch boxes.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Starbacks(id:1018), 真紀(id:68525), ロリ(id:613), Takoradee(id:82103), こたつ狼(id:27622), Melan(id:28879), マクガイア(id:33346), Hhaithait(id:37092), かかりせ(id:178555), Roger(id:9883), J8takagi(id:20409), Jazzy(id:3202), Shimotsuke(id:19741), ファービィ(id:129184), Opponent(id:720), Neko2(id:21083), Hermeneus(id:380), Yoriyori(id:67575), 月下美人(id:116398), An-chan(id:14590), Loveless(id:129239), Uron(id:10424), Point136(id:211299), Alljal(id:46858), Baffclan(id:499), Bramble(id:30443), 白糸(id:47025), STB-1(id:8775), 博多商人コイツミ(id:63820), Yukarin(id:42276), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>