<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>入内雀</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nyunaisuzume</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nyunaisuzume</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nyunaisuzume</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>入内雀（にゅうないすずめ）または実方雀（さねかたすずめ）とは、平安時代の歌人である藤原実方の伝承にある怪鳥。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nyunaisuzume or Sanekatasuzume is the monstrous bird based the legend of FUJIWARA no Sanekata, a poet in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nyunaisuzume (Russet Sparrow) or Sanekatasuzume is a mysterious bird appearing in legend of FUJIWARA no Sanekata, a poet in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>文法、表現、補足。「怪」の訳：monstrousは異常な大きさを思わせるニュアンスがある為、mysteriousに置き換えました。　実在の入内雀をRusset sparrowと呼ぶようです。http://www.flickr.com/photos/10394300@N05/3403936570/</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nyunaisuzume (Russet Sparrow) or Sanekatasuzume is a mysterious bird appearing in legend of FUJIWARA no Sanekata, a poet in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>藤原実方は一条天皇の侍臣でもある名高い歌人だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Sanekata was a noted poet and Emperor Ichijo&apos;s valet.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Sanekata was a noted poet and Emperor Ichijo&apos;s valet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Sanekata was a noted poet and Emperor Ichijo&apos;s valet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>しかし、藤原行成に陰口を叩かれたために殿上で行成と口論になり、行成の冠を奪って投げ捨てた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, when Fujiwara no Yukinari backbit Sanekata, he disputed with Yukinari in the court and took Yukinari&apos;s crown and threw away.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, when Fujiwara no Yukinari backbit Sanekata, he disputed with Yukinari in the court and took Yukinari&apos;s crown and threw it away.</e>
<cmt>文法</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, when Fujiwara no Yukinari backbit Sanekata, he disputed with Yukinari in the court and took Yukinari&apos;s crown and threw it away.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>この失態のため、京都から陸奥国（東北地方）へ左遷させられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For his blunder, he was relegated from Kyoto to Mutsu Province (Tohoku region).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For his blunder, he was relegated from Kyoto to Mutsu Province (Tohoku region).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For his blunder, he was relegated from Kyoto to Mutsu Province (Tohoku region).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>当時の陸奥は地区の孤島ともいうべき土地だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In those days, Mutsu was a desert area.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In those days, Mutsu was a desert area of the district.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In those days, Mutsu was a desert area of the district.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>実方はこの仕打ちへの怨みと京都への想いを募らせつつ、失意の内に陸奥で没した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanekata was dead in Mutsu holding grudge of the treatment and nostalgia for Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanekata was dead in Mutsu, having a grudge against backstabbers for relegating him and a nostalgia for Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>文法、補足</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanekata was dead in Mutsu, having a grudge against backstabbers for relegating him and a nostalgia for Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>京都には実方の訃報が届くと同時に、奇妙な噂が流れ始めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As soon as the obituary of Sanekata reached Kyoto, a strange rumor started circulate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As soon as the news of Sanekata&apos;s death reached Kyoto, a strange rumor started to circulate.</e>
<cmt>文法、用語。obituaryは新聞や公的文書上での死亡記事・告知の意味で使われる為、時代に合わないと判断しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As soon as the news of Sanekata&apos;s death reached Kyoto, a strange rumor started to circulate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>毎朝、京都の内裏の清涼殿へ1羽のスズメが入り込み、台盤（食事を盛る台）の飯をついばんであっという間に平らげてしまうというのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rumor had it that every morning, one sparrow entered to Seiryoden Chamber of the dairi (Imperial Palace) in Kyoto, and it ate up cooked rice on daiban (table on which food was served) in a split second.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rumor had it that every morning one sparrow entered the Seiryoden Chamber of the Dairi (Imperial Palace) in Kyoto, and it ate up cooked rice on daiban (a table on which food was served) in a split second.</e>
<cmt>文法</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rumor had it that every morning one sparrow entered the Seiryoden Chamber of the Dairi (Imperial Palace) in Kyoto, and it ate up cooked rice on daiban (a table on which food was served) in a split second.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>人々はこれを、京に帰りたい一心の実方の怨念が雀と化した、もしくは実方の霊が雀に憑いたといった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">People thought that deep-seated grudge of Sanekata wishing to return Kyoto transformed into the sparrow, or the soul of Sanekata possessed the sparrow.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">People thought that a deep-seated grudge of Sanekata wishing to return Kyoto should have transformed into the sparrow, or the soul of Sanekata had possessed the sparrow.</e>
<cmt>文法</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">People thought that a deep-seated grudge of Sanekata wishing to return Kyoto should have transformed into the sparrow, or the soul of Sanekata had possessed the sparrow.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>内裏に侵入する雀であることから「入内雀」、または「実方雀」と呼んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They called the sparrow &quot;Nyunaisuzume&quot; (dairi entering sparrow) or &quot;Sanekatasuzume&quot; (Sanekata sparrow).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They called the sparrow &quot;Nyunai-suzume&quot; (literally, dairi entering sparrow) or &quot;Sanekata-suzume&quot; (literally, Sanekata sparrow).</e>
<cmt>形式</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They called the sparrow &quot;Nyunai-suzume&quot; (literally, dairi entering sparrow) or &quot;Sanekata-suzume&quot; (literally, Sanekata sparrow).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>またこの雀は農作物を食い荒らしたともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, the sparrow allegedly ate and harm agricultural products.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, the sparrow allegedly ate and harm crops.</e>
<cmt>表現変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, the sparrow allegedly ate and harm crops.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>人々はこれを実方の怨霊の仕業といって大いに恐れたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">People might consider it deed of the vindictive spirit of Sanekata and be highly afraid.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">People reportedly considered it a deed of the vindictive spirit of Sanekata and was highly afraid.</e>
<cmt>文法</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">People reportedly considered it a deed of the vindictive spirit of Sanekata and was highly afraid.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>同じ頃に、藤原家の大学別曹である勧学院でも異変があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, there was also something unusual in Kangakuin, which was Daigaku-besso (academic facility for nobles) of the Fujiwara family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, there happened also something unusual in Kangakuin, which was a Daigaku-besso (an academic facility for nobles) of the Fujiwara family.</e>
<cmt>文法</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, there happened also something unusual in Kangakuin, which was a Daigaku-besso (an academic facility for nobles) of the Fujiwara family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>勧学院の住職・観智上人の夢の中に雀が現れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A sparrow appeared in the dream of Kanchi Shonin, the chief priest of Kangakuin.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A sparrow appeared in a dream to Kanchi Shonin, chief priest of the Kangakuin.</e>
<cmt>言い回し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A sparrow appeared in a dream to Kanchi Shonin, chief priest of the Kangakuin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>自らを京恋しさに雀と化してやって来た実方だと名乗り、自分のために誦経するようにと告げたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The sparrow said he was Sanekata having alchemized into a sparrow to come back to Kyoto and told to chant a sutra for him.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sparrow said that he was Sanekata having transmuted into a sparrow to come back to Kyoto and asked for chanting a sutra for him.</e>
<cmt>言い回し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sparrow said that he was Sanekata having transmuted into a sparrow to come back to Kyoto and asked for chanting a sutra for him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>上人は翌朝に境内の林で1羽の雀の死骸を見つけた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the following morning, Shonin found the corpse of a sparrow in the wood of the precincts.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The next morning, Shonin found the corpse of a sparrow between the trees in the temple precincts.</e>
<cmt>言い回し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The next morning, Shonin found the corpse of a sparrow between the trees in the temple precincts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>上人は、実方の変わり果てた姿に違いないと考え、霊を弔うために塚を築いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was convinced that it should be the remain of Sanekata and built a mound to perform a memorial service for his soul.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was convinced that it should be the remains of Sanekata and built a mound to perform a memorial service for his soul.</e>
<cmt>言い回し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was convinced that it should be the remains of Sanekata and built a mound to perform a memorial service for his soul.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="18">
<j>後に勧学院は更雀寺（俗称・雀寺）と改名し、現在では京都の左京区に場所を移している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterwards, the Kangakuin renames Kyoshaku-ji Temple (commonly known as Suzume-dera Temple), and the temple is now relocated in Sakyo Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Afterwards, the Kangakuin was renamed Kyoshaku-ji Temple (commonly known as Suzume-dera Temple), and the temple is now relocated in Sakyo Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>文法</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Afterwards, the Kangakuin was renamed Kyoshaku-ji Temple (commonly known as Suzume-dera Temple), and the temple is now relocated in Sakyo Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>火災が続いたこともあって規模は次第に縮小化され、もとの勧学院の面影は薄れつつある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its property has been gradually diminished because of several fire, and the visage of the original Kangakuin has been fading.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its property has gradually been diminished due to several fires, and the vestige of the original Kangakuin has been fading.</e>
<cmt>用語、言い回し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its property has gradually been diminished due to several fires, and the vestige of the original Kangakuin has been fading.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>しかし、前述の塚は雀塚と呼ばれて現存しており、現在でもなお実方のための供養が続けられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the mound, called suzumezuka, still exists, and the memorial service is still held for Sanekata at the present.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the mound that is called Suzumezuka still exists, and the memorial service is still continually held for Sanekata today.</e>
<cmt>形式</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the mound that is called Suzumezuka still exists, and the memorial service is still continually held for Sanekata today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="21">
<j>一定の時期に来訪する鳥や昆虫は人間の霊魂と同一視されることが多く、実在するニュウナイスズメは夏季に東北地方で繁殖し、秋季に全国に渡来して農作物に被害をもたらすことから、これが東北に左遷された実方の化身だと想像されたとの説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the Cinnamon Sparrows actually breed in Tohoku region in summer, migrate all over the country in autumn and damage agricultural products, they might be imagined to be the incarnation of Sanekata who was relegated to Tohoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Birds and insects which migrate seasonally and on a regular basis are frequently identified as human souls, and therefore, one theory has it that Russet (or Cinnamon) Sparrows which actually breed in Tohoku region in summer, migrate all over the country and damage agricultural products in autumn would probably be associated with the incarnation of Sanekata who had been relegated to Tohoku.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れによる加筆修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Birds and insects which migrate seasonally and on a regular basis are frequently identified as human souls, and therefore, one theory has it that Russet (or Cinnamon) Sparrows which actually breed in Tohoku region in summer, migrate all over the country and damage agricultural products in autumn would probably be associated with the incarnation of Sanekata who had been relegated to Tohoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 逃亡者(id:14864), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>