<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>髪結い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kamiyui (Hairdressor)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kamiyui (Hairdresser)</e>
<cmt>スペルミスを修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kamiyui (Hairdresser)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>髪結い（かみゆい）は江戸時代から明治にかけての理髪業に従事する人を総称する言葉で、今の美容師のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kamiyui is a general term referring those who were engaged in hairdressing from the Edo Period to the Meiji Period, which is now called hairdresser.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kamiyui is a general term referring those who were engaged in hairdressing from the Edo period to the Meiji period, who are now called hairdressers.</e>
<cmt>用語の形式を修正しました文法を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kamiyui is a general term referring those who were engaged in hairdressing from the Edo period to the Meiji period, who are now called hairdressers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>男性の髪を手がける男の髪結いで「髪結い床」という自分の店を持つものは床屋とも呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A male Kamiyui who dealt with male hair and had his own salon called &apos;Kamiyui doko&apos; was also called Tokoya.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文原則例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Male Kamiyui who dealt with male hair and had his own salons called &apos;Kamiyuidoko&apos; was also called Tokoya.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました用語の形式を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Male Kamiyui who dealt with male hair and had his own salons called &apos;Kamiyuidoko&apos; was also called Tokoya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>が、女性の髪を手がける女髪結いは遊郭（遊女は上得意だった）や顧客の家を訪問していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But an Onnakamiyui (female Kamiyui) who dealt with female hair visited yukaku (red-light district) (yujo [prostitutes] were best customers) and customers&apos; houses.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文原則例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But Onnakamiyui (female Kamiyui) who dealt with female hair visited yukaku (red-light district) (yujo [prostitutes] were their best customers) and customers&apos; houses.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But Onnakamiyui (female Kamiyui) who dealt with female hair visited yukaku (red-light district) (yujo [prostitutes] were their best customers) and customers&apos; houses.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>以下「床屋」では男性の髪結い、「女髪結い」では女性の髪結いについて扱う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A male Kamiyui is mentioned in &apos;Tokoya&apos; and female Kamiyui in &apos;Onnakamiyui&apos; below.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A male Kamiyui is mentioned in &apos;Tokoya&apos; and female Kamiyui in &apos;Onnakamiyui&apos; below.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A male Kamiyui is mentioned in &apos;Tokoya&apos; and female Kamiyui in &apos;Onnakamiyui&apos; below.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>床屋</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokoya</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokoya</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokoya</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>男性の髪結いは、月代が広まった室町時代後期に一銭程度の料金で髪を結い月代を剃った「一銭剃」（いっせんぞり）が起源である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A male Kamiyui originated in &apos;Issenzori,&apos; who fixed hairdo and shaved sakayaki (shaved part of the forehead) at a price of 1 sen (hundredth of a yen) or so in the end of Muromachi Period when sakayaki became popular.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A male Kamiyui originated in &apos;Issenzori,&apos; who fixed hairdo and shaved sakayaki (shaved part of the forehead) at a price of 1 sen (hundredth of a yen) or so in the end of Muromachi period when sakayaki became popular.</e>
<cmt>用語の形式を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A male Kamiyui originated in &apos;Issenzori,&apos; who fixed hairdo and shaved sakayaki (shaved part of the forehead) at a price of 1 sen (hundredth of a yen) or so in the end of Muromachi period when sakayaki became popular.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>雑用をこなす召使がいる武士と違い、庶民は自分で月代を剃ることができず（貧しい人は月代を伸ばしっぱなしにしたり妻に剃ってもらうなどした）髪結いに頼んだのだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Different from samurai, who had servants doing chores, the common people had Kamiyui shave their sakayaki because they were not able to do so by themselves (the poor left their sakayaki unshaven or had their wife shave it).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Different from samurai, who had servants doing chores, the common people had Kamiyui shave their sakayaki because they were not able to do that by themselves (the poor left their sakayaki unshaven or had their wife shave it).</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Different from samurai, who had servants doing chores, the common people had Kamiyui shave their sakayaki because they were not able to do that by themselves (the poor left their sakayaki unshaven or had their wife shave it).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>彼らは町や村単位で抱えられ、床と呼ばれる仮店で商売を行ったため床屋とも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They worked in the whole town or village, and they were also called Tokoya because they did business at a makeshift salon called toko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They worked in the whole town or village, and they were also called Tokoya because they did business at a makeshift salon called toko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They worked in the whole town or village, and they were also called Tokoya because they did business at a makeshift salon called toko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>床屋が特に多かったのは独身男性が多い江戸だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was Edo (present Tokyo), where there were lots of single men, that had especially lots of Tokoya.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文原則例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was Edo (present Tokyo), where there were lots of single men, that had especially lots of Tokoya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was Edo (present Tokyo), where there were lots of single men, that had especially lots of Tokoya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>江戸の男性はかなり頻繁に床屋に通っていたらしく床屋は番所や社交場としても利用された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Men in Edo apparently went to Tokoya quite often, and Tokoya was used also as a bansho (guard house) or a place for a social interaction.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文原則例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Men in Edo apparently went to Tokoya quite often, and Tokoya was used also as a bansho (guard house) or a place for a social interaction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Men in Edo apparently went to Tokoya quite often, and Tokoya was used also as a bansho (guard house) or a place for a social interaction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>江戸や大阪・京都では、床屋は幕府に届出して開業した後は町の管理下で見張りなどの役割を果たしていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Edo, and Osaka and Kyoto, Tokoya played a role of lookout under the control of the city, after registering with bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and opening the business.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文原則例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Edo, Osaka and Kyoto, Tokoya played a role of lookout and so on under the control of the city, after registering with bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and opening the business.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Edo, Osaka and Kyoto, Tokoya played a role of lookout and so on under the control of the city, after registering with bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and opening the business.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>番所や会所と融合したものを内床、橋のそばや辻で営業するものを出床、道具を持って得意先回りをするものは廻り髪結いと呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those who were integrated with bansho or kaisho (meeting place) were called Uchidoko, those who did their business near a bridge or on the street were called Dedoko, and those who visited customers with their tools were called Mawari Kamiyui.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文原則例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those who were integrated with bansho or kaisho (meeting place) were called Uchidoko, those who did their business near a bridge or on the street were called Dedoko, and those who visited customers with their tools were called Mawarikamiyui.</e>
<cmt>用語登録の訳に修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those who were integrated with bansho or kaisho (meeting place) were called Uchidoko, those who did their business near a bridge or on the street were called Dedoko, and those who visited customers with their tools were called Mawarikamiyui.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>当時の床屋は現在の美容院と違って客の髭を剃ったり眉を整えたり耳掃除までしていたため、かなり長い年月の修行が必要になる技術職でもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokoya of the day was a technical job which required quite many years of training because they shaved customers&apos; beard, trimmed their eyebrows, and cleaned their ears, different from the present hairdresser.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Different from the present hairdresser, Tokoya of the day was a technical job which required quite many years of training because they shaved customers&apos; beard, trimmed their eyebrows, and cleaned their ears.</e>
<cmt>語順を変更しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Different from the present hairdresser, Tokoya of the day was a technical job which required quite many years of training because they shaved customers&apos; beard, trimmed their eyebrows, and cleaned their ears.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>床屋の料金は天明年間でおおよそ一回280文前後で、月代・顔剃り、耳掃除、髪の結いなおしをする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The price of Tokoya was around 280 mon (an old currency unit in Japan) each time in the Tenmei era, which included shaving sakayaki and face, cleaning ears, and fixing hairdo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The price of Tokoya was around 280 mon (an old currency unit in Japan) each time in the Tenmei era, which included shaving sakayaki and face, cleaning ears, and fixing hairdo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The price of Tokoya was around 280 mon (an old currency unit in Japan) each time in the Tenmei era, which included shaving sakayaki and face, cleaning ears, and fixing hairdo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="14">
<j>一方、得意先と年季契約して出張する「廻り髪結い」は大店などに抱えられており、主人からは一回100文前後、ほかの従業員はその半額程度の料金を取った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, &apos;Mawari Kamiyui&apos; who visited customers with an annual contract was hired by big stores, and charged the owner around 100 mon each time and his employees about the half price.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, &apos;Mawarikamiyui&apos; who visited customers with articles of apprenticeship was hired by big stores, and charged the owner around 100 mon each time and his employees about the half price.</e>
<cmt>単語の訳を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, &apos;Mawarikamiyui&apos; who visited customers with articles of apprenticeship was hired by big stores, and charged the owner around 100 mon each time and his employees about the half price.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>決められた料金のほかに、「あごつき」といって得意先に食事を出してもらう契約のところもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some contracts included meals from the customer as well as the fixed price, which was called &apos;agotsuki (work with meals).&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文原則例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some contracts included meals from the customer as well as the fixed price, which was called &apos;agotsuki&apos; (work with meals).</e>
<cmt>記号の位置を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some contracts included meals from the customer as well as the fixed price, which was called &apos;agotsuki&apos; (work with meals).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>また祝い事のご祝儀なども届けられるなど腕のよい髪結いならそれなりに余裕のある暮らしを送れたらしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Given some tips on celebratory occasions, a good Kamiyui was relatively well-off.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文原則例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Given some tips on celebratory occasions, a good Kamiyui was relatively well-off.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Given some tips on celebratory occasions, a good Kamiyui was relatively well-off.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>女髪結い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Onnakamiyui</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Onnakamiyui</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Onnakamiyui</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="17">
<j>結髪が習慣化して以来、成人女性は自分で髪を結うのが嗜みだったのだが、髪型が複雑化した明和年間ごろにはもはや結髪の素人には手に負えず、また、後ろ髪を大きく突き出すような自分では結うのが難しい髪型が氾濫した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since keppatsu (hairdo) became common practice, it was accomplishment for an adult woman to fix her hairdo by herself, but around the Meiwa era when the hairstyle became complicated, nonprofessional women could not handle the hairdo anymore, and the hairstyle with back hair widely projected, which was difficult to fix single-handed, became popular.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文原則例外処理原文の「結髪の素人には」は「結髪は素人には」でないと意味が通りにくいため、そのように訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since keppatsu (hairdressing) became common practice, it was accomplishment for an adult woman to fix her hairdo by herself, but around the Meiwa era, when the hairstyle became complicated, nonprofessional women could not handle the hairdo anymore, and the hairstyle with back hair widely projected, which was difficult to fix single-handedly, became popular.</e>
<cmt>用語登録の訳に修正しました文法を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since keppatsu (hairdressing) became common practice, it was accomplishment for an adult woman to fix her hairdo by herself, but around the Meiwa era, when the hairstyle became complicated, nonprofessional women could not handle the hairdo anymore, and the hairstyle with back hair widely projected, which was difficult to fix single-handedly, became popular.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>そのため、多彩な髪型を熟知し顧客の容姿や好みに合わせて結い上げる専門職が必要になり男性の「廻り髪結い」が遊郭を出入りして遊女の髪を結った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, specialists who were familiar with various hairstyles and fixed hairdo by suiting a customer&apos;s appearance or preference became required, so a male &apos;Mawari Kamiyui&apos; visited yukaku and fixed yujo&apos;s hairdo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文原則例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this reason, specialists who knew fully well various hairstyles and had skill to fix hairdo to suit a customer&apos;s appearance or preference were required, therefore, male &apos;Mawarikamiyui&apos; visited yukaku and fixed yujo&apos;s hairdo.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました単語の訳を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For this reason, specialists who knew fully well various hairstyles and had skill to fix hairdo to suit a customer&apos;s appearance or preference were required, therefore, male &apos;Mawarikamiyui&apos; visited yukaku and fixed yujo&apos;s hairdo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="19">
<j>しかし、男性にはさらに複雑化してゆく髪型を熟知し顧客の細かな要望に応える作業は厳しく、安永ごろになると女性の髪結いが登場して遊郭の「廻り髪結い」は急速に衰退していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the work to understand more and more complicated hairstyles and to meet customers&apos; detailed demands was hard for men, so female Kamiyui appeared around the Anei era, which made &apos;Mawari Kamiyui&apos; in yukaku rapidly disappear.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the work to understand more and more complicated hairstyles and to meet customers&apos; detailed demands was hard for men, so female Kamiyui appeared around the Anei era, which made &apos;Mawarikamiyui&apos; in yukaku rapidly disappear.</e>
<cmt>単語の訳を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the work to understand more and more complicated hairstyles and to meet customers&apos; detailed demands was hard for men, so female Kamiyui appeared around the Anei era, which made &apos;Mawarikamiyui&apos; in yukaku rapidly disappear.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="20">
<j>彼女たちは筋目櫛や梳き櫛などを風呂敷に包んで顧客を訪ね、客の要望を聞きながら最新の髪形を結っていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Female Kamiyui visited their customers with sujimekushi (comb for line) and sukigushi (fine-toothed comb) wrapped in furoshiki (wrapping cloth), and fixed customers&apos; hairdo with the latest hairstyle by meeting their demands.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文原則例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Female Kamiyui visited their customers with sujimekushi (comb for line) and sukigushi (fine-toothed comb) wrapped in furoshiki (wrapping cloth), and fixed their hairdo into the latest hairstyles based on their requests.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Female Kamiyui visited their customers with sujimekushi (comb for line) and sukigushi (fine-toothed comb) wrapped in furoshiki (wrapping cloth), and fixed their hairdo into the latest hairstyles based on their requests.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>江戸時代後期には毎年のようにスタイルブックが売り出され髪結いはそれを参考にアレンジを加えてゆっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the end of Edo Period, style books were sold every year, and Kamiyui fixed hairdo by referring to them and adding their own style.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文原則例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the end of Edo period, style books were come out every year, and Kamiyui referred to them and added their own style while fixing hairdo.</e>
<cmt>用語の形式を修正しました文法を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the end of Edo period, style books were come out every year, and Kamiyui referred to them and added their own style while fixing hairdo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="22">
<j>女髪結い自体は着古した地味な衣装に前垂れを帯代わりにするような堅実で質素な女性が多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Female Kamiyui themselves were mostly solid and modest women, who wore outworn plain clothes with a maedare (apron) as an obi sash.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文原則例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Female Kamiyui themselves were mostly solid and modest women, who wore outworn plain clothes with a maedare (apron) instead of the obi sash.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Female Kamiyui themselves were mostly solid and modest women, who wore outworn plain clothes with a maedare (apron) instead of the obi sash.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>だが、幕府には他人に髪を結わせるという行為が贅沢だと目をつけられてたびたび禁止令を出されていた（とはいえ耳を貸すような女性は皆無に等しかったのだが）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, bakufu regarded the deed to have someone fix hairdo as luxury and imposed the ban (still, little women listened).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文原則例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, bakufu regarded the deed to have someone fix hairdo as luxury and often imposed the ban (still, little women listened).</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, bakufu regarded the deed to have someone fix hairdo as luxury and often imposed the ban (still, little women listened).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="24">
<j>髪結い料は安永ごろの資料を見ると一回で200文程度で、物価の上下や時代ごとに多少の変遷があったと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the document around the Anei era, the price of Kamiyui was about 200 mon each time, and it seems to have changed a little depending on fluctuations in price or the times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the document around the Anei era, the price of Kamiyui was about 200 mon each time, and it seems to have changed a little depending on fluctuations in price or the times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the document around the Anei era, the price of Kamiyui was about 200 mon each time, and it seems to have changed a little depending on fluctuations in price or the times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>また、遊郭の女郎や大店の妻女からは季節ごとに祝儀の品が届いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And they got gifts seasonally from joro in yukaku and wives of big shops.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文原則例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And they got gifts seasonally from joro (courtesan) in yukaku and wives of big shops.</e>
<cmt>単語の訳を補足しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And they got gifts seasonally from joro (courtesan) in yukaku and wives of big shops.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>「髪結いの亭主」といえば高給取りの女房のおかげで楽な暮らしをする男の代名詞であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&apos;A husband of Kamiyui&apos; was a synonym of a man who was well-off thanks to his well-paid wife.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文原則例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&apos;A husband of Kamiyui&apos; was a synonym of a man who was well-off thanks to his well-paid wife.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&apos;A husband of Kamiyui&apos; was a synonym of a man who was well-off thanks to his well-paid wife.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Rusk(id:9895), 踏蹟(id:51201), 桜井悠士(id:72420), ぎゅうひ(id:9206), Taka76(id:283895), 松茸(id:27535), STHN(id:19106), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>