<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>寿司屋</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sushi restaurant.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sushi restaurant</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sushi restaurant</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>寿司屋（すしや、すし屋・鮨屋）は、寿司商（すししょう）、寿司店（すしてん）とも言い、日本食である寿司を供する飲食店である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sushi restaurant is also called sushisho or sushiten and is a restaurant which serves Japanese food sushi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sushi restaurant is also called sushisho or sushiten and is a restaurant which serves Japanese food sushi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sushi restaurant is also called sushisho or sushiten and is a restaurant which serves Japanese food sushi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>寿司屋は、寿司（特に寿司握り寿司）を主として供する飲食店（サービス業）ではあるが、刺身を含め食材に生のものが多く鮮度も重視される点で、他の飲食店と決定的に異なる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sushi restaurant is the one (service business) which serves mainly sushi (especially nigirizushi (sushi shaped by hand)), but it is critically different from the other restaurants in that the freshness counts because the food materials include many perishables like sashimi (fresh slices of raw fish).</e>
<cmt>「寿司握り寿司」を、「握り寿司」と取りました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A sushi restaurant is one (service business) which serves mainly sushi (especially nigirizushi (sushi shaped by hand)), but it is critically different from other restaurants in that freshness counts because the food materials include many perishables like sashimi (fresh slices of raw fish).</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A sushi restaurant is one (service business) which serves mainly sushi (especially nigirizushi [sushi shaped by hand]), but it is critically different from other restaurants in that freshness counts because the food materials include many perishables like sashimi (fresh slices of raw fish).</e>
<cmt>「()」箇所の修正。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>鮮度の良い材料を使用して調理をし、鮮度の良いうちに提供される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fresh materials are used and cooked and served while the freshness is kept.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fresh materials are used and cooked and served while fresh.</e>
<cmt>while fresh</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fresh materials are used and cooked and served while fresh.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>現代では冷蔵庫など食品の保存に便利な装置や輸送面での技術的進歩によりあまり意識されない所ではあるが、かつては食材の鮮度保持や雑菌繁殖予防などで様々な工夫が行われ、その一部は今日ヅケと呼ばれる調理や味付けの技法に生き残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At one time various kinds of efforts were made for keeping the freshness or preventing the contamination and so on, but now they are not noticed because of convenient devices for keeping foods such as refrigerators or technical developments of transportation, a part of which remains in the cooking or seasoning technique called zuke (tuna preserved with soy sauce).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At one time various kinds of efforts were made for preserving freshness or preventing contamination and so on, but now they are not noticed because of convenient devices for keeping foods such as refrigerators or technical developments of transportation, a part of which remains in the cooking or seasoning technique called zuke (tuna preserved with soy sauce).</e>
<cmt>keep-&gt;preserve</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At one time various kinds of efforts were made for preserving freshness or preventing contamination and so on, but now they are not noticed because of convenient devices for keeping foods such as refrigerators or technical developments of transportation, a part of which remains in the cooking or seasoning technique called zuke (tuna preserved with soy sauce).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>酢の利用も経験的に殺菌効果があることを利用したものだと見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The use of vinegar seems to have been because of its sterilization effect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The use of vinegar seems to have been because of its sterilization effect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The use of vinegar seems to have been because of its sterilization effect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>こういった鮮度保持の必要性から、かつて輸送技術が低かった時代には、沿海部など限られた地域を中心に寿司屋も偏在した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of such necessities of keeping freshness, when the transportation technique was low in previous times, sushi restaurants were located centering on limited areas such as coastal areas and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of such necessities of keeping freshness, in times when transportation technology was low, sushi restaurants were located centering on limited areas such as coastal areas and so on.</e>
<cmt>technique-&gt;technology</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of such necessities of keeping freshness, in times when transportation technology was low, sushi restaurants were located centering on limited areas such as coastal areas and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>今日では輸送技術の発達により、極端な例を挙げれば山里などでも寿司屋が存在している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Now with the development of transportation technique, there are sushi restaurants even in mountainside as an extreme example.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Now with the development of transportation technology, there are sushi restaurants even in the mountains, for example.</e>
<cmt>technique-&gt;technology</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Now with the development of transportation technology, there are sushi restaurants even in the mountains, for example.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>その一方で魚など食材の買い付けでは鮮度の面から中間業者が介在しにくく、現代のように小分けした流通形態が無かった時代には、マグロでも「一本」という単位で仕入れられることもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hands, it is difficult for middlemen to intervene in the purchase of foods such as fish and so on because of keeping the freshness and when there were not minutely divided circulation systems as in present days, even tunas were sometimes purchased with a unit of &apos;ippon&apos; (one fish).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, it is difficult for middlemen to intervene in the purchase of foods such as fish and so on because of the need for freshness, and when there were not minutely divided circulation systems as there are now, even tunas were sometimes purchased in units of one fish.</e>
<cmt>phrasing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, it is difficult for middlemen to intervene in the purchase of foods such as fish and so on because of the need for freshness, and when there were not minutely divided circulation systems as there are now, even tunas were sometimes purchased in units of one fish.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>なお1980年代のバブル景気の頃よりは、鮮魚から活魚などのような活きたまま輸送する技術も発達、こういった活魚市場の末端を寿司屋が担っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the bubble economy during 1980s, with the development of transportation, fresh fish or live fish could be transported and sushi restaurants are situated in the end of such live fish market.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the bubble economy of the 1980s, with the development of transportation, fresh fish or live fish could be transported and sushi restaurants are situated next to such live fish markets.</e>
<cmt>plural markets</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the bubble economy of the 1980s, with the development of transportation, fresh fish or live fish could be transported and sushi restaurants are situated next to such live fish markets.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>ただし食通筋などに言わせると、活魚はストレス (生体)を受けているため、適切に市場で処理されたものに味が劣るという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However gourmets say that live fish are subjected to stress and are inferior in taste to the ones adequately processed in the market.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, gourmets say that live fish are subjected to stress and are inferior in taste to the ones adequately processed in the market.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, gourmets say that live fish are subjected to stress and are inferior in taste to the ones adequately processed in the market.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>しかしそれでも「扱いが悪い死んだ魚」に比べたら鮮度の面では良いため、大衆向けの寿司屋などでは店内の生簀に活魚が泳ぐ姿もまま見られ、客の目を楽しませている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, they are better in freshness than &apos;maltreated dead fish&apos; and thus in sushi restaurants for the public, live fish are seen to swim in the preserves at times and customers enjoy it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, they are better in freshness than &apos;maltreated dead fish&apos; and thus in sushi restaurants for the public, live fish are seen to swim in the preserves at times and customers enjoy it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, they are better in freshness than &apos;maltreated dead fish&apos; and thus in sushi restaurants for the public, live fish are seen to swim in the preserves at times and customers enjoy it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>ただ、活魚は魚の生活する海水までもを一緒に輸送するため、輸送コストを含め些か割高になるのは避け得ない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, live fish cannot avoid being a bit costly because they have to be transported with sea water where the fish live, including transportation costs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, live fish cannot avoid being a bit costly because they have to be transported with sea water where the fish live, including transportation costs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, live fish cannot avoid being a bit costly because they have to be transported with sea water where the fish live, including transportation costs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="13">
<j>20世紀末頃よりは冷凍技術の発達にも伴い、鮮度や味の面ではやや劣るものの、適切に温度管理されれば保存や流通にも耐え、適切に解凍することで生に近い状態に出来る冷凍の食材が流通しており、その供給も安定している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the development of freezing technique from the late twentieth century the frozen food materials have been circulated and they can keep good and be circulated if their temperatures are properly managed and be served in the states as good as the raw ones if properly thawed, though a bit inferior in freshness or taste, and the supplies are stabilized.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the development of freezing techniques from the late twentieth century frozen foods have been circulated and they can keep good and be circulated if their temperatures are properly managed and be served in a state as good as the raw ones if properly thawed, though a bit inferior in freshness or taste, and the supplies are stabilized.</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the development of freezing techniques from the late twentieth century frozen foods have been circulated and they can keep good and be circulated if their temperatures are properly managed and be served in a state as good as the raw ones if properly thawed, though a bit inferior in freshness or taste, and the supplies are stabilized.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>しかし今日でも生の食材を市場で仕入れて調理するような寿司専門店では、その日や季節によって得られる食材が変化することから特にメニュー表や値札を出しておらず、「時価」や「お任せ」というコースが見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However even today, in sushi restaurants where raw food materials are purchased in the market and cooked, the food materials change day by day, or season by season and thus they do not indicate menus or price tags in particular and the courses such as &apos;market value&apos; or &apos;whatever&apos; are seen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However even today, in sushi restaurants where raw food materials are purchased in the market and cooked, the food materials change day by day, or season by season and thus they do not indicate menus or price tags in particular and the courses such as &apos;market value&apos; or &apos;whatever&apos; are seen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However even today, in sushi restaurants where raw food materials are purchased in the market and cooked, the food materials change day by day, or season by season and thus they do not indicate menus or price tags in particular and the courses such as &apos;market value&apos; or &apos;whatever&apos; are seen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="15">
<j>握り寿司の場合は二つずつの注文となることがほとんどだが、ちらし寿司などと同じく「1人前」や、「松」「竹」「梅」等のメニューを出している店も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the case of nigirizushi, most of them are served with a pair, but many restaurants have menus such as &apos;ichininmae&apos; (one serving) as in chirashi zushi (vinegared rice with thin strips of egg, pieces of raw fish, vegetables and crab meat arranged on top), or &apos;sho&apos; (pine), &apos;chiku&apos; (bamboo) and &apos;bai&apos; (plum trees) and so on.</e>
<cmt>「一人前」を、ichininmae (one serving)としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the case of nigirizushi, most of them are served with a pair, but many restaurants have menus such as &apos;ichininmae&apos; (one serving) as in chirashi zushi (vinegared rice with thin strips of egg, pieces of raw fish, vegetables and crab meat arranged on top), or &apos;sho&apos; (pine), &apos;chiku&apos; (bamboo) and &apos;bai&apos; (plum trees) and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the case of nigirizushi, most of them are served with a pair, but many restaurants have menus such as &apos;ichininmae&apos; (one serving) as in chirashi zushi (vinegared rice with thin strips of egg, pieces of raw fish, vegetables and crab meat arranged on top), or &apos;sho&apos; (pine), &apos;chiku&apos; (bamboo) and &apos;bai&apos; (plum trees) and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="16">
<j>『今昔物語集』 巻第31 第32に「市町に賣る」鮨鮎と言及されており、これが『今昔物語集』が成立した平安時代末期に、形態は不明ではあるが京都に寿司屋が存在したとみられる最古の記録である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The 31 and 32 volume of &quot;Konjaku Monogatari (Shu) &quot; (The Tale of Times Now Past) referred to ayuzushi (fermented sushi with sweetfish) &apos;sold in town,&apos; which is the oldest record that there existed a sushi restaurant in Kyoto, whose form was unknown, during the late Heian period when &quot;Konjaku Monogatari (Shu) &quot; was finished.</e>
<cmt>「鮨鮎」を、「鮎鮨」と取りました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Volumes 31 and 32 of &quot;Konjaku Monogatari Shu &quot; (Tales of Times Now Past) referred to ayuzushi (fermented sushi with sweetfish) &apos;sold in town,&apos; which is the oldest record that there existed a sushi restaurant in Kyoto, whose form was unknown, during the late Heian period when &quot;Konjaku Monogatari Shu&quot; was finished.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Volumes 31 and 32 of &quot;Konjaku Monogatari Shu &quot; (Tales of Times Now Past) referred to ayuzushi (fermented sushi with sweetfish) &apos;sold in town,&apos; which is the oldest record that there existed a sushi restaurant in Kyoto, whose form was unknown, during the late Heian period when &quot;Konjaku Monogatari Shu&quot; was finished.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>『義経千本桜』（延享四年（1747年）初演）には舞台のひとつとして奈良吉野の下市村 釣瓶鮓が取り上げられており、有名となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In one scene of &quot;Yoshitsune Senbonzakura&quot; (Yoshitsune and One Thousand Cherry Trees) (the first performance was in 1747), tsurubezushi of Shimoichi village in Nara Yoshino was referred to and became famous.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In one scene of &quot;Yoshitsune Senbonzakura&quot; (Yoshitsune and One Thousand Cherry Trees) (first performed in 1747), tsurubezushi of Shimoichi village in Nara Yoshino was referred to and became famous.</e>
<cmt>first performed</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In one scene of &quot;Yoshitsune Senbonzakura&quot; (Yoshitsune and One Thousand Cherry Trees) (first performed in 1747), tsurubezushi of Shimoichi village in Nara Yoshino was referred to and became famous.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="18">
<j>江戸前</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Edomae (Tokyo style).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Edomae (Tokyo style)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Edomae (Tokyo style)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>江戸時代以前寿司と言えば貯蔵を目的とした「なれずし」や「押しずし」・「蒸しずし」などであったが江戸時代には、江戸前といわれにぎり寿司を供する寿司店となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sushi before Edo period were &apos;nare-zushi&apos; (fermented sushi), &apos;oshi-zushi&apos; (lightly-pressed piece of sushi topped with cooked ingredients), &apos;mushi-zushi&apos; (steamed sushi) and so on, but during Edo period, sushi restaurant came to serve nigirizushi called Edomae.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sushi before the Edo period was &apos;nare-zushi&apos; (fermented sushi), &apos;oshi-zushi&apos; (lightly-pressed piece of sushi topped with cooked ingredients), &apos;mushi-zushi&apos; (steamed sushi) and so on, but during the Edo period, sushi restaurants came to serve nigirizushi called Edomae.</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sushi before the Edo period was &apos;nare-zushi&apos; (fermented sushi), &apos;oshi-zushi&apos; (lightly-pressed piece of sushi topped with cooked ingredients), &apos;mushi-zushi&apos; (steamed sushi) and so on, but during the Edo period, sushi restaurants came to serve nigirizushi called Edomae.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>握りすしは「早ずし」といわれ、文字通り早く簡単に食べられるのが人気を呼んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nigirizushi was called &apos;haya-zushi&apos; (quick sushi) and it was popular because literally it was eaten quickly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nigirizushi was called &apos;haya-zushi&apos; (quick sushi) and it was popular because literally it was eaten quickly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nigirizushi was called &apos;haya-zushi&apos; (quick sushi) and it was popular because literally it was eaten quickly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>店主が一人で切り盛りする小規模な店が多く、お茶のお代わりまで手がまわらず、鮨屋独特の大型の湯呑がうまれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many sushi restaurants were managed by one owner and were small-scaled and he was too busy to serve green tea and thus a large tea cup peculiar to sushi restaurant was born.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many sushi restaurants were managed by one owner and were small-scale, and he was too busy to serve green tea and thus a large tea cup peculiar to sushi restaurants was born.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many sushi restaurants were managed by one owner and were small-scale, and he was too busy to serve green tea and thus a large tea cup peculiar to sushi restaurants was born.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>現代の寿司屋</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Present-day sushi restaurant.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Present-day sushi restaurants</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Present-day sushi restaurants</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="22">
<j>典型的な寿司屋はカウンターとテーブル席（または座敷）で構成されることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Typically, many sushi restaurants consist of a counter and tables and chairs (or zashiki (Japanese style tatami room)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Typically, many sushi restaurants consist of a counter and tables and chairs (or zashiki (Japanese style tatami room)).</e>
<cmt>spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Typically, many sushi restaurants consist of a counter and tables and chairs (or zashiki [Japanese style tatami room]).</e>
<cmt>「()」箇所の修正。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>多くの場合、冷蔵庫とショーウィンドウを兼ねたカウンターのガラスケース（ショーケース）内に寿司種が並べられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mostly, sushi toppings are displayed in a glass case (showcase) on the counter which combines a refrigerator and a show window.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mostly, sushi toppings are displayed in a glass case (showcase) on the counter which combines a refrigerator and a show window.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mostly, sushi toppings are displayed in a glass case (showcase) on the counter which combines a refrigerator and a show window.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>これが寿司職人によって客の目の前で捌かれ、寿司に調理される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are cut in front of the customers by a sushi chef and made into sushi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are cut in front of the customers by a sushi chef and made into sushi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are cut in front of the customers by a sushi chef and made into sushi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="25">
<j>にぎり寿司の場合、店内では通常下駄の歯のような足の付いた板（「ゲタ」という）に寿司を乗せて供する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the case of nigirizushi, sushis are usually served on a wooden board (called &apos;geta&apos;) which looks like a geta (Japanese footwear, wooden clogs) in a sushi restaurant.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the case of nigirizushi, sushis are usually served on a wooden board (called &apos;geta&apos;) which looks like a geta (Japanese footwear, wooden clogs) in a sushi restaurant.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the case of nigirizushi, sushis are usually served on a wooden board (called &apos;geta&apos;) which looks like a geta (Japanese footwear, wooden clogs) in a sushi restaurant.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>店によっては、木製カウンターの一部が高くなっており、そこへ直に置かれることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In some restaurants, sushis are directly served on a wooden counter whose part is raised.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In some restaurants, sushis are directly served on a wooden counter whose part is raised.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In some restaurants, sushis are directly served on a wooden counter whose part is raised.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>食器代わりにササの葉を敷く店も見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some restaurants serve sushis on a leaf of bamboo grass, instead of dishes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some restaurants serve sushis on a leaf of bamboo grass, instead of dishes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some restaurants serve sushis on a leaf of bamboo grass, instead of dishes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="28">
<j>特に酒も提供する店で、刺身の状態で提供する場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially in restaurants which serve sake, sushis are sometimes served in the state of sashimi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Especially in restaurants which serve sake, sushis are sometimes served in the state of sashimi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Especially in restaurants which serve sake, sushis are sometimes served in the state of sashimi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>(つまみ)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Nibbles for drinks).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Nibbles for drinks)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Nibbles for drinks)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="30">
<j>出前の場合には、寿司桶と呼ばれる、ふち（縁）の低い桶に盛り込む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the case of a home-delivery service, sushis are put in a bowl whose hem is low, called sushi oke (wooden bowl for sushi rice).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the case of a home-delivery service, sushis are put in a bowl with a low brim, called sushi oke (wooden bowl for sushi rice).</e>
<cmt>hem-&gt;brim</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the case of a home-delivery service, sushis are put in a bowl with a low brim, called sushi oke (wooden bowl for sushi rice).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>寿司桶は本来木製の漆器であるが、現在多くのそれは漆器を模したベークライト製である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sushi oke was originally a wooden lacquer ware, but now many of them are made of bakelite, imitating lacquer wares.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sushi oke was originally a wooden lacquer ware, but now many of them are made of bakelite, imitating lacquer wares.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sushi oke was originally a wooden lacquer ware, but now many of them are made of bakelite, imitating lacquer wares.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>寿司桶には、寿司の乾燥を防ぐためサランラップなどの食品包装用ラップフィルムが掛けられることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order for sushi not to dry, a kitchen wrap such as Saran Wrap and so on was often covered over a sushi oke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order for sushi not to dry, a kitchen wrap such as Saran Wrap often covers a sushi oke.</e>
<cmt>shortened</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order for sushi not to dry, a kitchen wrap such as Saran Wrap often covers a sushi oke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>人数分の、割箸と醤油を入れる樹脂製の小皿を添える店舗も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many restaurants put in chopsticks and resin small dishes for soy sauce of the ordered number.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many restaurants put in chopsticks and small plastic dishes for soy sauce according to the number ordered.</e>
<cmt>resin-&gt;plastic</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many restaurants put in chopsticks and small plastic dishes for soy sauce according to the number ordered.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>寿司桶は使用後に、店舗が出前先を再訪し回収する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After sushi oke is used, the restaurant revisits the customer and collect it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After a sushi oke is used, the restaurant revisits the customer to collect it.</e>
<cmt>verb conjugation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After a sushi oke is used, the restaurant revisits the customer to collect it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="35">
<j>容器を用意し、持ち帰りも可能な寿司店もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If customers bring a container, some restaurants can put sushis in it and the customers can take sushis back home.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If customers bring a container, some restaurants can put sushis in it and the customers can take it back home.</e>
<cmt>it</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If customers bring a container, some restaurants can put sushis in it and the customers can take it back home.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>回転寿司</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaitenzushi (conveyer-belt sushi).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaitenzushi (conveyer-belt sushi)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaitenzushi (conveyer-belt sushi)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="36">
<j>回転寿司はゆっくり動くベルトコンベアの上に寿司の乗った皿を載せ、店内を回して提供している店。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In kaitenzushi restaurants, sushis on a dish are served on conveyer-belts moving slowly and the dishes moves around in a restaurant.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In kaitenzushi restaurants, sushis on a dish are served on conveyor belts moving slowly and the dishes moves around the restaurant.</e>
<cmt>spelling; articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In kaitenzushi restaurants, sushis on a dish are served on conveyor belts moving slowly and the dishes moves around the restaurant.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>ベルトコンベアーの上から好きなものを自分で選んで皿を取り、食べるシステムになっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Customers take favorite dishes from conveyer-belts by themselves and eat them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Customers take dishes from conveyor belts by themselves and eat them.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Customers take dishes from conveyor belts by themselves and eat them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>勘定は皿の枚数と皿の柄などによって行われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bill is counted by the number and design of the dishes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bill is counted by the number and design of the dishes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bill is counted by the number and design of the dishes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>セントラルキッチンや寿司握りロボットを導入するなどして人件費を削減している場合が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many restaurants introduce a central kitchen system or a robot shaping sushi and so on to lower labor costs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many restaurants introduce a central kitchen system or a robot shaping sushi and so on to lower labor costs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many restaurants introduce a central kitchen system or a robot shaping sushi and so on to lower labor costs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="40">
<j>フランチャイズの店舗が多くを占める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many of them are franchise chain stores.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many of them are franchise chain stores.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many of them are franchise chain stores.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="41">
<j>詳しくは回転寿司を参照のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">See the details in the section of kaitenzushi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">See the details in the section on kaitenzushi.</e>
<cmt>prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">See the details in the section on kaitenzushi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>持ち帰り・出前専門店</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takeout, home-delivery service shop.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takeout, home-delivery service shop.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takeout, home-delivery service shop.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="42">
<j>食事をする席が設けられておらず、買った人が持ち帰る、あるいは各家庭へ出前をすることを専門とする形式の寿司屋。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a sushi shop where there are no seat for eating and customers take sushi out or there is a home-delivery service.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a sushi shop where there are no seats for eating and customers take sushi out, or there is a home-delivery service.</e>
<cmt>plural seats</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a sushi shop where there are no seats for eating and customers take sushi out, or there is a home-delivery service.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>符牒</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Secret languages.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Secret languages</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Secret languages</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="43">
<j>寿司屋では独特の言い回しがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are special phrasings in a sushi restaurant.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are special phrasings in a sushi restaurant.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are special phrasings in a sushi restaurant.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>今は客へ一般化したが、本来は寿司職人の間のみの符牒である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are now popularized among the public, but originally they were secret languages only among sushi chiefs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are now popularized among the public, but originally they were secret languages only among sushi chiefs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are now popularized among the public, but originally they were secret languages only among sushi chiefs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>客が符丁を使って店員に話しかけるのは恥ずかしいことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is shameful for customers to speak to the staffs by secret languages.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is shameful for customers to speak to the staffs in secret languages.</e>
<cmt>prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is shameful for customers to speak to the staffs in secret languages.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="46">
<j>詳しい寿司の符牒については「寿司」を参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">See &apos;Sushi&apos; section on detailed secret languages of sushi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">See &apos;Sushi&apos; for details on the secret languages of sushi.</e>
<cmt>deleted “section”</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">See &apos;Sushi&apos; for details on the secret languages of sushi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>日本国外各地における寿司屋</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sushi restaurants around the world out of Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sushi restaurants around the world outside of Japan.</e>
<cmt>prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sushi restaurants around the world outside of Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="47">
<j>「日系人オーナーは10%以下」と言われる程、中国人や韓国人など日本人以外の経営・調理による寿司屋が増加している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sushi restaurants where non-Japanese manage and cook, such as Chinese or Korean, have increased and it is said that &apos;Japanese owners are under 10%.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sushi restaurants where non-Japanese manage and cook, such as Chinese or Korean, have increased and it is said that &apos;Japanese owners are under 10%.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sushi restaurants where non-Japanese manage and cook, such as Chinese or Korean, have increased and it is said that &apos;Japanese owners are under 10%.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>そのため、日本の伝統的な寿司の調理法から大きく飛躍（あるいは逸脱）した調理法の料理までもが「スシ」として販売されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this reason, even the dishes, whose cooking method for sushi is largely out of the traditional one in Japan, are sold as &apos;sushi&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this reason, even the dishes, whose cooking method for sushi is largely out of the traditional one in Japan, are sold as &apos;sushi&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For this reason, even the dishes, whose cooking method for sushi is largely out of the traditional one in Japan, are sold as &apos;sushi&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>しかも自分の創作和食と紹介せず日本の伝統的で正式な料理方法と題しているため、日本食に詳しくない外国人に間違った日本文化を植えつけているのが問題になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, they do not call them their creative cuisine, but traditional and formal Japanese cooking methods, and thus it is problematic that wrong Japanese culture is spread among foreigners who are not familiar with Japanese foods.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, they do not call them their creative cuisine, but traditional and formal Japanese cooking methods, and thus it is problematic that wrong Japanese culture is spread among foreigners who are not familiar with Japanese foods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, they do not call them their creative cuisine, but traditional and formal Japanese cooking methods, and thus it is problematic that wrong Japanese culture is spread among foreigners who are not familiar with Japanese foods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>そのため、農林水産省が海外の日本食レストランを「正しい和食」と認証する、いわゆる「日本食を名乗る創作料理」と「伝統的な日本食」を明確にする「スシポリス」を派遣する事が検討された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this reason, Ministry of Agriculture, Forestry and Fisheries planned to send &apos;sushi police&apos; to certify Japanese food restaurants abroad as &apos;authentic Japanese food&apos; by distinguishing between so-called &apos;creative cuisine called Japanese food&apos; and &apos;traditional Japanese food.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this reason the Ministry of Agriculture, Forestry and Fisheries planned to send &apos;sushi police&apos; to certify Japanese food restaurants abroad as &apos;authentic Japanese food&apos; by distinguishing between so-called &apos;creative cuisine called Japanese food&apos; and &apos;traditional Japanese food.&apos;</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For this reason the Ministry of Agriculture, Forestry and Fisheries planned to send &apos;sushi police&apos; to certify Japanese food restaurants abroad as &apos;authentic Japanese food&apos; by distinguishing between so-called &apos;creative cuisine called Japanese food&apos; and &apos;traditional Japanese food.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>よって、海外の寿司屋が日本の寿司屋と同じかどうかは注意する必要がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, you need to be alert as to whether sushi restaurants abroad are the same as sushi restaurants in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, you need to be alert as to whether sushi restaurants abroad are the same as sushi restaurants in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, you need to be alert as to whether sushi restaurants abroad are the same as sushi restaurants in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>アメリカ合衆国</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">United States of America.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">United States of America</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">United States of America</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="52">
<j>1960年代後半、ロサンゼルスの日本人街リトル・トーキョーの「川福（かわふく）」に寿司カウンターが設置されたのが始まりとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the late 1960s &apos;Kawafuku&apos; in Japanese town Little Tokyo in Los Angeles began to install the sushi counter, which is thought to have been the beginning.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the late 1960s &apos;Kawafuku&apos; in Little Tokyo in Los Angeles to installed a sushi counter, which is thought to have been the first.</e>
<cmt>deleted a few things</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the late 1960s &apos;Kawafuku&apos; in Little Tokyo in Los Angeles to installed a sushi counter, which is thought to have been the first.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>これは、主に日本人移民を対象としていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was mainly for Japanese immigrants.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was mainly for Japanese immigrants.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was mainly for Japanese immigrants.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>その直後には、同地にレストラン「栄菊（えいぎく）」、そして「東京会館」（1990年代後半に閉店）が、それぞれアメリカで2番目、3番目のスシ・レストランとして開店した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Immediately after that, the restaurants called &apos;Sakaegiku&apos; and &apos;Tokyo Kaikan Co., Ltd.&apos; (closed during the late 1990s) were opened in the town as the second and third sushi restaurants in America.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Immediately after that, the restaurants called &apos;Sakaegiku&apos; and &apos;Tokyo Kaikan Co., Ltd.&apos; (closed during the late 1990s) were opened in the town as the second and third sushi restaurants in America.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Immediately after that, the restaurants called &apos;Sakaegiku&apos; and &apos;Tokyo Kaikan Co., Ltd.&apos; (closed during the late 1990s) were opened in the town as the second and third sushi restaurants in America.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>栄菊の経営者家族は、現在でも同地に2店の日本食レストランを経営している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The owner family of Sakaegiku runs two Japanese food restaurants in the town even now.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The owner family of Sakaegiku runs two Japanese food restaurants in the town even now.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The owner family of Sakaegiku runs two Japanese food restaurants in the town even now.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>また、東京会館の寿司職人・真下一郎は、マグロの代わりにアボカドを用いた「カリフォルニアロール」の考案者である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And Ichiro MASHITA, sushi chief in Tokyo Kaikan Co., Ltd., is an inventor of &apos;California roll&apos; which uses avocados, instead of tunas.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And Ichiro MASHITA, sushi chief in Tokyo Kaikan Co., Ltd., is inventor of the &apos;California roll&apos; which uses avocados instead of tuna.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And Ichiro MASHITA, sushi chief in Tokyo Kaikan Co., Ltd., is inventor of the &apos;California roll&apos; which uses avocados instead of tuna.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="57">
<j>アメリカ人向けに寿司を提供する寿司屋は、1980年代以降、健康食として日本食が注目されるとともに、バブル景気に至る日本の経済的進出とも相まって、大きく店数を伸ばした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The number of sushi restaurants, which serve sushi for Americans, largely increased when Japanese foods attracted attention as healthy foods and Japan economically advanced up until bubble economy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The number of sushi restaurants serving sushi for Americans largely increased when Japanese food attracted attention as healthy food and Japan economically advanced up until bubble economy.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The number of sushi restaurants serving sushi for Americans largely increased when Japanese food attracted attention as healthy food and Japan economically advanced up until bubble economy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>1983年には、ニューヨークの寿司店「初花（はつはな）」が、ニューヨーク・タイムス紙のレストラン評で最高の4ッ星を獲得、この頃までには寿司のイメージが転換していたことが窺える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1983 the sushi restaurant &apos;Hatsuhana&apos; in New York got the best four-star in the restaurant rating in The New York Times and we see that until that time the image of sushi changed</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1983 the sushi restaurant &apos;Hatsuhana&apos; in New York got the best four-star restaurant rating in The New York Times and we see that until that time the image of sushi changed.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1983 the sushi restaurant &apos;Hatsuhana&apos; in New York got the best four-star restaurant rating in The New York Times and we see that until that time the image of sushi changed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="59">
<j>一部の大都市では純粋に寿司屋専業としての出店もみられるが、日本食の看板を掲げるほぼ全てのレストランのメニューには寿司が含まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In some of big cities there are pure sushi restaurants, but the menus of almost all Japanese food restaurants include sushi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In some of big cities there are pure sushi restaurants, but the menus of almost all Japanese food restaurants include sushi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In some of big cities there are pure sushi restaurants, but the menus of almost all Japanese food restaurants include sushi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>人気のあるネタは、マグロ（スパイシーツナ）、サーモン、ブリ、ウナギなどで、油の強い食材が好まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Popular sushi toppings are oily ones such as tuna (spicy tuna), sermon, yellowtail, eel and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Popular sushi toppings are oily ones such as tuna (spicy tuna), salmon, yellowtail, eel and so on.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Popular sushi toppings are oily ones such as tuna (spicy tuna), salmon, yellowtail, eel and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>このため、ネタと一緒に揚げ玉などが使われることがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this reason, agedama (crunchy bits of deep-fried dough produced as a byproduct of cooking tempura) is sometimes used with sushi toppings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this reason, agedama (crunchy bits of deep-fried dough produced as a byproduct of cooking tempura) is sometimes used with sushi toppings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For this reason, agedama (crunchy bits of deep-fried dough produced as a byproduct of cooking tempura) is sometimes used with sushi toppings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>また海苔を好まないアメリカ人がいるために、巻物を、出来るだけ海苔が見えないように裏巻きにされる場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, as some Americans do not like nori (dried sheets of a type of red algae), sushi rolls are sometimes made as Uramaki (inside-out sushi roll) in order for nori not to be seen as much as possible.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, as some Americans do not like nori (dried sheets of a type of red algae), sushi rolls are sometimes made as Uramaki (inside-out sushi roll) in order to hide the nori as much as possible.</e>
<cmt>not to be seen-&gt;to hide</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, as some Americans do not like nori (dried sheets of a type of red algae), sushi rolls are sometimes made as Uramaki (inside-out sushi roll) in order to hide the nori as much as possible.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="63">
<j>こうした環境下における進化の結果、前述のカリフォルニアロールを始めアメリカ独自で考案された寿司も多く出現し、地方都市のスーパーマーケットですら普通に寿司が売られるほどに一般化している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result of progress under such circumstances, many sushi invented uniquely in America, such as California roll, appeared and even in supermarkets in local cities sushi is usually sold and popularized.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result of progress under such circumstances, many sushi invented uniquely in America, such as California rolls, appeared and even in supermarkets in local cities sushi is usually sold and popularized.</e>
<cmt>plural rolls</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result of progress under such circumstances, many sushi invented uniquely in America, such as California rolls, appeared and even in supermarkets in local cities sushi is usually sold and popularized.</e>
<cmt>「appeared」の前の余分なスペースの削除。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>また、寿司の人気に伴い、韓国料理や中華料理など米飯食を供するアジア料理店の一角に日本風のスシバーが設けられることも珍しくない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, with the popularization of sushi, Asian food restaurants serving rice foods, such as Korean food ones or Chinese food ones, have a Japanese-style sushi bar on the corner, which is not rare.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, with the popularization of sushi, it is not rare for Asian food restaurants serving rice foods, such as Korean food ones or Chinese food ones, have a Japanese-style sushi bar on the corner.</e>
<cmt>order of phrases</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, with the popularization of sushi, it is not rare for Asian food restaurants serving rice foods, such as Korean food ones or Chinese food ones, have a Japanese-style sushi bar on the corner.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="65">
<j>寿司職人も比較的安易に養成されている傾向があり、一例としてニューヨーク・タイムズ紙（2007年7月29日）は韓国人が主催する「寿司教室」を紹介している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sushi chiefs tend to be relatively easily trained and for an instance The New York Times (July 29 in 2007) introduces &apos;Sushi Lesson&apos; managed by Koreans.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sushi chefs tend to be relatively easily trained and, for example, The New York Times (July 29, 2007) introduced &apos;Sushi Lessons&apos; managed by Koreans.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sushi chefs tend to be relatively easily trained and, for example, The New York Times (July 29, 2007) introduced &apos;Sushi Lessons&apos; managed by Koreans.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>同教室では、1日4時間・6週間を全課程として寿司職人を養成し、学費1,000ドルでそのコースを修了した大勢の生徒はアメリカ各地の寿司屋や日本料理店のシェフになるという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In those lessons sushi chiefs are trained with the entire course of four hours per day and six weeks, and many of the students who finished the course with the tuition 1,000 dollars become chefs in sushi restaurants or Japanese food restaurants across America.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In those lessons sushi chefs are trained with the entire course of four hours per day and six weeks, and many of the students who finished the course with the tuition 1,000 dollars become chefs in sushi restaurants or Japanese food restaurants across America.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In those lessons sushi chefs are trained with the entire course of four hours per day and six weeks, and many of the students who finished the course with the tuition 1,000 dollars become chefs in sushi restaurants or Japanese food restaurants across America.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="67">
<j>近年は、日本人寿司職人を擁する本格的、もしくは高級志向の日本食レストランと、日本人以外のアジア系移民が配置された安価で気軽な日本風レストランとに二極分化する傾向が見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Recently there is a bipolar tendency of authentic or high-end Japanese foods restaurants and cheap and easy Japanese-style restaurants, where Asian immigrants are positioned.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Recently there is a bipolar tendency of authentic or high-end Japanese foods restaurants and cheap and easy Japanese-style restaurants, where Asian immigrants are positioned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Recently there is a bipolar tendency of authentic or high-end Japanese foods restaurants and cheap and easy Japanese-style restaurants, where Asian immigrants are positioned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>ドイツ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Germany.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Germany</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Germany</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="68">
<j>日本人駐在員の多い都市には寿司屋が存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There exist sushi restaurants in the cities where many Japanese resident officers live.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There exist sushi restaurants in the cities where many Japanese resident officers live.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There exist sushi restaurants in the cities where many Japanese resident officers live.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>日本人があまりいない・行かない都市では、イタリア料理など日本食と関係のない店で、日本へ行ったことのあるシェフが見よう見まねで作った寿司がオードブルとしてメニューに入っていることがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the cities where many Japanese do not live or do not often go, the restaurants such as Italian one, which do not have a relation with Japanese foods, have sushis as hors d&apos;oeuvre in the menus, which the chefs made by following someone&apos;s example.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the cities where many Japanese do not live or do not often go, the restaurants such as Italian ones, which do not have a relation with Japanese foods, have sushis as hors d&apos;oeuvre in the menus, which the chefs made by following someone&apos;s example.</e>
<cmt>ones</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the cities where many Japanese do not live or do not often go, the restaurants such as Italian ones, which do not have a relation with Japanese foods, have sushis as hors d&apos;oeuvre in the menus, which the chefs made by following someone&apos;s example.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>外観が似ている以外、寿司とは全く別の料理といっていい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Except for similar appearance, they are totally different dishes from sushis.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Except for similar appearance, they are totally different dishes from sushis.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Except for similar appearance, they are totally different dishes from sushis.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>台湾</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taiwan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taiwan</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taiwan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="71">
<j>台湾伝統の屋台で寿司屋がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some of traditional food stalls in Taiwan serve sushi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some traditional food stalls in Taiwan serve sushi.</e>
<cmt>prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some traditional food stalls in Taiwan serve sushi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>回転寿司も見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are also kaitenzushi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are also kaitenzushi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are also kaitenzushi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>アフリカ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Africa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Africa</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Africa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="73">
<j>少なくとも南アフリカ共和国内に25軒、エジプト国内に5軒、モーリシャス国内に4軒、ケニア国内に2軒の寿司屋が営業している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are at least 25 sushi restaurants in the Republic of South Africa, 5 in Egypt, 4 in Mauritius and 2 in Kenya.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are at least 25 sushi restaurants in the Republic of South Africa, 5 in Egypt, 4 in Mauritius and 2 in Kenya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are at least 25 sushi restaurants in the Republic of South Africa, 5 in Egypt, 4 in Mauritius and 2 in Kenya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>（2007年1月現在）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(As of January in 2007).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(As of January in 2007)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(As of January in 2007)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>南極</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Antarctica.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Antarctica</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Antarctica</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="75">
<j>昭和基地内の食堂で寿司が提供されることがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sometimes sushis are served in the dining hall in Showa Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sometimes sushis are served in the dining hall in Showa Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sometimes sushis are served in the dining hall in Showa Station.</e>
<cmt>文末にピリオドを付けました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>基地内のバーカウンターを使用して寿司屋のカウンターに擬する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bar counter in the Station is used as the counter in a sushi restaurant.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bar counter in the Station is used as the counter in a sushi restaurant.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bar counter in the Station is used as the counter in a sushi restaurant.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>但し、ネタは南極観測船及び基地内の冷凍庫の仕様から、零下20度で冷凍保存することが出来るものに限られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, sushi toppings are limited to the ones which can be frozen and kept below zero because of the spec of freezers in Antarctica station vessel or station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, sushi toppings are limited to the ones which can be frozen and kept below zero because of the spec of freezers in the Antarctica station or vessels.</e>
<cmt>repetitive station</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, sushi toppings are limited to the ones which can be frozen and kept below zero because of the spec of freezers in the Antarctica station or vessels.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>このためマグロや生サバなどは提供することが出来ず、サーモン、カツオ、イカ、タコ、エビ、卵焼き等が中心となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this reason tuna or raw mackerel can not be served and mainly sermon, bonito, squid, octopus, shrimp, fried egg and so on are served.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this reason tuna or raw mackerel can not be served and mainly salmon, bonito, squid, octopus, shrimp, fried egg and so on are served.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For this reason tuna or raw mackerel can not be served and mainly salmon, bonito, squid, octopus, shrimp, fried egg and so on are served.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Monaneko(id:28864), 妖精書士(id:101212), Papamaruchan22(id:71152), ととりん(id:31982), J8takagi(id:20409), （あ）(id:81659), Mishika(id:276), No Barnstar Required(id:102665), Yatobi(id:9686), 00ykj00(id:104284), Himetv(id:21833), Opponent(id:720), Fryed-peach(id:63402), 氷鷺(id:73707), 竃馬(id:102733), たまけん(id:117243), 306E(id:132257), Knua(id:66861), Point136(id:211299), 獅子の鬣(id:147190), わたあめひみつ(id:81640), やすとし(id:63220), Totti(id:35433), Comyu(id:58135), Peek-poke(id:68004), Excavator(id:25917), Remington(id:98835), っ(id:4481), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>