<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>不落不落</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Burabura</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Burabura</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Burabura</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>不落不落、不落々々（ぶらぶら）は、鳥山石燕の妖怪画集『百器徒然袋』に描かれている日本の妖怪の一種で、提灯の妖怪。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Burabura is a lantern specter, which is a Japanese specter portrayed in &quot;Hyakki Tsurezure Bukuro&quot; (One hundred bags in idlenss) by Sekien TORIYAMA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Burabura is a lantern specter and one of Japanese yokai (ghosts, spirits and monsters) that was portrayed in Sekien TORIYAMA&apos;s yokai art collection book: &quot;Hyakki Tsurezure Bukuro&quot; (The Bag of One Hundred Random Demons; the term &apos;hyakki&apos; in its title is a pun on the usual hyakki, replacing the character for demon which is written as &quot;鬼&quot; in Japanese with a character for vessel written as &quot;器,&quot; and sure enough, most of the yokais shown in this book are tsukumogami [a type of Japanese spirits that originate in items or artifacts that have reached their 100th birthday and become alive]).</e>
<cmt>補足訳</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Burabura is a lantern specter and one of Japanese yokai (ghosts, spirits and monsters) that was portrayed in Sekien TORIYAMA&apos;s yokai art collection book: &quot;Hyakki Tsurezure Bukuro&quot; (The Bag of One Hundred Random Demons; the term &apos;hyakki&apos; in its title is a pun on the usual hyakki, replacing the character for demon which is written as &quot;鬼&quot; in Japanese with a character for vessel written as &quot;器,&quot; and sure enough, most of the yokais shown in this book are tsukumogami [a type of Japanese spirits that originate in items or artifacts that have reached their 100th birthday and become alive]).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>『百器徒然袋』中にある石燕の解説文によれば、外観は提灯の火だが、実体は狐火とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Sekien&apos;s commentary in &quot;Hyakki Tsurezure Bukuro,&quot; it appears lantern; however, it is actually a will-o&apos;-the-wisp.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Sekien&apos;s commentary in the &quot;Hyakki Tsurezure Bukuro,&quot; the Burabura looks like a lantern light, however, it is actually believed to be a Kitsune-bi (a Japanese will-o&apos;-the-wisp).</e>
<cmt>用語、表現</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Sekien&apos;s commentary in the &quot;Hyakki Tsurezure Bukuro,&quot; the Burabura looks like a lantern light, however, it is actually believed to be a Kitsune-bi (a Japanese will-o&apos;-the-wisp).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>なお提灯の妖怪は有名な割に伝承資料に乏しい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are few traditional references about the lantern specter although it is a popular specter.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。用語集によると鬼火と狐火は同訳でした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are few references on lore of the lantern yokai despite its popularity.</e>
<cmt>用語</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are few references on lore of the lantern yokai despite its popularity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>しかし提灯お化けのような妖怪ではなく、狐火や提灯火のような怪火として伝承されていることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it may be often passed down as a fire of mysterious or suspicious origin, such as a will-o&apos;-the-wisp.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the lantern yokai has often been reported not as a Chochin Obake (literally, lantern ghost) but as a fire of mysterious or suspicious origin, such as the kitsune-bi and chochin-bi (lantern light).</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ。原文「鬼火鬼火の種類」はリンク先表示ですので、wiki原文に準じて「提灯火」と修正し、再訳出しました。http://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E4%B8%8D%E8%90%BD%E4%B8%8D%E8%90%BD</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the lantern yokai has often been reported not as a Chochin Obake (literally, lantern ghost) but as a fire of mysterious or suspicious origin, such as the kitsune-bi and chochin-bi (lantern light).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>器物の妖怪として描かれていることから、解説文のような狐火の妖怪ではなく、俗にいう提灯お化けの一種と見なす方が妥当とする意見もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since it is portrayed as a specter of an object, some say that it should not be considered as a specter of will-o&apos;-the-wisp like described in the commentary, but as commonly known lantern ghost.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since it is portrayed as a yokai of items and artifacts, some say that it should not be considered as a kitsune-bi yokai as described in the commentary but as a variation of the so-called Chochin Obake.</e>
<cmt>用語、表現の正確性</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since it is portrayed as a yokai of items and artifacts, some say that it should not be considered as a kitsune-bi yokai as described in the commentary but as a variation of the so-called Chochin Obake.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 逃亡者(id:14864), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>