<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>鬼童丸</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kidomaru</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kidomaru</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kidomaru</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>鬼童丸、鬼同丸（きどうまる）は、鎌倉時代の説話集『古今著聞集』などに登場する鬼。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kidomaru is an oni (creature from Japanese folklore) that appears in Kamakura period texts such as the collection of stories entitled &quot;Kokon Chomonshu&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kidomaru is an oni (creature from Japanese folklore) that appears in Kamakura period texts such as the collection of stories entitled &quot;Kokon Chomonshu&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kidomaru is an oni (or ogre, a creature from Japanese folklore) that appears in Kamakura period texts such as the collection of stories entitled &quot;Kokon Chomonshu&quot; (A collection of Tales Heard, Past and Present).</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>『古今著聞集』には以下のように記述されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kokon Chomonshu&quot; states the following.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kokon Chomonshu&quot; states the following.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Kokon Chomonshu&quot; states the following.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>酒呑童子討伐で知られる武将・源頼光が弟・源頼信の家へ行ったとき、厠に鬼童丸が捕えられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the military commander MINAMOTO no Yorimitsu known for the subjugation of Shuten Doji went to the home of his younger brother, MINAMOTO no Yorinobu, he caught Kidomaru in the toilet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the military commander MINAMOTO no Yorimitsu known for the subjugation of Shuten Doji went to the home of his younger brother, MINAMOTO no Yorinobu, he caught Kidomaru in the toilet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the military commander MINAMOTO no Yorimitsu known for the subjugation of Shuten Doji went to the home of his younger brother, MINAMOTO no Yorinobu, Kidomaru was caught in the toilet.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>頼光は、無用心だから鎖でしっかり縛っておくようにと頼信に言い、その晩は頼信の家に泊まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Yorimitsu was careless, Yorinobu reminded him to fasten the chain securely and spent the night in the house.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Yorimitsu was careless, Yorinobu reminded him to fasten the chain securely and spent the night in the house.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yorimitsu told Yorinobu to put it into chains tightly for sure and spent the night at Yorinobu&apos;s residence.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>鬼童丸は縛めの鎖をたやすく引きちぎり、頼光を怨んで彼の寝床を覗いて様子を窺った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kidomaru escaped from the chain with ease, cursed Yorimitsu and spied on him in his bed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kidomaru escaped from the chain with ease, cursed Yorimitsu and spied on him in his bed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kidomaru escaped from the chain with ease, cursed Yorimitsu and spied on him in his bed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>頼光はこれに気づき、従者たちに「明日は鞍馬に参詣する」と言った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yorimitsu became aware of this and told his attendants that &quot;Tomorrow I will go to pray at Kurama&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yorimitsu became aware of this and told his attendants that &quot;Tomorrow I will go to pray at Kurama&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yorimitsu became aware of this and told his attendants that &apos;Tomorrow I will go to pray at Kurama.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>そこで鬼童丸は鞍馬に先回りし、市原野で放し飼いの1頭の牛を殺して体内に隠れ、頼光を待ち受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kidomaru then went on ahead to Kurama and killed a grazing ox at Ichiharano and hid inside the body where he awaited Yorimitsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kidomaru then went on ahead to Kurama and killed a grazing ox at Ichiharano and hid inside the body where he awaited Yorimitsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kidomaru then went on ahead to Kurama and killed a free-range ox at Ichiharano and hid inside the body where he awaited Yorimitsu.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>しかし頼光はこれをも見抜き、頼光の命を受けた渡辺綱が弓矢で牛を射抜いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Yorimitsu discovered Kidomaru&apos;s plan and he ordered WATANABE no Tsuna to shoot an arrow into the ox.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Yorimitsu discovered Kidomaru&apos;s plan and he ordered WATANABE no Tsuna to shoot an arrow into the ox.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Yorimitsu discovered Kidomaru&apos;s plan and he ordered WATANABE no Tsuna to shoot an arrow into the ox.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>牛の中から鬼童丸が現れて頼光に斬りかかってきたが、頼光が一刀のもとに鬼童丸を斬り捨てたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kidomaru emerged from the ox&apos;s carcass and attempted to attack Yorimitsu but it is said that Yorimitsu cut him down with a single blow.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kidomaru emerged from the ox&apos;s carcass and attempted to attack Yorimitsu but it is said that Yorimitsu cut him down with a single blow.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kidomaru emerged from the ox&apos;s carcass and attempted to attack Yorimitsu but it is said that Yorimitsu cut him down with a single blow.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>鳥山石燕の妖怪画集『今昔百鬼拾遺』には「鬼童」と題し、鬼童丸が雪の中で牛の皮をかぶり、市原野で頼光を待ち受ける姿が描かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sekien TORIYAMA&apos;s book of images of ghosts and demons, &quot;Konjaku Hyakki Shui&quot; (Supplement to The Hundred Demons from the Present and the Past), refers to Kidomaru as &apos;Kido&apos; and depicts him in the snow wearing an ox hide awaiting Yoshimitsu at Ichiharano.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sekien TORIYAMA&apos;s book of images of ghosts and demons, &quot;Konjaku Hyakki Shui&quot; (Supplement to The Hundred Demons from the Present and the Past), refers to Kidomaru as &apos;Kido&apos; and depicts him in the snow wearing an ox hide awaiting Yoshimitsu at Ichiharano.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sekien TORIYAMA&apos;s book of images of ghosts and demons, &quot;Konjaku Hyakki Shui&quot; (Supplement to The Hundred Demons from the Present and the Past), refers to Kidomaru as &apos;Kido&apos; and depicts him in the snow wearing an ox hide awaiting Yorimitsu at Ichiharano.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="11">
<j>鬼童丸の話はこの『古今著聞集』がよく知られているものの、ほかにも武者絵本類や伝承などで様々に伝えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This &quot;Kokon Chomonshu&quot; story of Kidomaru is well known but other tales appear in musha-e (prints depicting battle scenes and heroic armored warriors.) books and legends.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This &quot;Kokon Chomonshu&quot; story of Kidomaru is well known but other tales appear in musha-e (prints depicting battle scenes and heroic armored warriors.) books and legends.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This &quot;Kokon Chomonshu&quot; story of Kidomaru is well known but other tales appear in musha-e (prints depicting battle scenes and heroic armored warriors.) books and legends.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>京都府福知山市雲原の口碑では、鬼童丸は酒呑童子の子として以下のように伝承されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following legend about Kidomaru being the child of Shuten Doji is told in the folklore of Fukuchiyama City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following legend about Kidomaru being the child of Shuten Doji is told in the folklore of Fukuchiyama City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following legend about Kidomaru being the child of Shuten Doji is told in the folklore of Kumohara, Fukuchiyama City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>Kumoharaを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>源頼光が酒呑童子を討ち取った後、酒呑童子に捕われていた女子供たちは故郷へと帰されたが、その中の1人の女は精神に異常を来たしており、故郷へ帰ることができず、雲原で酒呑童子の子供を産んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After MINAMOTO no Yorimitsu captured Shuten Doji, the young women who had been held captive by oni were returned home but of them developed a mental abnormality, becoming unable to return to her home and later giving birth to Shuten Doji&apos;s child in Kumohara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After MINAMOTO no Yorimitsu captured Shuten Doji, the young women who had been held captive by oni were returned home but one of them developed a mental abnormality, becoming unable to return to her home and later giving birth to Shuten Doji&apos;s child in Kumohara.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After MINAMOTO no Yorimitsu killed Shuten Doji, the young women who had been held captive by Shuten Doji were returned home but one of them developed a mental abnormality, becoming unable to return to her home and later giving birth to Shuten Doji&apos;s child in Kumohara.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>その子供は産まれながらにして歯が生えそろっており、7、8歳の頃には石を投げてシカやイノシシを仕留めて食べていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This baby grew teeth while being born and at around the ages of seven and eight he would kill deer and wild boar by throwing stones before eating them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This baby grew teeth while being born and at around the ages of seven and eight he would kill deer and wild boar by throwing stones before eating them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This baby grew teeth while being born and at around the ages of seven and eight he would kill deer and wild boar by throwing stones to eat them.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>やがてこの子供が成長して鬼童丸となり、父の仇として頼光たちを狙うようになったのだという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This child eventually grew up to become Kidomaru and it is said that he targeted Yorimitsu in revenge for his father.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This child eventually grew up to become Kidomaru and it is said that he targeted Yorimitsu in revenge for his father.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This child eventually grew up to become Kidomaru and it is said that he targeted Yorimitsu in revenge for his father.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="16">
<j>また軍記物語『前太平記』などによる別説では、酒呑童子が捨て童子であったという説と同様、もとは鬼童丸も比叡山の稚児であり、悪行が災いして比叡山を追われたため、山中の洞穴に移り住んで盗賊となったともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Similar to other stories claiming that Kidomaru was a child abandoned by Shuten Doji, other accounts of Kidomaru according to texts such as the military tale &quot;Zen Taiheiki&quot; state that he was originally a chigo (a boy kept by a pederast) on Mt. Hiei but that his wrongdoings caused him to be expelled from the mountain after which he dwelled in a cave in the mountains and became a thief.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Similar to other stories claiming that Kidomaru was a child abandoned by Shuten Doji, other accounts of Kidomaru according to texts such as the military tale &quot;Zen Taiheiki&quot; state that he was originally a chigo (a boy kept by a pederast) on Mt. Hiei but that his wrongdoings caused him to be expelled from the mountain after which he dwelled in a cave in the mountains and became a thief.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Similar to other stories claiming that Kidomaru was a child abandoned by Shuten Doji, other accounts of Kidomaru according to texts such as the military tale &quot;Zen Taiheiki&quot; state that he was originally a chigo (a boy kept by a pederast) on Mt. Hiei but that his wrongdoings caused him to be expelled from the mountain after which he dwelled in a cave in the mountains and became a thief.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="17">
<j>曲亭馬琴による『四天王剿盗異録』では鬼童丸が山中の洞窟で、『今昔物語集』などにある盗賊・袴垂に会って術比べをする場面がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Kyokutei Bakin&apos;s &quot;Shitenno Shoto Iroku&quot;, Kidomaru met the thief Hakamadare described in &quot;Konjaku Monogatarishu&quot; (Anthology of Tales from the Past) at his mountain cave and competed in a magic competition.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Kyokutei Bakin&apos;s &quot;Shitenno Shoto Iroku&quot;, Kidomaru met the thief Hakamadare described in &quot;Konjaku Monogatarishu&quot; (Anthology of Tales from the Past) at his mountain cave and competed in a magic competition.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Bakin KYOKUTEI&apos;s &quot;Shitenno Shoto Iroku&quot; (picaresque novel of the life of Yasusuke HAKAMADARE, a robber), Kidomaru met the thief Hakamadare described in &quot;Konjaku Monogatarishu&quot; (Anthology of Tales from the Past) at his mountain cave and competed in a magic competition.</e>
<cmt>用語を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>これを描いた作品に、歌川国芳による『鬼童丸』や月岡芳年の『袴垂保輔鬼童丸術競図』などの浮世絵がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Images depicting this scene include the ukiyo-e &quot;Kidomaru&quot; by Kuniyoshi UTAGAWA and &quot;Hakamadare Yasusuke Kidomaru Jutsukurabe no Zu&quot; by Yoshitoshi TSUKIOKA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Images depicting this scene include the ukiyo-e &quot;Kidomaru&quot; by Kuniyoshi UTAGAWA and &quot;Hakamadare Yasusuke Kidomaru Jutsukurabe no Zu&quot; by Yoshitoshi TSUKIOKA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Images depicting this scene include the ukiyo-e &quot;Kidomaru&quot; by Kuniyoshi UTAGAWA and &quot;Hakamadare Yasusuke Kidomaru Jutsukurabe no Zu&quot; (battle picture of Yasusuke HAKAMADARE and Kidomaru) by Yoshitoshi TSUKIOKA.</e>
<cmt>用語を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 逃亡者(id:14864), 健ちゃん(id:60346), ポン(id:91676), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>