<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>出作</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Desaku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Desaku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Desaku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>出作（でさく/でつくり）とは、ある地域の住民が別の地域にある田畑を耕作することを指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Desaku, also referred to as Detsukuri (literally going out to plow) means that inhabitants in a region cultivate the fields in other regions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Desaku, also referred to as Detsukuri (literally, going out to plow) means that inhabitants in a region cultivate fields in other regions.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Desaku, also referred to as Detsukuri (literally, going out to plow) means that inhabitants in a region cultivate fields in other regions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>耕作先の側からは入作（いりさく）と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is called Irisaku (coming in to plow) by those who accept the farmers from other regions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is called Irisaku (coming in to plow) by those who accept the farmers from other regions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is called Irisaku (coming in to plow) by those who accept the farmers from other regions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>古代から中世にかけては、特定の所領（公領・荘園）に属する住民が、別の所領内にある田畑を耕作することを指した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From ancient times to the Middle Ages, it meant inhabitants who belonged to a certain shoryo (territory) (Koryo or Shoen) cultivated the fields in other shoryo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From ancient times to the Middle Ages, it meant inhabitants who belonged to a certain shoryo (territory) (Koryo or Shoen) but cultivated fields in other shoryo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From ancient times to the Middle Ages, it meant inhabitants who belonged to a certain shoryo (territory) (Koryo or Shoen) but cultivated fields in other shoryo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>法的な土地所有者と現地における実際の権利関係が錯綜して安定していなかった古代・中世期にはこうした現象は多く存在した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This phenomenon was often observed during ancient times and the Middle Ages, when the rights of a legal land owner and an actual lord of the land were intricated and unstable.</e>
<cmt>「現地における実際の」は「実際の現地の支配者」ととらえてactual lord of the landとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This phenomenon often occurred during ancient times and the Middle Ages, when the rights of a legal land owner and an actual lord of the land were intricate and unstable.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This phenomenon often occurred during ancient times and the Middle Ages, when the rights of a legal land owner and an actual lord of the land were intricate and unstable.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>貢租に関しては公事・在家役は居住地の領主に帰属し、年貢・官物は耕作地の領主に帰属する原則であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for koso (annual tax), Kuji and Zaikeyaku (public duties) were supposed to be paid to the lord of the land where an inhabitant lived while Nengu (land tax) and Kanmotsu (tribute goods paid as taxes or tithes) to the lord of the land where an inhabitant cultivated the filelds.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for koso (annual tax), Kuji and Zaikeyaku (public duties) were supposed to be paid to the lord of the land where an inhabitant lived but Nengu (land tax) and Kanmotsu (tribute goods paid as taxes or tithes) were to be paid to the lord of the land in which the individual cultivated the fields.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for koso (annual tax), Kuji and Zaikeyaku (public duties) were supposed to be paid to the lord of the land where an inhabitant lived but Nengu (land tax) and Kanmotsu (tribute goods paid as taxes or tithes) were to be paid to the lord of the land in which the individual cultivated the fields.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>しかし、堺相論などが盛んになると、それは領民と土地の一元支配を名目として支配地域拡大を図る居住地側領主と耕作者の取り込みを図る耕作地側領主による対立の一因となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as conflicts over the territory were getting intensified, koso became a cause of the conflicts between lords of the lands where farmers lived and where farmers worked because the former intended to expand their territory by ruling unitarily over the inhabitants and the lands and the latter aimed to invite more farmers into their territory to work.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as conflicts over the territory intensified, koso became a cause of conflicts between the lords of the lands where farmers lived and where the farmers worked, because the former intended to expand their territory by ruling unitarily over the inhabitants and the lands but the latter aimed to invite more farmers into their territory to work.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as conflicts over the territory intensified, koso became a cause of conflicts between the lords of the lands where farmers lived and where the farmers worked, because the former intended to expand their territory by ruling unitarily over the inhabitants and the lands but the latter aimed to invite more farmers into their territory to work.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>近世になると、新田開発によって本村に住む農民が居住地をそのままとして新田側に出作する例が多くなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In modern times, when more lands were reclaimed, more farmers living in a village went out to a newly developed field to plow, leaving their village well alone.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In modern times, when more lands were reclaimed, more farmers living in villages went out to newly developed fields to plow, leaving their villages quite alone.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In modern times, when more lands were reclaimed, more farmers living in villages went out to newly developed fields to plow, leaving their villages quite alone.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>当該農民は本村・新田それぞれの耕地において年貢負担を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this case, the farmers paid Nengu to both lords of their home village and their working fields.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this case, the farmers paid Nengu to both lords of their home village and their working fields.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this case, the farmers paid Nengu to both lords of their home village and their working fields.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Zw105000(id:144931), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>