<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>精霊流し</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shoronagashi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoronagashi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoronagashi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>精霊流し（しょうろうながし）とは、長崎県の各地でお盆に行なわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shoronagashi is an event held during the Obon festival (a Festival of the Dead or Buddhist All Soul&apos;s Day in mid-August) in different parts of Nagasaki Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処置event と memorial service の両方を使うために分けました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoronagashi is an event held during the Obon festival (a Festival of the Dead or Buddhist All Soul&apos;s Day in mid-August) in different parts of Nagasaki Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoronagashi is an event held during the Obon festival (a Festival of the Dead or Buddhist All Soul&apos;s Day in mid-August) in different parts of Nagasaki Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>死者の魂を弔って送る行事のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a memorial and farewell service for the spirits of the deceased.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a memorial and farewell service for the spirits of the deceased.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a memorial and farewell service for the spirits of the deceased.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>長崎市をはじめ、長崎県内各地でお盆に行われる伝統行事である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a traditional event held in various parts of Nagasaki Prefecture during the Obon festival.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a traditional event held in various parts of Nagasaki Prefecture during the Obon festival.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a traditional event held in various parts of Nagasaki Prefecture during the Obon festival.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>初盆を迎えた故人の家族らが、盆提灯や造花などで飾られた精霊船（しょうろうぶね）と呼ばれる船に故人の霊を乗せて、流し場と呼ばれる終着点まで運ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At hatsubon (first obon following the death of a family member) of the deceased, the surviving family members tow boats called shorobune, which are decorated with bon-lanterns and imitation flowers and are believed to hold the spirits of the deceased on board, to a terminal spot called nagashiba.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At hatsubon (first obon following the death of a family member) of the deceased, the surviving family members tow boats called shorobune, which are decorated with bon-lanterns and imitation flowers and are believed to hold the spirits of the deceased on board, to a terminal spot called the nagashiba.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the first obon following the death of a family member (hatsubon) the surviving family members tow boats called shorobune, which are decorated with bon-lanterns and imitation flowers and are believed to hold the spirits of the deceased on board, to a place called the nagashiba.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="6">
<j>毎年8月15日の夕刻から開催され、爆竹の破裂音・鉦の音・掛け声が交錯する喧騒のなかで行われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It starts at the dusk of August 15 every year in the bustle of shouts, sounds of gongs, and blasts of firecrackers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It starts at the dusk of August 15 every year amidst the bustle of shouts, sounds of gongs, and blasts of firecrackers.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It starts at the dusk of August 15 every year amidst the bustle of shouts, sounds of gongs, and blasts of firecrackers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>精霊船は山車を連想させる華美なものであり、見物客が集まる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The shorobune boats are decorated luxuriously enough like floats to attract viewers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shorobune boats are decorated so luxuriously they are like floats and attract viewers.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The shorobune boats are decorated so luxuriously like floats and attract a large audience.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>「祭り」と誤解されることもあるが、あくまでも故人を追悼する仏教の行事である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is often taken as a &apos;festival,&apos; but it is actually a Buddhist memorial service for the deceased.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is often misinterpreted as a festival, but it is actually a Buddhist memorial service for the deceased.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is often misinterpreted as a festival, but it is actually a Buddhist memorial service for the deceased.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="9">
<j>初盆でない場合は精霊船は作らず、わらを束ねた小さなこもに花や果物（供物）を包み、流し場に持っていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Families who do not bear hatsubon do not make shorobune, and instead, they bring flowers and fruits (offerings) wrapped inside small bundles of straws to nagashiba.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Families who do not bear hatsubon do not make shorobune, and instead, they bring flowers and fruits (offerings) wrapped inside small bundles of straws to nagashiba.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Families who do not bear hatsubon do not make shorobune, and instead, they bring flowers and fruits (offerings) wrapped inside small bundles of straws to nagashiba.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>精霊船や供物は、以前は実際に海へと流されていたが、長崎市では1871年（明治4年）に禁止された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They used to release shorobune and offerings on water towards the sea, but the practice was banned in Nagasaki City in 1871.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They used to release shorobune and offerings on water towards the sea, but the practice was banned in Nagasaki City in 1871.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They used to release shorobune and offerings on water towards the sea, but the practice was banned in Nagasaki City in 1871.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>精霊船も水に浮かぶような構造にはなっていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shorobune are not made to float on water now.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shorobune are no longer made to float on water.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shorobune are no longer made to float on water.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>現在でも島原市、西海市、松浦市、五島市などでは、実際に川面や海上に浮かべることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even today, they sometimes put shorobune afloat on rivers or on the sea in Shimabara City, Saikai City, Matsuura City, and Goto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even today, they sometimes set shorobune afloat on rivers or on the sea in Shimabara City, Saikai City, Matsuura City, and Goto City.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even today, they sometimes set shorobune afloat on rivers or on the sea in Shimabara City, Saikai City, Matsuura City, and Goto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="13">
<j>長崎市には長崎くんちという祭りがあり、精霊船の造りはくんちの出しものの一つである曳物に似ている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagasaki City has a festival called Nagasaki-kunchi Festival, hikimono (floats) of which have a structure that resembles that of shorobune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagasaki City has a festival called Nagasaki-kunchi Festival, the hikimono (floats) of which have a structure that resembles that of the shorobune.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagasaki City has a festival called Nagasaki-kunchi Festival, the hikimono (floats) of which have a structure that resembles that of the shorobune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="14">
<j>曳物は山車を引き回すことがパフォーマンスで行われており、精霊船をそれを真似て引き回すことが一部で行われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those floats are often pulled around in a circular motion to show off at Nabasaki-kunchi Festival, so some towing people of shorobune imitate them to do similar acts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those floats are often pulled around in a circular motion to show off at Nabasaki-kunchi Festival, so those that tow shorobune imitate them to give a similar effect.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those floats are often pulled around in a circular motion in the performance, so some people who tow shorobune imitate them to give a similar effect.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。原文に合わせて「at Nabasaki-kunchi Festival」をのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>郷土史家の越中哲也は長崎放送の録画中継の中で「難破船になるですばい」と毎年、出演の旅に「悪しき行為」と解説している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tetsuya ECCHU, a local history researcher, says &apos;They may shipwreck,&apos; and comments on those acts as &apos;bad behaviors&apos; when he comes on a videotaping show of Nagasaki Broadcasting Company every year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Every year, Tetsuya ECCHU, a local history researcher, regulalry says &apos;They may wreck them,&apos; and considers that act as &apos;bad behavior&apos; when he appears on a videotaped show of Nagasaki Broadcasting Company.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Every year, Tetsuya ETCHU, a local history researcher, regularly comments that &apos;They may wreck them,&apos; and considers that act as &apos;bad behavior&apos; when he appears on a videotaped show of Nagasaki Broadcasting Company.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>この行為は一般的には好ましい行為と見られておらず、警察も精霊船を回す行為には制止を行っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many people do not like these behaviors; police usually restrain acts of pulling around shorobune in a circular motion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many people do not like this behavior; and, the police usually come down on acts of pulling around shorobune in a circular motion.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many people do not like this behavior and the police usually caution people engaging in such behavior.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。スペースをのぞきスペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="17">
<j>代表的な流し場である長崎市の大波止には、精霊船を解体する重機が置かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At Ohato (大波止) in Nagasaki City, a typical nagashiba, a heavy machine is ready to disassemble shorobune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At Ohato (大波止) in Nagasaki City, a typical nagashiba, a heavy machine is ready to disassemble shorobune.</e>
<cmt>word in red lettering requires explanation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At Ohato in Nagasaki City, a typical nagashiba, a heavy machine is ready to disassemble shorobune.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。「流し場nagashiba」は前出で説明されているため、補足をのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>家族、親類らにより盆提灯や遺影、位牌など、家に持ち帰る品々が取り外され、船の担ぎ（曳き）手の合掌の中、その場で破壊される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After families and relatives of the deceased remove what are supposed to be kept at home, such as bon lanterns, photos of the deceased, Buddhist mortuary tablets, shorobune will be dismantled on site as the pullers of shorobune join their hands in prayer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After families and relatives of the deceased remove what are supposed to be kept at home, such as bon lanterns, photos of the deceased, Buddhist mortuary tablets, shorobune will be dismantled on site as the pullers of shorobune join their hands in prayer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After families and relatives of the deceased remove what are supposed to be kept at home, such as bon lanterns, photos of the deceased and the Buddhist mortuary tablets, the shorobune will be dismantled on site as the pullers of shorobune join their hands in prayer.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>遺族にとっては悲しい瞬間である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Surviving family members watch this in sorrow.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Surviving family members watch this in sorrow.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Surviving family members watch this in sorrow.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="20">
<j>精霊船</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shorobune</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shorobune</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shorobune</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="21">
<j>精霊船は大きく2つに分けることができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shorobune are categorized into two types.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shorobune are categorized into two types.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shorobune are categorized into two types.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>個人船と「もやい船」と呼ばれる自治会など地縁組織が合同で出す船である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One type is personal one, and the other type is a jointly sponsored boat called &apos;moyai-bune&apos; which is built by a local connection organization, such as a neighborhood residents&apos; association.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One type is a personal one, and the other type is a jointly sponsored boat called &apos;moyai-bune&apos; which is built by a local organization, such as a neighborhood residents&apos; association.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some boats are private ones while some are jointly sponsored boats called &apos;moyai-bune&apos; which are built by local organizations, such as a neighborhood residents&apos; associations.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>個人で精霊船を流すのが一般的になったのは、戦後のことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was after the Second World War that personal shorobune became common.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was after the Second World War that personal shorobune became common.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was after the Second World War that personal shorobune became common.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>昭和30年代以前は「もやい船」が主流であり、個人で船を1艘つくるのは、富裕層に限られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before 1955, most shorobune were &apos;moyai-bune,&apos; and only rich people made personal shorobune of each family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before 1955, most shorobune were &apos;moyai-bune,&apos; and only rich people made personal shorobune of each family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Up until 1955, most shorobune were &apos;moyai-bune&apos; and only rich people made family shorobune boats.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="25">
<j>もやい船、個人船に限らず「大きな船」「立派な船」を出すことが、ステータスと考えている人もいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some people believe making big and glamorous shorobune proves their social status regardless of Moyai-bune or personal ones.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some people believe making big and glamorous shorobune proves their social status regardless of Moyai-bune or personal ones.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some people believe making &apos;big&apos; and &apos;glamorous&apos; shorobune proves their social status, whether the boats are private or moyai-bune.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。クォーテーション補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>現代でも「もやい船」の伝統は息づいており、自治会で流す船のほか、病院や葬祭業者が音頭をとり流す船もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The tradition of &apos;moyai-bune&apos; is active today, examples of which are the shorobune construction led by hospitals or funeral companies in addition to those of local associations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The tradition of &apos;moyai-bune&apos; is active today, examples of which are the shorobune construction led by hospitals or funeral companies in addition to those of local associations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The tradition of &apos;moyai-bune&apos; is active today, examples of which are the shorobune construction led by hospitals or funeral companies in addition to those of local associations.</e>
<cmt>‘→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>また、人だけでなく、ペットのために流す船もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some shorobune are for pets.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some shorobune are for pets.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some shorobune are for pets.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="28">
<j>流し場までの列は家紋入りの提灯を持った喪主や、町の提灯を持った責任者を先頭に、長い竿の先に趣向を凝らした灯篭をつけた「印灯篭」と呼ばれる目印を持った若者、鉦、その後に、そろいの白の法被で決めた大人が数人がかりで担ぐ精霊船が続く（「担ぐ」といっても船の下に車輪をつけたものが多く、実際には「曳く」ことが多い）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A procession to nagashiba is headed by hosts of the funerals holding lanterns with their family crests and town caretakers holding their town lanterns, followed by young people holding long marker poles with an elaborate lantern on the top end called &apos;shirushi toro,&apos; gongs, and at the end the shorobune carried by several adult people clad with uniform white happi coats (workman&apos;s livery coats) (&apos;carry&apos; may not be an appropriate word, because most shorobune have wheels, so they are usually &apos;pulled,&apos; or &apos;towed&apos;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A procession to nagashiba is headed by hosts of the funerals holding lanterns with their family crests and town caretakers holding their town lanterns, followed by young people holding long marker poles with an elaborate lantern on the top end called a shirushi toro, gongs, and at the end, the shorobune hauled by several adults clad in white happi coats (workman&apos;s livery coats).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A procession to nagashiba is headed by hosts of the funerals holding lanterns with their family crests and town caretakers holding their town lanterns, followed by young people holding long marker poles with an elaborate lantern on the top end called a &apos;shirushi toro,&apos; gongs, and at the end, the shorobune (most shorobune have wheels) hauled by several adults clad in white happi coats (workman&apos;s livery coats).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。クォーテーションの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="29">
<j>精霊流しは午後5時頃-10時過ぎまで掛かる事も珍しくない為、多くの船は明かりが灯るように制作されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Shoronagashi begins around 5 p.m. and often lasts until 10 p.m. or later, many shorobune are equipped with lamps to illuminate themselves.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Shoronagashi begins around 5 p.m. and often lasts until 10 p.m. or later, many shorobune are equipped with lamps to illuminate themselves.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the custom launching the boats begins around 5 p.m. and often lasts until 10 p.m. or later, many shorobune are equipped with lamps for illumination.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>一般的な精霊船では提灯に電球を組み込み、船に積んだバッテリーで点灯させる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A most common shorobune has lanterns with light bulbs in them powered by a battery on board.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A most common shorobune has lanterns with light bulbs in them powered by a battery on board.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many shorobune boats have lanterns with light bulbs in them powered by a battery on board.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>小型な船や一部の船ではロウソクを用いるが、振動により引火する危険があるため電球を用いる事が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some shorobune, such as small ones, use candles, but many use electric bulbs because the swing can cause fire.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some shorobune, such as small ones, use candles, but many use electric bulbs because the swing can cause a fire.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some shorobune, such as small ones, use candles, but many use electric bulbs because of the danger of fire.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>また、数十メートルの大型な船では発電機を搭載する大がかりな物もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some large scale shorobune of dozens of meters long are equipped with an electric generator.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some large scale shorobune, dozens of meters in length, are equipped with an electric generator.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some large scale shorobune, dozens of meters in length, are equipped with an electric generator.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="33">
<j>精霊船は「みよし」と呼ばれる舳先に家紋や苗字（○○家）、もやい船の場合は町名が書かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shorobune has a family crest or a family name (the so-and-so family) on the bow called &apos;miyoshi&apos;; moyai-bune has a town&apos;s name on it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shorobune have a family crest or a family name (the so-and-so family) on the bow called the miyoshi; moyai-bune have a town&apos;s name on it.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shorobune have a family crest or a family name on the bow and moyai-bune have the town&apos;s name on the bow.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。スペースをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>艦橋の部分には位牌と遺影、供花が飾られ、盆提灯で照らされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Photos of the deceased, Buddhist mortuary tablets, and offering flowers are placed at the middle of the boat illuminated by bon lanterns.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Photos of the deceased, Buddhist mortuary tablets, and offering flowers are placed at the middle of the boat illuminated by bon lanterns.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Photos of the deceased, Buddhist mortuary tablets, and flowers are placed at the middle of the boat illuminated by bon lanterns.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>仏様や観音様、お経を書いた帆がつけられることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many have sails with drawings of Buddha, Kannon Buddhist deity of mercy, or Buddhist sutra.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many have sails with drawings of Buddha, the Kannon Buddhist deity of mercy, or Buddhist sutras.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many have sails with drawings of Buddha, the Kannon Buddhist deity of mercy, or Buddhist sutras.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="36">
<j>印灯篭は船ごとに異なる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Each shirushi toro has a unique design to each boat.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Each shirushi toro has a unique design to each boat.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Each shirushi toro has a unique design.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>もやい船の場合はその町のシンボルになるものがデザインされている（例町内に亀山社中跡がある自治会は坂本龍馬を描いている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moyai-bune has a symbol of its town on the sail (e.g., a neighborhood association that has remains of Kameyama shachu (the first trading company in Japan led by Ryoma SAKAMOTO at the end of the Edo period) in its town posts a sail depicting Ryoma SAKAMOTO).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moyai-bune has a symbol of its town on the sail (e.g., a neighborhood association that has remains of Kameyama shachu [the first trading company in Japan led by Ryoma SAKAMOTO at the end of the Edo period] in its town posts a sail depicting Ryoma SAKAMOTO).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moyai-bune has a symbol of its town on the sail (e.g., a neighborhood association in a town which has remains of Kameyama shachu (the first trading company in Japan led by Ryoma SAKAMOTO at the end of the Edo period) in its town posts a sail depicting Ryoma SAKAMOTO).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>個人船の場合は家紋や故人の人柄を示すもの（例：将棋が好きだった人は将棋の駒、幼児の場合は好きだったアニメキャラなど）が描かれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A personal boat has a sail of a family crest or a drawing that indicates characteristics of the deceased (e.g., a piece of shogi (Japanese chess) for a shogi lover; for a toddler, anime characters it loved).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A personal boat has a sail of a family crest or a drawing that indicates the idiosyncrasies of the deceased (e.g., a shogi piece (Japanese chess) for a shogi lover; for a toddler, an anime characters he or she loved).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A personal boat has a sail with a family crest or a drawing that indicates the idiosyncrasies of the deceased (e.g., a shogi piece (Japanese chess) for a shogi lover; or cartoon characters for a toddler).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="39">
<j>船の大きさは様々で、全長1-2m程度のものから、長いもので船を何連も連ね20-50mに達するものまである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are various boats in size, from small ones that are one or two meters long to long ones of 20 to 50 meters made of trains of boats.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are various boats in size, from small ones that are one or two meters in length to long ones of 20 to 50 meters made of trains of boats.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The boats vary in size, from one or two meters in length to long series of boats reaching 20 to 50 meters.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="40">
<j>精霊船の基本形は前述の通りであるが、近年では印灯篭の「遊び心」が船本体にも影響を及ぼし、船の形をなしていない、いわゆる「変わり精霊船」も数多く見られる（例ヨット好きの故人→ヨット型、バスの運転士→西方浄土行の方向幕を掲げたバス型など）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the basic structure of shorobune is as mentioned above, having been influenced by &apos;asobi-gokoro&apos; (a playful spirit) of shirushi toro nowadays, many so called &apos;kawari-shorobune&apos; (deformed shorobune) which do not have a shape of boat are seen today (e.g., yacht type shorobune for the dead who loved yachts; a bus type with a destination blind for the Western Pure Land for a bus driver).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the basic structure of shorobune is, as mentioned above, influenced by asobi-gokoro (a playful spirit) of shirushi toro, nowadays, many so called kawari-shorobune (deformed shorobune) which do not hold the shape of boat are seen today (e.g., yacht type shorobune for the dead who loved yachts; a bus type with a destination bound for the Western Pure Land for a bus driver).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the basic structure of shorobune is, as mentioned above, influenced by the playful spirit of shirushi toro, nowadays, many so called alternative shorobune are made these days (e.g., yacht type shorobune for the dead who loved yachts; a bus type with a destination bound for the Western Pure Land for a bus driver).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="41">
<j>由来と爆竹</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The origin of using firecrackers</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The origin of the use of firecrackers</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The origin of firecrackers</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。「爆竹の由来」として訳出しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>由来は諸説あるが、中国の彩船流しの影響が色濃くでているものとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although there are several stories, a common opinion says that the practice of using firecrackers has been strongly influenced by Chinese event of Saisen-nagashi (which was held to pay respects to deceased Chinese).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although there are several stories, common opinion holds that the practice of using firecrackers has been strongly influenced by the Chinese event of Saisen-nagashi (which was held to pay respects to deceased Chinese).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although there are several stories, common opinion holds that the practice of using firecrackers has been strongly influenced by the Chinese event of Saisen-nagashi (which was held to pay respects to deceased Chinese).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>また、流し場までの道行で鳴らされる爆竹は、中国が起源であるなら「魔よけ」の意味であり、精霊船が通る道を清める為とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If firecrackers set off on the way to nagshiba has an origin in China, they work as amulets to purify the tracks shorobune follow.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If firecrackers set off on the way to the nagshiba finds its origins in China, then they work as amulets to purify the tracks shorobune that follow.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is thought that if the use of firecrackers may have originated in China and signify amulets to purify the tracks shorobune that follow.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>近年ではその意味は薄れ、中国で問題になっている春節の爆竹と同様に、「とにかく派手に鳴らせばよい」という傾向が強まっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The meaning has faded away today, and more and more people believe &apos;the bigger the explosion is, the better&apos; just like Chinese firecrackers at the lunar New Year which are at issue in China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The meaning has faded away today, and more and more people believe &apos;the bigger the explosion is, the better&apos; just like Chinese firecrackers at the lunar New Year which are at issue in China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The meaning has faded away today, and more and more people believe &apos;the bigger the explosion is, the better&apos; just like Chinese firecrackers at the lunar New Year which are causing problems in China.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>数百個の爆竹を入れたダンボール箱に一度に点火して火柱が上がったりする等、危険な点火行為が問題視されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dangerous acts, such as lighting up a cardboard of hundreds of firecrackers to set off a big fireball, are criticized.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dangerous acts, such as lighting up cardboard boxes full of hundreds of firecrackers to set off a big fireball, are frowned upon.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dangerous acts, such as lighting cardboard boxes full of hundreds of firecrackers to set off a big fireball, are becoming a problem.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>観覧者を直撃する事が多くあるため、ロケット花火の使用は禁止されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rocket fireworks are banned, because they often fly directly to viewers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rocket fireworks are banned, because they often fly directly towards viewers.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rocket fireworks are banned, because they often fly directly towards viewers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>度を過ぎた花火の使用をした場合、各船の花火取扱者（事前に精霊流しの花火についての講習を受けた者）に警察から指導が行く場合がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If any members of a shorobune group went overboard in using fireworks, police may call on a person (who has been trained on how to use fireworks at Shoronagashi beforehand) in charge of fireworks of the group to warn him or her.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If any members of a shorobune group went overboard in using fireworks, the police may call on a person (who has been trained on how to use fireworks at Shoronagashi beforehand) in charge of fireworks of the group to warn him or her.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If any members of a shorobune group went overboard in using fireworks, the police may call on a person (who has been trained on how to use fireworks at Shoronagashi beforehand) in charge of fireworks of the group to warn him or her.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="48">
<j>見物ポイント</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Viewing spots</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Viewing spots</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Viewing locations</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。ピリオドをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>長崎市の場合は長崎放送が中継録画を行う長崎県庁前には数多くの船が流れ、「変わり精霊船」も多く見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A good viewing spot in Nagasaki City is at the front of Nagasaki Prefectural Government&apos;s Office where Nagasaki Broadcasting Company videotape the event and many shorobune parade there including many &apos;deformed shorobune.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A good viewing spot in Nagasaki City is at the front of the Nagasaki Prefectural Government Office where the Nagasaki Broadcasting Company videotapes the event and many shorobune parade there way past there, including many &apos;deformed shorobune&apos;.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A good viewing spot in Nagasaki City is at the front of the Nagasaki Prefectural Government Office where the Nagasaki Broadcasting Company videotapes the event and many shorobune float past there, including many of the so-called &apos;alternative shorobune.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。クォーテーションを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>一方、長崎市役所周辺ではもやい船の伝統が残る下町が多く、3連、4連の巨大な精霊船を見物することができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around Nagasaki Municipal Office, huge shorobune trains of three or four boats can be seen because many neighborhoods there preserve the tradition of moyai-bune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around Nagasaki Municipal Office, huge shorobune trains of three or four boats can be seen because many neighborhoods there preserve the tradition of moyai-bune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Huge shorobune series of three or four boats can be seen in the area of the Nagasaki Municipal Office as many neighborhoods in that area preserve the tradition of moyai-bune.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="51">
<j>法的な規定</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Regulations</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regulations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regulations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>道路上での船の作成や全長2m以上の船を流す場合は所轄の警察署長の許可が必要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Approval of the chief of police station under the jurisdiction is required to build a boat on a road or to parade a boat with a length of more than two meters.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Approval of the chief of the police station under the jurisdiction is required to build a boat on a road or to parade a boat with a length of more than two meters.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Approval of the chief of the police station under the jurisdiction is required to build a boat on a road or to parade a boat with a length of more than two meters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>船の大きさは最大で全長10m、胴体7m、幅2.5m、高さ3.5m。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The maximum allowed size of a boat is ten meters in total length, seven meters in body length, 2.5 meters in width, and 3.5 meters in height.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The maximum allowed size of a boat is ten meters in total length, seven meters in body length, 2.5 meters in width, and 3.5 meters in height.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The maximum boat size is 10 meters in total length, 7 meters in body length, 2.5 meters in width, and 3.5 meters in height.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>なお、高さは本体高さでなく持ち上げたり担いだりしたときの高さとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The height should be measured when the boat is shouldered; it is not body height.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The height should be measured when the boat is shouldered; it is not body height.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The height is not the height of the body of the boat but the height when the boat is lifted up.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="55">
<j>花火取扱者以外の花火取り扱いは禁止</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Only people who are licensed to handle fireworks are allowed to use fireworks.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Only people who are licensed to handle fireworks are allowed to use fireworks.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Only people with fireworks&apos; licenses may handle fireworks.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>矢火矢（やびや、ロケット花火）、連発花火などの使用禁止</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yabiya (rocket fireworks) and repeating fireworks are banned.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yabiya (rocket fireworks) and repeating fireworks are banned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yabiya (rocket fireworks) and volley fireworks are banned.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>花火を人や車両に向けて使ってはいけない</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fireworks must not be directed towards people or cars.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fireworks must not be directed towards people or cars.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fireworks must not be directed towards people or cars.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>流し場で取り扱える精霊船の大きさは各所で異なり、大きいものは大波止など一部の場所でしか扱えない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Each nagashiba can deal with different maximum size of shorobune; only a few places are capable of scrapping large ones.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Each nagashiba can deal with a different maximum size of shorobune; only a few places are capable of scrapping larger ones.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Each nagashiba can deal with a different maximum size of shorobune; and only a few places, such as Ohato, are capable of handling larger ones.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="59">
<j>責任者は青、花火取扱者は赤のたすきが必要。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The leader and the fireworks licensee of a parading group are required to wear a blue and a red cross brace, respectively.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The leader and the fireworks licensee of a parading group are required to wear a blue and red cross brace, respectively.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The leader and the fireworks licensee of a parading group are required to wear a blue and red cross brace, respectively.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>このたすきは事前の届け出を行う際に所轄警察署の署長から交付される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The chief of police station under the jurisdiction provides these sashes for cross braces on application for prior permission.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The chief of the police station under the jurisdiction provides these sashes for cross braces on application for advanced permission.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The chief of the police station under the jurisdiction provides these sashes for cross braces on application in advance.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="61">
<j>精霊流しに伴う影響</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Services affected by Shoronagashi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Services affected by Shoronagashi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Services affected by Shoronagashi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>精霊流しが行われる時間帯は長崎市中心部をはじめとする各所で交通規制が行われ、バスや長崎電気軌道は経路を変更する形で運行される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Traffic is regulated at various places, such as at the center of Nagasaki City, during the parades of Shoronagashi; buses and streetcars of Nagasaki Electric Tramway operate on routs different from usual.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Traffic is regulated at various places, such as at the center of Nagasaki City, during the parades of Shoronagashi; buses and streetcars of Nagasaki Electric Tramway operate on routes different from usual.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Traffic is stopped or re-routed at various places, such as at the center of Nagasaki City, during the parades of Shoronagashi; and buses and streetcars of Nagasaki Electric Tramway operate on routes different from usual.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="63">
<j>精霊流しの後は自治体が精霊船の処分を行うため一定期間粗大ごみの搬入が停止される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Shoronagashi, in order for municipal offices to scrap shorobune, they decline other bulk trashes for a certain period of time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Shoronagashi, in order for municipal offices to scrap shorobune, they decline other bulk trash for a certain period of time.</e>
<cmt>singular noun</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Shoronagashi festival, in order for municipal offices to scrap shorobune, they cannot accept other large trash for a certain period.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="25">
<sen id="64">
<j>さだまさしと精霊流し</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masashi SADA and Shoronagashi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masashi SADA and Shoronagashi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masashi SADA and Shoronagashi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>長崎市の人にとっては大変重要な行事である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shoronagashi is a very important event for people in Nagasaki City.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoronagashi is a very important event for people in Nagasaki City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoronagashi is a very important event for people in Nagasaki City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>長崎出身の歌手さだまさしが聞いた話によれば、1945年8月9日の長崎原爆投下の際には多くの人が「自分が死んだら、誰が精霊船を出してくれるのだろうか」と気に懸けながら亡くなっていったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masashi SADA, a singer from Nagasaki City, once heard about a story of many people who died worrying, &apos;Who would put me aboard shorobune after my death?&apos; after the atomic bombing of Nagasaki on August 9, 1945.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masashi SADA, a singer from Nagasaki City, once heard about a story of many people who died worrying, &apos;Who would put me aboard a shorobune after my death?&apos; after the atomic bombing of Nagasaki on August 9, 1945.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masashi SADA, a singer from Nagasaki, once heard about a story of many people who died worrying, &apos;Who would put me aboard a shorobune after my death?&apos; after the atomic bombing of Nagasaki on August 9, 1945.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="26">
<sen id="67">
<j>そのさだまさしは、自分の従兄弟の死に際して行なわれた精霊流しを題材にして、ヒット曲『精霊流し』を作った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masashi Sada created a hit song &quot;Shoronagashi&quot; inspired by Shoronagashi after his cousin&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masashi Sada created the hit song &apos;Shoronagashi&apos; having been inspired by Shoronagashi after his cousin&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>wording; punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masashi SADA created the hit song &quot;Shoronagashi&quot; having been inspired by Shoronagashi after his cousin&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>原文の『』に合わせ&apos;を&quot;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>しかし、その歌と一般的な灯篭流しの情景を結び付け悲愴なイメージを作り上げてしまった観光客が実際に長崎の精霊流しを目の当たりにしてあまりの賑やかさに「歌と違う！」と驚くこともしばしばあるらしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tourists who have created a sad image connecting the song and well-known toronagashi (ceremony in which paper lanterns that are believed to bear souls of the deceased are floated down a river) are often said to be surprised to see with their own eyes boisterous parades of Shoronagashi of Nagasaki saying, &apos;So different from the song!&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tourists who have created a sad image connecting the song and well-known toronagashi (ceremony in which paper lanterns that are believed to bear the souls of the deceased are floated down a river) are often said to be surprised to see with their own eyes boisterous parades of Shoronagashi of Nagasaki saying, &apos;So different from the song!&apos;</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tourists who have a sad image connecting the song and well-known toronagashi (ceremony in which paper lanterns that are believed to bear the souls of the deceased are floated down a river) are often said to be surprised to see with their own eyes boisterous parades of Shoronagashi of Nagasaki exclaiming that it is so different from the song.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>実は、さだも歌詞の中で「精霊流しが華やかに」と書いており、グレープのデビューアルバム『わすれもの』では『精霊流し』の導入部に爆竹の音が入っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Actually, Sada&apos;s lyrics includes &apos;Shoronagashi ga hanayakani&apos; (spectacular Shoronagashi), and also his group&apos;s first album &quot;Wasuremono&quot; contains &quot;Shoronagashi&quot; which includes sounds of firecrackers at its lead-in.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Actually, Sada&apos;s lyrics includes &apos;Shoronagashi ga hanayakani&apos; (spectacular Shoronagashi), and also his group&apos;s first album &apos;Wasuremono&apos; contains &apos;Shoronagashi&apos; which includes the sounds of firecrackers during its lead-in.</e>
<cmt>wording; punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Actually, Sada&apos;s lyrics includes &apos;Shoronagashi ga hanayakani&apos; (spectacular Shoronagashi), and also his group&apos;s first album &quot;Wasuremono&quot; contains &quot;Shoronagashi&quot; which includes the sounds of firecrackers during its lead-in.</e>
<cmt>‘→&apos;原文の『』に合わせ&apos;を&quot;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>賑やかさの奥底にある哀しみを描いているのだが、一般的な行事の印象が如何に強いかを物語るエピソードとも言える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although he had intended to express sorrow behind boisterous scenes, the anecdote above indicates how impressions of well-known events dominate.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although he had intended to express sorrow behind the boisterous scenes, the anecdote above indicates how impressions of well-known events often overshadow the message.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although he had intended to express sorrow behind the boisterous scenes, the anecdote above indicates how impressions of well-known events often overshadow the message.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 青子守歌(id:37161), Nnh(id:474), 0null0(id:582), Acha(id:1556), Lupinoid(id:68), Sapphire123(id:147732), Ohura(id:5986), Marine-Blue(id:20162), Ｈｉｒｏ２００６(id:59115), Mit33(id:62177), Khoriuchi(id:139877), Neko2(id:21083), Janus01(id:69663), Ponta2(id:129030), MioUzaki(id:89034), Sonic883(id:36201), Iouri(id:9681), Namazu-tron(id:135120), 10cm(id:147838), タケナカ(id:28800), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>