<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>カラオケ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Karaoke</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Karaoke</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Karaoke</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>カラオケとは、歌を歌う際、またはメロディパート（主旋律）を担う楽器を演奏する際に、生演奏ではなく事前に録音された伴奏を再生することにより演奏を再現することをいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Karaoke is a reproduction of a musical performance by reproducing a musical accompaniment recorded in advance, instead of a live music, when one sings a song or plays a melody part (main part) on an instrument.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Karaoke is a reproduction of a musical performance by musical accompaniment recorded in advance, instead of a live music, when one sings a song or plays a melody part (main part) on an instrument.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Karaoke is a reproduction of a musical performance by musical accompaniment recorded in advance, instead of a live music, when one sings a song or plays a melody part (main part) on an instrument.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>さらに井上大佑がこれを音源製作、再生装置、販売方法をセットにした「エイトジューク」というサービスとして一般に提供し、これが広まり「カラオケ」とよばれるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, Daisuke INOUE provided a service called &quot;8 JUKE&quot; including a production of music source, a reproduction device, and a sales method for the public, which became popular to be called &quot;karaoke.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, Daisuke INOUE provided a service called &quot;8 JUKE&quot; including the production of a music source, a reproduction device, and a sales method for the public, which popularly became known as &quot;karaoke.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, Daisuke INOUE provided a service called &apos;8 JUKE&apos; including the production of a music source, a reproduction device, and a sales method for the public, which popularly became known as &apos;karaoke.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>後者「カラオケ」がその使用対象の大きさからも通常一般に第一に思い起こされる（想起される）ものとなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For its popularity, the latter &quot;karaoke&quot; is generally recalled first.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term&quot;karaoke&quot; is the popular term.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This &apos;karaoke&apos; has widely spread and most people mean this one when they say &apos;karaoke&apos;.</e>
<cmt>ＮＣの訳が原文と異なるので訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>そして機能的には前者は後者の一部と捉えられることも多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In terms of function, the former is often regarded as a part of the latter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In terms of function, the former is often regarded as a part of the latter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In terms of function, the former is often regarded as a part of the latter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>しかしながら、厳密には前者後者はその使用範囲が異なる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, strictly speaking, the ranges of use are different between the former and the latter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, strictly speaking, the ranges of use are different between the former and the latter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, strictly speaking, the ranges of use are different between the former and the latter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>また、後者だけでなく前者も現在でも現役の用語である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, not only the latter but also the former are currently-used active words.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, not only the latter but also the former are currently-used active words.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, not only the latter but also the former are currently-used active words.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>カラオケという言葉が普及する以前は「空演奏」と表現されることが多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before the word &quot;karaoke&quot; became common, it was usually expressed as &quot;kara enso (literally means empty performance).&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before the word &quot;karaoke&quot; became common, it was usually expressed as &quot;kara enso (literally meaning empty performance).&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before the word &apos;karaoke&apos; became common, it was usually expressed as &apos;kara enso (literally meaning empty performance).&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>通常、楽曲の伴奏部分だけが「事前に記録」されている記録媒体（音楽テープやディスク等）で再生される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The accompaniment of the music is generally reproduced by a &quot;previously recorded&quot; recording medium (music tape, disc, or the like).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The music accompaniment is reproduced by a &quot;previously recorded&quot; recording medium (music tape, disc, or the like).</e>
<cmt>wordy, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The music accompaniment is reproduced by a &apos;previously recorded&apos; recording medium (music tape, disc, or the like).</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>この言葉のうまれは、「生伴奏なし」と同義で、「カラオケね」は「伴奏なしでやろう」という意味だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The origin of the word was synonymous with &quot;no live accompaniment,&quot; and &quot;karaoke&quot; used to mean &quot;let&apos;s play without an accompaniment.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The origin of the word was synonymous with &quot;no live accompaniment,&quot; and &quot;karaoke&quot; that used to mean &quot;let&apos;s play without accompaniment.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The origin of the word was synonymous with &apos;no live accompaniment,&apos; and &apos;karaokene&apos; was used to mean &apos;let&apos;s perform without accompaniment.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせて訳を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>これは放送業界で生放送において伴奏へ多くの注意や経費を払わなくていいところから重宝された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This style was convenient in the broadcasting scene because there was no need to pay a lot of attention and cost to the accompaniment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This style was convenient in the broadcasting scene because there was no need to pay a lot of attention and cost for the accompaniment.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This style was convenient in the broadcasting scene because there was no need to pay a lot of attention and cost for the accompaniment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>ここまでは放送業界用語であり、この意味のカラオケはいまでも使われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was a jargon in broadcasting scene in the above meaning, and karaoke in this meaning is still in use.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It became a jargon in broadcasting scene and karaoke in this sense is still in use.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It became a jargon in broadcasting scene and karaoke in this sense is still in use.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>その後、酒場での流しのギター弾きを仕事としていた井上大佑が、8トラックテープを用いて伴奏を事前録音したものを再生する装置を開発する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, Daisuke Inoue, who was working as a strolling guitarist in bars, developed a device to reproduce pre-recorded accompaniments using an eight-track tape.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, Daisuke Inoue, who was working as a strolling guitarist in bars, developed a device to reproduce pre-recorded accompaniment using an eight-track tape.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, Daisuke INOUE, who was working as a strolling guitarist in bars, developed a device to reproduce pre-recorded accompaniment using an eight-track tape.</e>
<cmt>Inoue→INOUE</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>流しのレパートリーに左右されず、本物の演奏が再現されるとあって、これが評判となり、酒場で評判となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because real performance was reproduced regardless of the strolling guitarist&apos;s repertoires, it gained popularity in the bars.</e>
<cmt>「これが評判となり、酒場で評判となる」は冗長ですので、「これが酒場で評判となる」として訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because a real performance was reproduced regardless of the strolling guitarist&apos;s repertoires, it gained popularity in the bars.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because a real performance was reproduced regardless of the strolling guitarist&apos;s repertoires, it gained popularity in the bars.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>ここに大衆文化となるカラオケが誕生する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was the origin of Karaoke as a popular culture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was the origin of Karaoke as a popular culture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was the origin of Karaoke as a popular culture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>現在では、カラオケのしかけ、つまり、歌を歌うための装置、さらにはその装置を使って歌うことだけでなく、歌うための場所を提供している店（カラオケボックス）のことなどをカラオケと略して指すようにもなっており、これはカラオケがそれだけ一般化していることの証でもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In these days, not only the device of karaoke, i.e. the device to sing a song, as well as to sing using the device, but also a bar that provides a place to sing (e.g. karaoke box) are also abbreviated to karaoke, which proves that karaoke has become so popular.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These days, not only the karaoke device, i.e. the device used to sing a song, as well as to sing using the device, but also a bar that provides a place to sing (e.g. karaoke box) are also abbreviated as karaoke, which proves that karaoke has become so popular.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These days, not only the karaoke device, i.e. the device used to sing a song, as well as to sing using the device, but also a bar that provides a place to sing (e.g. karaoke box) are also abbreviated as karaoke, which proves that karaoke has become so popular.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>カラオケは、歌ってストレス (生体)を発散させたりするため、娯楽に分類され、レジャー白書で統計が取られる一項目ともなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because one&apos;s stress is relieved by singing, karaoke is now categorized in an amusement and it is one of the items on which statistics are taken in the White Paper on Leisure.</e>
<cmt>「白書」をウェブから補いました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because one&apos;s stress is relieved by singing, karaoke is now categorized as amusement and it is one of the items on which statistics are given in the White Paper on Leisure.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because one&apos;s stress is relieved by singing, karaoke is now categorized as amusement and it is one of the items on which statistics are given in the White Paper on Leisure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="17">
<j>この形式は日本で生まれたもので、英語の「Karaoke」（「キャリオキ」と聞こえる）や中国語の「「卡拉OK」（kǎlā OK）、ロシア語の「Караокэ」など、外国でも日本語の音をそのまま使った言葉が使われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This style emerged in Japan, and words based on the sound of the Japanese word are used in foreign languages such as &quot;karaoke&quot; (sounds rather &quot;kyarioki&quot; than &quot;karaoke&quot; to Japanese) in English, &quot;卡拉OK&quot; (kǎlā OK) in Chinese, and &quot;Караокэ&quot; in Russian.</e>
<cmt>各国語の表記をウェブから補いました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This style emerged in Japan, and words based on the sound of the Japanese word are used in foreign languages such as &quot;karaoke&quot; (sounds rather &quot;kyarioki&quot; than &quot;karaoke&quot; to Japanese) in English, &quot;卡拉OK&quot; (kǎlā OK) in Chinese, and &quot;Караокэ&quot; in Russian.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This style emerged in Japan, and words based on the sound of the Japanese word are used in foreign languages such as &apos;karaoke&apos; (sounds rather &apos;kyarioki&apos; than &apos;karaoke&apos; to Japanese) in English, &apos;卡拉OK&apos; (kǎlā OK) in Chinese, and &apos;Караокэ&apos; in Russian.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="18">
<j>イギリス政府が2500人以上の成人を対象にした調査で「最も重要と思いつつも最も不快に感じる発明品」として、カラオケが22%を獲得し携帯電話などを抑えて1位となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A survey among more than 2,500 adults conducted by the British government, karaoke won the first place with 22% over mobile phones and so on as &quot;the most irritating invention to have blighted Britain.&quot;</e>
<cmt>最も重要と思いつつも最も不快に感じる発明品→most irritating invention to have blighted Britain　[http://74.125.153.132/search?q=cache:tlBhp5WeySAJ:www.andhranews.net/Technology/2009/January/8-Karaoke-machine-named-82748.asp+%22Britain%22+%22invention%22+%22karaoke%22&amp;cd=5&amp;hl=ja&amp;ct=clnk&amp;gl=jp]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A survey among more than 2,500 adults conducted by the British government, karaoke won first place with 22% over mobile phones and so on as &quot;the most irritating invention to have blighted Britain.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A survey among more than 2,500 adults conducted by the British government, karaoke won first place with 22% over mobile phones and so on as &apos;the most irritating invention to have blighted Britain.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>イギリスでは、日本のように防音施設が整った個室型のカラオケボックスがまだあまり広まっておらず、カラオケが設置されているパブで音痴の人や酔っぱらいの歌声が“騒音”被害を招いているとの理由から。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reason for the result is that the singing voice of a tone deaf singer or a drunk in pubs with karaoke causes noise pollution, for karaoke boxes with soundproof compartments as often seen in Japan are not common in the Britain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reason for the result is that the singing voice of a tone deaf singer or a drunk in pubs with karaoke causes noise pollution, for karaoke boxes with soundproof compartments as often seen in Japan are not common in the Britain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reason for the result is that the singing voice of a tone deaf singer or a drunk in pubs with karaoke causes noise pollution, for karaoke boxes with soundproof compartments as often seen in Japan are not common in the Britain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>カラオケの発祥</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Origin of karaoke</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Origin of karaoke</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Origin of karaoke</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="20">
<j>カラオケの、カラは「空っぽ」、オケは「オーケストラ」の略で、オーケストラによる生演奏ではなく、テープやレコードで代用することを表す放送業界ではじまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kara&quot; of karaoke stands for &quot;karappo (empty)&quot; and &quot;oke&quot; stands for &quot;orchestra&quot;, and the term started to be used in the broadcasting scene indicating use of tapes and records instead of live performance by an orchestra.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kara&quot; of karaoke stands for &quot;karappo (empty)&quot; and &quot;oke&quot; stands for &quot;orchestra,&quot; and the term started to be used in the broadcasting scene indicating use of tapes and records instead of live performance by an orchestra.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kara of karaoke stands for &apos;karappo (empty)&apos; and &apos;oke&apos; stands for &apos;orchestra,&apos; and the term started to be used in the broadcasting scene indicating use of tapes and records instead of live performance by an orchestra.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos; （文頭は削除）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>そしてそれは今でも続いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term is still used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term is still used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term is still used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>一説によればNHK交響楽団員らの雑談から出た言葉だという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to one explanation, the term came out in an idle conversation by the members of NHK Symphony Orchestra.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to one explanation, the term came out in an idle conversation by the members of the NHK Symphony Orchestra.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to one explanation, the term came out in an idle conversation by the members of the NHK Symphony Orchestra.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="23">
<j>ラジオ、テレビでの放送は当初はその番組自体、生放送でおこなわれており、流行（はやり）の歌も、当然のことながらすべて生。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the beginning, radio and TV programs were live, and therefore all popular songs were naturally performed live.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the beginning, radio and TV programs were live, and therefore all popular songs were naturally performed live.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the beginning, radio and TV programs were live, and therefore all popular songs were naturally performed live.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>つまり、その場で実際におこなった歌と演奏が放送された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That is, songs and music performed at the scene were broadcasted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That is, songs and music performed at the scene were broadcasted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That is, songs and music performed at the scene were broadcasted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>これが、オープンリールテープなどの録音機材が導入され、音響効果等が事前に録音したものでまかなえるようになってきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As recording equipments such as an open-reel tape were introduced, it became possible to supply sound effects using previously recorded sources.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As recording equipment such as open-reel tape were introduced, it became possible to supply sound effects using previously recorded sources.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As recording equipment such as open-reel tape were introduced, it became possible to supply sound effects using previously recorded sources.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>後には、映像記録が可能なビデオが導入されるが、その中間期、映像は生放送だったが音響は録音でまかなえるようになった時代にカラオケは誕生する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Videos capable of recording moving images were introduced later, but in the interim period when the image was live but sounds were supplied by recorded sources, karaoke was invented.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Videos capable of recording moving images were introduced later, but in the interim period when the image was live, but sounds were supplied by recorded sources, karaoke was invented.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Videos capable of recording moving images were introduced later, but in the interim period when the image was live, but sounds were supplied by recorded sources, karaoke was invented.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>映像として歌手は必要だが、オーケストラは不要であり、もしくは、ラジオでもトークも含めて歌手は現場に必要だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were cases in which a singer was essential as an image but no orchestra was required, or, in the case of a radio program, the singer was required on the scene for free talk.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were cases in which a singer was essential as an image, but no orchestra was required, or, in the case of a radio program, the singer was required on the scene for free talk.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were cases in which a singer was essential as an image, but no orchestra was required, or, in the case of a radio program, the singer was required on the scene for free talk.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>そのような場合、歌を歌う際の伴奏は録音したものを再生することで大幅に手間が省けるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In such cases, much less effort was required by reproducing recorded accompaniments when the singer sings a song.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In such cases, much less effort was required by reproducing recorded accompaniments when the singer sings a song.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In such cases, much less effort was required by reproducing recorded accompaniments when the singer sings a song.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>カラオケのソース（音源）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Source of karaoke (sound source)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Source of karaoke (sound source)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Source of karaoke (sound source)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="29">
<j>「カラオケは、メロディなしの音楽、つまり伴奏を再生すること」であり、そのためには再生する装置と再生される音楽（音楽ソース）が必要だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Karaoke is a reproduction of music without main melody, or reproduction of an accompaniment,&quot; and it required a device for the reproduction and music (music source) to be reproduced.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Karaoke is a reproduction of music without the main melody, or reproduction of an accompaniment,&quot; and it required a device for the reproduction and music (music source) to be reproduced.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Karaoke is a reproduction of music without the main melody, or reproduction of an accompaniment, and it required a device for the reproduction and music (music source) to be reproduced.</e>
<cmt>文頭の&quot; &quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="30">
<j>放送局でうまれたカラオケは、それまで生で演奏していたオーケストラを一度録音すればいいだけであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Karaoke, emerged in broadcast stations, was produced recording music by orchestra just once, which had been performed live.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Karaoke, emerged in broadcast stations, it produced recording music by an orchestra just once, which had been performed live.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Karaoke, emerged in broadcast stations, it produced recording music by an orchestra just once, which had been performed live.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>オーケストラにとって何度も忙しく放送局に呼ばれ仕事ができていた時代はすぐに過ぎ去った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Orchestras were not busy anymore being often called in to the broadcast stations to work.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Orchestras were not busy anymore being often called in to the broadcast stations to work.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Orchestras were not busy anymore being often called in to the broadcast stations to work.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>新曲は一度録音すればそれで終了ということになってしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They had only to record a new song once, and that was it.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They had only to record a new song once, and that was it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They had only to record a new song once, and that was it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>もちろん録音への報奨は生演奏一度よりは高いものだったが従来の活動全部を補えるものでは到底なかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Of course the performance fee for recording was higher than that for a single live performance, but it was not enough to compensate the total fee for the conventional activities.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Of course the performance fee for recording was higher than that for a single live performance, but it was not enough to compensate the total fee for conventional activities.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Of course the performance fee for recording was higher than that for a single live performance, but it was not enough to compensate the total fee for conventional activities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>こうして特定の人々が使う、つまり放送局内だけで使う音楽ソース（音源）が蓄えられていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The music sources (sound sources) to be used by particular people, or to be used only in the particular broadcast station, were stored more and more.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The music sources (sound sources) used by particular people, or to be used only in the particular broadcast station, were stored more and more.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The music sources (sound sources) used by particular people, or to be used only in the particular broadcast station, were stored more and more.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>カラオケの機材</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Karaoke equipment</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Karaoke equipment</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Karaoke equipment</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="35">
<j>この時期使われた再生装置は、オープンリールタイプのテープレコーダーである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reproduction device used at the time was an open reel tape recorder.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reproduction device used at the time was an open reel tape recorder.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reproduction device used at the time was an open reel tape recorder.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>それは録音機能も備えたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was also capable of recording.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was also capable of recording.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was also capable of recording.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>後になっていわゆる民生用も誕生するオープンリール・テープレコーダーであるが、この時期はまだ業務用として最先端の機器であり非常に高価なものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although consumer open reel tape recorders were produced later, it was the state-of-the-art equipment for professional use, and therefore it was very expensive at the time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although consumer open reel tape recorders were produced later, it was the state-of-the-art equipment for professional use, and therefore it was very expensive at the time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although consumer open reel tape recorders were produced later, it was the state-of-the-art equipment for professional use, and therefore it was very expensive at the time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>カラオケ装置の誕生</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emergence of karaoke machine</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emergence of the karaoke machine</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emergence of the karaoke machine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>カラオケ以前</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before karaoke</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before karaoke</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before karaoke</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>ジュークボックス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Juke box</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Juke box</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Juke box</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="38">
<j>第二次世界大戦後、日本にやってきた進駐軍がもってきたといわれるジュークボックス。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that juke boxes were brought by the occupation army that came to Japan after the World War II.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that juke boxes were brought by the occupation army that came to Japan after World War II.</e>
<cmt>grammer</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that juke boxes were brought by the occupation army that came to Japan after World War II.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>飲食業界で流行の音楽が聞きたいときに聞けることと、アメリカを感じさせるその装置により客は100円玉を投入していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the restaurant business, customers inserted a 100-yen coin into the machine that played a popular song as desired and that conveyed an American atmosphere.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the restaurant business, customers inserted a 100-yen coin into the machine that played a popular song as desired and that conveyed an American atmosphere.</e>
<cmt>gramma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the restaurant business, customers inserted a 100-yen coin into the machine that played a popular song as desired and that conveyed an American atmosphere.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>テープレコーダーの普及</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Spread of tape recorders</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Spread of tape recorders</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Spread of tape recorders</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="40">
<j>大型のオープンリールを使用した装置には民生用があることにはあったが、1960年代後半にコンパクトカセットテープとそのレコーダーが登場し録音再生という行為が一般大衆に浸透していく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although there was a consumer product using a large open reel, a compact cassette tape and a recorder for it emerged in the late half of 1960&apos;s, and an act of recording and reproducing sound became common among general people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although there was a consumer product using a large open reel, a compact cassette tape and a recorder for it emerged in the late half of 1960&apos;s, and the act of recording and reproducing sound became common among the general population.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although there was a consumer product using a large open reel, a compact cassette tape and a recorder for it emerged in the late half of 1960&apos;s, and the act of recording and reproducing sound became common among the general population.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="41">
<j>コンパクトカセットはオランダの電機メーカーであるフィリップス社が1962年に開発したオーディオ用磁気記録テープ媒体の規格である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The compact cassette was a standard of an audio magnetic recording tape medium developed by a Dutch electronics company, Philips, in 1962.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The compact cassette was a standard of an audio magnetic recording tape medium developed by a Dutch electronics company, Philips, in 1962.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The compact cassette was a standard of an audio magnetic recording tape medium developed by a Dutch electronics company, Philips, in 1962.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>8トラックはRCAビクター社が1965年にカーオーディオ用のメディアとして開発した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The eight-track was developed by RCA Victor as a car audio medium in 1965.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The eight-track was developed by RCA Victor as a car audio medium in 1965.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The eight-track was developed by RCA Victor as a car audio medium in 1965.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="43">
<j>コンパクトカセットはまだ音楽用途とは捉えられておらず、8トラックがジュークボックス代わりに音楽を差し替えながら再生する装置として活用され始めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The compact cassette was not regarded for music application yet, and the eight-track began to be employed as a reproduction device with the music replaced instead of the juke box.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The compact cassette was not regarded for music application yet, and the eight-track began to be employed as a reproduction device with the music replaced instead of the juke box.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The compact cassette was not regarded for music application yet, and the eight-track began to be employed as a reproduction device with the music replaced instead of the juke box.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>井上大佑によるカラオケシステムの発明</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Invention of karaoke system by Daisuke INOUE</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Invention of karaoke system by Daisuke INOUE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Invention of karaoke system by Daisuke INOUE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="44">
<j>最初のカラオケというサービスの考え方とそれを実現する装置が1971年に井上大佑（いのうえ だいすけ）という一人のバンドマンによって発明された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The initial idea of the service of karaoke and the device that realized the idea were invented by a musician called Daisuke INOUE in 1971.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The initial idea of the service of karaoke and the device that realized the idea were invented by a musician called Daisuke INOUE in 1971.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The initial idea of the service of karaoke and the device that realized the idea were invented by a musician called Daisuke INOUE in 1971.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>井上は既存の楽曲を単に再生するだけでなく、バンドマンには当然の発想である歌う人に合わせた音階やテンポという概念をシステムとして実現した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Inoue realized not only a system for reproducing existing songs but also a concept of musical scales and tempo adapted to each singer, which was a matter of courses for him.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Inoue realized not only a system for reproducing existing songs but also a concept of musical scales and tempo adapted to each singer, which was a matter of courses for him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Inoue realized not only a system for reproducing existing songs but also a concept of musical scales and tempo adapted to each singer, which was a matter of course for him.</e>
<cmt>courses→course</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>再生装置は「8Juke（エイトジューク）」と名づけられ、リースで販売した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reproduction device was named &quot;8 Juke (eight juke),&quot; and sold on lease.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reproduction device was named &quot;8 Juke (eight juke),&quot; and was leased.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reproduction device was named &apos;8 Juke (eight juke),&apos; and was leased.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="47">
<j>井上は弾き語り、なじみの客から「社員旅行で使いたいので、伴奏だけを入れたテープ（カラオケテープ）を作って欲しい」と依頼された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Inoue was asked by his old customer to make a tape with only a musical accompaniment (karaoke tape) to use in a company trip.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Inoue was asked by his old customer to make a tape with only a musical accompaniment (karaoke tape) to use on a company trip.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Inoue was asked by his old customer to make a tape with only a musical accompaniment (karaoke tape) to use on a company trip.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>彼は依頼主にあわせてキーを移調し、テンポも変えていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Inoue transposed keys and changed the tempo according to the requestor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Inoue transposed keys and changed the tempo according to the request.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Inoue transposed keys and changed the tempo according to the request.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>そしてそこから潜在的な需要に気づいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He found a potential demand there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He found a potential demand there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He found a potential demand there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>そこで8トラックのカラオケテープを作り、コインボックス式の再生装置に入れて、スナックなどに置くこととした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He decided to produce eight track karaoke tapes to be inserted in a coin-operated reproduction device, and to place it in snack bars.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He decided to produce eight track karaoke tapes to be inserted in a coin-operated reproduction device, and to place it in snack bars.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He decided to produce eight track karaoke tapes to be inserted in a coin-operated reproduction device, and to place it in snack bars.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>このときのテープ内容は8トラックテープ1本に付き4曲10本で計40曲で、当時の料金は5分で100円だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the time, each eight track tape included four songs times ten tapes makes forty songs, and the charge was a hundred yen per five minutes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the time, each eight track tape included four songs times ten tapes makes forty songs, and the charge was a hundred yen per five minutes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the time, each eight track tape included four songs times ten tapes makes forty songs, and the charge was a hundred yen per five minutes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="52">
<j>8トラックのテープを使い、また曲にアレンジを加えて長さを調整することで、1本のテープに何曲も入れることができ、また、できるだけ早く頭出しが出来るようになっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By using an eight track tape and arranging the song to adjust the length of it, it became possible to record many songs on a single tape and cueing the next song as quickly as possible.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By using an eight track tape and arranging the song to adjust the length of it, it became possible to record many songs on a single tape and cueing the next song as quickly as possible.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By using an eight track tape and arranging the song to adjust the length of it, it became possible to record many songs on a single tape and cueing the next song as quickly as possible.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>1曲は3～4分になるように調整されており、1曲目を気分よく歌ったあと、2曲目の途中で次のコインを投入する必要が出てくるため、客はついつい100円玉を景気よく使ってしまう……というパターンが生まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With each song arranged to last three to four minutes, after singing the first song on a good note, the customer had to insert another coin while he was singing the second song, and therefore he spent a lot of 100-yen coins without thinking... which became a typical pattern.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With each song arranged to last three to four minutes, after singing the first song on a good note, the customer had to insert another coin while he was singing the second song, and therefore he spent a lot of 100-yen coins without thinking... which became a typical pattern.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With each song arranged to last three to four minutes, after singing the first song on a good note, the customer had to insert another coin while he was singing the second song, and therefore he spent a lot of 100-yen coins without thinking... which became a typical pattern.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="54">
<j>また、カラオケというビジネスモデルが成功した理由のひとつとして、このときリースを導入したことが挙げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of the reasons why the business model of karaoke was successful may be an introduction of a lease system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of the reasons why the business model of karaoke was successful may be an introduction of a lease system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of the reasons why the business model of karaoke was successful may be an introduction of a lease system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>新譜が次々と出る状況で毎回テープを購入していては店が大変だろうという配慮からと言われているが、それが今日に続く隆盛の原動力の一つとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reason is believed to be solicitude that purchasing all tapes every time a new tape is released would be hard for the snack bar, and consequently it served as the driving force for the still-growing prosperity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reason is believed to be solicitude that purchasing all tapes every time a new tape is released would be hard for the snack bar, and consequently it served as the driving force for the still-growing prosperity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reason is believed to be solicitude that purchasing all tapes every time a new tape is released would be hard for the snack bar, and consequently it served as the driving force for the still-growing prosperity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="56">
<j>以下に産業となっていくカラオケの詳しい歴史が記述されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Detailed history of karaoke that grew into an industry is described below.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Detailed history of karaoke that grew into an industry is described below.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Detailed history of karaoke that grew into an industry is described below.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>→全国カラオケ事業者協会</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">All-Japan Karaoke Industrialist Association</e>
<cmt>リンク先名称をウェブより補いました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">All-Japan Karaoke Industrialist Association</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">All-Japan Karaoke Industrialist Association</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="58">
<j>技術としては様々な変遷があるものの、カラオケという装置およびビジネスモデルは井上がセットで生み出したものだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Apart from the twists and turns of technological transition, a set of the device and the business model of karaoke was invented by Inoue.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Apart from the twists and turns of technological transition, a set and the business model of the karaoke device was invented by Inoue.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Apart from the twists and turns of technological transition, a set and the business model of the karaoke device was invented by Inoue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>しかし、井上は特許を申請していなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Inoue did not apply for a patent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Inoue did not apply for a patent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Inoue did not apply for a patent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>もし特許を申請し取得できていたとしたら、年に100億円の特許権収入が発生するという試算がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a calculation that ten billion yen would be generated per year by a patent if he had applied for and obtained the patent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a calculation that ten billion yen would be generated per year by a patent if he had applied for and obtained the patent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a calculation that ten billion yen would be generated per year by a patent if he had applied for and obtained the patent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="61">
<j>彼は1999年、米国タイム誌の「今世紀、アジアにもっとも影響のあった人物20人」という特集の中で「毛沢東やマハトマ・ガンディーがアジアの昼を変えたならば、井上はアジアの夜を変えた男だ」と紹介された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was named in a top twenty in a special issue of &quot;The Most Influential Asians of the Century&quot; in Time Magazine in the United States in 1999, and introduced &quot;as much as Mao Zedong or Mohandas Gandhi changed Asian days, Inoue transformed its nights.&quot;</e>
<cmt>カッコ内の訳が原文と若干異なりますが、タイム誌のログより引用しました。[http://74.125.153.132/search?q=cache:_DJWDFeasfYJ:www.time.com/time/asia/asia/magazine/1999/990823/inoue1.html+%22Daisuke+Inoue%22+%22Mohandas+Gandhi+%22+%22changed%22&amp;cd=1&amp;hl=ja&amp;ct=clnk&amp;gl=jp]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was named in a top twenty in a special issue of &quot;The Most Influential Asians of the Century&quot; in Time Magazine in the United States in 1999, and introduced &quot;as much as Mao Zedong or Mohandas Gandhi changed Asian days, Inoue transformed its nights.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was named in a top 20 in a special issue of &apos;The Most Influential Asians of the Century&apos; in Time Magazine in the United States in 1999, and introduced &apos;as much as Mao Zedong or Mohandas Gandhi changed Asian days, Inoue transformed its nights.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;twenty→20</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>また2004年には、イグノーベル賞（平和賞）を受賞している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Inoue was also awarded The Ig Nobel Prize in 2004.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Inoue was also awarded The Ig Nobel Prize in 2004.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Inoue was also awarded The Ig Nobel Prize in 2004.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>2005年には井上をモデルにした映画「KARAOKE-人生紙一重-」が上映された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 2005, a movie &quot;Karaoke&quot; that modeled Inoue was released.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 2005, a movie &quot;Karaoke&quot; that modeled Inoue was released.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 2005, a movie &apos;Karaoke&apos; that modeled Inoue was released.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>音源の製作</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Production of sound source</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Production of sound source</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Production of sound source</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="64">
<j>井上は自分で演奏して音源を作った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Inoue played instruments and produced the music source by himself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Inoue played instruments and produced the music source by himself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Inoue played instruments and produced the music source by himself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>その後、各社が主旋律抜きの演奏を録音する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, many companies recorded accompaniments without the melody.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, many companies recorded accompaniments without the melody.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, many companies recorded accompaniments without the melody.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>カラオケが流行しだすと、その楽曲のCD自体にカラオケが付属するようにもなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As karaoke became popular, CDs were made to include a karaoke version of the song.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As karaoke became popular, CDs were made to include a karaoke version of the song.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As karaoke became popular, CDs were made to include a karaoke version of the song.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>カラオケの特別の音源がなくとも自宅でカラオケができるようにもなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Karaoke became available at home without a special music source of karaoke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Karaoke became available at home without a special music source of karaoke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Karaoke became available at home without a special music source of karaoke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>音源の供給</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Supply of sound source</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Supply of sound source</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Supply of sound source</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="68">
<j>発明当初より「媒体」で供給された音源は現在では媒体を使用せず「通信」により供給されるものが主流となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The music sources have been supplied via &quot;a medium&quot; since the invention was made, but now most of them are supplied &quot;online communication&quot; without using the medium.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The music sources have been supplied via &quot;a medium&quot; since the invention was made, but now most of them are supplied by &quot;online communication&quot; without using the medium.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The music sources have been supplied via &apos;a medium&apos; since the invention was made, but now most of them are supplied by &apos;online communication&apos; without using the medium.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="69">
<j>媒体使用時は、音楽メディア（メディア媒体）の進化にしたがって、8トラック、コンパクトカセット、レーザーディスク、VHD、ビデオCD、DVDなどを経た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the medium was used, it changed from the eight track to the compact cassette, the laser disk, the VHD&lt; the video CD, the DVD, and the like, as the music medium was improved.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the medium was used, it changed from the eight track to the compact cassette, the laser disk, the VHD&lt; the video CD, the DVD, and the like, as the music medium was improved.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the medium was used, it changed from the eight track to the compact cassette, the laser disk, the VHD, the video CD, the DVD, and the like, as the music medium was improved.</e>
<cmt>VHD&lt;→VHD,</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>日本では現在は通信カラオケが主流となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Currently, the online karaoke is the main stream in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Currently, online karaoke is the main stream in Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Currently, online karaoke is the main stream in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>バリエーション</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Variation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Variation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Variation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="71">
<j>本来、伴奏部分だけのものがカラオケであるが、練習用ということでヴォーカル部分を含んで再生可能な機能を持つカラオケシステムも多数ある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Karaoke is originally the accompaniment alone, but there are many karaoke systems that can reproduce a vocal part for practice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Karaoke is originally the accompaniment alone, but there are many karaoke systems that can reproduce a vocal part for practice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Karaoke is originally the accompaniment alone, but there are many karaoke systems that can reproduce a vocal part for practice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>歌う側にあわせてキーを変化させたり、テンポを調整したり、また、男性の声を女性の声に、女性の声を男性の声に変換させたりすることも可能となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also possible to change keys to be adapted to each singer, adjust the tempo, or convert a male voice into female voice and vice versa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also possible to change keys to adapt to each singer, adjust the tempo, or convert a male voice into female voice and vice versa.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also possible to change keys to adapt to each singer, adjust the tempo, or convert a male voice into female voice and vice versa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>カラオケ演奏機がゲーム機能や点数をつけたりする機能を備えている場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some karaoke players are equipped with a game function or a scoring function.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some karaoke players are equipped with a game function or a scoring function.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some karaoke players are equipped with a game function or a scoring function.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="74">
<j>カラオケ演奏機は、本体にあるボタン、つまみで操作するほか、通常はリモコンでも操作可能である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The karaoke player can be generally operated through not only buttons on the main body but also a remote control.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The karaoke player can be generally operated through not only buttons on the main body, but also by a remote control.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The karaoke player can be generally operated through not only buttons on the main body, but also by a remote control.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>選曲は、歌曲を歌手別あるいは歌詞の出だし順に並べた本で、曲名の索引なども参照して、歌いたい曲に割り当てられた番号を検索し、その番号を機械に入力することにより行われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To select a song, a user searches a book that includes songs listed in the order of the singer&apos;s name or the first words of the song for a number assigned to the desired song, also referring to the index of the song titles, and inputs the number to the machine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To select a song, a user searches a book that includes songs listed in the order of the singer&apos;s name or the first words of the song for a number assigned to the desired song, also referring to the index of the song titles, and inputs the number into the machine.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To select a song, a user searches a book that includes songs listed in the order of the singer&apos;s name or the first words of the song for a number assigned to the desired song, also referring to the index of the song titles, and inputs the number into the machine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="76">
<j>現在はリモコン側に設けられた液晶画面で曲名やアーティスト名から検索し、本体に送信することで選曲することができるものもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Presently, some of the karaoke players enable the user to search for the song from among the song titles or artist names displayed on an LCD panel provided on the remote control and transmit the selected song to the main body, thereby selecting the song.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Presently, some of the karaoke players enable the user to search for the song from among the song titles or artist names displayed on an LCD panel provided on the remote control and transmit the selected song to the main body, thereby selecting the song.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Presently, some of the karaoke players enable the user to search for the song from among the song titles or artist names displayed on an LCD panel provided on the remote control and transmit the selected song to the main body, thereby selecting the song.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>中にはタッチパネルを備えたものもあり、ボタン操作は一切必要のない機種も登場している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are those equipped with a touch panel, which requires no button operation at all.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are those equipped with a touch panel, which requires no button operation at all.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are those equipped with a touch panel, which requires no button operation at all.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="78">
<j>当初は歌詞カードや歌詞の書かれた本を見ながら歌っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At first, users used to sing a song looking at a lyric sheet or a lyric book.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At first, users used to sing a song looking at a lyric sheet or a lyric book.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At first, users used to sing a song looking at a lyric sheet or a lyric book.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>しかし、現在ではビデオモニターに歌詞が字幕スーパーの形で表示され、歌う部分を色を変えて示す仕組みになっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Presently, however, the lyrics are displayed on a video monitor in the form of TV caption indicating each part to sing by changing the color.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Presently, however, the lyrics are displayed on a video monitor in the form of TV caption indicating each part to sing by changing the color.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Presently, however, the lyrics are displayed on a video monitor in the form of TV caption indicating each part to sing by changing the color.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="80">
<j>近年は歌唱にとどまらず、ブレーンの吹奏楽CD「マイナス・ワン」シリーズのように特定の楽器のソロパートを除いた「楽器演奏用のカラオケ」も現れている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Recently, there are not only karaoke for singing but also &quot;karaoke for an instrument&quot; that excludes a solo part for a particular instrument, like &quot;Minus One&quot; series of wind orchestra CD from BRAIN MUSIC.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Recently, there are not only karaoke for singing, but also &quot;karaoke for an instrument&quot; that excludes a solo part for a particular instrument, like &quot;Minus One&quot; series of wind orchestra CD from BRAIN MUSIC.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Recently, there are not only karaoke for singing, but also &apos;karaoke for an instrument&apos; that excludes a solo part for a particular instrument, like &apos;Minus One&apos; series of wind orchestra CD from BRAIN MUSIC.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>カラオケ文化</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Karaoke culture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Karaoke culture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Karaoke culture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="14">
<tit>
<j>酒場の余興</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Side show in bar</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Side show in bar</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Side show in bar</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="81">
<j>カラオケは、スナックバー (飲食店)などの飲食業者の店舗や、ホテルの宴会場などに置かれることが多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Karaoke was mainly placed in snack bars or hotel banquet rooms.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Karaoke was mainly placed in snack bars or hotel banquet rooms.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Karaoke was mainly placed in snack bars or hotel banquet rooms.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>カラオケは酒席の余興という格好だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Karaoke was regarded as a side show in bars.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Karaoke was regarded as a side show in bars.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Karaoke was regarded as a side show in bars.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>この時期の利用者は酒の飲める世代、つまり20代以上である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, the users were the generations allowed to drink alcohol, or in the twenties and over.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, the users were the generations allowed to drink alcohol, or those in their twenties and over.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, the users were the generations allowed to drink alcohol, or those in their 20&apos;s and over.</e>
<cmt>数字表記変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>しかし、多くはより年齢層が上の層であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most of them were actually in higher age groups.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most of them were actually in older age groups.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most of them were actually in older age groups.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>その理由は、カラオケとして録音されている曲（カラオケ・ソース）の多くが演歌だったからである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was because most of the songs recorded as karaoke (karaoke source) were enka (Japanese ballad).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was because most of the songs recorded as karaoke (karaoke source) were enka (Japanese ballad).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was because most of the songs recorded as karaoke (karaoke source) were enka (Japanese ballad).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="15">
<tit>
<j>産業としての広がり</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Growth as industry</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Growth as industry</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Growth as industry</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="86">
<j>1980年代半ば、カラオケを専門的に提供する、カラオケボックスという事業形態が誕生。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the mid 1980&apos;s, a business structure of the karaoke box that exclusively provide karaoke emerged.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the mid 1980&apos;s, a business structure of the karaoke box that exclusively provide karaoke emerged.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the mid 1980&apos;s, a business structure of the karaoke box that exclusively provide karaoke emerged.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>酒のついでにカラオケを楽しむのではなく、純粋にカラオケで歌うために赴く場所であり、それ以前の概念を根底から覆す画期的な業態だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was a place to go not to enjoy karaoke while drinking but to purely sing to karaoke, and was a revolutionary structure that knocked the bottom out of the old concept.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was a place to go not to enjoy karaoke while drinking but to purely sing to karaoke, and was a revolutionary structure that knocked the bottom out of the old concept.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was a place to go not to enjoy karaoke while drinking but to purely sing to karaoke, and was a revolutionary structure that knocked the bottom out of the old concept.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="88">
<j>カラオケボックス成功の一要因として、下記があげられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One factor that contributed to the success of karaoke box may be the following fact.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One factor that contributed to the success of karaoke box may be the following fact.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One factor that contributed to the success of karaoke box may be the following fact.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="89">
<j>ある年代以上の日本人には「酒も入らない状態で人前で歌うこと」に対する拒絶反応が存在したが、それ以降の世代は（少なくとも気心の知れた仲間同士の前では）屈託なく歌って楽しむという意識が存在していたこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese people of a certain age and over rejected &quot;to sing in front of people without drinking,&quot; but younger ones had a feeling to enjoy singing without any inhibition (at least in front of their familiar friends).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese people of a certain age and over rejected &quot; singing in front of people without drinking,&quot; but the younger ones enjoyed singing without any inhibition (at least in front of their familiar friends).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese people of a certain age and over rejected &apos;singing in front of people without drinking,&apos; but the younger ones enjoyed singing without any inhibition (at least in front of their familiar friends).</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="90">
<j>通常の飲食店でカラオケを行う場合、知人以外の客もいる場所で歌うことになる場合が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the case of singing to karaoke in a common bar, one often has to sing in front of customers who are strangers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When singing karaoke in a common bar, one often has to sing in front of customers who are strangers.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When singing karaoke in a common bar, one often has to sing in front of customers who are strangers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>しかしカラオケボックスの個室内は基本的に友人知人しかおらず、純粋に歌う楽しさを満喫できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, basically there are only friends in a compartment of karaoke box, and therefore one can fully enjoy pure singing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, basically there are only friends in a compartment of a karaoke box, and therefore one can fully enjoy singing.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, basically there are only friends in a compartment of a karaoke box, and therefore one can fully enjoy singing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>たとえ下手な歌だとしても、見知らぬ他人から揶揄される心配もない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is no worry about being made fun of by a stranger even if he sings badly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is no worry about being made fun of by a stranger even if he sings badly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is no worry about being made fun of by a stranger even if he sings badly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="93">
<j>「カラオケで歌う歌を覚えるためにCDを買う」層が増え、1990年代の日本でシングルコンパクトディスクのミリオンセラーが多発した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An increasing number of people &quot;purchased CDs to learn a song to sing to karaoke,&quot; and many of Japanese single CDs sold more than a million copies in the 1990&apos;s.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An increasing number of people &quot;purchased CDs to learn a song to sing with karaoke,&quot; and many of Japanese single CDs sold more than a million copies in the 1990&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An increasing number of people &apos;purchased CDs to learn a song to sing with karaoke,&apos; and many of Japanese single CDs sold more than a million copies in the 1990&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="94">
<j>カラオケボックスは、学生のコンパやサラリーマンなどの懇親会の二次会の会場としてよく利用される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Karaoke box is frequently used for an after-party of a social gathering by students and corporate employees.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A Karaoke box is frequently used for an after-party of a social gathering by students and corporate employees.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A Karaoke box is frequently used for an after-party of a social gathering by students and corporate employees.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>日本人の娯楽の代表の一つである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is one of typical amusement for the Japanese.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is one of typical amusements for the Japanese.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is one of typical amusements for the Japanese.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>しかしいつの世にも人前で歌うことを苦手とする人は少なからず存在している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, not a few people do not like singing in front of others in any generation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, quite a few people do not like singing in front of others in any generation.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, quite a few people do not like singing in front of others in any generation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="97">
<j>詳細はカラオケボックスを参照のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Refer to karaoke box for detail.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Refer to karaoke box for details.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Refer to karaoke box for details.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="16">
<tit>
<j>通信カラオケ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Online karaoke</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Online karaoke</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Online karaoke</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="98">
<j>1992年、タイトーが通信カラオケ「X2000」を発売する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1992, Taito Corporation released online karaoke &quot;X2000.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1992, Taito Corporation released online karaoke &quot;X2000.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1992, Taito Corporation released online karaoke &apos;X2000.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>同年、エクシングも「JOYSOUND」を発売。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same year, Xing Inc. released &quot;JOYSOUND.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same year, Xing Inc. released &quot;JOYSOUND.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same year, Xing Inc. released &apos;JOYSOUND.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>通信カラオケは、いままでメディア（媒体）で供給されていた楽曲が、通信により提供されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While songs were conventionally supplied through media, the online karaoke is configured to supply them through online communication.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While songs were conventionally supplied through media, the online karaoke is configured to supply them through online communications.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While songs were conventionally supplied through media, the online karaoke is configured to supply them through online communications.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>カラオケ装置は独立して存在するものではなく、通信で接続された一つのシステムの中に組み込まれた端末装置となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The karaoke machine was not an independent machine anymore but a terminal device incorporated in an online communication system.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The karaoke machine is not an independent machine anymore, but a terminal device incorporated in an online communication system.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The karaoke machine is not an independent machine anymore, but a terminal device incorporated in an online communication system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>大量にソフト（メディア (媒体)）を各カラオケ装置脇に用意する必要がなく、機械駆動装置がないため小型化し省スペース化も図れ、新曲の配布も早くなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was no need of preparing a lot of software (media) beside each karaoke machine, the footprint was reduced by downsizing without using machine drive system, and new songs were distributed faster than before.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was no need of preparing a lot of software (media) beside each karaoke machine, the footprint was reduced by downsizing without using a machine drive system, and new songs were distributed faster than before.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was no need of preparing a lot of software (media) beside each karaoke machine, the footprint was reduced by downsizing without using a machine drive system, and new songs were distributed faster than before.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>ビジネスモデルとして、機器を販売、ソフトを販売するものが、使用量に応じた課金システムとなっていくことでもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The business model also changed from selling devices and software to charging based on the amount used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The business model also changed from selling devices and software to charging based on the amount used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The business model also changed from selling devices and software to charging based on the amount used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="104">
<j>その後、他メーカーも相次いで参入。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other karaoke companies entered the industry on after the other.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other karaoke companies entered the industry one after another.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other karaoke companies entered the industry one after another.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>第一興商は「DAM」、ギガネットワークスは「GIGA」、パイオニアは「BeMAXS」、ビクターは「孫悟空 (カラオケ)」、セガは「セガカラ」、USENは「U-kara」を発売。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daiichikosho released &quot;DAM,&quot; GIGAnetworks released &quot;GIGA,&quot; Pioneer Corporation released &quot;BeMAXS,&quot; Victor Company of Japan released released &quot;SONGOKU (karaoke),&quot; SEGA released &quot;segakara,&quot; and USEN released &quot;U-kara.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daiichikosho released &quot;DAM,&quot; GIGAnetworks released &quot;GIGA,&quot; Pioneer Corporation released &quot;BeMAXS,&quot; Victor Company of Japan released released &quot;SONGOKU (karaoke),&quot; SEGA released &quot;segakara,&quot; and USEN released &quot;U-kara.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daiichikosho released &apos;DAM,&apos; GIGAnetworks released &apos;GIGA,&apos; Pioneer Corporation released &apos;BeMAXS,&apos; Victor Company of Japan released &apos;SONGOKU (karaoke),&apos; SEGA released &apos;segakara,&apos; and USEN released &apos;U-kara.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;released released→released</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="106">
<j>詳細は通信カラオケを参照のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Refer to online karaoke for detail.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Refer to online karaoke for details.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Refer to online karaoke for details.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="17">
<tit>
<j>オリコンカラオケチャート</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oricon karaoke chart</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oricon karaoke chart</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oricon karaoke chart</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="107">
<j>オリコンでは、1990年代半ば頃から全国のカラオケのリクエストランキングを集計したカラオケチャートを発表している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oricon has been publishing karaoke chart listing the national ranking of songs requested in karaoke since the mid 1990&apos;s.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oricon has been publishing karaoke chart listing the national ranking of songs requested in karaoke since the mid 1990&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oricon has been publishing karaoke chart listing the national ranking of songs requested in karaoke since the mid 1990&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>ただし、データ集計にかかる時間の関係上、各カラオケメーカーが発表するデータよりも2週ほど遅れたランキングとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, due to time required for processing data, the ranking is published two weeks later than data released by each karaoke company.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, due to the time required for processing data, the ranking is published two weeks later than the data is released by each karaoke company.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, due to the time required for processing data, the ranking is published two weeks later than the data is released by each karaoke company.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="109">
<j>カラオケチャートの特徴は、長期間にわたって1位やトップ10入りをする曲が多いことで、カラオケファンの人気曲がごく一部に集中していることを示している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The karaoke chart is characterized in that many songs stay at the top or within the top 10 for a long time, which means only a handful of songs are popular among karaoke fans.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The karaoke chart is characterized by many songs that stay at the top or within the top 10 for a long time, which means only a handful of songs are popular among karaoke fans.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The karaoke chart is characterized by many songs that stay at the top or within the top 10 for a long time, which means only a handful of songs are popular among karaoke fans.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>また、毎年ある時期になると同じ曲が入ってくる（例えば高校野球の季節には岩崎良美 (歌手)の「タッチ」が必ず上位に入る）傾向が強いことも挙げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is also a strong tendency that the same song enters the chart in a certain season of every year (for example, &quot;Touch&quot; by Yoshimi IWASAKI always enters high on the list in the season of high school baseball games).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is also a strong tendency that the same song enters the chart in a certain season of every year (for example, &quot;Touch&quot; by Yoshimi IWASAKI always enters high on the list in the season of high school baseball games).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is also a strong tendency that the same song enters the chart in a certain season of every year (for example, &apos;Touch&apos; by Yoshimi IWASAKI always enters high on the list in the season of high school baseball games).</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="18">
<tit>
<j>利用者の変遷とソフトの変遷</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Transition of user and transition of software</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Transition of user and transition of software</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Transition of user and transition of software</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="111">
<j>カラオケで再生された音楽は装置が置かれた場所で好まれるものが主流だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The mainstream of the songs reproduced by karaoke were what were favored in the place where the device was placed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The mainstream of the songs reproduced by karaoke were what was favored in the place where the device was placed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The mainstream of the songs reproduced by karaoke were what was favored in the place where the device was placed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>カラオケ装置が最初に置かれたのは井上が仕事場としていた酒場であり、酒場で好まれる歌、演歌が中心だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At first, the karaoke machine was placed in bars where Inoue worked, and therefore enka, which was favored in the bars, was the mainstream.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At first, the karaoke machine was placed in bars where Inoue worked, and therefore enka, which was favored in the bars, was the mainstream.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At first, the karaoke machine was placed in bars where Inoue worked, and therefore enka, which was favored in the bars, was the mainstream.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="113">
<j>その後、カラオケボックスとなり、学生までその対象が広がると、歌謡曲やヒット曲、そして洋楽へと音源は広がった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, when the karaoke box emerged and students were included in the target, the music source ranged popular songs, hit songs, and Western music.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, when the karaoke box emerged and students were targeted, the music source range included popular songs, hit songs, and Western music.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, when the karaoke box emerged and students were targeted, the music source range included popular songs, hit songs, and Western music.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="114">
<j>さらに、ファミリー層までが通いだすと、子供向けの曲、さらにそしてさらには、通常のレコード、CDではなかなか手に入らなかった諸外国の音楽まで現在は幅広い音源が提供されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, children&apos;s songs were covered when families started to go to karaoke, and now a wide range of music is provided including even foreign music that was not available through records and CDs.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, children&apos;s songs were covered when families started to go to karaoke, and now a wide range of music is provided including even foreign music that was not available through records and CDs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, children&apos;s songs were covered when families started to go to karaoke, and now a wide range of music is provided including even foreign music that was not available through records and CDs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="19">
<tit>
<j>装置の変遷</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Transition of equipment</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Transition of equipment</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Transition of equipment</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="20">
<tit>
<j>カラオケボックス・ルーム</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Karaoke box/room</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Karaoke box/room</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Karaoke box/room</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="115">
<j>カラオケボックスは、岡山県内において廃車になった貨物列車/貨物自動車のコンテナを改造したのが始まりである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Karaoke box started by converting disused containers of freight trains/motor trucks into karaoke box in Okayama Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Karaoke box started by converting disused containers of freight trains/motor trucks into karaoke boxes in Okayama Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Karaoke box started by converting disused containers of freight trains/motor trucks into karaoke boxes in Okayama Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="116">
<j>近年はカラオケ専門のルームタイプが主流である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Room type exclusive for karaoke is the recent main stream.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Room types exclusive for karaoke is the recent main stream.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Room types exclusive for karaoke is the recent main stream.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="117">
<j>詳細はカラオケボックスを参照のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Refer to karaoke box for detail.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Refer to karaoke box for details.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Refer to karaoke box for details.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="21">
<tit>
<j>通信カラオケ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Online karaoke</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Online karaoke</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Online karaoke</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="118">
<j>初期の通信カラオケは、音楽音質の悪さと映像のバリエーションが貧弱などクリアしなければならない面もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The online karaoke in the early years had some problems to be solved, such as poor sound quality of music and poor variations of images.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The online karaoke in the early years had some problems to be solved, such as poor sound quality of music and poor variations of images.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The online karaoke in the early years had some problems to be solved, such as poor sound quality of music and poor variations of images.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="119">
<j>それまでの媒体経由の音源はアナログ録音で基本的にはレコードやラジオ、テレビで放送される音楽を再記録したものに近いものであり音源は似たようなものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The music source via a medium before that was analog recorded, which was basically almost music once played on a record, radio, or TV and recorded again using similar sources.</e>
<cmt>「似たようなもの」とありますが、「レコードやラジオ、テレビで放送される音楽」の音源が似たようなものであると解釈して訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The music source via a medium before that was analog recorded, which was basically almost music once played on a record, radio, or TV and recorded again using similar sources.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The music source via a medium before that was analog recorded, which was basically almost music once played on a record, radio, or TV and recorded again using similar sources.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="120">
<j>しかし、通信カラオケで使われているのは音源はMIDIデータで構成されたデジタルデータでありカラオケ装置はMIDI再生装置であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the online karaoke used digital data in the form of MIDI data as the music source, and the karaoke machine was a MIDI player.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the online karaoke used digital data in the form of MIDI data as the music source, and the karaoke machine was a MIDI player.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the online karaoke used digital data in the form of MIDI data as the music source, and the karaoke machine was a MIDI player.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="121">
<j>このMIDI再生装置は基本的には音楽演奏用シンセサイザーであり、これは演奏を録音した音源の再生とは全く異なる再生形態であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The MIDI player was basically a synthesizer for playing music, and the reproduction method was very different from reproduction of the music source made by recording a live performance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The MIDI player was basically a synthesizer for playing music, and the reproduction method was very different from reproduction of the music source made by recording a live performance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The MIDI player was basically a synthesizer for playing music, and the reproduction method was very different from reproduction of the music source made by recording a live performance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="122">
<j>質の悪さはMIDIデータが悪いというよりはMIDI再生装置側のクオリティの低さによってもたらされたものであり、その実態はアナログ録音されたプロの演奏と比べて全く比べ物にならなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The poor sound quality was brought by the poor quality of the MIDI player rather than the MIDI data, and the actual condition was far from the analog recorded professional performance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The poor sound quality was brought by the poor quality of the MIDI player rather than the MIDI data, and the actual condition was far from the analog recorded professional performance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The poor sound quality was brought by the poor quality of the MIDI player rather than the MIDI data, and the actual condition was far from the analog recorded professional performance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="123">
<j>さらに、付け加えられた映像バリエーションの質もこれに加わり当初の印象は質よりも楽曲の多様性と早期提供度合いにそのメリットがあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, with the poor variation of the added images, the initially impressed merit was the variety of songs and early supply of new songs rather than the quality.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, with the poor variation of the added images, the initially impressed merit was the variety of songs and early supply of new songs rather than the quality.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, with the poor variation of the added images, the initially impressed merit was the variety of songs and early supply of new songs rather than the quality.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="124">
<j>現在ではデジタル音楽技術が進歩し、MIDI再生装置だけでなく、デジタル音楽再生装置を内蔵するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Now that technologies of digital music have advanced, not only the MIDI player but also a digital music player are incorporated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Now that technologies of digital music have advanced, not only the MIDI player, but also a digital music player are incorporated.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Now that technologies of digital music have advanced, not only the MIDI player, but also a digital music player are incorporated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="125">
<j>シンセサイザー機能に加えデジタル録音データ再生機能（いわゆるサンプリングデータ再生機能）をもつようになり再生装置は音質向上、機能向上している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With a function of reproducing digital recorded data (so-called sample data reproduction function) in addition to the synthesizer, the reproduction device has improved in view of sound quality and function.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the function of reproducing digital recorded data (so-called sample data reproduction function) in addition to the synthesizer, the reproduction device has improved in view of sound quality and function.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the function of reproducing digital recorded data (so-called sample data reproduction function) in addition to the synthesizer, the reproduction device has improved in view of sound quality and function.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="126">
<j>詳細は通信カラオケを参照のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Refer to the online karaoke for details.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ対応しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="22">
<tit>
<j>カラオケの画面</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Karaoke screen</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Karaoke screen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Karaoke screen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="127">
<j>初期はテレビ画面そのものがなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In early times, no TV screen was used at all.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In early times, no TV screen was used at all.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In early times, no TV screen was used at all.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="128">
<j>その後、テレビ画面に字幕が出るようになり、その字幕の通りに歌うが、かつては同じものしか出なかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, caption was played on the TV screen to sing along the caption, but the same images were displayed on it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, captions were played on the TV screen to sing along with the caption, but the same images were displayed on it.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, captions were played on the TV screen to sing along with the caption, but the same images were displayed on it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="129">
<j>その後、曲のタイトルや歌詞の意味にあわせた、一種の寸劇といえる画像が追加された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, images like a skit adapted to the meanings of the title or the lyric of the song were added.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, images like a skit adapted to the meanings of the title or the lyric of the song were added.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, images like a skit adapted to the meanings of the title or the lyric of the song were added.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="130">
<j>これは地域性としてご当地ソングや歌詞の重みのあるフォークソングで重要視される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such images are highly appreciated for a gotochi (local) song that highly regards the locality and a folk song with serious lyrics.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such images are highly appreciated for a gotochi (local) song that highly regards the locality and folk song with serious lyrics.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such images are highly appreciated for a gotochi (local) song that highly regards the locality and folk song with serious lyrics.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="131">
<j>たとえば狩人の曲であるあずさ2号の場合はあずさ (列車)の走行シーンが流れるといった具合である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, in the case of &quot;Azusa 2-go&quot; sung by Kariudo, an image of running Azusa (train) is played.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, in the case of &quot;Azusa 2-go&quot; sung by Kariudo, an image of running Azusa (train) is played.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, in the case of &apos;Azusa 2-go&apos; sung by Kariudo, an image of running Azusa (train) is played.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="23">
<tit>
<j>自宅でのカラオケ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Karaoke at home</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Karaoke at home</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Karaoke at home</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="132">
<j>1970年代に入ると、家庭用テープレコーダーは、コンパクトカセットタイプのものも音楽鑑賞に堪え得るレベルに達していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the 1970&apos;s, household tape recorders including the compact cassette type reached a high level enough for music appreciation.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the 1970&apos;s, household tape recorders including the compact cassette type reached a high level enough for music appreciation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the 1970&apos;s, household tape recorders including the compact cassette type reached a high level enough for music appreciation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="133">
<j>特にラジオカセットレコーダー（ラジカセ）が普及すると、これをカラオケ用の装置として使うようになった（多くのラジカセには、マイク接続による拡声器機能が付いていた）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially when a radio cassette recorder grew popular, it was used as a karaoke device (many of the radio cassette recorders had a loudspeaker function connected to a microphone).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Especially when a radio cassette recorder grew popular, it was used as a karaoke device (many of the radio cassette recorders had a loudspeaker function connected to a microphone).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Especially when a radio cassette recorder grew popular, it was used as a karaoke device (many of the radio cassette recorders had a loudspeaker function connected to a microphone).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="134">
<j>1980年代後半には、レーザーディスクによるカラオケシステムが現れ、ある程度の普及を見た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the late 1980&apos;s, a karaoke system using a laser disk was released and diffused to a certain degree.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the late 1980&apos;s, a karaoke system using a laser disk was released and diffused to a certain degree.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the late 1980&apos;s, a karaoke system using a laser disk was released and diffused to a certain degree.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="135">
<j>これはメディアの性質上、映像が含まれており、テレビ画面上に映像と歌詞を表示して使われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The medium included images by nature, and was capable of displaying the images and the lyrics on the TV screen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The medium included images of nature, and was capable of displaying the images and the lyrics on the TV screen.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the nature of the medium, it included images, and was capable of displaying the images and the lyrics on the TV screen.</e>
<cmt>「メディアの性質上」がＮＣ訳では違うので変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="136">
<j>一般のレーザーディスクプレーヤーと異なり、マイク入力とそれへのエフェクトの機構があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Unlike general laser disk players, a microphone input terminal and a mechanism for an effect on it were included.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unlike general laser disk players, a microphone input terminal and a mechanism for an effect on it were included.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unlike general laser disk players, a microphone input terminal and a mechanism for an effect on it were included.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="137">
<j>さらに選曲ボタンが多かったりと、カラオケ使用のための操作ボタンが多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, it had many operation buttons for karaoke use, such as many song selection buttons.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, it had many operational buttons for karaoke use, such as many song selection buttons.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, it had many operational buttons for karaoke use, such as many song selection buttons.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="138">
<j>1995年には家庭用にも通信カラオケが登場している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1995, the online karaoke for domestic use was released.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1995, the online karaoke for domestic use was released.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1995, the online karaoke for domestic use was released.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="139">
<j>家庭用ゲーム機でもPCエンジンではCD-G、ドリームキャストやWiiでは通信カラオケによるカラオケシステムに対応している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among home-use game machines, PC Engine is adapted to a karaoke system based on CD-G, and Dreamcast and Wii are adapted to an online karaoke system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among home-use game machines, PC Engine is adapted to a karaoke system based on CD-G, and Dreamcast and Wii are adapted to an online karaoke system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among home-use game machines, PC Engine is adapted to a karaoke system based on CD-G, and Dreamcast and Wii are adapted to an online karaoke system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="140">
<j>音源媒体については、1970年代初めごろよりラジオ番組の中でカラオケ（伴奏のみの音楽）を流す企画もあり、これを録音する聴取者も居た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the early 1970&apos;s, there were radio programs that played karaoke (accompaniment), and some listeners recorded them as a music source.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the early 1970&apos;s, there have been radio programs that played karaoke (accompaniment), and some listeners recorded them as a music source.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the early 1970&apos;s, there have been radio programs that played karaoke (accompaniment), and some listeners recorded them as a music source.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="141">
<j>また、市販のレコードにはカラオケがほとんど存在しなかったが、ミュージックテープ（音楽カセット）では、カラオケのみを収録したものが多くラインナップされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although there were almost no karaoke records in store, many music tapes (music cassette tapes) exclusive for karaoke were listed on lineup.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although there were almost no karaoke records in stores, many music tapes (music cassette tapes) exclusively for karaoke were listed on lineup.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although there were almost no karaoke records in stores, many music tapes (music cassette tapes) exclusively for karaoke were listed on lineup.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="142">
<j>テレビの歌番組で歌手の歌に合わせて歌詞の字幕スーパーも放映するようになって以後、楽曲によってはそのCD自体にカラオケが付属するようにもなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since lyrics started to be captioned along with the song by a singer in a TV music show, a karaoke version of some songs was made to be included in its CD.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since lyrics started to be captioned along with the song by a singer in a TV music show, a karaoke version of some of the songs was made to be included in his CD.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since lyrics started to be captioned along with the song by a singer in a TV music show, a karaoke version of some of the songs was made to be included in his CD.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="143">
<j>特別にカラオケの音源がなくとも自宅でカラオケができるようにもなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It became possible to enjoy karaoke without a special music source for karaoke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It became possible to enjoy karaoke without a special music source for karaoke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It became possible to enjoy karaoke without a special music source for karaoke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="144">
<j>また、カラオケ機能を搭載したゲームなども数多く出ている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are also released many video games with a karaoke function.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also released were many video games with a karaoke function.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also released were many video games with a karaoke function.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="145">
<j>（任天堂の「大合奏!バンドブラザーズDX」「カラオケJOYSOUND Wii」やなど）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(For example, &quot;Band Brothers DX&quot; and &quot;Karaoke JOYSOUND Wii&quot; from Nintendo Co., Ltd.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(For example, &quot;Band Brothers DX&quot; and &quot;Karaoke JOYSOUND Wii&quot; from Nintendo Co., Ltd.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(For example, &apos;Band Brothers DX&apos; and &apos;Karaoke JOYSOUND Wii&apos; from Nintendo Co., Ltd.)</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="24">
<tit>
<j>マイク一体型カラオケ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Karaoke with microphone</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Karaoke with microphone</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Karaoke with a microphone</e>
<cmt>不定冠詞を追加しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="146">
<j>マイク一体型カラオケの登場。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emergence of karaoke with microphone</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emergence of karaoke with microphone</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emergence of karaoke with a microphone</e>
<cmt>不定冠詞を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="147">
<j>ハードウェアに収録済みの曲と、それに補充するRead Only Memoryを使用し、個人用でカラオケボックスにも負けない人気を得た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With music recorded in a hardware in advance and additional read only memories for personal use, the karaoke with microphone became as popular as the karaoke box.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With music recorded in hardware in advance and additional read only memories for personal use, karaoke with a microphone became as popular as the karaoke box.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With music recorded in hardware in advance and additional read only memories for personal use, karaoke with a microphone became as popular as the karaoke box.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="148">
<j>収録曲は懐メロや歌謡曲、演歌など高年層好みが中心のものも多く、若年層が中心のJ-POPが少なめであったが、最近は増加傾向にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many of them mainly contained &apos;natsumero&apos; (nostalgic popular songs), popular songs, and enka favored by old generations and few of J-pops favored by young people were contained, but J-pop songs are increasing recently.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many of them mainly contained &apos;natsumero&apos; (nostalgic popular songs), popular songs, and enka favored by old generations and few of J-pops favored by young people, and J-pop songs are increasing recently.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many of them mainly contained &apos;natsumero&apos; (nostalgic popular songs), popular songs, and enka favored by old generations and few of J-pops favored by young people, and J-pop songs are increasing recently.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="149">
<j>個人用としては、携帯電話やパーソナルコンピュータにカラオケソフトや楽曲データをダウンロードする、新しいサービスも試みられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For personal use, a new service of downloading karaoke software and music data to a mobile phone or a personal computer is attempted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For personal use, a new service for downloading karaoke software and music data to a mobile phone or a personal computer is being attempted.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For personal use, a new service for downloading karaoke software and music data to a mobile phone or a personal computer is being attempted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="25">
<tit>
<j>楽曲のカラオケヴァージョン</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Karaoke versions of music</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Karaoke versions of music</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Karaoke versions of music</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="150">
<j>1990年ころからカラオケヴァージョンの入ったシングルCDが現れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around 1990, single CDs including a karaoke version were released.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around 1990, single CDs including a karaoke version were released.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around 1990, single CDs including a karaoke version were released.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="151">
<j>アイドル歌手のCDには必須であるし、ポップス系のCDにも多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The karaoke version is a must for teenage singers&apos; CDs, and it is also common among pop music CDs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The karaoke version is a must for teenage singers&apos; CDs, and it is also common among pop music CDs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The karaoke version is a must for teenage singers&apos; CDs, and it is also common among pop music CDs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="152">
<j>呼び名は当初は「オリジナル・カラオケ」が多かったが、現在では「instrumental（inst.と略）」が主流である（宇多田ヒカル、竹内電気は現在でも基本的に「Original Karaoke」）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The product was initially called &quot;original karaoke,&quot; but now it is mainly called &quot;Instrumental (abbreviated to &apos;inst.&apos;)&quot; (Basically it is still called &quot;original karaoke&quot; for Hikaru UTADA and Takeuchi Denki).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The product was initially called &quot;original karaoke,&quot; but now it is mainly called &quot;Instrumental (abbreviated to &apos;inst.&apos;)&quot; (Basically it is still called &quot;original karaoke&quot; for Hikaru UTADA and Takeuchi Denki).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The product was initially called &apos;original karaoke,&apos; but now it is mainly called &apos;Instrumental (abbreviated to &apos;inst.&apos;)&apos; (Basically it is still called &apos;original karaoke&apos; for Hikaru UTADA and Takeuchi Denki).</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="153">
<j>2枚組アルバムの2枚目をカラオケヴァージョンとすることがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sometimes the second of a double album is a karaoke version.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sometimes the second of a double album is a karaoke version.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sometimes the second of a double album is a karaoke version.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="154">
<j>（槇原敬之の「smiling gold」、キリンジのスウィートソウルe.p.、竹内まりやのExpressions）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(for example, &quot;Smiling Gold&quot; by Noriyuki MAKIHARA, &quot;Sweet Soul e.p.&quot; by Kirinji, and &quot;Expressions&quot; by Mariya TAKEUCHI)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(for example, &quot;Smiling Gold&quot; by Noriyuki MAKIHARA, &quot;Sweet Soul e.p.&quot; by Kirinji, and &quot;Expressions&quot; by Mariya TAKEUCHI)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(for example, &apos;Smiling Gold&apos; by Noriyuki MAKIHARA, &apos;Sweet Soul e.p.&apos; by Kirinji, and &apos;Expressions&apos; by Mariya TAKEUCHI)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="155">
<j>シングルの場合、旧来のレコードからの伝統により、A面とB面に対応する二曲を含み、それらのカラオケバージョンをあわせて四曲を収録する形が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the case of single CDs, two songs corresponding to sides A and B as with the old records are contained, and four tunes are often recorded along with karaoke versions of them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the case of single CDs, two songs corresponding to sides A and B as with the old records are contained, and four tunes are often recorded along with karaoke versions of them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the case of single CDs, two songs corresponding to sides A and B as with the old records are contained, and four tunes are often recorded along with karaoke versions of them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="156">
<j>これは、他方ではCDのシングルが8cmから12cm（マキシングル）に移行し、時間的な余裕が大きくなったことにも対応している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is also adapted to the fact that the size of a single CD increased from 8 cm to 12 cm (maxi single) allowing more temporal capacity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is also adapted to the fact that the size of a single CD increased from 8 cm to 12 cm (maxi single) allowing more temporal capacity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is also adapted to the fact that the size of a single CD increased from 8 cm to 12 cm (maxi single) allowing more temporal capacity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="157">
<j>ただし、移行する前からもこのような形態になりつつあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, such a tendency was seen even before the upsizing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, such a tendency was seen even before the upsizing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, such a tendency was seen even before the upsizing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Tommy6-bot(id:171289), AlleborgoBot(id:119729), Los688(id:12316), Fuji-77(id:22233), Nnh(id:474), 杉村(id:239446), Meter7(id:71606), 0null0(id:582), Lupinoid(id:68), Tribot(id:186681), Ygn kamiya(id:627), Nakanoootsuka(id:17040), OSY(id:35563), たぬき(id:27723), Dr jimmy(id:111486), Manekinn(id:196063), IwaimBot(id:190695), Point136(id:211299), Number4(id:205983), 新幹線(id:57409), Ｋｓ(id:15319), FlaBot(id:30804), Hoge-(id:158), Starbacks(id:1018), Kkkdc(id:32227), Hideyuki(id:9577), Shinkaiakikazu(id:108660), Carbuncle(id:346), Balmung0731(id:99201), カラオケ先生(id:115120), COCKY(id:19672), Edogawaconan(id:130408), Pararinpooh(id:42015), Sh(id:2707), Tetsujin(id:81219), Escarbot(id:59151), MDR-SK(id:192066), Utasong(id:145806), SuisuiBot(id:10165), TYSGCFAN(id:64043), あんも騎士(id:139357), Trashwriter(id:79181), やすとし(id:63220), Mee-san(id:33270), Nsq(id:54991), Suisui(id:69), Milkteas(id:35800), Jade0416(id:104181), 弥(id:61590), JAnDbot(id:66507), Modeha(id:1276), Sunflowerbed(id:152950), Kstigarbha(id:13376), Charenji(id:7908), わに(id:95540), TXiKiBoT(id:107492), Toto-tarou(id:16648), Sundaymondaytuesday(id:120975), Su-no-G(id:52744), Ponta2(id:129030), Rei-bot(id:94097), TERMINAL(id:107022), Masabb(id:71275), Bankokuya(id:91191), Kozawa(id:672), Doppo1127(id:169097), Tassi-(id:81774), R-pro(id:7329), Frame(id:95820), Wikiwind(id:144172), Eveningmist(id:28648), Ajtnk(id:18368), Vina-iwbot(id:56449), そそんそ(id:226686), Yukichin(id:725), Shevchenko(id:130320), YurikBot(id:18605), FeZn(id:444), TottyBot(id:101680), TaBOT-zerem(id:257085), Fromm(id:71291), Chadow(id:296365), ニューロン(id:8089), Comyu(id:58135), Cpro(id:28341), SieBot(id:126695), Ete(id:28565), Katsuya(id:21306), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>