<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>枡席</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masuseki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masuseki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masuseki (box seating)</e>
<cmt>補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>枡席（ますせき、升席とも）とは、日本の伝統的な観客席。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masuseki (box seat, 枡席 or 升席 in Chinese character) is a traditional auditorium in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masuseki, or box seating, (枡席 or 升席 in Chinese characters) is a traditional kind of auditorium in Japan.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masuseki, or box seating, (枡席 or 升席 in Chinese characters) is a traditional kind of auditorium in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>土間や板敷きの間を木組みによって人数人が座れるほどの四角形に仕切る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Doma (earthen floor) and wooden floor are squarely divided by wooden frames to make a space for several audiences to sit together.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The doma (earthen floor) or wooden floor is divided into squares by wooden frames to make a space for several people to sit together.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The doma (earthen floor) or wooden floor is divided into squares by wooden frames to make a space for several people to sit together.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>これを「枡」として観客に提供したことからこう呼ばれるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Regarding the divided space as a unit called &apos;masu&apos; (square pillar-shaped measuring box), they are provided for audience, which is the origin of the name &quot;Masuseki&quot; (masu seat).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term &quot;masuseki&apos; derives from the square shape called &apos;masu&apos; and &apos;seki&apos; which means seat.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term &quot;masuseki&quot; derives from the square shape called &apos;masu&apos; and &apos;seki&apos; which means seat.</e>
<cmt>一部シングルクォーテーションからダブルクォーテーションに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>劇場の枡席</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masuseki in theater</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masuseki in theater</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masuseki in theater</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>歴史と背景</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History and background</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History and background</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History and background</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>枡席は江戸時代の初め頃から歌舞伎や人形浄瑠璃の劇場で普及しはじめた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masuseki had gradually become popular in the theater for enjoying Kabuki (traditional drama performed by male actors) and Ningyo joruri (traditional drama performed by puppet) since around the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masuseki gradually became popular in theaters showing kabuki (a kind of traditional drama performed by male actors) and ningyo joruri (a traditional drama performed with puppets) from early in the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity, grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masuseki gradually became popular in theaters showing kabuki (a kind of traditional drama performed by male actors) and ningyo joruri (a traditional drama performed with puppets) from early in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>period 小文字としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>芝居小屋の枡席は一般に「土間｣（どま）と呼ばれ、料金は最も安く設定されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masuseki in the playhouse was generally called &apos;doma,&apos; whose charge was set at the lowest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masuseki in small playhouses were generally called &apos;doma,&apos; and they were the lowest priced seats in the house.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masuseki in small playhouses were generally called &apos;doma,&apos; and they were the lowest priced seats in the house.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>これは初期の芝居小屋には屋根を掛けることが許されていなかったからである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reason why the charge was set at so low is that nascent playhouses were not permitted to have a roof.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A reason why the price was set so low is that early playhouses were not permitted to have a roof.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A reason why the price was set so low is that early playhouses were not permitted to have a roof.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>雨が降り始めると土間は水浸しになって芝居見物どころではなくなってしまったからである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, if it started to rain, doma got soaked, with the result that enjoying plays became the last thing for audience.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, if it started to rain, the doma got soaked, with the result that the audience found it difficult to enjoy the play.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, if it started to rain, the doma got soaked, with the result that the audience found it difficult to enjoy the play.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>したがってこの頃の土間にはまだ仕切りがなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Accordingly, there was no partition in doma at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Accordingly, there were no divided sections in the doma at that time.</e>
<cmt>Word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Accordingly, there were no divided sections in the doma at that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>瓦葺の屋根を備えた芝居小屋が初めて建てられたのは享保9年 (1724) のことで、雨天下の上演が可能になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was 1724 when the playhouse with a tiled roof was first established, which enabled the running even in the rain.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was 1724 when the first playhouse with a tiled roof was established, and this enabled the play to be performed even in the rain.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was 1724 when the first playhouse with a tiled roof was established, and this enabled the play to be performed even in the rain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>その結果この頃から土間は板敷きとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, wooden floor had been adopted to cover the doma since this period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result wooden flooring was adopted to cover the doma from this period onwards.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result wooden flooring was adopted to cover the doma from this period onwards.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>すると座席を恒常的に仕切ることができるようになり、明和のはじめ頃（1760年代後半）から次第に枡席が現れるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The appearance of the wooden floor allowed the auditorium to be divided constantly, which resulted in the gradual advent of Masuseki from the late 1760s.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The advent of the wooden floor allowed the auditorium to be divided permanently, which resulted in the gradual appearance of masuseki from the late 1760s.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The advent of the wooden floor allowed the seats to be divided permanently, which resulted in the gradual appearance of masuseki from the late 1760s.</e>
<cmt>「座席を分ける」ので、auditorium →seats としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>当時の芝居小屋の枡席は一般に「七人詰」で、料金は一桝あたり25匁だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Each Masuseki in the playhouse at that time had a seating capacity of seven, whose charge was 25 monme (old denomination).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Each masuseki in the playhouse at that time had a seating capacity of seven, which cost 25 monme (old denomination).</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Each masuseki in the playhouse at that time had a seating capacity of seven, which cost 25 monme (old denomination).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>これを家族や友人などと買い上げて芝居を見物した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Usually, family or friends as a unit purchased the Masuseki for enjoying plays.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Usually, family or friends purchased the masuseki as a unit.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Usually, family or friends purchased the masuseki as a unit.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>一人が飛び込みで見物する場合には「割土間」といって、一桝の料金のおよそ七等分にあたる1朱を払って「他所様（よそさま）と御相席（ごあいせき）」ということになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When a stranger joined the unit, he or she paid one shu (old denomination), one seventh of the charge of 25 monme, to &apos;watch the play with other people by sharing the seat,&apos; which was called &apos;wari-doma&apos; (sharing a box seat).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If a stranger sat in the unit, he or she paid one shu (old denomination), one seventh of the price of 25 monme, to &apos;watch the play with other people sharing a seat&apos;, and this was called &apos;wari-doma&apos; (sharing a box seat).</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity, grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If a stranger sat in the unit, he or she paid one shu (old denomination), one seventh of the price of 25 monme, to &apos;watch the play with other people sharing a seat,&apos; and this was called &apos;wari-doma&apos; (sharing a box seat).</e>
<cmt>カンマを位置を移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>土間の両脇には一段高く中二階造りにした畳敷きの「桟敷｣（さじき）があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the both sides of doma, there were mezzanine called &apos;Sajiki,&apos; which were one-step higher seats than other seats, equipped with tatami flooring.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On either side of the doma there was a mezzanine style &apos;sajiki,&apos; which was one-step higher than the other seats, equipped with tatami flooring.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity, grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On either side of the doma there was a mezzanine style &apos;sajiki,&apos; which was one-step higher than the other seats, equipped with tatami flooring.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>さらにその上に場内をコの字に囲むようにして三階造りにした畳敷きの「上桟敷｣（かみさじき）があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, above the Sajiki, there were seats with tatami flooring called &apos;Kami-sajiki&apos; composing the top layer of the three layered structure, which were arranged as if surrounding the inside of the theater in U-shape.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, above the sajiki, there were seats with tatami flooring called &apos;kami-sajiki&apos; composing the top layer of the three layered structure, which was arranged to surround the center of the theater in a U-shape.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word choice, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, above the sajiki, there were seats with tatami flooring called &apos;kami-sajiki&apos; composing the top layer of the three layered structure, which was arranged to surround the center of the theater in a U-shape.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>料金は現在とは逆で、上へいくほど高くなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Contrary to the current system, seats arranged at higher layer requested higher charge.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Contrary to the current system seats at a higher level cost more.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Contrary to the current system seats at a higher level cost more.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>こうして場内が総板張りになったことで、客席の構成にも柔軟性がでてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, boarding over the whole floor created flexibility in the construction of auditorium.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, boarding over the whole floor created flexibility in the construction of the auditorium.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, boarding over the whole floor created flexibility in the construction of the auditorium.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>享和2年 (1802) 中村座が改築された際に、桟敷の前方に土間よりも一段高い板敷きの土間が設けられたのを嚆矢とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reconstruction work of Nakamura-za Theater in 1802 established one-step higher doma with wooden floor ahead of Sajiki for the first time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reconstruction work on the Nakamura-za Theater in 1802 established a one-step higher doma with a wooden floor in front of the sajiki for the first time.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reconstruction work on the Nakamura-za Theater in 1802 established a one-step higher doma with a wooden floor in front of the sajiki for the first time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>以後の芝居小屋では土間にもさまざまな段差をつけるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Following the example of Nakamura-za Theater, other playhouses later established were equipped with doma at various different levels.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Following the example of the Nakamura-za Theater, other playhouses established later were equipped with doma at various different levels.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Following the example of the Nakamura-za Theater, other playhouses established later were equipped with doma at various different levels.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>こうして格差がついた後方の土間のことを「高土間｣（たかどま）といい、舞台近くの「平土間｣（ひらどま）と区別した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Doma established in the rear as well as at higher level was called &apos;taka-doma&apos; (doma situated at higher level) to distinguish it from doma established in the vicinity of the stage, which was called &apos;hira-doma&apos; (doma situated at the base).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Doma placed at the rear at a higher level were called &apos;taka-doma&apos; (raised earthen floor) to distinguish them from the doma in the vicinity of the stage, which were called &apos;hira-doma&apos; (flat earthen floor).</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity, grammar, English translations made more explanatory.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Doma placed at the rear at a higher level were called &apos;taka-doma&apos; (raised earthen floor) to distinguish them from the doma in the vicinity of the stage, which were called &apos;hira-doma&apos; (flat earthen floor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="22">
<j>やがてそれぞれの枡席には座布団が敷かれ、煙草盆（中に水のはいった木箱の灰皿）が置かれるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before long, Zabuton (traditional Japanese cushions used to sit on the floor) and Tobacco-bon (tobacco tray, a wooden box containing water) were prepared for each Masuseki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before long, zabuton (traditional Japanese cushions used when sitting on the floor) and tabako-bon (tobacco trays, or wooden boxes containing water) were placed in each masuseki.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before long, zabuton (traditional Japanese cushions used when sitting on the floor) and tabako-bon (tobacco trays, or wooden boxes containing water) were placed in each masuseki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>枡席に芝居茶屋から出方が幕の内弁当や飲物を運んでくるようになったのもこの頃からである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The service that attendants deliver Makunouchi-bento (lunch box) and drinks from Shibai jaya (tea house located within a theater) to audience sitting at Masuseki started in those days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A service where attendants delivered makunouchi-bento (lunch boxes) and drinks from the shibai jaya (tea house located within the theater) to the audience while they sat in the masuseki started at around this time.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A service where attendants delivered makunouchi-bento (lunch boxes) and drinks from the shibai jaya (tea house located within the theater) to the audience while they sat in the masuseki started at around this time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>当時の芝居見物は早朝から日没までの一日がかりの娯楽だったので、枡席にもいくらかの「居住性の改善」が求められたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As enjoying plays spent the whole day at that time, people pursued some &apos;Improvement of the livability&apos; in Masuseki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a play was a whole day event at that time, people attempted to make the masuseki more &apos;livable&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a play was a whole day event at that time, from early in the morning to the sundown, people attempted to make the masuseki more &apos;livable.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を移動しました。一部翻訳を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="25">
<j>明治になると東京をはじめ各都市に新しい劇場が建てられてたが、そのほぼすべてが枡席を採用していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">New theaters were constructed in each city including Tokyo in the Meiji period, most of which were equipped with Masuseki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">New theaters were constructed in each city including Tokyo in the Meiji Period, most of which were equipped with masuseki.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">New theaters were constructed in each city including Tokyo in the Meiji period, most of which were equipped with masuseki.</e>
<cmt>period 小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>文明開化を謳ったこの時代にあっても、日本人は座布団の上に「坐る」方が居心地が良かったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although civilization and enlightenment was exhorted in that period, the Japanese preferred &apos;sitting&apos; on a Zabuton to sitting on a chair.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although civilization and enlightenment was encouraged in that period, the Japanese preferred &apos;sitting&apos; on a zabuton to sitting on a chair.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although civilization and enlightenment was encouraged in that period, the Japanese preferred &apos;sitting&apos; on a zabuton to sitting on a chair.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>全席を椅子席にして観客が「腰掛ける」ようにしたのは、演劇改良運動の一環として明治22年 (1889) に落成した歌舞伎座が最初だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kabuki-za Theater, which was completed in 1889 as part of Engeki kairyo undo (theatrical performance improvement movement), was the first theater to change all floor seats for chair seats, with the result that audiences were forced to &apos;sit&apos; on chairs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kabuki-za Theater, which was completed in 1889 as part of the Engeki kairyo undo (theatrical performance improvement movement), was the first theater to change all the floor seats to chair-based seating, with the result that audiences were forced to &apos;sit&apos; on chairs.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kabuki-za Theater, which was completed in 1889 as part of the Engeki kairyo undo (theatrical performance improvement movement), was the first theater to change all the floor seats to chair-based seating, with the result that audiences were forced to &apos;sit&apos; on chairs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>これを境に以後の劇場では専ら椅子席が採用されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since then, theaters newly constructed had adopted chair seats exclusively.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since then, newly constructed theaters have adopted chair seats exclusively.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since then, newly constructed theaters have adopted chair seats exclusively.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>その結果昭和の戦前頃までには、地方の伝統的小劇場を除いて、枡席は日本の劇場からほとんどその姿を消してしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, most Masuseki were eliminated from theaters in Japan except those in the traditional small theaters in local cities by around the prewar times in the Showa period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, most masuseki were eliminated from theaters in Japan except for those in the traditional small theaters in local cities by the early Showa Period.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, most masuseki were eliminated from theaters in Japan except for those in the traditional small theaters in local cities by the early Showa period.</e>
<cmt>period 小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>相撲興行の枡席</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masuseki for enjoying the professional sumo performance</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masuseki and sumo</e>
<cmt>Rewritten.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masuseki and sumo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>歴史と背景</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History and background</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History and background</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History and background</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="30">
<j>一方、勧進相撲として発達した大相撲は、その歴史的背景から各地の寺社の境内で不定期に興行されるのが常態で、長らくの専用の競技場を持たなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the grand sumo tournament has a historical background of having been developed from kanjin zumo (a fund-raising sumo held in aid of a temple or a shrine), it used to be performed irregularly at the precincts of temples and shrines, without having its own stadium for a long period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the grand sumo tournament has a historical background of having been developed from kanjin zumo (fund-raising sumo held in aid of a temple or a shrine), it used to be performed irregularly in the precincts of temples and shrines, and lacked its own stadium for a long period.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the grand sumo tournament has a historical background of having been developed from kanjin zumo (fund-raising sumo held in aid of a temple or a shrine), it used to be performed irregularly in the precincts of temples and shrines, and lacked its own stadium for a long period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>江戸では天保4年 (1833) 以降にようやく本所・回向院での相撲興行が定着する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was not until 1833 that the sumo performance had come to be held on a regular basis at Honjo-ecoin Temple In Edo (old Tokyo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was not until 1833 that sumo tournaments came to be held on a regular basis at Honjo-ecoin Temple In Edo (old Tokyo).</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was not until 1833 that sumo tournaments came to be held on a regular basis at Honjo Eko-in Temple in Edo (old Tokyo).</e>
<cmt>本所回向院→Honjo Eko-in Temple としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="32">
<j>劇場の場合とは対照的に、相撲興行の場から枡席は一度もその姿を消すことがなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Unlike Masuseki in theater, Masuseki for enjoying the sumo performance has never been eliminated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unlike masuseki in theaters, the masuseki for watching sumo have been a constant feature of the sport.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unlike masuseki in theaters, the masuseki for watching sumo have been a constant feature of the sport.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>明治以後も大相撲の開催地では、土俵も観客席も数日間の興行に耐えられるだけの仮仕立てで造ればよかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even after the Meiji period, Dohyo (sumo ring) and auditorium were improvised with the strength to withstand performance lasting for several days.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the Meiji Period, the dohyo (sumo ring) and the auditorium were built durable enough to last through tournaments lasting several days.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation, word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the Meiji period, the dohyo (sumo ring) and the auditorium were built durable enough to last through tournaments lasting several days.</e>
<cmt>period 小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>そのため木組みで簡単に客席を仕切ることができる枡席はかえって好都合だったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, Masuseki was adopted as a convenient system, because this system could easily and freely divide the auditorium only by wooden frames.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, masuseki were adopted as a convenient system because it was possible to easily and freely divide the auditorium through the use of wooden frames.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, masuseki were adopted as a convenient system because it was possible to easily and freely divide the auditorium through the use of wooden frames.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="35">
<j>回向院の境内に初めて常設の競技場「國技舘｣（両国国技館）が建てられたのは実に明治42年 (1909) になってのことだった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was 1909 that the permanent stadium &apos;Kokugikan&apos; (stadium for national sports, now Ryogoku Kokugikan) was first built at the precinct of Honjo-ecoin Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1909 the permanent stadium &apos;Kokugikan&apos; (stadium for national sports, now Ryogoku Kokugikan) was built in the precincts of Honjo-ecoin Temple.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1909 the permanent stadium &apos;Kokugikan&apos; (stadium for national sports, now Ryogoku Kokugikan) was built in the precincts of Honjo Eko-in Temple.</e>
<cmt>本所回向院→Honjo Eko-in Temple としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>この常設の國技舘にも枡席が導入され、しかもその後の相次ぐ失火や関東大震災による焼失と再建の際にもそれを存続させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This permanent stadium Kokugikan not only adopted Masuseki but also maintained it even if the stadium was burnt down due to repeated accidental fires and the Great Kanto Earthquake, and was demolished for reconstruction.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kokugikan not only adopted masuseki but also maintained them through its turbulent history, the stadium being burnt down due to repeated accidental fires, and rebuilt following the Great Kanto Earthquake.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity, grammar, word choice, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kokugikan not only adopted masuseki but also maintained them through its turbulent history, the stadium being burnt down due to repeated accidental fires, and rebuilt following the Great Kanto Earthquake.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>このことが、枡席が大相撲の会場とは不可分の伝統として定着する契機となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These became the momentum for Masuseki to be recognized as an inseparable tradition from the facilities prepared for the grand sumo tournament.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This became the impetus for masuseki to be recognized as an inseparable tradition as part of the facilities for the grand sumo tournament.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This became the impetus for masuseki to be recognized as an inseparable tradition as part of the facilities for the grand sumo tournament.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>國技舘は戦時中に陸軍によって接収され、以後大相撲は後楽園球場・明治神宮外苑の相撲場・浜町公園の仮設国技館を経て、昭和25年 (1950) からは蔵前国技館で、昭和60年 (1985) 以後は両国国技館で興行されるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Imperial Japanese Army took over the Kokugikan during the war, the grand sumo tournaments were held at Koraku-en garden baseball stadium, a sumo stadium established in the outer garden of the Meiji-jingu Shrine and then a temporary Kokugikan established in Hamacho park during the wartime, at Kuramae Kokugikan from 1950 to 1984, and has been held at Ryogoku Kokugikan since 1985.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the Imperial Japanese Army took over the Kokugikan during the war, the grand sumo tournaments were held consecutively at Koraku-en garden baseball stadium, a sumo stadium established in the outer garden of Meiji-jingu Shrine, a temporary Kokugikan established in Hamacho Park during the war, at Kuramae Kokugikan from 1950 to 1984, finally being held at Ryogoku Kokugikan since 1985.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, changed for clarity..</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the Imperial Japanese Army took over the Kokugikan during the war, the grand sumo tournaments were held consecutively at Koraku-en garden baseball stadium, a sumo stadium established in the outer garden of Meiji-jingu Shrine, a temporary Kokugikan established in Hamacho Park during the war, at Kuramae Kokugikan from 1950 to 1984, finally being held at Ryogoku Kokugikan since 1985.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>これらすべての会場に枡席が設けられたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">All of these facilities were equipped with Masuseki.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">All of these facilities were equipped with masuseki.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">All of these facilities were equipped with masuseki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="40">
<j>この間に変ったことといえば、枡席の土台が木組みから鉄骨組みになったこと、そしてそれまで枡席では認められていた喫煙が平成17年 (2005) から全面禁止となり、枡席にあった煙草盆が姿を消したことぐらいなもので、今日目にする大相撲本場所の模様は、往時のそれとほとんど変わらないものとなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Comparison between the atmosphere of the official grand sumo tournament in these days and that in old days shows that there is no remarkable change between them except the wooden-framed foundation of Masuseki was replaced with the steel-framed foundation as well as Tobacco-bon was removed since the smoking, which had been forgiven in Masuseki, at stadium was totally prohibited by a rule established in 2005.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Comparisons between the atmosphere of the official grand sumo tournament today and that in olden times show that there have been no remarkable changes except for the wood-frame foundations of the masuseki being replaced with steel-frame foundations and the disappearance of the tabako-bon since smoking, which had been permitted in masuseki, was totally prohibited at stadiums by a regulation established in 2005.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity, word choice, grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Comparisons between the atmosphere of the official grand sumo tournament today and that in olden times show that there have been no remarkable changes except for the wood-frame foundations of the masuseki being replaced with steel-frame foundations and the disappearance of the tabako-bon since smoking, which had been permitted in masuseki, was totally prohibited at stadiums by a regulation established in 2005.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>現状と課題</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Current situations and problems</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Current situation and problems with masuseki</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Current situation and problems with masuseki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="41">
<j>今日大相撲本場所が行なわれる両国国技館・大阪府立体育会館・愛知県体育館・福岡国際センターでは、いずれも一階席のほぼ全席が高土間式の枡席となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryogoku Kokugikan, Osaka Prefectural Gymnasium, Aichi Prefectural Gymnasium, and Fukuoka Convention Center, where the official grand sumo tournament is held today, adopt the Masuseki of taka-doma type for almost all seats on the first floor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryogoku Kokugikan, Osaka Prefectural Gymnasium, Aichi Prefectural Gymnasium, and Fukuoka Convention Center, the venues where the official grand sumo tournament is held today, have adopted the masuseki of taka-doma type for almost all the seats on the first floor.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryogoku Kokugikan, Osaka Prefectural Gymnasium, Aichi Prefectural Gymnasium, and Fukuoka Convention Center, the venues where the official grand sumo tournament is held today, have adopted the masuseki of taka-doma type for almost all the seats on the first floor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>国技館は耐火建材の土台にのった恒常床、他の三会場は鉄骨組みの仮設床が、それぞれ約1.5メートル四方の枡に仕切られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Permanent floor mounted on the foundation made of fire-resistant building materials in Ryogoku Kokugikan, as well as temporary steel-framed floor in other three facilities, are divided into square spaces, each square about 1.5m on a side.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The permanent floor mounted on a foundation made of fire-resistant building materials in Ryogoku Kokugikan, as well as the temporary steel-framed floor of the other three facilities, are divided into square spaces, each square measuring about 1.5m across.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity, word choice, grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The permanent floor mounted on a foundation made of fire-resistant building materials in Ryogoku Kokugikan, as well as the temporary steel-framed floor of the other three facilities, are divided into square spaces, each square measuring about 1.5 m across.</e>
<cmt>1.5 の後にスペースを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>そこに所定数の座布団が敷かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, prescribed numbers of Zabuton are put side by side for each square.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A set number of zabuton are put side by side in each square.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A set number of zabuton are put side by side in each square.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="44">
<j>国技館では「四人枡｣「五人枡｣「六人枡」の三種類の枡席があるが、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryogoku Kokugikan provides three types of Masuseki, &apos;Masuseki for four,&apos; &apos;Masuseki for five&apos; and &apos;Masuseki for six.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryogoku Kokugikan provides three types of masuseki, &apos;masuseki for four&apos;, &apos;masuseki for five&apos; and &apos;masuseki for six.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryogoku Kokugikan provides three types of masuseki, &apos;masuseki for four,&apos; &apos;masuseki for five&apos; and &apos;masuseki for six.&apos;</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置を移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>その大多数が伝統的な「四人枡」で、枡の中には4枚の座布団が所狭しと敷かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The traditional &apos;Masuseki for four&apos; occupies the majority, at which four pieces of Zabuton are put side by side as if squeezing into a small space.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The majority are the traditional &apos;masuseki for four&apos;, in which four zabuton are squeezed side by side into the small space.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The majority are the traditional &apos;masuseki for four,&apos; in which four zabuton are squeezed side by side into the small space.</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置を移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>「四人枡」とは、「その枡には4人まで坐ることができる」という意味である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The definition of &apos;Masuseki for four&apos; is &apos;The square has a seating capacity of four.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The definition of &apos;masuseki for four&apos; is &apos;the square has a seating capacity of four.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The definition of &apos;masuseki for four&apos; is &apos;the square has a seating capacity of four.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>したがって一人や二人でこれを使っても構わない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, only one person or two people may use &apos;Masuseki for four.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, it is fine for one or two people to sit there.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, it is fine for one or two people to sit there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>しかし料金はあくまでも枡ごとの料金なので、頭数が少ないと一人当たりの負担が増加する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, since charge must be paid by each Masuseki as a unit, the cost borne by individual would increase when &apos;Masuseki&apos; was occupied by the smaller number of people than the fixed number.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, since the cost is fixed for the whole masuseki, the cost borne by each person is higher if it is occupied by a smaller number.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, since the cost is fixed for the whole masuseki, the cost borne by each person is higher if it is occupied by a smaller number.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>例えば3万6800円の枡席Cを、4人で使えば一人当たり9200円になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For instance, when the charge for Masuseki C is 36,800 yen, the cost is 9,200yen per person if the Masuseki was occupied by four.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For instance, when the charge for Masuseki C is 36,800 yen, the cost is 9,200yen per person if the masuseki is occupied by four.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For instance, when the charge for Masuseki C is 36,800 yen, the cost is 9,200 yen per person if the masuseki is occupied by four.</e>
<cmt>yenの前にスペースを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>3人で一人当たり1万2267円、2人だと一人当たり1万8400円という高額の負担となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Similarly, the cost is 12,267 yen per person if Masuseki C was occupied by three, and the cost becomes as high as 18,400 yen per person if occupied by two.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Similarly, the cost is 12,267 yen per person if occupied by three, and as high as 18,400 yen per person if occupied by two.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Similarly, the cost is 12,267 yen per person if occupied by three, and as high as 18,400 yen per person if occupied by two.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>このため少々窮屈でも「四人枡」はやはり四人で使っているのがほとんどである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, almost all &apos;Masuseki for four&apos; are used by four people, even if they may feel cramped on a confined space.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, almost all &apos;masuseki for four&apos; are used by four people, even if they feel cramped in such a confined space.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, almost all &apos;masuseki for four&apos; are used by four people, even if they feel cramped in such a confined space.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="52">
<j>実際、約1.5メートル四方に4人が坐るというのは、今日の日本人の体格からみるとかなり窮屈な状態である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In fact, considering the fine physique of today&apos;s Japanese, sharing an about 1.5m square by four people makes them feel quite cramped.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In fact, considering the larger physical nature of today&apos;s Japanese, sharing a roughly 1.5m square space between four people makes can be quite cramped.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity, grammar, word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact, considering the larger physical nature of today&apos;s Japanese, sharing a roughly 1.5 m square space between four people can be quite cramped.</e>
<cmt>makes を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>そこに出方が弁当や飲物を運んでくると、もう足の踏み場もないほどになってしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After attendants delivered lunch boxes and drinks there, the Masuseki becomes as narrow as people can find no room to put their feet.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the attendants have brought lunch boxes and drinks, the masuseki becomes so cramped people can hardly find room to put their feet.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the attendants have brought lunch boxes and drinks, the masuseki becomes so cramped people can hardly find room to put their feet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>国技館では昨今の観客数の減少に歯止めをかける改革の一環として、特別限定チケット「二人枡」を試験的に導入したが、その数はまだ極めて少数に止まっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As part of reform aiming to put the brakes on the declining number of audience in these days, Japan Sumo Association experimentally introduced &apos;Masuseki for two&apos; by selling the special-limited tickets in the tournament at Ryogoku Kokugikan, however, only a few tickets have been sold.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As part of an initiative aiming to put the brakes on declining audience figures, the Japan Sumo Association introduced &apos;masuseki for two&apos; as an experiment by selling special limited tickets for the tournament at Ryogoku Kokugikan, however, this has not proved popular.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity, grammar, word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As part of an initiative aiming to put the brakes on declining audience figures, the Japan Sumo Association introduced &apos;masuseki for two&apos; as an experiment by selling special limited tickets for the tournament at Ryogoku Kokugikan, however, this has not proved popular.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>一方、大阪・名古屋・福岡の各会場でも観客の要望に応えるかたちで「二人枡」や「三人枡」を新たに導入し初めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, to meet people&apos;s demands, each facility in Osaka, Nagoya and Fukuoka newly introduced &apos;Masuseki for two&apos; and &apos;Masuseki for three.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, following requests from customers, each facility in Osaka, Nagoya and Fukuoka have begun to introduce &apos;masuseki for two&apos; and &apos;masuseki for three.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity, grammar, word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, following requests from customers, each facility in Osaka, Nagoya and Fukuoka have begun to introduce &apos;masuseki for two&apos; and &apos;masuseki for three.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="56">
<j>大相撲の枡席をめぐるもう一つの課題として、その購入方法の問題があげられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One more problem related to Masuseki for enjoying the grand sumo tournament is in the way to sell the tickets.</e>
<cmt>原文では購入方法ですが，内容は販売方法ではないかと思われました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One more problem connected to masuseki for enjoying the grand sumo tournament relates to the way tickets are sold.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity, word choice, grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One more problem connected to masuseki for enjoying the grand sumo tournament relates to the way tickets are sold.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>一概に枡席といっても、そこには土俵に近いものから遠いもの、土俵が観やすいものから観にくいものいものなど、さまざまな条件がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Masuseki&quot; sounds simple enough, but they have various types ranging from Masuseki established near to the Dohyo to Masuseki established far from the Dohyo, as well as from Masuseki at which people can enjoy a good view of the Dohyo to Masuseki at which people find difficulties in watching the Dohyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Masuseki&quot; sounds simple enough, but there are various types ranging from masuseki near to the dohyo to masuseki placed quite far back, as well as masuseki from which people can enjoy a good view of the dohyo to masuseki from which people have difficulty getting a clear view of the event.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity, word choice, grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Masuseki&quot; sounds simple enough, but there are various types ranging from masuseki near to the dohyo to masuseki placed quite far back, as well as masuseki from which people can enjoy a good view of the dohyo to masuseki from which people have difficulty getting a clear view of the event.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>ところが国技館では、一般に「良い枡席」と考えられている枡席のほぼすべてを「相撲案内所」と呼ばれる20軒の相撲茶屋が占有している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Ryogoku Kokugikan, however, almost all Masuseki graded &apos;excellent&apos;, which provides people with a good view of the Dohyo, are monopolized by 20 sumo-jaya restaurants (tea house located within the facility) called &apos;Sumo annai-jo&apos; (sumo information office).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Ryogoku Kokugikan, however, almost all the masuseki have been graded as &apos;excellent&apos;, and provide people with a good view of the dohyo, but these are monopolized by 20 sumo-jaya restaurants (tea houses located within the facility) called &apos;sumo annai-jo&apos; (sumo information offices).</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Ryogoku Kokugikan, however, almost all the masuseki have been graded as &apos;excellent,&apos; and provide people with a good view of the dohyo, but these are monopolized by 20 sumo-jaya restaurants (tea houses located within the facility) called &apos;sumo annai-jo&apos; (sumo information offices).</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置を移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>これらを通してでなければ良い枡席のチケットは購入することができない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, people are unable to buy the tickets for the &apos;excellent&apos; Masuseki without asking these restaurants for mediation.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, people are unable to buy the tickets for the &apos;excellent&apos; masuseki without asking these restaurants for mediation.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, people are unable to buy the tickets for the &apos;excellent&apos; masuseki without asking these restaurants for mediation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>各種プレイガイドやインターネットでも枡席のチケットを購入することはできるが、それでは観にくい枡席しか取れないというのが現状である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Certainly, people can buy the tickets for Masuseki at ticket agencies and on the Internet, however, under the present circumstances, they can only obtain such tickets that they can hardly enjoy a good view of the Dohyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Certainly, it is true that people can buy tickets for masuseki from ticket agencies and on the Internet, however, in the present circumstances they can only obtain tickets where they do not enjoy a good view of the dohyo.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity, grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Certainly, it is true that people can buy tickets for masuseki from ticket agencies and on the Internet, however, in the present circumstances they can only obtain tickets where they do not enjoy a good view of the dohyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 白拍子花子(id:244805), UE-PON2600(id:18149), ねこぱんだ(id:35119), ジェイド(id:31020), ピノキオ(id:245510), Lombroso(id:20212), Ktoetx(id:104437), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>