<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>角盥漱</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsunohanzo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsunohanzo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunohanzo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>角盥漱（つのはんぞう）は、鳥山石燕の妖怪画集『画図百器徒然袋』にある日本の妖怪。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsunohanzo is a Japanese specter portrayed in Sekien TORIYAMA&apos;s book of specter paintings, &quot;Hyakki Tsurezure Bukuro&quot; (One hundred bags in idleness).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A Tsunohanzo is one of Japanese yokai (ghosts, spirits and monsters) which is portrayed in Sekien TORIYAMA&apos;s yokai art collection book, &quot;Gazu Hyakki Tsurezure Bukuro&quot; (The Illustrated Bag of One Hundred Random Demons; the term &apos;hyakki&apos; in its title is a pun on the usual hyakki, replacing the character for demon which is written as &quot;鬼&quot; in Japanese with a character for vessel written as &quot;器,&quot; and sure enough, most of the yokais shown in this book are tsukumogami [a type of Japanese spirits that originate in items or artifacts that have reached their 100th birthday and become alive]).</e>
<cmt>原文に「画図」を補足のうえ再訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunohanzo is one of Japanese yokai (ghosts, spirits and monsters) which is portrayed in Sekien TORIYAMA&apos;s yokai art collection book, &quot;Gazu Hyakki Tsurezure Bukuro&quot; (The Illustrated Bag of One Hundred Random Demons; the term &apos;hyakki&apos; in its title is a pun on the usual hyakki, replacing the character for demon which is written as &quot;鬼&quot; in Japanese with a character for vessel written as &quot;器,&quot; and sure enough, most of the yokais shown in this book are tsukumogami [a type of Japanese spirits that originate in items or artifacts that have reached their 100th birthday and become alive]).</e>
<cmt>A Tsunohanzo→Tsunohanzo</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>付喪神の一種。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a kind of Tsukumo-gami (gods to a variety of things).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a kind of the tsukumogami.</e>
<cmt>前項とのつながりで調整。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a kind of the tsukumogami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>角盥（つのだらい）とは漆塗りの洗面道具のことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsunodarai refer lacquered toilet articles.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A tsuno-darai (literally, horned washtub) refers to any lacquered washbowl.</e>
<cmt>説明追加、文法</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsuno-darai (literally, horned washtub) refers to any lacquered washbowl.</e>
<cmt>A tsuno-darai→Tsuno-darai</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>特に口や喉をすすぐためのものを角盥漱と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among them, an item for washing mouth and throat is called tsunohanzo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The tsuno-darai used particularly for rinsing mouth and throat is called a tsuno-hanzo (a lacquered washbowl with two pairs of long horn-like handles on the both sides).</e>
<cmt>説明追加、表現修正、。参考資料：http://www.pref.mie.jp/saiku/hp/siryou/005-replica/010-rep-tunodarai/010rep-tunodarai.htm</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The tsuno-darai used particularly for rinsing mouth and throat is called a tsuno-hanzo (a lacquered washbowl with two pairs of long horn-like handles on the both sides).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>『画図百器徒然袋』の角盥漱は、平安時代の歌人・小野小町の使用していた角盥漱の妖怪化として創作されたものとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsunohanzo portrayed in &quot;Hyakki Tsurezure Bukuro&quot; is thought to be a specter of the tsunohanzo, used by ONO no Komachi who was kajin (waka poet) in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A Tsunohanzo as a yokai portrayed in the &quot;Gazu Hyakki Tsurezure Bukuro&quot; is thought to be Sekien&apos;s creation inspired by an episode of the tsunohanzo owned by ONO no Komachi, a waka poet who lived in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>原文の「百鬼」は「百器」の誤植につき、修正のうえ再訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunohanzo as a yokai portrayed in the &quot;Gazu Hyakki Tsurezure Bukuro&quot; is thought to be Sekien&apos;s creation inspired by an episode of the tsunohanzo owned by ONO no Komachi, a waka poet who lived in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>A Tsunohanzo→Tsunohanzo</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>小町と同じく六歌仙の1人である大伴黒主が、小町の歌を自分の歌として歌集に書き込んだという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that OTOMO no Kuronushi, who was one of the Rokkasen (six best Waka poets) like Komachi, plagiarized Komachi&apos;s poetry on the collection of poetries.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that OTOMO no Kuronushi, who was one of the Rokkasen (six best Waka poets) like Komachi, plagiarized Komachi&apos;s waka poem and introduced the poem in the anthology of waka poems.</e>
<cmt>表現修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that OTOMO no Kuronushi, who was one of the Rokkasen (six best Waka poets) like Komachi, plagiarized Komachi&apos;s waka poem and introduced the poem in the anthology of waka poems.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>その際、小町がそれを自分のものと証明するために歌の書かれた紙を角盥漱で洗ったところ、文字が流れ落ちて黒主の罪が明らかになったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then Komachi washed the piece of paper in which poetry was written in the tsunohanzo to prove that it was her work; the letters were washed out, and Kuronushi&apos;s guilt was revealed.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Finding out the plagiarism, Komachi attempted to prove the true authorship of her work and therefore poured some water from her tsunohanzo onto a page on which the waka in question had been handwritten with Chinese ink by Kuronushi, so that the letters were washed out, thereby exposing Kuronushi&apos;s guilt.</e>
<cmt>表現修正、文脈調整</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Finding out the plagiarism, Komachi attempted to prove the true authorship of her work and therefore poured some water from her tsunohanzo onto a page on which the waka in question had been handwritten with Chinese ink by Kuronushi, so that the letters were washed out, thereby exposing Kuronushi&apos;s guilt.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>「草紙洗い」と呼ばれる逸話である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The anecdote is called &quot;soshiarai (letter washing).&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This anecdote is known as the story of &quot;soshi-arai (book washing).&quot;</e>
<cmt>草紙英訳：http://tangorin.com/words/%E8%8D%89%E7%B4%99</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This anecdote is known as the story of &apos;soshi-arai&apos; (book washing).</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot; → &apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>石燕はこれをもとに妖怪の角盥漱を描いたものとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Sekien portrayed the tsunohanzo as specter based on the incident.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sekien supposedly based his portrayal of the tsunohanzo as a yokai on this story.</e>
<cmt>用語選択</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sekien supposedly based his portrayal of the tsunohanzo as a yokai on this story.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>衣服は小町のような十二単で、頭部に角盥漱を頂いており、小町の執心を表すように、盥の2本の柄が鬼の角のように突き出た姿として描かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to his painting, the specter wears juni-hitoe (twelve-layered ceremonial kimono), which remains Komach, it has a tsunohanzo as the head, and grips are stretched out like demon&apos;s horns so that Komachi&apos;s devotion may be seen.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In his illustration, the Tsunohanzo looks like Komachi wearing juni-hitoe (twelve-layered ceremonial kimono) and has her tsunohanzo put in the place of the head with a pair of handles protruding like a demon&apos;s horns as if they symbolized Komachi&apos;s obsession.</e>
<cmt>文脈調整、表現修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In his illustration, the Tsunohanzo looks like Komachi wearing juni-hitoe (twelve-layered ceremonial kimono) and has her tsunohanzo put in the place of the head with a pair of handles protruding like a demon&apos;s horns as if they symbolized Komachi&apos;s obsession.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 逃亡者(id:14864), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>