<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>ちりめんじゃこ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chirimenjako (small dried fish)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chirimenjako (small dried fish)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chirimenjako (small dried fish)</e>
<cmt>タイトルのため、カッコ内の補足を削除→新規ルールにより括弧内の補足を追加</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>ちりめんじゃこ（縮緬雑魚）は、イワシ類（カタクチイワシ・マイワシ・ウルメイワシ・シロウオ・イカナゴなど）の仔稚魚を食塩水で煮た後、天日などで干した食品。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chirimenjako (small dried fish) is shichigyo (small young fish, fry), such as type of sardines (anchovy, maiwashi (sardinops melanostictus), urume iwashi (round herring big-eye sardine, etrumeus teres), shirouo sardine, ikanago (sand eel)), cooked in the salted water and dried in the sun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chirimenjako (small dried fish) is small, young fish, such as type of sardines (anchovy, maiwashi, urume iwashi, shirouo sardine, ikanago), cooked in salted water and dried in the sun.</e>
<cmt>shortened a bit (too much explanation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chirimenjako (small dried fish) is small, young fish, such as type of sardines (anchovy, maiwashi, urume iwashi, shirouo sardine, ikanago), cooked in salted water and dried in the sun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>ごく小さな魚を平らに広げて干した様子が、細かなしわをもつ絹織物のちりめん（縮緬）を広げたように見えることからこの名前がついた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is called Chirimen since small fish spread to be dried, look similar to Chirimen, a type of silk textile (Crepe Kimono) which has partly wrinkled textile.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is called Chirimen since small fish spread to be dried, look similar to Chirimen, a type of silk fabric (Crepe Kimono) that is partly wrinkled.</e>
<cmt>textile-&gt;fabric</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is called Chirimen since small fish spread to be dried, look similar to Chirimen, a type of silk fabric (Crepe Kimono) that is partly wrinkled.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>魚そのものはシラス (魚)といい、しっかり干さないものはその名で呼ばれることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fish itself is called shirasu (young sardine, whitebait) and it is known as the name of shirasu when the fish is not totally dried.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fish itself is called shirasu (young sardine, whitebait) and it is known by the name of shirasu when the fish is not totally dried.</e>
<cmt>prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fish itself is called shirasu (young sardine, whitebait) and it is known by the name of shirasu when the fish is not totally dried.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>収量が多く、油分の少ないカタクチイワシの仔魚が用いられることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Often small anchovy are used for chirimen, which can be caught in bulk and the fish does not contain too much oil.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Often small anchovies are used for chirimen, which can be caught in bulk and the fish does not contain too much oil.</e>
<cmt>plural anchovies</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Often small anchovies are used for chirimen, which can be caught in bulk and the fish does not contain too much oil.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>ちりめんじゃこの体長は一般に10～40mmのものを指し、20mm前後のものが商品として一般的である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The length of the fish used in chirimanjako is usually 10-40 mm, and the ones around 20 mm are popular for selling in shops.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The length of the fish used in chirimanjako is usually 10-40 mm, and the ones around 20 mm are popular for selling in shops.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The length of the fish used in chirimanjako is usually 10-40 mm, and the ones around 20 mm are popular for selling in shops.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>また、牛乳と共にカルシウムを多く含む食品の代名詞ともなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chirimenjako is also well known food which contains lots of calcium, same as milk.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chirimenjako is also well known as a food that contains lots of calcium, same as milk.</e>
<cmt>articles; which-&gt;that</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chirimenjako is also well known as a food that contains lots of calcium, same as milk.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>呼び名</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>ちりめんじゃこは関西での呼び名で比較的良く乾燥させたものを指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chirimenjako is the name for relatively well dried fish in Kansai area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chirimenjako is the name for relatively well dried fish in Kansai area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chirimenjako is the name for relatively well dried fish in Kansai region.</e>
<cmt>Kansai regionとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>関東ではシラス干しと呼ばれ生乾きの状態で出荷されていたが、現在ではその区別はあいまいになってきている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kanto area it is called Shirasu boshi and was used to be shipped as half dried fish, however the difference of the name between Chirimenjako and Shirasuboshi is gray nowadays.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Kanto area it is called Shirasu boshi and used to be shipped as half dried fish, however the difference between Chirimenjako and Shirasuboshi is not so distinct nowadays.</e>
<cmt>gray-&gt;not distinct</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Kanto region it is called Shirasu boshi and used to be shipped as half dried fish, however the difference between Chirimenjako and Shirasuboshi is not so distinct nowadays.</e>
<cmt>Kanto regionとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>漁獲</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fishing</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fishing</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fishing</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="9">
<j>春から秋はカタクチイワシの仔魚、冬季はマイワシやウルメイワシの仔魚が漁獲される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Small anchovies are caught between spring and autumn, mariachi (sardinops melanostictus) and urume iwashi (round herring big-eye sardine, etrumeus teres) are caught in winter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Small anchovies are caught between spring and autumn, mariachi and urume iwashi are caught in winter.</e>
<cmt>spacing; removed the long explanations</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Small anchovies are caught between spring and autumn, maiwashi and urume iwashi are caught in winter.</e>
<cmt>mariachi→maiwashiに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>マイワシは2～3月に日本の南側の海で産卵し、その稚魚は3～5月に太平洋岸や瀬戸内海で水揚げされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Small anchovies spawn in the south sea of Japan between February and March, and those small fish are caught between March and May at Pacific side and Seto Inland Sea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Small anchovies spawn in the southern sea of Japan between February and March, and those small fish are caught between March and May on the Pacific side and in the Seto Inland Sea.</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Maiwashi spawn in the southern sea of Japan between February and March, and those small fish are caught between March and May on the Pacific side and in the Seto Inland Sea.</e>
<cmt>Small anchovies→Maiwashiに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>主な産地は愛媛、徳島、広島、高知、兵庫、和歌山、愛知、静岡。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mainly they are caught in Ehime Prefecture, Tokushima Prefecture, Hiroshima Prefecture, Kochi Prefecture, Hyogo Prefecture, Wakayama Prefecture, Aichi Prefecture, Shizuoka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mainly they are caught in Ehime, Tokushima, Hiroshima, Kochi, Hyogo, Wakayama, Aichi and Shizuoka Prefectures.</e>
<cmt>added “and”; deleted repetitive “prefecture”</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mainly they are caught in Ehime, Tokushima, Hiroshima, Kochi, Hyogo, Wakayama, Aichi and Shizuoka Prefectures.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>加工</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Process</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Process</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Process</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="12">
<j>いったん漁獲された仔魚は傷みが早いので、水揚げ当日に製品まで加工される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since small fish do not last once they are caught, they are processed to be ready to sell on the same day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since small fish do not last once they are caught, they are processed to be ready to sell on the same day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since small fish do not last once they are caught, they are processed to be ready to sell on the same day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>この項では天日干しによる生産を解説する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following is the explanation how to dry and sell the fish in this chapter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following is an explanation of how to dry and sell the fish.</e>
<cmt>deleted “in this chapter”</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following is an explanation of how to dry and sell the fish.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>漁獲</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Catching fish</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Catching fish</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Catching fish</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="14">
<j>当日天日干しする関係から、漁期中でも雨の日は出漁しない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the fish is dried on the day they are caught, the fishermen will not go fishing when it rains even though it is in fishing season.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the fish are dried on the day they are caught, fishermen will not go fishing when it rains even though it is in fishing season.</e>
<cmt>Noun-verb agreement</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the fish are dried on the day they are caught, fishermen will not go fishing when it rains even though it is in fishing season.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>毎朝当日の天候や波の状況を確認した上で出漁の可否を判断する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Every morning it is decided whether or not to go fishing, after checking the weather and the situation of the waves.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Every morning it is decided whether or not to go fishing, after checking the weather and the situation of the waves.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Every morning it is decided whether or not to go fishing, after checking the weather and the situation of the waves.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>漁船は単独または2隻一組になって目の細かい網を引く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Two fishing boats are used together and as pair and there will be fishing net with small mesh put across two boats.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Two fishing boats are used together as a pair and a fine-mesh fishing net is put across them.</e>
<cmt>grammar; repetition</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Two fishing boats are used together as a pair and a fine-mesh fishing net is put across them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>漁獲後は直ちに漁港に帰還するが、出漁から帰港まで1～数時間である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As soon as the fish is caught, the boats will go back to the port and it only takes one to a few hours for the boats to go fishing and come back to the port.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As soon as the fish are caught, the boats will go back to the port and it only takes one to a few hours for the boats to go fishing and come back to the port.</e>
<cmt>is-&gt;are</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As soon as the fish are caught, the boats will go back to the port and it only takes one to a few hours for the boats to go fishing and come back to the port.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>選別</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Selection</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Selection</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Selection</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="18">
<j>漁港で水揚げされた仔稚魚は直ちに加工場に運ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The small fish unload at the fishing port are immediately moved to the processing factory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The small fish unloaded at the port are immediately moved to the processing factory.</e>
<cmt>problems with the verbs</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The small fish unloaded at the port are immediately moved to the processing factory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>細かい網での漁なのでイカ・タコ・アジ・サバ等の仔稚魚が混入しており、これらの異種魚を除く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since they are caught by small mesh, other seafood or fish caught at the sama time, such as calamari, octopus, Japanese horse mackerel, mackerel are removed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since they are caught with fine nets, other fish caught at the same time, such as calamari, octopus, Japanese horse mackerel and mackerel are removed.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since they are caught with fine nets, other fish caught at the same time, such as calamari, octopus, Japanese horse mackerel and mackerel are removed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>この状態の生の仔稚魚を高知県ではドロメと呼び、酢味噌で味付けしたものは酒の肴として珍重される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The row small fish are called dorome (raw young fish) in Kochi Prefecture, and they were mixed with vinegary miso (soy bean paste) which goes well with alcohol.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The raw small fish are called dorome (raw young fish) in Kochi Prefecture, and they were mixed with vinegary miso (soy bean paste), which goes well with alcohol.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The raw small fish are called dorome (raw young fish) in Kochi Prefecture, and they were mixed with vinegary miso (soy bean paste), which goes well with alcohol.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>煮る</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cooking</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cooking</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cooking</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="21">
<j>漁船の帰港時には既に大釜に食塩水が煮立っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the fishing boat come back to the port, there will already be salted boiling water ready in a large cooking pot.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the fishing boat comes back to port, there will already be salted boiling water ready in a large cooking pot.</e>
<cmt>Noun-verb agreement</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the fishing boat comes back to port, there will already be salted boiling water ready in a large cooking pot.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>選別された仔稚魚は釜で短時間煮られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The selected small fish are cooked in the pot for a short time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The selected small fish are cooked in the pot for a short time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The selected small fish are cooked in the pot for a short time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>釜から取り出した未乾燥品を『釜揚げシラス』と呼び、冷凍して出荷する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fish just being cooked and not dried are called &quot;Kamaage shirasu&quot; (kamaage shirasu (straight-from-the-pot young sardine which is freshly boiled)) and will be frozen and shipped.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fish just being cooked and not dried are called &quot;Kamaage shirasu&quot; (straight-from-the-pot young sardine which is freshly boiled) and will be frozen and shipped.</e>
<cmt>deleted repetitive bit</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fish just being cooked and not dried are called &quot;Kamaage shirasu&quot; (straight-from-the-pot young sardine which is freshly boiled) and will be frozen and shipped.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>（観光地ではみやげ物として地元の冷凍釜揚げシラスを売っている。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In sightseeing place, the local frozen kamaage shirasu is sold for souvenir.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(In sightseeing spots, the local frozen kamaage shirasu are sold as souvenirs.)</e>
<cmt>place-&gt;spots; is-&gt;are; plural souvenirs</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(In sightseeing spots, the local frozen kamaage shirasu are sold as souvenirs.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>天日にて乾かす</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Drying fish in the sun</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Drying fish in the sun</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Drying fish in the sun</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="25">
<j>日当たり・風通しの良いところに細かい網を水平に開き、その上に煮あがったちりめんじゃこを拡げる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Put small mesh on the sunny place with breeze, then spread cooked fish on the mesh.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Put a fine mesh in a sunny place with a breeze, then spread cooked fish on the mesh.</e>
<cmt>articles; prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Put a fine mesh in a sunny place with a breeze, then spread cooked fish on the mesh.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>これは手作業で行われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is done by hand.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is done by hand.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is done by hand.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>干す時間は当日の天気や、風の具合によって判断する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The length of the drying time depends on the weather on the day or the wind.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The length of the drying time depends on the weather of the day or the wind.</e>
<cmt>prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The length of the drying time depends on the weather of the day or the wind.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="28">
<j>1980年代までは、日持ちがする塩分の高い（塩辛い）物が好まれたが、最近は健康への関心の高まりから減塩された製品が多くなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The salty Chirimenjako which last longer was more popular until 1980&apos;s, but recently people are more health cautious and more salt reduced products are becoming popular.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The salty Chirimenjako, which last longer, were more popular until the 1980s, but recently people are more health cautious and more salt reduced products are becoming popular.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The salty Chirimenjako, which last longer, were more popular until the 1980s, but recently people are more health cautious and more salt reduced products are becoming popular.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="29">
<j>まれに小さなタコやエビ、カニやタツノオトシゴが混入される場合がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rarely small octopus or shrimp, crab, sea horse are contained in the Chirimenjako.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rarely small octopus or shrimp, crab and sea horse are contained in the Chirimenjako.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rarely small octopus or shrimp, crab and sea horse are contained in the Chirimenjako.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>加工風景</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The image when fish is dried</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A scene of fish being dried</e>
<cmt>this is better</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A scene of fish being dried</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Gleam(id:4760), とらでじこ(id:11570), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), マクガイア(id:33346), Roger(id:9883), Labrax(id:56168), やすとし(id:63220), Corwin(id:973), Ｋｓ(id:15319), Miya.m(id:4662), Hotei(id:7664), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>