<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>雲外鏡</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Ungaikyo&quot; (one of Japanese ghosts)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Ungaikyo&quot; (a type of Japanese ghost)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ungaikyo</e>
<cmt>他と統一し、 &quot; &quot; を削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>雲外鏡（うんがいきょう） は、特殊な鏡が長い年月を経たのちに変じたという、日本の妖怪の一種。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Ungaikyo&quot; is a kind of a Japanese ghost, into which a peculiar mirror changed after long years went by.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Ungaikyo&quot; is a type of a Japanese ghost, that metamorphizes from a peculiar mirror after the passing of many long years.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term &quot;Ungaikyo&quot; is a type of a Japanese ghost, that metamorphizes from a peculiar mirror after the passing of many long years.</e>
<cmt>一部表現を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>浮世絵師・鳥山石燕の妖怪画集『百器徒然袋』（天明4年〈1784年〉）に描かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ungaikyo was illustrated in the ghosts&apos; collection &quot;Hyakki Tsurezure Bukuro&quot; (A Hundred Gods to Things Imagined in Idleness) made in 1784 by &quot;Sekien TORIYAMA,&quot; who was an &quot;ukiyoe&quot; (Japanese woodblock prints) artist.</e>
<cmt>※『百器徒然袋』は、『徒然なるままに夢想した百の付喪神』と訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ungaikyo was illustrated in the ghosts&apos; collection &quot;Hyakki Tsurezure Bukuro&quot; - A Hundred Gods of Things Imagined in Idleness) made in 1784 by &quot;Sekien TORIYAMA,&quot; who was an &quot;ukiyoe&quot; (Japanese woodblock print) artist.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ungaikyo was illustrated in the ghosts&apos; collection &quot;Hyakki Tsurezure Bukuro&quot; (A Hundred Gods of Things Imagined in Idleness) made in 1784 by Sekien TORIYAMA, who was an ukiyoe (Japanese woodblock print) artist.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot; を一部削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>民俗学的知見から、鏡の付喪神（つくもがみ）と見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seen from a folkloric perspective, Ungaikyo is a mirror version of &quot;Tsukumo-gami&quot; (gods to a variety of things).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seen from a folkloric perspective, Ungaikyo is a mirror version of &quot;Tsukumo-gami&quot; (gods of a variety of things).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seen from a folkloric perspective, Ungaikyo is a mirror version of &quot;Tsukumo-gami&quot; (gods of a variety of things).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>本来の雲外鏡</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Original Ungaikyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Original Ungaikyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Original Ungaikyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>石燕の雲外鏡</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sekien&apos;s Ungaikyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sekien&apos;s Ungaikyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sekien&apos;s Ungaikyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>化け物の正体を明らかにする「照魔鏡（しょうまきょう）」と呼ばれる鏡が、長い年月を経た末に妖怪化したものとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sekien explained that a mirror called &quot;Shomakyo,&quot; which had revealed the original shape of a ghost, changed into a ghost itself after long years went by.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sekien illustrates a mirror called &quot;Shomakyo,&quot; in which the image of a ghost appears and then changes into the actual ghost itself after a number of years have passed by.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sekien illustrates a mirror called &apos;Shomakyo,&apos; in which the image of a ghost appears and then changes into the actual ghost itself after a number of years have passed by.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>『百器徒然袋』（右上の画像がそれ）では、公家の屋敷にある丸鏡として描かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ungaikyo in &quot;Hyakki Tsurezure Bukuro&quot; (cf. the upper right image) was illustrated as a round mirror in a Court noble&apos;s residence.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ungaikyo in &quot;Hyakki Tsurezure Bukuro&quot; (cf. the upper right image) was illustrated as a round mirror in a Court noble&apos;s residence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ungaikyo in &quot;Hyakki Tsurezure Bukuro&quot; (cf. the upper right image) was illustrated as a round mirror in a Court noble&apos;s residence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>鏡はすだれ御簾（みす）の陰から半面のみ姿を見せており、怪しげな黒雲（あるいは、そのような意匠の鏡立て）を伴っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The mirror was illustrated to be hidden in its right half behind a blind screen, and to be accompanied by a weird black cloud (or by a mirror stand of such a design).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The right half of the mirror is hidden behind a blind screen, accompanied by a weird black cloud (or by a mirror stand with such a design).</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The right half of the mirror is hidden behind a blind screen, accompanied by a weird black cloud (or by a mirror stand with such a design).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>その鏡面には邪（よこしま）な雰囲気を漂わせつつ舌を出してこちらに視線をくれる化け物の顔面が浮かび上がっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And the mirror was illustrated to reflect the face of an evil-looking ghost throwing its eyes to us with its tongue out.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And in the mirror is the the face of an evil-looking ghost staring at us with its tongue out.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And in the mirror is the face of an evil-looking ghost staring at us with its tongue out.</e>
<cmt>the のダブりを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>研究者の分析と知見</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Researchers&apos; analyses and views</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Researchers&apos; analysis and comments</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Researchers&apos; analysis and comments</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>妖怪研究家（作家）・多田克己らの著書においては、雲外鏡は、鏡の付喪神と解釈されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some people, such as &quot;Katsumi TADA,&quot; a psychic researcher &amp; a writer, explain in their books that Ungaikyo is a mirror version of Tsukumo-gami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some people, like &quot;Katsumi TADA,&quot; a psychic researcher &amp; a writer, explain in their books that Ungaikyo is a mirror version of Tsukumo-gami.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some people, like Katsumi TADA, a ghost researcher and a writer, explain in their books that Ungaikyo is a mirror version of Tsukumo-gami.</e>
<cmt>妖怪研究家 →ghost researcher　としました。 &quot; &quot; を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>また、妖怪作品の多い漫画家・水木しげるの説明もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And the comic artist &quot;Shigeru MIZUKI,&quot; who produced many comic books about ghosts, explains as follows :</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And the comic artist &quot;Shigeru MIZUKI,&quot; who produced many comic books about ghosts, explains as follows:</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And the comic artist Shigeru MIZUKI, who produced many comic books about ghosts, explains as follows:</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot; を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>8月 (旧暦)の十五夜に月明かりの下（もと）で石英のトレイに水を張り、その水で鏡面に化け物の姿を描くと、鏡の中に化け物が棲みつく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If you run water into a tray made from quartz - under the moonlight on the fifteenth night of the eighth lunar month - and portray a ghost on a mirror with the water, a ghost will haunt the mirror;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If you run water into a tray made from quartz - under the moonlight on the fifteenth night of the eighth lunar month - and portray a ghost on a mirror with the water, a ghost will haunt the mirror;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If you run water into a tray made from quartz - under the moonlight on the fifteenth night of the eighth lunar month - and portray a ghost on a mirror with the water, a ghost will haunt the mirror.</e>
<cmt>ピリオドに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>それが雲外鏡であるという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">and this mirror is Ungaikyo, he says.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">and this mirror is called Ungaikyo, he says.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This mirror is called Ungaikyo, he says.</e>
<cmt>ピリオドに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>今様の雲外鏡</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Modern Ungaikyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Modern Ungaikyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Modern Ungaikyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>デフォルメ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Deformation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Destortion</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Distortion</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="12">
<j>現代的大衆文化に基づいて著される妖怪図鑑や画集では、雲外鏡は腹に鏡をつけた（腹が鏡になっている）化け狸のような姿の妖怪であるとか、自らの体に様々なものを映し出すことができる、などと解説されることが少なくない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Based on the modern mass culture, picture books of ghosts (or collections of paintings of ghosts) not rarely deform Ungaikyo into, for example, a ghost like a raccoon dog disguised as a mirror (a raccoon dog whose body has a mirror on itself), or a ghost that can project various images on its own body.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based on the modern mass media culture, picture books of ghosts (or collections of paintings of ghosts) destort the form of Ungaikyo into, for example, a ghost like raccoon dog disguised as a mirror (a raccoon dog whose body incorporates a mirror), or a ghost that can project various images on its own body.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based on the modern mass media culture, picture books of ghosts or collections of paintings of ghosts distort the form of Ungaikyo into, for example, a ghost like raccoon dog disguised as a mirror (a raccoon dog whose body incorporates a mirror), or a ghost that can project various images on its own body.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>しかし、妖怪研究家（作家）・村上健司の指摘によれば、そのようなデフォルメされた形と能力を持った雲外鏡の原典は特撮映画『妖怪大戦争 (1968年の映画)』に登場する古狸（ふる-だぬき）様の雲外鏡にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, &quot;Kenji MURAKAMI,&quot; a psychic researcher &amp; a writer, points out such Ungaikyo which is deformed in its figure &amp; exaggerated in its capability, originated from the Ungaikyo that appeared as an old-looking raccoon dog in &quot;Yokai Daisenso&quot; (A Great War of Ghosts), the special effects movie made in 1968.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, &quot;Kenji MURAKAMI,&quot; a psychic researcher &amp; a writer, points out such Ungaikyo that have a distorted figure &amp; is exaggerated in its capability, originated from the Ungaikyo that appeared as an old-looking raccoon dog in &quot;Yokai Daisenso&quot; (The Great War of Ghosts), a special effects movie made in 1968.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Kenji MURAKAMI, a ghost researcher and a writer, points out such Ungaikyo that have a distorted figure and is exaggerated in its capability, originated from the Ungaikyo that appeared as an old-looking raccoon dog in &quot;Yokai Daisenso&quot; (The Great War of Ghosts), a special effects movie made in 1968.</e>
<cmt>妖怪研究家 →ghost researcher　としました。 &quot; &quot; を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>彼は、以降のイメージをその影響下での二次創作物であるとする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He says images of Ungaikyo created after that were imitations affected by the above-mentioned original one.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He says images of Ungaikyo created after that were imitations influenced by the above.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He says images of Ungaikyo created after that were imitations influenced by the above.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>その他の不可思議な鏡</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other supernatural mirrors</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other supernatural mirrors</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other supernatural mirrors</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="15">
<j>類似点が多いもの、および、類縁ではないが「不可思議な鏡」という点での相似性が見られるものをここに示す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A mirror that has many points similar to Ungaikyo, and other supernatural mirrors - though not similar to Ungaikyo - are explained below.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A mirror that has many similarities to Ungaikyo, and other supernatural mirrors - though not similar to Ungaikyo - are explained below.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A mirror that has many similarities to Ungaikyo, and other supernatural mirrors - though not similar to Ungaikyo - are explained below.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="16">
<j>照妖鏡（照妖鑑とも称する）は、中国明代の伝奇『封神演義』に登場する、本来の姿を映し出す鏡。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Shoyokyo&quot; (also called &quot;Shoyokan&quot;) was the mirror that revealed the original shape of the subject, which appeared in &quot;Feng-Shen-Yen-I,&quot; the bizarre tale created in the Ming dynasty of China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Shoyokyo&quot; (also called &quot;Shoyokan&quot;) was a mirror that revealed the original shape of the subject that appeared in &quot;Feng-Shen-Yen-I,&quot; a bizarre tale created in Ming dynasty of China.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Shoyokyo&quot; (also called &quot;Shoyokan&quot;) was a mirror that revealed the original shape of the subject that appeared in &quot;Feng-Shen-Yen-I,&quot; a bizarre tale created in Ming dynasty of China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>終南山の仙人・雲中子の宝貝（パオペイ。仙術の武具）で、 人に化けた魔物の正体を看破することができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Owned by &quot;Unchushi&quot; (a hermit) who lived in Shunan-san Mountain, Shoyokyo was &quot;Paopei&quot; (a weapon for &quot;senjutsu&quot; [the supernatural arts of a hermit]), and it could reveal the original shape of the ghost disguised as a human.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Owned by &quot;Unchushi&quot; (a hermit) who lived in Shunan-san Mountain, Shoyokyo was &quot;Paopei&quot; (a weapon for &quot;senjutsu&quot; [the supernatural art of a hermit]), and it could reveal the original shape of the ghost disguised as a human.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Owned by a hermit, Unchushi (雲中子), who lived in Mt. Shunan, Shoyokyo was Paopei (a weapon for senjutsu (the supernatural art of a hermit)), and it could reveal the original shape of the ghost disguised as a human.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot; を削除しました。Mt. Shunan　としました。中国名が分からないため、（雲中子）を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>妖怪化する以前の雲外鏡（照魔鏡）と類似点が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shoyokyo has many points similar to &quot;Shomakyo,&quot; the original mirror before its changing into the ghost &quot;Ungaikyo.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoyokyo has many similarities to &quot;Shomakyo,&quot; the original mirror before it changes into the &quot;Ungaikyo&quot; ghost.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoyokyo has many similarities to Ungaikyo (Shomakyo), the original mirror, before it changes into Ungaikyo ghost.</e>
<cmt>一部翻訳を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="19">
<j>浄玻璃鏡（じょうはりのかがみ）は、（日本の）地獄 (仏教)の閻魔が亡者の善悪を見極めるのに用いる水晶製の鏡。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Johari no Kagami&quot; is a crystal mirror which is said in Japanese Buddhism to be used by &quot;Enma&quot; (the King of Hell) for inquiring into if the dead was right-minded or not before its death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Johari no Kagami&quot; is a crystal mirror which is said in Japanese Buddhism to be used by &quot;Enma&quot; (the King of Hell) for inquiring into if the dead were right-minded or not before its death.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Johari no Kagami&quot; is a crystal mirror which is said in Japanese Buddhism to be used by Enma (the King of Hell) for inquiring into if the dead were right-minded or not before its death.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot; を一部削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="20">
<j>ドイツ民話であり童話である『白雪姫』に登場する魔法の鏡は、鏡の精霊が宿ったもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The magic mirror, which appears in the German folklore &amp; fairy tale &quot;Snow White and the Seven Dwarfs,&quot; is the thing into which the spirit of mirror goes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The magic mirror, which appears in the German folklore &amp; fairy tale &quot;Snow White and the Seven Dwarfs,&quot; is the where the spirit of mirror goes.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The magic mirror, which appears in the German folklore and fairy tale &quot;Snow White and the Seven Dwarfs,&quot; is the one where the spirit of mirror dwells.</e>
<cmt>一部翻訳を変更しました。&amp; →and　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>しかし、強い自我を持っており、西洋占星術で用いられる水晶球を鏡に変えたようなところもあって、雲外鏡とは大きく異なる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But this magic magic mirror is quite different from Ungaikyo, because the former has a strong ego &amp; a characteristic similar to the crystal ball used in the Western astrology.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But this magic mirror is quite different from Ungaikyo, because the former has a strong ego &amp; is characteristic of the crystal ball used in the Western astrology.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But this magic mirror is quite different from Ungaikyo, because the former has a strong ego and is characteristic of the crystal ball used in the Western astrology.</e>
<cmt>&amp; →and　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="22">
<j>古代中国や日本に実在する「魔鏡」は、光の屈折で像を映し出す仕掛けを持つ銅鏡（青銅鏡）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Makyo,&quot; a bronze mirror existent in both ancient China &amp; Japan, has a mechanism to show some image using the refraction of light.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Makyo,&quot; a bronze mirror existing in both ancient China &amp; Japan, has a feature that shows an image making use of light refraction.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Makyo,&apos; a bronze mirror existing in both ancient China and Japan, has a feature that shows an image making use of light refraction.</e>
<cmt>&amp; →and　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>隠れ切支丹鏡。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was the mirror used by underground Christians in feudal Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was the mirror used by underground Christians in feudal Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Kakure Kirishitan Kagami&quot; was the mirror used by underground Christians in feudal Japan.</e>
<cmt>「隠れ切支丹鏡」は新たな鏡の紹介と解釈し、そのように翻訳を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Cyclops(id:210075), 逃亡者(id:14864), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>