<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>中村鴈治郎 (2代目)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ganjiro NAKAMURA (Nidaime (Second))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ganjiro NAKAMURA (Nidaime (Second))</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ganjiro NAKAMURA (the Second)</e>
<cmt>nidaimeをのぞきました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>二代目 中村鴈治郎（にだいめ なかむら がんじろう、明治35年（1902年）2月17日 - 昭和58年（1983年）4月13日）は昭和を代表する歌舞伎役者の一人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ganjiro NAKAMURA II (February 17, 1902 - April 13, 1983) was a kabuki actor who represent the Showa era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ganjiro NAKAMURA II (February 17, 1902 - April 13, 1983) was a kabuki actor who is representative of the Showa era.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ganjiro NAKAMURA, the second (February 17, 1902 - April 13, 1983) was a kabuki actor who is representative of the Showa period.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>関西歌舞伎の伝統を継承し、立役から女形まで幅広い芸域を誇った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He succeeded the heritage of Kansai Kabuki and was capable to cover a wide range of his performance as an actor from tachiyaku (a leading male-role actor) to oyama (actor of female roles)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He succeeded the heritage of Kansai Kabuki and was capable of covering a wide range of performances as an actor from tachiyaku (a leading male-role actor) to oyama (actor of female roles)</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He succeeded the heritage of Kansai Kabuki and was capable of covering a wide range of performances as an actor from tachiyaku (a leading male-role actor) to oyama (actor of female roles).</e>
<cmt>ピリオド補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>特に、父中村鴈治郎 (初代)譲りの二枚目役においてその本領を発揮した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In particular, he showed his real ability in roles of a lover inherited from his father, Ganjiro NAKAMURA I.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In particular, he showed his real ability in roles as a lover, something inherited from his father, Ganjiro NAKAMURA I.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In particular, he showed his real ability in roles as a lover, something inherited from his father, Ganjiro NAKAMURA (the first).</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>本名は林 好雄（はやし よしお）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His real name was Yoshio HAYASHI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His real name was Yoshio HAYASHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His real name was Yoshio HAYASHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>略歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Brief personal history</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Brief personal history</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>大阪生まれ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born in Osaka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born in Osaka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born in Osaka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>中村鴈治郎 (初代)の二男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the second son of Ganjiro NAKAMURA I.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the second son of Ganjiro NAKAMURA I.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the second son of Ganjiro NAKAMURA (the first).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>1906年、京都南座で初舞台。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1906, he made a debut in Kyoto Minamiza theater.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1906, he made his debut in Kyoto Minamiza theater.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1906, he made his debut in Kyoto Minamiza theater.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>1909年、初代中村扇雀に改名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1909, he changed his name to Senjaku NAKAMURA I.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1909, he changed his name to Senjaku NAKAMURA I.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1909, he changed his name to Senjaku NAKAMURA I.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>幼少期は子供芝居で、やや長じては青年劇中村扇雀一座の座頭として活躍する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the infant stage, he performed in a children&apos;s play and later actively performed as zagashira (the leader of a troupe) of the troupe of Senjaku NAKAMURA for youth&apos;s play.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the infant stage, he performed in a children&apos;s play and later actively performed as zagashira (the leader of a troupe) of the troupe of Senjaku NAKAMURA for youth plays.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the infant stage, he performed in a children&apos;s play and later actively performed as zagashira (the leader of a troupe) of the troupe of Senjaku NAKAMURA for youth plays.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>1924年、大歌舞伎に復帰し、初代鴈治郎、實川延若 (2代目)、片岡仁左衛門 (12代目)などのもとで修行。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1924, he came back to daikabuki and learned under Ganjiro I, Enjaku JITSUKAWA (Nidaime (second)), Nizaemon KATAOKA (Junidaime (twelfth)), etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1924, he came back to daikabuki and learned under Ganjiro I, Enjaku JITSUKAWA (Nidaime (second)), Nizaemon KATAOKA (Junidaime (twelfth)), etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1924, he came back to okabuki (kabuki performance by A-listers) and learned under Ganjiro I, Enjaku JITSUKAWA (the second), Nizaemon KATAOKA (the twelfth), etc.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>主に女形を勤めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He mainly performed as oyama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He mainly performed as oyama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He mainly performed as a male actor of female roles.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>1935年、父・初代鴈治郎死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1935, his father, Ganjiro I died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1935, his father, Ganjiro I died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1935, his father, Ganjiro I died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>このころから若手の有望株と目され、1941年には四代目中村翫雀を、また1947年には二代目中村鴈治郎を襲名した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since around this time, he was deemed as a promising young actor and, in 1941, he succeeded Kanjaku NAKAMURA IV and, in 1947, Ganjiro NAKAMURA II.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since around this time, he was deemed as a promising young actor and, in 1941, he succeeded Kanjaku NAKAMURA IV and, in 1947, Ganjiro NAKAMURA II.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since around this time, he was deemed as a promising young actor and, in 1941, he succeeded Kanjaku NAKAMURA, the fourth, and, in 1947, Ganjiro NAKAMURA, the second.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>1952（昭和27）年には宇野信夫の脚本により近松門左衛門の『曾根崎心中』を復活上演、以後生涯の当たり役となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1952, he performed &quot;Sonezaki shinju&quot; (Lovers&apos; suicide in Sonezaki) &quot; of Monzaemon CHIKAMATSU with the script by Nobuo UNO and it became his star role throughout his life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1952, he performed &quot;Sonezaki shinju&quot; (Lovers&apos; suicide in Sonezaki) &quot; by Monzaemon CHIKAMATSU with the script by Nobuo UNO and it became his star role throughout his life.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1952, he performed revival &quot;Sonezaki shinju&quot; (Lovers&apos; suicide in Sonezaki) by Monzaemon CHIKAMATSU with the script by Nobuo UNO and it became his star role throughout his life.</e>
<cmt>復活上演を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>しかしこの頃になると関西歌舞伎の凋落がいちじるしく、周囲の期待の重圧に対する自身の芸の伸び悩み、さらに市川壽海 (3代目)を主とする興行方針をめぐる松竹との軋轢などがあり、1955年に松竹を離れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the decline of Kansai Kabuki became significant and because of sluggish growth of his own performance due to pressure of expectation of those around him and friction with Shochiku with respect to the policy of performance to mainly use Jukai ICHAWA III, he left Shochiku in 1955.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the decline of Kansai Kabuki became significant and because of sluggish growth in his own performances, due to the pressure of expectation of those around him and friction with Shochiku with respect to the performance policy to mainly use Jukai ICHAWA III, he left Shochiku in 1955.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the decline of Kansai Kabuki became significant and because of sluggish growth in his own performances, due to the pressure of expectation of those around him and friction with Shochiku with respect to the performance policy to mainly use Jukai ICHAWA, the third, he left Shochiku in 1955.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>以後は長男坂田藤十郎 (4代目)とともに映画やテレビで活躍するようになり、とりわけ映画では大映を中心に約10年間目覚しい活躍を見せた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, together with the eldest son, Tojuro SAKATA IV, he was actively engaged in movies and TV and, in particular in cinemas, he played an important role centering on Daiei for approximately ten years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, together with the eldest son, Tojuro SAKATA IV, he was actively engaged in movies and TV and, in particular in cinemas, he played an important role centering on Daiei for approximately ten years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, together with the eldest son, Tojuro SAKATA, the fourth, he was actively engaged in movies and TV and, in particular in cinemas, Ganjiro played an important role centering on Daiei Co., Ltd. for approximately ten years.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>当時の主な出演作には『炎上_(映画)』『鍵』（市川崑監督）、『浮草』『小早川家の秋』（小津安二郎監督）、『どん底 (1957年の映画)』（黒澤明監督）、『雁の寺』（川島雄三監督）などが挙げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As main works in which he appeared in that period., we can name &quot;Enjo (burning)&quot; (movie), &quot;Kagi (key)&quot; (directed by Kon ICHIKAWA), &quot;Ukikusa (Floating Weeds),&quot; &quot;Kohayagawa-ke no Aki (the Autumn of the Kohayagawa Family)&quot; (directed by Yasujiro OZU), &quot;Donzoko (rock bottom)&quot;(movie of 1957) (directed by Akira KUROSAWA) and &quot;Kari no tera (temple of the wild geese)&quot; (directed by Yuzo KAWASHIMA).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As main works in which he appeared in that period., we can name &quot;Enjo (burning)&quot; (movie), &quot;Kagi (key)&quot; (directed by Kon ICHIKAWA), &quot;Ukikusa (Floating Weeds),&quot; &quot;Kohayagawa-ke no Aki (the Autumn of the Kohayagawa Family)&quot; (directed by Yasujiro OZU), &quot;Donzoko (rock bottom)&quot;(movie of 1957) (directed by Akira KUROSAWA) and &quot;Kari no tera (Temple of the Wild Geese)&quot; (directed by Yuzo KAWASHIMA).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As main works in which he appeared in that period, there are &quot;Enjo&quot; (burning), &quot;Kagi&quot; (key) (directed by Kon ICHIKAWA), &quot;Ukikusa&quot; (Floating Weeds), &quot;Kohayagawa-ke no Aki&quot; (The End of Summer) (directed by Yasujiro OZU), &quot;Donzoko&quot; (rock bottom) (directed by Akira KUROSAWA) and &quot;Kari no tera&quot; (Temple of the Wild Geese) (directed by Yuzo KAWASHIMA).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="19">
<j>映画出演の傍ら、1958年からは片岡仁左衛門 (13代目)らとともに歌舞伎の自主公演「七人の会」にも出演した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While acting for movies, he took part in the independent performance of Kabuki &quot;Shichinin no kai&quot; (party of seven persons) from 1958 together with Nizaemon KATAOKA XIII.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While acting for movies, he took part in the independent performance of Kabuki &quot;Shichinin no kai&quot; (party of seven persons) from 1958 together with Nizaemon KATAOKA XIII.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While acting for movies, he took part in the independent performance of the kabuki &apos;Shichinin no kai&apos; (party of seven persons) from 1958 together with Nizaemon KATAOKA, the thirteenth, and others.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>しかし、関西での歌舞伎公演が激減する状況下では充分な活躍ができないと、関西を離れ東京歌舞伎と一座することが多くなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as he could not perform sufficiently under situation in which performance of kabuki in Kansai drastically decreased, he often leave Kansai and perform with Tokyo Kabuki.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as he could not perform sufficiently under a situation in which performance of kabuki in Kansai was drastically decreased, he often left Kansai and performed with Tokyo Kabuki.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as he could not perform sufficiently under the situation in which performance of kabuki in Kansai was drastically decreased, he often left Kansai and performed with Tokyo Kabuki.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>その間に映画出演などで芸の力がつきスランプを脱すると上方和事の真髄とも言う芸を見せて高く評価された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the meantime, he could improve his performance by appearing in cinemas and came out of slump, and he displayed performance which we can call the spirit of Kamigata wagoto (the production style of a love scene) and he was highly appreciated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the meantime, he could improve his performance by appearing in cinemas and came out of slump, and he displayed performance which we can call the spirit of Kamigata wagoto (the production style of a love scene) and he was highly appreciated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the meantime, he could improve his art by appearing in cinemas and came out of doldrums, and he displayed the art which we can call the spirit of Kamigata wagoto (the production style of a love scene in Kamigata (Kyoto and Osaka area)) and he was highly appreciated.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>主な受賞歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Main awards he received:</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Main awards he received:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Main Prizes He Won</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>1967年、重要無形文化財保持者認定（人間国宝）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1967, recognition as the holder of the Important Intangible Cultural Property (Living National Treasure).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1967, recognition as the holder of the Important Intangible Cultural Property (Living National Treasure).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1967, recognition as the holder of the Important Intangible Cultural Property (Living National Treasure).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>1968年、紫綬褒章。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1968, Shiju hosho (medal of honor with purple ribbon).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1968, Shiju hosho (medal of honor with purple ribbon).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1968, Shiju hosho (medal of honor with purple ribbon).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>1969年、日本放送協会放送文化賞。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1969, Cultural Award by Japan Broadcasting. Corporation (NHK).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1969, Cultural Award by Japan Broadcasting. Corporation (NHK).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1969, Cultural Award by Japan Broadcasting Corporation (NHK).</e>
<cmt>余分なピリオドをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>1970年、芸術院賞。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1970, Award of the Japan Art Academy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1970, Award of the Japan Art Academy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1970, Award of the Japan Art Academy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>1972年、芸術院会員。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1972, a member of the Japan Art Academy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1972, a member of the Japan Art Academy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1972, a member of the Japan Art Academy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>1974年、勲三等瑞宝章。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1974, the Third Order of Merit with the Order of the Sacred Treasure</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1974, the Third Order of Merit with the Order of the Sacred Treasure</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1974, the Third Order of Merit with the Order of the Sacred Treasure.</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>1980年、文化功労者。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1980, Bunkakorosha, (Person of Cultural Merits).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1980, Bunkakorosha, (Person of Cultural Merits).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1980, Bunkakorosha (Person of Cultural Merits).</e>
<cmt>余分なピリオドをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="30">
<j>1983年4月13日死去、正四位勲二等瑞宝章が追贈された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died on April 13, 1983 and he was conferred posthumously Shoshii (Senior Forth Rank) and the Second Order of Merit with the Order of the Sacred Treasure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died on April 13, 1983 and he was conferred posthumously Shoshii (Senior Forth Rank) and the Second Order of Merit with the Order of the Sacred Treasure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died on April 13, 1983 and he was conferred posthumously Shoshii (Senior Forth Rank) and the Second Order of Merit with the Order of the Sacred Treasure.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="31">
<j>家族</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>兄に林又一郎、妹に長谷川一夫に嫁したたみ、中村富十郎 (4代目)に嫁した女優の中村芳子など。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had an elder brother, Mataichiro HAYASHI and younger sisters, Tami who married Kazuo HASEGAWA and Yoshiko Nakamura who was an actress and married Tomijuro NAKAMURA (IV).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had an elder brother, Mataichiro HAYASHI and younger sisters, Tami who married Kazuo HASEGAWA and Yoshiko Nakamura who was an actress and married Tomijuro NAKAMURA (IV).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had an elder brother, Mataichiro HAYASHI and younger sisters, Tami who married Kazuo HASEGAWA and Yoshiko NAKAMURA who was an actress and married Tomijuro NAKAMURA (the fourth).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>長男は坂田藤十郎 (4代目)、長女は女優の中村玉緒。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His first son is Tojuro SAKATA (IV) and the first daughter is Tamao NAKAMURA, who is an actress.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His first son is Tojuro SAKATA (IV) and the first daughter is Tamao NAKAMURA, who is an actress.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His first son is Tojuro SAKATA (the fourth) and the first daughter is Tamao NAKAMURA, who is an actress.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="34">
<j>芸風・当たり役</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Style of performance and star roles</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Style of performance and star roles</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Style of Performance and Star Roles</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>立役、女形、敵役、老役とあらゆる役種をこなしたが、本領は父・初代鴈治郎ゆずりの二枚目と二代目延若の影響を受けたつっころばしなどの上方和事にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He could perform all types of role including tachiyaku, oyama, katakiyaku (a hate figure) and fukeyaku (a role of an aged person), but he showed his real ability in roles of lover inherited from this father Ganjiro I and Kamigata wagoto influenced by Enjaku II such as tsukkorobashi (a weak and feeble but somehow comical nimaime in Kamigata wagoto).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He could perform all types of roles, including tachiyaku, oyama, katakiyaku (a hate figure) and fukeyaku (a role of an aged person), but he showed his real ability in roles as a lover, inherited from this father Ganjiro I and Kamigata wagoto influenced by Enjaku II such as tsukkorobashi (a weak and feeble but somehow comical nimaime in Kamigata wagoto).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He could perform all types of roles, including tachiyaku, oyama, katakiyaku (a hate figure) and fukeyaku (a role of an aged person), but he showed his real ability in roles as a lover, inherited from his father Ganjiro, the first, and Kamigata wagoto influenced by Enjaku, the second, such as tsukkorobashi (a weak and feeble but somehow comical nimaime in Kamigata wagoto).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>上方歌舞伎の伝統にのっとって、型を意識しない写実的な芸風が特徴で、身ごなしや風情に独特の艶のある役者であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Based on traditions of Kamigata Kabuki, his characteristics is realistic performance without sticking to the pattern and he was an actor who had unique charm in his expression and a taste (elegance).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based on traditions of Kamigata Kabuki, his characteristics were realistic performance without sticking to the pattern and he was an actor who had unique charm in his expression and taste (elegance).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based on traditions of Kamigata Kabuki, his characteristics were realistic art without sticking to the patterns and he was an actor who had unique charm in his carriage and taste (elegance).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>「曾根崎心中」の徳兵衛、「心中天網島」の治兵衛、「恋飛脚大和往来・封印切」の忠兵衛、『伊賀越道中双六・沼津』の重兵衛、『双蝶々曲輪日記・引窓』の南方十次兵衛、『義経千本櫻・すし屋』のいがみの権太、『土屋主税』の土屋侯などが代表作。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His important works are Tokubei in &quot;Sonezaki shinju,&quot; Jihei in &quot;Shinju ten no amishima&quot; (Lovers&apos; suicide in Amijima), Chubei in &quot;Koibikyaku Yamato orai/fuinkiri,&quot; Jubei in &quot;Iga-goe dochu sugoroku/Numazu,&quot; Jujibei MINAMIGATA in &quot;Futatsu chocho kuruwa nikki/Hikimado&quot;(Skylight of &quot;A Diary of Two Butterflies in the Pleasure Quarters&quot;), Igami no gonta of &quot;Yoshitsune senbon zakura/sushiya&quot; (Sushiya of &quot;Yoshitsune 1000 cherry trees&quot;)and Lord Tsuchiya in &quot;Tsuchiya Chikara.&quot;</e>
<cmt>歌舞伎の題名の括弧内の英語による説明は用語集に記載のあるものに限りました。(その他は確認できませんでした。)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His important works are Tokubei in &quot;Sonezaki shinju,&quot; Jihei in &quot;Shinju ten no amishima&quot; (Lovers&apos; suicide in Amijima), Chubei in &quot;Koibikyaku Yamato orai/fuinkiri,&quot; Jubei in &quot;Iga-goe dochu sugoroku/Numazu,&quot; Jujibei MINAMIGATA in &quot;Futatsu chocho kuruwa nikki/Hikimado&quot;(Skylight of &quot;A Diary of Two Butterflies in the Pleasure Quarters&quot;), Igami no gonta of &quot;Yoshitsune senbon zakura/sushiya&quot; (Sushiya of &quot;Yoshitsune 1000 cherry trees&quot;)and Lord Tsuchiya in &quot;Tsuchiya Chikara.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His important works are Tokubei in &apos;Sonezaki shinju,&apos; Jihei in &apos;Shinju ten no amishima&apos; (Lovers&apos; suicide in Amijima), Chubei in &apos;Fuinkiri (breaking the seal), Koibikyaku Yamato orai&apos; (The Amorous Courier on the Yamato Highway), Jubei in &quot;Iga-goe dochu sugoroku (Japanese backgammon); Numazu&quot; (Through Iga Pass with the Tokaido Board Game, Numazu post), Jujibei MINAMIGATA in &quot;Futatsu chocho kuruwa nikki; Hikimado&quot;(Skylight of &quot;A Diary of Two Butterflies in the Pleasure Quarters&quot;), Igami no Gonta of &quot;Yoshitsune senbon zakura; sushiya&quot; (Sushi restaurant of &quot;Yoshitsune and the 1000 cherry trees&quot;) and Lord Tsuchiya in &quot;Tsuchiya Chikara&quot; (Chikara TSUCHIYA, hatamoto (a direct vassal of the shogun)).</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>女形では『菅原伝授手習鑑・寺子屋』の千代、『鏡山旧錦絵』のお初・岩藤、『伽羅先代萩』の八汐。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As oyama, we can name Chiyo in &quot;Sugawara denju tenarai kagami (Sugawara&apos;s secrets of calligraphy)/terakoya,&quot; Ohatsu in &quot;Kagamiyama kokyo no nishikie (old brocade pictures of Mt. Kagamiyama)&quot; and Yashio in &quot;&quot;Meiboku sendai hagi (The trouble in the Date Clan).&quot;</e>
<cmt>歌舞伎の題名の括弧内の英語による説明は用語集に記載のあるものに限りました。(その他は確認できませんでした。)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As oyama, we can name Chiyo in &quot;Sugawara denju tenarai kagami (Sugawara&apos;s secrets of calligraphy)/terakoya,&quot; Ohatsu in &quot;Kagamiyama kokyo no nishikie (old brocade pictures of Mt. Kagamiyama)&quot; and Yashio in &quot;&quot;Meiboku sendai hagi (The trouble in the Date Clan).&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As oyama, his important works are Chiyo in &quot;Sugawara denju tenarai kagami; terakoya&quot; (Terakoya (temple elementary school during the Edo period) of Sugawara&apos;s secrets of calligraphy), Ohatsu in &quot;Kagamiyama kokyo no nishikie&quot; (old brocade pictures of Mt. Kagami) and Yashio in &quot;Meiboku sendai hagi&quot; (The trouble in the Date Clan).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>老女形では『道明寺』の覚寿、敵役は『仮名手本忠臣蔵』の師直、『菅原伝授手習鑑・車引』の時平公、また勇壮な『妹背山婦女庭訓』の鱶七、『新薄雪物語』の妻平、喜劇では『三升蒔画（ちょいのせ）』の善六なども得意とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also good at as fukeoyama (oyama as aged woman) at Kakuju in &quot;Domyoji (Domyo-ji temple)&quot;, as katakiyaku Moronao in &quot;Kanadehon chushingura (The Treasury of Loyal Retainers)&quot; and Lord Tokihira in &quot;Sugawara denju tenarai kagami (Sugawara&apos;s secrets of calligraphy),&quot; as heroic roles Fukashichi in &quot;Imoseyama onna teikin&quot; and Tsumahei in &quot;Shin usuyuki monogatari,&quot; and among comics as Zenroku in Mitsugumakie no Sakazuki (choinose).&quot;</e>
<cmt>歌舞伎の題名の括弧内の英語による説明は用語集に記載のあるものに限りました。(その他は確認できませんでした。)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also good at as fukeoyama (oyama as aged woman) at Kakuju in &quot;Domyoji (Domyo-ji temple)&quot;, as katakiyaku Moronao in &quot;Kanadehon chushingura (The Treasury of Loyal Retainers)&quot; and Lord Tokihira in &quot;Sugawara denju tenarai kagami (Sugawara&apos;s secrets of calligraphy),&quot; as heroic roles Fukashichi in &quot;Imoseyama onna teikin&quot; and Tsumahei in &quot;Shin usuyuki monogatari,&quot; and among comics as Zenroku in Mitsugumakie no Sakazuki (choinose).&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also good at playing as fukeoyama (oyama as aged woman) at Kakuju in &quot;Domyoji&quot; (Domyo-ji temple), as katakiyaku, Moronao in &quot;Kanadehon Chushingura&quot; and Lord Tokihira in &quot;Sugawara denju tenarai kagami; kurumabiki&quot; (Pulling the Cow Carriage of Sugawara&apos;s secrets of calligraphy), as heroic roles, Fukashichi in &quot;Imoseyama onna teikin&quot; (An Exemplary Tale of Womanly Virtue) and Tsumahei in &quot;Shin usuyuki monogatari&quot; (The Tale of Usuyuki), and among comics as Zenroku in &quot;Mitsugumi Makie (or Choinose).&quot;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>中村歌右衛門 (6代目)と共演した『建礼門院』の後白河法皇、『隅田川』の舟長や、晩年長男・二代目扇雀と共演した『宿無団七』の並木正三など枯れた芸風で演じた役も傑作。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, roles which he played with mellowed style of performance were masterpieces, such as the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa in &quot;Kenreimonin&quot; and Funaosa (shipmaster) in &quot;Sumida-gawa (Sumida River)&quot; which he performed with Utaemon NAKAMURA VI and Shozo NAMIKI in &quot;Yadonashi Danshichi&quot; which he performed with his first son Senjaku II in his later years.</e>
<cmt>歌舞伎の題名の括弧内の英語による説明は用語集に記載のあるものに限りました。(その他は確認できませんでした。)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, roles which he played with a mellowed style of performance were masterpieces, such as the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa in &quot;Kenreimonin&quot; and Funaosa (shipmaster) in &quot;Sumida-gawa (Sumida River)&quot; which he performed with Utaemon NAKAMURA VI and Shozo NAMIKI in &quot;Yadonashi Danshichi&quot; which he performed with his first son Senjaku II in his later years.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, roles which he played with a seasoned style of performance were masterpieces, such as the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa in &quot;Kenreimonin&quot; and Funaosa (shipmaster) in &quot;Sumida-gawa&quot; (the Sumida-gawa River) which he performed with Utaemon NAKAMURA, the sixth, and Shozo NAMIKI in &quot;Yadonashi Danshichi&quot; (Homeless Danshichi) which he performed with his first son Senjaku the second in his later years.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>また、歌舞伎だけにとどまらず、『わてらの年輪』で花柳章太郎と共演するなど幅広く活躍した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Not staying within the frame of kabuki, he was active in a wide range including &quot;Watera no nenrin &quot; (literally, our growth rings)&quot; in which he performed with Shotaro HANAYAGI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Not staying within the frame of kabuki, he was active in a wide range including &quot;Watera no nenrin &quot; (literally, our growth rings)&quot; in which he performed with Shotaro HANAYAGI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Not staying within the world of kabuki, he was active in a wide range including &quot;Watera no nenrin&quot; (literally, our growth rings) in which he performed with Shotaro HANAYAGI.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="42">
<j>人物・逸話</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Personality and episodes</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Personality and episodes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Personal Profile and Episodes</e>
<cmt>他の記事と統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>最後まで若々しい芸を見せ、「曽根崎心中」で共演した長男・四代目藤十郎（当時・二代目扇雀）が人気を集めると「嫉みますがな」とライバル心をむき出しにしていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He displayed youthful performance until his last and, when his first son, Tojuro IV (Senjaku II at that time) with whom he performed together in &quot;Sonezaki shinju,&quot; found favor with public, he showed his competitive spirit saying &quot;No need to say, I feel jealous.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He displayed youthful performance until his last and, when his first son, Tojuro IV (Senjaku II at that time) with whom he performed together in &quot;Sonezaki shinju,&quot; found favor with public, he showed his competitive spirit saying &quot;No need to say, I feel jealous.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He displayed youthful performances until his last and, when his eldest son, Tojuro the fourth (Senjaku the second at that time) with whom he performed together in &apos;Sonezaki shinju,&apos; found favor with public, he showed his competitive spirit saying &apos;No need to say, I feel jealous.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="44">
<j>庶民的な気さくな面を持ちパチンコや競馬が好きであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also had a common-man and sociably personality and liked pachinko and horse races.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also had a common-man and sociably personality and liked pachinko and horse races.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also had a common-man and sociable personality and liked pachinko (Japanese pinball) and horse races.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>人間国宝に認定されると「国宝なったら競馬したらアカンのか」と本気で心配した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When he designated to a Living National Treasure, he really felt uneasy telling &quot;If I become a national treasure, may I not enjoy the horse race?&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When he became designated as a Living National Treasure, he really felt uneasy telling &quot;If I become a national treasure, may I not enjoy the horse race?&quot;</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When he became designated a Living National Treasure, he really felt uneasy telling &apos;If I become a national treasure, may I not enjoy the horse race?&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>また、当時孤軍奮闘していた市川猿之助 (3代目)を可愛がり彼の一座によく参加するなど義侠心も併せ持つ人物だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also had a chivalrous spirit as seen in the fact that he treated Ennosuke ICHIKAWA III, who had been fighting singlehanded at that time, kindly and often took part in his troupe.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also had a chivalrous spirit as seen in the fact that he treated Ennosuke ICHIKAWA III, who had been fighting singlehanded at that time, kindly and often took part in his troupe.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also had a chivalrous spirit as seen in the fact that he treated kindly Ennosuke ICHIKAWA the third, who had been fighting singlehanded at that time, and often took part in his troupe.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="47">
<j>台詞覚えは悪かったものの、新作や新しい役柄には進んで挑戦するチャレンジ精神に富んでいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although he was not good at remembering his lines, he had a plenty of challenging spirit to cope with new works or new roles aggressively.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although he was not good at remembering his lines, he had plenty of challenging spirit to cope with new work or new roles aggressively.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although he was not good at remembering his lines, he had a bold challenging spirit to cope with new programs or new roles aggressively.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>台詞がうろ覚えでも本番では観客に悟られることなく演じることが出来る特技を持っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had a special talent that, even if he had only faint memory of his lines, he could perform without making audience notice it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had a special talent that, even if he had only faint memory of his lines, he could perform without making the audience notice it.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had a special talent that, even if he had only a faint memory of his lines, he could perform without having the audience notice it.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>ある新作の稽古で、原作者から「鴈治郎さん。台詞覚えて下さい！」と駄目を出された時は、今まで見せたことのない怒りの表情になり、後々までもこのことを恨んでいたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In practicing for a new work, when he was pointed out by the writer of the original work, &quot;Ganjiro-san, please memorize your lines!,&quot; he showed an angry expression and he continued to resent this.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In practicing for a new work, when he was told by the writer of the original work, &quot;Ganjiro-san, please memorize your lines!,&quot; he showed an angry expression and he continued to resent this.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In practicing for a new program, when he was asked by the writer of the original work, &apos;Ganjiro-san, please memorize your lines!,&apos; he showed an angry expression and he continued to resent this.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="50">
<j>また、「妹背山・金殿」の鎌七を演じたとき、周囲は荒事の鎌七を和事の鴈治郎が演じられるのか、あるいはミスキャストではないかと案じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When he performed Kamashichi in &quot;Imoseyama/Kinden,&quot; his surroundings were worried if Ganjiro who was good at wagoto could play Kamashichi, which was aragoto in its nature or it might be miscasting.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When he performed Kamashichi in &quot;Imoseyama/Kinden,&quot; people around him were worried if Ganjiro, who was good at wagoto, could play Kamashichi, which was aragoto in its nature or it might be a miscasting.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When he performed Kamashichi in &apos;Imoseyama; Kinden,&apos; people around him were worried if Ganjiro, who was good at wagoto, could perform Kamashichi, which was aragoto (Kabuki play featuring exaggerated posture, makeup, and costume) in its nature or it might be a miscasting.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>しかし鴈治郎は尾上松緑 (2代目)から役の性を教えてもらうなど、自身なりの鎌七を見事に演じ切って賞賛を浴びた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Ganjiro learned from Shoroku ONOE II concerning the nature of the role and played his own Kamashichi excellently and received praise.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Ganjiro learned from Shoroku ONOE II concerning the nature of the role and played his own Kamashichi excellently and received praise.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Ganjiro learned from Shoroku ONOE (II) concerning the nature of the role and played his own Kamashichi excellently and received praise.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>これには、お三輪役で共演した中村歌右衛門 (6代目)が、以前から「成駒屋(鴈治郎のこと）の鎌七はすごいわよ」とその芸力を認め強く推薦していたからであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was because Utaemon NAKAMURA, who performed together as Omiwa, had acknowledged his capability of performing and had strongly recommended telling &quot;Kamashichi by Narikomaya (Ganjiro) must be fantastic.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was because Utaemon NAKAMURA, who performed together as Omiwa, had acknowledged his performing capability and had strongly recommended telling &quot;Kamashichi by Narikomaya (Ganjiro) must be fantastic.&quot;</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was because Utaemon NAKAMURA (VI), who performed together as Omiwa, had acknowledged his performing capability and had strongly recommended telling &apos;Kamashichi by Narikoma-ya (Ganjiro) must be fantastic.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Adachiyo(id:10617), ととりん(id:31982), Hikichimin Jr.(id:147077), Cprobot(id:97843), ウィキウィ2(id:83093), 松茸(id:27535), Uraios(id:72687), MDR-SK(id:192066), 白拍子花子(id:244805), スティロウ(id:89199), Ponta2(id:129030), Mymelo(id:122034), ゐ(id:795), Ajcxx(id:103602), 氷室浩次(id:180895), Point136(id:211299), こぶまき(id:38278), 兇状旅(id:137772), Ik1973(id:293582), Bankokuya(id:91191), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>