<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>仕舞</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shimai</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shimai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shimai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>仕舞（し-まい）とは能の一部を素で舞うこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shimai means to dance part of Noh play without wearing masks and costumes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shimai refers to a part of Noh play where a performer dances without wearing masks or costumes.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shimai refers to a part of the Noh play where a performer dances without wearing masks or costumes.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>能における略式上演形態の一種。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is a kind of casual performing style in Noh.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is a casual form of Noh performance.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is a casual form of the Noh performance.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>広義にはいわゆる仕舞と舞囃子を含めたものを指すが、一般的には舞囃子とは異り、囃子を伴わず、舞事・働事などの部分を略した短い素舞を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a broad sense, it indicates so-called performance including Shimai and Maibayashi (an abbreviated style of Noh); however, differently from Maibayashi, Shimai generally indicates short dancing without accompaniment of hayashi (musical accompaniment played on traditional Japanese instruments) and wearing masks and costumes, in which mai-goto (instrumental dances) and hataraki-goto (descriptive pieces) are abbreviated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In a broad sense, it indicates performances that include Shimai and Maibayashi (an abbreviated style of Noh); however, in contrast with Maibayashi, Shimai generally indicates short dancing without being accompanied by hayashi (musical accompaniment played on traditional Japanese instruments) or wearing masks and costumes, in which mai-goto (instrumental dances) and hataraki-goto (descriptive pieces) are abbreviated.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In a broad sense, it indicates performances that include Shimai and Maibayashi (an abbreviated style of Noh); however, in contrast with Maibayashi, Shimai generally indicates a short dance without being accompanied by music, in which mai-goto (instrumental dances) and hataraki-goto (descriptive pieces) are abbreviated.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>舞囃子が一曲のうち能シテの舞がかかわる部分の大半を上演するのに対して、仕舞においては謡のあるシテの舞を抜きだしたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Maibayashi, most part relating to dances by Noh shite (leading role) is performed in one play, while in Shimai, dances performed by the shite which accompany Utai (the chanting of a Noh text) are extracted.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Maibayashi, most parts relating to dances by Noh shite (leading role) is performed in one play, while in Shimai, dances performed by the shite which accompany Utai (the chanting of a Noh text) are extracted.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Maibayashi, most parts relating to dances by Noh shite (leading role) is performed in one play, while in Shimai, dances performed by the shite which is accompanied by Utai (the chanting of a Noh text) are extracted.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>そのため、場合によっては一曲の能から数番の仕舞が掲出されていることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, several numbers of Shimai are extracted from one piece in some cases.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, several numbers of Shimai are extracted from one piece in some cases.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, several numbers of Shimai are excerpted from one piece in some cases.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>たいていはクセ（舞グセ）およびこれに準ずるもの、キリ、段物などで、型は能のそれを基本とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In most cases, a style is based on kuse in Noh (a long segment, the aural highlight of a Noh play) (Maiguse (the aural highlight of a Noh play delivered while the shite (main role) dances)), segments subject to it, Kiri (the concluding segment of a Noh play which combines chant and dance) and danmono (the most important type of shirabemono (the koto solo instrumental music)).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In most cases, a style is based on kuse in Noh (a long segment, the aural highlight of a Noh play) (Maiguse (the aural highlight of a Noh play delivered while the shite (main role) dances)), segments subject to it, Kiri (the concluding segment of a Noh play which combines chant and dance) and danmono (the most important type of shirabemono (the koto solo instrumental music)).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In most cases, a style is based on kuse or Maiguse in Noh (a long segment, the aural highlight of a Noh play), segments subject to it, Kiri (the concluding segment of a Noh play which combines chant and dance) and danmono (the most important type of the koto solo instrumental music.)</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>しかし、始曲部分や終曲部分は収まりのよいように仕舞独自の型が付され、そのほかの部分でもあて振り的な要素のつよい型はこれを改めて全体的に象徴性をより高くする方向で型付が行われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, a form specific to Shimai is choreographed so that the beginning and ending parts of piece are settled, and in other parts, forms are also choreographed toward raising a symbolic nature in the whole by revising choreography having a strong nature of Ateburi (expressing the meaning of verses by dancing).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, a form specific to Shimai is choreographed so that the beginning and ending parts are settled, and in other parts, forms are also choreographed toward raising a symbolic nature of the whole by revising choreography which has a strong nature of Ateburi (expressing the meaning of verses by dancing).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, a form specific to Shimai is originally choreographed so that the beginning and ending parts are settled, and in other parts, forms are also choreographed toward raising the symbolic nature of the whole by revising the choreography that has a strong nature of Ateburi (expressing the meaning of verses by dancing).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>伴奏は能地謡のみによって行われ、能装束・能面は用いず、紋付袴か裃などで演ずる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shimai is performed only with the accompaniment of Noh-jiuta (Noh chorus), and wearing Montsuki hakama (formal Japanese attire for a man, consisting of a kimono dyed with the family crest and a long, loose, pleated skirt) or kamishimo (samurai costume, old ceremonial costume), but without wearing Noh costumes and Noh masks.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shimai is performed only to the accompaniment of Noh-jiuta (Noh chorus), and donning of Montsuki hakama (formal Japanese attire for a man, consisting of a kimono dyed with the family crest and a long, loose, pleated skirt) or kamishimo (samurai costume, old ceremonial costume), without wearing Noh costumes and Noh masks.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shimai is performed only to the accompaniment of Noh-jiuta (Noh chorus), and donning of Montsuki hakama (formal Japanese attire for a man, consisting of a kimono dyed with the family crest and a long, loose, pleated skirt) or kamishimo (samurai costume, old ceremonial costume), instead of wearing Noh costumes and Noh masks.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>演者は、本来の指定にかかわらず最初の一句を坐ったまま謡い、次に立ち上って舞い、最後に打ち込みと呼ばれる型を行って坐って一曲を終える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A performer chants the first one phrase in a sitting posture regardless of original designation, secondly stands up and dances, and lastly performs a form called Uchikomi, and then sits down and finishes one piece.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A performer chants the first phrase in a sitting posture regardless of original designation, then stands up and dances, and finally performs a form called Uchikomi, and then sits down and finishes the piece.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A performer chants the first phrase in a sitting posture regardless of original designation, then stands up and dances, and finally performs a movemenet called Uchikomi (the Scooping Point), and then sits down and finishes the piece.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>謡曲はほとんどを地謡が取るが、なかには演者との掛け合いになっているものもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For most Yokyoku (Noh song), Jiutai (Noh chorus) is used; however, conversational songs with a performer are used sometimes.</e>
<cmt>掛け合い→conversational songs[会話的な謡と解釈しました]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For most Yokyoku (Noh song), Jiutai (Noh chorus) is used; however, conversational songs with a performer are sometimes used.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For most Yokyoku (Noh song), Jiutai (Noh chorus) is used; however, sometimes the performer and Jiutai sing in turn.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>上演にあたっての時間はきわめて短く、平均で十分程度、長くても二十分ほどのものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The performance is quite short, about ten minutes in average, and the longest is about twenty minutes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The performance is quite short, about ten minutes on average, and the longest being about twenty minutes.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The performance is quite short, about ten minutes on average, and the longest being about twenty minutes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>主としてシテ方が一人で行うが、なかには「小袖曾我」や「二人静」のように両ジテ的な相舞のもの、「龍虎 (能)」「舎利 (能)」のようにシテとツレが異なった舞をひとつの舞台で見せるものがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Shimai is mainly performed by one of shite-kata (main roles), there are other variations such as dances by two performers in the form of Ryojite (dual Shite) like &quot;Kosode Soga (The Soga and the wadded silk robe) and &quot;Futari Shizuka (a couple of the young ladies named Shizuka), and performance of different dances between Shite (main role) and Tsure (performer appearing after the shite) on the same stage like &quot;Ryoko (Noh)&quot; and &quot;Shari (Noh).&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Shimai is mainly performed by a shite-kata (main roles), there are other variations such as dances carried out by two performers in the form of Ryojite (dual Shite) like &quot;Kosode Soga (The Soga and the wadded silk robe) and &quot;Futari Shizuka (a couple of the young ladies named Shizuka), and performances of different dances between Shite (main role) and Tsure (performer appearing after the shite) on the same stage like &quot;Ryoko (Noh)&quot; and &quot;Shari (Noh).&quot;</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Shimai is mainly performed by a shite-kata (main role), there are other variations such as dances carried out by two performers in the form of Ryojite (dual Shite) like &apos;Kosode Soga&apos; (The Soga and the wadded silk robe) and &quot;&apos;Futari Shizuka&apos; (a couple of the young ladies named Shizuka), and performances of different dances between Shite (main role) and Tsure (performer appearing after the shite) on the same stage like &apos;Ryoko (Noh)&apos; (dragon and tiger) and &apos;Shari (Noh)&apos; (bones left after cremation).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>このような場合には演者が二人となる（「大蛇 (能)」のようにシテとワキの二人で舞う仕舞もある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this case, two actors perform together (Shimai also has another variation in which two actors, Shite and Waki (supporting actor), perform together like &quot;Daija (&quot;big snake,&quot; Noh).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this case, two actors perform together (Shimai also has another variation in which two actors, Shite and Waki (supporting actor), perform together like &quot;Daija (&quot;big snake,&quot; Noh).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this case, two actors perform together (Shimai also has another variation in which two actors, Shite and Waki (supporting actor), perform together like &apos;Daija&apos; (big snake).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>また「張良 (能)」「羅生門 (能)」のようにワキ方の仕舞もあり、能狂言方においても小舞として仕舞に似た上演形態がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shimai is also performed by Waki-kata (supporting actors) like &quot;Choryo (Noh)&quot; and &quot;Rashomon (Noh),&quot; and a Noh farce actor also performs komai (short dances in Noh farce) which is similar to Shimai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shimai is also performed by Waki-kata (supporting actors) like &quot;Choryo (Noh)&quot; and &quot;Rashomon (Noh),&quot; and a Noh farce actor also performs komai (short dances in Noh farce) which is similar to Shimai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shimai is also performed by Waki-kata (supporting actors) like &apos;Choryo&apos; and &apos;Rashomon Gate,&apos; and a Noh farce actor also performs komai (short dances in Noh farce) that is similar to Shimai.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>仕舞は鑑賞用としても上演されているが、能を演ずるための稽古の段階としても利用されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shimai is also performed for appreciation, but, is used as a step of practice to perform Noh.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shimai is also performed for appreciation, but, is used as a step in practicing Noh.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shimai is also performed for stage, but, is used as a phase of practicing Noh.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="16">
<j>仕舞の基本は摺り足であるが、足裏を舞台面につけて踵をあげることなくすべるように歩む独特の運歩法で（特にこれをハコビと称する）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The basis of Shimai is Suriashi (shuffle) which is a unique way of walking (known as Hakobi) in which the sole of the feet slide along the floor without raising the heels.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The basis of Shimai is Suriashi (shuffle) which is a unique way of walking (known as Hakobi) in which the sole of the feet slide along the floor without raising the heels.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The basis of Shimai is Suriashi (shuffle), which is a unique way of walking (Particularly known as Hakobi) in which the sole of the feet slide along the floor without raising the heels.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>これを円滑に行うためには膝を曲げ腰を入れて重心を落とした体勢をとる必要がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order to do this way smoothly, actors have to lower the center of gravity by bending the knees.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to do this, actors have to lower their center of gravity by bending the knees.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to do this smoothly, actors have to lower their center of gravity by bending their knees.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>すなわちこれが「構え」である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In other words, this is &quot;Kamae (posture).&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In other words, this is &quot;Kamae (posture).&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In other words, this is &apos;Kamae&apos; (posture.)</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>また能は、歌舞伎やそこから発生した日本舞踏が横長の舞台において正面の客に向って舞踏を見せることを前提とするのに対して、正方形の舞台の上で三方からの観客を意識しながら、円を描くようにして動く点にも特徴がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another characteristic of Noh is that performers move in a circular pattern on a square stage in consideration of audiences on three sides, while Kabuki (traditional Japanese drama performed by male actors) and Classical Japanese dance derived from Kabuki are performed on a rectangular stage on the premise of showing the performance to front audiences.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another characteristic of Noh is that performers move in a circular pattern on a square stage in consideration to audiences on three sides, while Kabuki (traditional Japanese drama performed by male actors) and Classical Japanese dance derived from Kabuki are performed on a rectangular stage on the premise of showing the performance to audiences in the front.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another characteristic of Noh is that performers move in a circular pattern on a square stage in consideration for audiences on three sides, while Kabuki (traditional Japanese drama performed by male actors) and Classical Japanese dance derived from Kabuki are performed on a rectangular stage on the premise for showing the performance to audiences in the front.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>能舞台は音がよく反響するように作られており、演者が足で舞台を踏む（足拍子）ことも重要な表現要素である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Noh stage is made so as to resonate the sound, and it is one of the important expressing elements that performers stamp the floor of the stage (Ashi byoshi).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Noh stage is made so as to resonate sound, as performers stamping the floor of the stage (Ashi Byoshi) is considered an important element.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Noh stage is made so as to resonate sound, as performer&apos;s stamping on the floor of the stage (Ashi Byoshi) is considered an important element.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="21">
<j>以下に主な仕舞の型の例を示す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following are major forms in Shimai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following are major forms in Shimai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following are major forms in Shimai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="22">
<j>シカケ（サシコミ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shikake (sashikomi)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shikake (sashikomi)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shikake (sashikomi)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>すっと立ち、扇を持った右手をやや高く正面にだす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Stand upright, and extend a right hand holding a fan forward a little highly</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Stand upright, and extend the right hand high while holding a fan forward.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Stand upright, and extend the right hand high while holding a fan forward.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="24">
<j>ヒラキ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hiraki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hiraki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hiraki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>左足、右足、左足と三足（さんぞく）後退しながら、両腕を横に広げる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Open hands horizontally while taking three steps backward in the order corresponding to left foot, right foot and left foot</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Open hands horizontally while taking three steps backward in the order corresponding to left foot, right foot and left foot</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Open hands horizontally while taking three steps backward in the order corresponding to left foot, right foot and left foot.</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>シカケとヒラキを連続させる型をシカケヒラキ（サシコミヒラキ）と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The form of performing Shikake and Hiraki in succession is called Shikake-hiraki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The form of performing Shikake and Hiraki in succession is called Shikake-hiraki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The form of performing Shikake and Hiraki in succession is called Shikake-hiraki (or Sashikomi-hiraki).</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="27">
<j>左右（さゆう）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sayu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sayu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sayu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>左手を掲げて左に一足ないし数足出た後、右手を掲げて右に一足ないし数足出る型。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Form of raising a right hand and taking one step or several steps rightward after raising a left hand and taking one step or several steps leftwards</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Form of raising the right hand and taking one step or several steps to the right after raising a left hand and taking one step or several steps to the left</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The form of raising the right hand and taking one or several steps to the right after raising a left hand and taking one or several steps to the left.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="29">
<j>サシ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sashi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sashi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sashi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>右手の扇を横から上げて正面高くに掲げる型。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Form of raising a fan held with a right hand from the side to the top, and holding it up highly at the front</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Form of raising a fan held with a right hand from the side to the top, and holding it up high to the front</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The form of raising a fan held with a right hand from the side to the top, and holding it up high to the front.</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="31">
<j>シオリ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shiori</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shiori</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shiori</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>目の前に手を差し出す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Extend the hand to the front</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Extend the hand to the front</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Extending the hand to the front.</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>泣くことを示す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This form indicates crying.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This form indicates crying.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This form indicates crying.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="34">
<j>枕扇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Makuraogi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Makuraogi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Makuraogi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>左手で扇を持って顔を隠し、寝ていることを示す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hide a face using a fan held with a left hand, which indicates sleeping.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hide the face using a fan held with the left hand, which indicates sleeping.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hide the face using a fan held with the left hand, indicating sleeping.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="36">
<j>これら種々の型の連続によって仕舞が構成される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shimai consists of series of these forms.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shimai consists of a series of these forms.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shimai consists of a series of these forms.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>柳田国男の論を受けた渡辺保によれば、「踊り」が飛躍や跳躍を含む語であるのに対し、「舞」は「まわる」つまり円運動を意味する語である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Tamotsu WATANABE following a theory of Kunio YANAGIDA, the term &quot;Odori (dances in Classical Japanese dance, etc.&quot; includes a meaning of jumping, but, the term &quot;Mai (dances in Noh)&quot; means &quot;revolving&quot; which means a circular movement.</e>
<cmt>踊り→Odori (dances in Classical Japanese dance, etc.)[「舞」と区別するため、『日本舞踊などの踊り』の説明を付しました。]舞→Mai (dances in Noh)[「踊り」と区別するため、『能の踊り』の説明を付しました。]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Tamotsu WATANABE following a theory of Kunio YANAGIDA, the term &quot;Odori (dances in Classical Japanese dance, etc.&quot; includes a meaning of jumping, but, the term &quot;Mai (dances in Noh)&quot; means &quot;revolving&quot; which means a circular movement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Tamotsu WATANABE who is following a theory by Kunio YANAGIDA, the term &apos;Odori&apos; (dances in Classical Japanese dance, and so on) also refers to jumping, but, the term &apos;Mai&apos; (dances in Noh) means &apos;revolving&apos; which means a circular movement.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>能の舞の特徴は、極端な摺り足と独特の身体の構え、そして円運動である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Characteristics of dances in Noh are Suriashi in an extreme manner, unique posture, and circular movement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Characteristics of dances in Noh are extreme Suriashi, a unique posture, and circular movement.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Characteristics of dances in Noh are extreme Suriashi, a unique posture, and a circular movement.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="39">
<j>能の舞はきわめて静的であるという印象が一般的だが、序破急と呼ばれる緩急があり、ハコビにおいてもゆっくりと動き出して、徐々にテンポを早くし、ぴたっと止まるように演じられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The general impression is that dances in Noh are static; however, dances in Noh have a slow and quick movement called Johakyu (three segments of performance and speed of plays; slower and quieter performance during the jo (beginning), gradually gaining tempo in the ha (middle portion), and becoming more energetic during the kyu (denouement)), and in Hakobi, performers also start moving slowly, step up the tempo gradually and stop suddenly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The general impression is that dances in Noh are static; however, dances in Noh have a slow and quick movement called Johakyu (three segments of performance and speed of plays; slower and quieter performance during the jo (beginning), gradually gaining tempo in the ha (middle portion), and becoming more energetic during the kyu (denouement)), and in Hakobi, performers also start moving slowly, step up the tempo gradually and stop suddenly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The general impression of dances in Noh is static; however, dances in Noh have a slow and quick movement called Johakyu (three segments of performance and speed of plays; slower and quieter performance during the jo (beginning), gradually gaining tempo in the ha (middle portion), and becoming more energetic during the kyu (denouement)), and in Hakobi, performers also start moving slowly, step up the tempo gradually and stop suddenly.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>稀に激しい曲ではアクロバテックな演技（飛び返りや仏倒れなど）もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In some rare cases, acrobatics (Tobikaeri (backward somersault), Hotokedaore (performance that represents death or falling unconscious), etc.) are performed in the aggressive type of pieces.</e>
<cmt>飛び返り→Tobikaeri (backward somersault)[バック転と解釈し、説明の英訳を付しました。]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In some rare cases, acrobatics (Tobikaeri (backward somersault), Hotokedaore (performance that represents death or falling unconscious), etc.) are performed in aggressive types of pieces.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In some rare cases, acrobatic performances (Tobikaeri (backward somersault), Hotokedaore (performance that represents death or falling unconscious), and so on) are performed in aggressive types of pieces.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>しかし止まっている場合でもじっと休んでいるわけでなく、いろいろな力がつりあったために静止しているだけにすぎない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it does not mean that performers do not take a rest even while standing still, but it means that erformers just remain stationary because forces balance.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it does not mean that performers are taking a break while standing still, rather it means that performers are simply remaining stationary in order to balance a multitude of forces.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it does not mean that performers are taking a break while standing still; rather it means that performers are simply remaining stationary in order to balance a multitude of the forces.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>このように、身体に極度の緊張を強いることで、内面から湧き上がる迫力や気合を表出させようとする特色も持っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As stated above, Shimai has another characteristic of eliciting forces and willpower welling up from the inside by giving tremendous stress to the body.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As stated above, Shimai has another characteristic of eliciting forces and tension from the inside out, producing a large impact on the audience.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As stated above, Shimai has another characteristic of eliciting forces and tension from inside out, producing a large impact on the audience.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), ファービィ(id:129184), COCKY(id:19672), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>