<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>肥後古流 (茶道)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Higo Old School (Tea Ceremony)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Higo-koryu Old School (a school of tea ceremony)</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Higo-koryu Old School (a school of tea ceremony)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>肥後古流（ひごこりゅう）は、熊本藩で伝承された茶道の流派の一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Higo old school is one of the schools of tea ceremony passed on in the Kumamoto domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Higo-koryu old school is one of the schools of tea ceremony passed on in the Kumamoto Domain.</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Higo-koryu old school is one of the schools of tea ceremony passed on in the Kumamoto Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>千利休の流儀をそのまま伝えていると称される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The school is said to exactly transmit the styles of SEN no Rikyu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The school is said to exactly transmit the styles of SEN no Rikyu.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The school is said to exactly transmit the styles of SEN no Rikyu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>古市・小堀・萱野の三家で伝承したことからそれぞれ古市流(ふるいちりゅう)・小堀流(こぼりりゅう)・萱野流(かやのりゅう)とも呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The school was succeeded to by the three families, the Furuichi family, the Kobori family, and the Kayano family; therefore, the schools of these families are called as the Furuichi school, the Kobori school, and the Kayano school respectively.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The school was succeeded to by the three families of Furuichi, Kobori, and Kayano; therefore, they are called as the Furuichi-ryu school, the Kobori-ryu school, and the Kayano-ryu school respectively.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The school was succeeded to by the three families of Furuichi, Kobori, and Kayano; therefore, they are called as the Furuichi-ryu school, the Kobori-ryu school, and the Kayano-ryu school respectively.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>細川三斎（細川忠興）は利休七哲に数えられるほどの達人であるが、豊前国小倉藩で細川忠利に家督を譲ると、忠利は寛永2年（1625年）に円乗坊宗圓の婿である古市宗庵を細川家の茶道役として召し抱えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sansai HOSOKAWA, being such an excellent tea master that he was numbered among the &apos;Rikyu Shichitetsu (seven disciples of Rikyu),&apos; transferred his family estate to Tadatoshi HOSOKAWA in the Kokura domain, Buzen Province, and in 1625, Tadatoshi hired Soan FURUICH, a son-in law of Soin ENJOBO, as a chabozu (a tea-server sustaining Japanese tea ceremony of bakufu and domains) for the Hosokawa family.</e>
<cmt>細川忠興（細川忠興）→Webでは細川三斎となっておりましたので三斎と訳出しました</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sansai HOSOKAWA, being such an excellent tea master that he was numbered among the Rikyu Shichitetsu (the seven disciples of SEN no Rikyu), transferred his family estate to Tadatoshi HOSOKAWA in the Kokura Domain, Buzen Province, and in 1625, Tadatoshi hired Soan FURUICHI, a son-in-law of Soin ENJOBO, as a sadoyaku (a tea-server sustaining Japanese tea ceremony) for the Hosokawa family.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sansai HOSOKAWA, being such an excellent tea master that he was numbered among the Rikyu Shichitetsu (the seven disciples of SEN no Rikyu), transferred his family estate to Tadatoshi HOSOKAWA in the Kokura Domain, Buzen Province, and in 1625, Tadatoshi hired Soan FURUICHI, a son-in-law of Soin ENJOBO, as a sadoyaku (a tea-server sustaining Japanese tea ceremony) for the Hosokawa family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>三斎も忠利も、古市宗庵に利休から変えることのない「古風の茶の湯」を伝えることを命じている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Both Sansai and Tadatoshi ordered Soan FURUICHI to transmit &apos;old styles of tea ceremony&apos; which had been passed on since Rikyu&apos;s time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Both Sansai and Tadatoshi ordered Soan FURUICHI to transmit &apos;old styles of tea ceremony&apos; which had been passed on since Rikyu&apos;s time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Both Sansai and Tadatoshi ordered Soan FURUICHI to transmit &apos;old styles of tea ceremony&apos; which had been passed on since Rikyu&apos;s time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>これが肥後古流の祖である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was the origin of the Higo old school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was the origin of the Higo old school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was the origin of the Higo old school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>円乗坊宗円（圓乗坊宗圓）は元は本能寺の僧であったが還俗して利休の婿となり、利休から極真台子および盆点法を伝えられた唯一の人であると伝えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soen ENJOBO, being originally a monk of Honno-ji Temple, was secularized to become a son-in-law of Rikyu; he is said to have been only a person who was given gokushindaisu (a self putting tools of boiling tea for a tea ceremony) and bonten-ho (a style of temae, tea serving method of the tea ceremony) from Rikyu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soen ENJOBO, being originally a priest of Honno-ji Temple, was secularized to become a son-in-law of Rikyu; he is said to have been only a person who was given gokushindaisu (a self putting tools of boiling tea for a tea ceremony) and bonten-ho (a style of temae, tea serving method of the tea ceremony) from Rikyu.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soen ENJOBO, being originally a priest of Honno-ji Temple, was secularized to become a son-in-law of Rikyu; he is said to have been only a person who was given gokushindaisu (a self putting tools of boiling tea for a tea ceremony) and bonten-ho (a style of temae, tea serving method of the tea ceremony) from Rikyu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>それによれば、利休の実子である千道安はあまりにも器用で、独自の創意が多いため伝授されないまま利休が没してしまい、一方で養子の千少庵は不器用であったため伝授されなかったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That was because Doan SEN, a biological child of Rikyu, was too dexterous and ingenious to pass on his own ways of tea ceremony before the death of Rikyu, while Shoan SEN, an adopted child of Rikyu, was too awkward to pass on Rikyu&apos;s way of tea ceremony.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That was because SEN no Doan, a biological child of Rikyu, was too dexterous and ingenious to pass on his own ways of tea ceremony before the death of Rikyu, while SEN no Shoan, an adopted child of Rikyu, was too awkward to pass on Rikyu&apos;s way of tea ceremony.</e>
<cmt>読みを他と合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That was because SEN no Doan, a biological child of Rikyu, was too dexterous and ingenious to pass on his own ways of tea ceremony before the death of Rikyu, while SEN no Shoan, an adopted child of Rikyu, was too awkward to pass on Rikyu&apos;s way of tea ceremony.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>宗圓には道鉄という子があったが、医業に秀でてこれに専念したため、婿の古市宗庵が一切を相伝されたと伝えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because Dotetsu, a child of Soen, was excellent at medicine which he devoted himself to, not to tea ceremony, it is believed that all the styles and techniques the school had were handed down to Soan FURUICHI who was a son-in-law of Soen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Dotetsu, a child of Soen, was excellent at medicine which he devoted himself to, not to tea ceremony, it is believed that all the styles and techniques of the school were handed down to Soan FURUICHI who was a son-in-law of Soen.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Dotetsu, a child of Soen, was excellent at medicine which he devoted himself to, not to tea ceremony, it is believed that all the styles and techniques of the school were handed down to Soan FURUICHI who was a son-in-law of Soen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>古市宗庵は後に京都に出て利休の孫同士として千宗旦に伝授した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soan FURUICHI, subsequently, went up to Kyoto to instruct Sotan SEN, because they had their mutual grandfather, Rikyu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soan FURUICHI, subsequently, went up to Kyoto to instruct SEN no Sotan, as both were the grandchildren of Rikyu.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soan FURUICHI, subsequently, went up to Kyoto to instruct SEN no Sotan, as both were the grandchildren of Rikyu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>その際の礼状があったが、昭和28年の大水害で失われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The flood disaster in 1953 resulted in losing the then letters of thanks for his instruction.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were a letter of thanks for his instruction; however, it was lost by the flood disaster in 1953.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were a letter of thanks for his instruction; however, it was lost by the flood disaster in 1953.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>熊本に伝わる宗旦作の茶杓や竹花入などが、その傍証となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some bamboo tea spoons for making Japanese tea and bamboo vases made by Sotan and passed on in Kumamoto proves their relationship.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sotan&apos;s chashaku (bamboo tea spoons for making Japanese tea) and bamboo vases, and so on, handed down in Kumamoto prove their relationship.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sotan&apos;s chashaku (bamboo tea spoons for making Japanese tea) and bamboo vases, and so on, handed down in Kumamoto prove their relationship.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="14">
<j>歴代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>古市家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Furuichi family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Furuichi family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Furuichi family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>古市家は初め200石、2世宗庵は加増されて300石、以後8世宗安まで茶道頭を勤めるが天保3年（1832年）に不行跡により知行召し上げとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Furuichi family was primarily in possession of a fief yielding 200 koku in rice, and Soan, the second head of the family, had the fief increased to 300 koku, and the following heads till the eighth head, Soan, served as chadogashira (a director in charge of maintaining tea utensils and performing the tea ceremony for bakufu and domains); however Soan&apos;s misconduct caused the family&apos;s enfeoffment to be confiscated in 1832.</e>
<cmt>茶道頭→chadogashira→a director in charge of maintaining tea utensils and performing the tea ceremony for bakufu and domainsと訳出しました</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Furuichi family was primarily in possession of a fief yielding 200 koku (crop yield), and the second head, Soan had the fief increased to 300 koku, and the following heads till the eighth head, Soan, served as chadogashira (a director in charge of maintaining tea utensils and performing the tea ceremony for a shogunate and domains); however Soan&apos;s misconduct caused the family&apos;s enfeoffment to be confiscated in 1832.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Furuichi family was primarily in possession of a fief yielding 200 koku (crop yield), and the second head, Soan had the fief increased to 300 koku, and the following heads till the eighth head, Soan, served as chadogashira (a director in charge of maintaining tea utensils and performing the tea ceremony for a shogunate and domains); however Soan&apos;s misconduct caused the family&apos;s enfeoffment to be confiscated in 1832.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>9世宗栄は200石の茶道役に復し、10世宗安の時に維新を迎える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ninth head, Soei, returned to the family&apos;s old position as chabozu with a fief yielding 200 koku in rice and during the time of the tenth head, Soan, the Meiji Restoration happened.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ninth head, Soei, returned to the family&apos;s old position as sadoyaku with a fief yielding 200 koku and during the time of the 10th head, Soan, the Meiji Restoration happened.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ninth head, Soei, returned to the family&apos;s old position as sadoyaku with a fief yielding 200 koku and during the time of the 10th head, Soan, the Meiji Restoration happened.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>維新後は武田家に受け継がれており、同門組織として的々社がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Restoration, the school was succeeded to by the Takeda family and had its fellow organization called Tekiteki-sha.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Restoration, the school was succeeded to by the Takeda family and had its fellow organization called Tekiteki-sha.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Restoration, the school was succeeded to by the Takeda family and had its fellow organization called Tekiteki-sha.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>小倉藩の茶道役にも古市家があるとのこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the Furuichi clan also served as a chabozu for the Kokura domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the Furuichi clan also served as a sadoyaku for the Kokura Domain.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the Furuichi clan also served as a sadoyaku for the Kokura Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="20">
<j>古市家歴代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History of the Furuichi family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The chronological order of the Furuichi family</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The chronological order of the Furuichi family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="21">
<j>小堀家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kobori family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kobori family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kobori family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>小堀家は豊前において小姓に召し抱えられた小堀長左衛門を祖とし、その子長斎が慶安4年（1651年）に茶道役となったことに始まる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The founder of the Kobori family was Chozaemon KOBORI, who was hired as a kosho (a servant) in Buzen Province and it was an origin of the Kobori school that Chosai, a child of Chozaemon, became a chabozu in 1651.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The founder of the Kobori family was Chozaemon KOBORI, who was hired as a kosho (a servant) in Buzen Province and the school originated that Chosai, a child of Chozaemon, became the sadoyaku in 1651.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The founder of the Kobori family was Chozaemon KOBORI, who was hired as a kosho (a servant) in Buzen Province and the school originated that Chosai, a child of Chozaemon, became the sadoyaku in 1651.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>2世茂竹は古市家4世宗佐から皆伝を受け、これを5世宗佐に伝えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The second tea master, 茂竹, was certified as full proficiency from the fourth-generation head of the Furuichi family, Sosa, and transmitted the full proficiency and his name to Sosa of the fifth-generation tea master.</e>
<cmt>茂竹→読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The second head of the school, Shigetake (茂竹), was certified as full proficiency from Sosa, the fourth head of the Furuichi family, and transmitted the full proficiency to Sosa of the fifth head.</e>
<cmt>推定できる読みを補足し、表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The second head of the school, Shigetake (茂竹), was certified as full proficiency from Sosa, the fourth head of the Furuichi family, and transmitted the full proficiency to Sosa of the fifth head.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>3世長順常春は多才な人で、文筆に長け『茗理正伝』など多くを著し、また実父村岡伊太夫の立てた水術を受け継いで水練師範として小堀流踏水術を創始した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chojun Tsuneharu, the third tea master, was versatile and excellent in literature: he wrote many books including &quot;Meirin Seiden (authentic biography),&quot; and succeeded to the art of swimming created by his biological father, Idayu MURAOKA, to establish the Kobori school of treading water as a swimming instructor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chojun Tsuneharu, the third head of the school, was versatile and excellent in literature: He wrote many books including &quot;Meirin Seiden&quot; (authentic biography), and succeeded to the art of swimming created by his biological father, Idayu MURAOKA, to establish the Kobori school of treading water as a swimming instructor.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chojun Tsuneharu, the third head of the school, was versatile and excellent in literature: He wrote many books including &quot;Meirin Seiden&quot; (authentic biography), and succeeded to the art of swimming created by his biological father, Idayu MURAOKA, to establish the Kobori school of treading water as a swimming instructor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>同門組織として白水会がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its fellow organization is Hakusui-kai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its fellow organization is Hakusui-kai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its fellow organization is Hakusui-kai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="26">
<j>小堀家歴代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History of the Kobori family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The chronological order of the Kobori family</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The chronological order of the Kobori family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="27">
<j>萱野家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kayano family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kayano family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kayano family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>古田重然の弟古田重府は、織部改易の折に難を逃れて豊前小倉の萱野伝左衛門に身を寄せた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">重府 FURUTA, a brother of Juzen FURUTA (a founder of the Oribe school), took refuge at Denzaemon KAYANO in the Kokura domain, Buzen Province ｗhen the Oribe family was punished by being deprived of its fief.</e>
<cmt>重府→読み方不明 / 織部家との関係が分かるように、古田重然（a founder of the Oribe school)を補足しました</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigefu (重府) FURUTA, a younger brother of Juzen FURUTA (a founder of the Oribe school), took refuge at Denzaemon KAYANO in the Kokura Domain, Buzen Province when the Oribe family was punished by being deprived of its fief.</e>
<cmt>推定できる読みを補足し、表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigefu (重府) FURUTA, a younger brother of Juzen FURUTA (a founder of the Oribe school), took refuge at Denzaemon KAYANO in the Kokura Domain, Buzen Province when the Oribe family was punished by being deprived of its fief.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>萱野家の初代萱野正的は伝左衛門の姉の婿であり、「茶事に因縁ある」と記されていることから重府の子と見られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first-generation head of the Kayano family, 正的 KAYANO, a husband of Denzaemon&apos;s elder sister, was recorded to be related with chaji (tea ceremony), so that he was regarded as a child of 重府.</e>
<cmt>正的→読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first head of the Kayano family, Masateki (正的) KAYANO, a husband of Denzaemon&apos;s older sister, was recorded to &apos;be related with chaji, tea ceremony,&apos; so that he was regarded as a child of Shigefu.</e>
<cmt>推定できる読みを補足し、表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first head of the Kayano family, Masateki (正的) KAYANO, a husband of Denzaemon&apos;s older sister, was recorded to &apos;be related with chaji, tea ceremony,&apos; so that he was regarded as a child of Shigefu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>古市家1世宗庵に師事して茶道役となり、茶道頭として200石を受けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">正的 studied under the first-generation head of the Furuichi family, Soan; he became a chabozu and received a fief yielding 200 koku in rice as a chadogashira.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masateki studied under the first head of the Furuichi family, Soan to become a sadoyaku and received a fief yielding 200 koku crop yield as a chadogashira.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masateki studied under the first head of the Furuichi family, Soan to become a sadoyaku and received a fief yielding 200 koku crop yield as a chadogashira.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>7世正房は維新の後に姓を古田に復して、以後門下の指導に当たっていたが、現在、古田家は指導を離れている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Meiji Restoration, Tadafusa, the seventh tea master, restored the family name to the original one, Furuta, and taught students of the school, but now the Furuta family stops teaching.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Meiji Restoration, Masafusa, the seventh head of the school, restored the family name to the original Furuta, and taught students of the school, but now the Furuta family doesn&apos;t teach the school.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Meiji Restoration, Masafusa, the seventh head of the school, restored the family name to the original Furuta, and taught students of the school, but now the Furuta family doesn&apos;t teach the school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>同門組織として松風会がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its fellow organization is Shohu-kai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its fellow organization is Shohu-kai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its fellow organization is Shohu-kai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Call Tenderas(id:169753), 耳順庵(id:160416), NS-690Ⅲ(id:143393), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), Mzaki(id:61977), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>