<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>楢柴肩衝</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Narashiba Katatsuki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Narashiba Katatsuki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Narashiba Katatsuki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>楢柴肩衝とは、新田肩衝・初花肩衝と共に天下三肩衝と呼ばれた茶器の1つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Narashiba Katatsuki is one of the three best Katatsuki type tea canisters, among Nitta Katatsuki and Hatsuhana Katatsuki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Narashiba Katatsuki is a tea canister which was called one of the three major Katatsuki, along with Nitta Katatsuki and Hatsuhana Katatsuki.</e>
<cmt>一部翻訳を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Narashiba Katatsuki is a tea canister which was called one of the three major Katatsuki, along with Nitta Katatsuki and Hatsuhana Katatsuki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>（肩衝とは、肩の部分が角ばっている茶入のこと）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Katatsuki is the type of tea canister whose shoulder part has a square shape)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Katatsuki is the type of a tea canister whose shoulder part has a square shape.)</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Katatsuki is the type of a tea canister whose shoulder part has a square shape.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>千利休の高弟・山上宗二が天下一品の壷と絶賛したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Souji YAMANOUE, the leading disciple of SEN no Rikyu, extolled this tea canister as unrivalled by any others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soji YAMANOUE, the leading disciple of SEN no Rikyu, extolled this tea canister as unrivalled by any others.</e>
<cmt>人名のスペルを一部変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soji YAMANOUE, the leading disciple of SEN no Rikyu, extolled this tea canister as unrivalled by any others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>釉色が濃いアメ色で、これを 「恋」 にかけて万葉集の「御狩する狩場の小野の楢柴の汝はまさらで恋ぞまされる」の歌に因みこの名になったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name of this tea canister is said to be derived from the play on word with &quot;koi&quot; meaning both &quot;deep&quot; and &quot;love,&quot; &lt;double enténdre/pun&gt; while the color of the glaze of this tea canister is in a unique &quot;Koi&quot; amber, (meaning deep amber) and a Tanka (Japanese short poem) from Manyoshu (the oldest existing collection of Japanese poetry) includes the word &quot;Koi&quot; in its phrase, &quot;Mikarisuru Karihano Onono &quot;Narashiba&quot; no Nareha masarade &quot;Koi&quot; (meaning love) zo masareru&quot;then the word &quot;Narashiba&quot; was taken from this Tanka for the name of this tea canister.</e>
<cmt>非常に説明が難しい文章です。分割することもできないようです。なお、「御狩する狩場の小野の楢柴の汝はまさで恋ぞまされる」は、「御狩する狩場の小野の楢柴の汝はまさらで恋ぞまされる」が正しいようです。「ら」がないと5-7-5-7-7になりませんし韻が踏まれません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name of this tea canister is said to be derived from the play on word with &apos;koi&apos; meaning both &apos;deep&apos; and &apos;love,&apos; (double entente/pun) while the color of the glaze of this tea canister is in a unique &apos;koi&apos; amber (meaning deep amber); a tanka (thirty-one syllables&apos; poem) from Manyoshu (Collection of Ten Thousand Leaves) includes the word &apos;koi&apos; in its phrase, &apos;Mikarisuru Karihano Onono Narashiba no Nareha masarade Koi zo masareru,&apos; then the word &apos;Narashiba&apos; was taken from this tanka for the name of this tea canister.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。一部翻訳を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name of this tea canister is said to be derived from the play on word with &apos;koi&apos; meaning both &apos;deep&apos; and &apos;love,&apos; (double entente/pun) while the color of the glaze of this tea canister is in a unique &apos;koi&apos; amber (meaning deep amber); a tanka (thirty-one syllables&apos; poem) from Manyoshu (Collection of Ten Thousand Leaves) includes the word &apos;koi&apos; in its phrase, &apos;Mikarisuru Karihano Onono Narashiba no Nareha masarade Koi zo masareru,&apos; then the word &apos;Narashiba&apos; was taken from this tanka for the name of this tea canister.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="5">
<j>もともとは足利義政の所有物であったが、彼の死後は持ち主を転々とし、堺の商人を通じて、博多の島井宗室へ渡った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally this tea canister was owned by the 8th Shogun of the Muromachi Shogunate, Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA, but the tea canister was passed through many hands after his death, and later it was handed over to a tea master Soushitsu SHIMAI living in Hakata, Kyushu, by a merchant in Sakai, Osaka.</e>
<cmt>「足利義政」を「室町幕府8代将軍足利義政」としました。また地名が都市名しか記されていないため一応地域名までは加えました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally this tea canister was owned by the eighth shogun of the Muromachi Shogunate, Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA, but it was passed through many hands after his death, and later handed over to a tea master Soshitsu SHIMAI living in Hakata, Kyushu, by a merchant in Sakai, Osaka.</e>
<cmt>人名のスペルを一部変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally this tea canister was owned by the eighth shogun of the Muromachi Shogunate, Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA, but it was passed through many hands after his death, and later handed over to a tea master Soshitsu SHIMAI living in Hakata, Kyushu, by a merchant in Sakai, Osaka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>織田信長も、この名物を欲しがり、上洛するように宗室へ命じたが、本能寺の変で死亡。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobunaga ODA also wanted to acquire this famous piece and gave Soshitsu the order to bring it to Kyoto, although Nobunaga died in the Incident at Honno-ji Temple before acquiring it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobunaga ODA also wanted to acquire this famous piece and gave Soshitsu the order to bring it to Kyoto, although Nobunaga died in the Honnoji Incident before acquiring it.</e>
<cmt>本能寺の変　表現を統一しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobunaga ODA also wanted to acquire this famous piece and gave Soshitsu the order to bring it to Kyoto, although Nobunaga died in the Honnoji Incident before acquiring it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="7">
<j>その後は、大友宗麟から大金を出すので譲って欲しいと再三要請があったが、宗室はこれを断り続けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After this incident, Sorin OTOMO repeatedly requested Soshitsu to hand over the tea canister at any cost, although Soshitsu kept refusing the requests.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After this incident, Sorin OTOMO repeatedly requested Soshitsu to hand over the tea canister at any cost, although Soshitsu kept refusing the requests.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After this incident, Sorin OTOMO repeatedly requested Soshitsu to hand over the tea canister at any cost, although Soshitsu kept refusing the requests.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>のち、大友氏の衰退と逆に博多のある筑前国で勢力を伸ばしてきた秋月種実が、この名物を欲した為、譲る事となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The power of OTOMO family soon declined, and Tanezane AKIZUKI took over the Chikuzen Province; (where Hakata is located) Soshitsu decided to hand over this tea canister when Tanezane requested the piece.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The power of OTOMO family later declined; in the meantime Tanezane AKIZUKI gradually gained power in the Chikuzen Province (where Hakata is located), and Soshitsu decided to hand over this tea canister when Tanezane requested the piece.</e>
<cmt>一部翻訳を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The power of OTOMO family later declined; in the meantime Tanezane AKIZUKI gradually gained power in the Chikuzen Province (where Hakata is located), and Soshitsu decided to hand over this tea canister when Tanezane requested the piece.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>この際、秋月氏から大豆百俵が送られているが、楢柴の価値は約3000貫、現在の価値でいえば数億円以上ともされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Tanezane sent 100 bales of soybeans to Soshitsu, the price of the Narashiba was said to be about 3,000 Kan, which is about several million Yen in today&apos;s value.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Tanezane sent 100 bales of soybeans to Soshitsu, the price of the Narashiba was said to be about 3,000 Kan, which is about several million Yen in today&apos;s value.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Tanezane sent 100 bales of soybeans to Soshitsu, the price of the Narashiba was said to be about 3,000 Kan, which is about several million Yen in today&apos;s value.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>宗室ら博多商人が武力行使をちらつかせられ、半ば脅迫に近い形で奪われたのは歴然としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore it is obvious that Soshitsu and other merchants of Hakata was threatened and deprived of the tea canister by the armed force of Tanezane.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore it is obvious that Soshitsu and other merchants of Hakata were half-threatened and deprived of the tea canister by the armed force of Tanezane.</e>
<cmt>was→ were としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore it is obvious that Soshitsu and other merchants of Hakata were half-threatened and deprived of the tea canister by the armed force of Tanezane.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>しかし、種実が手にしていた期間も長くは無く、九州征伐の際、島津氏に属していた秋月氏から、降伏の証として、豊臣秀吉へと献上された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the period of Tanezane owning this famous piece was not very long, and this popular piece was given to Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI as the proofing gift of surrender, when Hideyoshi conquered Kyushu region and Shimazu clan and its vassal Akizuki clan surrendered to him.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the period of Tanezane owning this famous piece was not very long; it was presented to Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI as the proofing gift of surrender from Tanezane who was a vassal of Shimazu clan, when Hideyoshi conquered Kyushu region.</e>
<cmt>一部翻訳を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the period of Tanezane owning this famous piece was not very long; it was presented to Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI as the proofing gift of surrender from Tanezane who was a vassal of Shimazu clan, when Hideyoshi conquered Kyushu region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>天下三肩衝は全て秀吉の物となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Finally, all three best Katatsuki became the property of Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Finally, all three best Katatsuki became the property of Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Finally, all three best Katatsuki became the property of Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>後に秀吉臨終の際に、徳川家康に授けられ徳川将軍家の所有となったが、明暦3年（1657年）の明暦の大火で消失してしまったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the deathbed, Hideyoshi handed over the Narashiba to Ieyasu TOKUGAWA and became the property of Tokugawa Shogunate family; however, this piece disappeared or destroyed by the Meireki no Taika (the great fire of Meireki) in 1657.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that, at the deathbed of Hideyoshi, the piece was handed over to Ieyasu TOKUGAWA and became the property of Tokugawa Shogunate family, but disappeared or destroyed by the Great Fire in Meireki in 1657.</e>
<cmt>一部翻訳を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that, at the deathbed of Hideyoshi, the piece was handed over to Ieyasu TOKUGAWA and became the property of Tokugawa Shogunate family, but disappeared or destroyed by the Great Fire in Meireki in 1657.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 ポテンシャル0(id:160803), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>