<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>半片</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hanpen (a white, square shaped fish paste)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hanpen (a white, square shaped fish paste)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hanpen (a white, square shaped fish paste)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>半片（はんぺん、半平）は、タラスケトウダラなどの魚肉のすり身にすりおろしたヤマノイモを混ぜてよく摺り、調味して薄く四角形または半月型にしてゆでた魚肉練り製品。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hanpen is kneated fish cake made by fish such as suketo cod (Alaska Pollock, or Theragra chalcogramma mixed with grated yam with seasonings, which is then made into thin square or half moon shape and boiled.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hanpen is kneaded fish cake made of fish such as suketo cod (Alaska Pollock) mixed with grated yam with seasonings, which is then made into thin squares or half moon shapes and boiled.</e>
<cmt>spelling; prepositions; punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hanpen is kneaded fish cake made of fish such as suketo cod (Alaska Pollock) mixed with grated yam with seasonings, which is then made into thin squares or half moon shapes and boiled.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>ヨシキリザメ、アオザメ、オナガザメなどのサメ類やカジキなどが使われることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Often shprk such as yoshikiri-zame shark (blue shark, or Prionace glauca), ao-zame shark (Shortfin mako shark, or surus oxyrinchus), onaga-zame shark (Thresher shark) or Billfish are used for Hanpen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Often shark such as yoshikiri-zame (blue shark), ao-zame (Shortfin mako shark), onaga-zame (Thresher shark) or Billfish are used for Hanpen.</e>
<cmt>spelling; shortened a bit</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Often shark such as yoshikiri-zame (blue shark), ao-zame (Shortfin mako shark), onaga-zame (Thresher shark) or Billfish are used for Hanpen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>しかし、現在では新鮮なものが入手しにくいなどの問題から、サメなどを原料とするのは極上品とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However hanpen made by sharke is considered as the best quality since it is hard to obtain fresh sharke in nowadays.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, hanpen made from shark is considered the best quality since it is hard to obtain fresh shark nowadays.</e>
<cmt>prepositions; spelling; punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, hanpen made from shark is considered the best quality since it is hard to obtain fresh shark nowadays.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>ふんわりとした滑らかな舌触りで、煮汁を良く吸い込む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has soft smooth texture and it obsorb the sauce (when it is cooked with the sauce) very well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has soft smooth texture and it absorbs sauce very well.</e>
<cmt>spelling; removed an unnecessary aside</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has soft smooth texture and it absorbs sauce very well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>煮物、揚げ物、フライ、バター焼き、おでんだね、椀だねなどに用いられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is used for stew, deep fly, grilled dish with butter, ingrediants for oden (a Japanese dish containing all kinds of ingredients cooked in a special broth of soy sauce, sugar, sake, etc.) or cooked with soup.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is used for stew, deep fry, grilled dish with butter, ingredients for oden (a Japanese dish containing all kinds of ingredients cooked in a special broth of soy sauce, sugar, sake, etc.) or cooked with soup.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is used for stew, deep fry, grilled dish with butter, ingredients for oden (a Japanese dish containing all kinds of ingredients cooked in a special broth of soy sauce, sugar, sake, etc.) or cooked with soup.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>作り方</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">How to cook Hanpen</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">How to cook Hanpen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">How to cook Hanpen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>標準的な作り方としては、すり身400g、ヤマノイモ100g、塩小さじ1、昆布だしをよく摺り混ぜ、平らに整形し、約10分ゆでる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Popular cooking method is to mix 400g fish paste, 100g yam, one teaspoon of salt, kobu seaweed stock all together, then make the mixture into flat shape, then boil it for ten minutes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A popular cooking method is to mix 400g fish paste, 100g yam, one teaspoon of salt and kobu seaweed stock all together, make the mixture into a flat shape, then boil it for ten minutes.</e>
<cmt>articles, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A popular cooking method is to mix 400g fish paste, 100g yam, one teaspoon of salt and kobu seaweed stock all together, make the mixture into a flat shape, then boil it for ten minutes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>名前の由来</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The origin of the name</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The origin of the name</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The origin of the name</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>名前の由来には、江戸時代の駿河国の料理人・半平（はんぺい）が創案したところからこの名がついた、また椀蓋で半月型に整形したことから名がついたなどの多くの説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name came from a person who first made hanpen, who was the sheff in Suruga Province named Hanpei, or there is another theory that it was called Hanpen since it was shaped into half moon shape with the top of Japanese soup bowl.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name came from the person who first made hanpen, who was a chef in Suruga Province named Hanpei, or there is another theory that it was called Hanpen since it was shaped into half moon shape with the top of Japanese soup bowl.</e>
<cmt>articles, spelling, etc</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name came from the person who first made hanpen, who was a chef in Suruga Province named Hanpei, or there is another theory that it was called Hanpen since it was shaped into half moon shape with the top of Japanese soup bowl.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>元々は関東周辺のみで食されていた地域色の強い食品であったが、戦後になって東京の紀文食品が「紀文のはんぺん」として全国的に販売するようになって以降は、この白いはんぺんが「はんぺん」として定着した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was originally eaten only in Kanto and other surrounding area and had strong local influence, however after Kibun Food Inc of Tokyo started selling it as &apos;Kibun&apos;s Hanpen&apos; to all other areas in Japan, this white Hanpen became well known as Hanpen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was originally eaten only in Kanto and other surrounding area and had strong local influence, however after Kibun Food Inc of Tokyo started selling it as &apos;Kibun&apos;s Hanpen&apos; to all other areas in Japan, this white Hanpen became well known as Hanpen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was originally eaten only in Kanto and other surrounding area and had strong local influence, however after Kibun Food Inc of Tokyo started selling it as &apos;Kibun&apos;s Hanpen&apos; to all other areas in Japan, this white Hanpen became well known as Hanpen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>静岡県では、イワシなどを丸ごと用いて作った青灰色のいわゆる黒はんぺんを「はんぺん」と呼び、上記の白いはんぺんは「白はんぺん」と区別して呼称する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Shizuoka, Hanpen made by sardine or other fishes with blue gray color is called &apos;black Hanpen&apos; and abovementioned white Hanpen is called &apos;white Hanpen&apos; to distinguish each others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Shizuoka, Hanpen made of sardines or other blue/gray colored fish is called &apos;black Hanpen&apos; and white Hanpen is called &apos;white Hanpen&apos; to distinguish them from each other.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Shizuoka, blue/gray colored Hanpen, commonly called &apos;black Hanpen,&apos; made of sardines or other fish is recognized as &apos;Hanpen&apos; and white Hanpen is called &apos;white Hanpen&apos; to distinguish them from each other.</e>
<cmt>原文に沿うように書き換えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>上記の「はんぺん」の名の由来、駿河の国起源説にせよ、半月型が由来説にせよ、この黒はんぺんを連想させる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The origin of abovementioned &apos;Hanpen&apos; remind us of this black Hanpen, whether the origin of the name is from theory of Suruga Province or the other theory of half moon shape.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The origin of &apos;Hanpen&apos; reminds us of this black Hanpen, whether the origin of the name is from Suruga Province or from the half moon shape.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The origin of &apos;Hanpen&apos; reminds us of this black Hanpen, whether the origin of the name is from Suruga Province or from the half moon shape.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>愛知県、広島県などでは、魚の練り物を揚げたものの総称として「はんぺん」と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Aich and Hiroshima Prefecture, deep fried fish paste is called &apos;Hanpen&apos; in general.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Aichi and Hiroshima Prefectures, deep fried fish paste in general is called &apos;Hanpen&apos;.</e>
<cmt>typo, word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Aichi and Hiroshima Prefectures, deep fried fish paste in general is called &apos;Hanpen.&apos;</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>これを、いわゆる薩摩揚げと同じだと他の地方の人が誤解することが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is often misunderstood with what it is called Satsuma-age (fried fish cake) by people from other prefectures.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is often confused with what it is called Satsuma-age (fried fish cake) by people from other prefectures.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is often confused with what it is called Satsuma-age (fried fish cake) by people from other prefectures.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>上記の白いはんぺんは「紀文のはんぺん」などとメーカー名などをつけて区別する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The abovementioned white Hanpen is distinguish wigh others by calling &apos;Kibun&apos;s Hanpen.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The aforementioned white Hanpen is called &apos;Kibun&apos;s Hanpen&apos; to distinguish it from the others.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The aforementioned white Hanpen is called &apos;Kibun&apos;s Hanpen&apos; to distinguish it from the others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>尚、「はんぺん」の大量生産化を最初に可能にしたのは、株式会社紀文食品であり、特許期限が失効されるまでは、今日のように多くのメーカーから販売されることはなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By the way, Kibun Food Co., Ltd Inc was the first company to make bulk produciton of &apos;Hanpen&apos; possibble, no other company was selling Hanpen until the sale of Hanpen of Kibun Food became off-patent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On a related note, Kibun Food Co., Ltd Inc was the first company to make bulk production of &apos;Hanpen&apos; possible, and no other company was selling Hanpen until Kibun Food&apos;s patent expired.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On a related note, Kibun Food Co., Ltd Inc was the first company to make bulk production of &apos;Hanpen&apos; possible, and no other company was selling Hanpen until Kibun Food&apos;s patent expired.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>関西地方にはあんぺいと呼ばれるハモなど白身魚のすり身から作った魚肉練り製品が存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kansai area, there is kneated fish paste product exist which was made by white fish paste such as conger pike, and it is called Anpei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Kansai area, there is a kneaded fish paste product made of white fish such as conger pike, and it is called Anpei.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Kansai area, there is a kneaded fish paste product made of white fish such as conger pike, and it is called Anpei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>語感や外見が似ているためによく混同されるが、こちらはむしろしんじょうに近い蒸しかまぼこの一種である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since it looks similer outside to Hanpen, it is often minunderstood with Hanpen, but this is rather close type to shinjo (a kind of kamaboko, steamed white fish cake, mixed with yam) and is a type of steamed Kamaboko (steamed kamaboko).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since it looks similar, it is often confused with Hanpen, but this is rather close to shinjo (a kind of kamaboko, steamed white fish cake, mixed with yam) and is a type of steamed Kamaboko.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since it looks similar, it is often confused with Hanpen, but this is rather close to shinjo (a kind of kamaboko, steamed white fish cake, mixed with yam) and is a type of steamed Kamaboko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="17">
<j>漢字では「半片」か「半平」と書くが、「半弁」「鱧餅」などとあてられることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kanji caractor Hanpen is written 半片,半平, or 半弁, 鱧餅.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Kanji characters Hanpen is written 半片, 半平, 半弁, or 鱧餅.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Kanji characters Hanpen is written 半片, 半平, 半弁, or 鱧餅.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Izayohi(id:13095), いろはにほへと(id:89648), REDSTONE(id:87473), Nighthawks(id:36125), Roger(id:9883), BitBucket(id:30999), 田島健太(id:173379), Revth(id:12179), Rusk(id:9895), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), 健ちゃん(id:60346), Tenmams(id:72762), Mochi(id:9489), ＮｉＫｅ(id:7512), 珊底(id:143081), Piros(id:20417), Somosan(id:258894), ★★★0102(id:36063), Corwin(id:973), 1029man(id:93235), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>