<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>露天商</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rotensho (stallholder)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rotensho (Stallholders)</e>
<cmt>Punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rotensho</e>
<cmt>以下説明が続くので、英語説明を削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>露天商（ろてんしょう）とは露天（屋外や青空の下）で店舗を持たず商売をする者。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Rotensho&quot; are people who do business in open-air (outside or under the sun), without a store.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Rotensho&quot; are people who do business outside or under the sun, and who have no store.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Rotensho&quot; (露天商) are people who do business outside or under the sun, and who have no store.</e>
<cmt>(露天商)補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>露店商とも表記し、街商（がいしょう）ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also written as 露店商, and is referred to as gaisho (stallholder).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also written as 露店商, and is referred to as gaisho (street stallholder).</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also written as 露店商, and is referred to as gaisho (street stallholder).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>日本</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>露天商と言われるもの</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those called rotensho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Groups referred to as rotensho</e>
<cmt>Rewritten.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Groups referred to as rotensho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>的屋</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tekiya (peddlers)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tekiya (peddlers)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tekiya (peddlers)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>- 的屋とは基本的には祭礼や縁日や時節や年中行事で、寺社の参道や境内または門前町を主に、人出が見込まれる場所を渡り歩き商売をする、日本古来の伝統的な生業を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tekiya is basically a traditional ancient Japanese regular vocation in which one travels for business in locations where turnout is expected, mainly around the sando (an approach to the temple) or precincts of temples and shrines, for rites and festivals, fairs, annual events, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tekiya is basically a traditional ancient Japanese vocation in which one travels looking for business in locations where a large number of people are expected, mainly around the sando (an approach to the temple) or precincts of temples and shrines, for rites and festivals, fairs, and annual events.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tekiya is basically a traditional ancient Japanese vocation in which one travels looking for business in locations where a large number of people are expected, mainly around the sando (an approach to the temple) or precincts of temples and shrines, for rites and festivals, fairs, and annual events.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>商売の手段としては、地面に引いた敷物のうえに商品を並べる簡易なものから、仮設建築としての見世物小屋を集団組織で営むものまで様々である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Their business methods vary from simple ones placing products on a mat on the ground to show tents built as temporary buildings operated by organizations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their business methods vary from simple ones where products are placed on a mat on the ground to show tents built as temporary buildings operated by organizations.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Their business methods vary from simple ones where products are placed on a mat on the ground to show tents built as temporary buildings operated by organizations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>詳しくは的屋を参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Refer to tekiya for details.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Refer to tekiya for details.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Refer to tekiya for details.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>屋台</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yatai (street stall)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yatai (street stalls)</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yatai (street stalls)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>- 屋台とは商売の方法ではなく、簡易の屋根と売り台を持って商売をする形態であり、的屋などもこの形態を用いる者もあるが、一般的には日本各地に見られる屋台街といわれる屋台の飲食店などを指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yatai is not a method of business, but a form of business using a simple roof and counter, and while some tekiya take this form, it generally refers to yatai restaurants called yatai-gai seen all over Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yatai is not a method of business, but the use of a simple roof and counter, and while some tekiya conduct business in this way the word generally refers to yatai restaurants called yatai-gai seen all over Japan.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yatai is not a method of business, but the use of a simple roof and counter, and while some tekiya conduct business in this way the word generally refers to yatai restaurants called yatai-gai seen all over Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>物売り（引き売り）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Monouri (peddling) or hikiuri</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Monouri (peddling) or hikiuri</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Monouri (peddling) or hikiuri</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>- 物売りとは最近ではあまり見られなくなったが、独特の「呼び声」や「鳴り物」を使い町を練り歩きながら商売をする者を指し、大八車や自転車に積んだ商品を引いていたので引き売りとも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Monouri, which is not seen often today, are people who do business using unique &apos;yobigoe&apos; (call) and &apos;musical instrument&apos; while walking through town, and since they used to pull along products stacked on large carts and bicycles, they were also called hikiuri.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Monouri, not often seen today, are people who do business with a unique &apos;yobigoe&apos; (call) and a musical instrument while walking through town, and since they used to pull along products stacked on large carts and bicycles, they were also called hikiuri.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Monouri, not often seen today, are people who do business with a unique &apos;yobigoe&apos; (call) and a musical instrument while walking through town, and since they used to pull along products stacked on large carts and bicycles, they were also called hikiuri.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>行商</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gyosho (peddler)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gyosho (peddlers)</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gyosho (peddlers)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>- 行商とは一般的には固定客への訪問販売によって商売をする者を指すが、郊外や商圏の規模の小さい所では物売りであっても、固定客が主な客層である場合もあり、特に豆腐や納豆や野菜や魚の物売りなどがこの傾向にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gyosho generally refers to those who do business by door-to-door sales with regular customers, but in suburbs or areas with small trade-area, monouri&apos;s main customers may also be regular customers, and tofu, natto (fermented soybeans), vegetable, and fish monouri tend to fall under this category.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gyosho generally refers to those who do business through door-to-door sales with regular customers, but in suburbs or areas with a small trade-area, the main customers of monouri may also be regular customers, and tofu, natto (fermented soybeans), vegetables, and fish monouri tend to fall under this category.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gyosho generally refers to those who do business through door-to-door sales with regular customers, but in suburbs or areas with a small trade-area, the main customers of monouri may also be regular customers, and tofu, natto (fermented soybeans), vegetables, and fish monouri tend to fall under this category.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="15">
<j>日本</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>古くは市（朝市、定期市）や縁日などで時節の縁起物を売っていた蓮の葉商いや、その目抜き通りで大道芸などを行っていた手品師、太神楽とも言われる曲芸師や曲独楽師などが、現在の的屋の源流ともいわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is told that today&apos;s tekiya dates back to traders of lotus leaves (dealing with seasonal goods) who sold lucky charms of the season at markets (morning market, periodical market) and fairs, magicians performing street performances on the main streets, and acrobatic artists also known as Daikagura (lion dance) and kyokugomashi (spinning trick performer).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that today&apos;s tekiya date back to traders of lotus leaves (dealing with seasonal goods) who sold lucky charms of the season at markets (morning markets and seasonal markets) and fairs, magicians performing street performances on the main streets, and acrobatic artists also known as daikagura (lion dancer) and kyokugomashi (spinning trick performers).</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that today&apos;s tekiya date back to traders of lotus leaves (dealing with seasonal goods) who sold lucky charms of the season at markets (morning markets and seasonal markets) and fairs, magicians performing street performances on the main streets, and acrobatic artists also known as daikagura (lion dancer) and kyokugomashi (spinning trick performers).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>江戸時代に生活困窮者の救済を目的とした棒手売（棒手振）などの物売り、または江戸時代から盛んになった飲食を中心とした屋台（屋根、売り台はもちろん簡易な厨房設備や客の椅子まで備えていた）などが、起源といわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its origin is known to be the peddlers such as botefuri (pedlars) who helped the poor in Edo period, or the yatai (it had a roof, counter, as well as a simple kitchen and chairs for customers) mainly for eating and drinking which became popular from the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The origin is known to be the pedlars such as botefuri who helped the poor in the Edo Period, or the yatai (having a roof and counter, as well as a simple kitchen and chairs for customers) mainly for eating and drinking which became popular from the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, spelling, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The origin is known to be the peddlers such as botefuri who helped the poor in the Edo period, or the yatai (having a roof and counter, as well as a simple kitchen and chairs for customers) mainly for eating and drinking which became popular from the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>用語統一スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="18">
<j>現在でも観光地などでのアイスクリーム売りやパンの移動販売、郊外から都心へ通う行商人（関東圏では千葉の行商人が良く知られる存在である）公園付近で定置で営業するおでんの屋台、祭りや縁日の的屋業などは地方、都心に限らず健在な地域も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even today, ice cream sellers, mobile bakeries, peddlers coming to the inner-city from suburbs (in the Kanto area, peddlers from Chiba are well-known), oden (a Japanese dish containing all kinds of ingredients cooked in a special broth of soy sauce, sugar, sake, etc.) yatai doing business in a fixed location near parks, and tekiya at festivals and fairs remain common not only in inner-cities, but in various regions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even today, ice cream sellers, mobile bakeries, peddlers coming into the city from the suburbs (in the Kanto area, peddlers from Chiba are well-known), oden (a Japanese dish containing all kinds of ingredients cooked in a special broth of soy sauce, sugar, and sake) yatai doing business in a fixed location near parks, and tekiya at festivals and fairs remain common not only in inner-cities, but in various regions.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even today, ice cream sellers, mobile bakeries, peddlers coming into the city from the suburbs (in the Kanto area, peddlers from Chiba are well-known), oden (a Japanese dish containing all kinds of ingredients cooked in a special broth of soy sauce, sugar, and sake) yatai doing business in a fixed location near parks, and tekiya at festivals and fairs remain common not only in inner-cities, but in various regions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="19">
<j>新たな露天商としては、商店街や外食産業の無いビジネス街などで、改造した車両を用いて、屋台形式で商売する者もいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a new type of rotensho, some do business in a yatai style using altered vehicles in business districts where shopping areas or food service industry do not exist.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a new type of rotensho, some people do business in the yatai style using converted vehicles in business districts where shopping areas or the food service industry do not exist.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a new type of rotensho, some people do business in the yatai style using converted vehicles in business districts where shopping areas or the food service industry do not exist.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>また自治体などで主催する蚤の市やフリーマーケットと呼ばれる蚤の市のような場所で、ベンチャービジネスや趣味と実益を兼ねた一般人が露店商を営むものも多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, many ordinary people do rotensho business as venture or as both hobby and for profit in places such as the flea market hosted by municipalities.</e>
<cmt>蚤の市とフリーマーケットはいずれもflea marketなので「フリーマーケットと呼ばれる蚤の市」は省略しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, many ordinary people have a rotensho business as a venture or for both a hobby and for profit in places such as flea markets hosted by municipal organisations.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, many ordinary people have a rotensho business as a venture or for both a hobby and for profit in places such as flea markets hosted by municipal organizations.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>代表的な露天商</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Leading rotensho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Leading rotensho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Leading rotensho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="21">
<j>日本</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>ここでは、的屋や屋台や物売りや行商には含まれないものを挙げる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Here, only those not categorized as tekiya, yatai, monouri, gyosho are listed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Here, only those not categorized as tekiya, yatai, monouri or gyosho are listed.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Here, only those not categorized as tekiya, yatai, monouri or gyosho are listed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="23">
<j>靴磨き</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shoe polishing</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoe polishing</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoe polishing</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>- 靴磨きとは元々は欧米の革靴を履く習慣のある地域の職業であるが、明治維新の西欧化に伴い、日本でも職業として確立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shoe polishing is originally an occupation in Europe and the United States where leather shoes are worn, but with the Westernization during the Meiji Restoration, it developed as an occupation in Japan as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoe polishing is originally an occupation from Europe and the United States where leather shoes are worn, but with the Westernization which followed the Meiji Restoration, it developed as an occupation in Japan as well.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoe polishing is originally an occupation from Europe and the United States where leather shoes are worn, but with the Westernization which followed the Meiji Restoration, it developed as an occupation in Japan as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>第2次世界大戦後の復興時には、生活困窮者の生活の糧として日本各地で日常的に見られたが、近年ではほとんど見られることは無い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the restoration after Word War II, it was regularly seen all over Japan as a way the poor earned their bread and butter, but they are rarely seen in recent years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the economic restoration which followed World War II, it was regularly seen all over Japan as a way the poor earned their bread and butter, but they have become a rare sight in recent years.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the economic restoration which followed World War II, it was regularly seen all over Japan as a way the poor earned their bread and butter, but they have become a rare sight in recent years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="26">
<j>占い師</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fortune-teller</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fortune-tellers</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fortune-tellers</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>- 近年では店舗を持つものも多く見られるが、現在でも都心部では台一つで露天で商いする占い師の姿が見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many have outlets in recent years, but even today, there are fortune-tellers in the inner cities doing business in the open air with only a counter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many have bought their own shops in recent years, but even today, there are fortune-tellers in the centers of cities doing business in the open air with only a counter.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many have bought their own shops in recent years, but even today, there are fortune-tellers in the centers of cities doing business in the open air with only a counter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="28">
<j>砥ぎ屋</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Store to sharpen the blade etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Stores for sharpening blades.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Stores for sharpening blades.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>- 包丁や和裁や剃刀（和剃刀）または、大工なども研ぐ技術が拙い者（つたないもの）や高価な刃物などは砥ぎ師を利用した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Blade sharpeners were used for kitchen knives, pinking shears, razors, expensive knives, and even by carpenters who were not skiiled in sharpening.</e>
<cmt>原文には「和裁」とありますが、リンク先の単語のようです。ウェブで確認すると用語が「裁ちばさみ」となっており、本来はこちらの用語を使用していると思われますので、こちらを訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Blade sharpeners were used for kitchen knives, pinking shears, razors, expensive knives, and even by carpenters who were not skiiled in sharpening.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Blade sharpeners were used for kitchen knives, pinking shears, razors, expensive knives, and even by carpenters who were not skilled in sharpening.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>近年では金物屋が兼業で営むぐらいだが、和物（洋物の反対語）の刃物が世間一般で広く使われていた時代には、どの町でも人通りの多い商店街などでよく見られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In recent years, hardware stores simply do it as a side job, but in the days when Japanese (as opposed to Western) knives were commonly used, they were often seen in any town in busy shopping areas.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In recent years, hardware stores have taken it up as a side job, but in the days when Japanese (as opposed to Western) knives were commonly used, they were often seen in every town in busy shopping areas.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In recent years, hardware stores have taken it up as a side job, but in the days when Japanese (as opposed to Western) knives were commonly used, they were often seen in every town in busy shopping areas.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="31">
<j>天津甘栗の作り売り</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cooking and selling of tenshinamaguri (sweet broiled chestnut)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The cooking and selling of tenshinamaguri (sweet broiled chestnuts)</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The cooking and selling of tenshinamaguri (sweet broiled chestnuts)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>- 縁日で見かける例もあるが、駅前などで恒常的に商売するものをさす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some are seen at fairs, but it refers to those who constantly do business in front of stations, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some are seen at fairs, but it generally refers to those who constantly do business in front of stations, and in other busy areas.</e>
<cmt>Added for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some are seen at fairs, but it generally refers to those who constantly do business in front of stations, and in other busy areas.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>歌舞伎座の前の天津甘栗の露天商などが代表的な例である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The tenshinamaguri rotensho in front of the Kabuki-za Theater is a major example.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The tenshinamaguri rotensho in front of the Kabuki-za Theater is a famous example.</e>
<cmt>Word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The tenshinamaguri rotensho in front of the Kabuki-za Theater is a famous example.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="34">
<j>日本以外</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Outside Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Outside Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Outside Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>飲食店や大道芸以外の露天商を記載する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rotensho other than restaurants and street performances are listed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rotensho other than restaurants and street performances are listed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rotensho other than restaurants and street performances are listed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>飲食店の露天商は屋台を参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Refer to Yatai for restaurant rotensho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Refer to Yatai for restaurant rotensho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Refer to Yatai for restaurant rotensho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>大道芸の露天商は大道芸を参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Refer to Street performance for street peformance rotensho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Refer to Street Performance for street peformance rotensho.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Refer to Street Performance for street performance rotensho.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>また日本の露天商には無いものを主に記載する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, mainly the ones not seen as rotensho in Japan are listed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, rotensho which cannot be seen in Japan are often listed.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, rotensho which cannot be seen in Japan are often listed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="39">
<j>ボディーケア</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Body-care</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Body-care</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Body-care</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>身体測定</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Body measurement</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Body measuring</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Body measuring</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>- 欧米の遊園地や祭りで見られる有料の体重計が、インドや東南アジアを中心に広まり、個人で路上などにおいて定置や移動方式で商売している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The paid scales seen at amusement parks and festivals in Europe and the United States spread mainly to India and Southeast Asia, and have become a business done by individuals at fixed locations on the street or in mobile methods.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The coin-run scales seen at amusement parks and festivals in Europe and the United States spread mainly to India and Southeast Asia, and have become a business done by individuals at fixed locations on the street or in a mobile capacity.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The coin-run scales seen at amusement parks and festivals in Europe and the United States spread mainly to India and Southeast Asia, and have become a business done by individuals at fixed locations on the street or in a mobile capacity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>近年では同時に身長も計測でき、軽量で移動に適した機械が普及し、中国大陸などでも移動身体測定の商売人が見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In recent years, machines which can simultaneously measure the height, and are lighter for better portability became common, and sales people for mobile body measurement are seen even in the Chinese continent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In recent years, machines which can simultaneously also measure height, and are lighter for better portability have become common, and it has become possible to see sales people for mobile body measuring even on the Chinese continent.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In recent years, machines which can simultaneously also measure height, and are lighter for better portability have become common, and it has become possible to see sales people for mobile body measuring even on the Chinese continent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="43">
<j>血圧測定</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Blood-pressure check</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Blood-pressure checks</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Blood-pressure checks</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>- 中南米の休日の公園などでよく見られ、大抵は正式な資格を持った看護士が副収入として行っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Commonly seen at parks on weekends in South and Central America, and are often performed by nurses with formal qualification for additional income.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These are commonly seen in parks at weekends in South and Central America, and are often performed by nurses with formal qualification for additional income.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These are commonly seen in parks at weekends in South and Central America, and are often performed by nurses with formal qualification for additional income.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="45">
<j>床屋</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Barber</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Barbers</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Barbers</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>- 発展途上国の公園や路上で良く見られ、屋外で営業する床屋がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Commonly seen at parks or streets in developing countries, and there are barbers doing business outdoors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These are commonly seen in parks or on streets in developing countries, and some barbers do business outdoors.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These are commonly seen in parks or on streets in developing countries, and some barbers do business outdoors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>基本的には散髪だけだが、まれに貯水器などを利用して髭剃りや洗髪まで行う床屋もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They basically only do haircuts, but occasionally, there are barbers using water tanks, etc. to shave and shampoo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They basically only do haircuts, but occasionally there are barbers who use such things as water tanks, to shave and shampoo.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They basically only do haircuts, but occasionally there are barbers who use such things as water tanks, to shave and shampoo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="48">
<j>産毛取り</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Removing soft, downy hair</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Removing soft, downy hair</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Removing soft, downy hair</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>- 上記の床屋が兼任する場合もあるが、水が無い、または貴重であるというなどの理由から、産毛を2本の糸を紙縒る（こよる）ことによって、毛を巻き込み引き抜く方法や、アルコールなどを燃やして産毛を焼くといった方法で行う商売がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is sometimes performed concurrently by barbers described above, but because of lack of water or water is precious, there are businesses where the soft hair is removed by twisting two strings to entangle and pull off the hair, or burn alcohol to burn the soft hair, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is sometimes performed at the same time by the barbers described above, but because of the lack of water or as water is precious, there are businesses where the soft hair is removed by twisting two strings to twist and pull off the hair, or alcohol is used to burn the soft hair.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is sometimes performed at the same time by the barbers described above, but because of the lack of water or as water is precious, there are businesses where the soft hair is removed by twisting two strings to twist and pull off the hair, or alcohol is used to burn the soft hair.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="50">
<j>マッサージ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Massage</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Massage</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Massage</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>- 中華文明圏の国で見られるが、基本的は客を椅子に座らせて行うので上半身中心に行う事が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seen in areas with Chinese civilization, and is basically performed mainly on the upper body because the customer is seated on a chair.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seen in areas within the sphere of Chinese civilization, it is basically performed mainly on the upper body because the customer is seated in a chair.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seen in areas within the sphere of Chinese civilization, it is basically performed mainly on the upper body because the customer is seated in a chair.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>また東南アジアのビーチリゾートでは海水浴客が裸で寝そべっているので、タオルとオイルを持って全身マッサージを勧めるといった手軽な商売でもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, in beach resorts in Southeast Asia, beachgoers lay naked, so it is a simple business offering massage of the entire body with towel and oil.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, in beach resorts in Southeast Asia, some beachgoers lay almost naked, so it is a simple business offering a full-body massage using a towel and oil.</e>
<cmt>This has been altered to &apos;almost naked&apos; as I imagine this is referring to the majority of resorts where the customers are wearing beachwear.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, in beach resorts in Southeast Asia, some beachgoers lay almost naked, so it is a simple business offering a full-body massage using a towel and oil.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="53">
<j>ネイルケア</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nail care</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nail care</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nail care</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>上記のマッサージ師が兼任している場合が多く,当然別料金である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Often performed by the massager described above, naturally, for extra charge.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Often performed by the masseur described above, naturally for an extra charge.</e>
<cmt>Spelling, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Often performed by the masseur described above, naturally for an extra charge.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="55">
<j>ギャンブル</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gamble</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gambling</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gambling</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>カップアンドボール</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cup and ball</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cup and ball</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cup and ball</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>- 手品の起源と言われる賭け事、3つのカップと一つのボールを操り、一つのカップにボールを忍ばせる、客はどのカップに入っているかを当てると言うゲーム。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gambling known to be the origin of magic, played with three cups and one ball, hiding the ball under one cup, and the customer tries to guess which cup it is in.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A form of gambling known to be the origin of magic, played with three cups and one ball, hiding the ball under one cup, and the customer tries to guess which cup it is under.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A form of gambling known to be the origin of magic, played with three cups and one ball, hiding the ball under one cup, and the customer tries to guess which cup it is under.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="58">
<j>ポーカーゲーム</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Poker game</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Poker games.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Poker games</e>
<cmt>ピリオド削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>- 路上や公園で行われる賭けポーカーゲーム。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A poker game gambling played on streets or at parks.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Poker games played on the streets or in parks.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Poker games played on the streets or in parks.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="60">
<j>チェス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chess</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chess</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chess</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>- 路上や公園で行われる賭けチェス。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chess gambling played on streets or at parks.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chess for money, played on the streets or in parks.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chess for money, played on the streets or in parks.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="62">
<j>小売</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Retail</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Retail</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Retail</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>ガソリン販売</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gasoline sales</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gasoline sales</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gasoline sales</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>- 特にタンクの容量が少ないオートバイを主な移動手段としている国で見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is seen especially in countries where motorcycles with smaller tank capacities are the main means of transportation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is seen especially in countries where motorcycles with smaller tank capacities are the main means of transportation.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is seen especially in countries where motorcycles with smaller tank capacities are the main means of transportation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>ペットボトルなどに小分けにして道端でガソリンを売っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They sell small portions of gasoline in plastic bottles on the roadside.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They sell small amounts of gasoline in plastic bottles at the roadside.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They sell small amounts of gasoline in plastic bottles at the roadside.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="66">
<j>花売り</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Flower vendor</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Flower selling</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Flower selling</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>- 歴史的に非常に古い職業でもあり、物語りや文学作品などで題材や人物設定として表現される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is historically a very old occupation, used in stories and literature as themes or character setting.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is historically a very old occupation, appearing in stories and literature as a theme or character setting.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is historically a very old occupation, appearing in stories and literature as a theme or character setting.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>現在は発展途上国で児童労働の代表的な職業として知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is known today as the leading occupation for child labor in developing countries.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is known today as a leading occupation for child labor in developing countries.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is known today as a leading occupation for child labor in developing countries.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="69">
<j>タバコ売り</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tabacco vendor</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cigarette selling</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cigarette selling</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>- 荷台や本棚のようなものに綺麗に商品を並べ、引き売りしている姿が発展途上国を中心にみられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are seen mainly in developing countries pulling a luggage rack of something like a bookcase with products neatly displayed for sale.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are seen mainly in developing countries pulling a luggage rack with something akin to a bookcase with products neatly displayed for sale.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are seen mainly in developing countries pulling a luggage rack with something akin to a bookcase with products neatly displayed for sale.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>またインドやフィリピンなどでは、箱ではなく１本から販売している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In countries such as India and the Philippines, they are sold individually instead of in boxes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In countries such as India and the Philippines, the cigarettes are sold individually instead of in boxes.</e>
<cmt>Added for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In countries such as India and the Philippines, the cigarettes are sold individually instead of in boxes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="72">
<j>菓子売り</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Snack seller</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Snack selling</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Snack selling</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>- チューインガムや飴、味付けしたピーナッツなど様々であるが、発展途上国でよく見る事が出来る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Often seen in developing countries, selling chewing gum, candy, flavored peanuts, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is often seen in developing countries, and chewing gum, candy, and flavored peanuts are some examples of what is sold.</e>
<cmt>Added for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is often seen in developing countries, and chewing gum, candy, and flavored peanuts are some examples of what is sold.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>花売り同様に児童労働の代表的な職業として知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Similar to flower vendors, it is also known as the leading occupation for child labor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Similar to flower selling, it is also known as a leading occupation for child labor.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Similar to flower selling, it is also known as a leading occupation for child labor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>日本における露天商の衰退と存在理由</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Decline of rotensho in Japan and reason for its existence</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The decline of rotensho in Japan and reasons for their existence</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The decline of rotensho in Japan and reasons for their existence</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="75">
<j>衰退</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Decline</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Decline</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Decline</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>駅前や商店街などであり、商店街においてはアーケードを持つ商店街は露天商にとってうってつけの場所であったが、近年では薄暗い雰囲気や古臭いと言ったイメージ、メンテナンス費用の負担などから撤去される傾向がありこの様な事情も露天商の衰退の要因であろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among shopping areas, those with arcades were perfect locations for rotensho, but in recent years they tend to be removed due to images such as dark atmosphere and old-fashioned, as well as maintenance costs, and these conditions are among the causes for the decline of rotensho.</e>
<cmt>文頭の「駅前や商店街などであり、」が解釈できず、省略しました。「露天商が栄えたのは」などを補うと通じるようです。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among shopping areas those with arcades were perfect locations for rotensho, but in recent years these have tended to have been removed due to their image such as having a dark atmosphere and being old-fashioned, as well as with their high maintenance costs, and these conditions are among the causes of the decline in rotensho.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among shopping areas those with arcades were perfect locations for rotensho, but in recent years these have tended to have been removed due to their image such as having a dark atmosphere and being old-fashioned, as well as with their high maintenance costs, and these conditions are among the causes of the decline in rotensho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>駅前に関しては戦後の混乱期などから既得権を持つものが恒常的に営業してきたが、再開発に伴う刷新などの契機に排斥され無くなりつつある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In front of stations, those with vested rights since the time of disorder after the war constantly did business, but they are disappearing as they are cast aside for renovation, etc. during renewal.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In front of stations, those with vested rights since the time of disorder after the war continued to do business, but they are disappearing as they are removed during renovation when the buildings are rebuilt.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In front of stations, those with vested rights since the time of disorder after the war continued to do business, but they are disappearing as they are removed during renovation when the buildings are rebuilt.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="78">
<j>都心では屋台街が古くから存在している地域が日本各地に見られたが、既得権と道路使用や道路占有の問題や食品衛生法や電力、給排水の供給や路上を汚すといった問題などから、万博や世界選手権大会などが開催される地域で、それを契機に排除してきた事実がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In inner-cities, there were various areas in Japan where yatai-gai existed since long ago, but because of vested rights, road-use, and road-occupancy issues, as well as issues regarding the Food Sanitation Act, electricity supply, supply and drainage of water, street pollution, they were in fact eliminated in areas where expositions and world championships were held, using them as the impetus.</e>
<cmt>原文には「道路交通法や道路交通法」とありますが、リンク先の単語のようです。ウェブで確認すると用語が「道路使用や道路占有」となっており、本来はこちらの用語を使用していると思われますので、こちらを訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In inner-cities, there were various areas in Japan where yatai-gai existed for hundreds of years, but because of vested rights, road-use, and road-occupancy issues, as well as issues regarding the Food Sanitation Act, electricity supply, the supply and drainage of water and street pollution, they were in fact eliminated in areas where expositions and world championships were held, using them as an impetus to have them removed.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, added for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In inner-cities, there were various areas in Japan where yatai-gai existed for hundreds of years, but because of vested rights, road-use, and road-occupancy issues, as well as issues regarding the Food Sanitation Act, electricity supply, the supply and drainage of water and street pollution, they were in fact eliminated in areas where expositions and world championships were held, using them as an impetus to have them removed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>しかし博多のように「屋台は日本の文化である」といった地域住民や行政の意思により、官民一体となって存続される地域も出始めていて、観光誘致や地域振興として様々な恩恵を齎している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in some areas such as Hakata, they are beginning to be kept alive by public and private support, under the will of local residents and government that &apos;yatai is a culture of Japan,&apos; and they are bringing various benefits regarding tourism enticement and regional promotion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in some areas such as Hakata, they are beginning to be kept alive by public and private support, with the will of local residents and the belief of government that &apos;yatai are part of the culture of Japan&apos;, and they bring various benefits regarding tourism and regional promotion.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity, grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in some areas such as Hakata, they are beginning to be kept alive by public and private support, with the will of local residents and the belief of government that &apos;yatai are part of the culture of Japan,&apos; and they bring various benefits regarding tourism and regional promotion.</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="80">
<j>的屋に代表される露天商は寺社との繋がりが深く、古くから地域住民に支えられてきたが、近年では日本人自体が寺社との繋がりが薄く檀家や氏子として、祭りなどに積極的に参加しなくなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rotensho represented by tekiya were deeply connected to temples and shrines, supported by local residents from long ago, but in recent years, Japanese people have become less connected to temples and shrines, and do not actively participate in festivals as danka (supporter of a Buddhist temple) or ujiko (shrine parishioner).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rotensho represented by tekiya were deeply connected to temples and shrines supported by local residents over a long period of time, but in recent years Japanese people have become less connected to temples and shrines, and do not actively participate in festivals as a danka (supporter of a Buddhist temple) or ujiko (shrine parishioner).</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rotensho represented by tekiya were deeply connected to temples and shrines supported by local residents over a long period of time, but in recent years Japanese people have become less connected to temples and shrines, and do not actively participate in festivals as a danka (supporter of a Buddhist temple) or ujiko (shrine parishioner).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>この様な事や価値観や趣味や休日の過ごし方の多様化などから、祭り文化の衰退と共に的屋自体の収入の低下などから成り手が無いと言った現状がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of this and the diversification of values, hobbies, and the way people spend their weekends, nobody wants to take the job due to decline of the festival culture, as well as the decrease in profit of the tekiya.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of this and the diversification of values, hobbies, and the way people spend their weekends, few want to take the job due to the decline of festival culture, as well as the reduced profits of the tekiya.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of this and the diversification of values, hobbies, and the way people spend their weekends, few want to take the job due to the decline of festival culture, as well as the reduced profits of the tekiya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="82">
<j>存在理由</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reason for its existence</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reasons for existence</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reasons for existence</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>生活困窮者は世界中でいつの時代にも存在し、初期投資が少なくリスクが低く日銭の入る露天商は、社会において必要欠くべからざるものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The poor exist around the world any time in history, and rotensho which requires little initial investment and is low in risk is essential in society.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The poor of society have existed across the world and in any period in history, and the rotensho requires little initial investment and is low in risk and essential to society.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The poor of society have existed across the world and in any period in history, and the rotensho requires little initial investment and is low in risk and essential to society.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>ニューヨークでもホットドッグ売りなどの露天商はいまだに健在であり、その社会的役割を果たしているが、日本においては上記の理由や、高度成長を遂げた後の意識の変化などから、手軽に始められないのが現状である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In New York, rotensho such as hot dog sellers are still around, serving their social role, but in Japan, because of the reasons above and the change in attitudes after achieving the high-growth period, it cannot be easily started.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In New York, rotensho such as hot dog sellers continue to trade, serving their social role, but in Japan, because of the reasons above and the change in attitudes with the end of the high-growth period, they cannot be easily recreated.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In New York, rotensho such as hot dog sellers continue to trade, serving their social role, but in Japan, because of the reasons above and the change in attitudes with the end of the high-growth period, they cannot be easily recreated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>高齢化社会や格差社会、雇用問題などを含め露天商が一つの解決策であるにも拘らず、社会的にこれを見直すといった風潮はまだ無いと言えるだろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although rotensho could be one solution for the aging society, the gap-widening society, the employment issue, etc., there is no trend yet towards rethinking this as a society.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although rotensho could be one solution for aging societies, societies where the gap between rich and poor is widening, and those with employment issues, there is no trend yet towards rethinking this as a society.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although rotensho could be one solution for aging societies, societies where the gap between rich and poor is widening, and those with employment issues, there is no trend yet towards rethinking this as a society.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 長島左近(id:161003), Izayohi(id:13095), 与左衛門(id:159462), 0null0(id:582), Trt(id:8041), 竹麦魚(id:11012), NDR(id:5500), あすぺん(id:22344), 一文字猛(id:169827), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>