<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>盟三五大切</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kamikakete sango taisetsu (a kabuki kyogen play)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kamikakete sango taisetsu (a kabuki kyogen play)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kamikakete sango taisetsu (a kabuki kyogen play)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>盟三五大切（かみかけて さんご たいせつ）は、鶴屋南北 (4代目)による歌舞伎狂言。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kamikakete sango taisetsu was a kabuki kyogen play written by Nanboku TSURUYA (the fourth)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kamikakete sango taisetsu was a kabuki kyogen play written by Nanboku TSURUYA (the fourth)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kamikakete sango taisetsu was a kabuki kyogen play written by Nanboku TSURUYA (the fourth)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>文政8年9月（1825年10月）に江戸の中村座で初演。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was played for the first time in October, 1825, in the Nakamura theater in Edo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was first performed in October, 1825 at the Nakamura-za Theater in Edo.</e>
<cmt>文法も用語も問題ありません。メディアでよく使われるかたちに直します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was first performed in October, 1825 at the Nakamura-za Theater in Edo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>歌舞伎の演目としては世話物に分類される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is classified into sewamono (plays dealing with the lives of ordinary people) in the kabuki programs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is classified into sewamono (plays dealing with the lives of ordinary people) in the kabuki programs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is classified into sewamono (plays dealing with the lives of ordinary people) in the kabuki programs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>江戸時代における上演について詳細は不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Details of how this play was performed in the Edo period are unclear.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Details of how this play was performed in the Edo period are unclear.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Details of how this play was performed in the Edo period are unclear.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>しかしながら、昭和51年（1976年）に国立劇場において、郡司正勝の補綴、演出によって復活上演されて以来、現在でもしばしば上演されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, since the new version, revised and supplemented by Masakatsu GUNJI, was performed in 1976 at National Theater under his direction, this play has been performed and is often played even today.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, since the new version, revised and supplemented by Masakatsu GUNJI, was performed in 1976 at National Theater under his direction, this play has been performed and is often played even today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, since the new version, revised and supplemented by Masakatsu GUNJI, was performed in 1976 at National Theater under his direction, this play has been performed and is often played even today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>歌舞伎作品の中でも、当時（大まかな時代として江戸時代）の出来事を扱う世話物であるこの作品は、『東海道四谷怪談』の後日譚、並木五瓶の『五大力恋緘（ごだいりきこいのふうじめ）』の書き換え、『仮名手本忠臣蔵』の外伝としての性格を持つ物語が展開される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Of the kabuki plays, this sewamono play deals with events at that time (roughly the Edo period), and there, stories with the features of a sequel to Tokaido Yotsuya Kaidan (Tokaido Yotsuya ghost stories), of a rewritten version of &quot;Godairiki Koi no Fujime by Gohei NAMIKI&quot; and of a side story of Kanadehon Chushingura (a famous story of loyal retainers) are played.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the kabuki programs, this &apos;sewamono&apos; deals with the then current affairs (of roughly the Edo period) and contains various characteristic stories including a sequel to &quot;Tokaido Yotsuya Kaidan&quot; (a sewamono dealing with a ghost story in Yotsuya), a rewrite of &quot;Godairiki Koi no Fujime&quot; (a sewamono based on a real-life serial murderer) originally written by Gohei NAMIKI and a side story of &quot;Kanadehon Chushingura&quot; (a famous story of loyal retainers).</e>
<cmt>前段の世話物についての簡潔な説明と忠臣蔵についての説明を活かし、スタイルを統一します。「東海道四谷怪談」は一つの怪談話を扱っていますので、単数形で良いです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the kabuki programs, this &apos;sewamono&apos; deals with the then current affairs (of roughly the Edo period) and contains various characteristic stories including a sequel to &quot;Tokaido Yotsuya Kaidan&quot; (a sewamono dealing with a ghost story in Yotsuya), a rewrite of &quot;Godairiki Koi no Fujime&quot; (a sewamono based on a real-life serial murderer) originally written by Gohei NAMIKI and a side story of &quot;Kanadehon Chushingura&quot; (a famous story of loyal retainers).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>『忠臣蔵』で有名な不破数右衛門が薩摩源五兵衛に身をやつし金策をする中、逆に三五郎（実は徳右衛門倅千太郎）に百両を騙し取られ、凄惨な殺人鬼と化してしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While having changed his name to Gengobei SATSUMA for raising money, the famous Kazuemon FUWA was cheated out of hundred ryo (a currency unit) by Sangoro (actually, Sentaro, Sentaro, a son of Tokuemon), becoming a ghastly killer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the play, when Kazuemon FUWA, a famous character of &quot;Kanadehon Chushingura,&quot; disguises himself as Gengobe SATSUMA for gathering money, he is cheated out of 100 ryo (a monetary unit) by Sangoro (in fact a son of Tokuemon, Sentaro&apos;s disguise), and as a result he becomes a cold-blooded murderer.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れがあります。訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the play, when Kazuemon FUWA, a famous character of &quot;Kanadehon Chushingura,&quot; disguises himself as Gengobe SATSUMA for gathering money, he is cheated out of 100 ryo (a monetary unit) by Sangoro (in fact a son of Tokuemon, Sentaro&apos;s disguise), and as a result he becomes a cold-blooded murderer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>そのような源五兵衛が元の数右衛門に戻って、晴れて討ち入りする結末に、南北の武士社会への皮肉が表現されているとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that an irony concerning the northern samurai society and southern samurai society was expressed in the last scene where Gengobei SATSUMA, having returned to the original Kazuemon again, made a raid in public.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the last scene, Kazuemon takes off his disguise as Gengobe and avenged his master without shame with fellow ex-retainers, and it is said that especially in the scene the writer Nanboku described the then samurai society with a bitter irony.</e>
<cmt>「南北」は作者の鶴屋南北のことです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the last scene, Kazuemon takes off his disguise as Gengobe and avenged his master without shame with fellow ex-retainers, and it is said that especially in the scene the writer Nanboku described the then samurai society with a bitter irony.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>本作が作られた事情は、「四谷怪談」が大当たりのさなかに主演の三代目尾上菊五郎が太宰府参詣のため中村座を退座してしまい、困った関係者が作者南北に急きょ作成させたことにある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The situation that this play was produced was as follows: While the Yotsuya Kaidan (Yotsuya ghost stories) play was a big hit, its leading actor, Kikugoro ONOE, the third, left the Nakamura theater to pay a visit to Dazaifu, and the persons concerned who were embarrassed with the situation forced Manboku to produce this play in haste.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The background to the production of this play is as follows: While &quot;Tokaido Yotsuya Kaidan&quot; was making a big hit, its leading actor, the third Kikugoro ONOE left the Nakamura-za Theater for visiting Dazaifu Tenmangu Shrine, and the theater manager commissioned Nanboku to write a new play in haste to solve the predicament.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The background to the production of this play is as follows: While &quot;Tokaido Yotsuya Kaidan&quot; was making a big hit, its leading actor, the third Kikugoro ONOE left the Nakamura-za Theater for visiting Dazaifu Tenmangu Shrine, and the theater manager commissioned Nanboku to write a new play in haste to solve the predicament.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>小規模な作品だが綿密な構成、凄惨な殺し場に満ち、しかも喜劇の要素も絡ませるなどいている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though being small in size, it is structured elaborately, is full of ghastly killing scenes, and includes elements of a farce as well.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although it is small in size, it has an elaborate structure, and is full of scenes of brutal murder, and even includes the element of a comedy.</e>
<cmt>「喜劇」はこの場合「悲劇」に対して使われているので普通のcomedyで大丈夫です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it is small in size, it has an elaborate structure, and is full of scenes of brutal murder, and even includes the element of a comedy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>そのように、南北の作劇術の才能が溢れた作品で、「四谷怪談」とともに評価が高い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this way, the play, brimming with Nanboku&apos;s play-producing talent, is highly evaluated together with &quot;Yotsuya Kaidan.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore it can be said that in this play Nanboku&apos;s talent of writing plays was manifested, and it is well appreciated as much as &quot;Tokaido Yotsuya Kaidan.&quot;</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore it can be said that in this play Nanboku&apos;s talent of writing plays was manifested, and it is well appreciated as much as &quot;Tokaido Yotsuya Kaidan.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>狂言の構成</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The structure of the kyogen</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Structure of the Kyogen (the play)</e>
<cmt>スタイルを統一します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Structure of the Kyogen (the play)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="12">
<j>現在の歌舞伎として上演される際の構成は、三幕六場の形式である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When performed as a present kabuki play, this play is performed in the form of three parts and six scene.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When this play is performed as a present kabuki play, it is performed in the form of three acts and six scenes.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When this play is performed as a present kabuki play, it is performed in the form of three acts and six scenes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>序幕</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Initial part</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Act Ⅰ (Jomaku)</e>
<cmt>よく使われるかたちに直します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Act Ⅰ (Jomaku)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>佃沖新地鼻の場</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The scene of Shinchibana off Tsukuda</e>
<cmt>佃沖新地鼻：　正しい読み不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The scene of Tsukuda-oki Shinchi-bana</e>
<cmt>スタイルを統一します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The scene of Tsukuda-oki Shinchi-bana</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>深川大和町の場</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The scene of Fukagawa Yamato-cho</e>
<cmt>深川大和町：　正しい読み不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The scene of Fukagawa Yamato-cho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The scene of Fukagawa Yamato-cho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="16">
<j>二幕目</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The second part</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Act Ⅱ (Nimakume)</e>
<cmt>スタイルを統一します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Act Ⅱ (Nimakume)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="17">
<j>二軒茶屋の場</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The scene of Niken-jaya</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The scene of Niken-jaya</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The scene of Niken-jaya</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="18">
<j>五人切の場</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The scene of cutting five persons down</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The scene of Gonin-giri (murdering five people)</e>
<cmt>スタイルを統一します。「切（斬）」は世話物では悪意に満ちたmurderを意味します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The scene of Gonin-giri (murdering five people)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="19">
<j>大詰</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The final part</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Finale (Ozume)</e>
<cmt>スタイルを統一します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Finale (Ozume)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="20">
<j>四谷鬼横町の場</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The scene of Yotsuya Oniyoko-cho</e>
<cmt>四谷鬼横町：　正しい読み不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The scene of Yotsuya Oni-yokocho</e>
<cmt>「横」は「町」にくっつきます。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The scene of Yotsuya Oni-yokocho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="21">
<j>愛染院門前の場</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The scene in front of the Aizenin-mon gate</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The scene of Aizenin-mon-mae (in front of the gate of Aizenin Temple)</e>
<cmt>スタイルを統一します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The scene of Aizenin-mon-mae (in front of the gate of Aizenin Temple)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>登場人物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The characters</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Characters</e>
<cmt>スタイルを統一します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Characters</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="22">
<j>薩摩源五兵衛 実は不破数右衛門 塩冶浪人、不破数右衛門は御用金百両を盗賊に盗まれるという落度で主家を追われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gengobei SATSUMA, actually Kazuemon FUWA: Kazuemon FUWA, a ronin(master-less samurai) from the Enya clan, was exiled from his master clan due to a mistake that he had 100 ryo of goyokin (official money) stolen by a thief.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gengobe SATSUMA (in fact Kazuemon FUWA&apos;s disguise): Kazuemon FUWA, a ronin (master-less samurai) and ex-retainer of the Enya family, was banished by his master, since the goyokin (public money) 100 ryo, which he had been overseeing, had been stolen by thieves.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。歌舞伎で「実は」がつく場合、登場人物の見た目も本来の姿と違い、混乱や事件の原因になっています。ですから含みがありそうなdisguiseという語に統一します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gengobe SATSUMA (in fact Kazuemon FUWA&apos;s disguise): Kazuemon FUWA, a ronin (master-less samurai) and ex-retainer of the Enya family, was banished by his master, since the goyokin (public money) 100 ryo, which he had been overseeing, had been stolen by thieves.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>そのさなか塩冶判官の刃傷沙汰による主家お取潰しが起こった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While he was a ronin, the clan was abolished due to a sword-used injury case caused by the Enya hangan (the third highest of the four administrative ranks of the ritsuryo period).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While he was a ronin, his ex-master&apos;s clan was abolished sinece the lord of Enya Domain, Enya Hangan (the third highest official in the Ritsuryo system) hurt a man with a sword.</e>
<cmt>舞台は律令時代ではないので普通の国語辞典に説明されているように「律令制の」とするほうが混乱を招きません。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While he was a ronin, his ex-master&apos;s clan was abolished sinece the lord of Enya Domain, Enya Hangan (the third highest official in the Ritsuryo system) hurt a man with a sword.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>そこで、何とか百両を調達して仇討ちの一味に加わろうと、薩摩源五兵衛と名を変えて金策している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, to be included to the revenge group by acquiring the 100 ryo by all means, he was endeavoring to get a loan of that money.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kazuemon changed his name to Gengobe SATSUMA and tried hard to gather 100 ryo to be allowed joining the group of the avengers.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kazuemon changed his name to Gengobe SATSUMA and tried hard to gather 100 ryo to be allowed joining the group of the avengers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="25">
<j>芸者妲妃の小万 実は神谷召使お六 神谷の家人の娘であるお六は、父に勘当された三五郎と夫婦となり、三五郎の勘当を解いてもらうため、百両の金子を調達するために、芸者をしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dakki no Koman, a geisha (Japanese professional female entertainer at drinking party), who actually was Oroku, a daughter of a retainer of the Kamiya family and a meshitsukai (inferior officer) for the family, became the wife of Mitsugoro who had been disowned by his father, and worked as a geisha to gain 100 ryo so that Mitugoro could be released from the disowned state.</e>
<cmt>妲妃の小万：　正しい読み不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Geisha, Dakki no Koman (in fact a servant of the Kamiya family, Oroku&apos;s disguise): a daughter of a retainer of the Kamiya family, Oroku married Mitsugoro who had been disowned by his father, and worked as a geisha to gain 100 ryo so that Mitugoro&apos;s father could forgive his son.</e>
<cmt>この場合「芸者」は現代の芸者さんと違って「女郎（売春婦）」という意味です。括弧内説明は不要で、geishaで通じます。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Geisha, Dakki no Koman (in fact a servant of the Kamiya family, Oroku&apos;s disguise): a daughter of a retainer of the Kamiya family, Oroku married Mitsugoro who had been disowned by his father, and worked as a geisha to gain 100 ryo so that Mitugoro&apos;s father could forgive his son.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>自分に惚れている源五兵衛から金を貢がせようとしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was trying to make Gengobei, who was deeply in love with her, help financially.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then she tried to make Gengobe, who was deeply in love with her, give her money.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then she tried to make Gengobe, who was deeply in love with her, give her money.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="27">
<j>船頭笹野屋三五郎 実は徳右衛門倅千太郎 徳右衛門倅千太郎は、身持ちが悪く、徳右衛門から勘当を受け船頭笹野屋三五郎となっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sangoro SASANOYA, a sendo (boatman), actually Sentaro, a son of Tokuemon: Sentaro, a son of Tokuemon was immoral and had been disowned by Tokuemon, becoming a sendo named Sangoro SASANOYA.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sendo (boatman) Sangoro SASANOYA (in fact a son of Tokuemon, Sentaro&apos;s disguise): Sentaro was disowned by his father Tokuemon for his immoralities, and changed his name to Sangoro and become a boatman of Sasano-ya.</e>
<cmt>スタイルを統一します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sendo (boatman) Sangoro SASANOYA (in fact a son of Tokuemon, Sentaro&apos;s disguise): Sentaro was disowned by his father Tokuemon for his immoralities, and changed his name to Sangoro and become a boatman of Sasano-ya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>しかしながら、父から旧主のために百両の金子の用立てを頼まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he was asked by his father to gain 100 ryo for his father&apos;s former master.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, he was asked by his father to gain 100 ryo for his father&apos;s former master.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, he was asked by his father to gain 100 ryo for his father&apos;s former master.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>これによって勘当を解いてもらおうと、女房お六を小万と名乗る深川芸者をさせて、百両の調達しようとしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, to has his disowned state released by accomplishing the request, he made his wife, Oroku, a geisha named Koman, to gain 100 ryo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since he wanted his father&apos;s forgiveness, he made his wife Oroku work as a geisha named Koman in Fukagawa (in Edo, present Tokyo) to prepare 100 ryo.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れがあります。「深川」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since he wanted his father&apos;s forgiveness, he made his wife Oroku work as a geisha named Koman in Fukagawa (in Edo, present Tokyo) to prepare 100 ryo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>父の旧主の不破数右衛門が源五兵衛とは知らずに、小万を惚れさせて金を巻き上げようとしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Not knowing that Gengoro is actually Kazuemon FUWA, his father&apos;s former master, he tries to make Gengoro become deep in love with Koman to cheat him out of money.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Not knowing that Gengoro was in fact Kazuemon FUWA, his father&apos;s former master, Sangoro planned to make Gengoro become deep in love with Koman to cheat him out of money.</e>
<cmt>時制を統一します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Not knowing that Gengoro was in fact Kazuemon FUWA, his father&apos;s former master, Sangoro planned to make Gengoro become deep in love with Koman to cheat him out of money.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="31">
<j>若党 六七八右衛門 源五兵衛に仕える若党。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A wakato (young samurai), Hachiyemon ROKUSHICHI: a wakato (young samurai) serving Gengobei</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wakato (young samurai) Hachiemon ROKUSHICHI: He was a young samurai serving Gengobe.</e>
<cmt>スタイルを統一します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wakato (young samurai) Hachiemon ROKUSHICHI: He was a young samurai serving Gengobe.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="32">
<j>賤ヶ谷伴右衛門 実はごろつき勘九郎 深川のごろつき勘九郎は、三五郎の深川のごろつき仲間で、源五兵衛から金を巻き上げる手伝いをしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Banemon SHIZUGATANI, actually Kankuro, a ruffian: Kankuro, a ruffian in Fukagawa and a member of a Fukagawa ruffian group including Sangoro, was helping cheating Gengobei out of money.</e>
<cmt>賤ヶ谷伴右衛門：　正しい読み不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Banemon SHIZUGAYA (in fact Gorotsuki [ruffian] Kankuro&apos;s disguise): Kankuro, a ruffian of Fukagawa, was a bad friend of Sangoro and helping him in cheating Gengobe out of money.</e>
<cmt>スタイルを統一します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Banemon SHIZUGAYA (in fact Gorotsuki [ruffian] Kankuro&apos;s disguise): Kankuro, a ruffian of Fukagawa, was a bad friend of Sangoro and helping him in cheating Gengobe out of money.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="33">
<j>船頭お先の伊之助 船頭伊之助も、深川のごろつき仲間で三五郎の手伝いをしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A sendo, Osakino Inosuke: Inosuke, a sendo, was a member of the ruffian group in Fukawawa and was also helping Sangoro.</e>
<cmt>お先の伊之助：　正しい読み不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sendo (boatman) Osaki no Inosuke: A boatman Inosuke was a bad friend of Sangoro in Fukagawa and member of the ruffian group in Fukawawa and also helping him.</e>
<cmt>スタイルを統一します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sendo (boatman) Osaki no Inosuke: A boatman Inosuke was a bad friend of Sangoro in Fukagawa and member of the ruffian group in Fukawawa and also helping him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>芸者菊野とは男女の仲である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had a sexual relationship with Kikuno, a geisha.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had a sexual relationship with Kikuno, a geisha.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had a sexual relationship with Kikuno, a geisha.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="35">
<j>芸者 菊野 小万の朋輩である菊野は、源五兵衛を気の毒に思いながらも、伊之助との縁から三五郎と小万を手伝っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A geisha, Kikuno: Kikuno, Koman&apos;s friend, was helping Sangoro and Koman considering her relationship with Inosuke, although feeling pity for Gengobei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Geisha Kikuno: Kikuno, Koman&apos;s friend, was helping Sangoro and Koman for Inosuke although she was feeling pity for Gengobe.</e>
<cmt>スタイルを統一します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Geisha Kikuno: Kikuno, Koman&apos;s friend, was helping Sangoro and Koman for Inosuke although she was feeling pity for Gengobe.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="36">
<j>徳右衛門同心了心 三五郎の父、徳右衛門は出家して了心と名乗り、数右衛門のために金策している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A doshin (a police constable) named Ryoshin, actually Tokuemon: Tokuemon, the father of Sangoro, became a priest named Tyoshin, and was trying to gain money for Kazuemon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryoshin (Doshin [police constable] Tokuemon): Tokuemon, the father of Sangoro, became a priest named Ryoshin, and was trying to gain money for Kazuemon.</e>
<cmt>スタイルを統一します。徳右衛門さんは出家しているだけなので、「実は」の但し書きは不要です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryoshin (Doshin [police constable] Tokuemon): Tokuemon, the father of Sangoro, became a priest named Ryoshin, and was trying to gain money for Kazuemon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="37">
<j>家主くり廻しの弥助 実は神谷下郎土手平 偶然、三五郎夫婦が店子として入った長屋の家主の弥助は、お六の兄であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A yanushi (landlord), Kurimawari no Yasuke, actually, Dotehei KAMIYASHIRO: The landlord of the nagaya (long house) where the married couple of Sangoro and Koman rent a room was accidentally Yasuke, a brother of Oroku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yanushi (landlord) Kurimawashi no Yasuke (in fact a servant of the Kamiya family, Dotehe&apos;s disguise): Yasuke, the landlord of the nagaya (row house) which Sangoro and his wife Koman (Oroku) rented, was accidentally Yasuke, a brother of Oroku.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yanushi (landlord) Kurimawashi no Yasuke (in fact a servant of the Kamiya family, Dotehe&apos;s disguise): Yasuke, the landlord of the nagaya (row house) which Sangoro and his wife Koman (Oroku) rented, was accidentally Yasuke, a brother of Oroku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>あらすじ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The outline of the story</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Outline</e>
<cmt>スタイルを統一します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Outline</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>序幕 第一場 佃沖新地鼻の場</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The initial part, the first scene: the scene of Shinchibana off Tsukuda</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Act Ⅰ, Scene 1: The scene of Tsukuda-oki Shinchi-bana</e>
<cmt>スタイルを統一します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Act Ⅰ, Scene 1: The scene of Tsukuda-oki Shinchi-bana</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="38">
<j>佃沖で船頭お先の伊之助が漕ぐ舟に賤ヶ谷伴右衛門と名乗る侍が乗っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A samurai calling himself Banemon SHIZUGATANI is on board the boat rowed by Osakino Inosuke, the sendo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A boat, that a samurai calling himself Banemon SHIZUGAYA took, is passing across a river (Shinchi-bana, a point of Sumida-gawa River) near to Tsukuda-jima Island rowed by Sendo Osaki no Inosuke.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れがあります。「佃沖」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A boat, that a samurai calling himself Banemon SHIZUGAYA took, is passing across a river (Shinchi-bana, a point of Sumida-gawa River) near to Tsukuda-jima Island rowed by Sendo Osaki no Inosuke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>賤ヶ谷伴右衛門という侍は、実は深川のごろつき勘九郎であることがほのめかされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is hinted that the samurai called Banemon SHIZUGATANI might actually be Kankuro, a ruffian in Fukagawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the scene, it is hinted that the samurai called Banemon SHIZUGAYA is in fact Gorotsuki Kankuro, a rogue in Fukagawa (also near to Sumida-gawa River).</e>
<cmt>スタイルを統一します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the scene, it is hinted that the samurai called Banemon SHIZUGAYA is in fact Gorotsuki Kankuro, a rogue in Fukagawa (also near to Sumida-gawa River).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>二人が深川芸者小万から届けられた手紙の話題となると、一艘の舟がやってくる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the two persons started talking about a letter received by Koman, a geisha in Fukagawa, another boat comes up to the boat.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the two men just talked about a letter from a geisha of Fukagawa, Koman, another boat comes up.</e>
<cmt>文法の間違いがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the two men just talked about a letter from a geisha of Fukagawa, Koman, another boat comes up.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>この舟には妲妃と異名をとる小万と船頭笹野屋三五郎が乗っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koman, also called Dakki, and Sangoro SASANOYA, a sendo, were on board this boat.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On this boat are Koman who is given the nickname Dakki (ancient Chinese woman of great beauty who was murdered) and Sendo Sangoro SASANOYA.</e>
<cmt>異名の意味を江戸の人間はよくわかっていましたので括弧に説明を加えます。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On this boat are Koman who is given the nickname Dakki (ancient Chinese woman of great beauty who was murdered) and Sendo Sangoro SASANOYA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>実はこの二人は夫婦であり、三五郎は塩冶家に所縁のある者の倅、千太郎であるが、訳あって勘当されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Actually, these two are a husband and his wife, and Sangoro is Sentaro, a son of a person related to the Enya family, who has been disowned due to a reason.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In fact, these two are a husband and his wife, and Sangoro is Sentaro, a son of a person related to the Enya family, who has been disowned due to a reason.</e>
<cmt>用語を統一します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact, these two are a husband and his wife, and Sangoro is Sentaro, a son of a person related to the Enya family, who has been disowned due to a reason.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>このたび父が旧主のために金子百両を必要としていることを知り、これを用立てて勘当を解いてもらおうと考え、女房お六に因果を含め、小万と名乗らせて芸者勤めをさせている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Knowing this time that his father needs 100 ryo for his former master, he considers that he will have his disowned state released by gaining the amount of money and has his wife, Oroku, engaged in geisha in the name of Koman, explaining her the situation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Sangoro&apos;s father needs 100 ryo for his former master, Sangoro planned to prepare the money for gaining his father&apos;s forgiveness; he persuaded his wife Oroku of its necessity and she eventually became a geisha calling herself Koman.</e>
<cmt>日本語の「知る」には大抵大きな意味はなく、相手方を傷付ける大袈裟な動詞や接続詞を避けるために使われます。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Sangoro&apos;s father needs 100 ryo for his former master, Sangoro planned to prepare the money for gaining his father&apos;s forgiveness; he persuaded his wife Oroku of its necessity and she eventually became a geisha calling herself Koman.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="44">
<j>小万は三五郎が連れて来た薩摩源五兵衛という浪人している侍から、かなりの金を巻き上げたが、三五郎は小万に惚れた源五兵衛の心に取り入って、さらに金を搾り取るように小万にけしかけている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koman has already cheated out of a considerable amount of money a samurai, a ronin named Gengobei SATSUMA, whom Sangoro brought with him, but Sangoro urges her to cheat him out of more money, further trying to win Gengobei&apos;s favor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koman already cheated a ronin (master-less samurai) Gengobe SATSUMA, whom Sangoro had introduced, out of a considerable amount of money, however Sangoro is urging her to impose Gengobe&apos;s love for her and to squeeze more money out of him.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koman already cheated a ronin (master-less samurai) Gengobe SATSUMA, whom Sangoro had introduced, out of a considerable amount of money, however Sangoro is urging her to impose Gengobe&apos;s love for her and to squeeze more money out of him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="45">
<j>そのような話をしながら、夫婦でいちゃついていると、月が出てあたりは急に明るくなり、近くに一艘の屋形船が近くにいることに気づいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the husband and the wife is flirting with each other making such talks, the moon rises, making the area light, and then they notice that a roofed pleasure boat is located nearby.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While the couple is frolicking and talking about their trick, suddenly the moon appears through the clouds and illuminates the river, and they notice a roofed boat floating nearby.</e>
<cmt>誤訳です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While the couple is frolicking and talking about their trick, suddenly the moon appears through the clouds and illuminates the river, and they notice a roofed boat floating nearby.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>その舟に乗っていたのは薩摩源五兵衛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is Gengobei SATSUMA who has been on board the boat.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They notice Gengobei SATSUMA on the boat.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They notice Gengobei SATSUMA on the boat.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>源五兵衛も小万に気づき声をかける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gengobei finds Koman and says something to her.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gengobe also notices Koman and says hello to her.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gengobe also notices Koman and says hello to her.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>小万が愛想良く対応すると、三五郎は忌々しく思うのだった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sangoro is vexed to see that Koman responds amiably to Gengobei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Koman responds to him with a pleasant smile, Sangoro is upset.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Koman responds to him with a pleasant smile, Sangoro is upset.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>序幕 第二場 深川大和町の場</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The initial part, the second scene: the scene of Fukagawa Yamato-cho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Act Ⅰ, Scene 2: The scene of Fukagawa Yamato-cho</e>
<cmt>スタイルを統一します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Act Ⅰ, Scene 2: The scene of Fukagawa Yamato-cho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="49">
<j>源五兵衛の浪宅では、道具屋が家財一式を持ち出そうとするのを源五兵衛の若党、六七八右衛門がなんとか阻止しようとがんばっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the house where Gengobei lives as a ronin, persons at a doguya (a shop handling household goods) are going to bring a set of the household good out of the house, with Hachiyemon ROKUSHICHI, a wakato (young samurai) of Gengobei, trying to prevent it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the house where Gengobe lives as a ronin, employees of a secondhand store are just going to carry out all the pieces of furniture and Hachiemon ROKUSHICHI, a wakato serving Gengobe, is trying to prevent it.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the house where Gengobe lives as a ronin, employees of a secondhand store are just going to carry out all the pieces of furniture and Hachiemon ROKUSHICHI, a wakato serving Gengobe, is trying to prevent it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>しかし、戻ってきた源五兵衛が売り払ったと宣言するので、結局、家財一式は持ち去られてしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as Gengobei, who has now returned to his house, declares that he has sold them, the set of the household goods are brought out.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Gengobe just comes home and declares that he sold them all, therefore the furniture is carried out after all.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Gengobe just comes home and declares that he sold them all, therefore the furniture is carried out after all.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>そのような有様にも拘わらず、源五兵衛は一枚残った布団の上で小万のことを思う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even in such a situation, Gengobei thinks about Koman on a futon remaining.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even in such a situation, Gengobe sits on a futon which is the only thing remaining in the room and thinks about Koman.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even in such a situation, Gengobe sits on a futon which is the only thing remaining in the room and thinks about Koman.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>あまりの様子に堪りかねた八右衛門は涙ながらに主人に意見する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Being unable to bear such a situation anymore, Hachiemon reproves his master in tears.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Being unable to bear seeing his master in the descendent, Hachiemon reproves him in tears.</e>
<cmt>「様子」は主人の有り様のことです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Being unable to bear seeing his master in the descendent, Hachiemon reproves him in tears.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="53">
<j>源五兵衛は実は不破数右衛門という元塩冶家家臣であったが、盗賊に御用金を盗まれた落度によって浪人している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Being actually a former retainer of the Enya family, named Kazuemon FUWA, Gengobei is now a ronin due to his mistake that he had goryokin (official money) stolen by bandits.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gengobe is in fact Kazuemon FUWA, he had been a retainer of the Enya family; however, since goyokin (public money), which he had been overseeing, had been stolen by thieves, he was banished and became a ronin.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gengobe is in fact Kazuemon FUWA, he had been a retainer of the Enya family; however, since goyokin (public money), which he had been overseeing, had been stolen by thieves, he was banished and became a ronin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>しかし、塩冶家は主君が城内で高野師直に刃傷に及んだ罪を問われて切腹し、家名も断絶となっていた（『仮名手本忠臣蔵』の設定）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, being punished for injuring Moronao KONO in the castle, the head of the Enya family committed seppuku (suicide by disembowelment), and consequently his family name has been terminated (a setting based on &quot;Kanadehon Chushingura ((a famous story of loyal retainers).&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the head of the Enya family was given a sentence of seppuku for injuring Moronao KONO with his sword in the castle, and after his seppuku, the family was terminated (this setting was based on &quot;Kanadehon Chushingura&quot;).</e>
<cmt>誤訳があります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the head of the Enya family was given a sentence of seppuku for injuring Moronao KONO with his sword in the castle, and after his seppuku, the family was terminated (this setting was based on &quot;Kanadehon Chushingura&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>そのような時に芸者に入れ揚げる身持ち放埓は、盗まれた御用金百両を調達して義士の一味に加えられるよう謀っていることを敵方に知られないようにする計略であると、源五兵衛は八右衛門に諭す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this, Gengobei admonishes Hachiemon in the following way: He has behaved loosely, for example, trying to win a geisha&apos;s affection by lavishing money on, to prevent his adversary from noticing his plan to gain the 100 ryo, the same amount as the stolen goyoukin, and to be included in the loyal retainer group.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At such a crisis of the ex-master&apos;s family, Gengobe seemed to have been losing himself in playing with a geisha; however, he at last explains to Hachiemon that his such stupid behavior has been the disguise for deceiving the enemies, in fact, he has been secretly trying to prepare 100 ryo for the stolen money and to be allowed to join the group of the loyal avengers by offering the money.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At such a crisis of the ex-master&apos;s family, Gengobe seemed to have been losing himself in playing with a geisha; however, he at last explains to Hachiemon that his such stupid behavior has been the disguise for deceiving the enemies, in fact, he has been secretly trying to prepare 100 ryo for the stolen money and to be allowed to join the group of the loyal avengers by offering the money.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="56">
<j>そこに芸者小万が朋輩の芸者菊野や廻し男幸八、内びん虎蔵などを引き連れてやってくる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then Koman, a geisha, came there together with Kikuno, her geisha friend, Kohachi, Mawashi-otoko (廻し男), and Torazo, Uchibin (内びん).</e>
<cmt>”廻し男”　”内びん”：　何を意味するのか調べきれませんでしたので、発音通りの記載となっております。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time Geisha Koman comes to the house together with her friend Geisha Kikuno, Mawashi-otoko (employee of a brothel) Kohachi, and Naibin (employee of a brothel) Torazo.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れを補います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time Geisha Koman comes to the house together with her friend Geisha Kikuno, Mawashi-otoko (employee of a brothel) Kohachi, and Naibin (employee of a brothel) Torazo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>八右衛門はなんとか追い返そうとするが、心のどこかで小万に思いを寄せる源五兵衛は家に引き入れてしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hachiemon tries to turn them back, but Gengobei, who is in love with Koman in recesses of the mind, brings them into the house.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hachiemon tries to turn them out of the house, however Gengobe, who is attracted to Koman in the recesses of the mind, let them come in after all.</e>
<cmt>冠詞が抜けています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hachiemon tries to turn them out of the house, however Gengobe, who is attracted to Koman in the recesses of the mind, let them come in after all.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>伴右衛門の座敷を抜けてきたという小万の幸八が連れ帰ろうとして腕を取ると、小万の二の腕には「五大切」という入れ黒子（刺青）がみえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Kohachi takes Koman&apos;s arm to bring back her who has snuck away from the zashiki (Japanese style tatami room) where Banemon has been entertained, a tattoo of &quot;五大切&quot; (go taisetsu in pronunciation) is viewed on her upper arm.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kohachi, explaining that in fact Koman sneaked out of Banemon&apos;s party, takes her arm to bring her back, then the tattoo &apos;Go-taisetsu五大切&apos; (literally &apos;Go, precious&apos; which means &apos;I love Go&apos;) on her upper arm is seen.</e>
<cmt>誤訳です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kohachi, explaining that in fact Koman sneaked out of Banemon&apos;s party, takes her arm to bring her back, then the tattoo &apos;Go-taisetsu五大切&apos; (literally &apos;Go, precious&apos; which means &apos;I love Go&apos;) on her upper arm is seen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>源五兵衛への心中立てに彫ったと話す小万に、気を良くした源五兵衛が夫婦気取りとなるところに、源五兵衛の伯父、富森助右衛門が百両の金子を持ってやってくる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Koman tells that she tattooed it for shinju-date (an evidence for loving) Gengobei and he, getting satisfaction, tries to behave as man and wife, Sukeyemon TOMINOMORI, an uncle of Gengobei, appears bringing money of 100 ryo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koman tells that she tattooed it as shinju-date (an evidence of love) for Gengobe (&apos;Go五&apos; is one kanji character of the name of Gengobe源五兵衛), so he is pleased and poses as her husband, then Sukeemon TOMINOMORI, an uncle of Gengobe, comes to the house with 100 ryo.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koman tells that she tattooed it as shinju-date (an evidence of love) for Gengobe (&apos;Go五&apos; is one kanji character of the name of Gengobe源五兵衛), so he is pleased and poses as her husband, then Sukeemon TOMINOMORI, an uncle of Gengobe, comes to the house with 100 ryo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="60">
<j>百両と聞いて思案する小万を、助右衛門の来訪を機に八右衛門が追い返すと、助右衛門は源五兵衛に百両を渡す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hachiemon turns back Koman, who has been in thought for the information of 100 ryo, at the timing that Sukeemon appeared, and then Sukeyemon hands over the 100 ryo to Gengobei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hearing that he has 100 ryo, Koman ponders it, however Hachiemon, taking advantage of Sukeemon&apos;s sudden visit, takes out her and her followers, and Sukeemon hands that 100 ryo to Gengobe.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hearing that he has 100 ryo, Koman ponders it, however Hachiemon, taking advantage of Sukeemon&apos;s sudden visit, takes out her and her followers, and Sukeemon hands that 100 ryo to Gengobe.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>この金子を大星由良之介に持参して、亡君の仇討ちの一味に加われるように願い出よと勧めて、助右衛門は帰っていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sukeyemon advices Gengobei to bring the money to Yuranosuke OBOSHI and to request him to include Gengobei in the group to take revenge for the head of their clan who is now dead, and goes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sukeemon advices Gengobe to bring the money to Yuranosuke OBOSHI and to request him to include Gengobei in the group which is planning to avenge their ex-master, and he leaves.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sukeemon advices Gengobe to bring the money to Yuranosuke OBOSHI and to request him to include Gengobei in the group which is planning to avenge their ex-master, and he leaves.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="62">
<j>入れ代わるようにやってきた三五郎は、小万から聞いた百両の金子が源五兵衛の懐にあることを確認して、小万の手紙をだしに源五兵衛を誘い出そうとする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sangoro, who appears soon after Sukeyemon exits, confirms that the money of 100 ryo Koman talked is in Gengobei&apos;s possession and tries to lure Gengobei out, using Koman&apos;s letter skillfully.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soon after Sukeemon left, Sangoro visits Gengobe and confirms that Gengobe has the 100 ryo, which Koman told of, in his pocket, and tries to lure him out using the letter from Koman.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soon after Sukeemon left, Sangoro visits Gengobe and confirms that Gengobe has the 100 ryo, which Koman told of, in his pocket, and tries to lure him out using the letter from Koman.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>八右衛門は止めるが、小万が心底自分に惚れていると思っている源五兵衛は、最初こそ自重するものの、小万が窮地にあると聞いて、結局出かけようとする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hachiemon tries to stop responding to the lure, but, though having been prudent initially, Gengobei, who considers that Koman is deeply in love with him, finally tries to respond to the lure, hearing that Koman is deep in trouble.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hachiemon stops his master and Gengobe himself is prudent at first, however since he stupidly believes Koman&apos;s sincere love for him and is explained that she is in trouble, finally decides to go out.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hachiemon stops his master and Gengobe himself is prudent at first, however since he stupidly believes Koman&apos;s sincere love for him and is explained that she is in trouble, finally decides to go out.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>八右衛門は家賃の督促があると言って止める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hachiemon tries to stop responding to the lure saying that he has been urged to pay the house rent.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hachiemon still tries to stop him mentioning that the landlord is coming to gather the rent.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hachiemon still tries to stop him mentioning that the landlord is coming to gather the rent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>しかしながら、源五兵衛は脇差の千匹猿の細工を施した割り笄（こうがい）の片割れを支払いに宛てるようにと八右衛門に渡し、三五郎と出かけていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Gengobei hands over to Hachiemon a half part of a warikogai (a thing such as a metallic spatula placing in the shell of the sword, originally used as a potable comb) for a short sword, on which a craftwork of thousand monkeys is provided, saying that Hachiemon should pay the rent with it, and goes out of the house.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Gengobe takes the half of his short sword&apos;s wari-kogai (a metallic spatula set in the shell of a sword, originally used as a comb) carved with a lot of monkeys, and hands it to Hachiemon for the rent, and he leaves with Sangoro.</e>
<cmt>「千」はa lot ofまたはvarious</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Gengobe takes the half of his short sword&apos;s wari-kogai (a metallic spatula set in the shell of a sword, originally used as a comb) carved with a lot of monkeys, and hands it to Hachiemon for the rent, and he leaves with Sangoro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>二幕目 第一場 二軒茶屋の場</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The second part, the first scene: the scene of Niken-jaya</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Act Ⅱ, Scene 1: The scene of Niken-jaya</e>
<cmt>スタイルを統一します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Act Ⅱ, Scene 1: The scene of Niken-jaya</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="66">
<j>深川二軒茶屋では、源五兵衛の百両を巻き上げるために、賤ヶ谷伴右衛門に扮する勘九郎と、小万や菊野、小万の兄の役をする伊之助などが一芝居を打つ準備を進めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Niken-jaya, Kankuro, actually Banemon SHIZUGATANI, Koman, Kikuno, and Inosuke, playing the part of a brother of Koman, are preparing to play a trick to cheat Gengobei of the 100 ryo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Niken-jaya Tea House (a nightclub for guiding customers to brothels) of Fukagawa, Banemon SHIZUGAYA (Kankuro&apos;s disguise), Koman, Kikuno, and Inosuke who is going to be pretend to be her brother, are planning to put on an act for cheating Gengobe out of the 100 ryo.</e>
<cmt>誤訳があります。「茶屋」の説明を加えます。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Niken-jaya Tea House (a nightclub for guiding customers to brothels) of Fukagawa, Banemon SHIZUGAYA (Kankuro&apos;s disguise), Koman, Kikuno, and Inosuke who is going to be pretend to be her brother, are planning to put on an act for cheating Gengobe out of the 100 ryo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>伴右衛門が百両で小万を身請けする話をでっち上げ、小万を惜しむ源五兵衛から百両を引き出そうという算段である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The trick is as follows: They fabricate a story that Banemon is trying to buy the freedom of Koman&apos;s geisha status with 100 ryo, to cheat of 100 ryo Gengobei who does not want to lose Koman.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The trick is as follows: They fabricate a story that Banemon is going to buy out Koman for 100 ryo, and they are going to make Gengobe, who would not want to lose Koman, believe the story and make him pay 100 ryo.</e>
<cmt>「身請け」はbuy out。自由はありません。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The trick is as follows: They fabricate a story that Banemon is going to buy out Koman for 100 ryo, and they are going to make Gengobe, who would not want to lose Koman, believe the story and make him pay 100 ryo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="68">
<j>伴右衛門の身請け話を、小万が源五兵衛に心中立てして頑なに拒絶する様子を、三五郎と源五兵衛が窺っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sangoro and Gengobei are secretly looking the situation that Koman is strongly refusing Banemon&apos;s proposal of buying the freedom of her geisha status, for shinju-date (an evidence for loving) Gengobei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to their plan, Koman pretends to stubbornly refuse Banemon&apos;s proposal of buying out her, hinting that she swore to keep her earnest love for Gengobe, and from hiding Sangoro and Gengobe are watching them.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to their plan, Koman pretends to stubbornly refuse Banemon&apos;s proposal of buying out her, hinting that she swore to keep her earnest love for Gengobe, and from hiding Sangoro and Gengobe are watching them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>小万が頑なのを、何か理由があるのだろうと尋ねる伴右衛門に、伊之助が、小万には源五兵衛という相手がいると打ち明け、小万は腕の入れ黒子をみせる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To Banemon who asks Inosuke why she is so strongly reluctant to accept his proposal, Inosuke discloses that Koman is actually in love with Gengobei, and Koman shows the tattoo on her arm.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Banemon asks her reasons for stubbornly refusing, so Inosuke explains that Koman is, in fact, in love with a man called Gengobe, and Koman shows the tattoo on her arm.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Banemon asks her reasons for stubbornly refusing, so Inosuke explains that Koman is, in fact, in love with a man called Gengobe, and Koman shows the tattoo on her arm.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="70">
<j>そこへ三五郎が源五兵衛を連れて座敷に上がるが、源五兵衛はなす術もなく、「女房となろうが妾となろうが、お勝手次第」と言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then Sangoro and Gengobei enter the zashiki, but not knowing what to do, Gengobei says that &quot;You should do as you like, regardless of whether you will become a wife or mistress.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then Sangoro brings Gengobe to the room, however, Gengobe does not know what to do and just says: &quot;I don&apos;t care whether you are becoming his wife or whether you are becoming his mistress.&quot;</e>
<cmt>誤訳です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then Sangoro brings Gengobe to the room, however, Gengobe does not know what to do and just says: &quot;I don&apos;t care whether you are becoming his wife or whether you are becoming his mistress.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>これに対し、小万は三五郎の指図で源五兵衛の脇差を取り自害しようとする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this, Koman takes Gengobei&apos;s short sword and tries to kill herself with it, corresponding to Sangoro&apos;s direction.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hearing his answer, Koman, by Sangoro&apos;s direction, takes Gengobe&apos;s short sword and tries to commit suicide.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hearing his answer, Koman, by Sangoro&apos;s direction, takes Gengobe&apos;s short sword and tries to commit suicide.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>困り果てた源五兵衛は、身請けすると言って、伯父の用立ててくれた百両を差し出すことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Being at a complete loss, Gengobei proffers the 100 ryo prepared by his uncle, saying that he will buy the freedom of Koman&apos;s geisha status.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Being at a complete loss, Gengobe offers the 100 ryo prepared by his uncle, saying that he will buy out Koman.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Being at a complete loss, Gengobe offers the 100 ryo prepared by his uncle, saying that he will buy out Koman.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="73">
<j>ここに、八右衛門に案内された伯父の助右衛門が入ってくる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then Sukeyemon, the uncle, enters the room, being guided by Hachiemon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then Gengobe&apos;s uncle Sukeemon enters the room guided by Hachiemon.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then Gengobe&apos;s uncle Sukeemon enters the room guided by Hachiemon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>助右衛門は源五兵衛の放埓を責めた上で、伯父の縁を切ると言い渡して去っていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sukeyemon accuses Gengobei&apos;s immorality, and goes out of the room, declaring that he will cut his connection as an uncle with Gengobei</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sukeemon accuses Gengobe of such immoral behavior, and declaring that he has done with his nephew, Sukeemon leaves.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sukeemon accuses Gengobe of such immoral behavior, and declaring that he has done with his nephew, Sukeemon leaves.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="75">
<j>亡君の仇討ちの一味に加わる望みを絶たれた源五兵衛は小万を女房として連れて帰ろうとする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gengobei, who has lost his hope of being included in the group for revenging for their former clan head., tries to bring back Koman as his wife.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gengobe, who lost his hope of joining the group of the avengers for their ex-master, is about to bring back Koman as his wife.</e>
<cmt>訳語を統一します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gengobe, who lost his hope of joining the group of the avengers for their ex-master, is about to bring back Koman as his wife.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>しかし、三五郎は小万は自分の女房だと明かし、これまでのことは源五兵衛から百両を巻き上げるための作り話だと言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Sangoro discloses that Koman has actually been his wife and that what has occurred until now was a fabricated story to cheat Gengobei of the 100 ryo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Sangoro confesses that Koman is his wife and that the whole things are their lies to cheat Gengobe out of 100 ryo.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Sangoro confesses that Koman is his wife and that the whole things are their lies to cheat Gengobe out of 100 ryo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>逆上した源五兵衛は三五郎を斬ろうとするが、八右衛門に止められる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a frenzy, Gengobei tries to kill Sangoro, but Hachiemon stops it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Driven into frenzy, Gengobe pulls out his sword to kill Sangoro, however Hachiemon stops him.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Driven into frenzy, Gengobe pulls out his sword to kill Sangoro, however Hachiemon stops him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>これで開き直った三五郎は、源五兵衛を間男と口汚くののしるので、今度は八右衛門が飛びかかろうとするが、源五兵衛はこれを宥めて帰っていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then Sangoro, becoming defiant suddenly, abuses Gengoebei saying that he is a lover of his wife, and now Hachiemon tries to jump him, but Gengobei appeases him and goes out of the room.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then Sangoro turns to bay and sharply accuses Gengoebe of having tried to steal his wife, then Hachiemon is about to jump on him and Gengobe stops him, and eventually the two just leave.</e>
<cmt>誤訳です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then Sangoro turns to bay and sharply accuses Gengoebe of having tried to steal his wife, then Hachiemon is about to jump on him and Gengobe stops him, and eventually the two just leave.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>二幕目 第二場 五人切の場</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The second part, the second scene: the scene of cutting five persons down</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Act Ⅱ, Scene 2: The scene of Gonin-giri</e>
<cmt>スタイルを統一します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Act Ⅱ, Scene 2: The scene of Gonin-giri</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="79">
<j>源五兵衛から三五郎が百両を巻き上げるのを手助けした者たちが内びん虎蔵の家に集まっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The persons who helped Sangoro to cheat Gegobei of 100 ryo gather at the house of Torazo, Uchibin (内びん).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The people who helped Sangoro to cheat Gegobe of 100 ryo is gathering at Naibin Torazo&apos;s house.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れを補います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The people who helped Sangoro to cheat Gegobe of 100 ryo is gathering at Naibin Torazo&apos;s house.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>菊野は源五兵衛を気の毒がり、小万も気がとがめている様子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kikuno appears to feel pity for Gengobe and Koman also appears to feel guilty for the situation.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kikuno appears to feel pity for Gengobe and Koman also appears to feel guilty for the situation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kikuno appears to feel pity for Gengobe and Koman also appears to feel guilty for the situation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>しかし、三五郎は計略の成功に気をよくして小万の腕の彫り物に「三」の一字を加えて「三五大切」に変えて悦に入っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Sangoro, who feels good for the success of his strategy, is complacent about the tattoo on Koman&apos;s arm that has now become&quot;三五大切&quot; (sango taisetsu in pronunciation) by adding &quot;三&quot; (san in pronunciation) to the former one.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Sangoro feels good for the success of his trick and changes Koman&apos;s tattoo to &apos;Sango-taisetsu三五大切&apos; (literally, &apos;Sango, precious;&apos; &apos;sango三五&apos; sounds like Sangoro三五郎&apos;s nickname) by adding &apos;San三&apos; to the former one, and he watches her smugly.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Sangoro feels good for the success of his trick and changes Koman&apos;s tattoo to &apos;Sango-taisetsu三五大切&apos; (literally, &apos;Sango, precious;&apos; &apos;sango三五&apos; sounds like Sangoro三五郎&apos;s nickname) by adding &apos;San三&apos; to the former one, and he watches her smugly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="82">
<j>夜も更けて皆が寝入ると、丸窓を破って源五兵衛が忍び入り、まず伊之助と菊野を、三五郎と小万と思い込み殺害する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a deep night when all people has fallen to sleep, Gengobei secretly enters the house breaking the round window, and killed Inosuke and kikuno firstly, considering that they are Sangoro and Koman.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is getting late and all the people goes to bed, then Gengobe breaks a round window to sneak into the house; he first kills Inosuke and Kikuno mistaking for Sangoro and Koman.</e>
<cmt>誤訳です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is getting late and all the people goes to bed, then Gengobe breaks a round window to sneak into the house; he first kills Inosuke and Kikuno mistaking for Sangoro and Koman.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>すぐに間違いに気づくが、次々に寝ている者たちを殺していく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He notices his mistake immediately, and continues killing the sleeping persons one after another.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although he notices his mistake immediately, he continues killing the sleeping persons one after another.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although he notices his mistake immediately, he continues killing the sleeping persons one after another.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>物音に気づいて目を覚ました三五郎と小万は難を逃れるが、その場に来合わせた幸八を含め五人を斬り殺す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sangoro and Koman who wake at a sound can escape, but Gengobei cut five persons, including Kohachi who happens to have come there, down.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sangoro and Koman wake at the sound and escape, however Gengobe keeps swinging his sword; at a result he murdered five people including Kohachi who happened to come to the sight.</e>
<cmt>文法ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sangoro and Koman wake at the sound and escape, however Gengobe keeps swinging his sword; at a result he murdered five people including Kohachi who happened to come to the sight.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>大詰 第一場 四谷鬼横町の場</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The final part, the first scene: the scene of Yotsuya Oniyoko-cho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Finale, Scene 1: The scene of Yotsuya Oni-yokocho</e>
<cmt>スタイルを統一します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Finale, Scene 1: The scene of Yotsuya Oni-yokocho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="85">
<j>四谷鬼横町の長屋では、昨日引っ越してきたばかりの八右衛門が引っ越しをするというので、長屋の人々が引きとめている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At a nagaya in Yotsuya Oniyoko-cho, where Hachiemon moved in just yesterday, he is trying to move to another place and persons at the nagaya are preventing him from leaving.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the row house in Yotsuya Oni-yokocho, the residents are stopping Hachiemon who is saying he will move to another place although he just moved in the house yesterday.</e>
<cmt>文法ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the row house in Yotsuya Oni-yokocho, the residents are stopping Hachiemon who is saying he will move to another place although he just moved in the house yesterday.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>八右衛門が一日で引っ越すのは、前夜に幽霊を見たためであるという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hachiemon says that he is going to move because he saw a ghost last night.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hachiemon says that because he saw a ghost last night he has to move out although staying only one night.</e>
<cmt>文法ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hachiemon says that because he saw a ghost last night he has to move out although staying only one night.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>家主のくり廻しの弥助は、この家に塩冶浪人の神谷伊右衛門が住んでいたことがあり、殺害された妻のお岩の幽霊が出るのだと話す（『東海道四谷怪談』の設定）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The yanushi (landlord), Kurimawari no Yasuke, tells that once Iyemon KAMIYA, a ronin from the Enya clan, lived in this house and a ghost of Oiwa, his wife who was killed, appears (a setting based on &quot;Tokaido Yotsuya Kaidan (Tokaido Yotsuya Ghost Stories)).&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The landlord, Kurimawashi no Yasuke tells that once Iemon KAMIYA, a ronin and ex-retainer of the Enya family, lived in this house and the ghost of his wife who was murdered appears (this setting was based on &quot;Tokaido Yotsuya Kaidan&quot;).</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The landlord, Kurimawashi no Yasuke tells that once Iemon KAMIYA, a ronin and ex-retainer of the Enya family, lived in this house and the ghost of his wife who was murdered appears (this setting was based on &quot;Tokaido Yotsuya Kaidan&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>弥助の話に八右衛門は一刻も早く出て行こうとする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hearing the story told by Yanosuke, Hachiemon tries to leave the house immediately.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hearing Yanosuke&apos;s story, Hachiemon thinks he should leave the house more immediately.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hearing Yanosuke&apos;s story, Hachiemon thinks he should leave the house more immediately.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>しかしながら、弥助は半日住めば家賃をもらうと言い、互いに言い争う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Yasuke insists that the person who has lived there for more than half a day must pay the rent, and they squabble with each other.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Yasuke insists that the resident has to pay for even half a day and they have a squabble.</e>
<cmt>文法ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Yasuke insists that the resident has to pay for even half a day and they have a squabble.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>そこに、番小屋の番人の太郎七が新しい店子が見つかったことを知らせに来る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then Taroshichi, a guard at the sentry box comes to the place to inform Yasuke that the persons who want to rent a room have appeared.</e>
<cmt>太郎七：　正しい読み不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then Taroshichi, a guard at a sentry box, comes to inform Yasuke that there is a man who is looking for a room.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then Taroshichi, a guard at a sentry box, comes to inform Yasuke that there is a man who is looking for a room.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>八右衛門は新しい店子に幽霊のことを話すと言い立てると、弥助も引き下がり、樽代を半分返すことで話がつく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Hachiemona insists that he will tell the new tenants about the ghost, Yasuke backs down and comes to terms with the condition that Yasuke returns half of tarudai (the money to be paid in moving in, instead of sake).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hachiemon threatens that he will tell the new tenants about the ghost, so Yasuke backs down and comes to terms with the condition that Yasuke returns half of tarudai (money that a new tenant pays when moving in as a gift conforming to a old custom).</e>
<cmt>「樽代」の説明として大事なのは（酒代という名のもとで行われる）日本ならではの奇妙なgiftということです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hachiemon threatens that he will tell the new tenants about the ghost, so Yasuke backs down and comes to terms with the condition that Yasuke returns half of tarudai (money that a new tenant pays when moving in as a gift conforming to a old custom).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="92">
<j>太郎七に案内されてきた新しい店子は、三五郎と小万。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The new tenants having come guided by Taroshichi are Sangoro and Koman.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The new tenants Taroshichi brought are Sangoro and Koman.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The new tenants Taroshichi brought are Sangoro and Koman.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>二人の間に生まれた子供と、その里親のおくろを伴っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are accompanied by their child and Okuro, the foster mother of the child.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They brought their child and Okuro, the foster mother of the child.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They brought their child and Okuro, the foster mother of the child.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>弥助と挨拶を交わすところで、小万と弥助は妹と兄であることが分かって驚く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In exchanging greetings with Yasuke, they are astonished to find that Yasuke is Koman&apos;s brother.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Introducing themselves, they are astonished to find that Yasuke is Koman&apos;s brother.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Introducing themselves, they are astonished to find that Yasuke is Koman&apos;s brother.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>これを聞いた三五郎は、女房の兄なら自分の兄と、改めて弥助に挨拶し、家に落ち着くこととなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Knowing the situation, Sangoro exchanged greetings with Yasuke saying that a brother of his wife is his brother as well, and becomes to live in the house.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Knowing that, Sangoro says that his wife&apos;s brother is his brother and bows down to Yasuke, then the family decides to stay in Yasuke&apos;s row house.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Knowing that, Sangoro says that his wife&apos;s brother is his brother and bows down to Yasuke, then the family decides to stay in Yasuke&apos;s row house.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="96">
<j>そこにお岩稲荷建立の幟を手にした出家、了心が門口に立つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then Ryoshin, a priest, stands at the door of the house with a banner for building an Oiwa-inari shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then a priest Ryoshin comes to the gate with a banner for building Oiwa-inari shrine.</e>
<cmt>「立つ」は来ること。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then a priest Ryoshin comes to the gate with a banner for building Oiwa-inari shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>了心は三五郎の父、徳右衛門が出家した姿で、三五郎はさっそく源五兵衛から巻き上げた百両を父に渡す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryoshin is actually Tokuemon, Sangoro&apos;s father, who has become a priest, and Sangoro hands over to his father the 100 ryo that he cheated Gengobei of.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryoshin&apos;s real name is Tokuemon; he is Sangoro&apos;s father who became a priest; seeing him, Sangoro comes out and hands his father the 100 ryo that he took from Gengobe.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryoshin&apos;s real name is Tokuemon; he is Sangoro&apos;s father who became a priest; seeing him, Sangoro comes out and hands his father the 100 ryo that he took from Gengobe.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>金子を受け取った了心は三五郎の勘当を許し、旧主へ百両を渡すために出かけていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Receiving the money, Ryoshin releases the disowned state of Sangoro, and goes to hand over the money to his former master.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Receiving the money, Ryoshin forgives Sangoro whom he disowned, and goes to offer the money to his former master.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Receiving the money, Ryoshin forgives Sangoro whom he disowned, and goes to offer the money to his former master.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="99">
<j>そのようなところに、三五郎夫婦がこの辺りに引っ越したことを突き止めた源五兵衛が訪ねてくる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In such a situation, Gengobei finds where Sangoro and his wife have moved and visits the house.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then Gengobe, who found out the area Sangoro and his wife have moved to, comes to the house.</e>
<cmt>誤訳です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then Gengobe, who found out the area Sangoro and his wife have moved to, comes to the house.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>三五郎と小万は自分たちを殺しに来たとおびえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sangoro and Koman are scared of that he might come to kill them.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thinking that he wants to kill them, Sangoro and Koman are scared.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thinking that he wants to kill them, Sangoro and Koman are scared.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>しかし、源五兵衛は穏やかに、今までの行きがかりを捨て今後は兄弟同然に付き合って欲しいと持参した酒樽を渡す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Gengobei presents a sake barrel he has brought with, saying gently that he desires that both of them deal with him like their brother, forgetting the circumstances until then.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Gengobe gently asks them to forget the whole things which happened between them and to get along well from now on like brothers and sisters, and he offers a small sake barrel.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Gengobe gently asks them to forget the whole things which happened between them and to get along well from now on like brothers and sisters, and he offers a small sake barrel.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>そこで、三五郎は手元にあった酒で源五兵衛をもてなす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this, Sangoro entertains Gengobei with sake at hand.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then Sangoro takes out sake from his room and entertains Gengobe.</e>
<cmt>誤訳です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then Sangoro takes out sake from his room and entertains Gengobe.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>そこに、源五兵衛を五人切りの下手人として捕らえようと役人の出石宅兵衛がやってくる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then Takubei IZUSHI comes there to capture Gengobei as the murderer who cut five persons down.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time Officer Takube IZUSHI comes to arrest Gengobe on suspicion of the murder of five people.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time Officer Takube IZUSHI comes to arrest Gengobe on suspicion of the murder of five people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>源五兵衛は人違いとしらを切るが、宅兵衛は人殺しの場所に落ちていたと言って、証拠となる割り笄の片割れを取り出す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gegobei denies that he is the murderer, but Takubei produces a half part of the warikogai that constitutes an evidence, saying that it was at the place where the persons were killed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gegobe pretends not to know saying that he suspects a wrong person, however Takube takes out an evidence, a half of a wari-kogai which was collected from the murder site.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gegobe pretends not to know saying that he suspects a wrong person, however Takube takes out an evidence, a half of a wari-kogai which was collected from the murder site.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>この証拠に源五兵衛も言葉を失う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this evidence, Gengobe is left speechless.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this evidence, Gengobe is left speechless.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For this evidence, Gengobe is left speechless.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>しかしながら、傍らの番屋から八右衛門が飛び出し、渡されていた割り笄の片割れを差し出し、自分が五人切りの下手人だと名乗り出る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Hachibei dashes out of the nearby sentry box, and announces that he is the murderer who cut five persons down, showing that the half part of the warikogai having been handed over to him.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Hachibe dashes out of the nearby sentry box and announces that he is the murderer murdered the five people, showing the half of the wari-kogai that Gengobe handed him.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Hachibe dashes out of the nearby sentry box and announces that he is the murderer murdered the five people, showing the half of the wari-kogai that Gengobe handed him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>宅兵衛は八右衛門に縄を打って引き立てていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takube binds Hachibe with a rope and drags him away.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takube binds Hachibe with a rope and drags him away.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takube binds Hachibe with a rope and drags him away.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>これを見送った源五兵衛は、小万を思い切ったと言い捨てて去っていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seeing them off, Gengobei left the place, saying that he has abandoned Koman.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After seeing them leave, Gengobe leaves as well saying that he gives up Koman.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After seeing them leave, Gengobe leaves as well saying that he gives up Koman.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="109">
<j>三五郎と小万は、源五兵衛が自分たちに害を与えずに去ったことに安堵して、床に就いたところ、枕もとに幽霊が現れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Being relieved of not having been harmed by Gengobei, Sangoro and Koman goes to bed, and then a ghost appears.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Relieved that Gengobe did not do anything, Sangoro and Koman go to bed, and then a ghost appears at their bedside.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Relieved that Gengobe did not do anything, Sangoro and Koman go to bed, and then a ghost appears at their bedside.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>二人は恐れることなく幽霊を殴りかかり、幽霊の正体を家主の弥助と見破る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Not being fazed, both of them strike out the ghost fearlessly, and reveals that the ghost is actually Yasuke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They fearlessly jump at the ghost and hit it, then they find out the ghost was the landlord Yasuke.</e>
<cmt>二重訳になっています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They fearlessly jump at the ghost and hit it, then they find out the ghost was the landlord Yasuke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>弥助は幽霊に化けて店子を怯えさせ、樽代をとって店子を追い出して、稼いでいたことを白状する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasuke confesses that he has changed into a ghost to frighten his tenants so that he can gain tarudai by making them leave the house.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasuke confesses that he has been disguising himself as a ghost to frighten away his tenants so that he can gain tarudai.</e>
<cmt>二重訳になっています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasuke confesses that he has been disguising himself as a ghost to frighten away his tenants so that he can gain tarudai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>そのとき、三五郎が一枚の絵図面を見つける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, Sangoro finds a drawing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, Sangoro finds a drawing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, Sangoro finds a drawing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="113">
<j>この絵図面は以前住んでいた高野家に出入りの大工が持っていた高野家屋敷の絵図面だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is a drawing of the Kono family residence that a carpenter, who frequently worked for the Kono family, possessed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is the drawing of the residence of the Kono family and it must be a possession of the ex-resident, a carpenter working for the Kono family.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is the drawing of the residence of the Kono family and it must be a possession of the ex-resident, a carpenter working for the Kono family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="114">
<j>三五郎は塩冶浪人に見方する立場から、この絵図面を渡して欲しいと弥助に頼むが、弥助はこれを懐に入れてしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sangoro asks Yasuke to give him the drawing, from his standpoint of supporting ronin from the Enaya clan, but Yasuke places it into his pocket.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Sangoro sympathizes with the ex-retainers of the Enya family, he asks Yasuke to give him the drawing, however Yasuke ignores him and puts it into his pocket.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Sangoro sympathizes with the ex-retainers of the Enya family, he asks Yasuke to give him the drawing, however Yasuke ignores him and puts it into his pocket.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>そして、源五兵衛が持参した酒を飲み始める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then they start drinking the Gengobei has brought.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then Yasuke starts drinking the sake Gengobe brought.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then Yasuke starts drinking the sake Gengobe brought.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="116">
<j>杯を重ねるうちに、酔った弥助が袖をまくると、その腕の彫り物から弥助が塩冶家の御用金を盗んだ盗賊と知れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Yasuke rolls up his sleeve while they drink cup after cup of sake, it is known from the tattoo on his arm that Yasuke is the bandit who stole the goyokin of the Enya family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasuke gets drunk on the sake and tucks up his sleeves, then Sangoro sees the tattoo on Yasuke&apos;s arm and notices that Yasuke was the thief who stole the goyokin of the Enya family.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasuke gets drunk on the sake and tucks up his sleeves, then Sangoro sees the tattoo on Yasuke&apos;s arm and notices that Yasuke was the thief who stole the goyokin of the Enya family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="117">
<j>昔の悪事を弥助は開き直って、絵図面を高野家へ届けると言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Assuming a defiant attitude for the crime in the past, Yasuke says that he will bring the drawing to the Kono family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Accused of his past crime, Yasuke becomes defiant and says that he will deliver the drawing to the Kono family.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Accused of his past crime, Yasuke becomes defiant and says that he will deliver the drawing to the Kono family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="118">
<j>しかし、そのうちに血を吐いて苦しみだす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in a while, he vomits blood and starts agonizing.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in a while, he vomits blood and starts agonizing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in a while, he vomits blood and starts agonizing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="119">
<j>弥助が酒樽を割ると、中から毒蜥蜴が出てきて、源五兵衛が持ってきた酒は毒酒であったのだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Yasuke breaks the sake barrel, a poisonous lizard appears from it, showing that the sake Gengobei brought was actually poisonous.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Yasuke breaks the sake barrel, a poisonous lizard appears from it, showing that the sake Gengobe brought was, in fact, deadly poisonous alcohol.</e>
<cmt>用語を統一します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Yasuke breaks the sake barrel, a poisonous lizard appears from it, showing that the sake Gengobe brought was, in fact, deadly poisonous alcohol.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="120">
<j>苦しむ弥助を三五郎は出刃包丁で殺害し、高野家屋敷の絵図面を小万に、父の了心へ届けるようにと言って自害しようとする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sangoro kills the agonizing Yasuke with a cleaver, says to Koman that she should bring the drawing of the Kono family residence to Ryoshin, his father, and then tries to kill himself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Yasuke keep suffering greatly, Sangoro kills him with a kitchen knife, and tries to commit suicide persuading Koman to deliver the drawing of the residence of the Kono family to his father Ryoshin.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Yasuke keep suffering greatly, Sangoro kills him with a kitchen knife, and tries to commit suicide persuading Koman to deliver the drawing of the residence of the Kono family to his father Ryoshin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="121">
<j>これを小万が止めようとしているところに、了心が戻ってきて旧主が三五郎に会って礼を言うと伝える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Koman is trying to stop it, Ryoshin returns and tells that his former master will come to see Sangoro to return thanks.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Koman is trying to stop him, Ryoshin comes back and tells them that his former master wants to thank them directly for preparing the money.</e>
<cmt>誤訳です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Koman is trying to stop him, Ryoshin comes back and tells them that his former master wants to thank them directly for preparing the money.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="122">
<j>三五郎から絵図面を渡され、事情を聞いた了心は、出刃包丁を用心のために持たせた三五郎を四斗樽に中に身を忍ばせて、自分の寺へと運んでいく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Being handed over the drawing by Sangoro and hearing the situation, Ryoshin places Sangoro into a shitodaru (a big barrel) and brings the barrel to his temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sangoro hands Ryoshin the drawing and explains what happened to them, then Ryoshin let his son have the kitchen knife for caution and hides him in a shitodaru (a big barrel), and he carries it to his temple.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sangoro hands Ryoshin the drawing and explains what happened to them, then Ryoshin let his son have the kitchen knife for caution and hides him in a shitodaru (a big barrel), and he carries it to his temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="123">
<j>了心が去ると、毒酒を三五郎と小万が飲んだかを確かめるために、源五兵衛が再びやって来る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Ryoshin leaves the place, Gengobei comes again to check whether Sangoro and Koman have drunk the poisonous sake.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Ryoshin leaves, Gengobe comes again to check whether Sangoro and Koma already drank the poisonous sake.</e>
<cmt>訳語を統一させます。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Ryoshin leaves, Gengobe comes again to check whether Sangoro and Koma already drank the poisonous sake.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="124">
<j>源五兵衛は一間の内に三五郎と小万の赤子がいるのに気づき、赤子を抱いて出てくる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a room, Gengobei finds an infant born between Sangoro and Koman, and comes out of the room holding the infant in his arms.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In a room, Gengobe finds an infant Koman bore Sangoro; he lifts the infant in his arms and comes out of the room.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In a room, Gengobe finds an infant Koman bore Sangoro; he lifts the infant in his arms and comes out of the room.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="125">
<j>小万の腕を掴み上げると、そこには「三五大切」の彫り物があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When gripping and raising Koman&apos;s arm, he finds that tattoo of &quot;三五大切.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seeing Koman, he instantly grips her arm, and notices her tattoo changed to &apos;Sango-taisetsu三五大切.&apos;</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seeing Koman, he instantly grips her arm, and notices her tattoo changed to &apos;Sango-taisetsu三五大切.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="126">
<j>これを見た源五兵衛に猛然と殺意の炎が燃え上がる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When he sees the tattoo, his desire to kill her becomes very strong.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When he sees the tattoo, a wild desire to kill her comes over him.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When he sees the tattoo, a wild desire to kill her comes over him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="127">
<j>ただならぬ気配に小万が逃げようとすると、源五兵衛は斬りかかる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Feeling an unusual atmosphere, Koman tries to escape, but Gengobei attacks her with his sword.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sensing danger approaching, Koman tries to run away, and Gengobe slashes at her with his sword.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sensing danger approaching, Koman tries to run away, and Gengobe slashes at her with his sword.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="128">
<j>小万が、せめて子供の命だけでも助けて欲しいと懇願すると、小万の手を刀に添えさせて、その刀で赤子の体を突き刺す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Koman entreats him not at the very least to kill the child, he makes koman hold the sword as well and stabs the infant with the sword,.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Koman desperately asks him just not to kill her baby, he grips her hands and makes her hold the sword with him to stab the infant to death.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Koman desperately asks him just not to kill her baby, he grips her hands and makes her hold the sword with him to stab the infant to death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="129">
<j>また赤子に乳をあげていたおくろも殺してしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then he also kills Okuro who has given her breast to the infant.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then he also kills Okuro who has been giving the breast to the infant for Koman.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then he also kills Okuro who has been giving the breast to the infant for Koman.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="130">
<j>小万は「お前は鬼じゃ、鬼じゃわいなぁ」と泣き叫ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koman cries saying that &quot;You are an ogre, must be an ogre.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koman cries saying that &quot;You are an ogre, must be an ogre.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koman cries saying that &quot;You are an ogre, must be an ogre.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="131">
<j>源五兵衛は「いかにも鬼じゃ、みどもを鬼には、おのれら二人がいたしたぞ」と答え、小万を斬り殺してしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gengobei responds to this, saying that &quot;Yes, I am an ogre, the ogre that the two of you have created,&quot; and cuts Koman down.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gengobe responds: &quot;Yes, I am an ogre, the ogre that the two of you created,&quot; and he slashes Koman to death.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gengobe responds: &quot;Yes, I am an ogre, the ogre that the two of you created,&quot; and he slashes Koman to death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="132">
<j>そして、首を打ち落として懐に入れ、雨の振る中、悠々と長屋を後にするのだった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then he places her cut-down head into his robe, and leaves the nagaya in the rain calmly.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then he cuts her head off and puts it into his robes, and composedly leaves the row house in the rain.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then he cuts her head off and puts it into his robes, and composedly leaves the row house in the rain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>大詰 第二場 愛染院門前の場</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The final part, the second scene: the scene in front of the Aizenin-mon gate</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Finale, Scene 2: the scene of Aizenin-mon-mae</e>
<cmt>スタイルを統一します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Finale, Scene 2: the scene of Aizenin-mon-mae</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="133">
<j>隠れ住む愛染院の庵室に源五兵衛は、小万の首を前に食事をする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gengobei is having a meal in front of the Koman&apos;s head in the hermitage in the Aizen-in temple where he lives secretly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gengobe is having dinner in front of Koman&apos;s head in the hermitage in Aizenin Temple where he lives secretly.</e>
<cmt>訳語を統一します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gengobe is having dinner in front of Koman&apos;s head in the hermitage in Aizenin Temple where he lives secretly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="134">
<j>しかし、怒りがおさまらず女の首に茶をぶっかける。（このくだりは並木五瓶「五大力」のパロデイ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, with his anger not subsiding, he throws tea over the head.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However he cannot restrain his anger, so douses tea over the head (this scene is the parody of &quot;Godairiki&quot; by Gohei NAMIKI).</e>
<cmt>オリジナルの括弧をはりかえます。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However he cannot restrain his anger, so douses tea over the head (this scene is the parody of &quot;Godairiki&quot; by Gohei NAMIKI).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="135">
<j>そこへ了心がやってくる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(This scene is a parody of &quot;Godairiki&quot; by Gohei NAMIKI. Then, Ryoshin comes there.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then Ryoshin comes to the room.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then Ryoshin comes to the room.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="136">
<j>実は三五郎の父である了心の旧主は、源五兵衛、すなわち不破数右衛門であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Actually, the former master of Ryoshin, the father of Sangoro, is Gengobei, or Kazuemon FUWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The former master of Sangoro&apos;s father Ryoshin is, in fact, Gengobe, Kazuemon FUWA&apos;s disguise.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The former master of Sangoro&apos;s father Ryoshin is, in fact, Gengobe, Kazuemon FUWA&apos;s disguise.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="137">
<j>源五兵衛は、了心からすでに受け取っていた百両に加えて、絵図面を受け取り驚く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Receiving the drawing in addition to the 100 ryo that has been handed over by Ryoshin to him, Gengobei is astonished.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryoshin already gave Gengobe 100 ryo and now he offers an important drawing, so Gengobe is very surprised.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryoshin already gave Gengobe 100 ryo and now he offers an important drawing, so Gengobe is very surprised.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="138">
<j>了心に、百両と絵図面を大星由良之介に届けるように頼み、自分の犯した罪を打ち明け、もはや仇討ちに加わることは出来ないので、自害しようとする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He asks Ryoshin to bring the 100 ryo and the drawing to Yuranosuke OBOSHI, discloses his crime, and tries to kill himself because he could not be included to the members for the revenge.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He asks Ryoshin to deliver the 100 ryo and the drawing to Yuranosuke OBOSHI (the ex-leader of the retainers of the Enya family and the leader of the avengers) and confesses his crimes, then saying he no longer hope to join the avengers, he tries to commit suicide.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He asks Ryoshin to deliver the 100 ryo and the drawing to Yuranosuke OBOSHI (the ex-leader of the retainers of the Enya family and the leader of the avengers) and confesses his crimes, then saying he no longer hope to join the avengers, he tries to commit suicide.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="139">
<j>了心はこの話を聞いて、源五兵衛の身代わりにとなって死のうと決意した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hearing what Gengobei has told, Ryoshin has determined that he should kill himself instead of Gengobei.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hearing Gengobe&apos;s confession, Ryoshin decides to die for taking all the blame and saving Gengobe.</e>
<cmt>「身代わり」の説明を加えます。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hearing Gengobe&apos;s confession, Ryoshin decides to die for taking all the blame and saving Gengobe.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="140">
<j>そのとき、傍らの四斗樽から声がして箍が外れると、出刃包丁を腹に突き刺した三五郎が出てきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, voice is heard from inside the shitodaru that has been placed nearby, and then its hoops are broken and Sangoro comes out of it with his abdomen stabbed with a cleaver.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, a voice comes from the shitodaru that Ryoshin put nearby, and its hoops are broken, then Sangoro comes out with the kitchen knife stabbed in his stomach.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, a voice comes from the shitodaru that Ryoshin put nearby, and its hoops are broken, then Sangoro comes out with the kitchen knife stabbed in his stomach.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="141">
<j>お互いの素性も顔も知らぬ故に、主筋と知らず源五兵衛から金を騙し取ったと悔やむ三五郎は、源五兵衛の犯した罪も全て引き受けると言って、源五兵衛に仇討ちに加わるようにと願い出る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Repenting having cheated Gegobei of money because they had no knowledge about their backgrounds and faces with each other and therefore because he did not know that Gengobei was in the line leading to the master, Sangoro requests Gengobei to participate in the revenge, saying that he will shoulder all crimes Gengobei committed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He says he is sorry that they were hiding their real backgrounds and real faces and that without knowing he should have served Gengobe from the beginning, he cheated him out of money; besides he says he will die taking the blame for all the crimes and asks Gengobe to join the avengers.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He says he is sorry that they were hiding their real backgrounds and real faces and that without knowing he should have served Gengobe from the beginning, he cheated him out of money; besides he says he will die taking the blame for all the crimes and asks Gengobe to join the avengers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="142">
<j>ここに、鬼横町の長屋に住む店子に身をやつしていた塩冶浪士の面々が、仇討ちの準備万端調ったと、源五兵衛を迎えに来る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Here, the roshi (master-less samurais) from the former Enya clan who have disguised themselves as tenants of nagaya houses in Oniyoko-cho call for Gengobei, saying that all preparations for the revenge have now been complete.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, the ex-retainers of the Enya family, who have been in row houses in Oni-yokocho disguising themselves, come to tell Gengobe that they finished all the preparation for the vengeance against their master&apos;s enemy and they allow him join in.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, the ex-retainers of the Enya family, who have been in row houses in Oni-yokocho disguising themselves, come to tell Gengobe that they finished all the preparation for the vengeance against their master&apos;s enemy and they allow him join in.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="143">
<j>これを訴え出ようとする太郎七を、三五郎が斬り、源五兵衛は数右衛門となって高野屋敷へと向かって行く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sangoro cuts down Taroshichi who has tried to give the information to the police, and Gengobei goes for the Kono family residence as Kazuemon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taroshichi hears their conversation and tries to run to the police, then Sangoro notices him and kills him; Kazuemon sheds his disguise as Gengobe and leaves for the residence of the Kono family.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taroshichi hears their conversation and tries to run to the police, then Sangoro notices him and kills him; Kazuemon sheds his disguise as Gengobe and leaves for the residence of the Kono family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>初演当時の時代背景</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Historical backdrops at the time when this performance was played for the first time</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Backdrop for Producing the Play</e>
<cmt>後段の内容から判断してわかりやすくします。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Backdrop for Producing the Play</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="144">
<j>並木五瓶の『五大力恋緘』は、寛政7年（1795年）1月に江戸の都座で初演されており、上方の猟奇的な事件に題材に取りながら、登場人物の心情を細やかに表現して大当たりを取った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Godairiki Koi no Fujime&quot; written by Gohei NAMIKI was played for the first time in February - March, 1795, at the Miyako-za theater in Edo, and hit the jackpot, because it expressed feelings of the characters elaborately, although the theme was centered on a bizarre incident in Kamigata (the Kyoto-Osaka area).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Godairiki Koi no Fujime&quot; written by Gohei NAMIKI was first performed played in January, 1795 (in old lunar calendar) at the Miyako-za Theater in Edo, and succeeded phenomenally because based on a real brutal murders in Kamigata (Kansai region), it depicted the characters&apos; feelings elaborately.</e>
<cmt>誤訳があります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Godairiki Koi no Fujime&quot; written by Gohei NAMIKI was first performed played in January, 1795 (in old lunar calendar) at the Miyako-za Theater in Edo, and succeeded phenomenally because based on a real brutal murders in Kamigata (Kansai region), it depicted the characters&apos; feelings elaborately.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="145">
<j>この作品には、若き南北も五枚目の戯作者として上演に参加したと言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that young Nanboku also participated in the play as a popular writer, whose name was written on the gomaime (fifth) advertising display board.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that young Nanboku also participated in the play as a writer of popular stories, whose name was written in the fifth line (the fifth most important) of the advertisement board.</e>
<cmt>二重訳があります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that young Nanboku also participated in the play as a writer of popular stories, whose name was written in the fifth line (the fifth most important) of the advertisement board.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="146">
<j>それから30年後、南北、71歳のとき、最も精力的に活躍した時代に、名作と名高かった『五大力恋緘』に『仮名手本忠臣蔵』、『東海道四谷怪談』を混ぜ合わせた作品として書いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 30 years after that, the 71-year old Nanboku, in his most productive era, wrote this play by mixing elements of &quot;Kanadehon Chushingura&quot; and of &quot;Tokaido Yotsuya Kaidan&quot; into &quot;Godairiki Koi no Fujime&quot; that was famous as a masterpiece.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thirty years after that, at the age of 71 Nanboku entered his most productive era and wrote this play by mixing elements of &quot;Kanadehon Chushingura&quot; and of &quot;Tokaido Yotsuya Kaidan&quot; into &quot;Godairiki Koi no Fujime&quot; that had been already famous as a masterpiece.</e>
<cmt>用語の表記を統一させます。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thirty years after that, at the age of 71 Nanboku entered his most productive era and wrote this play by mixing elements of &quot;Kanadehon Chushingura&quot; and of &quot;Tokaido Yotsuya Kaidan&quot; into &quot;Godairiki Koi no Fujime&quot; that had been already famous as a masterpiece.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="147">
<j>特に自身の名作『東海道四谷怪談』は、2ヶ月前に初演され大当たりを取っており、大きくこの作品にも影響を与えたと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In particular, &quot;Tokaido Yotsuya Kaidan,&quot; one of his masterpieces that was performed for the first time two months before, hit the jackpot, and it is considered that the situation affected this play considerably.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of his masterpieces &quot;Tokaido Yotsuya Kaidan&quot; had been first performed two months before and succeeded particularly well, therefore it is considered that the success of the play affected the production of the new play considerably.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of his masterpieces &quot;Tokaido Yotsuya Kaidan&quot; had been first performed two months before and succeeded particularly well, therefore it is considered that the success of the play affected the production of the new play considerably.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>現代の評価</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Evaluations in the present day</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Evaluations in the present day</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Evaluations in the present day</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="148">
<j>傑作ながらも不当に低く評価されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though being a masterpiece, this play was evaluated unreasonably lowly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although being a masterpiece, this play had been evaluated unreasonably lowly.</e>
<cmt>時制を直します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although being a masterpiece, this play had been evaluated unreasonably lowly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="149">
<j>まず、初演時に内容が暗すぎるのと菊五郎の退座もあり評判が悪かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">First, it was evaluated lowly when performed for the first time, for the reason that the story was too gloomy and because Kikugoro left the theater.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the beginning, people did not like it because the story was too gloomy and even their favorite actor Kikugoro left the theater.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the beginning, people did not like it because the story was too gloomy and even their favorite actor Kikugoro left the theater.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="150">
<j>9月25日初日がわずか3週間後の10月14日に打ち切られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The performance of the play started on September 25, but was terminated on October 14, only in three weeks after it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The performance of the play started on September 25, and only three weeks later, on October 14 it was terminated.</e>
<cmt>文法ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The performance of the play started on September 25, and only three weeks later, on October 14 it was terminated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="151">
<j>そのため長らく上演されなかったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, the play was not performed for a long period of time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, this play had not been performed for many years.</e>
<cmt>時制を直します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, this play had not been performed for many years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="152">
<j>大正時代に澤田正二郎が上演したり、戦後新劇が演じたりするくらいであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following were only occasions this play was performed: Shojiro SAWADA brought it on a stage in the Taisho period and the shingeki (literally, new play) group performed it after the war.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Occasionally, in the Taisho period Shojiro SAWADA presented it, and after World War Ⅱ some company of Shingeki (modern play) performed it.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Occasionally, in the Taisho period Shojiro SAWADA presented it, and after World War Ⅱ some company of Shingeki (modern play) performed it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="153">
<j>歌舞伎関係者の上演は郡司正勝の補綴、演出と尾上辰之助 (初代)の源五兵衛・片岡仁左衛門 (15代目)の三五郎・坂東玉三郎 (5代目)の小万の配役によって復活されるまで、長く絶えていたようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It appears that, in the Kabuki world, this play was not performed until the new version, revised and supplemented by Masakatsu GUNJI, was performed again with the characters of Tatsunosuke ONOE (the first) for Gengobei, of Nizaemon KATAOKA (the 15th) for Sangoro and of Tamasaburo BANDO (the fifth) for Koman.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for the performance by the Kabuki actors, it appears that this play had not been performed until the new version was produced; the new version was supplemented and directed by Masakatsu GUNJI, and Tatsunosuke ONOE (the first) played Gengobe, Ninzaemon KATAOKA (the fifteenth) played Sangoro, and Tamasaburo BANDO (the fifth) played Koman.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for the performance by the Kabuki actors, it appears that this play had not been performed until the new version was produced; the new version was supplemented and directed by Masakatsu GUNJI, and Tatsunosuke ONOE (the first) played Gengobe, Ninzaemon KATAOKA (the fifteenth) played Sangoro, and Tamasaburo BANDO (the fifth) played Koman.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="154">
<j>深川の無頼者たちを仲間にする三五郎が、父の旧主の困窮のために人を騙すのに対して、結局のところ痴情によって多数の人を斬り殺す源五兵衛が、最終的には数右衛門に戻って晴れて義士の列に加わる点において、不条理な身分の違いを、暗に、しかし強烈に、南北は皮肉っているとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that, in the following points, Nanboku satirized, indirectly but strongly, unreasonable situations due to differences in social statuses: Sangoro, a member of a ruffian group in Fukagawa, cheated a person for a financial difficulty in his father&apos;s master, while Gengobei, who cut many persons down due to a foolish passion, could return to Kazuemon and could participate in the loyal samurai group ultimately</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Nanboku satirized the unreasonable hierarchical society indirectly and severely by depicting the outcomes of main two characters&apos; lives; although Sangoro is just a ruffian of the common people&apos;s town Fukagawa, he cheats a person to save his father&apos;s ex-master who has been in difficulties; however, although Gengobe murders many people by passions, at last he sheds his disguise and as real himself Kazuemon, joins the group of the loyal samurai with no shame.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Nanboku satirized the unreasonable hierarchical society indirectly and severely by depicting the outcomes of main two characters&apos; lives; although Sangoro is just a ruffian of the common people&apos;s town Fukagawa, he cheats a person to save his father&apos;s ex-master who has been in difficulties; however, although Gengobe murders many people by passions, at last he sheds his disguise and as real himself Kazuemon, joins the group of the loyal samurai with no shame.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>初演時の配役</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Actors in the first-time performance of the play</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Actors in the opening</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Actors in the opening</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="155">
<j>薩摩源五兵衛実は不破数右衛門・家主弥助実は神谷下郎土手平・・・松本幸四郎 (5代目)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gengobei SATSUMA, actually Kazuemon FUWA and Yasuke, the yanushi, actually Dotehei KAMIYASHIRO: Koshiro MATSUMOTO (the fifth)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gengobe SATSUMA (in fact Kazuemon FUWA), Yanushi Yasuke (in fact a servant of the Kamiya family Dotehei): Koshiro MATSUMOTO (the fifth)</e>
<cmt>誤訳があります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gengobe SATSUMA (in fact Kazuemon FUWA), Yanushi Yasuke (in fact a servant of the Kamiya family Dotehei): Koshiro MATSUMOTO (the fifth)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="156">
<j>船頭笹野屋三五郎実は了心倅千太郎・・・・市川團十郎 (7代目)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koshiro MATSUMOTO, a sendo, actually Sentaro, a son of Ryoshin: Danjuro ICHIKAWA (the seventh)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sendo, Sangoro SASANOYA (in fact a son of Ryoshin, Sentaro): Danjuro ICHIKAWA (the seventh)</e>
<cmt>誤訳があります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sendo, Sangoro SASANOYA (in fact a son of Ryoshin, Sentaro): Danjuro ICHIKAWA (the seventh)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="157">
<j>芸者小万実は神谷下女お六・・・・・岩井半四郎 (6代目)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koman, a geisha, actually Oroku, a maid servant at the Kamiya family: Hanshiro IWAI (the sixth)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Geisha Koman (in fact a servant of the Kamiya family, Oroku): Hanshiro IWAI (the sixth)</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Geisha Koman (in fact a servant of the Kamiya family, Oroku): Hanshiro IWAI (the sixth)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="158">
<j>了心・・・・市川宗三郎</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryoshin: Sozaburo ICHIKAWA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryoshin: Sozaburo ICHIKAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryoshin: Sozaburo ICHIKAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="159">
<j>おくろ・・・鎌倉平九郎</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Okuro: Heikuro KAMAKURA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Okuro: Heikuro KAMAKURA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Okuro: Heikuro KAMAKURA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 白拍子花子(id:244805), BoB774(id:148281), Hermes(id:21387), R28Bot(id:177951), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>