<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>尺八</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shakuhachi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shakuhachi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shakuhachi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>尺八（しゃくはち）は日本の伝統的な楽器。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The shakuhachi is a traditional Japanese musical instrument.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shakuhachi is a traditional Japanese musical instrument.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The shakuhachi is a traditional Japanese musical instrument.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>木管楽器の一種である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a type of woodwind instrument.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a type of woodwind instrument.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a type of woodwind instrument.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>リード (楽器)しないエアリード楽器に分類される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It falls under the category of reed instruments, and is classified as an &quot;air reed&quot; instrument.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It falls under the category of reed instruments, and is classified as an &quot;air reed&quot; instrument.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It falls under the category of reed instruments, and is classified as an &quot;air reed&quot; instrument.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>中国の唐を起源とし、日本に伝来したが、その後空白期間を経て、鎌倉時代から江戸時代ごろに現在のかたちの祖形が成立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It oeiginated in China during the Tang Dynasty, and was transmitted to Japan during that period; however, it subsequently fell out of use for a period of approximately 2-3 centuries before reemerging during the Kamakura Period, and has been used continuosly since, evolving during the Edo period into the precurssor of its current form.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It oeiginated in China during the Tang Dynasty, and was transmitted to Japan during that period; however, it subsequently fell out of use for a period of approximately 2-3 centuries before reemerging during the Kamakura Period, and has been used continuosly since, evolving during the Edo period into the precurssor of its current form.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It originated in China during the Tang Dynasty, and was transmitted to Japan during that period; however, it subsequently fell out of use for a certain period before reemerging during the Kamakura period, and has been used continuously since, evolving during the Edo period into the precursor of its current form.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。2-3 centuries を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>尺八の名は、標準の管長が一尺八寸（約54.5cm）であることに由来する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The origin of the name shakuhachi is derived from a traditional standardized measure of length, consiting of units expressed in terms of one &quot;shaku&quot; and eight &quot;sun&quot; (or 1.8 shaku, which is approximately 54.5 cm).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The origin of the name shakuhachi is derived from a traditional standardized measure of length, consiting of units expressed in terms of one &quot;shaku&quot; and eight &quot;sun&quot; (or 1.8 shaku, which is approximately 54.5 cm).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The origin of the name shakuhachi is derived from a traditional standardized measure of length, consisting of units expressed in terms of one &quot;shaku&quot; and eight &quot;sun&quot; (or 1.8 shaku, which is approximately 54.5 cm).</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>語源に関する有力な説は、『旧唐書』列伝の「呂才伝」の記事によるもので、7世紀はじめの唐の楽人である呂才が、筒音を十二律にあわせた立笛を作った際、中国の標準音の黄鐘（日本の十二律では壱越西洋音階のD）の音を出すものが一尺八寸であったためと伝えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The most widely accepted theory of the etymological origin of the word itself traces its appearance to the Tang Dynasty text titled &quot;Teachings of &quot;, which was written in the 7th century by Tang musician, and describes a vertical flute tuned to a 12 tone scale, with the tonic being the Tang standard tone of (according to the 12-tone Japanese scale, the equivalent of the tone D on the scale of the West); the dimension at which this tonic was obtained is said to have been one shaku and eight sun, thus the name &apos;shakuhachi&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The most widely accepted theory of the etymological origin of the word itself traces its appearance to the Tang Dynasty text titled &quot;Teachings of &quot;, which was written in the 7th century by Tang musician, and describes a vertical flute tuned to a 12 tone scale, with the tonic being the Tang standard tone of (according to the 12-tone Japanese scale, the equivalent of the tone D on the scale of the West); the dimension at which this tonic was obtained is said to have been one shaku and eight sun, thus the name &apos;shakuhachi&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The most widely accepted theory of the etymological origin of the word itself traces its appearance to the text in &apos;Biography of Lucun&apos; in the series of &quot;Jiu Tang Shu&quot; (Old Tang History), which describes that Lucun, a Tang musician who lived in the early seventh century, created a vertical flute tuned to a 12 tone scale, with the Oshikicho tone being the Tang standard tone (according to the 12-tone Japanese scale, the equivalent of the tone D on the scale of the West); the dimension at which this tonic was obtained is said to have been one shaku and eight sun, thus the name &apos;shakuhachi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>翻訳を追加しました。「呂才伝」→&apos;Biography of Lucun としました。(正しい読み方が分からず、このファイルでも呂才をLucunと表記しているため）。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>演奏者のあいだでは単に竹とも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amongst players, the shakuhachi is sometimes referred to simply as &quot;bamboo&quot; (&quot;ta-ke&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amongst players, the shakuhachi is sometimes referred to simply as &quot;bamboo&quot; (&quot;ta-ke&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amongst players, the shakuhachi is sometimes referred to simply as &quot;bamboo&quot; (&quot;ta-ke&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>英語ではあるいは、とも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In English and other languages this term has also been adopted.</e>
<cmt>somewhat unclear</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In English and other languages this term has also been adopted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In English and other languages it is called shakuhachi or bamboo flute.</e>
<cmt>原文wikiを参照し、左記のようにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>マダケの根元を使い、7個の竹の節を含むようにして作るものが一般的である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The rootend of the &quot;madake&quot; bamboo plant is used, and the shakuhachi is generallay crafted so as to include seven nodes of the bamboo from the rootend upward.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The rootend of the &quot;madake&quot; bamboo plant is used, and the shakuhachi is generallay crafted so as to include seven nodes of the bamboo from the rootend upward.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The rootend of the &quot;madake&quot; bamboo plant is used, and the shakuhachi is generally crafted so as to include seven nodes of the bamboo from the rootend upward.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>上部のマウスピース (楽器)歌口に息を吹きつけて音を出す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The blowing edge (or &quot;utaguchi&quot;) is located at the upper end of the shakuhachi, and a player directs a stream of breath at this blowing edge to cause sound to be emitted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The blowing edge (or &quot;utaguchi&quot;) is located at the upper end of the shakuhachi, and a player directs a stream of breath at this blowing edge to cause sound to be emitted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The blowing edge (or &quot;utaguchi&quot;) is located at the upper end of the shakuhachi, and a player directs a stream of breath at this blowing edge to cause sound to be emitted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>一般的に音孔は前面に4つ、背面に1つある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Generally speaking, the layout of the tone holes is four on the front face and one on the rear face of the bamboo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Generally speaking, the layout of the tone holes is four on the front face and one on the rear face of the bamboo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Generally speaking, the layout of the tone holes is four on the front face and one on the rear face of the bamboo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>尺八に似た楽器として、西洋のフルートや南アメリカのケーナがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Instruements from other countries resembling the shakuhachi include the Western flute, the South American quena, and the ney, which is played in countries including Turkey, Iran, and Egypt.</e>
<cmt>added the ney, as some think that the first vertical flute was developed in that region and transmitted east…</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Instruements from other countries resembling the shakuhachi include the Western flute, the South American quena, and the ney, which is played in countries including Turkey, Iran, and Egypt.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Instruments from other countries resembling the shakuhachi include the Western flute and the South American quena.</e>
<cmt>原文にない部分を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>これらは、フィップル（ブロック）を持たないエアリード楽器である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These instruments are all air reed instruments that do not use a fipple (block).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These instruments are all air reed instruments that do not use a fipple (block).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These instruments are all air reed instruments that do not use a fipple (block).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>起源と雅楽尺八</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Origins and the gagaku shakuhachi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Origins and the gagaku shakuhachi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Origins and the gagaku shakuhachi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="14">
<j>尺八の起源として有力な説は、前述した『旧唐書』列伝の「呂才伝」の記事によるもので、唐初期の貞観 (唐)年間（627年 - 649年）に呂才(600年 - 665年）が考案したというものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The most widely accepted theory of the origins of the shakuhachi accords with the a depiction found in the aforementioned Tand dynasty document &quot;Jiu Tang Shu&quot; (Old Tang History) relating to the accomplishments of an individual named Lucun (呂才, Japanese: Ryosai), which records that Lucun (600-665 C.E.) designed the shakuhachi in the first stage Jyogan era (Tang dynasty China).</e>
<cmt>highlighted text unclear</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The most widely accepted theory of the origins of the shakuhachi accords with the a depiction found in the aforementioned Tand dynasty document &quot;Jiu Tang Shu&quot; (Old Tang History) relating to the accomplishments of an individual named Lucun (呂才, Japanese: Ryosai), which records that Lucun (600-665 C.E.) designed the shakuhachi in the first stage Jyogan era (Tang dynasty China).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The most widely accepted theory of the origins of the shakuhachi accords with the a depiction found in the aforementioned &apos;Biography of Lucun&apos; of the Tang dynasty document &quot;Jiu Tang Shu,&quot; which records that Lucun (呂才, Japanese: Ryosai; 600 - 665) designed the shakuhachi in the first stage Jogan era (Tang dynasty China) (627 - 649).</e>
<cmt>一部翻訳を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="15">
<j>日本には雅楽楽器として、7世紀末から8世紀はじめに伝来した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The shakuhachi was first transmitted to Japan sometime around the end of the 7th century to the beginning of the 8th century as an instrument used in the preformance of gagaku (court music of a type developed in Tang dynasty China).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shakuhachi was first transmitted to Japan sometime around the end of the 7th century to the beginning of the 8th century as an instrument used in the preformance of gagaku (court music of a type developed in Tang dynasty China).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The shakuhachi was first transmitted to Japan sometime around the end of the seventh century to the beginning of the eighth century as an instrument used in the performance of gagaku (court music of a type developed in Tang dynasty China).</e>
<cmt>数字をスペルアウトしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>東大寺の正倉院には六孔三節の尺八が八管収められている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Shousou-in repository of the treasures from the Toudai-ji Temple in Nara stores eight examples of shakuhachi from this period, each of which has six tone holes and three nodes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Shousou-in repository of the treasures from the Toudai-ji Temple in Nara stores eight examples of shakuhachi from this period, each of which has six tone holes and three nodes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Shoso-in Treasure Repository from the Todai-ji Temple in Nara stores eight examples of shakuhachi from this period, each of which has six tone holes and three nodes.</e>
<cmt>Toda-ji, Shoso-in としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="17">
<j>その後中国では、歌口の傾斜が管の外側にあるタイプの縦笛は断絶し、日本でも雅楽の楽器としての尺八は使われなくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later years in China saw this type of vertical flute with the blowing edge formed cut outward from the uppermost end of the bamboo disappear, and the shakuachi also cesaed to be used as a gagaku instrument in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later years in China saw this type of vertical flute with the blowing edge formed cut outward from the uppermost end of the bamboo disappear, and the shakuachi also cesaed to be used as a gagaku instrument in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later years in China saw this type of vertical flute with the blowing edge formed cut outward from the uppermost end of the bamboo disappear, and the shakuhachi also ceased to be used as a gagaku instrument in Japan.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>一節切と薦僧の時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The era of the komoso and hitoyogiri</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The era of the komoso and hitoyogiri</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The era of the hitoyogiri and komoso</e>
<cmt>順番を変更しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="18">
<j>歴史上の空白期間ののち、鎌倉時代になると一節切（ひとよぎり）と呼ばれる縦笛があらわれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the period of history in which there is no record of the shakuhachi, a vertical flute called the hitoyogiri (literally, &quot;one node cut&quot;) appeared in the Kamakura Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the period of history in which there is no record of the shakuhachi, a vertical flute called the hitoyogiri (literally, &quot;one node cut&quot;) appeared in the Kamakura Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the period of history in which there is no record of the shakuhachi, a vertical flute called the hitoyogiri (literally, &quot;one node cut&quot;) appeared in the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>period 小文字としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>これは、五孔一節で真竹の中間部を用いたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The hitoyogiri was a five hole, one-node vertical flute fashioned from the center section of the madake bamboo plant.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The hitoyogiri was a five hole, one-node vertical flute fashioned from the center section of the madake bamboo plant.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The hitoyogiri was a five hole, one-node vertical flute fashioned from the center section of the madake bamboo plant.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>田楽法師などの遊芸人の中にこれを吹いて物乞いをする集団が現れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bands of travelleling entertainers, formed by people such as priest-like dressed Dengaku performers, who would beg for alms playing the hitpyogiri appeared.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bands of travelleling entertainers, formed by people such as priest-like dressed Dengaku performers, who would beg for alms playing the hitpyogiri appeared.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bands of traveling entertainers, formed by people such as priest-like dressed Dengaku performers, who would beg for alms playing the hitoyogiri appeared.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>薦僧と呼ばれる集団がそれで、後に普化宗と結びつき虚無僧となっていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Medicant ascetics called komoso (literally, &quot;straw mat monk&quot;) formed, and subsequently established a connection with Fuke-shu (a form of Zen related to the Rinzai sect), becoming the komuso (literally, &quot;monks of empty nothingness&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Medicant ascetics called komoso (literally, &quot;straw mat monk&quot;) formed, and subsequently established a connection with Fuke-shu (a form of Zen related to the Rinzai sect), becoming the komuso (literally, &quot;monks of empty nothingness&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mendicant ascetics called komoso (literally, &quot;straw mat monk&quot;) formed, and subsequently established a connection with Fuke sect of Zen Buddhism (a form of Zen related to the Rinzai sect), becoming the komuso (literally, &quot;monks of empty nothingness&quot;).</e>
<cmt>Fuke sect of Zen Buddhism としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="22">
<j>一節切は、室町時代に中国から日本に渡った禅僧・蘆安がもたらしたもので、名手といわれた大森宗勲（1570年 - 1625年）が出たのち、急速に広まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The hitoyogiri was brought to Japan during the muromachi Period by a foreigner named Roan, and Zen monks from China; after Sokun OMORI emerged and became a famous for playing the hitoyogiri, the instrument&apos;s popularity spread rapidly.</e>
<cmt>what is the slash between Zen monks/Roan to signify?</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The hitoyogiri was brought to Japan during the muromachi Period by a foreigner named Roan, and Zen monks from China; after Sokun OMORI emerged and became a famous for playing the hitoyogiri, the instrument&apos;s popularity spread rapidly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The hitoyogiri was brought to Japan during the Muromachi period by a Zen priest named Roan from China; after Sokun OMORI (1570 - 1625) emerged and became a famous for playing the hitoyogiri, the instrument&apos;s popularity spread rapidly.</e>
<cmt>period 小文字としました。生没年　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>一節切は17世紀後半に全盛を迎えたが、その後急速に衰退した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The hitoyogiri reached the height of its popularity during the later half of the 17th century; however, it rapidly fell out of favor thereafter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The hitoyogiri reached the height of its popularity during the later half of the 17th century; however, it rapidly fell out of favor thereafter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The hitoyogiri reached the height of its popularity during the later half of the 17th century; however, it rapidly fell out of favor thereafter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>普化尺八</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fukeshu shakuhachi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fukeshu shakuhachi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fuke shakuhachi</e>
<cmt>Fuke としました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="24">
<j>江戸時代は尺八は法器として普化宗に属する虚無僧のみが演奏するものとされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Edo Period the shakuhachi was recognized as a Buddhist religious implement used for transmitting the Dharma, and only the Fukeshu komuso were permitted to play the shakuachi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Edo Period the shakuhachi was recognized as a Buddhist religious implement used for transmitting the Dharma, and only the Fukeshu komuso were permitted to play the shakuachi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Edo period the shakuhachi was recognized as a Buddhist religious implement used for transmitting the Dharma, and only the komuso of Fuke sect were permitted to play the shakuhachi.</e>
<cmt>period 小文字としました。Fuke sect としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>建前上は一般の者は吹いてはならなかったが、実際には尺八をたしなむ者はいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Officially, it was prohibited for the general public to play the shakuachi; in actuality, however, there were people who enjoyed playing the shakuhachi as a passtime.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Officially, it was prohibited for the general public to play the shakuachi; in actuality, however, there were people who enjoyed playing the shakuhachi as a passtime.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Officially, it was prohibited for the general public to play the shakuhachi; in actuality, however, there were people who enjoyed playing the shakuhachi as a pastime.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>明治時代以降には、普化宗が廃止されたことにより虚無僧以外の者も演奏するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the onset of the Meiji Period, the Fukeshu sect of Zen Buddhism was abollished, and from that point onward the shakuhachi was permitted to be played by people who were not komuso.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the onset of the Meiji Period, the Fukeshu sect of Zen Buddhism was abollished, and from that point onward the shakuhachi was permitted to be played by people who were not komuso.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the onset of the Meiji period, the Fuke sect was abolished, and from that point onward the shakuhachi was permitted to be played by people who were not komuso.</e>
<cmt>period 小文字としました。Fuke sect としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>普化宗の廃止から新日本音楽まで</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the abolishment of Fukeshu to the appearance of so-called new Japanese music (Shin Ｎihon Ongaku).</e>
<cmt>not sure if it should be Nihon or Nippon</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the abolishment of Fukeshu to the appearance of so-called new Japanese music (Shin Ｎihon Ongaku).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the abolishment of Fuke sect to the appearance of so-called new Japanese music (Shin Nihon Ongaku)</e>
<cmt>Fuke sect としました。</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>現代音楽と尺八</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Modern music and the shakuachi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Modern music and the shakuachi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Modern music and the shakuhachi</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>音程の範囲と基本的な音階</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Range of the scale and basic tuning</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Range of the scale and basic tuning</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Range of the scale and basic tuning</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="27">
<j>基本的には2オクターブ強である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The range of the scale of the shakuhachi is basically two octaves.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The range of the scale of the shakuhachi is basically two octaves.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The range of the scale of the shakuhachi is basically a little over two octaves.</e>
<cmt>a little over を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>用いられる頻度は少ないが、倍音を用いてその上の約1オクターブの音を出すことができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, though infrequently used and generally only in more modern forms of shakuhachi music, overtones, which increase the range by approximately one octave, are sometimes used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, though infrequently used and generally only in more modern forms of shakuhachi music, overtones, which increase the range by approximately one octave, are sometimes used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, though infrequently used, overtones, which increase the range by approximately one octave, are sometimes used.</e>
<cmt>一部翻訳を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="29">
<j>シンプルな運指においては、陽音階や律音階となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rudimentary playing techniques produce the sounds of two anhemitonic pentatonic scales (pentatonic scales containing no semitones).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rudimentary playing techniques produce the sounds of two anhemitonic pentatonic scales (pentatonic scales containing no semitones).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rudimentary playing techniques produce the sounds of two anhemitonic pentatonic scales (pentatonic scales containing no semitones).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>基本的な運指において、西洋の12音音階すべての演奏が可能である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Basic playing techniques enable the production of all notes withing the western 12 tone scale.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Basic playing techniques enable the production of all notes withing the western 12 tone scale.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Basic playing techniques enable the production of all notes within the western 12 tone scale.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>楽器の構造</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Structure of the shakuachi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Structure of the shakuachi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Structure of the shakuhachi</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>物理的構造</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Physical structure of the shakuhachi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Physical structure of the shakuhachi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Physical structure of the shakuhachi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="31">
<j>現行の尺八は、真竹の根元を使用して作る五孔三節のものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The modern shakuachi is fashioned from the madake bamboo plant has five tone holes and three nodes of bamboo (with 7 joints, ideally), including the rootend.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The modern shakuachi is fashioned from the madake bamboo plant has five tone holes and three nodes of bamboo (with 7 joints, ideally), including the rootend.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The modern shakuhachi is fashioned from the madake bamboo plant and has five tone holes and three nodes of bamboo, including the rootend.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="32">
<j>古くは一本の竹を切断せずに延管（のべかん）を作っていたが、現在では一本の竹を中間部で上下に切断してジョイントできるように加工したものが主流である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In former times the shakuhachi was fashioned from a single piece of bamboo (referred to as a &quot;nobekan); however, at present the most widely used type of shakuachi is made by cutting the length of bamboo into upper and lower halves, and providing a joint between the two halves.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In former times the shakuhachi was fashioned from a single piece of bamboo (referred to as a &quot;nobekan); however, at present the most widely used type of shakuachi is made by cutting the length of bamboo into upper and lower halves, and providing a joint between the two halves.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In former times the shakuhachi was fashioned from a single piece of bamboo (referred to as a &quot;nobekan&quot;); however, at present the most widely used type of shakuhachi is made by cutting the length of bamboo into upper and lower halves, and providing a joint between the two halves.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>これは製造時に中の構造をより細密に調整できるとの理由からだが、結果として持ち運びにも便利になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The original intent of this development was to enable more fine tuning of the bore during the fabrication stage; however, it also has resulted in making the instrument more portable, making it more convenient to carry around than the nobekan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The original intent of this development was to enable more fine tuning of the bore during the fabrication stage; however, it also has resulted in making the instrument more portable, making it more convenient to carry around than the nobekan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The original intent of this development was to enable more fine tuning of the bore during the fabrication stage; however, it also has resulted in making the instrument more portable, making it more convenient to carry around.</e>
<cmt>一部翻訳を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="34">
<j>材質は真竹であるが、木製の木管尺八やプラスチックなどの合成樹脂でできた安価な尺八が開発され、おもに初心者の普及用などの用途で使用されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The primary material from which shakuhachi are fashioned is still madake bamboo; however, inexpensive shakuhachi made from wood, plastic and other synthetic materials have been developed, and are primarily aimed at improviong accessibilty to the instrument and targeted at beginning students.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The primary material from which shakuhachi are fashioned is still madake bamboo; however, inexpensive shakuhachi made from wood, plastic and other synthetic materials have been developed, and are primarily aimed at improviong accessibilty to the instrument and targeted at beginning students.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The primary material from which shakuhachi are fashioned is still madake bamboo; however, inexpensive shakuhachi made from wood, plastic and other synthetic materials such as plastic have been developed, and are primarily aimed at improving accessibility to the instrument and targeted at beginning students.</e>
<cmt>プラスチック　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="35">
<j>尺八の音色と材質は科学的には無関係とされているが、関係があるとする論争もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to scientific theory, the tone of the shakuhachi should not be dependent upon the material from which the instrument is made; however, there are people who disagree with that, and insist that the material does effect the tonal characteristics of hte instrument.</e>
<cmt>what scientific theory is this? I think that acoustics and the like recognize that different materials have different vibratory and resonatory characteristics that would affect tone.</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to scientific theory, the tone of the shakuhachi should not be dependent upon the material from which the instrument is made; however, there are people who disagree with that, and insist that the material does effect the tonal characteristics of hte instrument.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to scientific theory, the tone of the shakuhachi should not be dependent upon the material from which the instrument is made; however, there are people who disagree with that, and insist that the material does effect the tonal characteristics of the instrument.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="36">
<j>尺八の歌口は、外側に向かって傾斜がついている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The blowing edge of the shakuhachi is formed by cutting the upper end of the bamboo outward at an oblique angle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The blowing edge of the shakuhachi is formed by cutting the upper end of the bamboo outward at an oblique angle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The blowing edge of the shakuhachi is formed by cutting the upper end of the bamboo outward at an oblique angle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>現行の尺八には、歌口に、水牛の角・象牙・エボナイトなどの素材を埋め込んである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The blowing edge of shakuhachi produced today are usually reinforced with an embedded piece of water buffalo horn, ivory, ebonite, or the like.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The blowing edge of shakuhachi produced today are usually reinforced with an embedded piece of water buffalo horn, ivory, ebonite, or the like.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The blowing edge of shakuhachi produced today are usually reinforced with an embedded piece of water buffalo horn, ivory, ebonite, or the like.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="38">
<j>明治時代以降の西洋音楽の影響により、七孔、九孔の尺八が開発された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Being influenced by Western music after the onset of the Meiji period, shakuachi provided with seven, or even nine holes were developed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Being influenced by Western music after the onset of the Meiji period, shakuachi provided with seven, or even nine holes were developed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Being influenced by Western music after the onset of the Meiji period, shakuhachi provided with seven, or even nine holes were developed.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>このうち、七孔のものは、五孔の尺八に比べれば主流ではないものの使用されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In comparison to the widespread five-hole shakuachi, though the seven- and nine-hole shakuhachi are not widely used, there are people who use them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In comparison to the widespread five-hole shakuachi, though the seven- and nine-hole shakuhachi are not widely used, there are people who use them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In comparison to the widespread five-hole shakuhachi, though the seven-hole shakuhachi are not widely used, there are people who use them.</e>
<cmt>nine-hole を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>既存の五孔の尺八に孔を開けることでの改造が可能である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An already existing five-hole shakuachi can be modified into a seven- or nine-hole shakuachi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An already existing five-hole shakuachi can be modified into a seven- or nine-hole shakuachi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An already existing five-hole shakuhachi can be modified into a seven-hole shakuhachi.</e>
<cmt>七孔　について前文より触れていると考え、九孔については削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="41">
<j>現行の尺八の管の内部は、管の内側に残った節を削り取り、漆の地（じ）を塗り重ねることで管の内径を精密に調整する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Present day shakuachi are fabricated by removing all traces of the joints from the inside of the bamboo to produced a relatively smooth bore, and then coating the bore with layers of urushi-ji (a kind of workable plaster medium containing natural lacquer) to finely tune the bore.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Present day shakuachi are fabricated by removing all traces of the joints from the inside of the bamboo to produced a relatively smooth bore, and then coating the bore with layers of urushi-ji (a kind of workable plaster medium containing natural lacquer) to finely tune the bore.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Present day shakuhachi are fabricated by removing all traces of the joints from the inside of the bamboo to produce a relatively smooth bore, and then coating the bore with layers of urushi-ji (a kind of workable plaster medium containing natural lacquer) to finely tune the bore.</e>
<cmt>produce としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>これにより音が大きくなり、正確な音程が得られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By adjusting the thickness of the coating of urushi-ji within the bore, the pitch can be fine tuned, and the volume produced adjusted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By adjusting the thickness of the coating of urushi-ji within the bore, the pitch can be fine tuned, and the volume produced adjusted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This process allows the volume to increase and the pitch to be fine tuned.</e>
<cmt>翻訳を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="43">
<j>これに対し「古管」あるいは「地無し管」と呼ぶ古いタイプの尺八は、管の内側に節による突起を残し、漆地も塗らない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In contrast to shakuhachi fabricated using urushi-ji paste, the bore of older shakuachi called &quot;ko-kan&quot; (literally, &quot;antique shakuachi&quot;), or ji-nashi shakuhachi (literally, &quot;shakuachi without urushi-ji) are not coated with urushi-ji, and remnants of the joints often visible.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In contrast to shakuhachi fabricated using urushi-ji paste, the bore of older shakuachi called &quot;ko-kan&quot; (literally, &quot;antique shakuachi&quot;), or ji-nashi shakuhachi (literally, &quot;shakuachi without urushi-ji) are not coated with urushi-ji, and remnants of the joints often visible.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In contrast to the shakuhachi fabricated using the above method, the bore of older shakuhachi called &apos;ko-kan&apos; (literally, &quot;antique shakuhachi&quot;), or &apos;ji-nashi-kan&apos; (literally, &quot;shakuhachi without urushi-ji) are not coated with urushi-ji, and remnants of the joints often visible.</e>
<cmt>「上記の方法で作られた尺八に対し」、　という表現にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>正確な音程が得られないため、奏者が音程の補正をする必要がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because it is generally not possible to obtain an accurate tuning in shakuachi having a bore that has not been tuned using urushi-ji, the player must make adjustments for pitch irregularities while playing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because it is generally not possible to obtain an accurate tuning in shakuachi having a bore that has not been tuned using urushi-ji, the player must make adjustments for pitch irregularities while playing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because it is generally not possible to obtain an accurate tuning in the older shakuhachi as mentioned above, the player must make adjustments for pitch irregularities while playing.</e>
<cmt>「古いタイプの尺八では、」　とい表現に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>古典的な本曲の吹奏では、このひとつひとつの尺八のもつ個性もその魅力となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the perforance of early honkyoku compositions, the unique characteristics of each ko-kan or ji-nashi shakuachi can be attractive.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the perforance of early honkyoku compositions, the unique characteristics of each ko-kan or ji-nashi shakuachi can be attractive.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the performance of classic honkyoku (pieces originally composed and played with the shakuhachi), the unique characteristics of each ko-kan or ji-nashi-kan shakuhachi can be attractive.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。本曲　補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>筒音</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsutsune (tonic)</e>
<cmt>not sure of this reading, but it is definitely not つつのおと</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsutsune (tonic)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsutsune (tonic)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="46">
<j>尺八の手孔をすべて塞いだときの音を筒音と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The tsutsune (i.e., the tonic) is the tone produced when the shakuachi is played with all tone holes covered.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The tsutsune (i.e., the tonic) is the tone produced when the shakuachi is played with all tone holes covered.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The tsutsune (i.e., the tonic) is the tone produced when the shakuhachi is played with all tone holes covered.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>これはその尺八で出すことのできる最低音である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This represents the lowest basic tone that can be produced by the shakuachi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This represents the lowest basic tone that can be produced by the shakuachi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This represents the lowest basic tone that can be produced by the shakuhachi.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>標準の尺八は、日本の十二律で壱越（D4）の筒音を持つ一尺八寸管である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The standard shakuachi is the one-shaku eight-sun length shakuachi, and has a tsutsune of D4 according to the Japanese twelve note scale.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The standard shakuachi is the one-shaku eight-sun length shakuachi, and has a tsutsune of D4 according to the Japanese twelve note scale.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The standard shakuhachi is the one-shaku eight-sun length shakuhachi, and has a tsutsune of D4 according to the Japanese twelve note scale.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>次いで、春の海などで使用される一尺六寸管（筒音 E4）や、二尺四寸管（筒音 A3）などが使用される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, there are other lengths of shakuachi that are also used, inluding the one-shaku six-sun length shakuachi (tsutsune of E4), which is used to perform the piece &quot;Haru-no-umi&quot;, and the two-shaku four-sun length shakuachi (tsutsune A3).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, there are other lengths of shakuachi that are also used, inluding the one-shaku six-sun length shakuachi (tsutsune of E4), which is used to perform the piece &quot;Haru-no-umi&quot;, and the two-shaku four-sun length shakuachi (tsutsune A3).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, there are other lengths of shakuhachi that are also used, including the one-shaku six-sun length shakuhachi (tsutsune of E4), which is used to perform the piece &quot;Haru-no-umi&quot; (Spring Sea), and the two-shaku four-sun length shakuhachi (tsutsune A3).</e>
<cmt>春の海　補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>長さのバリエーションは、半音ぶんずつ寸刻みで一尺一寸管から二尺四寸管も存在するが、標準的なものにくらべ使用頻度ははるかにすくない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are also numerous other variations based on the length of the shakuachi, differing in half-tone intervals starting from one-shaku one-sun length to three-shaku length shakuachi; however, compared to the more standard lengths of shakuachi (1.6. 1.8, 1.9, and 2.0), shakuachi of these lengths are seldom used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are also numerous other variations based on the length of the shakuachi, differing in half-tone intervals starting from one-shaku one-sun length to three-shaku length shakuachi; however, compared to the more standard lengths of shakuachi (1.6. 1.8, 1.9, and 2.0), shakuachi of these lengths are seldom used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are also numerous other variations based on the length of the shakuhachi, differing in half-tone intervals starting from one-shaku one-sun length to two-shaku four-sun length shakuhachi; however, compared to the more standard lengths of shakuhachi, shakuhachi of these lengths are seldom used.</e>
<cmt>三尺→二尺四寸　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>奏法</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">How to play the shakuhachi</e>
<cmt>翻訳を追加しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="51">
<j>尺八はフルートと同じく、奏者が自らの口形（マウスピース (楽器)アンブシュア）によって吹き込む空気の束を調整しなければならない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same manner as with the flute, the shape into which a player forms his or her mouth (mouthpiece (instrument) embochure) must be used to the speed of the air stream blown into the shakuhachi.</e>
<cmt>Instead of &quot;(mouthpiece (instrument) embochure)&quot;, &quot;(embochure)&quot; might suffice.</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same manner as with the flute, the shape into which a player forms his or her mouth (mouthpiece (instrument) embochure) must be used to the speed of the air stream blown into the shakuhachi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same manner as with the flute, the shape into which a player forms his or her mouth (mouthpiece (instrument) embouchure) must be used to adjust to the speed of the air stream blown into the shakuhachi.</e>
<cmt>翻訳を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>リコーダー(いわゆる「縦笛」)はマウスピース (楽器)の構造（フィップル、ブロック）によって初心者でも簡単に音が出せるが、尺八・フルートで音を出すには熟練が必要である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The recorder (a so-called &quot;vertical flute&quot;) has a mouthpiece (instrument) constructed in the form of a fipple, block), which enables a beginner to produce a sound easily; however, to produce a sound on a shakuachi, it generally takes intensive practice.</e>
<cmt>縦笛 is not helpful here, as the recorder has a built in mouthpiece, and is not a &quot;blowing edge&quot; instrument like the shakuhachi or transverse flute.l</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The recorder (a so-called &quot;vertical flute&quot;) has a mouthpiece (instrument) constructed in the form of a fipple, block), which enables a beginner to produce a sound easily; however, to produce a sound on a shakuachi, it generally takes intensive practice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The recorder (a so-called &apos;vertical flute&apos;) has a structure (instrument) constructed in the form of a fipple, block, which enables a beginner to produce a sound easily; however, to produce a sound on a shakuhachi, it generally takes intensive practice.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>尺八は音孔（指孔）が5個しか存在しないため、都節音階、7音音階や12半音を出すために手孔を半開したり、メリ、カリと呼ばれる技法を多用する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because the shakuachi has only five tone holes (finer holes), in order to play the Miyako-bushi scale (a japanese scale), a seven-tone scale or a twelve-tone scale, it is necessary to use techiques referred to as &quot;meri&quot; and &quot;kari&quot;, involving the covering half of a tone hole and the adjusting of the angle of ones embochure, to produce sharp or flat tones.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because the shakuachi has only five tone holes (finer holes), in order to play the Miyako-bushi scale (a japanese scale), a seven-tone scale or a twelve-tone scale, it is necessary to use techiques referred to as &quot;meri&quot; and &quot;kari&quot;, involving the covering half of a tone hole and the adjusting of the angle of ones embochure, to produce sharp or flat tones.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because the shakuhachi has only five tone holes (finger holes), in order to play the Miyako-bushi scale (a Japanese scale), a seven-tone scale or a twelve-tone scale, it is necessary to use techniques referred to as &quot;meri&quot; and &quot;kari,&quot; involving the covering half of a tone hole and the adjusting of the angle of ones embouchure, to produce sharp or flat tones.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>唇と歌口の鋭角部（エッジ）との距離を変化させることで、音高（音程）を変化させる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By changing the distance between the lips and blowing edge of the utaguchi, the pitch (tone) can be caused to change.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By changing the distance between the lips and blowing edge of the utaguchi, the pitch (tone) can be caused to change.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By changing the distance between the lips and blowing edge of the utaguchi, the pitch (tone) can be caused to change.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>音高を下げることをメリ、上げることをカリと呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Lowering the pitch is called &quot;meri&quot;, and raising the pitch &quot;kari&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Lowering the pitch is called &quot;meri&quot;, and raising the pitch &quot;kari&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Lowering the pitch is called &quot;meri,&quot; and raising the pitch &quot;kari.&quot;</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置を移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>メリ、カリの範囲は開放管（指で手孔を押さえない）の状態に近いほど広くなり、メリでは最大で半音4個ぶん以上になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The range of meri-kari expands the closer to the state of being played open (i.e., with the fingers covering no tone holes), with the meri capable of extending to more than four half tones.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The range of meri-kari expands the closer to the state of being played open (i.e., with the fingers covering no tone holes), with the meri capable of extending to more than four half tones.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The range of meri-kari expands the closer to the state of being played open (i.e., with the fingers covering no tone holes), with the meri capable of extending to more than four half tones.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>通常の演奏に用いる範囲はメリで2半音、カリで1半音程度）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under normal playing conditions, meri is generally played with a scope of two half tones, and kari one half tone.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under normal playing conditions, meri is generally played with a scope of two half tones, and kari one half tone.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under normal playing conditions, meri is generally played with a scope of two half tones, and kari one half tone.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>奏者の動作としては楽器と下顎（下唇よりやや下）との接点を支点にして顎を引く（沈める）と「メリ」になり、顎を浮かせると「カリ」になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With respect to the movements the player, if the player pulls back and down (withdraws) the point on which the shakuhaci rests (point on the lower jaw between the chin and lower lip), a meri effect is produced, and if the player extends the lower jaw, a kari effect is produced.</e>
<cmt>maybe this can be deleted?（沈める）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With respect to the movements the player, if the player pulls back and down (withdraws) the point on which the shakuhaci rests (point on the lower jaw between the chin and lower lip), a meri effect is produced, and if the player extends the lower jaw, a kari effect is produced.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With respect to the movements of the player, if the player pulls back and down (withdraws) the point on which the shakuhachi rests (point on the lower jaw between the chin and lower lip), a meri effect is produced, and if the player extends the lower jaw, a kari effect is produced.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="59">
<j>メリ、カリ、つまり顎の上下動（縦ユリ）、あるいは首を横に振る動作（横ユリ）によって、一種のビブラートをかけることができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By repeatedly performing meri and kari in succession by withdrawing and extending the lower jaw (tate yuri), or by shaking the head gently from side to side (yoko yuri), a type of vibrato can be produced.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By repeatedly performing meri and kari in succession by withdrawing and extending the lower jaw (tate yuri), or by shaking the head gently from side to side (yoko yuri), a type of vibrato can be produced.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By repeatedly performing meri and kari in succession by withdrawing and extending the lower jaw (tate yuri), or by shaking the head gently from side to side (yoko yuri), a type of vibrato can be produced.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>この動作をユリ（ユリ、あごユリ）と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This type of technique is called yuri (or agoyuri).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This type of technique is called yuri (or agoyuri).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This type of technique is called yuri (or agoyuri).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>フルートなどの息の流量変化によるビブラートとは異なり、独特の艶を持つ奏法である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The yuri technique differs from the technique of varying the volume of breath used to produced vibrato with the flute, and produces a unique, alluring effect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The yuri technique differs from the technique of varying the volume of breath used to produced vibrato with the flute, and produces a unique, alluring effect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The yuri technique differs from the technique of varying the volume of breath used to produced vibrato with the flute, and produces a unique, alluring effect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>フルートと同じく息の流量変化によるビブラートも使用される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The technique of varying them volume of breath is also ued to produce vibrato with the shakuahci.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The technique of varying them volume of breath is also ued to produce vibrato with the shakuahci.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The technique of varying the volume of breath is also used to produce vibrato with the shakuhachi.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>息ユリと呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That technique is referred to as iki yuri (literally, &quot;breath yuri&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That technique is referred to as iki yuri (literally, &quot;breath yuri&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That technique is referred to as iki yuri (literally, &quot;breath yuri&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="64">
<j>手孔を、閉 - 半開 - 開 動作を滑らかに行い、さらに、メリ、カリを併用することにより、滑らかなポルタメントが可能である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By moving the fingers in a manner such as to smoothly transition between closed, half-open, and open states in combination with a meri/kari action, a smooth portamento can be produced.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By moving the fingers in a manner such as to smoothly transition between closed, half-open, and open states in combination with a meri/kari action, a smooth portamento can be produced.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By moving the fingers in a manner such as to smoothly transition between closed, half-open, and open states in combination with a meri/kari action, a smooth portamento can be produced.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>これをスリアゲ、スリサゲと呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is called suriage (rising tone) or surisage (descending tone).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is called suriage (rising tone) or surisage (descending tone).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is called suriage (rising tone) or surisage (descending tone).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>音高の上下を細かく繰り返すコロコロというものもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is also an effect called korkoro, which involves the repeated fine control of raising and lowering the pitch.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is also an effect called korkoro, which involves the repeated fine control of raising and lowering the pitch.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is also an effect called korokoro, which involves the repeated fine control of raising and lowering the pitch.</e>
<cmt>korokoro に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="67">
<j>口腔内の形状変化や流量変化等により、倍音構成はよく通る音色や丸く柔らかいものなど、適宜変化させることができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By varying the shape of the oral cavity, the volume of breath and the like, the tone can be modulated so as to produce tone colors traversing harmonic structures, soft tones, round tones and the like can be produced by modulation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By varying the shape of the oral cavity, the volume of breath and the like, the tone can be modulated so as to produce tone colors traversing harmonic structures, soft tones, round tones and the like can be produced by modulation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By varying the shape of the oral cavity, the volume of breath and the like, the tone can be modulated so as to produce tone colors traversing harmonic structures such as soft tones, round tones, and so on.</e>
<cmt>一部翻訳を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>尺八の流派と吹奏人口</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shakuhachi lineages and number of players</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shakuhachi lineages and number of players</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shakuhachi lineages and number of players</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="68">
<j>尺八の吹奏人口についての本格的な調査はされておらず、正確な人口は不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a full-scale survey of the number of shakuhaci players has not been caried out, the exact number is unnknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a full-scale survey of the number of shakuhaci players has not been caried out, the exact number is unnknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a full-scale survey of the number of shakuhachi players has not been carried out, the exact number is unknown.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>推定では3万人程度といわれている</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is estimated that there are 30,000 players.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is estimated that there are 30,000 players.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is estimated that there are 30,000 players.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>明暗諸流派</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The various Meian lineages</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The various Meian lineages</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The various Myoan lineages</e>
<cmt>Myoan　に修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="14">
<tit>
<j>琴古流</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kinko-ryu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kinko-ryu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kinko school</e>
<cmt>流→school としました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="70">
<j>琴古流は、江戸時代に初代黒沢琴古（1710年 - 1771年）によって創始された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kinko-ryu is a lineage was founded by Kurosawa KINKO the first (1710-1771), during the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kinko-ryu is a lineage was founded by Kurosawa KINKO the first (1710-1771), during the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kinko school is a lineage that was founded by Kinko KUROSAWA the first (1710 - 1771), during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>The Kinko school、Kinko KUROSAWA　に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>初代は俗名を幸八といい黒田藩の藩士であったが浪人となり、江戸へ出て一月寺、鈴法寺の吹合指南役となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Kurosawa KINKO 1st was a samurai retainer of Kuroda-han, whose name was originally Kohachi, who, having become a ronin, eventually made his way to Edo, where he came to be engaged in teaching the shakuachi at the fukiawase-dokoro (shakuachi teaching place) of Ichigetu-ji Temple and Reiho-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>expanded slightly</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Kurosawa KINKO 1st was a samurai retainer of Kuroda-han, whose name was originally Kohachi, who, having become a ronin, eventually made his way to Edo, where he came to be engaged in teaching the shakuachi at the fukiawase-dokoro (shakuachi teaching place) of Ichigetu-ji Temple and Reiho-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that he was a samurai retainer of Kuroda domain, whose name was originally Kohachi, who, having become a ronin (a masterless samurai), eventually made his way to Edo, where he came to be engaged in teaching the shakuhachi at the fukiawase-dokoro (&quot;fukiawase&quot; refers to a Zen related mode of instruction that is generally one-to-one, and in the case of shakuhachi involves the teacher and student playing a piece together while seated facing each other across sheet music, and &quot;dokoro&quot; simply means &quot;place&quot;) of Ichigetsu-ji Temple and Reiho-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>Kuroda domain　としました。浪人　の補足を追加しました。吹合所　の補足をこちらに移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>尺八曲の整理を行い、全36曲の琴古流本曲を制定した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He collected and arranged shakuachi pieces, compiling 36 pieces that form the Kinko-ru honkyoku (pieces originally composed and played with the shakuachi).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He collected and arranged shakuachi pieces, compiling 36 pieces that form the Kinko-ru honkyoku (pieces originally composed and played with the shakuachi).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He collected and arranged shakuhachi pieces, compiling 36 pieces that form the Kinko school honkyoku.</e>
<cmt>本曲　既出のため、補足を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>黒沢琴古の名は3代で途絶えたが、琴古流はその後、吉田一調、荒木古童らにより隆盛を築いていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kurosawa KINKO name was carried for three generations before disappearing; however, thereafter the Kinko-ryu continued to flourish and grow under the guidance of Itcho YOSHIDA, Kodo ARAKI and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kurosawa KINKO name was carried for three generations before disappearing; however, thereafter the Kinko-ryu continued to flourish and grow under the guidance of Itcho YOSHIDA, Kodo ARAKI and others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name of Kinko KUROSAWA was carried for three generations before disappearing; however, thereafter the Kinko school continued to flourish and grow under the guidance of Itcho YOSHIDA, Kodo ARAKI and others.</e>
<cmt>Kinko KUROSAWA　に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="74">
<j>琴古流は大小いくつもの組織の総体であり琴古流として統一した組織をもつものではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kinko-ryu is comprised of a number of large and small organizations that form the lineage, and is not a unified or monolithic organization.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kinko-ryu is comprised of a number of large and small organizations that form the lineage, and is not a unified or monolithic organization.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kinko school is comprised of a number of large and small organizations that form the lineage, and is not a unified or monolithic organization.</e>
<cmt>Kinko school としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="15">
<tit>
<j>都山流</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Tozan-ryu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Tozan-ryu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tozan school</e>
<cmt>Tozan school としました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="75">
<j>都山流は明治期に初代中尾都山が創始した流派であり、普化宗とは直接のつながりを持たない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Tozan-ryu is a lineage that was founded during the Meiji Period by first generation Tozan NAKAO, and is not directly connected to Fuke-shu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Tozan-ryu is a lineage that was founded during the Meiji Period by first generation Tozan NAKAO, and is not directly connected to Fuke-shu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tozan school is a lineage that was founded during the Meiji period by first generation Tozan NAKAO, and is not directly connected to Fuke sect.</e>
<cmt>Tozan school としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>宮城道雄と提携し、宮城作曲の尺八譜の公刊を独占したこと、評議員制の導入など中央集権的な組織作りを行ったことなど都山流は尺八界最大の組織となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By collaborating with Michio MIYAGI and coming to hold the exclusive rights to publishing shakuhachi notation for MIYAGI&apos;s compositions, introducing a council system and the like, Tozan Nakao established a centralized organization that grew to become the largest organization in the shakuachi world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By collaborating with Michio MIYAGI and coming to hold the exclusive rights to publishing shakuhachi notation for MIYAGI&apos;s compositions, introducing a council system and the like, Tozan Nakao established a centralized organization that grew to become the largest organization in the shakuachi world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By collaborating with Michio MIYAGI and coming to hold the exclusive rights to publishing shakuhachi notation for MIYAGI&apos;s compositions, introducing a council system and the like, Tozan NAKANO established a centralized organization that grew to become the largest organization in the shakuhachi world.</e>
<cmt>名字を大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="16">
<tit>
<j>上田流</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ueda-ryu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ueda-ryu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ueda school</e>
<cmt>ueda school としました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="77">
<j>上田流は、都山流を除名された上田芳童が1817年に創始した流派である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ueda-ryu is a lineage that was founded in 1917 by Hodo UEDA, who had been expelled from the Tozan-ryu.</e>
<cmt>1817年 should be 1917</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ueda-ryu is a lineage that was founded in 1917 by Hodo UEDA, who had been expelled from the Tozan-ryu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ueda school is a lineage that was founded in 1917 by Hodo UEDA, who had been expelled from the Tozan school.</e>
<cmt>ueda school としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>上田は、五線譜、7孔尺八などを導入し、尺八の近代化につとめた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Uada-ryu adopted the staff notation system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Uada-ryu adopted the staff notation system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ueda school adopted the staff notation system, seven-hole shakuhachi and the like, and worked to modernize the shakuhachi.</e>
<cmt>次セルの、「7孔尺八～」の文章とつながっていると解釈し、結合しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>また、長唄に多く手付けを行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, the Ueda-ryu also wrote shakuachi parts for many Nagauta pieces.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, the Ueda-ryu also wrote shakuachi parts for many Nagauta pieces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, the Ueda school also wrote shakuhachi parts for many nagauta (long epic song with shamisen [a three-stringed Japanese banjo] accompaniment) pieces.</e>
<cmt>長唄　の補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>五線譜の採用は途中で断念したものの、7孔尺八に関しては上田創案のものが現在でも使用されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the Ueda-ryu eventually abandoned five-line Western notation, the 7-hole shakuachi developed by the Ueda-ryu continues to be used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the Ueda-ryu eventually abandoned five-line Western notation, the 7-hole shakuachi developed by the Ueda-ryu continues to be used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the Ueda school eventually abandoned five-line Western notation, the seven-hole shakuhachi developed by the Ueda school continues to be used.</e>
<cmt>ueda school としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="81">
<j>現在は上田流尺八道と称している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At present, the name of the Ueda-ryu is the Ueda-ryu Way of Shakuhachi.</e>
<cmt>Official English version?</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At present, the name of the Ueda-ryu is the Ueda-ryu Way of Shakuhachi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At present, the name of the Ueda school calls themselves as &quot;Ueda-ryu Shakuhachi-do&quot; (Ueda school Way of Shakuhachi).</e>
<cmt>翻訳を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="17">
<tit>
<j>竹保流</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Chikuho-ryu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Chikuho-ryu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Chikuho school</e>
<cmt>Chikuho school としました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="82">
<j>竹保流は、酒井竹保が1817年に創始した流派である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Chkiuho-ryu is a lineage that was founded by Chikuho SAKAI in 1917.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Chkiuho-ryu is a lineage that was founded by Chikuho SAKAI in 1917.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Chikuho school is a lineage that was founded by Chikuho SAKAI in 1917.</e>
<cmt>Chikuho school としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>宗悦流の流れを汲み、譜にロツレチではなく、フホウエヤイを用いるフホウ譜を用いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taking up the influence of the Soetsu-ryu, the notation does not use the letters Ro, Tsu, Re and Chi, but Hu, Ho, U, Eh, Ya and Ee, which is referred to as the HuHoU system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taking up the influence of the Soetsu-ryu, the notation does not use the letters Ro, Tsu, Re and Chi, but Hu, Ho, U, Eh, Ya and Ee, which is referred to as the HuHoU system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taking up the influence of the Soetsu school, the notation does not use the letters Ro, Tsu, Re and Chi, but Hu, Ho, U, Eh, Ya and Ee, which is referred to as the HuHoU system.</e>
<cmt>Soetsu school としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="18">
<tit>
<j>その他の古典系流派</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other ancient lineages</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other ancient lineages</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other ancient lineages</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="19">
<tit>
<j>廃絶した流派</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Extinct lineages</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Extinct lineages</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Extinct lineages</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="20">
<tit>
<j>民謡系尺八</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Folk song shakuachi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Folk song shakuachi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Folk song shakuhachi</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="21">
<tit>
<j>楽曲</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shakuachi music</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shakuachi music</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shakuachi music</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="84">
<j>尺八で演奏される楽曲は多岐にわたっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are many types music played on the shakuachi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are many types music played on the shakuachi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are many types of music played on the shakuhachi.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>尺八の楽曲分類で大きなウエイトを占めるのは、本曲と外曲という対概念である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The most emphasis on distinguishing types of music played with the shakuchi falls on the genres called &quot;honkyoku&quot; and &quot;gaikyoku&quot;, which occupy opposite ends of the conceptual field..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The most emphasis on distinguishing types of music played with the shakuchi falls on the genres called &quot;honkyoku&quot; and &quot;gaikyoku&quot;, which occupy opposite ends of the conceptual field..</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The most emphasis on distinguishing types of music played with the shakuhachi falls on the genres called &quot;honkyoku&quot; and &quot;gaikyoku,&quot; which occupy opposite ends of the conceptual field.</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>本曲は、「その楽器のみによる楽器本来の楽曲」を意味し、外曲は、「他種目の旋律をその楽器用に編曲した楽曲」を意味する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term &apos;honkyoku&apos; means, &quot;music that was originally performed only on a specific instrument and which is the original music played on that instrument&quot;, whereas the term &apos;gaikyoku&apos; means, &quot;music of a different type of genre that has been arranged to be played on a specific instrument not originally used in that genre&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term &apos;honkyoku&apos; means, &quot;music that was originally performed only on a specific instrument and which is the original music played on that instrument&quot;, whereas the term &apos;gaikyoku&apos; means, &quot;music of a different type of genre that has been arranged to be played on a specific instrument not originally used in that genre&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term honkyoku means, &apos;music that was originally performed only on a specific instrument and which is the original music played on that instrument,&apos; whereas the term &quot;gaikyoku&quot; means, &apos;music of a different type of genre that has been arranged to be played on a specific instrument not originally used in that genre.&apos;</e>
<cmt>　&quot; →&apos; を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="22">
<tit>
<j>本曲</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Honkyoku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Honkyoku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Honkyoku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="87">
<j>もともとの本曲は、普化宗で吹禅に使われた曲を指していたが、1871年の普化宗廃止後は宗教音楽とは無縁な尺八のみの独奏曲や重奏曲も本曲と呼ばれるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term honkyokyu originally referred to the pieces that were practiced by adherents to the Fukeshu Zen sect; however, following the abolition of the Fukeshu Zen sect in 1871, the scope of meaning of the term expanded to include solo musical compositions unrelated to religion that were played on the shakuachi, and even compositions consiting of more than one part for the shakuachi came to be called honkyoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term honkyokyu originally referred to the pieces that were practiced by adherents to the Fukeshu Zen sect; however, following the abolition of the Fukeshu Zen sect in 1871, the scope of meaning of the term expanded to include solo musical compositions unrelated to religion that were played on the shakuachi, and even compositions consiting of more than one part for the shakuachi came to be called honkyoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term honkyoku originally referred to the pieces that were practiced by adherents to the Fuke sect; however, following the abolition of the Fuke sect in 1871, the scope of meaning of the term expanded to include solo musical compositions unrelated to religion that were played on the shakuhachi, and even compositions consisting of more than one part for the shakuhachi came to be called honkyoku.</e>
<cmt>Fuke sect としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>これらの比較的新しい本曲と普化宗で吹奏された狭義の本曲を区別するため、後者を特に古典本曲と呼ぶことがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order to maintain a disctinction between the honkyoku practiced by adherents of Fukeshu Zen and the more modern compositions that came to be referred to as honkyoku, the term &quot;kotenhonkyoku&quot; (literally, &quot;ancient honkyoku&quot;) came into use.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to maintain a disctinction between the honkyoku practiced by adherents of Fukeshu Zen and the more modern compositions that came to be referred to as honkyoku, the term &quot;kotenhonkyoku&quot; (literally, &quot;ancient honkyoku&quot;) came into use.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to maintain a distinction between the more modern compositions that came to be referred to as honkyoku and the honkyoku practiced by adherents of Fuke sect, the term &quot;koten-honkyoku&quot; (literally, &quot;ancient honkyoku&quot;) is sometimes used to refer to the latter.</e>
<cmt>後半に翻訳を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="23">
<tit>
<j>普化宗の本曲</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fukeshu honkyoku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fukeshu honkyoku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Honkyoku of Fuke sect</e>
<cmt>Fuke sect としました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="89">
<j>江戸時代に虚無僧が吹いた本曲は、琴古流本曲をふくめ、150曲あまりが伝承されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With respect to honkyoku played by the komuso (mendicant Fukeshu Zen monks) during the Edo Period, included those included in the repertoire of the Kinko-ryu, there are more than 150 pieces known to have been transmitted at present.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With respect to honkyoku played by the komuso (mendicant Fukeshu Zen monks) during the Edo Period, included those included in the repertoire of the Kinko-ryu, there are more than 150 pieces known to have been transmitted at present.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With respect to honkyoku played by the komuso (mendicant Fuke sect priest) during the Edo period, which included those in the repertoire of the Kinko school, there are more than 150 pieces known to have been transmitted at present.</e>
<cmt>一部翻訳を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>これらは宗教音楽として成立し、作者、作曲年代ともに基本的に不詳である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These pieces were brought into being and transmitted as part of a meditative religios practice, and generally speaking, the names of the composers and the dates of composition are unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These pieces were brought into being and transmitted as part of a meditative religios practice, and generally speaking, the names of the composers and the dates of composition are unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These pieces were brought into being and transmitted as part of a meditative religious practice, and generally speaking, the names of the composers and the dates of composition are unknown.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>弘前の根笹派錦風流、浜松の普大寺の流れをくむ名古屋の西園流、京都の明暗寺の明暗真法流と明暗対山流、博多一朝軒、越後明暗寺、東北地方の布袋軒、松巖軒などの伝承である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kinpu-Nezasa school of Hirosaki, the Saien school of Nagoya, which incorporates influences from the Fudai-ji Temple school of Hamamatsu, the Meian-Shinpo school of Kyoto&apos;s Meian-ji Temple as well as the Meian Taizan school, the Hakata Itchoken school, the Echigo Meian-ji Temple school, the Fusoukan school of the Tohoku region, the Shoganken, and the like are schools that have been transmitted.</e>
<cmt>I&apos;m not really sure how to handle the differentiation between 「流」・「派」 here.</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kinpu-Nezasa school of Hirosaki, the Saien school of Nagoya, which incorporates influences from the Fudai-ji Temple school of Hamamatsu, the Meian-Shinpo school of Kyoto&apos;s Meian-ji Temple as well as the Meian Taizan school, the Hakata Itchoken school, the Echigo Meian-ji Temple school, the Fusoukan school of the Tohoku region, the Shoganken, and the like are schools that have been transmitted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nezasa-ha Kinpu school of Hirosaki, the Seien school of Nagoya, which incorporates influences from the Fudai-ji Temple of Hamamatsu, the Myoan Jinpo school of Kyoto&apos;s Meian-ji Temple as well as the Myoan Taizan school, the Hakata Itchoken school, the Echigo Meian-ji Temple school, the Fusokan school of the Tohoku region, the Shoganken, and the like are schools that have been transmitted.</e>
<cmt>Nenaza-kinpu school としました。Myoan Jinpo, Myoan Taizan としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="92">
<j>これらの本曲は、托鉢のため諸国を往来した虚無僧により伝播された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The honkyoku of these schools have been conveyed by the mendicant komuso active in each of the respective provinces.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The honkyoku of these schools have been conveyed by the mendicant komuso active in each of the respective provinces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The honkyoku of these schools have been conveyed by the mendicant komuso active in each of the respective provinces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>全国の寺院で伝承される本曲には同名異曲が多くある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are many instances of honkyoku transmitted at the various temples throughout the country where the tradition is practiced that have the same name, but are completely different compositions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are many instances of honkyoku transmitted at the various temples throughout the country where the tradition is practiced that have the same name, but are completely different compositions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are many instances of honkyoku transmitted at the various temples throughout the country that have the same name, but are completely different compositions.</e>
<cmt>一部翻訳を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>『鈴慕』『三谷』『鶴の巣籠』などは本曲の代表的な曲名であるが、曲によっては10種類以上の旋律の異なるものが伝承されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Reibo&quot;, &quot;Sanya&quot;, Tsuru-no-sugomori&quot;, and the like are representative names of honkyuoku; however, depending on the piece, more than ten versions of some pieces have been passed down to the present, each of which has a different melody.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Reibo&quot;, &quot;Sanya&quot;, Tsuru-no-sugomori&quot;, and the like are representative names of honkyuoku; however, depending on the piece, more than ten versions of some pieces have been passed down to the present, each of which has a different melody.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Reibo,&quot; &quot;Sanya,&quot; &quot;Tsuru-no-sugomori,&quot; and the like are representative names of honkyoku; however, depending on the piece, more than ten versions of some pieces have been passed down to the present, each of which has a different melody.</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="95">
<j>宗教音楽としての本曲は、各地の本曲を収集した黒沢琴古の琴古流本曲、西園流を学び明治期に明暗対山流を興し、明暗教会の再興に尽力した樋口対山（1856年 - 1915年）の系統をはじめ、各地において明治維新後も伝承されたものが現代においても血脈を保っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Being a form of religious music, shakuhachi honkyoku continue to be practiced and transmitted within the tradition to this day, largely in the form of the honkuoku pieces gathered from various places across the country by Kurosawa KINKO in his travels as a ronin, which he assembled into a coherent body to form the honkyoku repertoire of the Kinko-ryu, resulting in the creation of a &quot;lineage&quot; that elevated the cultural status and recognition of the shakuhachi. There are also various local and regional groups that fall under the umbrella of the Meian-ryu, which is not a lineage per say, but an agglomeration of different schools under the Meian Kyokai (established in 1881) that practice honkyoku which have been transmitted within their respectrive regions. Perhaps the most well known among these groups is the Meian Taizan-ha, which was established during the Meiji Period by Taizan HIGUCHI (1856-1915), who had studied in the Seien-ryu and is credited with having made exhaustive efforts to rehabilitate Fuke-shu shakuachi through the Meian Kyokai.</e>
<cmt>The groups falling under the Meian-ryu are generally referred to as &quot;ha&quot;, not &quot;ryu&quot;. http://myoanflute.blogspot.com/ There is too much ground covered in this sentence, so I have broken it up and added some basic supplementa information to add a little clarity to the distinctions.</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Being a form of religious music, shakuhachi honkyoku continue to be practiced and transmitted within the tradition to this day, largely in the form of the honkuoku pieces gathered from various places across the country by Kurosawa KINKO in his travels as a ronin, which he assembled into a coherent body to form the honkyoku repertoire of the Kinko-ryu, resulting in the creation of a &quot;lineage&quot; that elevated the cultural status and recognition of the shakuhachi. There are also various local and regional groups that fall under the umbrella of the Meian-ryu, which is not a lineage per say, but an agglomeration of different schools under the Meian Kyokai (established in 1881) that practice honkyoku which have been transmitted within their respectrive regions. Perhaps the most well known among these groups is the Meian Taizan-ha, which was established during the Meiji Period by Taizan HIGUCHI (1856-1915), who had studied in the Seien-ryu and is credited with having made exhaustive efforts to rehabilitate Fuke-shu shakuachi through the Meian Kyokai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Honkyoku as religious music continues to be practiced to this today; the following lineages of honkyoku, including those transmitted after Meiji Restoration across the country, has been transmitted as follows; Kinko school honkyoku, which was gathered throughout the country by Kinko KUROSAWA; and that of Taizan HIGUCHI (1856 - 1915), who first learned the Seien school shakuhachi and established Myoan Taizan school, and later made effort to restore Myoan Kyokai (Myoan Church).</e>
<cmt>原文の記載に沿って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="24">
<tit>
<j>琴古流本曲</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinko-ryu honkyoku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kinko-ryu honkyoku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinko school honkyoku</e>
<cmt>Kinko school としました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="96">
<j>琴古流本曲は、琴古流の始祖である初代黒沢琴古が日本各地の虚無僧寺に伝わる楽曲をまとめ、本曲として制定した36曲である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kinko-ryu honkyoku consist of a repertoire of 36 pieces that the founder of the lineage, Kurosawa KINKO the 1st, gathered in his travels to komuso temples throughout the country.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kinko-ryu honkyoku consist of a repertoire of 36 pieces that the founder of the lineage, Kurosawa KINKO the 1st, gathered in his travels to komuso temples throughout the country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kinko school honkyoku consists of a repertoire of 36 pieces that the founder of the lineage, Kinko KUROSAWA the first, gathered in his travels to komuso temples throughout the country.</e>
<cmt>Kinko KUROSAWA としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>吹合所の指南役であった初代琴古は、これらの曲の譜字のや習曲順の整理を行い、宗教音楽をはなれた琴古流の基礎を築いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As head instructor at the fukiawase-dokoro (&quot;fukiawase&quot; refers to a Zen related mode of instruction that is generally one-to-one, and in the case of shakuhachi involves the teacher and student playing a piece together while seated facing each other across sheet music, and &quot;dokoro&quot; simply means &quot;place&quot;), Kurosawa KINKO set the pieces he had gathered to notation and established an order in which the repertoire of honkyoku was to be studied, as well as layed the foundation enabling the Kinko-ryu to later adapt the shakuachi to secular music in the form of the sankyoku ensemble compositions.</e>
<cmt>maybe a separate entry for &quot;fukiawase&quot;? There is both an overstatement regarding the removal of the Kinko-ryu from religious music and an apparent complete neglect of the higher forms of master-disciple training in Zen, such as koan training, which, as far as I know, is always a one-to-one interaction.</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As head instructor at the fukiawase-dokoro (&quot;fukiawase&quot; refers to a Zen related mode of instruction that is generally one-to-one, and in the case of shakuhachi involves the teacher and student playing a piece together while seated facing each other across sheet music, and &quot;dokoro&quot; simply means &quot;place&quot;), Kurosawa KINKO set the pieces he had gathered to notation and established an order in which the repertoire of honkyoku was to be studied, as well as layed the foundation enabling the Kinko-ryu to later adapt the shakuachi to secular music in the form of the sankyoku ensemble compositions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As head instructor at the fukiawase-dokoro, Kinko KUROSAWA set the pieces he had gathered to notation and established an order in which the repertoire of honkyoku was to be studied, as well as laid the foundation enabling the Kinko school to later adapt the shakuhachi to secular music.</e>
<cmt>Kinko KUROSAWA としました。一部翻訳を削除しました（原文に無い箇所など）。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="25">
<tit>
<j>都山流本曲</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tozan-ryu honkyoku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tozan-ryu honkyoku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tozan school honkyoku</e>
<cmt>Tozan school としました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="98">
<j>中尾都山らが作曲した現代曲、尺八独奏曲または尺八二重奏曲をさす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Tozan-ryu honkyoku repertoire consits of pieces composed by Nakao TOZAN, as well as modern compositions for the shakuachi for solo or multiple parts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Tozan-ryu honkyoku repertoire consits of pieces composed by Nakao TOZAN, as well as modern compositions for the shakuachi for solo or multiple parts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tozan school honkyoku repertoire consists of pieces composed by Tozan NAKAO, as well as compositions for the shakuhachi for solo or multiple parts.</e>
<cmt>Tozan NAKAO としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="26">
<tit>
<j>上田流本曲</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ueda-ryu honkyoku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ueda-ryu honkyoku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ueda school honkyoku</e>
<cmt>school としました。</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="27">
<tit>
<j>竹保流本曲</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chikuho-ryu honkyoku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chikuho-ryu honkyoku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chikuho school honkyoku</e>
<cmt>school としました。</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="28">
<tit>
<j>三曲合奏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sankyoku ensemmble pieces</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sankyoku ensemmble pieces</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sankyoku ensemble pieces</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="99">
<j>江戸時代の地歌では箏・三絃（三味線）・胡弓の合奏が行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Edo Period jiuta pieces were performed by an ensemble consiting of koto, shamisen, and kokyu (a bowed three string instrument).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Edo Period jiuta pieces were performed by an ensemble consiting of koto, shamisen, and kokyu (a bowed three string instrument).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Edo period jiuta (a genre of traditional songs with samisen accompaniment) pieces were performed by an ensemble consisting of koto (a long Japanese zither with thirteen strings), shamisen, and kokyu (a bowed three string instrument).</e>
<cmt>楽器の補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>これが三曲合奏である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is the origin of the term sankyoku pieces (literally, &quot;compositions for three instruments&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is the origin of the term sankyoku pieces (literally, &quot;compositions for three instruments&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is the origin of the term sankyoku pieces (literally, &quot;compositions for three instruments&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>明治維新以降、胡弓は尺八にとってかわられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Meiji Restoration, kokyu was replaced by shakuhachi.</e>
<cmt>翻訳を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>江戸時代にも尺八と箏や三味線の合奏は行われていたと考えられるが、尺八が普化宗の手から離れ合奏が解禁となったのは普化宗廃止後のことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It can be imagined that there were instances of collaborative performances between the shakuhachi and koto or shamisen even during the Edo Period, during which the shakuachi was tacitly relegated by the government to the exclusive use of the komuso mendicant monks; however, the lifting of the restriction that the shakuachi could only be used by the komuso of the Fuke-shu Zen sect, in which its status was that of a Buddhist religious implement (法器) used in religious practice, with official recognition of the shakuachi as a &quot;musical instrument&quot; permissible for use in ensemble with other instruments didn&apos;t come until after the Fuke-shu Zen sect was abolished in the Meiji Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It can be imagined that there were instances of collaborative performances between the shakuhachi and koto or shamisen even during the Edo Period, during which the shakuachi was tacitly relegated by the government to the exclusive use of the komuso mendicant monks; however, the lifting of the restriction that the shakuachi could only be used by the komuso of the Fuke-shu Zen sect, in which its status was that of a Buddhist religious implement (法器) used in religious practice, with official recognition of the shakuachi as a &quot;musical instrument&quot; permissible for use in ensemble with other instruments didn&apos;t come until after the Fuke-shu Zen sect was abolished in the Meiji Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It can be imagined that there were instances of collaborative performances between the shakuhachi and koto or shamisen even during the Edo period, however, it was not until after the abolition of Fuke sect that shakuhachi went out of hands of Fuke sect and the ensemble was permitted.</e>
<cmt>原文の記載に沿って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>現在では通常は三曲合奏といえば尺八が入るものを指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At present, sankyoku ensembles almost always include the shakuhachi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At present, sankyoku ensembles almost always include the shakuhachi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At present, sankyoku ensembles almost always include the shakuhachi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>古典的な三曲合奏では、尺八の手付けは三絃の手をベタ付けで尺八向けに編曲したものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the case of adapting a classical sankyokyu pieces for shakuachi, the shakuhaci part was generally added in a manner so as to roughly parallel that of the shamisen part.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the case of adapting a classical sankyokyu pieces for shakuachi, the shakuhaci part was generally added in a manner so as to roughly parallel that of the shamisen part.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the case of adapting a classical sankyoku pieces for shakuhachi, the shakuhachi part was generally added in a manner so as to roughly parallel that of the shamisen part.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="105">
<j>こうした三曲の一員としての尺八は、西洋音楽の影響を受けた明治新曲や、春の海で知られる宮城道雄などの新日本音楽を経て、現代邦楽と呼ばれるジャンルを形成するに至った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sankyoku compositions of this sort, which have been adapted to include a single shakuhachi player, along with Meiji shinkyoku, which are a type of music composed in Japan after the Meiji period reflecting the influence of classical western compostion, and including Shin Nihon compositions, such as Haru no Umi (The Sea in Spring), by Michio MIYAGI, form the genre of music commonly referred to as modern Japanese music.</e>
<cmt>Somewhat unclear as to the meaning of 経て here, and the relation of classical ssankyoku compositions to Meiji shinkyoku, for example.</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sankyoku compositions of this sort, which have been adapted to include a single shakuhachi player, along with Meiji shinkyoku, which are a type of music composed in Japan after the Meiji period reflecting the influence of classical western compostion, and including Shin Nihon compositions, such as Haru no Umi (The Sea in Spring), by Michio MIYAGI, form the genre of music commonly referred to as modern Japanese music.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sankyoku compositions of this sort, which have been adapted to include a single shakuhachi player, along with Meiji shinkyoku, which are a type of music composed in Japan after the Meiji period reflecting the influence of classical western composition, and including Shin Nihon compositions, such as Haru-no-umi, by Michio MIYAGI, form the genre of music commonly referred to as modern Japanese music.</e>
<cmt>春の海　補足を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="106">
<j>三曲系の演奏者のあいだでは、古典的な地歌箏曲を古曲、宮城道雄などの明治期から戦前までの楽曲曲を新曲、それ以降の楽曲を現代曲と呼ぶこともある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among sankyoku ensemble performers, classical jiuta-sokyoku pieces (jiuta compositions based on the koto part) are referred to as kokyoku (old pieces, or classical pieces), pieces composed by Michio MIYAGI and other from the Meiji Period up to the begining of WWI are referred to as shinkyoku (new pieces), and pieces composed subsequently are referred to as modern pieces.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among sankyoku ensemble performers, classical jiuta-sokyoku pieces (jiuta compositions based on the koto part) are referred to as kokyoku (old pieces, or classical pieces), pieces composed by Michio MIYAGI and other from the Meiji Period up to the begining of WWI are referred to as shinkyoku (new pieces), and pieces composed subsequently are referred to as modern pieces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among sankyoku ensemble performers, classical jiuta-sokyoku pieces (jiuta compositions based on the koto part) are referred to as kokyoku (old pieces, or classical pieces), pieces composed by Michio MIYAGI and other from the Meiji period up to the beginning of WWI are referred to as shinkyoku (new pieces), and pieces composed subsequently are referred to as modern pieces.</e>
<cmt>period 小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="29">
<tit>
<j>民謡尺八</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Folk song shakuachi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Folk song shakuachi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Folk song shakuhachi</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="107">
<j>多くの民謡の伴奏に尺八が使用される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The shacuhachi is often used to accompany performances of folk songs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shacuhachi is often used to accompany performances of folk songs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The shakuhachi is often used to accompany performances of folk songs.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>特に追分、馬子唄の伴奏には尺八が多用される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many oiwake-bushi (a form popular in many parts of central and northern Japan) and mago-uta songs, in particular, are performed accompanied by the shakuachi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many oiwake-bushi (a form popular in many parts of central and northern Japan) and mago-uta songs, in particular, are performed accompanied by the shakuachi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many oiwake-bushi (a form popular in many parts of central and northern Japan) and mago-uta songs, in particular, are performed accompanied by the shakuhachi.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="109">
<j>江差追分では、尺八の伴奏が必須となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the case of Esashi oiwake-bushi pieces, from the coastal regions of Hokkaido, ports along the Sea of Japan, etc, shakuachi accompaniment is mandatory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the case of Esashi oiwake-bushi pieces, from the coastal regions of Hokkaido, ports along the Sea of Japan, etc, shakuachi accompaniment is mandatory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the case of Esashi oiwake-bushi pieces (from the coastal regions of Hokkaido, ports along the Sea of Japan, etc.) shakuhachi accompaniment is mandatory.</e>
<cmt>江差追分　の補足を括弧内に要れました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="30">
<tit>
<j>現代音楽と尺八</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Modern music and the shakuachi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Modern music and the shakuachi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Modern music and the shakuhachi</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="110">
<j>1960年代から尺八はクラシック音楽の現代音楽で使用されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Starting from about the 1960s, the shakuachi began to be adopted in compositions of modern classical music.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Starting from about the 1960s, the shakuachi began to be adopted in compositions of modern classical music.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Starting from about the 1960s, the shakuhachi began to be adopted in compositions of modern classical music.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>1964年にニューヨーク・フィルハーモニックと尺八の横山勝也、薩摩琵琶の流れをくむ鶴田流の琵琶奏者鶴田錦史のために作曲された武満徹のノヴェンバー・ステップスは反響を呼んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shakuachi player Katsuya YOKOYAMA appeared with with the New York Philharmonic in 1964 to high acclaim, performing a piece called &quot;November Steps&quot;, which was composed by Toru TAKEMITSU for biwa player Nishikishi TSURDA of the Tsuruda-ryu lineage, a lineage influenced by the Satsuma style of biwa playing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shakuachi player Katsuya YOKOYAMA appeared with with the New York Philharmonic in 1964 to high acclaim, performing a piece called &quot;November Steps&quot;, which was composed by Toru TAKEMITSU for biwa player Nishikishi TSURDA of the Tsuruda-ryu lineage, a lineage influenced by the Satsuma style of biwa playing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shakuhachi player Katsuya YOKOYAMA appeared with the New York Philharmonic in 1964 to high acclaim, performing a piece called &quot;November Steps,&quot; which was composed by Toru TAKEMITSU for biwa player Kinshi TSURUTA of the Tsuruta-school lineage, a lineage influenced by the Satsuma style of biwa playing.</e>
<cmt>Kinshi TSURUTA としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="31">
<tit>
<j>現代邦楽</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Modern Japanese music</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Modern Japanese music</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Modern Japanese music</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="32">
<tit>
<j>ポピュラー音楽と尺八</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Popular music and the shakuachi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Popular music and the shakuachi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Popular music and the shakuhachi</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="112">
<j>現在では、藤原道山、ZAN、遠音などのアーティストが活躍している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At present, performers such as Tone, ZAN, and Dozan FUJIWARA are active performing modern music on the shakuhachi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At present, performers such as Tone, ZAN, and Dozan FUJIWARA are active performing modern music on the shakuhachi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At present, performers such as Dozan FUJIWARA, ZAN and Tone are active performing modern music on the shakuhachi.</e>
<cmt>人名の順番を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="113">
<j>製管</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Making shakuachi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Making shakuachi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Making shakuhachi</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="114">
<j>尺八を製作することを指して製管という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt>Omit this from the english</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Making shakuhachi is called &quot;seikan&quot; (literally, &quot;making the tube&quot;).</e>
<cmt>製管→making the tube として、翻訳を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>尺八の製作者のことを製管師とよぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt>Omit this from the english</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The maker of shakuhachi is called &quot;Seikan-shi&quot; (literally, &quot;a maker of the tube&quot;).</e>
<cmt>製管師→a maker of the tube　として、翻訳を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="116">
<j>専業の製管師のほかに、尺八奏者がみずから尺八を製作する場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Aside from professional shakuachi makers, there are players who make their own shakuhachi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Aside from professional shakuachi makers, there are players who make their own shakuhachi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Aside from professional shakuhachi makers, there are players who make their own shakuhachi.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="117">
<j>製管師のなかには、特定の流派や師匠と結びついている者もいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among makers, there are those who are linked exclusively to a particular lineage or teacher.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among makers, there are those who are linked exclusively to a particular lineage or teacher.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among makers, there are those who are linked exclusively to a particular lineage or teacher.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="118">
<j>アマチュアの尺八奏者のなかには、この製管を趣味とするものもいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are also amatuer shakuachi players who take up an interest in trying their hand at making shakuachi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are also amatuer shakuachi players who take up an interest in trying their hand at making shakuachi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are also amateur shakuhachi players who take up an interest in trying their hand at making shakuhachi.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Los688(id:12316), Suguri F(id:11127), 0null0(id:582), Cprobot(id:97843), Eskimbot(id:29676), Aedfafdasdfaeraea(id:10172), Dabbler(id:65389), Preacher(id:39996), 708sc709sc(id:198353), お星さま(id:94800), Estrepito728(id:121477), Qazzx(id:8772), ハヤマの釣人(id:187762), PipepBot(id:146181), Uraios(id:72687), ＋－(id:17104), Mymelo(id:122034), Michey.M(id:906), Loveless(id:129239), Point136(id:211299), Yas(id:739), Yamabig(id:21134), Hermes(id:21387), バナナ(id:29810), Yasu(id:685), Bankokuya(id:91191), 詠狸庵(id:41048), いろはにほへと(id:89648), Lombroso(id:20212), YonaBot(id:125006), Kokoperi(id:32223), TS(id:481), Iwatake(id:32921), NekoJaNekoJa(id:23311), Martin(id:6394), Hatsune(id:26654), L26(id:119681), Azu(id:1328), Tanuki Z(id:612), VolkovBot(id:105371), Tietew(id:4054), Sonido86(id:117353), プリン寿司(id:199038), Solla(id:198437), Corwin(id:973), U.S.S.Momotaro(id:646), Quick10(id:249326), Suisui(id:69), LeonardoRob0t(id:25875), SieBot(id:126695), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>