<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>燗酒</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanzake</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanzake (warmed sake)</e>
<cmt>Kanzake に (warmed sake) を追記しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanzake (warmed sake)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>燗酒（かんざけ）とは、加熱した酒のことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanzake is warmed alcoholic beverage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanzake is warmed alcoholic beverage.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanzake is warmed alcoholic beverage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>なお、酒自体を加熱する行為のことを、燗（かん）を付ける、お燗（おかん）するなどと言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, the action to warm alcoholic beverage itself is expressed as kan wo tsukeru (put on kan), okan suru (do okan), and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further, the action to warm alcoholic beverage itself is expressed as kan wo tsukeru (to warm up sake), okan suru (to warm sake), and so on.</e>
<cmt>put on kan を to warm up sake に修正しました。出典：http://tangorin.com/words/燗をつけるdo okan を to warm sake に修正しました。出典：http://books.google.com/books?id=43puKgiAK2YC&amp;pg=PA88&amp;dq=to+warm+sake&amp;as_brr=3&amp;hl=ja&amp;cd=1#v=onepage&amp;q=to%20warm%20sake&amp;f=false※put on kan, do okan は米国版Yahoo、あるいはgoogle booksでもヒットしませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further, the action to warm alcoholic beverage itself is expressed as kan wo tsukeru (to warm up sake), okan suru (to warm sake), and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>ただし、お湯を加えることで酒の温度を上げる行為を燗とは言わず、その場合は、お湯割り（おゆわり）と呼んで区別される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, action to raise the temperature of alcoholic beverage by adding hot water is not called kan, and in that case, it is distinguished by calling it oyuwari.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, adding hot water to raise the temperature of sake does not mean warming sake, and in that case, it is distinguished by calling it &apos;oyuwari.&apos;</e>
<cmt>action to raise the temperature of alcoholic beverage by adding hot water is not called kan をadding hot water to raise the temperature of sake does not mean warming sake に修正しました。oyuwari にコーテーションを追記しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, adding hot water to raise the temperature of sake does not mean warming sake, and in that case, it is distinguished by calling it &apos;oyuwari.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>基本的に、燗を行う時、加水（お湯も含む）は行われない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Basically, when kan is done, water is not added (including hot water).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Basically, when warming sake, no water is added (including hot water).</e>
<cmt>when kan is done, water is not added を warming sake, no water is added に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Basically, when warming sake, no water is added (including hot water).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>（加水が行われるケースについては、「燗の現状 (焼酎)」の節を参照のこと。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(refer to article &apos;Kanzake, present situation of kan (shochu)&apos; for the case in which water is added.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(refer to article &apos;Present situation of warming up sake (shochu)&apos; for the case in which water is added.)</e>
<cmt>「燗酒燗の現状」の「燗酒」を削除しました。Kanzake, present situation of kan を Present situation of warming up sake に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(refer to article &apos;Present situation of warming up sake (shochu)&apos; for the case in which water is added.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>燗は、普通、日本酒、または、中国酒の一部を飲む際に行われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Normally, kan is done in a situation where Japanese sake and part of Chinese alcoholic beverage are being drunk.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Normally, sake is warmed up when Japanese sake or part of Chinese sake are consumed.</e>
<cmt>kan is done in a situation where Japanese sake and part of Chinese alcoholic beverage are being drunk をsake is warmed up when Japanese sake or part of Chinese sake are consumed に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Normally, sake is warmed up when Japanese sake or part of Chinese sake are consumed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>日本酒を加熱したものを燗酒と呼ぶこともあるが、燗が行われるのは日本酒だけではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Warmed Japanese sake is called kanzake, too, but Japanese sake is not the only alcoholic beverage which kan is done.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Warmed Japanese sake is called kanzake, too, but Japanese sake is not the only alcoholic beverage which is warmed up.</e>
<cmt>kan is done を is warmed up に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Warmed Japanese sake is called kanzake, too, but Japanese sake is not the only alcoholic beverage which is warmed up.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>ただし、基本的には醸造酒でしか燗は行われない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, basically, kan is done only to brewage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, basically, kan is done only to brewage.</e>
<cmt>kan is done only to brewage を only brewage is warmed up に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, basically, kan is done only to brewage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>（蒸留酒で燗が行われるケースについては、「焼酎と燗」の節を参照のこと。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(refer to article &apos;Kanzake, shochu and kan&apos; for the case in which kan is done to distilled spirits.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(refer to article &apos;Shochu and warming up sake&apos; for the case of warming distilled spirits.)</e>
<cmt>「燗酒焼酎の現状」の「燗酒」を削除しました。Kanzake, shochu and kan を Shochu and warming up sake に修正しました。in which kan is done to を of warming に修正しました。原文の文末にカッコを追記しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(refer to article &apos;Shochu and warming up sake&apos; for the case of warming distilled spirits.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>また、暑い時期にはあまり行われず、寒い時期に多く行われる傾向にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, it is rarely done in hot period, and tend to be done a lot in cold period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further, warming sake is rare during hot season, but often during cold season.</e>
<cmt>原文の文頭にあった閉じカッコを削除しました。it is rarely done in hot period, and tend to be done a lot in cold period. をwarming sake is rare in hot a season, but often in a cold season に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further, warming sake is rare during hot season, but often done during cold season.</e>
<cmt>done を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>燗は、日本や中国では古くから行われてきた行為であり、現在でも行われる行為だが、世界的に見ると珍しい行為である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kan is an action done from old times in Japan and in China which is still being done in present days, but if seen globally, it is an unique action.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although warming sake has been done in Japan and China from old times to present days, if seen globally, it is an unique action.</e>
<cmt>Kan is an action done from old times in Japan and in China which is still being done in present days, but をAlthough warming sake has been done in Japan and China from old times to present days に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although warming sake has been done in Japan and China from old times to present days, if seen globally, it is an unique action.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>対して、酒のお湯割りは、世界中で行われる行為である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, action of mixing hot water to alcoholic beverages is done throughout the world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, mixing hot water to alcoholic beverages is common in the world.</e>
<cmt>action of mixing hot water to alcoholic beverages is done throughout をmixing hot water to alcoholic beverages is common in に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, mixing hot water to alcoholic beverages is common in the world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>なお、ワインを燗することもあるものの、日本酒や中国酒に比べると頻度が低く、ワインの場合、どちらかと言えばカクテルとしての扱いとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, there is a case in which kan is done to wine, but it is less frequently done compared to Japanese sake and Chinese alcoholic beverage, and as for wine, it is rather treated as a cocktail.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further, sometimes wine is warmed, too, but it is less frequently done compared to Japanese sake and Chinese alcoholic beverage, and as for wine, it is rather treated as a cocktail.</e>
<cmt>there is a case in which kan is done to wine をsometimes wine is warmed, too に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further, sometimes wine is warmed, too, but it is less frequently done compared to Japanese sake and Chinese alcoholic beverage, and as for wine, it is rather treated as a cocktail.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>（詳しくはワインと燗の節を参照のこと。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(for details, refer to article &apos;Atuzake, wine and kan.&apos;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(for details, refer to the article &apos;Warming wine&apos;)</e>
<cmt>原文「燗酒ワインと燗の節」の「ワインと燗」に修正しました。refer to article &apos;Atuzake, wine and kan. を refer to the article &apos;Warming wine&apos; に修正しました。※「詳しくは～の節を」の「～」に、他の文章では「」が付いていますが、この文章のみついていません。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(for details, refer to the article &apos;Warming wine&apos;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>日本酒と燗</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese sake and kan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Warming Japanese sake</e>
<cmt>Japanese sake and kan を Warming Japanese sake に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Warming Japanese sake</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="15">
<j>燗をする際、加水などは行わない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When kan is done, water is not added.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When warming sake, water is not added.</e>
<cmt>kan is done を warming sake に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When warming sake, water is not added.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>また、基本的にスパイスや砂糖などが加えられることはない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, basically, spice, sugar, and so on are not added.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, basically, spice, sugar, and so on are not added.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, basically, spice, sugar, and so on are not added.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>暑い時期にはあまり行われず、寒い時期に多く行われる傾向にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is rarely done in hot period, and tend to be done a lot in cold period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Warming Japanese sake is rare during hot season, but often during cold season.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Warming Japanese sake is rare during hot season, but often done during cold season.</e>
<cmt>done を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>日本酒の中でも吟醸酒については原則的に燗をつけないが、人によっては「沈んでいた香りが立ってくる」としてぬるめに燗をつける場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Essentially, kan is not done to ginjo sake (high-quality sake brewed at low temperatures from rice grains milled to 60 % weight or less) even though it is a kind of Japanese sake, but some people lightly put on kan to it because &apos;hidden fragrance appears.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Essentially, kan is not done to Ginjoshu (high-quality sake brewed at low temperatures from rice grains milled to 60 % weight or less) even though it is a kind of Japanese sake, but some people lightly put on kan to it because &apos;hidden fragrance appears.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ginjo sakeをGinjoshu に修正しました。出典：http://www.japansake.or.jp/sake/english/types_sake.html</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Essentially, kan is not done to Ginjoshu (high-quality sake brewed at low temperatures from rice grains milled to 60 % weight or less) even though it is a kind of Japanese sake, but some people lightly put on kan to it because &apos;hidden fragrance appears.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>アル添酒の問題</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Problem of sake with distilled alcohol added</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Problem of sake with distilled alcohol added</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Problem of sake with distilled alcohol added</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="19">
<j>日本酒は、古くから燗が行われてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kan has been done to Japanese sake from old times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Warming Japanese sake has been done from old times.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Warming Japanese sake has been done from old times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>燗という行為は、世界的に珍しい行為ではあるものの、醸造酒に燗をするのは、焼酎のような蒸留酒に燗をすることに比べると、珍しい行為ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The action of kan is globally an unique action, but doing kan to brewage is not so unique compared to doing kan to distilled spirits such as shochu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Warming sake is a rare action in the world, however, to warm brewage is not rare compared with the case of distilled alcoholic beverage such as shochu.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Warming sake is a rare action in the world, however, to warm brewage is not rare compared with the case of distilled alcoholic beverage such as shochu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>例えば、中国の黄酒を飲む際などにも、古くから行われてきた行為である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, it had been done from the old times when drinking Chinese Huangjiu (yellow wine).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, people used to enjoy warm Chinese Huangjiu (yellow wine) from the old times.</e>
<cmt>For example 以下を全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, people used to enjoy warm Chinese Huangjiu (yellow wine) from the old times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>（詳しくは「中国酒と燗」の節などを参照のこと。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(for details, refer to article &apos;Atuzake, Chinese alcoholic beverage and kan.&apos;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(for details, refer to article &apos;Warming Chinese alcoholic beverage.&apos;)</e>
<cmt>原文「燗酒中国酒と燗」を「中国酒と燗」に修正しました。refer to article &apos;Atuzake, Chinese alcoholic beverage and kan.&apos; を refer to the article &apos;Warming Chinese alcoholic beverage&apos; に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(for details, refer to article &apos;Warming Chinese alcoholic beverage.&apos;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="23">
<j>ただし、昨今の日本酒には醸造アルコールという名称で、蒸留酒が添加されるケースが多々あり、そのような日本酒（いわゆるアル添酒）の場合、醸造酒とは言えないのではないかとの指摘もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there are many cases nowadays where spirit is added to Japanese sake with the name of distilled alcohol, and there are some opinions stating that Japanese sake in such cases can&apos;t be called as brewage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, nowadays, there are many cases of Japanese sake added distilled alcohol in the name of &apos;brewage alcohol,&apos; and some point out that the Japanese sake in that case (so-called &apos;alcohol-added sake&apos;) could not be called as brewage.</e>
<cmt>原文に句読点を追記しました。全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, nowadays, there are many cases of Japanese sake added distilled alcohol in the name of &apos;brewage alcohol,&apos; and some point out that the Japanese sake in that case (so-called &apos;alcohol-added sake&apos;) could not be called as brewage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="24">
<j>しかし、醸造アルコールの添加は古くから大々的に行われてきたわけではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, adding of distilled alcohol was not done popularly in old times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, adding of distilled alcohol was not done popularly in old times.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, adding of distilled alcohol was not done popularly in old times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="25">
<j>大々的に行われるようになったのは、第2次大戦後である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It became popular after the World War II.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It became popular after the World War II.</e>
<cmt>原文に句読点を追記しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It became popular after the World War II.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="26">
<j>日本酒の醸造が行われたのは、それよりもずっと以前の話であり、燗が行われるようになったのも、同じくずっと以前の話である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The brewing of Japanese sake had began way before that, and kan had been began to be done way before that, also.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Brewing Japanese sake has begun before World War II, and so has warming sake.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Brewing Japanese sake has begun before World War II, and so has warming sake.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>したがって、燗が行われる対象としての日本酒は、基本的にアル添酒ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Consequently, the Japanese sake as object for kan to be done is basically not the sake with distilled alcohol added.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequently, the Japanese sake as object to be warmed is basically not the sake with distilled alcohol added.</e>
<cmt>for kan to be done をto be warmed に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently, the Japanese sake as object to be warmed is basically not the sake with distilled alcohol added.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>（燗という行為はアル添酒に対して行われてきたわけではない。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Action of kan has not been done to sake with distilled alcohol added.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(They have not warmed sake with distilled alcohol added.)</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(They have not warmed sake with distilled alcohol added.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="29">
<j>よって本節『日本酒と燗』では、特別にことわりが無い場合、醸造アルコールの添加を行っていない日本酒を対象として（つまりアル添酒を対象とせずに）話を進めるものとし、日本酒は醸造酒の1種であるとして話を進める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, in this article &quot;Japanese sake and kan,&quot; if there is no special explanation, description is made with Japanese sake without distilled alcohol added as a subject (in other words, sake with distilled alcohol is not included as a subject), and the description will advance by treating Japanese sake as a kind of brewage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, in this article &quot;Warming Japanese sake&quot; if there is no special explanation, description is made with Japanese sake without distilled alcohol added as a subject (in other words, sake with distilled alcohol is not included as a subject), and the description will advance by treating Japanese sake as a kind of brewage.</e>
<cmt>Japanese sake and kan を Warming Japanese sake に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, in this article &quot;Warming Japanese sake&quot; if there is no special explanation, description is made with Japanese sake without distilled alcohol added as a subject (in other words, sake with distilled alcohol is not included as a subject), and the description will advance by treating Japanese sake as a kind of brewage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>醸造アルコールを添加された日本酒が醸造酒であるか否かという問題については、ひとまず考えないことにする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The problem whether Japanese sake with distilled alcohol added is a brewage or not is put aside for right now.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The problem whether Japanese sake with distilled alcohol added is a brewage or not is put aside for right now.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The problem whether Japanese sake with distilled alcohol added is a brewage or not is put aside for right now.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>アル添酒の1つである吟醸酒についても、以降記述しない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Description is not made for ginjo sake, too, which is a kind of sake with distilled alcohol added.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Description is not made for Ginjoshu, either, which is a kind of sake with distilled alcohol added.</e>
<cmt>ginjo sakeをGinjoshu に修正しました。too を either に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Description is not made for Ginjoshu, either, which is a kind of sake with distilled alcohol added.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>手法</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Method</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Method</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Method</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="32">
<j>鍋や銚子を直火にかけて燗をつけていたが、文化年間には、銅製または錫製のチロリで燗をつけた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kan had been put by putting pot and sake bottle over direct fire, but in Bunka era, kan was put with chirori (a metal container for heating sake) made of copper or tin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They used to warm sake with a pan or sake decanter over direct heat, but in the Bunka era, copper or tin made chirori (a metal container for heating sake) was used.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。in Bunka eraにtheを追記しました。※用語集ではsake decanter となっておりますが、米国版yahooによるヒット数から鑑みた場合、sake pourer の方が容認度が高いようです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They used to warm sake with a pan or sake decanter over direct heat, but in the Bunka era, copper or tin made chirori (a metal container for heating sake) was used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>天保年間には、畿内地方ではチロリがもちいられていたが、江戸ではすでに燗徳利（かんとっくり／かんどくり）が流行していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Tempo era, chirori was used in Kinai area, but kan tokkuri (sake bottle) became popular in Edo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Tempo era, chirori was used in the Kinai area, but kantokkuri/kandokuri (bottle for warming sake) became popular in Edo.</e>
<cmt>In Tempo era, Kinai area にそれぞれ the を追記しました。kan tokkuri (sake bottle) を kantokkuri/kandokuri (bottle for warming sake) に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Tempo era, chirori was used in the Kinai area, but kantokkuri/kandokuri (bottle for warming sake) became popular in Edo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>箱火鉢には、脇に水を入れてその中に燗徳利を漬ける設備が備わるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Equipment to fill water to put in kan tokkuri had began to be put on to braziers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A brazier encased in a wooden box came to equip a corner to pour water and place the kandokuri in it.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A brazier encased in a wooden box came to equip a corner to pour water and place the kandokuri in it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="35">
<j>明治時代、一般に燗徳利が、まれにチロリや鳩徳利が、使用された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Meiji period, kan tokkuri was commonly used, and rarely, chirori and hatodokkuri (a kind of tokkuri bottle) were used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Meiji period, kandokuri was commonly used, and rarely, chirori and hatodokkuri (a kind of tokkuri bottle) were used.</e>
<cmt>In Meiji period に定冠詞 the を追記しました。Kan tokkuri を kandokuri に修正しました。※辞書類（大辞林、単語林、Kanji Dictionary, The New Nelson）を検索した結果、全てkandokuriとなっていました。また、米国版Yahooではkan tokkuriではヒットしないことから、kandokuriの方が容認度が高いものと判断し、kandokuri とさせていただきました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Meiji period, kandokuri was commonly used, and rarely, chirori and hatodokkuri (a kind of tokkuri bottle) were used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>のちに酒場では酒燗器がつかわれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later in bars, sake heating equipments were used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later in bars, the sake warmer dispenser was used.</e>
<cmt>sake heating equipments を sake warmer dispenserに修正しました。※出典：http://www.taiji.co.jp/e/faq/#sake</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later in bars, the sake warmer dispenser was used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>これは、器内で湯を沸かし、内管に上から酒をそそぎ、下部の活栓をひらけばただちに燗のつけられた酒が流れ出るものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Water is boiled in this equipment, sake is poured in a tube that goes through this equipment, and if the stopper cock at the bottom is opened, sake with kan put will pour out.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Water is boiled in this equipment, sake is poured in a tube that goes through this equipment, and if the stopper cock at the bottom is opened, warmed sake will pour out.</e>
<cmt>sake with kan putを warmed sakeに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Water is boiled in this equipment, sake is poured in a tube that goes through this equipment, and if the stopper cock at the bottom is opened, warmed sake will pour out.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="38">
<j>現在一般家庭では電子レンジを使うことより徳利を湯煎する方法が薦められる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Using microwave to warm tokkuri with hot water is recommended in general household in present days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nowadays, to warm sake at home, it is recommended to place the sake bottle in the hot water rather than to microwave.</e>
<cmt>誤訳のため全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nowadays, to warm sake at home, it is recommended to place the sake bottle in the hot water rather than to microwave.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>日本酒の燗における温度表現</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Expressions for temperatures in kan of Japanese sake.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Temperature expressions for warm Japanese sake</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Temperature expressions for warm Japanese sake</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="39">
<j>日本酒の燗では、細かな温度表現が使用されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In kan of Japanese sake, delicate expressions for temperatures are used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On warmed sake, delicate expressions for temperatures are used.</e>
<cmt>In kan of Japanese sake をOn warmed sake に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On warmed sake, delicate expressions for temperatures are used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="40">
<j>以下、一般的な温度表現として日本酒の記事より転載する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In following part, descriptions of article about Japanese sake is reprinted as general expressions for temperatures.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In following part, descriptions of article about Japanese sake is reprinted as general expressions for temperatures.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In following part, descriptions of article about Japanese sake is reprinted as general expressions for temperatures.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>なお、飲用温度はあくまでも目安であり、人によって名称から連想する温度は異なる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, the drinking temperature described is only a guide, and the temperature imagined from the expression differs from person to person.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, the drinking temperature described is only a guide, and the temperature imagined from each expression depends on the drinker.</e>
<cmt>from the expression differs from person to person をfrom each expression depends on the drinker に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, the drinking temperature described is only a guide, and the temperature imagined from each expression depends on the drinker.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>また、温度表現の仕方が統一されているわけでもない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, the integration of ways to express temperature is not done, either.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further, the ways to express temperature has not been integrated yet.</e>
<cmt>the integration of ways to express temperature is not done, either をthe ways to express temperature has not been integrated yet に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further, the ways to express temperature has not been integrated yet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="43">
<j>これら以外の名称として、飛び切り燗を更に越えた温度に対して煮酒と呼ぶなど様々な表現が存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other than these expressions, there are various expressions such as calling temperature of sake higher than that of tobikiri kan as nizake.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other than these expressions, there are various expressions such as calling temperature of sake higher than that of tobikiri kan (very hot) as &apos;nizake&apos; (boiled sake).</e>
<cmt>tobikiri kan に (very hot) を追記しました。nizake を &apos;nizake&apos; (boiled sake) に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other than these expressions, there are various expressions such as calling temperature of sake higher than that of tobikiri kan (very hot) as &apos;nizake&apos; (boiled sake).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>用語</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Terms</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Terms</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Terms</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="44">
<j>以下に日本酒の記事より抜粋して、日本酒を燗した時に関連する用語を説明する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the following, descriptions for terms relating to kan of Japanese sake is excerpted from the article about Japanese sake.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the following, we describe the terms related with warming sake, excerpted from the article of Japanese sake.</e>
<cmt>descriptions for terms relating to kan of Japanese sake is excerpted from the article about Japanese sake をwe describe the terms related with warming sake, excerpted from the article of Japanese sake に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the following, we describe the terms related with warming sake, excerpted from the article of Japanese sake.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>「燗映え（かんばえ）する」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanbae suru&apos;</e>
<cmt>用語そのものが取り扱われているのでそのままにしてあります</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanbae suru&apos;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanbae suru&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="45">
<j>- 燗をつけることで味が格段に良くなる、日本酒のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese sake which taste turns dramatically tasty by putting kan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese sake which tastes dramatically better when warmed up.</e>
<cmt>which taste turns dramatically tasty by putting kan. を tastes dramatically better when warmed up に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese sake which tastes dramatically better when warmed up.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>「燗上がり（かんあがり）する」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanagari suru&apos;</e>
<cmt>用語そのものが取り扱われているのでそのままにしてあります</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanagari suru&apos;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanagari suru&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="46">
<j>- 日本酒に燗をつけたことで、味が引き出された状態のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A condition in which Japanese sake&apos;s taste became better by putting kan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A condition in which warming sake has derived its taste.</e>
<cmt>Japanese sake&apos;s taste became better by putting kan をwarming sake has derived its taste に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A condition in which warming sake has derived its taste.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>「味が開く」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Aji ga hiraku&apos;</e>
<cmt>用語そのものが取り扱われているのでそのままにしてあります</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Aji ga hiraku&apos;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Aji ga hiraku&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="47">
<j>- 日本酒に燗をつけたことで、冷たかった時には十分に感じられなかった味が、表に出た状態のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A condition in which Japanese sake&apos;s taste which could not have been sensed at cold condition became apparent by putting kan to it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A condition in which Japanese sake&apos;s taste which could not have been sensed at cold condition became apparent when warmed up.</e>
<cmt>by putting kan to it をwhen warmed up に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A condition in which Japanese sake&apos;s taste which could not have been sensed at cold condition became apparent when warmed up.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>「香りが開く」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaori ga hiraku&apos;</e>
<cmt>用語そのものが取り扱われているのでそのままにしてあります</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaori ga hiraku&apos;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaori ga hiraku&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="48">
<j>- 日本酒に燗をつけたことで、冷たかった時には十分に感じられなかった香りが、表に出た状態のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A condition in which Japanese sake&apos;s fragrance which could not have been sensed at cold condition became apparent by putting kan to it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A condition in which Japanese sake&apos;s fragrance which could not have been sensed at cold condition became apparent when warmed up.</e>
<cmt>by putting kan to it をwhen warmed up に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A condition in which Japanese sake&apos;s fragrance which could not have been sensed at cold condition became apparent when warmed up.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>「燗冷まし（かんざまし）になる」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanzamashi ni naru&apos;</e>
<cmt>用語そのものが取り扱われているのでそのままにしてあります</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanzamashi ni naru&apos;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanzamashi ni naru&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="49">
<j>- 一旦燗をつけた日本酒が、冷えてしまった状態のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A condition in which Japanese sake was once put on kan, but became cold again.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A condition in which the Japanese sake once warmed but became cold again.</e>
<cmt>Japanese was once put on kan, but became cold again をthe Japanese sake once warmed but became cold again に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A condition in which the Japanese sake once warmed but became cold again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>「燗崩れ（かんくずれ）」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kankuzure&apos;</e>
<cmt>用語そのものが取り扱われているのでそのままにしてあります</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kankuzure&apos;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kankuzure&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="50">
<j>- 燗冷ましになった時、日本酒の風味のバランスが崩れてしまった状態のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A condition in which Japanese sake&apos;s balance of flavor collapsed after becoming kanzamashi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A condition in which kanzamashi has broken the flavor balance of Japanese sake.</e>
<cmt>Japanese sake&apos;s balance of flavor collapsed after becoming kanzamashi を kanzamashi has broken the flavor balance of Japanese sake に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A condition in which kanzamashi has broken the flavor balance of Japanese sake.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="51">
<j>（なお、燗冷ましになっても、必ずしも燗崩れになるとは限らない。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Meanwhile, becoming kanzamashi doesn&apos;t necessarily results in kankuzure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Meanwhile, Kanzamashi does not always result in Kankuzure.)</e>
<cmt>becoming kanzamashi doesn&apos;t necessarily results in kankuzure をKanzamashi does not always result Kankuzure に修正しました。閉じカッコを追記しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Meanwhile, Kanzamashi does not always result in Kankuzure.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>「冷よし、燗よし、燗冷めよし」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hiyayoshi, kanyoshi, kanzameyoshi&apos;</e>
<cmt>用語そのものが取り扱われているのでそのままにしてあります</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hiyayoshi, kanyoshi, kanzameyoshi&apos;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hiyayoshi, kanyoshi, kanzameyoshi&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="52">
<j>- 日本酒は、冷もよいし、燗もよい、燗が冷えたものもよい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">No matter whether it is hiya (cold), kan, or kan became cold, Japanese sake is good.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">No matter whether it is chilled, warmed or warmed then cooled down, Japanese sake tastes good.</e>
<cmt>hiya (cold), kan, or kan became cold, Japanese sake is good をchilled, warmed or warmed then cooled down, Japanese sake tastes good に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">No matter whether it is chilled, warmed or warmed then cooled down, Japanese sake tastes good.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>呑兵衛はどの状態でも日本酒が好きとの意。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its meaning is that a drunkard likes Japanese sake in any condition.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It means that heavy drinkers love Japanese sake in any condition.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It means that heavy drinkers love Japanese sake in any condition.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>歴史的変遷</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Historical change</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Historical change</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Historical change</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="54">
<j>『貞順故実聞書条々』によれば、酒の燗は9月9日から3月2日までであるという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Teijun kojitu kikigaki jojo,&quot; kan of sake is good from September 9 through March 3.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Teijun kojitu kikigaki jojo,&quot; warming sake is good from September 9 through March 2.</e>
<cmt>Kan of sake を warming sake に修正しました。March 3 を March 2 に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Teijun kojitu kikigaki jojo,&quot; warming sake is good from September 9 through March 2.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="14">
<tit>
<j>カクテルの材料</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ingredient for cocktail</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ingredient for cocktail</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ingredient for cocktail</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="55">
<j>カクテルの材料に燗した日本酒が用いられる例として、オレンジ・サキニーや卵酒がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For examples in which Japanese sake with kan is used for ingredient of cocktail, there are Orange Sakini and tamagozake (egg sake).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For examples in which warmed Japanese sake is used for ingredient of cocktail, there are Orange Sakini and tamagozake (egg sake).</e>
<cmt>Japanese sake with kan をwarmed Japanese sake に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For examples in which warmed Japanese sake is used for ingredient of cocktail, there are Orange Sakini and tamagozake (egg sake).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>しかし、オレンジ・サキニーや卵酒は、燗酒ではなく、カクテルとして扱われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Orange Sakini and tamagozake are treated as cocktail, not kanzake.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Orange Sakini and tamagozake are classified into cocktail, not.warmed sake</e>
<cmt>treated as を classified into に修正しました。Kanzake を warmed sake に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Orange Sakini and tamagozake are classified into cocktail, not.warmed sake</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="15">
<tit>
<j>中国酒と燗</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chinese alcoholic beverages and kan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Warming Chinese alcoholic beverages</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Warming Chinese alcoholic beverages</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="57">
<j>中国の醸造酒（黄酒）である紹興酒もまた、燗をつけて飲むことがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shaoxing rice wine, which is a Chinese brewage (Huangjiu) is also being drunk by putting kan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chinese brewage (Huangjiu) called Shaoxing rice wine is sometimes warmed up, too, when consumed.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chinese brewage (Huangjiu) called Shaoxing rice wine is sometimes warmed up, too, when consumed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>日本酒の場合と同様で、暑い時期にはあまり行われず、寒い時期に多く行われる傾向にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is not so much done in hot period, and tend to be done a lot in cold period, like in Japanese sake.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Like in Japanese sake, warming Shaoxing rice wine is rare during hot season, but often during cold season.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Like in Japanese sake, warming Shaoxing rice wine is rare during hot season, but often done during cold season.</e>
<cmt>doneを追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>また、基本的にスパイスや砂糖などが加えられることはなく、加水も行わない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, basically spice and sugar are not added, and water is not added, either.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, no spice, sugar or water is basically added.</e>
<cmt>basically spice and sugar are not added, and water is not added, either をno spice, sugar or water is basically added に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, no spice, sugar or water is basically added.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="16">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="60">
<j>日本酒を燗するのと同様に、紹興酒などの黄酒を燗することも古くから行われてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Like doing kan to Japanese sake, doing kan to Huangjiu such as Shaoxing rice wine has been done from old times, too.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Like warming Japanese sake, warming Huangjiu such as Shaoxing rice wine has been done from old times.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Like warming Japanese sake, warming Huangjiu such as Shaoxing rice wine has been done from old times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="17">
<tit>
<j>焼酎と燗</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shochu and kan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Warming shochu</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Warming shochu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="61">
<j>日本酒の場合と同様で、暑い時期にはあまり行われず、寒い時期に多く行われる傾向にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is not so much done in hot period, and tend to be done a lot in cold period, like in Japanese sake.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Like in Japanese sake, warming Shaoxing rice wine is rare during hot season, but often during cold season.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Like in Japanese sake, warming Shaoxing rice wine is rare during hot season, but often done during cold season.</e>
<cmt>doneを追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>また、基本的にスパイスや砂糖などが加えられることはない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, basically spice and sugar are not added, and water is not added, either.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, no spice or sugar is basically added.</e>
<cmt>basically spice and sugar are not added, and water is not added, either. をno spice or sugar is basically added に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, no spice or sugar is basically added.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>ただし、日本酒とは違って加水が行われることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, not like in Japanese sake, water is sometimes added.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, not like in Japanese sake, water is sometimes added.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, not like in Japanese sake, water is sometimes added.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="18">
<tit>
<j>焼酎に燗を行うことの特殊性</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Specialty About Doing Kan to Shochu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Particularity of warming shochu</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Particularity of warming shochu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="19">
<tit>
<j>燗を行うことの特殊性</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Specialty about doing kan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Particularity of warming sake</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Particularity of warming sake</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="64">
<j>上記にもある通り、燗とは、酒自体を加熱する行為のことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Like mentioned above, kan is an action to warm up alcoholic beverage itself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As mentioned above, warming sake is an action to warm up alcoholic beverage itself.</e>
<cmt>Like mentioned above, kan をAs mentioned above, warming sake に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As mentioned above, warming sake is an action to warm up alcoholic beverage itself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>通常は、日本酒や中国酒の一部を飲む際に行われることもある行為だ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Normally, it is an action done in drinking Japanese sake and part of Chinese alcoholic beverages.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Normally, it is an action for Japanese sake and part of Chinese alcoholic beverages.</e>
<cmt>done in drinking を for に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Normally, it is an action for Japanese sake and part of Chinese alcoholic beverages.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>お湯割りとの違いは、加水（お湯を加える行為）を行わないで、酒の温度を上げている点にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The difference between oyuwari is that it raise up the temperature of alcoholic beverage with no kasui (action to add hot water).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The difference between oyuwari is that it raise up the temperature of alcoholic beverage without adding hot water.</e>
<cmt>with no kasui (action to add hot water) をwithout adding hot water に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The difference between oyuwari is that it raise up the temperature of alcoholic beverage without adding hot water.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>この燗を行うという行為自体、世界的に見ても珍しい飲酒法だ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This action itself, doing kan, is a unique way to drink alcoholic beverage if seen globally.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Warming sake itself is a unique way to drink alcoholic beverage if seen globally.</e>
<cmt>This action itself, doing kan, をWarming sake itself に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Warming sake itself is a unique way to drink alcoholic beverage if seen globally.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="20">
<tit>
<j>蒸留酒に燗を行うことの特殊性</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Specialty about doing kan to distilled spirits</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Particularity of warming distilled alcoholic beverage</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Particularity of warming distilled alcoholic beverage</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="68">
<j>焼酎は、日本酒とは違い、蒸留酒である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shochu, unlike Japanese sake, is a distilled spirit.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shochu, unlike Japanese sake, is a distilled alcoholic beverage.</e>
<cmt>spirit を alcoholic beverage に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shochu, unlike Japanese sake, is a distilled alcoholic beverage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>醸造酒を燗するのではなく、蒸留酒を燗するというのは、世界的に見て非常に珍しい飲酒法だ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Doing kan to distilled spirits, not to brewage, is very unique way to drink alcoholic beverage, if seen globally.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Warming not brewage but distilled alcoholic beverage is very unique, if seen globally.</e>
<cmt>Doing kan to distilled spirits, not to brewage, をWarming not brewage but distilled alcoholic beverage に修正しました。way to drink alcoholic beverage を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Warming not brewage but distilled alcoholic beverage is very unique, if seen globally.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>つまり、この蒸留酒を燗するという飲酒法は、醸造酒を燗することよりもさらに珍しい飲酒法なのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That is to say, doing kan to distilled spirit is more unique way to drink alcohol beverage than doing kan to brewage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That is to say, warming distilled alcoholic beverage is more unique way to drink than warming brewage.</e>
<cmt>doing kan to distilled spirit is more unique way to drink alcohol beverage than doing kan to brewage をwarming distilled alcoholic beverage is more unique way to drink than warming brewage に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That is to say, warming distilled alcoholic beverage is more unique way to drink than warming brewage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>焼酎に燗を行うというのは、非常に特殊な飲酒法であるとも言える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It can be said that doing kan to shochu is very special way to drink alcoholic beverage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It can be said that warming shochu is very special way to drink alcoholic beverage.</e>
<cmt>doing kan to を warming に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It can be said that warming shochu is very special way to drink alcoholic beverage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="21">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="72">
<j>かつて日本では、焼酎を燗して飲むという飲酒法が、よく行われていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At one time in Japan, it was common to do kan to shochu as a way to drink alcoholic beverage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At one time in Japan, it was common to warm shochu as a way to drink alcoholic beverage.</e>
<cmt>do kan to を warm に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At one time in Japan, it was common to warm shochu as a way to drink alcoholic beverage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>例えば日向国では、焼酎を入れた、日向燗徳利（ひゅうがちろり）と呼ばれる、素焼きで作られた酒器やスズで作られた酒器を、囲炉裏（いろり）にさして燗を行った上で、焼酎を飲んでいたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example in Hyuga Province, people drunk shochu by sticking Hyuga chirori, which is unglazed Japanese sake-related tool, or drinking vessels made of tin into irori fireplace (open hearth).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example in Hyuga Province, people used to enjoy warmed shochu by placing a vessel unglazed or made of tin called &apos;Hyuga chirori&apos; into irori fireplace (open hearth).</e>
<cmt>原文「素焼きで作られた日本酒日本酒に関する道具」を「素焼きで作られた酒器」に修正しました。people drunk shochu by sticking Hyuga chirori, which is unglazed Japanese sake-related tool, or drinking vessels made of tin をpeople used to enjoy warmed shochu by placing a vessel unglazed or made of tin called &apos;Hyuga chirori&apos; に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example in Hyuga Province, people used to enjoy warmed shochu by placing a vessel unglazed or made of tin called &apos;Hyuga chirori&apos; into irori fireplace (open hearth).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>鹿児島県でも、焼酎に燗を付けて飲むことがあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shochu was sometimes being dunk by putting kan, too, in Kagoshima Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also in Kagoshima Prefecture, they sometimes had warmed shochu.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also in Kagoshima Prefecture, they sometimes had warmed shochu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>（現在でも、稀に焼酎を燗して飲むということが行われることもある。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(In rare cases, shochu with kan is being drunk in present days, too.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(They take warmed shochu infrequently even in present days.)</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(They take warmed shochu infrequently even in present days.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="76">
<j>この焼酎を燗して飲むという飲酒法は、日本酒を燗して飲む飲酒法がすでに存在していたことに起因するのではないかという説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is even a theory stating that this way of drinking alcohol beverage, doing kan to shochu, may have been originated from the way to drink Japanese sake with kan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is even a theory which states that the way of drinking warmed shochu may have originated from the way of drinking warmed Japanese sake.</e>
<cmt>stating that this way of drinking alcohol beverage, doing kan to shochu, may have been originated from the way to drink Japanese sake with kan. をwhich states that the way of drinking warmed shochu may have originated from the way of drinking warmed Japanese sake に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is even a theory which states that the way of drinking warmed shochu may have originated from the way of drinking warmed Japanese sake.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>つまり、焼酎の登場が日本酒の登場よりも、ずっと後であったために、日本酒の飲み方が、そのまま焼酎にも当てはめられたのではないか、というわけだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In other words, since shochu appeared much later than Japanese sake, the way to drink Japanese sake was directly applied to shochu, too.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In other words, since shochu appeared much later than Japanese sake, the way to drink Japanese sake was directly applied to shochu, too.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In other words, since shochu appeared much later than Japanese sake, the way to drink Japanese sake was directly applied to shochu, too.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="22">
<tit>
<j>燗の現状 (焼酎)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Current situation of kan (shochu)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Current situation of warming shochu</e>
<cmt>kan (shochu) を warming shochu に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Current situation of warming shochu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="78">
<j>燗をして飲まれる焼酎は、アルコール度数が低いことが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most of shochu which are drunk by doing kan contain less alcohol.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most of shochu which are warmed and drunk contain less alcohol.</e>
<cmt>drunk by doing kan をwarmed and drunk に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most of shochu which are warmed and drunk contain less alcohol.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>なお、アルコール度数が高い焼酎（特にアルコール度数35％を超える焼酎）は、加水（水、または、湯を加える行為）を行って、アルコール度数を下げてから燗をすることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, shochu with high alcohol (especially shochu with more than 35% alcohol) sometimes have kan done after they had kasui (action to adding water or hot water) and had their alcohol level lowered.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, shochu with high alcohol (especially those of more than 35%) are sometimes added water or hot water in order to lower its alcohol level then warmed up.</e>
<cmt>(Especially 以下を全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, shochu with high alcohol (especially those of more than 35%) are sometimes added water or hot water in order to lower its alcohol level then warmed up.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>しかし、アルコール度数が高い焼酎の場合は、お湯で割ることにより、燗の代わりとして飲むことが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it is common for shochu with high alcohol to be drunk by mixing with hot water, instead of doing kan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is common for shochu with high alcohol to be drunk by mixing with hot water, instead of being warmed.</e>
<cmt>doing kan をbeing warmed に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is common for shochu with high alcohol to be drunk by mixing with hot water, instead of being warmed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>お湯で割れば自動的に温度が上がるからである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is because mixing with hot water automatically raise up the temperature.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is because mixing with hot water automatically raises up the temperature.</e>
<cmt>raise を raises に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is because mixing with hot water automatically raises up the temperature.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="82">
<j>ただし、お湯で割っただけの状態の場合、燗をしたとは言えない点に注意が必要だ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, note must be made that the condition in which hot water is mixed only can&apos;t be said as having kan done.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, we have to be careful to the fact that only mixing hot water does not mean warming shochu.</e>
<cmt>However 以下を全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, we have to be careful to the fact that only mixing hot water does not mean warming shochu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>つまり、たとえ焼酎にお湯を加えて温度が上昇したとしても、その後、さらに加熱を行わなければ、燗をしたとは言えないのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In other words, even if hot water is added to shochu and the temperature is raised, if there is not more heating in addition to that, it can&apos;t be said that kan had been done.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In other words, even if hot water is added to shochu and the temperature is raised, if there is not more heating in addition to that, it is not warming sake.</e>
<cmt>it can&apos;t be said that kan had been done をit is not warming sake に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In other words, even if hot water is added to shochu and the temperature is raised, if there is not more heating in addition to that, it is not warming sake.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>この点を混同してはならない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This point must not be mixed up.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">You should not confuse warmed shochu with oyuwari.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">You should not confuse warmed shochu with oyuwari.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="85">
<j>なお、事前（飲む前日以前に。直前ではない。）に、加水（お湯は使用しない。）しておくことを、前割りと呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, adding water (hot water is not used) before drinking (before the day before drinking, not the moment right before drinking) is called maewari.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, adding water (not hot water) one day or more prior to the drinking (not right before drinking) is called &apos;maewari&apos; (pre-dilution).</e>
<cmt>Meanwhile 以下を全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, adding water (not hot water) one day or more prior to the drinking (not right before drinking) is called &apos;maewari&apos; (pre-dilution).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>前割りすることで焼酎と水が馴染むため、前割りした焼酎を燗すれば、お湯割りよりもまろやかさが増す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Maewari settles shochu and water, so if the shochu with maewari had kan done, the mellowness will be increased more than that of oyuwari.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Maewari settles shochu and water, so once already-diluted shochu is warmed, it tastes mellower than oyuwari.</e>
<cmt>if the shochu with maewari had kan done, the mellowness will be increased more than that of oyuwari をonce already-diluted shochu is warmed, it tastes mellower than oyuwari に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Maewari settles shochu and water, so once already-diluted shochu is warmed, it tastes mellower than oyuwari.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="87">
<j>焼酎を燗するための酒器に薩摩焼の「黒ぢょか」がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is Satsuma ware called &apos;Kurojoka&apos; as a Japanese sake related tool to do kan for shochu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is Satsuma ware called &apos;Kurojoka&apos; as a Japanese sake related tool to warm shochu.</e>
<cmt>原文「日本酒日本酒に関する道具」を「酒器」に修正しました。do kan for shochu を to warm shochu に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is Satsuma ware called &apos;Kurojoka&apos; as a Japanese sake related tool to warm shochu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>「黒ぢょか」で燗をする場合は前割りした方が好ましい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When doing kan with &apos;Kurojoka,&apos; maewari is recommended.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If you are going to enjoy warmed &apos;Kurojoka,&apos; maewari is recommended.</e>
<cmt>When doing kan with &apos;Kurojoka,&apos; をIf you are going to enjoy warmed &apos;Kurojoka,&apos; に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If you are going to enjoy warmed &apos;Kurojoka,&apos; maewari is recommended.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>まれに、電子レンジに入れて燗をつけることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rarely, it has kan done by putting into microwave.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On rare occasions, people use a microwave to warm Kurojoka.</e>
<cmt>Meanwhile 以下を全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On rare occasions, people use a microwave to warm Kurojoka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>1980年代の鹿児島県では、この飲み方が基本であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This way of drinking was common in Kagoshima Prefecture in 1980&apos;s.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This way of drinking was common in Kagoshima Prefecture in 1980&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This way of drinking was common in Kagoshima Prefecture in 1980&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="91">
<j>この焼酎に燗をするというのは、あくまで現在では稀に行われることもある焼酎の飲み方である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Consistently, doing kan to shochu is a way to drink shochu which is rarely done in present days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nowadays, they rarely enjoy the warm shochu.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nowadays, they rarely enjoy the warm shochu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>たとえ、かつては燗して飲まれたものと同じ焼酎であっても、現在では、室温のままストレート、水割り、お湯割りなどが圧倒的に多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even if it is the same kind of shochu with the ones that had been drunk by doing kan back then, it is overwhelmingly common in present days for it to be drunk straight in room temperature, mixed with water, or mixed with hot water.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even if it is the same kind of shochu with the ones that had been drunk by warming up back then, it is overwhelmingly common in present days for it to be drunk straight in room temperature, mixed with water, or mixed with hot water.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even if it is the same kind of shochu with the ones that had been drunk by warming up back then, it is overwhelmingly common in present days for it to be drunk straight in room temperature, mixed with water, or mixed with hot water.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>さらには、燗とは全く逆に、冷蔵庫や氷などを用い冷やした上で、焼酎を飲むということまで行われることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, in complete opposition to kan, sometimes shochu is even drunk cold by using refrigerator and ice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, in an opposite manner to warm shochu, shochu refrigerated or cooled down by ice are drunk.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, in an opposite manner to warm shochu, shochu refrigerated or cooled down by ice are drunk.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>普通、焼酎に燗をして飲まれることは無くなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In common situations, a way to drink shochu with kan is not done anymore.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In common situations, ｗarmed shochu has not consumed any more.</e>
<cmt>a way to drink shochu with kan is not done anymore をｗarmed shochu has not consumed any more に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In common situations, ｗarmed shochu has not consumed any more.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="23">
<tit>
<j>ワインと燗</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wine and kan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Warming wine</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Warming wine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="95">
<j>ヨーロッパでは赤ワインにスパイス（シナモンやクローブなど）や砂糖などを加えて燗をつけたグリューワインがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Europe, there is gluhwein (mulled wine) which is red wine with spices (cinnamon and clove) and sugar added and had kan put.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Europe, there is gluhwein (mulled wine) which is warmed red wine with spices (cinnamon and clove) and sugar added.</e>
<cmt>red wine with spices (cinnamon and clove) and sugar added and had kan put をwarmed red wine with spices (cinnamon and clove) and sugar added に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Europe, there is gluhwein (mulled wine) which is warmed red wine with spices (cinnamon and clove) and sugar added.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>しかし、日本酒、中国酒、焼酎の場合は、基本的に何も加えずに燗を行うのだが、対してグリューワインの場合はスパイスなどを加えるため、カクテルとしての扱いとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in Japanese sake, Chinese alcoholic beverage, and shochu, basically kan is done with nothing added, and since on the other hand gluhwein has spices and so on added, it is treated as a cocktail.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese sake, Chinese alcoholic beverage or shochu is warmed with nothing added, however, on the other hand, as warm gluhwein contains spices etc., it is classified into cocktail.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese sake, Chinese alcoholic beverage or shochu is warmed with nothing added, however, on the other hand, as warm gluhwein contains spices etc., it is classified into cocktail.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="24">
<tit>
<j>その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Others</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="97">
<j>富久娘酒造の燗番娘のように、火を用いずに燗を行えるようになっているものも存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Like Kanban musume of FUKUMUSUME SAKE BREWERY CO.,LTD., there are products that enable kan to be done without using fire.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Like Kanban musume of FUKUMUSUME SAKE BREWERY CO.,LTD., some products can heat sake without using fire.</e>
<cmt>there are products that enable kan to be done をsome products can heat sake に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Like Kanban musume of FUKUMUSUME SAKE BREWERY CO.,LTD., some products can heat sake without using fire.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>生石灰（酸化カルシウム）と水を混合した時に起こる発熱反応を利用している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It uses exothermic reaction, which occurs when quicklime (calcium oxide) is mixed up with water.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They use an exothermic reaction caused by quicklime (calcium oxide) mixed up with water.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They use an exothermic reaction caused by quicklime (calcium oxide) mixed up with water.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 ねこぱんだ(id:35119), Ranjin(id:11831), Laichuan Yinfu(id:152533), Iwai.masaharu(id:50663), Corwin(id:973), G-Sounds(id:198992), Peek-poke(id:68004), 和太郎(id:86064), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>