<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>伝統野菜</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Traditional vegetables</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Traditional vegetables</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Traditional vegetables</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>伝統野菜（でんとうやさい）とは、各地で古くから栽培・利用されてきた野菜の在来品種。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Traditional vegitables are vegetables of native varieties, which has been cultivated in various places since ancient times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Traditional vegetables are vegetables of native varieties that have been cultivated in various places since the ancient times.</e>
<cmt>&quot;vegitables&quot; changed to &quot;vegetables,&quot; &quot;has&quot; changed to &quot;have,&quot; &quot;the&quot; added before &quot;ancient times&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Traditional vegetables are vegetables of native varieties that have been cultivated in various places since the ancient times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>地方野菜とも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are also called local vegetables.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are also called local vegetables.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are also called local vegetables.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>1970年代以降、生産・流通・販売におけるコスト要素から、大消費地向けにはほとんど消滅した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the 1970s, their cultivation for mass consumption areas has been almost disappeared due to their production, distribution, and sales cost elements.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of costs associated with production, distribution and sales, they have been rarely cultivated for shipment to mass-consumption areas since the 1970s.</e>
<cmt>sentence reworded</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of costs associated with production, distribution and sales, they have been rarely cultivated for shipment to mass-consumption areas since the 1970s.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>近年は、農家の自家需要などで生存していた品種を、産地の地域おこしとして取り入れ、近傍の都市向けには地産地消商品、大都市圏向けにはスローフード商品とする戦略などがみられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such strategies as to incorporate vegetables of indigenous varieties, which have been existing for self-demend of farmers, into the local market to boost the development of the producing areas, to ship these vegetables to neighboring cities as locally produced products for local consumption, and to metropolitan areas as slow-food products, can be seen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of the strategies used in recent years is to take the indigenous varieties of vegetables, which had been grown solely for the farmer&apos;s own consumption, and incorporate them into the local market to reinvigorate the producer areas, sell them to neighboring cities as local produce, and ship them to metropolitan areas as &quot;slow-food&quot; products.</e>
<cmt>sentence rewritten</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of the strategies used in recent years is to take the indigenous varieties of vegetables, which had been grown solely for the farmer&apos;s own consumption, and incorporate them into the local market to reinvigorate the producer areas, sell them to neighboring cities as local produce, and ship them to metropolitan areas as &quot;slow-food&quot; products.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 飯屋(id:269956), Okia(id:73923), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>