<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>経凛々</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyo rin rin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyo rin rin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyo rin rin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>経凛々（きょうりんりん）は、鳥山石燕の妖怪画集『百器徒然袋』にある日本の妖怪の一つで、経典の妖怪。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyo rin rin is one of Japanese specters drawn in &quot;Hyakki Tsurezure Bukuro&quot; (One hundred bags in idleness), a collection of specters illustrations by Sekien TORIYAMA; and it is a specter of Buddhist scriptures.</e>
<cmt>『百器徒然袋』－定訳不明。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A Kyo rin rin is one of Japanese yokai (ghosts, spirits and monsters) that was portrayed in Sekien TORIYAMA&apos;s yokai art collection book: &quot;Hyakki Tsurezure Bukuro&quot; (The Bag of One Hundred Random Demons; the term &apos;hyakki&apos; in its title is a pun on the usual hyakki, replacing the character for demon which is written as &quot;鬼&quot; in Japanese with a character for vessel written as &quot;器,&quot; and sure enough, most of the yokais shown in this book are tsukumogami [a type of Japanese spirits that originate in items or artifacts that have reached their 100th birthday and become alive]), and a yokai of Buddhist scriptures.</e>
<cmt>表現、補足訳</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A Kyo rin rin is one of Japanese yokai (ghosts, spirits and monsters) that was portrayed in Sekien TORIYAMA&apos;s yokai art collection book: &quot;Hyakki Tsurezure Bukuro&quot; (The Bag of One Hundred Random Demons; the term &apos;hyakki&apos; in its title is a pun on the usual hyakki, replacing the character for demon which is written as &quot;鬼&quot; in Japanese with a character for vessel written as &quot;器,&quot; and sure enough, most of the yokais shown in this book are tsukumogami [a type of Japanese spirits that originate in items or artifacts that have reached their 100th birthday and become alive]), and a yokai of Buddhist scriptures.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>くちばしを持つ妖怪が頭に経文を巻いた姿で描かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is portrayed as a specter with a bill putting scrolls of sutras on its head.</e>
<cmt>原文「頭に経文を巻いた」からは頭に巻物を巻きつけた姿が思い浮かびますが、実際の画を見て訳文のようにしました。　http://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E3%83%95%E3%82%A1%E3%82%A4%E3%83%AB:SekienKyorinrin.jpg</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is portrayed as a yokai with a beak, having scrolls of sutras tied up on the both sides of the head.</e>
<cmt>言い回し、正確化</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is portrayed as a yokai with a beak, having scrolls of sutras tied up on the both sides of the head.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>軍記物語『太平記』にある平安時代前期の僧・守敏の逸話をもとに石燕が創作した妖怪とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said to be a specter created by Sekien based on an anecdote about Shubin, a Buddhist monk of the early Heian period; which is written in a war chronicle &quot;Taiheiki&quot; (The Record of the Great Peace).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said to be a yokai created by Sekien based on an anecdote about Shubin, a Buddhist monk of the early Heian period, which appeared in a war chronicle &quot;Taiheiki&quot; (The Record of the Great Peace).</e>
<cmt>用語、言い回し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said to be a yokai created by Sekien based on an anecdote about Shubin, a Buddhist monk of the early Heian period, which appeared in a war chronicle &quot;Taiheiki&quot; (The Record of the Great Peace).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>守敏は京都西寺の祈祷僧として知られていたが、東寺の僧・空海との法力比べで敗れ去った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Shubin had been known as a Buddhist monk for offering prayers in Sai-ji Temple of Kyoto, he lost the match in power of Buddhism with Kukai, a Buddhist monk of Toji Temple.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Shubin had been known as a Buddhist monk for offering prayers in Sai-ji Temple of Kyoto, he lost the match in power of Buddhism with Kukai, a Buddhist monk of Toji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Shubin had been known as a Buddhist monk for offering prayers in Sai-ji Temple of Kyoto, he lost the match in power of Buddhism with Kukai, a Buddhist monk of Toji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>不用となって捨てられた守敏の経文が付喪神と化したものが経凛々とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shubin&apos;s scriptures were discarded as useless and became tsukumogami (the spirits of discarded object); thus Kyo rin rin came into being.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shubin&apos;s scriptures were discarded as useless and became the tsukumogami, and Kyo rin rin thus came into being.</e>
<cmt>言い回し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shubin&apos;s scriptures were discarded as useless and became the tsukumogami, and Kyo rin rin thus came into being.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>また『百器徒然袋』の妖怪は、室町時代の妖怪絵巻『百鬼夜行絵巻』をモチーフとして描かれたものが多いが、この経凛々についても同様、『百鬼夜行絵巻』の中にある、くちばしの長い鳥状の妖怪が経文を頭に巻いている姿にデザイン上の共通点が見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many specters in &quot;Hyakki Tsurezure Bukuro&quot; were drawn borrowing motifs from &quot;Picture scroll of Hyakki yagyo,&quot; specter emaki (picture scroll) of Muromachi period; Kyo rin rin also share common features with a specter in &quot;Picture scroll of Hyakki yagyo&quot;: a long bill, bird-like shape, and Buddhist scriptures on the head.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many yokais in the &quot;Hyakki Tsurezure Bukuro&quot; were drawn borrowing motifs from &quot;Hyakki yagyo emaki&quot; (&apos;Night Parade of One Hundred Demons&apos; picture scroll) of the Muromachi period, and the Kyo rin rin also share the common features in terms of a design of a bird monster having a long beak and Buddhist sutra scrolls tied up on the head, with a yokai in the &quot;Hyakki yagyo emaki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>言い回し、補足</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many yokais in the &quot;Hyakki Tsurezure Bukuro&quot; were drawn borrowing motifs from &quot;Hyakki yagyo emaki&quot; (&apos;Night Parade of One Hundred Demons&apos; picture scroll) of the Muromachi period, and the Kyo rin rin also share the common features in terms of a design of a bird monster having a long beak and Buddhist sutra scrolls tied up on the head, with a yokai in the &quot;Hyakki yagyo emaki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 逃亡者(id:14864), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>