<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>武田流</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takeda-ryu school</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takeda-ryu school</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takeda-ryu school</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>武田流（たけだりゅう）は弓術・馬術・礼法などからなる弓馬軍礼故実（弓馬故実・武家故実）の流派。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takeda-ryu is one of the schools of the Kyuba-gunrei Kojitsu (Japanese ancient practices of customs about archery, equestrian and military etiquette).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takeda-ryu is one of the schools of the Kyuba-gunrei Kojitsu (Japanese ancient practices of customs about archery, equestrian and military etiquette).</e>
<cmt>スペースを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takeda-ryu is one of the schools of the Kyuba-gunrei Kojitsu (Japanese ancient practices of customs about archery, equestrian and military etiquette).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>細川流とも呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This school was also called Hosokawa-ryu (Hosokawa school)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This school was also called Hosokawa-ryu (Hosokawa school).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを挿入しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This school was also called Hosokawa-ryu (Hosokawa school).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>小笠原流と同じく、流鏑馬に代表される弓馬故実を伝える流派である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Like Ogasawara-ryu school, the school inherits Kyuba kojitsu (the ancient practices of customs about archery and equestrianism) that Yabusame represents.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Just the same as Ogasawara-ryu school, the school inherits Kyuba kojitsu (the ancient practices of customs about archery and equestrianism) that Yabusame represents.</e>
<cmt>Like→Just the same as と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Just the same as Ogasawara-ryu school, the school inherits Kyuba kojitsu (the ancient practices of customs about archery and equestrianism) that Yabusame represents.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>現在は起源を同じくする３団体、武田流騎射流鏑馬（武田流騎射流鏑馬保存会：熊本市）、武田流弓馬道（社団法人大日本弓馬会：鎌倉市）、武田流鎌倉派（日本古式弓馬術協会：鎌倉市）が存在し、それぞれ武田流を名乗り活動している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The three associations from the same origin, Takeda-ryu Kisha Yabusame (Takeda-ryu Kisha Yabusame Preservation Society, Kumamoto City), Takeda-ryu Kyubado (The Japan Equestrian Archery Association, Kamakura City) and Takeda-ryu Kamakura school (Japanese traditional archery on horseback association, Kamakura City) are active identifying themselves as Takeda-ryu school</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The three associations which come from the same origin, Takeda-ryu Kisha Yabusame (Takeda-ryu Kisha Yabusame Preservation Society, Kumamoto City), The Takeda School of Horseback Archery (The Japan Equestrian Archery Association, Kamakura City) and Takeda-ryu Kamakura school (Japanese traditional archery on horseback association, Kamakura City) are active identifying themselves as Takeda-ryu school.</e>
<cmt>which come を挿入しました。武田流弓馬道: The Takeda School of Horseback Archery と修正しました。ピリオドを挿入しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The three associations which come from the same origin, Takeda-ryu Kisha Yabusame (Takeda-ryu Kisha Yabusame Preservation Society, Kumamoto City), The Takeda School of Horseback Archery (The Japan Equestrian Archery Association, Kamakura City) and Takeda-ryu Kamakura school (Japanese traditional archery on horseback association, Kamakura City) are active identifying themselves as Takeda-ryu school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>両団体の伝承は若干異なるが、概略を述べる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following is the summery of the history of Takeda-ryu, although the three associations have slightly different traditions.</e>
<cmt>「両」団体となっていますが、前列を受けて３団体で訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following is the summery of the history of Takeda-ryu, although the three associations have slightly different traditions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following is the summery of the history of Takeda-ryu, although the three associations have slightly different traditions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>起源～安土桃山時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the origin to the Azuchi Momoyama Period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the origin to the Azuchi Momoyama Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the origin to the Azuchi Momoyama Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>清和天皇の皇子貞純親王が、朝廷の諸儀礼に通じていた源能有（文徳天皇皇子）から故実を伝授されたのが起源であるという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The origin is said that Imperial Prince Sadazumi, a son of Emperor Shinwa received instruction of the ancient practices from MINAMOTO no Yoshiari (a son of Emperor Buntoku) who was familiar with etiquettes of the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The origin is said to be that Imperial Prince Sadazumi, a son of Emperor Seiwa received the instruction of the ancient practices from MINAMOTO no Yoshiari (a son of Emperor Buntoku) who was familiar with manners of the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>スペースの修正、Emperor Shinwa→Emperor Seiwa,etiquettes→manners と修正し、the を挿入しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The origin is said to be that Imperial Prince Sadazumi, a son of Emperor Seiwa received the instruction of the ancient practices from MINAMOTO no Yoshiari (a son of Emperor Buntoku) who was familiar with manners of the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>その後清和源氏を経て 武田氏・小笠原氏に伝えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then it was handed down to the Takeda clan and the Ogasawara clan through Seiwa-Genji (Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then it was handed down to the Takeda clan and the Ogasawara clan through Seiwa-Genji (Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then it was handed down to the Takeda clan and the Ogasawara clan through Seiwa-Genji (Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>武田氏では武田氏安芸武田氏に伝えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the Takeda clan, it was handed down to the Takeda clan Aki Takeda clan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the Takeda clan, it was handed down to the Takeda clan of Aki, Aki Takeda clan.</e>
<cmt>Takeda clan of Aki として、理解がスムースになるよう補強しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the Takeda clan, it was handed down to the Takeda clan of Aki, Aki Takeda clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>安芸武田氏が若狭国守護職を得たことから武田氏若狭武田氏に伝わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Aki Takeda clan held Wakasa shugoshiki (the military governor of Wakasa Province), the Tekeda clan Wakasa Takeda clan inherited the ancient practices.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Aki Takeda clan held Wakasa shugoshiki (the military governor of Wakasa Province), the Tekeda clan of Wakasa, Wakasa Takeda clan inherited the ancient practices.</e>
<cmt>Takeda clan of Wakasa として、理解がスムースになるよう補強しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Aki Takeda clan held Wakasa shugoshiki (the military governor of Wakasa Province), the Tekeda clan of Wakasa, Wakasa Takeda clan inherited the ancient practices.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>安土桃山時代に若狭武田氏が滅亡すると、武田信直（吸松斎）から姻戚（下記参照）の細川幽斎（幽斎）に伝授された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Wakasa Takeda clan fell in the Azuchi Momoyama Period, it was handed down to Yusai HOSOKAWA (called Yusai), through Nobunao TAKEDA (called Kyushosai), who was a relative of Yusai (see below).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Wakasa Takeda clan collapsed in the Azuchi Momoyama period, it was handed down to Yusai HOSOKAWA (called Yusai), through Nobunao TAKEDA (called Kyushosai), who was a relative of Yusai (see below).</e>
<cmt>fell→collapsed,Period→period と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Wakasa Takeda clan collapsed in the Azuchi Momoyama period, it was handed down to Yusai HOSOKAWA (called Yusai), through Nobunao TAKEDA (called Kyushosai), who was a relative of Yusai (see below).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="13">
<j>歴代のうち、武田元信・元光・信豊は騎射に優れ、弓馬故実書を書写・著述した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the Wakasa Takeda clan, Motonobu, Motomitsu and Nobutoyo TAKEDA excelled in horseback archery and they copied or wrote a book of Kyuba Kojitsu.</e>
<cmt>この文章ですと主語がはっきりしないので、元信、元光、信豊三人が「弓馬故実書」を書いたようですが、調べる限り元信しか言及されていません。ただし、原文から外れないよう　they　で訳しました。　出典　http://www.archives.pref.fukui.jp/fukui/07/kenshi/T2/T2-6-01-04-02-03.htm　</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the Wakasa Takeda clan, Motonobu, Motomitsu and Nobutoyo TAKEDA excelled in horseback archery and they copied or wrote the books of Kyuba Kojitsu.</e>
<cmt>a book→the books と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the Wakasa Takeda clan, Motonobu, Motomitsu and Nobutoyo TAKEDA excelled in horseback archery and they copied or wrote the books of Kyuba Kojitsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>信豊以降の信時・信恭・信直などは一般的な若狭武田氏の系図には見られない人物であり、信直の経歴は不詳である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Nobutoyo, successive Nobutoki, Nobuyasu and Nobutada TAKEDA were not shown in the general Wakasa Takeda clan record and the biography of Noobutada is unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Nobutoyo, his successors Nobutoki, Nobuyasu and Nobunao TAKEDA were not shown in the general record of Wakasa Takeda clan, and the biography of Nobunao is unknown.</e>
<cmt>succesive→his successors,Nobutada→Nobunao,Noobutada→Nobunao,record of として位置を修正し、カンマを挿入しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Nobutoyo, his successors Nobutoki, Nobuyasu and Nobunao TAKEDA were not shown in the general record of Wakasa Takeda clan, and the biography of Nobunao is unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="15">
<j>若狭武田氏と細川氏の関係であるが、幽斎の姉は武田信豊の弟、武田信高 (戦国武将)（宮川殿、若狭新保山城主）に嫁していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for the relationship between the Wakasa Takeda clan and the Hosokawa clan, Yusai&apos;s older sister married Nobutaka TAKEDA (a military commander, called Miyagawa Dono, the castellan of Wakasa Shibo Yama), who was the younger brother of Nobutoyo TAKEDA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for the connection between the Wakasa Takeda clan and the Hosokawa clan, Yusai&apos;s older sister married Nobutaka TAKEDA (a military commander, called Miyagawa Dono, the castellan of Wakasa Shibo Yama), who was the younger brother of Nobutoyo TAKEDA.</e>
<cmt>relationship→connectionと修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for the connection between the Wakasa Takeda clan and the Hosokawa clan, Yusai&apos;s older sister married Nobutaka TAKEDA (a military commander, called Miyagawa Dono, the castellan of Wakasa Shibo Yama), who was the younger brother of Nobutoyo TAKEDA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>信高も騎射に秀でて弓馬故実書を伝えており、その子の英甫永雄も多くの故実書を所有していたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobutaka, also excelled in horseback archery, handed down the book of Kyuba Kojitsu and his son Eiyu EIHO possessed many books of Kojitsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobutaka, also excelled in horseback archery, handed down the book of Kyuba Kojitsu and his son Eiyu EIHO possessed many books of Kojitsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobutaka, also excelled in horseback archery, handed down the book of Kyuba Kojitsu and his son Eiyu EIHO possessed many books of Kojitsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="17">
<j>武田流弓馬道（鎌倉）は、「幽斎の妹が安芸武田氏の信重（光広、安国寺恵瓊の父とされる）に嫁した」とし、「信直は光広の弟か」としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takeda-ryu Kyubado (Kamakura City) insists &quot;Yusai&apos;s younger siter married Nobushige (considered a father of Mitsuhiro and Ekei ANKOKUJI) from the Aki Takeda clan&quot; &quot;Nobutada could be a younger brother of Mitsuhiro&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takeda-ryu Kyubado (Kamakura City) insists &apos;Yusai&apos;s younger sister married Nobushige from the Aki Takeda clan&apos; (considered a father of Mitsuhiro and Ekei ANKOKUJI), &apos;Nobunao could be a younger brother of Mitsuhiro.&apos;</e>
<cmt>引用符を修正しました。ピリオドの位置を修正しました。siter→sister,Nobutada→Nobunao と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takeda-ryu Kyubado (Kamakura City) insists &apos;Yusai&apos;s younger sister married Nobushige from the Aki Takeda clan&apos; (considered a father of Mitsuhiro and Ekei ANKOKUJI), &apos;Nobunao could be a younger brother of Mitsuhiro.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="18">
<j>江戸時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the Edo Period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Edo Period</e>
<cmt>the→The と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Edo Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>幽斎の後は細川家で細川忠興、 細川忠利と継承された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Yusai, successive Tadaoki Hosokawathe, then Tadatoshi Hosokawa of the Hosokawa family inherited the ancient practices.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Yusai, his successors Tadaoki HOSOKAWA, then Tadatoshi HOSOKAWA of the Hosokawa family inherited the ancient practices.</e>
<cmt>successive→his successors,Hosokawath, hosokawa→HOSOKAWA と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Yusai, his successors Tadaoki HOSOKAWA, then Tadatoshi HOSOKAWA of the Hosokawa family inherited the ancient practices.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>しかし、忠利は家臣の竹原惟成に継承させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Tadatoshi handed it down to his vassal, Koreshige TAKEHARA.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Tadatoshi handed it down to his vassal, Koreshige TAKEHARA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Tadatoshi handed it down to his vassal, Koreshige TAKEHARA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>以後は竹原家が継承し、熊本藩藩校時習館では二条流和歌や礼法とともに武田流の流鏑馬が必修科目とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, the Takehara family inherited it and at Jishukan, a domain school of the Kumamoto domain, Yabusame of Takeda-ryu became a compulsory subject along with Nijyo style waka (Japanese traditional poems) and manners.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, the Takehara family inherited it and at Jishukan, a domain school of the Kumamoto Domain, Yabusame of Takeda-ryu became a compulsory subject along with Nijyo style waka (Japanese traditional poems) and manners.</e>
<cmt>domain→Domain と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, the Takehara family inherited it and at Jishukan, a domain school of the Kumamoto Domain, Yabusame of Takeda-ryu became a compulsory subject along with Nijyo style waka (Japanese traditional poems) and manners.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>笠懸・犬追物・草鹿なども稽古された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kasagake (bamboo-hat target shooting), Inuoimono (dog shooting),Kusajishi (grass deer shooting) and others were also practiced.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kasagake (bamboo-hat target shooting), Iinuoumono (dog-hunting event, a skill of an archery), Kusajishi and others were also practiced.</e>
<cmt>Inouoimono→inuoumono と修正し、カッコ内を修正しました。カンマを修正しました。&quot;grass deer shooting&quot;は意味が不明であるので削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kasagake (bamboo-hat target shooting), Iinuoumono (dog-hunting event, a skill of an archery), Kusajishi and others were also practiced.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>ちなみに、細川重賢藩政改革（宝暦の改革）を行った堀勝名（平太左衛門）を藩主細川重賢に推薦したのは、竹原惟成の五代後の竹原惟親（勘十郎）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By the way, Korechika TAKEHARA (Kanjuro), the fifth generation from Korenari TAKEHARA recommended Katsuna HORI (Heitazaemon), to Shigetaka HOSOKAWA., a lord of the domain and Katsuna operated the reformation of domain duties of Shigetaka HOSOKAWA (the reformation of Horeki)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By the way, Korechika TAKEHARA (Kanjuro), the fifth generation from Korenari TAKEHARA recommended Katsuna HORI (Heitazaemon), to Shigekata HOSOKAWA, a lord of the domain and Katsuna operated the reformation of domain duties of Shigetaka HOSOKAWA (the reformation of Horeki).</e>
<cmt>Shigetaka→Shigekata,ピリオドの位置を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By the way, Korechika TAKEHARA (Kanjuro), the fifth generation from Korenari TAKEHARA recommended Katsuna HORI (Heitazaemon), to Shigekata HOSOKAWA, a lord of the domain and Katsuna operated the reformation of domain duties of Shigetaka HOSOKAWA (the reformation of Horeki).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="24">
<j>熊本藩には室町幕府の弓馬師範家であった京都小笠原氏（備前小笠原家）もおり、故実を伝えていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Kumamoto domain, the Kyoto Ogasawara clan (the Bizen Ogasawara family) who was the master of Kyuba in the Muromachi Period also inherited the ancient practices.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処　</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Kumamoto Domain, there was the Kyoto Ogasawara clan (the Bizen Ogasawara family) who was the master of Kyuba in the Muromachi period also inherited the ancient practices.</e>
<cmt>domain→Domain,Period→period,there was を挿入しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Kumamoto Domain, there was the Kyoto Ogasawara clan (the Bizen Ogasawara family) who was the master of Kyuba in the Muromachi period also inherited the ancient practices.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>維新後に活動を停止し、その装束・伝書などは武田流弓馬道（鎌倉）に引き継がれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, they ceased the activity after the Restoration and Takeda-ryu Kyubado (Kamakura) took over their style of costumes, books and so on.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, they ceased the activity after the restoration, and Takeda-ryu Kyubado (Kamakura) took over their costumes, books and so on.</e>
<cmt>Restoration→restoration,stye of を削除し、カンマを挿入しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, they ceased the activity after the restoration, and Takeda-ryu Kyubado (Kamakura) took over their costumes, books and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="26">
<j>明治以降</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Meiji Period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Meiji Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Meiji Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>明治維新で武家社会が終焉を迎えると活動を一時中絶するが、竹原家や旧藩士の尽力により保存された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When samurai society came to the end due to Meiji Restration, Takeda-ryu was temporally stopped the activity but it was preserved due to the Takeda family&apos;s and former clansmen&apos;s effort.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When samurai society came to the end due to Meiji Restoration, Takeda-ryu was temporally stopped the activity but it was preserved by the Takehara family&apos;s and former clansmen&apos;s effort.</e>
<cmt>Restration→Restoration,due to→by,Takeda→Takehara と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When samurai society came to the end due to Meiji Restoration, Takeda-ryu was temporally stopped the activity but it was preserved by the Takehara family&apos;s and former clansmen&apos;s effort.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>明治28年に竹原惟路が没した時に男子がなかったため、細川興増男爵（細川氏一門の子飼細川家〈長岡刑部家〉当主）に幽斎の印・伝統系図・伝書類などが預けられ、松井氏（旧家老家、八代城主）ら門人により伝統が守られたが、昭和5年に竹原家の後継者正文に返還された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1895, when Koremichi TAKEHARA died, since there were no men in the family, Yusai&apos;s seal, the family record, books and others were put under Baron Tadamasu HOSOKAWA&apos;s charge (a lord of the Nagaoka Gyobu family, a relative of the Hotokawa clan) and the Matsui clan (old Karo, the chief retainer family, the eighth castellan) and followers preserved the tradition until they gave them back to Masafumi, the heir of the Takehara family in 1930.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1895, when Koremichi TAKEHARA died, since there were no men in the family, Yusai&apos;s seal, the family record, books and others were put under Baron Tadamasu HOSOKAWA&apos;s charge (a lord of the Nagaoka Gyobu family, a relative of the Hotokawa clan) and the Matsui clan (old Karo, the chief retainer family, the eighth castellan) and followers preserved the tradition until they gave them back to Masafumi, the heir of the Takehara family in 1930.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1895, when Koremichi TAKEHARA died, since there were no men in the family, Yusai&apos;s seal, the family record, books and others were put under Baron Tadamasu HOSOKAWA&apos;s charge (a lord of the Nagaoka Gyobu family, a relative of the Hotokawa clan) and the Matsui clan (old Karo, the chief retainer family, the eighth castellan) and followers preserved the tradition until they gave them back to Masafumi, the heir of the Takehara family in 1930.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>竹原正文は昭和36年に武田流(細川流)騎射流鏑馬の技術保持者として熊本県無形文化財の指定を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1961, Masafumi TAKEHARA was designated an intangible cultural property of Kumamoto Prefecture as a holder of Takeda-ryu (Hosokawa Ryu) Kisya-ryu Yabusame technique.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1961, Masafumi TAKEHARA was designated an intangible cultural property of Kumamoto Prefecture as a holder of Takeda-ryu (Hosokawa-ryu) Kisya-ryu Yabusame technique.</e>
<cmt>Hosokawa Ryu→Hosokawa-ryu と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1961, Masafumi TAKEHARA was designated an intangible cultural property of Kumamoto Prefecture as a holder of Takeda-ryu (Hosokawa-ryu) Kisya-ryu Yabusame technique.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>昭和46年に武田流騎射流鏑馬保存会が熊本で発足し、昭和50年3月24日には同保存会が団体として熊本県の指定文化財に登録された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1971, Takeda-ryu Kisha Yabusame Preservation Society was established in Kumamoto Prefecture and on March 24, 1975, the preservation society was registered as a group of the cultural property designated by Kumamoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1971, Takeda-ryu Kisha Yabusame Preservation Society was established in Kumamoto Prefecture and on March 24, 1975, the preservation society was registered as a group of the cultural property designated by Kumamoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1971, Takeda-ryu Kisha Yabusame Preservation Society was established in Kumamoto Prefecture and on March 24, 1975, the preservation society was registered as a group of the cultural property designated by Kumamoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>現在は竹原陽次郎が「宗家師範（47代）」である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At present, Yojiro TAKEHARA is the 47th Grand Master.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At present, Yojiro TAKEHARA is the &apos;47th Grand Master.&apos;</e>
<cmt>引用符を挿入しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At present, Yojiro TAKEHARA is the &apos;47th Grand Master.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="32">
<j>これとは別に、明治～昭和期の高弟、井上平太の系統の団体が存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides it, there is another association from the line of Heita INOUE, who was a high-caliber disciple between the Meiji Period and the Showa Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides it, there is another association from the line of Heita INOUE, who was a high-caliber disciple between the Meiji period and the Showa period.</e>
<cmt>Period→period と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides it, there is another association from the line of Heita INOUE, who was a high-caliber disciple between the Meiji period and the Showa period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>竹原惟路の没後、旧熊本藩主の細川護久侯爵は井上平太に伝書一切を印可相伝させ、「第三十三代武田流司家」を襲名させたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that, when Koremichi TAKEHARA died, Marquis Morihisa HOSOKAWA, a lord of the former Kumamoto clan transmitted every book and art to Heita INOUE and made him succeed &quot;the 33rd Takeda-ryu tsukasake family&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that, after Koremichi TAKEHARA died, Marquis Morihisa HOSOKAWA, a lord of the former Kumamoto clan transmitted all books on the esoterica to Heita INOUE and made him succeed &apos;the 33rd Takeda-ryu tsukasake family.&apos;</e>
<cmt>when→after,every book and art→all books on the esoterica,引用符、ピリオドの位置を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that, after Koremichi TAKEHARA died, Marquis Morihisa HOSOKAWA, a lord of the former Kumamoto clan transmitted all books on the esoterica to Heita INOUE and made him succeed &apos;the 33rd Takeda-ryu tsukasake family.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>井上は昭和8年に没し、翌9年に井上の弟子金子有鄰が細川護立侯爵（当時の細川家当主）の許しを得て、細川侯・熊本県知事立会のもと、「三十四代武田流弓馬軍礼故実司家」を相伝した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1933 INOUE died, and in 1934, his disciple Yurin KANEKO obtained permission from Marquis Morihisa HOSOKAWA (a head of the Hosokawa family at the time) and inherited &quot;the 34th tsukasake family of Takeda Kyuba-gunrei Kojitsu &quot;in witness whereof Marquis HOSOKAWA and the governor of Kumamoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1933 Inoue died, and in 1934, his disciple Yurin KANEKO obtained the permission from Marquis Morihisa HOSOKAWA (a head of the Hosokawa family at the time) and inherited &apos;the 34th tsukasake family of Takeda Kyuba-gunrei Kojitsu&apos; in witness whereof Marquis HOSOKAWA and the governor of Kumamoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>INOUE→Inoue,the を挿入しました。引用符を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1933 Inoue died, and in 1934, his disciple Yurin KANEKO obtained the permission from Marquis Morihisa HOSOKAWA (a head of the Hosokawa family at the time) and inherited &apos;the 34th tsukasake family of Takeda Kyuba-gunrei Kojitsu&apos; in witness whereof Marquis HOSOKAWA and the governor of Kumamoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>昭和14年には金子堅太郎を会長に社団法人大日本弓馬会が設立された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1939, The Japan Equestrian Archery Association, led by the chairperson Kentaro KANEKO, was established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1939, The Japan Equestrian Archery Association, led by the chairperson Kentaro KANEKO, was established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1939, The Japan Equestrian Archery Association, led by the chairperson Kentaro KANEKO, was established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>以来、武田流弓馬道を名乗り鎌倉市に所在し活動している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, they have been annoncing themselves as the Takeda School of Horseback Archery and operating in Kamakura City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, they have been announcing themselves as the Takeda School of Horseback Archery and operating in Kamakura City.</e>
<cmt>annoncing→announcing と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, they have been announcing themselves as the Takeda School of Horseback Archery and operating in Kamakura City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>現会長は金子家教で、「武田流司家、弓馬軍礼故実司家芸州武田氏正統師範」を名乗っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The current chairperson is Ietaka KANEKO and he announces himself as &quot;a legitimate Master of Takeda school tsukasake family, Kyuba-gunrei Kojitsu tsukasake Geishu Takeda clan &quot;.</e>
<cmt>家教氏は２００９年に亡くなっています。が原文のとおり訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The current chairperson is Ietaka KANEKO and he announces himself as &apos;the legitimate Master of Takeda school tsukasake family, Kyuba-gunrei Kojitsu tsukasake Geishu Takeda clan.&apos;</e>
<cmt>引用符を修正、スペースの修正、ピリオドの位置を修正しました。a→ｔhe と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The current chairperson is Ietaka KANEKO and he announces himself as &apos;the legitimate Master of Takeda school tsukasake family, Kyuba-gunrei Kojitsu tsukasake Geishu Takeda clan.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="38">
<j>また別に、金子有鄰の六郎家堅氏を師範として日本古式弓馬術協会（武田流鎌倉派）が結成され、弓馬軍礼武田家の道統を受継ぎ活動している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides, having Rokuroietaka from Yurin KANEKO as a Master, Japanese traditional archery on horseback association was established (Takeda-ryu Kamakura school) and they inherits and performs the tradition of Kyuba-gunrei Takeda family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides, having Rokuroietaka from Yurin KANEKO as a Master, Japanese Traditional Archery on Horseback Association was established (Takeda-ryu Kamakura school) and they inherits and performs the tradition of Kyuba-gunrei Takeda family.</e>
<cmt>”六郎家堅”の読み方が確認できておりません。Japanese Traditional Archery on Horseback Association と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides, having Rokuroietaka from Yurin KANEKO as a Master, Japanese Traditional Archery on Horseback Association was established (Takeda-ryu Kamakura school) and they inherits and performs the tradition of Kyuba-gunrei Takeda family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="39">
<j>活動</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Activities</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Activities</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Activities</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="40">
<j>武田流騎射流鏑馬保存会（熊本）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takeda-ryu Kisha-ryu Yabusame Preservation Society (Kumamoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takeda-ryu Kisha Yabusame Preservation Society (Kumamoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>Takeda-ryu Kisha Yabusame Preservation Society と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takeda-ryu Kisha Yabusame Preservation Society (Kumamoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="41">
<j>熊本市の出水神社例大祭（春・秋）、「くまもと秋のお城まつり」などで公演している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They perform in the annual festivals of Izumi-jinja Shrine (held in spring and autumn) in Kumamoto City, &quot;Kumamoto autumn castle festival &quot; and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They perform in the annual festivals of Izumi-jinja Shrine (held in spring and autumn) in Kumamoto City, &apos;Kumamoto autumn castle festival&apos; and so on.</e>
<cmt>引用符を修正しました。others→so on と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They perform in the annual festivals of Izumi-jinja Shrine (held in spring and autumn) in Kumamoto City, &apos;Kumamoto autumn castle festival&apos; and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="42">
<j>大日本弓馬会（鎌倉）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Japan Equestrian Archery Association (Kamakura City)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Japan Equestrian Archery Association (Kamakura City)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japan Equestrian Archery Association (Kamakura City)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="43">
<j>鶴岡八幡宮流鏑馬（神奈川県鎌倉市、鎌倉まつり）、三浦道寸まつり笠懸（神奈川県三浦市）、明治神宮流鏑馬神事（東京都渋谷区、秋の大祭）など、関東地方を中心に活動するほか、海外での公演も行っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are active around mainly Kanto area such as in Tsuruoka Hachiman-gu Shrine Yabusame (Kamakura Festival, Kamakura City of Kanagawa Prefecture), Miura Dosun Maturi Kasagake (Miura City of Kanagawa Prefecture) and Meiji-jingu Shrine Yabusame Shinto Ritual (Autumn big Festival, Shibuya-ku Ward, Tokyo) but they also have overseas performances.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are active around mainly Kanto area such as in Tsuruoka Hachiman-gu Shrine Yabusame (Kamakura Festival, Kamakura City, Kanagawa Prefecture), Miura Dosun Matsuri Kasagake (Miura City, Kanagawa Prefecture) and Meiji-jingu Shrine Yabusame Shinto Ritual (Autumn big Festival, Shibuya-ku Ward, Tokyo Metropolis) but they also have overseas performances.</e>
<cmt>Maturi→Matsuri,カッコ内の住所をそれぞれ修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are active around mainly Kanto area such as in Tsuruoka Hachiman-gu Shrine Yabusame (Kamakura Festival, Kamakura City, Kanagawa Prefecture), Miura Dosun Matsuri Kasagake (Miura City, Kanagawa Prefecture) and Meiji-jingu Shrine Yabusame Shinto Ritual (Autumn big Festival, Shibuya-ku Ward, Tokyo Metropolis) but they also have overseas performances.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>2001年10月の米国ブッシュ大統領来日時には明治神宮で流鏑馬を披露した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In October, 2001, when U.S. President Bush visited Japan, they performed Yabusame in Maiji-jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In October 2001, when U.S. President Bush visited Japan, they performed Yabusame in Maiji-jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>不要なカンマを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In October 2001, when U.S. President Bush visited Japan, they performed Yabusame in Maiji-jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>またNHK大河ドラマなどの演技に協力している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also they help acting performance of NHK&apos;s period drama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also they help acting performance of NHK Historical drama an so on.</e>
<cmt>NHK大河ドラマの部分を修正しました。and so on を挿入しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also they help acting performance of NHK Historical drama an so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="46">
<j>日本古式弓馬術協会（武田流鎌倉派）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese traditional archery on horseback association (Takeda-ryu Kamakura school)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese Traditional Archery on Horseback Association (Takeda-ryu Kamakura school)</e>
<cmt>大文字に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese Traditional Archery on Horseback Association (Takeda-ryu Kamakura school)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="47">
<j>近江神宮流鏑馬を行っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They perform Yabusame of Omi-jingu Shrine school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They perform Yabusame of Omi-jingu Shrine school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They perform Yabusame of Omi-jingu Shrine school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="48">
<j>特徴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Characteristics</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Characteristics</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Characteristics</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="49">
<j>伊勢貞丈では、流鏑馬には小笠原・武田・三浦の３流があるとしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Sadatake ISE, Yabusame includes three schools: Ogasawara, Takeda and Miura.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Sadatake ISE, Yabusame includes three schools: Ogasawara, Takeda and Miura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Sadatake ISE, Yabusame includes three schools: Ogasawara, Takeda and Miura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>小笠原と武田の違いは矢の抜き方にあり、犬追物と弓袋に関しての違い２点との計３点の他は異なる点はないとしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said there were no differences between Ogasawara and Takeda school except three points: the way of taking out the arrows, Inuoimono shooting style and Yumi bukuro (a bow cover)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that there are no other differences between Ogasawara and Takeda school except three points: The way of taking out the arrows, Inuoumono shooting style and Yumi bukuro (a bow cover)</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを挿入しました。were→are, the→The,Inuoimono→Inuoumono,that, other を挿入しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that there are no other differences between Ogasawara and Takeda school except three points: The way of taking out the arrows, Inuoumono shooting style and Yumi bukuro (a bow cover)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>しかし現在では小笠原流とは式次第・射法・矢の本数・笠の形状などにも違いが見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, nowadays, the demonstration proceed, shooting form, number of the arrows and the shape of hats are also different from those of Ogasawara school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, nowadays, the order of demonstration, shooting form, number of the arrows and the shape of hats are also different from those of Ogasawara school.</e>
<cmt>demonstration proceed の部分を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, nowadays, the order of demonstration, shooting form, number of the arrows and the shape of hats are also different from those of Ogasawara school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="52">
<j>使用する笠は綾藺笠（あやいがさ）といい、古く武士が狩猟・流鏑馬などに用いたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The hat used is called Ayai gasa (hat) that samurai wore in hunting or Yabusame in old times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The hat used is called Ayai gasa (hat) that samurai wore in hunting or Yabusame in old times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The hat used is called Ayai gasa (hat) that samurai wore in hunting or Yabusame in old times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>本来は藺草（イグサ）で編んだ物であるが、武田流の使用する物は形状・材質とも変化している（小笠原流の流鏑馬では古式の綾藺笠を用いている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The hats were originally woven with rush but the ones used in Takeda school have different shape and material.(Ogasawara school uses traditional Ayai gasa for Yabusame)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The hats were originally woven with rush, but the ones used in Takeda school have different shape and material (Ogasawara school uses traditional Ayai gasa for Yabusame).</e>
<cmt>カンマを挿入しました。ピリオドの位置を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The hats were originally woven with rush, but the ones used in Takeda school have different shape and material (Ogasawara school uses traditional Ayai gasa for Yabusame).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>神事の流鏑馬では笠に鬼面を着けるが、小笠原流では付けない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Yabusame as a Shinto ritual, a devil mask is attached on the hat while Ogasawara-ryu school doesn&apos;t use the mask.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Yabusame as a Shinto ritual, a devil mask is attached on the hat while Ogasawara-ryu school doesn&apos;t use the mask.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Yabusame as a Shinto ritual, a devil mask is attached on the hat while Ogasawara-ryu school doesn&apos;t use the mask.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>矢は、鏃のない神頭矢（先端に樽状の木を付けた矢）を帯に挟み、引き出して用いる（本来の流鏑馬では鏃の付いた鏑矢を箙に差して用いる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jinto-ya arrows, with their ends covered with the barrel-shaped wooden tips instead of arrowheads, are put into the belt and taken out in use.(in original Yabusame, kabura-ya arrows with arrowheads are put into a quiver.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jinto-ya arrows, with their ends covered with the barrel-shaped wooden tips instead of arrowheads, are put into the belt and taken out in use (In original Yabusame, kabura-ya arrows with arrowheads are put into a quiver.)</e>
<cmt>不要なピリオドを削除し、スペースを修正しました。in→In と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jinto-ya arrows, with their ends covered with the barrel-shaped wooden tips instead of arrowheads, are put into the belt and taken out in use (In original Yabusame, kabura-ya arrows with arrowheads are put into a quiver.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="56">
<j>流鏑馬式次第</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yabusame demonstration proceed</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Order of Yabusame demonstration</e>
<cmt>Order of を使い、修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Order of Yabusame demonstration</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>以下は式の一部である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following is the part of the ceremony.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following is the part of the ceremony.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following is the part of the ceremony.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="58">
<j>天長地久式</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tenchochikyu (the sky and the ground)ceremony</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tenchochikyu (the sky and the ground) ceremony</e>
<cmt>カッコ、スペースを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tenchochikyu (the sky and the ground) ceremony</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="25">
<sen id="59">
<j>騎射の執行に先立ち、一番目の射手が「天下太平・万民息災・五穀豊穣」を祈願して神前で行う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prior to performing horseback archery, the first archer prays for &quot;the peace, people&apos;s health and good harvest&quot; then performs in front of the alter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prior to the horseback archery, it is performed by the first archer in front of the alter, praying for &apos;the peace, people&apos;s health and good harvest.&apos;</e>
<cmt>引用符を修正し、文脈に応じて文中を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prior to the horseback archery, it is performed by the first archer in front of the alter, praying for &apos;the peace, people&apos;s health and good harvest.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>呪文を唱えながら天と地に向かって鏑矢を射る仕草をする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While praying, he draws the bow and pretends to release the Kabura-ya arrow to the sky and the ground.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While incanting, he draws the bow and pretends to release the Kabura-ya arrow to the sky and the ground.</e>
<cmt>”呪文”の部分を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While incanting, he draws the bow and pretends to release the Kabura-ya arrow to the sky and the ground.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="26">
<sen id="61">
<j>流鏑馬式</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yabusame ceremony</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yabusame ceremony</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yabusame ceremony</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="27">
<sen id="62">
<j>流鏑馬用の矢を用い、馬場の三ヶ所に立てられた的に矢を放つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Using arrows for Yabusame, he releases the arrows to the targets build in the three points in the riding ground.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Using arrows designated to Yabusame, the archer releases the arrows to the targets build in the three places in the riding ground.</e>
<cmt>for→designated to,he →the archer,points→places と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Using arrows designated to Yabusame, the archer releases the arrows to the targets build in the three places in the riding ground.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>馬は2～30秒ほどで駆け抜ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It takes 20-30 seconds for the horse to gallop through.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It takes 20 to 30 seconds for the horse to gallop through.</e>
<cmt>20 to 30 と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It takes 20 to 30 seconds for the horse to gallop through.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>的は一辺一尺八寸（約55cm）の正方形の檜板、または竹を網代に編んで紙を張ったもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The target is 50cm X 50cm square, made of Japanese cypress board or woven bamboo with paper on it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The target is 55cm X 55cm square, made of Japanese cypress board or woven bamboo with paper on it.</e>
<cmt>50→55 と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The target is 55cm X 55cm square, made of Japanese cypress board or woven bamboo with paper on it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>成績優秀者により行われる競射では、直径三寸（約9cm）の皿2枚を合わせたものを的にする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, in Kyosha, a competition among the best archers, two dishes of 9cm in diameter are put together as a target.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, in Kyosha, a competition among the best archers, two dishes of about 9cm in diameter are put together as a target.</e>
<cmt>about を挿入しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, in Kyosha, a competition among the best archers, two dishes of about 9cm in diameter are put together as a target.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="28">
<sen id="66">
<j>馬場の長さ：百二十間（約220m）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The length of the course: approx. 220 m</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The length of the course: approx. 220 m</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The length of the course: approx. 220 m</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>的までの距離：三～五間（約5.4～9m）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The length to the target: approx 5.4-9m</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The distance to the target: approx. 5.4 to 9m</e>
<cmt>length→distance,approx→approx., 5.4-9m を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The distance to the target: approx. 5.4 to 9m</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>的の間隔：三十～四十間（約54m～73m）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Space betweeen targets: approx. 54m-73m</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Space between the targets: approx. 54 to 73m</e>
<cmt>betweeen→between,the targets,54 to 73m, と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Space between the targets: approx. 54 to 73m</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 子パンダ(id:178397), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), 水野白楓(id:22811), MizunoH(id:112470), Open-box(id:17893), Point136(id:211299), 青山コロハ(id:118527), Yoshihama(id:186078), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>