<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>落雁</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rakugan (Confectionery)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rakugan (Confectionery)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rakugan (Confectionery)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>落雁（らくがん）は、米などから作った澱粉質の粉に水飴や砂糖を混ぜて着色し、型に押して乾燥させた代表的な干菓子である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rakugan is a generic term for the representative Japanese confectionery and to make rakugan, flour derived from starch such as rice, starch syrup and sugar are mixed together with food coloring and dried in the mold.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rakugan is one of representative Japanese confectionery, and made by mixing flour of starch derived from rice or the like with starch syrup and sugar to apply coloring, and drying in a mold.</e>
<cmt>表現の見直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rakugan is one of representative Japanese confectionery, and made by mixing flour of starch derived from rice or the like with starch syrup and sugar to apply coloring, and drying in a mold.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>名は近江八景の「堅田の落雁」に因んでつけられたという説と、中国の軟落甘の「軟」が欠落したという説とがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are 2 explanations for its name whereby the first one is that it was named after one of the Eight Views of Omi &apos;Katata no rakugan&apos; and the second one is that it was named after nanrakukan (dried sweets that existed during the Ming Dynasty era in China) with &apos;nan&apos; being dropped.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are 2 explanations for its name whereby the first one is that it was named after one of the Eight Views of Omi &apos;Katata no rakugan&apos; and the second one is that it was named after nanrakukan (dried sweets that existed during the Ming Dynasty era in China) with &apos;nan&apos; being dropped.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are 2 explanations for its name whereby the first one is that it was named after one of the Eight Views of Omi &apos;Katata no rakugan&apos; and the second one is that it was named after nanrakukan (dried sweets that existed during the Ming Dynasty era in China) with &apos;nan&apos; being dropped.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>落雁の製法には二通りある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are 2 ways to make rakugan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are two methods to make rakugan.</e>
<cmt>ways をmethodsに変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are two methods to make rakugan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>すでに蒸して乾燥させた米（糒）の粉を用い、これに水飴や砂糖を加えて練り型にはめた後、ホイロで乾燥させたもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Add starch syrup and sugar to rice flour which has been steamed and dried, transfer the mixture into molds and let it dry in a temperature controlled chamber.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Add starch syrup and sugar to rice flour which has been steamed and dried, transfer the mixture into molds and let it dry in a temperature controlled chamber.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Add starch syrup and sugar to rice flour which has been steamed and dried, transfer the mixture into molds and let it dry in a temperature controlled chamber.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="5">
<j>加熱していない米の粉を用いて1.同様に水飴を加え成型した後、セイロで蒸し上げた後、ホイロで乾燥させたもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first method produces what is generally referred to as rakugan and the second recipe results in what is referred to as Hakusetsuko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Add starch syrup, like in the method above, to rice flour which has not been heat-treated, transfer the mixture into molds, steam and let it dry in a temperature controlled chamber.</e>
<cmt>表現の見直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Add starch syrup, like in the method above, to rice flour which has not been heat-treated, transfer the mixture into molds, steam and let it dry in a temperature controlled chamber.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="6">
<j>1.は通常落雁と呼ばれる物であり、2.は白雪糕（はくせつこう）と呼ばれるものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The product made by the first method is what is generally referred to as rakugan, whereas, that made by the second method is referred to Hakusetsuko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The product made by the first method is what is generally referred to as rakugan, whereas, that made by the second method is referred to Hakusetsuko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The product made by the first method is what is generally referred to as rakugan, whereas, that made by the second method is referred to Hakusetsuko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="7">
<j>2.は新潟県長岡市の越の雪が有名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koshi no Yuki in Nagaoka City, Niigata Prefecture is a well-known product made by the second method.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koshi no Yuki in Nagaoka City, Niigata Prefecture is a well-known product made by the second method.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koshi no Yuki in Nagaoka City, Niigata Prefecture is a well-known product made by the second method.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>ただし、改良の末、1.に限りなく近い製法となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After numerous modifications, however, the second method has become virtually identical to the first one.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Through many modifications, however, Koshi no Yuki has come to be produced by the method substantially identical to the first method.</e>
<cmt>表現の見直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Through many modifications, however, Koshi no Yuki has come to be produced by the method substantially identical to the first method.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="9">
<j>製法は明時代の中国における軟落甘（小麦粉・米粉を水飴や脂肪で練り固めて乾燥させた菓子。西～中央アジアに由来するといわれ、元 (王朝)時代に中国に伝来した）に基づき、室町時代に日明貿易で伝わり、茶道の勃興によって広まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The recipe is in based on that for nanrakukan (a sweet made by drying the kneaded mixture of wheat flour or rice flour and starch syrup and fat which is said to have originated from the western and central Asia and to have subsequently been introduced to China in the Yuan Dynasty era) from the Ming Dynasty era in China which was introduced to Japan through the Japan-Ming trade (the trade between Japan and the Ming Dynasty in China) and became popular along with the sudden rise of the tea ceremony.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The recipe is based on that for nanrakukan (a sweet made by drying the kneaded mixture of wheat flour or rice flour and starch syrup and fat, which is said to have originated from the western and central Asia and to have subsequently been introduced to China in the Yuan Dynasty era) produced in the Ming Dynasty era in China; the nanrakukan was introduced to Japan in the Muromachi period through the Japan-Ming trade (the trade between Japan and the Ming Dynasty in China) and became popular along with the rise of the tea ceremony.</e>
<cmt>説明、表現の見直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The recipe is based on that for nanrakukan (a sweet made by drying the kneaded mixture of wheat flour or rice flour and starch syrup and fat, which is said to have originated from the western and central Asia and to have subsequently been introduced to China in the Yuan Dynasty era) produced in the Ming Dynasty era in China; the nanrakukan was introduced to Japan in the Muromachi period through the Japan-Ming trade (the trade between Japan and the Ming Dynasty in China) and became popular along with the rise of the tea ceremony.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>なお、中国にはこの軟酪甘が現在も存在しており、長崎市には軟落甘が江戸時代に再上陸したものとしてこうさこ（口砂香）と言われる落雁がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This nanrakukan still remains in existence in China today and, in Nagasaki City, there is the rakugan known as Kosako which is considered to be the nanrakukan that was reintroduced to Japan in the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This nanrakukan still remains in existence in China today and, in Nagasaki City, there is rakugan known as Kosako which is considered to be the nanrakukan that was reintroduced to Japan in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>冠詞の見直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This nanrakukan still remains in existence in China today and, in Nagasaki City, there is rakugan known as Kosako which is considered to be the nanrakukan that was reintroduced to Japan in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="11">
<j>江戸時代には加賀藩が大々的に製菓事業に対して奨励策を取った事から、金沢市では落雁の技術が進化しており、長生殿はこうした成果の一つである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Edo Period, the Kaga Clan implemented extensive incentive measures for the confectionery business in its domain whereby, as a result, the manufacturing technique for rakugan advanced in Kanazawa City and Choseiden (the celebrated rakugan made in Kanazawa City) is one of the achievements of the time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Edo period, the Kaga Clan implemented extensive incentive measures for the confectionery business in its domain whereby, as a result, manufacturing techniques for rakugan has much progressed in Kanazawa City, and Choseiden (celebrated rakugan presently made in Kanazawa City) is one of the achievements of the time.</e>
<cmt>表現の見直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Edo period, the Kaga Clan implemented extensive incentive measures for the confectionery business in its domain whereby, as a result, manufacturing techniques for rakugan has much progressed in Kanazawa City, and Choseiden (celebrated rakugan presently made in Kanazawa City) is one of the achievements of the time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>なお、この原料である糒は軍事作戦には不可欠の食料であるため、奨励策は軍備維持における糒の在庫処分ではないかという説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, some say that, since hoshi-ii (dehydrated cooked rice), the key ingredient of Choseiden, was an indispensable food for military campaigns, the Kaga Clan&apos;s incentive measure may have been an excuse to build up the hoshi-ii supply to maintain the level of military preparedness.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, some say that, since hoshi-ii (dehydrated cooked rice), the key ingredient of Choseiden, was an indispensable food in military operation, the Kaga Clan&apos;s incentive measures may have been an excuse to maintain an adequate stock level of hoshi-ii for military preparedness.</e>
<cmt>表現の見直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, some say that, since hoshi-ii (dehydrated cooked rice), the key ingredient of Choseiden, was an indispensable food in military operation, the Kaga Clan&apos;s incentive measures may have been an excuse to maintain an adequate stock level of hoshi-ii for military preparedness.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="13">
<j>また、松江藩でも松平治郷（松平不昧）が茶道と共に和菓子を奨励したため、山川 (菓子)という落雁を生み出しており、前述の越の雪・長生殿と共に日本三大一覧銘菓として挙げられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With its lord Harusato MATSUDAIRA (also known as Fumai MATSUDRAIRA) fostering the development of Japanese confectionery in conjunction with the tea ceremony, a type of rakugan referred to as Yamakawa (confectionery) was developed in the Matsue Domain and is cited in the List of the Top 3 Representative Japanese Confectioneries along with the above-mentioned Koshi no Yuki and Choseiden today.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With its lord Harusato MATSUDAIRA (also known as Fumai MATSUDRAIRA) fostering the development of Japanese confectionery in conjunction with the tea ceremony, a type of rakugan referred to as Yamakawa (confectionery) was developed in the Matsue Domain, and is cited today in the List of the Top 3 Representative Japanese Confectioneries along with the above-mentioned Koshi no Yuki and Choseiden.</e>
<cmt>表現の見直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With its lord Harusato MATSUDAIRA (also known as Fumai MATSUDRAIRA) fostering the development of Japanese confectionery in conjunction with the tea ceremony, a type of rakugan referred to as Yamakawa (confectionery) was developed in the Matsue Domain, and is cited today in the List of the Top 3 Representative Japanese Confectioneries along with the above-mentioned Koshi no Yuki and Choseiden.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="14">
<j>このように茶席菓子や供物などに用いられることが多かったことから、茶の湯では薄茶点前に供される定番の菓子となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As mentioned earlier, since rakugan has frequently been used as sweets at tea ceremony and also as offerings during the Buddhist events, it has become an old standby served with usucha (thin, weak tea made from the tea powder).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As mentioned earlier, since rakugan has frequently been used as sweets at a tea ceremony and also as offerings during Buddhist events, it has become an old standby confection served with usucha (thin, weak tea made from tea powder).</e>
<cmt>表現の見直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As mentioned earlier, since rakugan has frequently been used as sweets at a tea ceremony and also as offerings during Buddhist events, it has become an old standby confection served with usucha (thin, weak tea made from tea powder).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>また、仏事等の供物として用いられることも多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rakugan is also often used as offerings for the Buddhist ceremonies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rakugan is also often used as offerings for Buddhist ceremonies.</e>
<cmt>Buddhist ceremoniesの前のtheを削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rakugan is also often used as offerings for Buddhist ceremonies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>このことから、落雁は和菓子の中でも高級なものとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In view of the above, rakugan is considered to be an upscale item among Japanese confectioneries.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In view of the above, rakugan is considered to be a high-grade item among Japanese confectioneries.</e>
<cmt>upscaleをhigh-gradeに変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In view of the above, rakugan is considered to be a high-grade item among Japanese confectioneries.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>このような高貴な場に供されるものは、糖類に和三盆、または精製された糖蜜の少ない黒砂糖が使われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For the rakugan that is offered at a place of distinction as mentioned above, wasanbon (refined sugar made from sugarcane grown in Japan) or refine brown sugar with a low molasses content is used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For the rakugan that is offered at a place of distinction as mentioned above, wasanbon (refined sugar made from sugarcane grown in Japan) or refine brown sugar with a low molasses content is used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For the rakugan that is offered at a place of distinction as mentioned above, wasanbon (refined sugar made from sugarcane grown in Japan) or refine brown sugar with a low molasses content is used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="18">
<j>中華人民共和国には、雲片糕（ユンピエンガオ、yúnpiàngāo）と呼ばれる、薄手の落雁がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In China, there is a thin rakugan referred to as yunpiangao.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In China, there is a thin rakugan referred to as yunpiangao.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In China, there is a thin rakugan referred to as yunpiangao.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Sodome(id:31200), Izayohi(id:13095), ととりん(id:31982), Nnh(id:474), Hhaithait(id:37092), 水野白楓(id:22811), Nighthawks(id:36125), Kumatora(id:16941), お掃除大好き(id:99320), ウェルワィ(id:15692), Carkuni(id:79281), Hot green tea(id:183737), 竃馬(id:102733), Bandalgom(id:31841), 玄史生(id:43670), Point136(id:211299), Akimoto(id:6951), Lebit(id:11805), うーみん(id:99264), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>