<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>ソメイヨシノ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Someiyoshino</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Someiyoshino</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Someiyoshino</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>ソメイヨシノ（染井吉野、学名：Prunus × yedoensis）は、エドヒガン系のコマツオトメとオオシマザクラの交配で生まれたサクラの園芸品種である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Someiyoshino (scientific name: Prunus X yedoensis) is a brand of cherry tree as garden plant which was bred by crossbreeding Cerasus spachiana &apos;Komatsuotome&apos; in line of Edohigan (P. pendula Maxim. f. ascendens (Makino) Ohwi) and Oshima cherry (P. lannesiana var. speciosa).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Someiyoshino (scientific name: Prunus X yedoensis) is a type of cherry tree as a garden plant, having been produced by crossbreeding Cerasus spachiana &apos;Komatsuotome&apos; in the line of Edohigan (P. pendula Maxim. f. ascendens (Makino) Ohwi) and the Oshima cherry (P. lannesiana var. speciosa).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Someiyoshino (scientific name: Prunus x yedoensis) is a type of cherry tree as a garden plant, having been produced by crossbreeding Cerasus spachiana &apos;Komatsuotome&apos; in the line of Edohigan (P. pendula Maxim. f. ascendens (Makino) Ohwi) and the Oshima cherry (P. lannesiana var. speciosa).</e>
<cmt>全角の記号をｘに訂正しました。全角の括弧を半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>現代の観賞用サクラの代表種であり、「吉野桜」と表記する場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is one of representative brand of ornamental cherry trees today, and is sometimes written as &apos;Yoshinozakura&apos; (Yoshino cherry).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today it&apos;s a representative type of ornamental cherry tree, and occasionally it&apos;s written as &apos;Yoshinozakura (Yoshino cherry).&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today it&apos;s a representative type of ornamental cherry tree, and occasionally it&apos;s written as &apos;Yoshinozakura&apos; (Yoshino cherry).</e>
<cmt>括弧の位置を訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>また、エドヒガンとオオシマザクラを交配したものすべてを「ソメイヨシノ」ということもあり、狭義のソメイヨシノを二名法の「ソメイヨシノ &apos;ソメイヨシノ&apos;」と書く場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, sometimes all the plants that were born by crossbreeding Edohigan and Oshima cherry are called &apos;Someiyoshino,&apos; and Someiyoshino in a narrow sense is sometimes written as binominal, &apos;Someiyoshino &apos;Someiyoshino.&apos;&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, sometimes all the plants that were born by crossbreeding Edohigan and Oshima cherries are called &apos;Someiyoshino,&apos; and Someiyoshino in a narrow sense is sometimes written as the binominal &apos;Someiyoshino &apos;Someiyoshino.&apos;&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, sometimes all the plants that were born by crossbreeding Edohigan and Oshima cherries are called &apos;Someiyoshino,&apos; and Someiyoshino in a narrow sense is sometimes written as the binominal &apos;Someiyoshino &apos;Someiyoshino.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>この項では狭義のソメイヨシノについて述べる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this section, Someiyoshino in means of narrow sense is described.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this section, Someiyoshino is described in the narrow sense.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this section, Someiyoshino is described in the narrow sense.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>命名の由来</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Origin of the name</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Origin of the name</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Origin of the name</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>江戸末期から明治初期に、江戸の染井村（現在の東京都豊島区駒込）に集落を作っていた造園師や植木職人達によって育成され「吉野桜（ヤマザクラの意）」として売り出していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the period from the end of Edo period to the beginning of Meiji period, it was raised by gardeners and artisans of garden trees who were making a colony in Somei Village in Edo (present-day Komagome, Toshima Ward, Tokyo Prefecture), and was put on sale as &apos;Yoshinozakura (meaning Yamazakura, or Prunus jamasakura).&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the time from the end of the Edo period to the beginning of the Meiji period, it was raised by gardeners and artisans of garden trees who had established a colony in Somei Village, in Edo (the present-day Komagome, Toshima Ward, Tokyo Prefecture), and was sold as &apos;Yoshinozakura (meaning Yamazakura, or Prunus jamasakura).&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the time from the end of the Edo period to the beginning of the Meiji period, it was raised by gardeners and artisans of garden trees who had established a colony in Somei Village, in Edo (the present-day Komagome, Toshima Ward, Tokyo Prefecture), and was sold as &apos;Yoshinozakura&apos; (meaning Yamazakura, or Prunus jamasakura).</e>
<cmt>括弧の位置を訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>藤野寄命の調査によってヤマザクラとは異なる種の桜であることが分かり、1900年（明治33年）「日本園芸雑誌」において「染井吉野」と命名された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By the research by Yorinaga FUJINO, it was discovered that it was a different kind from Yamazakura, and in 1900, it was named &apos;Someiyoshino&apos; in &apos;Japanese Gardening Magazine.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Through research conducted by Yorinaga FUJINO, it was discovered that it was distinct from Yamazakura, and in 1900 it was referred to as &apos;Someiyoshino&apos; in &apos;Japanese Gardening Magazine.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Through research conducted by Yorinaga FUJINO, it was discovered that it was distinct from Yamazakura, and in 1900 it was referred to as &apos;Someiyoshino&apos; in &apos;Japanese Gardening Magazine.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>名称は初め、サクラの名所として古来名高く西行法師の和歌にもたびたび詠まれた大和国の吉野山（奈良県山岳部）にちなんで「吉野」とされたが、「吉野（桜）」の名称では吉野山に多いヤマザクラと混同される恐れがあるため、上野公園のサクラを調査した藤野寄命博士が「日本園芸雑誌」において「染井吉野」と命名したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that at first, it was named &apos;Yoshino&apos; after Yoshino-yama Mountain in Yamato Province (mountainous district in Nara Prefecture), which is a noted place for its cherry blossoms, but since the name &apos;Yoshino (Yoshinozakura)&apos; had a fear of been confused with Yamazakura, which grows a lot in Yoshino-yama Mountain, Dr. Yorinaga FUJINO, who made research on cherry trees in Ueno Park, named it &apos;Someiyoshino&apos; in &apos;Japanese Gardening Magazine.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that it was initially called &apos;Yoshino&apos; after Mt. Yoshino-yama in Yamato Province (a mountainous district in Nara Prefecture), which is a place noted for its cherry blossoms; however, since there was concern that the name &apos;Yoshino (Yoshinozakura)&apos; would be confused with Yamazakura, which grows a lot in Mt. Yoshino-yama, Dr. Yorinaga FUJINO, who had conducted research on the cherry trees of Ueno Park, called it &apos;Someiyoshino&apos; in &apos;Japanese Gardening Magazine.&apos;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that it was initially called &apos;Yoshino&apos; after Mt. Yoshino-yama in Yamato Province (a mountainous district in Nara Prefecture), which is a place noted for its cherry blossoms; however, since there was concern that the name &apos;Yoshino (Yoshinozakura)&apos; would be confused with Yamazakura, which grows a lot in Mt. Yoshino-yama, Dr. Yorinaga FUJINO, who had conducted research on the cherry trees of Ueno Park, called it &apos;Someiyoshino&apos; in &apos;Japanese Gardening Magazine.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>特徴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Characteristics</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Characteristics</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Characteristics</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>ソメイヨシノ Prunus × yedoensis はエドヒガン P. pendula Maxim. f. ascendens （Makino） Ohwiとオオシマザクラ P. lannesiana var. speciosa の雑種が起源である可能性が高い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Someiyoshino, Prunus X yedoensis, is likely to have the hybrid between Edohigan, P. pendula Maxim. f. ascendens (Makino) Ohw, and Oshima Cherry, P. lannesiana var. speciosa, as its origin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Someiyoshino, Prunus X yedoensis, is likely to have as its origin the hybrid between Edohigan, P. pendula Maxim. f. ascendens (Makino) Ohw, and Oshima Cherry, P. lannesiana var. speciosa.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Someiyoshino, Prunus x yedoensis, is likely to have as its origin the hybrid between Edohigan, P. pendula Maxim. f. ascendens (Makino) Ohw, and Oshima Cherry, P. lannesiana var. speciosa.</e>
<cmt>全角の記号をｘに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>なお学名の×は自然種間交雑種の表記であり、人工交配種の場合この表記は用いられないという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, X in scientific names is a way to express that it is a natural hybrid, and it its said that in artificial hybrid, the sign is not used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, the X in scientific names is a way to indicate a natural hybrid, and it&apos;s said that the sign isn&apos;t not used in regard to artificial hybrids.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, the x in scientific names is a way to indicate a natural hybrid, and it&apos;s said that the sign isn&apos;t not used in regard to artificial hybrids.</e>
<cmt>全角の記号をｘに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>ソメイヨシノが自然交雑種なのか、人工交配種なのかは不明だとして、この学名の妥当性に疑問を呈する声もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Whether Someiyoshino is a natural hybrid or an artificial hybrid remains unknown, but there are some voices giving doubts to validity of this scientific name.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It isn&apos;t known whether Someiyoshino is a natural hybrid or an artificial hybrid, but some opinions have expressed doubt regarding the validity of this scientific name.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It isn&apos;t known whether Someiyoshino is a natural hybrid or an artificial hybrid, but some opinions have expressed doubt regarding the validity of this scientific name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>エドヒガンではなく、コマツオトメのこう配だという研究結果もある（ただしコマツオトメも種としてはエドヒガンの園芸品種で、その中の1クローンではある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a research result which states that it is a hybrid of Komatsuotome, not Edohigan (however, Komatsuotome is also one of a gardening brand of Edohigan, and it is one of a clone).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One finding of research states that it&apos;s a hybrid of Komatsuotome instead of Edohigan; however, Komatsuotome is also a gardening type of Edohigan as well as being a clone.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One finding of research states that it&apos;s a hybrid of Komatsuotome instead of Edohigan; however, Komatsuotome is also a gardening type of Edohigan as well as being a clone.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>外形的特徴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Characteristics in appearance</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Characteristics in appearance</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Characteristics in appearance</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="12">
<j>花弁は5枚で、葉が出る前に花が開き、満開となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are 5 petals, and before leaves grow out, the flowers open and become full bloom.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are five petals, and before the leaves grow out the flowers open and enter full bloom.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are five petals, and before the leaves grow out the flowers open and enter full bloom.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>開花期は九州地方で3月末ごろ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The flowering period is around the end of March in Kyushu Region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The flowering period is around the end of March in the Kyushu region.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The flowering period is around the end of March in the Kyushu region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>花色は、咲き始めは淡紅色だが、満開になると白色に近づく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The color of the flowers is pink when they start to open, and becomes whiter as they become full bloom.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The color of the flowers is pink when they start to open, but they whiten as they approach full bloom.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The color of the flowers is pink when they start to open, but they whiten as they approach full bloom.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>原種の一方であるエドヒガンと同じく、満開時には花だけが密生して樹体全体を覆うが、エドヒガンよりも花が大きく、派手である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Like Edohigan, one of its ancestor, only flowers crowd together and cover up the whole tree at the time of full bloom, but the flowers are bigger and showy than that of Edohigan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Like Edohigan, one of its ancestors, only flowers crowd together and cover the entire canopy of the tree at full bloom, but the flowers are bigger and more showy than those of Edohigan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Like Edohigan, one of its ancestors, only flowers crowd together and cover the entire canopy of the tree at full bloom, but the flowers are bigger and more showy than those of Edohigan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>エドヒガンの花が葉より先に咲く性質とオオシマザクラの大きくて整った花形を併せ持った品種である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a brand having both characteristics of Edohigan, flowers open before leaves grow, and Oshima cherry, shape of flowers is big and well-proportioned.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It&apos;s a type having the characteristics of Edohigan, in which the flowers open before the leaves grow, and the Oshima cherry, in which the flowers are large and well proportioned.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It&apos;s a type having the characteristics of Edohigan, in which the flowers open before the leaves grow, and the Oshima cherry, in which the flowers are large and well proportioned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="17">
<j>萼筒は紅色でつぼのような形をしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The color of calyx tube is red, and has a shape like a pot.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The color of the calyx tube is red, and it&apos;s shaped like a pot.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The color of the calyx tube is red, and it&apos;s shaped like a pot.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>樹高はおおよそ10m～15m。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The height of the tree is about 10m - 15m.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The tree is approximately ten to 15 meters in height.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The tree is approximately 10 to 15 meters in height.</e>
<cmt>数字に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>若い木から花を咲かすために非常に良く植えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is very commonly planted to make young trees bloom the flowers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is very commonly planted because it blooms with flowers even as a young tree.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is very commonly planted because it blooms with flowers even as a young tree.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>種子で自然に増えることがない</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It does not propagate naturally by seed</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It doesn&apos;t propagate naturally by seed.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It doesn&apos;t propagate naturally by seed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="20">
<j>ソメイヨシノは種子では増えない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Someiyoshino does not propagate by seed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Someiyoshino does not propagate by seed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Someiyoshino does not propagate by seed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>各地にある樹は、全て人の手で接木（つぎき）などで増やしたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">All the trees in many places are bred by people&apos;s hands in a way of grafting and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">All the trees in many places are bred by people&apos;s hands through means of grafting and other techniques.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">All the trees in many places are bred by people&apos;s hands through means of grafting and other techniques.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="22">
<j>一代雑種のため自家交配の結実率が極めて低い、とする説も有る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is also a theory stating that since it is a first filial hybrid, the fruition rate of self pollination is extremely low.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is also a theory that since it&apos;s a first filial hybrid, the fruition rate of self-pollination is extremely low.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is also a theory that since it&apos;s a first filial hybrid, the fruition rate of self-pollination is extremely low.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>しかしむしろ、交雑または交配の結果、自家不和合性 (植物)が強く出た品種の可能性が強い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it is rather likely that as a result of hybridization and crossbreeding, a self-incompatibility (plants) has become to strongly appear in this brand.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it&apos;s somewhat likely that, as a result of hybridization and crossbreeding, self-incompatibility (of the plant) has become very apparent in this type.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it&apos;s somewhat likely that, as a result of hybridization and crossbreeding, self-incompatibility (of the plant) has become very apparent in this type.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>実際、枝の条件により、かなりの結実を観察することができる場合も有る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Actually, under certain conditions of the branches, considerable number of fruition can be seen in some cases.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Actually, under certain branch conditions a considerable rate of fruition can be seen in some cases.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Actually, under certain branch conditions a considerable rate of fruition can be seen in some cases.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>もっとも、その場合でも同一個体内で受粉し結実した種が発芽に至ることは無い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, even in that case, seeds which were born by the self-pollination do not germinate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, even in such a case the seeds that were born through self-pollination do not germinate.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, even in such a case the seeds that were born through self-pollination do not germinate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>このためソメイヨシノの純粋な子孫はありえない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of that, the genuine descendent of Someiyoshino cannot be existing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequently, a genuine descendent of Someiyoshino cannot exist.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently, a genuine descendent of Someiyoshino cannot exist.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="27">
<j>とは言え、ソメイヨシノ以外の桜との間で交配することは可能であり、実をつけ、その種が発芽することもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it is possible to crossbreed with cherry trees other than Someiyoshino, and sometimes it makes fruition and the seeds germinate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is possible to crossbreed with cherry trees other than Someiyoshino, and sometimes it makes fruition and the seeds germinate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is possible to crossbreed with cherry trees other than Someiyoshino, and sometimes it makes fruition and the seeds germinate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>しかしながら、この場合ソメイヨシノの遺伝子特性を強く継いだとしても遺伝子的特性が変化してしまい、ソメイヨシノとは別種になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But, in this case, even if it strongly inherited the genetic characteristics of Someiyoshino, the genetic characteristics will change and it becomes a brand other than Someiyoshino.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in this case, even if it has strongly inherited the genetic characteristics of Someiyoshino, the genetic characteristics will change and it will become a type other than Someiyoshino.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in this case, even if it has strongly inherited the genetic characteristics of Someiyoshino, the genetic characteristics will change and it will become a type other than Someiyoshino.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>このため、ソメイヨシノの種から成長した桜はソメイヨシノということができない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of this, a cherry tree which was grown from the seed of Someiyoshino can&apos;t be called Someiyoshino.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of this, a cherry tree that has been grown from the seed of Someiyoshino can&apos;t be called Someiyoshino.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of this, a cherry tree that has been grown from the seed of Someiyoshino can&apos;t be called Someiyoshino.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>ソメイヨシノから取れる種はあれど「ソメイヨシノが生える種」なるものは現在存在していないのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are seeds that can be taken from Someiyoshino, but presently, there is no &apos;seed which will grow up to be Someiyoshino&apos; existing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are seeds that can be taken from Someiyoshino, but currently there is no &apos;seed that will grow up to be Someiyoshino.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are seeds that can be taken from Someiyoshino, but currently there is no &apos;seed that will grow up to be Someiyoshino.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="31">
<j>なお、ソメイヨシノとその他の品種の桜の実生子孫としてはミズタマザクラやウスゲオオシマ、ショウワザクラ、ソメイニオイ、ソトオリヒメ (サクラ)など、100種近くの亜種が確認されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, as seedling descendants between Someiyoshino and other brands of cherry trees, there are nearly a hundred kinds of subspecies confirmed, such as Mizutamazakura (Cerasus &apos;Manadzuru-littorea&apos;), Usugeoshima (Cerasus X yedoensis &apos;Candida&apos;), Showazakura (Cerasus X yedoensis &apos;Syouwa-zakura&apos;), Someinioi (Cerasus X yedoensis &apos;Somei-nioi&apos;), and Sotoorihime (Cerasus X yedoensis &apos;Sotorihime&apos;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further, as seedling descendants between Someiyoshino and other brands of cherry trees, there are nearly a hundred kinds of subspecies confirmed, such as Mizutamazakura (Cerasus &apos;Manadzuru-littorea&apos;), Usugeoshima (Cerasus X yedoensis &apos;Candida&apos;), Showazakura (Cerasus X yedoensis &apos;Syouwa-zakura&apos;), Someinioi (Cerasus X yedoensis &apos;Somei-nioi&apos;), and Sotoorihime (Cerasus X yedoensis &apos;Sotorihime&apos;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further, as seedling descendants between Someiyoshino and other brands of cherry trees, there are nearly a hundred kinds of subspecies confirmed, such as Mizutamazakura (Cerasus &apos;Manadzuru-littorea&apos;), Usugeoshima (Cerasus x yedoensis &apos;Candida&apos;), Showazakura (Cerasus x yedoensis &apos;Syouwa-zakura&apos;), Someinioi (Cerasus x yedoensis &apos;Somei-nioi&apos;), and Sotoorihime (Cerasus x yedoensis &apos;Sotorihime&apos;).</e>
<cmt>全角の記号をｘに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>また、「サクラエドヒガン群」と言うサクラの品種がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, there are brands of cherry trees called &apos;Sakuraedohigan group.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, there are types of cherry trees referred to as being of the &apos;Sakuraedohigan group.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, there are types of cherry trees referred to as being of the &apos;Sakuraedohigan group.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>この品種は、日米友好の為にアメリカに送られたアメリカにてソメイヨシノの実生から作られたとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These brands are said to be bred in America, from the seedlings of Someiyoshino which were sent to America for friendship between Japan and U.S.A..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These types are said to be bred in America from the seedlings of Someiyoshino that were sent to America to represent the friendship between Japan and the U.S.A.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These types are said to be bred in America from the seedlings of Someiyoshino that were sent to America to represent the friendship between Japan and the U.S.A.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>人の手による作出</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Breeding by hands of people</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Breeding by the hands of people</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Breeding by the hands of people</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="34">
<j>種ができない特性はソメイヨシノは人間の手によって以外に広まる手立てがないということでもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The characteristic that seeds can&apos;t be made means that it can&apos;t be spread without by the means of the hands of people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The characteristic inability to make seeds means it can&apos;t be spread without human intervention.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The characteristic inability to make seeds means it can&apos;t be spread without human intervention.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>ソメイヨシノは一般的に他の台木に接木をして育ったものや挿し木、植え替えによって増える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Generally, Someiyoshino is propagated by grafting on other stock, planting cuttings, and transplanting.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Generally, Someiyoshino is propagated by grafting onto other stock, planting cuttings and transplantation.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Generally, Someiyoshino is propagated by grafting onto other stock, planting cuttings and transplantation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>このため人間と切っても切れない関係にあり、人の手によって広まっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of this, it is inseparably related to human beings, and it was spread by people&apos;s hands.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, it&apos;s inseparably related to human beings, and it has been distributed as a human activity.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, it&apos;s inseparably related to human beings, and it has been distributed as a human activity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="37">
<j>全てのソメイヨシノは元をたどれば同一の一本に繋がり、全てのソメイヨシノが一本のソメイヨシノのクローンとも言える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Looking back at the time, all Someiyoshino is linked to same one tree, and all Someiyoshino can be said as clones of that one Someiyoshino.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Looking back at the time, all Someiyoshino trees are linked to a single tree, and all Someiyoshino can be called clones of that Someiyoshino.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Looking back at the time, all Someiyoshino trees are linked to a single tree, and all Someiyoshino can be called clones of that Someiyoshino.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>これは全てのソメイヨシノが一斉に咲き一斉に花を散らす理由になっているが、特定の病気に掛かりやすく環境変化に弱い理由ともなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This becomes to be the reason of all Someiyoshino blooming and falling their flowers at the same time, but it also becomes to be the reason of being weak against certain disease and environmental changes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is the reason that all Someiyoshino trees bloom and drop their flowers at the same time, but it&apos;s also the reason for weakness against environmental changes and certain diseases.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is the reason that all Someiyoshino trees bloom and drop their flowers at the same time, but it&apos;s also the reason for weakness against environmental changes and certain diseases.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>人気・話題性</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Popularity and being topical</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Popularity and topicality</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Popularity and topicality</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="39">
<j>ソメイヨシノは、街中では他種より目にする機会が圧倒的に多いことから、以前からその起源についてと共に、可否好悪についても、愛桜家の間で論争の絶えなかった品種である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Someiyoshino has overwhelmingly more chances to be seen in streets than other brands, disputes between enthusiasts have been held continuously from the past about its origin and its right or wrong and likes and dislikes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because Someiyoshino is much more likely to be seen along the streets than other types, disputes between enthusiasts have occurred continuously from the past in regard to its origin as to whether it&apos;s right or wrong, as well as in regard to people&apos;s likes and dislikes.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because Someiyoshino is much more likely to be seen along the streets than other types, disputes between enthusiasts have occurred continuously from the past in regard to its origin as to whether it&apos;s right or wrong, as well as in regard to people&apos;s likes and dislikes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>歴史的には江戸時代中期～末期に園芸種として生まれたとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Historically, it is assumed to have been born in middle through late years of Edo period as a brand of gardening plants.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Historically, it&apos;s assumed to have been born in the middle through late Edo period as a type of garden plant.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Historically, it&apos;s assumed to have been born in the middle through late Edo period as a type of garden plant.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>葉より先に花が咲き開花が華やかであることや、若木から花を咲かす特性が好まれ、明治以来徐々に広まり、更に第二次世界大戦後荒廃した国土に爆発的な勢いで植樹され、日本で最も一般的な桜となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the characteristics, flowers bloom faster than leaves and the blooms are showy, are loved by the people, it spread gradually from Meiji period, and after further being planted with terrific pace on the devastated lands of the country after the World War II, it became to be the most popular cherry tree in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Given the characteristics in which its flowers bloom before the leaves mature and the blooms are showy and therefore loved by people, it spread gradually from the Meiji period on, and after further being planted at a terrific pace on the devastated lands of the country after World War II, it came to be the most popular cherry tree in Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Given the characteristics in which its flowers bloom before the leaves mature and the blooms are showy and therefore loved by people, it spread gradually from the Meiji period on, and after further being planted at a terrific pace on the devastated lands of the country after World War II, it came to be the most popular cherry tree in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>現在もほぼ日本全域に分布する最もポピュラーな桜であり、例年3月に気象庁が発表する「さくらの開花予想」（桜前線）も本種の開花状況が基準となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It still is the most popular cherry tree in Japan, being planted in almost all the areas of Japan, and the &apos;bloom forecast&apos; (cherry blossom front) which is announced in March of every year by Japan Meteorological Agency is based on the blooming condition of this brand.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It&apos;s still the most popular cherry tree in Japan, being planted in nearly every area of the country, and the &apos;bloom forecast&apos; (cherry blossom front) which is announced in March of every year by the Japan Meteorological Agency is based on the bloom condition of this type.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It&apos;s still the most popular cherry tree in Japan, being planted in nearly every area of the country, and the &apos;bloom forecast&apos; (cherry blossom front) which is announced in March of every year by the Japan Meteorological Agency is based on the bloom condition of this type.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>起源についての諸説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Various theories about the origin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Various theories about the origin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Various theories about the origin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="43">
<j>ソメイヨシノは江戸時代中期～末期に園芸品種として確立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Someiyoshino was established as a brand of gardening plants in middle though late period of Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Someiyoshino was established as a type of garden plant in the middle though late Edo period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Someiyoshino was established as a type of garden plant in the middle though late Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>園芸家による人工的な品種改良作出説と、自然交雑した物を、園芸家が挿し木によって増やしたという説とがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are theories that it was selected and bred artificially by gardeners, or that the natural hybrid tree was propagated by planting of cuttings by gardeners.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are theories that it was selected and bred artificially by gardeners, or that the natural hybrid tree was propagated by gardeners who planted cuttings.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are theories that it was selected and bred artificially by gardeners, or that the natural hybrid tree was propagated by gardeners who planted cuttings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>また、アメリカの植物学者にはソメイヨシノはオオシマザクラとエドヒガンの雑種ではなく独立した種であるとの説を唱える者もいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, among American botanists, there are ones that advocate the theory that Someiyoshino is an independent brand, not the hybrid between Oshima cherry and Edohigan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, among American botanists there are some who advocate the theory that Someiyoshino is an independent type instead of a hybrid between the Oshima cherry and Edohigan.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, among American botanists there are some who advocate the theory that Someiyoshino is an independent type instead of a hybrid between the Oshima cherry and Edohigan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>自然発生説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Spontaneous Theories</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Spontaneous Theories</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Spontaneous Theories</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>伊豆半島説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Izu Peninsula theory</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Izu Peninsula theory</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Izu Peninsula theory</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="46">
<j>1916年に屋久島のウィルソン株にその名前を残すアメリカのアーネスト・ヘンリー・ウィルソン（enErnest Henry Wilson）によりオオシマザクラとエドヒガンの雑種説が唱えられ、国立遺伝学研究所の竹中要（たけなか かなめ）の交配実験により、オオシマザクラとエドヒガンの交雑種の中からソメイヨシノおよびソメイヨシノに近似の亜種が得られることが分かり、1965年に発表された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1916, Ernest Henry Wilson of America, who leaves his name in Wilson stump in Yaku-shima Island, advocated the theory that it is a hybrid between Oshima cherry and Edohigan, and by the crossbreeding experiment by Kaname TAKENAKA of National Institute of Genetics, it was discovered that Someiyoshino and subspecies of Someiyoshino could be seen among the hybrids between Oshima cherry and Edohigan, and was published in 1965.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1916, Ernest Henry Wilson, an American whose name is commemorated at the Wilson stump in Yaku-shima Island, advocated the theory that it&apos;s a hybrid between the Oshima cherry and Edohigan; moreover, through the crossbreeding experiment by Kaname TAKENAKA of National Institute of Genetics (published in 1965) it was discovered that Someiyoshino and its subspecies could be seen among the hybrids between the Oshima cherry and Edohigan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1916, Ernest Henry Wilson, an American whose name is commemorated at the Wilson stump in Yaku-shima Island, advocated the theory that it&apos;s a hybrid between the Oshima cherry and Edohigan; moreover, through the crossbreeding experiment by Kaname TAKENAKA of National Institute of Genetics (published in 1965) it was discovered that Someiyoshino and its subspecies could be seen among the hybrids between the Oshima cherry and Edohigan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>これを受けて自然交雑説を採る場合、オオシマザクラおよびエドヒガンの分布状況から、伊豆半島付近で発生したとする伊豆半島発生説が唱えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of this, in the case where spontaneous theory was adopted, from the condition of distributions of Oshima cherry and Edohigan, Izu Peninsula theory was advocated, stating that it had sprung around Izu Peninsula.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Accordingly, in the case where the &quot;spontaneous&quot; theory was adopted, from the distribution conditions of the Oshima cherry and Edohigan, the &quot;Izu Peninsula&quot; theory was advocated, stating that it had sprung up in the area around the peninsula.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Accordingly, in the case where the spontaneous theory was adopted, from the distribution conditions of the Oshima cherry and Edohigan, the Izu Peninsula theory was advocated, stating that it had sprung up in the area around the peninsula.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot; &quot;削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>しかし、現地調査から自然交雑の可能性は否定的である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, from the local investigation, there is less possibility of being a natural hybrid.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, based on local investigation there is less possibility of its being a natural hybrid.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, based on local investigation there is less possibility of its being a natural hybrid.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>韓国起源説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Korean origination theory</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Korean origination theory</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Korean origination theory</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="49">
<j>ソメイヨシノは韓国の王桜を期限とする説もあったが、2007年米国農務省による遺伝子調査によって、韓国の王桜は韓国固有であり日本のソメイヨシノとは別種であることが確認されたため、本説は完全に否定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was a theory regarding Osakura (王桜) of Korea as the origin of Someiyoshino, but in 2007, it was confirmed by genetic research by United States Department of Agriculture that Osakura of Korea is peculiar to Korea and is a different species from Someiyoshino in Japan, and because of this, this theory has been completely denied.</e>
<cmt>王桜→読み、定訳不明です</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was a theory regarding the Osakura (王桜), of Korea, as the origin of Someiyoshino, but in 2007 it was confirmed through genetic research by the U.S. Department of Agriculture that the Osakura of Korea is peculiar to Korea and is a different species from the Someiyoshino of Japan, and consequently this theory has been thoroughly refuted.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was a theory regarding the Osakura (王桜), of Korea, as the origin of Someiyoshino, but in 2007 it was confirmed through genetic research by the U.S. Department of Agriculture that the Osakura of Korea is peculiar to Korea and is a different species from the Someiyoshino of Japan, and consequently this theory has been thoroughly refuted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>しかし、大韓民国ではいまだに「王桜＝ソメイヨシノ」説を唱え（韓国起源説参照）、王桜の自生地にソメイヨシノを植林する活動が積極的に進められており、逆に韓国の在来種であるはずの王桜の絶滅が心配されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However in Republic of Korea, there are still activities which advocate the theory which regard that &apos;Osakura = Someiyoshino&apos; and plant Someiyoshino in places where Osakura naturally grow, and on the contrary, the extinction of Osakura, which is a native species of Korea, is being feared.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in the Republic of Korea there are still activities that advocate the theory that &apos;Osakura equals Someiyoshino&apos; and therefore plant Someiyoshino in places where Osakura naturally grow, and in fact the extinction of Osakura--a species native to Korea--is feared.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in the Republic of Korea there are still activities that advocate the theory that &apos;Osakura equals Someiyoshino&apos; and therefore plant Someiyoshino in places where Osakura naturally grow, and in fact the extinction of Osakura--a species native to Korea--is feared.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="51">
<j>1939年に小泉源一が大韓民国の済州島の王桜との類似を指摘して、済州島が自生地であり起源とする説を唱えたが、小泉がソメイヨシノと王桜との比較に用いたとされる押し葉標本が残されておらず、当初からこの説は疑問視されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1939, Genichi KOIZUMI pointed out the similarity with Osakura in Jeju of Republic of Korea and advocated the theory which regard Jeju as the place of spontaneous growth and origin, but since there is no pressed flower specimen, which is said to be used by Koizumi to compare Someiyoshino and Osakura, remained, this theory have been seen with doubts from the beginning.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1939, Genichi KOIZUMI pointed out the similarity with Osakura in Jeju, of the Republic of Korea, and advocated a theory that regarded Jeju as the place of spontaneous growth and origin, but since there is no extant pressed flower specimen, which is said to have been used by Koizumi to compare Someiyoshino and Osakura, this theory has been doubted since the beginning.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1939, Genichi KOIZUMI pointed out the similarity with Osakura in Jeju, of the Republic of Korea, and advocated a theory that regarded Jeju as the place of spontaneous growth and origin, but since there is no extant pressed flower specimen, which is said to have been used by Koizumi to compare Someiyoshino and Osakura, this theory has been doubted since the beginning.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>また、ソメイヨシノはオオシマザクラとエドヒガンの交配的形態を持ち、遺伝子の特性もオオシマザクラとエドヒガンの特性に似るが、オオシマザクラは伊豆諸島で進化したカスミザクラの島嶼型であって朝鮮半島には存在しておらずこの点からも不利であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, Someiyoshino has form of crossbreeding of Oshima cherry and Edohigan and also has similar genetic characteristics with Oshima cherry and Edohigan, and since Oshima cherry is an island form of Kasumizakura (Prunus Leveilleana Koene) which evolved in Izu Island chain and doesn&apos;t exist in Korean Peninsula, the theory was disadvantageous from this point, too.</e>
<cmt>島嶼型→定訳不明です</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, Someiyoshino has the form of crossbreeding of the Oshima cherry and Edohigan as well as certain genetic similarities to the Oshima cherry and Edohigan, and since the Oshima cherry is an island form of Kasumizakura (Prunus Leveilleana Koene) that evolved in the Izu Island chain and doesn&apos;t exist in the Korean Peninsula, the theory was disadvantageous from this perspective too.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, Someiyoshino has the form of crossbreeding of the Oshima cherry and Edohigan as well as certain genetic similarities to the Oshima cherry and Edohigan, and since the Oshima cherry is an island form of Kasumizakura (Prunus Leveilleana Koene) that evolved in the Izu Island chain and doesn&apos;t exist in the Korean Peninsula, the theory was disadvantageous from this perspective too.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>基督日報が「世界的な影響力を持ったサイトなどを訪問して、韓国に関する間違いを修正してくれるように願う。」として、enCherry blossomを書き換える方法を掲載し。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Christianity Daily writes that, &apos;We wish readers to visit sites that have worldwide influence and amend an error about Korea.</e>
<cmt>enCherry blossom→不明です</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Christianity Daily&quot; states, &apos;We wish readers to visit sites that have worldwide influence and amend an error about Korea.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &apos;Christianity Daily&apos; states, &apos;We wish readers to visit sites that have worldwide influence and amend an error about Korea, and place a way to rewrite enCherry blossom.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot; &quot;削除しました。原文分割位置をてい精しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="54">
<j>しかしながら2009年4月10日、韓国の三大紙の中央日報はソメイヨシノは韓国汝矣島が発祥であるとしている</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However on April 10, 2009, Joong Ang Daily, one of three great newspapers in Korea, regarded the origin of Someiyoshino as Yoi Island of Korea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However on April 10, 2009, the Joong Ang Daily, one of three great newspapers in Korea, regarded the origin of Someiyoshino as that country&apos;s Yoi Island.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However on April 10, 2009, the Joong Ang Daily, one of three great newspapers in Korea, regarded the origin of Someiyoshino as that country&apos;s Yoi Island.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>さらに、多くの韓国人学者達が桜は日本起源ではなく、韓国起源であると主張していることを明らかにしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, many Korean scholars clearly insist that cherry tree has been originated in Korea, not in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further, many Korean scholars insist that the cherry tree originated in Korea instead of Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further, many Korean scholars insist that the cherry tree originated in Korea instead of Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>人工作出説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Artificial breeding theory</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The artificial breeding theory</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The artificial breeding theory</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="56">
<j>これに対し、明治初年に樹齢100年に達するソメイヨシノが小石川植物園に植えられていたという記録や、染井村（現在の東京都豊島区駒込）の植木屋の記録にソメイヨシノを作出したという記録が発見されたことから、岩崎文雄らは染井村起源説を唱えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Against this theory, because a record which states that Someiyoshino, reaching the age of 100, had been planted in Koishikawa Botanical Gardens, and a record of a gardener in Somei Village (present-day Komagome, Toshima Ward, Tokyo Prefecture) which states that Someiyoshino was bred, were founded, Fumio IWASAKI and others advocate the theory which regard Somei Village as the place of origin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Against this theory, given a record stating that Someiyoshino, reaching the age of 100, had been planted in Koishikawa Botanical Gardens, and the record of a gardener in Somei Village (the present-day Komagome, Toshima Ward, Tokyo Prefecture) stating that Someiyoshino was bred, Fumio IWASAKI and others advocate the theory that regards Somei Village as the place of origin.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Against this theory, given a record stating that Someiyoshino, reaching the age of 100, had been planted in Koishikawa Botanical Gardens, and the record of a gardener in Somei Village (the present-day Komagome, Toshima Ward, Tokyo Prefecture) stating that Someiyoshino was bred, Fumio IWASAKI and others advocate the theory that regards Somei Village as the place of origin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>この植木屋の記録により1720～1735年ごろ、駒込の西福寺に墓の残る当地の伊藤伊兵衛政武が人工交配・育成したとの推定もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By this record by a gardener, there is an assumption that in around 1720 - 1735, ITO Ihei Masatake, who had lived in Komagome and has a tomb in Saifuku-ji Temple, artificially bred and grew Someiyoshino.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based on the gardener&apos;s record, there is an assumption that sometime in the period from 1720 from 1735, ITO Ihei Masatake, who had lived in Komagome and whose tomb is at Saifuku-ji Temple, artificially bred and grew Someiyoshino.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based on the gardener&apos;s record, there is an assumption that sometime in the period from 1720 from 1735, ITO Ihei Masatake, who had lived in Komagome and whose tomb is at Saifuku-ji Temple, artificially bred and grew Someiyoshino.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>これによって現在では染井村起源という可能性が有力である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By this, the possibility of place of origin being Somei Village is influential.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This gives credibility to the assertion that Somei Village is the place of origin.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This gives credibility to the assertion that Somei Village is the place of origin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="59">
<j>2007年3月、千葉大・静岡大などの研究グループが、遺伝子解析の結果、オオシマザクラとエドヒガンの園芸品種の一つであるコマツオトメの交配で生み出された可能性が高いと発表した</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In March, 2007, research group of Chiba University, Shizuoka University, and others announced that from the result of genetic analysis, Someiyoshino was likely to have been born by crossbreeding Oshima cherry and Komatsuotome, which is one of a gardening brand of Edohigan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In March 2007, a group comprised of researchers from Chiba University, Shizuoka University and elsewhere announced that, based on the results of genetic analysis, Someiyoshino was likely to have been born by crossbreeding the Oshima cherry and Komatsuotome, which is a gardening type of Edohigan.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In March 2007, a group comprised of researchers from Chiba University, Shizuoka University and elsewhere announced that, based on the results of genetic analysis, Someiyoshino was likely to have been born by crossbreeding the Oshima cherry and Komatsuotome, which is a gardening type of Edohigan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>第111回講演会　『』。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">111th Lecture &quot;&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">111th Lecture</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">111th Lecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>4/5ページ（中西印刷株式会社サイト）PDFファイル。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">4/5 page (site of Nakanishi Printing Company) PDF files.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">4/5 page (site of Nakanishi Printing Company) PDF files.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">4/5 page (site of Nakanishi Printing Company) PDF files.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="62">
<j>これは岩手大学講師であった橋本昌幸（2003年（平成15年）11月25日没75歳）が竹中要の説に従い交配した桜はソメイヨシノに似ず、橋本の助言がきっかけで中村郁郎らがDNA解析からオオシマザクラと上野恩賜公園のコマツオトメを交配し2008年春に千葉大学園芸部で5本を鉢に植え、4年または5年後の2012年または2013年にソメイヨシノが再現されると見込んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masayuki HASHIMOTO (died on November 25, 2003, at the age of 75), who was a lecturer of Iwate University, followed the theory by Kaname TAKENAKA but couldn&apos;t breed cherry tree being similar to Someiyoshino, and with an advice by Hashimoto, Ikuo NAKAMURA and others, from the DNA analysis, crossbred Oshima cherry and Komatsuotome in Ueno Onshi Koen park and planted 5 trees in pots at The Faculty of Horticulture of Chiba University, and expect them to be reappear as Someiyoshino in 2012 or 2013, which is 4 or 5 years later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masayuki HASHIMOTO, a lecturer at Iwate Univesity (who died on November 25, 2003, at the age of 75), followed the theory by Kaname TAKENAKA but couldn&apos;t breed a cherry tree similar to Someiyoshino; however, based on advice by Hashimoto, Ikuo NAKAMURA and others, from the DNA analysis, he crossbred the Oshima cherry and Komatsuotome of Ueno Onshi Koen park and planted five trees in pots at Chiba University&apos;s Faculty of Horticulture, expecting them to be reappear four or five years later (2012 or 2013) as Someiyoshino.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masayuki HASHIMOTO, a lecturer at Iwate Univesity (who died on November 25, 2003, at the age of 75), followed the theory by Kaname TAKENAKA but couldn&apos;t breed a cherry tree similar to Someiyoshino; however, based on advice by Hashimoto, Ikuo NAKAMURA and others, from the DNA analysis, he crossbred the Oshima cherry and Komatsuotome of Ueno Onshi Koen park and planted five trees in pots at Chiba University&apos;s Faculty of Horticulture, expecting them to be reappear four or five years later (2012 or 2013) as Someiyoshino.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>用途</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Use</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Use</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Use</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="63">
<j>街路樹、河川敷、公園の植え込みなどに広く用いられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is broadly planted in streets, flood plains, and parks.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is broadly planted in streets, flood plains and parks.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is broadly planted in streets, flood plains and parks.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>花見に一番使われる木となっており、人気種である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is the most used tree in flower viewing, and is popular.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It&apos;s popular as the tree most commonly used to encourage blossom viewing.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It&apos;s popular as the tree most commonly used to encourage blossom viewing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>病気等</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Disease and others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Diseases, etc.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Diseases, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="65">
<j>サクラ全般に共通の欠点として、ソメイヨシノも排気ガスによる大気汚染などの環境悪化に弱いこと、病気や虫の害を受けやすいことが指摘される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a common fault of cherry trees, it is pointed out that Someiyoshino too is frail against air pollution such as exhaust gas, and is easily damaged by disease and insects.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As is a common fault of cherry trees, it&apos;s pointed out that Someiyoshino too has low resistance to air pollution such as exhaust gas, and that it&apos;s easily damaged by disease and insects.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As is a common fault of cherry trees, it&apos;s pointed out that Someiyoshino too has low resistance to air pollution such as exhaust gas, and that it&apos;s easily damaged by disease and insects.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>全個体がクローンであるため、新しい耐性を手に入れる能力も低い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because all the individuals are clones, it has low ability of gaining new tolerance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because all the individuals are clones, it has low ability to acquire greater tolerance.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because all the individuals are clones, it has low ability to acquire greater tolerance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="14">
<tit>
<j>てんぐ巣病</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Witches&apos; broom disease</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Witch&apos;s broom disease</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Witch&apos;s broom disease</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="67">
<j>他のサクラよりてんぐ巣病（てんぐすびょう）にかかりやすい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is easily infected by witches&apos; broom disease than other cherry trees.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It&apos;s more easily infected by witch&apos;s broom disease than other cherry trees are.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It&apos;s more easily infected by witch&apos;s broom disease than other cherry trees are.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>サクラてんぐ巣病はTaphrina wiesneriという酵母菌状の子嚢菌の感染により起こる病気で、その上部では小枝が密生して、いわゆる「天狗の巣」を作る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cherry tree witches&apos; broom disease is a disease when a tree is infected by Taphrina wiesneri, an ascomycete with form of saccharomycete, and at the top part of the tree, twigs gather up and make what is called &apos;nest of tengu&apos; (nest of long-nosed goblin, or witches&apos; broom).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Witch&apos;s broom disease will strike when the cherry tree is infected by Taphrina wiesneri, an ascomycete with a form of saccharomycete, and at the top part of the tree twigs gather up and make what is called a &apos;nest of tengu&apos; (nest of long-nosed goblin, or a witch&apos;s broom).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Witch&apos;s broom disease will strike when the cherry tree is infected by Taphrina wiesneri, an ascomycete with a form of saccharomycete, and at the top part of the tree twigs gather up and make what is called a &apos;nest of tengu&apos; (nest of long-nosed goblin, or a witch&apos;s broom).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>更に、開花時には小さい葉が開くので目障りとなったり、罹病部位は数年で枯死したりといった被害を与える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, since small leaves grow at the time of blooming of the flowers, they become to be eyesore, and also give damage to tree because infected area will die in several years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further, because small leaves begin to grow as the flowers reach full bloom, they become an eyesore and subject the tree to damage because the infected area will die within a period of several years.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further, because small leaves begin to grow as the flowers reach full bloom, they become an eyesore and subject the tree to damage because the infected area will die within a period of several years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>罹病した病枝は切り取って焼却しなければならない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Infected branches must be cut and burned.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The infected branches must be cut off and burned.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The infected branches must be cut off and burned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="15">
<tit>
<j>キノコ類による被害</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Damages by mushrooms</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Damage due to mushrooms</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Damage due to mushrooms</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="71">
<j>サルノコシカケ等の白色腐朽菌類が繁殖し、罹病した病木を切り取らなければならないケースが急増しており、特に公園や街路樹として植えられている木が深刻な状況に陥っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The cases which white-rot fungus, such as bracket fungus, propagate, and the infected trees are forced to be cut down are increasing rapidly, and especially the trees planted in parks and streets are in serious condition.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Increasingly, there are cases in which white-rot fungus (such as bracket fungus) propagates and the infected trees must be cut down; particularly, the trees planted in parks and streets are in serious condition.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Increasingly, there are cases in which white-rot fungus (such as bracket fungus) propagates and the infected trees must be cut down; particularly, the trees planted in parks and streets are in serious condition.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>こうした症状は外からでは分からないため、特別な機械を使わないと診断できない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This kind of symptom can&apos;t be recognized from outside, so the special machine must be used for diagnosis.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This kind of symptom can&apos;t be recognized from outside, so a special device must be used for diagnosis.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This kind of symptom can&apos;t be recognized from outside, so a special device must be used for diagnosis.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="16">
<tit>
<j>アメリカシロヒトリによる被害</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Damages by America Shirohitori (Hyphantria cunea)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Damage by America Shirohitori (Hyphantria cunea)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Damage by America Shirohitori (Hyphantria cunea)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="73">
<j>アメリカシロヒトリによる葉の食害により、高齢木を中心に樹勢が減退することがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Damages are done to leaves when America Shirohitori eat leaves, and sometimes vitality of the tree is reduced, mainly in old trees.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Damage is done to the leaves when America Shirohitori consumes them, and sometimes the vitality of the tree is reduced, particularly in the case of an old tree.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Damage is done to the leaves when America Shirohitori consumes them, and sometimes the vitality of the tree is reduced, particularly in the case of an old tree.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>アメリカシロヒトリは、葉の裏に造る巣網の中で3齢虫まで集団で成長することから、成虫になる前に枝・葉を落とす直接除去もしくはフェニトロチオンやオルトラン乳剤などの殺虫剤を適宜散布することにより駆虫する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since America Shirohitori grow up in a group in the nest net which is on the back of the leaves until they become to be the final form as worms, they are removed directly by cutting of branches and leaves before they grow up to be imagoes, or are exterminated by spraying appropriate amount of insecticides such as fenitrothion or emulsion of acephate.</e>
<cmt>3齢虫→定訳不明です</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because America Shirohitori grow as a group in the nest net, which is on the back of the leaves, until they reach their final form as worms, they are removed directly by cutting off the affected branches and leaves before they grow up to be imagoes, or are exterminated by spraying an appropriate amount of insecticide such as fenitrothion or emulsion of acephate.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because America Shirohitori grow as a group in the nest net, which is on the back of the leaves, until they reach their final form as worms, they are removed directly by cutting off the affected branches and leaves before they grow up to be imagoes, or are exterminated by spraying an appropriate amount of insecticide such as fenitrothion or emulsion of acephate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="75">
<j>環境による樹勢低下</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reduction of tree&apos;s vitality by environment</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reduction of tree vitality due to the environment</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reduction of tree vitality due to the environment</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>排ガスなどの大気汚染ももちろん、近年の地球温暖化やヒートアイランド現象で、ソメイヨシノが急激な環境の変化についていけていないことが病気の遠因になっている節がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Not only the air pollution by exhaust gas, but also the global warming and the heat-island phenomenon seem to become remote causes of Someiyoshino becoming ill, for the trees can&apos;t keep up with rapid changes of environment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Not only are air pollution by exhaust gas but global warming and the heat-island phenomenon are also indirect causes of illness among Someiyoshino trees, since they can&apos;t keep up with the rapid pace of environmental change.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Not only are air pollution by exhaust gas but global warming and the heat-island phenomenon are also indirect causes of illness among Someiyoshino trees, since they can&apos;t keep up with the rapid pace of environmental change.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>根の近くが舗装されることも樹勢を削ぐ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The pavement of ground around the roots also reduce the vitality of the tree.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The pavement of ground around the roots also reduces the vitality of the tree.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The pavement of ground around the roots also reduces the vitality of the tree.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="78">
<j>また、花見に一番使われる木であることも病気の遠因といえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, being the most popular tree for flower viewing can also be said as a remote cause of disease.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, being the most popular tree for flower viewing can be called an indirect cause of disease.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, being the most popular tree for flower viewing can be called an indirect cause of disease.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>根に近い土壌を過剰に踏みしめられることは木に良いとはいえない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soil around the roots being stepped on excessively can&apos;t be said good for the trees.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The excessive compacting of the soil around the roots due to foot traffic can&apos;t be good for the tree, either.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The excessive compacting of the soil around the roots due to foot traffic can&apos;t be good for the tree, either.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>また、それ以上にマナーの悪さが木に影響する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, more than that, bad manners influence the trees.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, bad manners influence the trees.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, bad manners influence the trees.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>木の下で焼肉やバーベキューなどの火を使う行為は木に悪影響を与えるため避けるべきである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Using fire, such as grilling meat and barbecuing, under the tree has bad influence for the tree, so it should be avoided.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The use of fire beneath the tree, such as in grilling meat and barbecuing, has a negative influence and should therefore be avoided.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The use of fire beneath the tree, such as in grilling meat and barbecuing, has a negative influence and should therefore be avoided.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>あまつさえ花見客が枝を折ったり切り取ったりすることなどは問題外である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On top of that, breaking and cutting of the branches of tree by people viewing flowers are out of the question.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On top of that, people who view the flowers should absolutely be prohibited from breaking and cutting the branches of the trees.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On top of that, people who view the flowers should absolutely be prohibited from breaking and cutting the branches of the trees.</e>
<cmt>不要なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>桜全般に言えることであるが、枝を折られるとそこから腐りやすいため、知識もなく枝を折ることや切ることは慎むべきである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It can be said in general for cherry trees, but since it tend to rot from the place where branches were broken, breaking and cutting of branches without knowledge should be refrained.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It can be said in general for cherry trees, but since it tends to rot at the site of a broken branch, people untrained in tree care should refrain from breaking and cutting the branches.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It can be said in general for cherry trees, but since it tends to rot at the site of a broken branch, people untrained in tree care should refrain from breaking and cutting the branches.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>折れたり切れたりした部分は雑菌の繁殖を防ぎ、腐らないように保護することが重要である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is important to protect the part where branches were broken and cut from propagation of miscellaneous germs, preventing the rot.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is important that the areas where branches have been broken and cut are protected from the propagation of miscellaneous germs, so that rot can be prevented</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is important that the areas where branches have been broken and cut are protected from the propagation of miscellaneous germs, so that rot can be prevented.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="17">
<tit>
<j>寿命</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Span of life</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Life span</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Life span</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="85">
<j>ソメイヨシノには大きな欠点がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Someiyoshino has a big fault.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Someiyoshino has a major fault.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Someiyoshino has a major fault.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>数百年の古木になることもあるヤマザクラやエドヒガンに比べて高齢の木が少ないことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Compared with Yamazakura and Edohigan, which sometimes become to be an old tree with age of several hundred years, there are less old trees.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Compared with Yamazakura and Edohigan, which can live for several hundred years, there are fewer old trees.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Compared with Yamazakura and Edohigan, which can live for several hundred years, there are fewer old trees.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>「60年寿命説」なる俗説があるほどである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is even a popular belief called &apos;60 years life span theory.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is even a popular belief called the &apos;sixty-year lifespan theory.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is even a popular belief called the &apos;sixty-year lifespan theory.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>ただし、正確な寿命に関しては、統計数値がないため不明であり、また、大径になる木は理論上は寿命がないと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, accurate length of the lifespan is unknown because there is no statistics, and trees which become to have large diameter is believed to have limitless lifespan, theoretically.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the lifespan isn&apos;t known because there are no statistics, the tree that reaches a large diameter is theoretically believed to have an unlimited lifespan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the lifespan isn&apos;t known because there are no statistics, the tree that reaches a large diameter is theoretically believed to have an unlimited lifespan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="89">
<j>老木の少なさの原因ははっきりしていないが、「ソメイヨシノは成長が早いので、その分老化も早い」という説があるほか、街路のように排気ガスなどで傷むこと、公園と言った荒らされやすい場所に植樹されているということも、寿命を縮める原因となっているのではないかとの指摘もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reason for having less number of old trees is not clarified, but there is a theory stating that &apos;Someiyoshino age fast because it grow up fast,&apos; and it has been pointed out that the damages by exhaust gas and others in the streets, or the fact that the trees are likely to be planted in places where it is easily trashed, such as parks, seem to have become to be the reason to reduce the lifespan of Someiyoshino.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reason for having fewer old trees is not clear, but there is a theory that &apos;Someiyoshino ages quickly because it grows rapidly&apos;; it has been pointed out that the damage by exhaust gas and other factors occurring in the streets, or the fact that the trees are likely to be planted in places where they&apos;re easily trashed, such as parks, seem to have become the factors that reduce the Someiyoshino&apos;s lifespan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reason for having fewer old trees is not clear, but there is a theory that &apos;Someiyoshino ages quickly because it grows rapidly&apos;; it has been pointed out that the damage by exhaust gas and other factors occurring in the streets, or the fact that the trees are likely to be planted in places where they&apos;re easily trashed, such as parks, seem to have become the factors that reduce the Someiyoshino&apos;s lifespan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>ソメイヨシノは接ぎ木によって増やされる為、接ぎ木の台木とされたヤマザクラが腐って心材腐朽を起こし、寿命を縮めているという説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Someiyoshino is propagated by grafting, there is a theory stating that since Yamazakura, stock for grafting, rot, the center of the tree also rot and shortens the lifespan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because Someiyoshino is propagated by grafting, it is theorized that since Yamazakura--the stock for grafting--rots, the center of the tree also rots and thereby shortens the lifespan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because Someiyoshino is propagated by grafting, it is theorized that since Yamazakura--the stock for grafting--rots, the center of the tree also rots and thereby shortens the lifespan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>また、全てのソメイヨシノが同一の特性を持つために全てのソメイヨシノが病気や環境の変化に弱く、それらに負け一斉に枯れるという点もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, there is a point that since all the Someiyoshino have same characteristics, all the Someiyoshino are weak from diseases and changes of environment, and wither at the same time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has also been pointed out that because all Someiyoshino have same characteristics, all Someiyoshino have poor resistance to disease and environmental changes, and consequently they wither at the same time.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has also been pointed out that because all Someiyoshino have same characteristics, all Someiyoshino have poor resistance to disease and environmental changes, and consequently they wither at the same time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="92">
<j>しかし、こうしたイメージの一方、ソメイヨシノの老木も存在している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, against this impression, there is old trees of Someiyoshino existing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Contrary to that assertion, there are indeed old Someiyoshino trees to be found.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Contrary to that assertion, there are indeed old Someiyoshino trees to be found.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>東京都内の砧公園のソメイヨシノは1935年に植えられたものなので、すでに70年以上が経過している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Someiyoshino in Kinuta Park in Tokyo Prefecture was planted in 1935, so more than 70 years have already been passed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A Someiyoshino in Tokyo Prefecture&apos;s Kinuta Park was planted in 1935, so more than 70 years have already passed.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A Someiyoshino in Tokyo Prefecture&apos;s Kinuta Park was planted in 1935, so more than 70 years have already passed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>また、青森県弘前市ではリンゴの剪定技術をソメイヨシノの剪定管理に応用するなどして樹勢回復に取り組んだ結果、多くのソメイヨシノの樹勢を回復することに成功している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also in Hirosaki City, Aomori Prefecture, as a result of application of pruning techniques of apple tree to pruning of Someiyoshino to recover the vitality of the trees, they succeeded to recover the vitality of many Someiyoshino.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, in Hirosaki City, Aomori Prefecture, due to the use of apple-tree pruning techniques on Someiyoshino as a means to recover their vitality, many Someiyoshino have returned to health.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, in Hirosaki City, Aomori Prefecture, due to the use of apple-tree pruning techniques on Someiyoshino as a means to recover their vitality, many Someiyoshino have returned to health.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>但し、紅葉・落葉直後にすぐ剪定することでC/N比（炭素/窒素比）を変えたり、根回しや土壌交換による細根の発生をもたらすなど管理に留意を要する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the management must be paid attention, such as by pruning right after coloring and falling of the leaves to change C/N ratio (carbon/nitrogen ratio), and by promoting narrow roots to grow by digging around the roots of trees and changing the soil.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, attention must be paid to management, such as by pruning immediately after the leaves change color and fall in order to change the C/N (carbon/nitrogen) ratio, and by promoting the growth of narrow roots by digging around them and modifying the soil.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, attention must be paid to management, such as by pruning immediately after the leaves change color and fall in order to change the C/N (carbon/nitrogen) ratio, and by promoting the growth of narrow roots by digging around them and modifying the soil.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>弘前城跡公園には樹齢100年を超えるソメイヨシノがあり、これは本種の現存する最も古い株であろうと言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Hirosaki Park (Hirosaki Castle Ruins), there is Someiyoshino with age of over 100 years, and this is said to be the oldest tree existing among this species.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Hirosaki Park (at the ruins of Hirosaki Castle), there is a Someiyoshino more than a century old, and this is said to be the oldest tree existing among this species.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Hirosaki Park (at the ruins of Hirosaki Castle), there is a Someiyoshino more than a century old, and this is said to be the oldest tree existing among this species.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>なおこのソメイヨシノを1882年に植林したのは、擬似科学批判で知られる物理学者菊池誠 (大阪大学)の曽祖父で、「青森りんごの始祖」とも言われる菊池楯衛である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, a person who planted this Someiyoshino in 1882 was Tatee KIKUCHI, who is said to be the &apos;founder of Aomori apples,&apos; and he was also a great-grandfather of physicist Makoto KIKUCHI (Osaka University), who is known for criticism against pseudoscience,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further, this Someiyoshino was planted in 1882 by Tatee KIKUCHI, who is said to be the &apos;founder of Aomori apples&apos;; he was also a great-grandfather of the physicist Makoto KIKUCHI (Osaka University), who is known for his criticism against pseudoscience.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further, this Someiyoshino was planted in 1882 by Tatee KIKUCHI, who is said to be the &apos;founder of Aomori apples&apos;; he was also a great-grandfather of the physicist Makoto KIKUCHI (Osaka University), who is known for his criticism against pseudoscience.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="98">
<j>人によって広められたソメイヨシノは人の手を借りることでその命を永らえ、花を咲かすことができるのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Someiyoshino, being propagated by people&apos;s hands, lengthen its life and be able to bloom flower with the help of people&apos;s hands, also.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Propagation by human hands extends the life of the Someiyoshino, and thus it&apos;s also able to blossom through the work of human hands.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Propagation by human hands extends the life of the Someiyoshino, and thus it&apos;s also able to blossom through the work of human hands.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 向日葵三十郎(id:45034), SkrF(id:301186), Nnh(id:474), RevRev(id:203633), Cprobot(id:97843), Lupinoid(id:68), Marantz7(id:15267), Michael Friedrich(id:44338), Eikiti(id:198553), 蜂谷(id:92541), Janus01(id:69663), ぎゅうひ(id:9206), らりた(id:1327), OSY(id:35563), 橄欖岩(id:24996), Michey.M(id:906), Kenpei(id:11349), Riku(id:16088), あおもりくま(id:143606), Ｋｓ(id:15319), ドゥルーズ・ガタリ(id:147849), Kouko0515(id:100370), Fk(id:33514), Hibiki-c(id:171692), Sesirec(id:27279), いろはにほへと(id:89648), Deepimpact(id:129352), Seibuabina(id:37532), Mastar(id:39278), Dolfin(id:4331), くまたろう(id:46892), Kokada jnet(id:84730), Tarobo(id:17287), NIKE(id:16342), Dump(id:26383), ウミユスリカ(id:9504), ライリ(id:44834), 三日月(id:19540), Vicn(id:296576), Rosan(id:19310), Bluesky07(id:121929), ホロ部(id:45183), 68er(id:25081), Honeplus(id:35348), PLANT(id:16515), Araisyohei(id:378), Rikumio(id:99645), Rai koku(id:1661), Knife(id:10235), Hachikou(id:10676), Mintleaf(id:2216), 氷鷺(id:73707), Goki(id:7107), K-Phil(id:53114), Loveless(id:129239), R34SkylineGT-R V-SpecⅡNür(id:131871), 竹麦魚(id:11012), Chichiii(id:242358), Pqks758(id:35879), Namazu-tron(id:135120), Tatsujin28(id:9300), Manmt(id:49480), Nighthawks(id:36125), Oh-moo(id:23674), BitBucket(id:30999), Wilson Tam(id:17411), 雲居雁乃(id:15842), Peachkiller(id:99202), Inukawa(id:842), Kwakkun(id:19105), Louperibot(id:128971), Remington(id:98835), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>