<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>出汁</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soup Stock</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soup Stock</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soup Stock</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>出汁（だし）は、調味料の一つで、料理に甘味・酸味・苦味・塩味の味覚に加えて、肉や野菜、キノコや海藻に含まれるうま味を抽出して加えるための液体。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soup stock is a liquid seasoning for adding tastes - sweetness, sourness, bitterness, saltiness, and moreover, the good taste extracted from meat, a vegetable, a mushroom, a seaweed, or others - to dishes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soup stock is a liquid seasoning used to add certain tastes--sweetness, sourness, bitterness, saltiness, and particularly the good taste extracted from meat, a vegetables, mushrooms, seaweed or others--to dishes.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soup stock is a liquid seasoning used to add certain tastes--sweetness, sourness, bitterness, saltiness, and particularly the good taste extracted from meat, vegetables, mushrooms, seaweed or others--to dishes.</e>
<cmt>a削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>うま味成分である呈味性のアミノ酸や核酸を豊富に含み、栄養上の価値も高い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soup stock not only includes affluent amino acids &amp; nucleic acids, which are both appreciated via the sense of taste as the good one, but also has high nutritional value.</e>
<cmt>※「呈味性の」は「（ヒトの）味覚を通じ一定の味に認識される」という意味のようです。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soup stock not only includes abundant amino acids and nucleic acids--which are both appreciated via the sense of taste--but it also has high nutritional value.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soup stock not only includes abundant amino acids and nucleic acids--which are both appreciated via the sense of taste--but it also has high nutritional value.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>日本料理における出汁</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soup stock in Japanese cuisine</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soup stock in Japanese cuisine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soup stock in Japanese cuisine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>日本料理において、出汁は最も基本的で重要な材料のひとつである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japanese cuisine, soup stock is one of the most basic and important ingredients.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japanese cuisine, soup stock is one of the most basic, most important ingredients.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japanese cuisine, soup stock is one of the most basic, most important ingredients.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>出汁を上手に作れない者は日本料理を上手に作れない者とされる事も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is often said those who are poor at making soup stock are unable to make good Japanese dishes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is often said those who are unskilled at making soup stock are unable to make good Japanese dishes.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is often said those who are unskilled at making soup stock are unable to make good Japanese dishes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>日本料理では主にコンブ・鰹節・鯵節・煮干し（いりこ）・トビウオ・焼き干しなどを煮て作る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japanese cuisine, soup stock is extracted by simmering &quot;konbu&quot; (a kind of kelp), &quot;katsuobushi&quot; (a dried bonito), &quot;ajibushi&quot; (a dried scad), &quot;niboshi&quot; (also called &quot;iriko&quot;) [small dried sardines], a dried flying fish and other dried fishes.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。※鯵節に使われるのはムロアジ（scad)です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japanese cuisine, soup stock is extracted by simmering &quot;konbu&quot; (a kind of kelp), &quot;katsuobushi&quot; (a dried bonito), &quot;ajibushi&quot; (dried scad), &quot;niboshi&quot; (also called &quot;iriko&quot;) [small dried sardines], dried flying fish and other varieties of dried fish.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japanese cuisine, soup stock is extracted by simmering konbu (a kind of kelp), katsuobushi (a dried bonito), ajibushi (dried scad), niboshi (also called iriko) (small dried sardines), dried flying fish and other varieties of dried fish.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除カッコ統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>また、干し椎茸などの乾物を水に浸して徐々に成分を抽出する方法も用いられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soup stock is extracted also by gradually steeping the ingredients of dried goods, such as dried mushrooms, in water.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soup stock is also extracted by slowly steeping the dried ingredients, such as dried mushrooms, in water.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soup stock is also extracted by slowly steeping the dried ingredients, such as dried mushrooms, in water.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>代表的には鰹節を削ったものから抽出（手法や呼称の詳細は後述）したものを出汁と称する場合が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan, the soup stock extracted from the shaved katsuobushi is so typical as to be often called just &quot;soup stock&quot;; the details about how to extract and about the name of the extracts are explained below.</e>
<cmt>※原文は文章がこなれていないので以下のように訂正の上、訳しています。「日本では、鰹節を削ったものから抽出した出汁（手法や呼称の詳細は後述）が代表的なものなので、これを単に出汁と称する場合が多い。」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan, the soup stock extracted from the shaved katsuobushi is so typical as to often be called just &quot;soup stock&quot;; the details of extraction and the naming of the extracts are explained below.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan, the soup stock extracted from the shaved katsuobushi is so typical as to often be called just &quot;soup stock&quot;; the details of extraction and the naming of the extracts are explained below.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>鶏肉やスッポン、ウミガメを使うことも稀にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rare as it is, the meat of a chicken, a sea turtle, or a soft-shelled turtle is also used as the raw material.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rare as it is, the meat of a sea turtle, soft-shelled turtle (or chicken) is also used as a raw material.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rare as it is, the meat of a sea turtle, soft-shelled turtle (or chicken) is also used as a raw material.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>精進料理においては、コンブ、椎茸の他に、大豆、モヤシ、豆腐なども用いられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In vegetarian cuisine, soybeans, bean sprouts, &quot;tofu&quot; (bean curd) and other materials are used besides konbu and mushrooms;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In vegetarian cuisine, soybeans, bean sprouts, &quot;tofu&quot; (bean curd) and other materials are used besides konbu and mushrooms;</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In vegetarian cuisine, soybeans, bean sprouts, tofu (bean curd) and other materials are used besides konbu and mushrooms;</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>（西洋料理でいうフォンやブイヨン、中国料理でいう湯（タン）にあたるが、それらの料理では素材を長く煮詰めることが多い。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the counterparts in Western cuisine are &quot;fond&quot; &amp; &quot;bouillon,&quot; and that in Chinese cuisine is &quot;tan,&quot; but these are mostly extracted by simmering the material for long hours;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">the counterparts in Western cuisine are &quot;fond&quot; and &quot;bouillon,&quot; while that in Chinese cuisine is &quot;tan,&quot; but these are generally extracted by simmering the material for several hours;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(The counterparts in Western cuisine are fond and bouillon, while that in Chinese cuisine is tan, but these are generally extracted by simmering the material for several hours.)</e>
<cmt>スペル&quot;削除一文として扱いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>（中国料理・西洋料理における『出汁』については下に記述）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the soup stock in Chinese &amp; Western cuisine is explained below.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">the soup stock in Chinese and Western cuisine is explained below.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(The soup stock in Chinese and Western cuisine is explained below.)</e>
<cmt>一文として扱いました。()補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>日本料理の出汁は、しばしば短時間で素材の風味を抽出し利用することが多く、特徴的である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is characteristic of Japanese cuisine&apos;s soup stock that the savor of the material is extracted and utilized often within a short time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is characteristic of the soup stock used in Japanese cuisine that the savoriness of the material is extracted and utilized within a short time.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is characteristic of the soup stock used in Japanese cuisine that the savoriness of the material is extracted and utilized within a short time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>出汁は上記の汁物のほか、おでんなどの鍋料理に用いる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soup stock is used for the above-mentioned soup dishes, and for pot dishes, including &quot;oden&quot; (a Japanese dish containing all kinds of ingredients cooked in a special broth of soy sauce, sugar, sake, etc).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soup stock is used for the above-mentioned soup dishes as well as pot dishes, including &quot;oden&quot; (a Japanese dish containing all kinds of ingredients cooked in a special broth of soy sauce, sugar, sake, etc).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soup stock is used for the above-mentioned soup dishes as well as pot dishes, including oden (a Japanese dish containing all kinds of ingredients cooked in a special broth of soy sauce, sugar, sake, etc).</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>また酢などを割って二杯酢・三杯酢を作り、あるいは和え物の和え衣に少量を加えることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And there also exists vinegar-based soup stock, such as &quot;nihaizu&quot; (vinegar and soy sauce mixed in roughly equal proportions) and &quot;sanbaizu&quot; (vinegar, soy sauce and &quot;mirin&quot; [sweet cooking rice wine] mixed in roughly equal proportions), and occasionally, a small amount of soup stock is added to &quot;aegoromo&quot; (traditional Japanese dressing) which is used for &quot;aemono&quot; (chopped fish, shellfish, or vegetables, prepared with some dressing).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There also exists vinegar-based soup stock, such as &quot;nihaizu&quot; (vinegar and soy sauce mixed in roughly equal proportions) and &quot;sanbaizu&quot; (vinegar, soy sauce and &quot;mirin&quot; [sweet cooking rice wine] mixed in roughly equal proportions), and occasionally, a small amount of soup stock is added to &quot;aegoromo&quot; (traditional Japanese dressing), which is used for &quot;aemono&quot; (chopped fish, shellfish, or vegetables, prepared with some dressing).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There also exists vinegar-based soup stock, such as nihaizu (vinegar and soy sauce mixed in roughly equal proportions) and sanbaizu (vinegar, soy sauce and mirin [sweet cooking rice wine] mixed in roughly equal proportions), and occasionally, a small amount of soup stock is added to aegoromo (traditional Japanese dressing), which is used for aemono (chopped fish, shellfish, or vegetables, prepared with some dressing).</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>なお、西日本において「だし」と表記する場合は、上記の意味ではなくうどん用のつゆそのものを指す場合も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Incidentally, in western Japan, it is not rare for the Japanese word &quot;dashi&quot; to mean not the above-mentioned soup stock but the very sauce for &quot;udon&quot; (Japanese wheat noodles).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Incidentally, in western Japan it isn&apos;t rare for the Japanese word &quot;dashi&quot; to mean not the above-mentioned soup stock but the very sauce for &quot;udon&quot; (Japanese wheat noodles).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Incidentally, in western Japan it isn&apos;t rare for the Japanese word &apos;dashi&apos; to mean not the above-mentioned soup stock but the very sauce for udon (Japanese wheat noodles).</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>また讃岐うどんで知られる香川県ではつゆの作成のために出汁の成分をそのまま醤油に抽出させただし醤油というものが、よく家庭に置かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And in Kagawa Prefecture known for &quot;Sanuki udon&quot; (&quot;Sanuki&quot; is the old name of the prefecture), many households have their own &quot;dashi-joyu&quot; (the soup stock seeped into soy sauce) which is used for the udon sauce.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Kagawa Prefecture, which is known for &quot;Sanuki udon&quot; (&quot;Sanuki&quot; is the old name of the prefecture), many households have their own &quot;dashi-joyu&quot; (soup stock seeped into soy sauce), which is used as an udon sauce.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Kagawa Prefecture, which is known for Sanuki udon (&quot;Sanuki&quot; is the old name of the prefecture), many households have their own &quot;dashi-joyu&quot; (soup stock seeped into soy sauce), which is used as an udon sauce.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="17">
<j>沖縄料理では、鰹出汁と昆布出汁の他、豚の三枚肉を茹でた茹で汁を濾して豚出汁としてよく用いる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Okinawan cuisine, they often use the soup stock extracted from katsuobushi, konbu &amp; pork, and the pork one is made by straining the boiled pork&apos;s broth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Okinawan cuisine often uses the soup stock extracted from katsuobushi, konbu and pork, and the pork variety is made by straining the broth of boiled pork.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Okinawan cuisine often uses the soup stock extracted from katsuobushi, konbu and pork, and the pork variety is made by straining the broth of boiled pork.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="18">
<j>一番出汁</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Ichiban-dashi&quot; (First brew of soup stock)</e>
<cmt>※&quot;first brew of dashi&quot; の言い回しが下記のホームページに見受けられます。[http://washokufood.blogspot.com/2008/07/dashi.html]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Ichiban-dashi&quot; (first brewing of soup stock)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ichiban-dashi (first brewing of soup stock)</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>ここでは日本料理でよく使われる鰹節の出汁をより詳しく説明する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Here, how to extract the soup stock from katsuobushi is explained in detail, because this one is often used in Japanese cuisine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Here, the method of extracting the soup stock from katsuobushi is explained in detail, because this one is often used in Japanese cuisine.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Here, the method of extracting the soup stock from katsuobushi is explained in detail, because this one is often used in Japanese cuisine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="20">
<j>鰹節で出汁を取る際には、削った鰹節を投入してすぐ火をとめ鰹節が沈むのを待って漉（こ）して取る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To extract the soup stock from katsuobushi, you should put shaved pieces of katsuobushi into a pot&apos;s hot water, and then you should turn off the flame right away, and when the shaved katsuobushi sinks down, you should strain the extract-seeped hot water.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To extract the soup stock from katsuobushi, put shaved pieces of katsuobushi into a pot of hot water and then immediately turn off the flame; when the shaved katsuobushi sinks, strain the extract-seeped hot water.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To extract the soup stock from katsuobushi, put shaved pieces of katsuobushi into a pot of hot water and then immediately turn off the flame; when the shaved katsuobushi sinks, strain the extract-seeped hot water.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>これを一番出汁（いちばんだし）という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This strained soup stock is called &quot;ichiban-dashi.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This strained soup stock is called &quot;ichiban-dashi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This strained soup stock is called &quot;ichiban-dashi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="22">
<j>二番出汁</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Niban-dashi&quot; (Second brew of soup stock)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Niban-dashi&quot; (second brewing of soup stock)</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Niban-dashi (second brewing of soup stock)</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>一番出汁を取った後の鰹節に再び水を入れ、火にかけて取る出汁を二番出汁（にばんだし）という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To get &quot;niban-dashi,&quot; you should pour water on the already-used katsuobushi, and then you should heat the water for some time, and thirdly, you should strain the extract-seeped hot water.</e>
<cmt>※原文の「火にかけて」の後は多少説明が省略されていますので、以下の言葉を補って訳しています。「しばらく熱し、抽出エキスのしみ出した湯を漉して」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To get &quot;niban-dashi,&quot; pour water on the already-used katsuobushi, and then heat the water for some time; finally, strain the extract-seeped hot water.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To get niban-dashi, pour water on the already-used katsuobushi, and then heat the water for some time; finally, strain the extract-seeped hot water.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>一番出汁は澄まし汁、二番出汁は味噌汁や煮物に用いる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ichiban-dashi is used for clear soup, and niban-dashi is used for miso soup (soybean paste-based soup) or for foods boiled in broth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ichiban-dashi is used for clear soup, while niban-dashi is used for miso soup (soybean paste-based soup) or for foods boiled in broth.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ichiban-dashi is used for clear soup, while niban-dashi is used for miso soup (soybean paste-based soup) or for foods boiled in broth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>西洋料理における出汁</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soup stock in Western cuisine</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soup stock in Western cuisine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soup stock in Western cuisine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="25">
<j>西洋料理においては、ウシ・ニワトリ・魚および野菜・香草類などを素材として作る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Western cuisine, the raw materials of soup stock are beef, chicken, fish, vegetables, fragrant herbs and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Western cuisine, the raw materials of soup stock are beef, chicken, fish, vegetables, fragrant herbs and others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Western cuisine, the raw materials of soup stock are beef, chicken, fish, vegetables, fragrant herbs and others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>肉のほか、すじ肉や骨も使い、オーブンでこげ目をつけた上で長時間煮込む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides meat, their fibers &amp; bones are also used, and after being browned with an oven, they are simmered for long hours.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides meat, their fibers and bones are also used, and after being browned in an oven they&apos;re simmered for several hours.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides meat, their fibers and bones are also used, and after being browned in an oven they&apos;re simmered for several hours.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>においを取るためにブーケガルニと呼ばれる香草類のセットを用いる（パセリ、タイム、ローリエ）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To get rid of their smells, a set of fragrant herbs, called &quot;a bouquet garni&quot; (parsley, thyme, and bay-leaf), are used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To eliminate the odor, a set of fragrant herbs, called a &quot;bouquet garni&quot; (parsley, thyme and bay leaf), is used.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To eliminate the odor, a set of fragrant herbs, called a &quot;bouquet garni&quot; (parsley, thyme and bay leaf), is used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>エビやロブスターの料理では、むいた殻で出汁を取ることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When shrimps and lobsters are cooked, their shells are occasionally used as the materials of the soup stock.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When shrimp and lobster are cooked, the shells are occasionally used as materials in the soup stock.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When shrimp and lobster are cooked, the shells are occasionally used as materials in the soup stock.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>ストック(enStock (food))ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are called en Stock.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are referred to as &quot;en stock.&quot;</e>
<cmt>THIS IS NOT AN ACCURATE TERM.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are referred to as &quot;en stock.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="30">
<j>フランス料理では、子牛を素材として使ったものはフォン・ド・ヴォー、仔羊のものはフォン・ダニョー、シカ、イノシシ、ウサギやウズラなど野鳥獣のものはフォン・ド・ジビエ、鶏のものはフォン・ド・ヴォライユ、魚のものはフュメ・ド・ポアソンと呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In French cuisine, the soup stock extracted from veal is called &quot;fond de veau,&quot; that from lamb is called &quot;fond d&apos;agneau,&quot; that from a wild animal&apos;s meat (venison, boar, or rabbit meat) or a wild bird&apos;s meat (such as quail) are called &quot;fond de gibier,&quot; that from chicken is called &quot;fond de volaille,&quot; and that from fish is called &quot;fumet de poisson.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In French cuisine, the soup stock extracted from veal is called &quot;fond de veau,&quot; that from lamb is called &quot;fond d&apos;agneau,&quot; that from game (venison, boar or rabbit) or wildfowl (such as quail) is called &quot;fond de gibier,&quot; that from chicken is called &quot;fond de volaille,&quot; and that from fish is called &quot;fumet de poisson.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In French cuisine, the soup stock extracted from veal is called &quot;fond de veau,&quot; that from lamb is called &quot;fond d&apos;agneau,&quot; that from game (venison, boar or rabbit) or wildfowl (such as quail) is called &quot;fond de gibier,&quot; that from chicken is called &quot;fond de volaille,&quot; and that from fish is called &quot;fumet de poisson.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>中華料理における出汁</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soup stock in Chinese cuisine</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soup stock in Chinese cuisine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soup stock in Chinese cuisine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="31">
<j>中華料理では、鶏肉、鶏がら、豚肉、中国ハム、貝柱、干し海老などが材料としてよく使われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Chinese cuisine, the materials frequently used to extract soup stock are chicken, chicken bones, Chinese ham, scallop, dried shrimps, and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Chinese cuisine, the materials frequently used to extract soup stock are chicken, chicken bones, Chinese ham, scallop, dried shrimp and others.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Chinese cuisine, the materials frequently used to extract soup stock are chicken, chicken bones, pork, Chinese ham, scallop, dried shrimp and others.</e>
<cmt>pork補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>韓国料理・朝鮮料理における出汁</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soup stock in South Korean (or Korean) cuisine</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soup stock in South Korean (or Korean) cuisine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soup stock in South Korean (or Korean) cuisine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="32">
<j>韓国料理においては、牛肉、鶏肉などが材料としてよく使われる他、貝の出汁も用いられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In South Korean cuisine, they frequently use beef &amp; pork as the materials to extract soup stock, and in addition they use the soup stock from shellfish in cooking.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">South Korean cuisine frequently uses beef and pork as the materials for the extraction of soup stock, and additionally they use the soup stock from shellfish in cooking.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">South Korean cuisine frequently uses beef and pork as the materials for the extraction of soup stock, and additionally they use the soup stock from shellfish in cooking.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>簡易的な出汁</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Simple version</e>
<cmt>※&quot;soup stock&quot;という言い回しは液体にのみ当てはまると考えられますので、以下、固形のも包含する意味で使われる「出汁」には、この訳を充てていません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Simple version</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Simple version</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="33">
<j>近年では、上記の方法で出汁を取ることが長時間かかる作業であるという理由から、科学的に旨味成分だけを取り出したものが広まっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the above-mentioned method took much time to extract soup stock, the good taste ingredients in raw materials taken out selectively and scientifically have got popular recently.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because the above-mentioned method of soup-stock extraction took too much time, the good-tasting ingredients in the raw materials have been extracted scientifically and resulted in popular products.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because the above-mentioned method of soup-stock extraction took too much time, the good-tasting ingredients in the raw materials have been extracted scientifically and resulted in popular products.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>大きく分けて2種類あり、液体、固体に分けられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are roughly divided into two types, a liquid one and a solid one.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are roughly divided into two types: a liquid one and a solid one.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are roughly divided into two types: a liquid one and a solid one.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>多くはうま味調味料と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most of them are called &quot;a taste enhancer.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most of them are called &quot;taste enhancers.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most of them are called &quot;taste enhancers.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>液体出汁</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Liquid type</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The liquid type</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The liquid type</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="36">
<j>各種の液状の出汁が、瓶・袋入りで市販されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Various types of liquid soup stock are sold in a bottle or a bag on the market.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Various types of liquid soup stock are sold in bags or bottles.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Various types of liquid soup stock are sold in bags or bottles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>多くは濃縮液となっており、使用時に水を加えて薄める必要がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most of them are concentrated, so they have to be diluted with water when used in cooking.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most of them are concentrated, so they have to be diluted with water when used in cooking.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most of them are concentrated, so they have to be diluted with water when used in cooking.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>うどん・汁物・鍋物用の白だし、煮物用の朱だしなどが市販されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the market, for example, &quot;shirodashi&quot; (white soy sauce with soup stock), which is used for &quot;udon&quot; (Japanese wheat noodles), soup dishes and pot dishes, is sold, and &quot;akadashi&quot; (the soup stock utilizing dark-brown soybean paste), which is used for foods boiled in broth, is also sold.</e>
<cmt>※「白だし」は「白しょうゆに出汁を加えたもの」、「朱だし」は「赤みそを用いた出汁」と訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, &quot;shirodashi&quot; (white soy sauce with soup stock), which is used for &quot;udon&quot; (Japanese wheat noodles), soup dishes and pot dishes, is available in the marketplace, as is &quot;akadashi&quot; (a soup stock utilizing dark-brown soybean paste), which is used for foods boiled in broth.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, shirodashi (white soy sauce with soup stock), which is used for udon (Japanese wheat noodles), soup dishes and pot dishes, is available in the marketplace, as is akadashi (a soup stock utilizing dark-brown soybean paste), which is used for foods boiled in broth.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>固形出汁</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Solid type</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Solid type</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Solid type</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="39">
<j>水分を飛ばして粉末や固形に加工した出汁である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This type is the ingredients processed into powder or solid by draining the raw materials of water.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this type, the ingredients are processed into powder or solid form by draining the water from the raw materials.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this type, the ingredients are processed into powder or solid form by draining the water from the raw materials.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>カツオの旨味成分であるイノシン酸のみを取り出し、食塩を加えて粉末状にしたものなどが有名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A famous example is the inosinic acid (the ingredient of the dried bonito&apos;s good taste) taken out from the raw meterial, which is made into powder with salt combined.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A famous example is the inosinic acid (which gives dried bonito its good taste) taken from the raw material, which is made into powder in combination with salt.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A famous example is the inosinic acid (which gives dried bonito its good taste) taken from the raw material, which is made into powder in combination with salt.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>市販の製品としては味の素の「ほんだし」などのカツオ風味や、鶏がらスープ、ブイヨン、コンソメなどの種類がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the market, various kinds of products are sold, such as katsuobushi-flavored &quot;Hondashi&quot; (manufactured by Ajinomoto Co.,Inc.) and the extracts of chicken bone broth, bouillon, and consomme;</e>
<cmt>※「固形出汁」の話なので、「鶏がらスープ」「ブイヨン」「コンソメ」の3つは全てその「濃縮エキス」(extract)を意味するものとして訳しています。　　　　　　　　　　　　　　※また、「味の素の」はこの3つには係らないものと考えます。次のセルで「味の素は（味の素社の）登録商標である（＝独占使用を認められた商標である）。」とわざわざ説明されている以上、ここでの「鶏がらスープ」等が他社の製品であり、にもかかわらずそれらも「味の素」と呼ばれている、ととらえるのが文章の流れとして論理的だからです。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the marketplace, various kinds of products are sold, such as katsuobushi-flavored &quot;Hondashi&quot; (manufactured by Ajinomoto Co., Inc.) and the extracts of chicken-bone broth, bouillon and consomme;</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the marketplace, various kinds of products are sold, such as katsuobushi-flavored &quot;Hondashi&quot; (manufactured by Ajinomoto Co., Inc.) and the extracts of chicken-bone broth, bouillon and consomme;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>（総称的に『味の素』と呼ばれることが多いが、この名は登録商標である。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">in many cases, all of these products are generally called &quot;Ajinomoto,&quot; but this name is the registered trademark exclusively used by Ajinomoto Co.,Inc;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">in many cases, these products are generally called &quot;Ajinomoto,&quot; but this name is registered trademark exclusively used by Ajinomoto Co., Inc.;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(In many cases, these products are generally called &quot;Ajinomoto,&quot; but this name is registered trademark exclusively used by Ajinomoto Co., Inc.)</e>
<cmt>一文として扱いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>（また、本来の味の素はイノシン酸ではなく、グルタミン酸製剤を調味したものである。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">and originally, &quot;Ajinomoto&quot; means the seasoned formulation of the glutamic acid, not that of the inosinic acid;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">originally, &quot;Ajinomoto&quot; meant the seasoned formulation of glutamic acid, not that of inosinic acid;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Originally, &quot;Ajinomoto&quot; meant the seasoned formulation of glutamic acid, not that of inosinic acid.)</e>
<cmt>一文として扱いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>（但し業務用には純粋なグルタミン酸製剤が中華料理店など向けに提供されている。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">but, for business use, a pure formulation of the glutamic acid is provided for Chinese restaurants and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">however, for business use a pure formulation of glutamic acid is provided for Chinese restaurants and others.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(However, for business use a pure formulation of glutamic acid is provided for Chinese restaurants and others.)</e>
<cmt>一文として扱いました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>出汁パック</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Package for soup stock</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Packaged soup stock</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Packaged soup stock</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="45">
<j>基本的に、上の二つとは製法が異なるが、短時間で出汁を取る為の製品である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Basically, this type of products are different in production method from the above two, but they have the same purpose to extract the soup stock in a short time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Basically, this type of product employs a different production method than the previous two, but they have the same purpose of extracting the soup stock in a short time.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Basically, this type of product employs a different production method than the previous two, but they have the same purpose of extracting the soup stock in a short time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>鰹節、コンブ、魚粉などの材料を紙などのろ過の役割を果たす袋に入れ、熱湯に入れて出汁を取る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Put the material, such as katsuobushi, konbu or a fish meal, into a paper bag or the like that serves as a filter, then pour hot water on it, and you will get soup stock.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Put the material, such as katsuobushi, konbu or a fish meal, into a paper bag or the like that serves as a filter, then pour hot water on it to obtain soup stock.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Put the material, such as katsuobushi, konbu or a fish meal, into a paper bag or the like that serves as a filter, then pour hot water on it to obtain soup stock.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>慣用句として</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As an idiomatic phrase</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As an idiomatic phrase</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As an idiomatic phrase</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="47">
<j>自分の目的や利益のために、他の人やものを利用する・方便にすることを「出汁に使う(出汁にする)」と表現することがあり、食品を用いた慣用句の代表例の一つである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japanese, when a person uses somebody else or something for its own purpose or interest, this behavior can be described as &quot;dashi ni suru,&quot; which literally means, &quot;uses somebody else or something as his (or her) own &apos;dashi&apos; (soup stock),&quot; and this is a typical Japanese idiomatic phrase utilizing a food.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japanese, when a person uses somebody else or something for his own purpose or interest, this behavior can be described as &quot;dashi ni suru,&quot; which literally means, &quot;uses somebody else or something as his (or her) own &apos;dashi&apos; (soup stock),&quot; but this is also a typical Japanese idiomatic phrase in reference to food.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japanese, when a person uses somebody else or something for his own purpose or interest, this behavior can be described as &apos;dashi ni suru,&apos; which literally means, &apos;uses somebody else or something as his (or her) own &apos;dashi&apos; (soup stock),&apos; but this is also a typical Japanese idiomatic phrase in reference to food.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="48">
<j>なお、この慣用句を用いた文章を英語訳するときには、単に “use” の語で置き換えられることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Incidentally, this Japanese idiomatic phrase of &quot;dashi ni suru&quot; can be simply translated into the English word of &quot;use&quot; in many cases.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Incidentally, the Japanese idiomatic phrase of &quot;dashi ni suru&quot; can be simply translated into the English word of &quot;use&quot; in many cases.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Incidentally, the Japanese idiomatic phrase of &quot;dashi ni suru&quot; can be simply translated into the English word of &quot;use&quot; in many cases.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 アレシンロ(id:170344), S.Kiyama(id:9815), Darkicebot(id:272877), Nnh(id:474), 0null0(id:582), YMS(id:243327), Koba-chan(id:860), Roger(id:9883), Kumatora(id:16941), Tantant(id:7195), Yonidebot(id:247998), たぬき(id:27723), 橄欖岩(id:24996), Michey.M(id:906), にほんねこれん(id:186430), Parayan(id:214526), Rei-bot(id:94097), Loveless(id:129239), Point136(id:211299), Nipisiquit(id:62077), Starbacks(id:1018), Carbuncle(id:346), マクガイア(id:33346), Nighthawks(id:36125), Aphaia(id:3132), Baldanders(id:81163), Kiso(id:94763), Nikai(id:1648), Xqbot(id:273540), SuisuiBot(id:10165), 月下美人(id:116398), Nekosuki600(id:21263), Alexbot(id:157199), 営営(id:182402), Tamolist(id:52428), Freetrashbox(id:162354), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>