<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>忘年会</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bonenkai (year-end party)</e>
<cmt>Webの記事は大幅に改訂されています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bonenkai (year-end party)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bonenkai (year-end party)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>忘年会（ぼうねんかい）とは、組織や集団が一年の終わりにその一年間を振り返り、その間の苦労をねぎらい、忘れると共に新たな一年に向けて気持ちを新たにするために行われる年中行事である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bonenkai (literally, a party to forget the year) is an annual event held at the end of a year by an organization or a group to look back the efforts of the year, to reward together and then to forget, also to refresh minds towards the new year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bonenkai (literally, a party to forget the year) is an annual event held at the end of a year by an organization or a group to look back the efforts of the year, to reward together and then to forget, also to refresh minds towards the new year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bonenkai (literally, forget-the-year party) is an annual event held at the end of the year by an organization or group to give those attending a chance to look back at the past year and show their appreciation for the hardships they have each endured, before forgetting the current year and committing themselves to making a fresh start in the upcoming year.</e>
<cmt>一部変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>成人が大半を占める組織や集団では、酒を酌み交わす宴会の形で行われることが多く、居酒屋や宴会場などでは新年会と並んで大きな需要を喚起する契機となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If an organization or a group mainly consists of adults, Bonenkai is held as a party to drink together, therefore, it is a big opportunity along with Shinnenkai (new year party) for izakayas (Japanese-style pub) and party halls.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If an organization or a group mainly consists of adults, Bonenkai is held as a party to drink together, therefore, it is a big opportunity along with Shinnenkai (new year party) for izakayas (Japanese-style pub) and party halls.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If an organization or a group mainly consists of adults, Bonenkai is held as a party to drink together, therefore, it is a big opportunity along with Shinnenkai (new year party) for izakayas (Japanese-style pub) and party halls.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>縁起を担いで望年会と書くこともある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Believing in omens, Kanji 望 (to hope) is used for Bo of Bonenkai in some cases instead of 忘(to forget) as usual.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Believing in omens, Kanji 望 (to hope) is used for Bo of Bonenkai in some cases instead of 忘 (to forget) as usual.</e>
<cmt>忘の後にスペース</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Believing in omens, Kanji 望 (to hope) is used for Bo of Bonenkai in some cases instead of 忘 (to forget) as usual.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>忘年会の歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History of Bonenkai</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History of Bonenkai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History of Bonenkai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>日本の忘年会の歴史は鎌倉時代もしくは室町時代に始まったと言われていて、和歌を詠むなど静かで厳かな内容だったとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the history of Bonenkai of Japan began in Kamakura or Muromachi period and it is thought that behavior of people at Bonenkai was quiet and solemn such as composing waka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the history of Bonenkai of Japan began in the Kamakura or Muromachi period and it is thought that behavior of people at Bonenkai was quiet and solemn such as composing waka poems.</e>
<cmt>Kamakura→the Kamakurawaka→waka poems</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the history of Bonenkai of Japan began in the Kamakura or Muromachi period and it is thought that behavior of people at Bonenkai was quiet and solemn such as composing waka poems.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>江戸時代には、特権階級の人々の中で一年の憂さを晴らす行事になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Within Edo period, it became an event for diversion of privileged class.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Within the Edo period, it became an event for a diversion of the privileged class.</e>
<cmt>Edo-the Edoprivileged→the privilegeddiversion→a diversion</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Edo period, it became an event for venting among the privileged class.</e>
<cmt>Within →Duringfor a diversion of the privileged class→for venting among the privileged class.</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>近代の忘年会がお祭りムードに変化したのは明治時代からで、無礼講などのキャッチフレーズで広まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Meiji period, the mood of Bonenkai changed to be that of a celebrating party as present day, then Bonenkai became popular with a catchphrase like a Bureiko (unrestricted binge).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Meiji period, the mood of Bonenkai changed to be that of a celebrating party as the present day, and then Bonenkai became popular with a catchphrase like a Bureiko (unrestricted binge).</e>
<cmt>In Meiji→During the Meijipresent→the presentthen→and then</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was the Meiji period when the present Bonenkai, a festive event was established; it was widespread with catchphrases such as Bureiko (unrestricted binge).</e>
<cmt>文の構成を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 興味津々ノ助(id:29699), TRIBESMAN(id:4735), ととりん(id:31982), 経済準学士(id:22656), 218-225-118-245(id:14541), Tonync(id:21547), Iwai.masaharu(id:50663), Sketch(id:102), 220.(id:7930), Nkns(id:24876), 弥(id:61590), Chuta(id:10457), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>