<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>篠塚流</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinozuka school (of dance)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinozuka school (of dance)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinozuka school (of dance)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>篠塚流（しのづかりゅう）とは、江戸時代の後期、文化 (元号)・文政期（1804年-1830年）に、歌舞伎上方歌舞伎所作事の振付師・篠塚文三郎によって創設された上方舞最古の流派である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinozuka school is the oldest school of &quot;kamigata-mai dance&quot; established by a Kamigata Kabuki (kabuki of Kyoto and Osaka area) shosagoto (the way of dance) choreographer Bunzaburo SHINOZUKA during Bunka and Bunsei era of the end of Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Shinozuka school is the oldest school of &quot;kamigata-mai dance&quot; established by a Kamigata Kabuki (kabuki of the Kyoto and Osaka area) shosagoto (the way of dance) choreographer Bunzaburo SHINOZUKA during Bunka and Bunsei era at the end of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Shinozuka school is the oldest school of &quot;kamigata-mai dance&quot; established by a Kamigata Kabuki (kabuki of the Kyoto and Osaka area) shosagoto (the way of dance) choreographer Bunzaburo SHINOZUKA during Bunka and Bunsei era (1804-1830) at the end of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>西暦の表記を入れました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>文三郎は、名優といわれ当時絶大な人気があった三代目中村歌右衛門から手腕と力量を認められて梅扇の名を許され、以後は初代家元・篠塚梅扇を名乗る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bunzaburo was recognized his skill and competence by Utaemon NAKAMURA (the 3rd), who was said to be a great actor and enjoyed high popularity at the time, and permitted to use the name Baisen, and after that, he called the 1st Iemoto (the head family of a school) Baisen SHINOZUKA himself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bunzaburo was recognized for his skill and competence by Utaemon NAKAMURA (the third), who was said to be a great actor and enjoyed high popularity at the time, and was permitted to use the name Baisen, and after that, he called the 1st Iemoto (the head family of a school) Baisen SHINOZUKA himself.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bunzaburo was recognized for his skill and competence by Utaemon NAKAMURA (the third), who was said to be a great actor and enjoyed high popularity at the time, and was permitted to use the name Baisen, and after that, he called the 1st Iemoto (the head family of a school) Baisen SHINOZUKA himself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>幕末から明治初期にかけて、この篠塚流の「はんなり」とおおらかな所作が、京の町衆の間で大人気だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the end of Edo period to the early Meiji Era, its generous-hearted way called &quot;hannari&quot; (chic and bright) of this Shinozuka school obtained great popularity among the machi-shu (towns people) in Kyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the end of the Edo period to the early Meiji Era, its generous way called &quot;hannari&quot; (chic and bright) of the Shinozuka school achieved great popularity among the machi-shu (town people) in Kyo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the end of the Edo period to the early Meiji Era, its generous way called &quot;hannari&quot; (chic and bright) of the Shinozuka school achieved great popularity among the machi-shu (town people) in Kyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>三世篠塚梅扇が1886年（明治19年）に死去した後、篠塚流には後継の家元が不在という状態が長く続いたが、多くの門弟によって流風は残された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the death of the Baisen SHINOZUKA (the 3rd) in 1886, though the post of successor Iemoto had long been vacant, many disciples supported the way of the school and it remained.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the death of the Baisen SHINOZUKA (the third) in 1886, though the post for the successor Iemoto had long been vacant, many disciples supported the way of the school and it continued.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the death of the Baisen SHINOZUKA (the third) in 1886, although the post for the successor Iemoto had long been vacant, many disciples supported the way of the school and it continued.</e>
<cmt>&quot;though&quot;→&quot;although&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>しかし1946年（昭和21年）に篠塚流最後の町師匠と言われた水野つる女が死去すると、篠塚流は一時断絶という局面を迎えるにいたった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, after the death of Tsurujo MIZUNO who was said to be the last &quot;machi-shisho (literally, master in town) of the Shinozika school in 1946, the school was temporally discontinued.</e>
<cmt>「水野つる女」の読みが分かりません。Tsurumeかも知れませんが仮に左記の様にしています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, after the death of Tsurujo MIZUNO who was said to be the last &quot;machi-shisho&quot; (literally, master in town) of the Shinozika school in 1946, the school was temporally discontinued.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, after the death of Tsurujo MIZUNO who was said to be the last &quot;machi-shisho&quot; (literally, master in town) of the Shinozuka school in 1946, the school was temporally discontinued.</e>
<cmt>Shinozika→Shinozuka</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="6">
<j>1963年（昭和38年）水野つる女に幼少から師事し、地唄を主とした上方舞を学んでいた内弟子が四世篠塚梅扇を襲名して家元を継承、篠塚流を再興した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1963, an apprentice who learnt &quot;kamigata-mai dance&quot; mainly of jiuta dance under Tsurujo MIZUNO from his childhood succeeded to the professional name of Baisen SHINOZUKA (the 4th) and the Iemoto, and revived Shonozuka school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1963, an apprentice who learnt &quot;kamigata-mai dance&quot; mainly jiuta dancing under Tsurujo MIZUNO from his childhood, succeeded to the professional name of Baisen SHINOZUKA (the fourth) and the Iemoto, and revived the Shonozuka school.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1963, an apprentice who learnt &quot;kamigata-mai dance&quot; mainly jiuta dancing under Tsurujo MIZUNO from his childhood, succeeded to the professional name of Baisen SHINOZUKA (the 4th) and the Iemoto, and revived the Shinozuka school.</e>
<cmt>Shonozuka→Shinozuka</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>同年、小町踊りを復活させ、以後毎年7月10日には一門で祇園祭の神輿洗い神事お迎え提灯に参加している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same year, he revived &apos;komachi odori dance&apos; and later, the entire school participate in &apos;mikoshi arai shinji (Shinto rituals of purifying a portable shrine by water), omukae-chochin (a welcoming paper lantern)&apos; of Gion Festival on July 10, every year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same year, he revived &apos;komachi odori dance&apos; and later, the entire school participated in &apos;mikoshi arai shinji (Shinto rituals to purify a portable shrine using water), omukae-chochin (a welcoming paper lantern)&apos; of Gion Festival on July 10, every year.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same year, he revived &apos;komachi odori dance&apos; and later, the entire school participated in &apos;mikoshi arai shinji (Shinto rituals to purify a portable shrine using water), omukae-chochin (a welcoming paper lantern)&apos; of Gion Festival on July 10, every year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="8">
<j>五世篠塚梅扇は平成4年京都市芸術功労賞を受賞。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Baisen SHINOZUKA (the fifth) was awarded Kyoto-shi geijutsu koro sho (the Award for Distinguished Service to Art by Kyoto City) in 1992.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Baisen SHINOZUKA (the fifth) was awarded Kyoto-shi geijutsu koro sho (the Award for Distinguished Service to Art by Kyoto City) in 1992.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Baisen SHINOZUKA (the fifth) was awarded Kyoto-shi geijutsu koro sho (the Award for Distinguished Service to Art by Kyoto City) in 1992.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>祇園甲部歌舞練場、京都府立芸術会館などで、「京舞篠塚流の会」を開催したり、 重要文化財・芦花浅水荘、京都市指定有形文化財・野口邸、同じく杉本邸などで「座敷で見る京舞」を開催するなど、流派の発展に尽力するかたわら、重文・京都島原角屋で『島原三番艘』を披露するなど文化面での活動にも余念がない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While the school members take place events such as &quot;The gathering of Kyomai Shinozuka school&quot; at Gion Kobu Kaburenjo Theater and Kyoto Prefectural Art Center so on, and &quot;The gathering to appreciate Kyo dance at tatami room&quot; at Important Cultural Property, Rokasensui-sho Manor and A tangible Cultural Asset Designated by Kyoto City, Noguchi-tei Estate and Sugimoto-tei Estate to develop own school, they also devoted themselves to play an active role in the cultural field by showing off classical like &quot;Shimabara san banso (Shimabara 3rd boat)&quot; at Important Cultural Property, Kyoto Shimabara Sumiya.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While school members hold events such as &quot;The gathering of Kyomai Shinozuka school&quot; at Gion Kobu Kaburenjo Theater and Kyoto Prefectural Art Center, etc., and &quot;The gathering to appreciate Kyo dance in a tatami room&quot; as Important Cultural Property, Rokasensui-sho Manor and a Tangible Cultural Asset Designated by Kyoto City, Noguchi-tei Estate and Sugimoto-tei Estate to develop their own school, they also devoted themselves in playing an active role in the cultural field by presenting classical &quot;Shimabara san banso&quot; (Shimabara third boat) as an Important Cultural Property, Kyoto Shimabara Sumiya.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While school members hold events such as &quot;The gathering of Kyomai Shinozuka school&quot; at Gion Kobu Kaburenjo Theater and Kyoto Prefectural Art Center, etc., and &quot;The gathering to appreciate Kyo dance in a tatami room&quot; at Rokasensui-sho Manor (Important Cultural Property) and at Noguchi-tei Estate and Sugimoto-tei Estate (Tangible Cultural Asset Designated by Kyoto City) to develop their own school, they also devoted themselves in playing an active role in the cultural field by presenting classical &quot;Shimabara san banso&quot; (Shimabara third boat) at Kyoto Shimabara Sumiya (Important Cultural Property).</e>
<cmt>場所の表記がわかりにくかったので語順などを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Zuiou 2004(id:13177), Bellcricket(id:37640), Izayohi(id:13095), さららゆら(id:12274), PANYNJ(id:38638), Rghsk06(id:33185), Mop(id:12061), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>