<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>祭</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Feast (a festival)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Matsuri</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Matsuri</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>祭（まつり）もしくは祭り（まつ-り）とは、神霊魂などを祀る儀式や神事のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Japanese term &quot;祭 (feast; pronounced as Matsuri)&quot; or &quot;祭り (festival; pronounced as Matsu-ri)&quot; refers to ceremonies or Shinto rituals worshipping Shinreikon (the spirit of God).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Japanese term &quot;matsuri&quot; (festival, written as 祭 or 祭り) refers to ceremonies or Shinto rituals worshipping Shinreikon (the spirit of God).</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japanese term &quot;matsuri&quot; (festival, written as 祭 or 祭り) refers to ceremonies or Shinto rituals worshipping Shinreikon (the spirit of God).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>祭礼（さいれい）もしくは祭祀（さいし）とも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called Sairei (rites and festivals) or Saishi (religious service).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called Sairei (rites and festivals) or Saishi (religious service).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called Sairei (rites and festivals) or Saishi (religious service).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>また、それに伴う催事を含んで「祭」と呼ぶ場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, events associated with it is also called &apos;Matsuri&apos; (feast or festival) in some cases.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, events associated with it is also called &apos;matsuri&apos; in some cases.</e>
<cmt>前出補足を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, events associated with it is also called &apos;matsuri&apos; in some cases.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>ただし、現在では神霊などを祀る儀式と関わりのない催事を「祭」と呼ぶ場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, events irrelevant to ceremonies worshipping divine spirits and so on are sometimes called &apos;feast or festival&apos; at present.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, events irrelevant to ceremonies worshipping divine spirits and so on are sometimes called &apos;matsuri&apos; at present.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, events irrelevant to ceremonies worshipping divine spirits and so on are sometimes called &apos;matsuri&apos; at present.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>英語圏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">English-speaking sphere</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">English-speaking countries</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">English-speaking countries</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>カーニバル</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Carnival</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Carnival</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Carnival</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>- これは謝肉祭としてその期間に行われる祭りを指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This refers to a festival held as carnival during that period.</e>
<cmt>「。」で終わっていますが、「です」「ます」で終わっていないので、和文に赤字の部分を付け加え、英訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This refers to a festival held as carnival during that period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This refers to a festival held as carnival during that period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>世界各地で様々なスタイルで行われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This festival is held in various styles around the world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This festival is held in various styles around the world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This festival is held in various styles around the world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>フェスティバル</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Festival</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Festival</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Festival</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>- これはその他の宗教的な祭りや商業的な催しものを指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This refers to other religious festivals and commercial events.</e>
<cmt>「。」で終わっていますが、「です」「ます」で終わっていないので、和文に赤字の部分を付け加え、英訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This refers to other religious festivals and commercial events.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This refers to other religious festivals and commercial events.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>伝統的では、ないものも含め世界各地で様々なスタイルで行われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Including untraditional ones, festivals are held in various styles around the world.</e>
<cmt>伝統的では、ないものも含め→including untraditional ones[「伝統的ではないものも含め」と、解釈しました]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Including untraditional ones, festivals are held in various styles around the world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Including untraditional ones, festivals are held in various styles around the world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>観念や日本の語彙としては「催しもの」といったほうが近い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a concept and Japanese vocabulary, the term &apos;event&apos; is close.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a concept and Japanese vocabulary, the term &apos;event&apos; is close.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a concept and Japanese vocabulary, the term &apos;event&apos; is close.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>日本古来の祭は、歴史が長く伝統的であるが、日本の祭について英語で紹介する場合「フェスティバル」が訳語として用いられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese ancient Matsuri has a long history and is traditional, and when Japanese Matsuri is introduced in English, the term &apos;festival&apos; is used as a translated word.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese ancient matsuri has a long history and is traditional, and when Japanese matsuri is introduced in English, the term &apos;festival&apos; is used as a translated word.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese ancient matsuri has a long history and is traditional, and when Japanese matsuri is introduced in English, the term &apos;festival&apos; is used as a translated word.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>日本</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="14">
<j>「まつり」や「まつる」という古語が先であり、その後、漢字の流入により「祭り」・「奉り」・「祀り」・「政り」・「纏り」などの文字が充てられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ancient word, &apos;matsuri&apos; or &apos;matsuru&apos; in Japanese, came first, and thereafter, due to inflow of Chinese characters, characters such as &apos;祭り,&apos; &apos;奉り&apos; (dedication), &apos;祀り&apos; (worship), &apos;政り&apos; (ruling), &apos;纏り&apos; (organizing) and so on were allocated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ancient word, &apos;matsuri&apos; or &apos;matsuru&apos; (both means worship) in Japanese, came first, and thereafter, due to inflow of Chinese characters, characters such as &apos;祭り,&apos; &apos;奉り&apos; (dedication), &apos;祀り&apos; (worship), &apos;政り&apos; (ruling), &apos;纏り&apos; (organizing) and so on were allocated.</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ancient word, &apos;matsuri&apos; or &apos;matsuru&apos; (both means worship) in Japanese, came first, and thereafter, due to inflow of Chinese characters, characters such as &apos;祭り,&apos; &apos;奉り&apos; (dedication), &apos;祀り&apos; (worship), &apos;政り&apos; (ruling), &apos;纏り&apos; (organizing) and so on were allocated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>現在は「祭りと祀り」が同義で「祀りと奉り」が同義ともいわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At present, it is said that the Japanese terms &apos;祭り and 祀り&apos; (worship) have the same meaning, and &apos;祀り and 奉り&apos; (dedication) have the same meaning.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At present, it is said that the Japanese terms &apos;matsuri&apos; (祭り and 祀り, meaning worship) have the same meaning, and &apos;matsuri&apos; (祀り and 奉り, meaning dedication) have the same meaning.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At present, it is said that the Japanese terms &apos;matsuri&apos; (祭り and 祀り, meaning worship) have the same meaning, and &apos;matsuri&apos; (祀り and 奉り, meaning dedication) have the same meaning.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>しかし、漢字の由来とともに意味も分かれているので下記に記す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, since the meanings of these terms were divided in accordance with the origin from Chinese characters, each meaning is described in the following.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, since the meanings of these terms were divided in accordance with the origin from Chinese characters, each meaning is described in the following.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, since the meanings of these terms were divided in accordance with the origin from Chinese characters, each meaning is described in the following.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="17">
<j>「祀り」は、神・尊（みこと）に祈ること、またはその儀式を指すものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Japanese term &apos;祀り&apos; (worship) refers to a prayer for gods and Mikoto (personal god), or its ceremony.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Japanese term &apos;matsuri&apos; (祀り) refers to a prayer for gods and Mikoto (personal god), or its ceremony.</e>
<cmt>前出補足を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japanese term &apos;matsuri&apos; (祀り) refers to a prayer for gods and Mikoto (personal god), or its ceremony.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>これは祀りが、祈りに通じることから神職やそれに順ずる者（福男・福娘や弓矢の矢取り）などが行う「祈祷」や「神との交信の結果としての占い」などどであり、いわゆる「神社神道」の本質としての祀りでもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is because a worship leads to a prayer, and a worship refers to &apos;a prayer&apos; or &apos;fortune-telling as a result of communication with a god&apos; which is conducted by Shinto priesthood or a person subject to it (such as fukuotoko (the luckiest man), fukumusume (Good fortune girls), or arrow picker of Yumiya (bow and arrow)), and is so called a worship as an essence of &apos;Shrine Shinto.&apos;</e>
<cmt>弓矢の矢取り→arrow pickers of Yumiya (bow and arrow)[Wikipedia では、「弓矢の神事の矢取り」と記載されておりますが、本文に即した英訳としました。Wikipedia の表記に変更する場合は、arrow pickers in Shinto rituals of Yumiya (bow and arrow)への変更をお願い致します]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is because a worship leads to a prayer, and a worship refers to &apos;a prayer&apos; or &apos;fortune-telling as a result of communication with a god&apos; which is conducted by Shinto priesthood or a person subject to it (such as fukuotoko [the luckiest man], fukumusume [Good fortune girls], or arrow picker of Yumiya [bow and arrow]), and is so called a worship as an essence of &apos;Shrine Shinto.&apos;</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is because a worship leads to a prayer, and a worship refers to &apos;a prayer&apos; or &apos;fortune-telling as a result of communication with a god&apos; which is conducted by Shinto priesthood or a person subject to it (such as fukuotoko [the luckiest man], fukumusume [Good fortune girls], or arrow picker of Yumiya [bow and arrow]), and is so called a worship as an essence of &apos;Shrine Shinto.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>この祀りは神楽（かぐら）などの巫女の舞や太神楽などの曲芸や獅子舞などであり、広く親しまれるものとして恵比寿講などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This term &quot;worship&quot; refers to Miko no mai (shrine maidens dancing) such as Kagura (sacred music and dancing performed at shrines) and so on, or acrobatics and shishimai (lion dance) such as Daikagura (lion dance) and so on, and as a worship popularized broadly, a festival in honor of Ebisu is named.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This matsuri refers to Miko no mai (shrine maidens dancing) such as Kagura (sacred music and dancing performed at shrines) and so on, or acrobatics and shishimai (lion dance) such as Daikagura (Street performances of a lion dance and jugglery) and so on, and a festival in honor of Ebisu and so on is popularized broadly.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This matsuri refers to Miko no mai (shrine maidens dancing) such as Kagura (sacred music and dancing performed at shrines) and so on, or acrobatics and shishimai (lion dance) such as Daikagura (Street performances of a lion dance and jugglery) and so on, and a festival in honor of Ebisu and so on is popularized broadly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>その起源は古神道などの日本の民間信仰にもあり、古くは神和ぎ（かんなぎ）といい「そこに宿る魂や命が、荒ぶる神にならぬよう」にと祈ることである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It also originated from Japanese folk beliefs such as the Ancient Shinto and so on, and in ancient times, it was called Kannagi referring to praying &apos;so as to prevent spirits or gods dwelling there from becoming violent gods.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It also originated from Japanese folk beliefs such as the Ancient Shinto and so on, and in ancient times, it was called Kannagi referring to prayer &apos;so as to prevent spirits or deity dwelling there from becoming violent gods.&apos;</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It also originated from Japanese folk beliefs such as the Ancient Shinto and so on, and in ancient times, it was called Kannagi referring to prayer &apos;so as to prevent spirits or deity dwelling there from becoming violent gods.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>それらが、道祖神や地蔵や祠や塚や供養塔としての建立や、手を合わせ日々の感謝を祈ることであり、また神社神道の神社にて祈願祈念することも同様である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such praying led to an establishment of Doso-jin (a god who prevents evil spirits from coming), Jizo (guardian deity of children), hokora (a small shrine) or mound as a memorial tower, or to praying for daily kansha (gratitude) with one&apos;s palms together, and it is the same to offer a prayer and make a wish at shrines of Shrine Shinto.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such prayer led to an establishment of Doso-jin (a god who prevents evil spirits from coming), Jizo (guardian deity of children), hokora (a small shrine) or mound as a memorial tower, or to praying for daily gratitude with one&apos;s palms together, and it is the same to offer a prayer and make a wish at shrines of Shrine Shinto.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such prayer led to an establishment of Doso-jin (a god who prevents evil spirits from coming), Jizo (guardian deity of children), hokora (a small shrine) or mound as a memorial tower, or to praying for daily gratitude with one&apos;s palms together, and it is the same to offer a prayer and make a wish at shrines of Shrine Shinto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="22">
<j>「祭り」は命・魂・霊・御霊（みたま）を慰めるもの（慰霊）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Japanese term &apos;祭り&apos; refers to anything (comfort) consoling gods, spirits, souls and departed souls.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Japanese term &apos;matsuri&apos; (祭り) refers to anything consoling deities, spirits, souls and departed souls (comforting the sprit).</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japanese term &apos;matsuri&apos; (祭り) refers to anything consoling deities, spirits, souls and departed souls (comforting the sprit).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>「祭」は漢字の意味において中華文明圏では、葬儀のことであり、現在の日本と中国では祭りは正反対の意味と捉えられているが、慰霊という点に着眼すれば本質的な部分では同じ意味でもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the meaning of Chinese character, the term &apos;祭&apos; refers to a funeral ceremony in the Chinese Civilization bloc, and in present-day Japan, the term &quot;祭り&quot; has a meaning in contradiction to that in China, but, when focusing on the comfort, this term has the same meaning in essentials</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the meaning of Chinese character, the term &apos;matsuri&apos; (祭) refers to a funeral ceremony in the countries which use Chinese characters, and in present-day Japan, the term &apos;matsuri&apos; (祭り) has a meaning in contradiction to that in China, but, when focusing on the comfort, this term has the same meaning in essentials.</e>
<cmt>表記、用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the meaning of Chinese character, the term &apos;matsuri&apos; (祭) refers to a funeral ceremony in the countries which use Chinese characters, and in present-day Japan, the term &apos;matsuri&apos; (祭り) has a meaning in contradiction to that in China, but, when focusing on the comfort, this term has the same meaning in essentials.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>古神道の本質の一つでもある先祖崇拝が、仏教と習合（神仏習合）して現在に伝わるものとして、お盆（純粋な仏教行事としては釈迦を奉る盂蘭盆があり、同時期におこなわれる）があり、辞書の説明では先祖崇拝の祭りと記載されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As an ancestor worship, one of the essences of Ancient Shinto, which is passed down to the present day through syncretization with Buddhism (syncretization of Shinto with Buddhism), the Obon festival (a Festival of the Dead or Buddhist All Souls&apos; Day) is named (as a pure Buddhist event, the Urabon festival (a Festival of the Dead or Buddhist All Souls&apos; day, around the 15th of July or August, depending on local customs) worshiping the Buddha is held in the same period), and a dictionary explains that it is a festival for ancestor worship.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As an ancestor worship, one of the essences of Ancient Shinto, which is passed down to the present day through syncretization with Buddhism (syncretization of Shinto with Buddhism), the Obon festival (a Festival of the Dead or Buddhist All Souls&apos; Day) is named (as a pure Buddhist event, the Urabon festival [a Festival of the Dead or Buddhist All Souls&apos; day] worshiping the Buddha is held in the same period), and a dictionary explains that it is a festival for ancestor worship.</e>
<cmt>用語補足を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As an ancestor worship, one of the essences of Ancient Shinto, which is passed down to the present day through syncretization with Buddhism (syncretization of Shinto with Buddhism), the Obon festival (a Festival of the Dead or Buddhist All Souls&apos; Day) is named (as a pure Buddhist event, the Urabon festival [a Festival of the Dead or Buddhist All Souls&apos; day] worshiping the Buddha is held in the same period), and a dictionary explains that it is a festival for ancestor worship.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>鯨祭りといわれる祭りが、日本各地の津々浦々で行われているが、それらは、鯨突き（捕鯨）によって命を落としたクジラを慰霊するための祭りである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Festivals called whaling culture are held all over Japan in order to comfort whales dying by whale piking (whaling).</e>
<cmt>捕鯨文化といわれる祭り→festivals called whaling culture[Wikipedia では、「鯨祭りといわれる祭り」と記載されておりますが、本文に即した英訳としました。Wikipedia の表記に変更する場合は、festivals called whale festival への変更をお願い致します]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Matsuri called whaling festival are held all over Japan in order to comfort whales dying by whale piking (whaling).</e>
<cmt>リンク文字列が含まれていたため、原文・訳文共に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Matsuri called whaling festival are held all over Japan in order to comfort whales dying by whale piking (whaling).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="26">
<j>「奉り」は、奉る（たてまつる）とも読み。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Japanese term &apos;奉り&apos; is also pronounced as tatematsuru in Japanese.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Japanese term &apos;matsuri&apos; (奉り) is also pronounced as tatematsuru in Japanese.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japanese term &apos;matsuri&apos; (奉り) is also pronounced as tatematsuru in Japanese.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>献上や召し上げる・上に見るなどの意味もあり、一般的な捉え方として、日本神話の人格神（人の肖像と人と同じような心を持つ日本創世の神々）や朝廷や公家に対する行為をさす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This term also means presentation, to present, to respect and so on, and generally refers to acts conducted to humanized divinities (deities created in Japan which had human portraits and humane minds) in the Japanese Mythology, the Imperial Court and Court nobles.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This term also means presentation, to present, to respect and so on, and generally refers to acts conducted to humanized divinities (deities created in Japan which had human portraits and humane minds) in the Japanese Mythology, the Imperial Court and Court nobles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This term also means presentation, to present, to respect and so on, and generally refers to acts conducted to humanized divinities (deities created in Japan which had human portraits and humane minds) in the Japanese Mythology, the Imperial Court and Court nobles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>これは、神社神道の賽神の多くが人格神でもあるが、皇室神道に本質がある「尊（みこと）」に対する謙譲の精神を内包した「まつり」である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This means that it is a &apos;festival&apos; containing a spirit of modesty for &apos;Mikoto&apos; whose essence existed in the Imperial Household Shinto although many of Sai no kami in the Shrine Shinto were humanized divinities.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This means that it is &apos;a matsuri&apos; containing a spirit of modesty for &apos;Mikoto&apos; whose essence existed in the Imperial Household Shinto although many of Sai no kami (guardian deity) in the Shrine Shinto were humanized divinities.</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This means that it is &apos;a matsuri&apos; containing a spirit of modesty for &apos;Mikoto&apos; whose essence existed in the Imperial Household Shinto although many of Sai no kami (guardian deity) in the Shrine Shinto were humanized divinities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>その起源は、自然崇拝である古神道にまで遡り、日本神話の海幸彦と山幸彦にあるように釣針（古くは銛も釣針も一つの概念であった）や弓矢は、幸（さち）といい神に供物（海の幸山の幸）を「奉げる」神聖な漁り（いさり）・狩り（かり）の得物（えもの・道具や神聖な武器）であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its origin goes back to the Ancient Shinto worshipping the nature, and as described in Umisachihiko and Yamasachihiko of the Japanese Mythology, fish hooks (grains and fish hooks were categorized in the same concept in ancient times) and Yumiya were called Sachi which referred to sacred things obtained by fishing and hunting (catches, tools and sacred weapons) &apos;presented&apos; to a deity as altarage (seafood and mountain vegetables).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its origin goes back to the Ancient Shinto worshipping the nature, and as described in Umisachihiko and Yamasachihiko of the Japanese Mythology, fish hooks (grains and fish hooks were categorized in the same concept in ancient times), bow and arrows were called Sachi which referred to sacred things obtained by fishing and hunting (catches, tools and sacred weapons) &apos;offered&apos; to a deity as altarage (seafood and mountain vegetables).</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its origin goes back to the Ancient Shinto worshipping the nature, and as described in Umisachihiko and Yamasachihiko of the Japanese Mythology, fish hooks (grains and fish hooks were categorized in the same concept in ancient times), bow and arrows were called Sachi which referred to sacred things obtained by fishing and hunting (catches, tools and sacred weapons) &apos;offered&apos; to a deity as altarage (seafood and mountain vegetables).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>古くから漁師や猟師は、獲物（えもの）を獲る（える）と神々の取り分として、大地や海にその収穫の一部を還した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From ancient times, fishermen and hunters returned part of their catches to the land and the sea as a quota of deities when they obtained catches.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From ancient times, fishermen and hunters returned part of their catches to the land and the sea as a quota of deities when they obtained catches.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From ancient times, fishermen and hunters returned part of their catches to the land and the sea as a quota of deities when they obtained catches.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>このような行いは、漁師や猟師だけに限らず、その他の農林水産に係わる生業（なりわい）から、現在の醸造や酒造など職業としての神事や、各地域の「おまつり」にもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This kind of act was taken not only by fishermen and hunters, and existed in the Shinto rituals as a vocation such as present-day brewing and sake brewing due to other regular vocations relating to agriculture, forestry and fishery, and also in &apos;Omatsuri&apos; (festival) in every region.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Not only fishermen and hunters, but also those who make a living from agriculture, forestry, or fishery, as well as those engaged in present-day &quot;sacred callings&quot; such as the brewing of sake or soy products such as soy sauce return part of their &quot;catch&quot; at the &apos;Omatsuri&apos; (festivals) held in each of Japan&apos;s regions.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせて訳文を修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Not only fishermen and hunters, but also those who make a living from agriculture, forestry, or fishery, as well as those engaged in present-day &quot;sacred callings&quot; such as the brewing of sake or soy products such as soy sauce return part of their &quot;catch&quot; at the &apos;Omatsuri&apos; (festivals) held in each of Japan&apos;s regions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>地鎮祭や上棟式でも御神酒（おみき）や御米（おこめ）が大地に還される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Jichinsai (ground-breaking ceremony) and Jotoshiki (the roof-raying ceremony), omiki (sacred wine or sake) or okome (sacred rice) is also returned to the ground.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Jichinsai (ground-breaking ceremony) and Jotoshiki (the roof-raying ceremony), omiki (sacred wine or sake) or okome (sacred rice) is also returned to the ground.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Jichinsai (ground-breaking ceremony) and Jotoshiki (the roof-raying ceremony), omiki (sacred wine or sake) or okome (sacred rice) is also returned to the ground.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="33">
<j>「政り」については、日本は古代からの信仰や社会である、いわゆる古神道おいて、祭祀を司る者（まつり）と政治を司る者（まつり）は、同じ意味であり、この二つの「まつり」が一致した祭政一致といわれるものであったため、政治のことを政（まつりごと）とも呼んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Japanese term &apos;政り&apos; (pronounced as matsuri in Japanese) referred to a person in charge of religious service (matsuri in Japanese) and person in charge of politics (matsuri in Japanese), and which were taken as the same meaning in the ancient beliefs and society in Japan, so-called Ancient Shinto, and since a unity of these two &apos;matsuri&apos; was called saisei icchi (unity of church and state, theocracy), politics was also called 政 (pronounced as matsurigoto in Japanese, which means ruling).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the beliefs of ancient Japanese society, which followed what is known as &quot;ancient Shinto,&quot; someone who conducted religious services (&quot;matsuri&quot; in Japanese) was essentially the same as someone who was engaged in politics (also &quot;matsuri&quot; in Japanese); this was a case of what is called saisei itchi (the unity of shrine, temple and state; in other words, theocracy), and this led to politics occasionally being called matsurigoto (a word that can be used to refer both to government and worship) in Japan.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせて訳文を修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the beliefs of ancient Japanese society, which followed what is known as &quot;ancient Shinto,&quot; someone who conducted religious services (&quot;matsuri&quot; in Japanese) was essentially the same as someone who was engaged in politics (also &quot;matsuri&quot; in Japanese); this was a case of what is called saisei itchi (the unity of shrine, temple and state; in other words, theocracy), and this led to politics occasionally being called matsurigoto (a word that can be used to refer both to government and worship) in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>古くは卑弥呼なども祭礼を司る巫女や祈祷師であり、祈祷や占いによって執政したといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that in the ancient times, Himiko who was also a shrine maiden or shaman in charge of rites and festivals controlled the administration by prayer or fortune-telling.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that in the ancient times, Himiko who was also a shrine maiden or shaman conducting rites and festivals controlled the administration by prayer or fortune-telling.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that in the ancient times, Himiko who was also a shrine maiden or shaman conducting rites and festivals controlled the administration by prayer or fortune-telling.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>平安時代には神職が道教の陰陽五行思想を取り込み陰陽道と陰陽師という思想と役職を得て官僚として大きな勢力を持ち執政した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Heian period, the Shinto priesthood, who adopted Inyo [Onmyo] gogyo shiso (Yin-Yang Wu-Zing Idea) of Taoism and obtained ideas of Onmyodo (way of Yin and Yang; occult divination system based on the Taoist theory of five elements) and Onmyoji (Master of Ying yang), controlled the administration with a strong power as a bureaucrat.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Heian period, the Shinto priesthood, who adopted Inyo (also referred as Onmyo) gogyo shiso (Yin-Yang Wu-Zing Idea) of Taoism and obtained the idea of Onmyodo (way of Yin and Yang; occult divination system based on the Taoist theory of five elements) and the position of Onmyoji (Master of Ying yang), controlled the administration with a strong power as a bureaucrat.</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Heian period, the Shinto priesthood, who adopted Inyo (also referred as Onmyo) gogyo shiso (Yin-Yang Wu-Zing Idea) of Taoism and obtained the idea of Onmyodo (way of Yin and Yang; occult divination system based on the Taoist theory of five elements) and the position of Onmyoji (Master of Ying yang), controlled the administration with a strong power as a bureaucrat.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>またこうした政と祭りに一致は中央政府に限らず、地方や町や集落でも、その年の吉凶を占う祭りや、普請としての祭りが行われ、「自治としての政」に対し資金調達や、吉凶の結果による社会基盤の実施の時期の決定や執政の指針とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such unity of politics and religion was not limited to the central government, and in the provinces, towns and villages, festivals reading good omens or bad of the year, or festivals as fushin (group activities by a community) were also held, in which funds for &apos;matsurigoto as an autonomy&apos; were raised and the time to implement infrastructures was decided in accordance with the result of fortune, and which played a role of guidelines for administration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such unity of politics and religion was not limited to the central government, however; in the provinces, towns and villages of Japan, festivals were held to determine whether the area in question could expect to enjoy good fortune or to conduct construction work so as to raise funds for &apos;autonomous matsurigoto&apos; and, based on the results of the fortune telling, to determine when to start social infrastructure work and provide guidance for the administration.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせて訳文を修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such unity of politics and religion was not limited to the central government, however; in the provinces, towns and villages of Japan, festivals were held to determine whether the area in question could expect to enjoy good fortune or to conduct construction work so as to raise funds for &apos;autonomous matsurigoto&apos; and, based on the results of the fortune telling, to determine when to start social infrastructure work and provide guidance for the administration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>祭の曖昧さと現在</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ambiguity of feast (festival), and present-day feast</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ambiguity of matsuri (祭), and present</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ambiguity of matsuri (祭), and present</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="37">
<j>祭りは古神道に由来するものが多く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many festivals originated from the Ancient Shinto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many matsuri (祭り) originated from the Ancient Shinto.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many matsuri (祭り) originated from the Ancient Shinto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>原始宗教やシャーマニズム・アニミズムなどと呼ばれ、その信仰の対象は森羅万象に及ぶため、その行為でもある祭りを定義付けることは困難である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since it was called a primitive religion, shamanism, animism and so on, and the target of its belief extended to shinrabansho (all things in nature), it is difficult to define a festival which is also the action.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since it was called a primitive religion, shamanism, animism and so on, and the target of its belief extended to shinrabansho (all things in nature), it is difficult to define matsuri which is also the action.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since it was called a primitive religion, shamanism, animism and so on, and the target of its belief extended to shinrabansho (all things in nature), it is difficult to define matsuri which is also the action.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>また、神（客神や九十九神などいろいろ）・尊・魂・命・霊御・霊を定義したり分け隔てることなく享受してきたのも日本の文化の本質でもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was also the essence of Japanese culture to enjoy deities (many deities such as guest deities, divine spirit that resided in an extremely old tool or creature and so on), Mikoto, spirit, departed soul and soul without defining or discriminating against them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was also the essence of Japanese culture to enjoy gods (many deities such as guest deities, Tsukumogami [divine spirit that resided in an extremely old tool or creature], and so on), Mikoto, spirit, deities, departed soul and soul without defining or discriminating against them.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ。補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was also the essence of Japanese culture to enjoy gods (many deities such as guest deities, Tsukumogami [divine spirit that resided in an extremely old tool or creature], and so on), Mikoto, spirit, deities, departed soul and soul without defining or discriminating against them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="40">
<j>例えば大相撲も本来は皇室神道としての奉納の祭りであり、神事でもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, a grand sumo tournament was originally a festival for dedication as the Imperial Household Shinto, and was also the Shinto ritual.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, a grand sumo tournament was originally a matsuri for dedication as the Imperial Household Shinto, and was also the Shinto ritual.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, a grand sumo tournament was originally a matsuri for dedication as the Imperial Household Shinto, and was also the Shinto ritual.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>しかし、宗教への関心の薄れなどから、大相撲のように「神事や祭礼としての祭りである」ことが忘れられたり、祭祀に伴う賑やかな行事の方のみについて「祭」と認識される場合もあり、元から祭祀と関係なく行われる賑やかな催事、イベントについて「祭」と呼ばれることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, due to lessened interest in the religion, &apos;being a festival as a Shinto ritual or rite and festival&apos; is sometimes forgotten like a grand sumo tournament, and only cheerful events associated with rites and festivals are sometimes recognized as &apos;feast,&apos; and therefore, cheerful events which were originally held independently of rites and festivals were called &apos;feast&apos; in some cases.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, due to lessened interest in the religion, &apos;being a matsuri as a Shinto ritual or rite and festival&apos; is sometimes forgotten like a grand sumo tournament, and only cheerful events associated with rites and festivals are sometimes recognized as &apos;matsuri,&apos; and therefore, cheerful events which were originally held independently of rites and festivals were called &apos;matsuri&apos; in some cases.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, due to lessened interest in the religion, &apos;being a matsuri as a Shinto ritual or rite and festival&apos; is sometimes forgotten like a grand sumo tournament, and only cheerful events associated with rites and festivals are sometimes recognized as &apos;matsuri,&apos; and therefore, cheerful events which were originally held independently of rites and festivals were called &apos;matsuri&apos; in some cases.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>また、個人がそういった儀式に参加することも「まつり」であり、現在でも地鎮祭、ひな祭りや節分などの招福祈願がそれにあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The participation of individuals in such ceremonies was called &apos;festival,&apos; and a prayer for good luck charm such as Jichinsai, Doll&apos;s Festival, Setsubun (the traditional end of winter) and so on is equivalent to it even now.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The participation of individuals in such ceremonies was called &apos;festival,&apos; and a prayer for good luck charm such as Jichinsai, Doll&apos;s Festival, Setsubun (the traditional end of winter) and so on is equivalent to it even now.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The participation of individuals in such ceremonies was called &apos;festival,&apos; and a prayer for good luck charm such as Jichinsai, Doll&apos;s Festival, Setsubun (the traditional end of winter) and so on is equivalent to it even now.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>また、祭祀の際には、神霊に対して供物や行為等、様々なものが奉げられ、儀式が行われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the time of rites and festivals are held, various things including altarage, acts and so on were presented to the divine spirit, and a ceremony was held.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the time of rites and festivals are held, various things including altarage, acts and so on were presented to the divine spirit, and a ceremony was held.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the time of rites and festivals are held, various things including altarage, acts and so on were presented to the divine spirit, and a ceremony was held.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>その規模が大きく、地域を挙げて行われているような行事の全体を指して「祭」と呼ぶこともある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its scale was big, and the whole of event held across the region is sometimes called &apos;feast.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its scale was big, and the whole of event held across the region is sometimes called &apos;matsuri.&apos;</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its scale was big, and the whole of event held across the region is sometimes called &apos;matsuri.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="45">
<j>祭りの固有名称のあり方</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Desired form of specific name of festival</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Desired form of specific name of matsuri</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Desired form of specific name of matsuri</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="46">
<j>「祭」は様々な種類のものが各地で行われているため、ある地域で祭と言っても、どこのどの祭を指しているのか判断しにくい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since various kinds of &apos;feasts&apos; are held in various regions, it is difficult to tell that a feast in some region indicates which one in which region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since various kinds of &apos;matsuri&apos; are held in various regions, it is difficult to tell that a matsuri in some region indicates which one in which region.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since various kinds of &apos;matsuri&apos; are held in various regions, it is difficult to tell that a matsuri in some region indicates which one in which region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>このような場合、その祭が行われる地域名と、祭礼の行事の内容や、出し物の名前を指す名称を、組み合わせた名前で呼ばれることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this case, the feast is often called by combining the name of region where the feast is held, details of event held in the rite and festival, and name of attraction.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this case, the matsuri is often called by combining the name of region where the matsuri is held, details of event held in the rite and festival, and name of attraction.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this case, the matsuri is often called by combining the name of region where the matsuri is held, details of event held in the rite and festival, and name of attraction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>ただし、その祭の行われる地域の中では、正式な名称を短略化して呼ぶことも多く、時としては、行われる寺社などの名称に「（お）○○さん」または「（お）○○様」などの敬称・愛称をつけ、簡略化した祭りの通り名もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in some region where the feast is held, the feast is called by abbreviating its official name, and a simplified common name is sometimes used by attaching an honorary term or term of endearment such as &apos;(O) O san&apos; or &apos;(O) O sama&apos; to the name of temple or shrine where the feast is held.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in some region where the matsuri is held, it is called by abbreviating its official name, and a simplified common name is sometimes used by attaching an honorary term or term of endearment such as &apos;XX san&apos; (also referred as O-XX san) or &apos;XX sama&apos; (also referred as O-XX sama) to the name of temple or shrine where the matsuri is held.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in some region where the matsuri is held, it is called by abbreviating its official name, and a simplified common name is sometimes used by attaching an honorary term or term of endearment such as &apos;XX san&apos; (also referred as O-XX san) or &apos;XX sama&apos; (also referred as O-XX sama) to the name of temple or shrine where the matsuri is held.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>その他の意味</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other meanings</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other meanings</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other meanings</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>魚釣り</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fishing</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fishing</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fishing</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="49">
<j>隣り合った釣り人の、仕掛け、糸などが絡まることをお祭りという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is called Festival that own device or string tangles with that of neighboring angler.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omatsuri means to get your fishing line tangled with that of an angler near to you.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。原文に合わせて訳文を修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omatsuri means to get your fishing line tangled with that of an angler near to you.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>他人の糸、仕掛けに関係なく自分自身の糸、仕掛けがからまってしまう事を手前祭りという</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is called Temaematsuri (get tangled by oneself) that own string or device tangles each other independently of string and device of other people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Temaematsuri, however, means to get your fishing line tangled with itself, not with that of another angler.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせて訳文を修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Temaematsuri, however, means to get your fishing line tangled with itself, not with that of another angler.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>子作り・子宝</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Having babies</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Having babies</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Having babies</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="51">
<j>男女が性交を指す例え。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is an analogy referring to a sex between a man and woman.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is an analogy referring to a sexual activity between a man and woman.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is an analogy referring to a sexual activity between a man and woman.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>江戸時代の浄瑠璃の一節や柳樽（やなぎだると読み、柳多留とも表記する）という雑俳（巷から集めた俳句）の書籍のなかに「祭り」を男女の性行為の例えとして用いている表現がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was an expression likening a sex between a man and woman to a &apos;festival&apos; in one phrase of Joruri (dramatic narrative chanted to a samisen accompaniment) and in a book of playful literature originating from haiku (haiku collected in the streets) called yanagidaru (box-shaped, lacquered liquor cask) (written as 柳樽 and also as 柳多留 in Chinese characters) in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was expressions likening a sexual activity between a man and woman to &apos;matsuri&apos; in a phrase of Joruri (dramatic narrative chanted to a shamisen accompaniment) and in a book of zappai (playful literature originating from haiku [a Japanese poem in seventeen syllables having a 5-7-5 syllabic form and traditionally containing a reference to the seasons]) (haiku collected in the streets) called yanagidaru (box-shaped, lacquered liquor cask) (written as 柳樽 and also as 柳多留 in Chinese characters) in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was expressions likening a sexual activity between a man and woman to &apos;matsuri&apos; in a phrase of Joruri (dramatic narrative chanted to a shamisen accompaniment) and in a book of zappai (playful literature originating from haiku [a Japanese poem in seventeen syllables having a 5-7-5 syllabic form and traditionally containing a reference to the seasons]) (haiku collected in the streets) called yanagidaru (box-shaped, lacquered liquor cask) (written as 柳樽 and also as 柳多留 in Chinese characters) in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>また古神道においては、子宝・子作り信仰と言われるものがあり、子作りは、新しい氏子の誕生の場であるところから、性行為を「祭り」と言うようになったともいわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ancient Shinto also had a belief called having babies belief, and it is said that the sexual activity came to be called &apos;festival&apos; because having babies was an occasion of birth of new ujiko (shrine parishioner).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ancient Shinto also had a belief called having babies belief, and it is said that the sexual activity came to be called &apos;matsuri&apos; because having babies was an occasion of birth of new ujiko (shrine parishioner).</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ancient Shinto also had a belief called having babies belief, and it is said that the sexual activity came to be called &apos;matsuri&apos; because having babies was an occasion of birth of new ujiko (shrine parishioner).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>古神道には、常世（とこよ）と現世（うつしよ）という世界観があり、常世は神域や神の国をあらわす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ancient Shinto had a vision of world, Tokoyo (written as 常世 in Chinese characters, which means heaven) and Utsushiyo (the actual world), and Tokoyo referred to a sacred area or the kingdom of God.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ancient Shinto had a vision of world, Tokoyo (written as 常世 in Chinese characters, which means heaven) and Utsushiyo (the actual world), and Tokoyo referred to a sacred area or the kingdom of God.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ancient Shinto had a vision of world, Tokoyo (written as 常世 in Chinese characters, which means heaven) and Utsushiyo (the actual world), and Tokoyo referred to a sacred area or the kingdom of God.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>一説には常世は床世（床は性行為の意味もある）であり、性行為は神域で行われる（若しくは神域へ誘う）神聖なものとする考え方がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to one theory, the idea was that Tokoyo referred to tokoyo (written as 床世 in Chinese characters; 床 also means sexual activities), and the sexual activity was a sacred one conducted in the sacred area (or inviting people to the sacred area).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to one theory, the idea was that Tokoyo referred to tokoyo (written as 床世 in Chinese characters; 床 also means sexual activities), and the sexual activity was a sacred one conducted in the sacred area (or inviting people to the sacred area).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to one theory, the idea was that Tokoyo referred to tokoyo (written as 床世 in Chinese characters; 床 also means sexual activities), and the sexual activity was a sacred one conducted in the sacred area (or inviting people to the sacred area).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>お祭り騒ぎ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Festivity</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omatsuri Sawagi</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omatsuri Sawagi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="56">
<j>祭の賑やかな様子から、「お祭り騒ぎ」という慣用句が生まれ、何かが賑やかな状態や、喧騒や喧々諤々などの状態になっているのを例えてた態様表現がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A common expression, &apos;festivity,&apos; was generated from a cheerful atmosphere of feast, and there is a word describing a situation by likening a state that something is cheerful, or a state of hustle and bustle, kenkengakugaku (clamorous censure) and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A idiom, &apos;omatsuri sawagi&apos; (festivity), generated from a cheerful atmosphere of festival, is an expression of the states something cheerful, or hustle and bustle, kenkengakugaku (clamorous censure) and so on.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A idiom, &apos;omatsuri sawagi&apos; (festivity), generated from a cheerful atmosphere of festival, is an expression of the states something cheerful, or hustle and bustle, kenkengakugaku (clamorous censure) and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>以下はその派生である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following are its derivatives.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following are its derivatives.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following are its derivatives.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="58">
<j>インターネットスラングの「祭り」は一部の電子掲示板で、特定のスレッドが異常な盛り上がりを見せ、流れが通常よりも速くなっている状態を（お）祭りという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term &apos;festival&apos; used as an Internet slang refers to a situation that a certain thread is extraordinarily sensational in some electronic bulletin board, and a flow is faster than usual.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term &apos;matsuri&apos; (also referred as omatsuri) used as an Internet slang refers to a situation that a certain thread is extraordinarily sensational in some electronic bulletin board, and a flow is faster than usual.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term &apos;matsuri&apos; (also referred as omatsuri) used as an Internet slang refers to a situation that a certain thread is extraordinarily sensational in some electronic bulletin board, and a flow is faster than usual.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>その他のインターネットスラングとしての「祭り」はブログ炎上 (ネット用語)といわれるものがあり、特定の団体や個人による不祥事や不穏当発言などに対する、中傷や非難や批判が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term &apos;festival&apos; as an Internet slang has another meaning of blog flaming (terminology of the Internet), and calumniation, crimination and criticism are often given to scandals and improper words by a certain organization or individual.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term &apos;matsuri&apos; as an Internet slang has another meaning of blog flaming (terminology of the Internet), and calumniation, crimination and criticism are often given to scandals and improper words by a certain organization or individual.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term &apos;matsuri&apos; as an Internet slang has another meaning of blog flaming (terminology of the Internet), and calumniation, crimination and criticism are often given to scandals and improper words by a certain organization or individual.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>これは、ネットいじめ（祭り上げられる）といった悪意の迷惑行為、または社会に対する不安や批判などの発露であり、それに呼応したり尻馬に乗るなどの野次馬や、一過言を持つ人々がインターネット上の様々な場所で、意見や議論を拡散・増大させ、いわゆるネット上の「祭り」といわれる状態に更になっていく様をいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is an act of malicious nuisance called Internet bulling (to be picked on), or an exposure of uncertainty over or criticism of the society, and also refers to a situation that an expansion and enlargement of opinions or discussions conducted in various Internet sites by routs who act in concert with it or follow it blindly, or people having own opinions, develop to the state called so-called &apos;festival&apos; on the Internet.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is an act of malicious nuisance called Internet bulling (to be picked on), or an exposure of uncertainty over or criticism of the society, and also refers to a situation that an expansion and enlargement of opinions or discussions conducted in various Internet sites by routs who act in concert with it or follow it blindly, or people having own opinions, develop to the state called so-called &apos;matsuri&apos; on the Internet.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is an act of malicious nuisance called Internet bulling (to be picked on), or an exposure of uncertainty over or criticism of the society, and also refers to a situation that an expansion and enlargement of opinions or discussions conducted in various Internet sites by routs who act in concert with it or follow it blindly, or people having own opinions, develop to the state called so-called &apos;matsuri&apos; on the Internet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>祭の形態</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Form of feast</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Form of matsuri</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Form of matsuri</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>原初的形態</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Primitive form</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Primitive form</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Primitive form</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="61">
<j>祭礼の形は世界各地で多様な形を示すが、原初の祭は一つの信仰に基づいていたと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rites and festivals are held in various forms across the world, but, a primitive festival is considered to have been based on one belief.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rites and festivals are held in various forms across the world, but, a primitive matsuri is considered to have been based on one belief.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rites and festivals are held in various forms across the world, but, a primitive matsuri is considered to have been based on one belief.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>すなわち豊穣への感謝・祈りでありジェームズ・フレイザーの『金枝篇』で生命の死と再生の神を通して考察された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">More specifically, it was a gratitude or prayer for productiveness, and it was analyzed through a god for death and regeneration of life in &quot;Kinshihen&quot; (The Golden Bough) (A Study in Magic and Religion: wide-ranging, comparative study of mythology and religion) written by James Frazer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">More specifically, it was a gratitude or prayer for productiveness, and it was analyzed through a god for death and regeneration of life in &quot;Kinshihen&quot; (The Golden Bough) (A Study in Magic and Religion: Wide-ranging, comparative study of mythology and religion) written by James Frazer.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">More specifically, it was a gratitude or prayer for productiveness, and it was analyzed through a god for death and regeneration of life in &quot;Kinshihen&quot; (The Golden Bough) (A Study in Magic and Religion: Wide-ranging, comparative study of mythology and religion) written by James Frazer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>農耕社会においては収穫祭が古いものであるが他にも祭壇に動物の生贄を捧げる形式がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In an agrarian society, a harvest festival was an old one, but there were other festivals in the form of presenting animal sacrifices at the altar.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In an agrarian society, a harvest festival was an old one, but there were other festivals in the form of presenting animal sacrifices at the altar.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In an agrarian society, a harvest festival was an old one, but there were other festivals in the form of presenting animal sacrifices at the altar.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>ともに命によって豊穣を得られる信仰が窺える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The above festivals showed beliefs through which the productivity were obtainable by a life.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The above festivals showed beliefs through which the productivity were obtainable by a life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The above festivals showed beliefs through which the productivity were obtainable by a life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>『金枝篇』に載せられている例でいえばヨーロッパのキリスト教以前の色を濃く留めている風習の一つで、収穫した穀物を使い人形状のパンまたはクッキー（人体の象徴）を作り、分割する祭礼がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to an example stated in &quot;Kinshihen,&quot; there was a festival of making human-shaped bread or cookie (symbol of human body) using harvested cereals, and of dividing it, as one of very religious European customs before the Christianity.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to an example stated in &quot;Kinshihen,&quot; there was a festival of making human-shaped bread or cookie (symbol of human body) using harvested cereals, and of dividing it, as one of very religious European customs before the Christianity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to an example stated in &quot;Kinshihen,&quot; there was a festival of making human-shaped bread or cookie (symbol of human body) using harvested cereals, and of dividing it, as one of very religious European customs before the Christianity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>この聖餐との類似が指摘できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It can be pointed out that this was similar to the Eucharist.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It can be pointed out that this was similar to the Eucharist.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It can be pointed out that this was similar to the Eucharist.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>キリスト教・仏教などの世界宗教にも祭礼がみられるが、教義より儀式・慣習によるところが大きい点で祭の要素は本質的に民族宗教に顕著であるともいえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rites and festivals are also seen in the world religion such as Christianity, Buddhism and so on, but, from the viewpoint of greatly depending on ceremonies and conventions rather than creeds, it is possible to say that the element of feast was especially pronounced in the racial religion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rites and festivals are also seen in the world religion such as Christianity, Buddhism and so on, but, from the viewpoint of greatly depending on ceremonies and conventions rather than creeds, it is possible to say that the element of matsuri was especially pronounced in the racial religion.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rites and festivals are also seen in the world religion such as Christianity, Buddhism and so on, but, from the viewpoint of greatly depending on ceremonies and conventions rather than creeds, it is possible to say that the element of matsuri was especially pronounced in the racial religion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>狩猟民族でも獲物を捧げ豊猟を祈願する儀礼がみられる（熊送りなど）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A race of hunters also has a ceremony for praying for good hunting by presenting caught animals (sending of bear and so on).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A race of hunters also has a ceremony for praying for good hunting by presenting caught animals (sending of bear and so on).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A race of hunters also has a ceremony for praying for good hunting by presenting caught animals (sending of bear and so on).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="69">
<j>キリスト教の復活祭や、ボロブドゥール遺跡で行われているワイシャックのように、キリスト教・仏教などの世界宗教に基づく祭りもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Like Easter under the Christianity, and Hari Raya Waisak held at the remains of Borobudur, there are festivals based on the world religion such as Christianity, Buddhism and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Like Easter under the Christianity, and Hari Raya Waisak held at the remains of Borobudur, there are festivals based on the world religion such as Christianity, Buddhism and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Like Easter under the Christianity, and Hari Raya Waisak held at the remains of Borobudur, there are festivals based on the world religion such as Christianity, Buddhism and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>また、アングロ・サクソン人アングロ・サクソン諸国のハロウィーンなどのように、世界宗教以前の信仰に基づくものや、世界宗教が伝来した各地で習合した形で伝わっている事例もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, like Halloween held by Anglo-Saxons in Anglo-Saxon countries, there are some festivals which are based on a belief before the world religion, or which are passed down in the form of syncretization in each place where the world religion was introduced.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, like Halloween held by Anglo-Saxons in Anglo-Saxon countries, there are some festivals which are based on a belief before the world religion, or which are passed down in the form of syncretization in each place where the world religion was introduced.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, like Halloween held by Anglo-Saxons in Anglo-Saxon countries, there are some festivals which are based on a belief before the world religion, or which are passed down in the form of syncretization in each place where the world religion was introduced.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>キリスト教の祭</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Feast in the Christianity</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Festival in the Christianity</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Festival in the Christianity</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="71">
<j>キリスト教においても祭が存在し、降誕祭・復活祭などの重要な祭日をはじめとして、司祭・聖体祭儀などの表現にも「祭」の概念・表現がみられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Feasts also exist in the Christianity, and expressions of important festivals days such as Christmas, Easter and so on, and of priest, Eucharist ceremony and so on, a concept and words of &apos;feast&apos; are seen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Festivals also exist in the Christianity, and expressions of important festivals days such as Christmas, Easter and so on, and of priest, Eucharist ceremony and so on, a concept and words of &apos;matsuri&apos; are seen.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Festivals also exist in the Christianity, and expressions of important festivals days such as Christmas, Easter and so on, and of priest, Eucharist ceremony and so on, a concept and words of &apos;matsuri&apos; are seen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="72">
<j>日本語訳聖書中においても、旧約聖書・新約聖書の両方に「祭」の翻訳がなされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Bible translated into Japanese, a translation of &apos;feast&apos; is given in both the Old Testament and the New Testament.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Bible translated into Japanese, a translation of &apos;matsuri&apos; is given in both the Old Testament and the New Testament.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Bible translated into Japanese, a translation of &apos;matsuri&apos; is given in both the Old Testament and the New Testament.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>ただし、日本聖書協会の口語訳聖書では「祭」と表記されているが、新共同訳聖書においては「祭り」と表記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the orally translated Bible of the Japan Bible Society has a description of &apos;feast,&apos; but the New Testament jointly translated has a description of &apos;festival.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the orally translated Bible of the Japan Bible Society has a description of &apos;matsuri&apos; (祭) but the New Testament jointly translated has a description of &apos;matsuri&apos; (祭り).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the orally translated Bible of the Japan Bible Society has a description of &apos;matsuri&apos; (祭) but the New Testament jointly translated has a description of &apos;matsuri&apos; (祭り).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="74">
<j>正教会（ギリシャ正教）の一員たる日本正教会は、日常用語においても各種著作物においても、「祭」（まつり）もしくは「お祭」（おまつり）との言葉を単独で使う事を全く避けない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Japan Orthodox Church, one of the members of Orthodox Church (Greek Orthodox Church), never avoids singularly using the term &apos;feast&apos; or &apos;festival&apos; in the everyday language and in various works.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Japan Orthodox Church, one of the members of Orthodox Church (Greek Orthodox Church), never avoids singularly using the term &apos;matsuri&apos; or &apos;omatsuri&apos; in the everyday language and in various works.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japan Orthodox Church, one of the members of Orthodox Church (Greek Orthodox Church), never avoids singularly using the term &apos;matsuri&apos; or &apos;omatsuri&apos; in the everyday language and in various works.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>祭と斎（ものいみ）、祭日（さいじつ）と斎日（ものいみび）というように、喜ばしい時（祭）と、自らを喜ばしい時に備える時（斎）とを対比させるリズムは正教会の伝統に組み込まれて日常生活の規範となっており、これを説明する際に「祭」の語・概念が多用される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As shown by the terms, feast and Monoimi (to purify oneself by abstaining from certain foods), and festival day and holy day, a rhythm contrasting a joyful occasion (feast) with the time to get oneself ready for joyful occasion (Monoimi) is incorporated in the tradition of Orthodox Church and is a standard of everyday life, and when this is explained, the term &apos;feast&apos; and its concept are often used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As shown by the terms, matsuri and Monoimi (to purify oneself by abstaining from certain foods), and a festival day and a holy day, a rhythm contrasting a joyful occasion (festival) with the time to get oneself ready for joyful occasion (Monoimi) is incorporated in the tradition of Orthodox Church and is a standard of everyday life, and when this is explained, the term &apos;matsuri&apos; and its concept are often used.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As shown by the terms, matsuri and Monoimi (to purify oneself by abstaining from certain foods), and a festival day and a holy day, a rhythm contrasting a joyful occasion (festival) with the time to get oneself ready for joyful occasion (Monoimi) is incorporated in the tradition of Orthodox Church and is a standard of everyday life, and when this is explained, the term &apos;matsuri&apos; and its concept are often used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>代表的な例として、正教会で最大の祭である復活大祭と、それに自らを備える期間である大斎 (東方正教会)（おおものいみ）がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As representative examples, the Easter which is the biggest festival of Orthodox Church, and Omonoimi (Eastern Orthodox Church) which refers to a period to get oneself ready for the Easter are named.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As representative examples, the Easter which is the biggest festival of Orthodox Church, and Omonoimi (Eastern Orthodox Church) which refers to a period to get oneself ready for the Easter are named.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As representative examples, the Easter which is the biggest festival of Orthodox Church, and Omonoimi (Eastern Orthodox Church) which refers to a period to get oneself ready for the Easter are named.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="77">
<j>同様のリズムの伝統は正教会に限らず、西方教会（カトリック教会・聖公会など）においても復活祭と大斎の形などにみられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A tradition of similar rhythm is not limited to the Orthodox Church, and is also seen in the Western Orthodox Church (Catholic Church, Anglican Church and so on) in the forms of the Easter, Omonoimi and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A tradition of similar rhythm is not limited to the Orthodox Church, and is also seen in the Western Orthodox Church (Catholic Church, Anglican Church and so on) in the forms of the Easter, Omonoimi and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A tradition of similar rhythm is not limited to the Orthodox Church, and is also seen in the Western Orthodox Church (Catholic Church, Anglican Church and so on) in the forms of the Easter, Omonoimi and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>しかしながら殆どのキリスト教諸教派の一覧においては、日常用語として「祭」（まつり）という言葉は単独ではあまり用いられない傾向がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the term &apos;feast&apos; tends not to be used often by itself as an everyday language in the list of most Christian schools.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the term &apos;matsuri&apos; tends not to be used often by itself as an everyday language in the list of most Christian schools.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the term &apos;matsuri&apos; tends not to be used often by itself as an everyday language in the list of most Christian schools.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>「祭」の語を単独で用いる傾向が強いのは一部の例外を除き、殆ど日本正教会のみとなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Almost only the Japan Orthodox Church has a strong tendency to use the term &apos;feast&apos; singularly, excluding some exceptions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Almost only the Japan Orthodox Church has a strong tendency to use the term &apos;matsuri&apos; singularly, excluding some exceptions.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Almost only the Japan Orthodox Church has a strong tendency to use the term &apos;matsuri&apos; singularly, excluding some exceptions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>日本古来の祭</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese ancient feast</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese ancient matsuri</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese ancient matsuri</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="80">
<j>古代の神道いわゆる古神道は、もともとアニミズム・シャーマニズム的要素を持っており、世界宗教以前の民族宗教に分類される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Shinto in ancient times, so-called Ancient Shinto, originally had elements of animism and shamanism, and was categorized into a racial religion before the world religion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Shinto in ancient times, so-called Ancient Shinto, originally had elements of animism and shamanism, and was categorized into a racial religion before the world religion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Shinto in ancient times, so-called Ancient Shinto, originally had elements of animism and shamanism, and was categorized into a racial religion before the world religion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>今日伝わっている祭も土着のものを起源とするという意味では民間信仰も交え、神道系に分類されるものが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Feasts passed down today also include folk beliefs in the sense of originating from native feasts, and many of them are categorized as Shinto-related ones.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Matsuri passed down today also include folk beliefs in the sense of originating from native&apos;s, and many of them are categorized as Shinto-related&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Matsuri passed down today also include folk beliefs in the sense of originating from native&apos;s, and many of them are categorized as Shinto-related&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>しかし、道教や仏教伝来から密教を含め長く経った為、神仏習合や渡来の習俗の影響を受けているものもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, since a long time has passed after the introduction of Taoism, Buddhism and Esoteric Buddhism, some feasts were influenced by the syncretization of Shinto with Buddhism and imported folkways.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, since a long time has passed after the introduction of Taoism, Buddhism and Esoteric Buddhism, some matsuri are influenced by the syncretization of Shinto with Buddhism and imported folkways.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, since a long time has passed after the introduction of Taoism, Buddhism and Esoteric Buddhism, some matsuri are influenced by the syncretization of Shinto with Buddhism and imported folkways.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="83">
<j>祭は民俗学で「ハレとケ」の非日常性の空間を象徴するものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The feast symbolizes a space of extraordinariness, &apos;hare and ke&apos; (sacred-profane dichotomy), in the folklore.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The matsuri symbolizes a space of extraordinariness, &apos;hare and ke&apos; (sacred-profane dichotomy), in the folklore.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The matsuri symbolizes a space of extraordinariness, &apos;hare and ke&apos; (sacred-profane dichotomy), in the folklore.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>日本神話に出てくる天岩戸の話を摸した儀式などが日本で最も古いものとして知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A ceremony modeling the story of Ama no Iwato (Cave of heaven) in the Japanese Mythology is known as the oldest one in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A ceremony modeling the story of Ama no Iwato (Cave of heaven) in the Japanese Mythology is known as the oldest one in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A ceremony modeling the story of Ama no Iwato (Cave of heaven) in the Japanese Mythology is known as the oldest one in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>初期の「まつり」は、人目に触れない所で密かに行われるものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The primitive &apos;festival&apos; was held secretly at a secluded spot.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The primitive &apos;matsuri&apos; was held secretly at a secluded spot.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The primitive &apos;matsuri&apos; was held secretly at a secluded spot.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>今日でも、中心となる儀式を限られた者のみで行う祭が一部にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even today, a core ceremony is held by limited people in some feasts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even today, a core ceremony is held by limited people in some matsuri.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even today, a core ceremony is held by limited people in some matsuri.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>（伊勢神宮などの神主の奉仕、一般は奉賛、または奉納。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Service by the Shinto priest of Ise-jingu Shrine and so on, generally called hosan (support given to a temple or shrine or hono (dedication))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Service by the Shinto priest of Ise-jingu Shrine and so on, generally called hosan [support given to a temple or shrine] or hono [dedication].)</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Service by the Shinto priest of Ise-jingu Shrine and so on, generally called hosan [support given to a temple or shrine] or hono [dedication].)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="88">
<j>現在一般的な意味での祭は、神社や寺院をその主体または舞台として行われることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At present, many feasts in the general sense are held under the initiative of shrines or temples, or by having settings in shrines or temples.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At present, many matsuri in the general sense are held under the initiative of shrines or temples, or by having settings in shrines or temples.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At present, many matsuri in the general sense are held under the initiative of shrines or temples, or by having settings in shrines or temples.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>その目的や意義は、豊作の「五穀豊穣」を始め、「大漁追福」、「商売繁盛」、「疫病退散」、「無病息災」、「家内安全」、「安寧長寿」、「夫婦円満」、「子孫繁栄」、「祖先崇拝」、「豊楽万民」、「天下泰平」などを招福祈願、厄除祈念として行われるもの、またはそれらの成就に感謝して行われるもの、節句などの年中行事が発展して行われているもの、偉人の霊を慰めるために行われるものなど様々である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The purpose and meaning are diversified because some feasts are held for &apos;the productiveness of grain&apos; for good harvests, and a prayer for good luck charm and prayer for warding off evil such as &apos;good catch and memorial service,&apos; &apos;prosperous trade,&apos; &apos;an attempt to secure protection from a plague,&apos; &apos;state of perfect health,&apos; &apos;safety of one&apos;s family,&apos; &apos;peace and longevity,&apos; &apos;harmonious marriage,&apos; &apos;fertility and family prosperity,&apos; &apos;ancestor worship,&apos; &apos;abundance and joy to all people,&apos; &apos;universal peace&apos; and so on, some are held in appreciation for accomplishments of such prayers, some are held as a result of development of annual events such as Sekku and so on, or some are held to console spirits of great people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The purpose and meaning are diversified because some feasts are held for &apos;the productiveness of grain&apos; for good harvests, and a prayer for good luck charm and prayer for warding off evil such as &apos;good catch and memorial service,&apos; &apos;prosperous trade,&apos; &apos;an attempt to secure protection from a plague,&apos; &apos;state of perfect health,&apos; &apos;safety of one&apos;s family,&apos; &apos;peace and longevity,&apos; &apos;harmonious marriage,&apos; &apos;fertility and family prosperity,&apos; &apos;ancestor worship,&apos; &apos;abundance and joy to all people,&apos; &apos;universal peace&apos; and so on, some are held in appreciation for accomplishments of such prayers, some are held as a result of development of annual events such as Sekku and so on, or some are held to console spirits of great people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The purpose and meaning are diversified because some feasts are held for &apos;the productiveness of grain&apos; for good harvests, and a prayer for good luck charm and prayer for warding off evil such as &apos;good catch and memorial service,&apos; &apos;prosperous trade,&apos; &apos;an attempt to secure protection from a plague,&apos; &apos;state of perfect health,&apos; &apos;safety of one&apos;s family,&apos; &apos;peace and longevity,&apos; &apos;harmonious marriage,&apos; &apos;fertility and family prosperity,&apos; &apos;ancestor worship,&apos; &apos;abundance and joy to all people,&apos; &apos;universal peace&apos; and so on, some are held in appreciation for accomplishments of such prayers, some are held as a result of development of annual events such as Sekku and so on, or some are held to console spirits of great people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>その目的により開催時期や行事の内容は多種多様なものとなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The time of holding and contents of events are of great variety depending on the purpose.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The time of holding and contents of events are of great variety depending on the purpose.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The time of holding and contents of events are of great variety depending on the purpose.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>また同じ目的、祭神の祭りであっても、祭祀の様式や趣向または伝統などが、地方・地域ごとに大きく異なる場合も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In spite of the same purpose, and festival for enshrined deity, a style or variety of religious service, or a tradition differs greatly according to a province or region in many cases.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In spite of the same purpose, and festival for enshrined deity, a style or variety of religious service, or a tradition differs greatly according to a province or region in many cases.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In spite of the same purpose, and festival for enshrined deity, a style or variety of religious service, or a tradition differs greatly according to a province or region in many cases.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="92">
<j>祭の目的が時代の変化によって参加者達の利害とは離れてしまったものも多く、行事の内容も社会環境の変化等により変更を余儀なくされた祭もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In many cases, the purpose of feast departed from the interests of participants due to changes of the times, and details of events of some feasts were forced to be changed due to changes in the social environment and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In many cases, the purpose of matsuri departed from the interests of participants due to changes of the times, and details of events of some matsuri were forced to be changed due to changes in the social environment and so on.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In many cases, the purpose of matsuri departed from the interests of participants due to changes of the times, and details of events of some matsuri were forced to be changed due to changes in the social environment and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>それらの結果、祭を行うことそのものが目的に成り代わっているような、目的から考えると形骸化した状況の祭も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result of those, many feasts fell into the state of losing substance from the viewpoint of purpose as shown by an example that the holding of feast itself became a purpose.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result of those, many matsuri fell into the state of losing substance from the viewpoint of purpose as shown by an example that the holding of matsuri itself became a purpose.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result of those, many matsuri fell into the state of losing substance from the viewpoint of purpose as shown by an example that the holding of matsuri itself became a purpose.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>このため、全くの部外者や、見物する者や参加する者という当事者にとっても「祭＝楽しいイベント（お祭り騒ぎ）」という程度の認識しか持たれないことが多く、祭のために仕事を休むということは、例えば葬儀のためにということなどと比べると遥かに理解が得られにくい状況にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, in many cases, complete outsiders, viewers and concerned people called participants only have a recognition at a level of &apos;feast equaling to cheerful event (festivity),&apos; and now is in the situation where it is almost far from clear to take days off for a feast compared with cases of taking days off for funeral service and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, in many cases, complete outsiders, viewers and concerned people called participants only have a recognition at a level of &apos;matsuri equaling to cheerful event&apos; (omatsuri sawagi), and now is in the situation where it is almost far from clear to take days off for a feast compared with cases of taking days off for funeral service and so on.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, in many cases, complete outsiders, viewers and concerned people called participants only have a recognition at a level of &apos;matsuri equaling to cheerful event&apos; (omatsuri sawagi), and now is in the situation where it is almost far from clear to take days off for a feast compared with cases of taking days off for funeral service and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="95">
<j>一般的に神社における祭礼には、神輿（神様の乗り物）をはじめとして山車・太鼓台・だんじりなどの屋台などが出されることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the rites and festivals held at shrines, it is general to often use mikoshi (portable shrine carried in festivals) (carriage of deity), and also a large float used to carry taiko at festivals such as dashi (float), taiko-dai (dashi including a drum), decorative portable shrine and so on.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Generally, at the rites and festivals held at shrines, large floats used to carry taiko (drums) at festivals such as dashi (float), taiko-dai (dashi including a drum), decorative portable shrine and so on, including mikoshi (portable shrine carried in festivals) (carriage of deity).</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Generally, at the rites and festivals held at shrines, large floats used to carry taiko (drums) at festivals such as dashi (float), taiko-dai (dashi including a drum), decorative portable shrine and so on, including mikoshi (portable shrine carried in festivals) (carriage of deity).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>これらは地方によって氏神の化身とみなされる場合や、または神輿を先導する露払いの役目を持って町内を練り歩き、それをもてなす意味で沿道では賑やかな催しが行われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These are sometimes regarded as an incarnation of ujigami (a guardian god or spirit of a particular place in the Shinto religion) in some provinces, or parade with a role of outrider leading mikoshi, and joyous events are held along the street for the purpose of entertaining mikoshi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These are sometimes regarded as an incarnation of ujigami (a guardian god or spirit of a particular place in the Shinto religion) in some provinces, or parade with a role of outrider leading mikoshi, and joyous events are held along the street for the purpose of entertaining mikoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These are sometimes regarded as an incarnation of ujigami (a guardian god or spirit of a particular place in the Shinto religion) in some provinces, or parade with a role of outrider leading mikoshi, and joyous events are held along the street for the purpose of entertaining mikoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>また、伝統などの違いにより例外もあるが、多くの祭りにおいては工夫を凝らした美しい衣装や化粧、厚化粧を施して稚児、巫女、手古舞、踊り子、祭囃子、行列等により氏子が祭礼に参加することも多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In many festivals, although there are exceptions due to a difference of tradition, shrine parishioners often participate in the rites and festivals by putting on an artful and beautiful costume, and makeup or heavy makeup, as chigo (beautifully dressed children parading at festivals), miko, performers of tekomai (float leading dance), dancers, performers of festival music, participants in the parade and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In many matsuri, although there are exceptions due to a difference of tradition, shrine parishioners often participate in the rites and festivals by putting on an artful and beautiful costume, and makeup or heavy makeup, as chigo (beautifully dressed children parading at festivals), miko (a shrine maiden), performers of tekomai (float leading dance), dancers, performers of festival music, participants in the parade and so on.</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In many matsuri, although there are exceptions due to a difference of tradition, shrine parishioners often participate in the rites and festivals by putting on an artful and beautiful costume, and makeup or heavy makeup, as chigo (beautifully dressed children parading at festivals), miko (a shrine maiden), performers of tekomai (float leading dance), dancers, performers of festival music, participants in the parade and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>今日では世俗化も進んでいるが、今なお祭の時は都市化によって人間関係の疎遠になった地域住民の心を一体化する作用がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the secularity advances today, the feast still has a function of unifying a spirit of local residents whose interpersonal relation becomes poor due to urbanization.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the secularity advances today, the matsuri still has a function of unifying a spirit of local residents whose interpersonal relation becomes poor due to urbanization.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the secularity advances today, the matsuri still has a function of unifying a spirit of local residents whose interpersonal relation becomes poor due to urbanization.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>変わりない日常生活の中に非日常の空間を演出することによって、人々は意味を実感する営みを続けてきたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By producing an extraordinary space in the ordinary daily life, people continued activities realizing the meaning.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By producing an extraordinary space in the ordinary daily life, people continued activities realizing the meaning.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By producing an extraordinary space in the ordinary daily life, people continued activities realizing the meaning.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="100">
<j>基本的に神事としての祭りは厳粛な場面と賑やかな場面の二面性を持ち、厳粛な場面では人々は日常よりも厳しく、伝統や秩序を守ることを要求される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The festival as Shinto ritual basically has a bilateral character of solemn scene and joyous scene, and in the solemn scene, people are required to keep traditions and order more strictly than usual.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The matsuri as Shinto ritual basically has a bilateral character of solemn scene and joyous scene, and in the solemn scene, people are required to keep traditions and order more strictly than usual.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The matsuri as Shinto ritual basically has a bilateral character of solemn scene and joyous scene, and in the solemn scene, people are required to keep traditions and order more strictly than usual.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>しかし一方で、日常では許されないような秩序や常識を超えた行為（ふんどし一丁、男性の女装等）も、「この祭礼の期間にだけは」伝統的に許されると認識する地方が多く、そのため賑やかな場面を指して「お祭り騒ぎ」などの言葉が派生している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, order disallowed in the daily life and acts beyond the bounds of common sense (naked except for one&apos;s loincloth, dressing as a woman by men and so on) are recognized to be allowed traditionally in many provinces, and therefore, the term &apos;festivity&apos; referring to a joyous scene was derived.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, order disallowed in the daily life and acts beyond the bounds of common sense (naked except for one&apos;s loincloth, dressing as a woman by men and so on) are recognized to be allowed traditionally &apos;only during the matsuri&apos; in many provinces, and therefore, the term &apos;omatsuri sawagi&apos; referring to a joyous scene was derived.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ。補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, order disallowed in the daily life and acts beyond the bounds of common sense (naked except for one&apos;s loincloth, dressing as a woman by men and so on) are recognized to be allowed traditionally &apos;only during the matsuri&apos; in many provinces, and therefore, the term &apos;omatsuri sawagi&apos; referring to a joyous scene was derived.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="102">
<j>仏教の影響を受けた神仏習合の色が濃いものとしては土着の祖霊信仰や言霊の呪術性を帯びた念仏踊りを取り入れた盆踊りがあり、習合した盂蘭盆会に繋がる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a festival influenced by Buddhism and having a strong character of syncretization of Shinto with Buddhism, Bon Festival Dance incorporating a native ancestor worship or nenbutsu-odori dance (a dance with an invocation to the Buddha) with a magic of kotodama (soul or power of language) is named, and is conductive to Urabon-e Festival (a Festival of the Dead or Buddhist All Souls&apos; day, around the 15th of July or August, depending on local customs) syncretized.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a matsuri influenced by Buddhism and having a strong character of syncretization of Shinto with Buddhism, Bon Festival Dance incorporating a native ancestor worship or nenbutsu-odori dance (a dance with an invocation to the Buddha) with a magic of kotodama (soul or power of language) is named, and is conductive to Urabon-e Festival (a Festival of the Dead or Buddhist All Souls&apos; day, around July or August 15, depending on local customs) syncretized.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a matsuri influenced by Buddhism and having a strong character of syncretization of Shinto with Buddhism, Bon Festival Dance incorporating a native ancestor worship or nenbutsu-odori dance (a dance with an invocation to the Buddha) with a magic of kotodama (soul or power of language) is named, and is conductive to Urabon-e Festival (a Festival of the Dead or Buddhist All Souls&apos; day, around July or August 15, depending on local customs) syncretized.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>また、神事から発達した田楽・猿楽などが能など後の日本中世伝統芸能を形作る素地となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, Dengaku (ritual music and dancing in shrines and temples), sarugaku (form of theater popular in Japan during the 11th to 14th centuries) and so on which were developed from Shinto rituals became the base to form later Japanese medieval traditional performing arts such as Noh and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, Dengaku (ritual music and dancing in shrines and temples), sarugaku (form of theater popular in Japan during the 11th to 14th centuries) and so on which were developed from Shinto rituals became the base to form later Japanese medieval traditional performing arts such as Noh and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, Dengaku (ritual music and dancing in shrines and temples), sarugaku (form of theater popular in Japan during the 11th to 14th centuries) and so on which were developed from Shinto rituals became the base to form later Japanese medieval traditional performing arts such as Noh and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>古代ギリシャ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ancient Greece</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ancient Greece</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ancient Greece</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="104">
<j>エレウシス秘儀やディオニュソス祭が存在した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Eleusis esoterica and Dionysia existed</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Eleusis esoterica and Dionysia existed.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Eleusis esoterica and Dionysia existed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>マイナス (ギリシア神話)も参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also refer to Maenad (Greek Mythology).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also refer to Maenad (Greek Mythology).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also refer to Maenad (Greek Mythology).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>インドネシア</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Indonesia</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Indonesia</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Indonesia</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="106">
<j>トラジャ族による大規模な葬祭が知られ、首狩りとの関連も指摘される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A large-scale funeral by Toraja is known, and a relation with headhunting is pointed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A large-scale funeral by Toraja is known, and a relation with headhunting is pointed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A large-scale funeral by Toraja is known, and a relation with headhunting is pointed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>ボロブドゥール遺跡のワイシャックも知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hari Raya Waisak at the remains of Borobudur is also known.</e>
<cmt>「。」で終わっていますが、「です」「ます」で終わっていないので、和文に赤字の部分を付け加え、英訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hari Raya Waisak at the remains of Borobudur is also known.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hari Raya Waisak at the remains of Borobudur is also known.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="14">
<tit>
<j>その他の宗教の祭</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other religious feasts</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other religious matsuri</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other religious matsuri</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="15">
<tit>
<j>特定のテーマによるフェスティバル</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Festival under a specific theme</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Festival under a specific theme</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Festival under a specific theme</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="108">
<j>映画や産業（みかん、大漁まつり、－など）などをテーマにしたものがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Festivals under the theme of movie or industry (mandarin orange, Tairyo (good catch)-matsuri festival and so on) are held.</e>
<cmt>「-など」の「-」の部分が不明でしたので、&quot;and so on&quot;と英訳しました。また、「。」で終わっていますが、「です」「ます」で終わっていないので、和文に赤字の部分を付け加え、英訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Festivals under the theme of movie or industry (mandarin orange, Tairyo [good catch] matsuri festival and so on) are held.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Festivals under the theme of movie or industry (mandarin orange, Tairyo [good catch] matsuri festival and so on) are held.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="109">
<j>都市の特定のエリア（例えば、中華街、元町、神田神保町の古本祭り、浅草サンバカーニバル、YOSAKOIソーラン祭りなど）、文化施設（たとえば、Bunkamura、水戸芸術館など）、教育機関（中学校、高等学校、大学など）の祭り、フェスティバル等がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Festivals held atspecific areas in the city (e.g., China Town, Motomachi, Secondhand Book Fair at Kanda Jinbo-cho, Asakusa Samba Carnival, YOSAKOI Soran Festival and so on), at cultural facilities (e.g., Bunkamura, Art Tower Mito and so on), and at educational institutions (junior high schools, high schools, universities and so on) are named.</e>
<cmt>「。」で終わっていますが、「です」「ます」で終わっていないので、和文に赤字の部分を付け加え、英訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Festivals held at specific areas in the city (e.g., China Town, Motomachi, Secondhand Book Fair at Kanda Jinbo-cho, Asakusa Samba Carnival, YOSAKOI Soran Festival and so on), at cultural facilities (e.g., Bunkamura, Art Tower Mito and so on), and at educational institutions (junior high schools, high schools, universities and so on) are named.</e>
<cmt>スペース補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Festivals held at specific areas in the city (e.g., China Town, Motomachi, Secondhand Book Fair at Kanda Jinbo-cho, Asakusa Samba Carnival, YOSAKOI Soran Festival and so on), at cultural facilities (e.g., Bunkamura, Art Tower Mito and so on), and at educational institutions (junior high schools, high schools, universities and so on) are named.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="110">
<j>映画祭</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Film festival</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Film festival</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Film festival</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>音楽祭</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Music festival</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Music festival</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Music festival</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>文化祭</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Culture festival</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Culture festival</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Culture festival</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="113">
<j>大学祭</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">University festival</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">University festival</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">University festival</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="114">
<j>感謝祭</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thanksgiving festival</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thanksgiving festival</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thanksgiving festival</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 ちょるや氏(id:88738), AlleborgoBot(id:119729), Shirayuki(id:38420), Sionn(id:84971), Immanuel Giel(id:20517), Nnh(id:474), Chonan(id:645), Sina(id:10021), Mishika(id:276), 柑橘類(id:112137), Greenland4(id:114494), 宮本すぐる(id:40080), Alex K(id:86829), OKBot(id:143139), Gombe(id:27), Tomomarusan(id:17060), 赤井彗星(id:18381), たぬき(id:27723), 橄欖岩(id:24996), Wtp2005ap(id:35631), Knua(id:66861), Point136(id:211299), 男祭り(id:177415), 白糸(id:47025), Mikomaid(id:56139), Lemon(id:11234), GENMEI(id:31879), Starbacks(id:1018), Stanislaus(id:1806), 078(id:28534), MizusumashiBot(id:180225), Nallimbot(id:230812), STBot(id:137943), Seibuabina(id:37532), Vasa(id:88596), Sh(id:2707), YukkeBot(id:251107), 74FLIOA(id:151857), Higasi(id:38275), 白拍子花子(id:244805), Rusk(id:9895), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), Gussan01-cat(id:182813), SuisuiBot(id:10165), Nnn(id:26535), 廬舎那憂(id:168188), 海衛士(id:19229), Alexbot(id:157199), えすぱ(id:12144), 弥(id:61590), RadioActive(id:18024), いぬ(id:756), MIsogi(id:20599), Tom-spring(id:42457), Hayabusa future(id:21110), Kliment.A.K.(id:161714), Oasisjet(id:227726), Abeshi8(id:164139), 沢田(id:40580), Ozumoen(id:52528), Toto-tarou(id:16648), Siso-nori(id:48362), Su-no-G(id:52744), くっちゃめ(id:86793), Tomika(id:43050), Ok3229(id:11498), Nopira(id:29335), Hiro104(id:14333), G(id:21), MACアドレスは辛光洙(id:54680), ととりん(id:31982), Vold(id:86058), MASA(id:2399), Sadaharu(id:85339), Taisyo(id:6896), Shikine(id:12962), Yanahan(id:2437), MH(id:1586), お掃除大好き(id:99320), 依存性だんぢり中毒(id:79907), Negotiation(id:84503), 竃馬(id:102733), Joh shoh(id:9812), Zerry(id:63375), Eine kleine(id:32017), Hamasaki gion higashi(id:144985), Louperibot(id:128971), SieBot(id:126695), ホイップ(id:44812), Ete(id:28565), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>