<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>束帯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sokutai</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sokutai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sokutai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>束帯（そくたい）は、平安時代以降の、天皇以下公家の正装（平安装束）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sokutai is a formal costume for those from the Emperor to the court nobles in and after Heian period (Heian costume).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sokutai is a formal costume for those from the Emperor to the court nobles in and after Heian period (Heian costume).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sokutai is a formal costume for those from the Emperor to the court nobles in and after Heian period (Heian costume).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>衣冠を「宿直（とのい）装束」と呼ぶのに対し、束帯は「昼（ひの）装束」と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ikan is called &apos;tonoi (nighttime) costume&apos; whereas sokutai is called &apos;hino (daytime) costume&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ikan is called &apos;tonoi (nighttime) costume&apos;, whereas sokutai is called &apos;hino (daytime) costume&apos;.</e>
<cmt>コンマ追加</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ikan is called &apos;tonoi (nighttime) costume&apos;, whereas sokutai is called &apos;hino (daytime) costume&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>構成</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Configuration</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Composition</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">How sokutai is worn</e>
<cmt>修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>束帯の構成は下から、単（ひとえ）・袙（あこめ）・下襲（したがさね）・半臂（はんぴ）・袍（ほう）を着用、袍の上から腰の部位に革製のベルトである石帯（せきたい）を当てる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Configuring sokutai, hitoe, akome, sitagasane, hanbi, and ho are wore and sekitai which is a leather belt is wound on the narrow of the back on ho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for the composition of sokutai, first hitoe is put on, then akome, sitagasane, hanbi, and ho are placed in layer, lastly sekitai, a leather belt, is wound around the waist on top of the ho.</e>
<cmt>修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A sokutai is put on in the following order: first a hitoe (a single layer of a kimono that serves as an undergarment) is put on; next, an akome (a layer of clothing worn by nobles beneath their robe but over their undergarments) is put on; next, a shitagasane (long inner robe) is put on; next, a hanpi (short-sleeved or sleeveless undergarment) is put on; next, a ho (outer robe) is put on; and finally a leather belt is put on around the waist on top of the ho.</e>
<cmt>修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>袴（はかま）は大口袴・表袴の二種類あり、大口を履き、その上に表袴を重ねて履く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hakama has two types thereof which are oguchi-bakama and omote-bakama, and</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are two types of hakama, oguchi-bakama and omote-bakama, of which first oguchi-bakama is put on, then omote-bakama is worn on top of the oguchi.</e>
<cmt>訳抜けを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are two types of hakama, oguchi-bakama and omote-bakama: first oguchi-bakama is put on, then omote-bakama is worn on top of the oguchi.</e>
<cmt>, of which→:</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>冠を被り、足には襪（しとうず）を履く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A crown is put on the head and shitouzu is put on the feet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A crown is put on the head and shitouzu is put on the feet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A crown is put on the head and shitouzu is put on the feet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>帖紙（たとう）と檜扇（ひおうぎ）を懐中し、笏（しゃく）を持つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tatou and hiougi are put in a space on the chest and a shaku is held in a hand.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tatou and hiougi are put in a space on the chest and a shaku is held in a hand.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tatou and hiougi are put in a space on the chest and a shaku is held in a hand.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>公卿、殿上人は魚袋（ぎょたい）と呼ばれる装飾物を腰に提げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Each of the persons ranked at kugyo and the people in the Imperial palace had a decoration item called gyotai was hung at the waist.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kugyo (the top court officials) and tenjobito (a high-ranking courtier allowed into the Imperial Palace) had a decoration item called gyotai hung at the waist.</e>
<cmt>修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kugyo (the top court officials) and tenjobito (a high-ranking courtier allowed into the Imperial Palace) had a decoration item called gyotai hung at the waist.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>なお、束帯には文官・武官による区別があり、文官と三位以上の武官は、縫腋袍を用い、冠は垂纓とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sokutai differed between those for clerical officers and those for warriors, and the clerical officers and warriors at sani (the third court rank) or higher used nuiwakiho and tarehimo (hanging-down lace) was used for their crowns.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sokutai differed between those for civil officers and military officers, and military officers at Sanmi (Third Rank) or higher, and civil officers wore hoeki no ho (robe with a round collar stitched sides and a ran, worn by the imperor and high-ranking officials) and suiei for a cap (a kind of cap included into official uniform which is a type of having Ei, an attachement of cap hanging back of head).</e>
<cmt>修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although there were some differences between the sokutai worn by civil officers and that worn by military officers, military officers with a rank of Sanmi (Third Rank) or higher and civil officers both wore a hoeki no ho (robe with a round collar, stitched sides, and a ran that was worn by the emperor and high-ranking officials) and a suiei (a kind of &quot;tail&quot; that was attached to the back of formal headwear) attached to their kan (formal headwear).</e>
<cmt>修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>四位以下の武官は、闕腋袍を用い、冠は巻纓とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Warriors at the fourth court rank or lower used ketsuwakiho and makihimo (wound lace) was used for their crowns.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Military officers at the fourth court rank or lower used ketteki no ho (open sleeve steams outer robe) and kenei for a cap (an item which is a string of a crown rolling up inwardly and hold with black stained hasamigi).</e>
<cmt>修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Military officers at the fourth court rank or lower used ketteki no ho (open sleeve steams outer robe) and kenei for a cap (an item which is a string of a crown rolling up inwardly and hold with black stained hasamigi).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>さらに、武官・中務省の官人、勅許を得た参議以上の文官は、大刀を佩用した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, warriors, officers in chumu-sho ministry, and clerical officers at the ranks of sangi or higher who were permitted by the Emperor each had a sword at their waist.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, warriors, officers in Ministry of Central Affairs, civil officers at the rank of Sangi (councillor) or higher who were permitted by the Emperor had a sword at their waist.</e>
<cmt>修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, military officers, officers in Ministry of Central Affairs and civil officers at the rank of Sangi (councillor) or higher who were permitted by the Emperor had a sword at their waist.</e>
<cmt>warriors→military officerscivil officers→and civil officers</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>その場合、大刀は平緒（ひらお）で括り、腰に結びつけた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the above case, the sword was fastened with hirao (flat lace) and was tied up to the waist.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this case, the sword was fastened with hirao (cord of sword) and was tied up to the waist.</e>
<cmt>修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this case, the sword was fastened with hirao (cord of sword) and was tied up to the waist.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>特徴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Features</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Characteristics</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Characteristics</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="12">
<j>下襲の後ろ身頃（背部）は長くできており、着用時は長く尾を引くように引き擦った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The back bodice (the portion for the back) of shitagasane was made long and was trailed like a long tail when it was put on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ushiro-migoro (back main panel) of shitagasane (long inner robe) was made long and was trailed like a long tail when it was put on.</e>
<cmt>修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ushiro-migoro (back main panel) of shitagasane (long inner robe) was made long and was trailed like a long tail when it was put on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>この部位を「裾（きょ）」と呼び、束帯姿の大きな特徴である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This portion was called &apos;kyo (bottom)&apos; and was a remarkable feature of the figure of a person in sokutai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This portion was called &apos;kyo (hem)&apos; and was a remarkable feature of the figure of a person in sokutai.</e>
<cmt>kyoの説明　用語共有に沿い変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This portion was called &apos;kyo (hem)&apos; and was a remarkable feature of the figure of a person in sokutai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>また、裾の長さによって身分が表されるようになると、下襲自体が長大になった為、下襲と裾が分離するようになった（別裾）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the length of kyo started to indicate the rank of a person who was in sokutai, shitagasane and kyo were separated from each other because shitagasane itself became so large (bekkyo, separated kyo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the length of kyo started to indicate the rank of persons, shitagasane and kyo were separated from each other because shitagasane itself became so large (bekkyo, separated kyo).</e>
<cmt>シンプル化</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the length of kyo started to indicate the rank of persons, shitagasane and kyo were separated from each other because shitagasane itself became so large (bekkyo, separated kyo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>その場合、下襲を着た後に腰に裾を当て、裾から伸びる帯を前に回して結びつけた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this case, after putting on shitagasane, the ends of the belt extended from kyo were brought in front and were tied up.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this case, after putting on shitagasane, the ends of the belt extended from kyo were brought in front and were tied up.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this case, after putting on shitagasane, the ends of the belt extended from kyo were brought in front and were tied up.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>しかしながら、天皇と皇太子が着用するものに関しては下襲と裾が続くものとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as to sokutai that were worn by the Emperor and the princes, shitagasane and kyo were must be connected with each other.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as to sokutai worn by the Emperor and the princes, shitagasane and kyo were connected with each other.</e>
<cmt>修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as to sokutai worn by the Emperor and the princes, shitagasane and kyo were connected with each other.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>また、纔著（さいじゃく）と言われる丈の短い裾もあり、地下人の束帯に用いられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was also a short version of kyo called saijaku, and this was used for sokutai worn by chikanin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was also short kyo called saijaku, and this was used for sokutai for jigenin (a lower rank of ancient Japanese nobility).</e>
<cmt>修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was also short kyo called saijaku, and this was used for sokutai for jigenin (a lower rank of ancient Japanese nobility).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="18">
<j>文官は冬期は半臂を廃して着用していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The clerical officers abolished hanbi and put on sokutai in winter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In winter civil officers wore sokutai without hanbi.</e>
<cmt>用語共有に沿って修正。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In winter civil officers wore sokutai without hanbi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>これは文官の用いる縫腋袍は脇が縫われているので、着用の有無を外見から判別出来ない為である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was because the portions on both sides of the chest of nuiwakiho used by the clerical officers were closed and, therefore, whether hanbi was worn or not was impossible to judge.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was because the both sides of the chest of hoeki no ho were closed, therefore, it was not seen whether hanbi was worn or not.</e>
<cmt>修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was because the both sides of the chest of hoeki no ho were closed, therefore, it was not seen whether hanbi was worn or not.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>夏期は半臂が透ける（袍の布地が薄い為）ので着用されていたが、近世に入ってからは夏期も廃された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hanbi was worn in summer because hanbi could be seen through (because the cloth of ho was thin), however, hanbi was also abolished in summer when the modern times started.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hanbi was worn in summer because hanbi could be seen through (because the cloth of ho was thin), however, later during the early-modern times, hanbi was abolished even in summer.</e>
<cmt>修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hanbi was worn in summer because hanbi could be seen through (because the cloth of ho was thin), however, later during the early-modern times, hanbi was abolished even in summer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>なお、『今鏡』には、冬期にくだけた場面で袍を肩脱ぎした際、皆下襲が露わになる中で藤原教通のみがきちんと半臂を着用しており、周囲がいたく自らを恥じた、という逸話が残されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An episode was described in &quot;Imakagami&quot; that, in a scene in a casual atmosphere, when some people took off ho from their shoulders, the people exposed their shitagasane and only Norimichi FUJIWARA orderly wore hanbi and the people around were deeply ashamed of themselves.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to an episode described in &quot;Imakagami&quot; (The mirror of the Present), in a scene in a casual atmosphere, when some people took off ho from their shoulders, the people exposed their shitagasane and only Norimichi FUJIWARA orderly wore hanbi and the people around were deeply ashamed of themselves.</e>
<cmt>今鏡の説明　追加</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to an episode described in &quot;Imakagami&quot; (The mirror of the Present), in a scene in a casual atmosphere, when some people took off ho from their shoulders, the people exposed their shitagasane and only Norimichi FUJIWARA orderly wore hanbi and the people around were deeply ashamed of themselves.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>この事から、本来は冬期も半臂を着用する制であったことが伺える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It can be guessed from this episode that it was a rule that hanbi was originally worn even in winter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered from this episode that the rule holds hanbi should be worn even in winter in principle.</e>
<cmt>修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This indicates that hanbi should be worn even in winter in principle.</e>
<cmt>It is considered from this episode that the rule holds →This indicates that</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>天皇に関しては半臂を略さないとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that emperors do not omit their hanbi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperors are supposed not to omit their hanbi.</e>
<cmt>修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperors are not supposed to omit their hanbi.</e>
<cmt>supposed not to →not suppoised to</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="24">
<j>衣冠は、本来、宮中に於ける宿直用の装束（とのいぎぬ）であったが、宮中での勤務服として定着するにつれ、束帯は儀式に用いる儀礼的な服となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ikan was originally a costume for nighttime (called tonoiginu) in the Imperial Court, however, sokutai became a formal costume which was used in ceremonies as ikan started to be fixed as a working costume in the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ikan (traditional formal court dress) was originally a costume for nighttime (called tonoiginu) in the Imperial Court, however, started to take root as a working costume in the Imperial Court, then sokutai became to be worn as a formal costume in ceremonies..</e>
<cmt>修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ikan (traditional formal court dress) was originally a costume for night duty (called tonoiginu) in the Imperial Court, however, it started to take root as a working costume in the Imperial Court, then sokutai became to be worn as a formal costume in ceremonies.</e>
<cmt>宿直用の意味抜けに対応しました。nighttime→night duty</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Hand-culveriN(id:50887), Masyu(id:31065), 神祇官(id:99217), 桜井悠士(id:72420), BOTarate(id:185620), Blue-comet(id:192801), Sakura-no-kuni(id:115977), Kawai(id:5634), Koba-chan(id:860), Point136(id:211299), NDR(id:5500), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>