<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>傘福</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kasafuku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kasafuku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kasafuku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>傘福（かさふく）とは、山形県酒田市周辺で飾られるつるし飾り。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kasafuku (傘福) is a hanging decoration seen around Sakata City, Yamagata Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>次の文にもう一つの漢字表記が出るため漢字も表記。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kasafuku is a hanging decoration seen around Sakata City, Yamagata Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>removed original Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kasafuku is a hanging decoration seen around Sakata City, Yamagata Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>笠福とも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kasafuku is also written as 笠福.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kasafuku is also written as 笠福.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kasafuku is also written as 笠福.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>発祥は定かではないが、江戸時代において酒田は米の積み出し港として栄え、北前航路（西廻り）を通じて京都との交流があったことから、おそらく北前船によって伝えられたものと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The birthplace is unclear, but it is thought that it was probably brought by Kitamaebune (a trading ship in Edo and Maiji period) because Sakata flourished as a rice port in Edo period and had contacts with Kyoto via Kitamae route (travelling west).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its origin is unclear, but it is thought that it was probably brought by Kitamaebune (a trading ship in Edo and Meiji period) because Sakata flourished as a rice port in Edo period and had contacts with Kyoto via Kitamae route (traveling west).</e>
<cmt>birthplace-&gt;origin; spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its origin is unclear, but it is thought that it was probably brought by Kitamaebune (a trading ship in Edo and Meiji period) because Sakata flourished as a rice port in Edo period and had contacts with Kyoto via Kitamae route (traveling west).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>また、1765年に酒田市の豪商・本間家3代本間光丘は、京都の祇園祭山鉾巡行に習い、山王祭りを盛大にすることによって酒田の町を活性化させようと京都の人形師に山車製作を依頼した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also in 1765, Mitsuoka HOMMA, the 3rd generation of the Homma family, a great merchant from Sakata City, asked a puppet maker in Kyoto for float production to stimulate the town of Sakata by a big Sanno Festival like Yamahoko-junko (a parade of beautifully decorated floats) of the Gion Festival in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also in 1765, Mitsuoka HOMMA, the 3rd generation of the Homma family and a great merchant from Sakata City, asked a puppet maker in Kyoto for float production to stimulate the town of Sakata with a big Sanno Festival like Yamahoko-junko (a parade of beautifully decorated floats) of the Gion Festival in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also in 1765, Mitsuoka HOMMA, the 3rd generation of the Homma family and a great merchant from Sakata City, asked a puppet maker in Kyoto for float production to stimulate the town of Sakata with a big Sanno Festival like Yamahoko-junko (a parade of beautifully decorated floats) of the Gion Festival in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>このとき運ばれてきた山車の上段にあった傘との関係も指摘されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The float that was delivered at that time had an umbrella on the upper stage and it is said that it may have something to do with Kasafuku.</e>
<cmt>酒田祭りの亀鉾の写真から傘は一つと推測しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The float that was delivered at that time had an umbrella on the upper stage and it is said that it may have something to do with Kasafuku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The float that was delivered at that time had an umbrella on the upper stage and it is said that it may have something to do with Kasafuku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>なお、この山車は酒田の亀ヶ崎城にちなんで亀鉾と呼ばれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The float is called Kamehoko after Kamegasaki-jo Castle in Sakata.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The float is called Kamehoko after Kamegasaki-jo Castle in Sakata.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The float is called Kamehoko after Kamegasaki-jo Castle in Sakata.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>現在、かつての本間家の別館は本間美術館となっており、庄内藩の御用商人だった風間家の1対の傘福が雛壇とともに飾られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The former annex of the Honma family is Honma museum now and is decorated with a pair of Kasafuku of Kazama family that was purveyor of the Shonai Domain, together with hina dolls on a tiered platform.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The former annex of the Honma family is Honma museum now and is decorated with a pair of Kasafuku once owned by the Kazama family who were purveyors of the Shonai Domain, together with hina dolls on a tiered platform.</e>
<cmt>of the-&gt;once owned by</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The former annex of the Honma family is Honma museum now and is decorated with a pair of Kasafuku once owned by the Kazama family who were purveyors of the Shonai Domain, together with hina dolls on a tiered platform.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>これが傘福と桃の節句を結びつける由縁のようになっているが、本来この風習は観音堂に安産や子供の成長を願って地元の神社に納めたものであり、昔から傘の中には魂が宿るといわれ子どもが健やかに育つことを思い、また様々な願いを形にして61種類の細工が吊り下げられているといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That&apos;s why Kasafuku is associated with Momo no (peach&apos;s) sekku (Doll・fs Festival on March 3), but Kasafukus were originally placed in local shrines to wish safe deliveries and childrens growth to Kannondo temples by hanging 61 kinds ornaments representing various wishes in each umbrella and wishing healthy growth of children because it had been said that souls are living in it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That&apos;s why Kasafuku is associated with the peach Doll Festival, but Kasafukus were originally placed in local shrines to wish for safe deliveries and children&apos;s growth to Kannondo temples by hanging 61 kinds ornaments representing various wishes in each umbrella and wishing for healthy growth of children because it had been said that souls are living in it.</e>
<cmt>prepositions; parentheses</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That&apos;s why Kasafuku is associated with the peach Doll Festival, but Kasafukus were originally placed in local shrines to wish for safe deliveries and children&apos;s growth to Kannondo temples by hanging 61 kinds ornaments representing various wishes in each umbrella and wishing for healthy growth of children because it had been said that souls are living in it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>近年、福岡柳川のさげもん、伊豆稲取の雛のつるし飾りと結び付けられ、三大つるし飾りと呼ばれるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In recent years, it has been called the three hanging decorations together with Sagemon from Yanagawa in Fukuoka and Hina no Tsurushikazari from Izuinatori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In recent years, it has been called the three hanging decorations together with Sagemon from Yanagawa in Fukuoka and Hina no Tsurushikazari from Izuinatori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In recent years, it has been called the three hanging decorations together with Sagemon from Yanagawa in Fukuoka and Hina no Tsurushikazari from Izu Inatori.</e>
<cmt>伊豆稲取の表記</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="11">
<j>2006年、酒田商工会議所女性会の創立25周年の記念事業として、6000個の細工を使用した盛大な傘福製作が行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 2006, as its 25th anniversary big celebrations of The Sakata Chamber of Commerce and Industry business women&apos;s club, Kasafukus decorated with 6,000 ornaments were made.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kasafukus decorated with 6,000 ornaments were made in 2006 for the 25th anniversary celebration the Sakata Chamber of Commerce and Industry business women&apos;s club.</e>
<cmt>prepositions; capitalization; order of phrases</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kasafukus decorated with 6,000 ornaments were made in 2006 for the 25th anniversary celebration the Sakata Chamber of Commerce and Industry business women&apos;s club.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>最大のものは直径200cmの傘の中に999個の細工をつるした高さ270cmの傘福が山王クラブに展示されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The biggest one is 270cm high with umbrella of 200 cm in diameter and 999 hanging ornaments in it and exhibited in Sanno Club (a tourist facility of Sakata City).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The biggest one is 270cm high with and umbrella of 200 cm in diameter and 999 hanging ornaments, which is exhibited in Sanno Club (a tourist facility of Sakata City).</e>
<cmt>and-&gt;which is</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The biggest one is 270cm high with and umbrella of 200 cm in diameter and 999 hanging ornaments, which is exhibited in Sanno Club (a tourist facility of Sakata City).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Mois(id:30596), ととりん(id:31982), 橄欖岩(id:24996), TAMA(id:25299), Kira727(id:100270), Hamasaki gion higashi(id:144985), Kitaken1977(id:57583), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>