<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>笛</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fue</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fue (an instrument producing sound with an air current)</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>笛（ふえ）は気流によって音を出す器具一般を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term &quot;Fue&quot; refers to tools which produce sound with an air current in general.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term &quot;fue&quot; generally refers to instruments which produce sound with an air current.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term &quot;fue&quot; generally refers to instruments which produce sound with an air current.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>元来「吹き鳴らすもの」を意味し、現在では楽器、玩具、合図、警報など広い用途で用いられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its original meaning was &quot;a tool which people toot&quot;, and such tools are being utilized for a variety of purposes at present, including musical instruments, toys, signals and alarms etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its original meaning was &quot;an instrument which is blown&quot;, and such instruments are currently utilized for a variety of purposes including musical instruments, toys, signals and alarms.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its original meaning was &apos;an instrument which is blown,&apos; and such instruments are currently utilized for a variety of purposes including musical instruments, toys, signals and alarms.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションの位置等を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>特にリード (楽器)エアリード構造のものを指すことが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term &quot;Fue&quot; often refers specifically to the ones that have air-reed structure (musical instrument).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term &quot;fue&quot; often refers specifically to the instruments which have reed.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term &quot;fue&quot; often refers specifically to musical instruments which have reed.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>語源は吹柄、吹枝（いずれもフキエないしフクエ）といわれるが異説も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This term is said to have derived from 吹柄 or 吹枝 (fukie or fukue), but there are a lot of other theories.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This term is said to have derived from 吹柄 or 吹枝 (fukie or fukue), but there are many other theories.</e>
<cmt>a lot of &gt; many</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This term is said to have derived from fukie (吹柄) or fukue (吹枝), but there are many other theories.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>文献上の初出は日本書紀の「天之鳥笛」であるが詳しい形状などは不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term &quot;ten no toribue&quot; (heaven&apos;s flute) is seen in Nihon Shoki (Chronicles of Japan), but the details, including its shape, are unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term &quot;ten no toribue&quot; (heaven&apos;s flute) is seen in Nihon Shoki (Chronicles of Japan), but details such as its shape are unknown.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term &apos;Ten no Toribue&apos; (heaven&apos;s flute) is seen in Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan), but details such as its shape are unknown.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>万葉仮名では「輔曳」と表記された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fue was written &quot;輔曳&quot; in Manyo-gana (a form of syllabary used in the Manyo-shu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fue was written &quot;輔曳&quot; in Manyo-gana (a form of syllabary used in the Manyo-shu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fue was written &apos;輔曳&apos; in Manyo-gana (a form of syllabary used in the Manyoshu [Collection of Ten Thousand Leaves])</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>奈良時代・平安時代において笛というと主に雅楽の管楽器であり、現在の龍笛（竜笛）、笙、篳篥、高麗笛、神楽笛のほか尺八、簫（しょう）なども用いられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Nara/Heian period, the term fue mainly referred to wind instruments for gagaku (ancient Japanese court dance and music), including ryuteki, sho (a traditinal Japanese wind instrument), hichiriki (doubled-reed wind instrument), komabue and kagurabue, which are being used at present, as well as shakuhachi (vertical bamboo flute) and sho (Chinese end-blown flute).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Nara and Heian periods, the term fue mainly referred to wind instruments for gagaku (ancient Japanese court dance and music), including the ryuteki, sho (a traditinal Japanese wind instrument), hichiriki (doubled-reed wind instrument), komabue and kagurabue which are still used today, as well as the shakuhachi (vertical bamboo flute) and sho (Chinese end-blown flute).</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Nara and Heian periods, the term fue mainly referred to wind instruments for gagaku (ancient Japanese court dance and music), including the ryuteki (literally, dragon flute), sho (笙, a traditional Japanese wind instrument), hichiriki (doubled-reed wind instrument), komabue (a flute imported from ancient Korea) and kagurabue (a six-holed horizontal flute) which are still used today, as well as the shakuhachi (vertical bamboo flute) and sho (簫, Chinese end-blown flute).</e>
<cmt>同音異義語を区別するために、漢字補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>このうち笙、篳篥は後に笛とは区別されるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sho and hichirili were later distingushed from fue.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sho and hichirili were later distingushed from fue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sho and hichiriki were later distinguished from fue.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>神楽笛は大和笛とも呼ばれることから、大陸から龍笛や高麗笛が伝来する以前の日本に、すでに笛が存在していたと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In view of the fact that Kagurabue is also called yamatobue, fue is believed to have existed in Japan even before ryuteki and komabue were imported from the Asian Continent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In view of the fact that the kagurabue is also called the yamatobue, fue are believed to have existed in Japan even before ryuteki and komabue were imported from the Asian Continent.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In view of the fact that the kagurabue is also called the yamatobue (literally, Japanese flute), fue are believed to have existed in Japan even before ryuteki and komabue were imported from the Asian Continent.</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>事実、奈良県天理市星塚一号古墳（古墳時代後期）から横笛と思しき遺物が出土している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In fact, something like yokobue (a flute) was excavated at Hoshizuka Kofun (tomb) No.1 (late of Kofun period (tumulus period)) in Tenri City, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In fact, an instrument resembling the yokobue (a flute) was excavated at Hoshizuka Kofun (tomb) No.1 (late of Kofun period (tumulus period)) in Tenri City, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact, an instrument resembling the yokobue (a flute) was excavated at Hoshizuka-kofun Tumulus No.1 (late of Kofun period [Tumulus period]) in Tenri City, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>ただし、これは奈良時代以降の横笛の形状とは異なる点も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, its shape is different from flutes produced in the Nara period and afterward.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, its shape is different from flutes produced since the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, its shape is different from flutes produced since the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>源氏物語にも種々の笛が登場するが、単に笛という場合は龍笛（竜笛）を指すことが多く、そのほかは「さくはちのふえ」（尺八）、「さうのふえ」（笙）、「こまぶえ」（高麗笛）などのように限定している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Various fue appears in &quot;The Tale of Genji&quot;, but fue usually refers to ryubue when it is used alone and others are specifically called &quot;sakuhachi no fue&quot; (shakuhachi), &quot;sau no fue&quot; (sho) or &quot;komabue &quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Various fue appear in &quot;The Tale of Genji&quot;, but the word fue usually refers to ryubue when used alone and others are specifically called &quot;sakuhachi no fue&quot; (shakuhachi), &quot;sau no fue&quot; (sho) or &quot;komabue.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Various fue also appear in Genji Monogatari (The Tale of Genji), but the word fue usually refers to ryuteki when used alone and others are specifically called &apos;sakuhachi no fue&apos; (shakuhachi), &apos;sau no fue&apos; (sho [笙]) or &apos;komabue.&apos;</e>
<cmt>読みなどを変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>物語中で笛の登場する場面は数多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;The Tale of Genji&quot;, there are a lot of scenes where fue appears.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;The Tale of Genji&quot;, there many situations in which fue appear.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Genji Monogatari, there many situations in which fue appear.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>なかでも柏木の遺品となった笛が夕霧の手を介して薫の手に渡るという形で、薫の出生の秘密に関わる重要な小道具として扱われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among others, fue was used as an important gadget relating to the secret of Kaoru&apos;s birth in the scene where fue which had belonged to Kashiwagi was delivered to Kaoru through Yugiri.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among these, a fue was used as an important item relating to the secret of Kaoru&apos;s birth in the scene in which a fue which had belonged to Kashiwagi was delivered to Kaoru through Yugiri.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among these, a fue was used as an important item relating to the secret of Kaoru&apos;s birth in the scene in which a fue which had belonged to late Kashiwagi was delivered to Kaoru through Yugiri.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>このように平安時代、笛は貴族の男性にとって音楽の教養の基本とされた楽器であり、村上天皇や一条天皇は笛の名手であったといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As seen from the above, fue was an indispensible musical instrument for male court nobles in the Heian period, and the Emperor Murakami and the Emperor Ichijo are said to have been masters of fue.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As shown above, fue were indispensible musical instruments for male court nobles during the Heian period, and Emperor Murakami and Emperor Ichijo are said to have been masters of fue.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As shown above, fue were indispensible musical instruments for male court nobles during the Heian period, and Emperor Murakami and Emperor Ichijo are said to have been masters of fue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>また、平敦盛や源義平にまつわる笛はいずれも「青葉の笛」と呼ばれて伝えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fue related to TAIRA no Atsumori and MINAOTO no Yoshihira has been passed down as &quot;Aoba no Fue&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A fue connected to TAIRA no Atsumori and MINAOTO no Yoshihira has been passed down as the &quot;Aoba no Fue&quot;.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A fue connected to TAIRA no Atsumori and MINAOTO no Yoshihira has been passed down as the &apos;Aoba no Fue&apos; (literally, the flute of green leaves).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変え、用語集に合わせ補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="18">
<j>平安中期以降の田楽は鼓や鉦を中心とするものであったが、絵巻物には笛も見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dengaku (a style of dancing and music performed in association with rice planting), which was born in the middle of Heian period, was performed mainly with tsuzumi (hand drum) and sho (gong), but fue is seen in some picture scrolls.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dengaku (a style of dancing and music performed in association with rice planting), which was created in the mid-Heian period, was performed mainly with tsuzumi (hand drums) and sho (gongs), but fue are seen in some picture scrolls.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dengaku (a style of dancing and music performed in association with rice planting), which was created since the mid-Heian period, was performed mainly with tsuzumi (hand drums) and sho (鉦, gongs), but fue are seen in some picture scrolls.</e>
<cmt>同音異義語に漢字を補足し、表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>田楽その他の芸能が発展して室町時代にその形を整えた能においても、世阿弥の頃までには能囃子の中に笛が取り入れられていたようである.</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Noh, which derived from Dengaku and other folk entertainments, formed its style in the Muromachi Period, and fue seems to have been introduced into Noh-hayashi (accompaniment of Noh) around the era of Zeami.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Noh, which derived from dengaku and other folk entertainments, developed its style in the Muromachi period, and fue seem to have been introduced into noh-hayashi (noh muciscal accompaniment) around the time of Zeami.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Noh, which derived from dengaku and other folk entertainments, developed its style in the Muromachi period, and fue seem to have been introduced into Noh-hayashi (Noh musical accompaniment) around the time of Zeami.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>ただし、それが現在の能管と同じものかはわかっていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it is unknown whether it was the same one with current Nohkan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is unknown whether these fue were the same as the current nohkan.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is unknown whether these fue were the same as the current Nohkan (a flute used in Noh play).</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>ヨーロッパのフルートは 1549年に鹿児島に到着したフランシスコ・ザビエルと共に日本に入ったことがポルトガル側の資料に残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the material existent in Portugal, European flute was imported into Japan when Francis Xavier arrived at Kagoshima in 1549.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Historical sources in Portugal, state that the European flute was imported into Japan when Francis Xavier arrived at Kagoshima in 1549.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Historical sources in Portugal, state that the European flute was imported into Japan when Francis Xavier arrived at Kagoshima in 1549.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="22">
<j>江戸時代盛んになった歌舞伎には主に能管、篠笛が用いられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nohkan and shinobue (Japanese bamboo flute) were mainly used for kabuki, which became popular in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nohkan and shinobue (Japanese bamboo flutes) were mainly used for kabuki, which became popular in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>flute &gt; flutes</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nohkan and shinobue (Japanese bamboo flutes) were mainly used for Kabuki (traditional drama performed by male actors), which became popular in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>庶民の祭礼（祭囃子）、神楽里神楽（里神楽）、獅子舞には篠笛が多く見られるが、龍笛や能管を用いる地方もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinobue was mainly used in ordinary people&apos;s rites and festival (matsuri-bayashi festival music)), satokagura (kagura dance held at somehere other than the imperial court) and/or shishimai (lion dance), but ryuteki or Nohkan was used in some regions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinobue were often used in the rites and festivals (matsuri-bayashi festival music) of common people, satokagura (kagura dances held at somehere other than the imperial court) and the shishimai (lion dance), but ryuteki or nohkan were used in some regions.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinobue were often used in the rites and festivals (matsuri-bayashi festival music) of common people, satokagura (kagura dances held at somewhere other than the imperial court) and the shishimai (lion dance), but ryuteki or Nohkan were used in some regions.</e>
<cmt>原文には「神楽里神楽（里神楽）」とありますが、リンク先の単語が抽出されるバグのようですので、「神楽（里神楽）」として訳出しております。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>また、鳥や虫などの擬音を出すさまざまな笛も江戸時代に登場し、庶民の玩具として人気となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, various types of fue which produce sound effects of birds or insects were invented in the Edo period, and they became popular toys for ordinary people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, various types of fue which produce the sounds of birds or insects were invented in the Edo period, and they became popular toys for common people.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, various types of fue which produce the sounds of birds or insects were invented in the Edo period, and they became popular toys for common people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>1853年に浦賀に着いたマシュー・ペリーの艦隊には楽隊が含まれており、この後、多くの西洋の楽器が日本に流入することになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A military band was on board Mathew Perry&apos;s fleet which arrived at Uraga in 1853, and many western instruments were imported into Japan since then.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A military band was on board Mathew Perry&apos;s fleet which arrived at Uraga in 1853, and many western instruments were imported into Japan after this time.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A military band was on board Mathew Perry&apos;s fleet which arrived at Uraga in 1853, and many western instruments were imported into Japan after this time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>そしてクラリネットやオーボエなど木管楽器も総じて笛と呼び習わし、金管楽器はラッパ（らっぱ）と呼ばれるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, the woodwind, such as clarinets and oboes, came to be called fue and the brass came to be called trumpets.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, woodwind instruments such as clarinets and oboes came to be called fue and brass instruments came to be called rappa.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, woodwind instruments such as clarinets and oboes came to be called fue and brass instruments came to be called rappa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="27">
<j>笛の分類</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Classification of Fue</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Classification of Fue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Classification of Fue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>笛という語が表す範囲はかなり広いため、ここではいくつかの異なる観点から分類している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The classification of Fue shown below was made from several viewpoints since the coverage of the term fue is rather wide.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The classification of Fue shown below was made from several viewpoints since the coverage of the term fue is rather wide.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The classification of fue shown below was made from several viewpoints since the coverage of the term fue is rather wide.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="29">
<j>楽器としての笛</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fue as musical instruments</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fue as Musical Instruments</e>
<cmt>Title case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fue as Musical Instruments</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>ジャンルによっては「笛」だけで特定の楽器を指すことがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Fue&quot; alone sometimes means a specific musical instrument in some genres of music.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The word &quot;Fue&quot; alone sometimes refers to a specific musical instrument in some genres of music.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The word &quot;fue&quot; alone sometimes refers to a specific musical instrument in some genres of music.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>例えば能楽では能管、民謡や多くの祭礼では篠笛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, it means Nohkan in the case of Noh and shinobue in the case of folk music and/or many of rites and festival.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, it means nohkan in the case of Noh and shinobue in the cases of folk music as well as many of rites and festivals.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, it means Nohkan in the case of Noh and shinobue in the cases of folk music as well as many of rites and festivals.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>これは明治以前の身分制と関係がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The above is related to the class system existed in the pre-Meiji period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is related to the class system that existed prior to the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is related to the class system that existed prior to the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="33">
<j>龍笛（竜笛、りゅうてき）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryuteki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryuteki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryuteki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>雅楽で用いられる横笛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryuteki is a yokobue that is used for Gagaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ryuteki is a yokobue that is used for gagaku.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;The&quot;Corrected capitalisation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A ryuteki is a yokobue that is used for gagaku.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>催馬楽や大和歌にも用いる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also used for Saibara (a kind of Heian-period Japanese court music) and Yamatouta.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also used in saibara (a kind of Heian-period Japanese court music) and yamatouta.</e>
<cmt>for &gt; inCorrected capitalisation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also used in saibara (a kind of Heian-period Japanese court music) and yamatouta (literally, Yamato&apos;s song).</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>横笛（おうじょう、ようじょう、おうてき）あるいは主笛（おもぶえ）とも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called 横笛 (ojo, yojo or oteki) or 主笛 (omoteki).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called the 横笛 (ojo, yojo or oteki) or 主笛 (omoteki).</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called ojo, yojo, or oteki (literally, transverse flute) or omobue (literally, main flute).</e>
<cmt>用語補足し、原文に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="37">
<j>神楽笛（かぐらぶえ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kagurabue</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kagurabue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kagurabue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>宮廷の御神楽（みかぐら）に用いられる横笛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kagurabue is a yokobue that is used for Mikagura (music performed in court ritual ceremonies) at the imperial court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The kagurabue is a yokobue that is used in mikagura (music performed in court ritual ceremonies) at the imperial court.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;The&quot;for &gt; inCorrected capitalisation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A kagurabue is a yokobue that is used in mikagura (music performed in court ritual ceremonies) at the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>龍笛よりやや低い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its tone is a little lower than that of ryuteki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its tone is a little lower than that of the ryuteki.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its tone is a little lower than that of the ryuteki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>神笛（しんてき）、大和笛（やまとぶえ）、太笛（ふとぶえ）ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called shinteki, yamatobue or futobue.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called the shinteki, yamatobue or futobue.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called the shinteki (flute of god), yamatobue or futobue (thick flute).</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="41">
<j>能管（のうかん）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nohkan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nohkan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nohkan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>能や歌舞伎で用いられる横笛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nohkan is a yokobue that is used for Noh and Kabuki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The nohkan is a yokobue that is used in noh and kabuki.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;The&quot;for &gt; inCorrected capitalisation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A Nohkan is a yokobue that is used in Noh and Kabuki.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>能笛（のうてき）ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called Nohteki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called the nohteki.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;Corrected capitalisation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called the Nohteki (flute for Noh play).</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="44">
<j>篠笛（しのぶえ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinobue</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinobue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinobue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>お祭り（祭囃子、神楽里神楽、獅子舞など）、民謡、歌舞伎・日本舞踊（邦楽囃子）などの舞台音楽、座敷音楽（端唄、小唄など）で用いられる横笛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinobue is a yokobue that is used for festivals (matsuri-bayashi, satokagura, shishimai etc.) stage music such as folk music, Kabuki and classical Japanese dance (hogaku-byashi (orchestra of Japanese classical music) and zashiki (tatami-room) music (hauta and kouta etc.).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shinobue is a yokobue that is used in festivals (matsuri-bayashi, satokagura, shishimai etc.) stage music such as folk music, kabuki and classical Japanese dance (hogaku-byashi (orchestra of Japanese classical music) and zashiki (tatami-room) music (hauta and kouta etc.).</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;The&quot;for &gt; inCorrected capitalisation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A shinobue is a yokobue that is used in festivals (matsuri-bayashi, satokagura, shishimai, and so on) stage music such as folk music, Kabuki and classical Japanese dance (hogaku-bayashi [orchestra of Japanese classical music]) and zashiki music (literally, music in tatami-room; hauta [a Japanese traditional song or ballad sung to the accompaniment of the samisen, Japanese banjo] and kouta [a ballad sung to samisen accompaniment], and so on).</e>
<cmt>原文には「神楽里神楽」とありますが、リンク先の単語が抽出されるバグのようですので、「里神楽」として訳出しております。三味線</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>しの、竹笛（たけぶえ）ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called shino or takebue.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called the shino or takebue.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called the shino or takebue (bamboo flute).</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="47">
<j>高麗笛（こまぶえ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Komabue (高麗笛)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Komabue (高麗笛)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Komabue (高麗笛)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>狛笛とも表記される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Komabue is also written as 狛笛.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Komabue is also written as 狛笛.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A komabue is also written as 狛笛 in Chinese characters.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>雅楽で使われる竹製の横笛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a bamboo yokobue that is used for Gagaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a bamboo yokobue that is used in gagaku.</e>
<cmt>for &gt; inCorrected capitalisation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a bamboo yokobue that is used in gagaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>高麗楽や東遊びにもちいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also used for komagaku (Korean music) and azuma-asobi.</e>
<cmt>東遊び→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also used for komagaku (Korean music) and azuma-asobi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is used for komagaku (Korean music) and Azuma-asobi (ancient chants and dances of the eastern islands of Japan, accompanied by musical instruments).</e>
<cmt>用語補足し、原文に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>細笛（ほそぶえ）ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called hosobue.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called the hosobue.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called the hosobue (thin flute).</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="52">
<j>歌笛（うたぶえ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Utabue</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Utabue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Utabue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>古く東遊び(あずまあそび)に用いた横笛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Utabue is a yokobue that was used in the past for azuma-asobi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The utabue is a yokobue that was used in azuma-asobi in ancient times.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An utabue is a yokobue that was used in Azuma-asobi in ancient times.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>高麗笛に似た形状でやや大形。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its shape is similar to that of komabue while its size is a little bigger.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its shape is similar to that of the komabue while it is a little larger in size.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its shape is similar to that of the komabue while it is a little larger in size.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>のちに高麗笛で代用することが一般化し用いられなくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was later replaced by komabue and fell into obscurity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was later replaced by the komabue and fell into obscurity.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was later replaced by the komabue and fell into obscurity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>中管（ちゅうかん）ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called chukan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called the chukan.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called the chukan (literally, middle-sized flute).</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="57">
<j>唐笛（とうてき）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toteki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toteki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toteki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>雅楽の唐楽にもちいる場合、龍笛の異称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toteki the another name of ryuteki when it is used for togaku (Tang music) of Gagaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toteki the another name for the ryuteki when it is used for togaku (Tang Dynasty music) in gagaku.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A toteki is another name for the ryuteki when it is used for togaku (Tang Dynasty music) in gagaku.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>または朝鮮の李王朝の雅楽に用いた横笛で、長さ45cm、音孔は6個（古くは8個）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, it is a yokobue of 45cm length with six tone holes (eight tone holes in the ancient time) that was used for Gagaku at the court of Yi dynasty Korea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, it is a yokobue of 45cm in length with six tone holes (eight tone holes in ancient times) that was used for gagaku at the court of Yi dynasty Korea.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, it is a yokobue of 45 centimeters in length with six tone holes (eight tone holes in ancient times) that was used for gagaku at the court of Yi dynasty, Korea.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="60">
<j>明笛（みんてき）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Minteli</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Minteli</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Minteki</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>明楽に用いる竹製の横笛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Minteki is a bamboo yokobue that is used for mingaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The minteki is a bamboo yokobue that is used in mingaku.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;The&quot;for &gt; in</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A minteki is a bamboo yokobue that is used in mingaku (Ming-era Chinese music).</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>明楽は1629年に日本に入った明朝の音楽で一時京都の上流社会で大流行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mingaku is Ming-era Chinese music that was imported into Japan in 1629 and it once became very popular among the people of high society in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mingaku is Chinese Ming Dynasty music that was imported into Japan in 1629 and it once became very popular among the people of high society in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>Ming-era Chinese &gt; Chinese Ming Dynasty</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mingaku is Chinese Ming Dynasty music that was imported into Japan in 1629 and it once became very popular among the people of high society in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>マウスピース (楽器)歌口から先の頭部が細く、音孔は6個。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has six tone holes and its head becomes thinner from the position of mouthpiece.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has six tone holes and its head becomes thinner from the position of mouthpiece.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has six tone holes and its head becomes thinner from the position of mouthpiece.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>吹き口と指孔の間に竹紙（竹の内側の皮）を張るための響孔があるのが特徴。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its characteristic is having a sound hole for putting up bamboo paper (the inner skin of bamboo) between its mouth and finger holes.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is characteristic for hole used to cover with bamboo paper (the inner skin of bamboo) between its mouth and finger holes.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is characteristic for hole used to cover with bamboo paper (the inner skin of bamboo) between its mouth and finger holes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>清楽の流入とともに清笛にとって替わられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was replaced by shinteki after Shingaku (Zing-era Chinese music) was imported.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was replaced by the shinteki after shingaku (Zing-era Chinese music) was imported.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;Corrected capitalisation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was replaced by the shinteki (flute for shingaku) after shingaku (Zing-era Chinese music) was imported.</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>また、清笛を含めて明笛ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Minteki and Shinteki are sometimes collectively called Minteki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Minteki and shinteki are sometimes collectively called Minteki.</e>
<cmt>Corrected capitalisation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Minteki and shinteki are sometimes collectively called Minteki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>日本の祭囃子に用いられる6孔の篠笛の中には、明笛あるいは清笛が簡素化したと思われるものもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some shinobue with six tone holes that are used for Japanese matsuri-bayashi seem to be the simplified ones of minteli or shinteki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some shinobue with six tone holes that are used for Japanese matsuri-bayashi are thought to be simplified of minteki or shinteki.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.Spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some shinobue with six tone holes that are used for Japanese matsuri-bayashi are thought to be simplified of minteki or shinteki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="68">
<j>清笛（しんてき）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinteki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinteki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinteki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>清楽に用いる竹製の横笛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinteki is a bamboo yokobue that is used for shingaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shinteki is a bamboo yokobue that is used in shingaku.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;The&quot;for &gt; inCorrected capitalisation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A shinteki is a bamboo yokobue that is used in shingaku.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>清楽は文化文政の幕末に入った清朝の音楽で世俗に流行し、明清楽とも言われるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shingaku is Quin-era Chinese music that was imported in the Bunka-Bunsei era of Edo period, and it bacame popular among ordinary people and was also called Minshingaku (Ming &amp; Xing-era Chinese music).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shingaku is Chinese Qing Dynasty music that was imported in the Bunka-Bunsei era of the Edo period, and it bacame popular among ordinary people, also being called minshingaku (Ming &amp; Qing-era Chinese music).</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.Spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shingaku is Chinese Qing Dynasty music that was imported in the Bunka-Bunsei era (1786 to 1841) of the Edo period, and it became popular among ordinary people, also being called minshingaku (Ming and Qing-era Chinese music).</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>形状は明笛とほぼ同じで律は異なる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its shape is similar to that of minteki while the tune is different.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its shape is similar to that of minteki while the tune is different.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its shape is similar to that of minteki while the tune is different.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>明笛とあまり区別されない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is seldom distinguished from minteki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is seldom distinguished from minteki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is seldom distinguished from minteki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>日清戦争に際して明清楽は制限されたが、明笛（清笛）は長音階になっていることから大正時代まで青少年に愛奏された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although playing minshingaku was restricted when the First Sino-Japanese war occurred, minteki (shinteki) was favored by youngsters because of its major scale.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although playing minshingaku was restricted during the First Sino-Japanese War, minteki (shinteki) was favored by young people because of its major scale.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although playing minshingaku was restricted during the Sino-Japanese War, minteki (shinteki) was favored by young people until Taisho period because of its major scale.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ。「大正時代まで」を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="74">
<j>笙</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sho (笙)</e>
<cmt>同音異義語があるため漢字補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>雅楽で用いられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sho is used for Gagaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sho is used in gagaku.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;The&quot;for &gt; inCorrected capitalisation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A sho (笙) is used in gagaku.</e>
<cmt>同音異義語があるため漢字補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>笙の笛ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called sho no fue (flute of sho).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called &apos;sho no fue.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called &apos;sho no fue&apos; (sho, the flute).</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>子守唄の歌詞に「でんでん太鼓に笙の笛」というものがあるが笙は市井の楽器ではないためこれは別のものを指すと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A phrase &quot;denden-daiko ni sho no fue&quot; is seen in a lullaby, but this is considered to be the another one since sho was not a musical instrument for ordinary people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The phrase &quot;denden-daiko ni sho no fue&quot; is seen in a lullaby, but this is considered to be a different instrument because sho was not a musical instrument for common people.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The phrase &apos;denden-daiko ni sho no fue&apos; (a small toy drum and sho flute) is seen in a lullaby, but this is considered to be a different instrument because sho was not a musical instrument for common people.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="78">
<j>竽（う）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">U</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">U</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">U</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>奈良時代に中国から伝わった竹製の楽器。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">U is a bamboo instrument that was imported from China in the Nara period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The u is a bamboo instrument that was imported from China during the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;The&quot;in &gt; during</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An u is a bamboo instrument that was imported from China during the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>大型の笙で、笙より1オクターブ低く雅楽に用いられたが、平安中期に廃れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a large-size sho whose tone was lower than that of sho by an octave and was once used for Gagaku, but it became obsolete in the middle of Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a large sho whose tone is an octave lower than that of the sho and was once used in gagaku, but it became obsolete in the middle of Heian period.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a large sho whose tone is an octave lower than that of the sho and was once used in gagaku, but it became obsolete in the middle of Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>竽の笛ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called &quot;u no fue&quot; (flute of U)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called &quot;u no fue&quot; (flute of U)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called &apos;u no fue&apos; (u, the flute)</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="82">
<j>簫（しょう）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sho (簫)</e>
<cmt>同音異義語があるため漢字補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>中国の竹製縦笛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sho is a Chinese bamboo tatebue (vertical flute).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sho is a Chinese bamboo tatebue (vertical flute).</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;The&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A sho (簫) is a Chinese bamboo tatebue (vertical flute).</e>
<cmt>同音異義語があるため漢字補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>竹管一本で指孔のあるものを洞簫（どうしょう）、指孔なしで長短数本を一組にしたパンパイプ型のものを排簫（はいしょう）と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That of one bamboo pipe with finger holes is called dosho and that of panpipe-type, which is a set of several long-and-short pipes and has no finger holes, is called haisho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those consisting of one bamboo pipe with finger holes is called the dosho, while panpipe-type ones comprised of a set of several long and short pipes with no finger holes is called the haisho.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those consisting of one bamboo pipe with finger holes is called the dosho, while panpipe-type ones comprised of a set of several long and short pipes with no finger holes is called the haisho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="85">
<j>尺八</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shakuhachi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shakuhachi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shakuhachi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>マダケで作られた、長さ約54.5cm（一尺八寸）の縦笛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shakuhachi is a 54.5 centimeter (isshaku hassun)-long tatebue made of madake (Japanese timber bamboo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shakuhachi is a 1 shaku 8 sun (54.5cm) long tatebue made of madake (Japanese timber bamboo).</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A shakuhachi is a one shaku eight sun (54.5 centimeters) long tatebue made of madake (Japanese timber bamboo).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>用途によって、より長いものや短いものも使用される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Depending on purposes, the longer one or the shorter one is also used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Long or short variants may be used depending on the purpose.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Long or short variants may be used depending on the purpose.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>雅楽の尺八に由来するとされるが、詳細は明らかでない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although it is believed to have derived from shakuhachi used in Gagaku, details are unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although it is believed to have derived from the shakuhachi used in gagaku, details are unknown.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;Corrected capitalisation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it is believed to have derived from the shakuhachi used in gagaku, details are unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>江戸時代に虚無僧によって全国に広まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was spread across the nation by komuso (begging Zen priest of the Fuke sect) in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was spread throughout the nation by komuso (begging Zen priests of the Fuke sect) during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was spread throughout the nation by komuso (begging Zen priests of the Fukeshu sect) during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>明治維新で虚無僧が廃止されると民間へも普及した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After komuso was banned by Meiji Restoration, it spread among ordinary people.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After komuso were abolished by the Meiji Restoration, it spread among ordinary people.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After komuso were abolished by the Meiji Restoration, it spread among ordinary people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>古典本曲（独奏・重奏曲）、三曲合奏、民謡の伴奏などに用いられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is used for koten-honkyoku (traditional Japanese music) (solo, multiple instrumental music), sankyoku-gasso (a type of ensemble method) and/or the accompaniment of folk music.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is used in koten-honkyoku (traditional Japanese music) (solo, multiple instrumental music), sankyoku-gasso (a type of ensemble method) and the accompaniment of folk music.</e>
<cmt>for &gt; inand/or &gt; and</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is used in koten-honkyoku (traditional Japanese music) (solo, multiple instrumental music), sankyoku-gasso (a type of ensemble method) and the accompaniment of folk music.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>現在は、真竹の根元を用い、管内に漆などの「地」（じ）を塗り重ねる内径調整によって調律されたものが一般的である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At present, products which use the root of madake as material and were tuned by laying &quot;ji&quot; (paste), such as lacquer, on the inside of the pipe are generally used.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At present, products which use the root of the madake as material and are tuned by applying &quot;ji&quot; (paste), such as lacquer, on the inside of the pipe are generally used.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At present, products which use the root of the madake as material and are tuned by applying &apos;ji&apos; (paste), such as lacquer, on the inside of the pipe are generally used.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>しかし、内径加工を行わない「地無し管」も愛好されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, products whose inside are not lacquered, which is called &quot;jinashi-kan&quot; (flute made without lacquering), are also favored by not a few people.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, instruments called &quot;jinashi-kan&quot; which are not lacquered on the inside are also favored by many.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, instruments called &apos;jinashi-kan&apos; (shakuhachi without ji) which are not lacquered on the inside are also favored by many.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変え用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="94">
<j>一節切（ひとよぎり）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hitoyogiri</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hitoyogiri</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hitoyogiri</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>長さ約34cmで管の中央に節が一つある真竹の縦笛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hitoyogiri is a 34 centimeter-long madake tatebue which has a bamboo joint in the center of pipe.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The hitoyogiri is a 34cm long madake tatebue which has a bamboo joint in the center of pipe.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;The&quot;34 centimeter-long &gt; 34cm long</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A hitoyogiri is a 34-centimeter long madake tatebue which has a bamboo joint in the center of pipe.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>「一節切尺八」とも呼ばれ、尺八と相互に影響があったと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called &quot;hitoyogiri shakuhachi&quot;, and it is considered that hitoyogiri and shakuhachi were mutually affected each other.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called &quot;hitoyogiri shakuhachi&quot;, and it is though that the hitoyogiri and shakuhachi had a mutual influence on one another.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called &apos;hitoyogiri shakuhachi,&apos; and it is though that the hitoyogiri and shakuhachi had a mutual influence on one another.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="97">
<j>天吹（てんぷく）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tenpuku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tenpuku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tenpuku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>一節切に似た真竹の縦笛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tenpuku is a madake tatebue that resembles to hitoyogiri.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The tenpuku is a madake tatebue that resembles the hitoyogiri.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;The&quot;to &gt; the</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The tenpuku is a madake tatebue that resembles the hitoyogiri.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="99">
<j>オークラウロ（オークラロ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Okura-aulos (Okurora)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Okura-aulos (Okurora)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Okura-Aulos (or Okuraulo)</e>
<cmt>読み修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>1935年に大倉喜七郎の希望により、フルート奏者平林が開発した楽器で、フルートの管体に尺八の吹口をつけた金属製の縦笛である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Okura-aulos is a metal-made tatebue, which was invented by a flute player Hirabayashi in response to the request by Kihachiro OKURA, that consists of a flute pipe and a shakuhachi mouth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The okura-aulos is a metal-made tatebue, which was invented in 1935 by the flute player Hirabayashi in response to a request by Kihachiro OKURA, that consists of a flute pipe and a shakuhachi mouth.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;The&quot;a &gt; thethe &gt; a</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An okura-aulos is a metal-made tatebue, which was invented in 1935 by the flute player Hirabayashi in response to a request by Kihachiro OKURA, that consists of a flute pipe and a shakuhachi mouth.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>ピッコロ、ソプラニーノ、ソプラノ、アルト、テノール、バスの6種が作られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Six types of products, piccolo, sopranino, soprano, alt, tenor and bass, were produced.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Piccolo, sopranino, soprano, alt, tenor and bass versions were produced.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Six versions such as Piccolo, sopranino, soprano, alt, tenor, and bass were produced.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせ表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>アンサンブルとして一時成功したが、その後はほとんど演奏されない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were once successfully-played as instruments for ensemble but have been seldom played since then.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were briefly popular as ensemble instruments but have seldom ben played since.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were briefly popular as ensemble instruments but have seldom been played since.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="25">
<sen id="103">
<j>リコーダー、フルート等</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Recorder, flute etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Recorder, flute, etc.</e>
<cmt>Added comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Recorder, flute, and so on</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>クラリネットやオーボエなどの木管楽器</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The woodwind such as clarinet and oboe.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Woodwind such as the clarinet and oboe.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Woodwind such as the clarinet and oboe.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>笛子（てきし：DIZI）現代の中国の笛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tekishi (DIZI) : contemporary Chinese Fue.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tekishi contemporary Chinese fue.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tekishi (dizi): Contemporary Chinese fue.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>ディーズともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called DIZI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is called the dizi in Chinese.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for accuracy.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is called the dizi in Chinese.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>笛子にはC管D管などの曲笛やF管G管などのホウ笛（梆笛）がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tekishi is divided into two types; kyokuteki, products of C tune pipe and D tune pipe, and hoteki, products of F tune pipe and G tune pipe.</e>
<cmt>C管、Ｄ管、Ｆ管、Ｇ管→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tekishi are divided into two types; kyokuteki of pitch C or D, and hoteki of pitch F and G.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tekishi are divided into two types; kyokuteki of pitch C or D, and hoteki of pitch F and G.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>清笛や明笛はこの先祖にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinteki and minteki are its ancestors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shinteki and minteki are its precursors.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The shinteki and minteki are its precursors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="26">
<sen id="109">
<j>材料によるもの</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Classification based on the material</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Classification by Material</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Classification by Material</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>石笛（いわぶえ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Iwabue (石笛)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Iwabue (石笛)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Iwabue (石笛)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>古代の遺跡から穴の開いた石が発掘されることがあり、楽器ではないかという意見がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Stone with holes are sometimes found at ancient remains, and some people say these might be musical instruments.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Stones with holes are sometimes found at ancient ruins, and there is the opinion that these might be musical instruments.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Stones with holes are sometimes found at ancient ruins, and there is the opinion that these might be musical instruments.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>人工的に穴が穿たれたもの、自然に穴の開いたものがあり、貫通型と非貫通型もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some holes are artificially bored ones while some are natural ones, and some holes are bored through stones while some are not.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some holes are artificially bored while some are natural, and some holes completely penetrate the stones while others do not.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some holes are artificially bored while some are natural, and some holes completely penetrate the stones while others do not.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="113">
<j>大きいものは磐笛と書く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Large-size ones are written 磐笛 (iwabue)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Large ones are written 磐笛 (iwabue)</e>
<cmt>Large-size &gt; Large</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Large ones are written as 磐笛 (iwabue) in Chinese characters.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="27">
<sen id="114">
<j>角笛</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsunobue</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsunobue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunobue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>動物の角で作った笛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a fue made of a horn.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A fue made of a horn.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;It is&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A fue made of a horn.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="116">
<j>日本では角がそれほど入手できなかったため、ホラガイの方が一般的であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan, conches were generally used since horns couldn&apos;t be obtained easily..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan, conches were generally used since horns could not be obtained easily..</e>
<cmt>couldn&apos;t &gt; could not</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan, conches were generally used since horns could not be obtained easily.</e>
<cmt>余分なピリオドを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="28">
<sen id="117">
<j>葦笛（あしぶえ、よしぶえ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ashibue/yoshibue</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ashibue/Yoshibue</e>
<cmt>Title case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ashibue (also known as Yoshibue)</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="118">
<j>葦の葉を巻いて作った草笛、あるいは葦の茎で作った縦笛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ashibue/yoshibue is a kusabue (reed pipe) produced by winding up blades of grass or tatebue made of a stalk of reed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An ashibue/yoshibue is a kusabue (reed pipe) produced by winding up reeds grass or a tatebue made from the stalk of a reed.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ashibue is a kusabue (reed pipe) produced by winding up reeds grass or a tatebue made from the stalk of a reed.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="119">
<j>蘆笛と書いて「ろてき」ないし「あしぶえ」ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called &quot;roteki&quot; or &quot;ashibue&quot; by using Chinese character 蘆笛.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called the &quot;roteki&quot; or &quot;ashibue&quot; and written &quot;蘆笛.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called the &apos;roteki&apos; or &apos;ashibue&apos; and written as &apos;蘆笛.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="29">
<sen id="120">
<j>柴笛</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Murasakibue</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Murasakibue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Murasakibue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="121">
<j>樫や椎などの若葉の一端を唇に当てて吹き鳴らすもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Murasakibue means producing a sound by blowing a young leaf of oak or chinquapin that is being pushed against the lips.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The production of sound by blowing a young leaf of oak or chinquapin that is pushed against the lips.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The production of sound by blowing a young leaf of oak or chinquapin that is pushed against the lips.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="30">
<sen id="122">
<j>草笛</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kusabue</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kusabue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kusabue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="123">
<j>草の葉や茎をリード (楽器)及び共鳴管として音を出すものの総称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kusabue is a general term that refers to things which produce a sound by using a blade or a stalk of grass as a reed (musical instrument) and a resonant tube.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kusabue is a general term that refers to instruments which produce a sound by using a blade or a stalk of grass as a reed (musical instrument) and a resonant tube.</e>
<cmt>things &gt; instruments</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A kusabue is a general term that refers to instruments which produce a sound by using a blade or a stalk of grass as a reed (musical instrument) and a resonant tube.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="124">
<j>また、日本では素人作りの田舎じみた竹の横笛（篠笛）を指す場合がある（草競馬、草野球などと同様の用法）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan, it sometimes refers to a rustic bamboo yokobue (shinobue) produced by an amateur (as with the case of kusayakyu (sandlot baseball) or kusakeiba (local horse race).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan, it sometimes refers to a rustic bamboo yokobue (shinobue) produced by an amateur (as is the case for the use of the &quot;kusa&quot; prefix in kusayakyu (sandlot baseball) or kusakeiba (local horse race).</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency and clarification.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan, it sometimes refers to a rustic bamboo yokobue (shinobue) produced by an amateur (as is the case for the use of the &quot;kusa&quot; prefix in kusayakyu [sandlot baseball] or kusakeiba [local horse race]).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="31">
<sen id="125">
<j>麦笛</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mugibue</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mugibue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mugibue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="126">
<j>麦の茎を使った草笛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mugibue is a kind of kusabue using a stalk of barley.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The mugibue is a tyoe of kusabue using a stalk of barley.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A mugibue is a type of kusabue using a stalk of barley.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="127">
<j>夏の季語。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This word is a season word of summer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a haiku seasonal word for summer.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a haiku (Japanese 17-syllable poem) seasonal word for summer.</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="32">
<sen id="128">
<j>笹笛</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sasabue</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sasabue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sasabue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="129">
<j>笹の葉を使った草笛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sasabue is a kind of kusabue using a bamboo leaf.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sasabue is a type of kusabue using a bamboo leaf.</e>
<cmt>kind &gt; type</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A sasabue is a type of kusabue using a bamboo leaf.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="33">
<sen id="130">
<j>瓢（ひょん）の笛</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hyon no fue</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hyon no Fue</e>
<cmt>Title case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hyon no Fue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="131">
<j>イスノキの葉にできた壺形の虫こぶを瓢の実といい、その中の虫が飛び出して中空になったものを笛として吹き鳴らすもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A jar-shaped knock on the leaf of isunoki (a kind of tree) in which an insect resides is called hyon no mi (nut of hyon), and people produce a sound by blowing it after it became a hollow with an insect flown out.</e>
<cmt>イスノキ→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The jar-shaped gall on the leaf of the Distylium racemosum tree is known as a &apos;hyon no mi&apos; (lit. hyon nut) and the empty gall that remains when the insect has left is blown as a fue.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A jar-shaped gall on the leaf of the Distylium racemosum tree is known as a &apos;hyon no mi&apos; (literally, hyon nut) and the empty gall that remains when the insect has left is blown as a fue.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="132">
<j>秋の季語。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This word is a season word of autumn.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a haiku seasonal word for autumn.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a haiku seasonal word for autumn.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="34">
<sen id="133">
<j>音色による者</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Classification based on the tone quality</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Classification by Tone</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Classification by Tone</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="134">
<j>芝居（歌舞伎の下座音楽など）の効果音として使うもの、狩で獲物を誘い出すために使うものが多く、玩具としても使われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many kinds of fue are used for the purpose of producing sound effects of plays (geza (off-stage) music of Kabuki etc) or luring game, and some are also used as toys.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many kinds of fue are used to produce sound effects for plays (geza (off-stage) music for kabuki etc.) or luring game, and some are also used as toys.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many kinds of fue are used to produce sound effects for plays (geza [off-stage] music for Kabuki, and so on) or luring game, and some are also used as toys.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="35">
<sen id="135">
<j>赤子笛</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akagobue</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akagobue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akagobue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="136">
<j>赤ん坊の泣き声を出す竹製の笛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akagobue is a bamboo fue that produces the sound like baby&apos;s cry.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An akagobue is a bamboo fue that produces the sound like a baby&apos;s cry.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;An&quot;Added &quot;a&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An akagobue is a bamboo fue that produces the sound like a baby&apos;s cry.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="137">
<j>ダブルリードをもつ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has a double-reed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has a double-reed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has a double-reed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="138">
<j>芝居で使われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is used for plays.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is used for plays.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is used for plays.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="36">
<sen id="139">
<j>鶯笛</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Uguisubue</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Uguisubue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Uguisubue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="140">
<j>鶯（うぐいす）の鳴き声を出す竹製ないし陶製の笛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Uguisubue is a bamboo or pottery fue that produces the sound of bush warbler.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An uguisubue is a bamboo or ceramic fue that produces the sound of the Japanese bush warbler.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency and accuracy.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An uguisubue is a bamboo or ceramic fue that produces the sound of the Japanese bush warbler.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="141">
<j>中に水を入れて使うものもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some of them are used with water inside.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some are used with water inside.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;of them&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some are used with water inside.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="142">
<j>初音の笛ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called hatsune no fue.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called a hatsune no fue.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;a&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called &apos;hatsune no fue.&apos;</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="143">
<j>春の季語。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This word is a season word of spring.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a haiku seasonal word for spring.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a haiku seasonal word for spring.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="37">
<sen id="144">
<j>牛</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ushi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ushi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ushi (literally, a cow)</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="145">
<j>牛の鳴き声を出す竹製の笛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ushi is a bamboo fue that produces the cry of cattle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A bamboo fue that produces the sound of cattle.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A bamboo fue that produces the sound of cattle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="146">
<j>芝居で使われたが、現在はほとんど使用されない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was once used in plays, but it is seldom used at present.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was once used in plays, but it is rarely used any more.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was once used in plays, but it is rarely used any more.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="38">
<sen id="147">
<j>馬</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Uma</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Uma</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Uma (literally, a horse)</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="148">
<j>馬の鳴き声を出す竹製の笛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Uma is a bamboo fue that produces the cry of horse.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A bamboo fue that produces the sound of a horse.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A bamboo fue that produces the sound of a horse.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="149">
<j>芝居で使われたが、演奏法が難しいため現在は実際の馬の鳴き声を録音したものが使われることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although it was once used in plays, the recording of the cry of horse is usually used at present because playing uma is difficult.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although it was once used in plays, a recording of a horse is usually used nowadays because of the difficulty of playing the uma.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it was once used in plays, a recording of a horse is usually used nowadays because of the difficulty of playing the uma.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="39">
<sen id="150">
<j>鶉笛</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Uzurabue</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Uzurabue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Uzurabue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="151">
<j>鶉（うずら）の鳴き声に似た音を出す笛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Uzurabue is a fue that produces a uzura (Japanese quail)-like sound.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A fue that produces a sound similar to an uzura (Japanese quail).</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A fue that produces a sound similar to an uzura (Japanese quail).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="152">
<j>鶉狩りで鶉を誘い寄せるために使う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is used for luring uzura in uzura hunting.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is used for luring uzura during uzura hunting.</e>
<cmt>in &gt; during</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is used for luring uzura during uzura hunting.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="153">
<j>また、雅楽で横笛を短い拍子で吹くこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This term also means to play a yokobue with short rhythm in Gagaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This term also means to play a yokobue in short beats in gagaku.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This term also means to play a yokobue in short beats in gagaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="40">
<sen id="154">
<j>烏笛</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Karasubue</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Karasubue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Karasubue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="155">
<j>烏（からす）の鳴き声を出す竹製の笛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Karasubue is a bamboo fue that produces the sound of crow.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A bamboo fue that produces the sound of a crow.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A bamboo fue that produces the sound of a crow.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="156">
<j>ダブルリードをもつ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has a double-reed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has a double-reed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has a double-reed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="157">
<j>芝居で使われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is used in plays.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is used in plays.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is used in plays.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="41">
<sen id="158">
<j>雉笛</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kijibue</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kijibue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kijibue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="159">
<j>雉（きじ）の鳴き声に似た音を出す笛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kijibue is a flute that produces a kiji (Japanese pheasant)-like sound.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A fue that produces a sound similar to a kiji (Japanese pheasant).</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency and consistency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A fue that produces a sound similar to a kiji (Japanese pheasant).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="160">
<j>猟師が雉を誘い出すために使う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hunters use it in order to lure kiji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hunters use it in order to lure kiji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hunters use it in order to lure kiji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="161">
<j>春の季語</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This word is a season word of spring.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a haiku seasonal word for spring.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a haiku seasonal word for spring.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="42">
<sen id="162">
<j>水鶏笛（くいなぶえ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kuinabue</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kuinabue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kuinabue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="163">
<j>クイナの鳴き声に似た音を出す笛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kuinabue is a fue that produces a kuina (water rail)-like sound.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A fue that produces a sound similar to a kuina (water rail).</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A fue that produces a sound similar to a kuina (water rail).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="164">
<j>クイナを誘い出すために使う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is used for luring water rails.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is used for luring water rails.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is used for luring kuina.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="165">
<j>夏の季語。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This word is a season word of summer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a haiku seasonal word for summer.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a haiku seasonal word for summer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="43">
<sen id="166">
<j>駒笛、駒鳥笛（こまぶえ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Komabue</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Komabue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Komabue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="167">
<j>コマドリの鳴き声に似た音を出す笛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Komabue is a fue that produces a komadori (Japanese robbin)-like sound.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A fue that produces a sound similar to a komadori (Japanese robbin).</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency and consistency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A fue that produces a sound similar to a komadori (Japanese robin).</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="168">
<j>猟に使う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is used in hunting.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is used in hunting.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is used in hunting.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="44">
<sen id="169">
<j>鹿笛（しかぶえ、ししぶえ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shikabue/Shishibue</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shikabue/Shishibue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shikabue (also known as Shishibue)</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="170">
<j>鹿の鳴く声に似た音を出す笛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shikabue/Shishibue is a fue that produces a shika (dear)-like sound.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A fue that produces a sound similar to a shika dear.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency and consistency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A fue that produces a sound similar to a shika dear.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="171">
<j>この笛で雌鹿の鳴き声を出し、寄ってきた牡鹿を猟師が討つために使う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hunters lure stags by making the sound of doe and hunt them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is used by hunters lure stags by making the sound of doe.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is used by hunters to lure stags to be shot by making the sound of doe.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="172">
<j>アイヌが用いていたものはイテレップという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">What Ainus used in the past is called itereppu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That which was used by the Ainu people is calle a itereppu.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That which was used by the Ainu people is called a itereppu.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="45">
<sen id="173">
<j>蝉笛</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Semibue</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Semibue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Semibue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="174">
<j>蝉の鳴き声を出す竹製の笛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Semibue is a bamboo fue that produces the sound of cicada.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A bamboo fue that produces the sound of a cicada.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A bamboo fue that produces the sound of a cicada.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="175">
<j>特にヒグラシやミンミンゼミの鳴き声のものがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some of them are specifically crafted to make the sound of evening cicada or robust cicada.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some are specifically crafted to make the sound of the evening cicada or robust cicada.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some are specifically crafted to make the sound of the evening cicada or robust cicada.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="176">
<j>蝉の模造を飾りとして付けたものが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A dummy of cicada is attached to many of products.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many have an imitation attached.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many have an imitation of cicada attached.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="46">
<sen id="177">
<j>千鳥</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chidori</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chidori</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chidori</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="178">
<j>千鳥の鳴き声に似た音を出す笛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chidori is a fue that produces a chidori (plover)-like sound.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A fue that produces a sound similar to a chidori (plover).</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency and consistency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A fue that produces a sound similar to a chidori (plover).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="179">
<j>芝居で使われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is used in plays.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is used in plays.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is used in plays.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="47">
<sen id="180">
<j>トヒヨ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tohiyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tohiyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tohiyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="181">
<j>とんびの鳴き声に似た音を出す笛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tohiyo is a fue that produces a tonbi (kite)-like sound.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A fue that produces a sound similar to a tonbi (kite).</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency and consistency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A fue that produces a sound similar to a tonbi (kite).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="182">
<j>芝居で使われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is used in plays.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is used in plays.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is used in plays.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="48">
<sen id="183">
<j>鳥笛</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toribue</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toribue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toribue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="184">
<j>鳥の鳴き声に似た音を出す笛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toribue is a fue that produces a birdsong-like sound.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A fue that produces a sound resembling birdsong.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency and consistency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A fue that produces a sound resembling birdsong.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="185">
<j>または鳥の形をした笛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It also refers to a bird-shaped fue.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It also refers to a bird-shaped fue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It also refers to a bird-shaped fue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="49">
<sen id="186">
<j>鶏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Niwatori</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Niwatori</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Niwatori</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="187">
<j>ニワトリの鳴き声に似た音を出す笛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Niwatori is a fue that produces a rooster-like sound.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A fue that produces a sound similar to a rooster.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency and consistency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A fue that produces a sound similar to a rooster.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="188">
<j>芝居で使われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is used in plays.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is used in plays.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is used in plays.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="50">
<sen id="189">
<j>鳩笛</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hatobue</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hatobue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hatobue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="190">
<j>ハトの鳴き声を出す笛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hatobue is a fue that produces the sound of pigeon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A fue that produces the sound of a pigeon.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency and consistency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A fue that produces the sound of a pigeon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="191">
<j>狩りで鳥を呼ぶのに使う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is used in hunting for luring birds.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is used to lure birds while hunting.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is used to lure birds while hunting.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="192">
<j>またはハトの形をした素焼きなどのおもちゃの笛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It also refers to a pigeon-shaped toy fue made of unglazed pottery.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It also refers to a pigeon-shaped toy fue made of unglazed pottery.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It also refers to a pigeon-shaped toy fue made of unglazed pottery.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="193">
<j>オカリナを指すこともある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It sometimes refers to an ocarina.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It sometimes refers to an ocarina.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It sometimes refers to an ocarina.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="51">
<sen id="194">
<j>雲雀笛（ひばりぶえ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hibaribue</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hibaribue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hibaribue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="195">
<j>ヒバリの鳴き声を出す竹製の笛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hibaribue is a bamboo fue that produces the sound of hibari (skylark).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A bamboo fue that produces the sound of a hibari (skylark).</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency and consistency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A bamboo fue that produces the sound of a hibari (skylark).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="196">
<j>春の季語。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This word is a season word of spring.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a haiku seasonal word for spring.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency and consistency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a haiku seasonal word for spring.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="52">
<sen id="197">
<j>梟笛（ふくろうぶえ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fukurobue</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fukurobue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fukurobue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="198">
<j>フクロウの鳴き声を出す笛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fukurobue is a fue that produces the sound of fukuro (owl).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A fue that produces the sound of an owl.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency and consistency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A fue that produces the sound of an owl.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="199">
<j>芝居で使われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is used in plays.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is used in plays.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is used in plays.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="53">
<sen id="200">
<j>虫笛</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mushibue</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mushibue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mushibue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="201">
<j>虫の鳴き声を出す竹製の笛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mushibue is a bamboo fue that produces the chirping of insects.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A bamboo fue that produces the chirping of insects.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency and consistency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A bamboo fue that produces the chirping of insects.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="202">
<j>芝居で使われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is used in plays.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is used in plays.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is used in plays.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="54">
<sen id="203">
<j>用途によるもの</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Classification based on uses</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Classification by Use</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Classification by Use</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="204">
<j>ピッチパイプ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Pitch pipe</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Pitch pipe</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Pitch pipe</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="205">
<j>基準となる音高を鳴らす小さな笛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Pitch pipe is a small fue that is used for producing a benchmark interval.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A small fue that is used for producing a standard pitch.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A small fue that is used for producing a standard pitch.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="206">
<j>弦楽器の調弦や、無伴奏の合唱の歌い出しに用いる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is used for the tuning of stringed instruments or the start of chorus without accompaniment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are used for the tuning of stringed instruments or the start of chorus without accompaniment.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are used for the tuning of stringed instruments or the start of chorus without accompaniment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="55">
<sen id="207">
<j>牧笛（まきぶえ、ぼくてき）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Makibue/bokuteki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Makibue/Bokuteki</e>
<cmt>Title case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Makibue (also known as Bokuteki)</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="208">
<j>家畜への合図に牧童が吹く笛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Makibue/bokuteki is a fue which herdboys use as a signal to domestic animals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A fue which herdboys use as a signal to domestic animals.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency and consistency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A fue which herdboys use as a signal to domestic animals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="56">
<sen id="209">
<j>按摩笛（あんまぶえ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Anmabue</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Anmabue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Anmabue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="210">
<j>按摩が町の中を流して歩くときに吹く笛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Anmabue is a fue which anma (masseurs) use when they stroll in the town.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A fue which anma (masseurs) use as they stroll through town.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency and consistency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A fue which anma (masseurs) use as they stroll through town.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="211">
<j>発音原理はホイッスルに近い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its law of producing sound is similar to that of whistle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its sound is similar to that of a whistle.</e>
<cmt>Completely retranslated</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its sound is similar to that of a whistle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="57">
<sen id="212">
<j>汽笛</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiteki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiteki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiteki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="213">
<j>船や蒸気機関車で用いられる蒸気を吹き込んで鳴らす笛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiteki is a fue that is used for ships or steam locomotives and it produces a sound when steam is blown in.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A fue used on ships or steam locomotives and produces a sound when steam is blown in.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency and consistency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A fue used on ships or steam locomotives and produces a sound when steam is blown in.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="214">
<j>時報や合図・信号などに使う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is used as a time signal and other signals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are used to announce time and as signals.</e>
<cmt>Completely retranslated</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are used to announce time and as signals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="58">
<sen id="215">
<j>霧笛（むてき、きりぶえ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Muteki/Kiribue</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Muteki/Kiribue (Foghorn)</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;(Foghorn)&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Muteki (also known as Kiribue) (Foghorn)</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="216">
<j>濃霧などのため視界不良のとき、船や灯台などが位置を知らせるために鳴らす音響信号。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Muteki/Kiribue is a sound signal which ships and lighthouses make, when visibility is low owing to the dense fog, in order to notify their location.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A sound signal which ships and lighthouses emit when visibility is low due to dense fog in order to make their location known.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A sound signal which ships and lighthouses emit when visibility is low due to dense fog in order to make their location known.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="217">
<j>現在は電気的な音が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Electro-acoustic sound is mainly used at present.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Electrical sounds are often used nowadays.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Electrical sounds are often used nowadays.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="59">
<sen id="218">
<j>警笛</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keiteki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keiteki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keiteki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="219">
<j>注意をうながすために鳴らす音。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keiteki is a sound that is given out for the purpose of drawing attention.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A sound that is made for the purpose of drawing attention.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A sound that is made for the purpose of drawing attention.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="220">
<j>電車・自動車などについている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Electric cars and automobiles are equipped with an instrument to produce it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Used on trains and automobiles.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency and accuracy.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Used on trains and automobiles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="60">
<sen id="221">
<j>ホイッスル、呼子笛</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Whistle/ yobikobue</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Whistle/Yobikobue</e>
<cmt>Consistency</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Whistle or Yobikobue</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="222">
<j>捕物や競技の合図等に用いられる小さい笛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Whistle/yobikobue is a small fue that is used as a signal in an arrest and/or contest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A small fue used by police officers when pursuing suspects or during competitions.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency and accuracy.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A small fue used by police officers when pursuing suspects or by judges as signals during competitions.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="223">
<j>リズム楽器として用いられることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is sometimes used as a rhythm instrument.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are sometimes used as rhythm instruments.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are sometimes used as rhythm instruments.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="61">
<sen id="224">
<j>形状・演奏方法によるもの</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Classification based on the shape/way of performing</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Classification by Shape/Way of Performing</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency and consistency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Classification by Shape and Way of Performing</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="225">
<j>縦笛</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tatebue</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tatebue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tatebue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="226">
<j>縦に構えて吹く笛の総称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tatebue is a collective name of fue which people play while holding vertically.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The collective name for fue which are played while held vertically.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency and consistency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The collective name for fue which are played while held vertically.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="62">
<sen id="227">
<j>横笛</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yokobue</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yokobue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yokobue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="228">
<j>横に構えて吹く笛の総称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yokobue is a collective name of fue which people play while holding horizontally.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A collective name for fue which are played while held horizontally.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency and consistency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A collective name for fue which are played while held horizontally.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="63">
<sen id="229">
<j>鼻笛</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hanabue</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hanabue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hanabue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="230">
<j>鼻に当てて、鼻息で演奏する笛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hanabue is a fue which people play by the breath breathed out from their nose.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fue which are placed at the nose and played by breathing out air from the nose.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency and consistency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fue which are placed at the nose and played by breathing out air from the nose.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="231">
<j>日本の楽器にはないが、東南アジアからオセアニア地域にみられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although such instruments don&apos;t exist in Japan, they exist in South-East Asia and Oceania.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although such instruments do not exist in Japan, they can be found in Southeast Asia and Oceania.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although such instruments do not exist in Japan, they can be found in Southeast Asia and Oceania.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="232">
<j>口からの息は不浄であるとの考え方から鼻息を用いるとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the reason why the breath breathed out from the nose is used is because the breath breathed out from the mouth is believed to be dirty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that air breathed out of the nose is used because of the belief that air breathed out of the mouth is impure.</e>
<cmt>Poor translation.Completely retranslated.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that air breathed out of the nose is used because of the belief that air breathed out of the mouth is impure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="64">
<sen id="233">
<j>口笛</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kuchibue</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kuchibue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kuchibue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="234">
<j>口をすぼめて、息を強く出して笛のような音をたてること。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kuchibue means producing a fue-like sound by forcing breath through a narrow opening made by puckering the lips.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Producing a fue-like sound by forcing breath through a narrow opening made by puckering the lips.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;Kuchibue means&quot; for consistency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Producing a fue-like sound by forcing breath through a narrow opening made by puckering the lips.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="235">
<j>皮笛ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called kawabue.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called kawabue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called kawabue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="236">
<j>指笛を口笛ということもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yubibue is sometimes called kuchibue.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yubibue is sometimes called kuchibue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yubibue is sometimes called kuchibue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="65">
<sen id="237">
<j>指笛</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yubibue</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yubibue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yubibue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="238">
<j>口に指を入れ、息を強く出して笛のような音をたてること。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yubibue means producing a fue-like sound by forcing breath through fingers that are being inserted in the mouth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Producing a fue-like sound by forcing breath through fingers that have been inserted into the mouth.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency and consistency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Producing a fue-like sound by forcing breath through fingers that have been inserted into the mouth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="239">
<j>口笛ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called kuchibue.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called kuchibue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called kuchibue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="66">
<sen id="240">
<j>その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="241">
<j>唐人笛（とうじんぶえ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tojinbue</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tojinbue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tojinbue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="242">
<j>チャルメラのこと、またはラッパ（らっぱ）のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tojinbue means a charamera (a street vendor&apos;s flute) or a bugle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A charamera (a street vendor&apos;s flute) or a trumpet/bugle.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency and accuracy.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A shawm or a trumpet (bugle).</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="67">
<sen id="243">
<j>磯笛</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Isobue</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Isobue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Isobue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="244">
<j>海女が水中での仕事を終えて水面に顔を出したとき、詰めていた呼吸を戻す音が口笛のように鳴るもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Isobue means a kuchibue-like sound which ama (woman diver) produces when she breathes out after having surfaced.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A kuchibue-like sound which ama (female pearl divers) produce when they breath out after having surfaced.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency and consistency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A kuchibue-like sounds which ama (female pearl divers) produce when they breathe out after having surfaced.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="68">
<sen id="245">
<j>虎落笛（もがりぶえ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mogaribue</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mogaribue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mogaribue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="246">
<j>冬の激しい風が柵や竹垣、電線などに吹きつけて発する笛のような音。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mogaribue means a sound that is produced when strong winter wind blows against fences, bamboo fences and electric wires.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A sound that is produced when strong winter wind blows against fences, bamboo hedges and electric wires.</e>
<cmt>fences &gt; hedges</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A sound that is produced when strong winter wind blows against fences, bamboo hedges and electric wires.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="247">
<j>冬の季語。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This word is a season word of winter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a haiku seasonal word for winter.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency and consistency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a haiku seasonal word for winter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="248">
<j>香西かおりの演歌「風恋歌」(作詞・里村龍一)でも歌い込まれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is included in Kaori KOZAI&apos;s enka song &quot;Kaze Koiuta&quot; (lyrics by Ryuichi SATOMURA).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is included in Kaori KOZAI&apos;s enka song &quot;Kaze Koiuta&quot; (lyrics by Ryuichi SATOMURA).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is included in Kaori KOZAI&apos;s enka (Japanese ballad) song &apos;Kaze Koiuta&apos; (Breeze&apos;s Love Song) (lyrics by Ryuichi SATOMURA).</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="69">
<sen id="249">
<j>喉笛</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nodobue</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nodobue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nodobue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="250">
<j>のどの気管が通っている部分、または喉仏を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nodobue means the part of throat where the trachea passes, or the Adam&apos;s apple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The part of throat where the trachea passes, or the Adam&apos;s apple.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;Nodobue means&quot; for consitency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The part of throat where the trachea passes, or the Adam&apos;s apple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="251">
<j>本来の意味の笛とは異なるが、古くから単に「笛」でこれを指すこともある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the above differs from the original meaning of fue, the term &quot;fue&quot; sometimes refers to nodobue traditionally.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the above differs from the original meaning of fue, the term &quot;fue&quot; has long been used to refer to nodobue.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the above differs from the original meaning of fue, the term &quot;fue&quot; has long been used to refer to nodobue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="252">
<j>近代では森鴎外の『高瀬舟』の中にその用例がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the early modern times, an example is seen in Ogai MORI&apos;s novel &quot;Takasebune&quot;.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In modern times, an example can be seen in Ogai MORI&apos;s novel &quot;Takasebune&quot;.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;the early&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In modern times, an example can be seen in Ogai MORI&apos;s novel &quot;Takasebune&quot; (The Boat on the Takase-gawa River).</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 DumZiBoT(id:230315), AlleborgoBot(id:119729), JAnDbot(id:66507), ArthurBot(id:265089), TuvicBot(id:64131), Kokoperi(id:32223), DragonBot(id:161936), Iwatake(id:32921), TXiKiBoT(id:107492), Robbot(id:3063), NekoJaNekoJa(id:23311), YukkeBot(id:251107), BOT-Superzerocool(id:65015), DorganBot(id:149946), BodhisattvaBot(id:185411), Alecs.bot(id:194707), Dr jimmy(id:111486), Kadzuwo(id:3701), Iokseng(id:92490), Point136(id:211299), 曼珠沙華(id:26417), Ptbotgourou(id:229657), Bankokuya(id:91191), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>