<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>片岡仁左衛門 (13代目)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nizaemon KATAOKA (The Thirteenth)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nizaemon KATAOKA (XIII)</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nizaemon KATAOKA (XIII)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>十三代目 片岡 仁左衛門（じゅうさんだいめ かたおか にざえもん、明治36年(1903年)12月15日 - 平成6年(1994年)3月26日）は歌舞伎役者。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jusandai-me (the thirteenth) Nizaemon KATAOKA (male, December 15, 1903 to March 26, 1994) was a kabuki actor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jusandai-me (the thirteenth) Nizaemon KATAOKA (male, December 15, 1903 to March 26, 1994) was a kabuki actor.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jusandai-me (the thirteenth) Nizaemon KATAOKA (male, December 15, 1903 to March 26, 1994) was a kabuki actor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>本名片岡千代之助（かたおか　ちよのすけ）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His real name was Chiyonosuke KATAOKA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His real name was Chiyonosuke KATAOKA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His real name was Chiyonosuke KATAOKA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>昭和後期の歌舞伎界を支えた立役の名優。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was one of the excellent actors acting as man, who supported the kabuki society in the late Showa period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was one of the excellent actors acting as man, who supported the kabuki society in the late Showa period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was one of the excellent actors acting as man, who supported the kabuki society in the late Showa period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>晩年の十年間は完全に盲目だったにもかかわらず、主演の役者として舞台活動を続けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a decade in the later stage of his life, he was completely blind, however, he continued his activity on the stage as an actor playing the lead.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was completely blind in the last decade of his life, but he continued his activity on the stage as lead actor.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was completely blind in the last decade of his life, but he continued his activity on the stage as lead actor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>人物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Person</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The person</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Personal Profile</e>
<cmt>The personをPersonal Profileに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>子供は片岡我當 (5代目)、日本舞踊家花柳寿々、片岡秀太郎 (2代目)、片岡仁左衛門 (15代目)、新劇女優片岡静香（演劇集団 円）らがいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His children include: Gafu KATAOKA (the fifth); Suzu HANAYAGI, a dancer of the Japanese dancing; Hidetaro KATAOKA (the second); Nizaemon KATAOKA (the fifteenth); and Shizuka KATAOKA, an actress of shingeki (new dramas influenced by western stage plays).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His children include: Gafu KATAOKA (V); Suzu HANAYAGI, a performer of Japanese dance; Hidetaro KATAOKA (II); Nizaemon KATAOKA (XV); and Shizuka KATAOKA, an actress of shingeki (new dramas influenced by Western stage plays).</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His children include: Gafu KATAOKA (V); Suzu HANAYAGI, a performer of Japanese dance; Hidetaro KATAOKA (II); Nizaemon KATAOKA (XV); and Shizuka KATAOKA, an actress of shingeki (new dramas influenced by Western stage plays).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>日本舞踊花柳流二代目家元・二代目花柳壽輔改め花柳壽應とは、妻同士が姉妹（片岡のほうが妹）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His wife and the wife of Jukei HANAYAGI, the second head of the HANAYAGI School of Japanese dancing, who changed his name from Jusuke HANAYAGI, the second are sisters (KATAOKA&apos;s wife is younger).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His wife and the wife of Jukei HANAYAGI, the second head of the HANAYAGI School of Japanese dance, who changed his name from Jusuke HANAYAGI II, are sisters (KATAOKA&apos;s wife is younger).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His wife and the wife of Jukei HANAYAGI, the second head of the HANAYAGI School of Japanese dance, who changed his name from Jusuke HANAYAGI II, are sisters (KATAOKA&apos;s wife is younger).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>自身の娘も壽應に師事し、名取名「花柳寿々」を名乗る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His own daughter learned Japanese dancing from Jukei and names herself &apos;Suzu HANAYAGI&apos; which is an accredited master&apos;s name.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His own daughter learned Japanese dance from Jukei and calls herself &apos;Suzu HANAYAGI,&apos; which is the name of an accredited master.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His own daughter learned Japanese dance from Jukei and calls herself &apos;Suzu HANAYAGI,&apos; which is the name of an accredited master.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>壽應は三男の十五代目仁左衛門の仲人も務めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jukei played the role of the go-between for his third son, Nizaemon, the fifteenth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jukei played the role of the go-between for his third son, Nizaemon XV.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jukei played the role of the go-between for his third son, Nizaemon XV.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>なお、壽應の父（初代花柳壽輔）も壽應ももとは歌舞伎役者。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The father of Jukei (Jusuke HANAYAGI, the first) and Jukei used to be kabuki actors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The father of Jukei (Jusuke HANAYAGI I) and Jukei were once kabuki actors.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The father of Jukei (Jusuke HANAYAGI I) and Jukei were once kabuki actors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>壽應は六代目を師とし、尾上菊太郎という名で、歌舞伎のほか多数の映画にも出演した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jukei learned kabuki from the sixth and appeared in many movies by the name, Kikutaro ONOE, in addition to kabuki stages.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jukei learned kabuki from the sixth and appeared in many movies by the name Kikutaro ONOE, in addition to performing on kabuki stages.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jukei learned kabuki from the sixth and appeared in many movies by the name Kikutaro ONOE, in addition to performing on kabuki stages.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>自身のプロダクション「菊太郎プロダクション」を設立したこともある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had founded his own production &apos;Kikutaro Production&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had founded his own company, &apos;Kikutaro Productions.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had founded his own company, &apos;Kikutaro Productions.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>壽應は花柳壽輔 (3世)の父。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jukei is the father of Jusuke HANAYAGI (the third).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jukei is the father of Jusuke HANAYAGI III.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jukei is the father of Jusuke HANAYAGI III.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="14">
<j>戸籍上は十一代目仁左衛門の子だが、本当の父親は安田善三郎である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though he is legally a child of Nizaemon, the eleventh, his real father is Zenzaburo YASUDA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though he is legally a child of Nizaemon XI, his real father is Zenzaburo YASUDA.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though he is legally a child of Nizaemon XI, his real father is Zenzaburo YASUDA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>すなわちオノ・ヨーコの叔父にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">YASUDA is, that is, an uncle of YOKO ONO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">YASUDA is an uncle of YOKO ONO.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">YASUDA is an uncle of Yoko ONO.</e>
<cmt>YOKOをYokoに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>安田財閥の金が恒常的に流れてきたため、少なくとも財閥解体まではまったくお金に困らなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had no financial troubles at least until the dissolution of financial groups in Japan because the money of YASUDA financial group always flowed in to him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had no financial problems (at least until the dissolution of financial groups in Japan), because the money of the YASUDA financial group always flowed in to him.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had no financial problems (at least until the dissolution of financial groups in Japan), because the money of the YASUDA financial group always flowed in to him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>これが彼の芸に強い影響を及ぼしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This fact is strongly influencing his acting style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This fact was a strong influence on his acting style.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This fact had a strong influence on his acting style.</e>
<cmt>wasをhadに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>性格的に屈折したところがなく、高貴な役どころがぴたりとはまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He has no warped mind and he acts extremely excellently when he acts as a noble man.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had a steady mind and performed with the greatest excellence when playing a noble man.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had a steady mind and performed with the greatest excellence when playing a noble man.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>由良之助役者としても知られたが、七段目では、豪遊ぶりがいかにも自然で、それはまさしく普段から自分の金で現実に豪遊しているからだという評があるほどである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was famous as an actor to act as Yuranosuke (one of the core characters of Chushingura, a famous kabuki play), in the seventh episode of Chushingura, and his acting of going on an extravagant spree was really natural and this acting even raised a reputation that the natural acting was because he usually went on an extravagant spree at his own expense.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was famous for his work in the role of Yuranosuke (one of the core characters of Chushingura, a famous kabuki play), in the seventh episode of Chushingura, and his portrayal of going on an extravagant spree was totally natural; it even brought forth the opinion that such natural acting was because he usually went on extravagant sprees at his own expense.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was famous for his work in the role of Yuranosuke (one of the core characters of Chushingura, a famous kabuki play), in the seventh episode of Chushingura, and his portrayal of going on an extravagant spree was totally natural; it even brought forth the opinion that such natural acting was because he usually went on extravagant sprees at his own expense.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>実生活でもコセコセしたところがなく、どんな人に対しても人間のいやらしい部分、卑屈な部分を見せることがなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was unfussy in his life off the stage and he never showed any disgusting aspect and fawning aspect of a human to any body.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He wasn&apos;t fussy in his life off the stage; he neither displayed any distasteful characteristics, nor did he ever fawn over others.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He wasn&apos;t fussy in his life off the stage; he neither displayed any distasteful characteristics, nor did he ever fawn over others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="21">
<j>また、大の鉄道ファンとしても知られ、鉄道各社の新型車両デビューや新路線開業などの数々の記念イベントのテープカットに来賓として頻繁に招待されるなど、鉄道関係者や鉄道ファンに大いに慕われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also known as a railroad fanatic and was so adored by the railroad-related people and railroad fanatics that he was often invited as a guest to ribbon-cutting ceremonies of many commemorative events such as debut of new-model cars and starts of operation of new lines of many railroad companies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Widely known as a railroad fanatic, he was so adored by railroad-related people and fanatics that he was often invited as a guest at the ribbon-cutting ceremonies of commemorative events such as the debuts of new-model cars and the launches of railroad companies&apos; new lines.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Widely known as a railroad fanatic, he was so adored by railroad-related people and fanatics that he was often invited as a guest at the ribbon-cutting ceremonies of commemorative events such as the debuts of new-model cars and the launches of railroad companies&apos; new lines.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="22">
<j>略歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Brief personal history</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Brief personal history</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt>Brief personal historyをBrief Personal Historyに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>東京歌舞伎時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokyo-kabuki period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Tokyo-kabuki period</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tokyo-kabuki period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>1903年、東京に生れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1903, born in Tokyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born in Tokyo in 1903.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born in Tokyo in 1903.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>すでに東京に拠点を移していた片岡仁左衛門 (11代目)の養子に入り、三男となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was adopted by Nizaemon KATAOKA (the eleventh) who already had moved his base to Tokyo, and he became Nizaemon&apos;s third son.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was adopted by Nizaemon KATAOKA XI, who had moved his base to Tokyo, and he became Nizaemon&apos;s third son.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was adopted by Nizaemon KATAOKA XI, who had moved his base to Tokyo, and he became Nizaemon&apos;s third son.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>1905年、京都南座で初舞台。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1905, he acted for the first time in his life in Minami-za theater in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1905, he acted for the first time in his life in the Minami-za theater of Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1905, he acted for the first time in his life in the Minami-za theater of Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>本名の片岡千代之助を名乗る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He named himself Chiyonosuke KATAOKA which was his real name.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He called himself Chiyonosuke KATAOKA, which was his real name.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He called himself Chiyonosuke KATAOKA, which was his real name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>1912年以降は片岡少年劇（ちんこ芝居）で活躍した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In and after 1912, he played an important role in Kataoka-Shounen-geki (boys&apos; theatricals) (chinko-shibai).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Beginning in 1912, he played an important role in Kataoka-Shounen-geki (boys&apos; theatricals) (chinko-shibai).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After 1912, he played an important role in Kataoka-Shonen-geki (boys&apos; theatricals) (chinko-shibai).</e>
<cmt>Beginning inをAfterに変更しました。ShounenをShonenに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="29">
<j>1924年、歌舞伎座で四代目片岡我當を襲名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1924, he succeeded to the stage name, Gafu KATAOKA, and became the fourth of it in Kabuki-za theater.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1924, he succeeded to the stage name Gafu KATAOKA and became the fourth to do so in Kabuki-za theater.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1924, he succeeded to the stage name Gafu KATAOKA and became the fourth to do so in Kabuki-za theater.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>この前後から東京を中心に活動し、市川團十郎 (9代目)の芸系を受継ぐ市川中車 (7代目)などについて積極的に学ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around this time, he started to act mainly in Tokyo and started to actively learn from Chusha ICHIKAWA (the seventh) who had inherited the acting style of Danjuro ICHIKAWQ (the ninth), etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At around that time, he acted mainly in Tokyo and started studying under Chusha ICHIKAWA VII, who had inherited the acting style of Danjuro ICHIKAWA IX, etc.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At around that time, he acted mainly in Tokyo and started studying under Chusha ICHIKAWA VII, who had inherited the acting style of Danjuro ICHIKAWA IX, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>1932年、松竹・新宿第一劇場（現：大塚家具新宿店）で青年歌舞伎を結成し座頭をつとめる（書き出坂東志うか（十四代目守田勘弥）、トメ四代目片岡我當（千代之助））。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1932, he founded Seinen-kabuki (youth kabuki troupe) in Shinjuku Daiichi Gekijo (presently, Shinjuku branch of Otsuka Furniture Store) of Shochiku and he led the troupe (kakidashi (a young actor getting popular who appears first on the actor name board): Shiuka BANDO (Kanya MORITA, the fourteenth) and tome (the core actor appearing last on the actor name board): Gafu KATAOKA, the fourth (Chiyonosuke).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1932, he founded Seinen-kabuki (youth kabuki troupe) in Shinjuku Daiichi Gekijo (currently the Shinjuku branch of Otsuka Furniture Store) of Shochiku, and he led the troupe (as kakidashi, a young actor gaining popularity who appears first on the actors&apos; name board) along with Shiuka BANDO (Kanya MORITA XIV) and tome (the core actor appearing last on the actors&apos; name board) Gafu KATAOKA IV (Chiyonosuke).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1932, he founded Seinen-kabuki (youth kabuki troupe) in Shinjuku Daiichi Gekijo (currently the Shinjuku branch of Otsuka Furniture Store) of Shochiku, and he led the troupe (as kakidashi, a young actor gaining popularity who appears first on the actors&apos; name board) along with Shiuka BANDO (Kanya MORITA XIV) and tome (the core actor appearing last on the actors&apos; name board) Gafu KATAOKA IV (Chiyonosuke).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>青年歌舞伎の活動は足掛け七年にわたった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His activity in Seinen-kabuki continued for seven years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His activity in Seinen-kabuki continued for seven years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His activity in Seinen-kabuki continued for seven years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="33">
<j>関西歌舞伎時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kansai-kabuki period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kansai-kabuki period</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kansai-kabuki period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>1939年、関西歌舞伎へ移籍。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1939, he moved to Kansai kabuki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1939, he moved to Kansai kabuki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1939, he moved to Kansai kabuki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>1951年には亡父の後を襲って片岡仁左衛門を襲名するも、1960年代に入ってから関西歌舞伎の凋落いちじるしく、思わしい活動が行えなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1951, he succeeded to the stage name, Nizaemon KATAOKA after his late father, however, since 1960s started, the decline of Kansai kabuki was remarkable and he could not act as he wanted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1951, he succeeded to the stage name Nizaemon KATAOKA after his late father, but with the dawn of the &apos;60s Kansai kabuki started a significant decline and he couldn&apos;t act as he wanted.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1951, he succeeded to the stage name Nizaemon KATAOKA after his late father, but with the dawn of the &apos;60s Kansai kabuki started a significant decline and he couldn&apos;t act as he wanted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>中村鴈治郎 (2代目)、實川延若 (2代目)らとともに、自主公演の集まり「七人の会」をたちあげたが不調に終わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He launched a group of self-promoting plays &apos;Shichinin-no-kai (a group of seven persons)&apos; together with Ganjiro NAKAMURA (the second) and Enjaku MINOKAWA (the second), however, the group resulted failure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He launched a group of self-promoting plays &apos;Shichinin-no-kai (a group of seven persons)&apos; together with Ganjiro NAKAMURA II and Enjaku MINOKAWA II, but ultimately the group failed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He launched a group of self-promoting plays &apos;Shichinin-no-kai&apos; (a group of seven persons) together with Ganjiro NAKAMURA II and Enjaku MINOKAWA II, but ultimately the group failed.</e>
<cmt>()を&apos; &apos;の外に移動させました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>このような上方歌舞伎の現状を憂い、伝統の灯火を守ることを決意した仁左衛門は、私財を投じ「仁左衛門歌舞伎」と称して1962年以降五回にわたって自主公演を決行。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Being worried about the state of Kamigata (Kansai Region) kabuki, Nizaemon made up his mind to protect the presence of the tradition and daringly held self-promoted performance for five times in and after 1962, naming the performances &apos;Nizaemon Kabuki&apos; spending his own funds on them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Being worried about the state of Kamigata (Kansai region) kabuki, Nizaemon made up his mind to protect the presence of the tradition and daringly held self-promoted performances five times in and after 1962; he called them &apos;Nizaemon Kabuki&apos; and funded them himself.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Being worried about the state of Kamigata (Kansai region) kabuki, Nizaemon made up his mind to protect the presence of the tradition and daringly held self-promoted performances five times in and after 1962; he called them &apos;Nizaemon Kabuki&apos; and funded them himself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>関西歌舞伎界に与えた影響はきわめて大きい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The influence on Kansai kabuki was significant.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The influence on Kansai kabuki was significant.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The influence on Kansai kabuki was significant.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>一方では高校生を対象とする歌舞伎教室を開催、「若鮎の会」を主宰して若手俳優の指導など人材育成に努めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, he made efforts to develop human resources including holding of kabuki classes for high school students and instructing young actors and actresses by leading &apos;wakaayu-no-kai (group of young sweetfish)&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, he made efforts to develop human resources including holding kabuki classes for high-school students and instructing young actors and actresses by leading &apos;wakaayu-no-kai (group of young sweetfish).&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, he made efforts to develop human resources including holding kabuki classes for high-school students and instructing young actors and actresses by leading &apos;wakaayu-no-kai (group of young sweetfish).&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="40">
<j>その後</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later on</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>1966年、歌舞伎座で演じた『廓文章』（吉田屋）の伊左衛門が好劇家から高い評価を受け、それまでどちらかといえば独特な持味はあるものの、手堅いだけとされていた仁左衛門の演技に変化がおとずれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1966, Nizaemon&apos;s acting as Izaemon of &quot;Kuruwa-Bunsho&quot; (Yoshida-ya) at Kabuki-za theater received a high reputation from play-lovers and Nizaemon&apos;s acting which, until then, had been said to rather be only reliable, having a unique characteristic though, started to vary.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1966, Nizaemon&apos;s portrayal of Izaemon in &quot;Kuruwa-Bunsho&quot; (Yoshida-ya) at the Kabuki-za theater received a high reputation from play lovers, and Nizaemon&apos;s acting, which until then had been called merely reliable despite its unique characteristics, started to vary.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1966, Nizaemon&apos;s portrayal of Izaemon in &quot;Kuruwa-Bunsho&quot; (Yoshida-ya) at the Kabuki-za theater received a high reputation from play lovers, and Nizaemon&apos;s acting, which until then had been called merely reliable despite its unique characteristics, started to vary.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>仁左衛門の芸は、驚くべきことながら七十代の後半から八十代に至って飛躍的に深化し、一躍、名優の列に加えられることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Surprisingly, the acting of Nizaemon was drastically sophisticated from his late 70s to 80s and suddenly, he was added to the list of excellent actors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Surprisingly, the acting of Nizaemon was remarkably sophisticated from his late seventies to his eighties, and suddenly he was added to the list of excellent actors.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Surprisingly, the acting of Nizaemon was remarkably sophisticated from his late seventies to his eighties, and suddenly he was added to the list of excellent actors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>最晩年の滋味あふれる品格高い演技を賞賛する者は今でも少なくない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Not a few people still admire his acting in his last days which was full of tastefulness and highly graceful.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many people still admire the acting of his last days, which was very graceful and conveyed a great sense of taste.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many people still admire the acting of his last days, which was very graceful and conveyed a great sense of taste.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="44">
<j>1972年、重要無形文化財各個指定、芸術院賞受賞。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1972, he was designated as a respective case of important intangible cultural asset and received a Japan Art Academy Prize.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1972, he was designated as an important intangible cultural asset and received the Japan Art Academy Prize.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1972, he was designated as an important intangible cultural asset and received the Japan Art Academy Prize.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>1981年、国立劇場の『菅原伝授手習鑑』の菅丞相が神品とまで絶賛される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1981, his acting as Kanshoso of &quot;Sugawara-denju-tenarai-kagami&quot; at the National Theater was extremely highly reputed that the acting was that of a god.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1981, his portrayal of Kanshoso in &quot;Sugawara-denju-tenarai-kagami&quot; at the National Theater earned a reputation for being &quot;godlike.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1981, his portrayal of Kanshoso in &quot;Sugawara-denju-tenarai-kagami&quot; at the National Theater earned a reputation for being &quot;godlike.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>大向うから「松嶋屋天神！」の掛声がかかるほどだった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The acting was so adored that a shout of applause &apos;Matsushima-ya-tenjin!&apos; was thrown from the gallery.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The acting was so adored that a shout of &apos;Matsushima-ya-tenjin!&apos; came up from the gallery.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The acting was so adored that a shout of &apos;Matsushima-ya-tenjin!&apos; came up from the gallery.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>同時に、このころから緑内障のために徐々に視力が衰え、最晩年には失明状態に陥ったが、生涯舞台に立ちつづけた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time, his eye sight started to be gradually weakened around this time due to glaucoma and he lost his eyesight in his last days, however, he continued to act on the stage until the last day of his life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this his eyesight was gradually weakening due to glaucoma and he lost his eyesight in his last days, but he continued to act on the stage until the last day of his life.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this time his eyesight was gradually weakening due to glaucoma and he lost his eyesight in his last days, but he continued to act on the stage until the last day of his life.</e>
<cmt>thisの後にtimeを挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>1993年12月の京都南座顔見世における『八陣守護城・御座船の段』の佐藤正清が最後の舞台となり、1994年3月26日、京都で死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His last acting was that as Masakiyo SATO of &quot;Hachijinnokami-mamorijiro, Gozabune-no-dan&quot; performed in all-cast performance series at Minami-za in Kyoto in December 1993 and he died in Kyoto on March 26, 1994.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His final role was that of Masakiyo SATO in &quot;Hachijinnokami-mamorijiro, Gozabune-no-dan,&quot; which he performed in an all-cast performance series at Minami-za in Kyoto in December 1993; he died in Kyoto on March 26, 1994.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His final role was that of Masakiyo SATO in &quot;Hachijinnokami-mamorijiro, Gozabune-no-dan,&quot; which he performed in an all-cast performance series at Minami-za in Kyoto in December 1993; he died in Kyoto on March 26, 1994.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="49">
<j>人物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Person</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The person</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Personal Profile</e>
<cmt>The personをPersonal Profileに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>若いときに父を始め、松本幸四郎 (7代目)、七代目市川中車、市村羽左衛門 (15代目)、實川延若 (2代目)ら名優に歌舞伎狂言の型を教えられたが、これは、十三代目仁左衛門のみならず歌舞伎界にとって貴重な財産であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When he was young, he learned the forms of kabuki and kyogen from the excellent actors such as Koshiro MATSUMOTO (the seventh), Chusha ICHIKAWA, the seventh, Hazaemon ICHIMURA (the fifteenth), and Enjaku MINOKAWA (the second) in addition to his father., and this was an important asset not only for Nizaemon, the thirteenth, but also for the whole kabuki society.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When he was young, he learned the forms of kabuki and kyogen from excellent actors such as Koshiro MATSUMOTO VII, Chusha ICHIKAWA VII, Hazaemon ICHIMURA XV and Enjaku MINOKAWA II in addition to his father; this was an important asset not only for Nizaemon (XIII) but also for kabuki society as a whole.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When he was young, he learned the forms of kabuki and kyogen from excellent actors such as Koshiro MATSUMOTO VII, Chusha ICHIKAWA VII, Hazaemon ICHIMURA XV and Enjaku MINOKAWA II in addition to his father; this was an important asset not only for Nizaemon (XIII) but also for kabuki society as a whole.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>三男・十五代目仁左衛門やその孫片岡孝太郎の話では、十三代目仁左衛門は、一つの狂言を教えるのに色々な型を示し、あとは本人の選択に任せると言う方法であったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to his third son, Nizaemon, the fifteenth and this son&apos;s grand child, Kotaro KATAOKA, Nizaemon, the thirteenth, showed various forms to teach one kyogen story to them and let each of them select.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to his third son, Nizaemon XV and that son&apos;s grandchild, Kotaro KATAOKA, Nizaemon XIII demonstrated various forms by which to teach them one kyogen story and then let each of them choose.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to his third son, Nizaemon XV and that son&apos;s grandchild, Kotaro KATAOKA, Nizaemon XIII demonstrated various forms by which to teach them one kyogen story and then let each of them choose.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="52">
<j>戦前からの鉄道ファンとしても有名で、鉄道友の会の理事や名誉会長も勤め、ブルーリボン賞 (鉄道)叙与式、大阪市電最終運転日など関西での鉄道関係のセレモニーには来賓としてしばしば顔を出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was famous as a railroad fanatic which he became before WWII, and he acted as a director and a honorable chairman of Tetsudo-tomo-no-kai (Railroad Fanatics&apos; Association) and often attended railroad-related ceremonies held in Kansai Region such as presenting ceremony of Blue Ribbon Ward (railroad) and the final day of operation of Osaka City Railroad.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prior to World War II he became known as a railroad fanatic; he acted as a director and honorary chairman of Tetsudo-tomo-no-kai (Railroad Fanatics&apos; Association) and often attended railroad-related ceremonies held in the Kansai region, such as the presentatin ceremonies of Blue Ribbon Ward (railroad) and the Osaka City Railroad&apos;s final day of operation.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prior to World War II he became known as a railroad fanatic; he acted as a director and honorary chairman of Tetsudo-tomo-no-kai (Railroad Fanatics&apos; Association) and often attended railroad-related ceremonies held in the Kansai region, such as the presentation ceremonies of Blue Ribbon Ward (railroad) and the Osaka City Railroad&apos;s final day of operation.</e>
<cmt>presentatinをpresentationに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>ただし、新幹線のような超高速列車には批判的な見解を示し、「新幹線ができてから、旅に風情がなくなった」と嘆いていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he presented critical opinion about ultra high-speed trains such as shinkansen bullet train and he lamented saying &apos;after the shinkansen had been completed, the elegance of traveling was lost.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, he was critical of the ultra-high-speed trains such as the shinkansen (a.k.a., the bullet train), lamenting that &quot;after the shinkansen was completed, the elegance of travel was lost.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, he was critical of the ultra-high-speed trains such as the shinkansen (a.k.a., the bullet train), lamenting that &apos;after the shinkansen was completed, the elegance of travel was lost.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>古典芸能界の鉄道愛好家として、長唄の杵屋栄二と並び称される存在だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His presence as a railroad fanatic in the classical entertainment society was as big as Eiji KINEYA of the nagauta society.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His presence as a railroad fanatic in the classical entertainment society was equal to that of Eiji KINEYA among the nagauta society.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His presence as a railroad fanatic in the classical entertainment society was equal to that of Eiji KINEYA among the nagauta society.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="55">
<j>文才もあり、主な著書には「菅原と忠臣蔵」「夏祭と伊勢音頭」「とうざいとうざい」｢十一代目片岡仁左衛門」「嵯峨談語」「仁左衛門楽我記」「芝居譚」「忘れられている先祖の供養」などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also an excellent writer and his representative books include &apos;SUGAWARA to Chushingura (SUGAWARA and Chushingura)&apos;, &apos;Natsu-matsuri to Ise-ondo (summer festivals and Ise-ondo song)&apos;, &apos;Touzai-touzai (ladies and gentlemen, welcome)&apos;, &apos;Nizaemon KATAOKA, the eleventh&apos;, &apos;Saga-dango (episodes of Saga area)&apos;, &apos;Nizaemon-rakugaki (Nizaemon&apos;s graffiti)&apos;, &apos;Shibai-tan (episodes of stage acting)&apos;, and &apos;Wasurerareteiru-senzo-no-kuyo (forgotten memorial services for the ancestors)&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also an excellent writer whose representative books include &apos;SUGAWARA to Chushingura (SUGAWARA and Chushingura),&apos; &apos;Natsu-matsuri to Ise-ondo (summer festivals and Ise-ondo song),&apos; &apos;Touzai-touzai (ladies and gentlemen, welcome),&apos; &apos;Nizaemon KATAOKA XI,&apos; &apos;Saga-dango (episodes of the Saga area),&apos; &apos;Nizaemon-rakugaki (Nizaemon&apos;s graffiti),&apos; &apos;Shibai-tan (episodes of stage acting)&apos; and &apos;Wasurerareteiru-senzo-no-kuyo (forgotten memorial services for the ancestors).&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also an excellent writer whose representative books include &apos;SUGAWARA to Chushingura (SUGAWARA and Chushingura),&apos; &apos;Natsu-matsuri to Ise-ondo (summer festivals and Ise-ondo song),&apos; &apos;Touzai-touzai (ladies and gentlemen, welcome),&apos; &apos;Nizaemon KATAOKA XI,&apos; &apos;Saga-dango (episodes of the Saga area),&apos; &apos;Nizaemon-rakugaki (Nizaemon&apos;s graffiti),&apos; &apos;Shibai-tan (episodes of stage acting)&apos; and &apos;Wasurerareteiru-senzo-no-kuyo (forgotten memorial services for the ancestors).&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>とくに芸談や歌舞伎関係の貴重な資料も多く残した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He especially left talks on acting and important kabuki-related references.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Particularly, he left speeches on acting and important kabuki-related references.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Particularly, he left speeches on acting and important kabuki-related references.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="57">
<j>当たり役</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Character Nizaemon always made a hit with</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The character Nizaemon always made a hit with</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The character Nizaemon always made a hit with</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>『菅原』の菅丞相・松王・源蔵・時平。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanjoso, Matsuo, Genzo, and Tokihei of &quot;SUGAWARA&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanjoso, Matsuo, Genzo and Tokihei, of &quot;SUGAWARA&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanjoso, Matsuo, Genzo and Tokihei, of &quot;SUGAWARA&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>『忠臣蔵』の由良之助・判官・本蔵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yuranosuke, Hangan, Honzo of &apos;Chushingura&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yuranosuke, Hangan, Honzo of &apos;Chushingura&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yuranosuke, Hangan, Honzo of &quot;Chushingura&quot;</e>
<cmt>&apos;を&quot; &quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>『熊谷陣屋』の熊谷・『廓文章』の伊左衛門。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kumagai of &quot;Kumagai-jinya&apos;, and Izaemon of &apos;Kuruwa-bunsho&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kumagai, of &quot;Kumagai-jinya,&apos; and Izaemon, of &apos;Kuruwa-bunsho&apos;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kumagai, of &quot;Kumagai-jinya,&apos; and Izaemon, of &quot;Kuruwa-bunsho&quot;</e>
<cmt>Kuruwa-bunshoに&quot; &quot;を付加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>『夏祭』の團七・三婦。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Danshichi and Sanpu of &apos;Natsu-matsuri&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Danshichi and Sanpu, of &apos;Natsu-matsuri&apos;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Danshichi and Sanpu, of &quot;Natsu-matsuri&quot;</e>
<cmt>&apos;を&quot; &quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>『伊勢音頭』の福岡貢。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitsugu FUKUOKA of &apos;Ise-ondo&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitsugu FUKUOKA, of &apos;Ise-ondo&apos;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitsugu FUKUOKA, of &quot;Ise-ondo&quot;</e>
<cmt>&apos;を&quot; &quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>『新口村』の忠兵衛・孫右衛門。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chubei and Magoemon of &apos;Niiguchi-mura&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chubei and Magoemon, of &apos;Niiguchi-mura&apos;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chubei and Magoemon, of &quot;Niiguchi-mura&quot;</e>
<cmt>&apos;を&quot; &quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>『沼津』の平作。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Heisaku of &apos;Numazu&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Heisaku, of &apos;Numazu&apos;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Heisaku, of &quot;Numazu&quot;</e>
<cmt>&apos;を&quot; &quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="65">
<j>『帯屋』の長右衛門。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Choemon of &apos;Obiya&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Choemon, of &apos;Obiya&apos;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Choemon, of &quot;Obiya&quot;</e>
<cmt>&apos;を&quot; &quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>『名工柿右衛門』の柿右衛門。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kakiemon of &apos;Meiko-Kakiemon&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kakiemon, of &apos;Meiko-Kakiemon&apos;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kakiemon, of &quot;Meiko-Kakiemon&quot;</e>
<cmt>&apos;を&quot; &quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>『俊寛』の俊寛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shunkan of &apos;Shunkan&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shunkan, of &apos;Shunkan&apos;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shunkan, of &quot;Shunkan&quot;</e>
<cmt>&apos;を&quot; &quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>『対面』の十郎・工藤。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Juro and Kudo of &apos;Taimen&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Juro and Kudo, of &apos;Taimen&apos;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Juro and Kudo, of &quot;Taimen&quot;</e>
<cmt>&apos;を&quot; &quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>『堀川』の与五郎など</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yogoro of &apos;Horikawa&apos;, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yogoro, of &apos;Horikawa,&apos; etc.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yogoro, of &quot;Horikawa,&quot; etc.</e>
<cmt>&apos;を&quot; &quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 ととりん(id:31982), 松茸(id:27535), こうやま(id:74302), Cprobot(id:97843), ウィキウィ2(id:83093), Hinasuke(id:11466), BitBucket(id:30999), 211dot18dot204dot250(id:220672), Hajimari(id:205606), 白拍子花子(id:244805), スティロウ(id:89199), MB500SLC(id:73218), Ajcxx(id:103602), Unamu(id:14627), わたあめひみつ(id:81640), 竹麦魚(id:11012), 海の家(id:26045), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>