<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>からし</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mustard</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mustard</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mustard</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>からし（カラシ、芥子、辛子）はアブラナ科の植物カラシナおよび近縁種の種子から作られる香辛料。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mustard is a spice made from the seeds of Brassica juncea and other related species.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mustard is a spice made from the seeds of Brassica juncea and related species.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mustard is a spice made from the seeds of Brassica juncea and related species.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>黄色もしくは黄土色で、独特の刺激臭と辛味を持つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is yellow or yellow-ocher in color and has a pungent taste.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is yellow or yellow-ocher in color and has a pungent taste.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is yellow or yellow-ocher in color and has a pungent taste.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>大別して、「和からし（和がらし）」と「洋からし（洋がらし）」がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is generally categorized as Japanese mustard or just plain mustard (western).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It&apos;s generally categorized as Japanese mustard or plain mustard (Western).</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It&apos;s generally categorized as Japanese mustard or plain mustard (Western).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>洋からしは、大きく分け、ホワイト、ブラックの2種になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are white and black mustards among the western mustards.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are also white and black mustards among the Western mustards.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are also white and black mustards among the Western mustards.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>日本で単にからしと言う場合には主に和からしを指し、洋からしはマスタードと呼んで区別されることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan, &quot;karashi&quot; refers to Japanese mustard and western-type mustard is called simply &quot;mustard.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan, &quot;karashi&quot; refers to Japanese mustard and the Western-type mustard is called simply &quot;mustard.&quot;</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan, &quot;karashi&quot; refers to Japanese mustard and the Western-type mustard is called simply &quot;mustard.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>洋からしのほうが扱いは楽だが、味には明確な違いがあり、和からしと洋からしを取り替えた場合、そのままでも平気な場合と全く味が異なってしまう場合があることに注意する必要がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mustards are easier to handle, but there is a clear distinction between the flavor of Japanese and western mustards, and when one is mistakenly used, the effect may or may not turn out as planned.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mustards are easier to handle, but there is a clear distinction between the flavor of Japanese and Western mustards, so when one is mistakenly used the effect may or may not turn out as planned.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mustards are easier to handle, but there is a clear distinction between the flavor of Japanese and Western mustards, so when one is mistakenly used the effect may or may not turn out as planned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>また、和からしは独特のえぐみがあり、使用前にあく抜きが必要であることも、洋からしとは異なる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese mustard has distinctive bitter and astringent taste that needs to be removed before use, which is another point of distinction from mustard</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese mustard has a distinctive bitterness and an astringent aspect that needs to be removed before use, which is another point of distinction from mustard.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese mustard has a distinctive bitterness and an astringent aspect that needs to be removed before use, which is another point of distinction from mustard.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>また、その風味の違いを逆に利用して、日本ではサンドウィッチやハンバーガーなどに意図的に和からしを用いる場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taking advantage of this difference in flavor, Japanese mustard is purposely used for sandwiches and hamburgers in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taking advantage of this difference in flavor, Japanese mustard is specifically used for sandwiches and hamburgers in Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taking advantage of this difference in flavor, Japanese mustard is specifically used for sandwiches and hamburgers in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>なお、日本語では「和」からしと日本固有の食材であるかのように呼称するが、カラシナはもともと中央アジア原産の植物であり、香辛料としてのからしもインドや中国を経由して日本に伝わったものであると言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name &quot;Japanese mustard&quot; may imply that it originated in Japan, but in reality, mustard is a spice from central Asia and brought into Japan via India and China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name &quot;Japanese mustard&quot; may imply that it originated in Japan, but in reality mustard is a spice from central Asia that was brought into Japan via India and China.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name &quot;Japanese mustard&quot; may imply that it originated in Japan, but in reality mustard is a spice from central Asia that was brought into Japan via India and China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Modeha(id:1276), マクガイア(id:33346), Kenpei(id:11349), Sionnach(id:21673), Nighthawks(id:36125), 日本一弱い男(id:92046), Kzhr(id:131), 1029man(id:93235), 死郎(id:1683), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>