<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>隠居</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Inkyo-Retirement</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Inkyo-Retirement</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Inkyo (Retirement)</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>隠居（いんきょ）とは、戸主が家督を他の者に譲って、隠退すること。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Retirement is that head of the family gives away the reigns of the family to other family member and withdraw from official household affairs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Retirement is when the head of the family gives away the reigns of the family to another family member and withdraws from official household affairs.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Inkyo is when the head of the family gives away the reigns of the family to another family member and withdraws from official household affairs.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>または家督に限らず、それまであった立場などを他人に譲って、自らは悠々自適の生活を送ることなどを指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Or not limited to the reign of the family, a retiree gives his or her position he or she used to be to other person and he or she lives in otium cum dignitate himself or herself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Not limited to the reign of the family, a retiree gives his or her position to another person and he or she lives in otium cum dignitate himself or herself.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Not limited to the reign of the family, it means to give his or her position to another person and live a leisurely life.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>もしくは、第一線から退くことなど。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Or withdrawal from the front line of his or her life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Or withdrawal from his or her life occupation.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Or to withdraw from his or her life occupation.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>隠退（いんたい）とも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called &quot;Intai&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called &quot;Intai.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called intai.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>日本の民法上の制度としての隠居は、戸主が生前に家督を相続人へ譲ることを指し、日本国憲法の施行に伴う民法の応急的措置に関する法律（昭和22年法律第74号）により、日本国憲法の施行（1947年5月3日）と同時に、戸主制の廃止と共に隠居の制度は廃止された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On Civil Codes of Japan, retirement means that the head of the family hands over his reigns of the family to the heir before his death, and in accordance with the enforcement of &quot;the law regarding emergent measures on Civil Codes due to the enforcement of the Constitutions of Japan &quot; (1947 laws No.74), head of the family system and retirement system were abolished at the same time as the enforcement of the Constitutions of Japan (May 3rd, 1947).</e>
<cmt>法令名称は適訳です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With reference to the Civil Codes of Japan, retirement means that the head of the family hands over his reigns of the family to the heir before his death, and in accordance with the enforcement of &quot;the law regarding emergent measures on Civil Codes due to enforcement of the Constitution of Japan &quot; (1947 laws No.74), head of the family system and retirement system were abolished at the same time as the enforcement of the Constitution of Japan (May 3rd, 1947).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With reference to the Civil Codes of Japan, inkyo means that the head of the family hands over his reigns of the family to the heir before his death, and in accordance with the enforcement of the law regarding emergent measures on Civil Codes due to enforcement of the Constitution of Japan (No.74 laws in 1947), head of the family system and inkyo system were abolished at the same time as the enforcement of the Constitution of Japan (May 3, 1947).</e>
<cmt>日付表記を変え、クォーテーションをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>日本の隠居</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Retirement (Inkyo) in Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Retirement (Inkyo) in Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Inkyo in Japan</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>民法上の隠居</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Retirement in the Civil Codes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Retirement in the Civil Codes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Inkyo in the Civil Codes</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>民法上の隠居は、1890年（明治23年）にギュスターヴ・エミール・ボアソナードが起草し公布された旧民法（民法財産取得編人事編（明治23年法律第98号）。施行されずに廃止された。）にも見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Retirement in the Civil Codes is stipulated in the old Civil Codes drafted by Gustave Emile Boissonade and announced officially in 1890 (Civil Codes on acquisition of property and on person (laws of 1890 No.98)).</e>
<cmt>法名称は適訳です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Retirement in the Civil Codes is stipulated in the old Civil Codes drafted by Gustave Emile Boissonade and announced officially in 1890 (Civil Codes on the acquisition of property and on person - laws of 1890 No.98).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Inkyo in the Civil Codes was stipulated in the old Civil Codes drafted by Gustave Emile Boissonade and announced officially in 1890 (Civil Codes on the acquisition of property and on person (No.98 laws of 1890) which was abolished without enforcement).</e>
<cmt>原文と共に、下セルと統合しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>その後、1898年（明治31年）に公布・施行された民法第四編第五編（明治31年法律第9号）により制度化され、1947年（昭和22年）に改正されるまで続けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, retirement is institutionalized by the Civil Codes No.4 and No5 (1898 laws No.9) publicly announced and enforced in 1898, it was in effect by 1947 when Civil Codes were revised.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, retirement was institutionalized by Civil Codes No.4 and No5 (1898 laws No.9) publicly announced and enforced in 1898, it was in effect by 1947 when Civil Codes were revised.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, inkyo was institutionalized by Civil Codes No.4 and No.5 (No.9 laws in 1898) publicly announced and enforced in 1898, it was in effect by 1947 when Civil Codes were revised.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>改正前の民法では、家族の統率・監督を行うための権限である戸主権を戸主に与え、戸主たる地位を家督と言った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Civil Codes before the revision, the right to govern/direct the family I.e. the right of family head was assigned to the head of the family, and the title of the head of the family was called &quot;Katoku&quot;, the reigns of the family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Civil Codes before the revision, the right to govern/direct the family i.e. the right of family head was assigned to the head of the family, and the title of the head of the family was called &quot;Katoku,&quot; the reigns of the family.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Civil Codes before the revision, the right to govern and direct the family i.e. the right of family head was assigned to the head of the family, and the title of the head of the family was called Katoku, the reigns of the family.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>家督を家督相続人に承継させる制度が家督相続であって、隠居は家督相続の開始原因の一つである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The system of succession of reign of the family to the successor was &quot;succession of the reign of the family, and the retirement was one of the cause of the succession of reign of the family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Retirement was one of the causes for succession of the reigns of the family to a successor..</e>
<cmt>wordiness, redundancy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Inkyo was one of the causes for succession of the reigns of the family to a successor.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>隠居者およびその家督相続人が、隠居の意思表示に基づく届出を行うことにより、戸主の生前に家督相続が開始する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the retiree and the successor of the reigns of the family submit the application of retirement based on the declaration of intention of retirement, succession of the reigns of the family commenced while the head of the family is living.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When a retiree and his successor of the reigns of the family submit an application of retirement based upon a declaration of an intention to retire, succession of the reigns of the family commences while the current head of the family is still living.</e>
<cmt>grammar, wordiness, redundancy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When a retiree and his successor of the reigns of the family submit an application of inkyo based upon a declaration of an intention to retire, succession of the reigns of the family commences while the current head of the family is still living.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>改正前民法では752条以下で隠居について定め、戸主が隠居できる条件として、やむを得ない場合を除き、以下を挙げていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Civil Codes before the revision, in and after the article 752, conditions of retirement was stipulated as except for the due circumstances beyond their control,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Civil Code before the revision, in and after article 752, the conditions of retirement was stipulated a, except for the due circumstances beyond their control,</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Civil Code before the revision, in and after article 752, the conditions of inkyo was stipulated, except for the due circumstances beyond their control as follows.</e>
<cmt>原文とともに二つ下のセルと統合しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>（年齢）満六十年以上なること</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1) The head of the family becomes full 60-year old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1) The head of the family becomes 60-years old.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1) The head of the family is aged 60 or over.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>完全の能力を有する家督相続人が相続の単純承認を為すこと</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">2) Fully competent successor of the reigns of the family simply accepts the succession.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">2) Fully competent successor of the reigns of the family simply accepts the succession.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">2) Fully competent successor of the reigns of the family simply accepts the succession.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="14">
<j>隠居すると戸主は戸主権を失い、新戸主の戸主権に服することとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the head of family retired, he lost the right of the head of the family, and he had to be subject to the right of the head of the family of the new head of the family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the head of the family retires, he loses the right as the head of the family, and he has to become subject to the right of the new head of the family.</e>
<cmt>redundancy, wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the head of the family retires, he loses the right as the head of the family, and he has to become subject to the right of the new head of the family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>歴史上の隠居の実例</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Historical examples of retirement</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Historical examples of retirement</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Historical Examples of Inkyo</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="15">
<j>隠居したからと言って、それで悠々自適の生活を送るとは限らない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even once a person retired, he should not always live in otium cum dignitate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even once a person retires, he should not always live in otium cum dignitate.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even once a person retires, he or she should not always live a leisurely life.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>たとえば平安時代の白河天皇は、皇子の堀河天皇に皇位を譲って太上天皇となったが、1129年に崩御するまでは政治の実権を掌握していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, Emperor Shirakawa handed over his throne to his son, Emperor Horikawa, he became an abdicated Emperor and held the real political power until 1129 when he died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, Emperor Shirakawa handed over his throne to his son, Emperor Horikawa, he became an abdicated Emperor and held the real political power until 1129 when he died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, Emperor Shirakawa in the Heian period handed over his throne to his son, Emperor Horikawa, he became Daijo Tenno (the retired Emperor) and held the real political power until 1129 when he died.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>いわゆる院政であるが、天皇が上皇、または法皇となることも、一種の隠居と言える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a so-called &quot;In-sei&quot; (&quot;In&quot; rule), thus Emperor becomes abdicated Emperor or Cloistered Emperor and it is also a kind of retirement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a so-called &quot;In-sei&quot; (&quot;In&quot; rule), thus Emperor becomes an abdicated or Cloistered Emperor and it is also a kind of retirement.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a so-called Insei (rule by the retired Emperor), thus it is also a kind of inkyo that emperor becomes an retired or cloistered emperor.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。abdicated →retiredに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>ただしこれはあくまで律令上の公職からの隠退であり、治天の君として皇室の家督の地位はなお保持し、政治の実権を握っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, these examples were just retirements from the public duties of the Ritsuryo codes, and actually they retained the position of the head of the family and the real political power at the position of the ruler exercising his power of patriarch of the Imperial family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, these are examples of just retiring from the public duties of the Ritsuryo codes, and actually they retained the position of the head of the family and the real political power as the position of the ruler exercising his power as patriarch of the Imperial family</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, these are examples of just retiring from the public duties of the Ritsuryo codes, and in fact they retained the position of the head of the family and the real political power as the position of the ruler exercising his power as patriarch of the Imperial family</e>
<cmt>actually →in factに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>在世中に治天の君の地位をも退いた例は後鳥羽天皇や後宇多天皇などごく僅かにとどまる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were only a few examples that retired from the ruler exercising his power of patriarch of the Imperial family while he lived like Emperor Go-Toba and Emperor Go-Uda.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were only a few examples of those who retired as a ruler exercising his power as patriarch over the Imperial family while he lived, like Emperor Go-Toba and Emperor Go-Uda.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were only a few examples of those who retired as a ruler exercising his power as patriarch over the Imperial family while he lived, like Emperor Gotoba and Emperor Gouda.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="20">
<j>鎌倉幕府では、摂家将軍の藤原頼経が、将軍職からの離職を迫られて嗣子の藤原頼嗣に将軍職を譲ったものの、なお大殿と称され、将軍の後見人として振舞った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Kamakura-bakufu shogunate, although FUJIWARA no Yoritsune, a Sekke Shogun was forced to quit shogunship, and handed it over to his heir, FUJIWARA no Yoritsugu, he was still called Otono and acted as a guardian of the shogun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Kamakura-bakufu shogunate, although FUJIWARA no Yoritsune, a Sekke Shogun was forced to quit his position as shogun, and handed it over to his heir, FUJIWARA no Yoritsugu, he was still called Otono and acted as a guardian of the new shogun.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), although FUJIWARA no Yoritsune, a Sekke Shogun (Shogun from a regent family) was forced to quit his position as shogun, and handed it over to his heir, FUJIWARA no Yoritsugu, he was still called Otono and acted as a guardian of the new shogun.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>また北条時頼以降は執権を退いた得宗（北条宗家の家督）が実権を保持する例が常態となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And after the time of Tokiyori HOJO, Tokuso (reign of original house of Hojo family) who retired shikken (Shogunal Regent) retained the real power became the common style of the reign.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And after Tokiyori HOJO, Tokuso (reign of original household of the Hojo family) who retired shikken (Shogunal Regent) he retained the real power, and this became the common style during the reign.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And after Tokiyori HOJO, Tokuso (reign of original household of the Hojo family) who retired shikken (Shogunal Regent) he retained the real power, and this became the common style during the reign.</e>
<cmt>不要なスペースをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="22">
<j>室町幕府では、第3代将軍・足利義満が1394年、まだ9歳の嫡男・足利義持に将軍職を譲って出家し、居所も北山御所に移している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Muromachi-bakufu shogunate, the third shogun Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA abdicated from his shogunship and gave it to his 9-year old legitimate eldest son Yoshimochi ASHIKAGA, and became a priest and also moved his residence to Kitayama Gosho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Muromachi-bakufu shogunate, the third shogun Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA abdicated from his position as shogun and gave it to his 9-year old legitimate eldest son Yoshimochi ASHIKAGA, and became a priest and also moved his residence to Kitayama Gosho.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Muromachi bakufu, the third shogun Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA abdicated from his position as shogun and gave it to his 9-year old legitimate eldest son Yoshimochi ASHIKAGA in 1394, and became a priest and also moved his residence to Kitayama Gosho (Kitayama Palace).</e>
<cmt>年号などを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>しかし義満も1408年に51歳で死去するまでは、政治の実権を握り続けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Yoshimitsu also kept retaining the real power until he died at 51 in 1408.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Yoshimitsu also retained the real power until he died at 51 in 1408.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Yoshimitsu also retained the real power until he died at 51 in 1408.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>このように、将軍職を退いて大御所となることも、一種の隠居と言える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Like these examples, quitting shogunship and became a Ogosho (a retired leading figure) is a sort of retirement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Like these examples, quitting the position as shogun and becaming Ogosho (a retired leading figure) is a sort of retirement.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Like these examples, quitting the position as shogun and becoming Ogosho (a retired leading figure) is a sort of inkyo.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>この後も義持が足利義量に、足利義政が足利義尚に将軍職を譲りながらも実権を保持したが、これらは将軍後継を確定させる意図によるものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, Yoshimochi handed over the shugunship to Yoshikazu ASHIKAGA and Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA did the same to Yoshihisa ASHIKAGA while retaining the real power, all these were aimed at establishing the succession of shogunship.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, Yoshimochi handed over the shugunship to Yoshikazu ASHIKAGA and Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA did the same to Yoshihisa ASHIKAGA while retaining the real power, all these were aimed at establishing the succession of shoguns.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, Yoshimochi handed over the shogunship to Yoshikazu ASHIKAGA and Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA did the same to Yoshihisa ASHIKAGA while retaining the real power, all these were aimed at establishing the succession of shoguns.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>足利義稙（義稙）は家臣の細川政元により将軍職を追われて実権のない隠居となり、以降政治の実権のない守護大名およびその家臣の傀儡という立場に等しい将軍が続き、最終的には1573年、織田信長によって室町幕府は滅ぼされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshitane ASHIKAGA was forced to quit shogunship by his own subordinate Masamoto HOSOKAWA and became powerless retiree, and after this incident, shoguns became almost poweless puppets of Shugo (Military Governor) Daimyos and his subordinates, finally Muromachi-bakufu shogunate was ruined by Nobunaga ODA in 1573.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshitane ASHIKAGA was forced to quit as shogun by his own subordinate Masamoto HOSOKAWA and became a powerless retiree, and after this incident, shoguns became almost poweless puppets of Shugo (Military Governor) Daimyos and his former subordinates, finally the Muromachi-bakufu shogunate was ruined by Nobunaga ODA in 1573.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshitane ASHIKAGA was forced to quit as shogun by his own subordinate Masamoto HOSOKAWA and became a powerless retiree, and after this incident, shoguns became almost powerless puppets of Shugo daimyo (Japanese territorial lord as provincial constable) and his former subordinates, finally the Muromachi bakufu was ruined by Nobunaga ODA in 1573.</e>
<cmt>補足などをしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="27">
<j>その信長であるが、順調に天下布武を進めていた1576年、嫡男の織田信忠に家督を譲って隠居し、居城も岐阜城から安土城に移している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobunaga tried to unify Japan, and in 1576, he handed over the right of the head of the family to legitimate eldest son Nobutada ODA and retired to new residence, Azuchi Castle from Gifu Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobunaga tried to unify Japan, and in 1576, he handed over the right of the head of the family to his legitimate eldest son Nobutada ODA and retired to a new residence, Azuchi Castle from Gifu Castle.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobunaga tried to unify Japan, and in 1576, he handed over the right of the head of the family to his legitimate eldest son Nobutada ODA and retired to a new residence, Azuchi-jo Castle from Gifu-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>しかし家督は譲ったといっても、信長は1582年に本能寺の変で死去するまで、政治の実権を握り続けており、信忠の家督相続は形式的なものに過ぎなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although he assigned the right of reigns of the family, Nobunaga kept retained the real power of politics until he died at Honnoji Incident in 1582, and Nobutada&apos;s succession of the reigns of the family is merely a formal one.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although he assigned the right of the reigns of the family, Nobunaga retained the actual power of politics until he died in the Honnoji Incident in 1582, and Nobutada&apos;s succession to the reigns of the family was merely a formal one.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although he assigned the right of the reigns of the family, Nobunaga retained the actual power of politics until he died in the Honnoji Incident in 1582, and Nobutada&apos;s succession to the reigns of the family was just for form.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>一説では、信長が存命中から後継者の立場を明確にしておきたかったため、信忠に譲ったのだとも言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to one estimate, Nobunaga only gave the right of the reigns of the family to Nobutada because he wanted to establish the Nobutada&apos;s position as the heir while he was living.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to one estimate, Nobunaga only gave the right of the reigns of the family to Nobutada because he wanted to establish Nobutada&apos;s position as the heir while he was living.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to one estimate, Nobunaga only gave the right of the reigns of the family to Nobutada because he wanted to establish Nobutada&apos;s position as the heir while he was living.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>なお、信長は隠居後、「上様」という呼称を用いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the nominal retirement, Nobunga used the appellation, &quot;Uesama&quot; (the upper lord).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the nominal retirement, Nobunga used the appellation, &quot;Uesama&quot; (the upper lord).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the nominal inkyo, Nobunga used the appellation, &apos;Uesama&apos; (the upper lord).</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="31">
<j>そのほかの戦国大名では、後北条氏の歴代当主のほとんどが存命中から隠居して、家督を次代に譲って、次代の体制作りに務めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the other the Warring lords, almost all the line of family heads of Go-Hojo Clan retired while living and handed over the reigns of the family to the next generations and tried to stabilize the coming generations&apos; system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the other Warring lords, almost all family heads of the Go-Hojo Clan retired while living and handed over the reigns of the family to the next generation, trying to stabilize the future generation.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the other Warring lords, almost all family heads of the Gohojo clan retired while living and handed over the reigns of the family to the next generation, trying to stabilize the future generation.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="32">
<j>江戸幕府を開いた徳川家康も1605年、つまり将軍職に就任してからわずか2年で、三男の徳川秀忠に将軍職を譲って居城を駿府城に移している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ieyasu TOKUGAWA who established Edo bakufu shogunate retired shogunship in 1605, that is to say only 2 years after he became the shogun, and handed it over to his third son Hidetada TOKUGAWA, and moved his residence to the Sunpu-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ieyasu TOKUGAWA who established the Edo bakufu shogunate retired in 1605, only 2 years after he became shogun, and handed the position over to his third son Hidetada TOKUGAWA, and moved his residence to the Sunpu-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ieyasu TOKUGAWA who established the Edo bakufu retired in 1605, only 2 years after he became shogun, and handed the position over to his third son Hidetada TOKUGAWA, and moved his residence to the Sunpu-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>ただし、これは将軍職が以後は徳川氏によって世襲されるものであるということを諸大名や朝廷に知らしめるために行なわれただけであり、家康も信長と同じく、死ぬまで政治の実権は握り続けていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, what Ieyasu did was only to show that the shogunship was hereditary of the Tokugawa Clan afterwards to daimyos and the Court, and he also retained the real power of politics until he died just like Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, what Ieyasu did was only to show that the shogunship was hereditary in the Tokugawa Clan afterwards to daimyos and the Court, and he also retained the real power of politics until he died, just like Nobunaga did.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, what Ieyasu did was only to show that the shogunship was hereditary in the Tokugawa clan afterwards to daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) and the Imperial court, and he also retained the real power of politics until he died, just like Nobunaga did.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>現に、家康は存命中に将軍職は譲ったが、「源氏長者」の立場は決して秀忠に譲らなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Actually, although he gave his shogunship to his son while he was living, he never gave away the title of &quot;the Chief of the Genji Clan&quot; to Hidetada.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Actually, although he gave his position to his son while he was living, he never gave away the title of &quot; Chief of the Genji Clan&quot; to Hidetada.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact, although he gave his position to his son while he was living, he never gave away the title of &apos;Genji choja&apos; (the top of the Minamoto clan) to Hidetada.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。Actually→In factに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="35">
<j>その後、秀忠や徳川吉宗、徳川家斉なども将軍職を息子に譲って隠退し、大御所として政治の実権を握り続けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, Hidetada, Yoshimune Tokugawa, Ienari Tokugawa and so on handed over the shogunship to their sons and retired, and retained the real power of politics as Ogosho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, Hidetada, Yoshimune Tokugawa, Ienari Tokugawa and so on handed over their positions to their sons and retired, and retained the real power of politics as Ogosho.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, Hidetada, Yoshimune Tokugawa, Ienari Tokugawa and so on handed over their positions to their sons and retired, and retained the real power of politics as Ogosho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>江戸時代の藩主なども隠居した例は多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were many cases that lord of the domain in the Edo period retired.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were many cases where lord of the domain during the Edo period retired.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were many cases where lord of domain during the Edo period retired.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>しかし藩主においては、隠居して後も実権を握っていた例は少なく、また隠居したのも病気を理由にという例が少なくない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in the cases of lords of domains, a few of them retained the real power after retirement, and there are many cases that the reason of the retirement is illness</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in case of the lords of domains, a few of them retained the real power after retirement, and there are many cases where the reason of the retirement was illness</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in case of the lords of domains, a few of them retained the real power after inkyo, and there are many cases where the reason of the inkyo was illness</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>また、藩主の不行跡などで家臣団からの反発を受けて、強制的に後継者に家督を譲って隠居する（強制隠居）例もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, some of the lords were forced to quit the position by the group of subordinates due to his misconducts, and handed their reigns to the successors (forced retirement).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further, some of the lords were forced to quit their positions by a group of subordinates due to his misconduct, and handed their reigns to their successors (forced retirement).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further, some of the lords were forced to quit their positions by a group of subordinates due to his misconduct, and handed their reigns to their successors (forced inkyo).</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>幕末には隠居した元藩主が実権を保持または回復し、実質的な藩主として振舞った例が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the time of the last days of Tokugawa Shogunate, there are many cases that retired former Daimyos retained or regain the real power and acted substantially as Heads of the domains.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the last days of the Tokugawa Shogunate, there were many cases of retired former Daimyos retaining or regaining real power, acting substantially as Heads of the domains.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the last days of the Tokugawa Shogunate, there were many cases of retired former daimyo retaining or regaining real power, acting substantially as lords of the domains.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="40">
<j>明治時代では、一世一元の制などから、天皇が死去するまではその元号が用いられ、天皇が隠退して上皇になることなどもない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Meiji era, because of &quot;each emperor one era system&quot;, an era name was used until the Emperor died and it is not considered that Emperor retired and became a Retired Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Meiji era, because of &quot;each emperor one era system,&quot; an era name was used until the Emperor died and it is not considered that Emperor actually retired and became a Retired Emperor.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Meiji period, because of &apos;each emperor one era system,&apos; an era name was used until emperor died and it is not considered that emperor in fact retired and became a retired emperor.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。actually →in factに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="41">
<j>寺の住職も隠居する場合があり、宗派によって多少異なる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some priests of Buddhist temples retire, and in that case, the situations varies a little depends of the sects.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some priests of Buddhist temples retire, and in that case, the situation varies a little depending upon the sects.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some priests of Buddhist temples retire as inkyo, and in that case, the situation varies a little depending upon the sects.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>その場合は後任の住職をつける場合と、住職のまま隠居して副住職をつけ、副住職に寺務を代行させる場合がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some sects place successor priests, and other sects accepts the retirement and place the vice priests who take over operation of temples.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some sects place successor priests, and other sects accepts the retirement and place the vice priests who takes over the operation of the temples.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some sects place successor priests, and other sects accepts the inkyo and place the vice priests who takes over the operation of the temples.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="43">
<j>日蓮正宗総本山・大石寺の法主は隠居する場合、原則として後継者を定めて猊座を譲り、隠居することになっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the case of the archbishop of Taiseki-ji Temple, the Head Temple of Nichirenshoshu, as a principle, he has to retire after deciding the successor and gives over the position of the highest priestship to the successor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the case of the archbishop of Taiseki-ji Temple, the Head Temple of Nichirenshoshu, as a principle, he has to retire after deciding the successor and gives over the position of the highest priestship to the successor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the case of hossu (the chief priest) of Taiseki-ji Temple, the Head Temple of Nichiren Sho Sect, as a principle, he has to retire as inkyo after deciding the successor and gives over the position of the highest priestship to the successor.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>隠居しても、当代の法主が出張で不在の場合や体調不良等で代理で法要の導師を務めたり、本尊を書写したりする場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The retired archbishop may play role of the incumbent archbishop and work as the head priest at the time of Buddhist sermon or makes a copy of &quot;Honzon&quot; (principal image of the temple) when the incumbent is absent by trip or illness.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The retired archbishop may play the role of the incumbent archbishop and work as the head priest at the time of a Buddhist sermon or make a copy of &quot;Honzon&quot; (principal image of the temple) when the incumbent is absent because of a trip or illness.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The hossu in inkyo may play the role of the incumbent archbishop and work as the head priest at the time of a Buddhist sermon or make a copy of the principal image of the temple when the incumbent is absent because of a trip or illness.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>外国の隠居</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Retirement of the foreign countries</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Retirement in foreign countries</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Inkyo in Other Countries Than Japan</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>外国の隠居例</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Examples of the foreign countries</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Examples in foreign countries</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Examples in Foreign Countries</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="45">
<j>外国の王国・帝国に目を向けてみると、隠居の例は少ない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When looking around the case of foreign kingdoms and Empires, there are few cases of retirement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When considering cases in foreign kingdoms and Empires, there are few cases of retirement.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When considering cases in foreign kingdoms and Empires, there are few cases of inkyo.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>中国歴代の皇帝などでは、南宋の孝宗_(宋)や清の乾隆帝などが、皇位を後継者に譲って隠退し、上皇となっているが、ほとんどの歴代皇帝は、崩御するまで皇帝の位にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the case of line of emperors in China, though Emperor Gaozong of Southern Song Dynasty and Qian Long of Qing Dynasty retired and handed over the reigns to the successor and became Retired Emperor, the most emperors kept remains the reigns until their death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the case of the line of emperors in China, though Emperor Gaozong of the Southern Song Dynasty and Qian Long of the Qing Dynasty retired and handed over the reigns to their successors and became Retired Emperors, in contrast, most emperors kept their reigns until their death.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the case of the line of emperors in China, although Emperor Gaozong of the Southern Sung Dynasty and Qian Long of the Qing Dynasty retired and handed over the reigns to their successors and became Retired Emperors, in contrast, most emperors kept their reigns until their death.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。though →althoughに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>ヨーロッパではさらに例が少ないが、神聖ローマ帝国とスペイン王を兼任したカール5世 (神聖ローマ皇帝)（スペイン王としてはカルロス1世）は政務への疲労と病気のため退位し、残りの人生を修道院で送っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though fewer cases are found in Europe, Karl V of the Great Roman Empire who doubles with king of Spain as Carlos I retired due to the fatigue of state affairs and illness, and spent the rest of his life in a monastery.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though fewer cases are found in Europe, Karl V of the Great Roman Empire who doubles as the king of Spain as Carlos I, retired due to the fatigue of state affairs and illness, and spent the rest of his life in a monastery.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although fewer cases are found in Europe, Karl V of the Great Roman Empire who doubles as the king of Spain as Carlos I, retired due to the fatigue of state affairs and illness, and spent the rest of his life in a monastery.</e>
<cmt>Though →Althoughに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="48">
<j>このほかの欧米の国王や皇帝、アジア地域の君主のほとんども、自身が死去するまで王位・皇位についており、存命中に隠退したということはほとんどない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other than these example, the most of European kings and emperors, monarchs of Asian regions retain the reigns until his death, and there are few cases that they retired while they were alive.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other than these example, most European kings and emperors, monarchs of Asian regions retain their reigns of power until death, and there are few cases where they retired while they were alive.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other than these example, most European kings and emperors, monarchs of Asian regions retain their reigns of power until death, and there are few cases where they retired while they were alive.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>ただし、国王や皇帝が時の権力者によって廃されたり、その君主の身体的理由で政務を執れないということから、政治の実権を別の人物に譲っているという例はある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there are examples that kings and emperors were dethroned by the persons in authority at the time, and the monarchy could not administer the affairs of state due to his physical reasons and handed over the throne to the another person.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there are examples where kings and emperors were dethroned by the persons in authority at the time, and the monarchy could not administer the affairs of state due to physical limitations and handed over the throne to the another person.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there are examples where kings and emperors were dethroned by the persons in authority at the time, and the monarchy could not administer the affairs of state due to physical limitations and handed over the throne to the another person.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>隠居一般</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Retirement in general</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Retirement in general</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Inkyo in General</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>隠居による長所と短所</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Merit and demerit of retirement</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Merits and demerits of retirement</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Merits and Demerits of Inkyo</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="50">
<j>長所</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Merit</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Merits</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Merits</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>隠居のよいところは、優れた後継者を作りやすい、もしくはその後継者を身体的にも精神的にも鍛え上げることができるということである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Merit of retirement is that with this system, excellent successor could be built up, or the successor could be built up physically and mentally.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Merits of retirement is that with this system, an excellent successor could be mentored, or the successor could be prepared physically and mentally.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Merits of inkyo is that with this system, an excellent successor could be mentored, or the successor could be prepared physically and mentally.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>たとえば信長、家康などは嫡男に家督を譲って隠居した後も政治の実権は握り続けていたが、小さいことなどは息子に任せていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, while Nobunaga and Ieyasu retained the real power of politics even after their retirement, minor things were left for their sons.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, while Nobunaga and Ieyasu retained the real power of politics, even after being retired, minor things were left for their sons.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, while Nobunaga and Ieyasu retained the real power of politics, even after being retired, minor things were left for their sons.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>1582年の武田氏追討戦をはじめとする隠居後の戦いにおいては、信長は信忠を総大将にしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the battles after Nobunaga&apos;s retirement such as punitive battle of Takeda clan in 1582, Nobunaga designated the Nobutada as the head of the army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the battles after Nobunaga retired, such as the punitive battle of the Takeda clan in 1582, Nobunaga designated Nobutada as head of the army.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the battles after Nobunaga retired, such as the punitive battle of the Takeda clan in 1582, Nobunaga designated Nobutada as head of the army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>家康も秀忠に将軍職を譲った後、側近中の側近である本多正信と大久保忠隣などを守役としてつけて、秀忠の後継者としての養育に当たらせている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also after Ieyasu handed over shogunship to Hidetada, he designated the closest retainers, Masanobu HONDA and Tadachika OKUBO as a backer of the successor Hidetada and let them build him up.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also after Ieyasu handed over his position to Hidetada, he designated the closest retainers, Masanobu HONDA and Tadachika OKUBO as backers of successor Hidetada and let them build him up.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also after Ieyasu handed over his position to Hidetada, he designated the closest retainers, Masanobu HONDA and Tadachika OKUBO as supporters of successor Hidetada and let them build him up.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>また、天正12（1584）年に41歳の男盛りだった伊達輝宗が嫡男の伊達政宗に家督を譲ったことで、政宗とその弟伊達小次郎の後継者争いを抑え、政宗が飛躍する足がかりを作ったことも、隠居の成功例として有名だ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also famous success of retirement that Terumune DATE when he was 41 and in his virility handed over the right of the reigns of the family to legitimate eldest son Masamune DATE, and brought under control of the conflict between Masamune and his younger brother Kojiro DATE for the successor, and it gave Masamune a chance to make a giant step.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also famous is successful retirement Terumune DATE when he was just 41in his virility, he handed over the reigns of the family to his legitimate eldest son Masamune DATE, and brought under control of the conflict between Masamune and his younger brother Kojiro DATE for succession, and it gave Masamune a chance to take a giant step.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also famous is successful inkyo Terumune DATE in 1584 when he was just 41 in his virility, he handed over the reigns of the family to his legitimate eldest son Masamune DATE, and brought under control of the conflict between Masamune and his younger brother Kojiro DATE for succession, and it gave Masamune a chance to take a giant step.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>このように、隠居には後継者を作るという点で、様々なメリットがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Like these, retirement has many merits from the view point of building up a successor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Like these examples, retirement has many merits from the view point of building up a successor.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Like these examples, inkyo has many merits from the view point of building up a successor.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="57">
<j>短所</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Demerit</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Demerits</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Demerits</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>隠居の短所を挙げるとすれば、その実権をめぐっての争いである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When considering the demerit of the retirement, there often raises a conflict for the real power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When considering demerits of retirement, it often raises a conflict for real power.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When considering demerits of inkyo, it often raises a conflict for real power.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>例えば隠居したAという人物が、なおも実権を握り続けたために、新たに家督に就いた人物Ｂはただの傀儡に過ぎないという例があったとする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, if retired person &quot;A&quot; continues to retain the real power and &quot;B&quot; who newly hold the reigns of the family is only a puppet of &quot;A&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, when retired person &quot;A&quot; continues to retain real power and &quot;B&quot; who newly holds the reigns of the family is only a puppet of &quot;A&quot;.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, when retired person A continues to retain real power and B who newly holds the reigns of the family is only a puppet of A.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>すると、このような形式的な隠居に不満を持ったBが、Aに対して反乱を起こすということもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then &quot;B&quot; who is discontent with formal retirement may cause a rebel against &quot;A&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then &quot;B&quot; who is discontent with formal retirement may cause a rebel against &quot;A.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then B who is discontent with formal inkyo may cause a rebel against A.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="61">
<j>日本の戦国時代では、豊後国の大友義鎮と大友義統の例が挙げられるかも知れない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the history of Japan, example of Yoshishige OTOMO and Yoshimune OTOMO of the Province of Bungo in the Warring States period may be typical.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the history of Japan, the example of Yoshishige OTOMO and Yoshimune OTOMO from the Province of Bungo during the Warring States period, may be typical.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the history of Japan, the example of Yoshishige OTOMO and Yoshimune OTOMO of the Bungo Province during the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States), may be typical.</e>
<cmt>用語表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>宗麟は早くに嫡男の義統に家督を譲って出家したが、なおも実権は握り続けていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sorin OTOMO handed over the reigns of the family at an early stage to his legitimate eldest son, Yoshimune OTOMO and became a monk, however, he continued to retain the real power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sorin OTOMO handed over the reigns of the family at an early stage to his legitimate eldest son, Yoshimune OTOMO and became a monk, however, he continued to retain the real power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sorin (Sorin OTOMO) handed over the reigns of the family at an early stage to his legitimate eldest son, Yoshimune and became a priest, however, he continued to retain the real power.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>そのため、義統は形式的な君主に過ぎず、1580年頃には宗麟と義統の関係は不和だったと言われているし、大友氏が島津氏の侵攻に一方的に押されたのも、耳川の戦いにおける敗戦だけではなく、家中における権力闘争も原因だったと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of that, Yoshimune was a nominal monarchy and it is said that the relation with his father Sorin was not good around year 1580, and the reason why the Otomo Clan was one-sidedly pushed by the Shimazu Clan&apos;s invasion was not only the lost war of the battle of Mimikawa but also the infighting of the Otomo Clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of that, Yoshimune was a nominal monarchy and it is said that the relationship with his father, Sorin, was not good around the year 1580, and the reason why the Otomo Clan was one-sidedly pushed by the Shimazu Clan invasion was not only for losing the war at the battle of Mimikawa, but also the infighting of the Otomo Clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of that, Yoshimune was a nominal monarchy and it is said that the relationship with his father, Sorin, was not good around 1580, and the reason why the Otomo clan was one-sidedly pushed by the Shimazu clan invasion was not only for losing the war at the battle of Mimikawa, but also the infighting of the Otomo clan.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="64">
<j>また、武田信玄のように隠居せずに死去するまで実権を握り続け、次代の後継者作りや体制作りを忘れたがために滅びた例もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, there is an example such as Shingen TAKEDA that he retained the real power until his death and failed to build up the next generation&apos;s successor and system, and finally ruined.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further, there is the example of Shingen TAKEDA who retained real power until his death and failed to mentor the next generation&apos;s successor to maintain the system, and was finally ruined.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further, there is the example of Shingen TAKEDA who retained real power until his death and failed to mentor the next generation&apos;s successor to maintain the system, and was finally ruined.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>信玄の死後、武田氏が9年で滅びたのは、次代の武田勝頼における体制作りが行なわれていなかったためとも言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reason why Takeda Clan ruined only within nine years after the death of Shingen is said that inner system for Katsuyori TAKEDA of the next generation was not established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reason why the Takeda Clan was ruined only within nine years after the death of Shingen is said to be that the inner system for Katsuyori TAKEDA of the next generation was not established.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reason why the Takeda clan was ruined only within nine years after the death of Shingen is said to be that the inner system for Katsuyori TAKEDA of the next generation was not established.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>このため、武田家内部では信玄時代の老臣派と、勝頼時代の側近衆による不和も起きている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of the above, there were friction between the old vassals group of the time of Shingen and close retainers group of the time of Katsuyori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of the above, there was friction between the old vassals group from the time of Shingen and the close retainers group from the time of Katsuyori.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of the above, there was friction inside the Takeda family between the old vassals group from the time of Shingen and the close retainers group from the time of Katsuyori.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="67">
<j>隠居が問題で、その家が滅んだ例もあるほどで、隠居は言わば慎重に考える必要があると思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As there were cases that the retirement was problematic and the whole family ruined, retirement has to be considered carefully.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because there were cases where retirement was problematic and the whole family ruined, retirement has to be considered carefully.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because there were cases where inkyo was problematic and the whole family ruined, inkyo has to be considered carefully.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Izayohi(id:13095), Rusk(id:9895), Newport8865(id:71168), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), MIsogi(id:20599), 経済準学士(id:22656), 水野白楓(id:22811), 富樫仁(TOGASHI Jin)(id:53524), Ss67(id:119057), Extrahitz(id:26245), 伊集院聖(id:53199), Hokahoka(id:37244), シェーラ(id:17988), 磯野波平(id:28232), Aboshi(id:9318), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>