<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>能阿弥</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Noami</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Noami</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Noami</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>能阿弥（のうあみ、応永4年（1397年） - 文明 (日本)3年（1471年））は、室町時代の画家、茶人、連歌師。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Noami (1397 - 1471) is a painter, master of ceremonial tea, and Rengashi (poet who only writes Tsureuta (early Japanese poetry form)) who lived in the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Noami (1397 - 1471) is a painter, master of ceremonial tea, and Rengashi (poet who only writes Tsureuta - early Japanese poetry form) who lived during the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Noami (1397 - 1471) is a painter, master of ceremonial tea, and a renga (linked poem) poet who lived during the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>連歌師→a renga (linked poem) poetとしました。(参照: 新和英中辞典)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>本姓は中尾、名は真能（さねよし）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His real name is Saneyoshi NAKAO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His real name is Saneyoshi NAKAO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His real name is Saneyoshi NAKAO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>法号は真能。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His hogo (a Buddhist name) is Saneyoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His hogo (a Buddhist name) is Saneyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His hogo (a Buddhist name) is Shinno.</e>
<cmt>Saneyoshi→Shinnoに修正 (参照: http://kotobank.jp/word/%E7%9C%9F%E8%83%BD)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>号は鴎斎、春鴎斎子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He has Osai and Shun O Sai shi as his go, or names other than his real name.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He has Osai and Shun O Sai shi as his go, or names other than his real name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He has Osai and Shun O Sai shi as his go, or names other than his real name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>子に芸阿弥、孫に相阿弥がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Geiami is Noami&apos;s son, and Soami is Noami&apos;s grandson.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Geiami is Noami&apos;s son, and Soami is Noami&apos;s grandson.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Geiami is Noami&apos;s son, and Soami is Noami&apos;s grandson.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>元は越前朝倉氏の家臣だったが、足利義教、足利義政に同朋衆として仕えて能阿弥と号し、幕府における書画等（唐物）の鑑定や管理を行い、また東山御物の制定を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally a subordinate of Echizen-Asakurashi (Asakura clan), Noami served Yoshinori ASHIKAGA and Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA as a member of Doboshu (Shogun&apos;s cultural curators or experts) and called himself Noami; and he appraised and managed things imported from China such as paintings and writings, and he also established higashiyama gyomotsu (things, such as paintings, tea utensils, flower vases, collected by Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA, shogun of the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally a subordinate of Echizen-Asakurashi (Asakura clan), Noami served Yoshinori ASHIKAGA and Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA as a member of Doboshu (Shogun&apos;s cultural curators or experts) and called himself Noami; and he appraised and managed things imported from China such as paintings and writings, and he also established higashiyama gyomotsu (things, such as paintings, tea utensils, flower vases, collected by Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA, shogun of the Muromachi bakufu - Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally a subordinate of the Echizen-Asakura clan, Noami served Yoshinori ASHIKAGA and Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA as a member of Doboshu (Shogun&apos;s cultural curators or experts) and called himself Noami; and he appraised and managed things imported from China such as paintings and writings, and he also established higashiyama gyomotsu (things, such as paintings, tea utensils, flower vases, collected by Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA, shogun of the Muromachi bakufu - Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>Echizen-Asakurashi (Asakura clan)→the Echizen-Asakura clanとし、Shogun’sのアポストロフィーを半角に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>特に水墨画に優れ阿弥派の開祖とされ、鶴図を描き義政に絶賛されたといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Noami was especially excellent at Suiboku-ga (ink painting) and is considered the founder of Ami-ha group of painters; and it is said that Noami&apos;s painting of cranes was highly praised by Yoshimasa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Noami was especially excellent at Suiboku-ga (ink painting) and is considered the founder of the Ami-ha group of painters; and it is said that Noami&apos;s painting of cranes was highly praised by Yoshimasa.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Noami was especially excellent at Suiboku-ga (ink painting) and is considered the founder of the Ami-ha group of painters; and it is said that Noami&apos;s painting of cranes was highly praised by Yoshimasa.</e>
<cmt>Noami’sのアポストロフィーを半角に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>泉涌寺妙厳院のある「白衣観音図」は、1471年（文明3年）に能阿弥が描いたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Hakui Kannon zu (painting of Kannon (Buddhist deity of mercy) in white wearing) in Myogon-in, Sennyu-ji temple was painted by Noami in 1471.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hakui Kannon zu (painting of Kannon (Buddhist deity of mercy - wearing white) in Myogon-in, Sennyu-ji temple was painted by Noami in 1471.</e>
<cmt>punctuation, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &apos;Hakui Kannon zu&apos; (painting of Kannon (Buddhist deity of mercy - wearing white) in Myogon-in, Sennyu-ji Temple was painted by Noami in 1471.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション追加、Sennyu-ji Templeとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>茶道においては、書院飾りの完成、台子飾りの方式の制定などを行い、『山上宗二記』では「同朋中の名人」と記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Sado (tea ceremony), Noami completed the shoin kazari (decoration of shoin (one of Japan&apos;s most important residential architectural styles, established in the Momoyama period) rooms and buildings) and established the formalities for daisu kazari (decorating the utensil stand), among other achievements, and is described as an &quot;expert of the companions&quot; in YAMANOUE no Soji ki (book of secrets written by YAMANOUE no Soji, best pupil of SEN no Rikyu, a great tea master).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Sado (tea ceremony), Noami completed the shoin kazari (decoration of shoin (one of Japan&apos;s most important residential architectural styles, established in the Momoyama period - rooms and buildings) and established the formalities for daisu kazari (decorating the utensil stand), among other achievements, and is described as an &quot;expert of the companions&quot; in YAMANOUE no Soji ki (book of secrets written by YAMANOUE no Soji, best pupil of SEN no Rikyu, a great tea master).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Sado (tea ceremony), Noami completed the shoin kazari (decoration of shoin (one of Japan&apos;s most important residential architectural styles, established in the Momoyama period - rooms and buildings) and established the formalities for daisu kazari (decorating the utensil stand), among other achievements, and is described as an &apos;expert of the companions&apos; in &quot;Yamanoue no Soji ki&quot; (book of secrets written by YAMANOUE no Soji, best pupil of SEN no Rikyu, a great tea master).</e>
<cmt>Japan’sのアポストロフィーを半角に修正、&apos;expert of the companions&apos;、およびタイトルのため&quot;Yamanoue no Soji ki&quot;としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>そのほか連歌、華道にも優れ、連歌では七賢の一人に挙げられ、北野天満宮の連歌奉行も務めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, Noami also excelled at Tsureuta and Kado (flower arrangement); and he was named one of the seven wise men in Tsureuta and served Renga bugyo (magistrate of Renga (another term for Tsureuta) party) of Kitano Tenman-gu temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, Noami also excelled at Tsureuta and Kado (flower arrangement); and he was named one of the seven wise men in Tsureuta and served Renga bugyo (magistrate of Renga party - another term for Tsureuta) of Kitano Tenman-gu temple.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, Noami also excelled at renga and kado (flower arrangement); and he was named one of the Seven Wise Men in Renga and served Renga Bugyo (magistrate of renga party) of Kitano Tenmangu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>Tsureuta→rengaとし、Kadoの頭文字を小文字に変更、「七賢」「連歌奉行」の表記を修正、Kitano Tenman-gu temple→Kitano Tenmangu Shrineとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>著書に『君台観左右帳記』がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Noami is an author of Kundaikansochoki (book of secrets about zashiki-kazari (decoration of room or study with shoin)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Noami is the author of Kundaikansochoki (book of secrets about zashiki-kazari - decoration of room or study with shoin).</e>
<cmt>punctuation, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Noami is the author of &quot;Kundaikansochoki&quot; (book of secrets about zashiki-kazari - decoration of room or study with shoin).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>（相阿弥の時に完成）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Kundaikansochoki was completed by Soami)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Kundaikansochoki was completed by Soami)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Kundaikansochoki was completed by Soami)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 AlleborgoBot(id:119729), Oxhop(id:2551), Sugitaro(id:35441), Cprobot(id:97843), 松茸(id:27535), Mzaki(id:61977), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>