<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>市川壽海 (3代目)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jukai ICHIKAWA (Sandaime (third))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jukai ICHIKAWA (Sandaime (third))</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jukai ICHIKAWA (Sandaime (third))</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>昭和26年12月大阪歌舞伎座顔見世興行『少将滋幹の母』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">December 1951, Osaka Kabukiza kaomisekogyo (the season&apos;s first performance with the new company) &quot;Shosho Shigemoto no haha&quot; (Mother of shosho Shigemoto)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">December 1951, Osaka Kabukiza kaomisekogyo (the season&apos;s first performance with the new company) &quot;Shosho Shigemoto no haha&quot; (Mother of shosho Shigemoto)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 1951, Osaka Kabukiza kaomisekogyo (the season&apos;s first performance with the new company) &quot;Shosho Shigemoto no haha&quot; (Mother of shosho Shigemoto)</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>三代目 市川壽海（さんだいめ いちかわ じゅかい、新字体：寿海、明治16年（1886年）7月12日 - 昭和46年（1971年『4月3日）は大正から昭和前期にかけて活躍した歌舞伎役者。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jukai ICHIKAWA III (&apos;寿海&apos; in new character form; July 12, 1886 - April 3, 1971) was a kabuki actor, who was actively played in Taisho to the beginning of Showa era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jukai ICHIKAWA III (&apos;寿海&apos; in new character form; July 12, 1886 - April 3, 1971) was a kabuki actor, who was actively played in Taisho to the beginning of Showa era.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jukai (壽海) ICHIKAWA III (&apos;寿海&apos; in new simplified Chinese characters; July 12, 1886 - April 3, 1971) was a kabuki actor, who was active from the Taisho to the beginning of Showa period.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>屋号は成田屋。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His stage family name was Naritaya.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His stage family name was Naritaya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His acting house name was Naritaya.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>本名は太田 照造（おおた しょうぞう）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His real name was Shozo OOTA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His real name was Shozo OOTA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His real name was Shozo OTA.</e>
<cmt>Ota　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>「三代目」とはいいながら、この「市川壽海」の名跡を襲名したのはこの太田照造ただ一人なので、かれのことを単に市川壽海（いちかわ じゅかい）と呼ぶこともあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although, he was called &quot;Sandaime (third),&quot; only this Shozo OTA used the name &quot;Jukai ICHIKAWA,&quot; he was sometimes called simply &quot;Jukai ICHIAKAWA.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although, he was called &quot;Sandaime (third),&quot; only this Shozo OTA used the name &quot;Jukai ICHIKAWA,&quot; he was sometimes called simply &quot;Jukai ICHIAKAWA.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although, he was called &apos;Sandaime&apos; (third), only Shozo OTA used the name &apos;Jukai ICHIKAWA,&apos; and he was sometimes simply called &quot;Jukai ICHIKAWA.&quot;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。人名を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>主に関西歌舞伎を中心に舞台を勤め、中村鴈治郎 (初代)・中村魁車・中村梅玉 (3代目)らの死後は、阪東壽三郎 (3代目)と並んで「双壽時代」と呼ばれる一時代を築く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He mainly performed in Kansai Kabuki and, after death of Ganjiro NAKAMURA (I), Kaisha NAKAMURA and Baigyoku NAKAMURA (III), he established an epoch called &quot;Soju Jidai&quot; (era of two Ju) together with Jusaburo BANDO (III).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He mainly performed in Kansai Kabuki and, after death of Ganjiro NAKAMURA (I), Kaisha NAKAMURA and Baigyoku NAKAMURA (III), he established an epoch called &quot;Soju Jidai&quot; (era of two Ju) together with Jusaburo BANDO (III).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He mainly performed in Kansai Kabuki and, after the death of Ganjiro NAKAMURA (I), Kaisha NAKAMURA and Baigyoku NAKAMURA (III), he established an epoch called &apos;Soju Jidai&apos; (era of two Ju) together with Jusaburo BANDO (III).</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>来歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Histrical trail</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Historical trail</e>
<cmt>Spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>東京府東京市日本橋区日本橋蛎殻町の仕立職・中村力蔵の子として生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born as a child of Rikizo NAKAMURA, who was a tailor, in Nihonbashi Kakigara-cho, Nihonbashi Ward, Tokyo City, Tokyo Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born as a child of Rikizo NAKAMURA, who was a tailor, in Nihonbashi Kakigara-cho, Nihonbashi Ward, Tokyo City, Tokyo Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born as a child of Rikizo NAKAMURA, who was a tailor, in Nihonbashi Kakigara-cho, Nihonbashi Ward, Tokyo City, Tokyo Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>明治27年 (1894) 5月、市川小團次 (5代目)に入門して市川高丸と名乗り、明治座で初舞台。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In May 1894, he became a pupil of Kodanji ICHIKAWA (V) and took the name of Takamaru ICHIKAWA and performed for the first time in Meijiza theater.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In May 1894, he became a pupil of Kodanji ICHIKAWA (V) and took the name of Takamaru ICHIKAWA and performed for the first time in Meijiza theater.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In May 1894, he became a pupil of Kodanji ICHIKAWA (V) and took the name of Takamaru ICHIKAWA and performed for the first time at the Meijiza theater.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>明治36年 (1903) 1月、市川小満之助と改める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January 1903, he changed his name to Komanosuke ICHIKAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In January 1903, he changed his name to Komanosuke ICHIKAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In January 1903, he changed his name to Komanosuke ICHIKAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>明治38年 (1905) 5月、市川壽美蔵の養子となって市川登升を襲名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In May 1905, he was adopted by Sumizo ICHIKAWA and inherited the name of Tomasu ICHIKAWA [市川登升 正しい読み不明].</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In May 1905, he was adopted by Sumizo ICHIKAWA and inherited the name of Tomasu ICHIKAWA [市川登升 正しい読み不明].</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In May 1905, he was adopted by Sumizo ICHIKAWA and inherited the name of Tomasu ICHIKAWA (市川登升).</e>
<cmt>読み方が不明ですので、漢字を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>これが出世の糸口となって、翌年には名題昇進。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This led up to his advancement and he was promoted to the chief actor in next year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This led up to his advancement and he was promoted to chief actor the following year.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This led up to his promotion and he was promoted to chief actor the following year.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>翌明治40年 (1907) 3月、明治座において六代目市川壽美蔵を襲う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In March 1907, she succeeded Sumizo ICHIKAWA (VI) in Meijiza theater.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In March 1907, she succeeded Sumizo ICHIKAWA (VI) in Meijiza theater.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In March 1907, he succeeded Sumizo ICHIKAWA (VI) at the Meijiza theater.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="14">
<j>しかし東京大歌舞伎ではなかなか役に恵まれず、大正時代には市川左團次 (2代目)の演劇革新運動に加わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Tokyo Kabuki, however, he could not have satisfactory roles and, in the Taisho era, he joined Sadanji ICHIKAWA(II)&apos;s theater reform movement.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Tokyo Kabuki, however, he was unable to obtain satisfactory roles and, in the Taisho era, he joined Sadanji ICHIKAWA(II)&apos;s theater reform movement.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Tokyo Oo Kabuki, however, he was unable to obtain satisfactory roles and, in the Taisho period, he joined the theater reform movement of Sadanji ICHIKAWA (II).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>左團次の死後は昭和10年 (1935) から市川猿翁の一座に、また昭和23年 (1948) からは関西歌舞伎に身を投じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Sadanji&apos;s death, he joined Eno ICHIKAWA&apos;s company from 1935 and, from 1948, he joined Kansai Kabuki.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Sadanji&apos;s death, he joined Eno ICHIKAWA&apos;s company from 1935 and, from 1948, he joined Kansai Kabuki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Sadanji&apos;s death, he joined Eno ICHIKAWA&apos;s company from 1935, then he joined Kansai Kabuki from 1948.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="16">
<j>昭和24年2月、大阪歌舞伎座の『助六』と『大森彦七』で三代目市川壽海を襲名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In February 1949, he succeeded Jukai ICHKAWA (III) in &quot;Sukeroku&quot; and &quot;Omori Hikoshichi&quot; in Osaka Kabukiza theater.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In February 1949, he succeeded Jukai ICHKAWA (III) in &quot;Sukeroku&quot; and &quot;Omori Hikoshichi&quot; in Osaka Kabukiza theater.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In February 1949, he succeeded Jukai ICHIKAWA (III) in &quot;Sukeroku&quot; and &quot;Omori Hikoshichi&quot; at the Osaka Kabukiza theater.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>戦中戦後の名優の相次ぐ死で中堅の役者が手薄になった関西歌舞伎において、阪東壽三郎と並んで中心的な役割を担い、壽三郎の死後は文字通りその重鎮としてこれを見守った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kansai Kabuki, which did not have sufficient number of middle class actors because of successive death of famous actors from the time of the War and after the War, he played a central role together with Jusaburo BADO and, after Jusaburo&apos;s death, kept watching it as the leader.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Kansai Kabuki, which did not have a sufficient number of middle class actors because of successive deaths by famous actors from the time of the War and after the War, he played a central role together with Jusaburo BADO and, after Jusaburo&apos;s death, kept watching it as the leader.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Kansai Kabuki, which did not have a sufficient number of middle class actors because of the successive deaths by famous actors during and after the War, Jukai played a central role together with Jusaburo BANDO and, after Jusaburo&apos;s death, kept watching it as the leader.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="18">
<j>しかし「関西歌舞伎生え抜き」の壽三郎に対して、壽海には「東京から移籍してきよった役者」という偏見がつきまとった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In contrast with Jusaburo who was &quot;Kansai Kabuki actor from the start,&quot; Jukai was dogged with the prejudice that &quot;he is an actor transferred from Tokyo.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In contrast with Jusaburo who was &quot;Kansai Kabuki actor from the start,&quot; Jukai was dogged with the prejudice that &quot;he is an actor transferred from Tokyo.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In contrast with Jusaburo who was the &apos;Kansai Kabuki actor from the start,&apos; Jukai was dogged with the prejudice that &apos;he is an actor transferred from Tokyo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>その壽海を中心に据えたする興行の形態が、関西歌舞伎の役者たちからの反発を招いたのも無理はなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was only natural that the form of performance putting Jukai in the center elicited angry response from actors of Kansai Kabuki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was only natural that placing Jukai at the center of the performance elicited an angry response from actors of Kansai Kabuki.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was only natural that the performance having Jukai at the center of it elicited an angry response from actors of Kansai Kabuki.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>壽海自身も関西歌舞伎俳優協会会長の立場にありながら、壽三郎の死をきっかけに起きた関西歌舞伎の混乱と衰退への怒濤のような流れを食い止めることができなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Jukai himself was in the position of the chairman of the Kansai Kabuki Haiku Koki (the Kansai Kabuki Actors&apos; Association), he could not stop the surging wave of confusion in and decline of Kansai Kabuki occurred with Jusaburo&apos;s death as a start.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Jukai himself was in the position of the chairman of the Kansai Kabuki Haiku Koki (the Kansai Kabuki Actors&apos; Association), he could not stop the wave of confusion, and the decline of Kansai Kabuki started with the death of Jusaburo.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Jukai himself held the position of chairman of the Kansai Kabuki Haiyu Kyokai (the Kansai Kabuki Actors&apos; Association), he could not stop waves of confusion, and the decline of Kansai Kabuki started with the death of Jusaburo.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>要するに相性が良くなかったことがその大きな原因だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In short, the biggest cause was bad matching.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In short, the biggest cause was due to simple mismatching.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In short, the biggest cause was due to simple incompatibility.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>やがて壽海も自らの舞台の確保に苦しむことになり、これが養子に迎えた市川雷蔵 (8代目)が梨園と決別して映画界入りする一因ともなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, Jukai himself had difficulty to secure opportunities to perform and this became one of reasons for his adopted son, Raizo ICHIKAWA (VIII) left the kabuki world and enter the world of cinema.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eventually, Jukai himself had difficulty in securing opportunities to perform and this became one of the reasons his adopted son, Raizo ICHIKAWA (VIII) left the kabuki world to enter the world of cinema.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eventually, Jukai himself had difficulty in securing opportunities to perform, which was one of the reasons his adopted son, Raizo ICHIKAWA (VIII) left the kabuki world to enter the world of cinema.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="23">
<j>壽海は舞台上・日常を問わず、温厚な紳士だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a gentleman with a warm personality on and off the stage.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>京都が好きで晩年は伏見に居住している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He loved Kyoto and lived in Fushimi in his later years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He loved Kyoto and lived in Fushimi in his later years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He loved Kyoto and lived in Fushimi in his later years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>昭和46年 (1971) 4月3日死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 3, 1971, he died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 3, 1971, he died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died on April 3, 1971.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>84歳だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was eighty-four years old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was eighty-four years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was eighty-four years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="27">
<j>最後の舞台は前年12月京都南座顔見世『将軍江戸を去る』の徳川慶喜。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His last stage was the role of Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA in Kyoto Minamiza theater&apos;s kaomise kogyo &quot;Shogun Edo wo saru&quot; (Shogun leaving Edo) in December 1970.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His last stage was the role of Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA in Kyoto Minamiza theater&apos;s kaomise kogyo &quot;Shogun Edo wo saru&quot; (Shogun leaving Edo) in December 1970.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His last performance was the role of Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA in Kyoto Minamiza theater&apos;s kaomise kogyo &quot;Shogun Edo wo saru&quot; (Shogun leaving Edo) in December 1970.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>この時すでに体力が衰え、歩くことはおろか立つことさえもままならなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Already at that time, however, he had lost strength and, needless to say walking, he could not stand up freely.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By this time, he had lost much of his physical strength, and it was a great effort for him to stand, much less walk.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By this time, he had lost much of his physical strength, and it was a great effort for him to stand, much less walk.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>舞台ではずっと座りっぱなしだったが、千穐楽の日、大詰の「千住大橋の場」幕切れで、ふと何かに取り憑かれたかのようにすっくと立ち上った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although he kept sitting on the stage, on the day of senshuraku (closing day), he stood up as if possessed by something at the final scene of the &quot;Senju Ohashi no Ba&quot; (scene of Senju Ohashi bridge) just before the fall of curtain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although he kept sitting on the stage, on the day of senshuraku (closing day), he stood up as if possessed by something at the final scene of the &quot;Senju Ohashi no Ba&quot; (scene of Senju Ohashi bridge) just before the fall of curtain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While he mainly sat while on stage, on the day of senshuraku (closing day), he stood up as if possessed during the final scene of the &apos;Senju Ohashi no B&apos;&quot; (scene of Senju Ohashi Bridge) just before the fall of the curtain.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>観客は驚きどよめいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The audience was surprised and stirred.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The audience was surprised and stirred.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The audience was surprised and made a stir.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>大向うからの「立ったぁ〜！」の掛け声と場内万雷の拍手に包まれながら、定引幕が引かれて壽海を舞台奥に消し去った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Surrounded with enthusiastic shout from the regular audience &quot;Tatta!&quot; (stood) and thunderous applause in the hall, the johikimaku (curtain) was closed and Jukai disappeared into the back of the stage.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Surrounded with enthusiastic shout from the regular audience &quot;Tatta!&quot; (he stood up!) and thunderous applause in the hall, the johikimaku (curtain) was closed and Jukai disappeared into the back of the stage.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Surrounded by enthusiastic shouts from the regular audience &apos;Tatta!&apos; (he stood up!) and thunderous applause in the hall, the johikimaku (curtain) was closed to hide Jukai into the back of the stage.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>誰もがその遠くない最期を一瞬予感するような伝説的な最後となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was the legendary last scene which made everybody feel a foreboding of his last in near future.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was a legendary last scene which caused a sense of foreboding for everyone.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was a legendary last scene which caused a sense of foreboding for everyone.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="33">
<j>芸風</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Style of performance</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Style of performance</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Style of performance</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>若々しく、朗々とした口跡が特徴で、青春の香りを晩年まで漂わせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Youthful and silvery voice projection was one of his features and he had smell of the springtime of life around him until his later years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His main features lay in his young and silvery voice projection together which exuded youthfulness that surrounded him until his later years.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His main features lay in his young and silvery way of speaking his lines together which exuded youthfulness that surrounded him until his later years.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>真山青果や岡本綺堂の新作を「名作」の域に昇華させたのも壽海の功績である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was Jukai&apos;s merits to have sublimed new works of Seika MAYAMA and Kido OKAMOTO in &quot;masterpieces.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was Jukai&apos;s merits to have sublimed new works of Seika MAYAMA and Kido OKAMOTO in &quot;masterpieces.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jukai&apos;s merits lay in his taking new works by Seika MAYAMA and Kido OKAMOTO to the realm of &apos;masterpieces.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="36">
<j>二代目市川左團次によく学び、『頼朝の死』の源頼家、『桐一葉』の木村重成『鳥辺山心中』の菊地半九郎『番町皿屋敷』の青山播磨、『将軍江戸を去る』の徳川慶喜、『少将滋幹の母』の時平などの新作物の第一人者であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He learned from Sadanji ICHIKAWA (II) very well and was the top player of new works such as MINAMOTO no Yoriie in &quot;Yoritomo no shi&quot; (Yoritomo&apos;s death), Shigenari KIMUA in &quot;Kiri hitoha&quot; (a single paulownia leaf), Hankuro KIKUCHI in &quot;Toribe yama shinju&quot; (Love-suicides at Toribe-yama mountain), Harima AOYAMA in &quot;Ban-cho sarayashiki,&quot; Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA in &quot;Shogun Edo wo saru,&quot; and Tokihira in &quot;Shosho Shigemoto no haha.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He learned well from Sadanji ICHIKAWA (II) and was the top player of new works such as MINAMOTO no Yoriie in &quot;Yoritomo no shi&quot; (Yoritomo&apos;s death), Shigenari KIMUA in &quot;Kiri hitoha&quot; (a single paulownia leaf), Hankuro KIKUCHI in &quot;Toribe yama shinju&quot; (Love-suicides at Toribe-yama mountain), Harima AOYAMA in &quot;Ban-cho sarayashiki,&quot; Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA in &quot;Shogun Edo wo saru,&quot; and Tokihira in &quot;Shosho Shigemoto no haha.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He learned well from Sadanji ICHIKAWA (II) and was the top player in new plays such as MINAMOTO no Yoriie in &quot;Yoritomo no shi&quot; (Yoritomo&apos;s death), Shigenari KIMURA in &quot;Kiri hitoha&quot; (a single paulownia leaf), Hankuro KIKUCHI in &quot;Toribe yama shinju&quot; (Love-suicides at Mt. Toribe), Harima AOYAMA in &quot;Ban-cho sarayashiki,&quot; Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA in &quot;Shogun Edo wo saru,&quot; and Tokihira in &quot;Shosho Shigemoto no haha.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Mt. Toribe としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>古典作品では『天衣紛上野初花』（河内山）や『近江源氏先陣館』（盛綱陣屋）の盛綱、『競伊勢物語』の紀有常などが代表作としてあげられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From classic works, we can name &quot;Kumonimago Ueno no hatsuhana&quot; (Kochiyama), Moritsuna in &quot;Omi-Genji senjinyakata,&quot; KI no Aritsune in &quot;Hadekurabe Ise monogatari,&quot; etc. as his representative roles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His well known roles from classic works include, &quot;Kumonimago Ueno no hatsuhana&quot; (Kochiyama), Moritsuna in &quot;Omi-Genji senjinyakata,&quot; KI no Aritsune in &quot;Hadekurabe Ise monogatari,&quot; etc.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His well known roles from classic works include, &quot;Kumonimago Ueno no hatsuhana&quot; (Kochiyama), Moritsuna in &quot;Omi-Genji senjinyakata,&quot; KI no Aritsune in &quot;Hadekurabe Ise monogatari,&quot; etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="38">
<j>受賞・栄典</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Receivers awards and honors</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Awards and honors</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Awards and honors</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>昭和24年 (1950)、毎日演劇賞、大阪市復興文化祭賞。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1950, he received the Theatrical Performance Award of Mainichi Newspapers and the Award of Restored Cultural Festival of Osaka City</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1950, he received the Theatrical Performance Award of Mainichi Newspapers and the Award of Restored Cultural Festival of Osaka City</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1950, he received the Theatrical Performance Award of Mainichi Newspapers and the Award of Restored Cultural Festival of Osaka City</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>昭和29年 (1954)、なにわ芸術賞。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1954, he received Naniwa Art Award</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1954, he received Naniwa Art Award</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1954, he received Naniwa Art Award</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>昭和33年 (1958)、菊池寛賞、大阪市民文化賞。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1958, he received Kan KIKUCHI Award and Osaka Citizen Cultural Award</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1958, he received Kan KIKUCHI Award and Osaka Citizen Cultural Award</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1958, he received Kan KIKUCHI Award and Osaka Citizen Cultural Award</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>晩年にはその芸品が高く評価され、昭和34年 (1959)、芸術院会員に就任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In his late years, refinement of his performance was highly appreciated and he assumed the position of a member of the Japan Art Academy in 1959.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In his late years, refinement of his performance was highly appreciated and he assumed a position as a member of the Japan Art Academy in 1959.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In his late years, refinement of his performance was highly appreciated and he assumed a position as a member of the Japan Art Academy in 1959.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>翌年には重要無形文化財各個指定（人間国宝）を受けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In next year, he received individual designation to the Important Intangible Cultural Property (Living National Treasure).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The next year, he was individually designated as an Important Intangible Cultural Property (Living National Treasure).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The next year, he was individually designated as an Important Intangible Cultural Property (Living National Treasure).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 白拍子花子(id:244805), Rusk(id:9895), 中右(id:50196), Ponta2(id:129030), ととりん(id:31982), Ajcxx(id:103602), やる気man-man(id:36512), ArabianKnight(id:190561), Cprobot(id:97843), ウィキウィ2(id:83093), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>