<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>今川焼き</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imagawa-yaki (Japanese pastry)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imagawa-yaki (Japanese pastry)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imagawa-yaki (Japanese pastry)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>今川焼き（いまがわやき）は、小麦粉を主体として型で焼いた料理。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imagawa-yaki is a pastry which is made by baking batter filled in molds.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imagawa-yaki is a pastry which is made by baking batter in molds.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imagawa-yaki is a pastry which is made by baking batter in molds.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>和菓子のひとつ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is one of traditional Japanese sweets.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a traditional Japanese sweet.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a traditional Japanese cake.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>小麦粉・鶏卵・砂糖を水で溶いて作った生地を円形のくぼみのある鉄または銅製の焼き型に流し込んで餡（小豆あんが多いが、白餡やカスタードクリームなどのものもある）をのせ、その上にさらに生地を流し入れるか、別の型で焼いておいた同型の生地をのせて</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The way to cook the imagawa-yaki is to pour batter made of flour, eggs, sugar and water in round depressions or molds made of iron or copper, drop &apos;An (sweet bean paste)&apos; (red bean paste is very popular, but white bean paste and custard cream are available) into each batter-filled mold and pour remaining batter into each bean paste-added mold or cover each filled mold with another ban of the same shape baked in other molds.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The way to cook imagawa-yaki is to pour a batter made of flour, eggs, sugar and water in round depressions or molds made of iron or copper, drop &apos;An (sweet bean paste)&apos; (red bean paste is very popular, but white bean paste and custard cream are available) into each batter-filled mold and pour more batter into each mold containing bean paste-added, or cover each filled mold with another pastry of the same shape baked in another mold.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The way to cook imagawa-yaki is to pour batter made of flour, eggs, sugar and water in round molds made of iron or copper, drop sweet bean paste (red bean paste is very popular, but white bean paste and custard cream are available) into each batter-filled mold and cover this with batter or cover each filled mold with another pastry of the same shape baked in another mold.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>、高さの低い円筒形に焼いたもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The imagawa-yaki is in cylindrical form with its thickness of approximately twice pancake.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処「高さの低い」はあいまいなので、パンケーキの2倍ほどに英訳しておきました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imagawa-yaki is cylindrical in form with a thickness approximately twice that of a pancake.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imagawa-yaki is cylindrical in form with a thickness approximately twice that of a pancake.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>名称</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Name</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Name</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Name</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>「今川焼き」の名称は、江戸時代中期の安永年間に、江戸・神田 (千代田区)「今川橋」近くの店からこの種の焼き菓子が売り出されたことによる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This type of pastries began to be sold near the Kanda &apos;Imagawabashi bridge&apos; during An&apos;ei years in the Edo Period, and the name of imagawa-yaki originated from this time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This type of pastries began to be sold near the Kanda &apos;Imagawabashi bridge&apos; during the An&apos;ei years in the mid-Edo Period, and the name of imagawa-yaki originates from this time.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These kind of cakes began to be sold near the Kanda (Chiyoda Ward) of Edo, &apos;Imagawa-bashi Bridge&apos; during 1772 and 1780 in the mid-Edo period, and the name of imagawa-yaki originates from this time.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。グレゴリオ暦に直し、補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>この商品が評判になったため、今川焼きという商品名が一般名詞化し、各地に広がった（戦国大名の今川氏とは無関係である）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since this food became very popular, the product name, imagawa-yaki became a general noun and widespread to various areas (no relations to the Imagawa clan, daimyo (Japanese territorial lord) in the Sengoku Period.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since this food became very popular, the product name, imagawa-yaki became a general noun and spread to various areas (it is not related to the Imagawa clan, daimyo (Japanese territorial lord) in the Sengoku Period.)</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since these cakes became very popular, the product name, imagawa-yaki was adopted around the country (it is not related to the Imagawa clan, a sengoku daimyo (Japanese territorial lord in the Sengoku period).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>今川焼きの名称は全国的なものではなく各地により呼び名が違う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name, imagawa-yaki is not popular nationwide and called differently by area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name, imagawa-yaki is not used nationwide and different names are used in various areas.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name, imagawa-yaki is not used nationwide and different names are used in various areas.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>地域によって特定の名称以外は使用されていなかったり、人によって違う場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Only a certain name is used in a certain area or it can be differently called by persons.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sometimes a certain name is only used in a certain area, or it may be called a different name by different people.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sometimes a certain name is only used in a certain area, or it may be called a different name by different people.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>特に西日本では違う名前で呼ばれる事が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Particularly in the West Japan, it is often called by different names.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Particularly in western Japan, it is often called by different names.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Particularly in western Japan, this sweet is often called by different names.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>大判焼き（小判焼き）・二重焼き・回転焼き（回転饅頭）・きんつば・おやき（長野県のおやきとは異なる）など、形状や製法に基づく名だけではなく、甘太郎焼・七越焼き・義士焼き・太鼓焼き・太閤焼き・夫婦まんじゅう（フーマン）・太鼓饅頭・蜂楽饅頭・あじまんと店名などでも呼ばれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Names which originated in the shape and cooking method are like Obanyaki (Kobanyaki), Nijuyaki, Kaitenyaki (Kaiten-manju), Kintsuba, Oyaki (different from Oyaki in Nagano Prefecture), and also names which were taken after the names of shops or manufacturers are like Amataro-yaki, Nanakoshi-yaki (七越焼き), Gishi-yaki, Taiko-yaki, Taiko-yaki, Fufu-manju (Fuman), Taiko-manju, Horaku-manju and Ajiman.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Names which originated in the shape and cooking method include Obanyaki (Kobanyaki), Nijuyaki, Kaitenyaki (Kaiten-manju), Kintsuba, Oyaki (different from Oyaki in Nagano Prefecture), and also names which take after the names of shops or manufacturers including Amataro-yaki, Nanakoshi-yaki, Gishi-yaki, Taiko-yaki, Taiko-yaki, Fufu-manju (Fuman), Taiko-manju, Horaku-manju, and Ajiman.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cake names which are derived from the shape and cooking method include Obanyaki (Kobanyaki), Nijuyaki, Kaitenyaki (Kaiten-manju), Kintsuba, Oyaki (different from Oyaki in Nagano Prefecture), and cakes which were named after shops or manufacturers include Amataro-yaki, Nanakoshi-yaki, Gishi-yaki, Taiko-yaki (Drum cake), Taiko-yaki (Taiko (father of the Imperial adviser) cake), Fufu-manju (Fuman), Taiko-manju, Horaku-manju, and Ajiman.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。同じ読みの語を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>また、店名だけではなく日本中央競馬会の競馬場内で販売する「GI焼き」など、発売場所のイベントや祭りに関する名称を付けている場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to the names based on shops&apos; or manufacturers&apos; names, there is a case in which names are related to events or festivals held in places to sell, like &apos;GI-yaki&apos; which is sold in racetracks of the Japan Association for International Horse Racing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to the names based on shops&apos; or manufacturers&apos; names, there are also cases in which names are related to events or festivals held at places where imagawa-yaki are sold, like &apos;GI-yaki&apos; which is sold in racetracks of the Japan Association for International Horse Racing.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to cake named after shops or manufacturers, there are also cases in which names are related to events or festivals held at places where imagawa-yaki are sold; for example &apos;GI-yaki&apos; which is sold in racetracks of the Japan Association for International Horse Racing.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>調理の技術</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cooking technique</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cooking technique</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cooking technique</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="12">
<j>具が餡のように固い場合はひねるように入れるのが低く平らに焼くコツである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If filling is hard and stiff like &quot;An (bean paste)&quot;, it is a secret to put the filling into each mold in a way like giving a twist to the filling so that the imagawa-yaki can be turned out even in thickness.</e>
<cmt>”ひねるように入れる”という意味がわかりませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If the filling is hard and stiff like &quot;An (bean paste)&quot;, it is best to twist the filling as you put it into each mold so that the imagawa-yaki can be turned out with an even thickness.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If the filling is hard and stiff like bean paste, the filling can be filled evenly if it is twisted as is put into the cake mold.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>今川焼き用の鉄板には返しやすい様に傾斜がついている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An imagawa-yaki pan is slanted in order to be able to turn over imagawa-yaki easily.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An imagawa-yaki pan is slanted in order to be able to turn over imagawa-yaki easily.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An imagawa-yaki pan is slanted in order to be able to turn over imagawa-yaki easily.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>このため平らに焼くのが難しい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is not easy to make whole imagawa-yaki even in thickness.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is not easy to make imagawa-yaki with even thicknesses.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is difficult to make imagawa-yaki which are all of the same thickness.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>類似の料理</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Similar foods</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Similar foods</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Similar foods</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="15">
<j>今川焼き同様の生地を型に入れて焼いたものはいくつかあり、代表的なものに鯛の形を模した「たい焼き」がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are several types of pastries, which are made by pouring imagawa-yaki type batter in molds and baking it, and a typical one is &apos;tai (sea bream)-yaki&apos;, which resembles to a sea bream in shape.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are several types of pastries, which are made by pouring imagawa-yaki type batter in molds and baking it, and a typical one is &apos;tai (sea bream)-yaki&apos;, which is shaped like a sea bream.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are several types of cakes which are made by pouring batter in molds and baking it, and a typical one is &apos;tai-yaki,&apos; which is shaped like a sea bream (&apos;tai&apos;).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。スペースをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>詳細は「たい焼き」を参照の事。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For more details, refer to &apos;Tai-yaki&apos; section.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For more details, refer to &apos;Tai-yaki&apos;.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For more details, refer to &apos;Tai-yaki.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを&apos;内に移動</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="17">
<j>今川焼きの型にお好み焼きの具を入れ、卵を落として焼いた「大阪焼き」が東北地方、関東地方の縁日の屋台や店舗で販売されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Osaka-yaki&apos;, which is cooked by baking okonomiyaki-type batter and filling contained in imagawa-yaki molds with an egg added into each filled mold, is sold in shops and stands or stalls at a fair or festival in the Tohoku and Kanto regions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Osaka-yaki&apos;, which is cooked by baking okonomiyaki-type batter and filling contained in imagawa-yaki molds with an egg added into each filled mold, is sold in shops, stands, and stalls at fairs and festivals in the Tohoku and Kanto regions.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Osaka-yaki, which is cooked by baking okonomiyaki-type batter in imagawa-yaki molds and topping with an egg is sold in shops, stands, and stalls at fairs and festivals in the Tohoku and Kanto regions.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="18">
<j>台湾では「紅豆餅」や「車輪餅」と呼ば伝統的なお菓子のひとつとなっている（中国語では漢字の「餅」は、焼き菓子を指す）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Taiwan, imagawa-yaki is called &apos;red bean waffle&apos; or &apos;charyunbyon (定訳不明)&apos; and one of the traditional sweets (a Chinese character &apos;餅&apos; represents baked pastry.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Taiwan, imagawa-yaki is called &apos;red bean waffle&apos; or &apos;charyunbyon&apos; and is one of the traditional sweets (a Chinese character &apos;餅&apos; represents baked pastry.)</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Taiwan, imagawa-yaki is called &apos;red bean waffle&apos; or &apos;charyunbyon&apos; and is a traditional sweet (a Chinese character &apos;餅&apos; represents baked pastry).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。 #をのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>具はつぶあん、カスタードクリーム、タロイモ、ゴマあんとピーナツなどが多く、サツマイモ、バターコーン、キャベツ炒め、切干大根、チューナ、酸菜（台湾の高菜）、カレー、イチゴ練乳などを入れた物もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For the fillings, red bean paste, custard cream, taro potatoes, sesame paste and peanuts are popular, and sweet potatoes, buttered corns, fried cabbages, dried chopped daikon (radish), tuna, sansai (Taiwanese takana), curry paste and strawberry flavored condensed milk are available, too.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For the filling, red bean paste, custard cream, taro potatoes, sesame paste and peanuts are popular, and sweet potatoes, buttered corn, fried cabbage, chopped dried daikon (radish), tuna, sansai (Taiwanese leaf mustard), curry paste, and strawberry flavored condensed milk are also available.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The popular fillings include azuki bean paste, custard cream, taro potatoes, sesame paste and peanuts, while sweet potatoes, buttered corn, fried cabbage, chopped dried daikon (radish), tuna, sansai (Taiwanese leaf mustard), curry paste, and strawberry flavored condensed milk are also available.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Zoominshiodome(id:149045), 桂鷺淵(id:151322), カイロス(id:278723), Newaver02(id:218303), Im224(id:57113), Tigers boy(id:15761), やきとり(id:126941), Toto-tarou(id:16648), たこやき協会(id:106410), KAWASAKI Hiroyuki(id:1514), Naru-W(id:17852), Ryoji937(id:190619), Opponent(id:720), Tomomarusan(id:17060), 赤井彗星(id:18381), An-chan(id:14590), Arria Belli(id:133170), Edogawa(id:9879), Bit(id:2197), Yas(id:739), Tatsujin28(id:9300), Ynhockey(id:37444), Snakeeye(id:41100), Sizuru(id:52926), Izayohi(id:13095), Lonicera(id:20638), いろはにほへと(id:89648), たね(id:10372), Nighthawks(id:36125), Yiuchan(id:28580), 逆Ｌの男(id:8978), 彩華1226(id:64711), 竃馬(id:102733), VolkovBot(id:105371), Beagle(id:45036), To-emon(id:23140), Corwin(id:973), Guiteristkura(id:221867), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>