<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>茶道</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sado (Japanese Tea Ceremony)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sado (Japanese Tea Ceremony)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sado</e>
<cmt>補足をのぞきました。</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>茶道（さどう、ちゃどう）とは、様式にのっとって客人に茶をふるまう行為のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sado (chado) (way of tea) is the act of a ritual preparing and serving tea for guests.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sado (chado) (way of tea) is the act of a ritual preparing and serving tea for guests.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sado (also known as chado) (Japanese tea ceremony) is the act of a ritual preparing and serving tea for guests.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>元来は「茶湯」（ちゃとう）「茶の湯」といった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Formally, it was called as &quot;Chato&quot; (Hot Water Tea) or &quot;Chano yu&quot; (Hot Water for the Tea).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Formally, it was called as &quot;Chato&quot; (Hot Water Tea) or &quot;Chano yu&quot; (Hot Water for the Tea).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Formally, it was called as &apos;chato&apos; (literally, hot water tea) or &apos;chanoyu&apos; (literally, hot water for the tea).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えて補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>千利休は「数寄道」、小堀遠州は「茶の道」という語も使っていたが、やがて江戸時代初期には茶道と呼ばれるようになった（『茶話指月集』『南方録』など）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">SEN no Rikyu called it &quot;Suki no michi&quot; (the way of enjoying elegance), &quot;Cha no michi&quot; (the Way of Tea) by Enshu KOBORI, and it was eventually called as sado by the beginning of the Edo Period (according to &quot;Sawashigetsushu&quot; (the collection of tea talks pointing to the moon) and &quot;Nanpo roku&quot; (Nanpo Record)).</e>
<cmt>茶話指月集→Sawashigetsushu (the collection of tea talks pointing to the moon)[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">SEN no Rikyu called it &quot;Suki no michi&quot; (the way of enjoying elegance), &quot;Cha no michi&quot; (the Way of Tea) by Enshu KOBORI, and it was eventually called sado by the beginning of the Edo Period (according to &quot;Sawashigetsushu&quot; (the collection of tea talks pointing to the moon) and &quot;Nanpo roku&quot; - Nanpo Record).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">SEN no Rikyu called it &apos;Suki no michi&apos; (the way of enjoying elegance), &apos;Cha no michi&apos; (the art of Tea) by Enshu KOBORI, and it was eventually called sado by the beginning of the Edo period (according to &quot;Sawa Shigetsu shu&quot; (a collection of GENPAKU Sotan&apos;s talks about tea) and &quot;Nanporoku&quot; (Southern Record)).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えて補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>ただ、茶をいれて飲むだけでなく、生きていく目的や考え方、宗教、茶道具や茶室に置く美術品など、広い分野にまたがる総合芸術とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered to be a generalized art that practices not only serving and drinking tea but deals with the purpose of living, the way of thinking, religion, art of tea tools and art works placed in the tea room.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered to be a generalized art form that practices not only serving and drinking tea, but deals with the purpose of living, the way of thinking, religion, art of tea tools and art works placed in the tea room.</e>
<cmt>punctuation, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered to be a generalized art form that practices not only serving and drinking tea, but deals with the purpose of living, the way of thinking, religion, art of tea tools and art works placed in the tea room.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>現在、茶道は先発の抹茶道と後発の煎茶道があり、単に茶道というと前者を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Currently, Sado has the forerunning Macchado (way of maccha, powdered green tea) and the later Senchado (way of sencha, simmered tea), and it refers to the former if one mentions just about the sado.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Currently, Sado has the forerunning Macchado (way of maccha, powdered green tea) and the later Senchado (way of sencha, simmered tea), and it refers to the former if one mentions just about sado.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Currently, sado has the forerunning macchado (art of maccha (green powdered tea) ceremony) and the later senchado (art of sencha (simmered tea) ceremony), and it refers to the former if one mentions just about sado.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>日本の茶道</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese Sado</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese Sado</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese Sado</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>茶道の歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The History of Sado</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The History of Sado</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The History of Sado</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>茶の大元に成っているものは唐の陸羽（？ - 804年）の書いた『茶経』と言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">What is considered to be the leader of tea is &quot;Cha Jing&quot; (The Classics of Tea) written by Lu Yu of Tang China (date unknown-804).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">What is considered to be the leader of tea is &quot;Cha Jing&quot; (The Classics of Tea) written by Lu Yu of Tang China (date unknown-804).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">What is considered to be the leader of tea is &quot;Cha Jing&quot; (The Classics of Tea) written by Lu Yu of Tang China (unknown - 804).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>この本には、茶の製法、飲み方、歴史などが詳しく書かれており、まさに茶のバイブルと言える書物である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It wrote in detail about the tea production processes, drinking methods, and history and could be said that this is the bible of tea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He wrote in detail about the tea production process, drinking methods, and history and could be said that this is the bible of tea.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He wrote in detail about the tea production process, drinking methods, and history and could be said that this is the bible of tea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>茶を飲む習慣と茶の製法は平安時代に遣唐使によってもたらされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The tea drinking custom and production techniques were brought by envoys to Tang China during the Heian Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The tea drinking custom and production techniques were brought by envoys to Tang China during the Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The tea drinking custom and production techniques were brought by envoys to Tang China during the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>当時の茶は現代の烏龍茶に似た半発酵茶で、必要量のみを煎じて飲んだと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The tea at that time was semi-fermented tea which resembled current oolong tea and brewed it just enough amount and drank it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The tea at that time was semi-fermented tea resembling current oolong tea and it was brewed in just the right amount and drunk.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The tea at that time was semi-fermented tea resembling current oolong tea and it was brewed in just the right amount and drunk.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>しかし、当時は根付かず喫茶は廃れてしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it was not popular at that time and tea drinking customs disappeared.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it was not popular at that time and tea drinking customs disappeared.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it was not popular at that time and tea drinking customs disappeared.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>鎌倉時代に、日本に禅宗を伝えた栄西や道元によって薬として持ち込まれた抹茶が、禅宗の広まりと共に精神修養的な要素を強めて広がっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Maccha brought by Eisai, who spread Zen sect of Buddhism, and Dogen, who brought it as a medicine, spread along with Zen during the Kamakura period and increased the concept of spiritual training.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Maccha, brought by Eisai, who spread the Zen sect of Buddhism, and Dogen, who brought it as a medicine, spread along with Zen during the Kamakura period and increased the concept of spiritual training.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Maccha, brought by Eisai, who spread the Zen sect of Buddhism, and Dogen, who brought it as a medicine, spread along with Zen during the Kamakura period and increased the concept of spiritual training.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>さらに茶の栽培が普及すると茶を飲む習慣が一般に普及していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, as the tea cultivation became popular, tea drinking practices spread across the public.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, as the tea cultivation became popular, tea drinking practices spread amongst the public.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, as the tea cultivation became popular, tea drinking practices spread amongst the public.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>室町時代においては、飲んだ水の産地を当てる闘水という遊戯から、闘茶という、飲んだ茶の銘柄を当てる一種の博打が流行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Muromachi period, there was a gamble called Tocha (tea competition), made to guess the tea brand developed from the game Tosui (water competition) where the players had to guess the place of product.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Muromachi period, there was a gambling game called Tocha (tea competition), where participants were made to guess the tea brand and place of production developed from the game Tosui (water competition).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Muromachi period, there was a gambling game called Tocha (tea competition), where participants were made to guess the tea brand and place of production developed from the game Tosui (water competition).</e>
<cmt>余分なスペースをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>また、本場中国の茶器「唐物」がもてはやされ、大金を使って蒐集し、これを使用して盛大な茶会を催すことが大名の間で流行した（これを「唐物数寄」と呼ぶ）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, genuine Chinese tea utensils called &quot;Chinese thing&quot; was praised at that time, and it became popular among daimyo (feudal lords) to collect them in high amount and opened tea parties using these (this was called &quot;Karamono suki&quot; (likes Chinese thing)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, genuine Chinese tea utensils called &quot;Chinese thing&quot; were praised at that time, and it became popular among daimyo (feudal lords) to collect them in quantity and hold tea parties using these (this was called &quot;Karamono suki&quot; - like Chinese thing).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, genuine Chinese tea utensils called &apos;karamono&apos; (things imported from China) were praised at that time, and it became popular among daimyo (feudal lords) to collect them in quantity and hold tea parties using these (this was called &apos;karamono suki&apos; (the taste for karamono)).</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>これに対し、村田珠光が茶会での博打や飲酒を禁止し、亭主と客との精神交流を重視する茶会のあり方を説いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, Juko MURATA forbid the gambling and alcohol drinking at tea parties, and lectured on the importance of spiritual relationship between the host and the guest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, Juko MURATA forbid gambling and alcohol drinking at tea parties, and lectured on the importance of spiritual relationships between the host and the guest.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, Juko MURATA forbid gambling and alcohol drinking at tea parties, and lectured on the importance of spiritual relationships between the host and the guest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>これがわび茶の源流と成っていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This developed into the origin of wabi cha.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This developed into the origin of wabi cha.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This developed into the origin of wabicha (wabi style of tea ceremony).</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="17">
<j>わび茶はその後、堺市の町衆である武野紹鴎、その弟子の千利休によって安土桃山時代に完成されるに至った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wabi cha became fully developed by Shoo TAKENO, who was one of the merchant class of Sakai city, and his pupil, Rikyu SEN in Azuchi-Momoyama Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wabi cha was fully developed by Shoo TAKENO, who was one of the merchant class members in Sakai city, and his pupil, Rikyu SEN in Azuchi-Momoyama Period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wabicha was fully developed by Shoo TAKENO, who was one of the merchant class members in Sakai city, and his pupil, Rikyu SEN in Azuchi-Momoyama Period.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>利休のわび茶は武士階層にも広まり、蒲生氏郷、細川忠興、牧村兵部、瀬田掃部、古田重然、芝山監物、高山右近ら利休七哲と呼ばれる弟子たちを生んでいく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The wabi cha of Rikyu spread even to the bushi class, and created pupils called Rikyushichitetsu (Rikyu&apos;s Seven Adepts), which consisted of Ujisato GAMO, Tadaoki HOSOKAWA, Hyobu MAKIMURA, Kamon SETA, Shigenari (Shigeteru) FURUTA, Kenmotsu SHIBAYAMA, and Ukon TAKAYAMA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The wabi cha of Rikyu spread even to the bushi class, and created pupils called Rikyushichitetsu (Rikyu&apos;s Seven Adepts), which consisted of Ujisato GAMO, Tadaoki HOSOKAWA, Hyobu MAKIMURA, Kamon SETA, Shigenari (Shigeteru) FURUTA, Kenmotsu SHIBAYAMA, and Ukon TAKAYAMA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The wabicha of Rikyu spread even to the samurai class, and created pupils called Rikyushichitetsu (Rikyu&apos;s Seven Adepts), which consisted of Ujisato GAMO, Tadaoki HOSOKAWA, Hyobu MAKIMURA, Kamon SETA, Shigenari (Shigeteru) FURUTA, Kenmotsu SHIBAYAMA, and Ukon TAKAYAMA.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>さらにはわび茶から発展し、小堀政一、片桐貞昌、織田長益ら流派をなす大名も現われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, daimyos such as Masaichi KOBORI, Sadamasa KATAGIRI, and Nagamasu ODA, who created their own schools developed from wabi cha, appeared.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, daimyos appeared, such as Masaichi KOBORI, Sadamasa KATAGIRI, and Nagamasu ODA, who created their own schools developed from wabi cha.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, daimyos appeared, such as Masaichi KOBORI, Sadamasa KATAGIRI, and Nagamasu ODA, who created their own schools developed from wabicha.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>現代では特に武家茶道、或いは大名茶などと呼んで区別する場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Currently, it is distinguished by referring to it often as the Buke chado (the sado of samurai family) or daimyo cha (the tea of daimyo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Currently, it is distinguished by often referring to it as the Buke chado (the sado of the samurai family) or daimyo cha (the tea of the daimyo).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Currently, it is distinguished by often referring to it as the buke sado (buke sado (the tea ceremony of samurai family) or daimyo cha (the tea of the daimyo).</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="21">
<j>江戸時代初期までの茶の湯人口は、主に大名・豪商などが中心のごく限られたものであったが、江戸中期に町人階級が経済的勃興するとともに飛躍的に増加した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The population of those who practiced chano yu by the beginning of Edo period was limited to mainly daimyo and rich merchants, but increased dramatically as merchant class prospered economically in the mid-Edo Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The population of those who practiced chano yu in the beginning of the Edo period was limited to mainly daimyo and rich merchants, but increased dramatically as the merchant class prospered economically in the mid-Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The population of those who practiced chanoyu in the beginning of the Edo period was limited to mainly daimyo and rich merchants, but increased dramatically as the merchant class prospered economically in the mid-Edo period.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>これらの町人階級を主とする新たな茶の湯参入者を迎え入れたのが、元々町方の出自である三千家を中心とする千家系の流派である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The schools of Senke line that originated from Edo Period towns, centered around the Three Senke, was the school that invited the new chano yu participants mainly consisting of town class people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The school of the Senke line that originated from Edo Period towns, centered around the Three Senke, was the school that invited the new chano yu participants mainly consisting of town class people.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The school of the Senke (House of Sen) that originated from Edo period towns, centered around the Sansenke (three houses of tea ceremony (Omotesenke (the house of Omotesen), Urasenke (the house of Urasen) and Mushanokojisenke (the house of Mushanokojisen))), was the school that invited the new chanoyu participants mainly consisting of town class people.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>この時、大量の門弟をまとめるために、現在では伝統芸能において一般に見られる組織形態：家元制度が確立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The formation of head-master system commonly seen in a current traditional performance arts, developed in order to organize massive amount of disciples.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The formation of the head-master system commonly seen in a current traditional performing arts, developed in order to organize massive numbers of disciples.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The formation of the head-master system commonly seen in a current traditional performing arts, developed in order to organize massive numbers of disciples.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>また、表千家七代如心斎、裏千家八代又玄斎、如心斎の高弟、江戸千家初代川上不白などによって、大勢の門弟に対処するための新たな稽古方法として、七事式が考案された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, Shichijishiki (seven virtues style ceremony) was designed by Nyoshinsai of the seventh head of Omote Senke, Yugensai of the eighth Ura Senke as the new practice method to handle many disciples.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, Shichijishiki (the seven virtues style ceremony) was designed by Nyoshinsai of the seventh head of Omote Senke, Yugensai of the eighth Ura Senke as the new practice method to handle large numbers of disciples.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, Shichijishiki (the seven virtues style ceremony) was designed by Nyoshinsai of the seventh head of Omotesenke, Yugensai of the eighth Urasenke, and Fuhaku KAWAKAMI of the founder of Edosenke (the house of Edosen) as the new practice method to handle large numbers of disciples.</e>
<cmt>江戸千家初代川上不白、を補足、前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>これらの努力によって茶の湯は、庄屋、名主や商人などの習い事として日本全国に広く普及していったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These efforts made chano yu as lessons for the village headman, headman and merchants, and became popular across Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These efforts made chano yu lessons for the village headman, headman and merchants, and became popular across Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These efforts made chanoyu lessons for the village headman, headman and merchants, and became popular across Japan.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>ただ、同時に茶の湯の大衆化に拍車がかかり、遊芸化が進んでいったという弊害もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it triggered the large scale chano yu and developed into the bad influence of game.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it triggered the large scale chano yu and developed into the bad game influence.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it triggered the large scale chanoyu and developed into the bad game influence.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>「侘び・寂び」に対する理解も次第に変質し、美しい石灯籠を「完璧すぎる」とわざと打ち欠いたり、割れて接いだ茶碗を珍重するなど、大衆には理解し難い振る舞いもあって、庶民の間で「茶人」が「変人」の隠語となる事態も招いた（禅の極端化にも共通する過度の精神主義であるし、「粋な自分」を誇示する、本来の茶道とは外れた行為でもある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The understanding of &quot;wabi or sabi&quot; gradually changed, the behaviors, such as breaking the beautiful stone lantern for it being &quot;too perfect,&quot; treasuring a tea bowl that was reconnected after it being cracked, became incomprehensible for the masses that it made locals to call &quot;chajin&quot; (a man of tea) as &quot;henjin&quot; (abnormal man) (it had a close resemblance to extreme Zen and excessive spiritualism and was a behavior far away from the original sado).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The understanding of &quot;wabi or sabi&quot; gradually changed, behavior, like breaking a beautiful stone lantern for being &quot;too perfect,&quot; treasuring a tea bowl that was repaired after being cracked, became incomprehensible for the masses that it made locals to call &quot;chajin&quot; (a man of tea) as &quot;henjin&quot; (abnormal man) (it had a close resemblance to extreme Zen and excessive spiritualism and was a behavior far removed from the original sado).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The understanding of &apos;wabi (taste for the simple and quiet) or sabi (quiet simplicity)&apos; gradually changed, behavior, like breaking a beautiful stone lantern for being &apos;too perfect,&apos; treasuring a tea bowl that was repaired after being cracked, became incomprehensible for the masses that it made locals to call &apos;chajin&apos; (a man of tea) as &apos;henjin&apos; (abnormal man) (it had a close resemblance to extreme Zen and excessive spiritualism and was a behavior far removed from the original sado).</e>
<cmt>補足し、クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="28">
<j>他方でこのような遊芸化の傾向に対して、本来の茶道の目的である「人をもてなす際に現れる心の美しさ」が強調されるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, it began to stress the original purpose of sado, &apos;the beauty of the mind that appears when entertaining a guest&apos; in response to the inclination of it becoming a form of entertaiment in districts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, it began to stress the original purpose of sado, &apos;the beauty of the mind that appears when entertaining a guest&apos; in response to the inclination of it becoming a form of entertaiment in districts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, it began to stress the original purpose of sado, &apos;the beauty of the mind that appears when entertaining a guest&apos; in response to the inclination of it becoming a form of entertainment in districts.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>この際に大徳寺派の臨済宗寺院が大きな役割を果たし、利休流茶道の根本とされる「和敬清寂」という標語もこの過程で生み出された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Rinzai sect temples of the Daitoku-ji Temple line greatly contributed to this, and &quot;wakei seijaku&quot; (harmony, respect, purity, and tranquility), the motto that was considered to be the fundamental of the sado of the Rikyu school was created in this process.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Rinzai sect temples of the Daitoku-ji Temple line greatly contributed to this, and &quot;wakei seijaku&quot; (harmony, respect, purity, and tranquility), the motto that was considered to be fundamental to sado of the Rikyu school was created in this process.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Rinzai Sect temples of the Daitokuji School greatly contributed to this, and &apos;wakei seijaku&apos; (harmony, respect, purity, and tranquility), the motto that was considered to be fundamental to sado of the Rikyu School was created in this process.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>また幕末には、井伊直弼が「一期一会」の概念を完成させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, Naosuke II completed the general concept of &quot;Ichigo Ichie&quot; (a once-in-a-lifetime opportunity, Carpe Diem) in the last days of Tokugawa Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>一期一会→ichigo ichie (a once in-a-lifetime opportunity, Carpe Diem)[http://dictionary.goo.ne.jp/leaf/je/2064/m0u/一期一会/]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, Naosuke II completed the general concept of &quot;Ichigo Ichie&quot; (a once-in-a-lifetime opportunity, Carpe Diem) in the last days of the Tokugawa Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, Naosuke II completed the general concept of &apos;Ichigo Ichie&apos; (Treasure every meeting, for it will never recur) in the last days of the Tokugawa Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせ、クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>各流派による点前の形態や茶会様式の体系化と言った様式（「結婚式には礼服を着る事」程度のマナ−の範疇である）の整備に加えて、「人をもてなす事の本質とは（常日頃の振る舞いと、その奥底にある心の本質に気を使わないと、本当の意味で人をもてなす事はできない）」と言った茶道本来の精神を見直すことにによって、現在「茶道」と呼んでいる茶の湯が完成したのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The current chano yu called &quot;sado&quot; was completed by reexamining the structure of temae (a formalized chano yu procedure) of each school, adding the ritualization structure of tea parties (&quot;it is one of the basics of mannerism to wear full dress at weddings&quot;), and reexamination the original idea of sado, &quot;the essence of hosting a guest is (the guest cannot be truly entertained if the person does not take a full consideration of daily conduct and be aware of the essence at the bottom of one&apos;s heart).&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The current chano yu called &quot;sado&quot; was completed by reexamining the structure of temae (a formalized chano yu procedure) of each school, adding the ritualization structure of tea parties (&quot;one of the basic mannerism is to wear full dress at weddings&quot;), and reexamining the original idea of sado, &quot;the essence of hosting a guest is (the guest cannot be truly entertained if the person does not take a full consideration of daily conduct and be aware of the essence at the bottom of one&apos;s heart).&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The current chanoyu called &apos;sado&apos; was completed by reexamining the structure of temae (a formalized chano yu procedure) of each school, adding the ritualization structure of tea parties (&apos;one of the basic mannerism is to wear full dress at weddings&apos;), and reexamining the original idea of sado, &apos;the essence of hosting a guest is (the guest cannot be truly entertained if the person does not take a full consideration of daily conduct and be aware of the essence at the bottom of one&apos;s heart).&apos;</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="32">
<j>江戸末期になると、武家の教養として作法が固まっている抹茶の茶の湯を嫌い、気軽に楽しめる茶を求める声が町衆から出てきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the end of Edo Period came, people of the town, who despised the strict form of chano yu using maccha used for the education of the samurai family, demanded tea which could be enjoyed lightheartedly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the end of the Edo Period came, people of the town, who despised the strict form of chano yu using maccha for the education of samurai families, demanded tea which could be enjoyed lightheartedly.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the end of the Edo period came, people of the town, who despised the strict form of chanoyu using maccha for the education of samurai families, demanded tea which could be enjoyed lightheartedly.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>同時期に、単なる嗜好品と化してしまった煎茶の現状を憂い、煎茶に「道」を求める声があがった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same period, people became anxious about the status of sencha which became just the drink for pleasure and voiced to say that there should be a &quot;way&quot; for sencha.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same period, people became anxious about the status of sencha which became just a drink for pleasure and voiced to say that there should be a &quot;way&quot; for sencha.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same period, people became anxious about the status of sencha which became just a drink for pleasure and voiced to say that there should be an &apos;art&apos; for sencha.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>これらの声をくみ上げる形で、江戸時代中期に黄檗宗万福寺の元僧売茶翁（売茶翁）が行っていた煎茶の法に従い、改めて煎茶の作法を定めたのが煎茶道である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Sencha do was developed by redefining the way of sencha in response to the voice of people and followed the way of sencha performed by the Baisa-o of the former monk of Manpuku-ji Temple of Obaku sect during the mid-Edo Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sencha do was developed by redefining the way of sencha in response to the voices of the people and followed the way of sencha performed by the Baisa-o of the former monk of Manpuku-ji Temple of Obaku sect during the mid-Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Senchado was developed by redefining the way of sencha in response to the voices of the people and followed the way of sencha performed by the Baisao of the former monk of Manpuku-ji Temple of Obaku Sect during the mid-Edo period.</e>
<cmt>用語集、前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>煎茶道は文人を中心に広まり、確立されていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sencha do spread among the men of culture and began to be established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sencha do spread among men of culture and began to be established.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Senchado spread among men of culture and began to be established.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>煎茶を好んだ著名人として江戸初期の石川丈山、中期に上田秋成、後期には頼山陽の名が挙げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The names of famous people who favored sencha were Jozan ISHIKAWA, who was the famous person of the early Edo period, Akinari (Shusei UEDA) during the mid-Edo period, and Sanyo RAI of the late Edo Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The names of famous people who favored sencha were Jozan ISHIKAWA, who was a famous person in the early Edo period, Akinari (Shusei UEDA) during the mid-Edo period, and Sanyo RAI of the late Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The names of famous people who favored sencha were Jozan ISHIKAWA, who was a famous person in the early Edo period, Akinari UEDA during the mid-Edo period, and Sanyo RAI of the late Edo period.</e>
<cmt>上田秋成は、うえだあきなり、としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="37">
<j>明治時代になると、封建制度が崩壊し、諸藩に庇護されていた各流派が財政的に困難に陥るようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The feudal system collapsed at the beginning of Meiji era, and each school protected by domains became financially unstable.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The feudal system collapsed at the beginning of the Meiji era, and each school protected by a domain became financially unstable.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The feudal system collapsed at the beginning of the Meiji period, and each school protected by a clan became financially unstable.</e>
<cmt>藩をclanとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>そうした中、裏千家十三代円能斎鉄中は一時東京に居を移して茶道再興に努めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In midst of it, Ennosai Tecchu of the thirteenth Ura Senke resided temporarily in Tokyo to perform the revival of sado.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In midst of it, Ennosai Tecchu of the thirteenth Ura Senke resided temporarily in Tokyo to perform the revival of sado.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In midst of it, Tecchu ENNOSAI of the thirteenth Urasenke resided temporarily in Tokyo to perform the revival of sado.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>努力の甲斐あって有力財界人の関心を呼び、茶道を女子教育の必須科目として組み込むことに成功した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was worth his effort for he succeeded in grabbing the attention of the influential businessmen to incorporate sado as the required education of girls.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was worth his effort for he succeeded in grabbing the attention of influential businessmen to incorporate sado as required education for girls.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was worth his effort for he succeeded in grabbing the attention of influential businessmen to incorporate sado as required education for girls.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>このため茶道は、本来のわび茶とは別の「女子の教養」としての要素も獲得し、今では美しい着物姿での華やかな茶会が当たり前になっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, sado gained the aspect of &quot;young girls cultural need&quot; separate from the original wabi cha, and it became a norm to have a fancy tea party wearing a beautiful kimono now.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, sado gained the aspect of &quot;young girls cultural need&quot; separate from the original wabi cha, and it has now become the norm to have a fancy tea party wearing a beautiful kimono.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, sado gained the aspect of &apos;cultural need of girls&apos; separate from the original wabicha, and it has now become the norm to have a fancy tea party wearing a beautiful kimono.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>戦後は海外にも茶道は広まり、茶道の大衆化は世界的レベルとなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sado spread even around the world after World War II, and the popularization of sado became the world level.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sado spread even around the world after World War II, and the popularization of sado achieved world level recognition.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sado spread even around the world after World War II, and the popularization of sado achieved world level recognition.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="42">
<j>ボストン美術館中国日本部に勤務していた岡倉天心がアメリカで『THE BOOK OF TEA』（邦題『茶の本』）を1906年（明治39年）に出版紹介した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tenshin OKAKURA, who worked in the China-Japan Department, Museum of Fine Arts, Boston, published and introduced &quot;The Book of Tea (Japanese title was &quot;Cha no Hon&quot;) in 1906.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tenshin OKAKURA, who worked in the China-Japan Department, Museum of Fine Arts, Boston, published and introduced &quot;The Book of Tea (Japanese title was &quot;Cha no Hon&quot;) in 1906.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tenshin OKAKURA, who worked in the China-Japan Department, Museum of Fine Arts, Boston, published and introduced &quot;The Book of Tea&quot; (Japanese title was &quot;Cha no Hon&quot;) in 1906.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>この出版は欧米文化人の関心を呼び、「茶道」を英語で「tea ceremony」というのも一般的になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This publication brought the attention of European and Americans, and it became common to call &quot;sado&quot; as &quot;tea ceremony&quot; in English.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This publication brought the attention of European and Americans, and it became common to call &quot;sado&quot; as &quot;tea ceremony&quot; in English.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This publication brought the attention of European and Americans, and it became common to call &apos;sado&apos; as &apos;tea ceremony&apos; in English.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>（なお、岡倉が「茶の本」に於いて、欧米人にとっての「茶道」への近似体験として、「ティーパーティでのホストの心遣い」を挙げたことは、「茶を離れた茶道の本質」として興味深い。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(It was interesting that Okakura mentioned in &quot;Cha no Hon&quot; that the experience that closely resembleed &quot;sado&quot; for European and Americans was the &quot;consideration of the host during a tea party&quot; and was the &quot;essence of sado apart from tea&quot;.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(It was interesting that Okakura mentioned in &quot;Cha no Hon&quot; that the experience that closely resembled &quot;sado&quot; for European and Americans was the &quot;consideration of the host during a tea party&quot; and was the &quot;essence of sado apart from tea&quot;.)</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(It was interesting that Okakura mentioned in &apos;Cha no Hon&apos; that the experience that closely resembled &apos;sado&apos; for European and Americans was the &apos;consideration of the host during a tea party&apos; and was the &apos;essence of sado apart from tea.&apos;)</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="45">
<j>岡倉が茶道に与えた影響は大きく、岡倉の紹介以降、一般的には、茶の湯が茶道という名前に変わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The influence that Okakura brought to sado was great, and chano yu changed its name to sado in public after the introduction of Okakura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The influence that Okakura brought to sado was great, and chano yu changed its name to sado in public after the introduction of Okakura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The influence that Okakura brought to sado was great, and chanoyu changed its name to sado in public after the introduction of Okakura.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="46">
<j>1980年代初め頃には、日本の茶道の所作は中国茶（茶芸）に用いられるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The conduct of Japanese sado started to incorporate Chinese tea (art of tea) at the beginning of 1980&apos;s.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The conduct of Japanese sado started to incorporate Chinese tea (art of tea) at the beginning of 1980&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The conduct of Japanese sado started to incorporate Chinese tea (art of tea) at the beginning of 1980&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="47">
<j>現在の中国茶（茶芸）の「茶巾をたたむ」所作は、日本の茶道の影響の表れであるといえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The current &quot;folding chakin&quot; conduct in Chinese tea (art of tea) showed the influence from the Japanese sado.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The current &quot;folding chakin&quot; conduct in Chinese tea (art of tea) showed the influence from Japanese sado.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The current &apos;folding chakin&apos; conduct in Chinese tea showed the influence from Japanese sado.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>茶道の流派</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Various Schools of Sado</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Various Schools of Sado</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Various Schools of Sado</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>千利休以前の緒流派</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The schools which started before Rikyu SEN</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The schools which started before Rikyu SEN</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Schools Which Started Before SEN no Rikyu</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="48">
<j>流派と言うべきか定かではないが以下のような呼び習わしがあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is uncertain whether to be called as the school, but it was called as the following:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is uncertain as to whether or not to be called a school, but it was called follows:</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is uncertain as to whether or not to be called a school, but it was called follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="49">
<j>奈良流 （ならりゅう） 村田珠光</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nara School created by Juko MURATA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nara School created by Juko MURATA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nara School: Juko MURATA</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="50">
<j>東山流（ひがしやまりゅう） 能阿弥</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Higashiyama School created by Ami NO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Higashiyama School created by Ami NO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Higashiyama School: Noami</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="51">
<j>堺流 （さかいりゅう） 武野紹鴎</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sakai School created by Shoo TAKENO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sakai School created by Shoo TAKENO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sakai School: Shoo TAKENO</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="52">
<j>この時期の創始と伝えられ現存するものには以下がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following are believed to have originated during this period and present up to now:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following are believed to have originated during this period and are present up to now:</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following are believed to have originated during this period and are present up to now:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="53">
<j>珠光流（じゅこうりゅう） 村田珠光</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Juko School created by Juko MURATA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Juko School created by Juko MURATA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Juko School: Juko MURATA</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="54">
<j>志野流（しのりゅう） 志野宗信 志野流香道の家元</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Shino School created by Soshin SHINO, who was the servant of Shino school of incense.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Shino School created by Soshin SHINO, who was a servant of the Shino school of incense.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shino School: Soshin SHINO, who was iemoto (the head family of a school) of the Shino School of incense</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用し表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="55">
<j>瑞穂流（みずほりゅう） 玉置一咄 日高郡 (和歌山県)手取城城主 代々紀州徳川家に仕え明治に流儀を改めるが戦後は神戸を中心に伝承。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mizuho School created by Ittotsu TAMAKI, who was the lord of Tedori Castle, Hidaka District (Wakayama Prefecture), served the Kishu Tokugawa Family for generations, revised the school in Meiji, but spread the tradition after the World War II as Kobe as the center</e>
<cmt>玉置一咄→Ittotsu TAMAKI[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mizuho School created by Ittotsu TAMAKI, who was the lord of Tedori Castle, Hidaka District (Wakayama Prefecture), served the Kishu Tokugawa Family for generations, revised the school in Meiji, but spread the tradition after the World War II with Kobe as the center</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mizuho School: Ittotsu TAMAKI, who was the lord of Tedori-jo Castle, Hidaka-gun (Wakayama Prefecture), served the Kishu Tokugawa Family for generations, revised the school in Meiji, but spread the tradition after the World War II with Kobe as the center.</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>玉置一成『茶道要鑑』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(&quot;Sado yokan,&quot; written by Issei TAMAKI).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(&quot;Sado yokan,&quot; written by Issei TAMAKI).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Chado yokan&quot; (literally, summary of sado), written by Issei TAMAKI</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>千利休と同時期の創始による流派</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The school that originated during the same period as Rikyu SEN</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The school that originated during the same period as Rikyu SEN</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Schools That Originated During the Same Period as SEN no Rikyu</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="57">
<j>多くは武野紹鴎の門人か千利休の直弟子を創始者とするものであり、利休の影響はうけつつも「宗旦流」とは異なる独自の茶風を形成している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most of the founders were disciples of Shoo TAKENO or the direct pupil of Rikyu SEN, and formed a unique way of tea different from &quot;Sotan school&quot; even being influenced by Rikyu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most of the founders were disciples of Shoo TAKENO or a direct pupil of Rikyu SEN, and formed a unique way of tea different from &quot;Sotan school&quot; even being influenced by Rikyu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most of the founders were disciples of Shoo TAKENO or a direct pupil of SEN no Rikyu, and formed a unique way of tea different from &apos;Sotan School&apos; even being influenced by Rikyu.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>今日、武家茶道と呼ばれる流派の多くはここに見ることができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most of the schools of buke (bushi) sado are found here.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most of the schools of buke (bushi) sado are found here.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most of the schools of buke (samurai) sado are found here.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="59">
<j>利休流 （りきゅうりゅう） 利休の門人、円乗坊宗円の流れ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rikyu School is the way of Soen ENJOBO, who was the disciple of Rikyu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Rikyu School is the way of Soen ENJOBO, the disciple of Rikyu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rikyu School: the linage of Soen ENJOBO, the disciple of Rikyu.</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="60">
<j>藪内流 （やぶのうちりゅう） 藪内剣仲 利休の弟弟子</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yabunouchi school is created by Kenchu YABUNOUCHI, who was the fellow junior diciple of Rikyu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yabunouchi school was created by Kenchu YABUNOUCHI, the fellow junior disciple of Rikyu.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yabunouchi School: Kenchu YABUNOUCHI, the fellow junior disciple of Rikyu.</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="61">
<j>東藪内流（あづまやぶのうちりゅう） 華道宣法未生流と共に伝えられ神奈川・青森などに見られる</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amadumayabunochi School passed down along with the Senpo Misho Ryu School of Kado and could be found in Kanagawa and Aomori Prefectures.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amadumayabunochi School passed down along with the Senpo Misho Ryu School of Kado could be found in Kanagawa and Aomori Prefectures.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Azuma Yabunouchi School: Passed down along with the Senpo Misho School of Kado (flower arrangement), found in Kanagawa and Aomori Prefectures.</e>
<cmt>ウェブに合わせて原文を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="62">
<j>南坊流（なんぼうりゅう） 南坊宗啓始祖</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Nanbo School is created by the founder Sokei NANBO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Nanbo School was created by the founder Sokei NANBO.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nanbo School: Sokei NANBO, the founder</e>
<cmt>ウェブに合わせて原文を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="63">
<j>織部流 （おりべりゅう） 古田重然 利休七哲の一人</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oribe School is created by Shigenari FURUTA, who was one of the Rikyushichitetsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oribe School was created by Shigenari FURUTA, one of the Rikyushichitetsu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oribe School: Shigenari FURUTA, one of the Rikyushichitetsu (the seven disciples of Rikyu)</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="64">
<j>上田宗箇流 （うえだそうこりゅう） 上田重安 古田織部の門人</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ueda-Soko School is created by Shigeyasu UEDA, who was the disciple of Oribe FURUTA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ueda-Soko School was created by Shigeyasu UEDA, the disciple of Oribe FURUTA.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ueda-Soko School: Shigeyasu UEDA, the disciple of Oribe FURUTA</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="65">
<j>遠州流 （えんしゅうりゅう） 小堀遠州 古田織部の門人</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Enshu School is created by Enshu KOBORI, who was the disciple of Oribe FURUTA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Enshu School was created by Enshu KOBORI, the disciple of Oribe FURUTA.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Enshu School: Enshu KOBORI, the disciple of Oribe FURUTA</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="66">
<j>小堀遠州流 （こぼりえんしゅうりゅう） 小堀遠州 古田織部の門人</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kobori Enshu School is created by Kobori Enshu, who was the disciple of Oribe FURUTA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kobori Enshu School was created by Kobori Enshu, the disciple of Oribe FURUTA.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kobori Enshu School: Enshu KOBORI, the disciple of Oribe FURUTA</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="67">
<j>大和遠州流 （やまとえんしゅうりゅう） 小堀蓬雪 小堀遠州三男</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamato Enshu School is created by Osetsu KOBORI, who was the third son of Kobori Enshu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yamato Enshu School was created by Osetsu KOBORI, the third son of Kobori Enshu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamato Enshu School: Osetsu KOBORI, the third son of Enshu KOBORI</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="68">
<j>安楽庵流 （あんらくあんりゅう） 安楽庵策伝（現存するか不明）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Anrakuan school is created by Sakuden ANRAKUAN (it is uncertain whether he truly existed).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Anrakuan school was created by Sakuden ANRAKUAN (it is uncertain whether he truly existed or not).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Anrakuan School: Sakuden ANRAKUAN (it is uncertain whether it presents itself or not).</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="69">
<j>玉川遠州流（たまがわえんしゅうりゅう） 大森漸斎 小堀遠州の門人</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tamagawa-Enshu School is created by Zansai OMORI, who was the disciple of Enshu KOBORI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tamagawa-Enshu School was created by Zansai OMORI, the disciple of Enshu KOBORI.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tamagawa-Enshu School: Zansai OMORI, the disciple of Enshu KOBORI</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="70">
<j>壺月遠州流（こげつえんしゅうりゅう）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nigetsu-Enshu School</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nigetsu-Enshu School</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nigetsu-Enshu School</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="71">
<j>有楽流 （うらくりゅう） 織田長益</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Uraku School is created by Nagamasu ODA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Uraku School was created by Nagamasu ODA.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Uraku School: Nagamasu ODA</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="72">
<j>貞置流（さだおきりゅう） 織田貞置 織田有楽の甥信貞の子</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sadaoki School is created by Sadaoki ODA, who was the son of Nobusada, who was the nephew of Yuuraku ODA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sadaoki School was created by Sadaoki ODA, the son of Nobusada, who was the nephew of Yuuraku ODA.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sadaoki School: Sadaoki ODA, the son of Nobusada, who was the nephew of Yuraku ODA</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="73">
<j>三斎流 （さんさいりゅう） 一尾伊織 利休七哲の一人細川忠興の門人</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sansai School is created by Iori ICHIO, who was one of the Rikyushichitetsu, and the disciple of Tadaoki HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sansai School was created by Iori ICHIO, who was one of the Rikyushichitetsu, and the disciple of Tadaoki HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sansai School: Iori ICHIO, who was one of the Rikyushichitetsu, and the disciple of Tadaoki HOSOKAWA</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="74">
<j>御家流 (茶道)（おいえりゅう） 安藤信友 一尾伊織の門人米津田賢に師事</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Oie School is created by Nobutomo ANDO, who was the disciple of Iori ICHIJO, and studied under Tadakata (His first name was also pronounced Tadakata or Michikata) YONEKITSU.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Oie School was created by Nobutomo ANDO, the disciple of Iori ICHIJO, who studied under Tadakata (His first name was also pronounced Tadakata or Michikata) YONEKITSU.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oie School: Nobutomo ANDO, the disciple of Iori ICHIJO, who studied under Tadakata YONEKITSU</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用しまし、米津田賢は、よねつただかた、としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="75">
<j>肥後古流 (茶道)（ひごこりゅう） 熊本藩で伝承され利休の流儀をそのまま伝えていると称される</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Higo Old School was passed down in Kumamoto domain, and is said that it continues to teach the school of Rikyu as it was.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Higo Old School was passed down in the Kumamoto domain, and is said to continue to teach the school of Rikyu as it was.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Higo Ko School: Passed down in the Kumamoto clan, and is said to continue to teach the school of Rikyu as it was.</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="76">
<j>古市流 （ふるいちりゅう） 古市宗庵 円乗坊宗圓の女婿</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furuichi School is created by Soan FURUICHI, who was the son-in-law of Soen ENJOBO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furuichi School was created by Soan FURUICHI, the son-in-law of Soen ENJOBO.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furuichi School: Soan FURUICHI, the son-in-law of Soen ENJOBO</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="77">
<j>小堀流 （こぼりりゅう） 小堀長斎</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kobori School is created by Chosai KOBORI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kobori School was created by Chosai KOBORI.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kobori School: Chosai KOBORI</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="78">
<j>萱野流 （かやのりゅう） 萱野甚斎 古田織部の甥（現存するか不明）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kayano School is created by Jinsai KAYANO, who was the nephew of Oribe FURUTA (it is uncertain whether he really existed).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kayano School was created by Jinsai KAYANO, the nephew of Oribe FURUTA (it is uncertain whether he really existed or not).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kayano School: Jinsai KAYANO, the nephew of Oribe FURUTA (it is uncertain whether it presents itself or not)</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>小笠原流</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ogasawara School</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ogasawara School</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ogasawara School</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>千道安の流れを汲む流派</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Schools which practiced the way of SEN no Doan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Schools that practiced the way of SEN no Doan</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Schools That Practiced the Way of SEN no Doan</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="79">
<j>千家の本家である堺千家（さかいせんけ）は千利休の実子である千道安が継いだが、早期に断絶した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sakai-Senke, which is the head family of Senke, was inherited by the legal son of Rikyu SEN, but broke off early.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sakai-Senke, the head family of Senke, was inherited by the legal son of Rikyu SEN, but broke off early.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sakaisenke: The head family of Senke, was inherited by the biological son of SEN no Rikyu, but broke off early.</e>
<cmt>前出用語や統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="80">
<j>宗和流 （そうわりゅう） 金森重近 織部・遠州の影響を受けた</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sowa School created by Higechika KANAMORI, who was influenced by Oribe and Enshu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sowa School created by Higechika KANAMORI, who was influenced by Oribe and Enshu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sowa School: Higechika KANAMORI, who was influenced by Oribe and Enshu</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="81">
<j>石州流 （せきしゅうりゅう） 片桐石州 道安門下の桑山宗仙に師事</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sekishu School created by Sadamasa KATAGIRI studied under Sosen KUWAYAMA, who was the disciple of Doan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sekishu School created by Sadamasa KATAGIRI studied under Sosen KUWAYAMA, the disciple of Doan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sekishu School: Sekishu KATAGIRI (Also known as Sadamasa KATAGIRI) studied under Sosen KUWAYAMA, the disciple of Doan</e>
<cmt>ウェブに合わせて原文、訳文を変え、コロンを使用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="82">
<j>石州流宗猿系（そうえんけい） 下條信隆 石州庶子</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sekishu School of Soen Line is created by Nobutaka SHIMOJO, who was the legitimate son of Sekishu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sekishu School of the Soen Line was created by Nobutaka SHIMOJO, the legitimate son of Sekishu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sekishu School of the Soen Line: Nobutaka SHIMOJO, the child born out of wedlock of Sekishu</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="83">
<j>古石州流 （こせきしゅうりゅう） 藤林宗源 石州家老</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Old Sekishu School is created by Sogen FUJIBAYASHI, who was the chief vassal of Sekishu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Old Sekishu School created by Sogen FUJIBAYASHI, the chief vassal of Sekishu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ko Sekishu School: Sogen FUJIBAYASHI, the chief vassal of Sekishu</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="84">
<j>大口派 （おおぐちは） 大口樵翁</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oguchi Line is created by Shoo OGUCHI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oguchi Line created by Shoo OGUCHI.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oguchi Line: Shoo OGUCHI</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="85">
<j>清水派 （しみずは） 清水動閑</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shimizu Line is created by Dokan SHIMIZU.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shimizu Line was created by Dokan SHIMIZU.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shimizu Line: Dokan SHIMIZU</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="86">
<j>野村派 （のむらは） 野村休盛</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Nomura Line is created by Yasumori NOMURA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Nomura Line was created by Yasumori NOMURA.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nomura Line: Yasumori NOMURA</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="87">
<j>怡渓派 （いけいは） 怡渓宗悦</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ikei Line is created by Soetsu IKEI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ikei Line was created by Soetsu IKEI.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ikei Line: Soetsu IKEI</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="88">
<j>鎮信流 （ちんしんりゅう） 松浦鎮信 (天祥)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chinshin School is created by Shigenobu (Tensho) MATSUURA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chinshin School was created by Shigenobu (Tensho) MATSUURA.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chinshin School: Shigenobu (Also known as Tensho) MATSURA</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="89">
<j>不昧流 （ふまいりゅう） 松平治郷</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fumai School is created by Harusato MATSUDAIRA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fumai School was created by Harusato MATSUDAIRA.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fumai School: Harusato MATSUDAIRA</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="90">
<j>宗観流 （そうかんりゅう） 井伊直弼</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sokan School is created by Naosuke II.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sokan School was created by Naosuke II.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sokan School: Naosuke II</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>千宗旦の流れを汲む流派</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Schools which practiced the way of Sotan SEN</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Schools that practiced the way of Sotan SEN</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Schools That Practiced the Way of SEN no Sotan</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="91">
<j>いわゆる「宗旦流（そうたんりゅう）」であり、三千家の他に、宗旦四天王の系譜である松尾流、庸軒流、宗徧流、普斎流や久田流なども含む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In another words, it was the &quot;Sotan School&quot; and included Matsuo, Yoken, Sohen, Fusai, and Hisada schools that werepedigree of Sotanshiten-no (Four Disciples of Sotan) other than the Three Senke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In another words, it was the &quot;Sotan School&quot; and included Matsuo, Yoken, Sohen, Fusai, and Hisada schools that werepedigree of Sotanshiten-no (Four Disciples of Sotan) other than the Three Senke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In another words, it was the &apos;Sotan School&apos; and included Matsuo, Yoken, Sohen, Fusai, and Hisada Schools that were pedigree of Sotan Shitenno (Four Disciples of Sotan) other than the Sansenke.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>宗旦流は、江戸時代初期に、少庵の子である千宗旦とその弟子達に対して用いられた呼称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Sotan school was the name used for the Sotan SEN, who was the son of Shoan, and his disciples.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sotan school was the name used for the Sotan SEN, the son of Shoan, and his disciples.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sotan School was the name used for SEN no Sotan, the son of Shoan, and his disciples.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>侘びに徹することを旨とする傾向が強い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It had a strong inclination to consider that it is good to devote oneself to wabi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was a strong inclination to consider that it is good to devote oneself to wabi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was a strong inclination to consider that it is good to devote oneself to wabi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="94">
<j>三千家（さんせんけ） 千利休の後妻の連れ子である千少庵系統の家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sansenke is created by the house of Shoan SEN, who was the son of the second wife of Rikyu SEN.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sansenke was created by the house of Shoan SEN, the son of the second wife of Rikyu SEN.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sansenke: The house of SEN no Shoan, the son of the second wife of SEN no Rikyu</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>堺千家に対して傍系に当たる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was of the subsidiary line compared to Sakai Senke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was of the subsidiary line compared to Sakai Senke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was of the subsidiary line compared to Sakaisenke.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="96">
<j>表千家（おもてせんけ） 不審庵</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omote Senke is created by Fushin-an.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omote Senke was created by Fushin-an.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omotesenke: Fushin-an (a tea room in the residence of the head of the Omotesenke)</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用し、前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="97">
<j>裏千家（うらせんけ） 今日庵 表千家より分派</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ura Senke was divided from Konnichi-an of Omote Senke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ura Senke was separated from Konnichi-an of Omote Senke.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Urasenke: Konnichi-an (a tea room in the residence of the head of the Urasenke), separated from Omotesenke</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用し、前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="98">
<j>武者小路千家（むしゃのこうじせんけ） 官休庵 表千家より別派</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mushanokoji Senke was separated from Kankyu-an Omote Senke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mushanokoji Senke was separated from Kankyu-an Omote Senke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mushanokojisenke: Kankyu-an (a tea room in the residence of the head of the Mushanokojisenke school), separated from Omotesenke</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用し、前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="99">
<j>宗偏流 （そうへんりゅう） 山田宗偏 宗旦四天王</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sohen School is created by Sohen YAMADA of the Sotanshiten-no.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sohen School was created by Sohen YAMADA of the Sotanshiten-no.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sohen School: Sohen YAMADA of the Sotan Shitenno</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用し、前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="100">
<j>庸軒流（ようけんりゅう） 藤村庸軒 宗旦四天王</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoken School is created by Yoken FUJIMURA, who was a member of the Sotanshiten-no.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoken School was created by Yoken FUJIMURA, who was a member of the Sotanshiten-no.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoken School: Yoken FUJIMURA of the Sotan Shitenno</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用し、前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="101">
<j>庸軒流宗積諦観派</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoken School of Soseki-Teikan Line</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoken School of Soseki-Teikan Line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soseki-Teikan Line of Yoken School</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="102">
<j>普斎流 （ふさいりゅう） 杉木普斎 宗旦四天王（現存するか不明）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fusai School is created by Fusai SUGIMOTO, who was one of the Sotanshiten-no (it is uncertain whether he really existed).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fusai School was created by Fusai SUGIMOTO, who was one of the Sotanshiten-no (it is uncertain whether he really existed or not).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fusai School: Fusai SUGIMOTO of the Sotan Shitenno (it is uncertain whether it presents itself or not)</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用し、前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="103">
<j>久田流 （ひさだりゅう） 久田宗栄 表千家の縁戚および分派</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hisada School is created by Soei HISADA, and was the related line of Omote Senke which branched off.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hisada School was created by Soei HISADA, and was the related line of Omote Senke which branched off.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hisada School: Soei HISADA, and was the related line of Omotesenke which branched off.</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用し、前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="104">
<j>堀内家 （ほりのうちりゅう） 堀内仙鶴 表千家六代覚々斎の門人</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Horinouchi School is created by Senkaku HORINOCHI and was disciple of Kakukakusai, who was the disciple of sixth Omote Senke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Horinouchi School was created by Senkaku HORINOCHI and the disciple of Kakukakusai, who was the disciple of sixth Omote Senke.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Horinouchi School: Senkaku HORINOCHI and the disciple of Kakukakusai, the sixth Omotesenke</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用し、前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="105">
<j>松尾流 （まつおりゅう） 松尾宗二（楽只斎） 表千家六代覚々斎の門人</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Matsuo School is created by Soji MATSUO (Gakushisai), who was the disciple of Kakukakusai, who was the disciple of the sixth Omote Senke.</e>
<cmt>楽只斎→Gakushisai[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Matsuo School was created by Soji MATSUO (Gakushisai), the disciple of Kakukakusai, who was the disciple of the sixth Omote Senke.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Matsuo School: Soji MATSUO (also known as Rakushisai), the disciple of Kakukakusai, the sixth Omotesenke</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用し、前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="106">
<j>三谷流 （みたにりゅう） 三谷宗鎮 表千家六代覚々斎の門人（現存するか不明）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitani School is created by Sochin MITANI, who was the disciple of the sixth Omote Senke (it is unclear whether he really existed).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitani School was created by Sochin MITANI, the disciple of the sixth Omote Senke (it is unclear whether he really existed or not).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitani School: Sochin MITANI, the disciple of Kakukakusai, the sixth Omotesenke (it is unclear whether it presents itself or not)</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用し、前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="107">
<j>曲全流（きょくぜんりゅう） 河村曲全 表千家六代覚々斎の門人（現存するか不明）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyokuzen School is created by Kyokuzen KAWAKAMI, who was the disciple of the sixth Omote Senke (it is unclear whether he really existed).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyokuzen School wass created by Kyokuzen KAWAKAMI, the disciple of the sixth Omote Senke (it is unclear whether he really existed or not).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyokuzen School: Kyokuzen KAWAKAMI, the disciple of Kakukakusai, the sixth Omotesenke (it is unclear whether it presents itself or not).</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用し、前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="108">
<j>江戸千家 （えどせんけ） 川上不白 表千家七代如心斎の門人</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omote Senke Fuhaku School is created by Fuhaku KAWAKAMI, who was the disciple of Nyoshinsai, the seventh Omote Senke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omote Senke Fuhaku School was created by Fuhaku KAWAKAMI, the disciple of Nyoshinsai, the seventh Omote Senke.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Edosenke: Fuhaku KAWAKAMI, the disciple of Nyoshinsai, the seventh Omotesenke</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用し、前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="109">
<j>表千家不白流 （ふはくりゅう） 川上宗什 川上不白の門人</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omote Senke Fuhaku School is created by Soju KAWAKAMI, who was the disciple of Fuhaku KAWAKAMI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omote Senke Fuhaku School was created by Soju KAWAKAMI, the disciple of Fuhaku KAWAKAMI.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omotesenke Fuhaku School: Soju KAWAKAMI, the disciple of Fuhaku KAWAKAMI</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用し、前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="110">
<j>不白流石塚派 石塚宗通 川上不白の門人</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fuhaku School of Ishizuka line is created by Sotsu ISHIZUKA, who was the disciple of Fuhaku KAWAKAMI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fuhaku School of Ishizuka line is created by Sotsu ISHIZUKA, who was the disciple of Fuhaku KAWAKAMI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ishizuka Line of Fuhaku School: Sotsu ISHIZUKA, the disciple of Fuhaku KAWAKAMI</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用し、前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="111">
<j>都千家（みやこせんけ） 森山宗江 江戸千家の分派</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Miyako Senke is created by Soe MORIYAMA, and a school that divided from Edo Senke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Miyako Senke was created by Soe MORIYAMA, and a school that separated from Edo Senke.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Miyakosenke (the House of Miyakosen): Soe MORIYAMA, separated from Edosenke</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用し、前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="112">
<j>雅流（みやびりゅう） 水谷宗雅 不白流の分派</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Miyabi School created by Soga MIZUTANI was the branched line of Fuhaku School.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Miyabi School created by Soga MIZUTANI was a branch of the Fuhaku School.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Miyabi School: Soga MIZUTANI, a branch of the Fuhaku School</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用し、前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="113">
<j>江戸千家新柳流</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Edo Senke Sin-Yanagi School</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Edo Senke Sin-Yanagi School</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sin-Yanagi School of Edosenke</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="114">
<j>表千家都流</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omote Senke Miyako School</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omote Senke Miyako School</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Miyako School of Omotesenke</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="115">
<j>表千家看月庵</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omote Senke Kangetsu-an</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omote Senke Kangetsu-an</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kangetsu-an of Omotesenke</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="116">
<j>速水流 （はやみりゅう） 速水宗達 裏千家八代又玄斎の門人</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hayami School is created by Sotatsu HAYAMI, who was the disciple of Yugensai, who was the eighth Senke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hayami School was created by Sotatsu HAYAMI, the disciple of Yugensai, who was the eighth Senke.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hayami School: Sotatsu HAYAMI, the disciple of Yugensai, the eighth Urasenke</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用し、前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="117">
<j>大日本茶道学会（だいにっぽんちゃどうがっかい） 田中仙樵 裏千家十三代圓能斎の門人・後に石州流の秘伝も得て流儀返上</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dai Nihon Chado Gakkai (Japan Association of the Tea Ceremony) is created by Sensho TANAKA, who was the disciple of Ennosai, who was the thirteenth Ura Senke, and later gained the secrets of Ishida School and returned the teachings.</e>
<cmt>大日本茶道学会→Dai Nihon Chado Gakkai (Japan Association of the Tea Ceremony)[http://www.santokuan.or.jp/eng/index.html][原文では、「だいにっぽんちゃどうがっかい」と書かれていましたが、大日本茶道学会のサイトではDai Nihon Chado Gakkaiと書かれていました。]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dai Nihon Chado Gakkai (Japan Association of the Tea Ceremony) was created by Sensho TANAKA, the disciple of Ennosai, who was the thirteenth Ura Senke, and later gained the secrets of the Ishida School and returned the teachings.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dai Nihon Chado Gakkai (Japan Association of the Tea Ceremony): Sensho TANAKA, the disciple of Ennosai, the thirteenth Urasenke, and later gained the secrets of the Ishida School and returned the teachings</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用し、前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="25">
<sen id="118">
<j>宗旦古流（一身田流とも） 円猷上人 真宗高田派本山専修寺にて伝わる</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Sotan Old School (also called as the Isshinden Line) is created by Shonin ENYU and is still continues to be passed down in Senju-ji Temple, the head temple of Shinshu Sect Takada School.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sotan Old School (also called as the Isshinden Line) was created by Shonin ENYU and still continues to be passed down in the Senju-ji Temple, the head temple of Shinshu Sect Takada School.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sotan Ko School (also called as the Isshinden Line): Shonin ENYU, passed down in Senju-ji Temple, the head temple of Takada School of Shinshu Sect</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用し、前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>系譜不詳の流派</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Schools Where its Genealogy remains Uncertain</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Schools Where Genealogy remains Uncertain</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Schools Where Genealogy Remains Uncertain</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="119">
<j>中宮寺御流（ちゅうぐうじごりゅう） 奈良中宮寺に伝わる</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chugu-ji Goryu School is continued to be passed down in Nara Chugu-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chugu-ji Goryu School continues to be passed down in Nara Chugu-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chugu-ji Goryu School: Passed down in Nara Chugu-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用し、前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="120">
<j>紫野千家（むらさきのせんけ） 尾張徳川の家老家に伝わった今沢流の系譜らしい 現在自衛隊などで習流 また別に同名の流派もあるがどこの流れかは不明</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Murasakino Senke has a genealogy of it being passed down the house of chief vassal of Owari-Tokugugawa family and is a school taught within the Japanese Defense Army, and there is another school with a same name is uncertain about which.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Murasakino Senke has the genealogy of being passed down from the house of chief vassal of Owari-Tokugugawa family and is a school taught within the Japanese Defense Army, and there is another school with the same name.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Murasakinosenke (the house of Murasakinosen): Assumed to be the linage passed down from the house of chief vassal of Owari Tokugawa family, which taught within the Japanese Defense Army; there is another school with the same name which is unknown the linage</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用し、前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="121">
<j>覚花一心流（こうかいっしんりゅう） 巓崢宗光 千家流と絶縁・別派する</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koka-Isshin Ryu School is created by Munemitsu (巓崢宗光) and ended relation and divided from the School of Senke.</e>
<cmt>巓崢宗光→Munemitsu[定訳不明][日本語の名字の呼び方が分かりません。]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koka-Isshin Ryu School was created by Munemitsu (巓崢宗光) and ended it&apos;s relationship and separated from the School of Senke.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koka-Isshin School: Munemitsu TENKO (巓崢宗光) and ended it&apos;s relationship and separated from the School of Senke</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用し、前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>茶道富士庵流</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sado Fujian School</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sado Fujian School</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sado Fujian School</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="122">
<j>燁々流</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoyo School (燁々流)</e>
<cmt>燁々流→Yoyo School[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoyo School (燁々流)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoyo School (燁々流)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="123">
<j>PL茶道</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">PL Sado</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">PL Sado</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">PL Sado</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>著名な茶人</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Well known Chajin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Well known Chajin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Well known Chajin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="124">
<j>著名な茶人については茶人人物一覧を参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For more information about well known chajin, please refer to List of people, Chajin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For more information about well known chajin, please refer to the List of people, Chajin.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For more information about well known chajin, please refer to the List of people, Chajin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>茶道の実践</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sado Achievements</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sado Achievements</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sado Achievements</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="125">
<j>茶道とは客を茶でもてなすことであり、その実践には多様な形態がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sado is to entertain the guest with tea, and there were various forms of its achievements.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The purpose of Sado is to entertain guest with tea, and there were various forms to achieve this.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The purpose of Sado is to entertain guest with tea, and there were various forms to achieve this.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="126">
<j>茶道をたしなむ人が来客の際、ポットや茶盆を用いて薄茶を点てるといったものはもっとも簡略かつ日常的なことであるが、より様式化されたもてなしの形として、茶事および大寄せ茶会があげられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a simple everyday event to entertain the guest with Usucha (thin maccha) using a pot and tea tray for the person who practices sado, but more ceremonial forms of entertaining the guests were the Chaji (tea function) and Oyose Chakai (tea party of the masses).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a simple everyday event to entertain guest with Usucha (thin maccha) using a pot and a tea tray for a person who practices sado, but more ceremonial forms of entertaining guests were the Chaji (tea function) and Oyose Chakai (tea party of the masses).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a simple everyday event to entertain guest with Usucha (thin maccha) using a pot and a tea tray for a person who practices sado, but more ceremonial forms of entertaining guests were the Chaji (tea function) and Oyose Chakai (tea party of the masses).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="127">
<j>茶事とは少人数のあらかじめ決められた客を対象にして個人が行う茶会であり、亭主は茶室を花や掛物で飾り、炭手前、懐石、濃茶および薄茶の点前により客をもてなす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chaji is the form of tea party that individuals perform for a small number of designated guests, and the host decorates the tea room with flowers and the hanging scroll, and entertained the guest with charcoal temae, kaiseki (meal served in the tea ceremony), and koicha (thick tea) or usucha (thin tea).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chaji is a form of tea party that individuals perform for a small number of designated guests, and the host decorates the tea room with flowers and a hanging scroll, and entertains the guest with charcoal temae, kaiseki (meal served in the tea ceremony), and koicha (thick tea) or usucha (thin tea).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chaji is a form of tea party that individuals perform for a small number of designated guests, and the host decorates the tea room with flowers and a hanging scroll, and entertains the guest with charcoal temae, kaiseki (meal served in the tea ceremony), and koicha (thick tea) or usucha.</e>
<cmt>前出用語の補足をのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="128">
<j>招待客は最大5名程度までであり、3時間～5時間程度を要する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The maximum number of guests are up to five and requires three to five hours.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The maximum number of guests are five and requires three to five hours.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The maximum number of guests are five and requires three to five hours.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="129">
<j>昼食として懐石を供してから茶をふるまう正午の茶事が最も基本的な形であるが、趣向によって朝・夜などの時間帯の茶事も行われ、また客が食事をすませた後の時間帯にもてなすこともある（飯後の茶事。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The most common form is the afternoon chaji which incorporated kaiseki for lunch, but depending on the mood, chaji is performed in the time period of morning or evening, and also after meal times of the guests (It is called after meal tea function</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The most common form is the afternoon chaji which incorporated kaiseki for lunch, but depending upon the mood, chaji is performed in the morning or evening, and also after meal times (called after meal tea function)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The most common form is the afternoon chaji which incorporated kaiseki for lunch, but depending upon the mood, chaji is performed in the morning or evening, and also after meal times (called after meal tea function)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="130">
<j>食事はごく簡素なものとするか省略する）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The meal is very simple or simplified.).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The meal is very simple or simplified..</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The meal is very simple or simplified.</e>
<cmt>不要なピリオドをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="131">
<j>趣向によって、屋外を茶室に見立てる野点（のだて）や、テーブル・椅子を用いる立礼（りゅうれい）の茶事も行われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Depending on occasions, chaji is performed in the form of nodate (outdoor tea making) which makes outdoors as the tea room and ryurei (table seated style) which uses tables and chairs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Depending upon the occasion, chaji is performed in the form of nodate (outdoor tea making) which uses the outdoors in place of the tea room and ryurei (table seated style) which uses tables and chairs.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Depending upon the occasion, chaji is performed in the form of nodate (outdoor tea making) which uses the outdoors in place of the tea room and ryurei (table seated style) which uses tables and chairs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="132">
<j>大寄せ茶会とは、多数の客を対象にして行う茶会である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oyose chakai is tea ceremony which takes care of many guests.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oyose chakai is tea ceremony that serves many guests.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oyose chakai is tea ceremony that serves many guests.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="133">
<j>炭手前・懐石は通常省略され、道具の拝見を省略することも多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Charcoal temae and kaiseki is usually simplified, and often the examination of utensils are abbreviated as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Charcoal temae and kaiseki is usually simplified, and often the examination of utensils are abbreviated as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Charcoal temae and kaiseki is usually simplified, and often the examination of utensils are abbreviated as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="134">
<j>所要時間は1席当たり1時間程度であり、複数の茶席を設けて並行してもてなすこともある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It requires about an hour per one ceremony, and is entertained in several tea rooms arranged side by side.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It requires about an hour per ceremony, and is performed in several tea rooms arranged side by side.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It requires about an hour per ceremony, and is performed in several tea rooms arranged side by side.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>中国の茶芸（工夫茶）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chinese tea (art of tea)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chinese tea (art of tea)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chinese Tea (Art of Tea)</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="135">
<j>中国では、茶の作法を「茶芸」という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In China, people call the method of tea as &quot;Chagei.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In China, people call the method of tea as &quot;Chagei.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In China, people call the method of tea as &apos;Chagei.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="136">
<j>今日、日本で行われている中国茶の淹れ方は、福建・広東で発祥した形式である「工夫茶（功夫茶）」である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The way of pouring Chinese tea in Japan in current days is the form called &quot;kufu cha (gubu cha)&quot; that originated from Canton, Fujian Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The way of pouring Chinese tea in Japan in the present day is the form called &quot;kufu cha (gubu cha)&quot; that originated from Canton, Fujian Province.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The way of pouring Chinese tea in Japan in the present day is the form called &apos;kufu cha&apos; (gubu cha) that originated from Canton, Fujian Province.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="137">
<j>工夫茶は、もともと烏龍茶の淹れ方であるので他の種類の茶葉には適さないが、現在では中国茶芸の主流となっており、他の茶葉も工夫茶で淹れられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kufu cha uses the way of pouring oolong tea and does not apply to other tea leaves, but it is used as the main Chinese tea method and other leaves are used in the method of Kufu cha.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kufu cha uses the way of pouring oolong tea and this does not apply to other tea leaves, but it is used as the main Chinese tea method and other leaves are used in the method of Kufu cha.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kufu cha uses the way of pouring oolong tea and this does not apply to other tea leaves, but it is used as the main Chinese tea method and other leaves are used in the method of Kufu cha.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="138">
<j>中国茶はその種類が非常に多く、茶葉によって淹れ方が異なるため、「最も美味しく茶を淹れる方法」や一種のパフォーマンスとして、中国茶芸は発展した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are great types of Chinese tea and different ways of pouring tea depending on the tea leaves, that Chinese tea developed as &quot;the most beautiful way of pouring tea&quot; and one form of performance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are great types of Chinese tea and different ways of pouring tea depending on the tea leaves, that Chinese tea developed as &quot;the most beautiful way of pouring tea&quot; and one form of performance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are great types of Chinese tea and different ways of pouring tea depending on the tea leaves, that Chinese tea developed as &apos;the most beautiful way of pouring tea&apos; and one form of performance.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="139">
<j>中国においては、漢の時代には飲茶の習慣が根付いていたと考えられているが、嗜好品として広まったために、「道」としての茶道はおこらなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that the tea drinking custom settled in the ages of Han, but since it spread as a drink to just enjoy its taste, sado did not develop as &quot;the way.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that the tea drinking custom settled in the age of Han, but since then has spread as a drink to just enjoy its taste, sado did not develop as &quot;the way.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that the tea drinking custom settled in the age of Han, but since then has spread as a drink to just enjoy its taste, sado did not develop as &apos;the art.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="140">
<j>そのため、中国で単に「茶道」と言う場合は「日本の茶道」をさす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, when it is simply called &quot;sado&quot; in China, it points to the &quot;Japanese sado.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, when it is simply called &quot;sado&quot; in China, it points to the &quot;Japanese sado.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, when it is simply called &apos;sado&apos; in China, it points to the &apos;Japanese sado.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="14">
<tit>
<j>朝鮮の茶礼</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chare of Korea</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chare of Korea</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chare of Korea</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="141">
<j>朝鮮では芸道的な茶道ではなく、儀式としての「茶禮」（タレ）に重点が置かれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is no artistic school of sado in Korea and put the importance in &quot;tare&quot;(茶禮) as a ceremony.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is no artistic school of sado in Korea and the importance is placed on &quot;tare&quot;(茶禮) as a ceremony.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is no artistic school of sado in Korea and the importance is placed on &apos;tare&apos; (茶禮) as a ceremony.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="142">
<j>記事「茶」の項目、茶朝鮮半島参照</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Please refer to &quot;tea&quot; category in Tea of Korean Peninsula article.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Please refer to &quot;tea&quot; category in Tea of Korean Peninsula article.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Please refer to &apos;tea&apos; category in Tea of Korean Peninsula article.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="15">
<tit>
<j>茶道に関係する音楽作品</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Music works that relate to Sado</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Music that relates to Sado</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Music That Relates to Sado</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="143">
<j>『宇治巡り』（地歌・箏曲）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Uji meguri&quot; (Uji Tour) (jiuta (song played with shamisen) and koto music)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Uji meguri&quot; (Uji Tour) (jiuta (song played with shamisen) and koto music)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Uji meguri&quot; (Uji Tour) (jiuta (song played with shamisen) and koto music)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="144">
<j>文化文政の頃、京都で活躍した盲人音楽家、松浦検校が作曲した手事（てごと）もの地歌曲。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The tegoto mono (central music for shamisen, koto and shakuhachi) of jiuta composed by Kengyo MATSUUA, who was a blind musician who performed in Kyoto, during the Bunka and Bunsei era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The tegoto mono (central music for shamisen, koto and shakuhachi) of jiuta composed by Kengyo MATSUUA, who was a blind musician who performed in Kyoto, during the Bunka and Bunsei era.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The tegoto mono (central music for shamisen, koto and shakuhachi) of jiuta composed by Kengyo MATSURA, who was a blind musician who performed in Kyoto, during the Bunka and Bunsei era.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="145">
<j>箏の手付は八重崎検校。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The koto player was Kengyo YAEZAKI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The koto player was Kengyo YAEZAKI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The koto player was Kengyo YAEZAKI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="146">
<j>「喜撰」「雁が音」など、多数の茶の銘を詠み込み四季の順に配列しつつ、春夏秋冬の茶の名産地宇治を巡り歩くという風流な趣向の曲。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Music such as &quot;Kisen&quot; and &quot;Karigane&quot; named several tea brands lined up in the order of four seasons, and it had a calm atmosphere with an idea to walk around four seasons of Uji, the place of tea production.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Music such as &quot;Kisen&quot; and &quot;Karigane&quot; named several tea brands lined up in the order of four seasons, and it produced a calm atmosphere with the idea to walk around in the four seasons of Uji, the place of tea production.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Music such as &apos;Kisen&apos; and &apos;Karigane&apos; named several tea brands lined up in the order of four seasons, and it produced a calm atmosphere with the idea to walk around in the four seasons of Uji, a famous tea production area.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションなどを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="147">
<j>大曲で二箇所の手事（楽器だけで奏される器楽間奏部）も音楽的に凝ったもので、転調も頻繁に現れ、技術的にもなかなか難しい曲。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was a huge music and was musically solid even in two places of tegoto (part of a music played only with instruments), changed the key frequently, and is considered technically difficult song to play.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was a huge music success and was solid even in two parts of tegoto (partly played with just instruments), changed the key frequently, and is considered a technically difficult piece to play.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was a huge music success and was solid even in two parts of tegoto (partly played with just instruments), changed the key frequently, and is considered a technically difficult piece to play.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="148">
<j>「松浦の四つ物（四大名曲）」のひとつとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered to be one of the &quot;Four best music of Matsuura.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered to be one of the &quot;Four best pieces of music by Matsuura.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered to be one of the &apos;Four best pieces of music by Matsura.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションなどを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="149">
<j>『茶音頭』 （地歌・箏曲）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Cha ondo&quot; (Jiuta, koto song)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Cha ondo&quot; (Jiuta, koto song)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Cha ondo&quot; (Jiuta, koto song)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="150">
<j>文化文政時代、京都で活躍した盲人音楽家、菊岡検校が作曲、八重崎検校が箏の手付をした手事もの地歌曲。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was composed by Kengyo KIKUOKA, the blind musician, who performed in Kyoto in Bunka and Bunsei era, and a tegotomono jiuta where Kengyo YAEZAKI played the koto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was composed by Kengyo KIKUOKA, the blind musician, who performed in Kyoto in Bunka and Bunsei era, and a tegotomono jiuta where Kengyo YAEZAKI played the koto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was composed by Kengyo KIKUOKA, the blind musician, who performed in Kyoto in Bunka and Bunsei era, and a tegotomono jiuta where Kengyo YAEZAKI played the koto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="151">
<j>「茶の湯音頭」と呼ぶ流派もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a school that is called &quot;chano yu ondo.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a school that is called &quot;chano yu ondo.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a school that is called &apos;chanoyu ondo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションなどを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="152">
<j>「音頭」は本来雅楽用語であり、のち近世邦楽全般において広く使われ、この曲も民謡とは関係ないので注意が必要。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Ondo&quot; was originally the term of court music, and was used often in general modern Japanese songs, and should be noted that it is not related to a folk song.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Ondo&quot; was originally the term used for court music, and was often used in general modern Japanese songs, and it should be noted that it is not related to any folk songs.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ondo&apos; was originally the term used for court music, and was often used in general modern Japanese songs, and it should be noted that it is not related to any folk songs.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションなどを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="153">
<j>俳人横井也有の「女手前」から抜粋した歌詞で、多数の茶道具を詠み込みつつ男女の仲がいつまでも続くよう願った内容。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was a lyric selected from &quot;Onnatemae&quot; (Women&apos;s temae) written by the poet, Yayu YOKOI, and its content wished for good relation between a man and woman while calling out many names of tea tools.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was a lyric selected from &quot;Onnatemae&quot; (Women&apos;s temae) written by the poet, Yayu YOKOI, and its content wished for good relations between a man and woman while calling out many names of tea untensils.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was a lyric selected from &apos;Onna temae&apos; (Women&apos;s temae) written by the poet, Yayu YOKOI, and its content wished for good relations between a man and woman while calling out many names of tea utensils.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションなどを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="154">
<j>三味線の調弦が「六下がり」という非常に特殊なもので、独特な響きがこの曲独自の雰囲気を作り出しており、歌の節も凝っている一方で手事が長く、八重崎検校の箏手付も巧みで合奏音楽としてもよくできているので、現代でも演奏会でよく取り上げられる曲である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The tuning of Shamisen used in this song was the unique &quot;six down&quot; and brought out special atmosphere with this tune, while the passage of music is solid, tegoto is long, and the koto player of Kengyo YAEZAKI is done skillfully as a symphony, and is often performed in symphonies even now.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The tuning of Shamisen used in this song was the unique &quot;six down&quot; and produced a special atmosphere with this tune, while the passage of the music is solid, tegoto is long, and the koto player of Kengyo YAEZAKI is done skillfully as a symphony, and is often performed in symphonies even now.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The tuning of Shamisen used in this song was the unique &apos;six down&apos; and produced a special atmosphere with this tune, while the passage of the music is solid, tegoto is long, and the koto player of Kengyo YAEZAKI is done skillfully as a symphony, and is often performed in symphonies even now.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションなどを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="155">
<j>お手前の伴奏として演奏されることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is sometimes played to accompany temae.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is sometimes played to accompany temae.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is sometimes played to accompany temae.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="156">
<j>「上方舞」（地唄舞）においても好んで舞われ、いくつかの流派ごとの振り付けがあるが、どれも袱紗を使用する特徴のあるものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is used as a favorite of &quot;kamigata dance&quot; (jiuta dance), and the arrangement of dance differs depending on schools, but is unique in the way that it uses fukusa (silk cloths).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is used as a favorite &quot;kamigata dance&quot; (jiuta dance), and the arrangement of the dance differs depending upon schools, but is unique in the way that it uses fukusa (silk cloth).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is used as a favorite &apos;kamigata dance&apos; (jiuta dance), and the arrangement of the dance differs depending upon schools, but is unique in the way that it uses fukusa (silk cloth).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションなどを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 ZassouTori(id:136771), 瑞雲(id:27410), Eskimbot(id:29676), 無苦斎(id:179040), Manja(id:74455), 武嶋(id:89475), でここ(id:9565), Commonsenses(id:11185), らりた(id:1327), Michey.M(id:906), 橋本直樹(id:93912), Redattore(id:30931), Lulusuke(id:44392), カドミウム黄(id:184403), テオフィロ(id:18904), ウィキ豊(id:82961), Buru12070106(id:50602), YonaBot(id:125006), マクガイア(id:33346), Mmma Mia!(id:21142), Himazin(id:22034), 中村如栴(id:47313), BOT-Superzerocool(id:65015), Wrbd(id:81229), 燃(id:13732), Nidarin(id:6420), Miri(id:164), SuisuiBot(id:10165), 海衛士(id:19229), 上(id:14148), Xenon(id:77709), Tarobo(id:17287), Suisui(id:69), Jmho(id:10472), Jade0416(id:104181), Caicai(id:107989), Modeha(id:1276), Kstigarbha(id:13376), TuvicBot(id:64131), Moraykaita(id:125554), あーうー(id:1140), Roger(id:9883), Tekune(id:2690), Rai koku(id:1661), Hachikou(id:10676), Ohura(id:5986), Jossi(id:73665), 佐藤薫(id:51396), Qrerw(id:3487), Real Madrid(id:27490), Mzaki(id:61977), Tomika(id:43050), Yamabig(id:21134), 詠狸庵(id:41048), Okc(id:17021), Izayohi(id:13095), Skysea(id:54032), ととりん(id:31982), 仰天(id:33369), Phaedriel(id:150960), Aphaia(id:3132), Dome2000(id:15142), 悠卯斗(id:46277), 竃馬(id:102733), VolkovBot(id:105371), Otoshigo(id:80102), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), Diadiadiad(id:198099), Safkan(id:423), Corwin(id:973), Louperibot(id:128971), SieBot(id:126695), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>