<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>豆腐</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tofu (bean curd)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tofu (bean curd)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tofu (bean curd)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>豆腐（とうふ）は、ダイズを主原料とした、食品。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tofu is a food mainly made from soybeans.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tofu is a food that&apos;s made mainly from soybeans.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tofu is a food that&apos;s made mainly from soybeans.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>起源説等</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Theory of origin, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Theory of origin, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Theory of origin, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>起源説はいくつかあり定かではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There several theories of origin, but none of them is uncertain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There several theories regarding its origin, but none of them is definitive.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There several theories regarding its origin, but none of them is definitive.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>紀元前2世紀前漢時代の淮南王（わいなんおう）・劉安（りゅうあん）にちなむ中華人民共和国伝来の食品であるという説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One theory is that tofu is a food which was connected with Prince Liu An of Huainan in the Former Han Period in the second century B.C., and was introduced from the People&apos;s Republic of China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One theory is that tofu is connected with Prince Liu An of Huainan in the former Han period of the second century B.C., and that it was introduced from mainland China.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One theory is that tofu is connected with Prince Liu An of Huainan in the former Han period of the second century B.C., and that it was introduced from mainland China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>しかし、前漢に原料の大豆はなかったとも言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it is also said that there were no soybeans used as raw materials in Former Han.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is also said that there were no soybeans used as raw materials in the Han.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is also said that there were no soybeans used as raw materials in the Han.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>日本へは奈良時代に遣唐使によって伝えられたともされるが、それ以前に伝わっていた可能性も大きい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another theory is that tofu was introduced into Japan by a Japanese envoy to Tang Dynasty China in the Nara period, but, there is a high possibility that tofu had been introduced before that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another theory is that tofu was introduced into Japan by a Japanese envoy to the Tang Dynasty of China in the Nara period, but it&apos;s very possible that tofu was introduced prior to that time.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another theory is that tofu was introduced into Japan by a Japanese envoy to the Tang Dynasty of China in the Nara period, but it&apos;s very possible that tofu was introduced prior to that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>「腐」の字は本来『納屋の中で肉を熟成させる』という字義から転じて、柔らかく弾力性があるものを意味するものであったが（納豆名称）、日本では食品に「腐る」という字を用いることを嫌って、豆富や豆冨などと記すこともある（日本の豆腐は発酵していない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;腐&quot; (fu), a Japanese character which is part of 豆腐 (tofu), meant a soft and elastic thing (which is called Natto (fermented soybeans)) by being turned from the original meaning of &quot;maturing meat in the barn&quot;; however, 豆富 or 豆冨 is sometimes used in Japan because it is not preferred to use a Japanese character of &quot;腐&quot; meaning &quot;rotten&quot; for food (Japanese tofu is not fermented.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;腐&quot; (fu), a Japanese character that&apos;s part of 豆腐 (tofu), meant a soft, elastic thing (which is called natto (fermented soybeans)) by being turned from the original meaning of &quot;maturing meat in the barn&quot;; however, 豆富 or 豆冨 is sometimes used in Japan because it isn&apos;t preferred to use a Japanese character of &quot;腐&quot; meaning &quot;rotten&quot; for food (Japanese tofu is not fermented).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">腐&apos; (fu), a Japanese character that&apos;s part of 豆腐 (tofu), meant a soft, elastic thing (which is called natto (fermented soybeans)) by being turned from the original meaning of &quot;maturing meat in the barn&quot;; however, 豆富 or 豆冨 is sometimes used in Japan because it isn&apos;t preferred to use a Japanese character of &apos;腐&apos; meaning &apos;rotten&apos; for food (Japanese tofu is not fermented).</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;&apos;→&quot;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>すなわち腐っていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This means, tofu is not rotten.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Accordingly, tofu is not rotten.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Accordingly, tofu is not rotten.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>中華人民共和国には豆腐を発酵させた食品もある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The People&apos;s Republic of China has foods made by fermenting tofu.).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The People&apos;s Republic of China has foods made by fermenting tofu.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The People&apos;s Republic of China has foods made by fermenting tofu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>豆腐を好んだ作家泉鏡花は、極端な潔癖症でもあったことから豆府と表記した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoka IZUMI, a novelist, who liked tofu, displayed tofu as 豆府 because he was extremely obsessed with being clean.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoka IZUMI, a novelist who liked tofu, displayed tofu as 豆府 because he was obsessed with cleanliness.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoka IZUMI, a novelist who liked tofu, displayed tofu as 豆府 because he was obsessed with cleanliness.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>味噌汁や粕汁や鍋料理の具材などとして、日本料理では非常に一般的な食品である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tofu is a very general food in the Japanese cuisine as an ingredient of miso soup, kasujiru (soup made with sake lees) and one-pot dish cooked at the table.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tofu is a very general food in Japanese cuisine, being as an ingredient in miso soup, kasujiru (soup made with sake lees) and one-pot dishes cooked at the table.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tofu is a very general food in Japanese cuisine, being as an ingredient in miso soup, kasujiru (soup made with sake lees) and one-pot dishes cooked at the table.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>また、中国においても日本以上のさまざまな豆腐があり、各種の料理が作られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">China also has more various kinds of tofu than Japan, and a wide variety of dishes is made there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">China, however, has more kinds of tofu than Japan does, and a wide variety of dishes are made there.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">China, however, has more kinds of tofu than Japan does, and a wide variety of dishes are made there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>大韓民国、ベトナム、カンボジア、タイ王国、ミャンマー、インドネシアなどでも日常的に食べられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tofu is also eaten on a daily basis in the Republic of Korea, Vietnam, Cambodia, Kingdom of Thailand, Myanmar and Indonesia.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tofu is also eaten on a daily basis in the Republic of Korea, Vietnam, Cambodia, the Kingdom of Thailand, Myanmar and Indonesia.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tofu is also eaten on a daily basis in the Republic of Korea, Vietnam, Cambodia, the Kingdom of Thailand, Myanmar and Indonesia.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>また、アメリカ合衆国などでも以前から一定の人気があったが、今日では多くの食料品店で売られており、『tofu』 自体も英単語として定着している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the United States of America, tofu which has also been enjoying certain popularity long before is now sold at many grocery stores, and &quot;tofu&quot; itself obtains popularity as an English word.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the United States of America, tofu--which has long enjoyed a certain popularity--is now sold at many grocery stores, and the word &quot;tofu&quot; has become common in the English language.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the United States of America, tofu--which has long enjoyed a certain popularity--is now sold at many grocery stores, and the word &quot;tofu&quot; has become common in the English language.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>天明2年（1782年）に刊行された『豆腐百珍（とうふひゃくちん）』には、100種類の豆腐料理が記述されており、また様々な文学でも親しまれてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the &quot;Hundred Delicacies of Tofu&quot; issued in 1782, 100 kinds of tofu dishes were introduced, and tofu was familiar also in many kinds of literature.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the &quot;Hundred Delicacies of Tofu&quot; published in 1782, 100 kinds of tofu dishes were introduced, and tofu was familiar in various kinds of literature.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the &quot;Hundred Delicacies of Tofu&quot; published in 1782, 100 kinds of tofu dishes were introduced, and tofu was familiar in various kinds of literature.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>製法</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Process of making</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The production process</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The production process</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>一般的な豆腐</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">General tofu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">General tofu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">General tofu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="15">
<j>水につけて柔らかくしたダイズを水とともに摩砕し、煮出す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soybeans which are softened by being soaked in water are mashed together with water, and boiled.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soybeans, which are softened by being soaked in water, are mashed together with water and then boiled.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soybeans, which are softened by being soaked in water, are mashed together with water and then boiled.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>これをしぼって得られる液体が豆乳である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A liquid obtained by squeezing above boiled soybeans is soy milk.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The liquid obtained by squeezing the boiled soybeans is called soy milk.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The liquid obtained by squeezing the boiled soybeans is called soy milk.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>豆乳を作る際、加熱後に漉す製法を「煮しぼり」、加熱前に漉す製法を「生しぼり」という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In producing soy milk, a process of making of filtering after boiling is called &quot;nishibori&quot; (filtering method), and that of filtering before boiling is called &quot;namashibori&quot; (filtering method).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In producing soy milk, a process that involves filtering after boiling is called &quot;nishibori&quot; (filtering method), while the process of filtering before boiling is called &quot;namashibori&quot; (filtering method).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In producing soy milk, a process that involves filtering after boiling is called &apos;nishibori&apos; (filtering method), while the process of filtering before boiling is called &apos;namashibori&apos; (filtering method).</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>しぼった後の滓はおからと呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kasu (residues) after squeezing is called okara (bean curd residue).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The kasu (residue) after squeezing is called okara (bean-curd residue).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The kasu (residue) after squeezing is called okara (bean-curd residue).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="19">
<j>この豆乳がまだ熱いうちににがり（凝固剤）を加えると蛋白分子が後述するように網目状に繋がり、豆乳はプリン状に固まる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When bittern (coagulant) is added to this soy milk while it is warm, protein molecules spread in the form of net as stated below, and soy milk is curdled like a pudding.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When bittern (coagulant) is added to the warm soy milk, protein molecules spread in the form of a net as described below, and the soy milk curdles into a pudding-like consistency.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When bittern (coagulant) is added to the warm soy milk, protein molecules spread in the form of a net as described below, and the soy milk curdles into a pudding-like consistency.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>これを切り分け水にさらした物が絹ごし豆腐と呼ばれ、水にさらさず直接容器に掬い上げた物が寄せ豆腐と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Curdled soy milk which is cut and soaked in water is called kinugoshidofu (silken tofu), and which is scooped and put into a container directly without soaking in water is called yosedofu (fresh tofu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The curdled soy milk that is cut and soaked in water is called kinugoshidofu (silken tofu), while the kind that&apos;s scooped and put into a container directly without soaking in water is called yosedofu (fresh tofu).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The curdled soy milk that is cut and soaked in water is called kinugoshidofu (silken tofu), while the kind that&apos;s scooped and put into a container directly without soaking in water is called yosedofu (fresh tofu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>また、固まった豆乳を崩しながら、内側に布を敷いた型に入れ、水分を抜くと木綿豆腐となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Curdled soy milk which is put into a mold lined with a cloth while being broken down and is drained turns into momendofu (firm tofu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The curdled soy milk that&apos;s put into a mold lined with a cloth while it breaks down and is drained then turns into momendofu (firm tofu).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The curdled soy milk that&apos;s put into a mold lined with a cloth while it breaks down and is drained then turns into momendofu (firm tofu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>さらに、工業的な製法として、豆乳を一旦冷やし、凝固剤といっしょにプラスチック容器に流し込んでから加熱して固める充填豆腐もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, as an industrial process of making, juten dofu (filled tofu) is made through the processes of chilling soy milk, putting chilled soy milk into a plastic container with a coagulant, and curding it by heating.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, as an industrial production process, juten dofu (filled tofu) is made through the processes of chilling soy milk, putting the chilled soy milk into a plastic container with a coagulant, and curding it by heating.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, as an industrial production process, juten dofu (filled tofu) is made through the processes of chilling soy milk, putting the chilled soy milk into a plastic container with a coagulant, and curding it by heating.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>充填豆腐は保存性に優れ、ものによっては一か月保存できるものもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Juten dofu is superior in storage stability, and there are some which can be stored for a month.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Juten dofu is superior in storage stability, and certain varieties can be stored for a month.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Juten dofu is superior in storage stability, and certain varieties can be stored for a month.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="24">
<j>現在では、近代工業の発達により作業の機械化が進み、わずかの大豆から効率よく豆腐が生産されるようになり、より安価で提供されるようになった。。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At present, tofu is efficiently made from a small number of soybeans due to mechanized work by development of modern industry, and tofu is sold at a cheaper price.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Currently, tofu is efficiently made from a small number of soybeans due to the mechanized process that has developed with modern industry, and tofu is sold at cheaper prices.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Currently, tofu is efficiently made from a small number of soybeans due to the mechanized process that has developed with modern industry, and tofu is sold at cheaper prices.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>豆腐はかつては店頭で毎日つくられ、柔らかいので崩れないように水槽の中に沈めて売られるものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tofu used to be made every day in a shop, and be sold in the state of being immersed in a water tank to prevent it from being broken due to its softness.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tofu used to be made every day in a shop, and due to its softness it was sold immersed in a water tank to prevent it from breaking apart.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tofu used to be made every day in a shop, and due to its softness it was sold immersed in a water tank to prevent it from breaking apart.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>現在は工場で生産され、パック詰めで売られているものが主流である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nowadays, tofu is mainly made in a factory, and sold in a pack style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, tofu is mainly produced in factories and sold in packages.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, tofu is mainly produced in factories and sold in packages.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>化学的側面</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chemical aspect</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The chemical aspect</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The chemical aspect</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="27">
<j>豆腐の凝固は豆乳のたんぱく質が凝固剤によりゲル化することで起こる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Coagulation of tofu is caused by gelatinization of soy milk protein by a coagulant.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The coagulation of tofu is caused by the gelatinization of soy milk protein by a coagulant.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The coagulation of tofu is caused by the gelatinization of soy milk protein by a coagulant.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>したがって、豆腐は架橋されたたんぱく質の網目構造に多数の水分子を取り込んだ構造である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, tofu has a structure that many water molecules are contained in the net-like structure of cross-linked protein.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, tofu has a structure in which many water molecules are contained in the net-like structure of cross-linked protein.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, tofu has a structure in which many water molecules are contained in the net-like structure of cross-linked protein.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="29">
<j>大別するとマグネシウムイオンあるいはカルシウムイオンがたんぱく質側鎖のカルボキシル基を架橋してゲルを形成する場合と、酸がたんぱく質の高次構造を変える（変性）ことによりゲルを形成する場合（酸凝固）とがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Broadly classifying, there are two cases that a gel is formed through cross-linking between an ion of magnesium or calcium and a chain carboxyl group on the side of protein, and that a gel is formed through change (denaturalization) of high-order structure of protein by an acid (acid coagulation).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Generally, there is a case in which a gel is formed through cross-linking between an ion of magnesium or calcium and a chain carboxyl group on the side of protein, and a case in which a gel is formed through the change (denaturalization) of the high-order structure of protein by an acid (acid coagulation).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Generally, there is a case in which a gel is formed through cross-linking between an ion of magnesium or calcium and a chain carboxyl group on the side of protein, and a case in which a gel is formed through the change (denaturalization) of the high-order structure of protein by an acid (acid coagulation).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>前者には凝固剤として硫酸カルシウム、塩化マグネシウム、塩化カルシウム、硫酸マグネシウム等が使用され、後者はグルコノデルタラクトンが使用される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the former, calcium sulfate, magnesium chloride, calcium chloride, magnesium sulfate, etc. are used as a coagulant, and in the latter, Glucono-delta-Lactone is used as a coagulant.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the former, calcium sulfate, magnesium chloride, calcium chloride or magnesium sulfate, etc., is used as a coagulant, and in the latter glucono-delta-lactone is used as a coagulant.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the former, calcium sulfate, magnesium chloride, calcium chloride or magnesium sulfate, etc., is used as a coagulant, and in the latter glucono-delta-lactone is used as a coagulant.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>グルコノデルタラクトンの徐々に酸（グルコン酸）へと変化する性質が利用されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The nature of Glucono-delta-Lactone that it gradually changes to an acid (gluconic acid) is used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Glucono-delta-lactone is used because it gradually changes to an acid (gluconic acid).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Glucono-delta-lactone is used because it gradually changes to an acid (gluconic acid).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>なお、グルコン酸はグルコースの有機酸なので安全性は高い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The gluconic acid is very safe because it is an organic acid of glucose.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The gluconic acid is very safe because it&apos;s an organic acid of glucose.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The gluconic acid is very safe because it&apos;s an organic acid of glucose.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="33">
<j>大陸中国では石膏（硫酸カルシウム）を粉末とし水に溶いたものを凝固剤とするが、古来の日本の伝統的な製法では製塩の過程で生じるにがりが主に使われていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In mainland China, gypsum (calcium sulfate) powered and solved in the water is used as a coagulant; however, in the Japanese traditional process of making from ancient times, bittern produced in the process of salt production was mainly used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In mainland China, gypsum (calcium sulfate) powered and dissolved in the water is used as a coagulant; however, in the Japanese traditional process used since ancient times, bittern resulting from the process of salt production was mainly used.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In mainland China, gypsum (calcium sulfate) powered and dissolved in the water is used as a coagulant; however, in the Japanese traditional process used since ancient times, bittern resulting from the process of salt production was mainly used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>現在の日本では硫酸カルシウムやグルコノデルタラクトンなどが凝固剤として多く使われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Calcium sulfate, Glucono-delta-Lactone, etc. are often used as a coagulant in present-day Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Calcium sulfate, glucono-delta-lactone and so forth are often used as coagulants in modern-day Japan.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Calcium sulfate, glucono-delta-lactone and so forth are often used as coagulants in modern-day Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>また、中国や韓国でもこの製法を用いる工場がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This process of making is also used in some factories in China and Korea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This production process is also used in Chinese and Korean factories.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This production process is also used in Chinese and Korean factories.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="36">
<j>一般的ににがりと呼ばれているものは、塩化マグネシウムが主成分で、古くは、塩田で海水から塩を作るときに、いっしょに抽出される副産物であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An object generally called bittern mainly consists of magnesium chloride, and was a secondary product abstracted together when salt was abstracted from salt water at a salt field.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The substance generally referred to as bittern mainly consists of magnesium chloride, and was a secondary product co-abstracted with salt when it was drawn from the salt field.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The substance generally referred to as bittern mainly consists of magnesium chloride, and was a secondary product co-abstracted with salt when it was drawn from the salt field.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="37">
<j>現在では、工業化され塩化マグネシウムの純度の高いものや、海外の岩塩採掘場で採取されたもの、あるいは国内外の工業的な製塩の過程で抽出されたものが多く、実際に塩田から取っているものは少ない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At present, bittern which contains fine magnesium chloride due to industrialization, is obtained at rock salt mining places overseas, or is abstracted in the process of industrial salt production in and outside of Japan is used in most cases, and it is rare to use bittern actually abstracted at a salt field.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Currently, the bittern--which contains fine magnesium chloride due to the industrial process, is obtained at rock-salt mining places overseas or is abstracted in the process of industrial salt production in and outside Japan--is used in most cases, and it&apos;s rare to use bittern that&apos;s actually abstracted from a salt field.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Currently, the bittern--which contains fine magnesium chloride due to the industrial process, is obtained at rock-salt mining places overseas or is abstracted in the process of industrial salt production in and outside Japan--is used in most cases, and it&apos;s rare to use bittern that&apos;s actually abstracted from a salt field.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>また一部豆腐製造業者の間では、凝固剤の総称として「にがり」の呼称を使っている場合もあり、注意が必要である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since some tofu makers use the word &quot;bittern&quot; as a generic word for coagulant, it is necessary to be careful.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because some tofu makers use the word &quot;bittern&quot; as a generic term for coagulant, one must use the word with care.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because some tofu makers use the word &apos;bittern&apos; as a generic term for coagulant, one must use the word with care.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="39">
<j>戦前までは、このにがりを凝固剤に使用するのが主流であったが（一部では硫酸カルシウム（すましこ）も使われていた）、やがて統制品に指定されたため入手が困難となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although it was a main stream to use this bittern as a coagulant before the war (calcium sulfate (sumashiko) was used by some makers), it became difficult to obtain the bittern before long because it was designated as one of controlled goods.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although it was a mainstream practice to use this bittern as a coagulant before the war (calcium sulfate (sumashiko) was used by some makers), it soon became difficult to obtain the bittern because it was designated as controlled goods.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it was a mainstream practice to use this bittern as a coagulant before the war (calcium sulfate (sumashiko) was used by some makers), it soon became difficult to obtain the bittern because it was designated as controlled goods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>そこで同じように凝固反応を起こし、入手の容易な硫酸カルシウム（すましこ）への転換が進んでいった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, a shift to calcium sulfate which caused a coagulation reaction in a similar manner and was easy-to-obtain was enhanced.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently, there was an accelerated shift to calcium sulfate--which caused a coagulation reaction in a similar manner and was easy to obtain.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently, there was an accelerated shift to calcium sulfate--which caused a coagulation reaction in a similar manner and was easy to obtain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>硫酸カルシウムはにがりの主成分である塩化マグネシウムと比べ適正な凝固反応が起こるいわゆる凝固のストライクゾーンが広いため、保水性が高く肌理の細かい高品質な豆腐が、比較的容易に作りやすかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When comparing with magnesium chloride, a main ingredient of bittern, calcium sulfate had a broader zone where a proper coagulation reaction occurred, so-called strike zone of coagulation, and made it comparatively easy to make high-quality tofu which was water-retentive and fine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When compared with magnesium chloride, a main ingredient in bittern, calcium sulfate had a wider zone in which the proper coagulation reaction occurred (being referred to as the strike zone of coagulation) and made it comparatively easy to make high-quality tofu, which was water-retentive and fine.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When compared with magnesium chloride, a main ingredient in bittern, calcium sulfate had a wider zone in which the proper coagulation reaction occurred (being referred to as the strike zone of coagulation) and made it comparatively easy to make high-quality tofu, which was water-retentive and fine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>そのため、戦後も機械化が進むにつれ、凝固材として使いやすい硫酸カルシウムへの転換が進んでいった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, along with the mechanization, a shift to calcium sulfate which was easy-to-use as a coagulant was enhanced also after the war.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, along with the trend in mechanization, a shift to calcium sulfate, which was easy to use as a coagulant, was implemented after the war.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, along with the trend in mechanization, a shift to calcium sulfate, which was easy to use as a coagulant, was implemented after the war.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>1980年代後半になって、にがりで作られた豆腐の味が見直され始め、最近ではスーパーなどで容易ににがりを使った豆腐が入手できるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the latter half of the 1980s, a taste of tofu which was made with bittern started being revaluated, and tofu made with bittern is easily available at a supermarket, etc. nowadays.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the latter half of the 1980s, the taste of tofu made with bittern was again viewed with favor, and now tofu made with bittern is easily available at supermarkets, etc.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the latter half of the 1980s, the taste of tofu made with bittern was again viewed with favor, and now tofu made with bittern is easily available at supermarkets, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>古典的な製法</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Classic process of making</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The classic production process</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The classic production process</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="44">
<j>江戸時代には、落語の題材になったり、また『豆腐百珍』のような料理本まで出るほど、広く庶民の食べ物となっていた豆腐は、比較的加工の度合いも低く、経験さえつめば誰にでも容易に製造できた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tofu, which was a wide-spread popular food among ordinary people as it was used as a subject of rakugo (traditional comic storytelling) and a recipe book like &quot;Hundred Delicacies of Tofu&quot; was issued in the Edo period, could be made easily by anyone who acquired experience, because a degree of processing was comparatively low.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tofu, which enjoyed widespread popularity among ordinary people, as it was used as a subject of rakugo (traditional comic storytelling) and the recipe book &quot;A Hundred Delicacies of Tofu,&quot; published in the Edo period, could be made easily by anyone with sufficient experience, because the degree of processing was comparatively low.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tofu, which enjoyed widespread popularity among ordinary people, as it was used as a subject of rakugo (traditional comic storytelling) and the recipe book &quot;A Hundred Delicacies of Tofu,&quot; published in the Edo period, could be made easily by anyone with sufficient experience, because the degree of processing was comparatively low.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>そのため、大正から戦前にかけては、一つの町内に一軒ずつ製造業者が存在するほどであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, one maker each existed in one town from the Taisho period to the prewar times.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequently, from the Taisho period to the prewar era each town had one tofu maker.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently, from the Taisho period to the prewar era each town had one tofu maker.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>辺鄙な田舎であることを表すのに「酒屋へ三里 豆腐屋へ二里」という俚諺もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In expressing the remote countryside, there was a vulgar proverb of &quot;three ri (old Japanese unit of distance, approx. 3.927 km or 2.44 miles per ri) to a liquor shop, and two ri to a tofu shop.&quot;</e>
<cmt>俚諺→vulgar proverb[俚諺=俗間に言い伝えられてきた諺（http://homepage2.nifty.com/k-todo/kotobaen/sinngenn/sinngennindex.htm より）]（用語サイトには未登録です）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In describe the remote countryside, there was the vulgar proverb, &quot;Three ri (the old Japanese unit of distance, approximately 3.927 km or 2.44 miles per ri) to a liquor shop, and two ri to a tofu shop.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In describe the remote countryside, there was the vulgar proverb, &apos;Three ri (the old Japanese unit of distance, approximately 3.927 km or 2.44 miles per ri) to a liquor shop, and two ri to a tofu shop.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>また、味噌などと同様に、各集落で共同で作られることもしばしばあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As in the case of miso (bean paste), tofu was made communally in each village.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As was the case with miso (bean paste), tofu was made communally in each village.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As was the case with miso (bean paste), tofu was made communally in each village.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="48">
<j>まず原料の大豆を、一夜（12時間ほど）真水に漬けておく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At first, soybeans as raw materials are soaked in fresh water overnight (for about twelve hours).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">First, soybeans as raw materials are soaked in fresh water overnight (approximately 12 hours).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">First, soybeans as raw materials are soaked in fresh water overnight (approximately 12 hours).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>翌朝、十分に漬けあがった大豆を適度に水を加えながら石臼でクリーム状に磨り潰す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fully soaked soybeans are mashed and creamed with a stone mill over adding a moderate amount of water in the next morning.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The next morning, the fully soaked soybeans are then mashed and creamed in a stone mill together with a moderate amount of water.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The next morning, the fully soaked soybeans are then mashed and creamed in a stone mill together with a moderate amount of water.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>このクリーム状に磨り潰された大豆のことを「呉」と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mashed soybeans are called &quot;Go.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処「呉」→&quot;Go&quot;[用語サイトでは、「呉」を&quot;go&quot; (mashed soybeas) と表記しておりますが、この場合、mashed soybeansが重複するので、&quot;Go&quot;と表記を変更しました。これに合わせ、以下 呉 を Go と表記しました。]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The mashed soybeans are called &quot;go.&quot;</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The mashed soybeans are called &apos;go.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>次に呉をお釜に移し、適度に水を加えて濃度を調整し薪にて炊き上げる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, Go is put into an iron pot, a moderate amount of water is added to adjust a concentration, and Go is boiled with firewood.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The go is then placed in an iron pot, a moderate amount of water is added to adjust the concentration, and the go is boiled over firewood.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The go is then placed in an iron pot, a moderate amount of water is added to adjust the concentration, and the go is boiled over firewood.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>この時、呉はサポニンの作用で激しく泡立つため、消泡剤として食用油に石灰を加えたものを適度に振りかける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time, it is necessary to add a moderate amount of antifoaming agent which is obtained by adding lime to cooking oil because Go foams intensely by the action of saponin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this time, it&apos;s necessary to add a moderate amount of antifoaming agent, which is obtained by adding lime to cooking oil, because the go foams actively due to saponin.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this time, it&apos;s necessary to add a moderate amount of antifoaming agent, which is obtained by adding lime to cooking oil, because the go foams actively due to saponin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>十分に炊き上がった呉を、布で濾して豆乳を木桶に取る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Go fully boiled is filtered with a cloth, and soy milk is put in a wooden pail.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The go, once it has fully boiled, is filtered with a cloth, and the resultant soy milk is poured into a wooden pail.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The go, once it has fully boiled, is filtered with a cloth, and the resultant soy milk is poured into a wooden pail.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>この豆乳が冷えないうちに凝固剤としてにがりを適度に加え、櫂と呼ばれる木の板で撹拌する（にがりを打った以降の一連の作業を寄せと呼び、職人の技の見せ所である）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A moderate amount of bittern as a coagulant is added to this soy milk while it is warm, and it is stirred with a wooden board called kai (paddle) (a series of work after adding bittern is called yose, and is a high point where a workman shows his technique).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A moderate amount of bittern is added to the warm soy milk as a coagulant, and it&apos;s stirred with a wooden board called a kai (paddle) (the series of task after the addition of bittern is called &quot;yose,&quot; and it&apos;s a high point where the workman shows his technique).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A moderate amount of bittern is added to the warm soy milk as a coagulant, and it&apos;s stirred with a wooden board called a kai (paddle) (the series of task after the addition of bittern is called &quot;yose,&quot; and it&apos;s a high point where the workman shows his technique).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>豆乳の濃度、温度、にがりの量、そして適度な「寄せ」がそろうと、豆乳は水と分離することなく固まり始め、やがておぼろ状、またはプリン状の豆腐となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the concentration and temperature of soy milk, amount of bittern, and moderate degree of &quot;yose&quot; harmonize, the soy milk starts curdling without being separated from water, and is transformed into half curdled or pudding-like tofu before long.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the concentration and temperature of the soy milk, the amount of bittern and a moderate degree of &quot;yose&quot; harmonize, the soy milk starts curdling without separation from the water, whereupon it soon transforms into half-curdled or pudding-like tofu.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the concentration and temperature of the soy milk, the amount of bittern and a moderate degree of &quot;yose&quot; harmonize, the soy milk starts curdling without separation from the water, whereupon it soon transforms into half-curdled or pudding-like tofu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>これを崩しながら内側に布を敷いた型の中に盛り込み、蓋をして重石を掛け、硬く水を切ると豆腐（木綿豆腐）となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After putting this half curdled or pudding-like tofu into a mold lined with a cloth while being broken down, putting a lid on the mold, putting a stone weight on the lid, and draining it firmly, momendofu (firm tofu) is made.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the half-curdled or pudding-like tofu is placed into a mold lined with a cloth so that it will break down, a lid is set on the mold, a stone weight is placed on the lid and the tofu is drained, thus producing momendofu (firm tofu).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the half-curdled or pudding-like tofu is placed into a mold lined with a cloth so that it will break down, a lid is set on the mold, a stone weight is placed on the lid and the tofu is drained, thus producing momendofu (firm tofu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="57">
<j>石臼</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Stone mill</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Stone mill</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Stone mill</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="58">
<j>石臼で磨り潰されることにより、必要な蛋白分や糖分のみが液中に飛び出し、渋みの多い皮の部分はあまり細かくなることなく、おからとして排出されやすくなると言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that when soybeans are mashed with a stone mill, only necessary protein and sugar come out in the liquid, and it becomes easy to extract astringent skins as okara without breaking up.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that when soybeans are mashed with a stone mill, only the essential protein and sugar come out in the liquid, and it becomes easy to extract the astringent soybean skins as okara without allowing them to break up.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that when soybeans are mashed with a stone mill, only the essential protein and sugar come out in the liquid, and it becomes easy to extract the astringent soybean skins as okara without allowing them to break up.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>工業化された製法では、グラインダーで豆を微細に削る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the industrial process of making, soybeans are ground finely with a grinder.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the industrial production process, soybeans are ground finely with a grinder.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the industrial production process, soybeans are ground finely with a grinder.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>石臼を使うと、呉の焼け（酸化）が少なくなるとも言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the use of stone mill lessens yake (oxidation) of Go.</e>
<cmt>焼け（酸化）→yake (oxidation)[『焼け』は、「焼ける」等の&quot;burn&quot;とは違うものなので、読みをそのまま表記しました。]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the use of a stone mill lessens the &quot;yake (oxidation)&quot; of Go.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the use of a stone mill lessens the yake (oxidation) of Go.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="61">
<j>お釜</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Iron pot</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Iron pot</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Iron pot</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="62">
<j>いわゆる地釜（五右衛門釜）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is so-called jigama (goemon-gama) (iron pot)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is a so-called jigama (goemon-gama), or an iron pot.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is a so-called jigama (goemon-gama), or an iron pot.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>直火で炊き上げるため、呉が非常に焦げ付きやすい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because it is boiled over direct heat, Go gets burned very easily.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because it&apos;s boiled over direct heat, the go is easily scorched.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because it&apos;s boiled over direct heat, the go is easily scorched.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>そのため、濃く粘度の高い呉を使って、現在のような高濃度の豆乳を作ることは、事実上不可能であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is why it was virtually impossible to make present-day high concentrations of soy milk using thick and viscous Go.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is why it was virtually impossible to make the present-day high concentrations of soy milk using thick, viscous go.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is why it was virtually impossible to make the present-day high concentrations of soy milk using thick, viscous go.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>大豆固形分濃度は推定7〜8%であったと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The concentration of solid soybean was considered to be approx. 7 to 8%.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The concentration of solid soybean was considered to be approximately seven to eight percent.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The concentration of solid soybean was considered to be approximately seven to eight percent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>現在は蒸気釜で炊き上げるため焦げることはなく、豆腐の場合10〜13%の豆乳が一般的である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the case of present-day tofu, the general concentration of soy milk is 10 to 13% because Go does not get burned due to boiling with a steam boiler.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the case of present-day tofu, the general concentration of soy milk is ten to thirteen percent because go won&apos;t scorch when it&apos;s heated with a steam boiler.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the case of present-day tofu, the general concentration of soy milk is ten to thirteen percent because go won&apos;t scorch when it&apos;s heated with a steam boiler.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="67">
<j>消泡剤</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Antifoaming agent</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Antifoaming agent</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Antifoaming agent</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="68">
<j>呉を炊くと、大豆中のサポニンが激しく泡立つため、お釜から呉が容易に吹きこぼれてしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the saponin contained in soybeans foam intensely when Go is boiled, Go boils over the pot easily.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because the saponin contained in soybeans foams intensively when go is boiled, the go will easily boil over.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because the saponin contained in soybeans foams intensively when go is boiled, the go will easily boil over.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>また泡立った呉から取った豆乳もホイップ状の泡に包まれてしまうので、まともににがりを打ち、寄せの作業をすることが出来ない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, since soy milk extracted from foamed Go is covered with foam in the whipped form, it is impossible to add bittern and do work of yose properly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, since the soy milk extracted from the foamed go is covered with foam in a whipped state, it&apos;s impossible to add bittern and properly do the work of yose.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, since the soy milk extracted from the foamed go is covered with foam in a whipped state, it&apos;s impossible to add bittern and properly do the work of yose.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>このため古くから豆腐製造業者においては、前記の消泡剤を使うのが一般的であった（『豆腐集説』明治5年）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, it was general for tofu makers to use the aforementioned antifoaming agent from a long time ago (&quot;Tofu Shusetsu&quot; (Compilation of Tofu Making Theory) in 1872).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, for a long time it was a general practice for tofu makers to use the aforementioned antifoaming agent (&quot;Tofu Shusetsu (Compilation of Tofu Making Theory),&quot; published in 1872).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, for a long time it was a general practice for tofu makers to use the aforementioned antifoaming agent (&quot;Tofu Shusetsu (Compilation of Tofu Making Theory),&quot; published in 1872).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>また消泡剤には乳化剤としての側面も持っていて、呉液を乳化させることにより大豆中の旨み成分（大豆油のアミノ酸等）を豆乳の中に引き出す重要な役割も担っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The antifoaming agent also has an aspect of emulsifying agent, and plays an important role of drawing tasty ingredients (amino acid in soybean oil, and other ingredients) contained in soybeans by emulsifying fluid Go.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The antifoaming agent also serves as an emulsifying agent and plays an important role of drawing forth the flavorful ingredients (amino acid in soybean oil, and other ingredients) contained in soybeans by emulsifying the fluid go.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The antifoaming agent also serves as an emulsifying agent and plays an important role of drawing forth the flavorful ingredients (amino acid in soybean oil, and other ingredients) contained in soybeans by emulsifying the fluid go.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>他方、最近では無消泡剤仕様豆腐も注目を集めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, tofu made without using an antifoaming agent also receives attention.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, tofu made without using an antifoaming agent has also received attention.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, tofu made without using an antifoaming agent has also received attention.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="73">
<j>にがり、寄せ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bittern, yose</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bittern, yose</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bittern, yose</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="74">
<j>さまざまな寄せの方法があるが、典型的な例として、桶の中の豆乳をにがりと反応させながら、櫂で中心に「寄せる」作業を行う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are various methods of yose; however, a typical method is to do work of &quot;gathering&quot; (yoseru in Japanese) toward the center with kai while making soy milk in the pail react with bittern.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are various methods of yose, but a typical method is to do work of &quot;gathering&quot; (&quot;yoseru&quot; in Japanese) toward the center with a kai while making the soy milk in the pail react with the bittern.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are various methods of yose, but a typical method is to do work of &apos;gathering&apos; (&apos;yoseru&apos; in Japanese) toward the center with a kai while making the soy milk in the pail react with the bittern.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>この時、豆乳は、蛋白の分子がにがりに反応して水の分子を包みながら網の目状に繋がり始める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time, protein molecules react with bittern, and soy milk starts connecting in the form of mesh while wrapping water molecules.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this time, protein molecules react with the bittern and soy milk starts connecting in the form of mesh, as it enwraps the water molecules.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this time, protein molecules react with the bittern and soy milk starts connecting in the form of mesh, as it enwraps the water molecules.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>大きく見るとプリン状になり、豆腐となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In broad terms, soy milk becomes pudding-like, and becomes tofu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In broad terms, the soy milk becomes pudding-like, and ultimately it becomes tofu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In broad terms, the soy milk becomes pudding-like, and ultimately it becomes tofu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>お釜で炊かれた豆乳は、前述の通り濃度が薄いので、蛋白分子が繋がった網の目構造の網の目が粗いものとなる（濃度が濃いと、緻密な網となる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since soy milk boiled in the iron pot has low concentrations as mentioned above, the mesh of net-like structure in which protein molecules connect becomes rough (high concentrations make a fine-mesh net).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because the soy milk boiled in the iron pot has low concentrations as mentioned above, the net-like mesh structure in which protein molecules connect becomes rough (high concentrations make a fine-mesh net).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because the soy milk boiled in the iron pot has low concentrations as mentioned above, the net-like mesh structure in which protein molecules connect becomes rough (high concentrations make a fine-mesh net).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>このため水をその網に十分に捕らえることが出来ないので離水しやすい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is why the net cannot catch water sufficiently, and as a result, water is separated easily.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is why the net can&apos;t hold water sufficiently, and as a result the water is easily separated from it.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is why the net can&apos;t hold water sufficiently, and as a result the water is easily separated from it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>木綿豆腐を作ると、水切れがよく非常に硬い豆腐が出来上がる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When making momendofu, water is drained well and very hard tofu is made.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When making momendofu, water is drained well and very hard tofu is made.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When making momendofu, water is drained well and very hard tofu is made.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>ゆえに、古来の豆腐というのは、このように非常に硬い木綿豆腐であったと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, it is considered that ancient tofu was very hard momendofu like this.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, it&apos;s considered that ancient tofu was very hard momendofu, like this.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, it&apos;s considered that ancient tofu was very hard momendofu, like this.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="81">
<j>またこの方法で作られた豆腐は、最近まで山間部や離島などに残っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tofu was made by this process in mountain-ringed regions and remote islands until recently.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tofu was until recently made through this process in mountain-ringed regions and remote islands.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tofu was until recently made through this process in mountain-ringed regions and remote islands.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>1980年前後の岐阜県 徳山村、根尾村などで、この古典的な製法が確認されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This classic process of making was confirmed in Tokuyama Village (Gifu Prefecture) and Neo Village, Gifu Prefecture in around 1980.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This classic production process was confirmed in Tokuyama Village (Gifu Prefecture) and Neo Village, Gifu Prefecture, in about 1980.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This classic production process was confirmed in Tokuyama-mura and Neo-mura, Gifu Prefecture, in about 1980.</e>
<cmt>(岐阜県)原文から削除、合わせて訳も削除地名修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>最近では、山間部で、逆に濃度の濃い豆乳を使って作った硬い豆腐を土産物的に売っているが、これは近代的に作られた似て非なるものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, hard tofu which is made using high concentrations of soy milk is sold in mountain-ringed regions as a souvenir nowadays, but, this tofu made by a modern process is close but not the same.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, hard tofu, which is nowadays made in mountain-ringed regions as a souvenir using high concentrations of soy milk, but this tofu made by a modern process so it&apos;s close but not the same.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, hard tofu, which is nowadays made in mountain-ringed regions as a souvenir using high concentrations of soy milk, but this tofu made by a modern process so it&apos;s close but not the same.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>軟らかい豆腐</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soft tofu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soft tofu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soft tofu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="84">
<j>おぼろ豆腐</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oboro tofu (half curdled tofu that is being produced in the making of tofu)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oboro tofu (half-curdled tofu produced in the making of tofu)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oboro tofu (half-curdled tofu produced in the making of tofu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="85">
<j>寄せ豆腐</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yosedofu (fresh tofu)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yosedofu (fresh tofu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yosedofu (fresh tofu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="86">
<j>沖縄県の湯し豆腐</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yushi Dofu (fluffy tofu from Okinawa) in Okinawa Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yushi Dofu (fluffy tofu from Okinawa) in Okinawa Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yushi Dofu (fluffy tofu from Okinawa) in Okinawa Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="87">
<j>絹ごし豆腐、濃度の高い豆乳で、緻密な蛋白の網の目を作り、水分子をしっかりと取り込んでいるので、離水が少なく、結果、柔らかい豆腐となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinugoshidofu is soft tofu because a fine protein mesh made by high concentrations of soy milk catches water molecules firmly, and as a result, little water is separated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kinugoshidofu is soft tofu because a fine protein mesh resulting from high concentrations of soy milk catches the water molecules firmly, and as a result little water is separated.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinugoshidofu is soft tofu because a fine protein mesh resulting from high concentrations of soy milk catches the water molecules firmly, and as a result little water is separated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="88">
<j>いずれも豆乳を凝固させただけの状態で、水分をしぼる前なので柔らかい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Each of the above is soft because it is in the state of only curdling soy milk and water is not squeezed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Each of the above is soft because it&apos;s in the state of only curdling soy milk and water is not squeezed out.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Each of the above is soft because it&apos;s in the state of only curdling soy milk and water is not squeezed out.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>堅豆腐</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kata-dofu (hard tofu)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kata-dofu (hard tofu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kata-dofu (hard tofu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="89">
<j>一般的な豆腐の製法と異なり、濃度の濃い豆乳を使ったり、にがりの代わりに海水を使うなど、さまざまな方法を用いて保存できるようにした、いわゆる堅豆腐が各地で作られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Differently from a general process of making tofu, so-called Kata-dofu is made in many places by various methods such as using high concentrations of soy milk, using sea water instead of bittern, etc. so as to be conservable.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As opposed to the general tofu production process, so-called Kata-dofu is made in many places by various methods such as using high concentrations of soy milk, using sea water instead of bittern, etc., so as to be conservable.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As opposed to the general tofu production process, so-called Kata-dofu is made in many places by various methods such as using high concentrations of soy milk, using sea water instead of bittern, etc., so as to be conservable.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>流通の不便な豪雪地帯や山岳地帯あるいは離島などで作られ、なかには荒縄で縛って持ち運びできるほど堅いものもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kata-dofu is made in heavy snowfall areas, mountainous areas and remote islands where the distribution is inconvenient, and some of kata-dofu are hard enough to be bound with a straw rope for carrying.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kata-dofu is made in areas of heavy snowfall, mountainous areas and remote islands where distribution is inconvenient, and some kata-dofu is hard enough to be bound with a straw rope for carrying.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kata-dofu is made in areas of heavy snowfall, mountainous areas and remote islands where distribution is inconvenient, and some kata-dofu is hard enough to be bound with a straw rope for carrying.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>水分を減らしたもの</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tofu with low water content</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tofu with low water content</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tofu with low water content</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="91">
<j>沖縄県の島豆腐（しま豆腐）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shima Dofu (freshly made tofu with Okinawa water) in Okinawa Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shima Dofu (freshly made tofu with Okinawa water) in Okinawa Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shima Dofu (freshly made tofu with Okinawa water) in Okinawa Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="92">
<j>「生しぼり方」で作られ、豆乳の粘度が低い状態でにがりを混ぜるが、荷重と時間を多くかけて含水率を減らすため硬くなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although this tofu is made by a &quot;method of namashibori,&quot; and bittern is added to soy milk while its viscosity is low, tofu becomes hard because the moisture content is reduced by applying load for a long time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although this tofu is made by a &quot;method of namashibori,&quot; and bittern is added to the soy milk while its viscosity is low, the tofu becomes hard because the moisture content is reduced by applying a load for a long time.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although this tofu is made by a &apos;method of namashibori,&apos; and bittern is added to the soy milk while its viscosity is low, the tofu becomes hard because the moisture content is reduced by applying a load for a long time.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="93">
<j>出来上がった豆腐は十分な硬さがあるため水にさらさない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Finished tofu is not soaked in water because it is hard enough.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The resultant tofu isn&apos;t soaked in water because it&apos;s hard enough.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The resultant tofu isn&apos;t soaked in water because it&apos;s hard enough.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>濃い豆乳</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tofu made using concentrated soy milk</e>
<cmt>濃い豆乳→Tofu made using concentrated soy milk[豆腐の種類が下記に記載されているので、「濃い豆乳を使って作られた豆腐」として英訳しました]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tofu made using concentrated soy milk</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tofu made using concentrated soy milk</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="94">
<j>石川県白峰村の石豆腐（堅豆腐・固豆腐）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ishi-dofu (hard tofu) in Shiramine Village, Ishikawa Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ishi-dofu (hard tofu) in Shiramine Village, Ishikawa Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ishi-dofu (hard tofu) in Shiramine-mura, Ishikawa Prefecture</e>
<cmt>地名修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="95">
<j>富山県五箇山の岩豆腐</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Iwa-dofu (rock tofu) in Gokayama, Toyama Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Iwa-dofu (rock tofu) in Gokayama, Toyama Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Iwa-dofu (rock tofu) in Gokayama, Toyama Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="96">
<j>徳島県祖谷地方（東祖谷山村・東祖谷山村）の石豆腐</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ishi-dofu in the Iya Valley area (Higashi-Iyayama Village) of Tokushima Prefecture</e>
<cmt>（東祖谷山村・東祖谷山村）→(Higashi-Iyayama Village)[重複しているので、一つのみ表記しました]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ishi-dofu in the Iya Valley area (Higashi-Iyayama Village) of Tokushima Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ishi-dofu in the Iya Valley area (Higashi-Iyayama-mura) of Tokushima Prefecture</e>
<cmt>地名修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="97">
<j>熊本県球磨郡五木村の五木豆腐</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Itsuki dofu in Itsuki Village, Kuma District, Kumamoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt>五木豆腐→Itsuki dofu[糸満豆腐の表記に合わせました」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Itsuki dofu in Itsuki Village, Kuma District, Kumamoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Itsuki dofu in Itsuki-mura, Kuma-gun, Kumamoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt>地名修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>海水利用</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tofu made using salt water</e>
<cmt>海水利用→Tofu made using salt water[上記、濃い豆乳同様、「海水利用により作られた豆腐」として英訳しました]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tofu made using saltwater</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tofu made using saltwater</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="98">
<j>山口県祝島の祝島石豆腐</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Iwaishima ishi-dofu (hard tofu of Iwai-shima Island) in Iwai-shima Island, Yamaguchi Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Iwaishima ishi-dofu (hard tofu of Iwai-shima Island) in Iwai-shima Island, Yamaguchi Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Iwaishima ishi-dofu (hard tofu of Iwai-shima Island) in Iwai-shima Island, Yamaguchi Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="99">
<j>長崎県五島列島の潮豆腐</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shio-dofu (salt water tofu) in Goto-retto Islands, Nagasaki Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shio-dofu (saltwater tofu) in Goto-retto Islands, Nagasaki Prefecture</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shio-dofu (saltwater tofu) in Goto-retto Islands, Nagasaki Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="100">
<j>長崎県壱岐市の壱州豆腐</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ishu dofu (Ishu&apos;s tofu) in Iki City, Nagasaki Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ishu dofu (Ishu&apos;s tofu) in Iki City, Nagasaki Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ishu dofu (Ishu&apos;s tofu) in Iki City, Nagasaki Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="101">
<j>沖縄県の糸満豆腐</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Itoman dofu (tofu of Itoman area) in Okinawa Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Itoman dofu (tofu of the Itoman area) in Okinawa Prefecture</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Itoman dofu (tofu of the Itoman area) in Okinawa Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>乾燥豆腐</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanso dofu (dried tofu)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanso dofu (dried tofu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanso dofu (dried tofu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="102">
<j>豆腐を塩蔵乾燥、凍結乾燥したり、燻製で乾燥して保存性を高めた豆腐。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The above are tofu salt-dried, freeze-dried or smoke-dried in order to improve its shelf life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The above are cases in which the tofu is salt-dried, freeze-dried or smoke-dried in order to improve its shelf life.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The above are cases in which the tofu is salt-dried, freeze-dried or smoke-dried in order to improve its shelf life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="103">
<j>塩蔵乾燥させて作った豆腐には、山形県岩根沢地方（西村山郡西川町）の六浄豆腐がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As an example of salt-dried tofu, rokujo dofu (salted tofu) in Iwanezawa area (Nishikawa-machi, Nishimurayama district) of Yamagata Prefecture is named.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As an example of salt-dried tofu, rokujo dofu (salted tofu) in the Iwanezawa area (Nishikawa-machi, Nishimurayama district) of Yamagata Prefecture is representative.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As an example of salt-dried tofu, rokujo dofu (salted tofu) in the Iwanezawa area (Nishikawa-machi, Nishimurayama-gun) of Yamagata Prefecture is representative.</e>
<cmt>地名修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>豆腐を塩で水分を抜き、乾燥させたもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tofu is dried after removing the water content with salt.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tofu is dried after removing the water content with salt.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tofu is dried after removing the water content with salt.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>非常に堅いため削ったものを食べたり、料理に使ったりする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shaved pieces are eaten or used for cooking because this tofu is very hard.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shaved pieces are eaten or used for cooking, because this tofu is very hard.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shaved pieces are eaten or used for cooking, because this tofu is very hard.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="106">
<j>凍結乾燥してつくった凍り豆腐については高野豆腐参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For kori-dofu (frozen bean curd) made by freeze dry, refer to the article of koyadofu (freeze-dried bean curd).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For kori-dofu (frozen bean curd) made by freeze-drying, refer to the article on koyadofu (freeze-dried bean curd).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For kori-dofu (frozen bean curd) made by freeze-drying, refer to the article on koyadofu (freeze-dried bean curd).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="107">
<j>岐阜県郡上市大和町に伝わる燻り豆腐（いぶり豆腐）は、硬めの豆腐を長時間燻して作られた豆腐の燻製。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Iburidofu (smoked tofu) passed down in Yamato-cho (Gifu Prefecture), Gujo City, Gifu Prefecture is smoked tofu made by smoking hard tofu for a long time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Iburidofu (smoked tofu) passed down in Yamato-cho (Gifu Prefecture), Gujo City, Gifu Prefecture is smoked tofu made by smoking hard tofu for a long time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Iburidofu (smoked tofu) passed down in Yamato-cho, Gujo City, Gifu Prefecture is smoked tofu made by smoking hard tofu for a long time.</e>
<cmt>(岐阜県)原文から削除し、訳文からも削除。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>熊本県五木村にも同様にして製造する桜燻製豆腐が伝わっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sakurakunsei dofu (cherry-chip smoked tofu) which is made in a similar manner is also passed down in Itsuki Village, Kumamoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sakurakunsei dofu (tofu smoked over cherry chips), which is made in a similar manner, has been passed down in Itsuki Village, Kumamoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sakurakunsei dofu (tofu smoked over cherry chips), which is made in a similar manner, has been passed down in Itsuki-mura, Kumamoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>地名修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>焼き豆腐</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yakidofu (grilled tofu)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yakidofu (grilled tofu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yakidofu (grilled tofu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="109">
<j>- 木綿豆腐の表面をバーナーであぶって焦げ目をつけたもの</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">- browned tofu made by roasting momendofu with a burner</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">: A browned tofu made by roasting momendofu over a burner</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A browned tofu made by roasting momendofu over a burner</e>
<cmt>: 削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="110">
<j>秋田県の豆腐カステラ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tofu kasutera (tofu cake) in Akita Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tofu kasutera (tofu cake) in Akita Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tofu kasutera (tofu cake) in Akita Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="111">
<j>福島県南会津郡南会津町のつと豆腐</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsuto dofu (tofu rolled in a bamboo mat and boiled) in Minamiaizu-machi, Minamiaizu district, Fukushima Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsuto dofu (tofu rolled in a bamboo mat and boiled) in Minamiaizu-machi, in the Minamiaizu district of Fukushima Prefecture</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsuto dofu (tofu rolled in a bamboo mat and boiled) in Minamiaizu-machi, Minamiaizu-gun, Fukushima Prefecture</e>
<cmt>地名修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="112">
<j>茨城県のこも豆腐・つと豆腐</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Komo-dofu (tofu rolled in a wooden straw mat called &quot;komo&quot; and boiled) and tsuto dofu in Ibaraki Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Komo-dofu (tofu rolled in a wooden straw mat called &quot;komo&quot; and boiled) and tsuto dofu in Ibaraki Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Komo-dofu (tofu rolled in a wooden straw mat called &quot;komo&quot; and boiled) and tsuto dofu in Ibaraki Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="113">
<j>岡山県のすまき豆腐</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sumaki dofu (tofu made in the same manner as tsuto dofu) in Okayama Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sumaki dofu (tofu made in the same manner as tsuto dofu) in Okayama Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sumaki dofu (tofu made in the same manner as tsuto dofu) in Okayama Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="114">
<j>熊本県のすぼ豆腐</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Subo dofu (tofu made in the same manner as tsuto dofu)in Kumamoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subo dofu (tofu made in the same manner as tsuto dofu)in Kumamoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subo dofu (tofu made in the same manner as tsuto dofu)in Kumamoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="115">
<j>熊本県の豆腐の味噌漬け</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tofu preserved in miso in Kumamoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tofu preserved in miso in Kumamoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tofu preserved in miso in Kumamoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="116">
<j>沖縄県の豆腐よう</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tofuyo (fermented tofu) in Okinawa Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tofuyo (fermented tofu) in Okinawa Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tofuyo (fermented tofu) in Okinawa Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="14">
<tit>
<j>栄養</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nutrition</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nutrition</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nutrition</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="117">
<j>植物性たんぱく質が豊富。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tofu is rich in plant protein.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tofu is rich in plant protein.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tofu is rich in plant protein.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="118">
<j>カロリーは比較的低いため健康食品としてアメリカ合衆国やヨーロッパなどでも食材として使われるようになっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since its calorie is comparatively low, tofu comes to be used for cooking as health food even in the United States of America and Europe.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since its calorie is comparatively low, tofu has become common in cooking as a health food even in the United States and Europe.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since its calorie is comparatively low, tofu has become common in cooking as a health food even in the United States and Europe.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="119">
<j>製法上の理由から食物繊維は少ない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By reason of making, tofu is low in fiber.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to the production process, tofu is low in fiber.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to the production process, tofu is low in fiber.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="120">
<j>（→おから）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(=&gt;okara)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(=&gt;okara)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(=&gt;okara)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="15">
<tit>
<j>豆腐料理</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tofu dishes</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tofu dishes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tofu dishes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="121">
<j>江戸時代に著された『豆腐百珍』には、その名のとおり100種類の豆腐料理が紹介されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the &quot;Hundred Delicacies of Tofu&quot; written in the Edo period, 100 kinds of tofu dishes were introduced as implied by the name.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the &quot;Hundred Delicacies of Tofu&quot; written in the Edo period, 100 kinds of tofu dishes were introduced, thus justifying the title.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the &quot;Hundred Delicacies of Tofu&quot; written in the Edo period, 100 kinds of tofu dishes were introduced, thus justifying the title.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="16">
<tit>
<j>豆腐加工品と関連品</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Processed foods of tofu, and related foods</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Processed foods of tofu, and related foods</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Processed foods of tofu, and related foods</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="122">
<j>油揚げ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Agura-age (deep-fried bean curd)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Agura-age (deep-fried bean curd)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Abura-age (deep-fried bean curd)</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="123">
<j>厚揚げ（生揚げ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Atsuage (thick fried tofu)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Atsuage (thick fried tofu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Atsuage (thick fried tofu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="124">
<j>がんもどき</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ganmodoki (deep-fried tofu mixed with thinly sliced vegetables)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ganmodoki (deep-fried tofu mixed with thinly sliced vegetables)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ganmodoki (deep-fried tofu mixed with thinly sliced vegetables)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="125">
<j>焼き豆腐</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yakidofu (grilled tofu)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yakidofu (grilled tofu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yakidofu (grilled tofu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="126">
<j>高野豆腐(凍り豆腐)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koyadofu (kori-dofu (frozen bean curd))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koyadofu (kori-dofu (frozen bean curd))</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koyadofu (kori-dofu (frozen bean curd))</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="127">
<j>豆乳</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soy milk</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soy milk</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soy milk</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="128">
<j>ゆば（湯葉）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yuba (bean curd skin)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yuba (bean-curd skin)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yuba (bean-curd skin)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="129">
<j>おから</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Okara</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Okara</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Okara</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="17">
<tit>
<j>豆腐に関する慣用句</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Common expression concerning tofu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Common expressions related to tofu</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Common expressions related to tofu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="130">
<j>とても柔らかいものの例として用いられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tofu is used as an example of very soft thing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tofu is used as an example of something that&apos;s very soft.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tofu is used as an example of something that&apos;s very soft.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="131">
<j>豆腐に鎹</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Clamp into tofu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Clamp into tofu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Clamp into tofu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="132">
<j>木材をつなぎ止めるものである鉄製の鎹（かすがい）を軟らかい豆腐に打ち込もうとする様。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This expresses an action of driving an iron clamp which holds lumber into soft tofu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This expresses an action of driving an iron clamp that holds lumber into soft tofu.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This expresses an action of driving an iron clamp that holds lumber into soft tofu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="133">
<j>つまり、手応えがないという意味。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This means no effect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This means there is no effect.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This means there is no effect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="134">
<j>類似表現に「糠に釘」「暖簾に腕押し」がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Similar expressions are &quot;nail into nuka (rice bran)&quot; and &quot;push noren (a short (split) curtain hung at the entrance of a room) with arms.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Similar expressions are &quot;nail into nuka (rice bran)&quot; and &quot;push noren (a short (split) curtain hung at the entrance of a room) with the arms.&quot;</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Similar expressions are &apos;nail into nuka (rice bran)&apos; and &apos;push noren (a short (split) curtain hung at the entrance of a room) with the arms.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="135">
<j>豆腐の角に頭をぶつけて死ね</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Die by bumping your head on the corner of tofu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Die by bumping your head on the corner of tofu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Die by bumping your head on the corner of tofu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="136">
<j>類似表現に「うどんで首吊って死ね」がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another similar expression is &quot;die by hanging yourself with udon (Japanese wheat noodle).&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another similar expression is &quot;die by hanging yourself with udon (Japanese wheat noodle).&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another similar expression is &apos;die by hanging yourself with udon (Japanese wheat noodle).&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="18">
<tit>
<j>その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="137">
<j>ダイズとにがりを使用していない物でも柔らかく豆腐状の食品のなかには「かわり豆腐」などと呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even if soybeans and bittern are not used, soft foods in the form of tofu are called &quot;kawari dofu (unusual tofu).&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even if soybeans and bittern aren&apos;t used, soft foods in the form of tofu are called &quot;kawari dofu (unusual tofu).&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even if soybeans and bittern aren&apos;t used, soft foods in the form of tofu are called &apos;kawari dofu&apos; (unusual tofu).</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="138">
<j>玉子豆腐</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tamago dofu (egg tofu)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tamago dofu (egg tofu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tamago dofu (egg tofu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="139">
<j>胡麻豆腐</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Goma-dofu (crushed sesami seeds boiled in water and chilled like tofu)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Goma-dofu (crushed sesami seeds boiled in water and chilled like tofu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Goma-dofu (crushed sesami seeds boiled in water and chilled like tofu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="140">
<j>杏仁豆腐</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Annindofu (almond jelly)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Annindofu (almond jelly)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Annindofu (almond jelly)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="141">
<j>牛乳豆腐</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gyunyu dofu (milk tofu)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gyunyu dofu (milk tofu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gyunyu dofu (milk tofu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="142">
<j>ごどうふ 長崎県、佐賀県の郷土食</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Godofu (tofu made with kuzu vines), local food in Nagasaki and Saga prefectures</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Godofu (tofu made with kuzu vines) is a local food in the Nagasaki and Saga prefectures</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Godofu (tofu made with kuzu vines) is a local food in the Nagasaki and Saga prefectures</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="143">
<j>ラッカセイ豆腐・ジーマーミ豆腐</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rakkasei dofu (peanuts tofu), jimami-dofu (Okinawa peanuts tofu)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rakkasei dofu (peanut tofu), jimami-dofu (Okinawa peanut tofu)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rakkasei dofu (peanut tofu), jimami-dofu (Okinawa peanut tofu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="144">
<j>チェコ共和国のプラハでは、牛乳の代わりに豆乳を使って作ったチーズを「TOFU」として売っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Prague, Czech Republic, cheese which is made using soy milk instead of milk is sold as &quot;TOFU.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Prague, Czech Republic, cheese made using soy milk instead of milk is sold as &quot;TOFU.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Prague, Czech Republic, cheese made using soy milk instead of milk is sold as &apos;TOFU.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="145">
<j>プレーンタイプの他、燻製タイプなど数種が、スーパーマーケットのチーズ売場で見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to plain type, several types including smoked type are sold at a cheese corner of supermarket.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to the plain type, several other types-- including smoked varieties--are sold in the cheese sections of supermarkets.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to the plain type, several other types-- including smoked varieties--are sold in the cheese sections of supermarkets.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="146">
<j>またアメリカやイギリスではトーフと呼ばれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tofu is called tofu in the United States of America and England.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tofu is called by that name in the United States and England.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tofu is called by that name in the United States and England.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="147">
<j>フィリピンには「タホ（taho）」と呼ばれる菓子があり、水分の多い温かい豆腐（プリン状の豆乳）にタピオカと黒蜜をまぶして食べる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Philippines has confectionery called &quot;taho,&quot; which is warm tofu with high water content (pudding-like soy milk) and is eaten by dredging tapioca and brown sugar syrup.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">the Philippines has confectionery called &quot;taho,&quot; which is warm tofu with high water content (pudding-like soy milk) and is eaten by dredging tapioca and brown-sugar syrup.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Philippines has confectionery called &apos;taho,&apos; which is warm tofu with high water content (pudding-like soy milk) and is eaten by dredging tapioca and brown-sugar syrup.</e>
<cmt>スペル&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="148">
<j>現地では朝食前にタホを食べる習慣があり、毎朝、天秤を担いだ「タホ売り」が家々を回る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">People in Philippines have the custom of eating taho before breakfast, and a &quot;taho seller&quot; carrying taho on a pole goes from door to door every morning.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">People in Philippines have the custom of eating taho before breakfast, and each morning a &quot;taho seller&quot; carrying taho on a pole goes from door to door.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">People in Philippines have the custom of eating taho before breakfast, and each morning a &apos;taho seller&apos; carrying taho on a pole goes from door to door.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="149">
<j>この際、フィリピンのタホ売りは、かつての日本の豆腐の行商とまったく同じラッパを吹き鳴らして合図をする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time, a taho seller in Philippines gives a sign by blowing a bugle just as a Japanese tofu peddler did in the past.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, the Philippine taho seller signals with a bugle, just as a Japanese tofu peddler would have done in the past.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, the Philippine taho seller signals with a bugle, just as a Japanese tofu peddler would have done in the past.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="150">
<j>豆腐小僧という豆腐をモチーフにした妖怪伝説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a specter legend in the motif of tofu, which is called Tofu-Kozo (spirit child carrying a block of tofu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a legend of a specter in the motif of tofu, which is called Tofu-Kozo (a spirit child carrying a block of tofu).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a legend of a specter in the motif of tofu, which is called Tofu-Kozo (a spirit child carrying a block of tofu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="151">
<j>現在は殆ど見られないが、かつて、主に関東地方において、豆腐の売り歩きをする際に豆腐屋はラッパを吹きながら売り歩いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although it is seldom seen at present, a tofu seller peddled tofu over blowing a bugle when carrying tofu about for sales mainly in the Kanto region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although seldom seen today, the tofu seller blow a bugle when carrying tofu on his sales route, mainly in the Kanto region.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although seldom seen today, the tofu seller blow a bugle when carrying tofu on his sales route, mainly in the Kanto region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="152">
<j>明治初期に乗合馬車や鉄道馬車の御者が危険防止のために鳴らしていたものをある豆腐屋が「音が『トーフ』と聞こえる」ことに気づき、ラッパを吹きながら売り歩くことを始めたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One tofu seller who noticed that a bugle blown by a coachman of stagecoach or horse-draw streetcar for safety &quot;sounded tofu&quot; started peddling over blowing a bugle in early Meiji period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One tofu peddler in the early Meiji period, who noticed that a bugle blown by a coachman on a stagecoach or a horse-drawn streetcar for safety &quot;sounded tofu,&quot; took up the practice of blowing a bugle too.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One tofu peddler in the early Meiji period, who noticed that a bugle blown by a coachman on a stagecoach or a horse-drawn streetcar for safety &apos;sounded &quot;tofu,&quot;&apos; took up the practice of blowing a bugle too.</e>
<cmt>&quot;補足&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="153">
<j>なお、関西地方では豆腐屋はラッパではなく鐘（関東ではアイスクリーム屋が用いていた）を鳴らしていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Kansai region, a tofu seller sounded a bell, not blowing a bugle (an ice cream seller sounded a bell in the Kanto region).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Kansai region, a tofu seller sounded a bell instead of blowing a bugle (in the Kanto region, an ice-cream seller sounded a bell).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Kansai region, a tofu seller sounded a bell instead of blowing a bugle (in the Kanto region, an ice-cream seller sounded a bell).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="19">
<tit>
<j>日本の製造業者の問題点</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Problems of Japanese makers</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Problems encountered by Japanese makers</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Problems encountered by Japanese makers</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="154">
<j>日本では製造業者のほとんどが中小企業や個人商店である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most Japanese makers are medium and small companies, and family type operations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most Japanese makers are medium and small companies, and are family-type operations.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most Japanese makers are medium and small companies, and are family-type operations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="155">
<j>これは「豆腐製造が微妙な技術を要すること、長期保存ができないなど、豆腐の特性が関係していると思われる」（全豆連ホームページより引用）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is &quot;considered to be related to the characteristics of tofu such as requiring delicate technique for making tofu, impossibility of long storage, etc.&quot; (excerpt from the website of Zentoren (the Japanese National Tofu Association).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is &quot;considered to be related to the characteristics of tofu, such as requiring delicate technique for making tofu, impossibility of long storage, etc.,&quot; (as excerpted from the website of Zentoren, the Japanese national tofu association).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is &apos;considered to be related to the characteristics of tofu, such as requiring delicate technique for making tofu, impossibility of long storage, etc.,&apos; (as excerpted from the website of Zentoren, the Japanese national tofu association).</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="156">
<j>最近では、包装技術の向上（真空充填など）により長期保存が可能となり、中小企業の製品もコンビニなどで見かけることができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In these years, the long storage has become possible due to improvement of packaging technique (vacuum filling, etc.), and tofu products made by medium and small companies can be found also in convenience stores.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Over the past few years, long-term storage has become possible due to the improvement of packaging techniques (vacuum filling, etc.), and consequently tofu products made by medium and small companies can also be found in convenience stores.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Over the past few years, long-term storage has become possible due to the improvement of packaging techniques (vacuum filling, etc.), and consequently tofu products made by medium and small companies can also be found in convenience stores.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="157">
<j>その為、スーパーやコンビニ事業者の価格決定権が強く特売が当たり前になってしまい、特売が希望小売価格状態になってしまって経営を圧迫している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, the special sale becomes usual because supermarkets and convenience-store operators have a strong power to decide a price, and a price in the special sale becomes a recommended retail price, which cause a squeeze on management.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, the special sale becomes usual because supermarkets and convenience-store operators have a strong power to determine the price, and a price in a special sale becomes a recommended retail price, which causes a squeeze on management.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, the special sale becomes usual because supermarkets and convenience-store operators have a strong power to determine the price, and a price in a special sale becomes a recommended retail price, which causes a squeeze on management.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="158">
<j>さらに、原料である大豆はそのほとんどを米国に依存しているが、原料である非遺伝子組み換え大豆生産量はアメリカにおける生産数の一割以下であり、遺伝子組み換え価格の約3倍の価格もする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, although most of soybeans as raw materials are imported from the United States of America, the production volume of non-genetically-engineered soybeans which are used as raw materials is less than 10% of total production volume in the United States of America, and a price of those soybeans is approx. three times a price of genetically-engineered soybeans.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, although most of the soybeans used as raw materials are imported from the United States, the production volume of non-genetically engineered soybean raw materials is less than ten percent of the total production volume in the U.S., and the price of those soybeans is approximately three times that of genetically engineered soybeans.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, although most of the soybeans used as raw materials are imported from the United States, the production volume of non-genetically engineered soybean raw materials is less than ten percent of the total production volume in the U.S., and the price of those soybeans is approximately three times that of genetically engineered soybeans.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="159">
<j>また、米国のエネルギー安全保障政策でバイオ燃料作物への転作が進み急激な高騰や、包装等の資材の原油価格高騰による原材料費高騰も経営を圧迫している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, a squeeze on management is caused by steep price escalation due to enhancement of shift to crops for biofuel under the U.S. Energy Security Policy, and by escalating price of raw materials due to escalating price of oil as materials such as packaging materials, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, a squeeze on management is caused by steep price escalation due to the accelerated shift toward the use of crops for bio-fuel under the U.S. Energy Security Policy, and by raising the price of raw materials due to the escalating price of oil as an ingredient in packaging materials, etc.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, a squeeze on management is caused by steep price escalation due to the accelerated shift toward the use of crops for bio-fuel under the U.S. Energy Security Policy, and by raising the price of raw materials due to the escalating price of oil as an ingredient in packaging materials, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="160">
<j>また、製造工程からででくるおからは法的には産業廃棄物扱いであり、不法投棄や処分費問題をかかえている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Makers have problems of illegal dumping or cost of disposal because okara yielded in the manufacturing process is treated as industrial waste by law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Makers face the challenge of illegal dumping or the disposal expense, because by law the okara yielded in the manufacturing process is treated as industrial waste.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Makers face the challenge of illegal dumping or the disposal expense, because by law the okara yielded in the manufacturing process is treated as industrial waste.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="20">
<tit>
<j>動物にも食される木綿豆腐</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Momendofu which is also eaten by animals</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Momendofu, which also serves as animal feed</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Momendofu, which also serves as animal feed</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 奈緒(id:33238), Green spider(id:45359), Los688(id:12316), 島倉チョコ(id:184102), Nnh(id:474), KMT(id:1772), Hhaithait(id:37092), 0null0(id:582), ＲＪＡＮＫＡ(id:118019), XOP(id:42473), ﾃｭｲﾙﾘｰ(id:97615), Kamakura(id:472), Opponent(id:720), Michey.M(id:906), Aguri(id:87053), A-Taul(id:41790), 俊(id:14924), WikiDreamer Bot(id:225250), 日本一弱い男(id:92046), TY(id:1386), Knua(id:66861), 汲平(id:18186), Point136(id:211299), あら金(id:10820), Ebimu-man(id:70113), FlaBot(id:30804), Kzhr(id:131), 百科事典に綴じ込められた男(id:89823), もね～るmoner(id:28477), Mnd(id:15140), AITFIA(id:117937), Kazov(id:9237), いろはにほへと(id:89648), Carbuncle(id:346), マクガイア(id:33346), 松茸(id:27535), Hideki1976(id:106957), PixelBot(id:166734), ずんとく(id:58743), AlexS(id:50818), のののののの(id:1224), Blooms(id:30658), Escarbot(id:59151), はるひ(id:59079), 地理さん(id:106627), ふりゅ(id:74856), MDR-SK(id:192066), Nikai(id:1648), Rusk(id:9895), SilvonenBot(id:190970), SuisuiBot(id:10165), Amatellus(id:178152), Ribbon(id:172), KSKS(id:97637), 絶対◆2BenKiTYKw(id:11959), Bigben(id:1039), TANUKI(id:28527), けんち(id:5147), Nsq(id:54991), Suisui(id:69), JAnDbot(id:66507), Walks(id:63981), Takoradee(id:82103), Si-take.(id:91094), CRX(id:45108), Roger(id:9883), TXiKiBoT(id:107492), DK(id:35518), Sharksnow622(id:253903), Toto-tarou(id:16648), 死郎(id:1683), Wikishou(id:60829), Sonic883(id:36201), くっちゃめ(id:86793), Rei-bot(id:94097), Akaka(id:213318), Chobot(id:20846), Loveless(id:129239), 竹麦魚(id:11012), Nipisiquit(id:62077), Mizumono(id:606), Kozawa(id:672), LERK(id:4460), M-ogino(id:65364), Pieria(id:48925), Kamitani(id:30757), Vina-iwbot(id:56449), らせ(id:243306), 東日本国際(id:11518), 竃馬(id:102733), VolkovBot(id:105371), Yukichin(id:725), リトルデビル(id:34455), TottyBot(id:101680), Fromm(id:71291), Southerntask(id:281019), Muyo(id:14948), Namazunohito(id:78979), Louperibot(id:128971), LeonardoRob0t(id:25875), 1029man(id:93235), Raremetal(id:150540), Ete(id:28565), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>