<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>駒牽</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Komahiki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Komahiki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Komahiki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>駒牽（こまひき）とは、宮中行事の1つで毎年8月に東国に置かれた勅旨牧から貢進されたウマを内裏南殿において天皇の御前にて披露した後に出席した公卿らに一部を下賜し、残りを馬寮・近衛府に分配する行事。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The `komahiki` event was one ritual that occurred within the imperial court in August each year when horses that were agisted in the Eastern provinces according to imperial edict were brought to the south hall of the imperial palace and paraded in front of the Emperor and afterwards nobility selected some whilst the remainder were stabled or allocated to the imperial guard.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The `komahiki` event was one ritual that occurred within the imperial court in August each year when horses that were agisted in the Eastern provinces according to imperial edict were brought to the south hall of the imperial palace and paraded in front of the Emperor and afterwards nobility selected some whilst the remainder were stabled or allocated to the imperial guard.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &apos;komahiki&apos; event was one ritual that occurred within the imperial court in August each year when horses that were agisted in the Eastern provinces according to imperial edict were brought to the south hall of the imperial palace and paraded in front of the Emperor and afterwards nobility selected some whilst the remainder were stabled or allocated to the imperial guard.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション表記修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>勅旨牧は信濃国・甲斐国・武蔵国・上野国の4国に及んだため、牧単位で分散して行われ、『延喜式』・『政事要略』によれば、8月のうちから8日間に分けて儀式が開かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because the imperial agistment sites were required in 4 provinces (Shinano, Kai, Musashi and Kozuke), the plots of grazing land were dispersed and, according to ancient laws and political guidelines the ceremonies took place in an 8 day timeframe in August.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because the imperial agistment sites were required in 4 provinces (Shinano, Kai, Musashi and Kozuke), the plots of grazing land were dispersed and, according to ancient laws and political guidelines the ceremonies took place in an 8 day timeframe in August.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because the imperial agistment sites were required in four provinces (Shinano, Kai, Musashi and Kozuke), the plots of grazing land were dispersed and, according to ancient laws and political guidelines the ceremonies took place in an eight day timeframe in August.</e>
<cmt>4. 8をスペルアウト</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="3">
<j>また、儀式に先立って当日の朝に近衛府の将兵が貢進された馬を逢坂関で出迎える駒迎（こまむかえ）の儀式もあわせて行われていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, on the morning of the day prior to the ceremony another ceremony whereby a horse contributed by the officers and men of the imperial guard was taken to the Hosaka turnpike in a ceremony called the Komamukae (`Horse Welcoming`).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, on the morning of the day prior to the ceremony another ceremony whereby a horse contributed by the officers and men of the imperial guard was taken to the Hosaka turnpike in a ceremony called the Komamukae (`Horse Welcoming`).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, on the morning of the day prior to the ceremony another ceremony whereby a horse contributed by the officers and men of the imperial guard was taken to the Osaka no seki (the Osaka Barrier) in a ceremony called the Komamukae (&apos;Horse Welcoming&apos;).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション表記修正、Hosaka turnpike→Osaka no seki (the Osaka Barrier)としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="4">
<j>後に信濃国の一部の勅旨牧以外からの貢進は途絶えたが、奥州から予め購入あるいは現地の有力者から貢進された馬で不足分を補った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later on, parts of the grazing land outside of Shinano province stopped being used however, to make up for some sort of shortfall etc the Oshu area had previously been acquired and it is also thought that influential local people contributed horses.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処　</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later on, parts of the grazing land outside of Shinano province stopped being used however, to make up for some sort of shortfall etc the Oshu area had previously been acquired and it is also thought that influential local people contributed horses.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later on, parts of the grazing land outside of Shinano Province stopped being used; however, to make up for some sort of shortfall etc the Oshu area had previously been acquired and it is also thought that influential local people contributed horses.</e>
<cmt>provinceの頭文字を大文字に変更、howeverの前にセミコロン追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>応仁の乱の頃まで断続的に続けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The practice continued continuously up until around the time of the Onin War.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処　</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The practice continued continuously up until around the time of the Onin War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The practice continued continuously up until around the time of the Onin War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="6">
<j>なお、これとは別に毎年5月5日_(旧暦)の節会に先立って、騎射・競馬の儀式の際に用いられる馬を親王・公卿ら及び畿内周辺諸国から献上された馬を天皇の御前に披露する駒牽の儀式もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides this, on May 5 each year preceding the `komahiki` event, there was another ceremony where horses to be used in horseback archery and horse racing that had been presented to the emperor by princes and nobles were displayed in front of the Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides this, on May 5 each year preceding the `komahiki` event, there was another ceremony where horses to be used in horseback archery and horse racing that had been presented to the emperor by princes and nobles were displayed in front of the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides this, on May 5 (lunar calender) each year preceding the &apos;komahiki&apos; event, there was another ceremony where horses to be used in horseback archery and horse racing that had been presented to the emperor by princes and nobles were displayed in front of the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>旧暦であることを加えるため、May 5 (lunar calender)とし、クォーテーション表記修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>