<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>文武一道</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">文武一道 (Bunbu Ichido)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bunbu Ichido</e>
<cmt>Deleted kanji and brackets</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bunbu Ichido</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>文武一道（ぶんぶいちどう）とは、文武両道とは異なり、学問も武芸（スポーツ）も詰まるところは同じであるという意である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bunbu ichido means that both the literary and military (sports) arts are essentially the same, unlike 文武両道 (bunbu ryodo, both the literary and military arts).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bunbu ichido (literally &apos;the single path of the cultural and martial arts&apos;) means that both scholarship and martial arts (sports) are essentially the same, unlike bunbu ryodo (the dual path of the cultural and martial arts).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bunbu ichido (literally &apos;the single path of the cultural and martial arts&apos;) means that both scholarship and martial arts (sports) are essentially the same, unlike bunbu ryodo (the dual path of the cultural and martial arts).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>どちらも極めれば同じ要素が存在するという意味が込められている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a meaning that the same element is involved in both arts when mastered.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It implies that the same elements are involved in both arts when mastered.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It implies that the same elements are involved in both arts when mastered.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>空気投げを編み出したことで有名な講道館初期の柔道家、三船久蔵十段が残した言葉であるといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The word is believed to have been left by Kyuzo MIFUNE-judan (10th-Dan Judo master), a judo practitioner in the early days of The Kodokan Judo Institute famous for creating kuki nage (the air throw).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The word is believed to have been left by Kyuzo MIFUNE, a 10th dan judo wrestler in the early days of The Kodokan Judo Institute, who was famous for creating the kuki nage (the air throw).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The word is believed to have been left by Kyuzo MIFUNE, a 10th dan judo wrestler in the early days of The Kodokan Judo Institute, who was famous for creating the kuki nage (the air throw).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>三船の母校である宮城県仙台第二高等学校（三船の在学当時は旧制仙台二中)講堂には、三船の手による「文武一道」の書が掲げられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A calligraphy of &quot;文武一道&quot; written by Mifune is set up in an auditorium of his alma mater, Sendai Daini High School, Miyagi Prefecture (former Sendai Daini Junior High School).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A piece of calligraphy by Mifune consisting of the characters for bunbu ichido hangs in the auditorium of his alma mater, Sendai Daini High School, Miyagi Prefecture (formerly Sendai Daini Junior High School).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A piece of calligraphy by Mifune consisting of the characters for bunbu ichido hangs in the auditorium of his alma mater, Sendai Daini High School, Miyagi Prefecture (formerly Sendai Daini Junior High School).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 BoB774(id:148281), 曼珠沙華(id:26417), Keydaimon(id:17982), YAMAARASHI(id:18211), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>