<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>だんじり</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Danjiri&quot; (A Festival Float in Western Japan)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Danjiri&quot; (A Festival Float in Western Japan)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Danjiri (a festival float in western Japan)</e>
<cmt>ダブルクォーテーションを削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>「だんじり」もしくは「だんぢり」とは、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Danjiri&quot; has some meanings as follows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Danjiri&quot; has several meanings, as follows.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term &apos;danjiri&apos; has several meanings, as follows.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>祭に奉納される山車（だし）のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">First, danjiri refers to the float dedicated to the deity in a festival.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">First, danjiri refers to a float dedicated to the deity in a festival.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Danjiri refers to a float dedicated to the deity in a festival.</e>
<cmt>それぞれ項目が分かれているようですので、First を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>「楽車」・「壇尻」・「台尻」・「段尻」とも表記される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is written in Chinese characters as &quot;楽車,&quot; &quot;壇尻,&quot; &quot;台尻,&quot; or &quot;段尻.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is written in Chinese characters as &quot;楽車,&quot; &quot;壇尻,&quot; &quot;台尻,&quot; or &quot;段尻.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is written in Chinese characters as &apos;楽車,&apos; &apos;壇尻,&apos; &apos;台尻,&apos; or &apos;段尻.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>主に西日本の祭礼で登場し、「曳きだんじり」と「担ぎだんじり」の2種類に大別される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It appears mainly in festivals of western Japan, and is roughly categorized into two, &quot;hiki-danjiri&quot; (a decorative float towed by festival participants) &amp; &quot;katsugi-danjiri&quot; (a decorative float shouldered by festival participants).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Danjiri appear mainly in festivals of western Japan, and are roughly categorized into two types, &quot;hiki-danjiri&quot; (a decorative float towed by festival participants) &amp; &quot;katsugi-danjiri&quot; (a decorative float shouldered by festival participants).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Danjiri appear mainly in festivals of western Japan, and are roughly categorized into two types, &apos;hiki-danjiri&apos; (a decorative float towed by festival participants) and &apos;katsugi-danjiri&apos; (a decorative float shouldered by festival participants).</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>地方によっては、太鼓台や布団太鼓などをこう呼ぶ場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In some local communities, danjiri refers to &quot;taikodai&quot; (a festival float that is set a drum inside) and &quot;futon-daiko&quot; (a big &quot;taikodai&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In some local communities, danjiri refers to &quot;taikodai&quot; (a festival float in which a drum is fit inside) and &quot;futon-daiko&quot; (a big &quot;taikodai&quot;).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In some local communities, danjiri refers to taikodai (a festival float in which a drum is fit inside) and futon-daiko (a big taikodai).</e>
<cmt>ダブルクォーテーションを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>上記のだんじりの内の一つで、近畿地方の主に和泉国・河内国・摂津国地域の祭礼で登場する地車（だんじり）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Second, danjiri refers to the float --- one of the first ones --- that appears mainly in festivals of the former Izumi Province, Kawachi Province, and Settsu Province (the present Hyogo &amp; Osaka Prefecture) in the Kinki region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Second, danjiri refers to the type of float --- one of the first ones --- that appears mainly in festivals of the former Izumi Province, Kawachi Province, and Settsu Province (the present Hyogo &amp; Osaka Prefectures) in the Kinki region.</e>
<cmt>plural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Danjiri refers to the type of float --- one of the above mentioned --- that appears mainly in festivals of the former Izumi Province, Kawachi Province, and Settsu Province (the present Hyogo and Osaka Prefectures) in the Kinki region.</e>
<cmt>それぞれ項目が分かれているようですので、Second を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>近年ではテレビなどの影響により、特に大阪府岸和田市の祭礼（岸和田だんじり祭）が有名であるため、この祭に登場する地車の事を指すこともある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Recently, television broadcasts and others have made Kishiwada Danjiri Festival (the festival held in Kishiwada City, Osaka Prefecture) so famous that &quot;daijiri&quot; sometimes refers to the float that appears in this festival.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Recently, television broadcasts and others have made the Kishiwada Danjiri Festival (the festival held in Kishiwada City, Osaka Prefecture) so famous that &quot;daijiri&quot; sometimes refers to the float that appears in this festival.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Recently, television broadcasts and others have made the Kishiwada Danjiri Festival (the festival held in Kishiwada City, Osaka Prefecture) so famous that danjiri sometimes refers to the float that appears in this festival.</e>
<cmt>ダブルクォーテーションを削除しました。スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Special rapid(id:96013), Rusk(id:9895), OSY(id:35563), Miita(id:30561), 満月(id:82772), Hamasaki gion higashi(id:144985), 依存性だんぢり中毒(id:79907), っ(id:4481), 弥(id:61590), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>