<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>扇面法華経冊子</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Senmen Hokkekyo Sasshi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Senmen Hokekyo Sasshi</e>
<cmt>Spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Senmen Hokekyo Sasshi (fan-shaped articles decorated with sutras)</e>
<cmt>説明補足</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>扇面法華経冊子（せんめんほけきょうさっし）または扇面古写経（せんめんこしゃきょう）は、大阪市・四天王寺に伝来した装飾経の遺品。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Senmen Hokkekyo Sasshi or Senmen Koshakyo is an article with soshokukyo (decorative sutras) which has been handed down in Shitenno-ji Temple (Osaka City).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Senmen Hokekyo Sasshi or Senmen Koshakyo is a collection of fan-shaped articles decorated with sutras that has been passed down by Shitenno-ji Temple in Osaka.</e>
<cmt>Fro the list of existing articles at the end, I presume there is more than one, so revised to reflect this, although it is not explicitly stated in the Japanese.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Senmen Hokekyo Sasshi or Senmen Koshakyo is a collection of fan-shaped articles decorated with sutras that has been passed down by Shitenno-ji Temple in Osaka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>扇形に切った料紙（扇子扇面）に絵を描いて2つに折り、折り目で貼り合わせて冊子とし、そこに法華経・無量義経・観普賢経の経典の経文を書写したものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A fan-shaped piece of ryoshi (paper for writing) or the face of a fan, with a painting drawn on it, is folded in two, stick to another fan-shaped piece of paper by aligning folding lines and made into a booklet, in which sutras from Buddhist scriptures such as Hokekyo (Lotus Sutra), Muryo gikyo (Sutra of Immeasurable Meanings) and Kanfugenkyo (Samantabhadra Contemplation Sutra) were copied.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fan-shaped pieces of &apos;ryoshi&apos; writing paper (the fan face), decorated with pictures, are folded in two, and joined along the fold to other pieces to make a booklet, into which sutras from Buddhist scripture such as the Hokekyo (Lotus Sutra), Muryo gikyo (Sutra of Immeasurable Meanings) and Kanfugenkyo (Samantabhadra Contemplation Sutra) were copied.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fan-shaped pieces of &apos;ryoshi&apos; writing paper (the fan face), decorated with pictures, are folded in two, and joined along the fold to other pieces to make a booklet, into which sutras from Buddhist scripture such as the Hokekyo (Lotus Sutra), Muryo gikyo (Sutra of Immeasurable Meanings) and Kanfugenkyo (Samantabhadra Contemplation Sutra) were copied.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Overview</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Overview</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>Overview→Summary</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>平安時代とくに院政期に流行した装飾経の遺品のひとつであるが、扇形の料紙を使用し、濃彩の下絵を用いる点は他に類をみない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Senmen Hokkekyo Sasshi is one of the articles with soshokukyo which were popular in the Heian period, especially in the insei period (during the period of the government by the retired Emperor), but it is very unique because a fan-shaped piece of ryoshi is used and a design is drawn in deep coloring.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Senmen Hokekyo Sasshi is an example of the decorative sutras that were popular in the Heian period (794-1185), especially during the period of cloistered rule (1086-c.1185), but the use of fan-shaped ryoshi and the deep colors are unique.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Senmen Hokekyo Sasshi is an example of the decorative sutras that were popular in the Heian period (794-1185), especially during the period of cloistered rule (1086-c.1185), but the use of fan-shaped ryoshi and the deep colors are unique.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>成立は12世紀中葉と考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered to have been established in the middle of the 12th century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed to have been made in the mid-12th century.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed to have been made in the mid-12th century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>下絵の題材は、貴族や庶民の生活などから採られ、大和絵の手法で描かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its design featured nobles&apos; and common people&apos;s lifestyles and was drawn in the style of Yamato-e painting (a traditional Japanese style painting).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The pictures depicted everyday scenes in the lives of nobles and common people and were painted in the traditional Yamato-e style.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The pictures depicted everyday scenes in the lives of nobles and common people and were painted in the traditional Yamato-e style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>美術品としての価値が高く、当時愛玩された紙扇の絵の様式を伝える唯一の遺品でもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a highly valued object of art as well as being the only article representing the painting style of paper fans which were much cherished those days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a highly valued object of art as well as being the only existing example of the painting style of paper fans which were much cherished at the time.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a highly valued object of art as well as being the only existing example of the painting style of paper fans which were much cherished at the time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>書風は和様で数人の手になるものとみられ、書跡資料としても貴重である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sutras were written in the Japanese style of handwriting, probably by several people, and provide valuable data on calligraphy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sutras were written in the Japanese style of handwriting, probably by several people, and provide valuable data on calligraphy.</e>
<cmt>Article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sutras were written in the Japanese style of handwriting, probably by several people, and provide valuable data on calligraphy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>風俗画としては、絵巻物とならび、きわめて貴重な情報が織り込まれた重要な図像資料でもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Senmen Hokkekyo Sasshi, as a form of genre painting, also provides important visual data, embodying as valuable information as emakimono (an illustrated scroll).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a form of genre painting, the Senmen Hokekyo Sasshi, like &apos;emaki&apos; illustrated scrolls, are also important illustrated documents containing valuable information.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a form of genre painting, the Senmen Hokekyo Sasshi, like &apos;emaki&apos; illustrated scrolls, are also important illustrated documents containing valuable information.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>扇形の冊子本</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fan-shaped Booklet</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fan-shaped Booklets</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fan-shaped Booklets</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="9">
<j>中国の北宋の時代は書誌学のうえでは、巻子本から冊子本への転換のなされた一大画期であったが、その影響は平安時代の日本におよんでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In terms of bibliography Northern Sung Dynasty in China is one of the most important periods, in which there was a shift from Kansubon (books in scroll style) to booklets, and Japan was influenced by such a shift in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Northern Sung Dynasty period in China is one of the most important periods in the field of biblography, since there was a shift from scroll style books to booklets, with Japan being influenced by such a shift in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Northern Sung Dynasty period in China is one of the most important periods in the field of biblography, since there was a shift from scroll style books to booklets, with Japan being influenced by such a shift in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>扇面古写経の制作もその流れの延長上にあるが、紙扇を料紙とした点がユニークである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Senmen Koshakyo was created against such background, but it was unique in that it used paper fans as ryoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Senmen Koshakyo was created against such a background, but it was unique in that it used paper fans as ryoshi.</e>
<cmt>Article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Senmen Koshakyo was created against such a background, but it was unique in that it used paper fans as ryoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>縦の辺が約25.5センチメートル、上弦幅約49.5センチメートル、下弦幅約19センチメートルの夏扇（蝙蝠扇）の料紙を粘葉装（でっちょうそう）の冊子に仕立てたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Each ryoshi is a natsu-ogi or Kawahori-ogi (paper fan) with a side edge of about 25.5cm, an upper arc of about 49.5cm and a lower arc of about 19cm, and is made into a deccho-so (a way of bookbinding) booklet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Each ryoshi is a natsu-ogi or Kawahori-ogi folding fan with a side edge of about 25.5cm, an upper arc of about 49.5cm and a lower arc of about 19cm, and the booklets are bound in a style known as deccho-so.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Each ryoshi is a natsu-ogi or Kawahori-ogi folding fan with a side edge of about 25.5cm, an upper arc of about 49.5cm and a lower arc of about 19cm, and the booklets are bound in a style known as deccho-so.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>表紙には金字の経題のほか、十羅刹女を一体ずつ和装（女房装束）で描いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kyodai (title of Buddhist scriptures) was written in gold letters and one of Jurasetsunyo (Ten Demonesses) dressed in kimono (women&apos;s court costume) was drawn on the front page.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kyodai (title) was written in gold and one of the Jurasetsunyo (the Japanese name for the ten demonesses mentioned in the Lotus Sutra) dressed in a kimono was drawn on the front page.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kyodai (title) was written in gold and one of the Jurasetsunyo (the Japanese name for the 10 demonesses mentioned in the Lotus Sutra) dressed in a kimono was drawn on the front page.</e>
<cmt>ten→10</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>料紙装飾</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Decoration of Ryoshi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Decoration of Ryoshi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Decoration of Ryoshi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="13">
<j>料紙はいずれも雲母（きら）を引き、墨流しや金銀の切箔（きりはく）、野毛、砂子（すなご）などを散らしてきわめて多様に意匠をこらしたもので、そこに濃彩の優美な大和絵風俗画を手彩色の下絵として描き、その上に経文を書写する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The powder solution of Kira (mica) is applied, suminagashi (a marbleized pattern produced by dropping black ink) is put, and grains, foils or slices of gold or silver foils is randomly sprinkled over each ryoshi, and on such highly decorated paper, elegant Fuzokuga (pictures of manners and customs) of Yamato-e (traditional Japanese style painting) were drawn in deep coloring, as a manually colored design, and sutras were transcribed on it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A solution of powdered mica powder is applied to the paper, which is then decorated using a marbling technique, with grains, slices and pieces of gold or silver leaf randomly sprinkled over each ryoshi, and on such highly decorated paper, elegant Fuzokuga (pictures of manners and customs) in the Yamato-e style were hand painted in deep colors and then sutras then written.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A solution of powdered mica powder is applied to the paper, which is then decorated using a marbling technique, with grains, slices and pieces of gold or silver leaf randomly sprinkled over each ryoshi, and on such highly decorated paper, elegant Fuzokuga (pictures of manners and customs) in the Yamato-e style were hand painted in deep colors and then sutras written.</e>
<cmt>then sutras then→then sutra</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>なお、下絵は料紙の片面のみに描かれているので、見開き一開ごとに下絵のある面と経文のみの面が交互にあらわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As designs were drawn only on one side of the ryoshi, you can see a face with a design and a face only with sutras alternately as you turn pages.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the pictures were painted only on one side of the ryoshi, the opened pages show one side of pictures and one side of sutras only.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the pictures were painted only on one side of the ryoshi, the opened pages show one side of pictures and one side of sutras only.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>豪奢にして華麗な装飾的効果に富んでおり、工芸史上も重要である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The leaflet is highly valued in the history of craftwork, with its gorgeous and splendid decorative effects.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With their gorgeous and splendid decorative effects, they are highly valued in the history of craftwork.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With their gorgeous and splendid decorative effects, they are highly valued in the history of craftwork.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="16">
<j>この冊子は、当時大量につくられた扇の地紙をそのまま写経用紙として転用した珍しい例である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is rare in that basal paper for fans which was produced in abundance those days was used as paper for copying sutras.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are unusual in that the sutras are copied onto paper which was produced in large amounts for fans.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are unusual in that the sutras are copied onto paper which was produced in large amounts for fans.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>装飾経としてよりむしろ、扇面画や大和絵としての文化史的ないし資料的価値が高いと評されるゆえんである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That is why it is highly valued in the cultural history or considered to provide useful data as Senmen-ga (picture on a fan) or Yamato-e rather than as Soshokukyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this reason they are appreciated more for their historical and informational value as Senmen-ga (illustrated fans) or Yamato-e than as decorative sutras.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For this reason they are appreciated more for their historical and informational value as Senmen-ga (illustrated fans) or Yamato-e than as decorative sutras.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>書式・書風</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Form and Handwriting</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Style and Handwriting</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Style and Handwriting</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="18">
<j>経文は、一行17字、一頁12行（見開き24行）に定型化された書式に漢字で放射状に墨書されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sutras were written in black ink, in kanji, arranged in a radial fashion in the fixed form of twelve lines in a page (twenty-four lines in two adjacent pages) with each line composed of seventeen letters.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sutras were written with black ink, in Chinese characters arranged in a radial fashion in the fixed form of twelve lines per page (twenty-four lines on two adjacent pages), with each line composed of seventeen characters.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sutras were written with black ink, in Chinese characters arranged in a radial fashion in the fixed form of 12 lines per page (24 lines on two adjacent pages), with each line composed of 17 characters.</e>
<cmt>数字表記変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>ただし、彩色下絵の青色や墨の部分の上に字を書く場合は、墨書の上を金泥でなぞったり、1字を半分ずつ金泥と墨とで書き分けたりするなど、手のこんだ書写がなされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were, however, of elaborate craftsmanship in that letters in black ink were traced with kindei (gold paint), or a half of the letters were written in kindei and the other half in black ink, when they had to be written on blue or black part of the design.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were, however, of elaborate craftsmanship in that when the characters were written on a blue or black background, they were traced with kindei (gold paint) or half a character was written in kindei and the other half in black ink.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were, however, of elaborate craftsmanship in that when the characters were written on a blue or black background, they were traced with kindei (gold paint) or half a character was written in kindei and the other half in black ink.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>書風は和様であり、少なくとも数人の手によるものとみられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were written in the Japanese style of handwriting, probably by several people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were written in the Japanese style of handwriting, probably by several people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were written in the Japanese style of handwriting, probably by several people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>構成と遺存状況</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Composition and the Condition of Conservation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Composition and the Condition of Conservation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Composition and the Condition of Conservation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="21">
<j>扇面法華経冊子の成立は、「女人成仏」、「写経成仏」を説く法華経信仰がさかんとなるなかで、経典そのものも美しく飾りたてられるようになったことによるものとみられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that Senmen Hokkekyo Sasshi was created when Buddhist scriptures began to be beautifully decorated with the spread of belief in Hokkekyo (Lotus Sutra) which preached &quot;Nyonin Jobutsu&quot; (Attainment of Buddhahood by Women) and &quot;Syakyo Jobutsu&quot; (Attainment of Buddhahood by Copying of a Sutra).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that the Senmen Hokkekyo Sasshi was created when Buddhist scriptures began to be beautifully decorated with the spread of belief in the Lotus Sutra, which preached &quot;Nyonin Jobutsu&quot; (attainment of buddhahood by women) and &quot;Syakyo Jobutsu&quot; (attainment of buddhahood by copying of sutras).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that the Senmen Hokekyo Sasshi was created when Buddhist scriptures began to be beautifully decorated with the spread of belief in the Lotus Sutra, which preached &apos;Nyonin Jobutsu&apos; (attainment of buddhahood by women) and &apos;Shakyo Jobutsu&apos; (attainment of buddhahood by copying of sutras).</e>
<cmt>Hokkekyo→HokekyoSyakyo→Shakyo&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>元来は「妙法蓮華経（法華経）」8巻と開結経（かいけつきょう）2巻、すなわち、本経に先だって説かれる開経（かいきょう）の「無量義経」とむすびをなす結経（けちきょう）の「観普賢経（仏説観普賢菩薩行法経）」の合わせて10帖で一具をなし、扇紙は総計115枚であったと推定される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally one series consisted of ten leaflets; eight volumes of &apos;&apos;Myohorenge-kyo (hokkekyo) (the Lotus Sutra)&apos;&apos; and two volumes of Kaiketsu-kyo (sutras read before and after the main sutra) including &quot;Muryo Gikyo,&quot; which should be read before the main sutra, and &quot;Kanfugenkyo (Bussetsu Kanfugenbosatsu Gyoho-kyo&quot;to be read after the main sutra, and so the number of Ogi-e (fan paintings) is estimated to be 115 in total.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It originally consisted of ten volumes; eight volumes of &apos;&apos;Myohorenge-kyo (hokkekyo)&quot; (Lotus Sutra)&quot; and two volumes of Kaiketsu-kyo (sutras read before and after the main sutra) made up of the &quot;Muryo Gikyo,&quot; to be read before the main sutra, and &quot;Kanfugenkyo (Bussetsu Kanfugenbosatsu Gyoho-kyo)&quot; (Samantabhadra Contemplation Sutra) to be read after the main sutra, with the number of Ogi-e (fan paintings) estimated to be 115 in total.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It originally consisted of 10 volumes; eight volumes of &apos;Myohorenge-kyo (Hokekyo)&apos; and two volumes of Kaiketsu-kyo (sutras read before and after the main sutra) made up of the &apos;Muryo Gikyo,&apos; to be read before the main sutra, and &apos;Kanfugenkyo (Bussetsu Kanfugenbosatsu Gyoho-kyo)&apos; (Samantabhadra Contemplation Sutra) to be read after the main sutra, with the number of fan paintings estimated to be 115 in total.</e>
<cmt>数字表記変更&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;(hokkekyo)&apos;→(Hokekyo)(Lotus Sutra)　削除Ogi-e (fan paintings)→Ogi-paper→fan paintings</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>一具のうち、今日では四天王寺（大阪市）に「法華経」巻一、六、七および開結経2帖の計5帖が伝存するほか、東京国立博物館が「法華経」巻八の完本1帖を所蔵、他に断簡5葉が各所に分蔵され、合計59面、表紙絵5面を数える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today, of the series, the first, sixth and seventh volume of &quot;hokkekyo&quot; and two leaflets of Kaiketu-kyo are reserved by Shitenno-ji Temple in Osaka City, the Kanbon (complete edition) of &quot;hokkekyo&quot; Vol. 8 is reserved by the Tokyo National Museum, and five pieces of dankan (fragmentary leaves of a book) are separately reserved at various facilities, which means there remain 59 faces of Ogi-e and five cover paintings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, of the series, the first, sixth and seventh volume of &quot;hokkekyo&quot; and the two Kaiketsu-kyo books are kept at Shitenno-ji Temple in Osaka, the complete version of &quot;hokkekyo&quot; volume 8 is kept at the Tokyo National Museum, and five fragments are kept separately at various facilities, meaning a total of 59 faces and five cover paintings remain in existence.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, of the series, the first, sixth and seventh volume of &apos;Hokekyo&apos; and the two Kaiketsu-kyo books are kept at Shitenno-ji Temple in Osaka, the complete version of &apos;Hokekyo&apos; volume 8 is kept at the Tokyo National Museum, and five fragments are kept separately at various facilities, meaning a total of 59 faces and five cover paintings remain in existence.</e>
<cmt>hokkekyo→Hokekyo</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>作画技法と画風</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Technique and Style of Painting</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Technique and Style of Painting</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Technique and Style of Painting</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="24">
<j>貴族やそれに仕える男女、庶民の風俗や自然の景物を木版で刷ったり、図様を墨描きしたり、あるいは、両者を組み合わせたのちに彩色を加えて料紙としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the ryoshi, modes of life of nobles, their servants and common people as well as natural landscapes were depicted in woodblock prints, ink brush painting or a combination of both, and then colored.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the ryoshi, the way of life of nobles, their servants and common people as well as natural landscapes were depicted in woodblock prints, ink brush painting or a combination of both, and then colored.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the ryoshi, the way of life of nobles, their servants and common people as well as natural landscapes were depicted in woodblock prints, ink brush painting or a combination of both, and then colored.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>下店静市は、この点から版画史上の重要性を指摘している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the basis of this, Shizuichi SHIMOMISE points out the importance of those pictures in the history of woodblock prints.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the basis of this, Shizuichi SHIMOMISE points out the importance of the pictures in the history of woodblock prints.</e>
<cmt>Article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the basis of this, Shizuichi SHIMOMISE points out the importance of the pictures in the history of woodblock prints.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>美術史家の秋山光和は、作画技法の検討によりA類（27面）、B類（18面）、C類（9面）、さらにB類とC類の複合的な技法によるもの（5面）に分類している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hidekazu AKIYAMA, an art historian, classifies the Ogi-e into Class A (27 faces), Class B (18 faces), Class C (9 faces) and the combination of Classes B and C (5 faces), on the basis of consideration of painting techniques.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hidekazu AKIYAMA, an art historian, classifies the Ogi-e into Class A (27 faces), Class B (18 faces), Class C (9 faces) and a combination of Classes B and C (5 faces), based on consideration of the painting techniques.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hidekazu AKIYAMA, an art historian, classifies the Ogi-e into Class A (27 faces), Class B (18 faces), Class C (9 faces) and a combination of Classes B and C (5 faces), based on consideration of the painting techniques.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>A類は雲母（きら）引き下地の上に彩色したもの、B類は木版墨摺りの下絵に雲母引きを施し、彩色したもの、C類は雲母引きに金銀の箔を散らしたうえで木版で下絵を墨摺りし彩色したものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Class A is coloring on the ground with the powder solution of mica applied on it, Class B is coloring on woodblock prints in black ink after applying the powder solution of mica to them, and Class C is coloring on woodblock prints in black ink on the ground with the powder solution of mica applied and gold or silver foils sprayed on it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Class A is color applied to a mica solution undercoat; Class B is mica solution applied to black ink woodblock prints and then colors added; and Class C is gold and silver leaf scattered on mica, then black ink woodblock prints are added and colored.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Class A is color applied to a mica solution undercoat; Class B is mica solution applied to black ink woodblock prints and then colors added; and Class C is gold and silver leaf scattered on mica, then black ink woodblock prints are added and colored.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="28">
<j>画風は、唐絵の影響から脱した盛期の大和絵のなかでも、宮廷派の特徴を有する動的な様式に属している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The paintings are of a dynamic style with a few characteristics of court paintings, while belonging to the prime time of Yamato-e after the influences of Kara-e paintings faded away.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The paintings are of a dynamic style with a few characteristics of court paintings, while belonging to the post-Kara-e (Chinese style painting) heydey of Yamato-e.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The paintings are of a dynamic style with a few characteristics of court paintings, while belonging to the post-Kara-e (Chinese style painting) heyday of Yamato-e.</e>
<cmt>heydey→heyday</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>色調は、同時代の『源氏物語絵巻』や『平家納経』ほどの重厚さはないが、優美かつ多彩であり、品格がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The color tone is not as heavy as in &quot;Genji Monogatari Emaki&quot; (Illustrated handscrolls of the Tale of Genji) and &quot;Heike-nokyo&quot; (sutras dedicated by the Taira family), but is delicate, prismatic and full of grace.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The color tone is not as heavy as in &quot;Genji Monogatari Emaki&quot; (Illustrated handscrolls of the Tale of Genji) and &quot;Heike-nokyo&quot; (sutras dedicated by the Taira family), but is delicate, prismatic and full of grace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The color tone is not as heavy as in &quot;Genji Monogatari Emaki&quot; (Illustrated handscrolls of the Tale of Genji) and &quot;Heike-nokyo&quot; (sutras dedicated by the Taira family), but is delicate, prismatic and full of grace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>描線は細かく、木版の影響もあってやや硬質であり、肉筆は繊細または流麗なものが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The line is minute, rather rigid because of the woodblock, but most of the handwritten lines are delicate and flowing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The lines are fine and rather rigid because of the woodblock, but most of the handwritten lines are delicate and flowing.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The lines are fine and rather rigid because of the woodblock, but most of the handwritten lines are delicate and flowing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>貴族の表情は類型化された引目鈎鼻であるが、雑仕や婢女らの姿は市井の風俗もまじえて、生き生きと描き出されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While nobles&apos; faces are expressed with the typical Hikime Kagibana (dashes for eyes, hooks for noses as a drawing convention), Zoshi (low class maid) and Hashitame (maid servant) are vividly depicted, along with common people&apos;s mode of life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While nobles&apos; faces are expressed with the typical &apos;Hikime Kagibana&apos; style (dashes for eyes, hooks for noses), servants and the everyday life of common people are vividly depicted.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While nobles&apos; faces are expressed with the typical &apos;Hikime Kagibana&apos; style (dashes for eyes, hooks for noses), servants and the everyday life of common people are vividly depicted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>画題</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Subjects</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subjects</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subjects</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="32">
<j>画題は経文とは関係がないという指摘もある一方、直接的ないし間接的に関連があるとの指摘もなされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some researchers point out that the subject of the painting has nothing to do with the contents of the sutra. On the other hand, others insist that the subject of the painting is directly or indirectly connected with the sutra.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some researchers point out that the subjects of the paintings have nothing to do with the contents of the sutras but others insist that they are directly or indirectly connected.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some researchers point out that the subjects of the paintings have nothing to do with the contents of the sutras but others insist that they are directly or indirectly connected.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>ただし、後者においても、それをすべてにわたって明瞭に解明することは困難だとしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But even the latter consider that it is difficult to understand all the connections between subjects of the paintings and the sutras clearly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But even the latter consider that it is difficult to understand all the connections between the paintings and the sutras clearly.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But even the latter consider that it is difficult to understand all the connections between the paintings and the sutras clearly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>元来、扇は夏季に使用されることが多いことから、暖かさを感じさせる風景に比較すれば井戸や水辺、雪など涼しさを感じさせる風景が多く、また桜や紅葉、松なども多く描かれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As fans are mostly used in summer, there are more paintings which depict scenes associated with coolness, such as wells, waterside and snow, than those which depict scenes associated with warmness, and cherry blossoms, maples and pine trees are often depicted, too.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As fans are mostly used in summer, there are more paintings which depict scenes associated with coolness, such as wells, waterside and snow, than those which depict scenes associated with warmness; cherry blossoms, maples and pine trees are also often depicted.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As fans are mostly used in summer, there are more paintings which depict scenes associated with coolness, such as wells, waterside and snow, than those which depict scenes associated with warmness; cherry blossoms, maples and pine trees are also often depicted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>下店静市は、『伊勢物語』などの文学作品からも画題がとられているとしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shizuichi SHIMOMISE thinks that some subjects are from literary works including &quot;Ise Monogatari&quot; (The Tales of Ise).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shizuichi SHIMOMISE thinks that some subjects are from literary works, including &quot;Ise Monogatari&quot; (The Tales of Ise).</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shizuichi SHIMOMISE thinks that some subjects are from literary works, including &quot;Ise Monogatari&quot; (The Tales of Ise).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="36">
<j>表現対象としては、人物が大部分であるが、四天王寺所蔵のものには花鳥画が例外的に散見され、その伝統の上でも貴重な資料となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the majority of the paintings people are drawn, but Kacho-ga (painting of flowers and birds) are exceptionally seen in the leaflets held by Shitenno-ji Temple, providing valuable data.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The majority of the paintings depict people, but those kept by Shitenno-ji Temple are unusual in that they are Kacho-ga (paintings of flowers and birds), providing valuable data.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The majority of the paintings depict people, but those kept by Shitenno-ji Temple are unusual in that they are Kacho-ga (paintings of flowers and birds), providing valuable data.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>また、描かれる人物は、老若男女や貴賤を問わず、多種多様な職業の人びとを対象としており、その点でも歴史資料としてきわめて貴重なものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, men and women of all ages, all ranks and all vocations are depicted, and so the paintings provide valuable historical data in that sense.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, men and women of all ages, ranks and vocations are depicted, and so the paintings also provide valuable historical data in that sense.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, men and women of all ages, ranks and vocations are depicted, and so the paintings also provide valuable historical data in that sense.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="38">
<j>なかでも名高い遺品は、四天王寺所蔵の平安京の市場の風景を描いた二葉（法華経巻七扇6、同扇11）で、間口一間の小さな店では前掛けをした市女によって魚、果物、瓜、栗、布など多種多様な商品を売られており、その前を市女笠（いちめがさ）をかぶり、袿をまとった女性が通行しているようすが描かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The most famous paintings are two pieces held by Shitenno-ji Temple (the sixth and eleventh fans of &quot;hokkekyo&quot; vol. 7) depicting the market in Heian-kyo (the ancient capital of Japan in current Kyoto), in which a woman wearing an apron is selling various commodities including fish, fruits, pepos, chestnuts and cloths in a small shop with an ikken (or 1-ken) -width frontage (1-ken is approximately 1.8 meters) and another woman wearing Ichime-gasa (a kind of cap with a shade, worn by a woman) and Uchigi (ordinary kimono) is walking before the shop.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The most famous paintings are two pieces (the sixth and eleventh fans of &quot;hokkekyo&quot; vol. 7) held by Shitenno-ji Temple depicting the market in Heian-kyo (the ancient name of Kyoto), in which a woman wearing an apron is selling various commodities including fish, fruits, Japanese melons, chestnuts and cloths in a small 2-meter wide shop and another woman wearing an ichime-gasa (a kind of woman&apos;s cap with a shade) and uchigi (ordinary kimono) is walking before the shop.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The most famous paintings are two pieces (the sixth and eleventh fans of &quot;hokkekyo&quot; vol. 7) held by Shitenno-ji Temple depicting the market in Heian-kyo (the ancient name of Kyoto), in which a woman wearing an apron is selling various commodities including fish, fruits, Japanese melons, chestnuts and cloths in a small 2-meter wide shop and another woman wearing an ichime-gasa (a kind of woman&apos;s cap with a shade) and uchigi (ordinary kimono) is walking before the shop.</e>
<cmt>hokkekyo→hokekyo</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>当時の商業の実際や服飾などの知るうえで好資料となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The paintings are good materials on the actual customs of commercial activities and furnishings in those days.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The paintings are a good resource for information on the actual customs of commercial activities and furnishings in those days.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The paintings are a good resource for information on the actual customs of commercial activities and furnishings in those days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="40">
<j>また、井戸端に集う女性たちを描いたもの（法華経巻七扇1）があり、そこには曲物を頭に乗せながら裸の子どもの手をひく袿なし姿の里の女、つるべで水を汲みのどをうるおす袿を着た旅姿の女が描かれ、当時の地方の庶民生活がしのばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another painting features women gathering around a well (the first fan of &quot;hokkekyo&quot; vol. 7) in which a village woman wearing no Uchigi, with a magemono (wooden bucket) on her head, leads her naked child by hand, and another woman in travel clothing, wearing Uchigi, dips up water with the use of a tsurube (a tub for a well) and drinks it; they represent the mode of life of local people in those days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another painting that shows the everyday life of people at that time (the first fan of &quot;hokkekyo&quot; vol. 7)features women gathering around a well, with a village woman without an uchigi and carrying a wooden bucket on her head, leading her naked child by the hand, and another woman dressed for travel in an uchigi, quenching her thirst by drinking from the well bucket.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another painting that shows the everyday life of people at that time (the first fan of &quot;hokekyo&quot; vol. 7) features women gathering around a well, with a village woman without an uchigi and carrying a wooden bucket on her head, leading her naked child by the hand, and another woman dressed for travel in an uchigi, quenching her thirst by drinking from the well bucket.</e>
<cmt>閉じ括弧の前後のスペース調整hokkekyo→hokekyo</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="41">
<j>さらに、草合わせをする2人の少女（法華経巻七扇8）、小鳥捕りをする少年（法華経巻七扇9）、柿もぎのようす（法華経巻六扇11）など子どもの遊戯や風物詩も画題となっており、紅葉を愛でる女房と栗拾いの婢女を描いた場面（法華経巻一扇10）、文を読む公卿と童女（法華経巻一扇9）、遊女と傀儡子（または男巫）が今様を歌って道祖神に報宴し、神霊を慰めているのではないかと推定される場面などを描いたものもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, the subjects of the paintings include children&apos;s play and special seasonable features, such as two girls playing kusa-awase (a game where they show various grass they bring for a competition) (the eighth fan of &quot;hokkekyo&quot; vol. 7), a boy trying to catch a little bird (the ninth fan of &quot;hokkekyo&quot; vol. 7) and harvest of persimmons (the eleventh fan of &quot;hokkekyo&quot; vol. 6), as well as the scene of a lady watching maple leaves and a Hashitame picking chestnuts (the tenth fan of &quot;hokkekyo&quot; vol. 1), Kugyo (the top court officials) reading a letter and a warawame (little girl) (the ninth fan of &quot;hokkekyo&quot; vol. 1) and even the scene of a yujo (prostitute) and a kairai (puppet) or okannagi (sorcerer) singing Imayo (popular style of song in Heian period) as offerings to Doso-jin (traveler&apos;s guardian deity), probably solacing the spirit.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, the subjects of the paintings include children&apos;s play and seasonal images, such as two girls comparing grasses they have gathered in a game of kusa-awase (the eighth fan of &quot;hokkekyo&quot; vol. 7), a boy trying to catch a little bird (the ninth fan of &quot;hokkekyo&quot; vol. 7) and the persimmon harvest (the eleventh fan of &quot;hokkekyo&quot; vol. 6), as well as a scene of a court lady admiring the autumn leaves and a serving girl collecting chestnuts (the tenth fan of &quot;hokkekyo&quot; vol. 1), a little girl and a court official reading a letter (the ninth fan of &quot;hokkekyo&quot; vol. 1) and even a scene of a prostitute and a puppet (or sorcerer) singing Imayo (a popular style of song in the Heian period) as offerings to guardian deity of travelers, Doso-jin, probably to comfort the spirit.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity - I presume &quot;傀儡&quot; should be &quot;傀儡子&quot; but I left it as the former.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, the subjects of the paintings include children&apos;s play and seasonal images, such as two girls comparing grasses they have gathered in a game of kusa-awase (the eighth fan of &quot;hokekyo&quot; vol. 7), a boy trying to catch a little bird (the ninth fan of &quot;hokkekyo&quot; vol. 7) and the persimmon harvest (the 11th fan of &quot;hokkekyo&quot; vol. 6), as well as a scene of a court lady admiring the autumn leaves and a serving girl collecting chestnuts (the 10th fan of &quot;hokkekyo&quot; vol. 1), a little girl and a court official reading a letter (the ninth fan of &quot;hokkekyo&quot; vol. 1) and even a scene of a prostitute and a puppet player (or sorcerer) singing Imayo (a popular style of song in the Heian period) as offerings to guardian deity of travelers, Doso-jin, probably to comfort the spirit.</e>
<cmt>数字表記変更ＮＣのご指摘どおり、ウェブで確認したところ、「傀儡子」が正しいので、原文、訳文ともに訂正しました。hokkekyo→hokekyo</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="42">
<j>なお、十羅刹女はいずれも女房姿で描かれるが、「無量義経」の表紙絵のみは 汗衫（かざみ）姿の童女形で示されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Each of Jurasetsunyo is depicted as a lady, but only the one in the cover painting of &quot;Muryo gikyo&quot; is represented as a warawame wearing Kazami (young girl&apos;s formal costume).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Each of the Jurasetsunyo is depicted as a lady, but only the one in the cover painting of &quot;Muryo gikyo&quot; is depicted as a young girl wearing Kazami (formal costume).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Each of the Jurasetsunyo is depicted as a lady, but only the one in the cover painting of &apos;Muryo gikyo&apos; is depicted as a young girl wearing Kazami (formal costume).</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>制作時期・制作者</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Time of Production and Producers</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Period of Production and Identity of the Makers</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Period of Production and Identity of the Makers</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="43">
<j>制作時期については、絵画様式や風俗などの点から12世紀中頃とする説が有力である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the best guess at the moment, Senmen Hokkekyo Sasshi is supposed to have been created in the middle of the 12th century, judging from the painting style and the depicted mode of life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The most widely accepted theory is that, judging from the painting style and the wy of life depicted, the Senmen Hokkekyo Sasshi was probably created in the middle of the 12th century.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The most widely accepted theory is that, judging from the painting style and the way of life depicted, the Senmen Hokekyo Sasshi was probably created in the middle of the 12th century.</e>
<cmt>wy→wayHokkekyo→Hokekyo</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>かつては、『玉葉』や『吉記』の記事にある、文治4年（1188年）9月15日の四天王寺如法経供養の際に奉納されたものとする説もあったが、秋山光和、柳沢孝（やなぎさわたか）らの研究により、高貴な女性の発願になる可能性が高いとされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Formerly, it was supposed to have been devoted at the time of &apos;&apos;Shitennoji Nyoho-kyo Kuyo (holding a mass for the departed soul)&apos;&apos; on September 15, 1188, mentioned in articles of &quot;Gyokuyo&quot; (Diary of FUJIWARA no Kanezane) and &quot;Kikki&quot; (a diary of Tunefusa YOSHIDA), but later researchers Mitsukazu AKIYAMA and Taka YANAGISAWA discovered that it was probably created at the wish of an honorable lady.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It used to be believed that it was dedicated at the time of the &apos;&apos;Shitennoji Nyoho-kyo Kuyo&quot; (mass for departed souls) held on September 15, 1188, and which is mentioned in entries in FUJIWARA no Kanezane&apos;s diary &quot;Gyokuyo&quot; and Tunefusa YOSHIDA&apos;s diary &quot;Kikki&quot;, but later researchers such as Mitsukazu AKIYAMA and Taka YANAGISAWA discovered that it was probably created at the wish of a noble lady.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It used to be believed that it was dedicated at the time of the &apos;&apos;Shitennoji Nyoho-kyo Kuyo&quot; (mass for departed souls) held on October 14, 1188, and which is mentioned in entries in FUJIWARA no Kanezane&apos;s diary &quot;Gyokuyo&quot; and Tunefusa YOSHIDA&apos;s diary &quot;Kikki&quot;, but later researchers such as Mitsukazu AKIYAMA and Taka YANAGISAWA discovered that it was probably created at the wish of a noble lady.</e>
<cmt>旧暦→グレゴリオ暦</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>鳥羽天皇の皇后であった高陽院藤原泰子により仁平2年（1152年）に奉納されたものとする説が今日では有力である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is most widely believed today that Senmen Hokkekyo Sasshi was devoted in 1152 by Kayano-in FUJIWARA no Taishi, Empress of Emperor Toba.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, it is most widely believed that the Senmen Hokkekyo Sasshi was devoted in 1152 by Kayano-in FUJIWARA no Taishi, the Empress of Emperor Toba.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, it is most widely believed that the Senmen Hokekyo Sasshi was devoted in 1152 by Kayano-in FUJIWARA no Taishi, the Empress of Emperor Toba.</e>
<cmt>Hokkekyo→Hokekyo</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>いずれにしても、謹厳な書体の写経と彩り豊かな風俗・景物が扇のなかで一体となった品であり、平安時代末期の貴族の信仰生活のなかに種々の趣味的要素が盛りこまれていたことを端的に示す一例といえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Anyway, incorporating sutras in a reserved style and colorful pictures of fashion and landscapes, those fans clearly demonstrate that many factors of pleasure were included in nobles&apos; religious life at the end of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In any case, the reserved calligraphy of the sutras and the colorful pictures of customs and landscapes side by side in one work clearly demonstrate that nobles at the end of the Heian period celebrated relgion in a variety of ways.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In any case, the reserved calligraphy of the sutras and the colorful pictures of customs and landscapes side by side in one work clearly demonstrate that nobles at the end of the Heian period celebrated relgion in a variety of ways.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>扇面法華経冊子の現存遺品</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Existing Articles of Senmen Hokkekyo Sasshi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Existing Articles of the Senmen Hokkekyo Sasshi</e>
<cmt>Article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Existing Articles of the Senmen Hokekyo Sasshi</e>
<cmt>Hokkekyo→Hokekyo</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="47">
<j>以下のように各所に分蔵されるが、元来は一具だったものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As indicated below, the leaflets are separately held by various facilities, but they originally made up one series.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As indicated below, the volumes are separately held by various facilities, but they originally made up one series.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As indicated below, the volumes are separately held by various facilities, but they originally made up one series.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="48">
<j>四天王寺（大阪府大阪市）蔵（国宝）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">held by Shitenno-ji Temple (Osaka City, Osaka Prefecture): national treasures</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Held by Shitenno-ji Temple (Osaka City, Osaka Prefecture); national treasures</e>
<cmt>Capital letterPunctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Held by Shitenno-ji Temple (Osaka City, Osaka Prefecture); national treasures</e>
<cmt>コロンをセミコロンに訂正されているので以下、同じ文体はセミコロンとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>「法華経」巻一</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Hokkekyo&quot; vol. 1</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Hokkekyo&quot; vol. 1</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hokekyo&apos; vol. 1</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;Hokkekyo→Hokekyo</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>「法華経」巻六</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Hokkekyo&quot; vol. 6</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Hokkekyo&quot; vol. 6</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hokekyo&apos; vol. 6</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;Hokkekyo→Hokekyo</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>「法華経」巻七</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Hokkekyo&quot; vol. 7</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Hokkekyo&quot; vol. 7</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hokekyo&apos; vol. 7</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;Hokkekyo→Hokekyo</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>「無量義経」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Muryo Gikyo&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Muryo Gikyo&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Muryo Gikyo&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>「観普賢経」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kanfugenkyo&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kanfugenkyo&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanfugenkyo&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>東京国立博物館（東京都台東区上野公園）蔵（国宝）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">held by the Tokyo National Museum (Ueno Park, Taito-ku, Tokyo): national treasures</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Held by the Tokyo National Museum (Ueno Park, Taito-ku, Tokyo); national treasure</e>
<cmt>Capital letterPunctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Held by the Tokyo National Museum (Ueno Park, Taito Ward, Tokyo); national treasure</e>
<cmt>Taito-ku→Taito Ward</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>「法華経」巻八（普門品・陀羅尼品・厳王品・勧発品）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Hokkekyo&quot; vol. 8 (Fumonhon, Daranihon, Gono-bon and Kanboppon)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Hokkekyo&quot; vol. 8 (Fumonhon, Daranihon, Gono-bon and Kanboppon)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hokekyo&apos; vol. 8 (Fumonhon, Daranihon, Gono-bon and Kanboppon)</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;Hokkekyo→Hokekyo</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>西教寺（滋賀県大津市坂本）蔵断簡 掛幅装（重要文化財）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dankan in the style of kakefuku (a painting for hanging scroll), held by Saikyo-ji Temple (Sakamoto, Otsu City, Shiga Prefecture): important cultural properties</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fragment, as a hanging scroll, held by Saikyo-ji Temple (Sakamoto, Otsu City, Shiga Prefecture): important cultural property</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fragment, as a hanging scroll, held by Saikyo-ji Temple (Sakamoto, Otsu City, Shiga Prefecture); important cultural property</e>
<cmt>:→;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>「法華経」巻一扇8</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the eighth fan of &quot;Hokkekyo&quot; vol. 1</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The eighth fan of &quot;Hokkekyo&quot; vol. 1</e>
<cmt>Capital letter</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The eighth fan of &apos;Hokekyo&apos; vol. 1</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;Hokkekyo→Hokekyo</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>法隆寺（奈良県斑鳩町）蔵断簡 掛幅装（重要文化財）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dankan in the style of kakefuku, held by Horyu-ji Temple (Ikaruga-cho, Nara Prefecture): important cultural properties</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fragment, as a hanging scroll, held by Horyu-ji Temple (Ikaruga-cho, Nara Prefecture): important cultural property</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fragment, as a hanging scroll, held by Horyu-ji Temple (Ikaruga-cho, Nara Prefecture); important cultural property</e>
<cmt>:→;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>「観普賢経」扇8</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the eighth fan of &quot;Kanfugenkyo&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The eighth fan of &quot;Kanfugenkyo&quot;</e>
<cmt>Capital letter</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The eighth fan of &apos;Kanfugenkyo&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>藤田美術館（大阪市都島区網島町）蔵断簡 1枚（重要文化財）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">one piece of Dankan held by Fujita Museum of Art (Amijima-cho, Miyakojima-ku, Osaka City): important cultural properties</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fragment, held by Fujita Museum of Art (Amijima-cho, Miyakojima-ku, Osaka City): important cultural property</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fragment, held by Fujita Museum of Art (Amijima-cho, Miyakojima Ward, Osaka City); important cultural property</e>
<cmt>:→;Miyakojima-ku→Miyakojima Ward</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>「法華経」巻六 残欠</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">incomplete remains of &quot;Hokkekyo&quot; vol. 6</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Incomplete remains of &quot;Hokkekyo&quot; vol. 6</e>
<cmt>Capital letter</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Incomplete remains of &apos;Hokekyo&apos; vol. 6</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;Hokkekyo→Hokekyo</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>出光美術館（東京都千代田区丸の内）蔵断簡 掛幅装（重要文化財）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dankan in the style of kakefuku, held by Idemitsu Museum of Arts (Marunouchi, Chiyoda-ku, Tokyo): important cultural properties</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fragment, as a hanging scroll, held by Idemitsu Museum of Arts (Marunouchi, Chiyoda-ku, Tokyo): important cultural property</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fragment, as a hanging scroll, held by Idemitsu Museum of Arts (Marunouchi, Chiyoda Ward, Tokyo); important cultural property</e>
<cmt>:→;Chiyoda-ku→Chiyoda Ward</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>「法華経」巻一扇4</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the fourth fan of &quot;Hokkekyo&quot; vol. 1</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fourth fan of &quot;Hokkekyo&quot; vol. 1</e>
<cmt>Capital letter</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fourth fan of &apos;Hokekyo&apos; vol. 1</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;Hokkekyo→Hokekyo</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>個人蔵断簡 1枚（重要文化財）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">one piece of Dankan held by an individual: important cultural property</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fragment held by an individual: important cultural property</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fragment held by an individual; important cultural property</e>
<cmt>:→;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>「観普賢経」扇9</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the ninth fan of &quot;Kanfugenkyo&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ninth fan of &quot;Kanfugenkyo&quot;</e>
<cmt>Capital letter</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ninth fan of &apos;Kanfugenkyo&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="66">
<j>他に、1行のみの断簡、2行のみの断簡が存在し、それぞれ個人蔵となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to those listed above, there are Dankan only with one line and Dankan with two lines, both of which are held by individuals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to those listed above, there is a fragment containing one line and a fragment containing two lines, both of which are held by individuals.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to those listed above, there is a fragment containing one line and a fragment containing two lines, both of which are held by individuals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 白駒(id:144373), Fffkk(id:261100), Goki(id:7107), Greenland4(id:114494), Urania(id:7213), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>