<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>朝日焼</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Asahi yaki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Asahi yaki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Asahi Yaki</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>朝日焼（あさひやき）は京都府宇治市で焼かれる陶器。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Asahi yaki is a kind of earthenware produced in Uji City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Asahi yaki is a kind of earthenware produced in Uji City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Asahi yaki is a kind of earthenware produced in Uji City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>宇治茶の栽培が盛んになるにつれ、茶の湯向けの陶器が焼かれるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As plantation of Ujicha (Uji tea) became flourished, earthenware for chanoyu (tea ceremony) were actively produced,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Ujicha (Uji tea) plantations flourished, earthenware for chanoyu (tea ceremony) were actively produced,</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Uji cha (Uji tea) plantations flourished, earthenware for chanoyu (tea ceremony) were actively produced.</e>
<cmt>ピリオドにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>江戸時代には遠州七窯の一つにも数えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Edo period, a kiln of Asahi yaki was counted among the Enshu Nanagama (best seven kilns selected by Enshu, a famous master of ceremonial tea.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Edo period, a kiln of Asahi yaki was counted among the Enshu Nanagama (best seven kilns selected by Enshu, a famous master of ceremonial tea.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Edo period, a kiln of Asahi yaki was counted among the Enshu Shichiyo (best seven kilns selected by Enshu KOBORI, a famous master of ceremonial tea).</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>朝日焼という名前の由来については、朝日山という山の麓で窯が開かれていたという説と、朝日焼独特の赤い斑点（御本手）が旭光を思わせるという説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name of Asahi yaki is said to be derived from the Mount Asahi at the foot of which its kiln was located, or from its own red spots (Gohonte) which are suggestive of the morning sun (kyokko or asahi in Japanese.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name of Asahi yaki is said to be derived from the Mount Asahi at the foot of which its kiln was located, or from its own red spots (Gohonte) which are suggestive of the morning sun (kyokko or asahi in Japanese.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name of Asahi yaki is said to be derived from Mt. Asahi at the foot of which its kiln was located, or from its own red spots (Gohonte) which are suggestive of kyokko (the morning sun).</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>宇治地方は古くから良質の粘土が採れ、須恵器などを焼いていた窯場跡が見られていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since long time ago, Uji area has abounded in clays of good quality, where old kiln sites of unglazed (ceramic) ware are found.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since long ago, the Uji area has always had an abundance of good quality clays, where old kiln sites of unglazed (ceramic) ware are found.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since long ago, the Uji region has always had an abundance of good quality clays, where old kiln sites of unglazed (ceramic) ware are found.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>室町時代、朝日焼が興る前には、経歴も全く不詳な宇治焼という焼き物が焼かれ、今も名器だけが残されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Muromachi period, before Asahi yaki was started, Uji area had produced another earthenware called Uji yaki which had no clear historical background but some curios left.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Muromachi period, before Asahi yaki was born, the Uji area had produced another type of earthenware called Uji yaki which had no clear historical background, but some curios remain.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Muromachi period, before Asahi yaki was born, the Uji region had produced another type of earthenware called Uji yaki which had no clear historical background, but some famous wares remain.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>今日、最古の朝日焼の刻印があるのは慶長年間のものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today, we have the oldest pottery with the mark of Asahi yaki engraved in Keicho era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, we have the oldest pottery with the mark of Asahi yaki engraved during the Keicho era.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, we have the oldest pottery with the mark of Asahi yaki engraved during the Keicho era.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>しかし、桃山時代には茶の湯が興隆したため、初代、奥村次郎衛門藤作が太閤豊臣秀吉より絶賛され、陶作と名を改めたというエピソードも残っていることから、当時から朝日焼は高い評判を得ていたことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But, Asahi yaki seems to have been highly appreciated since Momoyama era when tea ceremony had arisen and prospered, and Jirouemon Tosaku OKUMURA, originator of Asahi yaki, had an episode that he was praised by Taiko Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI and then changed letters of his name from 藤作(literally, grower of wisteria) to 陶作 (creator of pottery) both of which remain unchanged in pronunciation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But, Asahi yaki seems to have been highly appreciated since the Momoyama era when tea ceremony had arisen and prospered, and Jirouemon Tosaku OKUMURA, originator of Asahi yaki, was praised by Taiko Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI and then changed the letters of his name from 藤作 (literally, grower of wisteria) to 陶作 (creator of pottery) both of which remain unchanged in pronunciation.</e>
<cmt>grammar, spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But, Asahi yaki seems to have been highly appreciated since the Momoyama period when tea ceremony had arisen and prospered, and Jirouemon Tosaku OKUMURA, originator of Asahi yaki, was praised by Taiko (father of the Imperial adviser) Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI and then changed the letters of his name from 藤作 (literally, grower of wisteria) to 陶作 (creator of pottery) both of which remain unchanged in pronunciation.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>後に二代目陶作の頃、小堀遠江守政一（小堀遠州）が朝日焼を庇護、そして指導したため、名を一躍高めることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Subsequently, the second generation Tosaku (陶作) has boosted reputation of Asahi yaki under protection and guidance of Kobori Totominokami Masaichi (Kobori Enshu.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently, the second generation Tosaku (陶作) has boosted the reputation of Asahi yaki under the protection and guidance of Kobori Totominokami Masaichi (Kobori Enshu.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently, the second generation Tosaku has boosted the reputation of Asahi yaki under the protection and guidance of Totoumi no kami (the Governor of Totoumi Province), Masaichi KOBORI (also known as Enshu KOBORI).</e>
<cmt>補足しました。Totomi →Totoumi に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>同時に遠州は朝日焼の窯場で数多くの名器を生み出している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time, Enshu has created a lot of valuable pottery works at the Asahi yaki kiln.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the same time, Enshu has created a lot of valuable pottery at the Asahi yaki kiln.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the same time, Enshu has created a lot of valuable pottery at the Asahi yaki kiln.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>三代目陶作の頃になると、茶の湯が一般武士から堂上、公家、町衆に広まっていき、宇治茶栽培もますます盛んになり、宇治茶は高値で取引されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the era of the third generation Tosaku (陶作,) when customs of tea ceremony spreaded widely from general warrior class to donoue (high rank couriers,) and kuge (court nobles) classes and also to townsmen, plantation of Uji cha (Uji tea) became increasingly productive and Uji cha was traded at high prices.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the era of third generation Tosaku (陶作,) when the custom of tea ceremony spread widely from the general warrior class to donoue (high rank couriers,) and kuge (court nobles) classes and also to the townsmen, Uji cha (Uji tea) plantations became increasingly productive and Uji cha was traded at high prices.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the period of third generation Tosaku, when the custom of tea ceremony spread widely from the general warrior class to donoue (high rank couriers), and kuge (court nobles) classes and also to the townsmen, Uji cha plantations became increasingly productive and Uji cha was traded at high prices.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>それに並行して朝日焼も隆盛を極め、宇治茶の志向に合わせて、高級な茶器を中心に焼かれるようになっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In parallel with such trend of Uji cha (Uji tea), Asahi yaki reached a new height of prosperity by producing high class utensils for tea ceremony.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In parallel with this Uji cha (Uji tea) trend, Asahi yaki reached a new height of prosperity by producing high class utensils for tea ceremony.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In parallel with this, Asahi yaki reached a new height of prosperity by producing high class utensils for tea ceremony according with the trend of Uji cha.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>朝日焼の特徴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Features of Asahi yaki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Features of Asahi yaki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Features of Asahi Yaki</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>朝日焼は原料の粘土に鉄分を含むため、焼成すると独特の赤い斑点が現れるのが最大の特徴である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The most distinctive feature of Asahi yaki is its typical red spots which appear by calcination of ferruginous material clay.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The most distinctive feature of Asahi yaki are its typical red spots that appear by calcination of ferruginous material clay.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The most distinctive feature of Asahi yaki are its typical red spots that appear by calcination of ferruginous material clay.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>そして、それぞれの特徴によって呼び名が決まっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Depending on how the red spots appear, there are different names.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Depending on how the red spots appear, there are different names.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Depending on how the red spots appear, there are different names.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="16">
<j>燔師（はんし）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hanshi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hanshi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hanshi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>分かりやすく解釈すると、師匠が焼いた物という意味である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Hanshi&quot; is the name given to what a master has created, to give an easily understandable explanation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Hanshi&quot; is the name given to what a master has created, to give an easily understandable explanation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is the name given to what a master has created, to give an easily understandable explanation.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>赤い粗めの斑点がぽつぽつと表面に浮き出たような器をいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This term refers to such potteries as have red rough spots standing out on the surface.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This term refers to pottery that have rough red spots standing out on the surface.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This term refers to pottery that have rough red spots standing out on the surface.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="19">
<j>鹿背（かせ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kase (literally, deer&apos;s back)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kase (literally, deer&apos;s back)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kase (literally, deer&apos;s back)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>燔師とは対照的に、肌理細かな斑点が見られる器をいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In contrast to Hanshi, &quot;Kase&quot; means potteries having a texture of fine spots on the surface.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In contrast to Hanshi, &quot;Kase&quot; means pottery that have a texture of fine spots on the surface.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In contrast to Hanshi, it means pottery that have a texture of fine spots on the surface.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>シカの背中のような模様から名付けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This name originates from the patterns similar to deer&apos;s back.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This name originates from patterns similar those found on a deer&apos;s back.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This name originates from patterns similar those found on a deer&apos;s back.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="22">
<j>紅鹿背（べにかせ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Beni kase (literally, pink deer&apos;s back)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Beni kase (literally, pink deer&apos;s back)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Beni kase (literally, pink deer&apos;s back)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>鹿背の中でも、特に鉄分が多く、よりくっきりと紅色が見えるものを指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among various potteries with kase patterns, such earthware as with more clearly red colored spots caused from particularly abundant iron is called &quot;Beni kase.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Pottery with kase patterns, such as earthware containing clear red spots caused from particularly abundant iron present in the clay is called &quot;Beni kase.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It indicates pottery with kase patterns, such as earthenware containing clear red spots caused from particularly abundant iron present in the.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Zenzai-Doji(id:98967), 表現等規制委員会(id:61918), Ray go(id:51282), Fortuna(id:30522), やきとり(id:126941), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>