<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>石橋 (能)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shakkyo (Stone Bridge, Noh [Japanese classical dance-drama] Play)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shakkyo (Stone Bridge) (Noh play)</e>
<cmt>能の説明をタイトルから次文に移しました。タイトルの一部ではないPlayを小文字にしました。ShakkyoとNoh playを分けました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shakkyo (Stone Bridge) (Noh play)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>『石橋』 (しゃっきょう) は能の作品の一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Shakkyo&quot; is one of noh plays.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Shakkyo&quot; is a Noh play (classical Japanese dance theater).</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。説明文を追加しました。説明文は英語版wikipediaのNohより引用しました。英語版wikipediaと同じくNohは大文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Shakkyo&quot; is a Noh play (classical Japanese dance theater).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>獅子口（獅子の顔をした能面）をつけた能シテの豪壮な能舞が見物である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Splendid Nomai (noh dance) of Noh Shite (a main actor of a noh play) wearing Shishiguchi (a noh mask with the face of shishi [a lion]) is the thing to see.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。Wikipediaの元ページでは「能シテ」でなく「後シテ」になっていますが、「能シテ」として訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The visual highlight is a splendid Nomai (Noh dance) performed by the Noshite (starring Noh actor) wearing a shishiguchi (Noh mask with the face of a lion).</e>
<cmt>英語版wikipediaと同じくNohは大文字にしました。自然な表現にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The visual highlight is a splendid Nomai (Noh dance) performed by the Noshite (starring Noh actor) wearing a shishiguchi (Noh mask with the face of a lion).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>能囃子の緊迫感と迫力を兼ね備えた秘曲が聞き物である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Secret music having both a feeling of high tension and an impact of Noh Hayashi (percussion ensemble) is the thing to hear.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The esoteric music of the Noh Hayashi (percussion ensemble), full of thrill and strength, is the acoustic highlight.</e>
<cmt>自然な表現にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The esoteric music of the Noh Hayashi (percussion ensemble), full of thrill and strength, is the acoustic highlight.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>なお後段の獅子の舞については古くは唐楽に由来する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The dance of shishi in godan (the latter part) was originally derived from Togaku (music of Tang).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The lion dance in the latter part is originally derived from Togaku (music from Tang dynasty China).</e>
<cmt>自然な表現にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The lion dance in the latter part is originally derived from Togaku (music from Tang dynasty China).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>世阿弥の時代には、猿楽や田楽にとりいれられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was adopted in sarugaku (form of theatre popular in Japan during the 11th to 14th centuries) and dengaku (a style of dancing and music performed in shrines and temples or in association with rice planting) by the time of Zeami.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During Zeami&apos;s (renowned Noh writer) time, it had been adopted in Sarugaku (form of theater popular during the 11th to 14th centuries) and Dengaku (style of dancing associated with rice planting rituals).</e>
<cmt>アメリカ英語の綴りに修正しました。自然な表現にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During Zeami&apos;s (renowned Noh writer) time, it had been adopted in Sarugaku (form of theater popular during the 11th to 14th centuries) and Dengaku (style of dancing associated with rice planting rituals).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Synopsis</e>
<cmt>意訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Synopsis</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>仏跡を訪ね歩いた寂昭法師（能ワキ）は、中国の清涼山の麓へと辿り着いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jakusho Hoshi (Buddhist monk), Noh Waki (a supporting actor), finally arrived at the foot of Mt. Qingliang in China after visiting historic Buddhist sites.</e>
<cmt>Wikipediaの元ページでは「能ワキ」でなく「ワキ」になっていますが、「能ワキ」として訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After visiting historic Buddhist sites, the Buddhist monk Jakusho Hoshi (supporting role) arrives at the foot of Mt. Qingliang in China.</e>
<cmt>訳し直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After visiting historic Buddhist sites, the Buddhist monk Jakusho Hoshi (supporting role) arrives at the foot of Mt. Qingliang in China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>まさに仙境である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is indeed Senkyo (the enchanted land).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is truly an enchanted land.</e>
<cmt>必要ないローマ字表記を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is truly an enchanted land.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>更に、ここから山の中へは細く長い石橋がかかっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, a narrow and long stone bridge crosses from there into the mountain.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, a long and narrow stone bridge crosses into the mountain.</e>
<cmt>自然な表現にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, a long and narrow stone bridge crosses into the mountain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>その先は文殊菩薩の浄土であるという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Pure Land of Monju Bosatsu (Manjusri) is said to be ahead of the bridge.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was said that the PureLland of Monju Bosatsu (Manjusri) was on the other side of the bridge.</e>
<cmt>自然な表現にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was said that the PureLland of Monju Bosatsu (Manjusri) was on the other side of the bridge.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>法師は意を決し橋を渡ろうとする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hoshi makes up his mind and begins to cross the bridge.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The priest makes up his mind and begins to cross the bridge.</e>
<cmt>Hoshiをpriestにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The priest makes up his mind and begins to cross the bridge.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>だが、そこに現われた樵（前シテ）は、尋常な修行では渡る事は無理だから止めておくように諭し、暫く橋のたもとで待つがよいと言い残して消える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But then kikori (a woodcutter), Mae-Shite (the leading role in the first half of a noh play), appears and admonishes him to stop crossing because it is impossible to cross with ordinary ascetic practices, and disappears after telling him that he had better wait a moment at the foot of the bridge.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But then a woodcutter (lead role of the first half of the play) appears and warns him to stop crossing because it would be impossible to reach the other side with ordinary ascetic practices, and disappears after telling him that he had better wait a while at the foot of the bridge.</e>
<cmt>Kikoriをそのままwoodcutterにしました。Mae-Shiteを削除し、説明を変えました。「渡る」をreach the other sideと意訳しました。Momentをa whileにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But then a woodcutter (lead role of the first half of the play) appears and warns him to stop crossing because it would be impossible to reach the other side with ordinary ascetic practices, and disappears after telling him that he had better wait a while at the foot of the bridge.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>ここまでが前段である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is the first part.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This concludes the first half.</e>
<cmt>訳し直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This concludes the first half.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>中入に後見によって、舞台正面に一畳台と牡丹が据えられ、後段がはじまる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ichijo-dai (a platform the size of one tatami [a floor covering made of tightly woven grass and straw]) and peonies are placed in front of the stage by kouken (a supporter of a noh play) during the intermission, and then godan starts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An ichijo-dai (platform the size of a tatami mat) and peonies are placed in front of the stage by stagehands during the intermission and the second half starts.</e>
<cmt>冠詞を追加しました。畳の説明を削除しました。Koukenをstagehandsにしました。Godanをsecond halfにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An ichijo-dai (platform the size of a tatami mat) and peonies are placed in front of the stage by stagehands during the intermission and the second half starts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>「乱序」という緊迫感溢れる特殊な囃子を打ち破るように獅子（後シテ）が躍り出る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shishi, Nochi-Shite (the leading role in the latter half of a noh play), leaps onto the stage as if to smash &apos;ranjo (swinging part of noh performance)&apos;, which is a special hayashi (musical accompaniment played on traditional Japanese instruments) bursting with a very tense atmosphere.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A lion (lead role of the second half of the play) leaps out dancing, as if to smash through the &apos;ranjo,&apos; dynamic hayashi music specifically arranged for lion dances.</e>
<cmt>訳し直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A lion (lead role of the second half of the play) leaps out dancing, as if to smash through the &apos;ranjo,&apos; dynamic hayashi music specifically arranged for lion dances.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>法師の目の前で舞台狭しと勇壮な舞を披露するのだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He displays a brave dance in front of hoshi&apos;s eyes using all over the stage.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The lion uses up all the space available to it to perform a valiant dance right in front of the priest.</e>
<cmt>訳し直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The lion uses up all the space available to it to perform a valiant dance right in front of the priest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>これこそ文殊菩薩の霊験である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is a miracle of Monju Bosatsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is the miracle of Monju Bosatsu.</e>
<cmt>冠詞を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is the miracle of Monju Bosatsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="17">
<j>小書（特殊演出）によっては、獅子が二体になることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sometimes two shishi are employed depending on Kogaki (special staging).</e>
<cmt>shishiは日本語の単語なので、複数でもsは付けませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sometimes there are two lions, depending on the kogaki (special staging).</e>
<cmt>two shishi are employedをthere are two lionsにしました。冠詞を追加しました。Kogakiを小文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sometimes there are two lions, depending on the kogaki (special staging).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>この場合、頭の白い獅子と赤い獅子が現われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In that case, shishi with the white head and shishi with the red head appear.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In such cases, one lion is white while the other is red.</e>
<cmt>自然な表現にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In such cases, one lion is white while the other is red.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>前者は荘重に、後者は活発に動くのがならいである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the custom, the former moves solemnly and the latter actively.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to custom, the former moves solemnly and the latter actively.</e>
<cmt>冠詞を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to custom, the former moves solemnly and the latter actively.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>前段を省略した半能として演じられることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is often played as Han-noh in which the first part is omitted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The play is often performed as a han-Noh (half Noh), with the first half omitted.</e>
<cmt>Playedをperformedにしました。Han-nohの説明を追加しました。自然な表現にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The play is often performed as a han-Noh (half Noh), with the first half omitted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>まことに目出度い、代表的な切能である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is quite auspicious and foremost Kirinoh (the last noh play at a day).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is very auspicious, and one of the most famous Kirinoh (last Noh play of the day).</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is very auspicious, and one of the most famous Kirinoh (last Noh play of the day).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>関連作品</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Related Works</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Related Works</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Related Works</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="22">
<j>石橋は歌舞伎にも取入れられ、石橋物と呼ばれる作品群を形成するに至っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shakkyo is also introduced to kabuki (traditional drama performed by male actors) to form a group of works called Shakkyomono (lion dances based on the Shakkyo legend).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shakkyo has also been incorporated into kabuki (traditional drama performed by male actors) to form a group of works called Shakkyomono (lion dances based on the Shakkyo legend).</e>
<cmt>時制を修正しました。Introducedをincorporatedにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shakkyo has also been incorporated into kabuki (traditional drama performed by male actors) to form a group of works called Shakkyomono (lion dances based on the Shakkyo legend).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>演目としては、『石橋 (歌舞伎)』（初期の作品でごく短いもの）・『相生獅子』（二人で獅子の舞を見せる華やかなもの）・『連獅子』（獅子の組合わせを親子に設定し物語性を持たせたもの）等多数。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are many programs including &quot;Shakkyo (kabuki)&quot; (an early work with short performance time), &quot;Aioi-jishi&quot; (a gorgeous work with the dance of shishi showed by two actors) and &quot;Renjishi (a string of lions)&quot; (the pair of shishi is assumed to be a parent and a child to add narrativity).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are many works, including &quot;Shakkyo (kabuki)&quot; (a short piece of work from the early period), &quot;Aioi-jishi&quot; (a gorgeous work with a lion dance performed by two actors) and &quot;Renjishi (a string of lions)&quot; (story features parent and child lions and places more emphasis on plot).</e>
<cmt>自然な表現にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are many works, including &quot;Shakkyo (kabuki)&quot; (a short piece of work from the early period), &quot;Aioi-jishi&quot; (a gorgeous work with a lion dance performed by two actors) and &quot;Renjishi (a string of lions)&quot; (story features parent and child lions and places more emphasis on plot).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>いずれも牡丹の前で獅子の舞を見せる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">All of these have the dance of shishi displayed in front of peonies.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They all feature lion dances performed in front of peonies.</e>
<cmt>訳し直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They all feature lion dances performed in front of peonies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>連獅子では間狂言を挟むなど大作となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Renjishi is a voluminous work with ai kyogen (comic interlude in noh) inserted.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Renjishi has become a massive piece of work including ai kyogen (comic interludes).</e>
<cmt>訳し直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Renjishi has become a massive piece of work including ai kyogen (comic interludes).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 赤井彗星(id:18381), ととりん(id:31982), Miya(id:1881), R28Bot(id:177951), ささがに(id:228586), NekoJaNekoJa(id:23311), Peachkiller(id:99202), Toki-ho(id:10691), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>