<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>上方歌</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kamigata Uta&quot; (A Song in &quot;Kamigata&quot; [Kyoto-Osaka Area], Accompanied With &quot;Shamisen&quot; [The Three-Stringed Japanese Banjo])</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kamigata Uta</e>
<cmt>タイトルなので&quot; &quot;削除しました。説明訳括弧を削除し、次行に補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kamigata Uta</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>上方歌（かみがたうた）は、「上方唄」とも、「上方端唄（歌）」とも呼ばれる京阪都市部の三味線音楽である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kamigata uta&quot; (also called &quot;Kamigata hauta&quot;) is the song with shamisen accompaniment, performed and enjoyed in urban areas of Kyoto and Osaka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kamigata uta&quot; (also called &quot;Kamigata hauta&quot;) is the songs with shamisen (the three-stringed Japanese banjo) accompaniment, performed and enjoyed in Kamigata (Kyoto-Osaka area).</e>
<cmt>説明訳を補足しました。songsに訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Kamigata uta&quot; (also called &quot;Kamigata hauta&quot;) is the songs with shamisen (the three-stringed Japanese banjo) accompaniment, performed and enjoyed in Kamigata (Kyoto-Osaka area).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>上方歌は「地歌」の別称としても使われる（特に江戸その他の地域から見ての呼称）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kamigata uta&quot; has been used as another name of &quot;jiuta&quot; (a genre of traditional songs accompanied with shamisen), especially in places other than Kamigata, such as &quot;Edo&quot; (Tokyo area).</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処　・江戸時代から今日まで「使われてきた」ものと推測されるので現在完了形にしています。　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　・「地歌」は文字どおりには「地元の歌」という意味ですが、これは上方の人々が自ら称しているわけで、他の地域から見ると「地元の歌」ではないので「上方歌」と称する、ということのようです。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term Kamigata uta has been used as another name of &apos;jiuta&apos; (a genre of traditional songs accompanied with shamisen), especially in places other than Kamigata, such as Edo (Tokyo area).</e>
<cmt>原文に合せて&quot; &quot;を削除しました。The term補足しました。原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term Kamigata uta has been used as another name of &apos;jiuta&apos; (a genre of traditional songs accompanied with shamisen), especially in places other than Kamigata, such as Edo (Tokyo area).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>地歌の「端歌（唄）もの」の別称として「上方端唄」があてられることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In some cases, &quot;Kamigata hauta&quot; has been used as another name of &quot;hauta mono&quot; (Japanese short ballads accompanied with shamisen) which belongs to jiuta.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In some cases, &apos;Kamigata hauta&apos; has been used as another name of &apos;hauta mono&apos; (Japanese short ballads accompanied with shamisen) which belongs to jiuta.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In some cases, &apos;Kamigata hauta&apos; has been used as another name of &apos;hauta mono&apos; (Japanese short ballads accompanied with shamisen) which belongs to jiuta.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>しかし、特に上方舞の世界や関西の一部の地歌箏曲の世界で使われるこの名称がさすものはそれとは少し異なるジャンルの音楽のようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kamigata uta&quot; has also been used in the world of &quot;Kamigata mai&quot; (dances born in the pleasure quarters of Kamigata) and in some parts of the world of &quot;jiuta sokyoku&quot; (songs accompanied with shamisen and &quot;koto&quot; [the long Japanese zither with thirteen strings]), but this &quot;Kamigata uta&quot; seems to be a little different from the above-mentioned &quot;Kamigata uta.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kamigata uta has also been used in the world of &quot;Kamigata mai&quot; (dances born in the pleasure quarters of Kamigata) and in some parts of the world of &quot;jiuta sokyoku&quot; (songs accompanied with shamisen and koto [the long Japanese zither with 13 strings]), but this Kamigata uta seems to be a little different from the above-mentioned &quot;Kamigata uta.&quot;</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を削除しました。数字に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kamigata uta has also been used in the world of &quot;Kamigata mai&quot; (dances born in the pleasure quarters of Kamigata) and in some parts of the world of &quot;jiuta sokyoku&quot; (songs accompanied with shamisen and koto [the long Japanese zither with 13 strings]), but this Kamigata uta seems to be a little different from the above-mentioned &quot;Kamigata uta.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>厳密に区別するのは難しいが、地歌の「端歌もの」同様、江戸時代以降花街や民衆の間で流行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kamigata uta has been, like hauta mono in jiuta, popular in geisha quarters and in the public from the Edo period, but many Kamigata uta seem to have more rhythmical melody and more cheerful lyrics than hauta mono in jiuta, though it is difficult to make a strict distinction between the two..</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kamigata uta has been popular like hauta mono of jiuta in geisha quarters and in the public from the Edo period though it is difficult to make a strict distinction between the two.</e>
<cmt>不要なピリオドを削除しました。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kamigata uta has been popular like hauta mono of jiuta in geisha quarters and in the public from the Edo period though it is difficult to make a strict distinction between the two.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>上方歌は、地歌の「端歌もの」と比較してテンポ・歌詞の内容が軽快で明るい曲調のものが多い傾向にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many Kamigata uta seem to have more rhythmical melody and more cheerful lyrics than hauta mono in jiuta.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many Kamigata uta seem to have more rhythmical melody and more cheerful lyrics than hauta mono in jiuta.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>地方（主に上方に近い地域）の民謡などの中から花柳界の座敷等で好まれたものも上方歌には含まれるようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kamigata uta seems to include some &quot;minyo&quot; (traditional Japanese songs), originally enjoyed in local areas (mainly those near Kamigata) and picked up and loved by people, including those in the quarters of geisha.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kamigata uta seems to include some minyo (traditional Japanese songs), originally enjoyed in local areas (mainly those near Kamigata) and picked up and loved by people, including those in the quarters of geisha.</e>
<cmt>原文に合せて&quot; &quot;削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kamigata uta seems to include some minyo (traditional Japanese songs), originally enjoyed in local areas (mainly those near Kamigata) and picked up and loved by people, including those in the quarters of geisha.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>上方舞の世界でも好んで伴奏に舞われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kamigata uta has also been in favor with the world of Kamigata mai as the dance accompaniment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kamigata uta has also been in favor with the world of Kamigata mai as the dance accompaniment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kamigata uta has also been in favor with the world of Kamigata mai as the dance accompaniment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>また、一部が江戸に上り、端唄（いわゆる「江戸端唄」）、小唄、うた沢、俗曲の曲の一部となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And some Kamigata uta were introduced into Edo, and became a part of the Edo music repertoire, that is, &quot;hauta&quot; (so called &quot;Edo hauta&quot;), &quot;kouta&quot; (a Japanese ballad accompanied with shamisen), &quot;utazawa&quot; (popular ballads), and &quot;zokkyoku&quot; (folk songs).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And some Kamigata uta were introduced into Edo, and became a part of the Edo music repertoire, that is, hauta (so called &quot;Edo hauta&quot;), kouta (a Japanese ballad accompanied with shamisen), utazawa (popular ballads), and zokkyoku (folk songs).</e>
<cmt>原文に合せて&quot; &quot;削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And some Kamigata uta were introduced into Edo, and became a part of the Edo music repertoire, that is, hauta (so called &quot;Edo hauta&quot;), kouta (a Japanese ballad accompanied with shamisen), utazawa (popular ballads), and zokkyoku (folk songs).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>京の花街や大阪の花街の花柳界、上方舞の世界の地方（じかた）を務める人々によって伝承されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kamigata uta has been handed down by people in the world of geisha of Kamigata, and by &quot;jikata&quot; (people in charge of music) in the world of Kamigata mai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kamigata uta has been handed down by people in the world of geisha of Kamigata, and by jikata (people in charge of music) in the world of Kamigata mai.</e>
<cmt>原文に合せて&quot; &quot;削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kamigata uta has been handed down by people in the world of geisha of Kamigata, and by jikata (people in charge of music) in the world of Kamigata mai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Spadaforte(id:154325), Mymelo(id:122034), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>