<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>丸帯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Maruobi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Maruobi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Maruobi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>丸帯（まるおび）とは日本で使われる女帯の一種。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Maruobi is a kind of onna-obi (a broad sash for a female) that is used in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Maruobi&quot; is a kind of women&apos;s obi (sash) used in Japan.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Maruobi&quot; is a kind of women&apos;s obi (sash) used in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>幅の広い（約68センチ）一枚の布地を半分に折って仕立てたもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is made through the process of folding a broad textile (about 68 cm) in half and sewing it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is made by folding a broad textile (about 68 cm) into half and sewing it.</e>
<cmt>through the process of をby に修正しました。in を into に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is made by folding a broad textile (about 68 cm) into half and sewing it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="3">
<j>礼装用に用いるが、帆布の帯芯を入れて布を折りたたむため重くて扱いにくい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is used for formal dress, but it is heavy and hard to handle because it is made of folded textile with obishin (padding of obi) inside.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is used for formal dress, but it is heavy and hard to handle because the cloth is folded with putting an obishin (padding of obi) made of sail cloth inside.</e>
<cmt>because 以下を全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is used for formal dress, but it is heavy and hard to handle because it is folded with an obishin (obi padding, which is made of sail cloth) placed inside it.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせて修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>このため、現在はほとんど廃れて、芸者、舞妓、等の花柳界や、婚礼衣装ぐらいにしか使われない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, it is seldom used at present other than by the people of karyukai (geisha world), such as geisha and maiko (apprentice geisha), or for bridal dress.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, it is seldom used at present other than by the people of karyukai (world of the geisha), such as geisha and maiko (apprentice geisha), or for bridal dress.</e>
<cmt>geisha world を world of the geisha に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, it is seldom used at present other than by the people of karyukai (world of the geisha), such as geisha and maiko (apprentice geisha), or for bridal dress.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 BitBucket(id:30999), こぶまき(id:38278), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>