<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>金平糖</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kompeito (confetti)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Konpeito (confetti)</e>
<cmt>Kompeito→Konpeito すべてこの表記に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Konpeito (confetti)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>金平糖（こんぺいとう，コンペイトー）は、砂糖と下味のついた水分で作られる、表面に凹凸状の突起（角状）をもつ小球形の菓子である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kompeito is small ball shaped candy with horn-like prongs on the surface made from sugar and flavored liquids.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Konpeito is small ball-shaped candy with horn-like prongs on the surface made from sugar and flavored liquids.</e>
<cmt>ball shaped→ball-shaped</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Konpeito is small ball-shaped candy with horn-like prongs on the surface made from sugar and flavored liquids.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>金米糖、金餅糖、糖花とも表記される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also written as kompeito in kanji characters delineating the golden rice candy, golden cake candy and flower candy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Konpeito is written in kanji characters such as: &quot;金米糖&quot; (golden rice candy), &quot;金餅糖&quot; (golden cake candy) and &quot;糖花&quot; (flower candy).</e>
<cmt>文頭を変更しました。漢字表記を記載。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Konpeito is written in kanji characters such as: &quot;金米糖&quot; (golden rice candy), &quot;金餅糖&quot; (golden cake candy) and &quot;糖花&quot; (flower candy).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>語源はポルトガル語のコンフェイト (confeito) である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The etymology of kompeito is the Portuguese word confeito.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The origin of konpeito is the Portuguese word confeito.</e>
<cmt>ethymology→origin</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The origin of konpeito is the Portuguese word confeito.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>初めて日本に金平糖が伝わった時期については諸説あるが、1550年にカステラ・有平糖などとともに南蛮菓子として伝えられたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are various opinions as to when kompeito was first introduced into Japan but it is considered that, kompeito, along with other Nanbangashi (Portuguese and Spanish confectioneries) such as kasutera sponge cake and aruheito (toffee), was introduced into Japan in 1550.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are various opinions as to when konpeito was first introduced into Japan but it is considered that, konpeito, along with other Nanbangashi (Portuguese and Spanish confectioneries) such as kasutera sponge cake and aruheito (toffee), was introduced into Japan in 1550.</e>
<cmt>文頭のスペース削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are various opinions as to when konpeito was first introduced to Japan but it is considered that, konpeito, along with other Nanbangashi (Portuguese and Spanish confectioneries) such as kasutera sponge cake and aruheito (toffee), was introduced to Japan in 1550.</e>
<cmt>into→to</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>（詳しくは南蛮菓子の項を参照のこと）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(See the chapter for Nanbangashi (Portuguese and Spanish confectioneries) for more details.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(See the section of Nanbangashi for more details.)</e>
<cmt>南蛮菓子の説明削除chapter for→section of</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(See the section of Nanbangashi for more details.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>この特徴的な突起がなぜ、またいくつ形成されるのかについてはまだ定説がないが、蔵本・シバンスキー式 (Kuramoto-Sivashinsky Equation) によって定式化が試みられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is no established explanation as to why and how many of these distinct prongs exist but there has been an attempt to establish a formula based on the Kuramoto-Sivashinsky Equation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is no established explanation as to why and how many of these characteristic prongs exist but there has been an attempt to establish a formula based on the Kuramoto-Sivashinsky Equation.</e>
<cmt>distinct→characteristic</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is no established explanation as to why and how many of these characteristic prongs exist but there has been an attempt to establish a formula based on the Kuramoto-Sivashinsky Equation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>正式な金平糖の突起の数は24個である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The formal number of prongs of kompeito is 24.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The formal number of prongs of kompeito is 24.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The formal number of prongs of kompeito is 24.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>製法</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Recipe</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Recipe</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Recipe</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>作り方は以下の通り。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The recipe for kompeito is as follows:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The recipe for kompeito is as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The recipe for kompeito is as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="10">
<j>氷砂糖に水を加えて煮詰め、蜜をつくる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Make syrup by simmering rock sugar and water in a pan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Make syrup by simmering rock sugar and water in a pan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Make syrup by simmering rock sugar and water in a pan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="11">
<j>回転鍋（その形から銅鑼と呼ばれる）を熱しながら、金平糖の核となるケシ粒（現在はザラメ糖が用いられることが多い）を入れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While keeping the rotating pan (referred to as dora, the Chinese gong after its shape) over a flame, add poppy seeds, which are often substituted by granulated sugar at present, that will become the core of kompeito.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While keeping the rotating pan (referred to as dora, the Chinese gong after its shape) over a flame, add poppy seeds, which are often substituted by granulated sugar at present, that will become the core of konpeito.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While keeping the rotating pan (referred to as dora, the Chinese gong after its shape) over a flame, add poppy seeds, which are often substituted by granulated sugar at present, that will become the core of konpeito.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="12">
<j>ケシ粒に熱い蜜を少量ずつかけ、回転させながら目的の大きさと凹凸状の突起ができあがるまで、1週間から2週間以上の時間をかけて粒をゆっくり成長させていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the rotating pan in constant motion, shower small amount of hot syrup over poppy seeds and slowly repeat the process for 1 to over 2 weeks until kompeito has grown to the desirable size and the prongs have been formed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With rotating the pan in constant motion, shower small amount of hot syrup over poppy seeds and slowly repeat the process for over 1 to 2 weeks until konpeito has grown to the desirable size and the prongs have been formed.</e>
<cmt>With the rotating →With rotating the</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With rotating the pan in constant motion, shower small amount of hot syrup over poppy seeds and slowly repeat the process for over 1 to 2 weeks until konpeito has grown to the desirable size and the prongs have been formed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="13">
<j>現在では、色付きやさまざまな味が付いたものも作られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today, kompeito is available in various colors and flavors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, kompeito is available in various colors and flavors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, kompeito is available in various colors and flavors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="14">
<j>菓子以外の利用方法</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kompeito as other than candy</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The use of Konpeito other than candy</e>
<cmt>rewritten</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The use of Konpeito other than candy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="15">
<j>非常食の乾パンの缶には、氷砂糖とともに、しばしば同梱されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kompeito, along with rock sugar, often comes with dry biscuits in a tin as emergency provisions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Konpeito, along with rock sugar, is often packed in a tin of sea biscuits as emergency provisions.</e>
<cmt>訳文では金平糖に乾パンが付いている意になるため、訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Konpeito, along with rock sugar, is often packed in a tin of sea biscuits as emergency provisions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>これは活動に必要なカロリー摂取と、乾パンを食べやすくするために唾液の分泌を促進する効果のためである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kompeito, included in the emergency food package with dry biscuit, provides calories necessary for physical work and is effective in encouraging salivation to moisten dry biscuits making them easier to ingest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Konpeito, included in the emergency food package, provides calories necessary for physical work as well as effective in encouraging salivation to moisten sea biscuits when eating in which it would be easier to ingest.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Konpeito, included in the emergency food package, provides calories necessary for physical work as well as effective in encouraging salivation to moisten sea biscuits when eating in which it would be easier to ingest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>また、カラフルで楽しげな金平糖を配する事により、非常食が必要と成るような災害時に被るであろうストレス (生体)を軽減させる効果が期待されてるためである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, it is expected that the colorful and delightful looking kompeito will have an effect of reducing the stress response that people may suffer in a time of disaster when emergency food is needed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, it is expected that the colorful and delightful looking kompeito will have an effect of reducing the stress response that people may suffer in a time of disaster when emergency food is needed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, it is expected that the colorful and delightful looking kompeito will have an effect of reducing the stress response that people may suffer in a time of disaster when emergency food is needed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>同様の理由により、自衛隊の戦闘糧食（レーション）にもこれを含むメニューが見受けられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The menu including kompeito is found in the ration used by Japan Self-Defense Forces for the similar reason.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The menu including konpeito is found in the ration used by the Japan Self-Defense Forces for the similar reason.</e>
<cmt>by→by the</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The menu including konpeito is found in the ration used by the Japan Self-Defense Forces for the similar reason.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="19">
<j>主成分がグラニュー糖であるため、喫茶店などではコーヒーや紅茶用の砂糖の代用としても使用されることがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the main component of kompeito being granulated sugar, it sometimes substitutes sugar for coffee and tea at coffee shops in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the main component of konpeito being granulated sugar, it sometimes substitutes sugar for coffee and tea at coffee shops.</e>
<cmt>in Japan 原文にもないし、不要と考え削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the main component of konpeito being granulated sugar, it sometimes substitutes sugar for coffee and tea at coffee shops.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="20">
<j>皇室の引出物として利用されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kompeito has been used as party favors or commemorative gifts for various occasions by the Imperial Family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Konpeito has been used as party favors or commemorative gifts for various occasions by the Imperial Family.</e>
<cmt>gifts の後のスペース短縮</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Konpeito has been used as party favors or commemorative gifts for various occasions by the Imperial Family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>これは引出物にボンボニエール（菓子器）が供される際に、中がカラだと体裁が悪いとして、日持ちの長さを買われて採用された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When bonbonniere (small candy box) is used as a gift, it is filled with kompeito to make it look more attractive.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When a bonbonniere (small candy box) is used as a gift, it is filled with konpeito to make it look more attractive.</e>
<cmt>bonbonniere→a bonbonniere</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When a bonbonniere (small candy box) is used as a gift, it is filled with konpeito to make it look more attractive.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="22">
<j>この小さく奇妙な形の菓子は、様々な色に着色可能であることから、その大きさに関わらず極めて目を引きやすい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since this little strange looking candy can be colored in a wide range of colors, it is quite conspicuous.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since this little strange looking candy can be colored in a wide range of colors, it is quite conspicuous regardless of its size.</e>
<cmt>「その大きさに関わらず」訳漏れ対応。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since this little strange looking candy can be colored in a wide range of colors, it is quite conspicuous regardless of its size.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>加えて高熱で焼き固める事から保存性が良く、湿気さえ気を付ければ20–30年経っても味が変わらないとさえいわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, because kompeito is made by going through the lengthy heating process at high temperatures, it has an exceptional shelf life whereby it is said that, in a dry condition, it will retain its original flavor for 20 to 30 years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further, because kompeito is made by going through the lengthy heating process at high temperatures, it has an exceptional shelf life whereby it is said that, in a dry condition, it will retain its original flavor for 20 to 30 years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further, because kompeito is made by going through the lengthy heating process at high temperatures, it has an exceptional shelf life whereby it is said that, in a dry condition, it will retain its original flavor for 20 to 30 years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>（ただし伝統的製法に拠る物のみで、一般には賞味期限は1年と設定されている。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(The long shelf life, however, is applicable only to that made by the traditional method and, generally, the shelf life for kompeito has been defined as 1 year.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(The long shelf life, however, is applicable only to that made by the traditional method and, generally, the shelf life for konpeito is defined as one year.)</e>
<cmt>has been→is1→one</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(The long shelf life, however, is applicable only to that made by the traditional method and, generally, the shelf life for konpeito is defined as one year.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>喫茶店で客へのサービスとして使用するにせよ、保存性の高さは重要な要素といえよう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If kompeito is used as one of the free items for customers at coffee shops, having good shelf life is an important factor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If konpeito is used as one of the free items for customers at coffee shops, having a long shelf life is an important factor.</e>
<cmt>good→a long</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If konpeito is used as one of the free items for customers at coffee shops, having a long shelf life is an important factor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="26">
<j>なお一般的に飴は夏場などを経て高い室温に晒されたり吸湿すると表面が柔らかくなり、味も損なわれるが、金平糖ではそのようなことはない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When stored at warm room temperatures during summer or if it absorbs moisture, the surface of candy becomes soft and the flavor is compromised in general but that is not the case with kompeito.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When candy is stored in a high room temperature during summer or absorbs moisture, the surface of it becomes soft and it loses flavor in general but that is not the case with konpeito.</e>
<cmt>全体的に書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When candy is stored in a high room temperature during summer or absorbs moisture, the surface of it becomes soft and it loses flavor in general but that is not the case with konpeito.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="27">
<j>発展形</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Product Evolution</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Product Development</e>
<cmt>用語変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Product Development</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>本来砂糖は湿気を嫌う事から、金平糖自体の水分含有量は極めて低くなるように作られているが、近年ではボンボン菓子のように焼酎を含む物も開発・発売されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since sugar has a tolerance for humidity by nature, kompeito is made by the process to ensure extremely low moisture content but, in recent years, the shochu (distilled spirit) injected kompeito has been developed and are available.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since sugar is not tolerant of humidity by nature, konpeito is made by the process to ensure extremely low moisture content but, in recent years, the shochu (distilled spirit) injected konpeito like bonbons has been developed and sold.</e>
<cmt>「ボンボン菓子のように」訳漏れ対応しました。has a tolerance for→is not tolerant ofare available→sold</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since sugar is not tolerant of humidity by nature, konpeito is made by the process to ensure extremely low moisture content but, in recent years, the shochu (distilled spirit) injected konpeito like bonbons has been developed and sold.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>厳密には金平糖とはやや違う菓子となっているが、金平糖が皇室の引出物にも利用されている事で、これにあやかって「おめでたいお菓子」と銘打っている製造元もあり、九州方面の土産物として販売されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Strictly speaking, the shochu-injected variation is somewhat different from kompeito but, because kompeito has been used as party favors and commemorative gifts by the Imperial Family, some manufacturers refer to the shochu-injected variation as an &apos;auspicious confectionery&apos; which is available as a souvenir in the Kyushu area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Strictly speaking, the shochu-injected variation is somewhat different from konpeito but, because konpeito has been used as party favors and commemorative gifts by the Imperial Family, some manufacturers refer to the variation as an &apos;auspicious confectionery,&apos; which is available as a souvenir in the Kyushu area.</e>
<cmt>二度目のshochu-injected　削除 which の前にカンマ</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Strictly speaking, the shochu-injected variation is somewhat different from konpeito but, because konpeito has been used as party favors and commemorative gifts by the Imperial Family, some manufacturers refer to the variation as an &apos;auspicious confectionery,&apos; which is available as a souvenir in the Kyushu area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="30">
<j>他社からもウイスキーや日本酒・梅酒等で風味を付けたものもあり、その他にも色々な風味で変化を持たせた物も存在している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are additional types of kompeito with various flavors including whiskey, Japanese sake, plum wine and the other wide range of flavors that are made by other companies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are additional types of konpeito with various flavors including whiskey, Japanese sake, plum wine and other wide range of flavors that are made by other companies.</e>
<cmt>the 削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are additional types of konpeito with various flavors including whiskey, Japanese sake, plum wine and other wide range of flavors that are made by other companies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="31">
<j>数え歌</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kazoe uta (Counting Song)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kazoe uta (Counting song)</e>
<cmt>Song→song</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kazoe uta (Counting song)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>昔から子供には人気のある菓子で、いわゆる「数え歌」の1番目の品物として登場する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kompeito has been a popular candy with children since long ago which is featured as the first item in the so-called &apos;Counting Song.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Konpeito has been a popular candy for children since long ago and so it is featured as the first item in the so-called &apos;Kazoe uta.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Counting Song→Kazoe uta</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Konpeito has been a popular candy for children since long ago and so it is featured as the first item in the so-called &apos;Kazoe uta.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>金平糖は「甘い」と連想され、それ以降は砂糖・雪・ウサギ・カエル・葉っぱ……と味・色・行動・形状などの要素をもとにした連想が続く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In that song, there is a chain of association starting with the sweet kompeito which is associated with &apos;sweet taste&apos; which reminds one of sweet sugar that melts which relates to melting snow that is white which connects to a white rabbit that hops which leads to a hopping frog that is green which suggests a green leaf and so continues the association of ideas on various elements such as tastes, colors, actions and shapes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In that song, there is a chain of association starting with konpeito which is associated with &apos;sweet taste&apos; which reminds one of sweet sugar that melts which relates to melting snow that is white which connects to a white rabbit that hops which leads to a hopping frog that is green which suggests a green leaf and so continues the association of ideas on various elements such as tastes, colors, actions and shapes.</e>
<cmt>with the sweet→with</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The lyrics to this song are based on a kind of word association starting with konpeito, which is thought of as having the &apos;sweet taste&apos; of sugar, which in turn leads us to think of melting snow (as sugar melts in the mouth), a white rabbit (as snow is white), a hopping frog (as rabbits hop), a green leaf (as frogs are green), and so on, continuing this word association based on various elements such as tastes, colors, actions and shapes.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせて訳文を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Izayohi(id:13095), ととりん(id:31982), Nanaha(id:52897), マクガイア(id:33346), AStarBot(id:245277), Balmung0731(id:99201), ぺいぺい(id:82575), 笹船団子(id:178738), MIO(id:31681), Revth(id:12179), 隼鷹(id:89949), ヨッサン(id:212562), Yatobi(id:9686), ウェルワィ(id:15692), 78(id:10935), Ucheniitza(id:32811), SpBot(id:209743), Fryed-peach(id:63402), Nisiguti(id:534), Rusk(id:9895), 竃馬(id:102733), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), Otoshigo(id:80102), 男の教室(id:62924), Muband(id:11662), MS472(id:58603), 竹麦魚(id:11012), Yas(id:739), Alexbot(id:157199), Corwin(id:973), Louperibot(id:128971), Calvero(id:38360), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>