<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>楽焼</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rakuyaki (Raku ware)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rakuyaki (Raku ware)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rakuyaki (Raku ware)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>楽焼（らくやき）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rakuyaki (Raku ware)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rakuyaki (Raku ware)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rakuyaki (Raku ware)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>日本の伝統的な陶磁器の一種。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is one of the traditional ceramic wares of Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of the traditional ceramic wares of Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of the traditional ceramic wares of Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>本項で詳述する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is detailed in this item.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is detailed as follows:</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is detailed as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>素焼きの陶器に絵付けをする、素人の趣味のための手軽な焼き物。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is an easy amateurs&apos; hobby which is hand-painted on an unglazed pottery.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Created easily by amateurs&apos; as a hobby and the unglazed pottery can be hand-painted.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Created easily by amateurs as a hobby and the unglazed pottery can be hand-painted.</e>
<cmt>amateurs&apos;→amateurs</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>楽焼（らくやき）は、一般的に電動轆轤や足で蹴って回す蹴轆轤（けろくろ）を使用せず手とへらだけで成形する「手捏ね」（てづくね）と呼ばれる方法で成形した後焼成した軟質施釉陶磁器。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rakuyaki is a soft-type glazed ceramic ware burnt after formed generally not by electric potter&apos;s wheel or kerokuro (a kicking potter&apos;s wheel) but only by hand and pallet in the way called tezukune (handmade.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rakuyaki is a soft-type glazed ceramic ware baked after formed not by electric potter&apos;s wheel or kerokuro (a kicking potter&apos;s wheel), but just by the hands with the clay on a pallet called tezukune (handmade.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rakuyaki is a soft-type glazed ceramic ware baked after formed not by an electric potter&apos;s wheel or kerokuro (a kicking potter&apos;s wheel), but just by the hands with the clay on a pallet called tezukune (handmade.)</e>
<cmt>electric→an electric ご確認願います。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>狭義には樂吉左衛門の歴代当主が作製した作品を示し、楽茶碗などとも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In sensu strico, it indicates products by the hand of the successive family heads of Kichizaemon RAKU, and also called as Rakujawan (Raku teacup.) etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In sensu strico, it indicates products made by the hand of the successive family heads of Kichizaemon RAKU, and are also called Rakujawan (Raku teacup.) etc.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In sensu strico, it indicates products made by the hand of the successive family heads of Kichizaemon RAKU, and are also called Rakujawan (Raku teacup.) etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>広義には同様の手法を用いて作製した陶磁器全体を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In sensu lato, entire ceramic wares made by the same way.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In sensu lato, entire ceramic ware sets are made in the same way.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In sensu lato, it indicates entire ceramic ware made in the same way.</e>
<cmt>修正された文は意味が違うと思い、変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>これらには樂家の手法を得た金沢の大樋焼や京都の玉水焼なども含まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This includes Oi-yaki (Oi ware) of Kanazawa and Tamamizu-yaki (Tamamizu ware) of Kyoto, etc. which was learnt from the way of Raku family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This includes Oi-yaki (Oi ware) of Kanazawa and Tamamizu-yaki (Tamamizu ware) of Kyoto, etc. which were learned from the methods of the Raku family.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This includes Oi-yaki (Oi ware) of Kanazawa and Tamamizu-yaki (Tamamizu ware) of Kyoto, etc. which were learned from the methods of the Raku family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>千利休らの嗜好を反映した、歪んで厚みのある形状が特徴である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its characteristic is distorted and thick body of ware which reflected the taste SEN no Rikyu loved.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its characteristics are the distorted and thick body reflecting the taste SEN no Rikyu loved.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its characteristics are the distorted and thick body reflecting the taste SEN no Rikyu loved.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="10">
<j>茶碗や花入、水指、香炉など茶道として使用される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is used as a teacup, hanaire (a vase), mizusashi (a water jug) and koro (an incense burner) in Sado tea ceremony.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is used as a teacup, hanaire (a vase), mizusashi (a water jug) and koro (an incense burner) in the Sado tea ceremony.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is used as a teacup, hanaire (a vase), mizusashi (a water jug) and koro (an incense burner) in the Sado tea ceremony.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="11">
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>天正年間（16世紀後半）、瓦職人だった長次郎が千利休の指導により聚楽第を建造する際に使用された土を使って焼いた「聚楽焼」（じゅらくやき）が始まりとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Rakuyaki began in Tensho years (latter half of the 16th century) when a roof tile artisan Chojiro burnt &apos;Jurakuyaki&apos; fired the soil applied for the construction of Jurakudai villa under the teaching of SEN no Rikyu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Rakuyaki began in the Tensho years (latter half of the 16th century) when a roof tile artisan Chojiro baked &apos;Jurakuyaki&apos; by firing the soil used in the construction of Jurakudai villa under the teaching of SEN no Rikyu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Rakuyaki began in the late 16th century when a roof tile artisan Chojiro baked &apos;Jurakuyaki&apos; by firing the soil used in the construction of Jurakudai villa under the teaching of SEN no Rikyu.</e>
<cmt>天正年間を削除し、１６世紀後半をlate 16th century としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="13">
<j>二代目・楽常慶の父、田中宗慶が豊臣秀吉より聚楽第からとった樂の印章を賜り、これを用いるとともに家号にしたことから楽焼となった、との説が広く知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An opinion is widely known that Sokei TANAKA who was the father of the 2nd head of the family, Jokei RAKU was given a seal engraved a character &apos;Raku&apos; taken from the name of Jurakudai from Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, and he began to use the seal and called his Yago (family name) Raku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An opinion is widely held that Sokei TANAKA who was the father of the 2nd head of the family, Jokei RAKU was given a seal with the engraved character &apos;Raku&apos; taken from the name of Jurakudai from Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, and he began to use the seal and called his Yago (family name) Raku.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An opinion is widely held that Sokei TANAKA who was the father of the second head of the family, Jokei RAKU was given a seal with the engraved character &apos;Raku&apos; taken from the name of Jurakudai from Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, and he began to use the seal and called his Yago (family name) Raku.</e>
<cmt>2nd→second</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="14">
<j>正統な楽家の楽焼を本窯、傍流の楽焼を脇窯という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rakuyaki of the authentic Raku family is called hon-gama (the main kiln), and those made by branches is called waki-gama (non-main kilns.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rakuyaki of the authentic Raku family is called hon-gama (the main kiln), and those made by it&apos;s branches are called waki-gama (non-main kilns.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rakuyaki of the authentic Raku family is called hon-gama (the main kiln), and those made by its branches are called waki-gama (non-main kilns.)</e>
<cmt>it&apos;s→its</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="15">
<j>特徴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Characteristics</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Characteristics</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Characteristics</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>黒楽</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kuroraku (Black Raku)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kuroraku (Black Raku)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kuroraku (Black Raku)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="16">
<j>初期の製法としては、素焼き後に加茂川黒石からつくられた鉄釉をかけて陰干しし、乾いたらまた釉薬をかけるといったことを十数回繰り返してから1000℃程度で焼成する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The process to make a Black Raku at the beginning is to souse tetsuyu (glaze containing iron) made of black stone in Kamo-gawa river on the bisque of work and dry it in the shade, and when it dries, the work is dipped in tetsyu again, and after this process is repeated 10-odd times, then the work is fired at about 1000 degrees Celsius in kiln.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The process to make Black Raku from the beginning is to souse tetsuyu (glaze containing iron) made of black stone in Kamo-gawa river on the bisque of work and then dry it in the shade, and when it dries, the work is dipped into tetsyu again, and after this process is repeated 10-odd times, then the work is fired at about 1000 degrees Celsius in a kiln.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the methos of early days, the process to make Black Raku is to souse tetsuyu (glaze containing iron) made of black stone in Kamo-gawa river on the bisque of work and then dry it in the shade, and when it dries, the work is dipped into tetsuyu again, and after this process is repeated 10-odd times, then the work is fired at about 1000 degrees Celsius in a kiln.</e>
<cmt>「from the biginning」が誤訳ですので訂正しました。tetsyu→tetsuyu</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>焼成中に釉薬が溶けたところを見計らって窯から引き出し急冷することで、黒く変色する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the glaze begins to melt, the work is taken out of the kiln and quickly cooled down, and then the work turns to be black.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the glaze begins to melt, the work is removed from the kiln and is quickly cooled down, and then the work turns black.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the glaze begins to melt, the work is removed from the kiln and is quickly cooled down, and then the work turns black.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>これは美濃焼と共通する手法である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This method is common with Mino-yaki (Mino ceramic ware.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This method is common as with Mino-yaki (Mino ceramic ware.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This method is common as with Mino-yaki (Mino ceramic ware.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="19">
<j>近年では、釉薬に鉛が多く入ってよく光沢のある仕上がりになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These days, lead is contained in the graze and finished work is more brilliant.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These days, lead is contained in the glaze and the finished work is more brilliant.</e>
<cmt>spelling, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These days, more lead is contained in the glaze and the finished work is more brilliant.</e>
<cmt>lead→more lead</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="20">
<j>天正9年（1581年）～同14年（1586年）頃に長次郎によって黒楽茶碗が焼かれたのが始まりである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The beginning of Black Raku was when Chojiro made a Black Raku tea bowl in around 1581 to 1586.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The beginning of Black Raku was when Chojiro made a Black Raku tea bowl around 1581 to 1586.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The beginning of Black Raku was when Chojiro made a Black Raku tea bowl around 1581 to 1586.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>赤楽</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Aka-Raku (Red Raku)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Aka-Raku (Red Raku)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Aka-Raku (Red Raku)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="21">
<j>赤土を素焼きし、透明の釉薬をかけて800℃程度で焼成する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is to biscuit-fire redddish soil and make a work and then souse transparent graze on it and fire it at about 800 degrees Celsius.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is to biscuit-fire reddish clay and create the work and then souse it in a transparent glaze and fire it at about 800 degrees Celsius.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is to biscuit-fire reddish clay and create the work and then souse it in a transparent glaze and fire it at about 800 degrees Celsius.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>樂家と関わりの深い本阿弥光悦や、樂道入の作品などが有名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The products by Koetsu HONAMI who was strongly related with Raku family and Donyu RAKU are famous.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The products by Koetsu HONAMI who was strongly associated with the Raku family and Donyu RAKU are famous.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The products by Koetsu HONAMI who was strongly associated with the Raku family and Donyu RAKU are famous.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 AlleborgoBot(id:119729), 浩(id:70121), Thijs!bot(id:69644), Okapia2(id:98589), Charenji(id:7908), BitBucket(id:30999), FlaBot(id:30804), Nakchipallang(id:71476), SieBot(id:126695), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>