<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>太秦発声映画</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Uzumasa Hassei Eiga</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Uzumasa Hassei Eiga</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Uzumasa Hassei Eiga</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>太秦発聲映畫株式會社（うずまさはっせいえいが-、1933年 設立 - 1936年 製作中止）は、かつて京都に存在した映画会社である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Uzumasa Hassei (a person chanting a first poem with a tune) Eiga (Film) (established 1933-stopped production in 1936) was a film firm that once existed in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Uzumasa Hassei Eiga (established 1933-stopped production in 1936) is a movie company once existed in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Uzumasa Hassei Eiga (established 1933-stopped production in 1936) is a movie company once existed in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>先進的なトーキーシステムを輸入したJ.Oスタヂオの敷地内に設立し、日活との提携で先駆的にトーキー映画を製作、日本映画の新しい時代を切り開いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was established within the compound of J.O. Studio that incorporated talkie (talking picture) system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was established within the site of J.O. Studio which imported advanced talkie system, produced talkie movies in tie-ups with Nikkatsu with a pioneering spirit, and carved out a new era of Japanese films.</e>
<cmt>「日活との提携で先駆的にトーキー映画を製作、日本映画の新しい時代を切り開いた」訳漏れのため、全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Being established within the site of J.O. Studio which imported advanced talkie system, Uzumasa Hassei Eiga produced talkie movies in tie-ups with Nikkatsu before any other film companies, and carved out a new era of Japanese films.</e>
<cmt>It was established→Being establishedwith a pioneering spirit→before any other film companies</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>略歴・概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Brief Personal History and Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Brief History and Summary</e>
<cmt>Personal を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Brief History and Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>1933年（昭和8年）3月、大沢商会グループ（J.Osawa Co., Ltd.）が京都・太秦蚕ノ社駅に貸しスタジオ「J.Oスタヂオ」を建設・開所、同社社長・大沢徳太郎の長男・大沢善夫が輸入したトーキーシステムを導入した先進的なものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">J. Osawa Co., Ltd. built and opened the &apos;J. O. Studio&apos; for rent at Uzumasa Kaiko no Yashiro Station, Kyoto city that used a pioneering talkie system imported by Yoshio OSAWA, who was the eldest son of the CEO of the same company, Tokutaro OSAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">J. Osawa Co., Ltd. built and opened the &apos;J. O. Studio&apos; for rent at Uzumasa Kaiko no Yashiro Station in Kyoto that used a pioneering talkie system imported by Yoshio OSAWA, who was the eldest son of the CEO of the same company, Tokutaro OSAWA.</e>
<cmt>, Kyoto city を in Kyoto に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">J. Osawa Co., Ltd. built and opened the &apos;J. O. Studio&apos; for rent at Uzumasa Kaiko no Yashiro Station in Kyoto that used a pioneering talkie system imported by Yoshio OSAWA, who was the eldest son of the CEO of the same company, Tokutaro OSAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>日活撮影所長を辞任した池永浩久をJ.Oスタヂオの顧問に迎え、池永が同所内に設立したのが、この「太秦発声映画」である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Uzumasa Hassei Eiga&apos; was established within the same compound by Tsunehisa IKENAGA, who was invited as an advisor for J. O. Studio after he quit being the chief of Nikkatsu Studio.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Uzumasa Hassei Eiga&apos; was established within the same compound by Tsunehisa IKENAGA, who was invited as an advisor for J. O. Studio after resigning the chief of Nikkatsu Studio.</e>
<cmt>he quit being を resigning に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Uzumasa Hassei Eiga&apos; was established within the same compound by Tsunehisa IKENAGA, who was invited as an advisor for J. O. Studio after resigning the chief of Nikkatsu Studio.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>設立第1作は、池永総指揮、池田富保監督、早川雪洲主演の『楠正成』で、同作は同年6月1日に公開された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first film after establishment was &quot;Masashige KUSUNOKI&quot; comanded by So IKENAGA, directed by Tomiyasu IKEADA and played by Sesshu HAYAKAWA, and the same work was released to the public on June 1 of the same year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first film after establishment was &quot;Masashige KUSUNOKI&quot; with executive producer So IKENAGA, directed by Tomiyasu IKEADA and starring Sesshu HAYAKAWA, and it was released on June 1 of the same year.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first film after establishment was &quot;Masashige KUSUNOKI&quot; with executive producer So IKENAGA, directed by Tomiyasu IKEADA and starring Sesshu HAYAKAWA, and it was released on June 1 of the same year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>マキノ雅弘がマキノトーキー製作所を設立しトーキーを量産し始める1935年（昭和10年）からは、多く日活と提携製作をした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masahiro MAKINO established the Makino Talking Picture Ltd. and made a massive talkie films from 1935 and collaborated often with Nikkatsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Masahiro MAKINO established the Makino Talkie Seisaku-jo and began mass production of talkie films in 1935, he often collaborated with Nikkatsu.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Masahiro MAKINO established the Makino Talkie Seisaku-jo and began mass production of talkie films in 1935, he often collaborated with Nikkatsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>どの監督もトーキー演出になかなか慣れず、斬新な演出で知られた古海卓二も志波西果もトーキーに敗れ去り、古海は古市の極東映画、志波は奈良の全勝キネマへと都落ちし、サイレント映画に退行してしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, all directors did not become familiar with talkie performance easily, and even Takuji FURUMI and Seika SHIBA famous for performances filled with originality failed in talkie and Furumi returned to Kyoto Eiga Co., Ltd. of Furuichi while Shiba to Zensho Kinema of Nara to retreat to silent films.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, all directors did not become familiar with talkie performance easily, and even Takuji FURUMI and Seika SHIBA famous for performances filled with originality failed in talkie and Furumi returned to Kyoto Eiga Co., Ltd. of Furuichi while Shiba to Zensho Kinema of Nara to retreat to silent films.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, all directors did not become familiar with talkie performance easily, and even Takuji FURUMI and Seika SHIBA famous for performances filled with originality failed in talkie and Furumi returned to Kyoto Eiga Co., Ltd. of Furuichi while Shiba to Zensho Kinema of Nara to retreat to silent films.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>1936年（昭和11年）には、トーキー脚本に力を見せた脚本家グループ「梶原金八」のメンバーである山中貞雄を起用、山中が『河内山宗俊』を日活との提携で撮り、また、その弟子の助監督・萩原遼 (映画監督)が、山中の原作を得て自ら脚色し、高勢実乗を主演にした『お茶づけ侍』で監督としてデビューした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It hired Sadao YAMANAKA, who was a member of &apos;Kinpachi KAJIWARA&apos; (Narutaki Group), which was the script writing group that showed power in talkie scripts, and Yamanaka took &quot;Soshun KOCHIYAMA&quot; with Nikkatsu, and his disciple assistant director Ryo HAGIWARA (film director) gained and adapted the original script of Yamanaka to make a debut as a director in &quot;Ochazuke Samurai&quot; (literally, rice soup samurai) with a leading actor Minoru TAKASE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The company hired Sadao YAMANAKA, who was a member of &apos;Kinpachi KAJIWARA&apos;, which was a group of script writers that proved their ability in talkie scripts, and Yamanaka shot &quot;Soshun KOCHIYAMA&quot; with Nikkatsu, and his disciple assistant director Ryo HAGIWARA (film director) gained and adapted the original script of Yamanaka to make a debut as a director in &quot;Ochazuke Samurai&quot; (literally, &quot;rice soup samurai&quot;), starring Minoru TAKASE.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The company hired Sadao YAMANAKA, who was a member of &apos;Kinpachi KAJIWARA&apos;, which was a group of script writers that proved their ability in talkie scripts, and Yamanaka shot &quot;Soshun KOCHIYAMA&quot; with Nikkatsu, and his disciple assistant director Ryo HAGIWARA (film director) gained and adapted the original script of Yamanaka to make a debut as a director in &quot;Ochazuke Samurai&quot; (literally, &quot;rice soup samurai&quot;), starring Minoru TAKASE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>やがて、J.O（大沢商会）が東宝映画配給と配給提携を進めるにいたって、太秦発声は、同年一杯をもって製作を中止した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">J. O. (J. Osawa Co., Ltd.) began to eventually produce with Toho Eiga Haikyu (Toho Movie Distributing Agency) that Uzumasa Hassei stopped its production at the end of same year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">J. O. (J. Osawa Co., Ltd.) then began to eventually produce with Toho Eiga Haikyu (Toho Movie Distributing Agency), and Uzumasa Hassei stopped its production at the end of same year.</e>
<cmt>「やがて」訳漏れのため、then を追記して対応しました。that Uzumasa を, and Uzumasa に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">J. O. (J. Osawa Co., Ltd.) then began to eventually produce with Toho Eiga Haikyu (Toho Movie Distributing Agency), and Uzumasa Hassei stopped its production at the end of same year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>最後の作品は辻吉朗監督、大城龍太郎・深水藤子主演の『お嬢さん浪人』で、同作は翌1937年（昭和12年）1月28日、日活の配給で公開された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The last work was &quot;Ojosan Ronin&quot; (Lady Masterless Samurai) directed by Kichiro TSUJI, played by leading actors Ryutaro OKI and Fujiko FUKAMIZU, and was released on January 28, 1937 distributed by Nikkatsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The last work was &quot;Ojosan Ronin&quot; (Lady Masterless Samurai) directed by Kichiro TSUJI, starring Ryutaro OKI and Fujiko FUKAMIZU, and was released on January 28, 1937 distributed by Nikkatsu.</e>
<cmt>played by leading actors を starring に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The last work was &quot;Ojosan Ronin&quot; (Lady Masterless Samurai) directed by Kichiro TSUJI, starring Ryutaro OKI and Fujiko FUKAMIZU, and was released on January 28, 1937 distributed by Nikkatsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>同年、J.Oスタヂオは4社合併で東宝映画を設立、スタジオごと「東宝映画京都撮影所」となっていく（1941年閉鎖）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">J. O. Studio established Toho Film by combining four companies and the studio became the &apos;Toho Eiga Kyoto Studio&apos; (closed in 1941).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">J. O. Studio established Toho Film by the merger of four companies and the studio became the &apos;Toho Eiga Kyoto Studio&apos; (closed in 1941).</e>
<cmt>combining を the merger of に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">J. O. Studio established Toho Film by the merger of four companies and the studio became the &apos;Toho Eiga Kyoto Studio&apos; (closed in 1941).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kmrt(id:101778), 江口磐世☆(id:168037), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>