<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>琵琶</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biwa</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biwa</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biwa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>琵琶（びわ、ビバ、ピーパー）は、東アジアの有棹（リュート属）弦楽器の一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biwa (biwa, biba, pipa) is one of the stringed instruments of the lute family in East Asia.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biwa (biwa, biba, pipa) is one of the stringed instruments of the lute family in East Asia.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biwa (biwa, biba, pipa) is one of the stringed instruments of the lute family in East Asia.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>弓を使わず、もっぱら弦をはじいて音を出す撥弦楽器である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a plucked string instrument that produces sounds by flicking strings with fingers without using a bow.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a plucked string instrument that produces sounds by flicking strings with fingers without using a bow.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a plucked string instrument that produces sounds by flicking strings with fingers without using a bow.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>古代において四弦系（曲頚琵琶）と五弦系（直頚琵琶）があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In ancient times, there were two types of biwa: the four-stringed type with a neck bent backward (Kyokukei Biwa) and the five-stringed type with a straight neck (Chokukei Biwa). The latter has not been used any more because its tradition has not been carried on, but the former developed later and had increased the number of its variety in China and Japan and many are still played even today.</e>
<cmt>2文に分けています。用語集では曲頚が winded になっていますが、bent backward としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In ancient times, there were two types of biwa: the four-stringed type with a neck bent backward (Kyokukei Biwa) and the five-stringed type with a straight neck (Chokukei Biwa). The latter is not used any more because its tradition has not been carried on, but the former developed later and had increased the number of its variety in China and Japan and many are still played even today.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In ancient times, there were two types of biwa: the four-stringed type with a neck bent backward (Kyokukei Biwa) and the five-stringed type with a straight neck (Chokukei Biwa).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処（分割処理がされていませんでした）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>後者は伝承が廃絶し使われなくなったが、前者は後に中国及び日本においていくつもの種類が生じて発展し、多くは現代も演奏されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The latter is not used any more because its tradition has not been carried on, but the former developed later and had increased the number of its variety in China and Japan and many are still played even today.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処（分割処理がされていませんでした）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>朝鮮半島にも伝えられ、郷琵琶（五絃琵琶）と唐琵琶（四絃）で分けられて宮廷楽士の基本楽器になって李氏朝鮮の末期まで用いられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was introduced to the Korean Peninsula and divided into the Kyo Biwa (five-stringed Biwa) and the To Biwa (four-stringed biwa) and became basic instruments of court musicians and had been used until the end of the Joseon Dynasty.</e>
<cmt>唐琵琶の読みですが、用語集でも2種類ありますがTo biwa としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was introduced to the Korean Peninsula and divided into the Kyo Biwa (five-stringed Biwa) and the To Biwa (four-stringed biwa) and became basic instruments of court musicians and had been used until the end of the Joseon Dynasty.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was introduced to the Korean Peninsula and divided into the Kyo biwa (five-stringed biwa) and the To biwa (four-stringed biwa) and became basic instruments of court musicians and had been used until the end of the Joseon Dynasty.</e>
<cmt>表記統一のため、Kyo Biwa→Kyo biwa、five-stringed Biwa→five-stringed biwa、To Biwa→To biwaとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>（1930年代にも演奏）ベトナムにはおそらく明代に伝播した四弦十数柱のものが伝承され、琵琶と書いて「ティパ」と発音する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(It was played in the 1930s, too.) The four-stringed biwa with more than a dozen frets that was introduced to the Ming Dynasty had been handed down in Vietnam and it is written biwa but pronounced as &quot;tipa.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(It was played in the 1930s, too.) The four-stringed biwa with more than a dozen frets that was introduced to the Ming Dynasty had been handed down in Vietnam and it is written biwa but pronounced as &quot;tipa.&quot;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(It was played in the 1930s, too.) The four-stringed biwa with more than a dozen frets that was introduced to the Ming Dynasty had been handed down in Vietnam and it is written biwa but pronounced as &apos;tipa.&apos;</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>なお、広義には阮咸（げんかん）や月琴などのリュート属弦楽器も琵琶に含めることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a broad sense, stringed instruments of the lute family such as genkan (ruanxian) (four or five-stringed Chinese lute) and gekkin (moon harp) are sometimes included in biwa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In a broad sense, stringed instruments of the lute family such as genkan (ruanxian) (four or five-stringed Chinese lute) and gekkin (moon harp) are sometimes included in the biwa group.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In a broad sense, stringed instruments of the lute family such as genkan (ruanxian) (four or five-stringed Chinese lute) and gekkin (moon harp) are sometimes included in the biwa group.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>四弦系（曲頚）琵琶は、西アジアのウード、ヨーロッパのリュートと共通の起源を持ち、形もよく似ている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The four-stringed type of biwa (Kyokukei) has a common origin with an oud (lute-like instrument of Arabic Origin) in West Asia and a lute in Europe and a similar shape to those.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The four-stringed type of biwa (Kyokukei) has a common origin with the oud (lute-like instrument of Arabic Origin) in West Asia and the lute in Europe and a similar shape to those.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The four-stringed type of biwa (Kyokukei) has a common origin with the oud (lute-like instrument of Arabic Origin) in West Asia and the lute in Europe and a similar shape to those.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>すなわち卵を縦に半分に割ったような形の共鳴胴に棹を付け、糸倉（ヘッド）がほぼ直角に後ろに曲がった形である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has a sound box shaped like an egg cut half lengthwise and a neck with a pegbox (the part which the tuning pegs are inserted into) bent backward roughly 90 degrees backwards.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has a sound box shaped like an egg cut in half lengthwise and a neck with a pegbox (the part which the tuning pegs are inserted into) bent roughly 90 degrees backwards.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has a sound box shaped like an egg cut in half lengthwise and a neck with a pegbox (the part which the tuning pegs are inserted into) bent roughly 90 degrees backwards.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>五弦系(直頚)琵琶はインド起源とされ、糸倉は曲がらず真っすぐに伸びている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The five-stringed type of biwa with straight neck (Chokukei) is said to have its origin in India and its pegbox is not bent but straight.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The five-stringed type of biwa with a straight neck (Chokukei) is said to have its origin in India and its pegbox is not bent but straight.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The five-stringed type of biwa with a straight neck (Chokukei) is said to have its origin in India and its pegbox is not bent but straight.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>正倉院に唯一の現物である「螺鈿紫檀五絃琵琶」（らでんしたんごげんのびわ、図参照）が保存されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The only existing actual biwa, &quot;Raden shitan Gogen no Biwa&quot; has been preserved in Shoso-in Treasure Repository (see figure).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The only existing actual biwa, &quot;Raden shitan Gogen no Biwa&quot; has been preserved in the Shoso-in Treasure Repository (see figure).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The only existing actual biwa, &apos;Raden shitan Gogen no Biwa&apos; has been preserved in the Shoso-in Treasure Repository (see figure).</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>起源</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Origin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Origin</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Origin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="12">
<j>実物は現存しないが、サーサーン朝ペルシア遺跡から出土する工芸品の浮彫り装飾などに、琵琶様の楽器がしばしば見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Instruments similar to biwa are often found such as in a relief carving decoration of artifacts excavated from remains of Sessanian Persia, though the actual ones do not exist any more.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Instruments similar to biwa are often found in relief carving decorations of artifacts excavated from remains of Sessanian Persia, though the actual ones do not exist any more.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Instruments similar to biwa are often found in relief carving decorations of artifacts excavated from remains of Sessanian Persia, though the actual ones do not exist any more.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>糸倉が後ろに曲がり、多くは撥をもって弾奏されており、この「バルバット」と呼ばれる楽器が四弦系琵琶やウード、リュートの祖先とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Their pegboxes were bent backward and many were played with a plectrum and these instruments called barbat (an old Persian instrument) are said to be an ancestor of the four-stringed type of biwa, oud, or lute.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their pegboxes were bent backward and many were played with a plectrum and these instruments called barbat (an old Persian instrument) are said to be an ancestor of the four-stringed type of biwa, oud, or lute.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Their pegboxes were bent backward and many were played with a plectrum and these instruments called barbat (an old Persian instrument) are said to be an ancestor of the four-stringed type of biwa, oud, or lute.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>これが中国に伝播したのは前漢の頃で、当初は「西方の琴（弦楽器）」を意味する「胡琴」の名称で呼ばれた（宋 (王朝)代以降現在までに胡琴と呼称される楽器はまったく別のもの）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was around the Former Han (dynasty of China) when these instruments were introduced to China and at first they were called as &quot;huqin&quot; (any Chinese string instrument played with a bow) which meant a &quot;Western harp (stringed instruments) (These instruments are totally different from the ones called huquin from the age of the Sung dynasty to today).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was around the Former Han (dynasty of China) when these instruments were introduced to China and at first they were called &quot;huqin&quot; (any Chinese string instrument played with a bow) which meant a &quot;Western harp&quot; (stringed instruments) (These instruments are totally different from the ones called huquin from the age of the Sung dynasty to today).</e>
<cmt>Flow, Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was around the Former Han (dynasty of China) when these instruments were introduced to China and at first they were called &apos;huqin&apos; (any Chinese string instrument played with a bow) which meant a &apos;Western harp&apos; (stringed instruments) (These instruments are totally different from the ones called huquin from the age of the Sung dynasty to today).</e>
<cmt>全角クォーテーションを半角に修正、シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>やがてウイグル語のバルバットが漢語に音訳された「琵琶」が呼称として定着した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, &quot;biwa&quot; transliterated into a word of Chinese origin from barbat in Uighur language became popular as their name.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, &quot;biwa&quot; transliterated into a word of Chinese origin from barbat in the Uighur language became popular as their name.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, &apos;biwa&apos; transliterated into a word of Chinese origin from barbat in the Uighur language became popular as their name.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>現存する世界最古の四弦琵琶は、今のところ正倉院に保存されている数面の琵琶であると思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is seemed that several biwas preserved in Shoso-in Treasure Repository are the most oldest four-stringed type of biwas in existence for now.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is seemed that several biwas preserved in the Shoso-in Treasure Repository are the oldest four-stringed type of biwas in existence presently.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is seemed that several biwas preserved in the Shoso-in Treasure Repository are the oldest four-stringed type of biwas in existence presently.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>いずれも奈良時代のものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were all made in the Nara period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were all made in the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were all made in the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>また楽譜も正倉院、及び敦煌市から発見されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Scores were also found in Shoso-in Treasure Repository and Dunhuang City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Scores were also found in the Shoso-in Treasure Repository and Dunhuang City.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Scores were also found in the Shoso-in Treasure Repository and Dunhuang City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>中国の琵琶</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biwa in China</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biwa in China</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biwa in China</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="19">
<j>唐時代の琵琶は現在の日本の楽琵琶とほぼ同じ形をしており、音楽理論が整備される中で、調弦法も多数定められ、様々な合奏にも用いられ、記譜法も確立し、宮廷音楽から民間音楽まで、合奏、独奏、歌唱の伴奏と広く愛好された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biwas in the Tang period had almost the same shape as those of present Japanese Gakubiwa Instrument, and the musical theory was developed, many tuning systems were defined, the musical notation was also established, and the instrument was played in various concerts, an ensemble, a solo, accompaniment for singing and became very popular from court music to folk music.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biwas in the Tang period had almost the same shape as those of present Japanese Gakubiwa Instruments, and musical theory was developed, many tuning systems were defined, musical notation was also established, and the instrument was played in various concerts, ensembles, solo, accompaniment for singing and became very popular from court music to folk music.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biwas in the Tang period had almost the same shape as those of present Japanese Gakubiwa Instruments, and musical theory was developed, many tuning systems were defined, musical notation was also established, and the instrument was played in various concerts, ensembles, solo, accompaniment for singing and became very popular from court music to folk music.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>白居易の詩「琵琶行」は有名であり、楊貴妃もよく琵琶を演奏したと言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the poem &quot;Biwako (a biwa song)&quot; by Haku Kyoi (Bai Juyi) was very popular and Yang Guifei often played the biwa, too.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the poem &quot;Biwako&quot; (a biwa song) by Haku Kyoi (Bai Juyi) was very popular and Yang Guifei often played the biwa, too.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the poem &apos;Biwako&apos; (a biwa song) by Haku Kyoi (Bai Juyi) was very popular and Yang Guifei often played the biwa, too.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを半角、シングルに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>清代に使用された琵琶は唐代までのものとは異なり、日本の盲僧琵琶にやや近い形をしており、弦数は変わらないがフレットはずっと増えて14個を備えていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biwa used in the Qing Dynasty were different from those used until the Tang Dynasty and had a shape slightly similar to Japanese moso-biwa (blind priests&apos; biwa), having the same number of stings but more frets as many as fourteen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biwa used in the Qing Dynasty were different from those used until the Tang Dynasty and had a shape slightly similar to Japanese moso-biwa (blind priests&apos; biwa), having the same number of stings but more frets as many as fourteen.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biwa used in the Qing Dynasty were different from those used until the Tang Dynasty and had a shape slightly similar to Japanese moso-biwa (blind priests&apos; biwa), having the same number of stings but more frets as many as fourteen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>撥ではなく、へら状の義甲（ピック）で弾奏する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are played with a spatular pick, not with a plectrum.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are played with a spatular pick, not with a plectrum.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are played with a spatular pick, not with a plectrum.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>江戸時代の文政頃、月琴や胡琴等と共に日本に伝来、明治初年頃まで明清楽として流行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were introduced to Japan around the Bunsei era in the Edo period along with gekkin and huqin and had been popular as the Ming &amp; Xing-era Chinese music (as popularized in Japan before the First Sino-Japanese war) until around the first year of Meiji period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were introduced to Japan around the Bunsei era in the Edo period along with gekkin and huqin and had been popular as Ming &amp; Xing-era Chinese music (as popularized in Japan before the First Sino-Japanese war) until around the first year of the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were introduced to Japan around the Bunsei era in the Edo period along with gekkin and huqin and had been popular as Ming and Xing-era Chinese music (as popularized in Japan before the First Sino-Japanese war) until around the first year of the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>&amp;→andに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>現在も長崎に伝承され、「唐琵琶」と呼ばれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They have been handed down in Nagasaki today and are called &quot;To biwa.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They have been handed down in Nagasaki today and are called &quot;To biwa.&quot;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They have been handed down in Nagasaki today and are called &apos;To biwa.&apos;</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>以後も中国ではこの形のものを使用しており、民間歌謡の伴奏を主にしていたが、20世紀に入り、劉天華（二胡、琵琶演奏家、作曲家・1895年〜1932年）らにより独奏曲が作られ始めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In China, this type of biwa had been used and mainly played as accompaniment for folk songs but, in the 20th century, solo music started to be composed by Ryu Ten Ka (erhu (two-stringed Chinese instrument played with a bow) and biwa player, composer, 1895 - 1932) and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In China, this type of biwa had been used and mainly played as accompaniment for folk songs but, in the 20th century, solo music started to be composed by Ryu Ten Ka (erhu (two-stringed Chinese instrument played with a bow) and biwa player, composer, 1895 - 1932) and others.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In China, this type of biwa had been used and mainly played as accompaniment for folk songs but, in the 20th century, solo music started to be composed by Tianhua LIU (erhu (two-stringed Chinese instrument played with a bow) and biwa player, composer, 1895 - 1932) and others.</e>
<cmt>劉天華→Ryu Ten Kaは日本語読みのため、仕様書に基づきTianhua LIUとしました。(参照: http://catalogue.nla.gov.au/Record/3029183)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>更に1950年代にこの琵琶（ビバ）を改良して現在の琵琶（ピーパー）が作られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the 1950s, this types of biwa was remodeled and the present day biwa (pipa) was made.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the 1950s, this type of biwa was remodeled and the present day biwa (pipa) was made.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the 1950s, this type of biwa was remodeled and the present day biwa (pipa) was made.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>ピーパー</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Pipa</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Pipa</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Pipa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="27">
<j>4本の金属弦を持ち、31個のフレットで半音階を演奏できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has four metal strings and can produce the chromatic scale with thirty-one frets.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has four metal strings and can produce the chromatic scale with thirty-one frets.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has four metal strings and can produce the chromatic scale with thirty-one frets.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>ギターの奏法が取り入れられ、弾奏には右手の全部の指を使用し、爪か義爪によって音を出す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Guitar-playing style was incorporated and it is played with all fingers of the right hand and produces sounds with nails or artificaial nails.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The guitar-playing style was incorporated and it is played with all fingers of the right hand and produces sounds with nails or artificial nails.</e>
<cmt>Flow, Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The guitar-playing style was incorporated and it is played with all fingers of the right hand and produces sounds with nails or artificial nails.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>日本の琵琶</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biwa in Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biwa in Japan</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biwa in Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="29">
<j>琵琶（ビバ）が7世紀、8世紀頃、中国から日本に入った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biwa (biba) was introduced to Japan from China around the 7th and 8th century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biwa (biba) was introduced to Japan from China around the 7th and 8th century.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biwa (biba) was introduced to Japan from China around the seventh and eighth century.</e>
<cmt>7th→seventh、8th→eighthとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>正倉院の宝物として伝来当時の琵琶が遺されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biwas at the time of introduction were preserved as treasures of Shoso-in Treasure Repository.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biwas at the time of introduction were preserved as treasures of Shoso-in Treasure Repository.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biwas at the time of introduction were preserved as treasures of Shoso-in Treasure Repository.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>半開の扇もしくはイチョウの葉の形に似た撥で弦（絃）を弾奏するのが特徴。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are characterized by plucking strings with a plectrum similar to a partly open fan or a ginkgo biloba.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are characterized by plucking strings with a plectrum similar to a partly open fan or a ginkgo biloba.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are characterized by plucking strings with a plectrum similar to a partly open fan or a ginkgo biloba.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>五弦琵琶、楽琵琶、平家琵琶、盲僧琵琶、唐琵琶、薩摩琵琶、筑前琵琶などの種類がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are many types of biwa namely Gogenbiwa Instrument, Gakubiwa Instrument, Heike biwa (a biwa with four strings and five frets used to play Heike Monogatari), moso-biwa, To Biwa (four-stringed Biwa), Satsuma biwa (Satsuma lute), or Chikuzen biwa (Chikuzen lute).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are many types of biwa namely Gogenbiwa Instrument, Gakubiwa Instrument, Heike biwa (a biwa with four strings and five frets used to play Heike Monogatari), moso-biwa, To Biwa (four-stringed Biwa), Satsuma biwa (Satsuma lute), or Chikuzen biwa (Chikuzen lute).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are many types of biwa namely Gogenbiwa Instrument, Gakubiwa Instrument, Heike biwa (a biwa with four strings and five frets used to play Heike Monogatari), moso-biwa, To biwa, Satsuma biwa (Satsuma lute), or Chikuzen biwa (Chikuzen lute).</e>
<cmt>To Biwa→To biwaとし、既出のため補足削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>それぞれの楽器は特有の音楽を持ち、その世界の中では単に「琵琶」と称される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Each instrument has its unique music and in their music world, it is called simply as biwa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Each instrument has its unique music and in their music world, it is simply called biwa.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Each instrument has its unique music and in their music world, it is simply called biwa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>またこれら異種の琵琶同士が合奏されることはまずない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These different kinds of biwa are never be played together.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These different kinds of biwa are never played together.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These different kinds of biwa are never played together.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>また、琵琶を主体とした音楽を「琵琶楽」と総称する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The music centered on biwa is collectively called &quot;Biwagaku.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The music centered on biwa is collectively called &quot;Biwagaku.&quot;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The music centered on biwa is collectively called &apos;Biwagaku.&apos;</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>五弦琵琶</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gogenbiwa Instrument</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gogenbiwa Instrument</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gogenbiwa Instrument</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="36">
<j>五弦琵琶は奈良時代より中国から伝来したが、ペルシア起源の四弦琵琶とは起源を異にし、インドで発生した楽器とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Gogenbiwa Instrument was came down from China in the Nara period but the Yongenbiwa instrument (four-stringed) was considered to have its origin in Persian.</e>
<cmt>四弦琵琶は、よんげんびわ と読みました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Gogenbiwa Instrument came down from China in the Nara period, but the Yongenbiwa instrument (four-stringed) was considered to have its origin in Persia.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Gogenbiwa Instrument came down from China in the Nara period, but the Yongenbiwa instrument (four-stringed) was considered to have its origin in Persia.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>五弦五柱。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Five-string five-fret</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Five-string five-fret</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Five-string five-fret.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>平安時代前期頃までは演奏する人もいたようで、当時の楽譜も現存しているが、その後断絶した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Until the early Heian period, this instrument was played by some musicians but extinguished later, though scores in those time is still preserved even today.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Until the early Heian period, this instrument was played by some musicians but extinguished later, though scores from those times are still preserved even today.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Until the early Heian period, this instrument was played by some musicians but extinguished later, though scores from those times are still preserved even today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>楽琵琶</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gakubiwa Instrument</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gakubiwa Instrument</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gakubiwa Instrument</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="39">
<j>楽琵琶は雅楽の管絃、催馬楽（さいばら）に用いる琵琶である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Gakubiwa Instrument is an instrument used in Kangen music, Saibara (genre of Heian-period Japanese court music (primarily consisting of gagaku-styled folk melodies)), of gagaku (ancient Japanese court dance and music).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Gakubiwa Instrument is an instrument used in Kangen music, Saibara (genre of Heian-period Japanese court music (primarily consisting of gagaku-styled folk melodies)), of gagaku (ancient Japanese court dance and music).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Gakubiwa Instrument is an instrument used in Kangen music, Saibara (genre of Heian-period Japanese court music (primarily consisting of gagaku-styled folk melodies)), of gagaku (ancient Japanese court dance and music).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>標準的なものとしては日本の琵琶の中で最も大きく、奈良時代に伝えられた唐代琵琶の形をほとんどそのまま現代に伝えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Standard type of this biwa is the biggest among Japanese biwas and the shape of the Tang Dynasty biwa introduced in the Nara period has been handed down to the present day with little modification.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The standard type of this biwa is the biggest among Japanese biwas and the shape of the Tang Dynasty biwa introduced in the Nara period has been handed down to the present day with little modification.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The standard type of this biwa is the biggest among Japanese biwas and the shape of the Tang Dynasty biwa introduced in the Nara period has been handed down to the present day with little modification.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>撥は逆に最も小さい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the contrary, it has the smallest plectrum.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the contrary, it has the smallest plectrum.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the contrary, it has the smallest plectrum.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>現在は合奏の中で分散和音を奏しながらリズム的に支える役目をしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today, the instrument plays an role to play arpeggio and supports rhythm in a concert.</e>
<cmt>2文に分けています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, the instrument plays a role playing arpeggio and supports the rhythm in concerts. There also exist solo music and &quot;Yoshinso,&quot; &quot;Takuboku,&quot; or &quot;Ryusen&quot; were known as masterpieces but they have not handed down to the present.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, the instrument plays a role playing arpeggio and supports the rhythm in concerts.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処（分割処理がされていませんでした）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>かつては独奏曲もあり、「楊真操」、「啄木」、「流泉」などが名曲として知られたが、現在に伝えられていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There also once existed solo music and &apos;Yoshinso,&apos; &apos;Takuboku,&apos; or &apos;Ryusen&apos; were known as masterpieces but they have not handed down to the present.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処（分割処理がされていませんでした）There also exist→There also once existedとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>また様々な技法も存在したようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is seemed that various playing techniques also existed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is seemed that various playing techniques also existed.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is seemed that various playing techniques also existed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>古くから愛された楽器で、文芸作品にもしばしば登場する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was a popular instrument since ancient times and often appeared in literary works.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was a popular instrument since ancient times and often appeared in literary works.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was a popular instrument since ancient times and often appeared in literary works.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>吉備真備、蝉丸、平経正など名人、名手といわれた人も多く、また多くの名器が伝えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were many masters or accomplished players such as KIBI no Makibi, Semimaru, or TAIRA no Tsunemasa, and many great instruments have been handed down.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were many masters or accomplished players such as KIBI no Makibi, Semimaru, or TAIRA no Tsunemasa, and many great instruments have been handed down.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were many masters or accomplished players such as KIBI no Makibi, Semimaru, or TAIRA no Tsunemasa, and many great instruments have been handed down.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>おおらかで豊かな音色を持ち、後世の諸琵琶との大きな違いは、他の楽器との合奏に用いられること、調ごとに調弦法が変わること、「弦楽器」の機構がないこと、左手の押弦が、柱（フレット）の間で絃を押さえる張力を変化させて音程を変える奏法がないこと、また小指まで使用すること、などである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has easygoing yet rich tones, and there are big differences from many types of biwa in later ages, namely it is played with other instruments, it has different tuning system for each tune, it has no mechanism for a string instrument, it has no playing system to peess strings with the left-hand fingers between frets to control the tension to make different tunes, or it is played using even a little finger.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has easygoing yet rich tones, and there are big differences from many types of biwa in later ages, namely it is played with other instruments, it has different tuning system for each tune, it has no mechanism for a string instrument, it has no playing system to press strings with the left-hand fingers between frets to control the tension to make different tunes, or it is played using even the pinky finger.</e>
<cmt>Flow, Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has easygoing yet rich tones, and there are big differences from many types of biwa in later ages, namely it is played with other instruments, it has different tuning system for each tune, it has no mechanism for a string instrument, it has no playing system to press strings with the left-hand fingers between frets to control the tension to make different tunes, or it is played using even the pinky finger.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>平家琵琶</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Heike biwa</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Heike biwa</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Heike biwa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="48">
<j>平家琵琶は楽琵琶から派生したもので、楽器は楽琵琶とほぼ同じつくりだが、小型の物が好まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Heike biwa came from the Gakubiwa and the structure of this instrument is almost the same as the Gakubiwa and smaller one is preferred.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Heike biwa came from the Gakubiwa and the structure of this instrument is almost the same as the Gakubiwa though smaller ones are preferred.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Heike biwa came from the Gakubiwa and the structure of this instrument is almost the same as the Gakubiwa though smaller ones are preferred.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>撥は逆にやや大きく、先端の開きが大きい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, its plectrum is rather big and its fan-out part at the top is wider.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, its plectrum is rather big and its fan-out part at the top is wider.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, its plectrum is rather big and its fan-out part at the top is wider.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>平家物語をかたるときの伴奏に用いる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is used as an accompaniment to chanting of &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; (The tale of the Heike).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is used as an accompaniment to the chanting of &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; (The tale of the Heike).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is used as an accompaniment to the chanting of Heike Monogatari (The tale of the Heike).</e>
<cmt>原文表記に合わせ、&quot;Heike Monogatari&quot;のクォーテーション削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>平家琵琶を用いた平家物語の語り物音楽を「平曲」と呼ぶ（薩摩琵琶、筑前琵琶にも平家物語を題材とする曲が多数あるが、これらは近世以降に作られたものであり、音楽的には平曲とはまったく違うものである）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The narrative music of &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; accompanied by a Heike biwa is called &quot;Heikyoku &quot; (the music played on the Heike biwa as accompaniment for the recitation of Heike monogatari) (There are also many songs based on Heike Monogatari for the Satsuma biwa and the Chikuzen biwa but they were composed after the early-modern times and are musically quite different from Heikyoku).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The narrative music of &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; accompanied by a Heike biwa is called &quot;Heikyoku &quot; (the music played on the Heike biwa as accompaniment for the recitation of Heike monogatari) (There are also many songs based on Heike Monogatari for the Satsuma biwa and the Chikuzen biwa but they were composed after the early-modern times and are musically quite different from Heikyoku).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The narrative music of Heike Monogatari accompanied by a Heike biwa is called &apos;Heikyoku&apos; (the music played on the Heike biwa as accompaniment for the recitation of Heike monogatari) (There are also many songs based on Heike Monogatari for the Satsuma biwa and the Chikuzen biwa but they were composed after the early-modern times and are musically quite different from Heikyoku).</e>
<cmt>&quot;Heike Monogatari&quot;のクォーテーション削除、余分なスペース消去、一部シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>伝承によれば、鎌倉時代のはじめ頃に生仏（しょうぶつ）という盲人音楽家がはじめたとされ、曲節には仏教音楽である声明（しょうみょう）の影響がみられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to traditions, it was started by a blind musician called Syobutsu at around the beginning of the Kamakura period and we can see the strong influence of Shomyo (chanting of Buddhist hymns) in its tunes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to traditions, it was started by a blind musician called Syobutsu at around the beginning of the Kamakura period and we can see the strong influence of Shomyo (chanting of Buddhist hymns) in its tunes.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to traditions, it was started by a blind musician called Shobutsu at around the beginning of the Kamakura period and we can see the strong influence of Shomyo (chanting of Buddhist hymns) in its tunes.</e>
<cmt>Syobutsu→Shobutsuに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>のち、南北朝時代 (日本)の盲人音楽家如一とその弟子明石検校明石覚一（1299年 - 1371年）が改変、整理し、一方（いちかた）流を創始した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, it was modified and organized by a blind musician, Nyoichi, and his apprentice, Kengyo AKASHI (an another name of Kakuichi AKASHI) (1299 - 1371), in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan) and they established the Ichikata-ryu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, it was modified and organized by a blind musician, Nyoichi, and his apprentice, Kengyo AKASHI (an another name of Kakuichi AKASHI) (1299 - 1371), in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan) and they established the Ichikata-ryu.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, it was modified and organized by a blind musician, Nyoichi, and his apprentice, Kengyo AKASHI (an another name of Kakuichi AKASHI) (1299 - 1371), in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan) and they established the Ichikata-ryu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>いっぽう城玄が創始した八坂流も生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, the Yasaka-ryu was also established by Jogen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, the Yasaka-ryu was also established by Jogen.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, the Yasaka-ryu was also established by Jogen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>室町時代には能楽と並び広く愛好され、中世日本音楽の代表的存在として並び称される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These became very popular along with nogaku (the art of Noh) in the Muromachi period and called as classics of the medieval Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These became very popular along with nogaku (the art of Noh) in the Muromachi period and called classics of medieval Japan.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These became very popular along with nogaku (the art of Noh) in the Muromachi period and called classics of medieval Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>江戸時代初期には前田検校により前田流が、波多野検校により波多野流が生まれ、前者は江戸を中心に、後者は京都を中心に行なわれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the early Edo period, the Maeda-ryu and the Hatano-ryu were established by Kengyo MAEDA and Kengyo HATANO respectively and the former developed around Edo and the latter in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the early Edo period, the Maeda-ryu and the Hatano-ryu were established by Kengyo MAEDA and Kengyo HATANO respectively and the former developed around Edo and the latter in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the early Edo period, the Maeda-ryu and the Hatano-ryu were established by Kengyo MAEDA and Kengyo HATANO respectively and the former developed around Edo and the latter in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>演奏は当道座に属する盲人音楽家により占有されていたが、江戸時代には晴眼の奏者もあらわれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Performances were exclusively given by blind musicians belonged to Todo-za (the traditional guild for the blind) but in the Edo period, some sighted players also gave performances.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Performances were exclusively given by blind musicians belonging to Todo-za (the traditional guild for the blind) but in the Edo period, some sighted players also gave performances.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Performances were exclusively given by blind musicians belonging to Todo-za (the traditional guild for the blind) but in the Edo period, some sighted players also gave performances.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>しかし地歌や浄瑠璃などの三味線音楽や箏曲の発展と共に次第に下火となり、波多野流は断絶、前田流は江戸時代中期に名古屋の荻野検校によって中興し、この流派のみがこんにちまで名古屋と仙台に伝えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, they had gradually cooled down as Shamisen music and sokyoku (koto music) such as Jiuta (a genre of traditional songs with samisen accompaniment) and Joruri (dramatic narrative chanted to a samisen accompaniment) developed, and the Hatano-ryu was put an end while the Maeda-ryu was restored by Kengyo OGINO in Nagoya in the middle of the Edo period, and only this school has been handed down to the present in Nagoya and Sendai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, they had gradually cooled down as Shamisen music and sokyoku (koto music) such as Jiuta (a genre of traditional songs with samisen accompaniment) and Joruri (dramatic narrative chanted to a samisen accompaniment) developed, and the Hatano-ryu was put to an end while the Maeda-ryu was restored by Kengyo OGINO in Nagoya in the middle of the Edo period, and only this school has been handed down to the present in Nagoya and Sendai.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, they had gradually cooled down as Shamisen music and sokyoku (koto music) such as Jiuta (a genre of traditional songs with samisen accompaniment) and Joruri (dramatic narrative chanted to a samisen accompaniment) developed, and the Hatano-ryu was put to an end while the Maeda-ryu was restored by Kengyo OGINO in Nagoya in the middle of the Edo period, and only this school has been handed down to the present in Nagoya and Sendai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>演奏者は非常に少ないが、稀に「鱸」「竹生島詣」「那須与一」などを聴く機会がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The number of players is very small but we sometimes have an opportunity to enjoy the performance of &quot;Susuki,&quot; &quot;Chikubushima mode,&quot; and &quot;Nasu no Yoichi.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The number of players is very small but we sometimes have an opportunity to enjoy the performances of &quot;Susuki,&quot; &quot;Chikubushima mode,&quot; and &quot;Nasu no Yoichi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The number of players is very small but we sometimes have an opportunity to enjoy the performances of &apos;Susuki,&apos; &apos;Chikubushima mode,&apos; and &apos;Nasu no Yoichi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>雅楽と平曲は絶対音高の音楽であるため、楽琵琶と平家琵琶は絶対音の楽器であり、相対音高の音楽である近世以降の琵琶楽と異なる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gagaku and Heikyoku are music by absolute pitch so the Gakubiwa and the Heikebiwa are the instrument with perfect pitch, and they are different from the Biwagaku, the music with relative pitch, after the early-modern times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gagaku and Heikyoku are music with absolute pitch so the Gakubiwa and the Heikebiwa are instruments with perfect pitch, and they are different from the Biwagaku, music with relative pitch, after the early-modern times.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gagaku and Heikyoku are music with absolute pitch so the Gakubiwa and the Heike biwa are instruments with perfect pitch, and they are different from the Biwagaku, music with relative pitch, after the early-modern times.</e>
<cmt>表記統一のため、Heikebiwa→Heike biwaとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="61">
<j>三味線の祖型が日本に伝来したとき、これを初めて扱い現在に近い楽器に改良したのが平家琵琶の演奏家たちであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When original shamisen (a three-stringed Japanese banjo) came down to Japan, it was players of the Heikebiwa who first handled it and improved it to the one similar to the present instrument.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the original shamisen (a three-stringed Japanese banjo) came down to Japan, it was players of the Heikebiwa who first handled it and improved it to make it similar to the present instrument.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the original shamisen (a three-stringed Japanese banjo) came down to Japan, it was players of the Heike biwa who first handled it and improved it to make it similar to the present instrument.</e>
<cmt>表記統一のため、Heikebiwa→Heike biwaとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>そのため、琵琶と同じように三味線を撥で弾くようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">So shamisen became to be played with a plectrum like biwa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">So shamisen came to be played with a plectrum like biwa.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">So shamisen came to be played with a plectrum like biwa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>ただし琵琶と三味線では撥の形状や持ち方に違いがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there are some differences between biwa and shamisen in the shape of plectrum and the way to hold it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there are some differences between biwa and shamisen in the shape of plectrum and the way it&apos;s held.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there are some differences between biwa and shamisen in the shape of plectrum and the way it&apos;s held.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>また三味線は楽器のみが伝わり楽曲は伴わなかったため、彼らにより新曲が次々に作り出されたが、その際にも平曲の音楽的要素が色々反映されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As shamisen came down with only an instrument without scores, many new songs were composed one after another by the Heikebiwa players and various musical elements of the Heikyoku were reflected.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As shamisen came down with only an instrument without scores, many new songs were composed one after another by the Heikebiwa players and various musical elements of the Heikyoku were reflected.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As shamisen came down with only an instrument without scores, many new songs were composed one after another by the Heike biwa players and various musical elements of the Heikyoku were reflected.</e>
<cmt>表記統一のため、Heikebiwa→Heike biwaとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>盲僧琵琶</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moso-biwa</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moso-biwa</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moso-biwa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="65">
<j>盲僧琵琶は仏教儀式に用いられたもので、盲人の僧侶がこの琵琶の伴奏で経文を唱えていたとされるが、娯楽的な音楽もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Moso-biwa was used for Buddhist ritual and it is said that blind priests used to chant sutras to an accompaniment of it but there were some pieces of entertainment-type music, too.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Moso-biwa was used for Buddhist rituals and it is said that blind priests used to chant sutras to an accompaniment of it, but there were some pieces of entertainment-type music, too.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The moso-biwa was used for Buddhist rituals and it is said that blind priests used to chant sutras to an accompaniment of it, but there were some pieces of entertainment-type music, too.</e>
<cmt>表記統一のため、Moso-biwa→moso-biwaとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>その起源は奈良時代に求められ、早くから盲僧の組織が作られていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The origin of this type of biwa was found in the Nara period and the guilds of blind priests had been organized from the early stage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The origin of this type of biwa was found in the Nara period and the guilds of blind priests had been organized from an early stage.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The origin of this type of biwa was found in the Nara period and the guilds of blind priests had been organized from an early stage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>蝉丸もその一人といわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Semimaru is said to be one of them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Semimaru is said to be one of them.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Semimaru is said to be one of them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>大別して薩摩盲僧と筑前盲僧とがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were main types of biwas: the Satsuma moso-biwa and the Chikuzen moso-biwa. The Satsuma biwa was created from the Satsuma moso-biwa from the middle of the Muromachi period to the Edo period and the Chikuzen biwa was created from the Chikuzen moso-biwa under the influence of the Satsuma biwa and shamisen music in the 1880s.</e>
<cmt>2文に分けています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were these main types of biwas: the Satsuma moso-biwa and the Chikuzen moso-biwa. The Satsuma biwa was created from the Satsuma moso-biwa from the middle of the Muromachi period to the Edo period and the Chikuzen biwa was created from the Chikuzen moso-biwa under the influence of the Satsuma biwa and shamisen music in the 1880s.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were these main types of biwas: the Satsuma moso-biwa and the Chikuzen moso-biwa.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処（分割処理がされていません）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>室町時代中期から江戸時代にかけて薩摩盲僧琵琶から薩摩琵琶が派生し、また薩摩琵琶および三味線音楽の影響のもと明治20年代に筑前盲僧琵琶から筑前琵琶が派生した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Satsuma biwa was created from the Satsuma moso-biwa from the middle of the Muromachi period to the Edo period and the Chikuzen biwa was created from the Chikuzen moso-biwa under the influence of the Satsuma biwa and shamisen music in the 1880s.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処（分割処理がされていません）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>盲僧琵琶には一定した制がなく、色々なかたちがみられるが、楽琵琶の系統とはやや異なり、近世中国の琵琶に似ているものが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Moso-biwa has no definite shape and has various shapes and it is slightly different from the Gakubiwa type and many are similar to biwas in modern China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Moso-biwa has no definite shape and has various shapes and it is slightly different from the Gakubiwa type and many are similar to biwas in modern China.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The moso-biwa has no definite shape and has various shapes and it is slightly different from the Gakubiwa type and many are similar to biwas in modern China.</e>
<cmt>表記統一のため、Moso-biwa→moso-biwaとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>細身のものが多く、特に細いものを笹の葉に見立てて「笹琵琶」と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are Many slender types of biwa and the ones especially slender is called sasa biwa (named for its slender &apos;bamboo leaf&apos; shape and a shorter, rounder-bodied instrument) to resemble a bamboo leaf.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are Many slender types of biwa and the ones that are especially slender are called sasa biwa (named for its slender &apos;bamboo leaf&apos; shape and a shorter, rounder-bodied instrument) because they resemble a bamboo leaf.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are Many slender types of biwa and the ones that are especially slender are called sasa biwa (named for its slender &apos;bamboo leaf&apos; shape and a shorter, rounder-bodied instrument) because they resemble a bamboo leaf.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>これらの盲僧たちはそれぞれの組織を持ち、室町時代から江戸時代にかけ、平曲の盲人演奏家の組織である当道座と対立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These blind priests belonged to their own guild and had a conflict with Todo-za, an organization of blind musicians of Heikyoku, from the Muromachi period to the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These blind priests belonged to their own guild and had a conflict with Todo-za, an organization of blind musicians of Heikyoku, from the Muromachi period to the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These blind priests belonged to their own guild and had a conflict with Todo-za, an organization of blind musicians of Heikyoku, from the Muromachi period to the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>薩摩琵琶</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Satsuma biwa</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Satsuma biwa</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Satsuma biwa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="73">
<j>薩摩琵琶は16世紀に活躍した薩摩の盲僧、淵脇了公が時の領主、島津忠良に召され、命を受けて、武士の士気向上のため、新たに教育的な歌詞の琵琶歌を作曲し、楽器を改良したのが始まりと言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the Satsuma biwa was made by Ryoko FUCHIWAKI, a blind priest in Satsuma, who worked actively in the 16th century, when he was called by Tadayoshi SHIMAZU, a feudal lord at that time, and was ordered to newly compose the Biwa uta (Biwa song) with educational poems and modify the instrument to inspire morals of samurais.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the Satsuma biwa was made by Ryoko FUCHIWAKI, a blind priest in Satsuma, who worked actively in the 16th century, when he was called by Tadayoshi SHIMAZU, a feudal lord at that time, and was ordered to compose Biwa uta (Biwa song) with educational poems and modify the instrument to inspire morals of samurai.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the Satsuma biwa was made by Ryoko FUCHIWAKI, a blind priest in Satsuma, who worked actively in the 16th century, when he was called by Tadayoshi SHIMAZU, a feudal lord at that time, and was ordered to compose Biwa uta (Biwa song) with educational poems and modify the instrument to inspire morals of samurai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>これまでの盲僧琵琶を改造し、武士の倫理や戦記・合戦物を歌い上げる勇猛豪壮な演奏に向いた構造にしたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He remodeled old moso-biwas and changed their structures suitable for a valiant and dynamic performance singing samurai&apos;s moral, war chronicle, and battles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He remodeled old moso-biwas and changed their structures to make them suitable for a valiant and dynamic performance singing about samurai&apos;s morals, war chronicles, and battles.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He remodeled old moso-biwas and changed their structures to make them suitable for a valiant and dynamic performance singing about samurai&apos;s morals, war chronicles, and battles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>盲僧琵琶では柔らかな材を使うことが多かった胴を硬い桑製に戻し、撥で叩き付ける打楽器的奏法を可能にした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He changed wood for the body of moso-biwa that used soft wood back to hard mulberry wood and made the instrument to be able to be played by striking it with a plectrum like a playing style of percussion instruments.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He changed the wood for the body of moso-biwa from a soft wood back to a hard mulberry wood and made the instrument able to be played by striking it with a plectrum like the playing style of percussion instruments.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He changed the wood for the body of moso-biwa from a soft wood back to a hard mulberry wood and made the instrument able to be played by striking it with a plectrum like the playing style of percussion instruments.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>撥は大型化し、杓文字型から扇子型へと形態も変化した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Plectrums became bigger and their shape were changed from a rice scoop-shaped one to sensugata (a folding fan-shaped).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Plectrums became bigger and their shape were changed from a rice scoop shaped to a sensugata (a folding fan-shaped) shape.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Plectrums became bigger and their shape were changed from a rice scoop shaped to a sensugata (a folding fan-shaped) shape.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>これにより、楽器を立てて抱え、横に払う形で撥を扱うことができるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By this, players could hold the instrument longitudinally and flick their plectrums sideways.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With this, players could hold the instrument horizontally and flick their plectrums sideways.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With this, players could hold the instrument horizontally and flick their plectrums sideways.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>江戸時代には「木崎ヶ原合戦」などの合戦を叙した曲が作られて次第に盛んになり、やがて武士だけでなく町民にも広まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These biwaa became gradually popular in the Edo period as songs derived from fights such as &quot;Kizakigahara gassen&quot; were composed, and they spread through not only samurais but also townspeople.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These biwas gradually became popular in the Edo period as songs derived from fights such as &quot;Kizakigahara gassen&quot; were composed, and they spread through not only samurai but also townspeople.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These biwas gradually became popular in the Edo period as songs derived from fights such as &apos;Kizakigahara gassen&apos; were composed, and they spread through not only samurai but also townspeople.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>こうして剛健な「士風琵琶」と優美な「町人琵琶」の2つの流れが成立する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">So, there established two schools of biwa: shifu biwa (samurai style biwa) and machifu biwa (townsman&apos;s style).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">So, there established two schools of biwa: shifu biwa (samurai style biwa) and machifu biwa (townsman&apos;s style).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">So, there established two schools of biwa: shifu biwa (samurai style biwa) and chonin biwa (townsman&apos;s biwa).</e>
<cmt>machifu biwa→chonin biwaに修正、補足修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>江戸時代末期に池田甚兵衛が両派の美点を一つに合わせ、一流を成し、以降、これが薩摩琵琶として現在まで続いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the end of the Edo Period, Jinbee IKEDA brought together the beauty of both schools and established his own school and this has came down to the present time as the Satsuma biwa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the end of the Edo Period, Jinbee IKEDA brought together the beauty of both schools and established his own school and this has came down to the present time as the Satsuma biwa.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the end of the Edo period, Jinbee IKEDA brought together the beauty of both schools and established his own school and this has came down to the present time as the Satsuma biwa.</e>
<cmt>Periodの頭文字を小文字に変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="81">
<j>薩摩出身者が力を持っていた明治時代には富国強兵政策とも相まって各地に広まり、吉村岳城、辻靖剛、西幸吉、吉水錦翁などの名手が輩出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They spread across the country combined with the policy of increasing wealth and military power in the Meiji period when people from Satsuma possessed power, and many super players appeared one after another such as Gakujo YOSHIMURA, Seijo TSUJI, Kokichi NISHI, or Kino YOSHIMIZU.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They spread across the country combined with the policy of increasing wealth and military power in the Meiji period when people from Satsuma possessed power, and many super players appeared one after another such as Gakujo YOSHIMURA, Seijo TSUJI, Kokichi NISHI, and Kino YOSHIMIZU.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They spread across the country combined with the policy of increasing wealth and military power in the Meiji period when people from Satsuma possessed power, and many super players appeared one after another such as Gakujo YOSHIMURA, Seigo TSUJI, Kokichi NISHI, and Kino YOSHIMIZU.</e>
<cmt>Seijo TSUJI→Seigo TSUJIに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>また明治天皇が終生愛好し、明治14年5月に、元薩摩藩主・島津忠義邸にて西幸吉が御前演奏をしたことから、社会的な評価がさらにあがり、やがて「筑前琵琶」とともに「宗家の琵琶節」は皇室向けにしか演奏しない「御止め芸」となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Meiji also loved this instrument through his life and the society&apos;s valuation got higher when Kokichi NISHI gave a performance in front of the Imperial family at the residence of Tadayoshi SHIMAZU in May, 1881 and &quot;Biwa-bushi&quot; of the head family became a performance only for the Imperial household along with the Chikuzen biwa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Meiji also loved this instrument throughout his life and society&apos;s valuation of the instrument became even higher when Kokichi NISHI gave a performance in front of the Imperial family at the residence of Tadayoshi SHIMAZU in May, 1881 and &quot;Biwa-bushi&quot; of the head family became a performance only for the Imperial household along with the Chikuzen biwa.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Meiji also loved this instrument throughout his life and society&apos;s valuation of the instrument became even higher when Kokichi NISHI gave a performance in front of the Imperial family at the residence of Tadayoshi SHIMAZU, the former lord of Satsuma Domain, in May, 1881 and &quot;Biwa-bushi&quot; of the head family became a performance only for the Imperial household along with the Chikuzen biwa.</e>
<cmt>「元薩摩藩主」→訳漏れのため訳出対応しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>また、永田錦心が出て、洗練された都会的で艶麗な芸風を特徴とする錦心流を打ち立て、これが評判となり全国に普及した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinshin NAGATA also appeared and established the Kinshin-ryu that was characterized by sophisticated, townish, and glamorous playing style and this created a sensation and penetrated the nation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kinshin NAGATA also appeared and established the Kinshin-ryu that was characterized by a sophisticated, townish, and glamorous playing style and this created a sensation and penetrated the nation.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinshin NAGATA also appeared and established the Kinshin-ryu that was characterized by a sophisticated, townish, and glamorous playing style and this created a sensation and penetrated the nation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>さらに昭和に入ると水藤錦穣が筑前琵琶の音楽要素を取り入れた「錦琵琶」を創始した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Showa period, Kinjo SUITO incorporated the music elements of the Chikuzen biwa and started the Nishiki biwa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Showa period, Kinjo SUITO incorporated the music elements of the Chikuzen biwa and started the Nishiki biwa.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Showa period, Kinjo SUITO incorporated the music elements of the Chikuzen biwa and started the Nishiki biwa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>楽器も筑前琵琶を取り入れ五弦五柱を持つよう改良された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He improved the instrument by taking in the Chikuzen biwa and remodeled them to five-string five-fret biwa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He improved the instrument by taking in the Chikuzen biwa and remodeled them to five-string five-fret biwa.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He improved the instrument by taking in the Chikuzen biwa and remodeled them to five-string five-fret biwa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>その後、水藤錦穣と同じく錦心流から出た鶴田錦史が五弦五柱をさらに改良すると共に、音楽的にも新しい分野へ飛躍させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, Kinshi TSURUTA who also came from the Kinshin-ryu same as Kinjo SUITO added refinements to the five-string five-fret biwa and made a leap forward into a new musical field.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, Kinshi TSURUTA who also came from the Kinshin-ryu, same as Kinjo SUITO, added refinements to the five-string five-fret biwa and made a leap forward into a new musical field.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, Kinshi TSURUTA who also came from the Kinshin-ryu, same as Kinjo SUITO, added refinements to the five-string five-fret biwa and made a leap forward into a new musical field.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>それまで語りの伴奏として用いられてきた琵琶に器楽的要素を大きく取り入れ、語りを伴わない琵琶演奏、西洋楽器やこれまで協奏することの無かった他の和楽器との合奏、また錦心流を基礎とした琵琶歌の改良、など斬新なアプローチを行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He took in the instrumental elements into biwa that had been used as accompaniment to narration and made fresh approaches such as biwa performance without narration, ensemble with Western musical instrument and other traditional Japanese musical instrument that had never been played with, or refinement of the Biwa uta based on the Kinshin-ryu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He took in the instrumental elements into biwa that had been used as accompaniment to narration and made fresh approaches such as biwa performances without narration, ensemble with Western musical instruments and other traditional Japanese musical instruments that had never been played with, or refinement of the Biwa uta based on the Kinshin-ryu.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He took in the instrumental elements into biwa that had been used as accompaniment to narration and made fresh approaches such as biwa performances without narration, ensemble with Western musical instruments and other traditional Japanese musical instruments that had never been played with, or refinement of the Biwa uta based on the Kinshin-ryu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>鶴田錦史の流れを汲む一派を「鶴田流」あるいは「鶴田派」と呼び、近年発展している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The school that followed Kinshi TSURUTA is called the Tsuruta-ryu or Tsuruta-school and is expanding its activities.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The school that followed Kinshi TSURUTA is called the Tsuruta-ryu or Tsuruta-school and is expanding its activities.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The school that followed Kinshi TSURUTA is called the Tsuruta-ryu or Tsuruta-school and is expanding its activities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>唐琵琶</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To biwa</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To biwa</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To biwa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="89">
<j>唐琵琶は、清代に民間で流行した琵琶で、その楽曲（清楽）や月琴等多数の楽器と共に文政年間頃日本に伝わったものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The To biwa was a biwa that became popular among people in the Qing Dynasty and was introduced into Japan around the Bunsei era along with its music, Qing-era Chinese music (popularized in Japan during the early 19th century), and gekkin and other many instruments.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The To biwa was a biwa that became popular among people in the Qing Dynasty and was introduced into Japan around the Bunsei era along with its music, Qing-era Chinese music (popularized in Japan during the early 19th century), and gekkin and other many instruments.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The To biwa was a biwa that became popular among people in the Qing Dynasty and was introduced into Japan around the Bunsei era along with its music, Qing-era Chinese music (popularized in Japan during the early 19th century), and gekkin and other many instruments.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>唐琵琶とは日本での呼び名で、唐代の琵琶とは大きく異なるので注意が必要である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">We have to keep in mind that the To biwa was a Japanese name and different from the biwa in the period of the Tang Dynasty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">We have to keep in mind that the To biwa was a Japanese name and different from the biwa in the period of the Tang Dynasty.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">We have to keep in mind that the To biwa was a Japanese name and different from the biwa in the period of the Tang Dynasty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>細身で胴は槽の材が表面にまで出て枠となり、そこに表板をはめ込む形をとっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was a slender type of biwa which body was made by inserting the &apos;Omote-Ita&apos;, a table, into a back board materials that were projected to the surface to made a frame.</e>
<cmt>槽の適訳が不明です。sound box としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was a slender type of biwa whose body was made by inserting the &apos;Omote-Ita,&apos; a table, into the back board materials that were projected to the surface to make the frame.</e>
<cmt>Flow, Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was a slender type of biwa whose body was made by inserting the &apos;Omote-Ita,&apos; a table, into the back board materials that were projected to the surface to make the frame.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>これは盲僧琵琶の多くや筑前琵琶と共通している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is common to the moso-biwa and the Chikuzen biwa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is common to the moso-biwa and the Chikuzen biwa.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is common to the moso-biwa and the Chikuzen biwa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>弦は四本、フレットは14個あり、撥ではなくへら状の義甲を用いて弾奏する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has foue strings and fourteen frets and is played with not a plectrum but a spatular pick.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has four strings and fourteen frets and is played with a spatular pick instead of a plectrum.</e>
<cmt>Flow, Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has four strings and fourteen frets and is played with a spatular pick instead of a plectrum.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>主に清代の民間楽曲（清楽）を他の楽器と合奏する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is mainly played with folk music (Qing-era Chinese music) in the Qing Dynasty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was mainly played with folk music (Qing-era Chinese music) in the Qing Dynasty.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was mainly played with folk music (Qing-era Chinese music) in the Qing Dynasty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>著名な曲としては「九連環」「茉莉花」「水仙花」などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are famous songs such as &quot;Kyurenkan,&quot; &quot;Matsurika,&quot; and &quot;Suisenka.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are famous songs such as &quot;Kyurenkan,&quot; &quot;Matsurika,&quot; and &quot;Suisenka.&quot;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are famous songs such as &apos;Kyurenkan,&apos; &apos;Matsurika,&apos; and &apos;Suisenka.&apos;</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>清楽は以前に伝わっていた明楽と合わせて明清楽と呼ばれ、幕末から明治初期にかけて流行したが、日清戦争の頃急速に下火となり、現在ではわずかに長崎に伝えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Qing-era Chinese music was called as the Ming &amp; Xing-era Chinese music combined with the Ming-era Chinese music (popularized in Japan during the early 17th century) that had been introduced before and became popular from the end of the Edo period to early Meiji period, but it died down around the Japanese-Sino War and it has slightly been carried on only in Nagasaki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Qing-era Chinese music was considered the combination of Ming and Xing-era Chinese music combined with the Ming-era Chinese music (popularized in Japan during the early 17th century) that had been introduced before and became popular from the end of the Edo period to the early Meiji period, but it died down around the Japanese-Sino War and it has slightly been carried on only in Nagasaki.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Qing-era Chinese music was considered the combination of Ming and Xing-era Chinese music combined with the Ming-era Chinese music (popularized in Japan during the early 17th century) that had been introduced before and became popular from the end of the Edo period to the early Meiji period, but it died down around the Japanese-Sino War and it has slightly been carried on only in Nagasaki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>筑前琵琶</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chikuzen biwa</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chikuzen biwa</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chikuzen biwa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="97">
<j>筑前琵琶は明治時代中期に筑前盲僧琵琶奏者の橘智定（たちばなちじょう）が薩摩で薩摩琵琶を研究して帰り、筑前盲僧琵琶を改良、新しい琵琶音楽を作り出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chijo TACHIBANA, a moso-biwa player in Chikuzen, remodeled the Chikuzen moso-biwa after he studied the Satsuma biwa in Satsuma and created new biwa music in the middle of the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chijo TACHIBANA, a moso-biwa player in Chikuzen, remodeled the Chikuzen moso-biwa after he studied the Satsuma biwa in Satsuma and created new biwa music in the middle of the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chijo TACHIBANA, a moso-biwa player in Chikuzen, remodeled the Chikuzen moso-biwa after he studied the Satsuma biwa in Satsuma and created new biwa music in the middle of the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>琵琶奏者の鶴崎賢定（つるさきけんじょう）や吉田竹子がこの新しい琵琶音楽を広めるのに一役買った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biwa players such as Kenjo TSURUSAKI and Takeko YOSHIDA helped promote this biwa music.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biwa players such as Kenjo TSURUSAKI and Takeko YOSHIDA helped promote this biwa music.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biwa players such as Kenjo TSURUSAKI and Takeko YOSHIDA helped promote this biwa music.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>明治29年、橘は東京へ進出し演奏活動を開始して注目を浴びた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1896, TACHIBANA went to Tokyo and started performing and won attention.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1896, TACHIBANA went to Tokyo and started performing and won attention.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1896, TACHIBANA went to Tokyo and started performing and won attention.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>そして名を旭翁と号し、筑前琵琶橘流を創始、明治天皇御前演奏をするなど急速に全国に広まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He took a second name or alias, Kyokuo, and started the Chikuzen biwa Tachibana-ryu and his name was rapidly known across the country by such as giving a performance in front of the Emperor Meiji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He took a second name or alias, Kyokuo, and started the Chikuzen biwa Tachibana-ryu and his name was rapidly known across the country by such as giving a performance in front of the Emperor Meiji.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He took a second name or alias, Kyokuo, and started the Chikuzen biwa Tachibana-ryu and his name was rapidly known across the country by such as giving a performance in front of the Emperor Meiji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>橘流は創始者である初代 旭翁の没後、「橘会」と「旭会」の二派に分かれ現在に至る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the first Kyokuo, the founder, died, the Tachibana-ryu was divided into two schools: the Tachibana-kai and the Asahi-kai, and hitherto existing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the first Kyokuo, the founder, died, the Tachibana-ryu was divided into two schools: the Tachibana-kai and the Asahi-kai, and hitherto existing.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the first Kyokuo, the founder, died, the Tachibana-ryu was divided into two schools: the Tachibana-kai and the Asahi-kai, and hitherto existing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>また吉田竹子の門下から高峰筑風（高峰三枝子の父）が出て一世を風靡したが、後継者がなくその芸風は途絶えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A disciple of Takeko YOSHIDA, Chikufu TAKAMINE (father of Mieko TAKAMINE) became famous and dominated the biwa world but he had no successor, so his performing style was put to an end.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A disciple of Takeko YOSHIDA, Chikufu TAKAMINE (father of Mieko TAKAMINE) became famous and dominated the biwa world but he had no successor, so his performing style came to an end.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A disciple of Takeko YOSHIDA, Chikufu TAKAMINE (father of Mieko TAKAMINE) became famous and dominated the biwa world but he had no successor, so his performing style came to an end.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>筑前琵琶の音楽は薩摩琵琶に比べ曲風がおだやかであり、楽器、撥ともやや小柄である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Music of the Chikuzen biwa has more gentle melodies compared to ones of the Satsuma biwa and the instrument and its plectrum are smaller.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Music of the Chikuzen biwa has more gentle melodies compared to ones of the Satsuma biwa and the instrument and its plectrum are smaller.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Music of the Chikuzen biwa has more gentle melodies compared to ones of the Satsuma biwa and the instrument and its plectrum are smaller.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>胴の表板は桐に変わり、音色は薩摩琵琶に比べ軟らかい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The wood of a body table was changed to paulownia and tones are softer than those of the Satsuma biwa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The wood of the body table was changed to paulownia and tones are softer than those of the Satsuma biwa.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The wood of the body table was changed to paulownia and tones are softer than those of the Satsuma biwa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>調絃も三味線に準ずるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The tuning system conformed to the one of shamisen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The tuning system conformed to the one of shamisen.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The tuning system conformed to the one of shamisen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>女性奏者に人気が出、娘琵琶としても流行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Women biwa players gain in popularity and were touted as &quot;musume biwa&quot;, namely maiden biwa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Women biwa players gained in popularity and were touted as &quot;musume biwa,&quot; namely maiden biwa.</e>
<cmt>Flow, Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Women biwa players gained in popularity and were touted as &quot;musume biwa,&quot; namely maiden biwa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>また一時期は花柳界にも「琵琶芸者」なるものが存在した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biwa was popular also in a karyukai (world of the geisha) and so-called &quot;biwa geisha&quot; appeared during a certain period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biwa was popular also in the karyukai (world of the geisha) and so-called &quot;biwa geisha&quot; appeared during a certain period.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biwa was popular also in the karyukai (world of the geisha) and so-called &apos;biwa geisha&apos; appeared during a certain period.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>薩摩琵琶では歌（語り）と楽器は交互に奏されるが、筑前琵琶の音楽には三味線音楽の要素が取り入れられており、歌いながら琵琶の伴奏を入れる部分がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Satsuma biwa music, songs (narrative part) and the instrument were played alternately while the music of the Chikuzen biwa took in the musical elements of shamisen and has a part of biwa as accompaniment for songs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Satsuma biwa music, songs (narrative parts) and the instrument were played alternately while the music of the Chikuzen biwa took in the musical elements of shamisen and had a part of biwa as accompaniment for songs.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Satsuma biwa music, songs (narrative parts) and the instrument were played alternately while the music of the Chikuzen biwa took in the musical elements of shamisen and had a part of biwa as accompaniment for songs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="109">
<j>著名な曲としては「湖水渡」「道灌」「義士の本懐」「敦盛」「本能寺」「石堂丸」などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Famous songs are &quot;Kosuiwatari,&quot; &quot;Dokan,&quot; &quot;Gishi no Honkai,&quot; &quot;Atsumori,&quot; &quot;Honno-ji Temple,&quot; or &quot;Ishidomaru.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Famous songs are &quot;Kosuiwatari,&quot; &quot;Dokan,&quot; &quot;Gishi no Honkai,&quot; &quot;Atsumori,&quot; &quot;Honno-ji Temple,&quot; or &quot;Ishidomaru.&quot;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Famous songs are &apos;Kosuiwatari,&apos; &apos;Dokan,&apos; &apos;Gishi no Honkai,&apos; &apos;Atsumori,&apos; &apos;Honno-ji Temple,&apos; or &apos;Ishidomaru.&apos;</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>筑前琵琶の種類は四弦と、四絃より音域をより豊かにする為に初代 旭翁とその実子である橘旭宗 一世によって考案された五弦があり、五弦の方が全体にやや大きい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The types of the Chikuzen biwa are Yongenbiwa Instrument (four-stringed) and Gogenbiwa Instrument (five-stringed) that was designed by the first Kyokuo and his biological child, Kyokuso TACHIBANA the first, and this Gogenbiwa Instrument is overall slightly bigger.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The types of Chikuzen biwa are Yongenbiwa Instrument (four-stringed) and Gogenbiwa Instrument (five-stringed) that were designed by the first Kyokuo and his biological child, Kyokuso TACHIBANA the first, and this Gogenbiwa Instrument is overall slightly bigger.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The types of Chikuzen biwa are Yongenbiwa Instrument (four-stringed) and Gogenbiwa Instrument (five-stringed) that were designed by the first Kyokuo and his biological child, Kyokuso TACHIBANA the first, and this Gogenbiwa Instrument is overall slightly bigger.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>撥も五弦用のものの方がやや開きの幅が広く、いくらか薩摩のものに近い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The plectrum for Gogenbiwa Instrument has a slightly wider fan-out part at the top and is similar in some degree to the Satsuma biwa&apos;s plectrum.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The plectrum for Gogenbiwa Instrument has a slightly wider fan-out part at the top and is similar in some degree to the Satsuma biwa&apos;s plectrum.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The plectrum for Gogenbiwa Instrument has a slightly wider fan-out part at the top and is similar in some degree to the Satsuma biwa&apos;s plectrum.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>柱はいずれも五柱（四絃五柱、五絃五柱）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Both have five frets (four-string five-fret, five-string five-fret).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Both have five frets (four-string five-fret, five-string five-fret).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Both have five frets (four-string five-fret, five-string five-fret).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="113">
<j>この他、高音用の「小絃」、低音用の「大絃」も作られたが、一般的に普及はしていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to these, &quot;shogen&quot; for high pitched tones and &quot;daigen&quot; for low pitched tones were made but they have not been generally unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to these, &quot;shogen&quot; for high pitched tones and &quot;daigen&quot; for low pitched tones were made but they have been generally unknown.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to these, &apos;shogen&apos; for high pitched tones and &apos;daigen&apos; for low pitched tones were made but they have been generally unknown.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>現代の琵琶</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biwa today</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biwa today</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biwa today</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="114">
<j>古典的な楽曲だけではなく、独奏、合奏ともに様々な作曲が試みられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Attempts have been made to compose not only classical-style songs but also new songs as well as solos and ensembles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Attempts have been made to compose not only classical-style songs but also new songs as well as solos and ensembles.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Attempts have been made to compose not only classical-style songs but also new songs as well as solos and ensembles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>古典のスタイルにのっとった新作もあるが、特に打楽器的効果の強い薩摩琵琶は、しばしば現代音楽にも用いられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are some songs composed according to a classical style but the Satsuma biwa that has a major effect like percussion instruments is often used in modern music.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are some songs composed according to a classical style but the Satsuma biwa that has a major effect like percussion instruments is often used in modern music.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are some songs composed according to a classical style but the Satsuma biwa that has a major effect like percussion instruments is often used in modern music.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="116">
<j>武満徹の「ノヴェンバー・ステップス」、「エクリプス」などが有名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;November Steps &quot;and &quot;Eclipse&quot; composed by Toru Takemitsu are well known.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;November Steps &quot;and &quot;Eclipse&quot; composed by Toru Takemitsu are well known.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November Steps&apos; and &apos;Eclipse&apos; composed by Toru TAKEMITSU are well known.</e>
<cmt>Toru Takemitsu→Toru TAKEMITSUに修正、余分なスペース消去、シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="117">
<j>この他、和楽器オーケストラの中で薩摩琵琶や筑前琵琶が1～2パートを受け持つことも少なくない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, the Satsuma biwa and the Chikuzen biwa often play one or two parts in a wagakki orchestra (orchestra of the traditional Japanese musical instrument).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, the Satsuma biwa and the Chikuzen biwa often play one or two parts in wagakki orchestra (orchestra of the traditional Japanese musical instrument).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, the Satsuma biwa and the Chikuzen biwa often play one or two parts in wagakki orchestra (orchestra of the traditional Japanese musical instrument).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="118">
<j>また楽琵琶では、新作雅楽曲のパートとしての演奏のほか、奈良時代の楽曲の復元演奏なども試みられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Gakubiwa, players are attempting to not only play a parts in new Gagaku-kyoku (Gagaku music) but also reproduce the music in the Nara period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Gakubiwa, players are attempting to not only play parts in new Gagaku-kyoku (Gagaku music) but also reproduce the music of the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Gakubiwa, players are attempting to not only play parts in new Gagaku-kyoku (Gagaku music) but also reproduce the music of the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>日本の琵琶のいくつかに共通の事項</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some common elements of Japanese biwa</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some common elements of Japanese biwa</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some common elements of Japanese biwa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="119">
<j>盲僧琵琶、薩摩琵琶、筑前琵琶は高いフレット（「柱」と称する）を持つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The moso-biwa, the Satsuma biwa, and the Chikuzen biwa have high frets (called &quot;jyu&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The moso-biwa, the Satsuma biwa, and the Chikuzen biwa have high frets (called &quot;jyu&quot;).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The moso-biwa, the Satsuma biwa, and the Chikuzen biwa have high frets (called &apos;ju&apos;).</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更、jyu→juに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="120">
<j>それだけ弦を押し込むことができ、張力を変化させることにより音程を調節できる範囲が広い（柱によっては長三度まで）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">So, players can press strings deeper and change the tension to have a wider range to control music interval (up to a major third depending on frets).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">So, players can press strings deeper and change the tension to have a wider range when controlling music intervals (up to a major third depending on frets).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">So, players can press strings deeper and change the tension to have a wider range when controlling music intervals (up to a major third depending on frets).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="121">
<j>中国の琵琶がフレットを増やして、楽器としての機能向上によって表現力を高めたのとは逆に、日本の琵琶はフレットを増やさず（場合によっては減らし）、その分演奏者の技倆をできるだけ活かして微妙な演奏を行うことを好んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese biwa favored to play nuanced performances by making more the most of the players&apos; techniques than increasing frets (reducing frets according to circumstance) while Chinese biwa increased frets and enhanced its powers of expression by improving functions as an instrument.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese biwa favored nuanced performances by making the most of a player&apos;s techniques rather than increasing the number of frets (reducing frets according to circumstance) while Chinese biwa increased frets and enhanced its powers of expression by improving functions as an instrument.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese biwa favored nuanced performances by making the most of a player&apos;s techniques rather than increasing the number of frets (reducing frets according to circumstance) while Chinese biwa increased frets and enhanced its powers of expression by improving functions as an instrument.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="122">
<j>また中国琵琶が金属弦を取り入れているのに対し、日本琵琶は絹糸の繊細な音色を大切にしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese biwa values the sensitive tones of silk strings but Chinese biwa used metal strings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese biwa values the sensitive tones of silk strings but Chinese biwa used metal strings.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese biwa values the sensitive tones of silk strings but Chinese biwa used metal strings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="123">
<j>いっぽうリュートが撥を捨て、指頭で弾くことから多音性を発達させ、弦数も増えていったのに比べ、日本の琵琶は逆に撥を大型化して一音にすべてを込め、また打楽器的効果を持たせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Lutes abandoned plectrums and developed polyphony by playing with fingers and increased the number of strings, but Japanese biwa made its plectrum bigger and tried to express all tones in one tone and also give the percussion-like effect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Lutes abandoned plectrums and developed polyphony by playing with fingers and increased the number of strings, but Japanese biwa made its plectrum bigger and tried to express all tones in one tone and also give a percussion-like effect.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Lutes abandoned plectrums and developed polyphony by playing with fingers and increased the number of strings, but Japanese biwa made its plectrum bigger and tried to express all tones in one tone and also give a percussion-like effect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="14">
<tit>
<j>音楽以外への影響</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Impact on thongs other than music</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Impact on things other than music</e>
<cmt>Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Impact on things other than music</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="124">
<j>日本最大の湖、琵琶湖は形が琵琶に似ていたので名づけられたという説が一般的である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is commonly said that the largest lake in Japan, Lake Biwa, is named after biwa as their shape were similar.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is commonly said that the largest lake in Japan, Lake Biwa, is named after biwa as their shapes are similar.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is commonly said that the largest lake in Japan, Lake Biwa, is named after biwa as their shapes are similar.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="125">
<j>陶磁器にも琵琶を模したものがしばしばみられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">We often see ceramics that represent biwa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">We often see ceramics that represent biwa.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">We often see ceramics that represent biwa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Paul Richter(id:5556), 0null0(id:582), Aotake(id:34929), Kstigarbha(id:13376), Cprobot(id:97843), Urania(id:7213), Mintleaf(id:2216), Qazzx(id:8772), Kamakura(id:472), Greenland4(id:114494), 高木あゆみ(id:6492), Mymelo(id:122034), Point136(id:211299), Yas(id:739), FlaBot(id:30804), Sielrace(id:124888), 詠狸庵(id:41048), Rika Aizu(id:123211), TS(id:481), テルフィーノ(id:79308), ZZZ(id:9462), NekoJaNekoJa(id:23311), Sh(id:2707), Hatsune(id:26654), 樒(id:35770), Azu(id:1328), SilvonenBot(id:190970), Kokada jnet(id:84730), Nnn(id:26535), SuisuiBot(id:10165), ウィキ太郎(id:81560), Thijssie!bot(id:111619), Heikeshikyoku(id:80784), Alexbot(id:157199), Corwin(id:973), Ptbotgourou(id:229657), っ(id:4481), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>