<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>肴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sakana</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sakana</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sakana</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>肴（さかな）とは、酒を飲む際に添えて共に楽しむ対象を言い、これは食品に限らない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sakana is a thing with which people enjoy having alcoholic beverages; yet, it is not necessarily a food item.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sakana is a thing with which people enjoy having alcoholic beverages; yet, it is not necessarily a food item.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sakana is a thing with which people enjoy having alcoholic beverages; yet, it is not necessarily a food item.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>酒肴（しゅこう）、酒にあてがうことからアテと呼ぶ事もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also referred to as &quot;shuko,&quot; or &quot;ate&quot; (since sakana accompanies, or &quot;ategau&quot; in Japanese, alcoholic beverages).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also referred to as &quot;shuko,&quot; or &quot;ate&quot; (since sakana accompanies, or &quot;ategau&quot; in Japanese, alcoholic beverages).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also referred to as &quot;shuko,&quot; or &quot;ate&quot; (since sakana accompanies, or &quot;ategau&quot; in Japanese, alcoholic beverages).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>語源</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Etymology</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Etymology</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Etymology</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>「酒菜」から。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The word sakana (肴) originated from saka-na (酒菜).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The word sakana (肴) originated from saka-na (酒菜).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The word sakana (肴) originated from &apos;saka-na&apos; (酒菜).</e>
<cmt>原文の「」の部分に&apos; &apos;を付加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>もともと惣菜を「な」といい、「菜」「魚」「肴」の字をあてていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japanese, dishes were called &quot;na,&quot; and the word na was represented by the kanji characters, &quot;菜,&quot; &quot;魚,&quot;or &quot;肴.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japanese, dishes were called &quot;na,&quot; and the word na was represented by the kanji characters, &quot;菜,&quot; &quot;魚,&quot;or &quot;肴.&quot;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japanese, dishes were called &apos;na,&apos; and the word na was represented by the kanji characters, &apos;菜,&apos; &apos;魚,&apos;or &apos;肴.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>酒のための「な（おかず）」という意味である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The word sakana, thus, meant na (dishes) for saka, or sake (alcoholic drinks).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The word sakana, thus, meant na (dishes) for saka, or sake (alcoholic drinks).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The word sakana, thus, meant &apos;na (dishes)&apos; for saka, or sake (alcoholic drinks).</e>
<cmt>原文の「」の部分に&apos; &apos;を付加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>つまり酒と一緒に楽しめれば魚介類でも野菜類でもよい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In other words, sakana can be seafood or vegetables as long as it goes well with alcoholic beverages.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In other words, sakana can be seafood or vegetables as long as it goes well with alcoholic beverages.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In other words, sakana can be seafood or vegetables as long as it goes well with alcoholic beverages.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>時には食品でなくとも、「上司の悪口」や「ご近所の噂」、あるいは野球やサッカーといったスポーツの話題や、美術品や花（桜など）の鑑賞を目的とするものをサカナに酒を飲んでも、言葉の使用法としてはなんら差し支えない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, people sometimes enjoy having alcoholic beverages with non-food sakana such as complaints about superiors, the talk of the neighborhood, topics about sports (baseball, soccer, etc.), and objects for viewing (art work or flowers, for example, cherry blossoms); this use of the word sakana for non-food items is acceptable.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, people sometimes enjoy having alcoholic beverages with non-food sakana such as complaints about superiors, the talk of the neighborhood, topics about sports (baseball, soccer, etc.), and objects for viewing (art work or flowers, for example, cherry blossoms); this use of the word sakana for non-food items is acceptable.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, people sometimes enjoy having alcoholic beverages with non-food sakana such as &apos;complaints about superiors,&apos; &apos;the talk of the neighborhood,&apos; topics about sports (baseball, soccer, etc.), and objects for viewing (art work or flowers, for example, cherry blossoms); this use of the word sakana for non-food items is acceptable.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」の部分に&apos; &apos;を付加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>「魚」の漢字に「さかな」の読みが当てられるようになったのも魚類（干物が多い）が酒（さか）の肴（な）として特に好まれていたからである（魚類の項目を参照）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The kanji character &quot;魚&quot; (fish) came to be pronounced as sakana because fish (mostly dried fish) was particularly preferred for dishes for alcoholic drinks (see the article on fish).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The kanji character &quot;魚&quot; (fish) came to be pronounced as sakana because fish (mostly dried fish) was particularly preferred for dishes for alcoholic drinks (see the article on fish).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The kanji character &apos;魚&apos; (fish) came to be pronounced as &apos;sakana&apos; because fish (mostly dried fish) was particularly preferred for dishes for alcoholic drinks (see the article on fish).</e>
<cmt>原文の「」の部分に&apos; &apos;を付加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>酒を嗜む事は娯楽の一とされ、その生成が比較的楽な事から古来から広く一般に楽しまれてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Drinking alcoholic beverages has been regarded as a recreational part of life and has been widely enjoyed by ordinary people since the old times thanks to their relatively easy production methods.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Drinking alcoholic beverages has been regarded as a recreational part of life and has been widely enjoyed by ordinary people since the old times thanks to their relatively easy production methods.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Drinking alcoholic beverages has been regarded as a recreational part of life and has been widely enjoyed by ordinary people since the old times thanks to their relatively easy production methods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>アルコール（エタノール）を摂取すると人はその麻酔作用により酩酊を得、抑制を引き起こすためにストレス (生体)から開放され、様々な快楽に対し抵抗感を無くす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When they consume alcohol (ethanol), people become intoxicated due to its sedative effect, get relieved from stress which has restrained them, and stop refraining from various pleasures.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When they consume alcohol (ethanol), people become intoxicated due to its sedative effect, get relieved from stress which has restrained them, and stop refraining from various pleasures.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When they consume alcohol (ethanol), people become intoxicated due to its sedative effect, get relieved from stress which has restrained them, and stop refraining from various pleasures.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>その際に提供される娯楽を一般に肴と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The enjoyment offered in such occasion is generally called sakana.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The enjoyment offered in such occasions is generally called sakana.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The enjoyment offered in such occasions is generally called sakana.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>そのため、酒の肴は酒だ、と酒豪（呑兵衛）によって使われる言葉はあながち間違いでもなく、またその者の酒への耽溺さを端的に表していると言える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Accordingly, the phrase uttered by heavy drinkers called nonbei, &quot;alcohol itself is sakana for alcohol,&quot; is not necessarily incorrect, and in fact, it clearly shows their dependence on alcohol.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Accordingly, the phrase uttered by heavy drinkers called nonbei, &quot;alcohol itself is sakana for alcohol,&quot; is not necessarily incorrect, and in fact, it clearly shows their dependence on alcohol.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Accordingly, the phrase uttered by heavy drinkers called nonbei, &quot;alcohol itself is sakana for alcohol,&quot; is not necessarily incorrect, and in fact, it clearly shows their dependence on alcohol.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>観劇や噺などの日常娯楽に浸る事に併せ酒を呑むという、娯楽が食文化を発展させ、また食文化が娯楽を発展させてきた歴史は世界各地に存在する</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In many parts of the world, history shows that enjoyment of drinking along with usual enjoyments such as going to plays and comic stories has helped food culture develop while food culture has helped enjoyments grow.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In many parts of the world, history shows that enjoyment of drinking along with usual enjoyments such as going to plays and comic stories has helped food culture develop while food culture has helped enjoyments grow.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In many parts of the world, history shows that enjoyment of drinking along with usual enjoyments such as going to plays and comic stories has helped food culture develop while food culture has helped enjoyments grow.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="15">
<j>とはいえ、いくら酒豪であってもビールであれ日本酒であれウイスキーであれ、それだけを飲み続けるというのは難しいものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even a heavy drinker, however, finds it difficult to keep on drinking alcohol only, whether it be beer, sake (Japanese rice wine), or whiskey.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even a heavy drinker, however, finds it difficult to keep on drinking alcohol only, whether it be beer, sake (Japanese rice wine), or whiskey.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even a heavy drinker, however, finds it difficult to keep on drinking alcohol only, whether it be beer, sake (Japanese rice wine), or whiskey.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>また、ある種の食品を酒と共に味わうことで、酒・肴ともにその味を引き立てあって1+1が3にも4にもなる場合がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, there are cases that enjoying alcoholic drinks with certain dishes will have a &quot;one plus one equals three or four&quot; effect since drinks and sakana complement each other.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, there are cases where enjoying alcoholic drinks with certain dishes will have a &quot;one plus one equals three or four&quot; effect since drinks and sakana complement each other.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, there are cases where enjoying alcoholic drinks with certain dishes will have a &quot;one plus one equals three or four&quot; effect since drinks and sakana complement each other.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>例えばワインとチーズを交互に口にすると、両者の味わいが単独の時よりも格段に増すことがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, having wine and cheese in turn may deepen the flavor of each much more than having only either one of them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, having wine and cheese in turn may deepen the flavor of each much more than having only either one of them.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, having wine and cheese in turn may deepen the flavor of each much more than having only either one of them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>フランスではこのワインとこのチーズ（に限らず他の食品でも）の相性が良い、という組み合わせを「マリアージュ」（結婚）と呼んでかまびすしく取り上げられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In France, a good combination of certain wine and cheese (as well as other food items) is called &quot;mariage&quot; (marriage) and is covered to a great extent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In France, a good combination of certain wines and cheeses (as well as other food items) is called &quot;mariage&quot; (marriage) and is covered to a great extent.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In France, a good combination of certain wines and cheeses (as well as other food items) is called &apos;mariage&apos; (marriage) and is covered to a great extent.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="19">
<j>また、酒だけを飲んだ場合に比べ、何か食べ物を一緒に摂った方がアルコールの吸収を緩和し、悪酔いや二日酔いを防止する効果がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Compared with having only alcohol, drinking with food slows down alcohol absorption, which saves a drinker from feeling sick and having a hangover.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Compared with having only alcohol, drinking with food slows down alcohol absorption, which saves a drinker from feeling sick and having a hangover.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Compared with having only alcohol, drinking with food slows down alcohol absorption, which saves a drinker from feeling sick and having a hangover.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>酒（アルコール）は生物的的にエネルギーとはなっても栄養学的に有効な「食事」にはならないため、酒だけでは不足する栄養素を補給するため、食品に分類される肴と一緒に飲むことが医学的にも望ましいとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An alcoholic beverage (alcohol) is biochemically a source of calories but can not be a nutritionally beneficial meal; thus, it is deemed clinically appropriate to drink alcoholic beverages with sakana which is categorized in a food item in order to compensate for the lack of nutrients in alcoholic beverages.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処原文には、「生物的的」 とありますが、「生物的」はリンク先の単語のようです。ウェブで確認すると用語は「生化学的 」となっており、本来はこちらの用語を使用していると思われますので、こちらを訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An alcoholic beverage (alcohol) is biochemically a source of calories but can not be a nutritionally beneficial meal; thus, it is deemed clinically appropriate to drink alcoholic beverages with sakana which is categorized as a food item in order to compensate for the lack of nutrients in alcoholic beverages.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An alcoholic beverage (alcohol) is biochemically a source of calories but can not be a nutritionally beneficial &apos;meal;&apos; thus, it is deemed clinically appropriate to drink alcoholic beverages with sakana which is categorized as a food item in order to compensate for the lack of nutrients in alcoholic beverages.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」の部分に&apos; &apos;を付加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="21">
<j>肴の条件</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Requirements for sakana</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Requirements for sakana</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Requirements for sakana</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>酒飲みにとってはある程度の塩分があるものであればたいていのものは肴となりうる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Any food can be sakana for drinkers as long as it has a salty taste to some degree.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Any food can be sakana for drinkers as long as it has a salty taste to some degree.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Any food can be sakana for drinkers as long as it has a salty taste to some degree.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>落語の「酢豆腐」で、暇人連中が集まって酒を飲むのに何か肴を、というのでどんなものがいいかという段になって、「安くって数が有って誰の口にも合って、腹にたまんなくって見てくれが良くって、しかも衛生にいい」というくだりがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In rakugo (traditional comic storytelling) called &quot;su-dofu&quot; (vinegar tofu), there is a scene in which people with too much free time gather for a drink and think about what kind of sakana to eat, saying, &quot;Sakana should be something inexpensive and abundant that everybody likes. It should be something pleasant to see that doesn&apos;t make one full. Furthermore, it should be healthy.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In rakugo (traditional comic storytelling) called &quot;su-dofu&quot; (vinegar tofu), there is a scene in which people with too much free time gather for a drink and think about what kind of sakana to eat, saying, &quot;Sakana should be something inexpensive and abundant that everybody likes. It should be something pleasant to see that doesn&apos;t make one full. Furthermore, it should be healthy.&quot;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In rakugo (traditional comic storytelling) called &apos;su-dofu&apos; (vinegar tofu), there is a scene in which people with too much free time gather for a drink and think about what kind of sakana to eat, saying, &apos;Sakana should be something inexpensive and abundant that everybody likes. It should be something pleasant to see that doesn&apos;t make one full. Furthermore, it should be healthy.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」の部分に&apos; &apos;を付加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>この「腹にたまらない」というのがひとつの条件になろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This &quot;something that doesn&apos;t make one full&quot; is one of the requirements for sakana.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This &quot;something that doesn&apos;t make one full&quot; is one of the requirements for sakana.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This &apos;something that doesn&apos;t make one full&apos; is one of the requirements for sakana.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>肴はあくまで酒に付随するもの、つまり酒が主で肴が従である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sakana is always a thing that accompanies drinks; that is to say, drinks are the main focus while sakana is supplementary.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sakana is always a thing that accompanies drinks; that is to say, drinks are the main focus while sakana is supplementary.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sakana is always a thing that accompanies drinks; that is to say, drinks are the main focus while sakana is supplementary.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>従ってフランス料理のフルコースでワインを飲んでも、料理は「肴」とは呼ばない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, the dishes served in a full course French meal are not called sakana even if one drinks wine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, the dishes served in a full course French meal are not called sakana even if one drinks wine.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, the dishes served in a full course French meal are not called &apos;sakana&apos; even if one drinks wine.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」の部分に&apos; &apos;を付加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>故にあまり量のあるものやご飯、パン、麺類など主食的なものは肴に向かない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This means that heavy foods or staple foods such as steamed rice, bread and noodles are unfit for sakana.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This means that heavy foods or staple foods such as steamed rice, bread and noodles are unfit for sakana.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This means that heavy foods or staple foods such as steamed rice, bread and noodles are unfit for sakana.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>しかし丼物や麺類の種物から飯や麺を除いたものは格好の肴となる場合がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The foods left after steamed rice and noodles are each removed from rice bowl dishes and noodle dishes with toppings, however, can be perfect sakana.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The foods left after steamed rice and noodles are each removed from rice bowl dishes and noodle dishes with toppings, however, can be perfect sakana.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The foods left after steamed rice and noodles each removed from rice bowl dishes and noodle dishes with toppings, however, can be perfect sakana.</e>
<cmt>noodlesの後のareを除去しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>前者は牛丼店における「牛皿」、後者は蕎麦屋におけるいわゆる「蕎麦蕎麦屋」といったものがそれに相当する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An example for the former is &quot;gyu-sara&quot; (literally, beef plate) in a beef bowl restaurant while one for the latter is &quot;nuki&quot; (literally, removal) in a soba (buckwheat noodle) restaurant.</e>
<cmt>原文には、「蕎麦蕎麦屋」 とありますが、「蕎麦蕎麦屋」はリンク先の単語のようです。ウェブで確認すると用語は「ヌキ 」となっており、本来はこちらの用語を使用していると思われますので、こちらを訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An example for the former is &quot;gyu-sara&quot; (literally, beef plate) in a beef bowl restaurant while one for the latter is &quot;nuki&quot; (literally, removal) in a soba (buckwheat noodle) restaurant.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An example for the former is &apos;gyu-sara&apos; (literally, beef plate) in a beef bowl restaurant while one for the latter is &apos;nuki&apos; (literally, removal) in a soba (buckwheat noodle) restaurant.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="30">
<j>日本酒の場合、同じく米を原料とするためか酒に合うものは飯に合い、飯に合うものは酒にも合う場合が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For sake, it is often the case that steamed rice goes well with foods that goes with sake while sake goes well with ones that go with steamed rice, probably because sake and steamed rice are both rice products.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For sake, it is often the case that steamed rice goes well with foods that goes with sake while sake goes well with ones that go with steamed rice, probably because sake and steamed rice are both rice products.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For sake, it is often the case that steamed rice goes well with foods that goes with sake while sake goes well with ones that go with steamed rice, probably because sake and steamed rice are both rice products.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="31">
<j>日本酒特有の肴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Typical sakana for sake</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Typical sakana for sake</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Typical sakana for sake</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>ビールにソーセージ、シャブリ（辛口の白ワイン）に生カキ (貝)、というように、紋切り型な肴が割り当てられている場合があるが、ここでは主に日本酒の肴に特化したものについて述べる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fixed sakana is often stereotypically arranged with a specific drink as seen in the examples of sausage for beer or raw oysters for Chablis (dry white wine), and in what follows, sakana specific to sake will be discussed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fixed sakana is often stereotypically arranged with a specific drink as seen in the examples of sausage for beer or raw oysters for Chablis (dry white wine), and in what follows, sakana specific to sake will be discussed.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fixed sakana is often stereotypically arranged with a specific drink as seen in the examples of sausage for beer or raw oysters for Chablis (dry white wine), and in what follows, sakana specific to sake will be discussed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>塩</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Salt</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Salt</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Salt</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="34">
<j>枡でのむ場合、枡の一角に盛り上げ、なめながら飲む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When sake is served in a masu (wooden box cup originally used to measure rice), one drinks sake and licks salt placed on one corner of the masu in turn.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When sake is served in a masu (wooden box cup originally used to measure rice), one drinks sake and licks salt placed on one corner of the masu in turn.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When sake is served in a masu (wooden box cup originally used to measure rice), one drinks sake and licks salt placed on one corner of the masu in turn.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>アルコールには水分摂取を促進させ利尿を行うため、塩分が体内から不足する場合があり、そのために酒を呑むと塩が美味しく感じられる時がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because alcohol causes one to drink more water and thus urinate, he/she may lack salt content in the body; as a result, one may feel that salt tastes good when drinking sake.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because alcohol causes one to drink more water and thus urinate, he/she may lack salt content in the body; as a result, one may feel that salt tastes good when drinking sake.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because alcohol causes one to drink more water and thus urinate, he/she may lack salt content in the body; as a result, one may feel that salt tastes good when drinking sake.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>また塩は糖の吸収を促進し甘味を感じ易くする効果があるため、カクテルにある「ソルティ～」の様に経験的に甘味を引き出すために用いられてきたモノもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, salt increases sugar absorption and causes one to be more sensitive to sweetness; salt has been empirically used to increase sweetness as shown in the names of cocktails with the word &quot;salty.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, salt increases sugar absorption and causes one to be more sensitive to sweetness; salt has been empirically used to increase sweetness as shown in the names of cocktails with the word &quot;salty.&quot;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, salt increases sugar absorption and causes one to be more sensitive to sweetness; salt has been empirically used to increase sweetness as shown in the names of cocktails with the word &apos;salty.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>テキーラでも「肴」として用いられる事がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Salt is sometimes served as sakana for tequila as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Salt is sometimes served as sakana for tequila as well.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Salt is sometimes served as &apos;sakana&apos; for tequila as well.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」の部分に&apos; &apos;を付加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="38">
<j>嘗味噌</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Name-miso (miso mixed with ingredients)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Name-miso (miso mixed with ingredients)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Name-miso (miso mixed with ingredients)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>味噌をそのまま、あるいは調味したり副材料を混ぜ込んだ物（金山寺味噌など）を肴にする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Miso itself, cooked miso, and miso mixed with additional ingredients (for example, kinzanji miso, or miso made from soybeans, barley and vegetables) are sakana for sake.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Miso itself, cooked miso, and miso mixed with additional ingredients (for example, kinzanji miso, or miso made from soybeans, barley and vegetables) are sakana for sake.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Miso itself, cooked miso, and miso mixed with additional ingredients (for example, kinzanji miso, or miso made from soybeans, barley and vegetables) are sakana for sake.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>葱、鰹節、生姜、蕗、蕎麦の実などを用い、直火で炙って供する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some name-miso is served after being broiled with green onion, dried bonito, ginger, Japanese butterbur or buckwheat seeds.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some name-miso is served after being broiled with green onion, dried bonito, ginger, Japanese butterbur or buckwheat seeds.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some name-miso is served after being broiled with green onion, dried bonito, ginger, Japanese butterbur or buckwheat seeds.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="41">
<j>ウメ肉・山葵・もみ海苔</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Plum pulp, wasabi (Japanese horseradish) and mominori (toasted and crushed dried laver seaweed)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Plum pulp, wasabi (Japanese horseradish) and mominori (toasted and crushed dried laver seaweed)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Plum pulp, wasabi (Japanese horseradish) and mominori (toasted and crushed dried laver seaweed)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>三種を少しずつ混ぜながら酒の合間に口に運ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This dish is eaten in between sips of sake with the three ingredients being lightly mixed each time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This dish is eaten in between sips of sake with the three ingredients being lightly mixed each time.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This dish is eaten in between sips of sake with the three ingredients being lightly mixed each time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="43">
<j>個々の料理、珍味やいわゆる「乾き物」とよばれるおつまみ類については個々の記事に譲る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">See individual articles for details about other dishes, delicacies, and tidbits called &quot;kawakimono&quot; (literally, dry food).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">See individual articles for details about other dishes, delicacies, and tidbits called &quot;kawakimono&quot; (literally, dry food).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">See individual articles for details about other dishes, delicacies, and tidbits called &apos;kawakimono&apos; (literally, dry food).</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 DumZiBoT(id:230315), クモハモハ大王(id:185685), Hutsuki(id:35332), マクガイア(id:33346), Balmung0731(id:99201), 0null0(id:582), Kamuin(id:5241), 青空流(id:216386), Sudpex(id:49537), XOP(id:42473), Tmtm(id:14181), Janus01(id:69663), Doratea(id:37080), Tnm(id:58695), Rislimric(id:54531), A-Taul(id:41790), Point136(id:211299), 1029man(id:93235), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>