<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>萬歳</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Manzai</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Manzai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Manzai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>萬歳（まんざい）とは、日本の伝統芸能の一つである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Manzai is a kind of traditional art in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Manzai is a kind of traditional art in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Manzai is a kind of traditional art in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>新年の言祝ぎの話芸として全国で興り、漫才の元になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It occurred as the art of speech for New Year celebration throughout Japan, which was the origin of manzai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It occurred as the art of speech for New Year celebration throughout Japan, which was the origin of manzai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It occurred as the art of speech for New Year celebration throughout Japan, which was the origin of manzai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>地名を冠して区別することが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is often distinguished by putting a place-name on it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is often distinguished by putting a place-name on it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is often distinguished by putting a place-name on it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>編成</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Organization</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Organization</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Organization</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>萬歳は太夫（たゆう）と才蔵（さいぞう）の2人が1組となるものが基本となるが、門（かど）付けではなく座敷などで披露されるものは3人以上から、多いもので十数人の組となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In manzais, a pair of performers called &quot;tayu&quot; and &quot;saizo&quot; is a basic unit, but on the performance not in front of the houses but in &quot;zashiki&quot; (parlor), the number of performers are from more than three up to a dozen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In manzai, a pair of performers called &quot;tayu&quot; and &quot;saizo&quot; is a basic unit, but in performances not in front of houses, but in &quot;zashiki&quot; (parlor), the number of performers are from more than three to up to a dozen.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In manzai, a pair of performers called &quot;tayu&quot; and &quot;saizo&quot; is a basic unit, but in performances not in front of houses, but in &quot;zashiki&quot; (parlor), the number of performers are from more than three to up to a dozen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>扇・楽器</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fans and musical instruments</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fans and musical instruments</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fans and musical instruments</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>多くの萬歳は舞扇のような扇子を用いるが、三河萬歳は中啓（能楽で使う扇の一種で、閉じた状態を横から見た時に先が広がっている）を用いる場合が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In many of manzais, the performers use a folding fan like &quot;maisen&quot; (folding fan for dancing), but in Mikawa manzai they often use a &quot;chukei&quot; (a kind of folding fan in nogaku, when we see the closed one from the side, its end is spreading).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In many manzai, the performers use a folding fan like &quot;maisen&quot; (folding fan for dancing), but in Mikawa manzai they often use a &quot;chukei&quot; (a kind of folding fan in nogaku, when we see the closed one from the side, its end is spreading).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In many manzai, the performers use a folding fan like &quot;maisen&quot; (folding fan for dancing), but in Mikawa manzai they often use a &quot;chukei&quot; (a kind of folding fan in nogaku, when we see the closed one from the side, its end is spreading).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>楽器について、基本は才蔵が持つ小鼓だけだが、演目によりさらに三味線と胡弓を加えたり、太鼓・三味線・拍子木を使用するものもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Concerning the musical instruments, basically there&apos;s only a &quot;kozutsumi&quot; (small hand drum) played by saizo, but according to the repertoire, shamisen and kokyu (Chinese fiddle) are added or sometimes drum, shamisen and clappers are used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Concerning musical instruments, basically there&apos;s only a &quot;kozutsumi&quot; (small hand drum) played by saizo, but according to the repertoire, shamisen and kokyu (Chinese fiddle) are added or sometimes drum, shamisen and clappers are used.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Concerning musical instruments, basically there&apos;s only a &quot;kozutsumi&quot; (small hand drum) played by saizo, but according to the repertoire, shamisen and kokyu (Chinese fiddle) are added or sometimes drum, shamisen and clappers are used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>越前萬歳と加賀萬歳はすり太鼓（小太鼓を細い竹の撥で擦るように鳴らす）を用いる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Echizen manzai and Kaga manzai, a &quot;suri-daiko&quot; (making a sound by scraping a kozutsumi with a thin bamboo plectrum) is used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Echizen manzai and Kaga manzai, a &quot;suri-daiko&quot; (making a sound by scraping a kozutsumi with a thin bamboo plectrum) is used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Echizen manzai and Kaga manzai, a &quot;suri-daiko&quot; (making a sound by scraping a kozutsumi with a thin bamboo plectrum) is used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="11">
<j>衣装</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Costume</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Costume</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Costume</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>古くは舞楽の装束をまね、太夫は鳥兜（とりかぶと）をかぶっていたが、室町時代になると烏帽子（さむらいえぼし）をかぶり、素襖（すおう）に平袴（ひらばかま）姿に、才蔵は大黒頭巾風のものをかぶり、大袋を背負う格好が普通であったようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In ancient times, imitating the costume of &quot;bugaku&quot; (court dance and music), tayu put on &quot;torikabuto&quot; (ornamental hat in bugaku), but in the Muromachi period tayu seems to have put on &quot;samurai-eboshi&quot; (formal headwear for court nobles), &quot;suo&quot; (ceremonial dress of lower-class samurai) and &quot;hirabakama&quot; (man&apos;s formal divided skirt) and saizo put on something like &quot;daikokuzukin&quot; (hood like the god of good luck) and normally shouldered a big bag.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In ancient times, imitating the costume of &quot;bugaku&quot; (court dance and music), tayu put on &quot;torikabuto&quot; (ornamental hat in bugaku), but in the Muromachi period tayu seems to have put on &quot;samurai-eboshi&quot; (formal headwear for court nobles), &quot;suo&quot; (ceremonial dress of lower-class samurai) and &quot;hirabakama&quot; (man&apos;s formal divided skirt) and saizo put on something like &quot;daikokuzukin&quot; (hood like the god of good luck) and normally shouldered a big bag.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In ancient times, imitating the costume of &quot;bugaku&quot; (court dance and music), tayu put on &quot;torikabuto&quot; (ornamental hat in bugaku), but in the Muromachi period tayu seems to have put on &quot;samurai-eboshi&quot; (formal headwear for court nobles), &quot;suo&quot; (ceremonial dress of lower-class samurai) and &quot;hirabakama&quot; (man&apos;s formal divided skirt) and saizo put on something like &quot;daikokuzukin&quot; (hood like the god of good luck) and normally shouldered a big bag.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>また、室町時代中期に門付けが一般化してくると、その際に太夫は裁着袴（たつつけばかま）をはいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, as the manzai performance in front of the houses became more common during the middle of Muromachi period, then tayu wore &quot;tatsutukebakama&quot; (man&apos;s formal divided skirt).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, as the manzai performances in front of houses became more common during the middle of the Muromachi period, then tayu wore &quot;tatsutukebakama&quot; (man&apos;s formal divided skirt).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, as the manzai performances in front of houses became more common during the middle of the Muromachi period, then tayu wore &quot;tatsutukebakama&quot; (man&apos;s formal divided skirt).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>江戸時代には三河出身の徳川家によって優遇された三河萬歳は、武士のように帯刀、大紋の直垂の着用が許された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Edo period, Mikawa manzai, which was preferentially treated by the TOKUGAWA family from Mikawa province, was allowed to belt on a sword and to wear a &quot;hitatare&quot; (a kind of court dress in old days) with large family crests.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Edo period, Mikawa manzai, which were preferentially treated by the TOKUGAWA family from Mikawa province, were allowed to belt on a sword and to wear a &quot;hitatare&quot; (a kind of court dress in old days) with large family crests.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Edo period, Mikawa manzai, which were preferentially treated by the Tokugawa family from Mikawa province, were allowed to belt on a sword and to wear a &quot;hitatare&quot; (a kind of court dress in old days) with large family crests.</e>
<cmt>Tokugawaに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>各地に広まった萬歳は、後に能や歌舞伎などの要素を取り入れたりしたことによって、さらに衣装が多様化した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The manzai spread across Japan became more diversified in its costume by incorporating the elements of &quot;noh&quot; or &quot;kabuki&quot; later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The manzai spread across Japan became more diversified in its costume by incorporating the elements of &quot;noh&quot; or &quot;kabuki&quot; later.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The manzai spread across Japan became more diversified in its costume by incorporating the elements of &quot;noh&quot; or &quot;kabuki&quot; later.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="16">
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>起源</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Origin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Origin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Origin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>起源については定かではないが、奈良時代の「踏歌（とうか）」より変遷したものと考える説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The origin is not clear, but manzai is theoretically considered to have changed from &quot;toka&quot; in the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The origin is not clear, but manzai is theoretically considered to have changed from &quot;toka&quot; in the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The origin is not clear, but manzai is theoretically considered to have changed from &apos;toka&apos; in the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>（踏歌は宮中などにおいて春を寿ぐ行事で、男踏歌の舞人が舞楽の「万春楽（ばんすらく）」を足を踏み鳴らすように舞う際には万春楽と囃し、女踏歌の時は千春楽（せんずらく）と囃した）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(&quot;Toka&quot; is the event to celebrate spring at court and so on, when the dancer of &quot;otoko-toka&quot; (male-toka) danced stomping, he sang &quot;bansuraku,&quot; and when the dancer of &quot;onna-toka&quot; (female-toka) danced, she sang &quot;senzuraku.&quot;)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(&quot;Toka&quot; is the event to celebrate spring at court and so on, when the dancer of &quot;otoko-toka&quot; (male-toka) danced stomping, he sang &quot;bansuraku,&quot; and when the dancer of &quot;onna-toka&quot; (female-toka) danced, she sang &quot;senzuraku.&quot;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Toka is the event to celebrate spring at court and so on, when the dancer of &quot;otoko-toka&quot; (male-toka) danced stomping, he sang &apos;bansuraku,&apos; and when the dancer of &quot;onna-toka&quot; (female-toka) danced, she sang &apos;senzuraku.&apos;)</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>また雅楽には君主の長久を祝うめでたい曲として、千秋楽と共に萬歳楽（まんざいらく）という曲が伝えられていて、ここから千秋萬歳（せんずまんざい）となり、単に萬歳となったともいわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also in &quot;gagaku&quot; (ancient Japanese court dance and music), the song called &quot;manzairaku&quot; as well as &quot;senshuraku&quot; to celebrate the longevity of the lord had been carried on, from which the name allegedly became &quot;senzumanzai,&quot; and simply &quot;manzai.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also in &quot;gagaku&quot; (ancient Japanese court dance and music), the song called &quot;manzairaku&quot; as well as &quot;senshuraku&quot; to celebrate the longevity of the lord had been carried on, from which the name allegedly became &quot;senzumanzai,&quot; and simply &quot;manzai.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also in gagaku (ancient Japanese court dance and music), the song called &quot;manzairaku&quot; as well as &quot;senshuraku&quot; to celebrate the longevity of the lord had been carried on, from which the name allegedly became &quot;senzumanzai,&quot; and simply &quot;manzai.&quot;</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>他にも、新年になると歳神が家々を訪れて寿福を授けるという民間信仰より来たものなどの説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, there is a theory that the name originates from the folk beliefs that &quot;toshigami&quot; (God of the Year) visited each house to give a celebration in the New Year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, there is a theory that the name originates from the folk beliefs that &quot;toshigami&quot; (God of the Year) visited each house to give a celebration in the New Year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, there is a theory that the name originates from the folk beliefs that Toshigami (the god of the Year) visited each house to give a celebration in the New Year.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を削除しました。Toshigami (the god of the Year)に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>これは、歳神に扮し自ら神の依代（よりしろ）となって祝福を与え歩いていたものが、やがて宮中に出入りするようになったというもので、豊年の秋を千回万回と迎えられるように長寿を祝う言葉の「千秋萬歳（せんしゅうばんぜい）」が名前の由来であるとする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This means that the man possessed by God acted toshigami and walked around to give a celebration and later he went in and out of the court and the word &quot;senshubanzei&quot; (literally, one thousand autumns and ten thousand years) to celebrate the longevity was the origin of the name, so as to welcome bumper autumns thousands or ten thousands times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This means that the man possessed by God acted toshigami and walked around to give a celebration and later he went in and out of the court and the word &quot;senshubanzei&quot; (literally, one thousand autumns and ten thousand years) to celebrate the longevity was the origin of the name, so as to welcome bumper autumns thousands or ten thousands times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This means that the man possessed by the god acted Toshigami and walked around to give a celebration and later he went in and out of the court and the word &apos;senshubanzei&apos; (literally, one thousand autumns and ten thousand years) to celebrate the longevity was the origin of the name, so as to welcome bumper autumns thousands or ten thousands times.</e>
<cmt>the godに訂正しました。Toshigamiに訂正しました。 &quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="23">
<j>11世紀に当時の芸能や世相の一端を書き記した『新猿楽記』の「千秋万歳之酒祷（せんずまんざいのさかほがい）」という記述からも、平安時代頃すでに芸能として成立していったことが伺える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As &quot;Shin sarugoki&quot; (a kind of textbook about manners and cultures of Kyoto in Heian era), where parts of the entertainment and social situation during the eleventh century were written, has the description &quot;senzumanzai no sakahogai,&quot; we can know that manzai as an entertainment already existed around the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As &quot;Shin sarugoki&quot; (a kind of textbook about manners and cultures of Kyoto in Heian era), where parts of the entertainment and social situation during the eleventh century were written, has the description &quot;senzumanzai no sakahogai,&quot; we can know that manzai as an entertainment already existed around the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As &quot;Shin sarugoki&quot; (a kind of textbook about manners and cultures of Kyoto in Heian era), where parts of the entertainment and social situation during the 11th century were written, has the description &apos;senzumanzai no sakahogai,&apos; we can know that manzai as an entertainment already existed around the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>数字に訂正しました。 &quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="24">
<j>変遷</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Transition</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Transition</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Transition</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>千秋萬歳は平安時代の末期には貴族の間で毎年正月の慣習となっており、千秋萬歳法師が訪れ祝い言を述べ舞を舞った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Senzumanzai was an annual practice of the New Year among the aristocrats during the late Heian period and the senzumazai hoshi (Buddhist priest wishing a New Year) visited each house to give a celebration and danced.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Senzumanzai was an annual practice of the New Year among the aristocrats during the late Heian period and the senzumazai hoshi (Buddhist priest wishing a New Year) visited each house to give a celebration and danced.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Senzumanzai was an annual practice of the New Year among the aristocrats during the late Heian period and the senzumazai hoshi (Buddhist priest wishing a New Year) visited each house to give a celebration and danced.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>貴族の衰退と入れ替わるように、武家が権力を持った鎌倉時代以降は、寺社や武家など権門勢家を訪れるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Replacing the aristocrats who were on the wane, samurai families became powerful after the Kamakura period and the priests visited the great and powerful such as temples, shrines and samurai families.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Replacing the aristocrats who were on the wane, samurai families became powerful after the Kamakura period and the priests visited the great and powerful such as temples, shrines and samurai families.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Replacing the aristocrats who were on the wane, samurai families became powerful after the Kamakura period and the priests visited the great and powerful such as temples, shrines and samurai families.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>室町時代になると、声聞師が千秋萬歳法師のかわりをするようになって、中頃には一般民家にも門付けしてまわるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Muromachi period, Shomonji (a group of itinerant performers whose work encompassed both no performance and religious ritual) substituted for the senzumanzai hoshi and during the middle of the Muromachi period, they performed in front of the ordinary houses.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Muromachi period, Shomonji (a group of itinerant performers whose work encompassed both no performance and religious ritual) substituted for the senzumanzai hoshi and during the middle of the Muromachi period, they performed in front of ordinary houses.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Muromachi period, Shomonji (a group of itinerant performers whose work encompassed both no performance and religious ritual) substituted for the senzumanzai hoshi and during the middle of the Muromachi period, they performed in front of ordinary houses.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="28">
<j>伝播と拡大</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Propagation and expansion</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Propagation and expansion</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Propagation and expansion</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>大和国（奈良県）の萬歳が千秋萬歳として京都で行われ、後に尾張萬歳、三河萬歳へと伝わり、さらに全国各地に広まったものと思われるが、尾張萬歳、三河萬歳とも、伝承由来はこの通りとしていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It seems that the manzai in Yamato province (Nara prefecture) was performed as senzumanzai in Kyoto and later introduced to Owari-manzai and Mikawa-manzai and furthermore across Japan, however, both Owari-manzai and Mikawa-manzai does not accept the origin of tradition.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It seems that the manzai in Yamato province (Nara prefecture) was performed as senzumanzai in Kyoto and later introduced to Owari-manzai and Mikawa-manzai and furthermore across Japan, however, both Owari-manzai and Mikawa-manzai does not accept the origin of tradition.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It seems that the manzai in Yamato Province (Nara Prefecture) was performed as senzumanzai in Kyoto and later introduced to Owari-manzai and Mikawa-manzai and furthermore across Japan, however, both Owari-manzai and Mikawa-manzai does not accept the origin of tradition.</e>
<cmt>Yamato Province (Nara Prefecture)に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>また越前萬歳（野大坪万歳）については、約1500年前の継体天皇にまつわる伝承を由来と主張するものもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, some insist that Echizen-manzai (Nootsubo-manzai) originates from the tradition connected to Emperor Keitai about 1500 years ago.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, some insist that Echizen-manzai (Nootsubo-manzai) originates from the tradition connected to Emperor Keitai about 1500 years ago.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, some insist that Echizen-manzai (Nootsubo-manzai) originates from the tradition connected to Emperor Keitai about 1500 years ago.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>しかし江戸時代以降に伝わった地域の萬歳は、大体継承過程を明らかにしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in the region where the manzai was introduced after the Edo period, the process of tradition is mostly elucidated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in the region where the manzai was introduced after the Edo period, the process of tradition is mostly elucidated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in the region where the manzai was introduced after the Edo period, the process of tradition is mostly elucidated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>加賀萬歳は越前萬歳の流れを汲むものであるが、秋田萬歳、会津萬歳などは三河萬歳からの派生であり、伊予萬歳は尾張萬歳の系統であるといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Kaga-manzai originates from Echizen-manzai, Akita-manzai, Aizu-manzai and so on from Mikawa-manzai and Iyo-manzai from Owari-manzai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Kaga-manzai originates from Echizen-manzai, Akita-manzai, Aizu-manzai and so on from Mikawa-manzai and Iyo-manzai from Owari-manzai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Kaga-manzai originates from Echizen-manzai, Akita-manzai, Aizu-manzai and so on from Mikawa-manzai and Iyo-manzai from Owari-manzai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="33">
<j>衰退と復興</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Decline and revival</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Decline and revival</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Decline and revival</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>明治時代に、さらに多くの地域に分かれて各地の名前を冠する萬歳が登場するようになったが、その多くは三河萬歳と尾張萬歳の系統であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Meiji period, even more manzais which have the names of the place appeared separately in many regions, but many of them originated from Mikawa-manzai and Owari-manzai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Meiji period, even more manzai which have the names of the place, appeared separately in many regions, but many of them originated from Mikawa-manzai and Owari-manzai.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Meiji period, even more manzai which have the names of the place, appeared separately in many regions, but many of them originated from Mikawa-manzai and Owari-manzai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>仏教色の濃い陰陽道の影響下にあった三河萬歳は、神道に変化して国家神道の政策の中で残っていき、大正時代の中頃まで萬歳の参内はあったようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mikawa-manzai, which was under the influence of the very Buddhism-oriented Onmyodo (way of Yin and Yang; occult divination system based on the Taoist theory of the five elements), changed into Shinto, survived through the policies of state-sanctioned Shinto and seems to have been performed in the court until the middle of Taisho period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mikawa-manzai, which was under the influence of the very Buddhism-oriented Onmyodo (way of Yin and Yang; occult divination system based on the Taoist theory of the five elements), changed into Shinto, survived through the policies of state-sanctioned Shinto and seems to have been performed in the court until the middle of the Taisho period.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mikawa-manzai, which was under the influence of the very Buddhism-oriented Onmyodo (way of Yin and Yang; occult divination system based on the Taoist theory of the five elements), changed into Shinto religion, survived through the policies of state-sanctioned Shinto religion and seems to have been performed in the court until the middle of the Taisho period.</e>
<cmt>religion補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>一方、尾張萬歳は娯楽性を高め、通年で興行として成立するものも現れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, Owari-manzai was more and more entertaining and some gave performances through a whole year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, Owari-manzai was more and more entertaining and some gave performances throughout the whole year.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, Owari-manzai was more and more entertaining and some gave performances throughout the whole year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>こういった新しい尾張萬歳の中から漫才の基礎となる形のものも生み出された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The new Owari-manzai gave rise to the basic form of manzai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The new Owari-manzai gave rise to the basic form of manzai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The new Owari-manzai gave rise to the basic form of manzai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>また、正月に行われる従来の萬歳も、民間での門付は第二次世界大戦頃までは盛んであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The traditional manzai performed in front of the houses in the New Year was also popular among folks until around the Second World War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The traditional manzai performed in front of the houses in the New Year was also popular among folks until around the Second World War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The traditional manzai performed in front of the houses in the New Year was also popular among folks until around World War II.</e>
<cmt>the World War II.に訂正しました。→the を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>しかし多くの萬歳は第二次大戦後に衰退し、大和萬歳については継承が無く途絶えてしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, many of manzais declined after the Second World War and Yamato-manzai discontinued because of no succession.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, many of these different manzai declined after the Second World War and Yamato-manzai discontinued because of no succession.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, many of these different manzai declined after World War II and Yamato-manzai discontinued because of no succession.</e>
<cmt>the World War II.に訂正しました。→the を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="40">
<j>現在ある、各地の萬歳には継承者を捜し出して復興させたものが多いが、成立時期が古いとされる三河萬歳（愛知県安城市・西尾市など）と越前萬歳（福井県越前市）が1995年（平成7年）に、尾張萬歳（愛知県知多市）が1996年（平成8年）にそれぞれ国の重要無形民俗文化財に指定された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many of the existing manzais in each place across Japan have found the successors and revived, but Mikawa-manzai (Anjo city, Nishio city and so on in Aichi prefecture) and Echizen-manzai (Echizen city in Fukui prefecture), whose time of formation is said to have been old, were designated as the nation&apos;s significant intangible folklore cultural assets in 1995, and so was Owari-manzai (Chita city in Aichi prefecture) in 1996.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many of the existing manzai in each place across Japan have found successors and been revived, but Mikawa-manzai (Anjo city, Nishio city and so on in Aichi prefecture) and Echizen-manzai (Echizen city in Fukui prefecture), whose time of formation is said to have been old, were designated as the nation&apos;s significant intangible folklore cultural assets in 1995, and so was Owari-manzai (Chita city in Aichi prefecture) in 1996.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many of the existing manzai in each place across Japan have found successors and been revived, but Mikawa-manzai (Anjo City, Nishio City and so on in Aichi Prefecture) and Echizen-manzai (Echizen city in Fukui Prefecture), whose time of formation is said to have been old, were designated as the nation&apos;s significant intangible folklore cultural assets in 1995, and so was Owari-manzai (Chita City in Aichi Prefecture) in 1996.</e>
<cmt>City、Prefecture大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="41">
<j>全国の萬歳</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Manzais around Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Manzai around Japan</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Manzai around Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>主な萬歳</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Main manzais</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Main manzai</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Main manzai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>秋田萬歳（秋田県）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akita-manzai (Akita prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akita-manzai (Akita prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akita-manzai (Akita Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>Prefecture大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>会津萬歳（福島県）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Aizu-manzai (Fukushima prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Aizu-manzai (Fukushima prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Aizu-manzai (Fukushima Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>Prefecture大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>加賀萬歳（石川県）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaga-manzai (Ishikawa prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaga-manzai (Ishikawa prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaga-manzai (Ishikawa Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>Prefecture大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>越前萬歳（福井県） 国指定文化財民俗文化財（1995年12月26日）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Echizen-manzai (Fukui prefecture) The nation&apos;s designated cultural assets folklore cultural assets (December 26, 1995)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Echizen-manzai (Fukui prefecture) The nation&apos;s designated cultural assets folklore cultural assets (December 26, 1995)</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Echizen-manzai (Fukui Prefecture) The nation&apos;s designated cultural assets folklore cultural assets (December 26, 1995)</e>
<cmt>Prefecture大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>三河萬歳（愛知県） 国指定重要無形民俗文化財（1995年12月26日）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mikawa-manzai (Aichi prefecture)The nation&apos;s designated significant intangible folklore cultural assets (December 26, 1995)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mikawa-manzai (Aichi prefecture)The nation&apos;s designated significant intangible folklore cultural assets (December 26, 1995)</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mikawa-manzai (Aichi Prefecture)The nation&apos;s designated significant intangible folklore cultural assets (December 26, 1995)</e>
<cmt>Prefecture大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>尾張萬歳（愛知県） 国指定重要無形民俗文化財（1996年12月20日）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Owari-manzai (Aichi prefecture)The nation&apos;s designated significant intangible folklore cultural assets (December 20, 1996)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Owari-manzai (Aichi prefecture)The nation&apos;s designated significant intangible folklore cultural assets (December 20, 1996)</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Owari-manzai (Aichi Prefecture)The nation&apos;s designated significant intangible folklore cultural assets (December 20, 1996)</e>
<cmt>Prefecture大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>伊勢萬歳（三重県）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ise-manzai (Mie prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ise-manzai (Mie prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ise-manzai (Mie Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>Prefecture大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>大和萬歳（奈良県）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamato-manzai (Nara prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yamato-manzai (Nara prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamato-manzai (Nara Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>Prefecture大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>伊予萬歳（愛媛県）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Iyo-manzai (Ehime prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Iyo-manzai (Ehime prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Iyo-manzai (Ehime Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>Prefecture大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="52">
<j>沖縄萬歳</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Okinawa-manzai</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Okinawa-manzai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Okinawa-manzai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>沖縄県の高平良萬歳（たかでーらまんぢゃい・高平萬歳とも表記）は、一般的に組踊「万歳敵討」（まんざいてきうち）の一場面を抜き出した舞踊の演目であって、この項目でいう萬歳とは異なる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takadera-manjai (spelled as 高平良萬歳 or高平萬歳) in Okinawa prefecture is generally a program of dancing which extracts one scene from &quot;kumi-odori&quot; (combination dance) called &quot;Manzai Tekiuchi&quot; (Vengeance Fulfilled) and is different from the manzai in this section.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takadera-manjai (spelled as 高平良萬歳 or高平萬歳) in Okinawa prefecture is generally a program of dancing which extracts one scene from &quot;kumi-odori&quot; (combination dance) called &quot;Manzai Tekiuchi&quot; (Vengeance Fulfilled) and is different from the manzai in this section.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takadera-manjai (written as 高平良萬歳 or 高平萬歳 in Chinese characters) in Okinawa Prefecture is generally a program of dancing which extracts one scene from kumi-odori (combination dance) called &apos;Manzai Tekiuchi&apos; (Vengeance Fulfilled) and is different from the manzai in this section.</e>
<cmt>Prefecture大文字にしました。(written as 高平良萬歳 or 高平萬歳 in Chinese characters)に訂正しました。&quot; &quot;を削除しました。 &quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>本来の沖縄の萬歳は、首里郊外の安仁屋部落にいた萬歳行者（まんぢゃいこーしー）が年のはじめに各家々の門に立ちよって祝言をとなえ人形を舞わせていたようであるが、大正時代には今帰仁などではすでに見受けられず、萬歳行者という言葉だけが伝えられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the traditional manzai in Okinawa, &quot;manjaikoshi&quot; (strolling comic dancer) in the Shuri suburb of Aniya hamlet seem to have stood by the gate of each house, given celebration words and made the dolls dancing at the beginning of year, but in the Taisho period they were not seen in Nakijin and so on, and only the word manjai-koshi remains.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the traditional manzai in Okinawa, &quot;manjaikoshi&quot; (strolling comic dancer) in the Shuri suburb of Aniya hamlet seems to have stood by the gate of each house, given celebration words and made dolls dance at the beginning of the year, but in the Taisho period they were not seen in Nakijin and so on, and only the word manjai-koshi remains.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the traditional manzai in Okinawa, manjai-koshi (strolling comic dancer) in the Shuri suburb of Aniya hamlet seems to have stood by the gate of each house, given celebration words and made dolls dance at the beginning of the year, but in the Taisho period they were not seen in Nakijin and so on, and only the word manjai-koshi remains.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を削除しました。ハイフン補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 伊勢山(id:188062), Cprobot(id:97843), D.h(id:79056), Himazin(id:22034), Tjan(id:17305), Akimoto(id:6951), 三日月(id:19540), Greenland4(id:114494), Qwui9a9a(id:211584), Hatsune(id:26654), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>