<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>左近桜</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sakon no sakura, Cherry tree of Sakon</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sakon no sakura, Cherry tree of Sakon</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sakon no Sakura</e>
<cmt>タイトルのため単語の頭文字を大文字にし、&quot;Cherry tree of Sakon&quot;を次行に移動</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>左近桜（さこんのさくら）は、平安京内裏紫宸殿からおりる南階の、紫宸殿から見て左方、東南隅第一間にあった桜の樹。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sakon no sakura is the cherry tree which existed in the first bay of the south-east corner at the left direction on the South floor down from the inner court ceremonial hall of Heian-kyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sakon no sakura is a cherry tree which existed in the first bay of the south-east corner to the left of the South floor down from the inner court ceremonial hall of Heian-kyo.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sakon no sakura (the cherry tree of Sakon) is a cherry tree which existed in the first bay of the south-east corner to the left of the South floor down from the inner court ceremonial hall of Heian-kyo.</e>
<cmt>the cherry tree of Sakonを追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>右近橘に相対した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was facing Ukon no Tachibana, the mandarin orange tree.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It faced Ukon no Tachibana, the mandarin orange tree.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It faced Ukon no Tachibana, the mandarin orange tree.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>左近桜という名称は、殿上で儀式のあるときこの桜の方に左近衛の陣を敷いたことによる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name of Sakon no sakura comes from the fact that the battle array of Capital Guard of the Left was set in the direction of this cherry tree at a ceremony of the court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name Sakon no sakura comes from the fact that the battle array for the Capital Guard of the Left was set in the direction of this cherry tree during court ceremonies.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name Sakon no sakura comes from the fact that the battle array for the Capital Guard of the Left was set in the direction of this cherry tree during court ceremonies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>南殿の桜ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called as the cherry tree of the south hall.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was also called the cherry tree of the south hall.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was also called the cherry tree of the south hall.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>もとは梅の樹で桓武天皇の遷都のときに植えられたが、承和 (日本)年間（834年-847年）枯死したため、仁明天皇のときあらためて桜を植えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally a plum tree was planted when Emperor Kanmu transferred the capital; however, a cherry tree was planted instead in the period of Emperor Ninmei as the original plum tree died during the Showa era (834 to 847).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally a plum tree was planted when Emperor Kanmu transferred the capital; however, a cherry tree was planted instead during the period of Emperor Ninmei as the original plum tree died during the Showa era (834 to 847).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally a plum tree was planted when the Emperor Kanmu transferred the capital; however, a cherry tree was planted instead during the period of the Emperor Ninmyo as the original plum tree died during the Showa era (834 to 847).</e>
<cmt>Emperor Ninmei→Emperor Ninmyoに修正&quot;the&quot; を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>貞観 (日本)年間（859年-876年）に枯れたが、その根から生じた芽を坂上滝守が勅命で培養し、ふたたび枝葉が盛んになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The cherry tree died during the Jogan era (859 to 876), but SAKANOUE no Takimori grew the germ came out of its root under the Emperor&apos;s ordinance, and the tree regained a lot of branches and leaves.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The cherry tree died during the Jogan era (859 to 876), but SAKANOUE no Takimori grew a spaling from its root as per the Emperor&apos;s orders, and the tree regained much of its branches and leaves.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The cherry tree died during the Jogan era (859 to 876), but SAKANOUE no Takimori grew a spaling from its root as per the Emperor&apos;s orders, and the tree regained much of its branches and leaves.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>天徳 (日本)3年（959年）9月内裏焼失のとき桜も焼けたため、内裏造営におよんで、重明親王の家の吉野桜を移植し、康保元年（964年）11月、同2年（965年）正月の2回にわたり改栽した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The cherry tree was also burnt down at the loss of the inner court by fire in September 959; the Yoshino cherry tree at the residence of Imperial Prince Shigeakira was replanted when the inner court was rebuilt, and it was replanted twice in November 964 and New Year in 965.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The cherry tree was also burnt down during a fire which occured in the inner court in September 959; the Yoshino cherry tree at the residence of Imperial Prince Shigeakira was replanted when the inner court was rebuilt, and it was replanted twice in November 964 and New Years in 965.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The cherry tree was also burnt down during a fire which occured in the inner court in September 959; the Yoshino cherry tree at the residence of Imperial Prince Shigeakira was replanted when the inner court was rebuilt, and it was replanted twice in November 964 and New Years in 965.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>その後しばしば焼け、堀河天皇のときに植えたものが最後となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The tree was burnt down several times since then and the one which was planted at the time of Emperor Horikawa was the last tree.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The tree was burnt down several times since then and the one which was planted at the time of Emperor Horikawa was the last tree.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The tree was burnt down several times since then and the one which was planted at the time of the Emperor Horikawa was the last tree.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the&quot; を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>ひな祭りでひな壇に並べられることがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sakon no sakura is sometimes displayed on a tiered stand at Doll&apos;s Festival.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sakon no sakura is sometimes displayed on a tiered stand during the Doll&apos;s Festival.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sakon no sakura is sometimes displayed on a tiered stand during the Doll&apos;s Festival.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>