<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>駒沢利斎</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Risai KOMAZAWA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Risai KOMAZAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Risai KOMAZAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>駒沢利斎（こまざわ　りさい）は千家十職の一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Risai KOMAZAWA is one of the Senke Jisshoku (The Sen Family&apos;s Ten Craftsmen).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Risai KOMAZAWA was one of the Senke Jisshoku (The Sen Family&apos;s Ten Craftsmen).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Risai KOMAZAWA was one of the Senke Jisshoku (The Ten Craftsmen of the House of Sen).</e>
<cmt>統一事項に基づき、The Sen Family&apos;s Ten Craftsmen→The Ten Craftsmen of the House of Senとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>三千家御用達の棚や香合、炉縁などを製作する指物師が代々継承する名跡である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a professional name of headship passed down in the family of joiner who has been making shelves, incense containers and hearth frames for the three Houses of Sen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a professional name of headship passed down through a family of joiners who have made shelves, incense containers and hearth frames for the three Houses of Sen.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a professional name of headship passed down through a family of joiners who have made shelves, incense containers and hearth frames for the three Houses of Sen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>当代は14代が昭和52年（1977年）に逝去後、長く空席が続いており、14代の甥の息子である吉田博三が後を嗣ぐべく修行中である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the death of the fourteenth generation in 1977, the position of headship has been vacant for a long time, and Hirozo YOSHIDA (吉田博三), a son of the fourteenth Risai KOMAZAWA&apos;s nephew, is taking a training in order to be a successor.</e>
<cmt>吉田博三→Hirozo YOSHIDA[正しい読み方が不明です]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the death of the fourteenth generation in 1977, the position of headmaster has been vacant for a long time, and Hirozo YOSHIDA (吉田博三), a son of the fourteenth Risai KOMAZAWA&apos;s nephew, is undergoing training in order to succeed the position.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the death of the fourteenth generation in 1977, the position of headmaster has been vacant for a long time, and Hirozo YOSHIDA (吉田博三), a son of the fourteenth Risai KOMAZAWA&apos;s nephew, is undergoing training in order to succeed the position.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>初代・宗源が延宝年間に指物業を始めたのが最初とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first generation, Sogen began working as a joiner during the Enpo era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first generation, Sogen began working as a joiner during the Enpo era.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first generation, Sogen began working as a joiner during the Enpo era.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="6">
<j>千家に関わったのは2代・宗慶からで、千宗旦の注文により指物を製作したと言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was the second generation, Sokei, who got involved in the House of Sen, being ordered by Sotan SEN to make joinery.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The second generation headmaster, Sokei, who became involved in the House of Sen, was ordered by Sotan SEN to make joinery.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The second generation headmaster, Sokei, who became involved in the House of Sen, was ordered by Sotan SEN to make joinery.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>しかし、積極的に千家に関わるのは4代・利斎からである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it was after the fourth generation, Risai, who was more deeply involved in the House of Sen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it was after the fourth generation, Risai, that they became more deeply involved in the House of Sen.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it was after the fourth generation, Risai, that they became more deeply involved in the House of Sen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>彼は表千家六世・覚々斎の知遇を得て千家出入りの茶方指物師として指名され、「利斎」の名を与えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He established a warm friendship with Kakukakusai, the sixth generation of Omote Senke (the main branch of the Senke school of tea ceremony), being designated as a regular joiner for the tea ceremony and given the name of &apos;Risai&apos; by the House of Sen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He established a warm friendship with Kakukakusai, the sixth generation of Omote Senke (the main branch of the Senke school of tea ceremony), and was designated as a regular joiner for tea ceremony and given the name of &apos;Risai&apos; by the House of Sen.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He established a warm friendship with Kakukakusai, the sixth generation of Omote Senke (the main branch of the Senke school of tea ceremony), and was designated as a regular joiner for tea ceremony and given the name of &apos;Risai&apos; by the House of Sen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>これ以後、代々の駒沢家当主は「利斎」を名乗るようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since then, the head of the Komazawa family has called himself &apos;Risai.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since then, the head of the Komazawa family has called himself &apos;Risai.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since then, the head of the Komazawa family has called himself &apos;Risai.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="10">
<j>江戸時代後期に活躍した7代・利斎は指物だけではなく塗師としても一流の腕を持ち、黒田正玄や飛来一閑らと合作を作るなど意欲的に製作を行い、長寿にも恵まれ「駒沢家中興の祖」といわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The seventh Risai, who was working vigorously in the late Edo period and also an excellent lacquerer as well as a joiner, collaborated with both Seigen KURODA and Ikkan HIKI, and lived long, being called &apos;the restorer of the Komazawa family.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The seventh Risai, who worked vigorously in the late Edo period and was also an excellent lacquerer as well as a joiner, collaborated with both Seigen KURODA and Ikkan HIKI, and lived a long life, being called &apos;the restorer of the Komazawa family.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The seventh Risai, who worked vigorously in the late Edo period and was also an excellent lacquerer as well as a joiner, collaborated with both Seigen KURODA and Ikkan HIKI, and lived a long life, being called &apos;the restorer of the Komazawa family.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="11">
<j>その後は大成する前に早世する当主が相次ぐ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the seventh generation, however, the heads of the family died young one after another before they achieved greatness.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the seventh generation, however, the heads of the family died young one after another before achieving greatness.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the seventh generation, however, the heads of the family died young one after another before achieving greatness.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>13代・利斎は70歳まで生きたものの、晩年に儲けた息子に先立たれると言う不幸にあう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The thirteenth Risai lived up to seventy, but he suffered misfortune of losing his son whom he got in his later years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The thirteenth Risai lived up to seventy, but suffered the misfortune of losing his son who was born in his later years.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The thirteenth Risai lived up to seventy, but suffered the misfortune of losing his son who was born in his later years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>13代の死後、妻であった浪江は娘・千代子を後継者とするべく家業の継承を決意、14代・利斎となるが、その千代子も昭和36年（1961年）に早世、14代も昭和52年に死去、以後現在に至るまで名跡は空席となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the death of the thirteenth generation, his wife Namie deicided to become the fourteenth Risai and have her daughter Chiyoko succeed to her in the future, but the daughter died young in 1961, and she also died in 1977; the position of the head is still vacant until today.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the death of the thirteenth generation, his wife Namie deicided to become the fourteenth Risai and have her daughter Chiyoko succeed her in the future, but the daughter died young in 1961, and she also died in 1977, leaving the position vacant to this day.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the death of the thirteenth generation, his wife Namie deicided to become the fourteenth Risai and have her daughter Chiyoko succeed her in the future, but the daughter died young in 1961, and she also died in 1977, leaving the position vacant to this day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 こぶまき(id:38278), Okapia2(id:98589), 「あなたには関係ない」(id:49400), D.h(id:79056), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>