<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>日本の宗教</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Religions of Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Religions of Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Religions of Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>日本の宗教（にほんのしゅうきょう）では、日本における宗教を解説する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Religions of Japan&quot; describes religions in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Religions of Japan&quot; describes religions in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Religions of Japan&quot; describes religions in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>日本における宗教の信者数は、文化庁「宗教年鑑」によると、神道系が約1億600万人、仏教系が約9,600万人、キリスト教系が約200万人、その他約1,100万人、合計2億1,500万人となり、日本の総人口の2倍弱の信者数になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Shukyo Nenkan&quot; (Annual Statistics of Religion) issued by the Agency for Cultural Affairs, there are around 106 million Shintoists, around 96 million Buddhists, around 2 million Christians, and around 11million followers of other religions in Japan, adding up to 215 million people, or nearly twice the total population of Japan, belonging to any religion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Shukyo Nenkan&quot; (Annual Statistics of Religion) issued by the Agency for Cultural Affairs, there are around 106 million Shintoists, around 96 million Buddhists, around 2 million Christians, and around 11million followers of other religions in Japan, adding up to 215 million people, or nearly twice the total population of Japan, belonging to any religion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &apos;Annual Statistics of Religion&apos; (Shukyo Nenkan) issued by the Agency for Cultural Affairs, there are around 106 million Shintoists, around 96 million Buddhists, around 2 million Christians, and around 11million followers of other religions in Japan, adding up to 215 million people, or nearly twice the total population of Japan, belonging to any religion.</e>
<cmt>書名の記載を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>神道系と仏教系だけで2億人をこえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Only Shintoists and Buddhists come to more than 200 million.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Only Shintoists and Buddhists come to more than 200 million.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Only Shintoists and Buddhists come to more than 200 million.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>これは、日本古来の民族信仰の基盤の上に、自然風土の中で培われた年中行事や、祭礼などを通じて、多くの日本人が七五三や初詣、あるいは季節の祭りを神社で行い、江戸時代の寺請制度の影響で、葬式や盆などを仏教式で行うなど、複数の宗教にまたがって儀礼に参加しているためである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is because many Japanese people engage in rituals of multiple religions, by holding the seven-five-three festival and other seasonal festivals at shrines and visiting shrines at the beginning of the New Year based on annual events and rituals developed in natural climate from ancient ethnic religion of Japan, and by holding funerals and bon festival (a festival of the dead or Buddhist all soul&apos;s day) with Buddhist rites, influenced by terauke seido (the system in which the public should be registered in any one of designated temples to prove their Buddhist faith) in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is because many Japanese people engage in rituals of multiple religions, holding the seven-five-three festival and other seasonal festivals at shrines and visiting shrines at the beginning of the New Year based on annual events and rituals developed in the natural climate from ancient ethnic religions of Japan, and hold funerals and bon festivals (a festival of the dead or Buddhist all soul&apos;s day) with Buddhist rites, and were influenced by terauke seido (the system in which the public should be registered in any one of designated temples to prove their Buddhist faith) in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is because many Japanese people engage in rituals of multiple religions, holding the seven-five-three festival and other seasonal festivals at shrines and visiting shrines at the beginning of the New Year based on annual events and rituals developed in the natural climate from ancient ethnic religions of Japan, and by the influence of the temple guarantee system in the Edo period, holding funerals and bon festivals (a festival of the dead or Buddhist all soul&apos;s day) with Buddhist rites.</e>
<cmt>寺請制度の訳を簡略化しました。寺請制度の説明の位置を変更いたしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>他国では洗礼を受けた時点でその宗教の信者に成るのに対し、日本ではその宗教の神を拝めば信者とみなす（氏子であり檀家でもある者などが多くいる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">People become a member of a religion when getting baptized in other countries, while those who worship God of a religion are deemed to be a believer of the religion in Japan (Many people are shrine parishioners and Buddhist parishioners at the same time.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">People become a member of a religion when becoming baptized in other countries, while those who worship a god of a religion are deemed to be a believer of a religion in Japan (Many people are shrine parishioners and Buddhist parishioners at the same time.)</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">People become a member of a religion by baptism in other countries, while those who worship a god of a religion are deemed to be a believer of that religion in Japan, (where many people are shrine parishioners and Buddhist parishioners at the same time).</e>
<cmt>洗礼を簡略化しました。文末を左記のように致しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>そのため、神や仏を同等に崇拝する日本人は複数の宗教を掛け持つ形となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, Japanese people who worship deities and Buddha equally belong to multiple religions.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, Japanese people who worship deities and Buddha equally belong to multiple religions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, Japanese people who worship deities and Buddha equally belong to multiple religions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>神道、仏教</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinto and Buddhism</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinto and Buddhism</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinto and Buddhism</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>前述の通り、日本では神道、仏教の信徒が大多数を占めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As discussed above, great majority of Japanese people are Shintoists and Buddhists.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As discussed above, great majority of Japanese people are Shintoists and Buddhists.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As discussed above, great majority of Japanese people are Shintoists and Buddhists.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>神道は明確な教義が存在しない（注：教派神道系のセクト宗教(新宗教)には明確な教義が存在する）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinto does not have clearly defined dogma (Note: Religious sects of Sect Shinto [new religions] have concrete dogmas.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinto does not have a clearly defined dogma (Note: Religious sects of Sect Shinto [new religions] have concrete dogmas.)</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinto does not have a clearly defined dogma (Note: Religious sects of Sect Shinto [new religions] have concrete dogmas.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>その為、厳密な入信規定などは神道に存在しないが、神棚の設置、神社への寄付、祭事への参加などをもって信者と見る向きが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are thus no strict rules to join Shinto, but they are usually considered to be believers by installing a household Shinto altar, making offerings to shrines, and participating in rituals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are thus no strict rules to join Shinto, but they are usually considered to be believers if they install a household Shinto altar, make offerings to shrines, and participate in rituals.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are thus no strict rules to join Shinto, but they are usually considered to be believers if they install a household Shinto altar, make offerings to shrines, and participate in rituals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>また生後の氏神参りを他宗教でいう洗礼とみなし、これをもって神道の一員になるという解釈も出来る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Visiting tutelary deities after birth can also be interpreted as baptism of other religions, which gives the membership to Shinto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Visiting tutelary deities after birth can also be interpreted as baptism of other religions, which gives the membership to Shinto.</e>
<cmt>Doesn&apos;t make sense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The custom of bringing a baby to the deity of the clan (ujigami) after birth may be interpreted as a kind of baptism of other religions, which gives the membership of Shinto.</e>
<cmt>左記のように変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>仏教は大部分が大乗仏教である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for Buddhism, Mahayana Buddhism is mainly practiced.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for Buddhism, mainly Mahayana Buddhism is practiced.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for Buddhism, mainly Mahayana Buddhism is practiced.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>鎌倉時代に普及した仏教（鎌倉仏教）が今日のものの礎となっており、日本の歴史に深く影響を与え、現在にいたるまで信者数も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Buddhism popular in the Kamakura period (Kamakura Bukkyo) has served as the basis for today&apos;s Mahayana Buddhism, has deeply influenced Japanese history, and has been followed by many people up to the present day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Buddhism that was popular in the Kamakura period (Kamakura Bukkyo) which served as the basis for today&apos;s Mahayana Buddhism, deeply influenced Japanese history, and has been followed by many people up to the present day.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Buddhism that was popular in the Kamakura period (Kamakura Buddhism) served as the basis of today&apos;s Mahayana Buddhism with profound influence in Japanese history, and has been followed by many people up to the present day.</e>
<cmt>左記のようにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>全体的に教祖信仰的な趣が強く、戒律も厳しくなく、他宗派との表だった論争も少ない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the whole the religion is based on faith of the founder, without strict principles and with few outright disputes with other religions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the whole the religion is based on faith of the founder, which has strict principles but few disputes with other religions.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the whole, this is based on the faith in the founder with few strict principles, so that there are few open disputes with other religions.</e>
<cmt>戒律は「厳しくない」という意味がわかるようにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>本来は出家することで正式な仏教徒となるが、多くの日本人の場合は自身の葬儀の場において戒名を得ることにより仏門に入る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those who become priests are supposed to be formally recognized as Buddhists, but many Japanese enter the Buddhist priesthood by receiving posthumous Buddhist names at their own funerals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those who become priests are supposed to be formally recognized as Buddhists, but many Japanese enter the Buddhist priesthood by receiving posthumous Buddhist names at their own funerals.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those who become priests are supposed to be formally recognized as Buddhists, but many Japanese enter the Buddhist priesthood by receiving posthumous Buddhist names at their own funerals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>ちなみに、チベット仏教などの諸外国の仏教は、一部のインテリ層には支持されているものの、大衆からの支持は得られておらず、存在感はきわめて薄い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Buddhism schools from other countries, such as Tibetan Buddhism, are not supported by the public, except some intellectuals, thus showing the very weak presence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Buddhist schools from other countries, such as Tibetan Buddhism, are not supported by the public, except by some intellectuals, and have a very weak presence.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Buddhist schools in other countries, such as Tibetan Buddhism, are not supported by the public, except by some intellectuals, and have a very weak presence.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="16">
<j>日本では長く神仏習合が行われたため、神道と仏教の間には明確な境界線が存在しない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since syncretism of Shinto and Buddhism has been promoted for a long time in Japan, there is no clear line between the two.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the syncretism of Shinto and Buddhism has been promoted for a long time in Japan, there is no clear line between the two.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the syncretism of Shinto and Buddhism has been seen for a long time in Japan, there is no clear line between the two.</e>
<cmt>神仏習合にはpromoteは不適切な感じがいたします。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>例えば、神棚を祀っている家庭には仏壇があることが多く、2つの宗教に同時に入信している家庭が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, many families with a household Shinto altar also have a Buddhist altar, belonging to two religions at the same time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, many families with a household Shinto altar also have a Buddhist altar, belonging to two religions at the same time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, many families with a household Shinto altar also have a Buddhist altar, belonging to two religions at the same time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>これが、神道と仏教で信者を合わせると2億人を超えると言われる所以である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is why Shintoists and Buddhists is said to come to the total of more than 200 million people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is why Shintoists and Buddhists are said to total more than 200 million people.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is why Shintoists and Buddhists are said to total more than 200 million people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="19">
<j>考え方を変えると、神道と仏教という二つの宗教が日本に存在したと捉えるのではなく、渾然一体となった宗教が一つあったと捉えるほうが自然であるともいえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In another point of view, it is more natural to assume that in Japan one religion has been created by a harmonious combination of Shinto and Buddhism than to take the two to exist separately.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From another point of view, it is more natural to assume that in Japan one religion has been created through a harmonious combination of Shinto and Buddhism than to have the two exist separately.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From another point of view, it is more natural to assume that in Japan one religion has been created through a harmonious combination of Shinto and Buddhism than to consider the two have existed separately.</e>
<cmt>後半を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>歴史的に見ても現在においても、神道と仏教はその機能を分担して担っており、両者をあわせて一つの宗教観を構成しているともいえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Historically as well as presently, Shinto and Buddhism share functions with each other and it can be said that the two come together to create one religious notion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Historically as well as presently, Shinto and Buddhism share functions and it can be said that the two come together to create a single religious notion.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Historically as well as presently, Shinto and Buddhism share functions and it can be said that the two come together to create a single religious notion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="21">
<j>加えて、宗教として意識されることは少ないが、葬儀、死生観を中心に儒教も大きな影響を残している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to these two religions, Confucianism has also left its mark mainly on funerals and the view of life and death, although it is less often cited as a religion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to these two religions, Confucianism has also left its mark mainly on funerals and the view of life and death, although it is less often cited as a religion.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to these two religions, Confucianism has also left its mark mainly on funerals and the view of life and death, although it is less often cited as a religion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>先祖霊などの観念は現在では仏教に組み込まれているが、本来は仏教哲学と矛盾するものであり、古来の民間信仰と儒教に由来する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An idea of ancestors&apos; spirits, based on ancient folk religion and Confucianism, originally conflicted with Buddhist philosophy, but is now incorporated into Buddhism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The idea of ancestors&apos; spirits, based on ancient folk religion and Confucianism, originally conflicted with Buddhist philosophy, but is now incorporated into Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The idea of ancestors&apos; spirits, based on ancient folk religion and Confucianism, fundamentally conflicts with Buddhist philosophy, but is now incorporated into Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更いたしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>位牌、法事など、先祖供養に関わる重要な習慣が儒教起源である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Buddhist mortuary tablet, memorial service, and other important rites for ancestors originated in Confucianism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Buddhist mortuary tablet, memorial service, and other important rites for ancestors originated in Confucianism.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Buddhist mortuary tablet, memorial service, and other important rites for ancestors originated in Confucianism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>思想、道徳としての儒学は支配階級を中心に学ばれ、明治以降は一般庶民にも直接、間接に影響を与えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Confucianism was studied as morals and ethics mainly by people in the dominant class, and after the Meiji period, it also exerted influence, directly and indirectly, on ordinary people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Confucianism was studied for its morals and ethics mainly by people in the dominant class, and after the Meiji period, also exerted influence, directly and indirectly, on ordinary people.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Confucianism was studied for its morals and ethics mainly by the ruling class, and after the Meiji period, its influence was directly and indirectly exerted on the ordinary people.</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更いたしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="25">
<j>民間信仰的要素は歴史的経緯もあり複雑な様相をなしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Elements of folk religion are complicated partly due to its historic background.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Elements of folk religion are complicated partly due to its historical background.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Elements of folk religion are complicated partly due to its historical background.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>これらは主にアニミズムを基盤としており社殿以前の磐座や山岳信仰などに顕著であるが、神仏習合の影響も受け形を変えて受け継がれているものも多い（道祖神と地蔵菩薩、えびす信仰など）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Folk religions are generally based on animism and appear prominently in iwakura (dwelling place of a god, usually in reference to a large rock) and mountain worship before shrine buildings came to be established, and many of them changed their forms under the influence of syncretism of Shinto and Buddhism to be passed down to today (e.g., Doso-shin [traveler&apos;s guardian deity], Jizo Bosatsu [Ksitigarbha], and Ebisu worship).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Folk religions are generally based on animism and appear prominently in iwakura (dwelling place of a god, usually in reference to a large rock) and mountain worship before shrine buildings came to be established, and many of them changed their forms under the influence of syncretism of Shinto and Buddhism to be passed down to today (e.g., Doso-shin [traveler&apos;s guardian deity], Jizo Bosatsu [Ksitigarbha], and Ebisu worship).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Folk religions are generally based on animism, and this aspect appears prominently in the previous belief style in sacred rock (iwakura) or mountain before the building for worship was constructed, and many of them changed their forms under the influence of syncretism of Shinto and Buddhism to be passed down to today (e.g., Doso-shin [traveler&apos;s guardian deity], Jizo Bosatsu [Ksitigarbha], and Ebisu worship).</e>
<cmt>前半部を変更いたしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>密教などの影響を受け仏教や神道の枠に収まりがたい発展を遂げた宗教には修験道、陰陽道などがあり、真言陀羅尼や功徳を積んだ法力への期待から御霊会など怨霊の鎮魂を担っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shugendo (Japanese ascetic and shamanistic practice in mountainous sites), yin-yang philosophy, and other religions have developed to go beyond Buddhism and Shinto under the influence of Esoteric Buddhism, etc., and because of the expectation for shingon darani (mantra) and power of Buddhism attained by accumulating virtues, these religions were used to pray for repose of vengeful spirits in goryoe (sacred spirit service) and other occasions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dharani commandment</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shugendo (mountaineering asceticism), the Way of Yin and Yang and others have developed to go beyond Buddhism and Shinto under the influence of Esoteric Buddhism, and these religions were used to to pray for repose of vengeful spirits in sacred spirit service (goryoe) and other occasions from the expectation for the manifestation of mantra dharani (commandment of true words) or the power of Buddhism attained by accumulated virtues.</e>
<cmt>語順を変えました。説明を短くしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>現代でも地鎮祭などにはこの考えが残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This idea is still found today in the ground-breaking ceremony, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This idea is still found today in the ground-breaking ceremony, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This idea is still found today in the ground-breaking ceremony, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="29">
<j>一方、政権政党である公明党の支持母体の日蓮正宗系（但し、現在は破門）新宗教団体創価学会の入信者数は教団の公式発表で827万世帯、世論調査などから割り出した推計数で400万人と言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, Soka Gakkai, or a new religious body of Nichiren Shoshu sect (but it is excommunicated by the sect at present), which is the power base of one of the governing parties, the New Komeito Party, officially announce that 8.27 million heads of families belong to the body, but a poll and other survey show there are estimated to be 4 million believers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, Soka Gakkai, or a new religious body of Nichiren Shoshu sect (but it is excommunicated by the sect at present), which is the power base of one of the governing parties, the New Komeito Party, officially announced that 8.27 million heads of families belong to the body, but a poll and other survey show there are estimated to be 4 million believers.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, Soka Gakkai, or a new religious body of Nichiren Shoshu sect (but it is excommunicated by the sect at present), which is the power base of one of the governing parties, the New Komeito Party, officially announced that 8.27 million heads of families belong to the body, but a poll and other survey show there are estimated to be 4 million believers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>キリスト教</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Christianity</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Christianity</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Christianity</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="30">
<j>キリスト教の信徒は全人口の0.8パーセント記号で、フランシスコ・ザビエルによる布教直後の一時期を除き、全人口の1%を超えたことはない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Christians account for 0.8 percent of the total population and this figure has never been more than one percent, except at one time right after Francis XAVIER conducted missionary work.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Christians account for 0.8 percent of the total population and this figure has never been more than one percent, except for a period right after Francis XAVIER conducted missionary work.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Christians account for 0.8 percent of the total population and this figure has never been more than one percent, except for a period right after Francis XAVIER conducted missionary work.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="31">
<j>欧米を中心とする先進諸国は勿論、アジア全体と比較しても異例の低比率のため、日本のキリスト教関係者は、かつてこれを「1%の壁」と形容していたこともある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The figure is extraordinary low compared with the whole of Asia as well as developed countries mainly in Europe and the United States, so those involved in Christianity in Japan once described this situation as &quot;the wall of one percent.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The figure is extraordinary low compared with the whole of Asia as well as developed countries mainly in Europe and the United States, and those involved in Christianity in Japan once described this situation as &quot;the wall of one percent.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The figure is extraordinary low compared with the whole of Asia as well as developed countries mainly in Europe and the United States, and those involved in Christianity in Japan once described this situation as &quot;the wall of one percent.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>日本のキリスト教団体の多くは、ヨーロッパ・アメリカ合衆国・韓国に比して小規模で（特にプロテスタント教会）、信徒数の多い教派の第一位はカトリック教会である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many Christian groups (Protestant churches in particular) in Japan are smaller in scale than those in Europe, the United States, and South Korea, and Catholic Church has the largest number of members.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many Christian groups (Protestant churches in particular) in Japan are smaller in scale when compared to those in Europe, the United States, and South Korea, while the Catholic Church has the largest number of members.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many Christian groups (Protestant churches in particular) in Japan are smaller in scale when compared to those in Europe, the United States, and South Korea, while the Catholic Church has the largest number of members.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>また、特定の教会には属さず、自宅で聖書とのみ対峙する、「無教会運動」（指導者として内村鑑三や南原繁などが有名）がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is also &quot;Non-church movement&quot; to advocate facing the Bible alone at home without belonging to any specific church (famous leaders include Kanzo UCHIMURA and Shigeru NANBARA.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is also a &quot;Non-church movement&quot; to advocate facing the Bible alone at home without belonging to any specific church (famous leaders include Kanzo UCHIMURA and Shigeru NANBARA.)</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is also a &apos;Non-church movement&apos; to advocate facing the Bible alone at home without belonging to any specific church (famous leaders include Kanzo UCHIMURA and Shigeru NANBARA).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置と&apos;を変更いたしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>プロテスタントの最大教派は日本基督教団である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The largest Protestant denomination is the United Church of Christ in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The largest Protestant denomination is the United Church of Christ in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The largest Protestant denomination is the United Church of Christ in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>また、プロテスタントの中で福音派と呼ばれるグループは、欧米圏のキリスト教に比べて「聖書信仰」という側面が強いという特徴が指摘されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is noted that a Protestant evangelical group depends more greatly on &quot;the Bible faith&quot; aspect than other Christian groups in Europe and the United States.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is noted that a Protestant evangelical group depends more on &quot;the Bible faith&quot; aspect than other Christian groups in Europe and the United States.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also noted that a Protestant evangelical group depends more on &apos;the Bible faith&apos; than other Christian groups in Europe and the United States.</e>
<cmt>左記に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>なお、ギリシャ正教（日本正教会）の信徒数は日本では1万人前後とみられ、数的にはイスラム教以下である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Greek Orthodox Church (Japan Orthodox Church) is believed to have some 10,000 followers in Japan, which is fewer than the number of Islamic believers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Greek Orthodox Church (Japan Orthodox Church) is believed to have some 10,000 followers in Japan, which is fewer than the number of Islamic believers.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Greek Orthodox Church (Japan Orthodox Church) is believed to have some 10,000 followers in Japan, which is fewer than the number of Islamic believers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>ただし、年中行事などは信徒であるなしに関わらず一般的に認知されており、キリスト教に対する理解は深い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, annual events are acknowledged by the general public, regardless whether they are Christians, so Christianity is deeply accepted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, annual events are acknowledged by the general public, regardless of whether they are Christians, so Christianity is deeply accepted.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, annual events are acknowledged by the general public, regardless of whether they are Christians, so Christianity is deeply accepted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other religions</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other religions</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other religions</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="38">
<j>その他の宗教では、イスラム教の信徒が約7万人いるといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among other religions, Islam is thought to have about 70,000 believers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among other religions, Islam is thought to have about 70,000 believers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among other religions, Islam is thought to have about 70,000 believers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>1990年代後半から徐々に増加傾向にあるといわれるが、これは中東出身者との結婚で改宗した人々が影響していると思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said the number of Muslims has continued to gradually increase since the late 1990s, which is thought to be due to those who convert to Islam after marrying people from the Middle East.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said the number of Muslims has continued to gradually increase since the late 1990s, which is thought to be due to those who convert to Islam after marrying people from the Middle East.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said the number of Muslims has continued to gradually increase since the late 1990s, which is thought to be due to those who convert to Islam after marrying people from the Middle East.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>ユダヤ教の信徒はまれである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are very few Jewish people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are very few Jewish people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are very few Jewish people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="41">
<j>明治時代および第二次世界大戦後には日本国内で様々な新興宗教が登場した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Meiji period and after World War II, various new religions emerged in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Meiji period and after World War II, various new religions emerged in Japan.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Meiji period and after World War II, various new religions emerged in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>新宗教は、現在においても新たに作られており、その状況は「神々のラッシュアワー」と呼ばれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">New religions are still being newly created and this situation is referred to as &quot;rush hour of the gods.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">New religions are still being created and this situation is referred to as &quot;rush hour of the gods.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">New religions are still being created and this situation is referred to as &apos;rush hour of the gods.&apos;</e>
<cmt>を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>しかし、あまりに数多くの宗派が発生した為に、どの宗教宗派も大量の信者を獲得しているとはいいがたい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There has appeared so many religious schools that any of the religions and schools have not gained many followers.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">So many religious schools have appeared that few religions and schools have gained any followers.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">So many religious schools have appeared that few religions and schools have gained sufficient followers.</e>
<cmt>左記のように変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>一説では、創価学会はその熱狂的な勧誘活動によって一大勢力を築いているといわれるが、それでも公称827万世帯、実勢400万人となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One view says that the Soka Gakkai has become a force through enthusiastic invitation activities, but it has only 8.27 million families nominally and 4 million people actually.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One view says that the Soka Gakkai has become a force through enthusiastic invitation activities, but it has only 8.27 million families nominally and and actual count of only 4 million people.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One view says that the Soka Gakkai has become a force through enthusiastic invitation activities, but it has only 8.27 million families nominally and and actual count of only 4 million people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>日本人の宗教観</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Religious idea of Japanese people</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Religious idea of Japanese people</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Religious idea of Japanese people</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="45">
<j>もともと日本においては、平安時代から明治維新以前は神仏習合が一般的で、神道と仏教が分けられない場合が一般的だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally syncretism of Shinto and Buddhism was widely promoted from the Heian period until the Meiji restoration, and Shinto and Buddhism were not distinguished from each other as a general rule.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally syncretism of Shinto and Buddhism was widely promoted from the Heian period until the Meiji restoration, and Shinto and Buddhism were not distinguished from each other as a general rule.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally syncretism of Shinto and Buddhism was widely seen from the Heian period until the Meiji restoration, and Shinto and Buddhism were not distinguished from each other as a general rule.</e>
<cmt>promoteをseenにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>寺院内に鳥居があったり、「八幡大菩薩」と神社の神を仏の呼び方で呼ぶ事例などに名残を見る事ができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The syncretism left traces, such as the torii (an archway to a Shinto shrine) in precincts of temples and &quot;Hachiman Daibosatsu&quot; (Great Bodhisattava Hachiman), a shrine deity called under a name of Buddha.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The syncretism left traces, such as the torii (an archway to a Shinto shrine) in precincts of temples and &quot;Hachiman Daibosatsu&quot; (Great Bodhisattava Hachiman), a shrine deity called under the name of Buddha.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The syncretism left traces, such as the torii (an archway to a Shinto shrine) in precincts of temples or the deity with the name of &apos;Hachiman Daibosatsu&apos; (Great Bodhisattava Hachiman), in which a name for a shrine deity (Hachiman) is connected with a name of Buddha (Daibosatsu).</e>
<cmt>説明を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>鎌倉仏教が普及したとは言え、一般庶民にとっては、現世での辛さを紛らす一種の「神」として信仰していたと言える（無論、どの時代にも熱心な信者がいることを忘れてはいけない）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kamakura Bukkyo became widespread, but ordinary people likely believed in it as a kind of &quot;God&quot; to escape from the distress of this world (It should be remembered, of course, that there are always avid followers in any age.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kamakura Bukkyo became widespread, but ordinary people likely believed in it as a kind of &quot;God&quot; to escape from the suffering in the world (It should be remembered, of course, that there are always avid followers in any age.)</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kamakura Buddhism became widespread, but it is likely that ordinary people believed in it as a kind of &apos;God&apos; to escape from the suffering in the world, (but it should be remembered, of course, that there are always avid followers in any age).</e>
<cmt>音訳を略しました。&quot;&quot;を&apos;&apos;にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="48">
<j>江戸時代に戸籍管理を目的として、仏教宗派のいずれかの寺院か、神社への帰属が義務付けられた事によって様々な習慣が生まれたが、今は希薄となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Edo period, the public was required to belong to a temple of any of the Buddhism denominations or a shrine for the purpose of managing family registrations, which gave rise to various customs that have become less common today.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Edo period, the public was required to belong to a temple of any of the Buddhism denominations or a shrine for the purpose of managing family registrations, which gave rise to various customs that have become less common today.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Edo period, for the purpose of family registration control the public were required to belong to a temple of any sect or a shrine, which gave rise to various customs but those customs have become less common today.</e>
<cmt>語順を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>また、七五三や結婚式が神社で行われるようにったのは明治以後のことで、宗門改めが起因ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The seven-five-three festival and wedding ceremony came to be held in a shrine, not when a religious census was carried out, but after the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The seven-five-three festival and wedding ceremony came to be held in a shrine, not due to a religious census being carried out, but after the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seven-five-three festivals and wedding ceremonies came to be held in a shrine, not due to a religious census, but after the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>左記のように変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="50">
<j>二宮尊徳の話をまとめた『二宮翁夜話』という書物には、宗教多元主義を示す次のような譬え話も含まれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Ninomiya-o Yawa&quot; (Night Talks of Ninomiya) on stories of Sontoku NINOMIYA contains the following allegory of religions pluralism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Ninomiya-o Yawa&quot; (Night Talks of Ninomiya) on stories of Sontoku NINOMIYA contains the following allegory of religions pluralism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Night Talks of the venerable Mr. Sontoku Ninomiya&quot; (Ninomiya-o Yawa) contains the following allegory of religious pluralism.</e>
<cmt>左記のように変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="51">
<j>「世の中に本当の真理はただ一つしかないが、その真理に近づく入り口はいくつもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;There is only one sheer truth in this world, but there are many gates to the truth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;There is only one sheer truth in this world, but there are many gates to the truth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is only one sheer truth in this world, but there are many gates to the truth.</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>神道、仏教、あるいは仏教でも天台宗、浄土宗、真言宗などいろいろあるが、これらは何れも、いくつもある真理への入り口に付いている小道の名前に過ぎない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinto and Buddhism, or even various sects of Buddhism, such as Tendai-shu sect, Jodo-shu sect (the Pure Land sect), and Shingon-shu sect, are all nothing more than names of paths to the many gates to the truth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinto and Buddhism, or even various sects of Buddhism, such as Tendai-shu sect, Jodo-shu sect (the Pure Land sect), and Shingon-shu sect, are all nothing more than names of paths to the many gates to the truth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinto and Buddhism, or even various sects of Buddhism, such as Tendai-shu sect, Jodo-shu sect (the Pure Land sect), and Shingon-shu sect, are all nothing more than names of paths to the many gates to the truth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>例えば富士山に登るのに、吉田から、須走りから、須山から、それぞれ登れるが、最終的に頂上に至れば同じ所である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">You can climb Mt. Fuji from any starting points at Yoshida, Subashiri, and Suyama, but you will eventually reach the summit to find yourself in one place.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">You can climb Mt. Fuji from any starting point at Yoshida, Subashiri, and Suyama, but you will eventually reach the summit and find yourself in the same place.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">You can climb Mt. Fuji from any starting point at Yoshida, Subashiri, and Suyama, but you will eventually reach the summit and find yourself in the same place.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>これを、違う目的に到達できる別々の道がある、と考えるのは誤りである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is wrong to think there are different paths leading to different destinations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is wrong to think there are different paths leading to different destinations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is wrong to think there are different paths leading to different destinations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>入り口が幾つもあっても、最終的に到達する場所は、一つである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even if there are more than one gates, you eventually get to one single destination.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even if there are more than one gates, you eventually get to one single destination.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even if there are more than one gates, you eventually get to one single destination.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>それは、誠である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is the truth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is the truth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is the truth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>ところが世の中では、これらを別々な道であると言い、真理が幾つもあるように言っている。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But, people say there are different paths and more than one truth.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But, people say there are different paths and more than one truth.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But, people say there are different paths and more than one truth.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="58">
<j>作家の芥川龍之介は、日本にいくら宗教を根付かせようとしても無理なのは、日本が古来から「八百万の神」を崇める、神道などに見られる独特の宗教観を持つからで、釈迦もイエス・キリストも日本にくれば神々の一人という扱いになる、といった主旨のことをある短編作品の登場人物に語らせている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Writer Ryunosuke AKUTAGAWA made a character in one of his short stories say things to the effect that efforts to have religions take root in Japan would not be rewarded because since ancient times Japanese people had had a unique view of religion to revere &quot;eight million different deities,&quot; which can be found in Shinto, and Shakyamuni and Jesus Christ were considered to be one of these deities in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Writer Ryunosuke AKUTAGAWA made a character in one of his short stories say things to the effect that efforts to plant religions in Japan would not be rewarded because Japanese people had had a unique view of religion to revere &quot;eight million different deities&quot; since ancient times, which can be found in Shinto, Shakyamuni and Jesus Christ were considered to be one of these deities in Japan.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Writer Ryunosuke AKUTAGAWA made a character in one of his short stories say things to the effect that efforts to plant any religion in Japan would not be rewarded because Japanese people had had a unique view of religion to revere &apos;eight million different deities&apos; since ancient times, which can be found in Shinto, Buddha and Jesus Christ being considered to be one of these deities in Japan.</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを変更しました。釈迦はBuddhaとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>また同時に、日本人が海外の思想に変化を加えて自分のものにする様子を「造りかへる力」とも表現している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time, he called it &quot;tsukuri kaeru chikara&quot; (the ability to recreate) that Japanese people changed overseas thoughts to make them their own thoughts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the same time, he called it &quot;tsukuri kaeru chikara&quot; (the ability to recreate) that Japanese people changed overseas thoughts to make them their own thoughts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the same time, he called it &apos;the ability to recreate&apos; that Japanese people made foreign thoughts to change into their own thoughts.</e>
<cmt>音訳は略しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="60">
<j>作家の井沢元彦は、日本には無意識の強烈な「怨霊」信仰と、怨霊を発生させない「和」への信仰があり、神道はその上に成立し、仏教も結局は怨霊を鎮魂する為の道具として活用されたと解説している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Writer Motohiko IZAWA explains that there are unconscious and strong belief in &quot;vengeful spirits&quot; and faith in &quot;harmony&quot; to prevent the vengeful spirits from coming into the world in Japan, and Shinto was established based on them and Buddhism, after all, was used as a tool to appease the vengeful spirits.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Writer Motohiko IZAWA explains that there are unconscious and strong belief in &quot;vengeful spirits&quot; and faith in &quot;harmony&quot; to prevent the vengeful spirits from coming into the world in Japan, which was used as a base to establish Shinto, and Buddhism was used as a tool to appease these vengeful spirits.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Writer Motohiko IZAWA explains that in Japan there are unconscious and strong belief in &apos;vengeful spirits&apos; and faith in &apos;harmony&apos; to prevent the vengeful spirits from coming into this world, and on this foundation Shinto was established, while Buddhism turned out to be used as a tool to appease these vengeful spirits.</e>
<cmt>左記のように変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>来日した外国人や、熱心な宗教信者となった日本人は、多くの日本人が無意識の内に「和」を至上のものとする思想をもつことを見出すことができるという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Foreign visitors to Japan and Japanese who are avid religious followers say they can see that many Japanese people unconsciously have an idea of placing supreme importance on the &quot;harmony.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Foreign visitors to Japan and Japanese who are avid religious followers say they can see that many Japanese people unconsciously have an idea of placing supreme importance on &quot;harmony.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Foreign visitors to Japan and the Japanese who become avid religious followers say they can see that many Japanese people unconsciously have an idea of placing supreme importance on &apos;harmony.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>また井沢は日本人の持つ「言霊」への特異な信仰を見出している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Izawa also found the belief in &quot;Kotodama&quot; (soul or power of language), which is peculiar to Japanese.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Izawa also found the belief in &quot;Kotodama&quot; (soul or power of language), which is peculiar to Japanese.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Izawa also found the belief in &apos;Kotodama&apos; (the soul or power of language), which is peculiar to Japanese.</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="63">
<j>日本人の死後の世界観としては、神道的な観点から人間も自然の一部と考えるため「生前の行いの善悪にかかわらず無に（自然）還る。」という考えや、仏教的な観点から死後釈迦の下で修行をし「仏に成る（成仏）」という考えがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For the afterlife, Japanese think &quot;one returns to nothing (nature) regardless of whether one did good or bad in one&apos;s lifetime&quot; based on the Shinto perspective that human beings are part of nature, but also think one undergoes training under Shakyamuni after his/her death to &quot;become a Buddha (jobutsu)&quot; from the Buddhist viewpoint.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With regards to the afterlife, Japanese think &quot;one returns to nothing (nature) regardless of whether one did good or bad in one&apos;s lifetime&quot; based on the Shinto perspective that human beings are part of nature, but also think one undergoes training under Shakyamuni after his/her death to &quot;become a Buddha (jobutsu)&quot; from a Buddhist viewpoint.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With regards to the afterlife, Japanese think &apos;one returns to nothing (nature) regardless of whether one did good or bad in one&apos;s lifetime&apos; based on the Shinto perspective that human beings are part of nature, but also think one undergoes training under Shakyamuni after his/her death to &apos;become a Buddha&apos; (entering Nirvana) from a Buddhist viewpoint.</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを変更しました。成仏の説明を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>また、「この世は天国、あの世は地獄」という言葉もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is also a phrase, &quot;this world is heaven and the other world is hell.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is also a phrase, &quot;this world is heaven and the other world is hell.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is also a phrase, &apos;this world is heaven and the other world is hell.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>日本人の「死んだ人を悪く言うもんではない」という考え方はこのような宗教的観点からきている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Based on these religious perspectives, Japanese people think &quot;we should not speak ill of the deceased.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based on these religious perspectives, Japanese people think &quot;we should not speak ill of the deceased.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based on these religious perspectives, Japanese people think &apos;we should not speak ill of the deceased.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>しかし、善人は天国へ行き、悪人は地獄へ落ちるという考え方も一般的なので、どんな悪行をはたらいても死んだら無罪（無罰）という訳ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the idea that the good go to heaven while the wicked go to hell is also common, so it is not that whatever misdeeds one has committed, one is justified (unpunished) after death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the idea that the good go to heaven while the wicked go to hell is also common, so it is not that whatever misdeeds one has committed, one is justified (unpunished) after death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the idea that the good go to heaven while the wicked go to hell is also common, so it is not that whatever misdeeds one has committed, one is justified (unpunished) after death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>ただ一方では現世に留まる霊魂の観念もあり伝統教義ではあまり説かれないが、幽霊・亡霊などの怪談はしばしば民衆の口に上り、現代でも都市伝説として流布することがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, there is also an idea of spirits that remain in this world, although traditional dogmas tell little about the idea, and stories of ghosts and spirits have been often talked about by the public and get around as urban legends even today.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, there is also an idea that spirits remain in this world, although traditional dogmas say little about the idea, and stories of ghosts and spirits have been often talked about by the public and get around as urban legends even today.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, there is also an idea that spirits remain in this world, although traditional dogmas say little about the idea, and stories of ghosts and spirits have been often talked about by the public and get around as urban legends even today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="68">
<j>なお、読売新聞が2005年8月6日、7日に行った宗教に関する世論調査では、宗教を信じないと答えた人が75%に上り、信じていると答えた人は23%と、1979年の調査の34%と比べて11%減っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In an opinion poll on religion, conducted by the Yomiuri Shimbun on August 6 and 7, 2005, 75 percent answered they do not have faith in religion, while 23 percent answered they do, which is a 11 percent decline from 34 percent in 1979 survey.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In an opinion poll on religion, conducted by the Yomiuri Shimbun on August 6 and 7, 2005, 75 percent answered they do not have faith in religion, while 23 percent answered they do, which is a 11 percent decline from 34 percent in the 1979 survey.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In an opinion poll on religion, conducted by the Yomiuri Shimbun on August 6 and 7, 2005, 75 percent answered they do not have faith in religion, while 23 percent answered they do, which is a 11 percent decline from 34 percent in the 1979 survey.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>現代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Modern age</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Modern age</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Modern age</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="69">
<j>日本では神道、仏教などの祭りに参加するものも多く、企業では神棚を設置する所があり、神道、仏教、キリスト教など宗教を超えて安全祈願などの礼拝を行う事がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan, many people participate in Shintoist and Buddhist festivals, some companies have a household Shinto altar, and services, such as prying for safety, are often held beyond religious boundaries of Shinto, Buddhism, Christianity, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan, many people participate in Shintoist and Buddhist festivals, some companies have a household Shinto altar, and services, such as praying for safety, are often held beyond religious boundaries of Shinto, Buddhism, Christianity etc.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan, many people participate in Shintoist and Buddhist festivals, some companies have a household Shinto altar, and services, such as praying for safety, are often held beyond religious boundaries of Shinto, Buddhism, Christianity etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>また、キリスト教の信徒が少数であるにもかかわらず、イベントとしてのクリスマス、バレンタインデー、教会結婚式、ハロウィン等の認知度は高く、企業も売上のために積極的に利用している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although there are few Christians, Christmas, Valentine&apos;s Day, church wedding, Halloween, etc. are well known as events, and companies actively utilize these events for increasing the sales.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although there are few Christians, Christmas, Valentine&apos;s Day, church wedding, Halloween, etc. are well known as events, and companies actively utilize these events to increase sales.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although there are few Christians, Christmas, Valentine&apos;s Day, church wedding, Halloween, etc. are well known as events, and companies actively utilize these events to increase sales.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>しかし、キリスト教徒を除けばこれらに宗教行事としての印象は持っておらず、クリスマスは、サンタクロースの贈り物、ツリーやケーキを連想し、バレンタインは恋愛をする上で重要なイベントというぐらいでしか認知されていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But because people other than Christians do not have an image of the events as religious rites, they associate Christmas with gifts from Santa Claus, trees, and cakes, and know Valentine&apos;s Day as nothing more than an important event for romance.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because people other than Christians do not have an image of the events as religious rites, they associate Christmas with gifts from Santa Claus, trees, and cakes, and know Valentine&apos;s Day as nothing more than an important event for romance.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because people other than Christians do not perceive these events as religious rites, they easily associate Christmas with gifts from Santa Claus, Christmas trees, and cakes, and Valentine&apos;s Day with nothing more than an important romantic event.</e>
<cmt>左記のように変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>教会結婚式は、バージンロードを花嫁が選択するといわれており、その後に教会に行って祈る人は1%もいない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Church wedding is said to be held because brides choose to walk down the church aisle, but less than one percent go to pray in church afterward.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Church weddings are said to be held because brides choose to walk down the church aisle, but less than one percent go to pray in church afterward.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Church weddings are said to be chosen because brides want to walk down the church aisle, but after the ceremony less than one percent go to pray in church.</e>
<cmt>左記のように変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>キリスト教行事は時節により行われているが、信仰とはまったく関係ないにもかかわらず受け入れられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Christian rites are carried out according to seasons, and Japanese people accepted the rites, not being involved in Christian faith at all.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Christian rites are carried out according to seasons, and Japanese people accepted the rites, not being involved in Christian faith at all.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Christian rites are carried out according to seasons, and Japanese people accepted the rites, not being involved in Christian faith at all.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="74">
<j>現代の日本人の大多数は、宗教に対する帰属意識は薄く、実際には宗教儀礼に参加しているにもかかわらず自分のことを「無宗教」と考える日本人も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The majority of Japanese people today lack a sense of belonging to religions, and many Japanese also consider themselves to have &quot;no religion,&quot; although they actually engage in religious rituals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The majority of Japanese people today lack a sense of belonging to religions, and many Japanese also consider themselves to have &quot;no religion,&quot; although they actually engage in religious rituals.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The majority of Japanese people today lack a sense of belonging to religions, and many Japanese also consider themselves to have &apos;no religion,&apos; although they actually engage in religious rituals.</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="75">
<j>しかし積極的に宗教や神仏を否定するわけではなく、いざとなった場合は神仏に頼ったり「祟り」や「罰（ばち）」などの宗教的概念を尊重する日本人が多いことからも、日本人の多くは特定の宗教を信仰しない無宗教ではあっても無神論者というわけではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most Japanese have no religion, or do not practice a particular religion, but they are not atheists, as seen from the fact that many of them do not strongly deny religions and Shinto and Buddhist deities, rely on the deities when they are in trouble, and respect religious ideas, such as a &quot;curse&quot; and &quot;bad karma.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most Japanese have no religion, nor practice a particular religion, but they are not atheists, as seen from the fact that many of them do not strongly deny religions or Shinto and Buddhist deities, and rely on the deities when they are in trouble, while respecting religious ideas, such as &quot;curses&quot; and &quot;bad karma.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most Japanese have no religion, nor practice a particular religion, but it may be not true that they are atheists, as seen from the fact that many of them do not strongly deny religions or Shinto and Buddhist deities, rely on the deities when they are in trouble, and respect religious ideas, such as &apos;curses&apos; and &apos;bad karma.&apos;</e>
<cmt>語順を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>現代日本における宗教団体</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Religious organizations in contemporary Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Religious organizations in contemporary Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Religious organizations in contemporary Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="76">
<j>日本において宗教団体は、宗教法人として法人格を得ることができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan, religious bodies can have corporate status as a religious corporation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan, religious bodies can have corporate status as a religious corporation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan, religious bodies can have corporate status as a religious corporation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>宗教法人の認証は、宗教法人法に基づいて行われており、主たる事務所の所在地を管轄する都道府県知事が行う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Religious corporations are certified, based on the Religious Corporation Act, by a prefectural governor who has jurisdiction over the location of the principal office.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Religious corporations are certified, based on the Religious Corporation Act, by a prefectural governor who has jurisdiction over the location of the principal office.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Religious corporations are certified, based on the Religious Corporation Act, by a prefectural governor who has jurisdiction over the location of the principal office.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>但し、他の都道府県内に境内建物を備える場合や他の都道府県内にある宗教法人を包括する宗教法人の場合などは文部科学大臣が認証を行う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In cases where the religious corporation has grounds and buildings in other prefectures and where it has other religious corporations in other prefectures under its control, Minister of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology certifies the corporation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In cases where the religious corporation has grounds and buildings in other prefectures and where it has other religious corporations in other prefectures under its control, Minister of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology certifies the corporation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In cases where the religious corporation has grounds and buildings in other prefectures and where it has other religious corporations in other prefectures under its control, Minister of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology certifies the corporation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>認証の後、事務所の所在地において設立の登記をすることにより成立する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After certified, the corporation comes into effect by registering for establishment at the location of the office.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After certified, the corporation comes into effect by registering for establishment at the location of the office.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After certified, the corporation comes into effect by registering for establishment at the location of the office.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>ただし、民間信仰や新宗教などの宗教団体の中には法人格を得ていない場合も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many organizations of folk religions and new religions do not gain corporate status.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many organizations of folk religions and new religions do not gain corporate status.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many organizations of folk religions and new religions do not gain corporate status.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="81">
<j>2002年の時点で、日本には、神道系85,212団体、仏教系77,640団体、キリスト教系4,445団体、諸教15,337団体が存在している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As of 2002, there are 85,212 Shinto organizations, 77,640 Buddhist organizations, 4,445 Christian organizations, and 15,337 organizations of other religions in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As of 2002, there are 85,212 Shinto organizations, 77,640 Buddhist organizations, 4,445 Christian organizations, and 15,337 other religious organizationsin Japan.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As of 2002, there are 85,212 Shinto organizations, 77,640 Buddhist organizations, 4,445 Christian organizations, and 15,337 other religious organizationsin Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 TT(id:46431), 2.2360679r5(id:220904), JAnDbot(id:66507), Straysheep(id:42448), Idioma-bot(id:129667), Nnh(id:474), 937(id:48634), Okome(id:98), Eskimbot(id:29676), ＲＪＡＮＫＡ(id:118019), Kliment.A.K.(id:161714), Rlgn(id:136663), PipepBot(id:146181), 死郎(id:1683), ErectricWire(id:311320), Call Tenderas(id:169753), Mois(id:30596), Gakuinryou(id:9665), Goki(id:7107), WikiDreamer Bot(id:225250), 16toki(id:60127), Cimero(id:121233), スミス16号(id:189050), Point136(id:211299), りょほう(id:334), DumZiBoT(id:230315), ArthurBot(id:265089), Stanislaus(id:1806), Aalulu(id:101169), Komatta(id:52309), MEDITATE(id:168298), Lucas0123(id:130266), 衝撃波(id:85003), Zwobot(id:23873), 文姫(id:66661), こま(id:101397), 廬舎那憂(id:168188), Chlewbot(id:33904), Louperibot(id:128971), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>