<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>獅子舞</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Shishimai&quot; (The Japanese Lion Dance)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Shishimai&quot; (Japanese Lion Dance)</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Shishimai&quot; (Japanese Lion Dance)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>獅子舞（ししまい）とは、伝統芸能の一つで、祭囃子にあわせて獅子が舞い踊るものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Shishimai&quot; (The Japanese lion dance) is one of the traditional Japanese performing arts, in which performers mimic a lion&apos;s movements in a lion costume to the festival music.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Shishimai&quot; (Japanese lion dance) is one of the traditional Japanese performing arts, in which performers mimic a lion&apos;s movements in a lion costume to festival music.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Shishimai&quot; (Japanese lion dance) is one of the traditional Japanese performing arts, in which performers mimic a lion&apos;s movements in a lion costume to festival music.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>また本項では、中国の獅子舞、いわゆるライオンダンスについてもあわせて解説する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This section also describes its Chinese version, which is simply called the lion dance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This section also describes the Chinese version, which is simply called the lion dance.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This section also describes the Chinese version, which is simply called the lion dance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="3">
<j>起源</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Origin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Origin</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Origin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>起源は、中国説やインド説など各説あり定かではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Various theories exist about the origin of shishimai, such as the Chinese-origin theory &amp; the Indian-origin theory, but nothing can be said for sure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Various theories exist about the origin of shishimai, such as the Chinese-origin theory &amp; the Indian-origin theory, but nothing can be said for sure.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Various theories exist about the origin of shishimai, such as the Chinese-origin theory and the Indian-origin theory, but nothing can be said for sure.</e>
<cmt>&amp; をandに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>日本の獅子舞</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shishimai</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shishimai</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese Shishimai</e>
<cmt>Japaneseを追加しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>日本の獅子舞は、全土で行われておりバリエーションは多岐にわたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shishimai is seen all over Japan, and its styles quite differ from place to place.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shishimai is seen all over Japan, and its styles differ greatly from place to place.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shishimai is seen all over Japan, and its styles differ greatly from place to place.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>大きく分けて、伎楽（ぎがく）系の獅子舞と風流（ふりゅう）系の獅子舞がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is roughly divided into two types, &quot;Gigaku&quot; school &amp; &quot;Furyu&quot; school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is roughly divided into two types, &quot;Gigaku&quot; school and &quot;Furyu&quot; school.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is roughly divided into two types, &quot;Gigaku&quot; school and &quot;Furyu&quot; school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>獅子の頭部（獅子頭：ししがしらと呼ばれる）は木製が多いが、和紙による張子のものや最近では発泡スチロールによるものもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The headgear of the lion costume, called &quot;shishi-gashira,&quot; is mostly made from wood, but there also exists the headgear which is made by sticking the traditional Japanese paper together, and recently, the headgear made from the styrene foam is seen, too.</e>
<cmt>・「和紙による張子のもの」は「和紙を張り重ねて作ったかぶりもの」（集英社・国語辞典参照）と訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The headgear of the lion costume, called &quot;shishi-gashira,&quot; is mostly made from wood, but there also exists headgear which is made by sticking traditional Japanese paper together, and recently, headgear made from styrene foam is seen, too.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The headgear of the lion costume, called &quot;shishi-gashira,&quot; is mostly made from wood, but there also exists headgear which is made by sticking traditional Japanese paper together, and recently, headgear made from styrene foam is seen, too.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>舞方は諸流派があり風流系（ふりゅうけい）、神楽系（かぐらけい）などが知られるが、他にも多くの舞があり同じ物は二つとないとも言える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A large variety of dance schools exist, including the well-known Furyu school &amp; &quot;Kagura&quot; school (&quot;Kagura&quot; means the sacred music and dancing performed at shrines), and every school can be said to be unique.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A large variety of dance schools exist, including the well-known Furyu school and &quot;Kagura&quot; school (&quot;Kagura&quot; means the sacred music and dancing performed at shrines), and every school can be said to be unique.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A large variety of dance schools exist, including the well-known Furyu school and &quot;Kagura&quot; school (&quot;Kagura&quot; means the sacred music and dancing performed at shrines), and every school can be said to be unique.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>伎楽系の獅子舞</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gigaku school of shishimai</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gigaku school of shishimai</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gigaku school of shishimai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="9">
<j>伎楽系（神楽系）の獅子舞は西日本を中心として全国的に分布し、胴体部分に入る人数で大獅子、中獅子、小獅子と区分される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gigaku school (also called Kagura school) is seen nationwide (in particular, in western Japan), and it is categorized into three types, that is, a big lion, a middle-sized lion, and a small lion, according to the number of people who get into the body part of the lion costume.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Gigaku school (also called Kagura school) is seen nationwide (in particular, in western Japan), and it is categorized into three types, big lion, middle-sized lion, and small lion, according to the number of people who get into the body part of the lion costume.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Gigaku school (also called Kagura school) is seen nationwide (in particular, in western Japan), and it is categorized into three types, big lion, middle-sized lion, and small lion, according to the number of people who get into the body part of the lion costume.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>大獅子では獅子を操作する人以外に囃子方も胴体に入って演奏する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the type of a big lion, &quot;hayashikata&quot; (people who play &quot;hayashi,&quot; or the musical accompaniment) get into the body part of the lion along with the costume swinger.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the big lion type, &quot;hayashikata&quot; (people who play &quot;hayashi,&quot; or musical accompaniment) get into the body part of the lion along with the costume swinger.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the big lion type, &quot;hayashikata&quot; (people who play &quot;hayashi,&quot; or musical accompaniment) get into the body part of the lion along with the costume swinger.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>小獅子では、獅子頭を操作する1人だけが胴体も兼ねる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the type of a small lion, one person swings the headgear and also mimics the movements of the body part of the lion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the small lion type, one person swings the headgear and also mimics the movements of the body part of the lion.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the small lion type, one person swings the headgear and also mimics the movements of the body part of the lion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>正月に見る獅子舞や神楽での獅子舞をはじめ、一般に獅子舞というとこの系統の獅子舞を指すことが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mostly, &quot;shishimai&quot; performances, including those shown at the New Year or in &quot;kagura,&quot; are this school&apos;s.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mostly, &quot;shishimai&quot; performances, including those shown at New Years or in &quot;kagura,&quot; are this school&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mostly, &quot;shishimai&quot; performances, including those shown at New Year&apos;s or in &quot;kagura,&quot; are this school&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>YearをYear&apos;sに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>起源は中国大陸から伝来したものと考えられ、現在の中国獅子舞とも繋がるものと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This school&apos;s shishimai is deemed to have originated from China, so it seems to have the same origin as today&apos;s Chinese lion dance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This school&apos;s shishimai is deemed to have originated from China, so it seems to have the same origin as today&apos;s Chinese lion dance.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This school&apos;s shishimai is deemed to have originated from China, so it seems to have the same origin as today&apos;s Chinese lion dance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>風流系の獅子舞</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furyu school of shishimai</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furyu school of shishimai</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furyu school of shishimai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="14">
<j>風流系の獅子舞は関東地方・東北地方に主に分布している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furyu school of shishimai is seen mainly in the Kanto &amp; Tohoku region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Furyu school of shishimai is seen mainly in the Kanto and Tohoku regions.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Furyu school of shishimai is seen mainly in the Kanto and Tohoku regions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>1人が1匹を担当し、それぞれが腹にくくりつけられた太鼓を打ちながら舞う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Furyu school, one person performs one lion, and each person does the dance beating the drum tied to its belly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Furyu school, one person performs one lion, and each person does the dance beating the drum tied to its belly.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Furyu school, one person performs one lion, and each person does the dance beating the drum tied to its belly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>東北の一部には7～8頭で1組の鹿踊もあるが、もっとも多いのは3匹1組の三匹獅子舞である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In some parts of the Tohoku region, &quot;shishiodori&quot; (the deer dance) is performed in groups of seven to eight people, and most common is the three lion dance performed in groups of three people.</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処 　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In some parts of the Tohoku region, &quot;shishiodori&quot; (the deer dance) is performed in groups of seven to eight people, and the most common is the three lion dance performed in groups of three people.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In some parts of the Tohoku region, &quot;shishiodori&quot; (the deer dance) is performed in groups of seven to eight people, and the most common is the three lion dance performed in groups of three people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>これは、東京都・埼玉県などのかつて武蔵国と呼ばれた地域の農山村では一般的な郷土芸能・民俗芸能となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This becomes the general local performing art &amp; folk entertainment at farming &amp; mountain villages in the area that was once called Musashi Province, which overlaps with today&apos;s Tokyo Metropolis &amp; Saitama Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is the general local performing art and folk entertainment at farming and mountain villages in the area that was once called Musashi Province, which overlaps with today&apos;s Tokyo Metropolis and Saitama Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is the general local performing art and folk entertainment at farming and mountain villages in the area that was once called Musashi Province, which overlaps with today&apos;s Tokyo Metropolis and Saitama Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>3匹のうちの1匹は女獅子（雌獅子）と呼ばれ、雄獅子が雌獅子を奪い合う女獅子隠しという演目を持つところが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of the three lions is a female (in Japanese, &quot;mejishi&quot;), and many local communities have the dance program called &quot;Mejishi Kakushi&quot; that two male lions fight with each other for a female lion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of the three lions is a female (in Japanese, &quot;mejishi&quot;), and many local communities have a dance program called &quot;Mejishi Kakushi&quot; where two male lions fight with each other for a female lion.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of the three lions is a female (in Japanese, &quot;mejishi&quot;), and many local communities have a dance program called &quot;Mejishi Kakushi&quot; where two male lions fight with each other for a female lion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>伴奏は、篠笛と竹でできたささらという楽器である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The dance is accompanied with &quot;shino-bue&quot; (the Japanese bamboo flute) and &quot;sasara&quot; (the Japanese bamboo percussion instrument).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The dance is accompanied with &quot;shino-bue&quot; (the Japanese bamboo flute) and &quot;sasara&quot; (the Japanese bamboo percussion instrument).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The dance is accompanied with &quot;shino-bue&quot; (the Japanese bamboo flute) and &quot;sasara&quot; (the Japanese bamboo percussion instrument).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>「ささら」をする人は舞庭の四方に配置され、この楽器を奏する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sasara performers play at the four corners of the garden stage of the dance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sasara performers play at the four corners of the garden stage of the dance.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sasara&apos; performers play at the four corners of the garden stage of the dance.</e>
<cmt>原文で｢｣の部分に&apos; &apos;を付加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>「ささら」を欠く三匹獅子舞もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The three lion dance is sometimes performed without a sasara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The three lion dance is sometimes performed without a sasara.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The three lion dance is sometimes performed without a &apos;sasara.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文で｢｣の部分に&apos; &apos;を付加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>起源は西日本の太鼓踊りあるいは陣役踊りといわれ、中心にいる数人が頭上のかぶり物を獅子頭に変えたものが始まりだろうという説が優勢である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furyu school of shishimai is said to have originated from Drum Dance or Imperial Court Guards&apos; Dance, both seen in western Japan, and a predominant theory says Furyu school of shishimai might begin when some star performers changed their headgears into &quot;shishigashira.&quot;</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処 ・「陣役踊り」にいう「陣役」が何を意味するのか、いろいろ調査いたしましたが結局わかりませんでした。（集英社国語辞典にある類似の項目の「陣屋」には「宮中警護の衛士の詰め所」と出ているところから、ここも「宮中警護の衛士」の意味と推測して訳しています。）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Furyu school of shishimai is said to have originated from Drum Dance or Imperial Court Guards&apos; Dance, both seen in western Japan, and a predominant theory says Furyu school of shishimai might have began when some star performers changed their headgears into &quot;shishigashira.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Furyu school of shishimai is said to have originated from Drum Dance or Imperial Court Guards&apos; Dance, both seen in western Japan, and a predominant theory says Furyu school of shishimai might have began when some star performers changed their headgears into &quot;shishigashira.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>だが、東国の風流系の獅子舞はもっと古くからある日本古来の獅子舞であり、獅子頭（ししがしら）も本来はシカやイノシシを模したものであったという説も根強い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But another long-lasting theory says that Furyu school of shishimai in eastern Japan originated from the ancient Japanese dance, and that the headgear originally modeled on that of a deer or a wild boar.</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But another long-lasting theory says that Furyu school of shishimai in eastern Japan originated from ancient Japanese dance, and that the headgear was originally modeled on that of a deer or wild boar.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But another long-lasting theory says that Furyu school of shishimai in eastern Japan originated from ancient Japanese dance, and that the headgear was originally modeled on that of a deer or wild boar.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>獅子頭は通常木製（桐製）であり、獅子以外に竜頭のものや鹿頭のものもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shishigashira is usually made from wood (paulownia), and besides shishigashira, there also exist the headgear of a dragon and of a deer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shishigashira is usually made from wood (paulownia), and besides shishigashira, there also exists the headgear of a dragon and deer.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shishigashira is usually made from wood (paulownia), and besides shishigashira, there also exists the headgear of a dragon and deer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>中国の獅子舞</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chinese lion dance</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chinese lion dance</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chinese lion dance</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="25">
<j>中国語で（ピンイン wǔshī）という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Pinyin, the Chinese lion dance is written as &quot;wǔshī&quot;</e>
<cmt>・「ピンイン」は中国語のローマ字表記法の一つです。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Pinyin, the Chinese lion dance is written as &quot;wǔshī.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Pinyin, the Chinese lion dance is written as &quot;wǔshī.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>また、英語で lion dance という場合、その多くはこうした中国式のものを指している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And when we simply say &quot;lion dance,&quot; it mostly means the Chinese lion dance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And when we simply say &quot;lion dance,&quot; it mostly means the Chinese lion dance.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And when we simply say &quot;lion dance,&quot; it mostly means the Chinese lion dance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="27">
<j>古くは唐の時代には存在したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Chinese lion dance is said to have existed as early as in the age of the Tang dynasty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Chinese lion dance is said to have existed as early as in the age of the Tang dynasty.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Chinese lion dance is said to have existed as early as in the age of the Tang dynasty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>『漢書』禮樂志の孟康注に「象人若今戯魚蝦師子者也」（象人は、今の魚、蝦、獅子を戯するがごとき者なり）と記述される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;The creature movement mimicker is like the person who was just performing the fish dance, the prawn dance, and the lion dance,&quot; says the Meng Kang&apos;s commentary on the book of ritual &amp; music in the series of Historical Records of the Han Dynasty.</e>
<cmt>・「禮楽志」の部分は「典礼と音楽に関する巻」と訳しています。　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　・「象人」が何を意味するのか明確にはわかりませんでした。ただ講談社・中日辞典によれば中国語で「象」は「まねる」の意味なので、「象人」も「モノまねをする人」の意味と推測して訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;The creature movement mimicker is like the person who was just performing the fish dance, the prawn dance, and the lion dance,&quot; says Meng Kang&apos;s commentary on the book of ritual and music in the series of Historical Records of the Han Dynasty.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;The creature movement mimicker is like the person who was just performing the fish dance, the prawn dance, and the lion dance,&quot; says Meng Kang&apos;s commentary on the book of ritual and music in the series of Historical Records of the Han Dynasty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>現在演じられる形は清の時代に確立された形で、北方の北獅と南方の南獅の系統（中国武術家で伝承されその身体技法による）があり、競技もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Established in the age of the Qing dynasty, the present performance styles of the Chinese lion dance are categorised into two, Northern style &amp; Southern style, - the latter has been handed down in the communities of the practitioners of Chinese martial arts, and it is performed with their physical techniques - and there exist the dance competitions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Established in the age of the Qing dynasty, the present performance styles of the Chinese lion dance are categorized into two, Northern style and Southern style, - the latter has been handed down in the communities of the practitioners of Chinese martial arts, and it is performed with their physical techniques - and there are dance competitions.</e>
<cmt>Typo, Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Established in the age of the Qing dynasty, the present performance styles of the Chinese lion dance are categorized into two, Northern style and Southern style, - the latter has been handed down in the communities of the practitioners of Chinese martial arts, and it is performed with their physical techniques - and there are dance competitions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>獅子頭と前足に1人、後ろ足と背中に1人の2人と楽団で構成されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A performance group consists of the musical band members and other two people, that is, a person in charge of the lion shishigashira &amp; forefeet, and another in charge of the back legs &amp; back.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A performance group consists of the musical band members and two other people, that is, a person in charge of the lion shishigashira and forefeet, and another in charge of the back legs and back.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A performance group consists of the musical band members and two other people, that is, a person in charge of the lion shishigashira and forefeet, and another in charge of the back legs and back.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>旧正月や商店の開店祝いなどの祝いで「招福駆邪」として演じられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The dance is performed in celebrations, such as the Chinese New Year and business opening ceremonies, for exorcising evil spirits and bringing good fortune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The dance is performed in celebrations, such as the Chinese New Year and business opening ceremonies, for exorcising evil spirits and bringing good fortune.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The dance is performed in celebrations, such as the Chinese New Year and business opening ceremonies, for exorcising evil spirits and bringing good fortune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="32">
<j>中国式の獅子舞は日本においては中華街や中国・台湾と関係の深い自治体・施設に獅子舞団がありイベントごとに演じられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also in Japan, there exist Chinese lion dance groups at Chinatowns and at the municipalities &amp; other institutions that have close ties with China or Taiwan, and their performances are seen whenever an event is held.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also in Japan, there exist Chinese lion dance groups at Chinatowns and at the municipalities and other institutions that have close ties with China or Taiwan, and their performances are seen whenever an event is held.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also in Japan, there exist Chinese lion dance groups at Chinatowns and at the municipalities and other institutions that have close ties with China or Taiwan, and their performances are seen whenever an event is held.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>ジャッキー・チェンの映画ヤングマスター 師弟出馬では南方のものが描写されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;The Young Master,&quot; a movie that was starred by Jackie Chan, the Southern style lion dance was seen.</e>
<cmt>・「師弟出馬」は「ヤングマスター」の中国語表記に過ぎないので訳出していません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;The Young Master,&quot; a movie that featured Jackie Chan, the Southern style lion dance was seen.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;The Young Master,&quot; a movie that featured Jackie Chan, the Southern style lion dance was seen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="34">
<j>日本の中国獅子舞団</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chinese lion dance groups in Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chinese lion dance groups in Japan</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chinese lion dance groups in Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>横浜中華街（神奈川県横浜市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yokohama Chinatown (in Yokohama City, Kanagawa Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yokohama Chinatown (in Yokohama City, Kanagawa Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yokohama Chinatown (in Yokohama City, Kanagawa Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>‐横浜華僑青年會龍獅團　横浜中華学院校友会</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Dragon &amp; Lion Dance Group of the Yokohama Overseas Chinese Youth Association/Yokohama Overseas Chinese School O.B. Association</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Dragon &amp; Lion Dance Group of the Yokohama Overseas Chinese Youth Association/Yokohama Overseas Chinese School O.B. Association</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Dragon and Lion Dance Group of the Yokohama Overseas Chinese Youth Association/Yokohama Overseas Chinese School O.B. Association</e>
<cmt>&amp;をandに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>神戸南京町（兵庫県神戸市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kobe Nankin-machi (in Kobe City, Hyogo Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kobe Nankin-machi (in Kobe City, Hyogo Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kobe Nankin-machi (in Kobe City, Hyogo Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>- 日本神戸獅藝體育會醒獅團</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Japanese Lion Dance Group of the Kobe Athletic Association</e>
<cmt>・定訳は発見できませんでしたので、訳者の創作です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Japanese Lion Dance Group of the Kobe Athletic Association</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japanese Lion Dance Group of the Kobe Athletic Association</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>長崎新地中華街（長崎県長崎市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagasaki Shinchi Chinatown (in Nagasaki City, Nagasaki Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagasaki Shinchi Chinatown (in Nagasaki City, Nagasaki Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagasaki Shinchi Chinatown (in Nagasaki City, Nagasaki Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>燕趙園（鳥取県湯梨浜町）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chinese Garden Enchoen (in Yurihama-cho, Tottori Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chinese Garden Enchoen (in Yurihama-cho, Tottori Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chinese Garden Enchoen (in Yurihama-cho, Tottori Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>日本鳥取志咸醒獅團</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Japanese Lion Dance Group in Tottori</e>
<cmt>・定訳は発見できませんでしたので、訳者の創作です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Japanese Lion Dance Group in Tottori</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japanese Lion Dance Group in Tottori</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>神戸華僑（兵庫県神戸市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kobe overseas Chinese (in Kobe City, Hyogo Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kobe overseas Chinese (in Kobe City, Hyogo Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kobe overseas Chinese (in Kobe City, Hyogo Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>- 神戸華僑総会舞獅隊　神戸南京町獅誠館</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Lion Dance Group of the Kobe Overseas Chinese Association/The Lion Dance Group of the Kobe Nankin-cho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Lion Dance Group of the Kobe Overseas Chinese Association/The Lion Dance Group of the Kobe Nankin-cho</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Lion Dance Group of the Kobe Overseas Chinese Association/The Lion Dance Group of the Kobe Nankin-cho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Izayohi(id:13095), ArthurBot(id:265089), ととりん(id:31982), Nnh(id:474), みゅり(id:266571), PixelBot(id:166734), Yanahan(id:2437), Fainman(id:137546), Toto-tarou(id:16648), Takanori1204(id:240111), Doratea(id:37080), Yosri(id:9357), ぎゅうひ(id:9206), クロサキ(id:169477), Rei-bot(id:94097), 663highland(id:18755), Loveless(id:129239), Point136(id:211299), Akimoto(id:6951), Hamasaki gion higashi(id:144985), Toki-ho(id:10691), SieBot(id:126695), Tatsujin28(id:9300), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>