<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>竹刀</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinai (bamboo sword)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinai</e>
<cmt>Removed explanation of shinai since it appears below</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>竹刀（しない）は、日本の武道である剣道の稽古および試合で防具 (剣道)に対して打突する竹でできた刀の代替品である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinai is substitute of sword made by bamboo, which is used in Japanese Traditional martial art, Kendo training, or being used to hit or push against protective armor in the Kendo tournament.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinai is a substitute sword made of bamboo used in the Japanese martial art of kendo for training or for hitting or pushing against armor in tournaments.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinai is a substitute sword made of bamboo used in the Japanese martial art of kendo for training or for hitting or pushing against armor (Kendo) in tournaments.</e>
<cmt>(剣道）　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>安土桃山時代に剣術の一部流派の打ち合い稽古のために袋竹刀が考案され、更に江戸時代になって防具の発達にともない割竹刀（わりじない）が考案された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fukuro shinai (bamboo sword covered with a bag) was designed for hitting training of certain school of sword play in Azuchi momoyama period, furthermore, warijinai (split bamboo sword) was designed as the protective armor got improved in Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Azuchi-Momoyama Period (1558-1600), some kenjutsu, or sword fighting, schools began using bamboo swords covered with leather sleeves and called &apos;fukuro shinai&apos; for sparring practice, and the Edo Period (1603-1868), with the development of armor, saw the appearance of the &apos;warijinai&apos; (split bamboo sword).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Azuchi-Momoyama period (1558-1600), some kenjutsu, or sword fighting, schools began using bamboo swords covered with leather sleeves and called &apos;fukuro shinai&apos; for sparring practice, and the Edo period (1603-1868), with the development of armor, saw the appearance of the &apos;warijinai&apos; (split bamboo sword).</e>
<cmt>periodを小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>稀に「ちくとう」という呼び方をする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is rarely called Chikuto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are occasionally called &apos;chikuto&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are occasionally called &apos;chikuto.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>「しない」と言う呼び名は、「撓（しな）う」ことに由来するという説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a theory that the name &apos;Shinai&apos; came from Janapese word, &apos;shinau&apos; (bend).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a theory that the name &apos;shinai&apos; comes from the Japanese word &apos;shinau&apos; (bend).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a theory that the name &apos;shinai&apos; comes from the Japanese word &apos;shinau&apos; (bend).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>これから、撓と書いて「しない」と読む事もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to this, it is often written in Kanji such as 撓 and pronounce &apos;shinai.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to this, although usually written with the charcaters for &apos;bamboo&apos; and &apos;sword&apos;, it is sometimes written with the charcter for &apos;bend&apos;.</e>
<cmt>*Revised for clarity - tried to get the point across without using kanji</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to this, although usually written with the characters for &apos;bamboo&apos; and &apos;sword,&apos; it is sometimes written with the character for &apos;bend.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>全日本剣道連盟の前身は、全日本撓競技連盟という名称であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The forerunner of All Japan Kendo Federation (AJKF) was All Japan Shinai (bamboo sword) Competition Federation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The forerunner of the All Japan Kendo Federation (AJKF) was the All Japan Shinai Competition Federation.</e>
<cmt>ArticlesRemoved explanation of shinai</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The forerunner of the All Japan Kendo Federation (AJKF) was the All Japan Shinai Competition Federation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>木刀にかわって竹刀が普及する事によって、直接打ち合える試合が可能になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Shinai became popular instead of wooden sword, it made it possible for people to directly hit each other with the shinai in the tournament.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With shinai replacing &apos;bokuto&apos; wooden swords, it became possible for people to directly hit each other in tournaments.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With shinai replacing &apos;bokuto&apos; wooden swords, it became possible for people to directly hit each other in tournaments.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>以下、本項では特に断らない限り、割竹刀について説明する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following is the explanation of Warijinai unless it is mentioned otherwise.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following describes warijinai unless otherwise mentioned.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following describes warijinai unless otherwise mentioned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="9">
<j>縦に八分割した竹（桂竹、真竹など）を四つを合わせて、シカの皮などで握りとを剣先を覆って纏めて作る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is made by bamboo (Keichiku (Taiwanese bamboo and Madake bamboo) stem which was cut into eight and four stems, were put together, then the point of sword and bottom part was wrapped with deer skin and tightened.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinai are made by cutting a piece of bamboo (usually Taiwanese &apos;keichiku&apos; bamboo or Japanese &apos;madake&apos; bamboo) lengthways into eight, four of which are are then tied together using deer skin to form to tip and the grip.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinai are made by cutting a piece of bamboo (usually Taiwanese &apos;keichiku&apos; bamboo or Japanese &apos;madake&apos; bamboo) lengthways into eight, four of which are then tied together using deer skin at the tip and the grip.</e>
<cmt>to form to tip and the grip　→at the tip and the grip としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>剣先から柄までに一本の糸（つるという）を張り、つるが張られた側を峰とし、反対側を刃部とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is one piece of strings (it is called tsuru) put through from the point of a sword to the edge of the sword, one side with tsuru is called Mine and the other side is called sword side.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A piece of string called a tsuru is tied along one side from the tip to the hilt, the side with the tsuru is called &apos;mine&apos; and the other side is called &apos;habu&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A piece of string called a tsuru is tied along one side from the tip to the tsuka (hilt), and the side with the tsuru is called &apos;mine&apos; and the other side is called &apos;habu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを移動しました。柄→tsuka としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>また近年では、耐久性に優れた炭素繊維竹刀も使われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In recent years durable carbon fiber shinai is used recently.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nowadays, durable carbon fiber shinai are also used.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nowadays, durable carbon fiber shinai are also used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="12">
<j>鍔は牛革製・プラスチック製（一部には猪皮製・鮫革製の鍔もある）が多く、穴があいた円盤状になっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most of Tsuba (guard) is made by cow skin or plastic (some Tsuba are made by wild big skin or shark skin), it has a disk shape with hole in the centre.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The tsuba, or guard, is usually made of leather or plastic (though some are made of wild boar or shark skin), and is disk-shaped with a hole in the center.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The tsuba, or guard, is usually made of leather or plastic (though some are made of wild boar or shark skin), and is disk-shaped with a hole in the center.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>柄頭側から柄に通し、滑りにくいゴム等で出来ている鍔止めを同様に柄に通して固定する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsuba is put through from tsuka-gashira (pommel) to Tsuka (hilt), it was then held with Tsubadome, which was also put through from the Tsuka, made by non-slip rubber.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The tsuba is slid from from the tsuka-gashira (pommel) to the tsuka (hilt) and is held in place with a tsubadome, made of non-slip rubber, which is also put on from the tsuka.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The tsuba is slid from the tsuka-gashira (pommel) to the tsuka and is held in place with a tsubadome, made of non-slip rubber, which is also put on from the tsuka.</e>
<cmt>from ダブりを削除しました。柄　既出のため、補足を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>また近年では鍔と鍔止めが一体になっている鍔も販売されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In recent years, there are Tsuba for sale which have Tsuba and Tsubadome combined together.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In recent years, combined tsuba and tsubadome have started to be sold.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In recent years, combined tsuba and tsubadome have started to be sold.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>鍔は簡単に着脱できる為、鍔と本体を分離して竹刀袋に入れて持ち運ぶ事が出来る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Tsuba can be taken off easily, it is possible to carry Tsuba and Shinai separately in the Shinai bag to carry.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the tsuba can be easily removed, it is possible to carry it separately from the shinai in the shinai bag.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the tsuba can be easily removed, it is possible to carry it separately from the shinai in the shinai bag.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>だが簡単に着脱出来てしまうため練習中に鍔が外れてしまうこともある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, since Tsuba can be easily taken off, it can come off easily from Shinai while training.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, since it can be easily removed, it can also come off easily while training.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, since it can be easily removed, it can also come off easily while training.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="17">
<j>また、WWE等、海外のプロレスなどでは大きい音が出るという利点から、ケンドースティックという名前で凶器 (プロレス)として用いられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinai is also used in overseas pro wrestling such as WWE as weapons, to be called Kendo stick, since it makes loud noise.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of the noise they make, shinai are also used as weapons in overseas pro wrestling, such as the WWE, where they are known as kendo sticks.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of the noise they make, shinai are also used as weapons in overseas pro wrestling, such as the WWE, where they are known as kendo sticks.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>長さ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The length</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Length</e>
<cmt>Article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Length</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="18">
<j>元々は日本刀とほぼ同じ長さであったが、江戸時代末期に試合に有利なため4尺を超える竹刀を使用する者が多く現れ（5尺3寸≒161cmの長大な竹刀を使用した大石進が代表的である）、その対抗上、竹刀の長さは刀より長いものを使用するようになったといわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally it was the same length as Japanese sword, however many people started using long Shinai which was longer than 1.2 meters since it had advantage in the tournament (大石進 who used very long shinai of 5 shaku 3 zun (equivalent to 161 cm) is well known.), due to this tournament, it is said shinai longer than sword is started to be used in common.</e>
<cmt>大石進→読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although originally the same length as Japanese swords,towards the end of the Edo period, many people started using shinai over 1.2 meters long since it gave them an advantage in tournaments (the famous Susumu OISHI used a very long shinai of 5 shaku 3 zun, or about 161 cm), and as people tried to out do each other, the longer shinai became common.</e>
<cmt>*According to this site www.koryu.com/library/chyakutake1.html his name was Oishi Susumu</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although originally the same length as Japanese swords, towards the end of the Edo period, many people started using shinai over 1.2 meters long since it gave them an advantage in tournaments (the famous Susumu OISHI used a very long shinai of 5 shaku 3 zun, or about 161 cm), and due to the above situation it is said that people began to use shinai longer than swords.</e>
<cmt>文末の翻訳を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="19">
<j>その長大化に歯止めをかけるべく、安政3年に講武所では「撓は柄共総長サ尺貫法ニて三尺八寸より長きは不相成」と3尺8寸までと決めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To regulate the length of the long sword, it was said in Kobusho in 1856, &apos;the shinai longer than 3 jaku 8 sun (about 95cm) was not acceptable.&apos; and the length was decided 3 jaku 8 sun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To regulate the increasing lengths of shinai, the Kobusho (a military academy set up by the Edo Shogunate) declared in 1856 that, &apos;shinai longer than 3 jaku 8 sun (about 95cm) are not acceptable&apos; and this became the set length.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To regulate the increasing lengths of shinai, the Kobusho (a military academy set up by the Edo Shogunate) declared in 1856 that, &apos;shinai longer than 3 jaku 8 sun (about 95cm) are not acceptable&apos; and this became the set length.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>この3尺8寸の寸法は明治以降も受け継がれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The tradition to use shinai of 3 jaku 8 sun was kept after the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The tradition of using shinai of 3 jaku 8 sun was maintained after the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>*Since 明治以降 means &apos;including the Meiji Period&apos;, revised to &quot;after the Edo Period&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The tradition of using shinai of 3 jaku 8 sun was maintained after the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>periodを小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>ただし、日本刀を想定して短い竹刀を用いる剣士もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However some swordsmen used short shinai, as if they use short sword.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However some swordsmen used short shinai, as if they were using a short sword.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However some swordsmen used short shinai, as if they were using a short sword.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>山岡鉄舟や中山博道がその代表的な人物であろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tesshu YAMAOKA and Hiromichi NAKAYAMA are well known using this kind of short sword.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tesshu YAMAOKA and Hiromichi NAKAYAMA are well known for using this kind of short sword.</e>
<cmt>Preposition</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tesshu YAMAOKA and Hiromichi NAKAYAMA are well known for using this kind of short sword.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="23">
<j>現在、竹刀には長さの分類があり、主に小学生用の36（3尺6寸、109cm）、中学生用37（3尺7寸、112cm）、高校生・大学生・社会人用38（3尺8寸、115cm）、大学生・社会人用39（3尺9寸、118cm）がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Currently there are different length of shinai available, common sizes are size 36 (3 jaku 6 sun, 109 cm) for primary students, size 37 (3 jaku 7sun, 112cm) for junior high school students, size 38 (3 jaku 8 sun, 115cm) for University students, and adults.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Currently there are different length of shinai available; common sizes are size 36 (3 jaku 6 sun, 109 cm) for primary students, size 37 (3 jaku 7sun, 112cm) for junior high school students, size 38 (3 jaku 8 sun, 115cm) for high school students, university students and adults, and size 39 (3 jaku 9 sun, 118cm) for university students and adults.</e>
<cmt>*Revised for clarity - added missing section</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Currently there are different length of shinai available; common sizes are size 36 (3 jaku 6 sun, 109 cm) for primary students, size 37 (3 jaku 7sun, 112cm) for junior high school students, size 38 (3 jaku 8 sun, 115cm) for high school students, university students and adults, and size 39 (3 jaku 9 sun, 118cm) for university students and adults.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>大学以上の場合、3尺9寸が上限となっているのは、従来の3尺8寸を、日本人の体格向上にあわせて1寸伸ばしたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The longest shinai is decided to 3 jaku 9 sun for University students and adults, which the length was extended from formerly regulated size of 3 jaku 8 sun to 3 jaku 9 sun, since the average of height of Japanese became higher than before.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With an increase in the average of height of Japanese, the longest shinai, for university students and adults, was also increased from 3 jaku 8 sun to 3 jaku 9 sun.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With an increase in the average of height of Japanese, the longest shinai, for university students and adults, was also increased from 3 jaku 8 sun to 3 jaku 9 sun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>形状</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The shape</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shape</e>
<cmt>Article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shape</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="25">
<j>一般の竹刀は柄の形は円だが、一部には小判型といって楕円形のものもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ordinal shape of tsuka (hilt) of Shinai is circle, but there is also oval shape tsuka available which is called kobangata.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The tsuka is usually circular, but there is also an oval-shaped tsuka, known as kobangata.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The tsuka is usually circular, but there is also an oval-shaped tsuka, known as kobangata.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>小判型の柄は、刀に近い手の内で握ることができるため、初心者にはこちらのほうがいいという声もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some people say kobangata tsuka is easier for beginner to use since the feeling of holding oval shaped tsuka is similar to sword.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some people say a kobangata tsuka is easier for beginners to use since the feeling of holding the oval-shaped tsuka is similar that of holding a sword.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some people say a kobangata tsuka is easier for beginners to use since the feeling of holding the oval-shaped tsuka is similar that of holding a sword.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 かんそうた(id:191943), TT(id:46431), Izayohi(id:13095), 妖精書士(id:101212), ミッドランドライダー(id:40104), Nighthawks(id:36125), Was a bee(id:48806), Nallimbot(id:230812), 晴雲(id:27169), Himazin(id:22034), TXiKiBoT(id:107492), Shino chan(id:27499), LaaknorBot(id:220851), Anexus6(id:190046), タノ(id:102440), Yupik(id:74566), Snow steed(id:9428), Thijs!bot(id:69644), VolkovBot(id:105371), 橄欖岩(id:24996), A-Taul(id:41790), Rei-bot(id:94097), Chobot(id:20846), Yas(id:739), Alexbot(id:157199), FlaBot(id:30804), Comyu(id:58135), GENMEI(id:31879), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>