<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>剣術</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kenjutsu (剣術) (Swordplay)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenjutsu (剣術) (Swordplay)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenjutsu (剣術) (Swordplay)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>剣術（けんじゅつ）とは古武道の一つであり、日本の刀剣であるかたな（日本刀）で以て相手を殺傷する武術である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kenjutsu is one of Kobudo (classical martial arts) to kill and wound opponents with katana (Japanese sword).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenjutsu is one of Japan&apos;s Kobudo (classical martial arts) with the focus of killing and wounding opponents with a katana (Japanese sword).</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenjutsu is one of Japan&apos;s Kobudo (classical martial arts) with the focus of killing and wounding opponents with a katana (Japanese sword).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>現代日本の武道である剣道の母体となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kenjutsu is the origin of Kendo, one of contemporary Japanese martial arts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenjutsu is the origin of Kendo, one of the contemporary Japanese martial arts.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenjutsu is the origin of Kendo, one of the contemporary Japanese martial arts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>なお術の名称については中国では、片刃の刀と両刃（諸刃）の剣が明確に別の武器であると認識されているが、日本では刀と剣の認識が混ざってしまい曖昧となってしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Concerning the name of this martial art, single edged swords&quot;katana (刀) and double edged swords &quot;tsurugi (剣) were clearly distinguished in China while their distinction was ambiguous in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Concerning the name of this martial art, single edged swords &quot;katana&quot; (刀) and double edged swords &quot;tsurugi&quot; (剣) were clearly distinguished in China while their distinction was ambiguous in Japan.</e>
<cmt>closed quotations</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Concerning the name of this martial art, single edged swords &quot;katana&quot; (刀) and double edged swords &quot;tsurugi&quot; (剣) were clearly distinguished in China while their distinction was ambiguous in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>日本では中国から伝来した刀剣が両刃（諸刃）の剣（つるぎ）から片刃の日本刀（かたな）へ完全に移行してしまったためである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As double edged &quot;tsurugi&quot; changed to single edged &quot;katana&quot; after they were imported from China to Japan, this martial art came to be called Kenjutsu (剣術).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As double edged &quot;tsurugi&quot; changed to single edged &quot;katana&quot; after they were imported from China to Japan, this martial art came to be called Kenjutsu (剣術).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As double edged &quot;tsurugi&quot; changed to single edged &quot;katana&quot; after they were imported from China to Japan, this martial art came to be called Kenjutsu (剣術).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>刀術という名称もあるが、『本朝武藝小傳』など極少数の江戸時代の文献に使用されているが定着はしなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although this art was also called Tojutsu (刀術), such name was used only by few documents, such as &quot;Honcho Bugei Shoden&quot; written in the Edo period, and didn&apos;t took root.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although this art was also called Tojutsu (刀術), this name was used only in a few documents, such as &quot;Honcho Bugei Shoden&quot; written in the Edo period, and didn&apos;t take root.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although this art was also called Tojutsu (刀術), this name was used only in a few documents, such as &quot;Honcho Bugei Shoden&quot; written in the Edo period, and didn&apos;t take root.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>なお中国の剣術に対しては中国剣を参照のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Concerning Chinese Kenjutsu, refer to Chinese swords.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Concerning Chinese Kenjutsu, refer to Chinese swords.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Concerning Chinese Kenjutsu, refer to Chinese swords.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>日本の剣術と世界各国の剣術・刀術を比較すると、刃長60cm以上の刀を両手で持ち、互いに盾を用いずに戦うという形式は珍しく、中世にドイツでツーハンデッドソードによる剣術があげられるくらいである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This type of swordplay, in which both parties fight, without shields, holding swords of 60cm over length by both hands, is seldom seen in other countries than Japan, with the exception of the swordplay called Two-handed sword in the medieval age of Germany.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This type of swordplay, in which both parties fight, without shields, holding swords of over 60cm in length with both hands, is seldom seen in countries other than Japan, with the exception of the swordplay called Two-handed swords in the medieval age of Germany.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This type of swordplay, in which both parties fight, without shields, holding swords of over 60cm in length with both hands, is seldom seen in countries other than Japan, with the exception of the swordplay called Two-handed swords in the medieval age of Germany.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>江戸時代に大きく発展したため、戦闘で着用する甲冑は前提とされず、平時の服装での斬り合いを想定している型が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Kenjutsu developed remarkably in the Edo period, most of kata (forms of Kenjutsu) were created on the premise of the fight in the peaceful time taht is done between persons wearing ordinary clothes, not the fight on the battlefields in which people wear kacchu (armor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Kenjutsu developed considerably during the Edo period, most of kata (forms of Kenjutsu) were created under the assumption that the fight would be in a peaceful time between people wearing ordinary clothes, not a fight on a battlefield in which people would wear kacchu (armor).</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Kenjutsu developed considerably during the Edo period, most of kata (forms of Kenjutsu) were created under the assumption that the fight would be in a peaceful time between people wearing ordinary clothes, not a fight on a battlefield in which people would wear kacchu (armor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>実際の戦場での切りあいは型通りではなく、袈裟（鎖骨・頚動脈）に切り込む事が主流であったともいわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the fight on the actual battlefields was not done according to kata but was done by attempting to cut kesa (the collarbone, the carotid).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the fights on actual battlefields were not done according to kata but were done by attempting to cut kesa (the collarbone, the carotid).</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the fights on actual battlefields were not done according to kata but were done by attempting to cut kesa (the collarbone, the carotid).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>また「二の太刀いらず」で有名なジゲン流（薬丸自顕流や示現流）を習得した薩摩藩士の戦いぶりにおいて、その斬殺死体の殆どが袈裟切りを受けて即死に至っていたとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also said that most of persons killed by feudal retainers of Satsuma Domain, who acquired the skill of Jigen School (Yakushimarujigen School and Jigen School), which is known for a phrase &quot;another blow is not necessary&quot;, were slashed to instant death by kesagiri (slashing diagonally from the shoulder).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also said that most people killed by feudal retainers of the Satsuma Domain, who acquired the skill of Jigen School (Yakushimarujigen School and Jigen School), which is known for the phrase &quot;another blow is not necessary&quot;, were slashed to instant death by kesagiri (slashing diagonally from the shoulder).</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also said that most people killed by feudal retainers of the Satsuma Domain, who acquired the skill of Jigen School (Yakushimarujigen School and Jigen School), which is known for the phrase &quot;another blow is not necessary&quot;, were slashed to instant death by kesagiri (slashing diagonally from the shoulder).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="11">
<j>人物については剣豪人物一覧及びカテゴリ剣客を参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for famous persons, refer to the list of kengo (a great swordsman) and the category of kenkyaku (an expert swordsman).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for famous persons, refer to the list of kengo (a great swordsman) and the category of kenkyaku (an expert swordsman).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for famous persons, refer to the list of kengo (a great swordsman) and the category of kenkyaku (an expert swordsman).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>古代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ancient times</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ancient times</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ancient times</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="12">
<j>日本において青銅製の武器の作成が開始されたのは、出土品から見て早くても紀元1世紀以降とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Judging from excavated articles, the production of bronze swords in Japan is believed to have started in the 1st century at the earliest.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Judging from excavated articles, the production of bronze swords in Japan is believed to have started in the 1st century at the earliest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Judging from excavated articles, the production of bronze swords in Japan is believed to have started in the 1st century at the earliest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>しかし、この時代の日本にはまだ文字がなかったため、この時代の剣術については伝わっておらず、その有無・詳細は不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the details concerning Kenjutsu at the time, including its existence, are unknown since there were no letters in Japan at the time.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the details concerning Kenjutsu at the time, including its existence, are unknown since there was no written language in Japan at the time.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the details concerning Kenjutsu at the time, including its existence, are unknown since there was no written language in Japan at the time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="14">
<j>鉄製の剣の使用は軍事的優位の源泉であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Using iron swords was the source of military advantage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Using iron swords was the source of military advantage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Using iron swords was the source of military advantage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>しかし鉄製の刀剣の国産が盛んになったのは7世紀以降である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the production of iron swords became active only after the 7th century in Japan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the production of iron swords became active only after the 7th century in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the production of iron swords became active only after the 7th century in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>推古天皇が「太刀ならば句礼（中国の呉）の真鋤（刀剣の意味）」と詠っているように、古代は大陸からの輸入品が主流であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the Emperor Suiko said &quot;masasabi (swords) produced in Kure (Wu-southern part of ancient China) is the best one&quot;, swords imported from China were mainly used in the ancient times.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the Emperor Suiko said &quot;masasabi (swords) produced in Kure (Wu-southern part of ancient China) are the best&quot;, swords imported from China were mainly used during ancient times.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the Emperor Suiko said &quot;masasabi (swords) produced in Kure (Wu-southern part of ancient China) are the best&quot;, swords imported from China were mainly used during ancient times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>刀工である「鍛冶戸」が朝廷によって各地におかれたのは8世紀以降である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kajitsube&quot;, a factory of to-ko (sword craftsman), was established at many places by the Imperial court in the 8th century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kajitsube&quot;, factories for to-ko (sword craftsman), were established at many places by the Imperial court in the 8th century.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Kajitsube&quot;, factories for to-ko (sword craftsman), were established at many places by the Imperial court in the 8th century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>これ以降、日本国内でも直刀や蕨手刀などの多種多様な鉄の剣が作られるようになっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since then, varieties of iron swords, including choku-to (straight sword) and warabite-to (curved sword), were produced in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since then, varieties of iron swords, including choku-to (straight sword) and warabite-to (curved sword), were produced in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since then, varieties of iron swords, including choku-to (straight sword) and warabite-to (curved sword), were produced in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>平安時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Heian period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Heian period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Heian period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="19">
<j>平安時代になると、日本国内での鉄製法は大陸と遜色ないレベルにまで達した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Technologies for producing iron sword in Japan reached the level comparable to that of China in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Technologies for producing iron swords in Japan reached levels comparable to that of China in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Technologies for producing iron swords in Japan reached levels comparable to that of China in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>さらに、従来の真っ直ぐな剣から、湾曲して人を斬りやすく、また馬上での戦いに適した形に進化し、やがて現在まで伝わる日本刀の原型ともいえる剣が登場する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Instead of then existing straight swords, curved swords which were more suitable for cutting persons or those suitable for the fight on horses were developed, and the original model of current Japanese sword was created.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Instead of the then existing straight swords, curved swords which were more suitable for cutting persons or those suitable for fighting on horseback were developed, and the original model of the current Japanese sword was created.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Instead of the then existing straight swords, curved swords which were more suitable for cutting persons or those suitable for fighting on horseback were developed, and the original model of the current Japanese sword was created.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="21">
<j>平安時代の日本においては、中国・朝鮮半島との紛争が沈静化し、隼人や蝦夷との戦いも終わりが見え始めて国内統一が実現された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan became an unified nation in the Heian period after the disputes with China/Korea were settled and the war against Hayato (ancient tribe in Kyushu) and Ezo (ancient tribe in Tohoku) ended.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan became a unified nation in the Heian period after the disputes with China/Korea were settled and the war against Hayato (ancient tribe in Kyushu) and Ezo (ancient tribe in Tohoku) ended.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan became a unified nation in the Heian period after the disputes with China/Korea were settled and the war against Hayato (ancient tribe in Kyushu) and Ezo (ancient tribe in Tohoku) ended.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>そのなかで、儒教の影響以前に、日本古来の呪術的発想から、軍事力ないし警察力の行使というケガレ仕事は国家の制度の内に公式のものとして存在を認めないという世界でも類の少ない特異な制度が採用された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under such situation, Japan adopted the unique system, based on the Japanese traditional magical philosophy rather than Confucian philosophy, under which the use of military and police force was not incorporated into the official system of the nation.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In such a situation, Japan adopted a unique system, based on Japanese traditional magical philosophy rather than Confucian philosophy, under which the use of military and police force was not incorporated into the official system of the nation.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In such a situation, Japan adopted a unique system in the world, based on Japanese traditional magical philosophy rather than Confucian philosophy, under which impure works such as the use of military and police force were not regarded as official system of the nation.</e>
<cmt>訳抜けを追加し、後半修正。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="23">
<j>このことによって、逆に地方における警察力の欠如の環境での生存確保のためには、紛争における自力救済が必要とされるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to the above, however, self-help in settling disputes became necessary in order to make up for the lack of police force as well as to secure lives.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to the above, however, self-help in settling disputes became necessary in order to make up for the lack of police force as well as to secure lives.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to the above, however, self-help in settling disputes became necessary in order to make up for the lack of police force as well as to secure lives.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>こうして、平安時代以降、各地の自衛農民団、もしくは自衛海運業者団としての武士団の発展を促した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, many of bushidan (samurai group) were organized in the Heian period as self-defense farmers&apos; groups or self-defense shipping agents&apos; groups.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, many bushidan (samurai group) were organized in the Heian period as self-defense groups for farmers and shipping agents.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, many bushidan (samurai group) were organized in the Heian period as self-defense groups for farmers and shipping agents.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="25">
<j>このころに日本刀が「片手持ち」から、柄が長くなり「諸手持ち」へと変わり現在にいたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around that time, the shape of Japanese sword changed into the current one, whose hilt is longer than previous one, and became suitable to hold it with both hands rather than with one hand.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around that time, the shape of the Japanese sword changed into that of the current one, whose hilt is longer than the previous one, and it became suitable to hold it with both hands rather than with one hand.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around that time, the shape of the Japanese sword changed into that of the current one, whose hilt is longer than the previous one, and it became suitable to hold it with both hands rather than with one hand.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>これにより平時において、瞬時に人を殺傷し得る能力を持った、武士に不可欠な日本刀と剣術とを組み合わせた様式は、この時代までには確立された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eventually, a pattern combining Japanese sword, which was an indispensible item for samurai and had the potential ability to kill or wound persons instantly, and Kenjutsu was established around that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eventually, a style combining the Japanese sword, which was an indispensible item for the samurai and had the potential ability to kill or wound persons instantly, and Kenjutsu was established around that time.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eventually, a style combining the Japanese sword, which was an indispensible item for the samurai and had the potential ability to kill or wound persons instantly, and Kenjutsu was established around that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>源平時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Genpei period (late 11th century - late 12th century)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Genpei period (late 11th century - late 12th century)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genpei period (late 11th century - late 12th century)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="27">
<j>『平家物語』に剣術の技名のようなものが見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">What looks like the name of Kenjutsu skill is seen in &quot;The Tale of Heike&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">What looks like the name of Kenjutsu skill is seen in &quot;The Tale of Heike&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">What looks like the name of Kenjutsu skill is seen in &quot;The Tale of Heike&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>鎌倉時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kamakura period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kamakura period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kamakura period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="28">
<j>武士が国家の中心勢力としての地位を確立するにいたって、日本は大陸の儒教文化圏からは異なった、古武道と為政者がその習得を行うことに上位の価値を認める文化の形成を開始した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the samurai class established its status as the core power of the nation, Japan began seceding from the Confucian cultural sphere and forming its unique culture under which the ruler highly values Kobudo and its training.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the samurai class established its status as the core power of the nation, Japan began seceding from the Confucian cultural sphere and forming its own unique culture under which the ruler highly valued Kobudo and its training.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the samurai class established its status as the core power of the nation, Japan began seceding from the Confucian cultural sphere and forming its own unique culture under which the ruler highly valued Kobudo and its training.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>戦国時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sengoku period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sengoku period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sengoku period (period of warring states)</e>
<cmt>用語集に沿い修正</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="29">
<j>戦国時代 (日本)の剣術（兵法）は、戦場での総合的な戦闘技術を包括したものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kenjutsu (art of warfare) in the Sengoku period (Japan) was the one that integrated various combat skills on the battlefields.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenjutsu (art of warfare) in the Sengoku period (Japan) integrated various combat skills on the battlefields.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenjutsu (art of warfare) in the Sengoku period (Japan) integrated various combat skills on the battlefields.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="30">
<j>当時の戦場での刀剣の使用において、太刀は主兵器ではなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Swords were not main weapons on the actual battle fields at the time.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Swords were not main weapons on the actual battle fields at the time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Swords were not main weapons on the actual battle fields at the time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>戦場では、体格に優れた者が野太刀・大太刀などの長大な刀をひたすら振り回して軽装歩兵に対して斬りつけるという方法か、騎兵突撃の際に加速のついた状態で馬上から敵の手足顔面を強くこすり斬るというのが一般的だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the actual battlefields, persons with good build tried to slash foot soldiers by swinging about long swords called nodachi or odachi, or cavalrymen tried to slash enemies&apos; hands/feet/face while making a rush.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On actual battlefields, people with good builds tried to slash foot soldiers by swinging long swords called nodachi or odachi, or cavalrymen tried to slash enemies&apos; hands/feet/face while rushing toward them.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On actual battlefields, people with good builds tried to slash foot soldiers by swinging long swords called nodachi or odachi, or cavalrymen tried to slash enemies&apos; hands/feet/face while rushing toward them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>多くの戦国大名が巨身の「力士」を雇い入れることに熱心であったのは、彼らでなければ振り回せない長刀を装備した上で、力士隊として編成して身辺警護や特殊兵力に用いるためであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many of daimyo (Japanese territorial lord) in the Sengoku period employed &quot;rikishi&quot; (persons with good build), gave them long swords that could be handled only by them, organized them into rikishitai and used them as bodyguards or special force.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many daimyo (Japanese territorial lord) during the Sengoku period employed &quot;rikishi&quot; (persons with good build), gave them long swords that could be handled only by them, organized them into rikishitai and used them as bodyguards or special forces.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many daimyo (Japanese territorial lord) during the Sengoku period employed &quot;rikishi&quot; (persons with good build), gave them long swords that could be handled only by them, organized them into rikishitai and used them as bodyguards or special forces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>戦場で重装備の相手に対しては、太刀よりも槍・薙刀術や棒のほうが適している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When fighting against heavily-armored soldiers, spears/naginata (Japanese halberd)/sticks were more suitable than swords.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When fighting against heavily-armored soldiers, spears/naginata (Japanese halberd)/sticks were more suitable than swords.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When fighting against heavily-armored soldiers, spears/naginata (Japanese halberd)/sticks were more suitable than swords.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>甲冑を装着した武者同士の太刀による戦闘方法は、当然、巨人がただ刀を振り回せばよいものとは異なった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Unlike the case of persons with good build, fighting style between heavily-armored samurai was not simply swinging about swords.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unlike those with good builds, fighting styles between heavily-armored samurai was not simply swinging about swords.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unlike those with good builds, fighting styles between heavily-armored samurai was not simply swinging about swords.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>介者剣術と呼ばれ、深く腰を落とした姿勢から目・首・脇の下・金的・内腿・手首といった、装甲の隙間となっている部位を突斬りで狙うようなスタイルであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was called Kaisha Kenjutsu and samurai involved tried to stab and cut, while taking bent-over posture, the site of armored gaps such as the eyes, the neck, the armpit, kin-teki, the inner thigh and the wrists.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was called Kaisha Kenjutsu and samurai involved tried to stab and cut, while in a bent-over posture, locations of gaps in armor such as the eyes, the neck, the armpit, kin-teki, the inner thigh and the wrists.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was called Kaisha Kenjutsu and samurai involved tried to stab and cut, while in a bent-over posture, locations of gaps in armor such as the eyes, the neck, the armpit, kin-teki, the inner thigh and the wrists.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>甲冑武者同士の戦闘は最終的には組討による決着に至ることが多く、ここにおける技法が組討術であり後の柔術の源流の一つとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fighting between heavily-armored samurai often became grappling eventually, and grappling skills employed in such fighting became the one of origins of Jujutsu (one of classical Japanese martial arts).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fighting between heavily-armored samurai often eventually became grappling, and grappling skills employed in such fighting became one of the origins of Jujutsu (one of the classical Japanese martial arts).</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fighting between heavily-armored samurai often finally came to an end by grappling, and grappling skills employed in such fighting became one of the origins of Jujutsu (one of the classical Japanese martial arts).</e>
<cmt>原文の意図に沿い修正。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>今日の柔道も、その柔術より派生したものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Contemporary Judo derived from Jujutsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Contemporary Judo is derived from Jujutsu.</e>
<cmt>ok</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Contemporary Judo is derived from Jujutsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="38">
<j>今日伝わる剣術の流派は「京八流・関東七流」を源流とする伝えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has been passed down that the origin of contemporary schools of Kenjutsu was &quot;Kyo-Hachiryu (eight schools in Kyoto)/Kanto-Shihiryu (seven schools in Kanto)&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has been passed down that the origin of contemporary schools of Kenjutsu was &quot;Kyo-Hachiryu (eight schools in Kyoto)/Kanto-Shihiryu (seven schools in Kanto)&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has been passed down that the origin of contemporary schools of Kenjutsu was &quot;Kyo-Hachiryu (eight schools in Kyoto)/Kanto-Shihiryu (seven schools in Kanto)&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="39">
<j>京八流は、平安時代末期に源義経を指導したといわれる陰陽師・鬼一法眼の8人の弟子に発すると伝わる（真偽は不明）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has been passed down that Kyo-Hachiryu were founded by eight disciples of Hogen KIICHI, onmyoji (Master of Yin yang) who is said to have instructed MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune during the late Heian period (truth remains to be confirmed).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has been passed down that Kyo-Hachiryu was founded by eight disciples of Hogen KIICHI, onmyoji (Master of Yin yang) who is said to have instructed MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune during the late Heian period (the truth of this remains to be confirmed).</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Kyo-Hachiryu was founded by eight disciples of Hogen KIICHI, onmyoji (Master of Yin yang) who was said to have instructed MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune during the late Heian period (the truth of this remains to be confirmed).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>京八流を祖とすると伝える流派は、鞍馬流・念流・中条流・吉岡流などである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Schools which originated from Kyo- Hachiryu include Kurama-ryu School, Nen-ryu School, Chujo-ryu School and Yoshioka-ryu School etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Schools which originated from Kyo-Hachiryu include the Kurama-ryu School, the Nen-ryu School, the Chujo-ryu School and the Yoshioka-ryu School etc.</e>
<cmt>removed space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Schools which originated from Kyo-Hachiryu include the Kurama-ryu School, the Nen-ryu School, the Chujo-ryu School and the Yoshioka-ryu School.</e>
<cmt>etc削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="41">
<j>関東七流は、日本神話で葦原中国平定を成功させた経津主神とタケミカヅチが香取郡鹿島郡 (茨城県)地方に居ついて以降、天孫降臨より香取神宮・鹿島神宮の神職に伝承され、その7家から発すると云われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the origin of Kanto-Shichiryu were seven families which derived from Futsunushi no kami and Takemikazuki, who, according to Japanese Mythology, settled in Katori-gun Kashima-gun (Ibaragi Prefecture) after the conquest of Ashihara no nakatsukuni and whose descendants inherited the position of Shinto priest at Katori-jingu Shrine and Kashima Jingu Shrine since tenson korin (descent of the grandson of the sun goddess).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the origin of Kanto-Shichiryu was seven families descended from Futsunushi no kami and Takemikazuki, who, according to Japanese Mythology, settled in Katori-gun Kashima-gun (Ibaragi Prefecture) after the conquest of Ashihara no nakatsukuni and whose descendants inherited the position of Shinto priest at Katori-jingu Shrine and Kashima Jingu Shrine due to tenson korin (descent of the grandson of the sun goddess).</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Kanto-Shichiryu was established by seven Shinto priest families from Katori-jingu Shrine and Kashima-jingu Shrine to whom the art of kenjutsu had been passed on by Futsunushi no kami and Takemikazuki when these kami settled in Katori county and Kashima county (Ibaragi Prefecture) after the conquest of Ashihara no nakatsukuni due to the tenson korin (descent of the grandson of the sun goddess).</e>
<cmt>神職が神の子孫なのではなく、天孫降臨した神の子孫から伝承されたという考え方と思われます。Katori-gun and Kashima-gun→Katori county and Kashima county</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>そこから新当流・念流・陰流という今日現存する日本の剣術の源流とされる3流派が生じたと云われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Shinto-ryu School, Nen-ryu School and Kage-ryu School, three schools of Kenjutsu in existence at present, originated from Kanto-Shichiryu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the Shinto-ryu School, Nen-ryu School and Kage-ryu School, the three schools of Kenjutsu in existence at present, originated from Kanto-Shichiryu.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the Shinto-ryu School, Nen-ryu School and Kage-ryu School, the three schools of Kenjutsu in existence at present, originated from Kanto-Shichiryu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="43">
<j>新当流は香取神道流など神道流（新当流）系、念流は馬庭念流、中条流系の諸流派、陰流は、新陰流（新陰流柳生新陰流）系につながる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shito-ryu School is related to Shinto-ryu group such as Katori Shinto-ryu School, Nen-ryu School is related to Maniwanen-ryu School and Chujo-ryu School, and Kage-ryu School is related to Shinkage-ryu School (Shinkage-ryu Yagyushinkage-ryu School).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Shito-ryu School is related to the Shinto-ryu group such as the Katori Shinto-ryu School, the Nen-ryu School is related to the Maniwanen-ryu School and the Chujo-ryu School, and Kage-ryu School is related to the Shinkage-ryu School (Shinkage-ryu Yagyushinkage-ryu School).</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Shinto-ryu School is related to the Shinto-ryu group such as the Katori Shinto-ryu School, the Nen-ryu School is related to the Maniwanen-ryu School and the Chujo-ryu School, and Kage-ryu School is related to the Shinkage-ryu School (Shinkage-ryu Yagyushinkage-ryu School).</e>
<cmt>Shito-ryu　→Shinto-ryu</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>（富田流や一刀流など、念流の開祖は念阿弥慈恩、また馬庭念流の樋口家に伝わる古文書に、念阿弥慈恩の弟子として「中条判官」や「猿御前」という名が記されているが、念流では中条判官は中条兵庫頭、猿御前は愛洲移香斎と伝えている）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(The founder of Nen-ryu School, including Toda-ryu School and Itto-ryu School, was Jion NENAMI. While &quot;Chujo hangan&quot; and &quot;Saru gozen&quot; were described as Jion NENAMI&apos;s disciples in the ancient document handed down in the Higuchi family of Maniwanen-ryu School, Nen-ryu School believes the former was Chujo Hyogo no kami and the Latter was Ikosai AISU)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(The founder of the Nen-ryu School, as well as the Toda-ryu School and the Itto-ryu School, was Jion NENAMI. While &quot;Chujo hangan&quot; and &quot;Saru gozen&quot; were described as Jion NENAMI&apos;s disciples in the ancient document handed down in the Higuchi family of the Maniwanen-ryu School, the Nen-ryu School believes the former was Chujo Hyogo no kami and the latter was Ikosai AISU)</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(The founder of the Nen-ryu School, as well as the Toda-ryu School and the Itto-ryu School, was Jion NENAMI. While &quot;Chujo hangan&quot; and &quot;Saru gozen&quot; were described as Jion NENAMI&apos;s disciples in the ancient document handed down in the Higuchi family of the Maniwanen-ryu School, the Nen-ryu School believes the former was Chujo Hyogo no kami and the latter was Ikosai AISU)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>ただし現在の武道史の研究では、京八流・関東七流の実在を確認できないため、単なる伝説と扱うのが一般的である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, current researchers of Kenjutsu history generally regard the above-mentioned as a legend since the existence of Kyo-Hachiryu and Kanto-Shichiryu has not been confirmed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, current researchers of Kenjutsu history generally regard the above-mentioned as a legend since the existence of Kyo-Hachiryu and Kanto-Shichiryu has not been confirmed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, current researchers of Kenjutsu history generally regard the above-mentioned as a legend since the existence of Kyo-Hachiryu and Kanto-Shichiryu has not been confirmed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="46">
<j>戦国時代も後期になるにつれ、一種の専門職としての剣術者が認識され、各地を渡り歩くようにもなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Expert swordsmen were recognized as professional personnel in the late Sengoku period, and they began to wander from place to place.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Expert swordsmen were recognized as professional personnel in the late Sengoku period, and they began to wander from place to place.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Expert swordsmen were recognized as professional personnel in the late Sengoku period, and they began to wander from place to place.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>彼らは、己の郎党を率いて戦場で働くことで戦功を重ねて、最終的に国取り、城持ちを目指した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They aimed to become the lord of country/castle by achieving distinguished service at battlefields while leading their retainers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They aimed to become the lord of countries/castles by achieving distinguished service on battlefields while leading their retainers.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They aimed to become the lord of countries/castles by achieving distinguished service on battlefields while leading their retainers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>これは軍人かつ政治家として大成する常道的なコース（例えば豊臣秀吉）ではなく、ひとえに剣術の卓越によって禄と名声を得ることを目的としていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Their aim was obtaining roku (stipend) and fame through their superior Kenjutsu skill, not the success as a military man cum a politician (like the case of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their aim was obtaining roku (stipend) and fame through their superior Kenjutsu skill, as opposed to success as a military man or a politician (like the case of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI).</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Their aim was obtaining roku (stipend) and fame through their superior Kenjutsu skill, as opposed to success as a military man or a politician (like the case of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>多くの流派の開祖はこのような人々であり、伊東一刀斎・塚原卜伝・上泉信綱（秀綱）・柳生宗厳・富田勢源・東郷重位といった大物の開祖が戦国時代後期から安土桃山時代にかけて輩出されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The founders of many schools were these people, and a lot of great founders, including Ittosai ITO, Bokuden TSUKAHARA, Nobutsuna (Hidetsuna) KAMIIZUMI, Muneyoshi YAGYU, Seigen TODA and Chui TOGO, appeared during the time from the late Sengoku period to the Azuchi-Momoyama period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The founders of many schools were these people, and a lot of great founders, including Ittosai ITO, Bokuden TSUKAHARA, Nobutsuna (Hidetsuna) KAMIIZUMI, Muneyoshi YAGYU, Seigen TODA and Chui TOGO, appeared during the time from the late Sengoku period to the Azuchi-Momoyama period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The founders of many schools were these people, and a lot of great founders, including Ittosai ITO, Bokuden TSUKAHARA, Nobutsuna (Hidetsuna) KAMIIZUMI, Muneyoshi YAGYU, Seigen TODA and Chui TOGO, appeared during the time from the late Sengoku period to the Azuchi-Momoyama period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="50">
<j>またこの時期に竹刀の元になった袋竹刀やひきはだ撓と呼ばれる道具が各流派の稽古に使われるようになったと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is thought that fukuro shinai (bamboo sword covered with a bag) and hikihada shinai (toad-skin bamboo sword), the origin of shinai (bamboo sword), came to be used for training around that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is thought that fukuro shinai (bamboo sword covered with a bag) and hikihada shinai (toad-skin bamboo sword), the origin of shinai (bamboo sword), came to be used for training around that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is thought that fukuro shinai (bamboo sword covered with a bag) and hikihada shinai (toad-skin bamboo sword), the origin of shinai (bamboo sword), came to be used for training around that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>安土桃山時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Azuchi-Momoyama period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Azuchi-Momoyama period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Azuchi-Momoyama period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="51">
<j>国内再統一の後、兵農分離、刀狩が行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the nation was reunified, the policy of heinobunri (separation of the warrior class in the domain from its soil) and katanagari (swords collection) were implemented.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the nation was reunified, the policy of heinobunri (separation of the warrior class in the domain from its soil) and katanagari (swords collection) were implemented.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the nation was reunified, the policy of heinobunri (separation of the warrior class in the domain from its soil) and katanagari (swords collection) were implemented.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>これ以前にはいわゆる武士でなくとも成人男性が平素から帯刀していた習慣があったことは、日本人と剣術とのかかわりの深さを認識する上で重要である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fact that Japanese adult males, including those who were not samurai, customarily wore a sword is an important factor in understanding a close relation between Japanese people and Kenjutsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fact that Japanese adult males, including those who were not samurai, customarily wore a sword is an important factor in understanding the close relation between Japanese people and Kenjutsu.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fact that Japanese adult males, including those who were not samurai, customarily wore a sword is an important factor in understanding the close relation between Japanese people and Kenjutsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>剣術において、戦場ではなく日常での使用が前提とされたものが主流になるのはこの時期からである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since that time, Kenjutsu which was supposed to be used in daily lives, instead of battlefields, became the mainstream.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since that time, Kenjutsu which was supposed to be used in daily lives, instead of on battlefields, became the mainstream.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since that time, Kenjutsu which was supposed to be used in daily lives, instead of on battlefields, became the mainstream.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>江戸時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Edo period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Edo period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Edo period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="54">
<j>介者剣術から平服、平時の偶発的個人の戦いを想定する素肌剣術に変わったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that kaisha-Kenjutsu changed into suhada-Kenjutsu, which was supposed to be used in an accidental fight in peace time that is done between persons wearing ordinary clothes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that kaisha-Kenjutsu changed into suhada-Kenjutsu, which was supposed to be used in an accidental fight during peace time between people wearing ordinary clothes.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that kaisha-Kenjutsu changed into suhada-Kenjutsu, which was supposed to be used in an accidental fight during peace time between people wearing ordinary clothes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="55">
<j>また、平和な江戸時代において、禅など心法に重きをおく流派がでるなど変化していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some schools which put more emphasis on shinpo (mind training), such as Zen, appeared in the peaceful Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some schools which put more emphasis on shinpo (mind training), such as Zen, appeared in the peaceful Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some schools which put more emphasis on shinpo (mind training), such as Zen, appeared in the peaceful Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>殺人刀と活人剣</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Setsuninto (the blade that kills) and Katsuninken (the sword that brings to life)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Setsuninto (the blade that kills) and Katsuninken (the sword that brings to life)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Setsuninto (the blade that kills) and Katsuninken (the sword that brings to life)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="56">
<j>「殺人刀」（せつにんとう）と「活人剣」（かつにんけん）とは、元来は禅の『無門関』・『碧巖録』などの公案での用語である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The terms of &quot;Setsuninto&quot; and &quot;Katsuninken&quot; were originally used in the koan (a method to learn the secrets of Zen) of Zen sect such as &quot;Mumonkan&quot; and &quot;Hekiganroku&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The terms of &quot;Setsuninto&quot; and &quot;Katsuninken&quot; were originally used in the koan (a method to learn the secrets of Zen) of Zen sects such as &quot;Mumonkan&quot; and &quot;Hekiganroku&quot;.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The terms of &quot;Setsuninto&quot; and &quot;Katsuninken&quot; were originally used in the koan (a method to learn the secrets of Zen) of Zen sects such as &quot;Mumonkan&quot; and &quot;Hekiganroku&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="57">
<j>上泉信綱が2月に肥後国の丸目長恵に与えた印可が「殺人刀・活人剣」とあり、また一刀流の本目録十四「まんじ・殺人刀・活人剣」という名前がみられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The terms of &quot;Setsuninto and Katsuninken&quot; are seen in the certificate which Nobutsuna Kamiizumi gave in February to Nagayoshi MARUME of Higo Province, and the terms of &quot;Manji, Setsuninto and Katsuninken&quot; are seen in the certificate 14 of Itto-ryu School.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The terms of &quot;Setsuninto and Katsuninken&quot; are seen in the certificate which Nobutsuna Kamiizumi gave in February to Nagayoshi MARUME of Higo Province, and the terms of &quot;Manji, Setsuninto and Katsuninken&quot; are seen in the certificate 14 of Itto-ryu School.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The terms of &quot;Setsuninto and Katsuninken&quot; are seen in the certificate which Nobutsuna Kamiizumi gave in February to Nagayoshi MARUME of Higo Province, and the terms of &quot;Manji, Setsuninto and Katsuninken&quot; are seen in the certificate 14 of Itto-ryu School.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>このように、武術に対して、他の禅の用語と同じく大きな影響をあたえた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As seen from the above, they gave big impacts on martial arts along with other Zen terms.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As seen above, they had a big impact on martial arts along with other Zen terms.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As seen above, they had a big impact on martial arts along with other Zen terms.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="59">
<j>兵法家伝書</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Heiho kadensho (book of the family transition of swordsmanship)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Heiho kadensho (book of the family transition of swordsmanship)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Heiho kadensho (book of the family transition of swordsmanship)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>江戸時代初期の柳生宗矩が兵法家伝書において次のように禅とは異なる意味で使用した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the early Edo period, Munenori YAGYU used these terms in a different sense from those of Zen in Heiho kadensho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the early Edo period, Munenori YAGYU used these terms in a different sense from those of Zen in the Heiho kadensho.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the early Edo period, Munenori YAGYU used these terms in a different sense from those of Zen in the Heiho kadensho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="61">
<j>「一人の悪に依りて、萬人苦しむ事あり。しかるに、一人の悪をころして萬人をいかす、是等誠に、人をころす刀は人をいかすつるぎなるべきにや。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Many people could be suffered by one person&apos;s wicked deed. As killing one wicked could help many people, the blade that kills persons could become the sword that brings persons to life.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Many people can suffer by one person&apos;s wicked deed. As killing one wicked person could help many people, the blade that kills people could become the sword that brings people to life.&quot;</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Many people can suffer by one person&apos;s wicked deed. As killing one wicked person could help many people, the blade that kills people could become the sword that brings people to life.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>「人をころす刀、却而人をいかすつるぎ也とは、夫れ亂れたる世には、故なき者多く死する也。亂れたる世を治めむ爲に、殺人刀を用ゐて、已に治まる時は、殺人刀即ち活人劔ならずや。こゝを以て名付くる所也。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;The reason why the blade that kills persons should become the sword that brings persons to life is because many people are killed without reason in the disordered society. If we use Setsuninto in order to calm the disordered society and the society becomes calm as the result, Setsuninto is exactly Katsuninken. That is the reason why I created these names.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;The reason why the blade that kills people should become the sword that brings people to life is because many people are killed without reason in a disordered society. If we use Setsuninto in order to calm the disordered society and the society becomes calm as the result, Setsuninto is exactly Katsuninken. That is the reason why I created these names.&quot;</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;The reason why the blade that kills people should become the sword that brings people to life is because many people are killed without reason in a disordered society. If we use Setsuninto in order to calm the disordered society and the society becomes calm as the result, Setsuninto is exactly Katsuninken. That is the reason why I created these names.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="63">
<j>仇なす悪に打ち勝って確実に殺すのが殺人刀であって、その悪を殺したゆえに万人が救われ「活きる」のが活人剣だと言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In brief, he says that Setsuninto means killing a wicked surely and Katsuninken means saving many people and &quot;bringing them to life&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In brief, he says that Setsuninto means definitively killing a wicked person and Katsuninken means saving many people and &quot;bringing them to life&quot;.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In brief, he says that Setsuninto means definitively killing a wicked person and Katsuninken means saving many people and &quot;bringing them to life&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>兵法、すなわち人を刀で切る行為にはこの両面がないとならないと諭し、日本の剣術が殺人技法にとどまらず昇華したことを示す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He admonished that the deed of killing a person with sword should have these two aspects, and it demonstrates the sublimation of Japanese Kenjutsu from the mere skill of killing a person.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He admonished that the deed of killing a person with a sword should have these two aspects, and it demonstrates the difference between Japanese Kenjutsu and the mere skill of killing a person.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He admonished that the deed of killing a person with a sword should have these two aspects, and it demonstrates the difference between Japanese Kenjutsu and the mere skill of killing a person.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>ここで、臨済宗の沢庵宗彭が柳生宗矩に「不動知神妙録」を与えたことにより江戸柳生で剣禅一致が説かれた結果として「刀法の尾張柳生」に対して「心法の江戸柳生」と言われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Soho TAKUAN of Rinzai Sect gave &quot;Fudo chishin myoroku&quot; to Munenori Yagyu and the term of Ken Zen Icchi (The Sword and Zen are One) was used by Edo-Yagyu, Edo-Yagyu was dubbed &quot;Edo-Yagyu of shinpo&quot; while Owari-Yagyu was dubbed &quot;Owari-Yagyu of toho (sword training)&quot;.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Soho TAKUAN of the Rinzai Sect gave &quot;Fudo chishin myoroku&quot; to Munenori Yagyu and the term of Ken Zen Icchi (The Sword and Zen are One) was used by Edo-Yagyu, Edo-Yagyu was dubbed &quot;Edo-Yagyu of shinpo&quot; while Owari-Yagyu was dubbed &quot;Owari-Yagyu of toho&quot; (sword training).</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Soho TAKUAN of the Rinzai Sect gave &quot;Fudo chishin myoroku&quot; to Munenori Yagyu and the term of Ken Zen Icchi (The Sword and Zen are One) was used by Edo-Yagyu, Edo-Yagyu was dubbed &quot;Edo-Yagyu of shinpo&quot; while Owari-Yagyu was dubbed &quot;Owari-Yagyu of toho&quot; (sword training).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>これは史実であり、禅の考え方が影響を与えたことは否定できない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the above historical fact, the influence of Zen&apos;s thought cannot be denied.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the above historical fact, the influence of Zen&apos;s thoughts cannot be denied.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the above historical fact, the influence of Zen&apos;s thoughts cannot be denied.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="67">
<j>なお現代の新陰流に伝わる、柳生宗厳の書に以下の記述がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the meantime, the following descriptions are seen in a book written by Muneyoshi YAGYU that has been inherited at Shinkage-ryu School.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, the following descriptions are seen in a book written by Muneyoshi YAGYU that has been inherited by the Shinkage-ryu School.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, the following descriptions are seen in a book written by Muneyoshi YAGYU that has been inherited by the Shinkage-ryu School.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>「当流に構える太刀を皆殺人刀という。構えのなき所をいずれも皆活人劔という。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;A sword that is being held in position is called Mina Setsuninto. A sword that is not being held in position is called Mina Katsuninken.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;A sword that is being held in position is called Mina Setsuninto. A sword that is not being held in position is called Mina Katsuninken.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;A sword that is being held in position is called Mina Setsuninto. A sword that is not being held in position is called Mina Katsuninken.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>「また構える太刀を殘らず裁断して除け、なき所を用いるので、其の生ずるにより活人劔という。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt>意味解釈が困難なため、訳出できず</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">「また構える太刀を殘らず裁断して除け、なき所を用いるので、其の生ずるにより活人劔という。」</e>
<cmt>意味解釈が困難なため、訳出できず</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="70">
<j>上記に挙げられている新陰流の刀法および兵法の武術的解釈では、活人剣と殺人剣という言葉に別の意味が存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The terms of Katsuninken and Setsuninken were used in a different sense in the above-mentioned interpretation made from the viewpoint of skills of Shinkage-ryu School.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The terms of Katsuninken and Setsuninken were used in a different sense in the above-mentioned interpretation made from the viewpoint of the skills of the Shinkage-ryu School.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From a martial art viewpoint on the toho (art of swords) and heiho (art of warfare) of the Shinkage-ryu School which was mentioned above, the terms of Katsuninken and Setsuninken have another meaning.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>新陰流には「転（まろばし）」と呼ばれる「相手の仕懸に対して転じて勝つ」根義がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A basic philosophy called &quot;Marobashi&quot;, which means &quot;winning by counterattacking&quot;, exists in Shinkage-ryu School.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A basic philosophy called &quot;Marobashi&quot;, which means &quot;winning by counterattacking&quot;, exists in the Shinkage-ryu School.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A basic philosophy called &quot;Marobashi&quot;, which means &quot;winning by taking advantage of an opponent&apos;s attack&quot;, exists in the Shinkage-ryu School.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>まず構えずに（新陰流ではこれを「無形の位」と呼ぶ）相手に仕掛けさせ、それに応じて「後の先」を取るわけである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It means waiting the opponent&apos;s move while not holding sword in position (it is called &quot;Mukei no kurai (neutral position) and taking &quot;go no sen&quot; (responsive initiative).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It means waiting for the opponent&apos;s move while not holding sword in position (it is called &quot;Mukei no kurai&quot; (neutral position) and taking &quot;go no sen&quot; (responsive initiative)).</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It means waiting for the opponent&apos;s move while not holding sword in position (it is called &quot;Mukei no kurai&quot; (neutral position) and taking &quot;go no sen&quot; (responsive initiative)).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>ここでの活人という言葉は「相手（すなわち人）が動く」という意味で用いられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the above, the term of katsunin was used in the sense of &quot;opponent&apos;s move&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the above, the term of katsunin was used to mean &quot;opponent&apos;s move&quot;.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the above, the term of katsunin was used to mean &quot;opponent&apos;s move&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>この場合の活人剣とは逆の意味で、自分から構えを取って斬り込むことを殺人剣と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the contrary, taking initiative while holding sword in position is called Setsuninken in this context.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the contrary, taking initiative while holding a sword in position is called Setsuninken in this context.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the contrary, taking initiative while holding a sword in position is called Setsuninken in this context.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>また「転」の根義により「浅く勝つ」こと、主に籠手へ小さく鋭く打ち込む斬撃が多用された（技法、魔の太刀、くねり打ち、一刀両段、西江水などにも見られるが、最も典型的な技法は「転打ち」である）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, based on the basic philosophy of &quot;Marobashi, skills for &quot;asaku katsu (literally win shallowly)&quot;, which means sharply striking on the forearm were often used in Shinkage-ryu Scool (including Ma no tachi, Kuneri uchi, Itto ryodan, Seiko sui and &quot;Marobashi uchi&quot;, the typical one).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, based on the basic philosophy of &quot;Marobashi&quot;, skills for &quot;asaku katsu&quot; (literally win shallowly), which means sharply striking on the forearm were often used in the Shinkage-ryu School (including Ma no tachi, Kuneri uchi, Itto ryodan, Seiko sui and &quot;Marobashi uchi&quot;, the typical one).</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, based on the basic philosophy of &quot;Marobashi&quot;, skills for &quot;asaku katsu&quot; (literally win shallowly), which means sharply striking on the forearm were often used in the Shinkage-ryu School (including Ma no tachi, Kuneri uchi, Itto ryodan, Seiko sui and &quot;Marobashi uchi&quot;, the typical one).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>結果として相手に致命傷を与えず勝つことも多く、その結果として「活人剣」と呼ばれることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, winning without delivering fatal wounds to an opponent became possible, and such skills came to be called &quot;Katsuninken&quot;.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, winning without delivering fatal wounds to an opponent became possible, and such skills came to be called &quot;Katsuninken&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, winning without delivering fatal wounds to an opponent became possible, and such skills came to be called &quot;Katsuninken&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>撓、竹刀と防具の発明</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Invention of shinai and protectors</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Invention of shinai and protectors</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Invention of shinai and protectors</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="77">
<j>古くから多くの流派で独自の袋竹刀（ひきはだ撓）や籠手を使用した稽古は行われていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Training using fukuro shinai (hikihada shinai) and kote (protector for the forearm) were adopted by schools from long ago.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Training using fukuro shinai (hikihada shinai) and kote (protector for the forearm) were adopted by schools from long ago.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Training using fukuro shinai (hikihada shinai) and kote (protector for the forearm) were adopted by schools from long ago.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>ただし多くの場合形稽古が中心であり、試合稽古は技が乱れる、理合の習得が出来ない等の理由によりあまり行われていなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, such training was introduced mainly in kata (a form) training, and it was seldom introduced in training matches on the ground that skills could be distorted by such training and that the learning of the skill of riai (taking a chance to hit) was impossible.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, such training was introduced mainly in kata (a form) training, and it was seldom introduced in training matches on the ground that skills could be distorted by such training and that the learning of the skill of riai (taking a chance to hit) was impossible.</e>
<cmt>Unsure of what &quot;distorted&quot; implies.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, these implements were used mainly in the performance of kata (a fixed sequence of moves) training, and were seldom employed in training matches on the grounds that skills could be eroded and that learning riai (the skill of being able to seize a chance to strike) was impossible.</e>
<cmt>skills could be distorted→ skills could be eroded</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>江戸時代中期～後期にかけて現在の剣道の防具と竹刀の原型が直心影流で発明され、続いて中西派一刀流（小野派一刀流）でも発明された防具と竹刀を採用した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the middle to late Edo period, the original model of shinai and protectors that are being used in contemporary Kendo was invented by Jikishinkage-ryu School, and Nakanishi-ha Itto-ryu School also invented and adopted its own protectors and shinai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the middle to late Edo period, the original model of shinai and protectors used in contemporary Kendo was invented by the Jikishinkage-ryu School, and the Nakanishi-ha Itto-ryu School also invented and adopted its own protectors and shinai.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the middle to late Edo period, the original model of shinai and protectors used in contemporary Kendo was invented by the Jikishinkage-ryu School, and the Nakanishi-ha Itto-ryu School also invented and adopted its own protectors and shinai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="80">
<j>その後急激に竹刀と防具着用の試合稽古が流行し、各流派で試合稽古が行われるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, training matches using shinai and protectors became rapidly popular, and various schools conducted such training matches.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, training matches using shinai and protectors became rapidly popular, and various schools conducted such training matches.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, training matches using shinai and protectors became rapidly popular, and various schools conducted such training matches.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>逆に尾張藩の新陰流や岩国藩・長州藩の片山伯耆流、弘前藩の當田流などといった、木刀や袋竹刀での形中心で防具着用の試合稽古を取り入れなかった流派には門弟の数に著しい増加はなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By contrast, substantial increase in the number of disciples was not seen in the schools that didn&apos;t introduce training matches using protectors while placing emphasis on kata training with wooden swords and fukuro shinai, such as Shinkage-ryu Scool in the Owari domain, Katayama-Hoki-ryu School in the Iwakuni and Choshu domain and Toda-ryu Scool in Hirosaki domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In contrast, a substantial increase in the number of disciples was not seen in the schools that didn&apos;t introduce training matches using protectors while instead placing emphasis on kata training with wooden swords and fukuro shinai, such as the Shinkage-ryu School in the Owari domain, the Katayama-Hoki-ryu School in the Iwakuni and Choshu domain and the Toda-ryu School in the Hirosaki domain.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In contrast, a substantial increase in the number of disciples was not seen in the schools that didn&apos;t introduce training matches using protectors while instead placing emphasis on kata training with wooden swords and fukuro shinai, such as the Shinkage-ryu School in the Owari domain, the Katayama-Hoki-ryu School in the Iwakuni and Choshu domain and the Toda-ryu School in the Hirosaki domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>また流祖以来試合を禁じていた流派が、やむなく試合稽古を行うようになった記録等も残っている（島津家中における示現流等の例外はある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are records stating that the schools which had prohibited doing matches since the time of their founder were forced to conduct training matches (except for Jigen-ryu School in Satsuma domain etc).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are records stating that the schools which had prohibited doing matches since the time of their founding were forced to conduct training matches (except for the Jigen-ryu School in the Satsuma domain etc).</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are records stating that the schools which had prohibited doing matches since the time of their founding were forced to conduct training matches (except for the Jigen-ryu School in the Satsuma domain etc).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>幕末</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The end of Edo period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The end of Edo period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The end of Edo period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="83">
<j>北辰一刀流剣術・神道無念流剣術・心形刀流・鏡心明智流・天然理心流剣術等、新興の試合稽古重視の流派が各地に誕生した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Schools which placed emphasis on training matches, such as Hokushin Itto-ryu Kenjutsu, Shinto Munen-ryu Kenjutsu, Shinkageto-ryu School, Kyoshin Meichi-ryu School and Tennen Rishin-ryu Kenjutsu, were born at various places.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Schools which placed emphasis on training matches, such as Hokushin Itto-ryu Kenjutsu, Shinto Munen-ryu Kenjutsu, Shinkageto-ryu School, Kyoshin Meichi-ryu School and Tennen Rishin-ryu Kenjutsu, were established in various places.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Schools which placed emphasis on training matches, such as Hokushin Itto-ryu Kenjutsu, Shinto Munen-ryu Kenjutsu, Shinkageto-ryu School, Kyoshin Meichi-ryu School and Tennen Rishin-ryu Kenjutsu, were established in various places.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="84">
<j>剣客を生んだ地域を見ると、剣術道場の多かった関東地方（関八州）や、倒幕運動に積極的な薩摩国・土佐国が知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanto region (Kan hasshu) where a lot of Kenjutsu dojo (hall used for swordplay training) were located and Satsuma/Tosa province which actively participated in the movement to overthrow the shogunate are known as the places from which many expert swordsmen hailed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanto region (Kan hasshu) where a lot of Kenjutsu dojo (hall used for swordplay training) were located and Satsuma/Tosa province which actively participated in the movement to overthrow the shogunate are known as the places from which many expert swordsmen hailed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanto region (Kan hasshu) where a lot of Kenjutsu dojo (hall used for swordplay training) were located and Satsuma/Tosa province which actively participated in the movement to overthrow the shogunate are known as the places from which many expert swordsmen hailed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>黒船襲来後の攘夷の高揚と国内の政争により新選組誕生した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the wake of the arrival of Black Ships (Perry&apos;s fleet), Shinsengumi (a group who guarded Kyoto during the end of Tokugawa Shogunate) was established in order to cope with the rise of the movement advocating for the expulsion of foreigners as well as political disturbance.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the wake of the arrival of the Black Ships (Perry&apos;s fleet), Shinsengumi (a group who guarded Kyoto during the end of Tokugawa Shogunate) was established in order to cope with the rise of the movement advocating for the expulsion of foreigners as well as political disturbance.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the wake of the arrival of the Black Ships (Perry&apos;s fleet), Shinsengumi (a group who guarded Kyoto during the end of Tokugawa Shogunate) was established in order to cope with the rise of the movement advocating for the expulsion of foreigners as well as political disturbance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>禁門の変・長州征伐・戊辰戦争などに関与し、明治維新に到るのであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was involved in the Kinmon Incident, the Choshu Conquest and the Boshin War, and the Meiji Restoration began.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were involved in the Kinmon Incident, the Choshu Conquest and the Boshin War, and the beginning of the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were involved in the Kinmon Incident, the Choshu Conquest and the Boshin War, and the beginning of the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>明治以降</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Meiji era</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Meiji era</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Meiji era</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="87">
<j>3月28日、廃刀令が公布され帯刀が禁止されるとともに、剣術は前時代のものという風潮が強まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wearing of swords was banned by Haitorei (decree banning the wearing of swords) proclaimed on March 28, and general atmosphere regarding Kenjutsu as the out-dated one became common.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wearing swords was banned by Haitorei (decree banning the wearing of swords) proclaimed on March 28th, and the general atmosphere regarding Kenjutsu as out-dated became common.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wearing swords was banned by Haitorei (decree banning the wearing of swords) proclaimed on March 28, 1876, and the general atmosphere regarding Kenjutsu as out-dated became common.</e>
<cmt>原文にも年は出ていませんが、唐突であり、wikipediaではでていたので1876を追加しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="88">
<j>しかし、、西南戦争での警視官（当時の警察官の呼称）によって編成された抜刀隊の活躍ゆえに、警視庁では警視流木太刀形が制定されるなど、剣術推奨の方針転換がなされ、剣術の復興の動きの端緒となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as Battotai (drawn sword quad) consisted of keishikan (policemen at the time) achieved distinguished military service in the Seinan War, policy of encouraging Kenjutsu was adopted, including the creation of Keishi-ryu katachi kata (attack and defend with wooden swords) by Tokyo Metropolitan Police Department, and it became the momentum for the restoration of Kenjutsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as Battotai (drawn sword squad) consisting of keishikan (policemen at the time) achieved distinguished military service in the Seinan War, a policy of encouraging Kenjutsu was adopted, including the creation of Keishi-ryu katachi kata (attack and defend with wooden swords) by Tokyo Metropolitan Police Department, and this became the momentum for the restoration of Kenjutsu.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as Battotai (drawn sword squad) consisting of keishikan (policemen at the time) achieved distinguished military service in the Seinan War, a policy of encouraging Kenjutsu was adopted, including the creation of Keishi-ryu katachi kata (attack and defend with wooden swords) by Tokyo Metropolitan Police Department, and this became the momentum for the restoration of Kenjutsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>後には巡査に対して必修となり、各警察署で指導のために剣術家が採用された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, Kenjutsu bacame a compulsory subject for policemen and all police stations recruited swordsmen as instructors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, Kenjutsu became a compulsory subject for policemen and all police stations recruited swordsmen as instructors.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, Kenjutsu became a compulsory subject for policemen and all police stations recruited swordsmen as instructors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="90">
<j>これは銃器の貫通・殺傷力向上や、後込め式小銃による火力の向上の結果として甲冑の意義が薄れ、歩兵は軽装となったがゆえに、かえって近接白兵戦の有効性が再認識されたためである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The context of the above was that the effectiveness of Kenjutsu in close combat was reconfirmed thanks to the situation where armor lost its significance due to the improvement of killing power of gun and solidiers came to fight lightly equipped.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The context of the above was that the effectiveness of Kenjutsu in close combat was reconfirmed due to situations where armor lost its significance due to the improved killing power of guns and soldiers coming to fights lightly equipped.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The context of the above was that the effectiveness of Kenjutsu in close combat was reconfirmed due to situations where armor lost its significance due to the improved killing power of guns and soldiers coming to fights lightly equipped.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>ただし大日本帝国陸軍では警察での剣術推奨の方針とは異なり、にフランス陸軍より教官を招聘し、日本の伝統的な剣術を廃してフェンシングを訓練させている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Unlike the policy of police, however, Japanese Imperial Army abolished Japanese traditional Kenjutsu and instead introduced fencing by inviting instructors from French Army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unlike the policy of police, however, the Japanese Imperial Army abolished Japanese traditional Kenjutsu and instead introduced fencing by inviting instructors from the French Army.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unlike the policy of police, however, the Japanese Imperial Army abolished Japanese traditional Kenjutsu and instead introduced fencing by inviting instructors from the French Army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>陸軍で日本式の剣術が復活するのは以降のことだった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese Kenjutsu revived in Army long afterward.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese Kenjutsu was revived in the Army long afterward.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese Kenjutsu was revived in the Army long afterward.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="93">
<j>またこのころ榊原鍵吉により撃剣興行が盛んにおこなわれ好評を博したが、後に廃れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gekiken kogyo (swordsmen&apos; show) by Kenkichi SAKAKIBARA was popular at that time, but it waned later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gekiken kogyo (swordsmen show) by Kenkichi SAKAKIBARA was popular at that time, but its popularity waned later.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gekiken kogyo (swordsmen show) by Kenkichi SAKAKIBARA was popular at that time, but its popularity waned later.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="94">
<j>明治末から大正にかけて、大日本武徳会が古武道を武道に、剣術を剣道に名称を変え、旧制中学校で剣道を教えたため剣道が一般にひろまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kendo spread among ordinary people during the period from the end of Meiji era to Taisho era because Dainihon butoku kai changed the names of Kobudo and Kenjutsu to Budo (martial arts) and Kendo respectively and began to instruct Kendo at junior high schools under the old education system.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kendo spread among ordinary people during the period from the end of Meiji era to the Taisho era because Dainihon butoku kai changed the names of Kobudo and Kenjutsu to Budo (martial arts) and Kendo respectively and began to instruct Kendo at junior high schools under the old education system.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kendo spread among ordinary people during the period from the end of Meiji era to the Taisho era because Dainihon butoku kai changed the names of Kobudo and Kenjutsu to Budo (martial arts) and Kendo respectively and began to instruct Kendo at junior high schools under the old education system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>この頃は剣道と伝統的な剣術との違いが余り認識されておらず、積極的に剣道の試合に出る流派も少なくなかった（明治末～戦前期の文献では、現在一般にいうところの剣道を含めた日本剣術全般を「剣道」と称することが多い）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around that time, the difference between Kendo and traditional Kenjutsu was not well acknowledged and not a few schools actively participated in Kendo matches (Japanese Kenjutsu in general, including contemporary Kendo, was collectively called &quot;Kendo&quot; in the documents written from the end of Meiji era to the end of World War Ⅱ).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around that time, the difference between Kendo and traditional Kenjutsu was not well acknowledged and many schools actively participated in Kendo matches (Japanese Kenjutsu in general, including contemporary Kendo, was collectively called &quot;Kendo&quot; in the documents written from the end of Meiji era to the end of World War Ⅱ).</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around that time, the difference between Kendo and traditional Kenjutsu was not well acknowledged and many schools actively participated in Kendo matches (Japanese Kenjutsu in general, including contemporary Kendo, was collectively called &quot;Kendo&quot; in the documents written from the end of Meiji era to the end of World War Ⅱ).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>当時としてはむしろ、一般に普及した剣道を、「剣術（剣道）の一流派」と認識していたのかもしれない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It seems that Kendo, which was popular among ordinary people, was regarded as &quot;one of schools of Kenjutsu (Kendo)&quot; at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It seems that Kendo, which was popular among ordinary people, was regarded as &quot;one of the schools of Kenjutsu (Kendo)&quot; at that time.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It seems that Kendo, which was popular among ordinary people, was regarded as &quot;one of the schools of Kenjutsu (Kendo)&quot; at that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>実際、「武徳会流」という呼ばれ方をすることもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In fact, Kendo was sometimes called &quot;Butokukai-ryu School&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In fact, Kendo was sometimes called &quot;Butokukai-ryu School&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact, Kendo was sometimes called &quot;Butokukai-ryu School&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>また、現在の剣道とは異なり、足払いや投げ技や抑え込んでの防具の面の剥ぎ取りも有効であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Unlike contemporary Kendo, the skills of ashibarai (foot sweep), nagewaza (throwing technique) and taking off face protector by holding down an opponent were allowed to use.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unlike contemporary Kendo, the skills of ashibarai (foot sweep), nagewaza (throwing technique) and taking off the face protector by holding down an opponent were allowed to be used.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unlike contemporary Kendo, the skills of ashibarai (foot sweep), nagewaza (throwing technique) and taking off the face protector by holding down an opponent were allowed to be used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="99">
<j>太平洋戦争での敗戦後、連合国軍最高司令官総司令部により武道（武術）が禁止された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Japan was defeated in the Pacific War, Budo (Bujutsu) was banned by General Headquarters (GHQ).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Japan was defeated in the Pacific War, Budo (Bujutsu) was banned by General Headquarters (GHQ).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Japan was defeated in the Pacific War, Budo (Bujutsu) was banned by General Headquarters (GHQ).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>剣道も「しない競技」と名前を変え競技性をより重視するようになり、伝統的な剣術との違いが大きくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kendo was renamed &quot;shinai game&quot;, its nature changed to a kind of sports and the difference from traditional Kenjutsu became bigger.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kendo was renamed &quot;shinai game&quot;, its nature changed to a kind of sport and the difference from traditional Kenjutsu grew larger.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kendo was renamed &quot;shinai game&quot;, its nature changed to a kind of sport and the difference from traditional Kenjutsu grew larger.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>このような状況下で剣術を稽古する者は少なくなり、武道禁止解禁後も剣術は各流派道場でのみ行なわれるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the number of people who learn Kenjutsu decreased under such circumstances, Kenjutsu trainig was conducted only at training halls of schools even after the ban of Budo was lifted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the number of people who learn Kenjutsu decreased under such circumstances, Kenjutsu training was conducted only at training halls of schools even after the ban of Budo was lifted.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the number of people who learn Kenjutsu decreased under such circumstances, Kenjutsu training was conducted only at training halls of schools even after the ban of Budo was lifted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="102">
<j>なお、小野派一刀流や直心影流剣術など、剣道と併習する者が比較的多い流派もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are some schools, such as Onoha Itto-ryu School and Jikishinkage-ryu Kenjutsu, at which not a few people learn both Kenjutsu and Kendo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are some schools, such as the Onoha Itto-ryu School and the Jikishinkage-ryu Kenjutsu, at which a comparatively large number of people learn both Kenjutsu and Kendo.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are some schools, such as the Onoha Itto-ryu School and theJikishinkage-ryu Kenjutsu, at which a comparatively large number of people learn both Kenjutsu and Kendo.</e>
<cmt>スペース調整</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>また、中山博道・羽賀準一の流れを汲む一剣会羽賀道場や日本剣道協会では、戦前のままの足払いや投げ技も有効な稽古を行っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ikkenkai Haga dojo and Nihon Kendo Kyokai, both are descended from Hiromichi NAKAYAMA and Junichi HAGA, are using ashibarai and nagewaza in training as they did in the prewar period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ikkenkai Haga dojo and Nihon Kendo Kyokai, both descended from Hiromichi NAKAYAMA and Junichi HAGA, are still using ashibarai and nagewaza in training as they did in the prewar period.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ikkenkai Haga dojo and Nihon Kendo Kyokai, both descended from Hiromichi NAKAYAMA and Junichi HAGA, are still using ashibarai and nagewaza in training as they did in the prewar period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 TT(id:46431), ドラムスコ(id:40234), Suguri F(id:11127), ロナルド(id:9943), Iaidou(id:47964), Rai koku(id:1661), Mintleaf(id:2216), Corvo(id:124656), Yakouhai(id:25799), SpBot(id:209743), Plume(id:28701), DisposableLove(id:66668), さららゆら(id:12274), Rei-bot(id:94097), 盛風力(id:54988), BotMultichill(id:132395), 夜天光(id:61243), 踏蹟(id:51201), Bit(id:2197), 竹麦魚(id:11012), Yas(id:739), FlaBot(id:30804), もんもん(id:133692), Izayohi(id:13095), みっち(id:10251), Swordarts(id:54566), Jbot(id:181157), Himazin(id:22034), WikiReader(id:44945), Yaky(id:22711), Edoo(id:59461), Tukushiko(id:216497), Mt3(id:118081), Dale(id:108779), 聖徒(id:176332), SilvonenBot(id:190970), Phew(id:74086), SuisuiBot(id:10165), FeZn(id:444), 麗葵(id:91029), Arakawa15(id:202761), Rislimric(id:54531), ＮｉＫｅ(id:7512), Chlewbot(id:33904), 福太郎(id:132415), Hakusai(id:58284), NDR(id:5500), Louperibot(id:128971), Tossie(id:140239), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>