<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>文車妖妃</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fuguruma-yobi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fuguruma-yobi</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fuguruma-yobi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>文車妖妃（ふぐるまようび）は、鳥山石燕の妖怪画集『百器徒然袋』にある日本の妖怪。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fuguruma-yobi is a Japanese apparition which appears in &quot;Hyakki Tsurezure Bukuro&quot;, a collection of paintings of apparition drawn by Sekien TORIYAMA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Fuguruma-yobi&quot; is a Japanese specter which appears in &quot;Hyakki Tsurezure Bukuro&quot;(The Bag of One Hundred Random Demons), a collection of paintings of specters drawn by Sekien TORIYAMA.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Fuguruma-yobi&quot; is a Japanese specter which appears in &quot;Hyakki Tsurezure Bukuro&quot;(The Bag of One Hundred Random Demons), a collection of paintings of specters drawn by Sekien TORIYAMA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>文車（ふぐるま）とは、内裏や寺などで本を運ぶための箱車で、失火などの非常時に備えるもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fuguruma means a box cart which was used at the imperial palace or temples for carrying books in the event of emergency like an accidental fire.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Fuguruma&quot; means a box cart which was used at the imperial palace or temples for carrying books in the event of emergency like an accidental fire.</e>
<cmt>Fuguruma にダブルコーテーションを追記しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Fuguruma&quot; means a box cart which was used at the imperial palace or temples for carrying books in the event of emergency like an accidental fire.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>これが付喪神になったものが文車妖妃である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The above box cart was called fuguruma after it became tsukumogami (the spirits of discarded object).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The above box cart was called fuguruma after it became tsukumogami (the spirits of discarded object).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The above box cart was called fuguruma after it became tsukumogami (the spirits of discarded object).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>江戸時代の怪談集『諸国百物語』には、ある寺の稚児が恋文を受け取り、それを捨てていたところ、恋文に込められた執念が鬼と化して人を襲ったという話がある.</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A tale is seen in &quot;Shokoku Hyaku Monogatari&quot;, a collection of ghost stories compiled in the Edo period, saying that a chigo (temple acolyte) received a love letter and threw away it and that the spirit of love letter became an ogre and attacked people.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A story in &quot;Shokoku Hyaku Monogatari&quot; (One Hundred Tales from Various Provinces), a collection of ghost stories compiled in the Edo period, tells that when a chigo (temple acolyte) received a love letter and threw it away, the spirit of love letter became an ogre and attacked people.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A story in &quot;Shokoku Hyaku Monogatari&quot; (One Hundred Tales from Various Provinces), a collection of ghost stories compiled in the Edo period, tells that when a chigo (temple acolyte) received a love letter and threw it away, the feeling of obsession that the writer conveyed in the letter caused an ogre to appear and attack people.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>同様に手紙の執念が妖怪化したものが文車妖妃ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As seen from the above, the spirit of letter that has become an apparition was also called Fuguruma-yobi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As seen from the above, the spirit of letter that has become a specter is also called &quot;Fuguruma-yobi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>an apparition was also called Fuguruma-yobi. を a specter is called &quot;Fuguruma-yobi.&quot; に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As seen from the above, the spirit of letter that has become a specter is also called &quot;Fuguruma-yobi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>『百器徒然袋』には、壊れた文車から子鬼が出て来たり、それを持っていて恨んでいる顔をした女性として描かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Hyakki Tsurezure Bukuro&quot;, it was depicted as a baby ogre which appeared from a broken fuguruma or a woman who held it with an expression of grudge.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;Hyakki Tsurezure Bukuro,&quot; it was depicted as a baby ogre which appeared from a broken fuguruma or a woman who held it with an expression of grudge.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Hyakki Tsurezure Bukuro&quot;, を&quot;Hyakki Tsurezure Bukuro,&quot; に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;Hyakki Tsurezure Bukuro,&quot; it was depicted as a baby ogre which appeared from a broken fuguruma or a woman who held it with an expression of grudge.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>また、石燕は『百器徒然袋』の妖怪の題材の多くに『徒然草』などの文章を使用している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sekien used sentences of &quot;Tsurezuregusa&quot; etc. in creating apparitions drawn in &quot;Hyakki Tsurezure Bukuro&quot;.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sekien cited the sentences from &quot;Tsurezuregusa&quot;(Essays in Idleness) and so on in creating the specters drawn in &quot;Hyakki Tsurezure Bukuro.&quot;</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sekien cited the sentences from &quot;Tsurezuregusa&quot;(Essays in Idleness) and so on in creating the specters drawn in &quot;Hyakki Tsurezure Bukuro.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>『徒然草』第72段に「多くて見苦しからぬは、文車の文、塵塚の塵」という一文があり、この「文車の文」から文車妖妃、「塵塚の塵」から塵塚怪王が創作されたとの説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a sentence &quot; fuguruma no fumi (文車の文 : books on a book cart) and chirizuka no chiri (塵塚の塵 : the rubbish at dust heap) are not unsightly even though there are many or there is much&quot; is seen in the chapter 72 of &quot;Tsurezuregusa&quot;, some people say that fuguruma-yobi (文車妖妃) and chirizuka-kaio (塵塚怪王) were created based on the above-mentioned &quot;文車の文&quot; and &quot;塵塚の塵 &quot; respectively.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a sentence &apos;fuguruma no fumi (books on a book cart) and chirizuka no chiri (the rubbish at dust heap) are not unsightly even though there are many or there is much&apos; is seen in the chapter 72 of &quot;Tsurezuregusa,&quot; some people say that fuguruma-yobi and chirizuka-kaio (the ghost king of the waste) were created based on the above-mentioned &apos;fuguruma no fumi&apos; and &apos;chirizuka no chiri&apos; respectively.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a sentence &apos;fuguruma no fumi (books on a book cart) and chirizuka no chiri (the rubbish at dust heap) are not unsightly even though there are many or there is much&apos; is seen in the chapter 72 of &quot;Tsurezuregusa,&quot; some people say that fuguruma-yobi and chirizuka-kaio (the ghost king of the waste) were created based on the above-mentioned &apos;fuguruma no fumi&apos; and &apos;chirizuka no chiri&apos; respectively.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 逃亡者(id:14864), BitBucket(id:30999), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>