<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>的屋</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tekiya</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tekiya</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tekiya</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>的屋（てきや）とは、祭礼（祭り）や市や縁日などが催される、境内、参道や門前町において屋台や露天で出店して食品や玩具等を売る小売商を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tekiya (a street vendor or peddler at local festivals in and around the precincts of shrines and temples) refer to small businesses that bring out street stall to sell food or toys at the precincts or a road to a shrine and a cathedral towns during rites and festivals, market, or fairs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tekiya are merchants who sell items such as food or toys from street stalls set up in shrines, on the approach to shrines or in temple towns during festivals and markets.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tekiya are merchants who sell items such as food or toys on the street or stalls set up in the ground of shrines or temples, on the approach to them or in temple towns during festivals, markets, and fairs.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ。補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>または、射幸心を伴う遊技（ゲーム）として射的やくじ引などを提供する街商（がいしょう）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are gaisho (stallholder) that provides shooting and lottery as a recreational means.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It also refers to stallholders who provide gambling activities such as shooting or a lottery.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It also refers to stallholders who provide gambling activities such as shooting or a lottery as game.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>または、大道芸にて客寄せをし商品を売ったり芸そのものを生業にする大道商人（だいどうしょうにん）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are also street vendors that use performances to gather customers to sell goods or charge the street performance itself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are also peddlars who use performances to attract customers, then selling goods or charging for the street performance itself.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, it refers to peddlers who use performances to attract customers, then selling goods or charging for the street performance itself.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>呼称</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Official name</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Names</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Names</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>職業神として元々は中華文明圏より伝わり、神道の神となった「神農の神」を祀り、独特の隠語を用いる者が多いため、狭い世界では神農（しんのう）とも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinno&apos; came from China as the business deity and began to be called as &quot;Shinno,&quot; which was a code used often within a closed society.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinno&apos;, the name of a Shinto deity derived from Shennong, the Chinese god of business, was often used as a code word and came to mean tekiya within certain circles.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As they worshipped &apos;Shinno no kami&apos; (Shennong God) which was originally introduced as the god of business from Chinese Civilization to be a Shinto deity, and often used own code words, tekiya are called Shinno within certain circles.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>的屋（まとや）、香具師（やし）、三寸（さんずん）とも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called as matoya (stall-keeper), yashi (a street stall vendor at shrines and temples), and sanzun (a street stall vendor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are also known as matoya, yashi, and sanzun.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are also known as matoya, yashi, and sanzun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>一般には馴染みが薄いと思われるが近年までは、よく使われた通り名であり、的屋（てきや）、香具師、三寸は辞書では、同じ説明がなされている場合が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term may seem unfamiliar at first, but it was a commonly used alias and dictionaries referred to tekiya, yashi, and sanzun with same definitions until recently.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although even most Japanese may be unfamiliar with these terms, until recently they were often used as synonyms and dictionaries used the same definitions for tekiya, yashi, and sanzun.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although even most Japanese may be unfamiliar with these terms, until recently they were often used as synonyms and dictionaries used the same definitions for tekiya, yashi, and sanzun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>祭礼や寺社との関わり</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Relationship with the Rites, Festivals, Shrines and Temples</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Relationship with Festivals, Shrines and Temples</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Relationship with Festivals, Shrines and Temples</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>上記の「祭礼（祭り）や市や縁日などが催される、境内、参道や門前町」を庭場という。（以下庭場と記述）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The niwaba (precincts or approaches where festivals and fairs are held) refers to &apos;temple or shrine precinct and path and castle towns where festivals, fairs, and markets&apos; were held (Following is the article about niwaba).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &apos;shrines...approach to shrines or...temple towns during festivals and markets&apos; mentioned above are known as &quot;niwaba&quot; (literally meaning &apos;garden&apos; and described below).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ground of shrines or temples, on the approach to them or in temple towns during festivals, markets, and fairs&apos; mentioned above are known as niwaba (literally meaning &apos;yard&apos; and described &apos;niwaba&apos; hereinafter).</e>
<cmt>表現を合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>その庭場において御利益品や縁起物を売を打つ（売る）商売人である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are merchants who sell profitable or charms at niwaba.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tekiya are merchants who sell blessed items or lucky charms at niwaba.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tekiya are merchants who sell blessed items or lucky charms at niwaba.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>商売人といっても、祭礼時などは町鳶、町大工などの冠婚葬祭の互助活動と同じで、いわゆる寺社普請と呼ばれる相互扶助の一環でもあり、支払われるお金も代金ではなく祝儀不祝儀であるともいえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although they were referred as merchants, it was similar to a mutual aid of ceremonial occasions and called as jisha fushin (Buddhist practitioners making effort for construction of temples and shrines) and money was not paid but returned with gratuity and condolence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although they are referred to as merchants, they are similar to the cooperatives formed for ceremonial occasions and are part of the mutual assistance known as jisha fushin (parishoners making efforts for the construction of temples and shrines) and as such, were not paid but rarher given money as a gift.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although they are referred to as merchants, they are similar to the cooperatives formed for ceremonial occasions such as scaffolding men or carpenters, and are part of the mutual assistance known as jisha fushin (to making efforts for the construction of temples and shrines), were not paid but rather given money as a gift.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ。補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>同時に寺社などとの取り交わしによって、縁起物を売る時は神の依り代になるともいえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time, it was considered to be the yorishiro (object representative of a divine spirit) of deity when charms were sold by temples and shrines.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the same time, through their dealings with temples and shrines, they were considered to be yorishiro (objects representative of a divine spirit) when selling lucky charms.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the same time, through their dealings with temples and shrines, they were considered to be yorishiro (objects representative of a divine spirit) when selling lucky charms.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="14">
<j>的屋は「露天商及び行商人」の一種であり、伝統的な文化を地域と共有している存在である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tekiya was a type of &quot;outdoor stall and a peddler&quot; and is an existence that shared traditions with the local regions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tekiya are a type of &quot;stallholder and peddler&quot; and are a part of an area&apos;s traditional culture.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tekiya are a type of &apos;stallholder and peddler&apos; and are a part of an area&apos;s traditional culture.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>しかし的屋は価格に見合った品質の商品を提供するというよりも、祭りの非日常（ハレとケ）を演出し、それを附加価値として商売にしている性格が強い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, it has a strong characteristic of providing the item of same value as the price, and used to show hare and ke (sacred-profane dichotomy) of festivals as additional value to have a business.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in addition to selling goods for what they are worth, a major characteristic of tekiya is that they have the added value of providing part of the &apos;specialness&apos; (the &apos;hare&apos;, or extraordinary, and &apos;ke&apos;, or ordinary) of festivals.</e>
<cmt>*Revised for clarity - although the Japanese has （ハレとケ） the very word before that surely means that they are only ハレ. However, translated it as in the original</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in addition to selling goods for what they are worth, a major characteristic of tekiya is that they have the added value of providing part of the specialness (the &apos;hare&apos; [extraordinary] and &apos;ke&apos; [ordinary]) of festivals.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="16">
<j>的屋はいわゆる現在の路上などで行う素人や時代的背景のないパフォーマーとは異なる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tekiya differed from current street performers that are beginners or without any cultural aspect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tekiya differ from current street performers, who are amateurs or without any cultural aspect.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tekiya differ from current street performers, who are amateurs or without any cultural aspect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>路上において人間を集めるための演芸は、パフォーマー（演歌師・壮士）とは区別されるべきである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Street performance that gather customers should be distinguished from other performers (Enka-shi (street performer of Enka (Japanese ballad) songs) and political activist).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Street performance to attract customers should be distinguished from other performers (buskers singing enka, a genre of Japanese pop music, and political activist).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Their street performance to attract customers should be distinguished from other performers (buskers singing enka [a genre of Japanese pop music] and political activist).</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>観客においても祭りというハレとケの場の非日常的な雰囲気を感じるか感じないかの違いがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was a difference in the experience of unusual atmosphere of hare and ke of festivals for watchers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The difference depends on whether the watchers feel the special atmosphere of the festival, which is a place of hare and ke, or not.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The difference depends on whether the watchers feel the special atmosphere of the festival, which is a place of hare and ke, or not.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="19">
<j>様々な成り立ち</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Different Styles</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Various Origins</e>
<cmt>Revised for accuracy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Various Origins</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>日本は古来から様々な職業において「組」と言う徒弟制度や雇用関係があり、的屋も噛み砕いて表現すれば、親分子分（親方子方・兄弟分・兄弟弟子）の関係を基盤とする企業や互助団体、その構成する人々でもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The tekiya was in a nutshell, the &apos;kumi&apos; (group) composed of business groups, mutual aid society, and members who had apprentice system (boss and apprentice, foster brothers, brother apprentice), and kumi existed for various businesses in Japan from long ago.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan has, since ancient, times had groups called &quot;kumi&quot; that offer employment or apprenticeships in various fields and, simply put, tekiya are businesses and mutual aid societies (as well as the people who found them) based on the traditional Japanese mentor-apprentice system.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan, since ancient times, has groups called &apos;kumi&apos; that offer employment or apprenticeships in various fields and, simply put, tekiya are businesses and mutual aid societies (as well as the people who found them) based on the traditional Japanese mentor-apprentice system (also referred as the relationship of Oyabun-kobun, Oyakata kokata [father-son], Kyodaibun [brother-brother], kyodai deshi [fellow pupil]).</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>的屋は零細資本の小売商または彼らに雇用されているプロレタリアートの団体というイメージがあるが、これに該当しない地域密着型や個人経営や兼業の的屋も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tekiya has an image of a group of proletarians hired by small profit business, but there were many tekiya of local or individually own additional business.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The image of tekiya is of retailers with little capital or of the working class groups hired by them but, in fact, many tekiya are community based, privately managed or run as a secondary business.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The image of tekiya is of retailers with little capital or of the working class groups hired by them but, in fact, many tekiya are community based, privately managed or run as a secondary business.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>地勢的・歴史的・人的・資本的要素が複雑に絡み合っていることから、単に的屋として一括りに定義することは難しいが、的屋の源流とされるもは以下の五つものに分類される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is hard to define it simply as a tekiya since there was a complex relationship between the local power, history, people, and financial aspects, but following five were believed to be the origin of tekiya.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is hard to define simply tekiya as a whole due the complex relationship between geography, history, people, and finance, but the origins of tekiya can be found in the following five categories.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is hard to define simply tekiya as a whole due the complex relationship between geography, history, people, and finance, but the origins of tekiya can be found in the following five categories.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="23">
<j>猿楽</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sarugaku (comical mimicry and speech performance in Heian period)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sarugaku</e>
<cmt>*Explained in the next sentence, so explanation not needed here</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sarugaku (form of theatre popular in Japan during the 11th to 14th centuries)</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>- 奇術・手品・曲芸・軽業・祈祷・占いなどを大道芸として行いながら,旅回りをしていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It went on a tour of various areas while performing magic shows, musical performances, acrobatics, prayers, and fortune telling as a street performance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Street performers who traveled around performing magic shows, acrobatics, prayers, and fortune telling.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Street performers who traveled around performing juggleries, magic shows, acrobatics, prayers, and fortune telling.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>香具師が漢方由来の薬を扱っていたように、猿楽も中華文明を起源とするものも多いが、太刀まわりや一人相撲など日本古来の芸も数多く存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many sarugaku originated from Chinese culture as yashi have handled Chinese herbal medicines, but many performances such as sword dance and one person sumo derived from Japanese performances that existed from ancient times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Like the yashi medicine sellers who had their origins in Chinese medicine, many sarugaku performances also had their beginnings in Chinese culture but many, such as the sword dance or solo sumo, were derived from Japanese performances that had existed from ancient times.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Like the yashi (a street stall vendor at shrines and temples) sold medicine derived from Chinese medicine, many sarugaku performances also had their beginnings in Chinese culture but many, such as the sword dance or solo sumo, were derived from Japanese performances that had existed from ancient times.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="26">
<j>蓮の葉商い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Trade of Lotus Leaves (Dealing with Seasonal Items)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Lotus Leaf Trade (Dealing with Seasonal Items)</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Lotus Leaf Trade (Dealing with Seasonal Items)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>- 時節や年中行事に必要な縁起物である木の実や葉っぱや野菜、魚（地域によっては普段は禁じられていた獣肉など）などのいわゆる、季節物・消え物（きえもの）を市や縁日で販売していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They sold tree fruits, vegetables, fish (depending on the district, it sold hunted animal meat banned in normal occasions), seasonal and use-once only objects for markets or on festival day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This term was used to refer the selling of seasonal items or items that would only be used once such as nuts, berries, vegetables, fish (and, depending on the district, meat, which was normally banned) at markets or festivals.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This term was used to refer the selling of lucky charms required for times or annual events, what is called, seasonal items or items that would only be used once such as nuts, berries, vegetables, fish (and, depending on the district, meat, which was normally banned) at markets or festivals.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ。補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="28">
<j>郊外においては、蓮の葉商いのそのまま形で、地域に根ざした人々が、祭りなどで先祖代々に渡り、季節の縁起物を販売している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In districts, Trade of Lotus Leaves were held as it is and local people sold seasonal good luck charms during festivals for many generations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the suburbs, the lotus leaf trade continues, with local people having sold seasonal items as lucky charms for generations.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the suburbs, the lotus leaf trade continues as it is, with local people having sold seasonal items as lucky charms for generations at festivals and so on.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ。補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>具体的には、農家でありながら、縁日や市の立つ日や祭り時には、福飴や餅などを製造し販売していて、それが何代にも継承されている事があげられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To put it in a nutshell, famers made and sold good luck candies and sticky rice during festivals, markets, and fairs and passed down the business over several generations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">More specifically, farmers make and sell good luck candies and sticky rice cakes during festivals, markets, and fairs, having passed down the business over several generations.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">More specifically, farmers make and sell good luck candies and sticky rice cakes during festivals, markets, and fairs, having passed down the business over several generations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="30">
<j>香具師</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yashi (a street stall vendor at shrines and temples)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yashi</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yashi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>- 芸や見世物を用いて客寄せをし、薬や香の製造販売・歯の医療行為をする者。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are people that gather customers with performances or goods on display and does medical services such as producing and selling medicines and incense.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yashi are people who attract customers with performances or shows and who make medicines and incense, as well as providing dental services.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yashi are people who attract customers with performances or shows and who make medicines and incense, as well as providing dental services.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>野士・野師・弥四とも表記し、すべて「やし」と読む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were also written to as &apos;Yashi&apos; (written as 野士, 野師, or 弥四).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Usually written with chacters meaning &quot;perfume practitioner&quot;, it can also be written with chacters that mean &quot;wild practitioner&quot; or with the the characters used in the name &quot;Yashiro&quot;.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was written 香具師 (literally, perfume practitioner) with Chinese characters and also 野士 (mountain priest), 野師 (wild practitioner), 弥四 (part of man&apos;s name &apos;Yashiro&apos;), however all of them are pronounced as &apos;yashi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ。補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>野武士が困窮して薬売りに身を投じたという説や弥四郎という者が薬の行商の祖と言われる事など諸説ある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were various theories concerning the origin of yashi, such as stray samurai, who faced a hardship switched to selling medicines, or the person named Yashiro was the founder of pharmacy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are several theories concerning the origins of yashi, including that they were masterless samurai who switched to selling medicines to avoid poverty, or that they were named after a medicine seller called Yashiro.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are several theories concerning the origins of yashi, including that they were mountain priest who switched to selling medicines to avoid poverty, or that they were named after a medicine seller called Yashiro.</e>
<cmt>用語訳を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="34">
<j>鳶職や植木職</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tobishoku (a scaffolding man) and Gardener</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Scaffolders and Gardeners</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Scaffolders and Gardeners</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>- 都市部においては、天下普請の施行により、鳶職や植木職などの建設に係わる者が、町場の相互関係の中で特別な義務と権限（町火消しなど）を持つようになり、特定の縁起物（熊手、朝顔）や売り上げが確実に見込める物（正月のお飾り）の販売を独占する傾向にあり、現在でもその不文律が継承されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By the tenka fushin (nation wide constructions), people with tobishoku and gardener positions that dealt with carpentry, had the special duties and rights (firefighter) under an unwritten law that continues even today and has the tendency to monopolize the market for selling special good luck charms (rake or morning glory) or those that are going to definitely sell (new year decorations).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the policy of nationwide construction carried out by the Edo Shogunate, people connected to construction, such as scaffolders and gardeners, were given special duties and rights (such as acting as firefighters) under an unwritten law that continues even today and tended to monopolize the market for special good luck charms (rakes or morning glories) or items that would definitely sell (for example, New Year decorations).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the urban site, with the policy of tenka fushin (nation wide constructions carried out by Tokugawa shogunate), people connected to construction, such as scaffolders and gardeners, were given special duties and rights (such as acting as firefighters) in the town&apos;s correlation and tended to monopolize the market for special good luck charms (rakes or morning glories) or items that would definitely sell (for example, New Year decorations); this unwritten law continues even today.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="36">
<j>弓矢（まとや）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Matoya (Archery)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Matoya (Archery)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Matoya (Archery)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>- 弓矢を使った射的遊技場を営むものであるが、「吹き矢」を使った回転版を的とする射的や「ぶん回し」と呼ばれるルーレットも江戸時代から存在していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were shooting games that used archery, but there were &apos;blow guns&apos; with rotating target and roulette called &apos;bunmawashi&apos; (turn it with force) that existed from Edo Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These were games where people shot arrows at targets, and from the Edo Period (1603-1868) also include shooting at a rotating target with &apos;blow guns&apos; and a kind of roulette called &apos;bunmawashi&apos;.</e>
<cmt>*I think bunmawashi was the name of the game that involved shooting at a target with a blow gun, not a separate game, but I&apos;ve left it as in the original</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These were games where people shot arrows at targets, and from the Edo Period (1603-1868) also include shooting at a rotating target with &apos;blow guns&apos; and a kind of roulette called &apos;bunmawashi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>これら射的やくじ引きなどの懸け物（景品交換の賭け事）を生業にする者。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These were people who had the gambling (gambling that involved barter) business for living such as shooting and selling raffles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It also refers to the people who made a living from the bets (gambling for gifts) from these games.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It also refers to the people who made a living from the bets (gambling for gifts) from these games.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>社会的文化的認知</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Social and Culture Understanding</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Social and Cultural Perceptions</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Social and Cultural Perceptions</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="39">
<j>小沢昭一などの文化人は的屋の啖呵を“昭和の風物”として文献や音源に残している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Men of culture such as Shoichi OZAWA mentioned selling cries of tekiya as &quot;representations of the Showa Period&quot; and left it in his writing and music.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Intellectuals such as Shoichi OZAWA have described the selling cries of tekiya as &quot;a signature of the Showa Period&quot; and wrote about them in his books and music.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Intellectuals such as Shoichi OZAWA have described the selling cries of tekiya as &quot;a signature of the Showa Period&quot; and wrote about them in his books and sound source.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="40">
<j>映画「男はつらいよ」の主人公の「フーテンの寅こと車寅次郎」の生業として知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was known as the main job of Torajiro Kuruma of &quot;Fuuten no Tora koto Kuruma Torajiro&quot; (フーテンの寅こと車寅次郎), who was the main character of the film, &quot;Otoko wa Tsuraiyo&quot; (It is Tough Being a Man).</e>
<cmt>フーテンの寅こと車寅次郎[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was the occupation of the &apos;wandering&apos; Torajiro Kuruma, the main character of the &quot;Otoko wa Tsurai yo&quot; (It is Tough Being a Man) films.</e>
<cmt>*&quot;フーテンの寅&quot; was the name of the 3rd film in the series but it&apos;s hard to fit it into an English sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was the occupation of the &apos;wandering tora,&apos; Torajiro KURUMA, the main character of the &apos;Otoko wa Tsurai yo&apos; (It is Tough Being a Man) films.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="41">
<j>「寺社などの神託」とは具体的には寺社普請といい、現在でも残っているが、特に明治以前の人々の暮らしは政（まつりごとが自治権として地域で認められていた）の中心として寺や神社があり、定期的な修繕や社会基盤としての拡張や一新を図るに当たり莫大な費用が必要であり、その一環として寄付を直接募るよりは、祭りを開催し的屋を招き地域住民に参加してもらい、非日常（ハレ）を演出する事で的屋から場所代として売り上げの一部を普請の資金とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;The oracle of temples or shrines&apos; was commonly called as jisha fushin and still remains today, but the pre-Meiji Period society (festivals were accepted in local districts as the self-government body) that centered around temples and shrines and was able to gather funds needed for repairmen or expansion of the district planning not by donations, but inviting tekiya for the locals to participate during festivals to create unusual atmosphere (hare) and made tekiya to contribute part of the profit as its rent for fushin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The requests of temples or shrines&apos; was basically jisha fushin and still exists today, but in pre-Meiji Period society (1868-1912) local government was fairly autonomous, revolving around temples and shrines and since repairs, improving infrastructure and planning renovations needed large amounts of money, the funds were raised not through donations, but by holding festivals, inviting tekiya and getting the locals to participate to create an atmosphere of &apos;hare&apos; and making tekiya contribute part of their profit as rent.</e>
<cmt>*The section in brackets is an explanation of &quot;政&quot; and not about festivals. Also I think the sentence cuold be split into 2 or 3 parts</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The signs of temples or shrines&apos; was basically jisha fushin and still exists today, but in pre-Meiji Period society (1868 - 1912) local government was fairly autonomous, revolving around temples and shrines and since regular repairs, improving infrastructure and planning renovations needed large amounts of money, the funds were raised not through donations, but by holding festivals, inviting tekiya and getting the locals to participate to create an atmosphere of extraordinary (hare) and making tekiya contribute part of their profit as rent.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>庶民も夜店や出店の非日常を楽しみ、日本の祭り文化が人生を豊かにし、技術を持った商売人としての的屋も生活がなりたったと言う背景がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese festival cultures fulfilled the life of citizens by making them enjoy the unusual atmosphere of night stalls and shops, and merchants with skills also made a living with tekiya.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As merchants with skils, teiya were able to make a living from festivals which, with their special atmosphere of night stalls and shops, were enjoyed by the common people and enriched their lives.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is part of the reason that as merchants with skills, tekiya were able to make a living from festivals which, with their special atmosphere of night stalls and shops, were enjoyed by the common people and enriched their culture of festival.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>ちなみに宝くじの起源である「富くじ」も、寺社普請のために設けられた、非日常を演出する資金収集の手段であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The &apos;tomikuji&apos; (lottery), which was the origin of current day lottery, was created to collect funds needed for building temples.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &apos;tomikuji&apos;, which was the origin of the modern lottery, was also created to collect funds needed for building temples.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &apos;tomikuji,&apos; which was the origin of the modern lottery and established to collect funds needed for building temples, was also produced special atmosphere.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ。補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="44">
<j>会日が縁日に変化し、庶民の生活習慣に深く根ざすようになった事や、各地域での経済の発展と市（定期市）の発生が、的屋を中心とする露天商の発展を促した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The meeting day transformed into a day of fairs and was deeply immersed in the life of normal citizens that businesses in the form of stalls centered around tekiya increased the economy and markets (periodical market) of local districts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The transformation of &apos;kaijitsu&apos; (gatherings) into fairs, becoming an integral part of people&apos;s lifestyle, together with the growth of local economies and the emergence of markets, prompted the growth of stalls centered around tekiya.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The transformation of &apos;kaijitsu&apos; (gatherings) into fairs, becoming an integral part of people&apos;s lifestyle, together with the growth of local economies and the emergence of markets, prompted the growth of stalls centered around tekiya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>また会日を根源とすることが、縁起と神事や祓いや占いなどの価値観が商売としても商品にも反映されているといえるだろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While meeting day was considered to be the origin, the values of having good luck charms, holy service, exorcism, and fortune telling became reflected in businesses and merchandize.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While kaijitsu are considered to be the origin, the goods sold also reflected values such as omens, rituals, exorcism, and fortune telling.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While kaijitsu are considered to be the origin, the goods sold also reflected values such as omens, rituals, exorcism, and fortune telling.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>そして、江戸時代には祭り文化とあいまってますます栄え、この勢いは昭和初期まで続き、第二次世界大戦前の東京都内では、年間600超える縁日が催されており、忌日をのぞき日に2・3ヶ所で縁日が行われていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This festival culture prospered even more during the Edo Period and continued until the early Showa Period, and there were more than six hundred fair days annually in Tokyo City before the World War II and were held in two or three locations except for unlucky days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The festival culture prospered even more during the Edo Period and continued until the early Showa Period (1926-1989); there were more than six hundred fairs held annually in Tokyo before World War II, with two or three held held everday except unlucky days.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The festival culture prospered even more during the Edo Period and continued until the early Showa Period (1926 - 1989); there were more than 600 fairs held annually in Tokyo Prefecture before World War II, with two or three held everyday except unlucky days.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>しかし戦争による疲弊から縁日は祭りとともに消えていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, fair days vanished with festivals from the exhaustion of wars.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, fairs and festivals vanished in the impoverished post-war period.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, fairs and festivals vanished in the impoverished post-war period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>祭りは住民参加型であれば、復活するものも多いが、縁日は職業としての的屋が担う部分が多くあり、廃業や転職などと時代錯誤的な世間の風潮とあいまって、その総数は減少の一途をたどった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Local festivals reestablished itself by local citizens, but fair days that used to have professional tekiya decreased in numbers due to businesses closing, transferring of jobs, and became something of the past in the eyes of the society.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many festivals have been reestablished by local residents, but most fairs are run by tekiya who, through leaving the business and changing jobs, as well as being seen as somewhat anachronistic, are stedily decreasing in number.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many festivals have been reestablished by local residents, but most fairs are run by tekiya who, through leaving the business and changing jobs, as well as being seen as somewhat anachronistic, are steadily decreasing in number.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>的屋という職の減少が日本の各地の縁日の減少に多大な影響を与えている事は否めない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It cannot be denied that the decrease of a job called tekiya contributed to the decrease in the number of fair days in local areas of Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It cannot be denied that the decrease of the tekiya profession contributed to the decrease in the number of fairs in local areas of Japan.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It cannot be denied that the decrease of the tekiya profession greatly contributed to the decrease in the number of fairs in local areas of Japan.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="50">
<j>的屋（まとや）が営む「懸け物の的場（景品交換式遊技場）」は、現在の温泉場や宿場町に残る射的場の起源であり、スマートボールやパチンコの源流でもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The shooting arena (that operates with exchange of prizes) of gambling&apos; originated from the shooting games that still remains today in hot spring or lodging districts and was also the original form of smart ball (similar to a pinball) and pachinko (Japanese pinball).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shooting galleries found in today&apos;s hot spring and inn towns, as well as &apos;smartball&apos; and &apos;pachinko&apos; (both forms of pinball), originated in the &apos;gambling shooting ranges&apos; run by &apos;matoya&apos;, with customers winning prizes rather than money.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The shooting galleries found in today&apos;s hot spring and inn towns, as well as &apos;smartball&apos; and &apos;pachinko&apos; (both forms of pinball), originated in the &apos;gambling shooting ranges&apos; run by &apos;matoya&apos; (shooting shop), with customers winning prizes rather than money.</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>また法律の成立においても懸け物の的場（景品交換式遊技場）が基本にあるので、「遊技」と言う言葉が「遊戯」ではないのは、弓矢は技術が伴う事に由来し、法律の根拠としても偶然性のみのくじ引きである、「富くじ（宝くじ）」との区別の根拠となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the gambling has a policy of exchanging prizes, the &apos;yuugi&apos; (遊技, game) is not considered to be &quot;yuugi&quot;(遊戯, game) since the word derived from the skill of a archery, and is a raffle under restriction of law that depended on a chance and luck that puts it apart from &quot;Tomikuji (lottery).&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In compliance with the law, the gambling is for prizes rather than money and, since the games (&quot;yugi&quot;) are based on archery, which is a skill, they are written with the characters for &apos;play&apos; and &apos;skill&apos; rather than the usual &apos;play&apos; and &apos;fun&apos; and classified differently from the &quot;tomikuji&quot;, which is a lottery based on pure chance.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In compliance with the law, the gambling is for prizes rather than money and, since &apos;yugi&apos; (the games) are based on archery, which is a skill, they are written with the characters for &apos;play&apos; and &apos;skill&apos; rather than the usual &apos;play&apos; and &apos;fun&apos; and classified differently from the &apos;tomikuji,&apos; which is a lottery based on pure chance.</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置などを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>また的屋や宿場町で営まれる射的場は文化や時代の背景があり、情緒を伴うものであるが、現在のパチンコなどは利害だけの産業といえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, shooting places of Tekiya and lodgings had cultural and historical background, and the modern day pachinko is just a businesses operated for profit.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, matoya and the shooting galleries in inn towns have a cultural and historical background, whereas modern day pachinko is just a businesses operated for profit.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, matoya and the shooting galleries in inn towns have a cultural and historical background, whereas modern day pachinko is just a businesses operated for profit.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="53">
<j>香具師（やし）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yashi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yashi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yashi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>的屋（てきや）は現在でも香具師（やし）と呼ばれる事がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tekiya are occasionally still called as Yashi nowadays.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tekiya are occasionally still called yashi.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tekiya are occasionally still called yashi even now.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>その語源は一説によると、『古事記』にも登場する火の神で、出雲国にて出産時に産道を焼いてイザナミを死に追いやりイザナギに切り刻まれて沢山の神に分裂したカグツチ（ほのかぐつちのかみ）の加具土が “加具士→加具師→香具師” と変化したもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to one theory for the origin of this word, it was the god of fire that appeared in &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters) named Kagutsuchi (Honokagutsuchinokami or god of fire, who burned the vagina and killed Izanami during birth before being chopped to pieces by Izanagi and its pieces turned into gods, and its name changed from &quot;加具士=&gt;加具師=&gt;香具師 (yashi).&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to one theory, the charachters used for this term (which, although pronounced &quot;yashi&quot;, is written &quot;kagushi&quot;) developed from Kagutsuchi (Honokagutsuchi no kami), the god of fire who appears in the &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters), and who kills his mother, Izanami, by burning her vagina as he was being born before being chopped to pieces by his father, Izanagi, the many pieces turning into gods.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to one theory, the characters used for this term (which, although pronounced &quot;yashi&quot;, is written &quot;kagushi&quot;) developed from Kagutsuchi (Honokagutsuchi no kami), the god of fire who appears in the &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters), and who kills his mother, Izanami, by burning her vagina as he was being born before being chopped to pieces by his father, Izanagi, the many pieces turning into gods.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="56">
<j>的屋の別称とされる神農の神は、農業と薬や医学の神であり、的屋の源流とされる香具師は江戸時代において、薬売りと、入れ歯の装丁・調整や販売、虫歯などの民間治療の歯科医でもあり、このことから神農の神を信仰していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Shinno deity considered to be the alias of tekiya was the god of farming and medicine, and yashi in Edo Period, believed to be the origin of Tekiya, followed Shinno as and acted as dentists by selling medicine, inserting, maintaining, and selling false teeth and provided treatments for cavity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The deity Shinno, considered an alias of tekiya, was the god of farming and medicine, and in the Edo Period, yashi, who are considered to be the origin of tekiya, worshipped Shinno and acted as dentists by selling medicine, inserting, maintaining, and selling false teeth and providing treatment for cavities.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The deity Shinno, considered an alias of tekiya, was the god of farming and medicine, and in the Edo Period, yashi, who are considered to be the origin of tekiya, worshipped Shinno and acted as dentists by selling medicine, inserting, maintaining, and selling false teeth and providing treatment for cavities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>また中華文明圏に由来する神農の神は、そもそも漢方薬の神であり、日本においても薬は漢方由来のものが歴史的にも多く存在した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Shinno from China was originally the god of Chinese medicine, and many historical Japanese medicine derived from Chinese medicine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinno was originally from China and was the god of Chinese medicine, from which many historical traditional medicines were derived.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinno was originally from Chinese Civilization and was the god of Chinese medicine, from which many historical traditional medicines were derived in Japan.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ。補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>これらのことは、的屋と香具師の繋がりが示されるとともに、的屋が日本古来の薬の神を信仰しなかった、要因の一つと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These were considered to be the connection between tekiya and yashi and became a reason for tekiya not following ancient Japanese deity for medicine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is one of the main reasons why tekiya, as well as being considered to be connected to yashi, do not follow traditional Japanese deities of medicine.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is one of the main reasons why tekiya, as well as being considered to be connected to yashi, do not follow traditional Japanese deities of medicine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="59">
<j>猿楽（さるがく）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sarugaku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sarugaku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sarugaku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>平安時代に生まれた古典芸能。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is the ancient performance that was founded during the Heian Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was an ancient form of theater that began in the Heian Period (794-1185).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was an ancient form of theater that began in the Heian Period (794 to 1185).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>日本古来からの物真似や形態模写などのお笑い芸や剣舞や独り相撲の舞踊りと唐から伝わった奇術や手品または、軽業や曲芸などの芸が合わさりできた芸能で、奉納相撲や御神楽祭の夜祭で演じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was the comedy skits such as the mimicry and copying forms, there were shows such as the sword dancing or one man sumo, magic shows, acrobatics, and stunts at night festivals such as honozumo (ritual sumo matches held at a shrine) and Kagura Matsuri (Kagura (Shinto music and dance numbers) Festival).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It consisted of impersonations and other comedy routines, sword dancing, and one man sumo, as well as Chinese magic shows, acrobatics and stunts performed at honozumo (ritual sumo matches held at a shrine) and kagura (Shinto music and dance) festivals held at night.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It consisted of impersonations and other comedy routines, sword dancing, and dancing in one man sumo, as well as Tang&apos;s magic shows, acrobatics and stunts performed at honozumo (ritual sumo matches held at a shrine) and kagura (Shinto music and dance) festivals held at night.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>寺社に所属する職業芸能人であり会日（縁日の原形）に寺社や大道で披露していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were performed by professional entertainers that belonged to temples and shrines and performed in shines and temples or big avenues on meeting days (the original form of fairs).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sarugaku was performed by professional entertainers who belonged to temples and shrines and performed at shines and temples or on main streets during kaijitsu (the original form of fairs).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sarugaku was performed by professional entertainers who belonged to temples and shrines and performed at shines and temples or on main streets during kaijitsu (the original form of fairs).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>また公家や武家に庇護されたものは、能や狂言にまで昇華し、ゆえに猿楽は能と狂言の総称でもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, those who were under the patronage of kuge (court noble) or buke (samurai family) was promoted to Noh (traditional Japanese masked dance-drama) and Kyogen (farce played during a No play cycle), and sarugaku became the generic term of noh and kyogen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, those who were under the patronage of kuge (court nobles) or samurai families developed into Noh (traditional Japanese masked dance-drama) and Kyogen (farce played during a Noh play cycle), and sarugaku became the generic term for noh and kyogen.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, those who were under the patronage of kuge (court nobles) or samurai families developed into Noh (traditional Japanese masked dance-drama) and Kyogen (farce played during a Noh play cycle), and sarugaku became the generic term for noh and kyogen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>現在においては、的屋家業としてその片鱗（がまの油売りの太刀まわりや南京玉簾など）は僅かにしか垣間見る事は出来ないが、寄席や演芸場で「染之介・染太郎」に代表される太神楽として広く知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are only few people who made the tekiya as a family business and are rare (the sword act of ama no abura uri (a street vendor of toad-oil ointment) Nankin tamasudare (a style of street performance using bamboo screens)) but were widely known as Daikagura (lion dance) by being represented by &apos;Somenosuke and Sometaro&apos; at parties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nowadays, the vestiges of sarugaku (such as the sword twirling &apos;gama no abura uri&apos; (toad-oil sellers) or &apos;nankin tama sudare&apos;, where the performer makes fancy shapes with a small bamboo screen) can be only be seen amongst a few family-run tekiya, but they are widely known from the &apos;daikagura&apos; (lion dances, juggling and other entertainment) performed at music halls and theaters by &apos;Somenosuke and Sometaro&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nowadays, the vestiges of sarugaku (such as the sword twirling &apos;gama no abura uri&apos; [toad-oil sellers] or &apos;nankin tama sudare&apos;, where the performer makes fancy shapes with a small bamboo screen) can be only be seen amongst a few family-run tekiya, but they are widely known from the &apos;daikagura&apos; (lion dances, juggling and other entertainment) performed at yose (storyteller theaters) and entertainment halls by &apos;Somenosuke and Sometaro&apos;.</e>
<cmt>用語、表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="65">
<j>蓮の葉商い・如何様師</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Trade of Lotus Leaves and Fraudster</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Lotus Leaf Trade and Fraudsters</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Lotus Leaf Trade and Fraudsters</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>古くは寺社などの神託を受けて商品ではなく縁起物を振舞うことを生業とし、その謝意として祝儀を受け取る祭りには欠かせない、職である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was the job that sold holy good luck charms rather than merchandize in temples and shrines and is necessary for festivals that celebrated in return.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Lotus Leaf Trade were businesses that were asked by shrines and temples to sell holy good luck charms, rather than merchandise, receiving in return gifts of gratitude, and as such were indispensible for festivals.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Lotus Leaf Trade were businesses that were asked by shrines and temples to sell holy good luck charms, rather than merchandise, receiving in return gifts of gratitude, and as such were indispensible for festivals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>お守りを売っているのと変わらないわけで、その品そのものの商品価値より縁起物としての色合いが強いのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is no different from selling charms, and it being good luck charm means more than just its price.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though it is no different from selling ordinary charms, the fact that they are holy charms means they are worth more than their actual value.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though it is no different from selling ordinary charms, the fact that they are holy charms means they are worth more than their actual value.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>そのため、一部からは粗悪品を巧みな口上で不当な価格で売る真っ当でない商人との蔑視を受けた歴史を持つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, they were looked down upon by some as the merchant who schemed to sell defective products and sell it more than what it is worth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, they were looked down upon by some as merchants who schemed to sell inferior products for more than they were worth worth.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, they were looked down upon by some as merchants who schemed to sell inferior products for more than they were worth.</e>
<cmt>重複する語を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>際物売り・まがい物売りなどと表現され、的屋の発祥の一つとされる蓮の葉商いや如何様師（いかさま師）などがあり、その語源の発祥とその経緯（蓮の葉商いも如何様師もまがい物や際物を売る者という意味がある）が一致している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were Trade of Lotus Leaves and fraudster who probably originated from tekiya labeled as cheap and fake product seller, since they share the origin with a word (Trade of Lotus Leaves and fraudster both have the meaning of people who sell fake or cheap objects).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The origins of tekiya, who are known for selling cheap and fake items, are believed lie in Lotus Leaf traders and &apos;ikasamashi&apos; (fraudsters), since they share etymology and background (both the Trade of Lotus Leaves and &apos;ikasamashi&apos; mean people who sell fake or cheap objects).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The origins of tekiya, who are known for selling cheap and fake items, are believed lie in Lotus Leaf traders and Ikasamashi (fraudsters), since they share etymology and background (both the Trade of Lotus Leaves and Ikasamashi mean people who sell fake or cheap objects).</e>
<cmt>リンク文字列が含まれていたため、原文・訳文共に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>手品や奇術の多くは唐から伝わり猿楽の芸の一つであり、如何様（いかさま）とも呼ばれ、それを行うものを如何様師とも呼称していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many of magic shows originated from China and a part of sarugaku performance called as Ikasama (fraud), and those who performed it were called as Ikasamashi (fraudster).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Japanese word &apos;ikasamashi&apos; comes from &apos;ikasama&apos;, a synonym for the magic shows performed in sarugaku, many of which originated in China.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japanese word &apos;ikasamashi&apos; comes from &apos;ikasama,&apos; a synonym for the magic shows performed in sarugaku, many of which originated in Tang.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>また的屋においても昭和初期まで奇術や手品を使い、客寄せをする者も多く存在し、「がまの油売り」が演じる「真剣を使って腕を切る」芸のカラクリにその片鱗が見て取れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tekiya also used magic shows until early Showa period and many used it to gather customers, and such glimpse could be seen in &apos;use a real sword to cut arm&apos; trick seen in &quot;gama no abura uri&quot; performance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tekiya also used magic shows until the early Showa Period and many used tricks such as the &apos;cutting the arm with a sword&apos; seen in the &apos;gama no abura uri&apos; performance to bring in customers.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tekiya also used magic shows until the early Showa Period and many used tricks such as the &apos;cutting the arm with a sword&apos; seen in the &apos;gama no abura uri&apos; performance to bring in customers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="72">
<j>的屋（まとや）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Matoya (Shooting Arena, written as target shop)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Matoya</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Matoya</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>平安時代の公家が楊弓という弓矢で遊興を楽しんだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The kuge of Heian Period used to participate in archery game called Yokyu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Heian Period, the kuge used to participate in an archery game called yokyu.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Heian Period, the kuge used to participate in an archery game called yokyu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>座ったままで行う正式な弓術であり、対戦式で的に当った点数で勝敗を争った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was done while remain sitting, and participants competed for the points gained by hitting the target.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was done while remaining seated, and participants competed for the points gained by hitting a target.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was done while remaining seated, and participants competed for the points gained by hitting a target.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>後に江戸時代には、この公家の楊弓と庶民の神事である祭り矢・祭り弓が元になり「的屋（まとや）」が営む懸け物（賭け事）の「的矢（弓矢の射的遊技）」として庶民に楽しまれ、江戸時代の後期には隆盛を極め、大正時代まで続いたといわれるが、江戸時代から大正に至るまで好ましくない賭博や風俗であるとされ、度々、規制や禁止がなされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This Yokyu of kuge combined with the festival arrows and bows that were holy to commoners became a gambling held by &apos;matoya&apos; called &apos;tekiya&apos; (arrow shooting game) and prospered during Edo Period and continued until Taisho Period, but was occasionally banned for being considered to be unfavorable gambling and corrupted public morals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Edo Period, yokyu combined with the common &apos;festival bows and arrows&apos; ritual to became a gambling game called &apos;matoya&apos; (written with the characters for &apos;target&apos; and &apos;arrow&apos;) run by people who were also called &apos;matoya&apos; (written with the characters for &apos;target&apos; and &apos;monger&apos;) and which prospered from the Edo Period through the Taisho Period (1912-1926), although it was occasionally banned as it was considered to be undesirable gambling and to corrupt public morals.</e>
<cmt>*Although I&apos;m not sure, I think &quot;的矢&quot; should be pronounce &apos;matoya&apos; since &quot;的屋&quot; is also pronounced &apos;matoya&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later in the Edo Period, yokyu combined with the common &apos;festival bows and arrows&apos; ritual to became a gambling game called &apos;matoya&apos; (written with the characters for &apos;target&apos; and &apos;arrow&apos;) run by people who were also called &apos;matoya&apos; (written with the characters for &apos;target&apos; and &apos;monger&apos;) and which prospered from the late Edo Period through the Taisho Period (1912 - 1926), although it was occasionally banned as it was considered to be undesirable gambling and to corrupt public morals.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>この的屋（まとや）が後の露天商を生業とする的屋（てきや）の起源の一つとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is considered to be one of the origins of later outdoor stall tekiya operated to make a living.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is considered to be one of the origins of the later tekiya, who make a living by running outdoor stalls.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is considered to be one of the origins of the later tekiya, who make a living by running outdoor stalls.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="77">
<j>「的矢」は、関西では楊弓場（ようきゅうじょう）、関東で矢場（やば）といわれ、祭礼の立つ日の庭場や遊郭で出店や夜店として、弓矢を使い的に当て、的の位置や種類により、商品や賞金が振舞われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tekiya&apos; was called as &apos;Yokyu-ba&apos; (house for Yokyu) in Kansai and &apos;Yaba&apos; archery range in Kanto regions to be held at festivals in gardens, red light district, vendors, or night stalls and merchandize or money was given as a prize for the position or the type of the target being shot with archery.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Matoya&apos; was known as &apos;yokyu-ba&apos; (yokyu place) in the Kansai region of western Japan and &apos;yaba&apos; (arrow place) in the eastern Kanto region and during festivals, stalls were set up around temples and shrines and in red light districts (or licensed quarters), with prizes or money awarded depending on the position or the type of the target</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Matoya&apos; was known as &apos;yokyu-jo&apos; (yokyu place) in the Kansai region of western Japan and &apos;yaba&apos; (arrow place) in the eastern Kanto region and during festivals, stalls were set up in niwaba and in red light districts (or licensed quarters), with prizes or money awarded depending on the position or the type of the target.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>また客が弓矢を楽しむ横からの矢の回収は危険であることから、関東の的屋の間で、危ない場所を矢場（やば）と言う様になり、危ない事を「矢場い・やばい」と表現し、隠語として使用した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since it was dangerous to gather arrows from the side while customers shot, the dangerous area started to be called in secret language as &apos;yaba&apos; and dangerous activity as &apos;yabai&apos; among tekiya of Kanto region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since it was dangerous to gather arrows from the side while customers were shooting, Kanto tekiya started calling any dangerous place &apos;yaba&apos; and dangerous activities &apos;yabai&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since it was dangerous to gather arrows from the side while customers were shooting, Kanto tekiya started calling any dangerous place &apos;yaba&apos; and dangerous activities &apos;yabai.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>この「やばい」という隠語は的屋を中心に堅気でない者の間に広まり、昭和40年前後には当時の若者に広まった言葉である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This &quot;yabai&apos; code spread among liberals, and was the word that became popular around 1965 among young people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This &apos;yabai&apos; code spread from tekiya to other disreputable groups, and became popular among young people around 1965.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This &apos;yabai&apos; code spread from tekiya to other disreputable groups, and became popular among young people around 1965.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="80">
<j>的屋と遊女</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tekiya and Prostitution house</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tekiya and Prostitutes</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tekiya and Prostitutes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>遊郭は一説に因れば「結界の意味を持つ」とする民俗学や民間信仰論もあり、政治的な治安維持としての役割と管理のし易さから、地域を特定したともいわれるが、一般の「定」から外れた部分を持つ治外法権でもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The red light district is considered to have &apos;the meaning of boundary&apos; according to folk art, beliefs, and religion and was considered to be special by having extraterritorial rights that deviated from normal &apos;laws&apos; due to its easy and steady political management and purpose.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Studies of folklore and discussions of folk religion often contend that the licensed quarters &apos;had the meaning of a barrier&apos; and since their political stability meant they were easy to control, they were said to identify an area, although they were considered to have extraterritorial rights.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Studies of folklore and discussions of folk religion often contend that the licensed quarters &apos;had the meaning of a barrier&apos; and since their political stability meant they were easy to control, they were said to identify an area, although they were considered to have some extraterritorial rights, not in the common &apos;rules.&apos;</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>また遊郭や遊女は古くは禊（みそぎ）や祓い（はらい）と言った神事でもあり、それは「渡り巫女」などの存在からも窺い知ることが出来る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, red light districts and prostitute were originally a holy activity called as purification and exoticism, and such view could be observed from the presence of &apos;watari miko&apos; (travelling miko (a shrine maiden)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, licensed quarters and prostitutes were originally related to Shinto purification and exorcism rites, as can be discerned from the existence of &apos;watari miko&apos; (shrine maidens who were also prostitutes and who traveled around performing purification rites at festivals).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, licensed quarters and prostitutes were originally related to Shinto purification and exorcism rites, as can be discerned from the existence of &apos;watari miko&apos; (shrine maidens who were also prostitutes and who traveled around performing purification rites at festivals).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>これらを背景として、遊郭は庭場（寺社や縁起に係わる場所）と同じ意味合いを持ち的屋が生業を営む場所であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The red light district was the place where it had the same meaning of niwaba (the place where temples and shrines dealt with good omens) and where tekiya was held as the business to make a living.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, licensed quarters carried the same meaning as the niwaba (places connected to temples, shrines and good omens) and was a place where tekiya plied their trade.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, licensed quarters carried the same meaning as the niwaba (places connected to temples, shrines and good omens) and was a place where tekiya plied their trade.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>そして的屋の源流とされる職種も遊女とのかかわりを持つものも多く存在している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, tekiya had many associations with prostitution house at the beginning.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, many of the professions that tekiya developed from were associated with prostitutes.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, many of the professions that tekiya developed from were associated with prostitutes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="85">
<j>お蔭参り（御伊勢参り）や富士詣などは途中の旅路も過程も含めて「詣で」であり、宿場町に遊女（飯盛女）が存在し、客が遊興することは、禊や祓いであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Okage mairi (a group pilgrimage to the Ise-jingu Shrine) and Fuji mode (a mode (pilgrimage) to Mount Fuji, climbing to the peak and visit the Sengen Shrine on the top) and the road to travel was considered all to be &apos;mode&apos; and inns had prostitutes (ladies who served food) that entertaining the guests was the form of purification and exoticism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On pilgrimages such as the Okage Mairi (to Ise-jingu Shrine) and Fuji Mode (to Sengen Shrine at the summit of Mount Fuji), the road traveled was also considered to be part of the pilgrimage, as such inn towns contained prostitutes (serving ladies) whose entertaining of the guests was a form of purification and exorcism.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On pilgrimages such as the Okage Mairi (to Ise-jingu Shrine) and Fuji Mode (to Sengen Shrine at the summit of Mount Fuji), the road traveled was also considered to be part of the pilgrimage, as such inn towns contained prostitutes (serving ladies) whose entertaining of the guests was a form of purification and exorcism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>この宿場町の風俗習慣と的屋（まとや）の営業する的場（景品交換式遊技場）が結びついて、宿場町や温泉街に矢場（射的場）が設けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These manners and morals of the lodging came in connection with the tekiya (the entertaining area that exchange prizes) and yaba (shooting arena) were established in inns and hot spring districts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The manners and morals of these inn towns came to be connected with shooting areas run by matoya, and yaba (shooting galleries) were established in inn towns and hot spring districts.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The manners and morals of these inn towns came to be connected with matoba areas (gambling for gifts) run by matoya, and yaba (shooting galleries) were established in inn towns and hot spring districts.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>これが現在の射的場（スマートボールなども含め）の原形であり、昭和30年代頃まで俗に「矢場の女」といわれる遊女が射的場に存在した理由である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was the original form of shooting arena (which also included the smart ball) and prostitution house that was called in slang, &apos;woman of yaba&apos; existed in shooting arena until around 1955.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was the original form of shooting galleries (including games such as &apos;smart ball&apos;), which until the 1950s coexisted with prostitutes, who were known in slang as &apos;women of the yaba&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was the original form of current shooting galleries (including games such as &apos;smart ball&apos;), which until the 1950s coexisted with prostitutes, who were known in slang as &apos;women of the yaba.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置などを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="88">
<j>傀儡女</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kugutsume (Puppeteer Ladies)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kugutsume (Female Puppeteers)</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kugutsume (Female Puppeteers)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>- 平安時代にあった傀儡師といわれる芸能集団で、猿楽の源流一つとされ、旅回りや定住せず流浪して、町々で芸を披露しながら金子（きんす）を得ていたが、後に寺社の「お抱え」となる集団もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was the entertaining troops called as Gugutsushi (puppeteers) that existed in Heian Period considered to be the origin of sarugaku, and wandered and travelled to areas without settling down to gain money by performing in cities and some groups came under patronage of temples and cities afterwards.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Heian Period, there were groups of entertainers called Kugutsushi (puppeteers), who are considered to be the one of the origins of sarugaku and who wandered from place to place, gaining money by performing in cities though some groups later came under the patronage of temples and shrines.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Heian Period, there were groups of entertainers called Kugutsushi (puppeteers), who are considered to be the one of the origins of sarugaku and who wandered from place to place, gaining money by performing in cities though some groups later came under &apos;the patronage&apos; of temples and shrines.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>男性は剣舞をし、女性は傀儡回しという唄に併せて動かす人形劇を行っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Men performed sword dancing and women did puppeteer shows with music called as Gugutsu mawashi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Men performed sword dancing and women did puppet shows to music called Kugutsu mawashi.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Men performed sword dancing and women did puppet shows to music called Kugutsu mawashi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>この傀儡を行う女を傀儡女とよび、時には客と閨をともにしたといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Women puppeteers called as Gugutsume (puppeteer ladies) sometimes slept with customers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The women puppeteers, known as kugutsume, sometimes slept with customers.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The women puppeteers, known as kugutsume, it is said that they sometimes slept with customers.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="92">
<j>蓮の葉女</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Woman of the Trade of Lotus Leaves</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Lotus Leaf Women</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Lotus Leaf Women</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>- 江戸中期の井原西鶴の著書の中で、描かれている上方の大店に雇用されていた遊女のことで、上客や常客の接待として閨をともにした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were prostitutes hired in big shops and slept the night with regular or high class customers as described by written works of Saikaku IHARA in mid-Edo Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As described in the works of the mid-Edo Period writer Saikaku IHARA, these were prostitutes hired by big shops in and around Kyoto to sleep with honored or regular customers.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As described in the works of the mid-Edo Period writer Saikaku IHARA, these were prostitutes hired by big shops in and around Kyoto to sleep with honored or regular customers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>蓮の葉女と蓮の葉商いはその語源について繋がりがあり、諸説あるが蓮の葉商いが遊女としての側面を持っていたことが示唆される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Lotus Leaves and the Trade of Lotus Leaves shared the origin of their words, and while it is just an assumption, Trade of Lotus Leaves had the characteristic of having prostitutes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term is related to the Lotus Leaf Trade, and though it is just an assumption, there is a suggestion Lotus Leaf traders may have also have worked as prostitutes.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term Lotus Leaf Women is related to the Lotus Leaf Trade etymologically, and though it is just an assumption, there is a suggestion Lotus Leaf traders may have also have worked as prostitutes.</e>
<cmt>リンク文字列が含まれていたため、原文・訳文共に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="95">
<j>矢取り女</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yatori Onna (women working in the archery hall)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yatori Onna (arrow collectors)</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yatori Onna (arrow collectors)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>- 江戸後期には的屋（まとや）が営む矢場に登場した女性で、客の放つ矢を掻い潜りながら、的に刺さった矢や落ちている矢を拾い集め、舞う様に矢の飛び交う中を駆け回るのが、一つの芸であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were ladies who worked in yaba owned by tekiya in the late Edo-Period and performed by gathering arrows shot by customers from the ground and ran in midst of shooting arrows as though dancing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These were women who, in the late Edo-Period, worked in the yaba owned by matoya, picking up arrows shot by customers from the ground and running through the flying arrows.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These were women who, in the late Edo-Period, worked in the yaba owned by matoya, picking up arrows shot by customers from the ground and running through the flying arrows which was considered as a kind of show.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>また特別な日には最高の賞品として一定の条件を満たせば気に入った矢取り女と閨を共にする事が出来た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On a special day, the winner was able to spend a night with yatori onna he liked as a highest award if he fulfilled certain standards.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On special days, the top prize was a night with the yatori onna of one&apos;s choice, if certain requirements were met.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On special days, the top prize was a night with the yatori onna of one&apos;s choice, if certain requirements were met.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="98">
<j>転び</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Korobi (Falling)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Korobi (Falling)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Korobi (Falling)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>- 的屋の販売形態のひとつを表す業界用語でもあるが、辞書では「路傍（ろぼう）で営む遊女」も意味すると記述されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was one of the business terms used by tekiya, but the dictionary referred to it as &quot;street prostitutes.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was a trade term used by tekiya, but dictionaries define it as &quot;street prostitutes.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was a trade term described a style of sale by tekiya, but dictionaries define it as &apos;street prostitutes.&apos;</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>双方とも茣蓙が大事な商売道具でもあり、偶然なのか洒落なのか、またはそのような実態が的屋としての「転び」にあったかは定かではないが、茣蓙の上に商品を乗せる商いの総称ともとれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Both required straw floor mats as important business tools, and was the general term used to describe the business that placed goods on top of a straw floor mats but is not certain whether &apos;korobi&apos; (falling) meant as a pun or actual falling of businesses.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Both required straw floor mats as important business tools, and it was a general term used to describe businesses where goods were sold from straw mats on the floor, rather than an actual stall, although is not certain whether &apos;korobi&apos; (falling) was a pun or referred to businesses actually &apos;collapsing&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Both required straw floor mats as important business tools, and it was a general term used to describe businesses where goods were sold from straw mats on the floor, rather than an actual stall, although is not certain whether &apos;korobi&apos; (falling) was a pun or just happened to be called, or referred to businesses actually collapsing.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="101">
<j>分類</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Classifications</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Classifications</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Classifications</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>売り場の高さによる分類</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Classifications Depending on the Height of a Counter</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Classification by size</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Classification by size</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>転び（ころび）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Korobi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Korobi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Korobi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>地面引いた茣蓙（ござ）などの上に直に商品を転ばして売っていたためにこう呼ばれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was referred to this since they sold items placed and rolled directly on goza floor mats placed on the ground.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This term was was used because the goods were sold from mats on the floor.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This term was used because the goods were sold on such as straw mats on the ground.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>新案品と呼ばれる目新しい商品を売る事でも知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was known to sell eye catching items that were called as new idea items.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were known for selling original and novelty goods.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were known for selling original and novelty goods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>その身軽さから、近年では庭場にとらわれず、小学校の下校時にあわせて、子供向けに売り場を開く事もあり、年代によっては、校門の近くで、消えるカラーインクセットやカラー砂絵セット（色別に着色した硅砂と木工用ボンド）、カラー油土の型枠セット（カタ屋）などを「ころび」から購入した経験を持つものも多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to it being light hearted atmosphere, the vendor is opened for children when they are coming back from school without the concern for niwaba nowadays, and children of certain generations bought a set of colored ink that disappeared, color sand illustration set (silicon sand that was colored and glue), mold for colored clays (called as kataya).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to the ease with which goods could be laid out, korobi have in recent times, regardless of the niwaba, set up near school gates when school finishes, selling goods aimed at children, many of whom, depending on the period, bought things such as disappearing colored-ink sets, colored-sand picture sets (colored silica sand and glue), mold for colored clays (known as kataya).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to the ease with which goods could be laid out, korobi have in recent times, regardless of the niwaba, set up other places when elementary school finishes, selling goods aimed at children, many of whom, depending on the period, bought things such as disappearing colored-ink sets, colored-sand picture sets (colored silica sand and glue), mold for colored clays (known as kataya) from &apos;korobi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="107">
<j>三寸（さんずん）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanzun (a street stall vendor)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanzun</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanzun</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>諸説あるが、売り台の高さが、一尺三寸になっているからといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although it is just a theory, it was supposedly called that way since the counter is one shaku three sun (39.4 cm) high.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although there are many theories as to the origin of this term, it is believed to refer to the fact that the counter is one shaku three sun (in Japanese, isshaku sanzun), or about 39.4cm, high.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although there are many theories as to the origin of this term, it is believed to refer to the fact that the counter is one shaku three sun (in Japanese, isshaku sanzun), or about 39.4cm, high.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="109">
<j>その他にも渡世人として各地方を渡り歩く的屋家業の者が、顔役に世話になる時の「仁義を切る」ときの口上が、やくざと違い「軒先三寸借り受けまして、、、」と始まる事、舌先三寸（口車）で商売するや胸三寸（心意気）で商売するなど、または、屋台の骨組みが木材商で販売されている一番小さい構造材の三寸角であったことなどが挙げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were people who travelled to districts as toseinin (gamblers who were similar to Japanese mafia) used to say a &apos;pay a respect&apos; speech that started with &quot;please let me borrowed three sun (around 9 cm) of your roof…&apos; unlike yakuza that coaxed people (expressed as &apos;three sun before the tongue&apos;) and sold with determination (expressed as &apos;three sun at chest&apos;) indicating that vendor stalls were made from three sun corners (a bar of wood that has a width and depth of around 9 cm) that was the smallest structure sold in wood shops.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other theories are that some tekiya traveled around as toseinin (yakuza-like gamblers) who, unlike yakuza, when paying their respects used to open their speeches with the phrase &quot;if I may may borrow three sun (around 9cm) of your roof...&quot; and who conducted business with flattery (known in Japanese as &apos;three sun of tongue&apos;) and determination (&apos;three sun of heart&apos;) or that their stalls were made from the smallest pieces of wood available, which was three sun square.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other theories are that some tekiya traveled around as toseinin (yakuza-like gamblers) who, unlike yakuza, when paying their respects for the local boss, used to open their speeches with the phrase &apos;if I may borrow three sun (around 9 cm) of your roof...&apos; and who conducted business with flattery (known in Japanese as &apos;three sun of tongue&apos;) and determination (&apos;three sun of heart&apos;) or that their stalls were made from the smallest pieces of wood available, which was three sun square.</e>
<cmt>余分な語を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="110">
<j>縁日や市や祭りが催される場所を求め渡り歩き（近隣や遠方への旅回り）床店（「とこみせ」とは組立式の移動店舗）で商売をする、いわゆる露天商であり、個人や個人経営の組もあるが、神農商業協同組合の組合員も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They travelled to seek fairs, markets, and festivals (local or faraway places) and held businesses at tokomise (movable shop) as individually owned or managed businesses, but many are Shinno Commercial Cooperative Association member.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They traveled to locations near and far in search of fairs, markets, and festivals, selling their goods from portable stalls known as tokomise, and while some were individually or privately run, most were members of the Shinno Commercial Cooperative Association.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They, so-called rotensho (stallholder), traveled to locations near and far in search of fairs, markets, and festivals, selling their goods from portable stalls known as tokomise, and while some were individually or privately run, most were members of the Shinno Commercial Cooperative Association.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>また旅回りの的屋の世話役や、庭場の場所決めの割り振りや場所代の取り決めや徴収をする顔役をさし、この顔役を中心に組織化したものが、神農商業協同組合などであり、相互扶助を目的とした露天商の連絡親睦団体として全国の各地域に存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinno Commercial Cooperative Association centered around the man of influence that controlled and managed the travelling tekiya and designated niwaba, and it is located in local districts around Japan as the mutual aid communication system for vendors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Shinno Commercial Cooperative Association, organized around the people who manage the traveling tekiya and set the niwaba and rents, is located in various places around Japan and acts as a mutual assistance and communication network for vendors.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Shinno Commercial Cooperative Association and so on, organized around the boss who manage the traveling tekiya, set the niwaba and rents, and collect the rents, is located in various places around Japan and acts as a mutual assistance and communication network for stallholders.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="112">
<j>高物（たかもの）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takamono (high object)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takamono</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takamono</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="113">
<j>高物（たかもの）は転びや三寸が地面で商売するのに対し、大掛かりに仮設建築として床を持つ小屋を作る（見世物小屋）舞台や床などがあるのでこのように呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takamono is called as such since it had a big temporarily housing (show house) with platforms and floors in comparison to korobi or sanzun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takamono (literally &apos;high thing&apos;) are so called because, in contrast with korobi or sanzun, they were big makeshift buildings (theaters) with stages and floors.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takamono (literally &apos;high thing&apos;) are so called because, in contrast with korobi or sanzun selling on the ground, they were big makeshift buildings (theaters) with stages and floors.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="114">
<j>見世物小屋で軽業師、手品師などの見世物やお化け屋敷などの興行を運営し、高物（たかもの）の多くは全国仮設興行組合に加盟していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They held performing acts by acrobats and magicians as well as having haunting house, and most of the takamono was a part of Cooperative Association of Temporary Show Case.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They showed acts by acrobats and magicians, as well as other entertainment such as haunted houses, and most takamono were affiliated with the National Temporary Entertainment Association.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They showed acts by acrobats and magicians, as well as other entertainment such as haunted houses, and most takamono were affiliated with the National Temporary Entertainment Association.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>サーカスも元はこれらの興行師が海外から取り入れ運営していたので加盟していた時代があったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The circus was originally registered in Cooperative Association of Temporary Show Case at one point since these registered members operated circus after incorporating it from abroad.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Circuses were also at one stage affiliated with the National Temporary Entertainment Association since they were operated by its members, who had adopted them from abroad.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Circuses were also at one stage affiliated with the National Temporary Entertainment Association since they were operated by its members, who had adopted them from abroad.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="116">
<j>代目や商売の内容は代わっているが現在でも活動している「○○興行部」と呼ばれる興行プロの源流が高物である場合も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Generation and business details have changed, but there are many professional show businesses called &apos;-- show category&apos; that originally started from takamono.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The times and entertainments offered may have changed, but there are still many companies in the entertainment industry whose names end in &apos;Kogyobu&apos; and whose roots lie in takamono.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The times and entertainments offered may have changed, but there are still many companies in the entertainment industry whose names end in &apos;Kogyobu&apos; and whose roots lie in takamono.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="117">
<j>的屋の世界では、この興行を行う者（興行師）を「引張り」という隠語で呼称する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These people, who perform show businesses, were called to as &apos;hippari&apos; (pull) in secret language of the world of tekiya.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The performers were known as &apos;hippari&apos; (pullers) in the secret language of the tekiya.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The performers were known as &apos;hippari&apos; (pullers) in the secret language of the tekiya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="118">
<j>売り物や販売方法による分類</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Category of Sold Goods and Business Methods</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Classification by business methods and goods sold</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Classification by business methods and goods sold</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="119">
<j>大占め（おおじめ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oojime</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oojime (literally &apos;large occupancy&apos;)</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ojime (literally &apos;large occupancy&apos;)</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="120">
<j>啖呵売（たんかばい）もこれに含まれ、啖呵口上や一種の手品や奇術を使い客寄せをする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tankabai (makes people to feel good before selling products) is also included in this and gather customers by manipulating words or doing one form of magic shows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The attracting of customers through the use of certain magic tricks or a style of banter known as tanka (literally &apos;caustic words&apos;); also includes tankabai (selling by tanka).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The attracting of customers through the use of certain magic tricks or a style of banter known as tanka (literally &apos;caustic words&apos;); also includes tankabai (selling by tanka).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="121">
<j>客寄せする技術があり人がたくさん集まるので、目抜きから離れた広い場所で行う事が多く（良い場所は庭場料も高いのでそれを避ける意味合いもある）大きな場所占めるのでこの様に呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since many people gather to watch the show, it is held often at a wide space (good location requires high renting fee so it avoids it) and is called as this when it takes up a great space.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since many people gather to watch the shows, they are often held in large spaces away from the main areas (good locations also require high rental fees so are often avoided) and are so called because they occupy a lot of space.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since many people gather to watch the shows, they are often held in large spaces away from the main areas (good locations also require high rental fees so are often avoided) and are so called because they occupy a lot of space.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="122">
<j>「ガマの油売り」や「南京玉簾」や「バナナの叩き売り」などがこれに含まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gama no abura uri,&apos; &apos;Nankin tamasudare&apos; (a style of street performance using bamboo screens), banana no tatakiuri (a seller who sells bananas at a greatly reduced price with showy performance) are included in this.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term also includes &apos;gama no abura uri,&apos; &apos;nankin tama sudare&apos;, and &apos;banana no tatakiuri&apos; (a seller who sells bananas at a greatly reduced price with a showy performance).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term also includes &apos;gama no abura uri,&apos; &apos;nankin tama sudare&apos;, and &apos;banana no tatakiuri&apos; (a seller who sells bananas at a greatly reduced price with a showy performance).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="123">
<j>小店（こみせ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Komise (Small Stalls)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Komise (Small Stalls)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Komise (Small Stalls)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="124">
<j>文字通り間口が小さな店が多く、飴などに代表される小間物（細かい、小さい物の事を指す。反対の言葉として荒物がある）を扱う事からもこの様に呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the word implies, many are small shops that are called as such since they have small front and sell candies that are komamono (It refers to small and fine objects.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the name implies, these are small stalls that sell candy and other small items (collectively known as &apos;komamono&apos;, or &apos;tiny things; the opposite is &apos;aramono&apos;).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the name implies, these are small stalls that sell candy and other small items (collectively known as &apos;komamono,&apos; or &apos;tiny things; the opposite is &apos;aramono&apos;).</e>
<cmt>原文が途中で分断されていたため、原文・訳文共に統合しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="125">
<j>元は市や縁日で蓮の葉商いや棒手振といわれる庶民の街商であったといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was originally the Trade of Lotus Leaves and botefuri (peddlers) that are outside stalls of normal citizens during market and fairs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were originally stalls run by people such as Lotus Leaf traders and botefuri (peddlers who who carried wares hanging from a pole) during markets and fairs.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were originally stalls run by common people such as Lotus Leaf traders and botefuri (peddlers who carried wares hanging from a pole) during markets and fairs.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="126">
<j>伝統的な的屋で地域密着であり地元の人々が行っていて既得権があるので、一般の的屋よりその地域においてはいろいろな条件面で優先される事が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a traditional tekiya that has strong associations with the local district and an established right to have a priority compared to other normal tekiya.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are traditional tekiya with strong connections to local areas and are usually given priority over other tekiya.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are traditional tekiya with strong connections to local areas having some acquired rights and are usually given priority over other tekiya.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="127">
<j>木（ぼく）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Boku (Wood)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Boku (tree/wood)</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Boku (tree/wood)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="128">
<j>文字通り植木を専門に売る的屋であり、元々は植木屋や現在でも植木屋と兼業する者も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the word implies, it is a tekiya that sells plants and are main or side businesses of gardener even till this day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the name implies, these are tekiya that sell plants and remains a side business of many gardeners even to this day.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the name implies, these are tekiya that sell plants and remains a side business of many gardeners even to this day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="129">
<j>とび職や植木屋などは現在でも既得権として、地元限定で酉の市や朝顔市や羽子板市などまたは、正月のお飾りや七夕の竹、笹などを販売している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">People of tobishoku and gardeners have vested rights and sell decorations for the new year and bamboo for Tanabata (star festival) at local Tori no Ichi (open-air market), Asagao-ichi (Morning-glory Fair), and Hagoita (battledore) Fair.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Scaffolders and gardeners still have vested rights in local Tori no Ichi (open-air markets), Asagao-ichi (Morning-glory fairs), and Hagoita (battledore) fairs, as well as in the selling of decorations for New Year and bamboo for Tanabata.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Scaffolders and gardeners still have vested rights in local Tori no Ichi (open-air markets), Asagao Ichi (Morning-glory fairs), and Hagoita Ichi (battledore fairs), as well as in the selling of decorations for New Year and bamboo for Tanabata festival.</e>
<cmt>表現を合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="130">
<j>商圏を背景とした組織・形態</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Structure and Forms of Business Areas of the Shop</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Structure and form based on business areas</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Structure and form based on business areas</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="131">
<j>旅回りという商圏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Business Areas of the Travelling Shop</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Traveling&apos; businesses</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Traveling businesses</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="132">
<j>近年までは旅回りの的屋の相互扶助を目的とした「神農会」や「街商組合」が機能していたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It functioned as the &apos;Shinno Association&apos; and &apos;Street Hall Union&apos; that gave mutual aid for travelling tekiya until recently.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Until recently, the &apos;Shinno Association&apos; and &apos;Stall Holders Union&apos; provided mutual aid for itinerant tekiya.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Until recently, the &apos;Shinno Association&apos; and &apos;Stall Holders Union&apos; provided mutual aid for itinerant tekiya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="133">
<j>旅においての不便や苦労を、互いに助け合うという精神の発露から、この様な組織が出来たといえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This society formed from the idea to share and help people who face hardship during travels.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These organizations formed from the idea of sharing and helping people who face hardship during travels.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These organizations formed from the idea of sharing and helping people who face hardship during travels.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="134">
<j>一般的には数件の店が一つのグループを作り、地方の縁日などを回っているが、都心の古くからある地域では一と六、二と八、三と七、五と十（四と九は縁起が悪いのと休みは的屋にも必要）の付く日で縁日を主要な町々で分けており、夏場や正月や花見など年中行事以外の限られた日数だけ地方に赴く団体もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Usually, several shops form a group and sell at local fairs, but old downtown areas hold fairs on days that have one and six, two and eight, five and ten (four and nine are numbers considered to have bad omen so even tekiya closes its business on that day), but some group goes to the district only on limited period such as summer, new year, or cherry blossom seeing season.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Usually, several shops form a group and travel around local fairs but, in areas with old towns, some groups only travel to irregular, limited-period fairs, e.g. those other than summer festivals, New Years or cherry blossom viewing festivals, dividing up the festvals held in the main towns on days in which there is a one and six, two and eight, three and seven, and five and ten (four and nine are considered unlucky so even tekiya close on those days) between them.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Usually, several shops form a group and travel around local fairs but, in old towns in urban areas, some groups do business at the festivals which held in the main towns at the fair dividing on days which there is a one and six, two and eight, three and seven, and five and ten (four and nine are considered unlucky so even tekiya close on those days), and some only travel to irregular, limited-period fairs other than annual events, such as summer festivals, New Years or cherry blossom viewing festivals.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="135">
<j>また、移動や宿泊の経費が大きくなり遠隔地に出かけずにいる的屋の団体も多いとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, there are many groups of tekiya that does not travel far to lighten up the cost for transportation and lodging.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, many groups of tekiya do not travel far in order to reduce transportation and lodging costs.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, many groups of tekiya do not travel far in order to reduce transportation and lodging costs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="25">
<sen id="136">
<j>マーケットという新しい商圏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">New Business Area as a Market</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Markets&apos; - new businesses</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Markets, new businesses</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="137">
<j>現在は祭礼や縁日に人出が減ったのに比べ、自治体が管理する公園や遊技場において各種団体が主催するフリーマーケットなどが多くなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While fewer people are present on festivals and fairs on current days, there is an increase of flea markets held by local districts in parks and entertainment areas and managed by individual groups.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While the number of people attending festivals and fairs is decreasing, the number of events such as flea markets, run by various organizations and held in municipally managed parks and recreation halls, is on the rise.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While the number of people attending festivals and fairs is decreasing, the number of events such as flea markets, run by various organizations and held in municipally managed parks and recreation halls, is on the rise.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="138">
<j>このため、地元の商店や店舗を持たない者が、副業や趣味または企業として露天での販売を行う姿も多くなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, there is an increasing number of people that do not own local shops, hold outdoor stalls for a hobby or business.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, the number of people who do not own local shops, but run stalls as a hobby, a sideline or a business is increasing.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, the number of people who do not own local shops, but run stalls as a hobby, a sideline or a business is increasing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="26">
<sen id="139">
<j>時代の変遷と共に、伝統的な的屋の非日常（ハレ）の場独特の雰囲気を演出する技量を持つ者も少なくなり、懐かしむ声も聞かれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the time passed, people who had the skill to bring out the unusual traditional atmosphere (hare) of tekiya decreased in numbers, and some people hold it with sweet memories.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As time has passed, the number of people with the skill to bring out the special traditional atmosphere (hare) of tekiya has decreased, leading some people to yearn for them.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As time has passed, the number of people with the skill to bring out the special traditional atmosphere (hare) of tekiya has decreased, leading some people to yearn for them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="140">
<j>それに対し、寺社が主催し的屋という専門職が演出し庶民による伝統的な祭りとは違う、自治体や企業が主催し地域住民が参加する「手作り」の日曜マーケットなどの蚤の市が全国的に広く開催されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In opposite, there are flea markets such as the &apos;handmade&apos; markets held on Sundays across Japan that is managed by local districts or businesses unlike professional tekiya that brought out traditional festivals managed by temples or shrines.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In contrast, there are flea markets, such as the &apos;handmade&apos; markets held on Sundays across Japan, that are run by local municipalities or businesses, though these are unlike the traditional festivals organized by temples and shrines and run by professional tekiya.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In contrast, there are flea markets, such as the &apos;handmade&apos; markets held on Sundays across Japan, that local people joined and are run by local municipalities or businesses, though these are unlike the traditional festivals by common people organized by temples and shrines and run by professional tekiya.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="141">
<j>そのマーケットといわれるものが、伝統、文化的背景が無い事に懐疑的な見方をする声もあり、また「マーケットが台頭し祭りが廃れる」のではないかと危惧する声も聞かれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some pointed out that such markets do not have traditional or cultural associations and fear that &apos;market would take over and festivals will face extinction.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has been pointed out that such markets do not have traditional or cultural associations and there is a fear that &apos;markets could take over and festivals will face extinction.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has been pointed out that such markets do not have traditional or cultural associations and there is a fear that &apos;markets could take over and festivals will face extinction.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="142">
<j>的屋と呼ばれる人々が「祭り」だけで成り立つのか、マーケットという新しい商圏に取り込まれ、伝統、文化的背景を無くしていくのか今後の時代の変遷が見守られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is not certain whether people called as tekiya is formed only by &apos;festivals&apos; or start losing culture and traditional backgrounds by incorporating market system, but it will be interesting to see what transition will happen to them in future.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Only time will tell if tekiya exist solely because of festivals or if they will lose their culture and traditional backgrounds by adapting to these new markets.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Only time will tell if tekiya exist solely because of &apos;festivals&apos; or if they will lose their culture and traditional backgrounds by adapting to these new markets.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="27">
<sen id="143">
<j>主な屋台</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Main Outdoor Stalls</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Main Stalls</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Main Stalls</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="144">
<j>下記の分類が重複している場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Following criteria sometime overlap with each other.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following criteria sometimes overlap with each other.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following criteria sometimes overlap with each other.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="145">
<j>その他は縁日を参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Please refer to fairs for other stalls.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Please refer to fairs for other stalls.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Please refer to fairs for other stalls.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="28">
<sen id="146">
<j>食品や玩具の販売</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Selling of Food and Toys</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Selling of Food and Toys</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Selling of Food and Toys</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="147">
<j>バナナの叩き売り</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Banana no Tatakiuri</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Banana no Tatakiuri</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Banana no Tatakiuri</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="148">
<j>- 屋台等の板を派手に叩きながら独特の口上でバナナを売る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They beat the board of outdoor stalls and sell banana by coaxing customers in a certain way.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The selling of bananas by beating the boards of stalls while delivering a unique sales pitch.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The selling of bananas by beating the boards of stalls while delivering a unique sales pitch.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="29">
<sen id="149">
<j>綿菓子</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cotton Candies</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cotton Candy</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cotton Candy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="150">
<j>- キザラ（グラニュー糖やザラメ）を高温で熱し、綿状にした菓子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a snack that is formed by heating up kizara (a mixture of granulated and crystal sugar) to a very high temperature and form it into fibers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A snack formed by heating a mixture of granulated and crystal sugar to a very high temperature and forming it into cotton-like fibers.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A snack formed by heating a mixture of granulated and crystal sugar to a very high temperature and forming it into cotton-like fibers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="30">
<sen id="151">
<j>リンゴ飴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ringoame (sweetened apple which is coated with a melted and sticky liquid sugar or syrup)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Candy Apples</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Candy Apples</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="152">
<j>- リンゴに飴を絡ませた物。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a candy coated apple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Candy coated apples.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Candy coated apples.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="153">
<j>現在は小さなリンゴなどもリンゴ飴にしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They also make small apples into ringoame in recent days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These days, small apples are also used.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These days, small apples are also used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="31">
<sen id="154">
<j>天津甘栗</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tenshinamaguri (Sweet Broiled Chestnut)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tenshin amaguri (Tianjin sweet roasted chestnuts)</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tenshin amaguri (Tianjin sweet roasted chestnuts)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="155">
<j>- 伝統的に天津市港が海外出荷拠点であったシナグリとキザラを混ぜたものを、小石に混ぜて煎ったもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are roasted Chinese chestnuts imported from Tianjin city harbor cooked by mixing with kizara and small rocks.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These are Chinese chestnuts, traditionally imported via Tianjin harbor, mixed with sugar and roasted together with small stones.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These are Chinese chestnuts, traditionally imported via Tianjin harbor, mixed with sugar and roasted together with small stones.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="156">
<j>天津産のシナグリを国内産で賄う事もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It occasionally uses chestnuts made in Japan instead of Chinese chestnuts made in Tianjin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Occasionally, chestnuts from Japan are used.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Occasionally, chestnuts from Japan are used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="157">
<j>この為、大きさが大きく異なる事がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, the size of the chestnuts varies greatly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, the size of the chestnuts varies greatly.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, the size of the chestnuts varies greatly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="32">
<sen id="158">
<j>ベビーカステラ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Baby Castella (sponge cake)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Baby Castella</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Baby Castella</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="159">
<j>- 小さなカステラという意味だが、ホットケーキの丸めた物という感じ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It means the small castella but something that reminds one of rounded pancakes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the name implies small castella (a kind of sponge cake), they are actually more reminiscent of pancakes.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the name implies small castella (a kind of sponge cake), they are actually more reminiscent of pancakes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="160">
<j>たこ焼き用の鉄板で作られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is made on hot plates for cooking takoyaki (octopus balls).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is made on hot plates for cooking takoyaki (octopus balls).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is made on hot plates for cooking takoyaki (octopus balls).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="161">
<j>東京ケーキ、チンチン焼、ピンス焼の名で売られることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is sometimes sold in the name of Tokyo cake, Chinchin yaki (roasted penis), or Pinsuyaki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are sometimes sold under the names Tokyo cake, Chinchin yaki, or Pinsu yaki.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are sometimes sold under the names Tokyo cake, Chinchin yaki, or Pinsu yaki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="162">
<j>独特の食感で根強い人気がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has an unique texture and is popular.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their unique texture has made them extremely popular.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Their unique texture has made them extremely popular.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="33">
<sen id="163">
<j>お面</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masks</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masks</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masks</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="164">
<j>- プラスチック製のアニメ・ゲーム・特撮等の人気キャラクターのものを販売する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Plastic masks are sold in shape of popular characters of anime, game, or films.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Plastic masks of popular characters from anime, video games, and films are sold.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Plastic masks of popular characters from anime, video games, and special effect films, and so on, are sold.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="34">
<sen id="165">
<j>カタ屋</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kataya (mold play dealer who offers a variety of molds typically in the shape of popular characters to children so that they can fill in clay and paint color)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kataya (sellers of clay molds, typically in the shape of popular characters, clay to fill them and paints used by children to color them)</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kataya (sellers of clay molds, typically in the shape of popular characters, clay to fill them and paints used by children to color them)</e>
<cmt>余分なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="166">
<j>- 詳しくはカタ屋 を参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Please refer to Kataya for more details.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Please refer to Kataya for more details.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Please refer to Kataya for more details.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="35">
<sen id="167">
<j>その他、籤や銀杏、椎などの元は時節や節気の縁起物である食品や祭礼用の品を売る屋台（古くは蓮の葉商いといった）などが縁日などではお馴染み深い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is the stall that sells lottery, ginko, and sweet acorns that are sold as seasonal, good luck, or celebration (it was traditionally called as the Trade of Lotus Leaves) and is often found in fairs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are also stalls that sell food and festival goods such as lottery tickets, ginko nuts and sweet acorns, which were originally sold as seasonal good luck charms (what was traditionally called the Lotus Leaf Trade) and are often found at fairs.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are also stalls that sell food and festival goods such as lottery tickets, ginko nuts and sweet acorns, which were originally sold as seasonal good luck charms (what was traditionally called the Lotus Leaf Trade) and are often found at fairs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="168">
<j>その他の売物について詳しくは蓮の葉商いを参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Please refer to the Trade of Lotus Leaves for other items sold for details.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Please refer to the Trade of Lotus Leaves for details of other items sold.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Please refer to the Trade of Lotus Leaves for details of other items sold.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="36">
<sen id="169">
<j>動植物の販売</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Animals being Sold</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sale of plants and animals</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sale of plants and animals</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="170">
<j>金魚すくい</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kingyo Sukui (Scooping Goldfish)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kingyo Sukui (goldfish scooping)</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kingyo Sukui (goldfish scooping)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="171">
<j>- 小さな金魚を掬う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is an activity that scoops up small goldfish.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The scooping up of small goldfish.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The scooping up of small goldfish.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="172">
<j>大抵は高級金魚養殖の選抜で間引かれた個体で、一晩で死んでしまうことも多いが、育て方が上手だと結構良い形に成長する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most of them were individuals thin out from expensive goldfish breeder, and they often die in a one night but grows to a good size when raised well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fish are usually those weeded out by breeders of expensive goldfish and, as such, usually die after one night but can grow to a good size when well looked after.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fish are usually those weeded out by breeders of expensive goldfish and, as such, usually die after one night but can grow to a good size when well looked after.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="173">
<j>もともと金魚は縁起物として中国より伝わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Goldfish was originally brought into Japan from China as a good luck charm.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Goldfish were originally brought to Japan from China as good luck charms.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Goldfish were originally brought to Japan from China as good luck charms.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="37">
<sen id="174">
<j>ひよこ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chicks</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chicks</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chicks</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="175">
<j>- 養鶏場で商品価値の低い雄の ひよこの処分手段として売られているケースが殆ど。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For most of cases, it was a method to get rid of male chicks that have low commercial value in poultry farms.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In most cases, this was a means to get rid of male chicks, which have a low commercial value for poultry farms.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In most cases, this was a means to get rid of male chicks, which have a low commercial value for poultry farms.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="176">
<j>スプレーで着色し「カラーひよこ」と称して売ったり、稀にウズラの子などを売るものもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are sprayed with color ink and sold as &apos;Colored Chicks&apos; or occasionally sold quail chicks.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were sprayed with colored ink and sold as &apos;Colored Chicks&apos;; occasionally quail chicks were also sold.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were sprayed with colored ink and sold as &apos;Colored Chicks;&apos; occasionally quail chicks were also sold.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="177">
<j>かわいらしい生き物ということで、定番となっていたが近年は余り見かけなくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was a common sight as cute animals but not often seen these days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The appeal of these animals meant that they were a common sight, although they are not often seen these days.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The appeal of these animals meant that they were a common sight, although they are not often seen these days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="178">
<j>フィリピンでは出店で日常的に見られるが、飼育する上で育てきれない場合や近隣からの苦情などで社会問題になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is seen everyday in Philippines at stalls but became a social problem due to the fact that they cannot be raised or raised without getting the complaint from neighbors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They can routinely be found at stalls in the Philippines, although they became a social problem due to people not being able to raise them or getting complaints from neighbors.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They can routinely be found at stalls in the Philippines, although they became a social problem due to people not being able to raise them or getting complaints from neighbors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="38">
<sen id="179">
<j>植物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Plants</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Plants</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Plants</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="180">
<j>-海ほおずきやホオズキ,朝顔や小さな鉢植えなど縁起のいいとされるもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Winter cherries, morning glories, or small potted plants that are considered to be good luck plants.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Winter cherries, morning glories, or small potted plants that are considered to be good luck plants.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Umi hozuki (a kind of sea nail), winter cherries, morning glories, or small potted plants that are considered to be good luck plants.</e>
<cmt>リンク文字列が含まれていたため、原文・訳文共に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="39">
<sen id="181">
<j>小動物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Small Animals</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Small Animals</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Small Animals</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="182">
<j>-鈴虫やキリギリス、かぶと虫やくわがた虫、ミズカマキリやタガメなど大人の好事家（音色を楽しんだ）や子供が好きなものや比較的珍しいものなど。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are Suzumushi (The Bell Cricket), a long-horned grasshopper (or a Japanese katydid (Gampsocleis buergeri)), Japanese rhinoceros beetle, stag beetle, mizukamakiri (a Chinese water scorpion (Ranatra chinensis)), and tagame (a giant water bug) that are favored by adults for their sounds, what kids like, or something unique.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These are insects that are favored by adults for their sounds, liked by children, or are comparatively rare, such as suzumushi (bell crickets), long-horned grasshoppers (or Japanese katydids), Japanese rhinoceros beetles, stag beetles, mizukamakiri (Chinese water scorpions), and tagame (giant water bugs) that are favored by adults for their sounds, what kids like, or something unique.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These are insects that are favored by adults for their sounds, liked by children, or are comparatively rare, such as suzumushi (bell crickets), long-horned grasshoppers (or Japanese katydids), Japanese rhinoceros beetles, stag beetles, mizukamakiri (Chinese water scorpions), and tagame (giant water bugs).</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="40">
<sen id="183">
<j>遊技や籤の提供</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Providing Games and Lotteries</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Providing Games and Lotteries</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Providing Games and Lotteries</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="184">
<j>カタ抜き</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Katanuki (cutting out shapes)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Katanuki (shape cutting)</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Katanuki (shape cutting)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="185">
<j>- 動物やキャラクターなどの絵柄がプリントされた、ハッカ味で板状の砂糖菓子を買い、絵柄通りにカタ抜きをしていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is done by purchasing the mint flavored sugar-based snack that has animal or character art printed on it, and cut out following the shape of the drawing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mint-flavored sugar-based snacks with a picture of an animal or a character printed on them, which people buy and then cout out the picture.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mint-flavored sugar-based placoid snacks with a picture of an animal or a character printed on them, which people buy and then cut out the picture.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正し、補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="186">
<j>綺麗に絵柄をカタ抜きできればお金がもらえるというシステムの屋台。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a stall that will give out money if one is able to cut out the drawing beautifully.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The stalls give out money if one is able to neatly cut out the drawing.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The stalls give out money if one is able to neatly cut out the drawing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="187">
<j>複雑な絵柄であるほど金額が上がる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The price goes up with more complex drawings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">More complex drawings pay put more money.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">More complex drawings pay put more money.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="188">
<j>地域によっては「ナメ抜き」などと呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Depending on the area, it is called as &apos;Namenuki&apos; (Lick and cut out).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In some areas, they are called &apos;Namenuki&apos; (Lick and cut out).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In some areas, they are called &apos;Namenuki&apos; (Lick and cut out).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="41">
<sen id="189">
<j>射的</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Target Shooting</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Target Shooting</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Target Shooting</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="190">
<j>-コルクを弾にした空気銃で的や景品に当てる射的遊技。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is the shooting game that uses cork as the bullet and shoot the target or a prize.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A shooting game that uses corks as bullets to shoot at targets or prizes.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A shooting game that uses corks as bullets to shoot at targets or prizes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="191">
<j>最近ではあまり見られなくなったが、古くは弓矢や吹き矢を使うこともあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is not commonly seen nowadays, but old ones used archery or blow guns.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though not so common nowadays, they also used to use bows and arrows or blow guns.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though not so common nowadays, they also used to use bows and arrows or blow guns.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="192">
<j>近年では商品を薄い紙で吊るし、水鉄砲を使いその紙紐を濡らして商品を落とすといった射的もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are some target shooting nowadays where they hang the merchandize with a thin strip of paper and make it fall by soaking the paper.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Recently, some stalls hang the prizes on thin strips of paper and customers use water guns to soak the paper and make the prizes drop.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Recently, some stalls hang the prizes on thin strips of paper and customers use water guns to soak the paper and make the prizes drop.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="42">
<sen id="193">
<j>競技（レース）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Competition (Racing)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Competition (Racing)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Competition (Racing)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="194">
<j>-小動物や昆虫や淡水魚（ウナギやフナ）などを使い直線コースのレースを行い勝敗を予想させるものでレースよりも出走する生き物が珍しかったり面白いので客が集まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It used to race small animals, insects, non-salt water fish (eels or crucian carp) on a straight course to bet on which will be the winner, and customers gathered not because they were interested in race but animals themselves that were interesting or funny.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Small animals, insects, fresh water fish (eels or crucian carp) are raced along a straight course with bets placed on which will win, though customers gathered not because they were interested in the race but because the animals themselves were interesting or funny.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Small animals, insects, fresh water fish (eels or crucian carp) are raced along a straight course with bets placed on which will win, though customers gathered not because they were interested in the race but because the animals themselves were interesting or funny.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="43">
<sen id="195">
<j>くじ引き</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Raffles</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Raffles</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Raffles</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="196">
<j>遊技銃</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toy Guns</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toy Guns</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toy Guns</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="197">
<j>-くじ（籤）を引き番号と同じ遊戯銃がもらえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Customers received a toy gun with the same number as the raffle ticket.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Customers drew a raffle ticket and received a toy gun with the same number.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Customers drew a raffle ticket and received a toy gun with the same number.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="198">
<j>最近では一回やって貰った物と、もう一回分の金額でワンランク上の物と変えてくれる屋台もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are stalls nowadays that customers receive the item by doing it once or get one level up quality goods with a price of two rounds.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are stalls nowadays where customers can exchange an item already received plus the price of another ticket for a higher quality prize.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are stalls nowadays where customers can exchange an item already received plus the price of another ticket for a higher quality prize.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="44">
<sen id="199">
<j>千本引き</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sen bon nuki (One Thousand Strings Lottery)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sen bon nuki (One Thousand Strings Lottery)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sen bon nuki (One Thousand Strings Lottery)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="200">
<j>-紐の先に色々な景品が結び付けられており全ての紐を一ヶ所に束ねている為、何が当たるか判らないという工夫をした、紐を使ったくじ引き。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a raffle that has a prize strung by a bundle of all strings that is made so it is not certain what kind of prize one wins.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is a raffle where the prizes are attached to strings which are then bundled together so that the customer does not know what prize they will win when they pull the string.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is a raffle where the prizes are attached to strings which are then bundled together so that the customer does not know what prize they will win when they pull the string.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="45">
<sen id="201">
<j>封筒引き</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Pulling Envelopes</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Drawing Envelopes</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Drawing Envelopes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="202">
<j>- 封筒の中に商品の番号を書いた紙を入れておき客に引かせる単純なもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a simple activity where the number of the item is placed within the envelope and make the customer pick one out of many.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is a simple game where prizes are given numbers, the numbers are placed in envelopes and the customer chooses an envelope.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is a simple game where prizes are given numbers, the numbers are placed in envelopes and the customer chooses an envelope.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="203">
<j>もとは、文鳥や十姉妹といった小鳥を使い手なずけて封筒を引かせる見世物でくじ引きだけではなく「おみくじ」が主だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It originally was a show that used tamed Japanese sparrow and common finch to pick the envelope and was mainly a &apos;fortune slip&apos; instead of raffle ticket</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They used to use tame Japanese sparrows and common finches to select the envelope, which usually contained a &apos;fortune slip&apos; instead of a raffle ticket</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They used to use tame Japanese sparrows and common finches to select the envelope, which usually contained a &apos;fortune slip&apos; instead of a raffle ticket</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="204">
<j>鳥を使ったおみくじの見世物をする人は日本に数人しかいないといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are only a few people in Japan that uses bird for the fortune slip.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are only a few people in Japan that use birds for this kind of fortune telling.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that there are only a few people in Japan that use birds for this kind of fortune telling.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="205">
<j>台湾では現在でも夜市などで文鳥占いを一般的に見る事が出来るが、日本統治時代に伝わった物か元々台湾が起源なのかは定かでない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is common to see fortune telling by a Japanese sparrow in night stalls in Taiwan even now, but it is not certain whether it came from Japan when it conquered Taiwan or was originally from Taiwan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is common to see fortune telling using Japanese sparrows in night stalls in Taiwan even now, but it is unclear whether was imported from Japan when Taiwan was a Japanese colony or whether it was originally Taiwanese.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is common to see fortune telling using Japanese sparrows in night stalls in Taiwan even now, but it is unclear whether was imported from Japan when Taiwan was a Japanese colony or whether it was originally Taiwanese.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="46">
<sen id="206">
<j>コリントゲーム</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Corinth Game</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Corinth Game</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Corinth Game</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="207">
<j>-パチンコやスマートボールの原型となったもので自作のもので一等、二等、三等、スカなどのゴールを作り、玉の入った先で商品の当たり外れを楽しむといった遊戯で、現在では古くなったパチンコ台を利用していることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a game that tries to put a ball inside a handmade goals with first, second, third or a fake prize labeled on it, and was a foundation of pachinko and smart ball, and currently uses the used and old pachinko machines often.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is a handmade game where customers try to get a ball in goals labeled first prize, second prize, third prize or a booby prize; it was the foundation of pachinko and smart ball, and nowadays often uses old pachinko machines.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is a handmade game where customers try to get a ball in goals labeled first prize, second prize, third prize or a booby prize; it was the foundation of pachinko and smart ball, and nowadays often uses old pachinko machines.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="47">
<sen id="208">
<j>水盆引き</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mizubon Biki (a lottery using a washbowl)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mizubon Biki (washbowl lottery)</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mizubon Biki (washbowl lottery)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="209">
<j>- 丸い金属製の盥（たらい）に周囲に区切りを設けて区域別にはずれや当りなどの色分けをして、水を張り、ドジョウや源五郎（ゲンゴロウ）を中心に落として行う一種のくじ引き。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is one type of raffle where they place a loach or diving beetle in a circular metal basin with separations with winning and lose regions labeled with different colors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A raffle where a loach or diving beetle is placed in a circular metal basin that is marked with different colored areas labeled win and lose.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A raffle where a loach or diving beetle is placed in a circular metal basin that is marked with different colored areas labeled win and lose.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="48">
<sen id="210">
<j>的屋と指定暴力団（やくざ・極道・博徒・筋者）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tekiya and Designated Mafia (yakuza (Japanese mafia), gangster, gambler, and sujimono (yakuza gangster)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tekiya and Organized Crime (yakuza, gangsters, gamblers).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tekiya and Organized Crime (yakuza, gangsters, gamblers, sujimono [a kind of gamblers]).</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="49">
<sen id="211">
<j>的屋は神農とも呼ばれ、また的屋を稼業人、博徒を渡世人とも呼び別ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tekiya was also called as Shinno as well as a businessman while bakuto as toseinin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tekiya were also called &quot;Shinno&quot; and are known as businessman while gamblers are known toseinin.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tekiya were also called Shinno and are known as businessman while gamblers are known toseinin (gamblers).</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="212">
<j>「無職渡世」とは本来、職業が公認されない博徒を指し、的屋について言われることはなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mushoku tose&apos; (live on gambling without working) originally referred to a gambler with an unofficial job and did not apply to tekiya.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mushoku tose&apos;, a phrase which means to make a living solely from gambling, originally referred to gamblers with no recognized occupation and did not apply to tekiya.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mushoku tose,&apos; a phrase which means to make a living solely from gambling, originally referred to gamblers with no recognized occupation and did not apply to tekiya.</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="213">
<j>生業とする縄張りも的屋では「庭場」、博徒では「島」と表現する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The territory of tekiya that makes it as a job for living is called as &apos;niwaba&apos; while bakuto refers to it as &apos;island.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The area where tekiya operate is called the &apos;niwaba&apos;, whereas gamblers use the term &apos;island.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The area where tekiya operate is called the &apos;niwaba,&apos; whereas gamblers use the term &apos;island.&apos;</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="214">
<j>古くは江戸時代の寺社奉行と町奉行の管轄の違いから来ているともいわれ、現在も地図上でその生業とする地域分けも江戸時代の名残が多く見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These derived from the difference in jurisdiction of the city versus temples and shrines of Edo Period, and such traces are left on areas with such jobs that are subdivided on a map.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This derives from the different jurisdictions of the city commissioner and the temple and shrine commissioner in the Edo Period, and the divisions according to occupation can be seen on maps in placenames that have survived from that period.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This derives from the different jurisdictions of the city commissioner and the temple and shrine commissioner in the Edo Period, and the divisions according to occupation can be seen on maps in placenames that have survived from that period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="215">
<j>また上記概要にも記述があるが、個々の信仰は別として的屋は職業神として神農を祀り博徒は職業神として天照大神を祀っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are many documents that refer to what was phrased above, but tekiya worshipped Shinno and bakuto worshipped Amaterasu Okami as the business god.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As mentioned above, they had different beliefs, with tekiya worshipping Shinno and gamblers worshipping Amaterasu Okami as the god of business.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As mentioned above, they had different beliefs, with tekiya worshipping Shinno, and gamblers worshipping Amaterasu Okami as the god of business, whether each believes which religion or not.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="50">
<sen id="216">
<j>やくざ、暴力団との関係については、ヤクザ及び暴力団を参照</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Please refer to yakuza and gangster for its relationship with them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For connections with the yakuza and gangsters, please refer to the relevant for articles.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For connections with the yakuza and gangsters, please refer to the article of yakuza and gangsters.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="217">
<j>組織として「組」を形成し互助活動を行っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It performed mutual aid activities as a &apos;group&apos; within the society.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were formed along the lines of the traditional Japanese &quot;kumi&quot; and acted as mutual assistance associations.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were formed along the lines of the traditional Japanese &apos;kumi&apos; (an organization) and acted as mutual assistance associations.</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="218">
<j>これは的屋特有のものではなく、大工、鳶、土方（つちかた）などの建設業団体や河岸、沖仲仕、舟方（ふなかた）などの港湾労働団体や籠屋、渡し、馬方（うまかた）などの運輸荷役団体と同じである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was not designated to tekiya and called as carpenter, tobi (kite), or tsuchikata (laborer)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was not unique to tekiya, with construction associations made up of carpenters, scaffolders, and tsuchikata (also known as doteninsoku, these were groups of civil engineers involved in land reclamation and levee protection projects in the Edo Period), longshoreman associations consisting of river bank and dock workers and transport associations consisting of messengers, palanquin bearers and ferrymen all formed along similar lines.</e>
<cmt>*Although this sentence and the following one were treated as separate sentences, they are actually one sentence so I revised as such.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was not unique to tekiya, with construction associations made up of carpenters, scaffolders, and tsuchikata (also known as doteninsoku, these were groups of civil engineers involved in land reclamation and levee protection projects in the Edo Period), longshoreman associations consisting of river bank and dock workers, ferrymen and so on, and transport associations consisting of messengers, palanquin bearers and packhorse drivers, and so on, all formed along similar lines.</e>
<cmt>ウェブ内の脚注文章が含まれていたため、原文・訳文共に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="219">
<j>しかし、互助活動に対しての謝礼の授受が今でいう民事介入と言う表現になりやくざと同一視される由縁である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its mutual aid system became associated with involvement with society and is viewed to be the same as yakuza.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the system of rewards that existed as part of their mutual assistance actvities developed into what is now called &apos;minji kainyu&apos; (essentially protection rackets) and which is associated with the yakuza.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the system of rewards that existed as part of their mutual assistance activities developed into what is now called &apos;minji kainyu&apos; (essentially protection rackets) and which is seemed associated with the yakuza.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="220">
<j>そもそも老舗の組も元をたどればこれらの職業であったといえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The old group had these jobs at the beginning.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The origins of some of the oldest companies in Japan can be traced back to these occupations.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The origins of some of the oldest companies in Japan can be traced back to these occupations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="51">
<sen id="221">
<j>指定暴力団・極東会が日本最大の的屋組織である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyokuto kai (Kyokuto Society) is one of the yakuza group and manages the biggest tekiya organization in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kyokuto-kai crime syndicate is the biggest tekiya organization in Japan.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kyokuto-kai, designated crime syndicate, is the biggest tekiya organization in Japan.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="222">
<j>他にも、飯島会、姉ヶ崎会などが的屋組織である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are other tekiya organizations such as Iijimakai and Anegasakikai Societies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other tekiya organizations include Iijima-kai and Anegasaki-kai.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other tekiya organizations include Iijima-kai and Anegasaki-kai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="52">
<sen id="223">
<j>各地の神農会を構成、運営していた「庭主」（世話役のこと）も、諸事情により その円滑な運営をなしえない状態にあるものもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were cases where &apos;Teishu&apos; (head of the garden) (the care-taker) that formed the Shinno Association of each district and could not manage it due to various reasons.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were cases where, for various reasons, the &apos;teishu&apos; (literally &apos;head of the garden&apos;, they were kind of stewards), who organized and managed the Shinno Association of each district, was unable to ensure smooth operations.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were cases where, for various reasons, the &apos;niwanushi&apos; (literally &apos;head of the niwaba,&apos; they were kind of stewards), who organized and managed the Shinno Association of each district, was unable to ensure smooth operations.</e>
<cmt>用語の読み等を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="224">
<j>本来、行商人や旅人（たびにん）の場所の確保や世話をする世話人が集まって組織となり神農会と呼ばれる庭主（組合）が起こったが、現在では、そのほとんどが各地の暴力団の傘下組織となり、一部には本来一番肝心な世話することを怠って何もしない「庭主」が「○○会○代目」、「○○組分家」、「○○会○○一家」と名乗り、競合する出店を脅迫し排除したり、挨拶に来るよう呼びつけ行商人などから着到（その地区の世話人に世話になる場合、到着した際に挨拶として持っていく手土産）名目で金品をたかる組織も存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Shinno Association of teishu (union) was formed by gathering caretakers of travelling merchants or travelers that reserved and managed the spot, but most of them went under the rule of local mafia that some had &apos;teishu&apos; without any particular duty that call themselves as &apos;-the generation of -- society,&apos; &apos;-family of -- society,&apos; or &apos;--society -- family&apos; and took away money when inviting merchants to greet them (as a gift given to a caretaker in appreciation for help) after arriving to the local district.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally, unions of teishu, known as Shinno Associations, were formed by groups of mediators who secured spots for and looked after peddlars and travelers, but these days, most are affiliated with criminal gangs, with some &apos;teishu&apos; completely ignoring the &apos;taking care of&apos; part, which was originally the most important, and while claiming to be the &apos;n-th teishu of such-and-such society&apos; or from &apos;a branch of so-and-so kumi&apos; or &apos;the such-and-such family of so-and-so society&apos;, they threaten and exclude rivals and demand gifts and money from from newly-arrived merchants seeking their services.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally, unions of niwanushi, known as Shinno Associations, were formed by groups of mediators who secured spots for and looked after peddlers and travelers, but these days, most are affiliated with criminal gangs, with some &apos;niwanushi&apos; completely ignoring the &apos;taking care of&apos; part, which was originally the most important, and while claiming to be the &apos;n-th niwanushi of such-and-such society&apos; or from &apos;a branch of so-and-so kumi&apos; or &apos;the such-and-such family of so-and-so society,&apos; they threaten and exclude rivals and demand gifts and money in the name of chakuto (gifts for caretakers of the area when merchants arrived, in a sign of greeting) from newly-arrived merchants seeking their services.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="53">
<sen id="225">
<j>現在では一部地域において県の公認を受けた協同組合として活動している組織もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are some societies that participate after given permission from the prefecture for certain regions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These days some organisations in certain areas operate as cooperatives licensed by the prefecture.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These days some organizations in certain areas operate as cooperatives licensed by the prefecture.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="226">
<j>この場合においても、実際には○○組組長や○○会会長が協同組合理事長を兼任している場合が多く、協同の組合というより親分の私物の組合といった趣きが強い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even with this case, there are chief or chair of certain society that has an additional job as a director of a certain union that it is not really a group of union but a privately owned group.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even in this case, the director of the cooperative is usually also a gang boss or the president of some society, meaning that rather than associations for cooperation, they are associations for the boss&apos;s benefit.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even in this case, the director of the cooperative is usually also a gang boss or the president of some society, meaning that rather than associations for cooperation, they are associations for the boss&apos;s benefit.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="227">
<j>極端には、理事長そのものが替え玉という場合も存在するという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In extreme cases, the director himself acts as a substitute.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In extreme cases, the director is a dummy.</e>
<cmt>*I presume &quot;替え玉&quot; doesn&apos;t mean &apos;double&apos; here.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In extreme cases, the director is a dummy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 奈緒(id:33238), Yoshipie nofear1983(id:31609), クモハモハ大王(id:185685), Ntrsbig(id:95887), Tararairan(id:29492), Dabbler(id:65389), Sloop25(id:35005), ロッカーズ(id:138827), Tjan(id:17305), Yaku(id:16824), Tribot(id:186681), Takeler(id:51437), Bandalgom(id:31841), Goki(id:7107), ラッパ食堂(id:255123), IwaimBot(id:190695), Point136(id:211299), 木島無名(id:29709), 諸星団(id:72202), 長島左近(id:161003), けふこえて(id:17107), Izayohi(id:13095), 貿易風(id:85487), Sh(id:2707), 沼田寅松(id:26068), Hamichan(id:4829), 天使の羽根(id:152455), Guchi(id:119384), Neko2(id:21083), ヘルム(id:55423), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), 松浪ケンシロウ(id:25283), アセルス(id:87426), 水雷久(id:31288), 水平芳(id:203583), 青山光二(id:25291), けんち(id:5147), ウミユスリカ(id:9504), 竹田友一(id:7429), Louperibot(id:128971), 宇和島太郎(id:105130), Ete(id:28565), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>