<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>おたべ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Otabe (oTA-BE; Japanese sweet)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Otabe (pronounced oTA-BAY; Japanese sweet)</e>
<cmt>I&apos;m not sure the part in brackets is necessary but revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Otabe</e>
<cmt>カッコ内の説明はここでは不要と思われるため削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>おたべとは、京都市南区 (京都市)に本社を置く、八ツ橋などを製造販売する企業であり、主力製品であるつぶあん入りの生八ツ橋の商品名でもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Otabe is the name of a Kyoto-based (Minami Ward, Kyoto City) pastry manufacturer which manufatures and sells yatsuhashi and other sweets, and also well known as the product name &quot;nama-yatsuhashi,&quot; a soft sweet dumpling filled with sweet azuki bean paste containing bean chunks, which is its main product.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Otabe is the name of a Kyoto-based (Minami Ward, Kyoto City) sweet manufacturer, and also the name of its main product, a soft sweet dumpling filled with chunky sweet azuki bean paste called &quot;nama yatsuhashi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Revisedfor clarity and to make less wordy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Otabe is the name of a Kyoto-based (Minami Ward, Kyoto City) sweet manufacturer, and also the name of its main product, a soft sweet dumpling filled with chunky sweet azuki bean paste called &quot;nama-yatsuhashi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>他の表記と統一するため、nama-yatsuhashiとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>また、東京ディズニーリゾートやユニバーサル・スタジオ・ジャパン土産のチョコレートやクッキー等の製造もしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The company also manufatures chocolates and cookies for Tokyo Disney Resort and Universal Studios Japan, who sell the pastries at the souvenir shops in the parks.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The company also manufatures chocolates and cookies for sale as souvenirs at Tokyo Disney Resort and Universal Studios Japan.</e>
<cmt>Revised to make less wordy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The company also manufatures chocolates and cookies for sale as souvenirs at Tokyo Disney Resort and Universal Studios Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="3">
<j>主な商品</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Main products</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Main products</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Main Products</e>
<cmt>頭文字を大文字に変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>おたべ（生八ツ橋）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Otabe (nama-yatsuhashi)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Otabe (nama-yatsuhashi)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Otabe (nama-yatsuhashi)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>黒おたべ（黒ゴマを使用したおたべ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kuro otabe (black otabe, a soft sweet dumpling with black sesami seeds filled with chunky sweet azuki bean paste.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kuro (black) Otabe, made with black sesame.</e>
<cmt>Revised to make less wordySpellingSince Otabe is a the name of the product, I think it should have a capital letter</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kuro (black) Otabe, made with black sesame.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>季節のおたべ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seasonal otabe products</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seasonal otabe products</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seasonal Otabe products</e>
<cmt>他の表記とあわせ、Otabeとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>秋おたべ（紫芋と栗を使用したおたべ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Aki (autumn) otabe, the dumpling filled with murasaki imo, or purple sweet potato, and sweet chestnut.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Aki (autumn) Otabe, filled with murasaki imo, or purple sweet potato, and sweet chestnut.</e>
<cmt>Since Otabe is a the name of the product, I think it should have a capital letterDeleted &quot;the dumpling&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Aki (autumn) Otabe, filled with murasaki imo, or purple sweet potato, and sweet chestnut.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>冬おたべ（黒豆と栗金団を使用したおたべ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fuyu (winter) otabe, the dumpling filled with black bean and mashed sweet chestnut.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fuyu (winter) otabe, filled with black beans and mashed sweet chestnut.</e>
<cmt>Since Otabe is a the name of the product, I think it should have a capital letterDeleted &quot;the dumpling&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fuyu (winter) Otabe, filled with black beans and mashed sweet chestnut.</e>
<cmt>他の表記とあわせ、Otabeとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>沿革</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>1946年 河原町通六角通において菓子小売店として創業</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1946, established as a Japanese pastry retailer on the streets of Kawaramachi-dori and Rokkaku-dori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1946, established as a Japanese pastry retailer on the corner of Kawaramachi-dori and Rokkaku-dori streets.</e>
<cmt>I presume this is part of a Kyoto-style address, usually given as north, south, east or west of a particular junction</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1946: Established as a Japanese pastry retailer on the corner of Kawaramachi-dori and Rokkaku-dori Streets.</e>
<cmt>他の記事の表記スタイルに変更、streetの頭文字に大文字に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>1949年 「京好み八ッ橋本舗」として八ッ橋の販売始める</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1949, the pastry shop started selling yatsuhashi under the name of &quot;Kyogonomi Yatsuhashi Honpo.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1949, the pastry shop started selling yatsuhashi under the name &quot;Kyogonomi Yatsuhashi Honpo.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;of&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1949: The pastry shop started selling yatsuhashi under the name &apos;Kyogonomi Yatsuhashi Honpo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記スタイルに変更他の記事の表記スタイルに変更ルクォーテーションに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>1957年 八ッ橋の製造を始める</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1957, the company started manufacturing yatsuhashi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1957, the company started manufacturing yatsuhashi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1957: The company started manufacturing yatsuhashi.</e>
<cmt>他の記事の表記スタイルに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>1965年 「さか井屋」を設立</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1965, the company established &quot;Sakaiya.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1965, the company established &quot;Sakaiya.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1965: The company established &apos;Sakaiya.&apos;</e>
<cmt>他の記事の表記スタイルに変更、シングルクォーテーションに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>1966年 つぶあん入り生八ツ橋「おたべ」を発売</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1966, Sakaiya started selling &quot;otabe,&quot; nama yatsuhashi, a soft sweet dumpling filled with sweet azuki bean paste containing bean chunks.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1966, Sakaiya started selling &quot;Otabe&quot; nama yatsuhashi.</e>
<cmt>Deleted explanation of yatsuhashi as it already appears above.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1966: Sakaiya started selling &apos;Otabe&apos; nama-yatsuhashi.</e>
<cmt>他の記事の表記スタイルに変更、シングルクォーテーションに修正、nama-yatsuhashiとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>1969年 現社名に変更</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1969, the company changed its name to Otabe.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1969, the company changed its name to Otabe.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1969: The company changed its name to Otabe.</e>
<cmt>他の記事の表記スタイルに変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 パの字(id:34188), ＋－(id:17104), BoB774(id:148281), Miyuki h(id:84952), 下総大納言(id:43461), Kansai explorer(id:48975), Aoiya(id:44787), Namaneko(id:19467), 三菱善次郎(id:21924), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>