<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>紅葉狩 (能)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Momijigari (Noh)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Momijigari (Noh play)</e>
<cmt>他のファイルと統一しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Momijigari (Noh play)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>『紅葉狩』 (もみじがり) は、能の一曲である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Momijigari&quot; is a Noh piece.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Momijigari&quot; is a Noh piece.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Momijigari&quot; is a Noh piece.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>平維茂の鬼退治を描く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It describes an onitaiji (ogre extermination) of TAIRA no Koreshige.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It depicts the onitaiji (ogre extermination) of TAIRA no Koreshige.</e>
<cmt>Describeをdepictにしました。冠詞を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It depicts the onitaiji (ogre extermination) of TAIRA no Koreshige.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>観世小次郎信光作。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a work of Kojiro Nobumitsu KANZE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a work of Kojiro Nobumitsu KANZE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a work of Kojiro Nobumitsu KANZE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>信光は『船弁慶』『鐘巻』（『道成寺 (能)』の原型）の作者でもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobumitsu also composed &quot;Funa Benkei (Benkei in the Boat)&quot; and &quot;Kanemaki (Coiling around a bell)&quot; (a model of &quot;Dojo-ji Temple (Noh)&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobumitsu also composed &quot;Funa Benkei (Benkei in the Boat)&quot; and &quot;Kanemaki (Coil Around a Bell)&quot; (the model for &quot;Dojo-ji Temple [Noh play]&quot;).</e>
<cmt>Coilingをcoilにしました。A model ofをthe model forにしました。Playを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobumitsu also composed &quot;Funa Benkei&quot; (Benkei in the Boat) and &quot;Kanemaki&quot; (Coil Around a Bell) (the model for &quot;Dojo-ji Temple [Noh play]&quot;).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション調整</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>本作もまた初期の登場人物が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This piece also includes many of earlier characters.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This piece also includes many earlier characters.</e>
<cmt>Ofを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This piece also includes many earlier characters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>ワキの積極的な関与が見られるなど、劇的構成を目指した比較的新しいスタイルの能である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is a relatively new style of Noh aimed at dramatic composition, including active involvement of waki (supporting actor).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is a relatively new style of Noh aimed at dramatic composition, with the active involvement of the waki (supporting actor).</e>
<cmt>Includingをwithにしました。冠詞を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is a relatively new style of Noh aimed at dramatic composition, with the active involvement of the waki (supporting actor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>美しい紅葉の情景、美女一行の姿と舞が前段の見どころ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Points of the first part are beautiful autumnal foliage scene and party of beautiful females.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The visual highlights of the first part are the beautiful autumnal foliage, a party of beautiful women and their dancing.</e>
<cmt>自然な表現にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The visual highlights of the first part are the beautiful autumnal foliage, a party of beautiful women and their dancing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>一転して派手な激闘となる後段との対比が楽しい能である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A contrast with latter part that transforms into a showy fierce fight scene is enjoyable in this Noh piece.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is an enjoyable Noh piece, with the contrast with the latter part that features a showy, fierce fight scene.</e>
<cmt>順序を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is an enjoyable Noh piece, with the contrast with the latter part that features a showy, fierce fight scene.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>登場人物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The characters</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Characters</e>
<cmt>他のファイルと統一しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Characters</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="9">
<j>能シテ 紅葉見物の上臈（実は鬼）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Noh shite (main role): a joro (high rank woman servant in the Imperial Court) in viewing of autumnal foliage (actually an Oni (ogre))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Noh shite (main role): Joro (high ranking female servant in the Imperial Court) viewing autumnal foliage (actually an Oni [ogre])</e>
<cmt>冠詞を削除しました。Rankを形容詞にしました。Womanをfemaleにしました。Inを削除しました。括弧を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Noh shite (main role): Joro (high ranking female servant in the Imperial Court) viewing autumnal foliage (actually an Oni [ogre])</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>ツレ 紅葉見物の美女一行</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsure (subordinate to main role): a party of beautiful females in viewing of autumnal foliage</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsure (companions of the main role): Party of beautiful women viewing autumnal foliage</e>
<cmt>他のファイルと統一しました。文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsure (companions of the main role): Party of beautiful women viewing autumnal foliage</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>能ワキ 平維茂</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">No waki (supporting role): TAIRA no Koreshige</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">No waki (supporting role): TAIRA no Koreshige</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">No waki (supporting role): TAIRA no Koreshige</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>ワキヅレ 平維茂一行</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wakizure, (companion who appears with the supporting actor in a Noh play): party of TAIRA no Koreshige</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wakizure (companion of the supporting role): TAIRA no Koreshige&apos;s party</e>
<cmt>上文と統一しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wakizure (companion of the supporting role): TAIRA no Koreshige&apos;s party</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>能狂言方 美女一行の供者</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Noh kyogenkata (Actors who perform lighthearted plays that are often staged between the more serious noh pieces): an attendant of party of beautiful females</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Noh kyogenkata (Actors who perform lighthearted plays that are often staged between the more serious noh pieces): Attendant of the party of beautiful women</e>
<cmt>上文と統一しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Noh kyogenkata (Actors who perform lighthearted plays that are often staged between the more serious noh pieces): Attendant of the party of beautiful women</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>能狂言方 八幡宮の神</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Noh kyogenkata: god of Hachiman-gu Shrine</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Noh kyogenkata: God of Hachiman-gu Shrine</e>
<cmt>Godを大文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Noh kyogenkata: God of Hachiman-gu Shrine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>作リ物 大小前に一畳台、その上に岩山と紅葉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Stage setting: ichijo-dai (a platform with the size of one tatami (a floor covering made of tightly woven grass and straw)) at center back of main stage with rugged mountain and autumn foliage on top of it</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Stage setting: ichijo-dai (a platform the size of one tatami mat) at center back of the main stage, and a rocky mountain and autumn foliage above it</e>
<cmt>訳し直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Stage setting: ichijo-dai (a platform the size of one tatami mat) at center back of the main stage, and a rocky mountain and autumn foliage above it</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>作品構成</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Composition of the piece</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Structure of the Play</e>
<cmt>他のファイルと統一しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Structure of the Play</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="16">
<j>場面は信濃国戸隠山である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Scene is at Mt. Togakushi, Shinano Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The piece is set at Mt. Togakushi-yama, Shinano Province.</e>
<cmt>自然な表現にしました。Yamaを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The piece is set at Mt. Togakushi-yama, Shinano Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>前シテ一行の道行きで幕を開ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The play begins with travel-dance scene of party of Mae-Shite (the leading role in the first half of a Noh play).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The play begins with the travel-dance scene of the party of Mae-Shite (leading role of the first half).</e>
<cmt>冠詞を追加しました。不要な部分を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The play begins with the travel-dance scene of the party of Mae-Shite (leading role of the first half).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>若い美女が数人連れ立って紅葉見物にやってきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Several young beautiful females come to viewing of autumn foliage together.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Several young beautiful women have come to view the autumn foliage together.</e>
<cmt>Femalesをwomenにしました。時制を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Several young beautiful women have come to view the autumn foliage together.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>絶景の中、地謡前に幕を巡らし宴会となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Stage is enclosed with a curtain before Jiutai (Noh chorus) and a banquet starts in magnificent scenery.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The stage is enclosed with a curtain before the jiutai (Noh chorus) and a banquet starts in magnificent scenery.</e>
<cmt>冠詞を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The stage is enclosed with a curtain before the jiutai (Noh chorus) and a banquet starts in magnificent scenery.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>次いで馬に乗り供の者を従えたワキが登場する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, waki and his attendants appear on stage riding on horseback.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Next, the waki appears on stage on horseback with his attendants in tow.</e>
<cmt>After thatをnextにしました。冠詞を追加しました。順序を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Next, the waki appears on stage on horseback with his attendants in tow.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>鹿狩りにやってきた平維茂の一行である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a party of TAIRA no Koreshige who come to deer hunting.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is the party of TAIRA no Koreshige who has come to hunt deer.</e>
<cmt>冠詞を修正しました。時制を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is the party of TAIRA no Koreshige who has come to hunt deer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>橋懸リでの道行きの後、楽しげな宴会が開かれているのを発見した維茂は、供の者に様子を見てこさせる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After a travel-dance scene at hashigakari (bridge-form passageway to main stage), Koreshige find joyous banquet held, and tells an attendant to see the run of events.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After a travel-dance scene at the hashigakari (bridge-form passageway to the main stage), Koreshige discovers the joyous banquet and tells an attendant to find out what is happening.</e>
<cmt>冠詞を追加しました。Findsをdiscoversにしました。最後の部分を自然な表現で置き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After a travel-dance scene at the hashigakari (bridge-form passageway to the main stage), Koreshige discovers the joyous banquet and tells an attendant to find out what is happening.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>アイとの問答があるが、美女一行は素性を明かさない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They hold dialogue with ai (the role of a kyogen actor in Noh) but the party of beautiful females does not tell their identities.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a dialogue with the ai (role of the kyogen actor – here, the women&apos;s attendant) but the beautiful women do not reveal their identities.</e>
<cmt>訳し直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a dialogue with the ai (role of the kyogen actor – here, the women&apos;s attendant) but the beautiful women do not reveal their identities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>そこで維茂は馬を降り通り過ぎようとするが、シテが現れ、どうかお出でになって、一緒に紅葉と酒を楽しみましょうと誘惑する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koreshige get off the horse and tries to walk pass, but shite appears and tempt him saying, do come along and let us enjoy autumn leaves and sake.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koreshige gets off his horse and tries to walk past, but the shite appears and tempts him by asking him to join them and enjoy the autumn leaves and sake (wine) together.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koreshige gets off his horse and tries to walk past, but the shite appears and tempts him by asking him to join them and enjoy the autumn leaves and sake (wine) together.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="25">
<j>無下に断ることもできず宴に参加した維茂であったが、美女の舞と酒のために不覚にも前後を忘れてしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koreshige could not reject the offer and participated the banquet, however he carelessly becomes beside himself with sake and dances of beautiful females.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unable to reject the offer, Koreshige participates the banquet, however he carelessly overcome by the power of sake and dances of the beautiful women.</e>
<cmt>訳し直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unable to reject the offer, Koreshige participates the banquet, however he carelessly overcome by the power of sake and dances of the beautiful women.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>シテの舞う美しい中ノ舞は突如激し急ノ舞となり、美女の本性を覗かせるが、維茂は眠ったままである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Beautiful Naka no mai (dance) performed by shite suddenly becomes violent Kyu no mai (high-tempo dance) and shows beautiful female&apos;s true nature, but Koreshige is sleeping.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The beautiful Naka no mai (dance) performed by the shite suddenly becomes a violent Kyu no mai (high-tempo dance) and shows the true nature of the beautiful women, but Koreshige remains asleep.</e>
<cmt>冠詞を修正しました。後半を訳し直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The beautiful Naka no mai (dance) performed by the shite suddenly becomes a violent Kyu no mai (high-tempo dance) and shows the true nature of the beautiful women, but Koreshige remains asleep.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>女達は目を覚ますなよと言い捨てて消える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Females disappears saying, do not wake up.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The women disappear, telling him not to wake up.</e>
<cmt>訳し直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The women disappear, telling him not to wake up.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="28">
<j>ここで場面は夜となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Here, scene turns to the night.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is now nighttime.</e>
<cmt>訳し直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is now nighttime.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>アイによる八幡宮の神が現れ維茂の夢中に、美女に化けた鬼を討ち果たすべしと告げ、神剣を授ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">God of Hachiman-gu Shrine, an ai, appears in the dream of Koreshige telling him to slay the oni who is taking form of beautiful female, and grant him the Divine Sword.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The god of Hachiman-gu Shrine, an ai, appears in Koreshige&apos;s dream and tells him to slay the oni taking the form of beautiful women, granting him the Divine Sword.</e>
<cmt>文法の誤りが多数あったので訳し直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The god of Hachiman-gu Shrine, an ai, appears in Koreshige&apos;s dream and tells him to slay the oni taking the form of beautiful women, granting him the Divine Sword.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>覚醒した維茂は鬼を退治すべく身構える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koreshige wakes up and stand ready to slay oni.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koreshige wakes up and stands ready to slay the oni.</e>
<cmt>動詞を修正しました。冠詞を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koreshige wakes up and stands ready to slay the oni.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>嵐と共に炎を吐きつつ現れた後シテ（能面は顰または般若の面）と丁々発止、激しい攻防の末ついに鬼を切り伏せることに成功する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He clashes swords in fierce combat against Nochi-Shite (the leading role in the latter half of a Noh play) (Noh mask, Shikami or hannya (female demon) mask), who appears with storm and breathing fire and finally, at the end of fierce combat, he succeeds in slaying the oni.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He clashes swords with the nochi-shite (leading role of the latter half) (wearing either a shikami [angry demon] or hannya [female demon] Noh mask) who appears with a storm breathing fire, and after a fierce battle finally succeeds in slaying the oni.</e>
<cmt>訳し直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He clashes swords with the nochi-shite (leading role of the latter half) (wearing either a shikami [angry demon] or hannya [female demon] Noh mask) who appears with a storm breathing fire, and after a fierce battle finally succeeds in slaying the oni.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>本説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Theory</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Origins</e>
<cmt>訳し直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Origins</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="32">
<j>不明だが、大日本史平維茂伝、太平記に鬼退治伝説が見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although it is unknown, legend of Onitaiji can be seen in Dai Nihon shi Taira no Koreshige den (Japanese literature, collection of TAIRA no Koreshige) and Taiheiki (The Record of the Great Peace).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although unclear, Onitaiji legends can be found in Dai Nihon shi Taira no Koreshige den (Japanese literature, collection of TAIRA no Koreshige) and Taiheiki (The Record of the Great Peace).</e>
<cmt>it is unknownをunclearにしました。後半の表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although unclear, Onitaiji legends can be found in Dai Nihon shi Taira no Koreshige den (Japanese literature, collection of TAIRA no Koreshige) and Taiheiki (The Record of the Great Peace).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>戸隠の紅葉の岩屋に鬼のアジトがあり、維茂によって殲滅される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a hiding place of oni in Iwaya of autumn leaves in Togakushi and annihilated by Koreshige.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In these legends the oni have a hiding place in a cavern within the autumn leaves in Togakushi, and are annihilated by Koreshige.</e>
<cmt>訳し直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In these legends the oni have a hiding place in a cavern within the autumn leaves in Togakushi, and are annihilated by Koreshige.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>後世への影響</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Influences to later period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Influences to Later Generations</e>
<cmt>大文字を使いました。Periodをgenerationsにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Influences to Later Generations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="34">
<j>多くの場合、能の鬼は女の妄念から生ずる（例えば鐡輪 (能)、葵上、道成寺 (能)）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In many cases, distracting thoughts creates oni in Noh (for example, Kanawa (Iron Wheel), Aoi no Ue (Lady Aoi) and Dojo-ji Temple (Noh)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In many cases, oni in Noh plays are products of female obsessions (for example, Kanawa [Iron Wheel], Aoi no Ue [Lady Aoi] and Dojo-ji Temple [all Noh plays]).</e>
<cmt>訳し直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In many cases, oni in Noh plays are products of female obsessions (for example, Kanawa [Iron Wheel], Aoi no Ue [Lady Aoi] and Dojo-ji Temple [all Noh plays]).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>しかし本作では鬼が本体であって、仮に美女の姿をとっている（黒塚 (能)もそのように解釈することが可能である）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However in this Noh piece, oni is the true form and a beautiful female is assumed form (Kurotsuka (Noh) is also possible to be interpreted like wise).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However in this Noh piece, the oni are the true forms and the beautiful women their assumed forms (Kurotsuka (Noh play) may also be interpreted likewise).</e>
<cmt>単数形／複数形を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However in this Noh piece, the oni are the true forms and the beautiful women their assumed forms (Kurotsuka (Noh play) may also be interpreted likewise).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>この点、戸隠山、鬼無里村の鬼女伝説と内容的に関連しており、後者が能の影響を受けている可能性がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this point, context is related to the legend of Kijo (an ogress) in Mt. Togakushi and Kinasa-mura, and it is possible for the Noh influenced the latter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this point, the story is related to the legend of Kijo (an ogress) set in Kinasa-mura Village at Mt. Togakushi, suggesting that the latter was influenced by the Noh piece.</e>
<cmt>訳し直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For this point, the story is related to the legend of Kijo (an ogress) set in Kinasa-mura Village at Mt. Togakushi, suggesting that the latter was influenced by the Noh piece.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>後に本作をもとに近松門左衛門によって歌舞伎の時代物（作品名　色狩剣本地：もみじがりつるぎのほんち　正徳 (日本)4年）、市川團十郎 (9代目)による歌舞伎舞踊（作品名　紅葉狩　明治20年）が作られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, based on this piece, Monzaemon CHIKAMATSU composed Jidaimono (Historical drama) (Name of the piece: Momijigaritsumugi no Honchi (land of origin for Maple Viewing sword), in 1714) for Kabuki (traditional drama performed by male actors) and Kabuki Buyo (Kabuki Dance) (Name of the piece: Momijigari, in 1887) was composed by Danjuro ICHIKAWA the ninth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, based on this piece, Monzaemon CHIKAMATSU composed a Kabuki Jidaimono (Historical drama in traditional style performed by male actors) (Momijigaritsumugi no Honchi [land of origin for Maple Viewing sword], 1714) and Daniuro ICHIKAWA the ninth composed a Kabuki Buyo (Kabuki Dance) (Momijigari, 1887).</e>
<cmt>括弧が多いので説明を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, based on this piece, Monzaemon CHIKAMATSU composed a Kabuki Jidaimono (Historical drama in traditional style performed by male actors) (Momijigaritsumugi no Honchi [land of origin for Maple Viewing sword], 1714) and Daniuro ICHIKAWA the ninth composed a Kabuki Buyo (Kabuki Dance) (Momijigari, 1887).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Oxhop(id:2551), U3002(id:66126), ととりん(id:31982), Miya(id:1881), ささがに(id:228586), NekoJaNekoJa(id:23311), Qurren(id:20140), YukkeBot(id:251107), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>