<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>ハヤシライス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hayashi rice</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hayashi rice</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hayashi rice</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>ハヤシライスとは、薄切りした牛肉とタマネギをバターで炒め、赤ワインとドミグラスソースで煮たものを白飯の上にかけた料理。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hayashi rice is a dish featuring a sauce served atop white rice, with the sauce being cooked by sautéing thin pieces of beef and chopped onion with butter and stewing them with red wine and a demi-glace sauce.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hayashi rice is a dish featuring a sauce served atop white rice, with the sauce being cooked by sautéing thin pieces of beef and chopped onion with butter and stewing them with red wine and a demi-glace sauce.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hayashi rice is a dish featuring a sauce served atop white rice, the sauce of which is cooked by stir-frying thin pieces of beef and chopped onion with butter and stewing it with red wine and demi-glace sauce.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>日本発祥の料理で、代表的な洋食のひとつ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The dish, which was invented in Japan, is one of Japan&apos;s most popular Western-style dishes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The dish, which was invented in Japan, is one of Japan&apos;s most popular Western-style dishes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The dish, which was invented in Japan, is one of the Japan&apos;s most popular Western-style dishes.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>見た目はカレーライスと似ている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It resembles Japanese curry rice in appearance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It resembles Japanese curry rice in appearance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It resembles Japanese curry rice in appearance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>大阪・神戸市では「ハイシライス」、略して「ハイライ」と称する場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Osaka and Kobe, the dish is sometimes called alternatively as &quot;Haishi rice,&quot; or &quot;Hairai&quot; for short.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Osaka and Kobe, the dish is sometimes called alternatively as &quot;Haishi rice,&quot; or &quot;Hairai&quot; for short.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Osaka and Kobe, the dish is sometimes called alternatively &apos;Haishi rice,&apos; or &apos;Hairai&apos; for short.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>洋食屋では薄切りの牛肉とたまねぎを炒めてトマトピューレまたはトマトケチャップで和え、ドミグラスソースで軽く煮込んで作る事が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is common for Western-style cuisine restaurants to prepare the dish by sautéing thin pieces of beef and chopped onion with tomato puree or tomato ketchup and slightly stewing them with a demi-glace sauce.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is common for Western-style cuisine restaurants to prepare the dish by sautéing thin pieces of beef and chopped onion with tomato puree or tomato ketchup and slightly stewing them with a demi-glace sauce.</e>
<cmt>word spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is common for Western-style cuisine restaurants to prepare the dish by stir-frying thin pieces of beef and chopped onion with tomato puree or tomato ketchup and slightly stewing it with a demi-glace sauce.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>また、即席の固形ルー (食品)が市販されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, instant roux blocks (food) are available.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, instant roux blocks (food) are available.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, instant roux blocks are available.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>名前の由来</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The origin of the name</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The origin of the name</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The origin of the name</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>ハッシュドビーフ・ウィズ・ライス（Hashed beef with Rice ただし本来ケチャップは使われない）が「ハッシ・ライス」と訛ったものであるとの説、または「ハイシ・ライス」となりそれが訛って「ハヤシライス」となった説。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One belief is that the English phrase &quot;hashed beef with rice&quot; (although ketchup is not used in an original form), was changed to &quot;Hasshi rice,&quot; or, according to another version of this belief, to &quot;Haishi rice&quot; and then again altered to &quot;Hayashi rice.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One belief is that the English phrase &quot;hashed beef with rice&quot; (although ketchup is not used in an original receipe), was changed to &quot;Hasshi rice,&quot; or, according to another version of this belief, to &quot;Haishi rice&quot; and then again altered to &quot;Hayashi rice.&quot;</e>
<cmt>terminology</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One belief is that the English name &apos;hashed beef with rice&apos; (although ketchup is not used in the original recipe) was changed to &apos;Hasshi rice,&apos; or, according to another version of this belief, to &apos;Haishi rice&apos; and then again altered to &apos;Hayashi rice.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>ハヤシライスを発明した人物が林子平の子孫（実質的には子平の姉の子孫）であるという説。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another theory is that the person who invented hayashi rice was a descendant of Shihei HAYASHI (a descendant of the elder sister of Shihei, in true sense).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another theory is that the person who invented hayashi rice was a descendant of Shihei HAYASHI (a descendant of the elder sister of Shihei, in a true sense).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another theory is that the person who invented hayashi rice was a descendant of Shihei HAYASHI (virtually, a descendant of the elder sister of Shihei).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>ハヤシライスは、四足の肉ということで牛肉が受け入れられていなかった時代、このような料理を食べていたら罰が当たる、「早死にする」ということから世間でハヤシライスと呼ばれはじめたとの説。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The third theory goes that in the era when eating beef was uncommon because the meat of four-legged animas was considered a taboo, it was believed that if you had a dish like this, you would be punished and &quot;hayajini suru&quot; (you would die young), and the public came to call the dish &quot;hayashi rice.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The third theory may come from the era when eating beef was uncommon because the meat of four-legged animals was considered taboo, it was believed that if you had a dish like this, you would be punished and &quot;hayajini suru&quot; (you would die young), and the public came to call the dish &quot;hayashi rice.&quot;</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The third theory is that when eating beef was uncommon because the meat of four-legged animals was considered taboo, it was believed that if you had a dish like this, you would be punished and &apos;hayajini suru&apos; (you would die young), and the public came to call the dish &apos;hayashi rice.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>明治の日清戦争後に開けた大陸航路の港、門司港の栄町商店街にある大衆レストランが、船に乗る急ぎの客用にケチャップベースの「早いライス」、すなわちハヤシライスとして呼ばれたからという説。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yet another belief is that at Sakae shopping street in the port of Moji, a port that developed as a gateway to mainland China after the (First) Sino-Japanese War in the Meiji period, a bistro served hurrying passengers a ketchup-base rice dish, which was nicknamed &apos;hayai (fast) rice&quot; and came to be called hayashi rice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yet another belief is that at Sakae shopping street at the port of Moji, a port that developed as a gateway to mainland China after the (First) Sino-Japanese War during the Meiji period, a bistro served rushed passengers a ketchup-base rice dish, which was nicknamed &apos;hayai (fast) rice&quot; and came to be called hayashi rice.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yet another belief is that at Sakae shopping street at the port of Moji, a port that developed as a gateway to mainland China after the (First) Sino-Japanese War during the Meiji period, a bistro served rushed passengers a ketchup based rice dish, which was nicknamed &apos;hayai (fast) rice&apos; and came to be called hayashi rice.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="11">
<j>上記のような諸説ある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As can be seen, there are several beliefs about the origin of the name of the dish.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As can be seen, there are several beliefs about the origin of the name of the dish.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As can be seen from the above description, there are several beliefs about the origin of the name of the dish.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。原文「など」→「上記のような」に変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>発祥</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Birthplace</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Birthplace</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Birthplace</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="12">
<j>日本における発祥の店においては諸説あり、現在数多くの店が元祖を名乗っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are various beliefs as to the birthplace of hayashi rice, and currently many restaurants allege that they are a originator of hayashi rice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are various beliefs as to the birthplace of hayashi rice, and currently many restaurants allege that they are the originator.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are various beliefs as to the birthplace of hayashi rice, and currently many restaurants allege that they are the originator.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>『丸善百年史』には、丸善創業者の早矢仕有的（はやし ゆうてき）が野菜のごった煮に飯を添えたものを友人に饗応し、それが有名となって人にハヤシライスと称され、いつしかレストランのメニューにもなったとの説が書かれてある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An article in the &quot;Maruzen Hyakunenshi (100 Years of Maruzen)&quot; reads that Yuteki HAYASHI, the founder of Maruzen, treated to his friends a stewed vegetables dish served with rice, which became famous and came to be called &apos;hayashi rice,&apos; and the dish also appeared on the menu of a restaurant before long.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An article in the &quot;Maruzen Hyakunenshi (100 Years of Maruzen)&quot; reads that Yuteki HAYASHI, the founder of Maruzen, treated his friends to a stewed vegetable dish served with rice, that became popular and came to be called &apos;hayashi rice,&apos; and the dish also appeared on the menus of restaurants before long.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An article in the &quot;Maruzen Hyakunenshi&quot; (100 Years of Maruzen) reads that Yuteki HAYASHI, the founder of Maruzen, treated his friends to stewed vegetable dishes served with rice, which became popular and came to be called &apos;hayashi rice,&apos; and the dish also appeared on the menus of restaurants before long.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>しかし、書中ではこれをあまりに話が出来すぎていると指摘し、明治初年以来の洋食屋である神田佐久間町の三河屋にてハッシュ・ビーフが流行った事が記載されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This allegation is refuted by another article in the book, which, pointing out that this anecdote is too convenient to be valid, says that hashed beef was a popular dish at that time at Mikawaya, a Western-style restaurant located in Kanda Sakuma-cho, which was founded in the first year of the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This allegation is refuted by another article in the book, which pointing out that this anecdote is too convenient to be valid, says that hashed beef was a popular dish at that time at Mikawaya, a Western-style restaurant located in Kanda Sakuma-cho, which was founded in the first year of the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This allegation is refuted by another article in the book, which points out that this episode is too convenient to be valid, and says that hashed beef was a popular dish at that time at Mikawaya, a Western-style restaurant located in Kanda Sakuma-cho, which was founded in the first year of the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>「これとライスと合せて称したものが、ハヤシライスの語源に違いない。しかし三河屋も有的が贔屓にした料理屋であるから、間接に関係があるといえば、いえないこともあるまい」とも記載されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The article continues, &quot;There is little doubt that the hushed beef dish in question combined with rice was somehow came to be called &apos;hayashi rice,&apos; but, taking into account that Mikawaya was one of Yuteki&apos;s favorite restaurants, it is not unsafe to assume that Yuteki was indirectly involved with the birth of hayashi rice.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The article continues, &quot;There is little doubt that the hushed beef dish in question combined with rice was somehow came to be called &apos;hayashi rice,&apos; but, taking into account that Mikawaya was one of Yuteki&apos;s favorite restaurants, it is not unsafe to assume that Yuteki was indirectly involved with the birth of hayashi rice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The article continues, &apos;There is little doubt that the hashed beef dish in question combined with rice was somehow came to be called &apos;hayashi rice,&apos; but, taking into account that Mikawaya was one of Yuteki&apos;s favorite restaurants, it is not unsafe to assume that Yuteki was indirectly involved with the birth of hayashi rice.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="16">
<j>この記述と関係なく、丸善は店内のレストランでハヤシライスを「早矢仕ライス」の名で供している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Apart from these articles, a restaurant inside a Maruzen shop has served hayashi rice under the name of &quot;早矢仕 rice&quot; (Yuteki&apos;s family name &apos;HAYASHI&apos; is spelled as &apos;早矢仕&apos; in Chinese characters).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Apart from these articles, a restaurant inside a Maruzen shop served hayashi rice under the name of &quot;早矢仕 rice&quot; (Yuteki&apos;s family name &apos;HAYASHI&apos; is spelled as &apos;早矢仕&apos; in Chinese characters).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Apart from these articles, a restaurant inside a Maruzen shop served hayashi rice under the name of &quot;早矢仕 rice&quot; (Yuteki&apos;s family name &apos;HAYASHI&apos; is spelled as &apos;早矢仕&apos; in Chinese characters).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>そしてハヤシライスソースの保存食品を自社ブランドで製造販売している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Maruzen also has released canned (vacuum-packed) hayashi rice under its own brand.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Maruzen also has released canned (vacuum-packed) hayashi rice under its own brand name.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Maruzen released canned (vacuum-packed) hayashi rice under its own brand name.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>食材</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cooking ingredients</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cooking ingredients</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cooking ingredients</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="18">
<j>肉は牛肉が一般的であるが、豚肉を使う場合（なお、豚肉を使用した場合は名前が「ポークハヤシ」となる）もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Beef is commonly used, but pork is also used (in this case, the dish is called &quot;pork hayashi.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Beef is commonly used, but pork is also (in this case, the dish is called &quot;pork hayashi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar, redundancy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Beef is commonly used, but pork is used in some cases (in this case, the dish is called &apos;pork hayashi.&apos;)</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>また、マッシュルームやしめじやエリンギ、あるいは薄くスライスしたシイタケやニンジンを入れることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ingredients sometimes include button mushrooms, shimeji mushrooms, king trumpet mushrooms, or thin sliced pieces of Chinese black mushrooms or carrot.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ingredients sometimes include button mushrooms, shimeji mushrooms, king trumpet mushrooms, or thin sliced pieces of Chinese black mushrooms or carrots.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ingredients sometimes include button mushrooms, shimeji mushrooms, king trumpet mushrooms, or thin sliced pieces of Chinese black mushrooms or carrots.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>ご飯の上に、プレーンオムレツを乗せた「オムライス」などもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of variations on the dish is &apos;omurice,&apos; which features a plain omlette served atop rice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of the variations of the dish is &apos;omurice,&apos; which features a plain omlette served atop rice.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of the variations of the dish is &apos;omurice,&apos; which features a plain omlette served atop rice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>林家ライス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Raisu (Rice) HAYASHIYA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Raisu (Rice) HAYASHIYA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Raisu (Rice) HAYASHIYA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="21">
<j>落語家（三升家小勝 (6代目)門下）から一時廃業を経て漫才師（初代林家三平門下）に転じた林家ライスは、明らかにハヤシライスからの命名である（命名者はもちろん林家三平）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Raisu (Rice) HAYASHIYA, who, after a hiatus, was converted from a rakugo storyteller (a disciple of Kokatsu MIMASUYA, the 6th) to a stand-up comedian (a disciple of Sanpei HAYASHIYA, the first), was obviously inspired by hayashi rice when creating his stage name (named, of course, by Sanpei HAYASHIYA).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Raisu (Rice) HAYASHIYA, who, after a hiatus, was converted from a rakugo storyteller (a disciple of Kokatsu MIMASUYA, the 6th) to a stand-up comedian (a disciple of Sanpei HAYASHIYA, the first), was obviously inspired by hayashi rice when creating his stage name (named, of course, by Sanpei HAYASHIYA).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Raisu (Rice) HAYASHIYA, who, after a hiatus, was converted from a rakugo storyteller (a disciple of Kokatsu MIMASUYA, the 6th) to a stand-up comedian (a disciple of Sanpei HAYASHIYA, the first), was obviously named after hayashi rice (of course, by Sanpei HAYASHIYA).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>当人の人となりと落語家廃業（破門）に至る過程は談志『談志楽屋噺』（文春文庫）に書いてある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Raisu&apos;s personality together with an episode of his abandonment of (exclusion from) a rakugo storyteller career are related by &quot;Danshi Gakuya Banashi&quot; (Greenroom talk of Danshi, publisher: Bunshu Bunko) authored by Danshi (TATEKAWA).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Raisu&apos;s personality together with an episode of his abandonment of (exclusion from) the rakugo storyteller career are related by &quot;Danshi Gakuya Banashi&quot; (Greenroom Talk of Danshi, publisher: Bunshu Bunko) authored by Danshi (TATEKAWA).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Raisu&apos;s personality together with an episode of his discontinuance of (expulsion from) the rakugo storyteller career are related by &quot;Danshi Gakuya Banashi&quot; (Greenroom Talk of Danshi, publisher: Bunshu Bunko) authored by Danshi (TATEKAWA).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>なお、小勝一門も三平一門もともに桂文楽 (8代目)一門である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Incidentally, both the Kokatsu (MIMASUYA) family and the Sanpei (HAYASHIYA) family belong to the Katsura BUNRAKU (the 8th) family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Incidentally, both the Kokatsu (MIMASUYA) family and the Sanpei (HAYASHIYA) family belong to the Katsura BUNRAKU (the 8th) family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Incidentally, both the Kokatsu (MIMASUYA) family and the Sanpei (HAYASHIYA) family belong to the Katsura BUNRAKU (the 8th) family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>夫婦漫才であり、相方である妻の芸名は林家カレー子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Raisu performs a double act with his wife, whose stage name is Kareko (curry powder) HAYASHIYA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Raisu performs a double act with his wife, whose stage name is Kareko (curry powder) HAYASHIYA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Raisu performs a double act with his wife, whose stage name is Kareko (curry powder) HAYASHIYA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>長男は太神楽の翁家勝丸（太神楽曲芸協会員、落語協会員）、長女はタレントの林家まる子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Raisu&apos;s first son is a performer of &quot;Daikagura&quot; (lion dance), Katsuma OKINAYA (a member of the Daigakugra Kyokugei Kyokai group and a member of the Rakugo Kyokai association), and his first daughter is Maruko HAYASHIYA, an entertainer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Raisu&apos;s first son is a performer of &quot;Daikagura&quot; (lion dance), Katsuma OKINAYA (a member of the Daigakugra Kyokugei Kyokai group and a member of the Rakugo Kyokai association), and his first daughter is Maruko HAYASHIYA, an entertainer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Raisu&apos;s eldest son is a performer of &quot;Daikagura&quot; (lion dance), Katsuma OKINAYA (a member of the Daigakugra Kyokugei Kyokai group and a member of the Rakugo Kyokai association), and his eldest daughter is Maruko HAYASHIYA, an entertainer.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Tyuta0055(id:205797), TT(id:46431), Poe(id:16973), みなみたけむら(id:10110), BoB774(id:148281), Takoradee(id:82103), こたつ狼(id:27622), Lombroso(id:20212), マクガイア(id:33346), Aotake(id:34929), Tmonzenet(id:92869), Hiratake(id:36180), 555accele(id:85185), ホワイト・ジャック(id:204020), Baldanders(id:81163), 時野(id:71158), つきみ(id:91808), Carkuni(id:79281), 森藍亭(id:209063), 竃馬(id:102733), 釣本直紀(id:85142), 月下美人(id:116398), Fromm(id:71291), Rislimric(id:54531), Wutheringheight(id:53832), Hyolee2(id:16439), Yas(id:739), Corwin(id:973), Snowchild-152(id:265254), 1029man(id:93235), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>