<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>幣六</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Heiroku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Heiroku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Heiroku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>幣六（へいろく）は、鳥山石燕の妖怪画集『百器徒然袋』にある日本の妖怪。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Heiroku is a Japanese specter portrayed in &quot;Hyakki Tsurezure Bukuro&quot; (One hundred bags in idlenss) by Sekien TORIYAMA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A Heiroku is one of Japanese yokai (ghosts, spirits and monsters) that was portrayed in Sekien TORIYAMA&apos;s yokai art collection book: &quot;Hyakki Tsurezure Bukuro&quot; (The Bag of One Hundred Random Demons; the term &apos;hyakki&apos; in its title is a pun on the usual hyakki, replacing the character for demon which is written as &quot;鬼&quot; in Japanese with a character for vessel written as &quot;器,&quot; and sure enough, most of the yokais shown in this book are tsukumogami [a type of Japanese spirits that originate in items or artifacts that have reached their 100th birthday and become alive]).</e>
<cmt>スペルミス。補足訳。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Heiroku is one of Japanese yokai (ghosts, spirits and monsters) that was portrayed in Sekien TORIYAMA&apos;s yokai art collection book: &quot;Hyakki Tsurezure Bukuro&quot; (The Bag of One Hundred Random Demons; the term &apos;hyakki&apos; in its title is a pun on the usual hyakki, replacing the character for demon which is written as &quot;鬼&quot; in Japanese with a character for vessel written as &quot;器,&quot; and sure enough, most of the yokais shown in this book are tsukumogami [a type of Japanese spirits that originate in items or artifacts that have reached their 100th birthday and become alive]).</e>
<cmt>A Heiroku→Heiroku</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>御幣を振りかざした異形の妖怪として描かれており、付喪神の一つとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is portrayed as a strange specter brandishing a ritual wand with pleated paper, and it is regarded as a tsukumo-gami (gods to a variety of things).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is portrayed as a strange yokai brandishing a gohei (wooden Shinto ritual wand with a pair of white zigzag paper streamers), and it is regarded as a tsukumogami.</e>
<cmt>補足</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is portrayed as a strange yokai brandishing a gohei (wooden Shinto ritual wand with a pair of white zigzag paper streamers), and it is regarded as a tsukumogami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>同画集中の石燕の解説にも記述が無いため委細は不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Sekien did not leave description on the book, the details are unknown.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Sekien did not leave any description on the Heiroku in the book, details are unknown.</e>
<cmt>誤読箇所修正、補足</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Sekien did not leave any description on the Heiroku in the book, details are unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>妖怪漫画家・水木しげるらは、「事触れの紙を振りかざし、ご神託と称してデマを流し、人々を混乱に陥れる妖怪」としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Shigeru MIZUKI, specter cartoonist, et al., &quot;it is the specter who brandishes the paper of message, claiming it an oracle, and spreads false rumor to confuse people.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to some researchers including Shigeru MIZUKI, yokai cartoonist, &quot;Heiroku is a yokai which brandishes a Kotobure paper (a piece of paper with a handwritten message), claiming it an oracle, and spreads false rumors to confuse people.&quot;</e>
<cmt>補足、表現修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to some researchers including Shigeru MIZUKI, yokai cartoonist, &apos;Heiroku is a yokai which brandishes a Kotobure paper (a piece of paper with a handwritten message), claiming it an oracle, and spreads false rumors to confuse people.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot; → &apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>妖怪探訪家・村上健司は、室町時代の『百鬼夜行絵巻』にも御幣を持つ赤鬼のような妖怪があり、これがモデルである、との説を展開している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kenji MURAKAMI, a specter inquirer, has insisted that the specter was modeled on a red ogre-like specter that holds a ritual wand with pleated paper in &quot;Hyakki yagyo (Night Parade of One Hundred Demons) picture scroll&quot; of the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenji MURAKAMI, a yokai investigator, has insisted that the Heiroku should be modeled on a red ogre-like yokai that holds the gohei which is depicted in &quot;Hyakki yagyo emaki (a &apos;Night Parade of One Hundred Demons&apos; picture scroll)&quot; of the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>補足、表現修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenji MURAKAMI, a yokai investigator, has insisted that the Heiroku should be modeled on a red ogre-like yokai that holds the gohei which is depicted in &quot;Hyakki yagyo emaki&quot; (a Night Parade of One Hundred Demons&apos; picture scroll) of the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションの位置調整</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 逃亡者(id:14864), 88(id:28711), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>