<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>石州流宗猿系</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soen-kei group of Sekishu school</e>
<cmt>※「石州宗猿系」の訳は用語集から採用しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soen-kei Group of Sekishu-ryu School (a school of tea ceremony for samurai family)</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soen-kei Group of Sekishu-ryu School (a school of tea ceremony for samurai family)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>石州流宗猿系は武家茶道。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soen-kei group of Sekishu school is a group in buke sado (the tea ceremony of samurai family)</e>
<cmt>※「武家茶道」の訳は用語集から採用しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soen-kei group of Sekishu-ryu school is a group in buke sado (the tea ceremony of samurai family)</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soen-kei group of Sekishu-ryu school is a group in buke sado (the tea ceremony of samurai family)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>石州流の一派。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is one of Sekishu schools.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is one of Sekishu-ryu school.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is one of Sekishu-ryu school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>流祖片桐貞昌（貞昌）の長男片桐貞信（幼名鶴千代）が1000石の旗本に取り立てられ、下條を称し名を下條信隆にあらためておこした旗本の家系で七世片桐宗猿まで一子相伝で伝承される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a family line of hatamoto (direct retainer of the shogun) that started when Sadanobu KATAGIRI, who was called Tsuruchiyo in childhood and was the oldest son of Sadamasa KATAGIRI, the initiator of the school, was patronized by hatamoto of 1,000 koku (approximately 180 thousand liters of crop yield), and changed his name to Nobutaka SHIMOJO; It had since been inherited to Soen KATAGIRI in the seventh generation from father to only one child.</e>
<cmt>※「旗本」の訳は用語集から採用しています。※「1000石」の訳は用語集の訳をもとに作成しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The group has the lineage of Hatamoto (direct retainer of the shogun), since Sadanobu KATAGIRI (Tsuruchiyo in childhood) who was the oldest son of Sadamasa KATAGIRI, the founder of the school, was appointed to Hatamoto of 1,000 koku (approximately 180 thousand liters of crop yield) and called himself Nobutaka SHIMOJO, and had been inherited to the seventh head, Soen KATAGIRI, from father to only one child.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The group has the lineage of Hatamoto (direct retainer of the shogun), since Sadanobu KATAGIRI (Tsuruchiyo in childhood) who was the oldest son of Sadamasa KATAGIRI, the founder of the school, was appointed to Hatamoto of 1,000 koku (approximately 180 thousand liters of crop yield) and called himself Nobutaka SHIMOJO, and had been inherited to the seventh head, Soen KATAGIRI, from father to only one child.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>昭和初期までただ石州流と称していたが、石州系他派と区別するため七世の信方の茶号宗猿より流派名をとり石州流茶道宗猿系（せきしゅうりゅうちゃどうそうえんけい）と称している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It had been called just Sekishu-ryu until the early Showa period, but to distinguish itself from other schools of Sekishu-ryu, it took its name from the title of Nobukata in the seventh generation, Soen, and changed its name to Sekishu-ryu chado Soen kei (Japanese tea ceremony Soen-kei group of Sekishu school).</e>
<cmt>※「石州流茶道宗猿系」の訳は用語集から採用しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It had been called just Sekishu-ryu school until the early Showa period, but to distinguish itself from other schools of Sekishu-ryu school, it took its name from the title of Nobukata in the seventh head, Soen, and changed its name to Sekishu-ryu chado Soen kei (Japanese tea ceremony Soen-kei group of Sekishu-ryu school).</e>
<cmt>用語などを変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It had been called just Sekishu-ryu school until the early Showa period, but to distinguish itself from other schools of Sekishu-ryu school, it took its name from the title of Nobukata in the seventh head, Soen, and changed its name to Sekishu-ryu chado Soen kei (Japanese tea ceremony Soen-kei group of Sekishu-ryu school).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>九世磯貝宗和の門人より石州流片桐宗猿派が分派している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soen KATAGIRI&apos;s group of Sekishu school was started out by disciples of Sowa ISOGAI in the ninth generation.</e>
<cmt>※「石州流片桐宗猿派」の訳は用語集から採用しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soen KATAGIRI&apos;s group of Sekishu-ryu school was started out by disciples of Sowa ISOGAI in the ninth head.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soen KATAGIRI&apos;s group of Sekishu-ryu school was started out by disciples of Sowa ISOGAI in the ninth head.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Mymelo(id:122034), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), 松茸(id:27535), Vvawavv(id:82129), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>