<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>偽銘</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gimei (counterfeit inscription)</e>
<cmt>Gimei (a false signature)→より適切な訳語と思われる→Gimei counterfeit inscription に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gimei (counterfeit inscription)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gimei (counterfeit inscription)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>偽銘（ぎめい）とは、本来の作者とは異なる人物の名が入れられた銘のことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gimei (counterfeit inscription) is an inscribed name of a person other than the original creator.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gimei (counterfeit inscription) is an inscribed name of a person other than the original creator.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gimei (counterfeit inscription) is an inscribed name of a person other than the original creator.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>日本刀、陶磁器、茶道具等の古美術品に付されることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gimei is often inscribed in antiques such as Japanese swords, ceramic ware, tea utensils.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gimei is often inscribed in antiques such as Japanese swords, ceramic ware, tea utensils.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gimei is often inscribed in antiques such as Japanese swords, ceramic ware, tea utensils.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>日本刀</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese sword</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese sword</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese sword</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>あらゆる古美術品には偽物が混在しており、日本刀も伝来品には偽物が多いことは玄人の間では常識となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Various imitations coexist with various antiques, and experts know that many Japanese imitation swords from other countries exist.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。伝来品→他国からの伝来と考え処理しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Various imitations coexist with various antiques, and experts know that many Japanese imitation swords from other countries exist.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Various imitations coexist with various antiques, and experts know that many Japanese imitation swords from other countries exist.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>日本刀は茶器と違って、伝来の事実ではなく、「正真」であることこそが重要とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Unlike tea utensils for which the fact of introduction is important, it is important for Japanese swords to be `real.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unlike tea utensils for which the fact of introduction is important, it is important for Japanese swords to be `real.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unlike tea utensils for which the fact of introduction is important, it is important for Japanese swords to be &apos;real.&apos;</e>
<cmt>全角の’を半角に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>古刀の偽銘</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gimei of old sword</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gimei of old sword</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gimei of old sword</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>相州上工の作は特徴ある作行きである事から、一通り知識がある場合は見破りやすい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the style of the old swords created by 相州上工 is characteristic, it is easy for someone with certain knowledge to detect the imitation.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。相州上工→定訳・読み方不明のため原文のままとしています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the style of the old swords created by 相州上工 is characteristic, it is easy for someone with certain knowledge to detect the imitation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the style of the old swords created by the Soshu artisans is characteristic, it is easy for someone with certain knowledge to detect the imitation.</e>
<cmt>相州上工→「相州の上工」の意なので、Soshu artisanとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>古備前（在銘）、古青江などの各代の特定もしくは真偽（当時の偽物）は専門家でも不可能である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for the old swords such as the old Bizen (with inscription), the old Aoe, even an expelt is not able to determine its generation or to judge its authenticity (old swords imitated at that time).</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。古青江→定訳不明ですが→the old Aoeと訳出しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for the old swords such as the old Bizen (with inscription), the old Aoe, even an expert is not able to determine its generation or to judge its authenticity (old swords imitated at that time).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for the old swords such as the old Bizen (with inscription), the old Aoe, even an expert is not able to determine its generation or to judge its authenticity (old swords imitated at that time).</e>
<cmt>expert文字を訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>特に平安後期の作は技量が平均的であり、しかも厄介なことに代があるため銘振りが一定していない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In particular, there is no difference in technique among the old swords created in the latter half of the Hein period, and the way of inscribing is not consistent due to the existence of generations.</e>
<cmt>代→定訳不明ですが→generation と訳出しています。銘振り→定訳不明ですが→the way of inscribingと訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In particular, there is no difference in technique among the old swords created in the latter half of the Heian period, and the way of inscribing is not consistent due to the existence of generations.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In particular, there is no difference in technique among the old swords created in the latter half of the Heian period, and the way of inscribing is not consistent due to the existence of generations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>また当時の偽物も混在しているのが実状である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides, imitation old swords created at that time also coexist.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides, imitation old swords created at that time also coexist.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides, imitation old swords created at that time also coexist.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>鎌倉期迄の当時の偽物、時代贋（じだいにせ）は、専門家でも看破することはできない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even the expert is not able to detect an imitation old sword created in the period until the Kamakura period, called the jidainise (imitation created at that time).</e>
<cmt>時代贋→定訳不明ですが→jidainise (fake one created at that time)と訳出しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even an expert is not able to detect an imitation old sword created in the period until the Kamakura period, called the jidainise (imitation created at that time).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even an expert is not able to detect an imitation old sword created in the period until the Kamakura period, called the jidainise (imitation created at that time).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>但し、室町期以降の古刀を含む新刀、新々刀を鎌倉期の刀に見せかけたもの等は地鉄、姿から看破できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, new swords including the old swords after the Muromachi period, and the very new sword pretended to be the sword in the Kamakura period can be detected by its material, iron and figure.</e>
<cmt>地鉄→定訳不明のため暫定的に→material, iron としています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, new swords including the old swords after the Muromachi period, and the very new sword claimed to be a sword from the Kamakura period, can be detected by its material, iron and figure.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, new swords including the old swords after the Muromachi period, and the very new sword claimed to be a sword from the Kamakura period, can be detected by its material, iron and figure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>ましてや現代刀工による鎌倉期の写しが国宝に指定されているなどというまことしやかな噂は荒唐無稽である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A glossy rumor about the imitation sword created by a sword craftsman today is designated as a national treasure is absolutely ridiculous.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A glossy rumor about an imitation sword created by a sword craftsman that today is designated as a national treasure, is absolutely ridiculous.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A glossy rumor about an imitation sword created by a sword craftsman that today is designated as a national treasure, is absolutely ridiculous.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>大磨上無銘であろうとも、古刀の場合は地鉄の特徴、匂い口が決定的に異なる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even if no inscription is carved on the sword, the feature of iron and the smell of the old sword is definitely different from a new one.</e>
<cmt>匂い口→定訳不明ですが→smell としています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even if no inscription is carved on the sword, the feature of iron and the smell of the old sword is definitely different from a new one.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even if no inscription is carved on the sword, the feature of iron and the Nioikuchi (a part of a sword where light seems to stand out) of the old sword is definitely different from a new one.</e>
<cmt>匂い口→刃紋のひときわ輝く部分の意。調査したところ、「Nioikuchi」と表記されていましたので Nioikuchi (a part of a sword where light seems to stand out)としました。[https://www.aoi-art.com/auction/en/auction.cgi?acc=disp&amp;no=1273196846&amp;t=1213703271]</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="14">
<j>例えば新刀最上作である堀川国広が相州上工の作を写しているが、鎌倉期の地鉄、匂い口と、慶長元和期の綺麗な新刀地鉄とでは時代の差が歴然としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For instance, Kunihiro HORIKAWA who is the best new sword craftsman imitated the work of 相州上工, but the difference in periods, in the iron quality and smell, between the one in the Kamakura period and the one whose iron is beautiful in Keicho Genwa era is obvious</e>
<cmt>新刀最上作→定訳不明ですが→</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For instance, Kunihiro HORIKAWA who was the best new sword craftsman, imitated the work of 相州上工, but the difference in periods, in the iron quality and smell, between that in the Kamakura period and those whose iron is beautiful in the Keicho Genwa era is obvious</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For instance, Kunihiro HORIKAWA who was the best new sword craftsman, imitated the work of Soshu artisans, but the difference in periods, in the iron quality and the Nioikuchi, between that in the Kamakura period and those whose iron is beautiful in the Keicho Genwa era is obvious</e>
<cmt>匂い口→Nioikuchi相州上工→Soshu artisans</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>また鎬地が柾がかり、帽子は新刀の小丸となり、正真作と比べれば一目瞭然である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinogichi (ridge) of the sword is with masame (straight grain), and the cutting part is same as komaru (style of a cutting part) of a new sword, which makes it easy to identify at a glance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinogichi (ridge) of the sword is with masame (straight grain), and the cutting part is the same as komaru (style of a cutting part) of a new sword, which makes it easy to identify at a glance.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinogichi (ridge) of the sword is with masame (straight grain), and the cutting part is the same as komaru (style of a cutting part) of a new sword, which makes it easy to identify at a glance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="16">
<j>伝来された贋作の一例</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A sample of introduced counterfeit sword</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A sample of introduced counterfeit sword</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A sample of introduced counterfeit sword</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="17">
<j>酒天童子安綱 古押し型と相違</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shuten Doji Yasutsuna Differs from the old pattern</e>
<cmt>古押し型→定訳不明ですが→the old pattern としています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shuten Doji Yasutsuna Differs from the old pattern</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shuten Doji Yasutsuna: Difference from the old oshigata (mold)</e>
<cmt>押し型→Oshigata (mold):補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="18">
<j>備前三郎国宗 古来（鎌倉中期）より偽物の存在が確認されている</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bizen saburo kunimune Imitation swords have been confirmed since the ancient times (the middle of the Kamakura period)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bizen saburo kunimune imitation swords have been confirmed since ancient times (the middle of the Kamakura period)</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bizen Saburo Kunimune: Imitation swords have been confirmed since ancient times (the middle of the Kamakura period).</e>
<cmt>:補足しました。Saburo Kunimune、Imitation大文字にしました。ピリオド補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="19">
<j>白山権現景光 白山権現信仰に問題あり 昭和初期の刀剣界で論争</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hakusan gongen kagemitsu A controversy about the belief in Hakusan gongen in the sword industry occurred in the early Showa period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hakusan gongen kagemitsu: A controversy about the belief in Hakusan gongen in the sword industry occurred in the early Showa period</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hakusan Gongen Kagemitsu: A controversy about the belief in Hakusan Gongen in the sword industry occurred in the early Showa period</e>
<cmt>Hakusan Gongen Kagemitsuに訂正しました。不要なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="20">
<j>古刀間、古刀－新刀間で偽銘が行われやすい刀工、流派を数種挙げておく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">List up several sword craftsmen and schools that often are subject to gimei between an old sword and a new sword, or between old swords.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">List up several sword craftsmen and schools that often are subject to gimei between an old sword and a new sword, or between old swords.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">List up several sword craftsmen and schools that often are subject to gimei between an old sword and a new sword, or between old swords.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="21">
<j>基本的に技術関係が深い（移住、修行、子孫等）一派の間で行われやすい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Basically, gimei is often used within the school with close technical relationship (immigration, training, descendant, etc.).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Basically, gimei is often used within the school with close technical relationships (immigration, training, descendant, etc.).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Basically, gimei is often used within the school with close technical relationships (immigration, training, descendant, etc.).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="22">
<j>美濃物については、鎬地柾がかり、沸出来となるため、新刀からの化かしが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for mino, it is with masame (straight grain), and 沸出来, it is often the imitation of a new sword.</e>
<cmt>美濃物→定訳不明ですが→mino と訳出しています。沸出来→定訳不明のため原文のままとしています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for mino, it is with masame (straight grain), and 沸出来, it is often the imitation of a new sword.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for the Mino swords, it is with masame (straight grain), and Nie deki (a type of temper line), it is often the imitation of a new sword.</e>
<cmt>美濃物→（美濃の刀工が鍛えた刀の総称）the Mino sword としました。沸出来→Nie deki (a type of temper line) としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="23">
<j>また、新刀、新々刀期を通して、志津写しが人気だったため、大磨上のものにはよくよく注意が必要である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Copy of shizu was popular throughout the period from the new sword to the very new sword, therefore, a great deal of attentions should be paid to the sword with major grind up.</e>
<cmt>後列とは本来一文であると思われるため結合しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Copies of shizu were popular throughout the period from the new sword to the very new sword, therefore, a great deal of attention should be paid to the sword with major grind up.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Copies of shizu were popular throughout the period from the new sword to the very new sword, therefore, a great deal of attention should be paid to the sword with major grind up.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="24">
<j>新刀からの贋作については、鎬地の鍛え目、帽子の焼き具合の２点を注視すれば看破するきっかけになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To detect a counterfeit new sword, focusing on two points; the strength of shinogichi (ridge) and the sharpness of a cutting part, would be a clue.</e>
<cmt>後列とは本来一文であると思われるため結合しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To detect a counterfeit new sword, focusing on two points; the strength of shinogichi (ridge) and the sharpness of the cutting part, would be a clue.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To detect a counterfeit new sword, focusing on two points; the strength of shinogichi (ridge) and the sharpness of the cutting part, would be a clue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="25">
<j>新刀、新々刀の偽銘作</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">New swords and the very new swords with Gimei</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">New swords and the very new swords with Gimei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">New swords and the very new swords with Gimei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>新刀以降、地鉄に顕著な全国的差異がないことから、弟子の作を師匠の作等、数多く診られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Using Gimei, including the case of imitating the work by a student as the work by a teacher, is common; there is no obvious difference in iron quality after an appearance of new sword.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Using Gimei, including the case of imitating the work by a student as the work by a teacher, is common; there is no obvious difference in iron quality after an appearance of new sword.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Using Gimei, including the case of imitating the work by a student as the work by a teacher, is common; there is no obvious difference in iron quality after an appearance of new sword.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>虎徹、津田越前守助広、井上真改、源清麿が著名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kotetsu, Tsuda Echizen no kami Sukehiro (Governor of Echizen Province Sukehiro TSUDA), Shinkai INOUE, MINAMOTO no Kiyomaro are famous.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kotetsu, Tsuda Echizen no kami Sukehiro (Governor of Echizen Province Sukehiro TSUDA), Shinkai INOUE, MINAMOTO no Kiyomaro are famous.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kotetsu, Tsuda Echizen no kami Sukehiro (Governor of Echizen Province Sukehiro TSUDA), Shinkai INOUE, MINAMOTO no Kiyomaro are famous.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>そのため銘振りを変えたり、中茎の棟を丸棟にしたり肉を持たせたり、隠し鏨を入れたり、化粧鑢を複雑にしたりと、様々な工夫が見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Various ideas; changing the way of inscribing, making the back of haft round, making it thick, or inscribing a secret mark, are found.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Various ideas; changing the way of inscribing, making the back of the haft round, making it thick, or inscribing a secret mark, are found.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Various ideas; changing the way of inscribing, making the back of the haft round, making it thick, or inscribing a secret mark, are found.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>当時に行われた偽銘は、中茎、銘の研究が進んだ今日においては中茎を見るだけでも比較的容易に見破ることが出来る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the research on the haft and signature was advanced, it is relatively easy to identify the sword with Gimei created in the ancient times even with a glance of the haft.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the research on the haft and signature was advanced, it is relatively easy to identify the sword with Gimei created in the ancient times even with a glance of the haft.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the research on the haft and signature was advanced, it is relatively easy to identify the sword with Gimei created in the ancient times even with a glance of the haft.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="30">
<j>現代刀工による新々刀の偽銘作</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The very new sword with Gimei created by a sword craftsman today</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The very new sword with Gimei created by a sword craftsman today</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The very new sword with Gimei created by a sword craftsman today</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>廃刀令以降、刀工は困窮し、中には偽銘を始めるものもいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the decree banning the wearing of sword was promulgated, some sword craftsmen straitened and started making swords with Gimei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the decree banning the wearing of swords was promulgated, some sword craftsmen straitened and started making swords with Gimei.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the decree banning the wearing of swords was promulgated, some sword craftsmen straitened and started making swords with Gimei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>殊に、刀剣界全体が困窮していたため、その細工は精緻を極める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the entire sword industry was straitened, their sword work was extremely refined.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the entire sword industry was straitened, their sword work was extremely refined.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the entire sword industry was straitened, their sword work was extremely refined.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>最も著名な偽銘師は直光、通称「鍛治平」である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The most famous sword craftsman who implemented Gimei was commonly called the`Kajihei.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The most famous sword craftsman who implemented Gimei was commonly called the`Kajihei.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The most famous sword craftsman who implemented Gimei was commonly called the &apos;Kajihei.&apos;</e>
<cmt>全角の’を半角にしました。スペース補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>鍛治平は古刀、新刀、新々刀問わず、それらしい刀を選んでは偽銘を施した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kajihei selected swords from all swords; the old, the new, or the very new swords, and inscribed Gimei to them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kajihei selected swords from all swords; the old, the new, or the very new swords, and inscribed Gimei to them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kajihei selected swords from all swords; the old, the new, or the very new swords, and inscribed Gimei to them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>後に皇室技芸員となる、月山貞一も得意の彫りで一竿子忠綱をはじめ偽銘を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sadakazu GASSAN who later became a member of Imperial Household Performance Art also inscribed Gimei including Ikkanshi Tadatsuna, with excellent skills.</e>
<cmt>皇室技芸員→定訳不明ですが→a member of Imperial Household Performance Art と訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sadakazu GASSAN who later became a member of Imperial Household Performance Art also inscribed Gimei including Ikkanshi Tadatsuna, with excellent skills.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sadakazu GASSAN who later became a member of Imperial Household Performance Art also inscribed Gimei including Ikkanshi Tadatsuna, with excellent skills.</e>
<cmt>不要なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="36">
<j>下って現代においては、押形や写真集により、刀工正真銘が多く知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today, 刀工正真銘 is widely known through presses or photo books.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, 刀工正真銘 is widely known through publications or photo books.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, the real inscription of sword craftsman is widely known through Oshigata (mold) or photo books.</e>
<cmt>刀工正真銘→the real inscription of sword craftsman としました。押し型→Oshigata (mold)に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>現代刀等を無銘にして、正真銘のコピーを中茎に貼り付け偽銘を切る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A copy of 正真銘 is marked to the haft of the modern sword removing its inscription.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A copy of 正真銘 is marked to the haft of the modern sword removing its inscription.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A copy of real inscription is marked to the haft of the modern sword removing its inscription.</e>
<cmt>正真銘→the real inscriptionとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>然しながら、現代における偽名は、中茎の錆色が不自然で、また地鉄も異なることから看破出来る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, today, it is easy to detect a sword to which Gimei was inscribed; the color of rust on the haft with Gimei was unnatural, and the iron used is also different from the ancient times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, today, it is easy to detect a sword to which Gimei was inscribed; the color of rust on the haft with Gimei was unnatural, and the iron used is also different from the ancient times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, today, it is easy to detect a sword to which Gimei was inscribed; the color of rust on the haft with Gimei was unnatural, and the iron used is also different from the ancient times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="39">
<j>刀の偽銘、贋作を見極めるには、五箇伝、各時代の姿（手持ちの重さ）、地鉄、焼き刃の特徴（匂い口、帽子）、中茎（姿、鑢目、棟仕上げ、目釘孔、銘の位置、銘そのもの）に精通していなければ困難である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To identify Gimei or counterfeit sword, one must be familiar with 五箇伝, figures in each period (weight of temochi; haft), iron, features of a blade (smell, cutting part), haft (figure, yasurime (grinding grid mark), finished way of the back of haft, hole (mekugi holes), the position of inscription, inscription itself).</e>
<cmt>五箇伝→定訳不明のため原文のままとしています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To identify Gimei or counterfeit swords, one must be familiar with 五箇伝, figures in each period (weight of temochi; haft), iron, features of a blade (smell, cutting part), haft (figure, yasurime (grinding grid mark), finished way of the back of haft, hole (mekugi holes), the position of inscription, inscription itself).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To identify Gimei or counterfeit swords, one must be familiar with the Gokaden (classification of Japanese swords), figures in each period (weight of temochi; haft), iron, features of a blade (Nioikuchi, cutting part), haft (figure, yasurime [grinding grid mark], finished way of the back of haft, hole [mekugi holes], the position of inscription, inscription itself).</e>
<cmt>五箇伝→Gokaden (classification of Japanese swords) としました。匂い口→Nioikuchi括弧内括弧を[]に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>その為には、正真正銘の刀と直接対峙し、自分なりに見極め処を覚えていく事が必要となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is required to face real swords and continue to learn key points for detecting real swords on one&apos;s own.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is required to face real swords and continue to learn key points for detecting real swords on one&apos;s own.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is required to face real swords and continue to learn key points for detecting real swords on one&apos;s own.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Su-no-G(id:52744), こぶまき(id:38278), Rokurokusanjin(id:285204), Aotake(id:34929), Metatron(id:64025), D.h(id:79056), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>