<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>幸流</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ko-ryu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ko school</e>
<cmt>school で統一しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ko school</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>幸流（こう-りゅう）は能楽小鼓方の一流派。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ko-ryu is one of the Ko-tsuzumi (small drum) schools for Noh.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ko school is one of the schools of kotsuzumi-kata (small hand drum players) in Nohgaku (the art of Noh).</e>
<cmt>他の記事と統一しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ko school is one of the schools of kotsuzumi-kata (small hand drum players) in Nohgaku (the art of Noh).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>かつては幸五郎次郎流とも称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It used to be called Ko-goro-jiro ryu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It used to be called Kogorojiro school.</e>
<cmt>school で統一しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It used to be called Kogorojiro school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>また大鼓方にも幸流と呼ばれる流儀があった（威徳流参照）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, the O-tsuzumi players used to have a school called Ko-ryu. (see Itoku-ryu)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, the otsuzumi-kata (large hand drum players) performers used to have a school called Ko school (see Itoku school).</e>
<cmt>school で統一しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, the otsuzumi-kata (large hand drum players) performers used to have a school called Ko school (see Itoku school).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>解説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Explanation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Description</e>
<cmt>他の記事と統一しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Description</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>家伝によれば、幸家はもと北面の武士として後花園天皇に仕え、後に幸正忠が「宇治幸大夫」と名のって金春流のツレとなったと伝えるが、本来は宇治市猿楽の大夫であった者が、後に勢力を失って金春座にツレ・囃子方などとして参加したものであるらしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the story handed down to the Ko family, the family served Emperor Gohanazono as Hokumen-no-bushi (guards who had their office in the north of the palace), and later Masatada KO became an associate actor called tsure in the Konparu troupe of Noh under the name of &apos;Ujikodayu,&apos; but in fact, it is said that an actor of Sarugaku (a form of theater) troupe in Uji, losing his influence, joined the Konparu troupe as an associate actor and music player.</e>
<cmt>正忠の読み方が不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the story handed down to the Ko family, the family served Emperor Gohanazono as Hokumen no bushi (the Imperial Palace Guards for the north side), and later Masatada KO became a tsure (an associate actor) in the Konparu school of Noh under the name of &apos;Uji Ko dayu,&apos; but in fact, it is said that an actor of Sarugaku (a form of theater) troupe in Uji joined the Konparu troupe as a tsure and hayashikata (people who play hayashi, or the musical accompaniment) after he lost his influence.</e>
<cmt>school で統一しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the story handed down to the Ko family, the family served Emperor Gohanazono as Hokumen no bushi (the Imperial Palace Guards for the north side), and later Masatada KO became a tsure (an associate actor) in the Konparu school of Noh under the name of &apos;Uji Ko dayu,&apos; but in fact, it is said that an actor of Sarugaku (a form of theater) troupe in Uji joined the Konparu troupe as a tsure and hayashikata (people who play hayashi, or the musical accompaniment) after he lost his influence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>宇治の猿楽座はもと幸・藤若・梅松・守菊の四座であったが、早くも天文年間には廃絶し、正忠の子四郎次郎忠能は小鼓の名人宮増親賢に師事し、また金春禅鳳に能を学ぶなどして、金春座で活躍した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were four Sarugaku troupes in Uji - Ko, Fujiwaka, Umematsu and Shugiku - but they were abolished between 1532 and 1554, and Masatada&apos;s son, Shiro-jiro-tadayoshi studied under Chikakata MIYAMASU, who was a master of Ko-tsuzumi, learned Noh from Zenpo KONPARU, and then played an active part in the Konparu troupe.</e>
<cmt>梅松・守菊の読み方が不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were four Sarugaku troupes in Uji - Ko, Fujiwaka, Umematsu (梅松) and Shugiku (守菊) - but they were abolished between 1532 and 1554, and Masatada&apos;s son, Shirojiro Tadayoshi studied under Chikakata MIYAMASU, who was a master of kotsuzumi, learned Noh from Zenpo KONPARU, and then played an active part in the Konparu troupe.</e>
<cmt>人名を一部修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were four Sarugaku troupes in Uji - Ko, Fujiwaka, Umematsu (梅松) and Shugiku (守菊) - but they were abolished between 1532 and 1554, and Masatada&apos;s son, Shirojiro Tadayoshi studied under Chikakata MIYAMASU, who was a master of kotsuzumi, learned Noh from Zenpo KONPARU, and then played an active part in the Konparu troupe.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>宮増が後嗣を欠いたまま没すると、忠能は兄弟子の観世豊次（小鼓方観世流の祖）と座を分って世襲し、小鼓方幸流の祖となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Miyamasu died with no successor, Tadayoshi became the originator of the Ko school of ko-tsuzumi players, separately from his senior pupil, Toyotsugu KANZE (the originator of the Kanze school).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Miyamasu died with no successor, Tadayoshi became the originator of the Ko school of kotsuzumi-kata, separately from his senior pupil, Toyotsugu KANZE (the originator of the kotsuzumi-kata Kanze school).</e>
<cmt>小鼓方　を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Miyamasu died with no successor, Tadayoshi became the originator of the Ko school of kotsuzumi-kata, separately from his senior pupil, Toyotsugu KANZE (the originator of the kotsuzumi-kata Kanze school).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>子の二世五郎次郎正能は名人として知られ、『幸正能口伝書』を残している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His son, the second head of the school, Goro-jiro-masayoshi was a well known master of ko-tsuzumi and he wrote &quot;Ko Masayoshi Kuensho&quot; (a book on his skill)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His son, the second head of the school, Gorojiro Masayoshi was a well known master of kotsuzumi and he wrote &quot;Ko Masayoshi Kudensho&quot; (a book on his skill).</e>
<cmt>人名を一部修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His son, the second head of the school, Gorojiro Masayoshi was a well known master of kotsuzumi and he wrote &quot;Ko Masayoshi Kudensho&quot; (a book on his skill).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>正能の後は嫡孫清次郎了能が幼少であったため、二男小左衛門一宗が三世を襲い、後に了能は幸清次郎家（幸清流）を興して別家した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Masayoshi, since his grandson, Seijiro-satoyoshi was too young to succeed, his second son, Kozaemon-kazumune assumed the third headship of the Ko school, and later Satoyoshi started the Ko Seijiro family (Kosei school) separately.</e>
<cmt>「了能」「小左衛門一宗」の読み方がが不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Masayoshi, since his grandson, Seijiro Satoyoshi (清次郎了能) was too young to succeed, his second son, Kozaemon Kazumune (小左衛門一宗) assumed the third headship of the Ko school, and later Satoyoshi started the Ko Seijiro family (Kosei school) separately.</e>
<cmt>読みが不明な人名に漢字を追記しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Masayoshi, since his grandson, Seijiro Satoyoshi (清次郎了能) was too young to succeed, his second son, Kozaemon Kazumune (小左衛門一宗) assumed the third headship of the Ko school, and later Satoyoshi started the Ko Seijiro family (Kosei school) separately.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>江戸時代には宗家が金春流の座付となったほか、一宗の二男が興した幸清五郎家も宝生流の座付として活躍した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Edo Period, the head family of the school belonged exclusively to the Konparu school, and the Ko Seigoro family, which Kazumune&apos;s second son started, belonged exclusively to the Hosho school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Edo period, the head family of the school belonged exclusively to the Konparu school, and furthermore, the Ko Seigoro family, which Kazumune&apos;s second son started, also flourished by performing exclusively for the Hosho school.</e>
<cmt>一部翻訳を補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Edo period, the head family of the school belonged exclusively to the Konparu school, and furthermore, the Ko Seigoro family, which Kazumune&apos;s second son started, also flourished by performing exclusively for the Hosho school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>また、一時大鼓方威徳流が幸流のアシライ鼓となって幸流と呼ばれたことがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Once the Itoku school of O-tsuzumi players became part of the Ko-ryu with certain rhythm called Ashirai-tsuzumi and so it was also called Ko-ryu.</e>
<cmt>アシライの意味が不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Once the Itoku school of otsuzumi-kata became part of the Ko school by performing as ashirai tsuzumi (accompanying hand drum), which was also called Ko school.</e>
<cmt>school で統一しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Once the Itoku school of otsuzumi-kata became part of the Ko school by performing as ashirai tsuzumi (accompanying hand drum), which was also called Ko school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>幕末期には十二世正員の代に義兄の正孚とのあいだで宗家継承の争いがおこり、維新後の能楽衰退と相まって宗家の権威が衰える一因となったが、高弟生駒秀三郎、三須錦吾（一時芸事総取締）らによって流儀の伝統は守られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the last days of the Edo Period, the 12th head Masakazu had a dispute over succession with his brother-in-law, 正孚, and together with the decline after the Meiji Restoration, it became one of the causes of the decline of the authority of the head family of the school, but the tradition of the school was preserved by senior pupils, Shuzaburo IKOMA, Kingo MISU (general director of entertainment for a while) and others.</e>
<cmt>「正孚」の読み方が不明です。。また、「一時芸事総取締」が何の組織の役員なのか調べられませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the last days of the Edo period, the 12th head Masakazu had a dispute over succession with his brother-in-law, Seifu (正孚), and together with the decline of Nohgaku after the Meiji Restoration, it became one of the causes of the decline of the authority of the head family of the school, but the tradition of the school was preserved by senior pupils, Shuzaburo IKOMA, Kingo MISU (general director of entertainment for a while) and others.</e>
<cmt>正孚→せいふ　と読むのではないかと推測し、漢字も追記して表記しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the last days of the Edo period, the 12th head Masakazu had a dispute over succession with his brother-in-law, Seifu (正孚), and together with the decline of Nohgaku after the Meiji Restoration, it became one of the causes of the decline of the authority of the head family of the school, but the tradition of the school was preserved by senior pupils, Shuzaburo IKOMA, Kingo MISU (general director of entertainment for a while) and others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>宗家は十五世に後嗣を欠いたため、三須の孫悟朗が養子となって相続した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the head family, as the 15th did not have a successor, Misu&apos;s grandson, Goro was adopted and succeeded to lead the school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the head family, as the 15th did not have a successor, Misu&apos;s grandson, Goro was adopted and succeeded to lead the school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the head family, as the 15th did not have a successor, Misu&apos;s grandson, Goro was adopted and succeeded to lead the school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>戦前戦後の名人として名高い後の十六世幸祥光である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the 16th Yoshimitsu KO, who was well known as a master player.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the 16th head Yoshimitsu KO, who was well known as a master player before and after the war.</e>
<cmt>戦前戦後　を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the 16th head Yoshimitsu KO, who was well known as a master player before and after the war.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>ポ・プ・タ・チ・ツの五種類の音を打ち分け、装飾的な手組みの少ないのが特徴。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Ko-ryu, there are five different sounds, which are called &quot;po,&quot; &quot;pu,&quot; &quot;ta,&quot; &quot;chi,&quot; and &quot;tsu&quot; and the school is characterized by fewer complicated playing methods.</e>
<cmt>「装飾的な手組み」という表現を「込み入った打ち方」と解釈しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The school is characterized by the differentiation of five different sounds, which are called &quot;po,&quot; &quot;pu,&quot; &quot;ta,&quot; &quot;chi,&quot; and &quot;tsu&quot; and also by fewer complicated playing methods.</e>
<cmt>翻訳を一部変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The school is characterized by the differentiation of five different sounds, which are called &quot;po,&quot; &quot;pu,&quot; &quot;ta,&quot; &quot;chi,&quot; and &quot;tsu&quot; and also by fewer complicated playing methods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>東京、京都を地盤とし、能楽協会には20名余の役者が登録されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It performs mainly in Tokyo and Kyoto, and there are over 20 players registered in the Nohgaku Kyokai (association for Noh plays).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are based mainly in Tokyo and Kyoto, and there are over 20 players who are registered with the Nohgaku Performers&apos; Association.</e>
<cmt>他の記事と表現を統一しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are based mainly in Tokyo and Kyoto, and there are over 20 players who are registered with the Nohgaku Performers&apos; Association.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>現宗家は十七世幸正影。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The present head of the school is the 17th, Masakage KO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The present head of the school is the 17th, Masakage KO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The present head of the school is the 17th, Masakage KO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Peachkiller(id:99202), 樒(id:35770), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>