<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>出世魚</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shusseuo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shusseuo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shusseuo (fish called by different names at different stages of its growth)</e>
<cmt>補足説明を追加しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>出世魚（しゅっせうお）とは、日本において、稚魚から成魚までの魚類の成長に応じて異なる名前で呼ばれる魚のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shusseuo is a term used in Japan to refer to fishes which are called by different names depending on their growth stage from an alevin to an adult fish.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Shusseuo&quot; is a term used in Japan to refer to fishes that are called by different names depending on their growth stage, from an alevin to an adult fish.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Shusseuo&quot; is a term used in Japan to refer to fishes that are called by different names depending on their growth stage, from an alevin to an adult fish.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>江戸時代までは、武士や学者などは、元服の際や、出世に伴って名前を変える習慣があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Until the Edo period, samurais and scholars customarily changed their names upon their coming-of-age ceremonies and promotion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Until the Edo period, samurai and scholars would customarily change their names upon their coming-of-age ceremonies and promotions.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Until the Edo period, samurai and scholars would customarily change their names upon their coming-of-age ceremonies and promotions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>出世魚という呼び方は、「成長に伴って出世するように名前が変わる魚」として、これになぞらえたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term Shusseuo is originated from this custom and represents fishes whose names change as they grow as if they were promoted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term &quot;Shusseuo,&quot; which originated from this custom, represents fishes whose names change as they grow, as if they&apos;re being promoted.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term &quot;Shusseuo,&quot; which originated from this custom, represents &apos;fishes whose names change as they grow, as if they&apos;re being promoted.&apos;</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>縁起のよい魚として扱われ、めでたい席や門出を祝う席などの料理として好んで使われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These fishes are treated as a lucky fish and used as an ingredient of food for happy events and celebrations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These fishes are considered to bear good luck and are used as ingredients in foods for happy events and celebrations.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These fishes are considered to bear good luck and are used as ingredients in foods for happy events and celebrations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>ブリ、スズキ (魚)、ボラなどが有名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Buri (adult yellowtail), Suzuki (seaperch), Bora (striped mullet), etc. are famous as Shusseuo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Buri (adult yellowtail), Suzuki (sea perch), Bora (striped mullet), etc., are famous as Shusseuo.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Buri (adult yellowtail), Suzuki (sea perch), Bora (striped mullet), etc., are famous as Shusseuo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>由来</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Origin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Origin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Origin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>同じ種類の魚が、違う名前で呼ばれる要因にはいくつかあるが、大きさや外見の違い、生息域や生態の変化などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fishes of the same kind may be called by different names depending on the size, the appearance, the area to live, the change of behavioral mode, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fishes of the same kind may be called by different names depending on their size, appearance, area of habitation, change of behavioral mode, etc.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fishes of the same kind may be called by different names depending on their size, appearance, area of habitation, change of behavioral mode, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>例えば、成長の早い魚類では、生まれた当年の魚、2年目の魚、3年目の魚…が、同じ時期に漁獲されると、それぞれ体の大きさが一回り以上異なるので、それらをはっきりと大きさで区別できることがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rapidly growing fishes of the same kind which differ in age can be easily distinguished by the size from one another when they are caught because the size may become more than double within a year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rapidly growing fishes of the same kind that differ in age can be easily distinguished from one another by size when they&apos;re caught, because the size may more than double within a year.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rapidly growing fishes of the same kind that differ in age can be easily distinguished from one another by size when they&apos;re caught, because the size may more than double within a year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>この際、それらの用途や味など、商品価値が異なる場合には、これらを同じ名前で呼ぶことは必ずしも便利ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Here, if their commercial value, such as application or taste, is different depending on the age, it is not necessarily convenient to call them by the same name.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Here, if their commercial value, in terms of application or taste, is different depending on the age, it isn&apos;t necessarily convenient to call them by the same name.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Here, if their commercial value, in terms of application or taste, is different depending on the age, it isn&apos;t necessarily convenient to call them by the same name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>逆に、それらの違いが、年齢の違うだけで同種の魚なのか、あるいは別の種類なのかを判断するのがそもそも難しい場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, it is sometimes difficult to determine if the difference in commercial value is because of the difference in age or difference in species.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, it&apos;s sometimes difficult to determine whether the difference in commercial value is because of the difference in age or the difference in species.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, it&apos;s sometimes difficult to determine whether the difference in commercial value is because of the difference in age or the difference in species.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>どちらの場合でも、漁業や流通の現場では、必ずしも同種か別種かを区別する必要があるとは限らないため、便宜的に異なる名前で取り扱われる場合がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In any case, because it is not necessarily important to distinguish if they belong to the same species or not when they are caught and distributed to retail stores, they may be called by different names for convenience.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In any case, because it isn&apos;t necessarily important to distinguish whether they belong to the same species or not when they&apos;re caught and distributed to retail stores, they may be called by different names for the sake of convenience.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In any case, because it isn&apos;t necessarily important to distinguish whether they belong to the same species or not when they&apos;re caught and distributed to retail stores, they may be called by different names for the sake of convenience.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="11">
<j>出世魚の場合、学術的な用途で通常用いられる和名は、その魚のいくつかの呼び名のうちの一つで、多くの場合、その魚の成熟したときの名前である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the case of Shusseuo, the Japanese name which is used for academic purposes is merely one of their names and frequently is the name which is used when they are matured.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the case of Shusseuo, the Japanese name that is used for academic purposes is merely one of their names and frequently is the name used once they&apos;ve matured.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the case of Shusseuo, the Japanese name that is used for academic purposes is merely one of their names and frequently is the name used once they&apos;ve matured.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>それ以外の成長段階の名前では、和名を決めるといった「名前の標準化」が行われていないため、それぞれの呼び名は、多くの場合、地方によってまちまちである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because standardization of names according to growth stages other than the matured stage, such as designation of Japanese name, are not made, they are frequently called by different names in different regions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because the standardization of names according to growth stages other than the mature stage, such as the designation of the Japanese name, aren&apos;t made, they&apos;re frequently called by different names in different regions.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because the &apos;standardization of names&apos; according to growth stages other than the mature stage, such as the designation of the Japanese name, aren&apos;t made, they&apos;re frequently called by different names in different regions.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>出世魚の例</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Examples of Shusseuo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Examples of Shusseuo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Examples of Shusseuo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>ブリ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Buri (Adult yellowtail)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Buri (adult yellowtail)</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Buri</e>
<cmt>既出のため、括弧内の補足を削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="13">
<j>ブリは、硬骨魚綱 スズキ目 アジ科に属する魚。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Buri refers to fishes which belong to Class Osteichthyes Order Perciformes Family Carangidae.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Buri&quot; refers to fishes that belong to the class Osteichthyes, order Perciformes, family Carangidae.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Buri&quot; refers to fishes that belong to the class Osteichthyes, order Perciformes, family Carangidae.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>「ぶり はまち、元はいなだの出世魚」という川柳がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is an old Senryu (Japanese verse) which says: &quot;Buri and Hamachi (young yellowtail) are Shusseuo because they were originally called as Inada (young yellowtail).&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is an old Senryu (Japanese verse) that says: &quot;Buri and Hamachi (young yellowtail) are Shusseuo because they were originally called Inada (young yellowtail).&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is an old Senryu (Japanese verse) that says: &apos;Buri and Hamachi (young yellowtail) are Shusseuo because they were originally called Inada (young yellowtail).&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>スズキ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Suzuki (Seaperch)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Suzuki (sea perch)</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Suzuki</e>
<cmt>既出のため、括弧内の補足を削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="15">
<j>スズキ (魚)は、硬骨魚綱 スズキ目 スズキ科に属する魚</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Suzuki refers to fishes which belong to Class Osteichthyes Order Perciformes Family Moronidae.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Suzuki&quot; refers to fishes that belong to the class Osteichthyes, order Perciformes, family Moronidae.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Suzuki&quot; refers to fishes that belong to the class Osteichthyes, order Perciformes, family Moronidae.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="16">
<j>セイゴ → フッコ → スズキ → オオタロウ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Their name changes as follows: Seigo (alevin of seaperch) to Fukko (alevin of seaperch larger than Seigo) to Suzuki to Otaro</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their name changes as follows: Seigo (alevin of sea perch) to Fukko (alevin of sea perch larger than Seigo) to Suzuki and then to Otaro.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Their name changes as follows: Seigo (alevin of sea perch) to Fukko (alevin of sea perch larger than Seigo) to Suzuki and then to Otaro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="17">
<j>関西セイゴ → ハネ →　スズキ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seigo to Hane (alevin of seaperch larger than Seigo) to Suzuki, in Kasai area</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Kansai area, the name changes from Seigo to Hane (alevin of sea perch larger than Seigo) to Suzuki.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Kansai area, the name changes from Seigo to Hane (alevin of sea perch larger than Seigo) to Suzuki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="18">
<j>また、ヒラスズキの幼魚をヒラセイゴなどと言ったりもする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, alevins of Hirasuzuki (a kind of seaperch) are also called as Hiraseigo (alevin of seaperch).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, alevins of Hirasuzuki (a kind of sea perch) are also called Hiraseigo (alevin of sea perch).</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, alevins of Hirasuzuki (a kind of sea perch) are also called Hiraseigo (alevin of sea perch).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>(ヒラハネはあまり聞かれない)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(The name Hirahane is not popular.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(The name Hirahane isn&apos;t commonly used.)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(The name Hirahane isn&apos;t commonly used.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>ボラ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bora</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bora</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bora</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="20">
<j>ボラは、硬骨魚綱 ボラ目 ボラ科に属する魚</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bora refers to fishes which belong to Class Osteichthyes Order Mugiliformes Family Mugilidae.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Bora&quot; refers to fishes that belong to the class Osteichthyes, order Mugiliformes, family Mugilidae.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Bora&quot; refers to fishes that belong to the class Osteichthyes, order Mugiliformes, family Mugilidae.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="21">
<j>コノシロ　出世魚に含めない考え方もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Konoshiro (they are classified under the order of Clupeiformes Clupeidae, although they are sometimes excluded from the Shusseuo category.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Konoshiro are classified under the order of Clupeiformes Clupeidae, although they&apos;re sometimes excluded from the Shusseuo category.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Konoshiro (dotted gizzard shad): Sometimes excluded from the Shusseuo category</e>
<cmt>コロンを追加し、表現を一部変更しました。コノシロ→dotted gizzard shad　と補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="22">
<j>マグロ　マグロは名前は変わるが出世魚とは呼ばない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Maguro (Tuna; although they are called by different names, they are not called as Shusseuo.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Maguro (tuna; despite being called by different names, they&apos;ren&apos;t called Shusseuo)</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Maguro (tuna): Despite being called by different names, they are not called Shusseuo)</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>サワラ、ウナギ、カンパチ、サケなども同様。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sawara (Spanish mackerel), Unagi (eel), Kanpachi (great amberjack), Sake (Chum salmon), etc. are also called by different names, but they are not called as Shusseuo either.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sawara (Spanish mackerel), Unagi (eel), Kanpachi (great amberjack), Sake (Chum salmon), etc., are also called by different names, but they&apos;ren&apos;t called Shusseuo either.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sawara (Spanish mackerel), Unagi (eel), Kanpachi (great amberjack), Sake (Chum salmon), etc., are also called by different names, but they are not called Shusseuo either.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="24">
<j>コイ　コイは登竜門の伝説から出世魚と呼ばれることもあるが名前が変わるわけではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koi (carp; although they are sometimes called as Shusseuo because of the Toryumon legend, their name does not change.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koi (carp; despite being sometimes called Shusseuo because of the Toryumon legend, their name doesn&apos;t change)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koi (carp): Despite being sometimes called Shusseuo because of the Toryumon legend, their name doesn&apos;t change.</e>
<cmt>コロンを追加し、表現を一部変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>日本国外の例</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Examples in foreign countries</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Examples in foreign countries</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Examples in foreign countries</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="25">
<j>アリストテレス：「バレロンの雑魚」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Aristotle: sardine</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Aristotle: sardine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Aristotle: sardine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="26">
<j>イギリスのサケ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Salmon in England</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Salmon in England</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Salmon in England</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Five-toed-sloth(id:85878), 釣ちごちゅが(id:22605), Kussy(id:3128), 30rKs56MaE(id:11801), JB2(id:59960), Nighthawks(id:36125), Tuffyrhodes20(id:55171), 横浜大塚(id:107010), Tara123(id:130635), Yukichin(id:725), 玄史生(id:43670), Miya(id:1881), Point136(id:211299), Chima(id:90531), Sasayaakihito(id:117099), Dora(id:1122), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>