<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>煎り酒</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Irizake</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Irizake</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Irizake</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>煎り酒（いりざけ）とは、江戸時代に用いられていた日本の古い調味料で、日本酒に梅干を入れて煮詰めたもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Irizake is a Japanese old seasoning used in the Edo period, which is made by putting umeboshi (pickled Japanese apricot) into Japanese sake, and boiling it down.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Irizake is an old Japanese seasoning used during the Edo period, which is made by putting umeboshi (pickled Japanese apricot) into Japanese sake (rice wine), and boiling it down.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten to read more naturally.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Irizake is an old Japanese seasoning used during the Edo period, which is made by putting umeboshi (pickled Japanese apricot) into Japanese sake (rice wine), and boiling it down.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>室町時代末期に考案されたといわれており、江戸時代中期まではタレと伴に広く用いられた液体調味料である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said to have originated in the end of the Muromachi period, and is a liquid seasoning which was broadly used in the middle of the Edo period, along with tare (sauce made with soy sauce, sake, and other seasonings).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said to have originated at the end of the Muromachi period, and is a liquid seasoning which was widely used during the mid-Edo period, along with tare (sauce made with soy sauce, sake, and other seasonings).</e>
<cmt>&quot;in&quot; &gt; &quot;at&quot;&quot;broadly&quot; &gt; &quot;widely&quot;&quot;in the middle of the&quot; &gt; &quot;during the mid-&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said to have originated at the end of the Muromachi period, and is a liquid seasoning which was widely used until the mid-Edo period, along with tare (sauce made with soy sauce, sake, and other seasonings).</e>
<cmt>until the mid-としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>江戸時代中期から醤油が普及するにしたがい次第に利用されなくなり、現在では一般に利用される事はほとんど無い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After soy sauce spread in the middle of the Edo period, it gradually bacame not to be used, and in present days, it is rarely used commonly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the use of soy sauce spread during the mid-Edo period, irizake gradually became used less often and is now not generally used.</e>
<cmt>Poor translation. Completely retranslated.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the use of soy sauce spread from the mid-Edo period, irizake gradually became used less often and is now not generally used.</e>
<cmt>from the mid-としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>醤油のような強い個性を持たず素材の風味を生かすので、白身魚や貝類の刺身に相性がよい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since it doesn&apos;t have strong characteristics like soy sauce and makes good use of the flavors of materials, it goes well with sashimi (fresh slices of raw fish) of whitefish (a fish with white flesh) and shellfish.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As it does not have a strong taste like soy sauce and makes good use of the flavors of its ingredients, it goes well with sashimi (fresh slices of raw fish) made from white fish and shellfish.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten to read more professionally.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As it does not have a strong taste like soy sauce and makes good use of the flavors of its ingredients, it goes well with sashimi (fresh slices of raw fish) made from white fish and shellfish.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>一時は完全に忘れ去られた調味料であるが、近年再評価されつつあり高級料亭などで刺身のつけだれとして利用される事が増えてきている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a seasoning which was once completely forgotten, but in recent years, it is beginning to be reevaluated and is increasingly used as sauce for sashimi in high rank first-class Japanese restaurants.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The seasoning briefly fell out of use completely, but has come to be reevaluated in recent years and is increasingly used as sauce for sashimi in high-class Japanese restaurants.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten to read more professionally.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The seasoning briefly fell out of use completely, but has come to be reevaluated in recent years and is increasingly used as sauce for sashimi in high-class Japanese restaurants.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>作り方</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Recipe</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Recipe</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Recipe</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>日本酒1合（180ml）に大き目の梅干1個を入れ火にかける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Put rather large umeboshi into 1 go (180ml) of Japanese sake and put it on fire.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Place 1 rather large umeboshi into 1 go (180ml) of Japanese sake and put on the heat.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten to read more professionally.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Place one rather large umeboshi into 1 go (180ml) of Japanese sake and put on the heat.</e>
<cmt>数字を一部スペルアウトしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>梅干の風味がよく出るように軽くほぐし、半量になるまで弱火で煮詰める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Lightly break up umeboshi to let the flavor come out, and boil it down with low flame until the volume becomes as half.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Lightly break up umeboshi to cause the flavor come out, and reduce over a low heat until it halves in volume.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten to read more professionally.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Lightly break up umeboshi to cause the flavor come out, and reduce over a low heat until it halves in volume.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>布巾や茶漉しで梅干を漉し、冷暗所で1～2日置いて味をなじませる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Filter out umeboshi with a table towel or a tea strainer, and leave it in cool, dark place for a day or two to match its taste.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Filter out the umeboshi with a dish cloth or tea strainer, and leave in a cool, dark place for 1-2 days in order to bring out its flavor.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten to read more professionally.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Filter out the umeboshi with a dish cloth or tea strainer, and leave in a cool, dark place for one to two days in order to bring out its flavor.</e>
<cmt>数字をスペルアウトしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>冷蔵庫に保管すれば、2週間程度は保存できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It can be preserved for around 2 weeks if it is kept in refrigerator.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It can be preserved for approximately 2 weeks if it is kept in a refrigerator.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten to read more professionally.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It can be preserved for approximately two weeks if it is kept in a refrigerator.</e>
<cmt>数字をスペルアウトしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>上記は最も発祥当初の原型に近い作り方であるが、風味やコクをつける為に「煎り米」、「鰹節」、「コンブ」などを加えて煮詰める作り方もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Above is a recipe witch is most similar to that of original one, but there are other recipes, adding &apos;irigome&apos; (parched wheat or rice), &apos;dried bonito,&apos; and &apos;kelp&apos; and boiling it down, adding flavor and body to the sauce.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The above is a recipe is closest to that of the original form of the seasoning, but there are other recipes which include steps such as the addition of irigome (parched wheat or rice), dried bonito and kelp before reducing in order to add flavor and body to the sauce.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten to read more professionally.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The above is a recipe closest to that of the original form of the seasoning, but there are other recipes which include steps such as the addition of irigome (parched wheat or rice), dried bonito and kelp before reducing in order to add flavor and body to the sauce.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>また、味を調整するために「みりん」や「塩」を加える場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, to adjust the taste, sometimes &apos;mirin&apos; (sweet cooking rice wine) and &apos;salt&apos; are added.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mirin (sweet cooking sake) and salt are also sometimes added.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten to read more professionally.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mirin (sweet cooking sake) and salt are also sometimes added.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>材料の酒は純米酒が、梅干は塩と赤紫蘇だけで漬けた昔ながらの塩辛いものが最適である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As sake, junmaishu (sake made without added alcohol or sugar) is most suitable, and as umeboshi, salty ones, pickled only with salt and red beefsteak plant like in the old days, is most suitable.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For best results, junmaishu (sake made without added alcohol or sugar) and old-fashioned salty umeboshi pickled in only salt and red shiso should be used.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten to read more professionally.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For best results, junmaishu (sake made without added alcohol or sugar) and old-fashioned salty umeboshi pickled in only salt and red shiso should be used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="14">
<j>『料理物語』によれば、「熬酒は鰹一升に梅干十五乃至二十、古酒二升、水少々、溜り少々を入れて一升に煎じ、漉し冷してよし、また酒二升、水一升入れて二升に煎じ使ふ人もある。煮出酒は、鰹に塩少々加へ、新酒で一泡二泡煎じ、漉し冷してよろし、精進の熬酒は、豆腐を田楽ほどに切り、炙つて、梅干、干蕪など刻み入れ、古酒で煎じてよし」という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Ryori Monogatari&quot; (tale of food), it is recorded that &apos;Irizake is made by putting fifteen to twenty umeboshi, 2 sho (unit of volume, approx. 1.8 liters) of old sake, little water, and little tamari (rich soy sauce) into 1 sho of dried bonito and boiling it down to 1 sho, filtering it and cooling it, and also, there are some people putting 2 sho of sake and 1 sho of water, boiling down to 2 sho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Ryori Monogatari&quot; (tale of food) records that &apos;Irizake is made by putting 15-20 umeboshi, 2 sho (approx. 1.8 liters) of old sake, a little water, and a little tamari (rich soy sauce) into 1 sho of dried bonito before reducing it down to 1 sho, filtering it and cooling it, while there are some people who add 2 sho of sake and 1 sho of water before reducing it down to 2 sho.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten to read more professionally and be more consistent.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Ryori Monogatari&quot; (tale of food) records that &apos;Irizake is made by putting 15-20 umeboshi, 2 sho (approx. 1.8 liters) of old sake, a little water, and a little tamari (rich soy sauce) into 1 sho of dried bonito before reducing it down to 1 sho, filtering it and cooling it, while there are some people who add 2 sho of sake and 1 sho of water before reducing it down to 2 sho; Nidashizake (extracted sake) is made by adding a little salt to dried bonito and boiling it for a while with new sake, filtering it and cooling it; and shojin irizake is made by putting chopped umeboshi and hoshi kabura (dried turnips) into grilled tofu with size of dengaku, and boiling it with old sake.&apos;</e>
<cmt>次セルと統合しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Izayohi(id:13095), Nyango(id:8484), Okapia2(id:98589), マクガイア(id:33346), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>