<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>温泉饅頭</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Onsen manju (a kind of steamed yeast bun with filling in hotsprings)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Onsen-manju</e>
<cmt>後段で詳しく説明されていますので括弧内説明ははぶきます。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Onsen-manju</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>温泉饅頭（おんせんまんじゅう）とは、温泉地で売られている饅頭のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Onsen manju is type of manju (a bun stuffed with azuki-bean paste) sold in a hot springs town.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Onsen-manju reffers to a manju (a bun stuffed with azuki-bean paste) sold in towns and resorts of hot springs.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくします。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Onsen-manju reffers to a manju (a bun stuffed with azuki-bean paste) sold in towns and resorts of hot springs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>生地に温泉水を使うこと、または蒸しの過程で、温泉の蒸気を使うことから付けられたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is supposedly named after the fact that it uses hot spring water for dough and also uses steam from hot spring for process of steaming buns.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is supposedly named after that hot spring water is used for its dough and the steam from hot spring is also used for steaming the buns.</e>
<cmt>文法ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is supposedly named after that hot spring water is used for its dough and the steam from hot spring is also used for steaming the buns.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>しかし、ふっくらした生地を造るのに適した重曹成分や蒸しに適した高温の蒸気が確保できる温泉は限られており、多くは単なる土産物としての饅頭である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there are only few hot springs, which have both sodium bicarbonate constituent suited for making soft and full dough, and steam of high temperature required for steaming, therefore many are just manju as a souvenirs.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there are only few hot springs which have both sodium bicarbonate suited for making soft and full dough, and steam of high temperature required for steaming, therefore many of the manju called Onsen-manju are normal manju just as a souvenirs.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくします。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there are only few hot springs which have both sodium bicarbonate suited for making soft and full dough, and steam of high temperature required for steaming, therefore many of the manju called Onsen-manju are normal manju just as a souvenirs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>つまり、温泉地で売られる饅頭、ということで「温泉饅頭」と呼ばれるようになったのであり、温泉地土産や旅館で出される和菓子の定番品として定着した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In other word, it is called &apos;Onsen-manju&apos;, as it is manju sold in hot springs towns, and it has come to stay as standard Japanese confectionery served in a Japanese-style hotel and souvenirs in a hot springs town.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In other word, it became called &apos;Onsen-manju&apos; since it was manju sold in towns of hot springs; and Onsen-manju became a standard Japanese confectionery sold in souvenir shops or served in a Japanese-style hotel of towns of hot springs.</e>
<cmt>時制を直します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In other word, it became called &apos;Onsen-manju&apos; since it was manju sold in towns of hot springs; and Onsen-manju became a standard Japanese confectionery sold in souvenir shops or served in a Japanese-style hotel of towns of hot springs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>全国的には白や茶色の蒸し饅頭が主であるが、趣味の多様化応える特徴的な商品も珍しくはない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">White or brown steamed manju are common through out Japan but there are also many distinctive products to meet various taste.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In all parts of Japan, Onsen-manju refers to mainly steamed manju and its color is white or brown, however it is not rare to find unique Onsen-manju which are made for meeting various tastes.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくします。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In all parts of Japan, Onsen-manju refers to mainly steamed manju and its color is white or brown, however it is not rare to find unique Onsen-manju which are made for meeting various tastes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="6">
<j>温泉饅頭の発祥地は、群馬県説、伊香保温泉説などが言われているが、それ以前に類似のものがなかったという証拠はない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are several theories for the birthplace of onsen manju, including Gunma Prefecture theory or Ikaho-onsen Hot Spring theory, but there is no evidence of similar product not existing before that.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for the birthplace of Onsen-manju, someone says it was Gunma Prefecture, and someone says it was Ikaho-onsen hot springs, however there is no evidence that similar manju had not existed before that.</e>
<cmt>時制を直してわかりやすくします。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for the birthplace of Onsen-manju, someone says it was Gunma Prefecture, and someone says it was Ikaho-onsen hot springs, however there is no evidence that similar manju had not existed before that.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>また、明治時代、温泉地の名物となる菓子商品を開発する際に、薄皮饅頭が注目された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Usukawa-manju (steamed yeast bun with filling with thin skin) was recognized when local specialty for hot springs town was in development in Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Meiji period, people of a town of hot spring were trying to make a new confectionery to be sold as a specialty, and the people gained some hints from Usukawa-manju (steamed yeast bun with filling with thin skin).</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Meiji period, people of a town of hot spring were trying to make a new confectionery to be sold as a specialty, and the people gained some hints from Usukawa-manju (steamed yeast bun with filling with thin skin).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>その中の成功事例が全国普及を後押しをしたことは想像に難くない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It can readily be imagined that the success case accelerated its spread through out Japan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is easy to imagine that the success case among them triggered the spread to hot springs of all parts of the country.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくします。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is easy to imagine that the success case among them triggered the spread to hot springs of all parts of the country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="9">
<j>発祥の地ともいわれる伊香保温泉では源泉をイメージする色を与えるために、源泉や湯の花を配合したこともあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At Ikaho-onsen Hot Spring, so-called the birthplace of onsen manju, spring source and hot springs mineral deposits (resembling flowers) were once added to manju to give spring-source like color.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the past, in Ikaho-onsen hot springs which has been called the birthplace of Onsen-manju, the water of the spring&apos;s source and the mineral deposits of the hot springs (resembling flowers) were used for adding the unique color which reminded of spring&apos;s source to the manju.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the past, in Ikaho-onsen hot springs which has been called the birthplace of Onsen-manju, the water of the spring&apos;s source and the mineral deposits of the hot springs (resembling flowers) were used for adding the unique color which reminded of spring&apos;s source to the manju.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>しかし、いい結果が得られなかったため、入手が容易になりつつあった黒糖を使用したと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However the result was not desirable, therefore it is said that unrefined sugar was used instead, as it started to be easily available.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However the result was not desirable, therefore it is said that confectioners used unrefined sugar, which was becoming available at that period, as a substitute for water and mineral deposits.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくします。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However the result was not desirable, therefore it is said that confectioners used unrefined sugar, which was becoming available at that period, as a substitute for water and mineral deposits.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>また、他の温泉地では源泉を配合したり、高温蒸気を用いて製造したケースもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other hot springs towns also tried blending spring source and manufactured using high temperature steam.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Confectioners of other towns of hot springs also tried blending water of spring&apos;s source, and someone tried making it by using high temperature steam of hot springs.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくします。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Confectioners of other towns of hot springs also tried blending water of spring&apos;s source, and someone tried making it by using high temperature steam of hot springs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="12">
<j>温泉蒸気を用いて饅頭を製造した例は、江戸時代に熱海温泉の源泉の一つ「風呂の湯」で行われた記録が残る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a record of the manju production using the steam from hot springs in Edo period at &apos;Furo no yu&apos;, which was one of spring source for Atami-onsen Hot Springs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for the production of manju using the steam from hot springs, there remains a record of the Edo period; according to it, at &apos;Furo no yu,&apos; one of spring&apos;s sources of Atami-onsen hot springs, such steam was used for making manju.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくします。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for the production of manju using the steam from hot springs, there remains a record of the Edo period; according to it, at &apos;Furo no yu,&apos; one of spring&apos;s sources of Atami-onsen hot springs, such steam was used for making manju.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>但し土産物としてではなく主食としての製造である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However this was manufactured as a staple diet, not as a souvenir.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However it was recorded that the manju made at that time was for a staple diet not as a souvenir.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくします。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However it was recorded that the manju made at that time was for a staple diet not as a souvenir.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="14">
<j>代表的な温泉饅頭</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Notable onsen manju</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Famous Onsen-manju</e>
<cmt>ableを使うよりも角が立たないです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Famous Onsen-manju</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>湯の花まんじゅう（群馬県・伊香保温泉）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yunohana manju (Ikaho-onsen hot springs in Gunma Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yunohana manju (Ikaho-onsen hot springs in Gunma Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yunohana manju (Ikaho-onsen hot springs in Gunma Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>ちちや 温泉まんじゅう（群馬県・草津温泉）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chichiya Onsen-manju (Kusatsu-onsen hot springs in Gunma Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chichiya Onsen-manju (Kusatsu-onsen hot springs in Gunma Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chichiya Onsen-manju (Kusatsu-onsen hot springs in Gunma Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 MD242(id:11277), Point136(id:211299), 花蝶風月雪月花警部(id:163674), 橄欖岩(id:24996), Clarin(id:60278), An-chan(id:14590), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>