<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>片岡千恵蔵プロダクション</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kataoka Chiezo Production</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kataoka Chiezo Productions</e>
<cmt>Production→Productions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kataoka Chiezo Productions</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>片岡千恵蔵プロダクション（かたおかちえぞう-、1928年5月10日 設立 - 1937年4月 解散）は、かつて京都府に存在した映画会社である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kataoka Chiezo Production (established on May 10, 1928, liquidated in April 1937) was a movie company once existed in Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kataoka Chiezo Productions (established May 10, 1928, liquidated in April of 1937) was a film company located in Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>Production→Productions; changed &quot;movie&quot; to &quot;film&quot;; fixed to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kataoka Chiezo Productions (established on May 10, 1928, liquidated in April of 1937) was a film company located in Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>establishedの後にonを挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>当時の若手人気俳優片岡千恵蔵が設立したスタープロダクションであり、設立の翌年に嵯峨野に独自の撮影所を建設した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was established by then popular young actor Chiezo Kataoka, and it constructed its own studio at Sagano in the year after establishment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Established by a popular actor of the time named Chiezo Kataoka, its own studio was constructed in Sagano a year after its establishment.</e>
<cmt>fixed to read more natually</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Established by a popular actor of the time named Chiezo Kataoka, its own studio was constructed in Sagano a year after its establishment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>稲垣浩の『瞼の母』、『弥太郎笠』、伊丹万作の『国士無双』、『赤西蠣太』、山中貞雄の『風流活人剣』など数々の名作を生み出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It produced a lot of classic films including Hiroshi INAGAKI&apos;s &quot;Mabuta no Haha&quot; and &quot;Yataro Gasa&quot;, Mansaku ITAMI&apos;s &quot;Kokushi Muso&quot; and &quot;Akanishi Kakita&quot; as well as Sadao YAMANAKA&apos;s &quot;Furyu Katsujinken&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This company produced many classic films, including Hiroshi INAGAKI&apos;s &quot;Mabuta no Haha&quot; and &quot;Yataro Gasa,&quot; Mansaku ITAMI&apos;s &quot;Kokushi Muso&quot; and &quot;Akanishi Kakita,&quot; as well as Sadao YAMANAKA&apos;s &quot;Furyu Katsujinken.&quot;</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;It&quot; to &quot;This company&quot;; fixed comma and period placements; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This company produced many classic films, including Hiroshi INAGAKI&apos;s &quot;Mabuta no Haha&quot; and &quot;Yataro Gasa,&quot; Mansaku ITAMI&apos;s &quot;Kokushi Muso&quot; and &quot;Akanishi Kakita,&quot; as well as Sadao YAMANAKA&apos;s &quot;Furyu Katsujinken.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>通称千恵プロ（ちえ-）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its common name was Chie Puro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was commonly referred to as &quot;Chie Puro.&quot;</e>
<cmt>added quotation marks; fixed to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was commonly referred to as &quot;Chie Puro.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>略歴・概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Brief history/summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Brief history/Summary</e>
<cmt>capitalized &quot;Summary&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Brief history/Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>前史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prehistory</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prior to Establishment</e>
<cmt>changed to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prior to Establishment</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>奈良に「連合映画芸術家協会」設立、映画製作をしていた小説家の直木三十五の紹介で牧野省三に会い、1927年（昭和2年）4月にマキノ・プロダクションに入社した片岡千恵蔵は、1928年（昭和3年）2月の月形龍之介の退社を期に、本契約に入った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chiezo KATAOKA met with Shozo MAKINO and Joined Makino Production in April 1927 through Sanjugo NAOKI, a novelist who had established &quot;Rengo Eiga Geijutsuka Kyokai&quot; (United Film Artists Association) in Nara and engaged in film production, and began the negotiation of this contract in February 1928 when Ryunosuke TSUKIGATA resigned from the company.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chiezo KATAOKA met Shozo MAKINO and joined Makino Productions in April of 1927 through a novelist who established &quot;Rengo Eiga Geijutsuka Kyokai&quot; (United Film Artists Association) in Nara and engaged in film production named Sanjuro NAOKI, and entered contract negotiations in February of 1928 when Ryunosuke TSUKIGATA resigned from the company.</e>
<cmt>rearranged sentence to read more smoothly; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chiezo KATAOKA met Shozo MAKINO and joined Makino Productions in April of 1927 through a novelist who established &apos;Rengo Eiga Geijutsuka Kyokai&apos; (United Film Artists Association) in Nara and engaged in film production named Sanjugo NAOKI, and entered contract negotiations in February of 1928 when Ryunosuke TSUKIGATA resigned from the company.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。SanjuroをSanjuroに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>しかしその過程で紛糾し、仲裁に入ったマキノの四国ブロック配給会社・三共社の山崎徳次郎すらマキノに怒りを感じる結果を生んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the negotiation became complicated in the process and even a mediator Tokujiro YAMAZAKI, a person of Sankyo-sha, Makino&apos;s distribution company in Shikoku region, felt a feeling of anger against Makino.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the negotiation process became so complicated that even the mediator named Tokujiro YAMAZAKI from Sankyo, Makino&apos;s distribution company in the Shikoku region, became angry with Makino.</e>
<cmt>Sankyo-sha &gt; Sankyo; fixed to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the negotiation process became so complicated that even the mediator named Tokujiro YAMAZAKI from Sankyo, Makino&apos;s distribution company in the Shikoku region, became angry with Makino.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>同年4月、山崎は、阪東妻三郎プロダクションの経営者・立花良介、神戸市の菊水キネマ商会の大島菊松らとともに、全国150館の独立系映画館主に呼びかけ、「日本活動常設館館主連盟映画配給本社」を設立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In April of the same year, Yamazaki, together with Ryosuke TACHIBANA, the chief officer of Bando Tsumasaburo Production, and Kikumatsu OSHIMA of Kikusui Kinema Shokai in Kobe, called for the owners of 150 movie theaters across the nation and established &quot;Nihon Katsudo Josetsukan Kanshu Renmei Eiga Haikyu Honsha&quot;.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April of the same year, Yamazaki, together with Ryosuke TACHIBANA, the chief officer of Bando Tsumasaburo Productions, and Kikumatsu OSHIMA of Kikusui Kinema Shokai in Kobe, contacted the owners of 150 movie theaters across the nation and established &quot;Nihon Katsudo Josetsukan Kanshu Renmei Eiga Haikyu Honsha&quot; (Distribution Company Headquarters for Movie Theater Owners in Japan) (also known as &quot;Kanshu Renmei&quot; [the Theater Owner&apos;s Association]).</e>
<cmt>Production &gt; Productions; changed &quot;called for&quot; to &quot;contacted&quot;; moved period to inside quotations; added description for &quot;Nihon Katsudo…&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April of the same year, Yamazaki, together with Ryosuke TACHIBANA, the chief officer of Bando Tsumasaburo Productions, and Kikumatsu OSHIMA of Kikusui Kinema Shokai in Kobe, contacted the owners of 150 movie theaters across the nation and established &apos;Nihon Katsudo Josetsukan Kanshu Renmei Eiga Haikyu Honsha&apos; (Distribution Company Headquarters for Movie Theater Owners in Japan) (also known as &quot;Kanshu Renmei&quot; [the Theater Owner&apos;s Association]).</e>
<cmt>原文「」の部分を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>そして、独立プロダクションへの製作費の出資と作品の直接公開の方針を打ち出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The above company adopted a policy to invest in independent film studios and distribute their films directly.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This company adopted a policy to invest in independent film studios and distribute their films directly.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;The above company&quot; to &quot;This company&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This company adopted a policy to invest in independent film studios and distribute their films directly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>そこで片岡は同年4月にマキノ・プロダクションを退社、同年5月10日に設立したのがこの「片岡千恵蔵プロダクション」である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taking this opportunity, Kataoka resigned from Makino Production in April of the year and established &quot;Kataoka Chiezo Production&quot; on May 10.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taking this opportunity, Kataoka resigned from Makino Productions in April and established &quot;Kataoka Chiezo Productions&quot; on May 10.</e>
<cmt>Production &gt; Productions; eliminated &quot;in the year&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taking this opportunity, Kataoka resigned from Makino Productions in April and established &apos;Kataoka Chiezo Productions&apos; on May 10.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>同時期にマキノを退社した嵐寛寿郎、山口俊雄 (新派俳優)、中根龍太郎、市川小文治、山本礼三郎がそれぞれプロダクションを設立、千恵プロとともに「日本映画プロダクション連盟」を結成した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanjuro ARASHI, Toshio YAMAGUCHI (actor of Shinpa-Geki), Ryutaro NAKANE, Kobunji ICHIKAWA and Reizaburo YAMAMOTO, those who resigned from Makino around the same time, established their own film production companies respectively, and these companies, including Chie Puro, organized &quot;Nihon Eiga Purodakushon Renmei&quot; (Japan Movie Production Federation).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanjuro ARASHI, Toshio YAMAGUCHI (actor of Shinpa-Geki), Ryutaro NAKANE, Kobunji ICHIKAWA and Reizaburo YAMAMOTO resigned from Makino around the same time, each establishing their own film production companies and worked together with Chie Puro to organize &quot;Nihon Eiga Purodakushon Renmei&quot; (Japan Movie Production Federation).</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to have less commas and read more smoothly</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanjuro ARASHI, Toshio YAMAGUCHI (actor of Shinpa-Geki), Ryutaro NAKANE, Kobunji ICHIKAWA and Reizaburo YAMAMOTO resigned from Makino around the same time, each establishing their own film production companies and worked together with Chie Puro to organize &apos;Nihon Eiga Purodakushon Renmei&apos; (Japan Movie Production Federation).</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>また、山崎に共鳴したマキノの大道具主任河合広始と撮影技師の田中十三もマキノを退社、京都・双ヶ丘に貸しスタジオ「日本キネマ撮影所」（双ヶ丘撮影所）を設立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Makino&apos;s chief stage carpenter Hiroshi Kawai and cameraman Juzo TNAKA also resigned from Makino in response to Yamazaki&apos;s call, and they established a rental studio called &quot;Nihon Kinema Studio&quot; (Narabigaoka Studio) at Narabigaoka in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Makino&apos;s chief stage carpenter Hiroshi Kawai and cameraman Juzo TANAKA also resigned from Makino in response to Yamazaki&apos;s call and established a rental studio called &quot;Nihon Kinema Studio&quot; (Narabigaoka Studio) at Narabigaoka in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>TNAKA &gt; TANAKA; eliminated comma after &quot;call&quot;; changed &quot;and they established&quot; to &quot;and established&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Makino&apos;s chief stage carpenter Hiroshi Kawai and cameraman Juzo TANAKA also resigned from Makino in response to Yamazaki&apos;s call and established a rental studio called &apos;Nihon Kinema Studio&apos; (Narabigaoka Studio) at Narabigaoka in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>嵯峨野の自社撮影所</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The company&apos;s own studio at Sagano</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The company&apos;s own studio in Sagano</e>
<cmt>at &gt; in</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The company&apos;s own studio in Sagano</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="12">
<j>千恵プロは設立6日後の同年5月16日に、双ヶ丘撮影所で第1作撮影を開始した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chie Puro began producing its first film at Narabigaoka Studio on May 16 of the year, six days after its establishment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chie Puro began producing its first film at Narabigaoka Studio on May 16, six days after its establishment.</e>
<cmt>eliminated &quot;of the year&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chie Puro began producing its first film at Narabigaoka Studio on May 16, six days after its establishment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>伊丹万作のオリジナル脚本、稲垣浩監督による『天下太平記』である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This film was &quot;Tenka Taiheiki&quot;, which was written by Mansaku ITAMI and directed by Hiroshi Inagaki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The film was called &quot;Tenka Taiheiki,&quot; written by Mansaku ITAMI and directed by Hiroshi Inagaki.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;This&quot; to &quot;The&quot;; added &quot;called&quot;; eliminated &quot;which was&quot;; moved comma to inside parenthesis</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The film was called &quot;Tenka Taiheiki,&quot; written by Mansaku ITAMI and directed by Hiroshi Inagaki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>同作には、同時期にマキノを退社して千恵プロに入社した武井龍三や、「市川小文治歌舞伎映画プロダクション」を設立した小文治も出演している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryuzo TAKEI, who resigned from Makino and joined Chie Puro around the same time, and Kobunji, who established &quot;Ichikawa Kobunji Kabuki Eiga Production&quot;, also appeared In this film.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Making appearances in this film were Ryuzo TAKEI, who resigned from Makino and joined Chie Puro around the same time, and Kobunji, who established &quot;Ichikawa Kobunji Kabuki Eiga Productions.&quot;</e>
<cmt>rearranged sentence to read more smoothly; Production &gt; Productions; moved period to inside quotations</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Making appearances in this film were Ryuzo TAKEI, who resigned from Makino and joined Chie Puro around the same time, and Kobunji, who established &apos;Ichikawa Kobunji Kabuki Eiga Productions.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>同作は山崎の「館主連盟」の第1回配給作品となったが、千恵プロの設立第2作伊丹原作・脚本、稲垣監督の『放浪三昧』が公開される直前の7月末に早くも「館主連盟」が瓦解する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The above film was the first film that was distributed by Yamazaki&apos;s &quot;Kanshu Renmei&quot;, but &quot;Kanshu Renmei&quot; collapsed as early as at the end of July, immediately before the release of &quot;Horo Zanmai&quot;, the second film of Chie Puro which was written/adapted by Itami and directed by Inagaki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This film was the first to be distributed by Yamazaki&apos;s &quot;Kanshu Renmei,&quot; but this distribution company had already collapsed by the end of July right before the release of &quot;Horo Zanmai,&quot; the second film produced by Chie Puro, written/adapted by Itami and directed by Inagaki.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;The above film&quot; to &quot;This film&quot;; changed the second usage of &quot;Kanshu Renmei&quot; to &quot;this distribution company&quot;; eliminated comma after &quot;July&quot;; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This film was the first to be distributed by Yamazaki&apos;s &apos;Kanshu Renmei,&apos; but this distribution company had already collapsed by the end of July right before the release of &apos;Horo Zanmai,&apos; the second film produced by Chie Puro, written/adapted by Itami and directed by Inagaki.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>同時に独立したプロダクションたちが解散を余儀なくされていくなかで、千恵プロのみが年内に6本の映画を製作、あらたな自前の撮影所用地の物色をした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under the situation where other film studios that were established around the same time were forced to be liquidated, only Chie Puro produced six films in the year and began to look for land for its own studio.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While other film studios that had been established around the same time were being forced to liquidate, Chie Puro was the only company to produce six films that year and began looking for land for their own studio.</e>
<cmt>fixed to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While other film studios that had been established around the same time were being forced to liquidate, Chie Puro was the only company to produce six films that year and began looking for land for their own studio.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="17">
<j>1929年（昭和4年）1月、嵯峨野秋街道町の三条通沿いに「千恵蔵プロダクション撮影所」を開設、骨組み状態で撮影を開始した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January 1929, the company established &quot;Chiezo Production Studio&quot; along the Sanjo Street in Sagano Akikaido-cho and began filming when the construction work was still underway.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In January of 1929,&quot;Chiezo Production Studio&quot; was established on Sanjo Street in Sagano Akikaido-cho and filming began while construction was still underway.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;of&quot; after &quot;January&quot;; changed &quot;the company established&quot; to a passive &quot;was established&quot;; changed &quot;along the&quot; to &quot;on&quot;; changed &quot;began filming&quot; to passive &quot;filming began&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In January of 1929,&apos;Chiezo Production Studio&apos; was established on Sanjo Street in Sagano Akikaido Town and filming began while construction was still underway.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。ChoをTownに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>その後同年5月には、日活撮影所の池永浩久により、『相馬大作 武道活殺の巻』、『絵本武者修業』から日活による配給が決まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In May of the same year, &quot;Soma Daisaku Budo Kassatsu no Maki&quot; and &quot;Ehon Musha Shugyo&quot; were distributed by Nikkatsu thanks to the mediation by Hirohisa IKENAGA of Nikkatsu Studio.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During May of the same year, &quot;Soma Daisaku Budo Kassatsu no Maki&quot; and &quot;Ehon Musha Shugyo&quot; were distributed by Nikkatsu through mediation by Hirohisa IKENAGA of Nikkatsu Studio.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;In&quot; to &quot;During&quot;; changed &quot;thanks to the&quot; to &quot;through&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During May of the same year, &quot;Soma Daisaku Budo Kassatsu no Maki&quot; and &quot;Ehon Musha Shugyo&quot; were distributed by Nikkatsu through mediation by Hirohisa IKENAGA of Nikkatsu Studio.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>また、9本の千恵プロ作品に出演した武井は同年2月に独立、双ヶ丘撮影所に武井龍三プロダクションを設立した（同年解散）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takei, who appeared in nine films of Chie Puro, became independent in February of the year and established Takei Ryuzo Production at Narabigaoka Studio (liquidated in the same year).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takei, who appeared in nine films produced by Chie Puro, became independent in February and established Takei Ryuzo Productions at Narabigaoka Studio (liquidated the same year).</e>
<cmt>added &quot;produced&quot; after &quot;films&quot;; eliminated &quot;of the year&quot; after &quot;February&quot;; Production &gt; Productions; changed (liquidated in the same year) to (liquidated the same year)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takei, who appeared in nine films produced by Chie Puro, became independent in February and established Takei Ryuzo Productions at Narabigaoka Studio (liquidated the same year).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="20">
<j>1932年（昭和7年）、撮影所内に「トーキー研究会」を設置、P.C.L.映画製作所の「P.C.L.トーキー」による稲垣監督の『旅は青空』を製作した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1932, the company set &quot;Talkie Study Group&quot; in its studio and produced &quot;Tabi wa Aozora&quot; directed by Inagaki using &quot;P.L.C. Talkie&quot; developed by P.L.C. Eiga Seisakusho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1932, Chie Puro set up &quot;Talkie Study Group&quot; in its studio and produced &quot;Tabi wa Aozora,&quot; directed by Inagaki, using &quot;P.L.C. Talkie&quot; developed by P.L.C. Eiga Seisakusho.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;the company&quot; to &quot;Chie Puro&quot;; changed &quot;set&quot; to &quot;set up&quot;; added comma after &quot;Aozora&quot; and &quot;Inagaki&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1932, Chie Puro set up &apos;Talkie Study Group&apos; in its studio and produced &quot;Tabi wa Aozora,&quot; directed by Inagaki, using &apos;P.C.L. Talkie&apos; developed by P.C.L. Eiga Seisakusho.</e>
<cmt>原文「」の部分を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。P.L.C.をP.C.L.に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>1934年（昭和9年）にはトーキー・ステージが完成し、「塚越式トーキー」による製作を開始した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1934, the company constructed talkie stage and started to produce talkie films using &quot;Tsukagoshi-method Talkie&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1934, they constructed a talkie stage and began producing talkie films using the &quot;Tsukagoshi Talkie method.&quot;</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;the company&quot; to &quot;they&quot;; added &quot;a&quot; before &quot;talkie stage&quot;; changed &quot;started to produce&quot; to &quot;began producing&quot;; changed &quot;Tsukagoshi-method Talkie&quot; to &quot;Tsukagoshi Talkie method&quot;; moved period to inside quotations</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1934, they constructed a talkie stage and began producing talkie films using the &apos;Tsukagoshi Talkie method.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>同年9月、伊藤大輔 (映画監督)監督『建設の人々』を製作する永田雅一の「第一映画」にステージをレンタルしたが、室戸台風でステージが崩壊する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September of the year, the company rented the stage to Masaichi NAGATA&apos;s &quot;Daiichi Eiga&quot;, which was to produce &quot;Kensetsu no Hitobito&quot; directed by Daisuke Ito (film director), but the stage was collapsed by Typhoon Muroto.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During September of the same year, the stage was rented to Masaichi NAGATA&apos;s &quot;Daiichi Eiga,&quot; which was to produce &quot;Kensetsu no Hitobito&quot; directed by Daisuke Ito (film director), but the stage collapsed in Typhoon Muroto.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During September of the same year, the stage was rented to Masaichi NAGATA&apos;s &apos;Daiichi Eiga,&apos; which was to produce &quot;Kensetsu no Hitobito&quot; directed by Daisuke Ito (film director), but the stage collapsed in Typhoon Muroto.</e>
<cmt>原文「」の部分を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>10月には復興作業に着手、仮ステージで同作の撮影は可能になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The company began restoration work in October, and the filming of the above film resumed using temporary stage.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Restoration work began in October and filming resumed using a temporary stage.</e>
<cmt>changed sentence from active to passive to avoid used of &quot;the company&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Restoration work began in October and filming resumed using a temporary stage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="24">
<j>同年末、日活に提携絶縁状を提出したがそれが訴訟に発展する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the end of the year, the company sent a letter breaking off its relationship with Nikkatsu, but this disputes became a litigation.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the end of the year, Chiezo Productions sent a letter to break off its relationship with Nikkatsu, but this turned into a dispute and went into litigation.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;the company&quot; to &quot;Chie Puro&quot;; fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the end of the year, Chiezo Productions sent a letter to break off its relationship with Nikkatsu, but this turned into a dispute and went into litigation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>翌1935年（昭和10年）1月、日活の瓦解を目論む松竹が設立した子会社「日本映画配給」に提携先を移す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January 1935, the company joined hands with &quot;Nihon Eiga Haikyu&quot;, a company which Shochiku established aiming to destroy Nikkatsu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In January of 1935, the company partnered with &quot;Nihon Eiga Haikyu,&quot; a company established by Shochiku with the aim of destroying Nikkatsu.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;joined hands&quot; to &quot;partnered&quot;; fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In January of 1935, the company partnered with &apos;Nihon Eiga Haikyu,&apos; a company established by Shochiku with the aim of destroying Nikkatsu.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>しかし日活は経営が立ち直り、松竹の目論みは破れて「日本映画配給」は解体、同年10月には新興キネマの配給となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Nikkatsu regained its footing, &quot;Nihon Eiga Haikyu&quot; was liquidated against the plan of Shochiku, and Shinko Kinema became the company&apos;s distribution company in October of the same year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Nikkatsu regained its footing, &quot;Nihon Eiga Haikyu&quot; was liquidated, breaking Shochiku&apos;s plan, and Shinko Kinema became Chiezo Productions&apos; distribution company in October.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;against the plan of Shochiku&quot; to &quot;breaking Shochiku&apos;s plan&quot;; changed &quot;the company&apos;s&quot; to &quot;Chiezo Productions&apos;&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Nikkatsu regained its footing, &apos;Nihon Eiga Haikyu&apos; was liquidated, breaking Shochiku&apos;s plan, and Shinko Kinema became Chiezo Productions&apos; distribution company in October.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>その間、第二トーキー・ステージが完成した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, No.2 talkie stage was completed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During this time, Number Two Talkie Stage was completed.</e>
<cmt>I am unclear on whether &quot;No.2 talkie stage&quot; is a new type of stage or if it was just the second &quot;talkie stage&quot; constructed.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During this time, Number Two Talkie Stage was completed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>その半年後の1936年（昭和11年）5月、小説家の長谷川伸の仲介で日活との提携を再開した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In May 1936, half a year later, the company resumed its cooperation with Nikkatsu thanks to the mediation by Shi HASEGAWA, a novelist.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Half a year later during May of 1936, Chiezo Productions resumed its partnership with Nikkatsu through mediation by a novelist named Shi HASEGAWA.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;the company&quot; to &quot;Chiezo Productions&quot;; changed &quot;resumed its cooperation&quot; to &quot;resumed its partnership&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Half a year later during May of 1936, Chiezo Productions resumed its partnership with Nikkatsu through mediation by a novelist named Shin HASEGAWA.</e>
<cmt>ShiをShinに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>終焉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The end</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The demise of Chiezo Productions</e>
<cmt>changed to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The demise of Chiezo Productions</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="29">
<j>1937年（昭和12年）4月、千恵プロ百本記念作品『浅野内匠頭』を撮り、『松五郎乱れ星』を製作して同社は解散した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The company produced &quot;Asano Takuminokami&quot;, a film to commemorate the 100th film of Chie Puro, in April 1937 and was liquidated after producing &quot;Matsugoro Midaregami&quot;.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April of 1937, Chiezo Productions produced &quot;Asano Takuminokami,&quot; a film to commemorate their 100th film, then liquidated after filming was completed for &quot;Matsugoro Midaregami.&quot;</e>
<cmt>moved date to the beginning of the sentence; changed &quot;the company&quot; to &quot;Chiezo Productions&quot;; changed &quot;Chie Puro&quot; to &quot;they&quot;; fixed to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April of 1937, Chiezo Productions produced &quot;Asano Takuminokami,&quot; a film to commemorate their 100th film, then liquidated after filming was completed for &quot;Matsugoro Midareboshi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>MidaregamiをMidareboshiに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>プロダクションごと日活京都撮影所に招かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The company was taken over by Nikkatsu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The company was then taken over by Nikkatsu.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;then&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The company was then taken over by Nikkatsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>同社の解散は、同年早々の片岡本人の3か月にわたる病気休養もあったが、大河内伝次郎の日活退社とJ.Oスタヂオ移籍による日活側の要望であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Kataoka was absent due to illness for three months at the beginning of the year, the reason of the company&apos;s liquidation was basically Nikkatsu&apos;s request, which was made under the situation where Denjiro Okochi resigned from Nikkatsu and joined J. O Studio, rather than his illness.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rather than Kataoka&apos;s absense due to illness for three months at the beginning of the year, Chie Puro was basically liquidated due to a request by Nikkatsu when Denjiro Okochi resigned from Nikkatsu and joined J.O Studio.</e>
<cmt>fixed to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rather than Kataoka&apos;s absence due to illness for three months at the beginning of the year, Chie Puro was basically liquidated due to a request by Nikkatsu when Denjiro Okochi resigned from Nikkatsu and joined J.O Studio.</e>
<cmt>absenseをabsenceに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>経営不振はなく、片岡の休養時も従業員への賃金の欠配はなかったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The company&apos;s management was healthy at the time, and employees&apos; salary was paid regularly even while Kataoka was absent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chie Puro&apos;s management was healthy at the time, and employee salaries were paid regularly even while Kataoka was absent.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;The company&apos;s&quot; to &quot;Chie Puro&apos;s&quot;; changed &quot;employees&apos; salary was paid&quot; to &quot;employee salaries were paid&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chie Puro&apos;s management was healthy at the time, and employee salaries were paid regularly even while Kataoka was absent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>資料としては『千恵プロ時代　片岡千恵蔵・稲垣浩・伊丹万作、洒脱にエンターテインメント』（冨田美香編、フィルムアート社、1997年）がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;The age of Chie Puro, Chiezo KATAOKA, Hiroshi INAGAKI, Mansaku ITAMI Free and Easy Entertainment&quot; (compiled by Mika TOMITA, Ato-sha, 1997) is available as material.</e>
<cmt>『千恵プロ時代　片岡千恵蔵・稲垣浩・伊丹万作、洒脱にエンターテインメント』→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;The age of Chie Puro, Chiezo KATAOKA, Hiroshi INAGAKI, Mansaku ITAMI Free and Easy Entertainment&quot; (compiled by Mika TOMITA, Ato-sha, 1997) is available as a record of the company.</e>
<cmt>fixed spacing after ITAMI; changed &quot;material&quot; to &quot;a record of the company&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;The age of Chie Puro, Chiezo KATAOKA, Hiroshi INAGAKI, Mansaku ITAMI Free and Easy Entertainment&quot; (compiled by Mika TOMITA, Ato-sha, 1997) is available as a record of the company.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Yanahan(id:2437), Kmrt(id:101778), Y-take(id:132371), IwaimBot(id:190695), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>