<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>味噌汁</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Miso soup</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Miso soup</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Miso Soup</e>
<cmt>タイトルのため単語の頭文字を大文字に変更</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>味噌汁（みそしる）は、出汁に野菜や魚介類などの具（「実」とも称される）を加え、煮て、味噌で調味した日本料理。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Miso soup is a Japanese dish that is cooked by adding ingredients (called &quot;gu&quot; or &quot;mi&quot;) such as vegetables and fishes in soup, boiling and seasoning with miso.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Miso soup is a Japanese dish that is cooked by adding ingredients (called &quot;gu&quot; or &quot;mi&quot;) such as vegetables and fish in soup, boiling and seasoning with miso.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Miso soup is a Japanese dish that is cooked by adding ingredients (called &apos;gu&apos; or &apos;mi&apos;) such as vegetables and fish in soup, boiling and seasoning with miso.</e>
<cmt>“gu” or “mi”→&apos;gu&apos; or &apos;mi&apos;に修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>日本の食文化において、主食とされる飯や雑穀飯の副食として、主要な位置を占める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japanese food culture, it occupies an important place as a side dish of the staple foods such as rice and cereals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japanese food culture, it occupies an important place as a side dish of staple foods such as rice and cereal.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japanese food culture, it occupies an important place as a side dish of staple foods such as rice and cereal.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>料亭で出されることもあるが、たいていは家庭で作られる家庭料理の代表である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also served in restaurants, but normally it is a typical home-style cooking.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also served in restaurants, but normally it is typically home-style cooking.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also served in restaurants, but normally it is typically home-style cooking.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>鰹節や煮干しなどで出汁をとり、食材と味噌で味を作るという、調理法としてはシンプルな料理であるといえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a dish with simple procedure as follows: make the soup from materials such as dried bonito, dried small sardines etc., add ingredients and season with miso.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a simple dish to make, make the soup from materials such as dried bonito, dried small sardines etc., add ingredients and season with miso.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a simple dish to make, make the soup from materials such as dried bonito, dried small sardines etc., add ingredients and season with miso.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース消去</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>本膳料理の膳立ては、飯と汁・香の物のほかに膾(なます)・平皿・焼物の3菜を添えたものを「一汁三菜」と表現して、主食に味噌汁のような汁物と、「菜（さい）」、「おかず」と称される固形の副食を組み合わせるのが理想的とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the serving style of honzen ryori (a basic style of traditional Japanese cooking) the ideal combination is thought as &quot;one soup and three types of side dishes&quot; which consists of a staple food, a soup like miso soup, solid side dishes called &quot;sai&quot; or &quot;okazu&quot; including rice, soup, pickles and three side dishes of namasu (a dish of raw fish and vegetables seasoned in vinegar), hirazara (a dish on a flat plate), yakimono (a dish of broiled fish or meat).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the honzen ryori (a basic style of traditional Japanese cooking) serving style the ideal combination is thought to be &quot;one soup and three types of side dishes&quot; consisting of a staple food, a soup like miso soup, solid side dishes called &quot;sai&quot; or &quot;okazu&quot; including rice, soup, pickles and three side dishes of namasu (a dish of raw fish and vegetables seasoned in vinegar), hirazara (a dish on a flat plate), yakimono (a dish of broiled fish or meat).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the honzen ryori (a basic style of traditional Japanese cooking) serving style the ideal combination is thought to be &apos;one soup and three types of side dishes&apos; consisting of a staple food, a soup like miso soup, solid side dishes called &apos;sai&apos; or &apos;okazu&apos; including rice, soup, pickles and three side dishes of namasu (a dish of raw fish and vegetables seasoned in vinegar), hirazara (a dish on a flat plate), yakimono (a dish of broiled fish or meat).</e>
<cmt>全角クォーテーション→半角・シングルに修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="6">
<j>また一汁一菜として粗食の代表とされる食生活でも、欠かせないものとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also a must in &quot;one soup and one side dish&quot; which is a typical plain food life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also a must to have &quot;one bowl of soup and one side dish&quot; with a typical meal.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also a must to have &quot;one bowl of soup and one side dish&quot; with a typical meal.</e>
<cmt>全角クォーテーション→半角に修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="7">
<j>とりわけ味噌汁は、主食を食べるに際しての食欲増進の役割をおかずと共に果たすと同時に、味噌に含まれる大豆の蛋白質は、かつての低蛋白の日本食における主要な蛋白源であったし、労働で汗とともに消耗する塩分の補給に大きな役割を果たしていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When people ate staple foods, miso soup functioned especially to enhance appetite together with side dishes and also soya bean protein in miso was a major source of protein when Japanese food was low protein food once and also functioned largely to restore the lost salt by laboring with sweating.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With staple food, miso soup especially enhanced the appetite together with side dishes and soya beans in miso, a major source of protein when Japanese food was lacking in protein and this also helped to restore salt lost from sweating doing physical labor.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With staple food, miso soup especially enhanced the appetite together with side dishes and soya beans in miso, a major source of protein when Japanese food was lacking in protein and this also helped to restore salt lost from sweating doing physical labor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="8">
<j>西洋料理のスープに相当する側面があるが、狭義のヨーロッパのスープは硬くなったパンに鍋物の汁をかけてふやかしたものを起源とするため、日本の味噌汁と食事の中の位置づけが多少異なり、より主食的な意味合いが強い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is equivalent to soup of Western food, but narrowly European soup originated from soaked stale bread in stew and therefore it is more like a staple food and it is slightly different from miso soup in Japanese food.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is equivalent to western style soup, but more specifically like European soup made from soaked stale bread in stew and therefore is more like a staple food slightly different from Japanese miso soup.</e>
<cmt>very wordy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is equivalent to western style soup, but more specifically like European soup made from soaked stale bread in stew and therefore is more like a staple food slightly different from Japanese miso soup.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース消去</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="9">
<j>ただし、飯に味噌汁をかけて食べるいわゆる「ねこまんま」は、まさにヨーロッパのスープの元来の形に酷似する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the so called &quot;neko manma (cat&apos;s meal)&quot; which is made by mixing rice in miso soup is just very similar to the original style of European soup.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, so called &quot;neko manma (cat&apos;s meal)&quot; which is made by mixing rice in miso soup is very similar to the original European soup.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, so called &apos;neko manma (cat&apos;s meal)&apos; which is made by mixing rice in miso soup is very similar to the original European soup.</e>
<cmt>全角クォーテーション→半角・シングルに修正、アポストロフィーを半角に修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="10">
<j>名称</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Names</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Names</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Names</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>東京近郊ではおみおつけとも呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called &quot;Omiotsuke&quot; around Tokyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is also called &quot;Omiotsuke&quot; around Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is also called Omiotsuke around Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>御味御付。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omiotsuke</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omiotsuke</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omiotsuke.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>「おみ」は「味噌」、「おつけ」は「汁」を意味する女房言葉。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is from the language of court ladies in former times and omi means miso, otsuke means shiru.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This term is from the language of court ladies during former times and omi means miso, otsuke means shiru.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This term is from the language of court ladies during former times and omi means miso, otsuke means shiru.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>江戸時代に江戸の地で使用され始めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Edo period it started being called in Edo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It began to be called this during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>redundancy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It began to be called this during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース消去</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>または御御御汁（御御御付）と書き、おつけにさらに接頭辞が付いたという説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also written 御御御汁(御御御付) that was created by adding another prefix in otsuke according to a theory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to a theory, it was also written 御御御汁(御御御付) created by adding another prefix added to otsuke.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to a theory, it was also written 御御御汁(御御御付) created by adding another prefix added to otsuke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="16">
<j>特にこの地域では伝統的に、味噌汁の中身の固形物のことを「具」とは呼ばず「実」と呼ぶ（「おつけの実」、など）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially in the area, the solid ingredients in miso soup have been called &quot;mi&quot; instead of &quot;gu&quot; traditionally like mi of otsuke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Especially in the loca area, the solid ingredients in miso soup have been called &quot;mi&quot; instead of &quot;gu&quot; traditionally like mi of otsuke.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Especially in the loca area, the solid ingredients in miso soup have been called &apos;mi&apos; instead of &apos;gu&apos; traditionally like mi of otsuke.</e>
<cmt>全角クォーテーション→半角・シングルに修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="17">
<j>京阪神では汁を総じておつゆと称する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Keihanshin area, soup is called otsuyu in general.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Keihanshin area, soup was generally called otsuyu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Keihanshin area, soup is generally called otsuyu.</e>
<cmt>was→isに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>おつゆを吸い物と味噌汁を区別して使用する場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Otsuyu was sometimes used to make a distinction between osuimono (a kind of soup) and miso soup.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Otsuyu was sometimes used to make a distinction between osuimono (a kind of soup) and miso soup.</e>
<cmt>spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Otsuyu is sometimes used to make a distinction between osuimono (a kind of soup) and miso soup.</e>
<cmt>was→isに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>なおつゆは現在ではこの地方でも一般にそうめんやそばのつけ汁のことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this area tsuyu mean generally dipping sauce of somen (thin wheat noodles) and buckwheat noodles now.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Now in this area tsuyu generally means dipping sauce of somen (thin wheat noodles) and buckwheat noodles.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Now in this area tsuyu generally means dipping sauce of somen (thin wheat noodles) and buckwheat noodles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="20">
<j>味噌汁が庶民の食卓に登場したのは室町時代の頃と言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that miso soup appeared on common people&apos;s tables since about the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that miso soup appeared on the common people&apos;s tables from the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that miso soup appeared on the common people&apos;s tables from the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>アポストロフィーを半角に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>元々は田舎料理で主に農家などで作られていたものであったが、時期が経つにつれ様々な階層にも次第に普及し、やがて日本人の食卓に欠かせないものになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally it was country cooking mainly of farmers, but gradually spread among various classes of people and became essential on Japanese people&apos;s tables.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally it was country cooking mainly done by farmers, but gradually spread among various classes of people and became essential on Japanese tables.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally it was country cooking mainly done by farmers, but gradually spread among various classes of people and became essential on Japanese tables.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="22">
<j>調理が簡単で大量に作れるみそ汁は戦国時代 (日本)に陣中食として考案されたとする説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a theory that it was created as a food to eat at the front in the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States) in Japan because it was able to cook easily in large quantities.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a theory that it was created as a food to eat during the beginning of the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States) in Japan because it was easy to cook in large quantities.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a theory that it was created as a food to eat during the beginning of the Sengoku period (period of Warring States) in Japan because it was easy to cook in large quantities.</e>
<cmt>Periodの頭文字を小文字に変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>里芋の茎を味噌で煮しめた芋がら縄は、ちぎって陣笠に入れて熱湯をかければ簡単に味噌汁ができる陣中食だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imogara nawa was a food to eat at the front that was cooked by simmering taros with miso and people could make miso soup soon by pouring hot water on it in their bamboo hats which were wore at the front.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imogara nawa was eaten at the battle front it was cooked by simmering taro with miso and miso soup could be made quickly by pouring hot water on it in their bamboo hats which were worn then.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imogara nawa was eaten at the battle front it was cooked by simmering taro with miso and miso soup could be made quickly by pouring hot water on it in their bamboo hats which were worn then.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>石田三成は、「熱湯に焼き味噌をかき立てて飲めば、終日米がなくとも飢えたることなし」と語ったとの言い伝えがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a legend that Mitsunari ISHIDA said &quot;if we drink baked miso with hot water poured over it, we will never be starved even without rice all the day&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a legend about Mitsunari ISHIDA who said &quot;if we drink baked miso with hot water poured over it, we will never be starved even without having any rice all the day&quot;.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a legend about Mitsunari ISHIDA who said &apos;if we drink baked miso with hot water poured over it, we will never be starved even without having any rice all the day.&apos;</e>
<cmt>全角クォーテーション→半角・シングルに修正、ピリオドの位置を移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>陣中食としての味噌汁は、むしろご飯に味噌をかけて湯を入れたものであることも多く、元々「汁かけ飯」だったものが、後にご飯と味噌汁の組み合わせに変化していったとも言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that miso soup as a food at the front was more like &quot;rice poured soup&quot; and often cooked by pouring hot water on rice and miso, but later it has changed gradually to the combination of rice and miso soup.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that miso soup, as a food consummed at the front, was more like &quot;rice poured soup&quot; and was often cooked by pouring hot water on rice and miso, but later it has changed gradually into a combination of rice and miso soup.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that miso soup, as a food consummed at the front, was more like &apos;rice poured soup&apos; and was often cooked by pouring hot water on rice and miso, but later it has changed gradually into a combination of rice and miso soup.</e>
<cmt>全角クォーテーション→半角・シングルに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>各地に残る味噌には、戦国武将の考案によるものとされるものがある（上杉謙信の越後国味噌、伊達政宗の仙台味噌など）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some of the misos remained in various areas supposed to be created by the bushos (Japanese military commanders) in the Sengoku Period (including Echigo miso of Kenshin UESUGI, Sendai miso of Masamune DATE etc.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some of the miso remained in various areas supposed to be created by the busho (Japanese military commanders) during the Sengoku Period (including Echigo miso of Kenshin UESUGI, Sendai miso of Masamune DATE etc.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some of the miso remained in various areas supposed to be created by the busho (Japanese military commanders) during the Sengoku period (including Echigo miso of Kenshin UESUGI, Sendai miso of Masamune DATE etc.).</e>
<cmt>Periodの頭文字を小文字に変更、ピリオド追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="27">
<j>調理</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cooking</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cooking</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cooking</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>調理時間も10分ほどと、食事をする少し前でも作ることが出来る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It takes only about ten minutes to cook, so people can cook it a little before eating.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It takes only about ten minutes to cook, so people can cook it a little bit before eating.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It takes only about ten minutes to cook, so people can cook it a little bit before eating.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="29">
<j>おふくろの味と称されるように、作る家庭によって十人十色の味となる非常に特徴的な料理でもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is called &quot;the taste of mother&apos;s cooking&quot; because it is a very characteristic dish that the tastes vary depending on each family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is called &quot;the taste of mother&apos;s home cooking&quot; because it is a very characteristic dish varying in tastesaccording to each family.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is called &quot;the taste of mother&apos;s home cooking&quot; because it is a very characteristic dish varying in tastes according to each family.</e>
<cmt>全角クォーテーション、アポストロフィーを半角に修正、tastesaccording→tastes accordingに修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="30">
<j>調理に際しては、味噌を加えた後に強く煮立たせると、味噌の香りが揮発して風味が減じることに気を配る必要がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the cooking it has to be careful that if it is boiled fully after adding miso the aroma of miso is volatilized and the flavour is decreased.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When cooking care must taken not to boil it completely after adding the miso, since the aroma will be volatilized and the flavour will decrease.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When cooking care must be taken not to boil it completely after adding the miso, since the aroma will be volatilized and the flavour will decrease.</e>
<cmt>must taken→must be takenに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>具材によっては「鱈汁」、「豚汁」、「三平汁」などのような名称を用いる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called &quot;tara jiru (cod roe soup)&quot; &quot;ton jiru (pork soup)&quot; &quot;sanpei jiru (a soup with fishes and vegetables from Hokkaido)&quot; depending on the ingredients.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called &quot;tara jiru (cod roe soup)&quot; &quot;ton jiru (pork soup)&quot; &quot;sanpei jiru (a soup with fishes and vegetables from Hokkaido)&quot; depending upon the ingredients.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called &apos;tara jiru&apos; (cod roe soup), &apos;ton jiru&apos; (pork soup), or &apos;sanpei jiru&apos; (a soup with fishes and vegetables from Hokkaido) depending upon the ingredients.</e>
<cmt>全角クォーテーション→半角・シングルに修正、位置を移動、カンマ、or追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>鍋物を味噌で仕立てた場合には味噌汁とは言わないのが普通である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even if miso is added in one-pot dish cooked at the table, it is not called miso soup normally.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even if miso is added to a one-pot dish cooked at the table, it is normally not called miso soup.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even if miso is added to a one-pot dish cooked at the table, it is normally not called miso soup.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>一般的には日本の一般家庭の朝食時にご飯と共に供される感も強いが、近年は朝食にご飯を食べない人が多くなったため、夕食時に味噌汁を飲む人が増えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It had been served with rice for breakfast at home commonly, but recently many people don&apos;t eat rice for the breakfast and therefore well eat miso soup for dinner.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has commonly been served with rice for breakfast at home, but recently many people don&apos;t eat rice for breakfast and therefore prefer miso soup for dinner.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has commonly been served with rice for breakfast at home, but recently many people don&apos;t eat rice for breakfast and therefore prefer miso soup for dinner.</e>
<cmt>アポストロフィーを半角に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>朝食に限らず食事の時の白米のご飯の付け合せの汁物として飲まれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is eaten not only for breakfast but also for other meals as a soup for white rice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is consummed not only for breakfast, but also for other meals as a soup for white rice.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is consummed not only for breakfast, but also for other meals as a soup for white rice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>日本人の食に一番密接している料理ともいえ、欠かすことの出来ない存在である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It can be said a closest dish for the Japanese people and essential food.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It can be said to be a common dish and essential food for Japanese.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It can be said to be a common dish and essential food for Japanese.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>味噌汁、特にシジミの味噌汁はアルコールの分解を助け二日酔いに効果があるとも言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that miso soup, especially of freshwater clams is a cure for a hangover by helping alcohol break down.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that miso soup, especially made with freshwater clams is a cure for a hangover as it helps to break down alcohol.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that miso soup, especially made with freshwater clams is a cure for a hangover as it helps to break down alcohol.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>味噌</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Miso</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Miso</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Miso</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="37">
<j>使用する味噌は各家庭によりまちまちだが、地域レベルで見ると相対的に赤味噌が好まれる地域・白味噌が好まれる地域などにブロック化することができ、それがそのままその地域の代表的な味噌の銘柄にもなっていることも多い（味噌を参照）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It depends on each family which miso to use, but seeing by areas there are red miso areas and white miso areas relatively, which have determined the major miso brands of each area into blocks (refer to Miso).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It depends upon each family which miso to use, but looking according to areas there are red miso areas and white miso areas, which have determined the major miso brands by each area (refer to Miso).</e>
<cmt>wordy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It depends upon each family which miso to use, but looking according to areas there are red miso areas and white miso areas, which have determined the major miso brands by each area (refer to Miso).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>しかし、戦後は流通経路の発達に伴って特に信州味噌が全国的に普及し、これを使う家庭も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But after the war, along with developing of the distribution channels, Shinshu miso spread throughout the country and many people use it at home.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But after the war, along with the development of distribution channels, Shinshu miso spread throughout the country and many people use it at home.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But after the war, along with the development of distribution channels, Shinshu miso spread throughout the country and many people use it at home.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="39">
<j>一杯分の味噌の使用量は15gが標準とされているが、好みや使用する味噌の違いなどによって若干幅がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The standard amount of miso for a bowl of miso soup is considered as 15g, but it ranges slightly depending on desired tastes and which miso to use.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The standard amount of miso for a bowl of miso soup is considered to be 15g, but it ranges slightly depending upon the desired tastes and which miso to use.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The standard amount of miso for a bowl of miso soup is considered to be 15g, but it ranges slightly depending upon the desired tastes and which miso to use.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>汁としての塩分濃度は概ね1%程度である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The salt level in a soup is approximately 1%.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The salt level in a soup is approximately one percent.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The salt level in a soup is approximately one percent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>出汁</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soup</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soup</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soup</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="41">
<j>出汁は、主にコンブ・煮干し・鰹節が多く使われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The soup is made mainly from sea tangles, dried small sardines or dried bonito.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soup is made mainly from sea tangles, dried small sardines or dried bonito.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soup is made mainly from sea tangles, dried small sardines or dried bonito.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>これも、各家庭で千差万別であるが、近年はうま味調味料でとる家も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It also depends on each family what to use for a soup, but recently there are many people who use chemical seasoning to make a soup at home.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It also depends upon each family what to use for soup, but recently there are many people who use chemical seasoning to make soup at home.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It also depends upon each family what to use for soup, but recently there are many people who use chemical seasoning to make soup at home.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>最近ではだし入り味噌と称して売られる物がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Recently there are miso products containing soup in it called &quot;miso with soup&quot; in markets.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Recently there are miso products containing soup called &quot;miso with soup&quot; in supermarkets.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Recently there are miso products containing soup called &quot;miso with soup&quot; in supermarkets.</e>
<cmt>全角クォーテーション→半角に修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>主な味噌汁の具</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Major ingredients of miso soup</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Major ingredients of miso soup</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Major ingredients of miso soup</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="44">
<j>味噌汁の具（実）には、地方風土により様々な差異があるがここに一例を記す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are various ingredients (mi) of miso soup depending on areas and places and a part of the examples are as follows;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are various ingredients (mi) of miso soup depending on the areas and some examples follow;</e>
<cmt>grammar, redundant</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are various ingredients (mi) of miso soup depending on the areas and some examples follow;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>魚介類・海藻類</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fishes and seaweeds</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fish and seaweed</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fish and seaweed</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>ワカメ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wakame seeweed</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wakame seeweed</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wakame seeweed</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="45">
<j>-- 乾物の場合、水で戻し、切ってから使う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rehydrate it if it is a dry food and cut it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rehydrate it if it is a dry food and cut it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rehydrate it if it is a dry food and cut it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>元々切ってある場合は、戻さずに入れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Use it without rehydrating if it is cut seaweed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Use it without rehydrating if it is cut seaweed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Use it without rehydrating if it is cut seaweed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>塩ワカメは塩抜きをする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soak in water to freshen it if it is salted seaweed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soak in water to freshen it if it is salted seaweed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soak in water to freshen it if it is salted seaweed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="48">
<j>シジミ、アサリ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Freshwater clams and short-neck clams</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Freshwater clams and short-neck clams</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Freshwater clams and short-neck clams</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="49">
<j>-- 貝ごと洗って水から入れ、全てが口を開いたら味噌を加える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wash them with the shells and put in water and add miso after the shells open.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wash them with the shells, place in water and add miso after the shells open.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wash them with the shells, place in water and add miso after the shells open.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="50">
<j>アオノリ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Green lavers</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Green lavers</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Green lavers</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>野菜・加工品</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Vegetables and processed foods</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Vegetables and processed foods</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Vegetables and processed foods</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>ネギ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Green onion</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Green onions</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Green onions</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="51">
<j>-- 小口切りにして吸い口として使われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cut it into small pieces to add as spice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cut into small pieces and add them as a spice.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cut into small pieces and add them as a spice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>また、ざく切りにして、主たる具材としても使われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Or cut coarsely to add as major ingredient.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Or cut coarsely to add as a major ingredient.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Or cut coarsely to add as a major ingredient.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>青菜</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Green vegetables</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Green vegetables</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Green vegetables</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="53">
<j>-- ホウレンソウ、小松菜、青梗菜（チンゲンサイ）など。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Spinach, komatsuna (a leafy green vegetable), pak-choi etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Spinach, komatsuna (a leafy green vegetable), pak-choi etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Spinach, komatsuna (a leafy green vegetable), pak-choi etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>豆腐</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bean curd</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bean curd</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bean curd</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="54">
<j>-- さいの目切りにする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cut it into dice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dice them.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dice them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>ナメコ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nameko mushroom</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nameko mushroom</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nameko mushroom</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="55">
<j>-- ぬめりを落として入れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Add after washing to take the slime out.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Add after washing to remove the sliminess.</e>
<cmt>gramamr</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Add after washing to remove the sliminess.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>独特の舌触りを楽しむ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Enjoy the unique feeling on the tongue.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Enjoy the unique feeling on the tongue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Enjoy the unique feeling on the tongue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>ダイコン</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese radish</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese radish</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese radish</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="57">
<j>-- 水から入れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Add it in water before boiled.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Add it to water before boiling.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Add it to water before boiling.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>厚めの輪切りにするほか、細長く切って入れる場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Slice it into thick rings or strips.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Slice it into thick rings or strips.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Slice it into thick rings or strips.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="14">
<tit>
<j>油揚げ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Deep-fried bean curd</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Deep-fried bean curd</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Deep-fried bean curd</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="59">
<j>-- 油抜きをする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Blanch it to take oil.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Blanch it to take oil.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Blanch it to take oil.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="15">
<tit>
<j>納豆</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Natto (fermented soybeans)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Natto (fermented soybeans)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Natto (fermented soybeans)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="60">
<j>--包丁で叩き割ったり、すりつぶしてから入れることもある（納豆汁）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Add it after chopped with a knife or mash (Natto jiru).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Add it after chopping with a knife or mashing (Natto jiru).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Add it after chopping with a knife or mashing (Natto jiru).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="16">
<tit>
<j>その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="61">
<j>鶏卵</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chicken egg</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chicken eggs</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chicken eggs</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="62">
<j>--味噌を入れてから入れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Add after miso.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Add after miso.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Add after miso.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>椀に盛った状態で半熟になるタイミングで入れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Add it after hot soup is poured in a bowl so that the egg becomes half-boiled.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Add it after hot soup is poured into a bowl so the the egg becomes half-boiled.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Add it after hot soup is poured into a bowl so the egg becomes half-boiled.</e>
<cmt>the the egg→the eggに修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="64">
<j>ちくわ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chikuwa (a tubular roll of boiled fish paste)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chikuwa (a tubular roll of boiled fish paste)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chikuwa (a tubular roll of boiled fish paste)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="65">
<j>豚肉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Pork</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Pork</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Pork</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="66">
<j>バリエーション</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Variations</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Variations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Variations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="67">
<j>沖縄県の「みそ汁」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Miso soup in Okinawa Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Miso soup in Okinawa Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Miso soup in Okinawa Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="68">
<j>沖縄県の大衆食堂には「みそ汁（みそしる、みそじる）」というメニューがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Okinawa Prefecture there is a menu called misoshiru or misojiru in eating houses.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Okinawa Prefecture the menu in restaurants lists misoshiru or misojiru.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Okinawa Prefecture the menu in restaurants lists misoshiru or misojiru.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>大きな椀に豚肉、ポーク（ランチョンミート）、ソーセージ、豆腐、野菜類、鶏卵などが入った味噌汁に、どんぶりに盛ったご飯と、場合によっては副菜もつく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The menu includes miso soup with pork (luncheon meat), sausage, bean curd, vegetables, chicken egg in a large bowl, rice in a bowl and sometimes a side dish.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The menu includes miso soup with pork (luncheon meat), sausage, bean curd, vegetables, chicken egg in a large bowl, a bowl of rice and sometimes a side dish.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The menu includes miso soup with pork (luncheon meat), sausage, bean curd, vegetables, chicken egg in a large bowl, a bowl of rice and sometimes a side dish.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>なお、沖縄県の味噌汁では調理時に油を入れるのが普通であり、具に肉が含まれない場合はラードやマーガリンを加えるなどする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, in Okinawa Prefecture people usually add oil in miso soup when they cook it, and also when no meat is in a miso soup, they add lard or margarine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, in Okinawa Prefecture people usually add oil in miso soup when they cook it, and also when there is no meat in miso soup, they add lard or margarine.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, in Okinawa Prefecture people usually add oil in miso soup when they cook it, and also when there is no meat in miso soup, they add lard or margarine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>これは野菜を軟らかく煮るのに効果があるという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It seems effective to soften vegetables.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It seems effective for softening vegetables.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It seems effective for softening vegetables.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>また豚肉、かまぼこ、こんにゃく、しいたけなどを白味噌仕立てにしたイナムドゥチや、魚汁（さかなじる）という魚（まるごと、あるいはぶつ切り）を具材とした味噌汁などもポピュラーである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also miso soups such as Inamuduchi which is made with ingredients like pork, kamaboko (fish sausage), konnyaku (a gelatinous food made from devil&apos;s-tongue starch), shiitake mushroom and seasoning with white miso, and sakanajiru which is made with fish (whole or chunks) are popular.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also miso soup such as Inamuduchi made with ingredients like pork, kamaboko (fish sausage), konnyaku (a gelatinous food made from devil&apos;s-tongue starch), shiitake mushroom and seasoning with white miso, and sakanajiru made with fish (whole or chunks) are popular.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also miso soup such as Inamuduchi made with ingredients like pork, kamaboko (fish sausage), konnyaku (a gelatinous food made from devil&apos;s-tongue starch), shiitake mushroom and seasoning with white miso, and sakanajiru made with fish (whole or chunks) are popular.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="17">
<tit>
<j>即席味噌汁</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Instant miso soup</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Instant miso soup</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Instant miso soup</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="73">
<j>フリーズドライの具と粉末味噌をお椀に入れ、熱湯をかけるだけで出来る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It can be made only by putting freeze-dry ingredients and powdered miso in a bowl and pouring hot water.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It can be easily made by just by putting freeze-dry ingredients and powdered miso in a bowl and pouring in hot water.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It can be easily made just by putting freeze-dry ingredients and powdered miso in a bowl and pouring in hot water.</e>
<cmt>made by just by→made just byに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>その後、インスタント味噌汁は生味噌を用いた製品が主流となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The mainstream of instant miso soup products has been those with fresh miso.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mainstream instant miso soup products have been those with fresh miso.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mainstream instant miso soup products have been those with fresh miso.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>現在、豚汁や殻付きのあさりが入ったカップ味噌汁など品揃えも豊富になっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are many variations now like a cup of instant miso soup with pork and short-neck clams with shells.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are many variations now like a cup of instant miso soup with pork and short-neck clams with shells.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are many variations now like a cup of instant miso soup with pork and short-neck clams with shells.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Ypacaraí(id:11031), 0null0(id:582), Lupinoid(id:68), JINKY.ECLEO(id:141716), Kamakura(id:472), Hykw-a4(id:14184), 曾孫太郎(id:168176), Opponent(id:720), ぎゅうひ(id:9206), Michey.M(id:906), RON ST(id:156891), 代言人(id:33675), イマリ(id:157949), IwaimBot(id:190695), 11ChamOK(id:100638), Ｋｓ(id:15319), BoB774(id:148281), セルシオ越前(id:138322), マクガイア(id:33346), Balmung0731(id:99201), リファイル(id:91084), Nightmare11(id:150160), SUMAKO(id:206516), ウェルワィ(id:15692), Nikai(id:1648), Otoko2008(id:238382), Neko2(id:21083), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), 午後紅茶(id:14285), Chlewbot(id:33904), KSKS(id:97637), Chiether(id:77421), うら(id:40695), Ptbotgourou(id:229657), ウミユスリカ(id:9504), Charenji(id:7908), Roger(id:9883), 北越6号(id:141986), Kumatora(id:16941), Im224(id:57113), Ix680(id:25168), ShikiH(id:181574), 死郎(id:1683), Basilico(id:9719), Ponta2(id:129030), Clair.S.F.(id:59514), スミス16号(id:189050), 竹麦魚(id:11012), Lonicera(id:20638), Kentin(id:6768), Izayohi(id:13095), Nshn(id:90878), 藤崎景子＠コナ研(id:89741), いすか(id:132539), Eveningmist(id:28648), ウィキページ(id:267182), Gleam(id:4760), 竃馬(id:102733), TottyBot(id:101680), Mochi(id:9489), Fromm(id:71291), Ponsaku(id:31417), 満月(id:82772), Louperibot(id:128971), 1029man(id:93235), ホイップ(id:44812), Katsuya(id:21306), Ete(id:28565), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>