<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>水琴窟</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Suikinkutsu (a traditional Japanese echoing system in the garden, like a water harp)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Suikinkutsu (a traditional Japanese echoing system in the garden, like a water harp)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Suikinkutsu (a traditional Japanese echoing system in the garden, like a water harp)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>水琴窟（すいきんくつ）は、日本庭園の装飾の一つで水滴により琴のような音を発生する仕掛けである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Suikinkutsu is a decoration device in a Japanese garden that generates a sound like the koto (Japanese harp) by drops of water.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Suikinkutsu is a decoration device in a Japanese garden that generates a sound like the koto (Japanese harp) with drops of water.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Suikinkutsu is a decoration device in a Japanese garden that generates a sound like the koto (Japanese harp) with drops of water.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>構造としては底に小さな穴の開いた瓶が逆さに伏せた状態で土中に埋められており、底は水が溜まるように粘土などで固められている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">About structure, it is an inverted jar with a tiny hole in the bottom buried in the soil. The bottom is fixed with clay such that it collects some water.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">About structure, it is an inverted jar with a tiny hole in the bottom buried in the soil. The bottom is fixed with clay such that it collects some water.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">About structure, it is an inverted jar with a tiny hole in the bottom buried in the soil and the bottom is fixed with clay such that it collects some water.</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>上には一般的に手水鉢（ちょうずばち）が置かれておりそこから流れ落ちる水が瓶の穴を通して滴り落ちるようになっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A wash basin (Chozu-bachi) is generally set up in the above, and dropping water from there drips and drops through the hole of the bottle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A wash basin (Chozu-bachi) is generally set above, and water drips from there and drops through the hole of the jar.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A wash basin (Chozu-bachi) is generally set above, and water drips from there and drops through the hole of the jar.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>その時の音が瓶の中で反響し琴の音のような音となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The sound at that time echoes in the bottle and becomes a sound like the sound of a harp.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sound at that time echoes in the bottle and sounds like a harp.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sound at that time echoes in the bottle and sounds like a harp.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>伝統的な水琴窟は茶室前のつくばい（つくばい）に併設されることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A traditional Suikinkutsu is often built in the Tsukubai (stone wash basin found in Japanese gardens) in front of a tea-ceremony house.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A traditional Suikinkutsu is often built in the Tsukubai (stone wash basin found in Japanese gardens) in front of the tea-ceremony house.</e>
<cmt>grammar, word spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A traditional Suikinkutsu is often built in the Tsukubai (stone wash basin found in Japanese gardens) in front of the tea-ceremony house.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>伝統的な構築方法</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Traditional construction method</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Traditional construction method</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Traditional construction method</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>水琴窟でよい音を出すには瓶など各要素の組み合わせとその調整が必要である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order that the Suikinkutsu may emit a good sound, adjustment is necessary for the combination of each element such as the jar.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order for the Suikinkutsu to emit a good sound, adjustment is necessary for the combination of each element, such as the jar.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order for the Suikinkutsu to emit a good sound, adjustment is necessary for the combination of each element, such as the jar.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>最も重要なのは、土中に逆さに置かれた瓶である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The most important thing is an inverted bottle put on the soil.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The most important thing is for an inverted jar put into the soil.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The most important thing is for an inverted jar put into the soil.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>近年は金属製のものもあるが瓶は米や水溜め用の素焼きの陶器のものが水滴を作るのに最も適しているとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though in recent years, there have been also metal jars, it is assumed that the most suitable ones are those unglazed earthenware for keeping rice grains or water.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While in recent years, there have been also metal jars, it is assumed that the most suitable jars are unglazed earthenware for storing rice grain or water.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While in recent years, there have been also metal jars, it is assumed that the most suitable jars are unglazed earthenware for storing rice grain or water.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>深さは30cmから1m、直径は30cmから50cm程度のものを用い底の穴は2cm程度とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The depth is from 30cm to 1m, the diameter is from 30 cm to about 50 cm, and the hole in the bottom is assumed to be about 2cm.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The depth is from 30cm to 1m, the diameter is from 30 cm to about 50 cm, and the hole in the bottom is assumed to be about 2cm.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The depth is from 30cm to 1m, the diameter is from 30cm to about 50cm, and the hole in the bottom is assumed to be about 2cm.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>ひびが入っていたりするとよい音はでない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If there is some crack, good sound may not be given out.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If there is a crack in the jar, it may not result in a good sound.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If there is a crack in the jar, it may not result in a good sound.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>瓶は地面に掘られた穴に水漏れ防止用の粘土または近年はモルタルで固められた上に伏せられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The jar is turned up-side down and fixed onto the ground with clay (or mortar in recent years) to prevent water from leaking into the hole dug up.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The jar is turned up-side down and fixed onto the ground with clay (or mortar in recent years) to prevent water from leaking into the hole that was dug up.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The jar is turned up-side down and fixed onto the ground with clay (or mortar in recent years) to prevent water from leaking into the hole that was dug up.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>古い水琴窟では水が自然に流出するのを待っている方式であったが一定の音色を保てないため、水位を一定に保つ排水用の管を設けるのが一般的となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The old suikinkutsu adopts a method in which water is waited to flow out naturally. However, because it does not keep a constant tone, draining tube is installed in general to keep the water level constant.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The old suikinkutsu adopts a method whereby the water is takes time to flow out naturally. However, because it does not keep a constant tone, a draining tube is installed to keep the water level constant.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The old suikinkutsu adopts a method whereby the water is takes time to flow out naturally, however, because it does not keep a constant tone, a draining tube is installed to keep the water level constant.</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>瓶の周りや上部は小石で全て覆われ、その上に手水鉢が置かれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The surroundings and the upper part of the jar are completely covered with small stones. On the top, the wash basin is put.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The surroundings and the upper part of the jar are completely covered with small stones. A wash basin is placed on top.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The surroundings and the upper part of the jar are completely covered with small stones, and a wash basin is placed on top.</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>音を聞くための竹筒が設けられている場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sometimes, a bamboo cylinder is installed such that the sound can be heard.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sometimes, a bamboo shaft is installed so the sound can be heard.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sometimes, a bamboo shaft is installed so the sound can be heard.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="16">
<j>これらの要素、構造は地域や時代により各種のバリエーションがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These elements and structure have various variations, depending on the region and the era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The elements and structure have variations, depending on the region and the era.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The elements and structure have variations, depending on the region and the era.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>通常、瓶は一つであるが2個の場合もあり愛知県日進市の岩崎城公園や群馬県高崎市の創造学園大学などに例がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Usually, there is only one jar but sometimes there are two. Examples include Iwasaki-jo koen (Iwasaki Site of a Castle Park) in Nisshin City, and University of Creation; Art, Music &amp; Social Work, in Takasaki City of Gunma Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Usually, there is only one jar but sometimes there are two. Examples include Iwasaki-jo koen (Iwasaki Site of a Castle Park) in Nisshin City, and University of Creation; Art, Music &amp; Social Work, in Takasaki City of Gunma Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Usually, there is only one jar but sometimes there are two: examples include Iwasaki-jo koen (Iwasaki Site of a Castle Park) in Nisshin City, and University of Creation; Art, Music &amp; Social Work, in Takasaki City of Gunma Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="18">
<j>現代における様々な試み</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nowadays, there are various designs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nowadays, there are various designs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nowadays, there are various designs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="19">
<j>現代では、伝統にこだわらず、様々なバリエーションの水琴窟の制作が試みられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nowadays, people do not stick to the tradition and try to create various variations of suikinkutsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nowadays, people do not hold on to tradition and they try to create variations of suikinkutsu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nowadays, people do not hold on to tradition and they try to create variations of suikinkutsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>たとえば以下のような例がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For instance, the following examples exist.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For instance, the following examples exist.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For instance, the following examples exist.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="21">
<j>手水鉢が併設されていない、あるいは日本庭園にはない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The wash basin is not built, or, the suikinkutsu is not in a Japanese garden.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is no wash basin suikinkutsu is not in this Japanese garden.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is no wash basin, suikinkutsu is not in this Japanese garden.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除、,補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="22">
<j>水がとぎれることなく連続的に流れるような工夫がされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The set up is such that the water flows continuously without breaking off.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The set up is such that the water flows continuously without any interruptions.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The set up is such that the water flows continuously without any interruptions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="23">
<j>陶器の代りに金属の瓶が用いられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Instead of earthenware, a metal jar is used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Instead of earthenware, a metal jar is used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Instead of earthenware, a metal jar is used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="24">
<j>地面ではなく彫刻などの一部として設置されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Instead of the ground, it is set up a part of a sculpture etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Instead of the ground, it is set up on a part of a sculpture etc.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Instead of the ground, it is set up on a part of a sculpture, etc.</e>
<cmt>,補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="25">
<j>屋内での設置。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Indoor installation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Indoor installation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Indoor installation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="26">
<j>音が聞こえやすいように電子的に増幅されスピーカで流される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order that the sound can be easily heard, it is amplified electronically and broadcasted with speaker.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order for the sound to be easily heard, it is amplified electronically and broadcasted through speaker.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order for the sound to be easily heard, it is amplified electronically and broadcasted through speaker.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="27">
<j>上記のいくつかを兼ね備えた例として京都駅ビルのモニュメント「火の鳥水時計」が挙げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The monument &quot;Phoenix water clock&quot; of Kyoto Station Building is an example having all of the above-mentioned variations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The monument called &quot;The Phoenix water clock&quot; of Kyoto Station Building is an example having all of the above-mentioned variations.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The monument called &apos;The Phoenix water clock&apos; of Kyoto Station Building is an example having all of the above-mentioned variations.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;にスペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>手水鉢の代りにガラスの水時計、連続的な音と増幅、彫刻（正確には漫画のキャラクター）で飾られ日本庭園ではない屋内の駅待合所に設置されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Instead of being a suikinkutsu with a wash basin in a Japanese garden, it is a suikinkutsu of a glass clock of water with continuous amplified sound decorated by a sculpture (to be more precise, it is a character in a comic) built inside the waiting room of the station building.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Instead of being a suikinkutsu with a wash basin in a Japanese garden, it is a suikinkutsu with a glass clock of water emitting a continuous amplified sound decorated by a sculpture (to be more precise, it is a comic book character) built inside the waiting room of the station building.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Instead of being a suikinkutsu with a wash basin in a Japanese garden, it is a suikinkutsu with a glass clock of water emitting a continuous amplified sound decorated by a sculpture (to be more precise, it is a comic book character) built inside the waiting room of the station building.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="29">
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>水琴窟は最初は洞水門（とうすいもん）と呼ばれており庭園に設置されるものではなく手洗い場の排水設備であったらしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It seems that suikinkutsu was first called &quot;Tosuimon (a drain facility of the lavatory)&quot;. It was not built in a garden, but was a facility for drainage at a lavatory for hand washing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It seems that suikinkutsu was first called &quot;Tosuimon (a drain facility of the lavatory)&quot;. It was not built in a garden, but was a facility for drainage of a lavatory basin when washing hands.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It seems that suikinkutsu was first called Tosuimon (a drain facility of the lavatory) that was not built in a garden, but was a facility for drainage of a lavatory basin when washing hands.</e>
<cmt>原文に『』がないので&quot;　&quot;を削除一文にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>それが時々いい音を出すことがわかり庭師により改良されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Noticing that it sometimes gave a good sound, a gardener improved the device.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Noticing that it sometimes gave a good sound, a gardener improved the device.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Noticing that it sometimes gave a good sound, a gardener improved the device.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>水琴窟として知られるようになったのは江戸時代中期である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It became known as suikinkutsu at midd Edo Era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It became known as suikinkutsu during the mid Edo Era.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It became known as suikinkutsu during the mid Edo period.</e>
<cmt>eraに訂正しました。era→ periodに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>そのころの著名な茶人であり庭園作家でもある小堀遠州の発明品という説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that it was invented by the contemporary famous master of tea ceremony Enshu KOBORI, who was also a garden designer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that it was invented by a famous contemporary master of tea ceremony Enshu KOBORI, who was also a garden designer.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that it was invented by a famous contemporary master of tea ceremony Enshu KOBORI, who was also a garden designer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>江戸後期には一旦廃れ、明治時代再興したものの昭和初期にはほとんど忘れられた存在となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In late Edo Era, it was once abolished. Though it was revived at Meiji Era, in early Showa Era</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the late Edo Era, it was once abolished, although it was revived during the Meiji Era, and in the early Showa Era</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the late Edo period, it was once abolished, although it was revived during the Meiji period, and in the early Showa period it was almost forgotten.</e>
<cmt>eraに訂正しました。下の行と統合しました。era→ periodに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>1959年の東京農業大学の平山教授の報告書では二つの例が報告されていたがほとんど地面に埋もれ修復も困難な状況であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a report by professor Hirayama&apos;s of Tokyo University of Agriculture in 1959, there were two examples reported, but most are buried in ground that they are in a difficult situation for restoration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In a report by professor Hirayama&apos;s of Tokyo University of Agriculture in 1959, there were two examples cited, but most were buried in the ground and this was a difficult situation for restoration.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In a report by professor Hirayama&apos;s of Tokyo University of Agriculture in 1959, there were two examples cited, but most were buried in the ground and this was a difficult situation for restoration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>しかし朝日新聞による1982年の報道が多くの水琴窟の再発見へつながった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the report in 1982 by the Asahi Shimbun Newspaper led to the rediscovery of a lot of suikinkutsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, a 1982 article iappeared in the Asahi Shimbun Newspaper that led to the rediscovery of a lot of different types of suikinkutsu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, an article in 1982 appeared in the Asahi Shinbun Newspaper that led to the rediscovery of a lot of different types of suikinkutsu.</e>
<cmt>Shinbunに訂正しました。an article in 1982 に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>このあとの日本放送協会により取り上げられ再び注目されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following report taken by Japan Broadcasting Corporation afterwards brought about public attention again.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following report produced by Japan Broadcasting Corporation, later brought about public attention again.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following report produced by Japan Broadcasting Corporation, later brought about public attention again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>音の出る庭園の装飾物としては他にししおどしもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a garden ornament that emits sound, there was also shishiodoshi (decorative bamboo irrigation pumps). Comparatively speaking, a suikinkutsu has smaller volume and better sound quality. Because of this, it is not uncommon that it was installed in private houses.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a garden ornament that emits sound, there was also the shishiodoshi (decorative bamboo irrigation pumps). Comparatively speaking, a suikinkutsu has smaller volume and better sound quality. Because of this, it was quite commonly installed in private houses.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a garden ornament that emits sound, there was also the shishiodoshi (decorative bamboo irrigation pumps).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>しかし、これに比べ水琴窟は音量が小さく音色もよいことから個人の住宅でも設置される例が少なくない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Comparatively speaking, because a suikinkutsu has smaller volume and better sound quality, it was quite commonly installed in private houses.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理一文にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>音</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sound</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sound</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sound</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="41">
<j>水琴窟の音は水琴音と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The sound of Suikinkutsu is called suikinon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sound of Suikinkutsu is called suikinon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sound of Suikinkutsu is called suikinon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="42">
<j>音はさらに流水音および水滴音の二つに分けることができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The sound can be further classified into two; namely water flowing sound and water dropping sound.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sound can be further classified into two types; namely a water flowing sound and a water dropping sound.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sound can be further classified into two types; namely a water flowing sound and a water dropping sound.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>手を洗っているとき大部分の水は小石や瓶の縁をつたって流れ去るがこれが流水音であり、内側の水滴音とハーモニーする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When one washes one&apos;s hands, the majority of water goes along on the edge of small stones or the jar, flows, and then leaves. This is the water flowing sound, in harmony with the water dropping sound inside.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When one washes one&apos;s hands, the majority of water goes along on the edge of small stones or the jar, it flows, and then leaves. This is the water flowing sound, in harmony with the water dropping sound inside.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When one washes one&apos;s hands, the majority of water goes along on the edge of small stones or the jar, it flows, and then leaves; this is the water flowing sound, in harmony with the water dropping sound inside.</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>手洗いが終わると流水音は徐々に終わり水滴音のみとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When one finishes washing one&apos;s hands, the water flowing sound gradually fades out and it becomes that only the water dropping sound can be heard.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When one finishes washing one&apos;s hands, the water flowing sound gradually fades out and only the water drops can be heard.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When one finishes washing one&apos;s hands, the water flowing sound gradually fades out and only the water drops can be heard.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="45">
<j>よくできた水琴窟は瓶の複数の場所から水が滴り落ちるようになっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A well designed suikinkutsu has water dripping and dropping from multiple positions of the jar.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A well designed suikinkutsu has water dripping and dropping from multiple positions of the jar.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A well designed suikinkutsu has water dripping and dropping from multiple positions of the jar.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>素焼きの瓶がよいのは湿気をよく保持し内面のより多くの場所から滴下が始まるからである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A good unglazed pottery jar has water dripping and dropping from multiple inside positions of which moisture is often maintained.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A good unglazed pottery jar has water dripping and dropping from multiple inside positions where moisture is often maintained.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A good unglazed pottery jar has water dripping and dropping from multiple inside positions where moisture is often maintained.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>音は水滴が水面に落ちたとき発生し瓶の内側で反響、増幅される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The sound is generated when the water drop falls onto the water surface. It is echoed inside the jar and amplified.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sound is generated when the water drop falls onto the water surface. It echoes inside the jar and is amplified.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sound is generated when the water drop falls onto the water surface and echoes inside the jar and is amplified.</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>音色は瓶の形状や大きさ、さらには底の水の溜まり具合など様々な条件で変化する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The sound quality changes in response to various conditions such as the shape and size of the jar, and the moisture condition of the bottom.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sound quality changes in response to various conditions such as the shape and size of the jar, and the moisture condition at the bottom.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sound quality changes in response to various conditions such as the shape and size of the jar, and the moisture condition at the bottom.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="49">
<j>水琴窟は各所にあるが、ひとつとして同じ音の水琴窟はないといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though suikinkutsu can be found in various places, it is said that no two suikinkutsu give the same sound.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though suikinkutsu can be found in various places, it is said that no two suikinkutsu give the same sound.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although suikinkutsu can be found in various places, it is said that no two suikinkutsu give the same sound.</e>
<cmt>Though →Although に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Mnd(id:15140), ＋－(id:17104), Carkuni(id:79281), Izayohi(id:13095), 乱(id:62619), IwaimBot(id:190695), PixelBot(id:166734), Himazin(id:22034), 松岡明芳(id:122110), Yas(id:739), Hide-sp(id:145562), Komura Jutaro(id:35057), うーみん(id:99264), BOT-Superzerocool(id:65015), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>