<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>箏曲</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sokyoku (koto music)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sokyoku (koto music)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sokyoku (koto music)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>箏曲（そうきょく）は、箏（そう）つまり「こと」の音楽。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sokyoku (koto music) is about so which means &quot;koto&quot; music.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sokyoku refers to music for the koto (long zither with 13 strings)</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sokyoku refers to music for the koto (long zither with 13 strings).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>特に現代では近世に発達した俗箏による音楽を指す場合が多く、大きく生田流箏曲と山田流箏曲に分かれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially recently, it is indicated about music by zokuso (modern sokyoku) which developed lately, which is divided widely Ikuta-School sokyoku and Yamada-School sokyoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The word is often used to refer to zokuso (recently developed koto music) which is broadly divided into two schools, the Ikuta school and the Yamada school.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The word is often used to refer to zokuso (recently developed koto music) which is broadly divided into two schools, the Ikuta school and the Yamada school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>三曲のひとつ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of the three songs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It may also refer to the koto part of a sankyoku (a three part piece for a koto, a samisen (three-stringed banjo-type instrument) and a shakuhachi (bamboo flute))</e>
<cmt>Added explanation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It may also refer to the koto part of a sankyoku (a kind of Japanese chamber music with three instruments: a koto, a shamisen (three-stringed banjo-type instrument) and a shakuhachi (bamboo flute)).</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。三曲→a kind of Japanese chamber music with a vocal and a three instruments: a koto, a shamisen (three-stringed banjo-type instrument) and a shakuhachi (bamboo flute)) としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>また、よく合奏される地歌（地歌）も含めた音楽ジャンルとみなされる場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also sometimes it indicated as the type of music which includes jiuta (a genre of traditional songs with samisen accompaniment) that often plays in concert</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Or to a genre of music including jiuta (traditional songs) which are often played in concert.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, in some cases it refers to a genre of music including jiuta (traditional songs) which are often played in concert.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>筑紫箏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsukushi goto (koto from the Tsukushi area of Kyushu)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsukushi goto (koto from the Tsukushi area of Kyushu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsukushi goto (koto from the Tsukushi area of Kyushu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>近世箏曲は、戦国末期から江戸時代はじめにかけて活躍した賢順が完成した「筑紫箏」（つくしごと）を始祖とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Recent sokyoku&apos;s founder is &apos;Tsukushi goto&apos; that Kenjun who was active in end of Sengoku to Edo period completed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Modern Sokyoku began with &apos;Tsukushi goto&apos; (a type of solo koto music) which was completed by Kenjun, a musician who was active at the end of Sengoku (Warring states) and beginning of the Edo periods.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Modern Sokyoku began with &apos;Tsukushi goto&apos; (a type of solo koto music) which was completed by Kenjun, a musician who was active from the end of Sengoku (Warring states) period to the beginning of the Edo periods.</e>
<cmt>一部修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>彼は浄土僧でもあり、寺院に伝承される雅楽や歌謡を修め、また当時来日していた明人の鄭家定に古琴（きん）を学び、 これらから箏曲を作り出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also Jodo Buddhist, and learns Miyabi-gaku and Kayo which was transmitted to the temple, also he learned Kin from Teiketei of Meijin who was visited in Japan and created Sokyoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A Joso Buddhist, Kenjun mastered Gagaku (a type of classical music) and Kayo (rhyming poetry accompanied by music), the traditions maintained by the monks of his temple, and studied the Kokin (Chinese zither with 3000 year history) under Teikatei, a Chinese musician who was in Japan at that time. Drawing on everything he had learnt, he began Sokyoku.</e>
<cmt>鄭家定 is romanized as Teikatei. I couldn&apos;t find any information on　明人　and have therefore omittted it. I have also added explanations where necessary.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenjun, a Jodo priest, mastered gagaku (ancient Japanese court dance and music) and Kayo (songs and ballads) that had been handed down to the monks of his temple, and learned how to play the Kokin (Chinese zither with 3000 year history) from Teikatei, a Chinese musician who was in Japan at that time; drawing on what he had learnt, he began making Sokyoku music.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>これが筑紫箏である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That is the Tsukushi goto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">What he created was &apos;Tsukushi goto&apos;</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">What he created was &apos;Tsukushi goto.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>ただし筑紫箏の音楽は、高尚で雅びであるが娯楽性は少なく、礼や精神性を重んじ、また調弦も雅楽に近い「律音階」に由っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsukushi goto is classic and elegant music but its not very enjoyable because it concerned great manner and spirits, also tune was based &apos;Ritsuonkai&apos; that was close to Miyabi-gaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although classic and elegant, the Tsukushi goto is religious music rather than entertainment. It is uses the &apos;ritsuonkai&apos; scale which is close to that used in Gagaku.</e>
<cmt>I am not entirerly sure about the second sentence of this translation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tsukushi goto was classic and elegant, put emphasis on manner and spiritualness rather than on entertainment, and used the &apos;ritsuonkai&apos; scale which was close to that used in gagaku.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。「&amp;apos;」→「&apos;」に修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>八橋流</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yatsuhashi school</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yatsuhashi school</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yatsuhashi school</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>賢順の弟子の法水に師事したのが当道座に属した盲目の音楽家、八橋検校であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The blind musician Kenko Yatsuhashi who belongs to Todo-za studied from Hosui who was Kenjun&apos;s student.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenko Yatsuhashi was a blind musician who belonged to the Todo-za school and studied from Hosui who himself had been a student of Kenjun.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kengyo (the highest title of the official ranks within the Todo-za) YATSUHASHI was a blind musician who belonged to the Todo-za school and studied from Hosui who himself had been a student of Kenjun.</e>
<cmt>検校の説明を左記のように追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>彼は三味線や胡弓の名手でもあったが、三味線の音楽などではすでに民間の新しい音階である「都節音階」が使われ、普及していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the master of shamisen and Koyumi, but the music like shamisen was already popular with public new tune of &apos;miyakobushi scale&apos; (characteristic Japanese hemitonic pentatonic scale: mi, fa, la, ti, do)&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a famous samisen and Kokum (a fiddle-like instrument) musician. In samisen music, the new &apos;miyakobushi scale&apos; (characteristic Japanese hemitonic pentatonic scale: mi, fa, la, ti, do)&apos; was already in use and popular.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a famous shamisen and kokyu (a Chinese fiddle) musician, but the new &apos;miyakobushi scale&apos; (characteristic Japanese hemitonic pentatonic scale: mi, fa, la, ti, do) was already popularly used for shamisen music.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>八橋はこれを箏に応用し、これまでの律音階による調弦から、都節音階による新たな調弦法である平調子（ひらぢょうし）、雲井調子（くもいぢょうし）に改めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yatsuhashi applied that into sou, and reformed it to new tune system hirajoshi scale (one of the most basic scales of Japanese sokyoku koto music: literally, &quot;tranquil tuning&quot;) and kumoijoshi scale (a scale of Japanese sokyoku koto music: scale based on hirajoshi scale) by miyakobushi scale from the tune by former integrity scales.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yatsuhashi applied this scale to the koto, moving away from tuning according the conventional ritsuonkai scale towards new tuning methods based on the miyakobushi scale, namely the hirajoshi (literally tranquil tuning) and kumochoshi (tuning based on hirajoshi tuning) methods.</e>
<cmt>箏 can also be translated as &quot;koto&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">YATSUHASHI applied this scale to the koto and moved away from tuning based on the conventional ritsuonkai scale towards new tuning methods based on the miyakobushi scale, namely the hirajoshi (literally tranquil tuning) and kumoijoshi (tuning based on hirajoshi tuning) methods.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>以後現在に至るまで、この平調子は箏のもっとも基本の調弦法とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since then the hirajoshi scale became the most basic tuned system of koto to the present.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, the hirajoshi method has remained as the standard tuning method for the koto.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, the hirajoshi method has remained as the standard tuning method for the koto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>こうしてこの新たな調弦法にのっとり、多数の新しい曲を作曲した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He made many new music by that new tuned system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On adopting this tuning method, Yatsuhashi produced a great number of new pieces.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On adopting the new tuning method, YATSUHASHI composed a great number of pieces.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>これらは筑紫箏よりもより世俗的、当世風でかつ芸術性も高く、当時の世に広く受け入れられることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These are more common parlance and fresh, also more artistic than Tukushi goto, so people accepted that at the time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">More worldly and up-to-date than Tsukushi goto music, the pieces were highly accomplished and quickly became popular.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">More temporal and up-to-date than Tsukushi goto music, the pieces were highly artistic and became popular at that time.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>八橋検校の箏作品には「箏組歌」（箏伴奏付き歌曲）と「段物」（器楽曲）の二種があり、いずれも整然とした楽式構造を持つのが特徴である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kengyo Yatsuhashi had two types of So works which is &apos;Sokumiuta&apos; (music with sou accompaniment) and &apos;Danbutsu&apos; (musical instrument), both music features well-organized structures of music system.</e>
<cmt>［検校というのは名前ではなく、官職のようなのですが、どう訳すのが正しいのか不明です。］</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kengyo Yatsuhashi produced two types of work, &apos;Sokumiuta&apos; (songs accompanied on koto) and &apos;Danmono&apos; (music having a number of distinct stages), both featuring a well-organized musical structure.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kengyo YATSUHASHI produced two types of work, i.e. &apos;So-kumiuta&apos; (songs accompanied by koto) and &apos;Danmono&apos; (solo instrumental music for koto), both featuring well-organized musical structures.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。「&amp;apos;」→「&apos;」に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>組歌としては「菜蕗」（ふき）、「雲井の曲」など、段物としては「六段の調」などが知られている（「六段の調」の作曲者について異説もある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fuki (Japanese butterbur)&apos; and &apos;Kumoi no kyoku&apos; are well known as kumiuta (koto suites of songs), rokudan no shirabe (music of six steps) is well known as danmono (most important type in shirabemono (the koto solo instrumental music)) (there is a dissent about composer of &apos;rokudan no shirabe).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Well-known kumiuta (suites of songs) composed by Yatsuhashi include &apos;Fuki (a type of plant)&apos; and &apos;Kumoi no kyoku&apos;, while well-known &quot;Danmono&quot; by him include &apos;Rokudan no shirabe&apos; (music of six steps) (although there is some controversy over who actually composed Rokudan no shirabe).</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Well-known kumiuta composed by YATSUHASHI include titles such as &apos;Fuki&apos; and &apos;Kumoi no kyoku,&apos; while well-known Danmono by him include &apos;Rokudan no shirabe&apos; (music of six steps) (however, there is some controversy over who actually composed &apos;Rokudan no shirabe&apos;).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。「&amp;apos;」→「&apos;」に修正、カンマの位置を移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>八橋以後もこれらの形式による作曲が行なわれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These style of music was kept making even after Yatsuhashi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Composition of this type of music continued after the death of Yatsuhashi.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Composition of this type of music continued after the death of YATSUHASHI.</e>
<cmt>名字を大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>なお 八橋検校の時代には、箏曲、三味線音楽はそれぞれ別の音楽として成立しており、基本的に合奏されることはなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But at Yatsuhashi school time, sokyoku and shamisen music was organized as different type of music, so basically these were not played together.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the era of Yatsuhashi, however, sokyoku and samisen music were seen as being different types of music and, generally speaking, were not played together.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the era of YATSUHASHI, however, sokyoku and shamisen music were seen as being different types of music and, generally speaking, were not played together.</e>
<cmt>名字を大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>八橋検校の弟子たちによって八橋流は継承、発展していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yatsuhashi school was succeed and developed from students of Kengyo Yatsuhashi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The music of the Yatsuhashi school was passed down to later generations by the pupils of Kengyo Yatsuhashi and continued to develop.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The music of the Yatsuhashi school was passed down to later generations by the pupils of Kengyo YATSUHASHI and continued to develop.</e>
<cmt>名字を大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>八橋検校の直接の伝承はその後も長く受け継がれ、現在でも細々と伝えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The direct transmission of Keijun Yatsuhashi is succeeding to long time, even now it teaches to others little by little.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The direct flow of the Yatsuhashi school style from teacher to pupil continued over time, and continues as a trickle to this day.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The direct flow of the Yatsuhashi school style from teacher to pupil continued over time, and continues as a trickle to this day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="23">
<j>生田流系</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ikutaryu School style</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ikutaryu School style</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ikutaryu School style</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>八橋検校ののち、北島検校を経て、元禄の頃に京都の生田検校によって箏曲は改変、整理されたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Jeijun Yatsuhashi and Keijun Kitajima, sokyoku was reformed and organized by Keijun Ikuta in Kyoto in Genroku era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Genroku era, after Kengyo Yatsuhashi and Kengyo Kitajima, sokyoku was reformed and organized by Kengyo Ikuta in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>I think this works better with Genroku era at the beginning of the sentence.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Genroku era, after Kengyo YATSUHASHI and Kengyo KITAJIMA, sokyoku was reformed and organized by Kengyo IKUTA in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>名字を大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>これは実際には師の北島がすでに密かに行なっていたのを生田が受け継ぎ、公にしたとも言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Actually Ikuta took over from the master Kitajima who done that secretly, and he opened to the public.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another theory says that the master Kitajima had already secretly reformed sokyoku, and Ikuta simply made public what he learned from his teacher.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another theory says that actually IKUTA just made public the sokyoku which the master KITAJIMA had already reformed secretly.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>また生田検校は地歌曲に箏を合奏させることを始めたとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also Keijun Ikuta started to ensemble koto into jiuta music.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kengyo Ikuta may have been the first to introduce the koto into jiuta music.</e>
<cmt>Natrual English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kengyo IKUTA may have been the first to introduce the koto into jiuta music.</e>
<cmt>名字を大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>そして三味線の技巧に対応させるため、箏の爪の形状が大きく変えられることとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And it was widely changed the shape of koto pick for technique of shamisen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shape of the samisen pick was then changed substantially to accommodate samisen techniques.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The shape of the koto pick was then changed substantially to accommodate shamisen techniques.</e>
<cmt>koto pick　と変更しました。shamisen　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>ただしこの時代、生田のみならず、大阪の継山検校の継山流などでも同様の流れがあり、実際には必ずしも生田検校一人が行なったことではないと言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But this time, Kengyo style from Kengyo (the highest title of the official ranks within the Todo-za) TSUGUYAMA in Osaka done the same thing with Ikuta, so it was not necessary to say it was only Kengyo Ikuta&apos;s work.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It should be noted, however, that there was a similar movement in the Tsuguyama school in Osaka, and the changes were not necessarily made by Kengyo Ikuta alone (Note that Kengyo, literally &apos;person who makes corrections&apos; is the highest title of the official ranks within the Todo-za)</e>
<cmt>Natural English. In the above sections &quot;検校&quot; is translated as &quot;Keijun&quot; but here it suddenly become &quot;Kengyo&quot;. Which is correct?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It should be noted, however, that there was a similar movement in the Tsuguyama school, led by Kengyo TSUGUYAMA in Osaka, and the changes were not necessarily made by Kengyo IKUTA alone.</e>
<cmt>検校の補足説明は既出のため、削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>この他にも上方では新八橋流、藤池流なども生まれたが、それら各流間の差異は大同小異であり、次第に「生田流系」とでも呼ぶべき一つの流れに収束して行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also Shin Yatsuhashi school (New Yatsuhashi school) and Fujiike school were opened in Kamigata, but these school were very different between each other so it naturally became one style to &apos;Ikuta School Style&apos;.</e>
<cmt>初出の場合Kamigata (Kyoto and Osaka area)とする。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A Shin-yatsuhashi school (New Yatsuhashi school) and Fujiike school were opened in Kamigata (Kyoto and Osaka area), but the styles taught in these schools were very similar and gradually converged to what should be called the &apos;Ikuta School Style&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shin-yatsuhashi school (New Yatsuhashi school) and Fujiike school also were established in Kamigata (Kyoto and Osaka area), but the styles taught in these schools were very similar and gradually integrated into what should be called the &apos;Ikuta School Style.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。「&amp;apos;」→「&apos;」に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>この生田流系はまた多くの派に分かれつつ、幕末までに京、大阪を中心にして、名古屋から中国、九州まで広く行なわれるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also this Ikuta school style started to divide to the many groups, it spread out to Nagoya to Chugoku, Kyushu based on Kyoto and Osaka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also this Ikuta school continued to divide into groups, spreading out and eventually reaching Nagoya and then Chugoku and Kyushu from its base in Kyoto and Osaka.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also this Ikuta school again divided itself into several groups, spreading out and from its base in Kyoto and Osaka and eventually reaching Nagoya, Chugoku and Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="31">
<j>山田流</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamada school</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yamada school</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamada school</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>上方で箏曲が早くから隆盛していたのに比べ、中期まで江戸ではあまり人気がなかったのか、演奏する人が少なかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Probably koto was not very popular in Edo so not many people played there compare with Kamigata where sokyoku was popular earlier.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although koto music prospered from an early stage in Kamigata, it was not initially popular in Edo (present-day Tokyo) and there were not many koto musicians there.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although koto music had been popular from an early stage in Kamigata, there were not many koto musicians in Edo (present-day Tokyo) until the middle period for its less popularity.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>そこで総検校の安村検校（1732年検校登官）は、江戸への勢力拡大を図り、弟子の長谷富検校を江戸へ下らせ、生田流系箏曲を広めさせたと言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kengyo YASUMURA (kengyo tokan in 1732) of all of kengyo tried to spread his power to Edo, he sent his student Kengyo Hasetomi to Edo to spread Ikuta school style sokyoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kengyo YASUMURA (head of the school in 1732) attempted to increase his influence in Edo, sending his pupil Kengyo Hasetomi to Edo to spread Ikuta school style sokyoku.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, Kengyo (the highest title of the official ranks within the Todo-za) YASUMURA who was the sokengyo (president of the Todo-za) (he became kengyo in 1732) attempted to increase his influence in Edo by sending his pupil Kengyo HASETOMI to Edo to spread Ikuta school style sokyoku.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。スペース追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>その弟子山田松黒に教えを受けたのが山田検校斗養一であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toyoichi Kengyo YAMADA was the person who had the lecture from the student Shokoku YAMADA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kengyo Hasetomi then taught Shokuku Yamada who in turn taught Kengyo Toyochi YAMADA.</e>
<cmt>I think this is correct, though Hasetomi is not mentioned by name in the source.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kengyo HASETOMI then taught Shokoku YAMADA who in turn taught Kengyo Toyochi YAMADA.</e>
<cmt>名字を大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>彼は江戸っ子好みの浄瑠璃を取り入れた新作を作り、山田流箏曲を創始した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He made a new music with joruri that people in Edo likes, and started to create Yamada school sokyoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He created new music influenced by joruri (ballad drama) which was popular in Edo, and started the Yamada school of sokyoku.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He created new music influenced by joruri (ballad drama) which was popular in Edo, and started the Yamada school of sokyoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>山田は大変な美声の持ち主で、銭湯で歌ってはその技と曲を知らしめたと言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">People said Yamada had very beautiful voice and show his technique of singing at publish bath.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Yamada had a very beautiful voice and would show off his technique and songs by singing in public baths.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that YAMADA had a very beautiful voice and would show off his technique and songs by singing in public baths.</e>
<cmt>名字を大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>かれはまた箏の改良も試み、より音量の大きな箏を完成させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also he tried to improve the koto and completed the koto which makes more volume.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also attempted to improve the koto, and succeeded in making a larger koto which produced a louder sound.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also attempted to enhance koto, and succeeded in making a koto which made a louder sound.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>これを山田箏と呼び、現在では生田流諸派においても広く山田箏が愛用されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is called Yamada koto, even people in Ikuta school group prefer to use Yamada koto lately.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This result is known as the Yamada koto, and enjoys great popularity today, even among the groups of the Ikuta school</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The koto made as a result of such enhancement is known as the Yamada koto, and enjoys great popularity today among the groups of the Ikuta school.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>こうして山田流箏曲は江戸人の嗜好に合い、以後江戸を中心に東日本に普及して、生田流と肩を並べる大流派となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamada school style sokyoku matched to the taste of people in Edo, and developed in the east Japan which based on Edo after that, and became a big group like Ikuta school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Yamada school style fitted the tastes of people in Edo, and thereafter spread through eastern Japan from Edo, eventually becoming a movement akin to the Ikuta school.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Yamada school style fitted the tastes of people in Edo, and thereafter spread through eastern Japan from Edo, eventually becoming a movement akin to the Ikuta school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>山田流箏曲は一中節などの浄瑠璃風の歌が中心である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamada school sokyoku is mainly joruri style song such as icchubushi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yamada school sokyoku is based around the songs of icchubushi (a particular type of joruri style) and other songs of the joruri style.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamada school sokyoku is based around the songs of icchubushi (a particular type of joruri style) and other songs of the joruri style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="41">
<j>地歌との一体化、三曲合奏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Unity of jiuta, trio</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unification of sokyoku with jiuta and the three instrument ensemble</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unification of sokyoku with jiuta and the three instrument ensemble</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>その後、生田流系の箏曲は箏曲独自の作曲が次第に下火になり、幕末に至るまで、厖大な数の地歌曲にパートとして合奏、参加することで発展していく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, the original sokyoku song of Ikuta school style getting declined, but it developed to join the jiuta music as a part of ensemble.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, song-making of the original Ikuta school style went into gradual decline but contributed, towards the end of the Edo era, the koto parts of an enormous number of jiuta songs.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While the original style of sokyoku went into gradual decline towards the end of the Edo period, sokyoku of the Ikuta school style prospered as a result of its contributing the koto parts for an enormous number of jiuta songs.</e>
<cmt>The meaning of this retranslation doesn&apos;t seem very clear to me, I&apos;m afraid (especially &quot;Ikuta style sokyoku developed by playing as the koto part of the enormous number of jiuta songs&quot;) so I have had to rewrite it quite a bit.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>地歌の肩を借り、地歌の後を追う形で進んで行ったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They got helped from Jiuta, and they developed run after jiuta.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thanks to its role in jiuta, song-making in the Ikuta school style could survive.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thanks to its role in jiuta, sokyoku survived.</e>
<cmt>翻訳を一部修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>つまり多くの地歌曲は、箏のパートが作られ合奏されるようになって、箏曲のジャンルともなったことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many jiuta music was started to ensemble with koto part and became a genre of sokyoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many jiuta songs were now made with a koto part and for an ensemble, and jiuta thus became a genre of sokyoku.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many jiuta songs were now made with a koto part and for an ensemble, and jiuta thus became a genre of sokyoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>こうして地歌と箏曲の一体化が進んでいった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thusly, jiuta and sokyoku became unity and developed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And, as a consequence, the unification of jiuta and sokyoku was a step closer.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently, the unification of jiuta and sokyoku was promoted.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>また、さらに胡弓が合奏に加わるようになり、これら三種の楽器による合奏がよく行なわれるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also Chinese fiddle joined to ensemble and started to have ensemble with these three instruments.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A koyumi (Chinese fiddle) was added to the ensemble, and it then became common to perform concerts including these three instruments.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, kokyu came to be added to the ensemble, and then performing concerts using these three instruments became common.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>これを三曲合奏と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is called trio.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The music performed by such a trio was called &apos;sankyokugasso&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Romanized 三曲合奏</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The music performed by such a trio was called &apos;sankyokugasso&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>後に尺八が加わり、現代では三弦、箏、尺八による三曲合奏が圧倒的に多くなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later shakuhachi joined the ensemble, now there are many trio ensembles with shamisen, koto, and shakuhachi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later the shakuhachi was included, and in modern times the vast majority of trio ensembles are composed of a samisen, a koto, and a shakuhachi.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later the shakuhachi was added to the ensemble and in modern times the vast majority of trio ensembles are composed of a shamisen, a koto, and a shakuhachi.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="49">
<j>江戸時代中期以降、大阪の峰崎勾当、三ツ橋勾当らにより器楽部分である手事を重要視した地歌の楽曲形式「手事物」が完成される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After middle of Edo period, the music of jiuta style &apos;tegotomono&apos; which is regarded to tegoto that is the part of instrument was completed by Koto MINEZAKI of Osaka, and Koto MITSUHASHI..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The middle of the Edo period saw the completion, by Koto MINEZAKI and Koto MITSUHASHI, of a jiuta musical style called &apos;tegotomono&apos; in which the instrumental part between songs was emphasized.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The mid Edo period and onward saw the completion, by Koto MINEZAKI and Koto MITSUHASHI, of a jiuta musical style called &apos;tegotomono&apos; in which importance was placed on the instrumental part between songs.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。「&amp;apos;」→「&apos;」に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>それに引き続き京都の松浦検校、石川勾当、菊岡検校らが京都地歌の曲を多数作曲し、それらの曲に八重崎検校らが箏のパートを作曲した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Continue to that Kengyo MATSUUA, Koto ISHIKAWA, Kengyo KIKUOKA created many music of Kyoto jika, and Kengyo YAEZAKI and others created koto part for these, it developed as enjoyable complicated ensemble of koto music with development of jika.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Using this, Kengyo MATSUUA, Koto ISHIKAWA and Kengyo KIKUOKA composed a large number of Kyoto jiuta for which Kengyo YAEZAKI and others wrote the koto parts, the result being koto music which could be enjoyed both as the best of jiuta and as sophisticated concert music.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Using this style, Kengyo MATSUUA, Koto ISHIKAWA and Kengyo KIKUOKA composed a large number of Kyoto jiuta for which Kengyo YAEZAKI and others wrote the koto parts.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>地歌の隆盛とともに複雑な合奏を楽しめる箏曲として発展した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, it was developed as sokyoku which could be enjoyed as sophisticated concert music along with jiuta&apos;s populatiry.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。一原文一訳文の例外対処「&amp;apos;」→「&apos;」に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>これら京都で作られた曲群を「京もの」「京流手事もの」と呼び、更に光崎検校、吉沢検校、幾山検校らに引き継がれて行く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These music that created in Kyoto is called &apos;Kyo mono&apos; and &apos;Kyoryu shuji mono&apos;, it succeeded to Kengyo MITSUZAKI, Kengyo YOSHIZAWA, Kengyo IKUYAMA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The music created in Kyoto is called &apos;Kyo mono&apos; or &apos;Kyoryu tegoto mono&apos;, and was passed down to Kengyo MITSUZAKI, Kengyo YOSHIZAWA and Kengyo IKUYAMA.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The music created in Kyoto is called &apos;Kyo mono&apos; or &apos;Kyoryu tegoto mono,&apos; and was passed down to Kengyo MITSUZAKI, Kengyo YOSHIZAWA and Kengyo IKUYAMA.</e>
<cmt>括弧の位置を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="53">
<j>幕末</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">End of Edo Period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">End of Edo Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">End of Edo period</e>
<cmt>小タイトル用に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>さらに江戸時代後期には、光崎検校、吉沢検校らによって箏曲は一段と発展する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, sokyoku developed more by Kengyo MITSUZAKI, Kengyo YOSHIZAWA in end of Edo Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sokyoku was further developed by Kengyo MITSUZAKI and Kengyo YOSHIZAWA at the end of the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sokyoku was further developed by Kengyo MITSUZAKI and Kengyo YOSHIZAWA at the end of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>periodを小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>これまでリードを続けてきた地歌は、すでにこれ以上進みようがないほど音楽的に頂点に達し、音楽家たちは新たな展開を箏や胡弓に求めることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The jika which continued to develop reached to the top of the music was not able to go on anymore, the musicians seek expanding of koto or Chinese fiddle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jiuta had represented the cutting edge, but were now seen to have reached a level which could not be surpassed, and this led musicians looked for new ways to develop koto and koyumi music.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jiuta had represented the cutting edge, but were now seen to have reached a level which could not be surpassed, and this led musicians look for new ways to develop koto and kokyu music.</e>
<cmt>kokyuとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>こうして、実に久しぶりに、地歌から離れた箏曲が再び作られ始める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thusly, sokyoku that was separated from jika started to make in a long while.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, for the first time in a long time, peopled started to make sokyoku outside the filed of jiuta.</e>
<cmt>Somewhere along the line &quot;jiuta&quot; has become &quot;jika&quot;. &quot;jiuta&quot; is correct.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, for the first time in a long time, people started to make sokyoku outside the field of jiuta.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>光崎検校は古い箏曲を見直し、組歌と段物を組み合わせた「秋風の曲」や、複雑精緻な高低二重奏曲である「五段砧」を作曲した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kengyo MITSUZAKI looked over old sokyoku and made &apos;Akikaza no kyoku&apos; which combined kumiuta (koto suites of songs) and danmono (most important type in shirabemono (the koto solo instrumental music)), and &apos;Godanginuda koto music&apos; which is a complicated and delicate high and low double music.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After looking over the old sokyoku, Kengyo MITSUZAKI composed &apos;Akikaze no kyoku (Song of the Autumn Wind)&apos; which combined kumiuta (suites of koto songs), danmono (koto music having a number of distinct stages), and &apos;Godanginuda&apos;, koto duet music with a sophisticated and delicate melody.</e>
<cmt>Natural English.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After looking over the old sokyoku, Kengyo MITSUZAKI composed &apos;Akikaze no kyoku&apos; (Song of the Autumn Wind) which combined kumiuta, danmono, and &apos;Godanginuda,&apos; a kind of koto duet music that makes use of high and low-pitched sounds to produce a sophisticated and delicate melody.</e>
<cmt>I agree that, as kumiuta and danmono have already been defined, there is no need to provide another explanation here.I have rewritten the last part of the sentence to make it read more naturally.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>また吉沢検校は、雅楽の盤渉調からヒントを得て古今調子と呼ばれる調弦法を考案した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also Kengyo YOSHIZAWA thought up a scale system which is called kokinchoshi scale by the idea from Banshikicho of gagaku (ancient Japanese court dance and music), and made &apos;Chidori no kyoku&apos;, &apos;Haru no kyoku&apos;, &apos;Natsu no kyoku&apos;, &apos;Aki no kyoku&apos;, &apos;Fuyu no kyoku&apos; by the scale system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Getting the idea from Banshikicho of gagaku (ancient Japanese court dance and music), Kengyo YOSHIZAWA also invented a tuning method called &apos;kokinchoshi (ancient tuning method)&apos; and based on this method composed &apos;Chidori no kyoku (song of the plover)&apos;, &apos;Haru no kyoku (song of the spring)&apos;, &apos;Natsu no kyoku (song of the summer)&apos;, &apos;Aki no kyoku (song of the Autumn)&apos;, &apos;Fuyu no kyoku (song of the Winter)&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Natural English.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Getting the idea from Banshikicho of gagaku, Kengyo YOSHIZAWA invented a tuning method called &apos;kokinchoshi&apos; (ancient tuning method).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。一原文一訳文の例外対処「&amp;apos;」→「&apos;」に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>この調弦法による「千鳥の曲」、「春の曲」、「夏の曲」、「秋の曲」、「冬の曲」を作曲した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based on this method, he composed &apos;Chidori no kyoku&apos; (song of the plover), &apos;Haru no kyoku&apos; (song of the spring), &apos;Natsu no kyoku&apos; (song of the summer), &apos;Aki no kyoku&apos; (song of the Autumn), and &apos;Fuyu no kyoku&apos; (song of the Winter).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。一原文一訳文の例外対処「&amp;apos;」→「&apos;」に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>このころから、箏曲は三弦音楽から独立して新たに独自の発展を遂げていくことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around this time, sokyoku developed newly and independently from shamisen (three-stringed Japanese guitar) music.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From this point onwards, sokyoku developed independently from samisen music.</e>
<cmt>Already have an explanation of shamisen.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From this point onwards, sokyoku developed independently from shamisen music.</e>
<cmt>shamisenとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>なお、吉沢検校による革新的な古今調子の考案や、それに基づく作曲は、箏本来の曲を目指したこと、曲の歌詞などに古今和歌集の和歌を多用したことなどから、復古主義と呼ばれることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, sometimes it is called revisionism from the idea of innovative kokinchoshi scale by Kengyo YOSHIZAWA, and the music which was based on that was going to the original music of koto, and it uses the waka words of music from Kokin Wakashu&apos; (A Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Note that the innovative new tuning method developed by Kengyo Yoshizawa and the new compositions based on it were a harkback to the beginnings of koto music, and the lyrics to the music were often from the waka of Kokin Wakashu&apos; (A Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry), and so this music is sometimes seen as being reactionary.</e>
<cmt>復古主義　is &quot;reactionism&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Note that the innovative tuning method developed by Kengyo YOSHIZAWA and compositions based on it aimed at going back to the beginnings of koto music, and the lyrics to the music were often used from the waka of Kokin Wakashu (A Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry), and so this music is sometimes seen as being reactionary.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="62">
<j>明治以降</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Meiji Period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the Meiji period onwards</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the Meiji period onwards</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>明治時代に入り、箏曲の地歌からの独立は進み、寺島花野の「新高砂」など、「明治新曲」と呼ばれる、箏のみの曲が多く作られていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Meiji Period, independence of koto from jika was developed, and many music with only koto was made which is called &apos;New Meiji music&apos; such as &apos;Shin Takasago song (literally, &quot;new version of &quot;Takasago&quot;)&apos; by Hanano TERASHIMA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Meiji Period, sokyoku became increasingly independent from jiuta, and many pieces of so-called New Meiji music were composed solely for the koto, one these being &apos;Shin Takasago (literally, &quot;new version of Takasago&quot;)&apos; by Hanano TERASHIMA.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Meiji period, sokyoku became increasingly independent from jiuta, and many pieces of so-called &apos;New Meiji music&apos; were composed solely for the koto, one of these being &apos;Shin Takasago&apos; (literally, &quot;new version of Takasago&quot;) by Hanano TERASHIMA.</e>
<cmt>periodを小文字にしました。 Of　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>ただし楽曲形式的にはほとんど地歌の手事物の踏襲であり、またこの時代でも、三味線と箏のための曲も引き続き作られてはいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But the style of the music is almost stick to tegotomono of jika, also this time, the music for shamisen and koto was continued to create.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, this music largely adhered to the traditions of tegotomono in jiuta, and the composition of music for the samisen and koto continued in this period.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, this music largely adhered to the traditions of tegotomono in jiuta, and the music for shamisen and koto continued to be composed in this period.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>さらに、大正・昭和の時代になって宮城道雄が伝統に根ざし、西洋音楽などの影響も受けた新たな曲を多数発表した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, Michio MIYAGI announced many new music which is a traditional and also influenced by Western music in Taisho and Showa period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Taisho and Showa periods Michio MIYAGI released many new pieces which had their roots in traditional music but also drew from Western music.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Taisho and Showa periods Michio MIYAGI released many new pieces which had their roots in traditional music but also drew from Western music.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>主なものとして尺八との合奏曲である「春の海」がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The masterpiece is &apos;Haru no umi&apos; which is an ensemble with shakuhachi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Of these, the masterpiece is &apos;Haru no umi (The sea in springtime)&apos; for an ensemble including a shakuhachi.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Of these, the masterpiece is &apos;Haru no umi&apos; (The sea in springtime) for an ensemble including a shakuhachi.</e>
<cmt>括弧の位置を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>また宮城は、チェロ並みの低音域を持つ十七絃（通常の箏は十三弦）や八十弦箏を開発した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also MIYAGI developed seventeen strings which has low tone like a cello (normally koto has thirteen strings), and koto with eighty strings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MIYAGI also developed a seventeen-stringed koto which has low tone like a cello and an eighty-stringed koto (a normal koto has 13 strings).</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MIYAGI also developed a seventeen-stringed koto which has low tone like a cello and an eighty-stringed koto (a normal koto has 13 strings).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>このうち十七弦箏は、邦楽合奏における低音楽器として現在でも広く使われ、独奏曲も生まれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The koto with seventeen strings is used as a low tone instrument on domestic ensemble lately, and also solo music is created.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The seventeen-stringed koto is still used today in ensembles to provide low notes and has had solos composed specifically for it.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The seventeen-stringed koto is still used today in ensembles for Japanese music to provide low notes and has had solos composed specifically for it.</e>
<cmt>邦楽　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="69">
<j>ことに大正末から昭和10年代にかけ、新しい作曲運動が大きな盛り上がりを見せ、宮城の他にも久本玄智、中村双葉、町田嘉声、中能島欣一、高森高山らにより、新しい形式、編成、作曲法による新曲がおびただしく作られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The new music campaign was surge of big movement from end of Taisho period to 10&apos;s of Showa period, other than MIYAGI, Genchi HISAMOTO, Soyo NAKAMURA, Kasei MACHIDA, Kinichi NAKANOSHIMA and Takayama TAKAMORI created new style, arrangement and composition of music.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The new music movement was at its most productive from the end of Taisho period to around the 20th year of the Showa period, and a huge amount of new music with new styles, arrangements and composition methods was created by both MIYAGI and others such as Genchi HISAMOTO, Soyo NAKAMURA, Kasei MACHIDA, Kinichi NAKANOSHIMA and Takayama TAKAMORI.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The movement of making new music was grew strong from the end of Taisho period to around 1935-1944, and a huge amount of new music with new styles, arrangements and composition methods was created by MIYAGI and others such as Genchi HISAMOTO, Soyo NAKAMURA, Kasei MACHIDA, Kinichi NAKANOSHIMA and Takayama TAKAMORI.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>これらを「新日本音楽」と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This music is called &apos;new Japanese music&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Source text in wrong area.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This music is called &apos;new Japanese music.&apos;</e>
<cmt>括弧の位置を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="71">
<j>戦後になると、邦楽系の作曲家に加え、これまで邦楽には疎かったクラシック系の作曲家も創作に参入するようになってきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the war, the composer of traditional Japanese music and the classic music composer which was ill-informed to traditional Japanese music was started to join to create the music.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the war, composers of traditional Japanese music and composers of classical music, who were ill-informed about traditional Japanese music started to collaborate in the creation of music.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the war, not only composers of traditional Japanese music but also composers of classical music who were unfamiliar with traditional Japanese music started to collaborate in the creation of music.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>現代音楽音楽の観点からは次第にクラシック音楽との違いが希薄になり、箏曲に限らずこうして創作される邦楽系の曲群を「現代邦楽」と呼んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gradually the difference from classic music and the view of modern music became weak, so the group of Japanese music which created like that is called &apos;modern Japanese music&apos; which is not specified only sokyoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gradually the distinction between what was viewed as classical and what was viewed as modern music blurred, and &apos;modern Japanese music&apos; came to mean all music composed in this way (rather than just new sokyoku).</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gradually the distinction between what was viewed as classical and what was viewed as modern music blurred, and &apos;modern Japanese music&apos; came to mean all music composed in this way (rather than just new sokyoku).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>現代でも西洋音楽やポピュラー音楽など、幅広い分野の影響を受けて、新しい曲が作曲されており、それらは三曲、箏曲の世界において「現代曲」と呼ばれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even now new music is created which influenced by many type of music such as western music and popular music, there are called &apos;modern music&apos; at the sankyoku and sokyoku world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The composition of new music which draws on a wide range of music including western and popular music continues to this day, and such music is all known as &apos;modern music&apos; in the worlds of sankyoku and sokyoku.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The composition of new music influenced by a wide range of music including western and popular music continues to this day, and such music is known as &apos;modern music&apos; in the worlds of sankyoku and sokyoku.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。「&amp;apos;」→「&apos;」に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>最近の傾向としては比較的ポピュラーに近いもの、またアジア的要素の強い曲が増えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It relatively tend to close to the popular music lately, also the music with traditional Asian style is increasing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Writing music which comparatively close to pop music is one recent trend and music with strong Asian feel is increasing.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Recently more music pieces which are comparatively similar to pop music or have strong Asian feel are being composed.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>音楽的特徴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The characteristic of music style</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Features of music</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Features of music</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="75">
<j>近世邦楽としての箏曲は本来「組歌」という歌のみの楽曲形式による曲を最も正式なジャンルとし、またその後も地歌とともに発展したため、歌のついている曲が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The sokyoku as modern Japanese music is originally the style of music with only song is a official genre which called &apos;kumika&apos;, also after that it was developed with jiuta, so there is many music with song.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since music following the arrangement of songs in the kumiuta style is the most formal style and later music was developed together with jiuta, much sokyoku music comes together with a song.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A lot of sokyoku music pieces have lyrics since the most formal style of sokyoku as early-modern traditional Japanese music is &apos;kumiuta,&apos; which is composition style of songs with vocals only, and sokyoku have been developed along with jiuta.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>純粋な器楽曲は江戸時代を通じ、「段もの」と「砧もの」の数曲のみである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The pure instrument music is only few which are &apos;Danmono&apos; and &apos;Kinumono&apos; since Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The only purely instrumental music from the Edo period is &apos;Danmono&apos; and &apos;Kinumono&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The only purely instrumental music from the Edo period is &apos;Danmono&apos; and &apos;Kinumono.&apos;</e>
<cmt>括弧の位置を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>しかし江戸時代後期には器楽部分を重要視する地歌の形式である「手事もの」が非常に発展したので、それに合わせて器楽的展開が見られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But &apos;Tegotomono&apos; which is the style of jiuta focused on the part of instrument was improved a lot in late of Edo period, it appeared that expand of instrument for that.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the late Edo period saw great developments in &apos;Tegotomono&apos;, a style of jiuta in which the part of the instrument is important, and this led to innovations in the koto itself.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the late Edo period saw great developments in &apos;Tegotomono,&apos; a style of jiuta in which instrumental parts of music were regarded important, and this led to innovations of the instruments.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。「&amp;apos;」→「&apos;」に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>一方、山田流箏曲は一中節など浄瑠璃の音楽要素を取り入れて作曲されているため、「段もの」及び「四段砧」を除きほとんど全ての曲が歌付きである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, Yamada school sokyoku installed constituent of music from joruri such as icchubushi to write a music, so most of their music except &apos;Danmono&apos; and &apos;Yodanginuda koto music&apos; has song.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Yamada school sokyoku, meanwhile, took in constituents of joruri (ballad plays) such as icchubushi, and so, with the exceptions of &apos;Danmono&apos; and &apos;Yodanginuda koto music&apos;, the music from this school all includes songs.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the Yamada school sokyoku, meanwhile, took in elements of joruri such as icchubushi, the music from this school all includes songs with the exceptions of &apos;Danmono&apos; and &apos;Yodanginuda koto music.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。「&amp;apos;」→「&apos;」に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>歌のついている曲の場合、演奏家は歌を歌いながら演奏する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Musician plays instrument with singing a song for the music with song.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When a song is associated with the music, the musician plays while singing.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In cases where the music has lyrics, the musician plays the musical instrument while singing.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>箏の奏法は、筑紫箏を通じ雅楽の箏の奏法が取り入れられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Playing koto adopted the style of gagaku koto through Tsukushi goto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The way of playing the koto has picked up influences from both gagaku koto and tsukushi goto.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The method of playing koto has picked up influences from playing method of koto in gagaku through tsukushi goto which had been influenced by gagaku.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>三本の右手指に爪をはめて奏する点も変わっていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The way to put picks on three of right fingers has not been changed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The addition of picks to three fingers on the right hand remains unchanged.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The addition of picks to three fingers on the right hand remains unchanged.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>ただ三味線と合奏することになってから、三味線の奏法に対応するため、爪の形に大幅な変革が行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But after it played together with shamiseen, the shape of pick changed widely for the way to play with shamisen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But when the koto came to be played together with the samisen, the shape of pick changed substantially to enable the musician to play the samisen too.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the koto came to be played together with the shamisen, however, the shape of the pick was changed substantially to enable the musician to play the shamisen as well.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>中でも三味線には特に「スクイ」という技法が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially shamisen has a technique of &apos;sukui&apos;, so the pick of koto of Ikuta School and Yamada School are able to play for that.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The so-called &apos;sukui&apos; technique is the most common of the samisen techniques, and so the koto pick of the Ikuta School and Yamada School was adapted so that this technique could be used.</e>
<cmt>Clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The so-called &apos;sukui&apos; (a technique of playing the koto, literally, &quot;skimming&quot;) is often used when playing shamisen.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>そのため、生田流、山田流の箏の爪ではそれができるようになっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, the koto pick of the Ikuta School and Yamada School adapted a shape with which this technique could be applied.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>地歌合流期の初期段階では、地歌の三弦の旋律とほぼ同様の旋律を演奏する曲が多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the beginning of the time when jika plays with koto, there are many music played almost same melody as sangen of jika.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the initial stages of the fashion for jiuta, there were many pieces with melodies which strongly resembled those of jiuta for the samisen.</e>
<cmt>Clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the initial stage of merging with jiuta, there were many pieces with melodies that were almost the same as those for the shamisen part in jiuta.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>また、器楽部分では掛け合いと呼ばれる類似の旋律を三弦と交互に演奏するような作曲もみられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, there is a composition called kakeai that plays similar melody by shamisen and koto alternately at a part of instrumental music</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were also compositions with parts (called &quot;kakeai&quot;) which are interchangeable between the koto and samisen.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were also compositions with parts (called &quot;kakeai&quot;) which are interchangeable between the koto and shamisen.</e>
<cmt>shamisen としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>その後、一般的に替手（かえで）と呼ばれる、地歌の三弦の旋律を引き立て、装飾するような複雑な旋律の作曲が多くなってゆく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, the composition became more decorative and complicated melody which brought out the melody of shamisen of jika which is called kaede generally.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, more compositions appeared with sophisticated melodies provided to make the melody of the samisen stand out within the jiuta.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, more compositions called &quot;kaede&quot; appeared with sophisticated melodies provided to make the melody of the shamisen stand out within the jiuta.</e>
<cmt>shamisen としました。替手 を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>さらに、地歌から独立した作曲が多くなってゆくと、箏独特の奏法を駆使した旋律による曲が作曲されるようになっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, the composition that separated from jika increased, the melody with good command of performance of unique koto music was composed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, as more compositions independent of jiuta appeared, music with melodies driven by the unique sound of the koto came to be written.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, as more music pieces composed independent of jiuta appeared, music came to be written that has melodies making full use of the unique technique of koto playing method.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="89">
<j>ただし、これらは箏曲として作曲された曲に限る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But these are only music that plays for sokyoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Note that the only compositions of this type are those specifically composed as sokyoku.</e>
<cmt>Isn&apos;t this a statement of the obvious?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Note that the only compositions of this type are those specifically composed as sokyoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>この他にも、箏は地歌の曲のほとんどすべてと合奏可能である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Except that, koto is able to ensemble with almost all jiuta music.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The koto is also able join the ensemble in nearly all jiuta music.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The koto is also able to join the ensemble in nearly all jiuta music.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>詳しくは地歌の項目を参照のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Please see the section of jiuta for detail.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Please see the jiuta section for details.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Please see the jiuta section for details.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>また胡弓本曲の伴奏として、胡弓と合奏されることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also it plays as accompaniment for Chinese fiddle, and ensemble with Chinese fiddle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The koto is also used as an accompaniment for the koyumi (Chinese fiddle) and in ensemble with the koyumi.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The koto is also used as an accompaniment for the kokyu and in ensemble with the kokyu.</e>
<cmt>kokyu　に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 氷鷺(id:73707), PiaCarrot(id:2115), Mymelo(id:122034), Yukichin(id:725), TS(id:481), Ando masateru(id:117537), Point136(id:211299), Yas(id:739), 0太郎(id:7375), Hermes(id:21387), 詠狸庵(id:41048), Mitsunari.u(id:103954), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>