<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>地久</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chikyu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chikyu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chikyu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>地久（ちきゅう）とは、雅楽の一曲。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chikyu&apos; is a piece of gagaku (ancient Japanese court dance and music).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chikyu is a piece from gagaku (an ancient Japanese court dance and music).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chikyu is a piece from gagaku (an ancient Japanese court dance and music).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>別名「円地楽」「円池楽」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also known as &apos;Enchiraku&apos; or &apos;Enikeraku.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「円地楽」「円池楽」読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also known as &quot;Enchiraku&quot; or &quot;Enikeraku.&quot;</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also known as &apos;Enchiraku&apos; or &apos;Enikeraku.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>右方（高麗楽）に属する四人舞。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a dance performed by a team of four dancers and belongs to Uho (a style of Japanese court dance and music, or the Komagaku music).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a dance performed by a team of four dancers and belongs to the Uho (a style of Japanese court dance and music, or the Komagaku music).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a dance performed by a team of four dancers and belongs to the Uho (a style of Japanese court dance and music, or the Komagaku music).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>高麗双調（こまそうじょう）の平舞。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a Hiramai Dance (slow dance) of Koma-sojo (one of Japanese chromatic scale based on Am).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a Hira-mai Dance (a slow-paced dance) utilizing Koma-sojo (one of Japanese chromatic scale based on A minor).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a Hira-mai Dance (a slow-paced dance) utilizing Koma-sojo (one of Japanese chromatic scale based on A minor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>襲装束（かさねしょうぞく）に面を着け、牟子(むし)・別甲を用いる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A dancer wears Kasane-shozoku costume (costume for Noh) and a mask and uses Mushi (a piece of cloth) and Chikyu-spefcified hat shaped like a phoenix.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It involves wearing a Kasane-shozoku costume (a costume for Noh) and a mask, and uses a Mushi (a piece of cloth) and a Chikyu-spefcific hat in the form of a phoenix.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It involves wearing a Kasane-shozoku costume (a costume for Noh) and a mask, and uses a mushi (a piece of cloth) and a betsu-kabuto (Chikyu-specific hat in the form of a phoenix).</e>
<cmt>別甲　読みを追加しました。スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>番舞は「万秋楽」或いは「陪臚」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsugaimai Dance (a dance that is simultaneously performed) is &apos;Manjuraku&apos; or &apos;Bairo.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a Tsugaimai Dance (a dance that is simultaneously performed) that involves either &apos;Manjuraku&apos; or &apos;Bairo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a Tsugaimai Dance (a performance consisting of two pieces of dance) that involves either &apos;Manjuraku&apos; or &apos;Bairo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「番舞」→a performance consisting of two pieces of dance　としました。（参考：http://dictionary.goo.ne.jp/leaf/jn/129026/m0u/）　定訳不明です。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>催馬楽の「桜人」に旋律が合わせて舞われたらしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It seems that Chikyu was performed in tandem with the melody of &apos;Sakurabito,&apos; a song collected in Saibara (genre of Heian-period Japanese court music (primarily consisting of gagaku-styled folk melodies)).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that Chikyu was performed together with the melody of &apos;Sakurabito,&apos; a song collected in Saibara (a genre of the Heian-period Japanese court music, which primarily consists of gagaku-styled folk melodies).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that Chikyu was performed together with the melody of &apos;Sakurabito,&apos; a song collected in Saibara (a genre of the Heian-period Japanese court music, which primarily consists of gagaku-styled folk melodies).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>紫宸殿の桜が盛りの頃に藤原公任が柱を扇で打ちながら催馬楽の「桜人」を歌ったところ、近衛陣の直所にいた多政資らが庭に出て「地久」の破を舞ったという話が残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is an episode that when FUJIWARA no Kinto sings &apos;Sakurabito&apos; of Saibara by clapping the pillar with his fan in rhythm at the Shishinden (hall for state ceremonies) around the prime season of cherry blossom, O no Masasuke and others, who stayed at a guards stall, come out to the garden and danced the Ha (middle part) of &apos;Chikyu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a story of FUJIWARA no Kinto singing &quot;Sakurabito&quot; of Saibara while rhythmically tapping a pillar with his fan at the Shishinden Hall (a hall for state ceremonies) around the prime season of the cherry blossoms, when O no Masasuke and others, who were stationed at the guard tower, came out to the garden and danced the Ha (the middle part) of &apos;Chikyu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a story of FUJIWARA no Kinto singing &apos;Sakurabito&apos; of Saibara while rhythmically tapping a pillar with his fan at the Shishinden Hall (a hall for state ceremonies) around the prime season of the cherry blossoms, when O no Masasuke and others, who were stationed at the guard tower, came out to the garden and danced the Ha (the middle part) of &apos;Chikyu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 YOSHI438(id:174755), Tribot(id:186681), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>