<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>都をどり</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Miyako Odori</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Miyako Odori</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Miyako Odori</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>都をどり（みやこをどり）は、毎年4月1日 - 4月30日にかけて祇園甲部歌舞練場で開催される祇園甲部の舞踊公演。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Miyako Odori&quot; is a dance performance of Gion Kobu district held in April at Gion Kobu Kabu-renjo Theater.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Miyako Odori&quot; is a dance performance of the Gion Kobu district held in April at the Gion Kobu Kabu-renjo Theater.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Miyako Odori&quot; is a dance performance of the Gion Kobu district held in April at the Gion Kobu Kabu-renjo Theater.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>沿革</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>1872年（明治5年）、博覧会の余興として上演されたのが始まりで時の京都府知事、槇村正直が作詞を、当時新進であった井上流家元、井上八千代（三世　片山春子）が伊勢の亀の子をどりを参考に振付を担当した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It started when it was performed by way of entertainment for the exhibition in 1872, and Masanao MAKIMURA, a governor of Kyoto Prefecture in those days, wrote lyric and Yachiyo INOUE, Inoue-ryu (school) Iemoto (grand master) (the third Haruko KATAYAMA) choreographed with referring to Iseno kamenoko-odori Dance.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It started when it was performed by way of entertainment for an exhibition in 1872, and Masanao MAKIMURA, a governor of Kyoto Prefecture in those days, wrote lyrics and Yachiyo INOUE, Inoue-ryu (school) Iemoto (grand master) (the third Haruko KATAYAMA) choreographed the dance, referring to Iseno kamenoko-odori Dance.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It started when it was performed by way of entertainment for an exhibition in 1872, and Masanao MAKIMURA, a governor of Kyoto Prefecture in those days, wrote lyrics and Yachiyo INOUE, Inoue school Iemoto (grand master) (the third Haruko KATAYAMA) choreographed the dance, referring to Iseno kamenoko-odori dance.</e>
<cmt>Inoue-ryu (school)→Inoue schoolDance→dance</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>舞台まで両側の花道が設え、今までの舞台とは一味違う革新的で、花道からおそろいの衣装を着けた踊り子たちが登場して観客を驚かせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The two passage through audience to stage of both sides were equipped, which were innovative and a bit different from the former stage, and the appearance of dancers putting the same costumes from the passage made the audience surprised.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were two passages on both sides of the audience to the stage on both sides, which were innovative and a bit different from former stages, and the appearance of dancers wearing the same costumes from the passage surprised the audience.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were two passages on both sides of the audience to the stage on both sides, which were innovative and a bit different from former stages, and the appearance of dancers wearing the same costumes from the passage surprised the audience.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>以来、歌舞伎や源氏物語などを題材して明治以来のスタイルを踏襲しながらその年の干支や話題にちなみ、新たなる志向で上演され続けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since then, Miyako Odori has been performed with devising new plans associated with Oriental Zodiac or topics of the year, as well as following the style since Meiji Period based on kabuki, (Japanese classical drama) or the Tale of the Genji.</e>
<cmt>「志向」は「趣向」の誤記と判断しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since then, Miyako Odori has been performed devising new plans associated with the Oriental Zodiac or topics of the year, as well as following the style since Meiji Period based on kabuki, (Japanese classical drama) or the Tale of the Genji.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since then, Miyako Odori has been performed devising new plans associated with the Oriental Zodiac or topics of the year, as well as following the style since Meiji Period based on kabuki (Japanese classical drama) or the Tale of the Genji.</e>
<cmt>,削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>この形式は伊勢古市の花街で踊られていた『亀の子踊り』にヒントを得て作られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This form gets a hint for &quot;Kamenoko-Odori Dance&quot; performed in a red-light district of Isefuruichi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This form gives a hint for &quot;Kamenoko-Odori Dance&quot; performed in the red-light district of Isefuruichi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This form gives a hint for &quot;Kamenoko-Odori Dance&quot; performed in the red-light district of Isefuruichi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>年表</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chronological table</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chronological table</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chronological table</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>1872年（明治5年） 都をどり初演。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1872: Miyako Odori was premiered.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1872: Miyako Odori was premiered.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1872: Miyako Odori was premiered.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="9">
<j>1915年（大正4年） 大正天皇即位記念公演。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1915: There was a performance commemorating the accession of Emperor Taisho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1915: There was a performance commemorating the accession of Emperor Taisho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1915: There was a performance commemorating the accession of Emperor Taisho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="10">
<j>1928年（昭和3年） 昭和天皇即位記念公演。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1928: There was a performance commemorating the accession of Emperor Showa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1928: There was a performance commemorating the accession of Emperor Showa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1928: There was a performance commemorating the accession of Emperor Showa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="11">
<j>1944年（昭和19年）－1949年（昭和24年） 第二次世界大戦で6年間休演。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From 1944 to 1949: It had been suspended because of the World War II.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From 1944 to 1949: It had been suspended because of World War II.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From 1944 to 1949: It had been suspended because of World War II.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="12">
<j>1950年（昭和25年） 南座で再開。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1950: It reopened at Minami-za Theater.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1950: It reopened at Minami-za Theater.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1950: It reopened at Minami-za Theater.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="13">
<j>1964年（昭和39年） 東京オリンピック大会記念公演。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1964 there was a performance commemorating Tokyo Olympic Games.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1964: There was a performance commemorating the Tokyo Olympic Games.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1964: There was a performance commemorating the Tokyo Olympic Games.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="14">
<j>1994年（平成6年） 平安遷都1200年記念公演。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1994: There was a performance commemorating the 1200th anniversary of the transfer of the national capital to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1994: There was a performance commemorating the 1200th anniversary of the transfer of the national capital to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1994: There was a performance commemorating the 1200th anniversary of the transfer of the national capital to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="15">
<j>2004年（平成16年） 四世井上八千代（本名　片山愛子）、死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">2004: The fourth Yachiyo INOUE (real name was Aiko KATAYAMA) died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">2004: The fourth Yachiyo INOUE (real name was Aiko KATAYAMA) died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">2004: The fourth Yachiyo INOUE (real name was Aiko KATAYAMA) died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="16">
<j>しくみ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Composition</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Composition</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Composition</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="17">
<j>都をどりは原則として、総踊形式で一貫し、京都の名所などを長唄などで紹介しながら踊り、明治以来その形式で踏襲されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Miyako Odori basically has adopted the style that all performers dance together while introducing the famous spots in Kyoto by long epic song with shamisen accompaniment, following the same style since Meiji Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Miyako Odori basically has adopted the style where all performers dance together while introducing famous spots in Kyoto with a long epic song to the accompaniment of a shamisen, following the same style since the Meiji Period.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Miyako Odori basically has adopted the style where all performers dance together while introducing famous spots in Kyoto with a long epic song to the accompaniment of a shamisen, following the same style since the Meiji Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>最初の場面は井上流の故事にちなみ銀襖を張り詰められた舞台から始まる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first scene was performed on the stage setting up Gin busuma (a sliding screen put on silver foil) based on the historical event of Inoue-ryu school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first scene was performed on the stage where a Gin busuma (a sliding screen put on silver foil) was set up, based upon the historical event of the Inoue-ryu school.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first scene was performed on the stage where a Gin busuma (a sliding screen put on silver foil) was set up, based upon the historical event of the Inoue school.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除-ryu削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>大正天皇即位記念公演から『別踊』（べつおどり）という中挿みの場面が加わり、さらに内容も増し、主に歌舞伎や文学、逸話などを取り入れ10分間で踊りながら物語の内容を説明をする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A scene called &quot;Betsu-odori Dance (another dance) &quot; which was inserted in the middle was added since the Emperor Taisho enthronement commemorative performance, and the contents were also increased to explain the story based on the subjects mainly from Kabuki, literature and anecdotes while dancing in 10 minutes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A scene called &quot;Betsu-odori Dance (another dance) &quot; inserted in the middle was added since the Emperor Taisho enthronement commemorative performance, and contents were also increased to explain the story based upon the subjects mainly from Kabuki, literature and anecdotes while dancing for 10 minutes.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A scene called &quot;Betsu-odori Dance (another dance) &quot; inserted in the middle was added since the Emperor Taisho enthronement commemorative performance, and contents were also increased to explain the story based upon the subjects mainly from Kabuki, literature and anecdotes while dancing for 10 minutes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>毎年、都をどりの作家らがマンネリを恐れ、それに悩ませながら製作し、振り付け、音楽、美術などの打ち合わせを重ねて、来年の春までに準備を続けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The writers of Miyako Odori produce new stories every year with worrying mannerism and repeat meetings such as choreography, music and art for preparation of the performance in next spring.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The writers of Miyako Odori produced new stories every year with nervous mannerism and had repeat meetings about choreography, music and art topreparae the next spring&apos;s performance.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The writers of Miyako Odori produced new stories every year with nervous mannerism and had repeat meetings about choreography, music and art to prepare the next spring&apos;s performance.</e>
<cmt>スペース補足スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="21">
<j>お茶席</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tea ceremony</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tea ceremony</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tea ceremony</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="22">
<j>上演前、祇園甲部歌舞練場の2階でお茶席が設けられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before the performance, a tea-ceremony is held in the second floor of the Gion Kobu Kaburenjo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before the performance, a tea-ceremony is held on the second floor of the Gion Kobu Kaburenjo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before the performance, a tea-ceremony is held on the second floor of the Gion Kobu Kabu-renjo.</e>
<cmt>表記統一のため-補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>一日交替制で点茶をする芸妓は京風島田を地毛で結い、衿を裏返す黒紋付の正装姿で登場する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The geisha who is in charge of boiling tea in a shift dresses Kyoto-style Shimada with ground hair and appears with the full dress figure of a black crested haori (kimono) reversing a neckband.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The geisha who is in charge of boiling tea in shifts dresses Kyoto-style Shimada with her own hair and appears with the full dress figure of a black crested haori (kimono) with a reversed neckline.</e>
<cmt>The term ground hair is not understood. Changed to &apos;her own hair.&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The geisha who is in charge of boiling tea in shifts dresses Kyoto-style Shimada with her own hair and appears with the full dress figure of a black crested haori (kimono) with a reversed neckline.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>控えは舞妓が担当をする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A maiko is in charge of the reserve.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A maiko is in charge of the reserve.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A maiko is in charge of the reserve.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>時代によっては舞妓、当時甲部にいた太夫が点茶を担当したり、複数の芸妓が時間によって交替することがあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A maiko or a tayu (leading actor) who was in Kobu district in those days was in charge of boiling tea depending on the times, or some geishas changed over by time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A maiko or a tayu (leading actor) in the Kobu district in those days was in charge of boiling tea depending on the times, or some geishas prepared tea as time went by.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A maiko or a tayu (leading actor) in the Kobu district in those days was in charge of boiling tea depending on the times, or some geishas prepared tea as time went by.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>また現在、控えの舞妓は一人だが、控えの舞妓が二人であった時代もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, the reserve maiko was alone, but there were the times when two maiko were reserved.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, the reserve maiko was often alone, but there were times when two maiko were reserved.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, the reserve maiko was often alone, but there were times when two maiko were reserved.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="27">
<j>点茶の形式は従来の形式ではなく「立礼式」というスタイルでこれは外国人を接待する為に裏千家により考案されたもので、最初は屋外で設置されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The style of boiling tea is not a conventional form but the style of &apos;Ritsurei shiki (standing up and making a bow),&apos; which was devised by Urasenke to attend to a foreigner and was placed outdoors first.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The style of boiling tea was not done in a conventional form, but in the style of &apos;Ritsurei shiki (standing up and bowing),&apos; which was devised by Urasenke to attend to foreigners and was done outdoors at first.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The style of boiling tea was not done in a conventional form, but in the style of &apos;Ritsurei shiki (standing up and bowing),&apos; which was devised by Urasenke school to attend to foreigners and was done outdoors at first.</e>
<cmt>school補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="28">
<j>歌舞練場が完成するとそこに移し現在に至る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Kabu-renjo Theater was completed, Miyako Odori was moved there and has been performed at the present location.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Kabu-renjo Theater was completed, Miyako Odori was moved there and has been performed at the present location.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Kabu-renjo Theater was completed, Miyako Odori was moved there and has been performed at the present location.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="29">
<j>歴代歌題</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Successive subjects of songs</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Successive subjects of songs</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Successive subjects of songs</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>1872年～1899年</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1872-1899</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1872-1899</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1872 - 1899</e>
<cmt>スペース補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 ととりん(id:31982), Ajcxx(id:103602), 今紫(id:9521), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>