<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>縫腋袍</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hoeki no ho (robe with a round collar, stitched sides and a ran, worn by the emperor and high-ranking officials)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hoeki no ho (robe with a round collar, stitched sides and a ran, worn by the emperor and high-ranking officials)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hoeki no ho (robe with a round collar, stitched sides and a ran, worn by an emperor and high-ranking officials)</e>
<cmt>Emperorの前のtheをanに変更しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>縫腋袍（ほうえきのほう）とは日本の朝服のうわぎの一つで、腋が縫われ、裾周りに襴という裂を横向きにめぐらされている和服用語集のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hoeki no ho is one of Japanese robes of chofuku (cloths which the people who come to work at the court on a regular basis wear), amd a ho (round-necked robe worn by members of nobility and the imperial court) which has sewn sleeve seams outer robe and fabrics called ran (brocade) sideways around the hem.</e>
<cmt>和服用語集というと意味が通じないので、ウィキペディアのサイトで確認したところ、「袍」となっていました。袍として訳しておきます。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hoeki no ho is one of the Japanese robes of chofuku (clothes worn by the people who come to work at the court on a regular basis), and a ho (round-necked robe worn by members of nobility and the Imperial Court), which has sewn sleeve seams, an outer robe and fabrics called ran (brocade) running sideways around the hem.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hoeki no ho is one of the Japanese robes of chofuku (clothes worn by the people who come to work at the court on a regular basis), and a ho (round-necked robe worn by members of nobility and the Imperial Court), which has sewn sleeve seams, an outer robe and fabrics called ran (brocade) running sideways around the hem.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>日本の「朝服」の祖形になったのは唐の「常服」であるが（唐の「朝服」とは同名異物）、この常服のうわぎは胡服の系統を引くものであった（夢渓筆談ほか）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The origin of Japanese chofuku is &quot;Shanfu (everyday court dress)&quot; in Tang (&quot;chofuku&quot; in Tang is a different thing of the same name), and the robe of this Shanfu derived from Kohuku (traditional clothes for Kojin [lived in Northern China in ancient times]) (according to &quot;Meng Xi Bi Tan (Dream Stream Essays)&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The origin of the Japanese chofuku is &quot;Shanfu (everyday court dress)&quot; in Tang (&quot;chofuku&quot; in Tang was a different thing of the same name), and the robe of this Shanfu derived from Kohuku (traditional clothes for Kojin [who lived in Northern China in ancient times]) (according to &quot;Meng Xi Bi Tan (Dream Stream Essays)&quot;).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The origin of the Japanese &apos;chofuku&apos; is &quot;Shanfu&quot; (everyday court dress) in Tang (&apos;chofuku&apos; in Tang was a different thing of the same name), and the robe of this Shanfu derived from Kohuku (traditional clothes for Kojin [who lived in Northern China in ancient times]) (according to &quot;Meng Xi Bi Tan&quot; (Dream Stream Essays)).</e>
<cmt>chofuに&apos; &apos;を付加しました。()を&quot; &quot;の外に移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>胡服のうわぎは元来腋に開きのあるものだったが、北周の皇族の宇文護が襴をつけることを建言して以来、縫腋袍が成立した（隋書ほか）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The robe of Kohuku had originally open sides, but since Yuwen Hu, an imperial family member in Northern Zhou, proposed to the government, this hoeki no ho was made (according to &quot;Zuisho (the Book of the Sui Dynasty) etc.).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The robe of Kohuku originally had open sides, but since Yuwen Hu, an member of the Imperial Family in Northern Zhou, proposed to the government, this hoeki no ho was made (according to &quot;Zuisho&quot; (the Book of the Sui Dynasty), etc.).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The robe of Kohuku originally had open sides, but since Yuwen Hu, an member of the Imperial Family in Northern Zhou, proposed to the government, this hoeki no ho was made (according to &quot;Zuisho&quot; (the Book of the Sui Dynasty), etc.).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>唐代の絵画によると警衛のものや宦官などが闕腋のうわぎを用い、文官などが有襴の縫腋袍を用いる例が多いが、すべてが沿うとも言い切れない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In drawings in Tang period, we can see many guarding officers and kangan (eunuch) wore these robes with ketteki (1. unstitched, open side of some traditional Japanese clothing, clothing with such an open side, or 2. robe worn by military officials with a round collar, unstitched open sides and no ran) and civil officers used hoeki no ho with ran, but it not necessarily appropriate to suggest so.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In drawings of the Tang period, one can see that many guarding officers and kangan (eunuchs) wore these robes with ketteki (1. unstitched, open-sided traditional Japanese clothing, or clothing with such an open side; or 2. a robe worn by military officials with a round collar, unstitched open sides and no ran) and civil officers used hoeki no ho with ran, but it wasn&apos;t necessarily appropriate to suggest so.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In drawings of the Tang period, one can see that many guarding officers and kangan (eunuchs) wore these robes with ketteki (1. unstitched, open-sided traditional Japanese clothing, or clothing with such an open side; or 2. a robe worn by military officials with a round collar, unstitched open sides and no ran) and civil officers used hoeki no ho with ran, but it wasn&apos;t necessarily appropriate to suggest so.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>日本では養老律令の「衣服令」に親王・王 (皇族)・文官の朝服に「衣」とあるものが縫腋袍、武官の朝服に「襖」とあるものが闕腋袍にあたると見られ、闕腋袍は武官や元服前の童子が使用した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan, it is considered that &quot;kinu&quot; in the chofuku for an Imperial Prince, members of the Imperial family in the&quot; Garment Code&quot; in the Yoro ritsuryo code (code promulgated in the Yoro period) was hoeki no ho, and &quot;ao&quot; in chofuku for military officers was ketteki no ho (an outer robe for military officers) and worn by military officers or child before genpuku (celebrate one&apos;s coming of age).</e>
<cmt>襖は、用語集では「ふすま」となっていますが、衣服の場合「あお」と読むと思います。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan, it is considered that &quot;kinu&quot; in the chofuku for an imperial prince, members of the Imperial Family in the &quot;Garment Code&quot; of the Yoro ritsuryo code (a code promulgated in the Yoro period) was hoeki no ho, and &quot;ao&quot; in chofuku for military officers was ketteki no ho (an outer robe for military officers) and worn by military officers or children before genpuku (the coming-of-age celebration).</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan, it is considered that &apos;kinu&apos; in the chofuku for an imperial prince, members of the Imperial Family in the &apos;Garment Code&apos; of the Yoro ritsuryo code (a code promulgated in the Yoro period) was hoeki no ho, and &apos;ao&apos; in chofuku for military officers was ketteki no ho (an outer robe for military officers) and worn by military officers or children before genpuku (the coming-of-age celebration).</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="6">
<j>平安時代初期に位階以上の者は警衛の時以外は縫腋袍を用いてもよくなり、また三位以上は警衛にあたっても縫腋袍を用いることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the early Heian Period, those in Ikai (court rank) or higher rank could wear hoeki no ho except for during guarding and those in Sanmi (Third Rank) or higher could wear hoeki no ho even during guarding.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the early Heian period, those of Ikai (court rank) or higher rank could wear hoeki no ho except for while on guard and those in Sanmi (Third Rank) or higher could wear hoeki no ho even while on guard.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the early Heian period, those of Ikai (court rank) or higher rank could wear hoeki no ho except for while on guard and those in Sanmi (Third Rank) or higher could wear hoeki no ho even while on guard.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="7">
<j>中国で「縫腋」の名称は一般的でないが、日本では『和名抄』においてすでにこの名称が見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name &quot;hoeki&quot; is not popular in China, but in Japan, this name was already found in &quot;Wamyo-sho (a dictionary compiled in the Heian period).&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name &quot;hoeki&quot; isn&apos;t popular in China, but in Japan this name was already found in &quot;Wamyo-sho,&quot; a dictionary compiled during the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name &apos;hoeki&apos; isn&apos;t popular in China, but in Japan this name was already found in &quot;Wamyo-sho,&quot; a dictionary compiled during the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」の部分を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Sillago(id:187189), Blue-comet(id:192801), COCKY(id:19672), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>