<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>年少芸妓</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nensho Geigi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nensho Geigi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nensho Geigi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>年少芸妓とはまだ芸妓としては一人前でない若い芸妓、または芸妓見習いとして花街のお座敷に出ている少女を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nensho geigi refers to a young geigi (a woman who gives fun with a song, dance or music instrument at a feast; geisha) who is not yet a full-fledged geigi, or a girl who appears in ozashiki (banquets in which guests are attended by geisha) in hanamachi (geisha districts) as a geigi apprentice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nensho geigi refers to a young geigi (a woman who gives fun with a song, dance or music instrument at a feast; geisha) who is not yet a full-fledged, or a girl who appears in ozashiki (banquets in which guests are attended by geisha) in hanamachi (geisha districts) as a geigi apprentice.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nensho geigi refers to a young geigi (a woman who gives fun with a song, dance or music instrument at a feast; geisha) who is not yet a full-fledged, or a girl who appears in ozashiki (banquets in which guests are attended by geisha) in hanamachi (geisha districts) as a geigi apprentice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>肩揚げ、袖揚げをした振袖の着物に紅系統の刺繍の半衿、ぽっくり下駄、少女向きの日本髪（桃割れ、唐人髷、結綿、割れしのぶ、おふく、といったもの）、花かんざしといったいかにも幼さを強調したいでたちであるのが特徴である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nensho geigi are characterized by the typical style which emphasizes their young age; they wear kimono with long, trailing sleeves, that are hemmed up, and haneri (neckpiece on a kimono), that is embroidered in red or reddish color, and pokkuri-geta (lacquered tall clogs), and their hair is done in the Japanese coiffure style for girls (such as &quot;momoware&quot;, &quot;tojinmage&quot;, &quot;yuiwata&quot;, &quot;wareshinobu&quot;, and &quot;ofuku&quot;) using tsumami kanzasi (flower kanzasi (a decorative hair-pin)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nensho geigi is characterized by the typical style which emphasizes their young age; they wear kimono with long, trailing sleeves, that are removed the tucks at the shoulders and hemmed up, and haneri (neckpiece on a kimono), that is embroidered in red or reddish color, and pokkuri-geta (lacquered tall clogs), and their hair is done in the Japanese coiffure style for girls (such as momoware [literally, split peach; a hairstyle that the bun is split and a red fabric woven in the center], tojinmage [maiden hairstyle around Meiji period, characterized by separating the upper knots from the lower, decorated with fabric], yuiwata [hair style like cotton wrapped up], wareshinobu [a hairstyle characterized by a bagel-shaped, rolled knot worn high on her head, decorated with ribbons, ornaments and silk flowers], and ofuku [female hair style in kimono that the bun is split and a red fabric woven in the bottom]) using hana kanzashi (flower kanzashi [a decorative hair-pin]).</e>
<cmt>原文にリンク文字列が含まれていたため、原文・訳文共に修正しました。訳漏れ。補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nensho geigi is characterized by the typical style which emphasizes their young age; they wear kimono with long, trailing sleeves, that are removed the tucks at the shoulders and hemmed up, and haneri (neckpiece on a kimono), that is embroidered in red or reddish color, and pokkuri-geta (lacquered tall clogs), and their hair is done in the Japanese coiffure style for girls (such as momoware [literally, split peach; a hairstyle that the bun is split and a red fabric woven in the center], tojinmage [maiden hairstyle around Meiji period, characterized by separating the upper knots from the lower, decorated with fabric], yuiwata [hair style like cotton wrapped up], wareshinobu [a hairstyle characterized by a bagel-shaped, rolled knot worn high on her head, decorated with ribbons, ornaments and silk flowers], and ofuku [female hair style in kimono that the bun is split and a red fabric woven in the bottom]) using hana kanzashi (flower kanzashi [a decorative hair-pin]).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="3">
<j>かつては「半人前」の身分であるとして「花代」（玉代、線香代とも）が芸妓の半分であることもあった（京都の舞妓はそうではない）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Formerly they earned half the &quot;hanadai&quot; (fee for geisha) of geigi (the same was true for tamadai and senkodai (other terms for fee for geisha), etc. since their status was considered to be &quot;half&quot; of that of geigi (excluding the geigi in Kyoto).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Formerly they earned half &apos;the hanadai&apos; (fee for geisha) of geigi (also referred as gyokudai or senkodai), since their status was considered to be &apos;half&apos; of that of geigi (excluding the geigi in Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>読み、表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Formerly they earned half &apos;the hanadai&apos; (fee for geisha) of geigi (also referred as gyokudai or senkodai), since their status was considered to be &apos;half&apos; of that of geigi (excluding the geigi in Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>現代ではそのようなことはない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today, however, this is not the case.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, however, this is not the case.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, however, this is not the case.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="5">
<j>呼称としては「半玉」「おしゃく（お酌とも雛妓とも書く）」「舞妓」「赤襟」「金魚」「雛妓（ひなつこ）」「振袖」など。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Names for nensho geigi include &quot;hangyoku&quot;, &quot;oshaku&quot; (written in Japanese as お酌 or 雛妓), &quot;maiko&quot; (written in Japanese as 舞妓), &quot;akaeri&quot;, &quot;kingyo&quot;, &quot;hinatsuko&quot;, and &quot;furisode&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Names for nensho geigi include &apos;hangyoku&apos; (literally, half gyokudai), &apos;oshaku&apos; (お酌 or 雛妓, person who pours sake liquor), &apos;maiko&apos; (舞妓, apprentice geisha), &apos;akaeri&apos; (red collar), &apos;kingyo&apos; (goldfish), &apos;hinatsuko&apos; (little geigi), and &apos;furisode&apos; (a kimono with long, trailing sleeves).</e>
<cmt>表記を変え、補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Names for nensho geigi include &apos;hangyoku&apos; (literally, half gyokudai), &apos;oshaku&apos; (お酌 or 雛妓, person who pours sake liquor), &apos;maiko&apos; (舞妓, apprentice geisha), &apos;akaeri&apos; (red collar), &apos;kingyo&apos; (goldfish), &apos;hinatsuko&apos; (little geigi), and &apos;furisode&apos; (a kimono with long, trailing sleeves).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="6">
<j>関西では「舞妓」、それ以外の地域の花街では「半玉」が一般的である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are called &quot;maiko&quot; (written in Japanese as 舞妓) in Kansai region, and commonly &quot;hangyoku&quot; in the hanamachi of other areas.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are called &apos;maiko&apos; (舞妓) in Kansai region, and commonly &apos;hangyoku&apos; in the hanamachi of other areas.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションなどを変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are called &apos;maiko&apos; (舞妓) in Kansai region, and commonly &apos;hangyoku&apos; in the hanamachi of other areas.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="7">
<j>山形・酒田では若手の社員芸妓を「舞娘」と呼んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Sakata City, Yamagata Prefecture, young &quot;shain geigi&quot; (geigi who are employed by organizations) are called &quot;maiko&quot; (written in Japanese as 舞娘).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Sakata City, Yamagata Prefecture, young shain geigi (geigi who are employed by organizations) are called &apos;maiko&apos; (舞娘).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションなどを変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Sakata City, Yamagata Prefecture, young shain geigi (geigi who are employed by organizations) are called &apos;maiko&apos; (舞娘).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="8">
<j>また、半玉も含めての「若手芸妓」を「きらり妓さん」（神奈川・箱根湯本温泉）「からり妓さん」（福島・会津東山温泉）といった愛称で呼ぶところもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, in some places, &quot;wakate geigi&quot; (young geigi), including hangyoku, are called by terms of endearment such as &quot;kirariko-san&quot; (Hakone Yumoto Hot Spring Resort, Kanagawa Prefecture) and &quot;karariko-san&quot; (Aizu Higashiyama Hot Spring Resort, Fukushima Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, in some places, &apos;younger geigi,&apos; including hangyoku, are called by terms of endearment such as &apos;kirariko-san&apos; (in Hakone Yumoto Hot Spring Resort, Kanagawa Prefecture) and &apos;karariko-san&apos; (Aizu Higashiyama Hot Spring Resort, Fukushima Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションなどを変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, in some places, &apos;younger geigi,&apos; including hangyoku, are called by terms of endearment such as &apos;kirariko-san&apos; (in Hakone Yumoto Hot Spring Resort, Kanagawa Prefecture) and &apos;karariko-san&apos; (Aizu Higashiyama Hot Spring Resort, Fukushima Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>