<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>高野豆腐</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koya-dofu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koya-dofu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koya-dofu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>高野豆腐（こうやどうふ）とは、豆腐を凍結乾燥させた保存食である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koya-dofu (freeze-dried bean curd) is preserved food having tofu (bean curd) freeze-dry.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koya-dofu (freeze-dried bean curd) is a food made of preserved tofu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koya-dofu (freeze-dried bean curd) is a food made of preserved tofu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>乾燥状態では軽く締まったスポンジ状で、これを水で戻し、出汁で煮込むなどして味を付ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is light and shrunk sponge-like status in a dry form, so you reconstitute it and season it by simmering in broth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In its dry form, it&apos;s light and shrunken to a sponge-like state, so it&apos;s reconstituted and seasoned by simmering in broth.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In its dry form, it&apos;s light and shrunken to a sponge-like state, so it&apos;s reconstituted and seasoned by simmering in broth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>歴史・名称起源</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History and origin of the name</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History and origin of the name</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History and origin of the name</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>冬期に豆腐を屋外に放置してしまった事から偶然に製法が発見されたといわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was said that the process was accidentally discovered by leaving tofu outdoors during winter season.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has been said that the process was accidentally discovered when tofu was left outdoors during the winter season.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has been said that the process was accidentally discovered when tofu was left outdoors during the winter season.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>俗に高野山で製造される凍り豆腐が、精進料理の一つとして全国に広まったものとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is commonly said that kori-dofu (frozen bean curd) manufactured on Mt.Koya spread throughout the nation as one of vegetarian dishes.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It&apos;s commonly said that the kori-dofu (frozen bean curd) manufactured at Mt. Koya spread throughout the nation as a vegetarian dish.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It&apos;s commonly said that the kori-dofu (frozen bean curd) manufactured at Mt. Koya spread throughout the nation as a vegetarian dish.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>しかし実際には、東北地方にも凍み豆腐（しみどうふ）と呼ばれる同じ製法の保存食がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there is actually preserved food with same process called shimi-dofu in Tohoku region.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in the Tohoku region there is a preserved food called shimi-dofu, for which the same process is used.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in the Tohoku region there is a preserved food called shimi-dofu, for which the same process is used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>中国にも同様の食品があるので中国より伝来した可能性も高い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is highly possible that it was introduced from China since there is a similar food in China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It&apos;s very possible that it was introduced from China, since there is a similar food in China.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It&apos;s very possible that it was introduced from China, since there is a similar food in China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>寒さの厳しい地方では、場所に限らず偶然の産物として発見され、普遍的に生産されてきた食品と見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In frigid regions, it was discovered accidentally regardless of places and seemed as universally-manufactured food.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In frigid regions, it was discovered accidentally regardless of the place, and therefore it seemed to be a universally manufactured food.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In frigid regions, it was discovered accidentally regardless of the place, and therefore it seemed to be a universally manufactured food.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>高野豆腐と呼ばれるに至ったのは、江戸時代に於いて高野山の土産として珍重されたからとも言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was said that people started to call it Koya-dofu since it was prized as a souvenir of Mt.Koya during Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was said that people started calling it Koya-dofu because it was prized as a souvenir of Mt. Koya during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was said that people started calling it Koya-dofu because it was prized as a souvenir of Mt. Koya during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>江戸時代に於いては最も流通した物がその販売地、販売者の地名を冠することがあり、これもその一つである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During Edo period, the thing that was most distributed took the name of its sales territory and seller, and this is one of that.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Edo period, the thing that was most distributed took the name of its sales territory and seller, and this is an example of the practice.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Edo period, the thing that was most distributed took the name of its sales territory and seller, and this is an example of the practice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>高野豆腐の名称は現在では全国に広まっているがもとは近畿地方で広く用いられていた名称である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name of Koya-dofu spread throughout the nation at present, but it was originally used widely in Kinki region.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name of Koya-dofu is known throughout the nation today, but originally it was used throughout the Kinki region.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name of Koya-dofu is known throughout the nation today, but originally it was used throughout the Kinki region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>甲信越地方、東北地方、北海道では凍み豆腐、凍り豆腐と呼ばれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was called shimi-dofu or kori-dufu in Koshinetsu Region, Tohoku region, and Hokkaido.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was called shimi-dofu or kori-dufu in the Koshinetsu region, the Tohoku region and Hokkaido.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was called shimi-dofu or kori-dufu in the Koshinetsu region, the Tohoku region and Hokkaido.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>甲信越、東北、北海道で作られる伝統的な製法の凍り豆腐は、藁で数個ずつ豆腐を連ねて軒先に吊るして作るのでその形から連豆腐とも呼ばれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The kori-dofu manufactured with traditional process in Koshinetsu, Tohoku, and Hokkaido, is manufactured by hanging string of several tofu with straw under eaves, and it is also called ren-dofu (string bean curd) from its shape.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The kori-dofu manufactured through the traditional process in Koshinetsu, Tohoku and Hokkaido is manufactured by hanging strings of several tofu with straw under eaves, and it&apos;s also called ren-dofu (string-bean curd) because of its shape.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The kori-dofu manufactured through the traditional process in Koshinetsu, Tohoku and Hokkaido is manufactured by hanging strings of several tofu with straw under eaves, and it&apos;s also called ren-dofu (string-bean curd) because of its shape.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>大阪ではちはや豆腐という呼び名もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called chihaya-dofu in Osaka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, it&apos;s called chihaya-dofu in Osaka.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, it&apos;s called chihaya-dofu in Osaka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>古くは氷豆腐と表記される事もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was written as kori-dofu (ice bean curd) in the old days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the old days it was was written as kori-dofu (ice-bean curd).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the old days it was written as kori-dofu (ice-bean curd).</e>
<cmt>was 繰り返しを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>東北地方では製造途中の凍ったものを凍り豆腐として冷凍販売し、乾物の状態のものを凍み豆腐として区別して販売されているため、注意が必要である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Tohoku region, the frozen one is sold as kori-dofu that is in the halfway of production, and dried one is distinctly sold as shimi-dofu, so it needs attention.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Tohoku region, the frozen type is sold as kori-dofu, which is at the midpoint of production, and the dried type is distinctly sold as shimi-dofu, so it needs attention.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Tohoku region, the frozen type is sold as kori-dofu, which is at the midpoint of production, and the dried type is distinctly sold as shimi-dofu, so it needs attention.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="16">
<j>日本農林規格(JAS)では、凍り豆腐が正式な名称となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kori-dofu is the official name under Japan Agricultural Standards (JAS).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kori-dofu is the official name under the Japan Agricultural Standards (JAS).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kori-dofu is the official name under the Japan Agricultural Standards (JAS).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="17">
<j>寒冷地で発達した食品であることから、現在でも長野県が日本最大の生産地である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since it has developed in cold area, Nagano Prefecture is still the largest production center in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because it developed in a cold area, Nagano Prefecture is still the largest production center in Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because it developed in a cold area, Nagano Prefecture is still the largest production center in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>高野山近辺では現在は製造されていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is currently no longer manufactured around Mt.Koya.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, it&apos;s no longer manufactured around Mt. Koya.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, it&apos;s no longer manufactured around Mt. Koya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>製法</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Process</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The process</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The process</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="19">
<j>最も伝統のある製法では、硬く水切りした豆腐を適当な大きさに切り、寒中の屋外に放置する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the most traditional process, cut tightly drained tofu in appropriate size and leave them outdoors in cold weather.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the most traditional process, cut tightly drained tofu into pieces of appropriate size and leave them outdoors in cold weather.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the most traditional process, cut tightly drained tofu into pieces of appropriate size and leave them outdoors in cold weather.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>夜間は凍結し、日中に溶けることを繰り返すうちに完全に水分が抜け乾物となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By repeating the cycle of freezing during the night and thawing during the day, it is completely dried out and becomes dry food.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By repeating the cycle of freezing overnight night and thawing during the day, it fully dehydrates and becomes a dry food.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By repeating the cycle of freezing overnight night and thawing during the day, it fully dehydrates and becomes a dry food.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>水分が凍るとき内部に無数の氷の結晶が出来るので、溶ける際にその部分が小さな穴として残る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When water freezes, countless ice crystals are created inside, and they remained as small holes when it is thawed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When water freezes, countless ice crystals are created inside the tofu, and when the tofu is thawed they leave small holes.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When water freezes, countless ice crystals are created inside the tofu, and when the tofu is thawed they leave small holes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>こうして、スポンジ状の多孔質な高野豆腐ができあがる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This way, sponge-like porous koya-dofu is made.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This way, a porous, spongy koya-dofu is created.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This way, a porous, spongy koya-dofu is created.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>甲信越、東北、北海道、および高野山での古い作り方とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said to be the old process in Koshinetsu, Tohoku, Hokkaido, and Mt.Koya.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It&apos;s said to be the old process used in Koshinetsu, Tohoku, Hokkaido and Mt. Koya.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It&apos;s said to be the old process used in Koshinetsu, Tohoku, Hokkaido and Mt. Koya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="24">
<j>高野山でも古くは上記の伝統製法で作っていたが、時代が下るに従い製法に工夫が施され独自の製法が確立されていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On Mt.Koya, the above traditional process was used in the old days, but the process was twisted in more recent years, and unique process has been established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The above traditional process was used in the old days at Mt. Koya, but the process was altered in recent years, and a unique process has been established.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The above traditional process was used in the old days at Mt. Koya, but the process was altered in recent years, and a unique process has been established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>夜間に凍結した豆腐が日中に溶けてしまわないように、専用の氷室に入れて数日間熟成させ、その後に解凍し乾燥させる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order for tofu that is frozen during the night not to thaw during the day, it is put in the separate ice room and let it mature for a few days, then dry it after thawing it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order for tofu that is frozen during the night not to thaw during the day, it&apos;s placed in a separate ice room and allowed to mature for a few days, and after thawing it is dried.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order for tofu that is frozen during the night not to thaw during the day, it&apos;s placed in a separate ice room and allowed to mature for a few days, and after thawing it is dried.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>乾燥法も初めは天日干しだったが、後には乾燥用の室の中で炭などを焚き強制的に乾燥させる方法が広まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The drying method used to be drying in the sun at first, but the method to dry forcibly spread later by burning coal in the room for drying.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sun-drying was originally the method used, but the forced-drying method spread later by burning coal in the drying room.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sun-drying was originally the method used, but the forced-drying method spread later by burning coal in the drying room.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="27">
<j>現在は冷凍機で凍結し、乾燥機で乾燥する機械製法がほとんどである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Currently, the machinery process is most likely used where it is frozen by refrigerating machine and dried by drying machine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Currently, the general practice is to use refrigeratin machinery for freezing and drying machinery for dehydration.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Currently, the general practice is to use refrigerating machinery for freezing and drying machinery for dehydration.</e>
<cmt>refrigeratingスペル訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>膨軟剤</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bonanzai (Leavening and softening agents)</e>
<cmt>「膨軟剤」の正しい読み方と意味を確認できませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bonanzai (leavening and softening agents)</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bonanzai (leavening and softening agents)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="28">
<j>伝統的な製法による高野豆腐は硬く、水戻しには一晩かかり、柔らかく炊き上げるのは難しく、調理に手間のかかる食材である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The koya-dofu processed by traditional way is hard, takes one night to reconstitute, and difficult to cook it softly, so it is time-consuming ingredient for cooking.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The koya-dofu processed the traditional way is hard, takes one night to reconstitute and is difficult to cook softly, so it&apos;s a time-consuming ingredient for use in cooking.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The koya-dofu processed the traditional way is hard, takes one night to reconstitute and is difficult to cook softly, so it&apos;s a time-consuming ingredient for use in cooking.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>このため現在市販されている高野豆腐のほとんどには、水戻しの時間を短縮し、柔らかく煮あがるように膨軟剤と呼ばれる食品添加物が加えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, food additive called Bonanzai is added to most koya-dofu currently on the market in order to shorten reconstituting time and cook it softly.</e>
<cmt>「膨軟剤」の正しい読み方と意味を確認できませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, a food additive called Bonanzai is added to most koya-dofu currently on the market in order to shorten the reconstituting time and allow it to cook softly.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, a food additive called Bonanzai is added to most koya-dofu currently on the market in order to shorten the reconstituting time and allow it to cook softly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>アンモニア</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ammonia</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ammonia</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ammonia</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="30">
<j>極めて吸水性が高いアンモニアの性質を生かし、高野豆腐の水戻し時間を短縮する役割を持つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By utilizing the property of highly absorbent ammonia, it serves to shorten reconstituting time of koya-dofu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By utilizing the property of highly absorbent ammonia, the time needed to reconstitute the koya-dofu is shortened.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By utilizing the property of highly absorbent ammonia, the time needed to reconstitute the koya-dofu is shortened.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>乾燥が終わった高野豆腐をアンモニア処理室にいれアンモニアガスを充満させる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Put koya-dofu in an ammonia processing room after drying it, and the room is filled with ammonia gas.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The koya-dofu is placed in an ammonia processing room after drying it, and then the room is filled with ammonia gas.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The koya-dofu is placed in an ammonia processing room after drying it, and then the room is filled with ammonia gas.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>スポンジ状の高野豆腐の内部までアンモニアガスが行き渡りアンモニアが全体に吸着したら、密封包装をして出荷される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When ammonia gas spread into spongy koya-dofu and ammonia is absorbed to the whole, it is hermetically sealed and shipped.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Once the ammonia gas spreads into the spongy koya-dofu and becomes fully absorbed, the tofu is hermetically sealed and shipped.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Once the ammonia gas spreads into the spongy koya-dofu and becomes fully absorbed, the tofu is hermetically sealed and shipped.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>アンモニアが揮発してしまうと効果がなくなるので、保存時は必ず密封しなければならない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has no effect if ammonia is vaporized, so it must be hermetically sealed when it is preserved.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ammonia has no effect if it&apos;s allowed to vaporize, so it must be hermetically sealed when it&apos;s preserved.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ammonia has no effect if it&apos;s allowed to vaporize, so it must be hermetically sealed when it&apos;s preserved.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="34">
<j>アンモニア臭を抜くために水ではなく熱湯で戻す事が推奨されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order to get rid of its ammonia odor, it is recommended to reconstitute with hot water, not water.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to get rid of the ammonia odor, it&apos;s recommended that hot water be used to reconstitute the product.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to get rid of the ammonia odor, it&apos;s recommended that hot water be used to reconstitute the product.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>戻した後、何度か水を替えて完全にアンモニア臭を抜いてから調理を行う必要がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After reconstituting it, it requires to change water several times to get rid of ammonia odor completely to cook it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the product is reconstituted, several changes of water are required in order to get rid of the ammonia odor completely.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the product is reconstituted, several changes of water are required in order to get rid of the ammonia odor completely.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>アンモニア自体が有害である事、保存時にアンモニアが揮発すると効果が無くなる事から現在ではほとんど利用されていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is no longer used since ammonia itself is harmful and has no effect if ammonia is vaporized when preserving it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This method is no longer because ammonia is harmful and has no preservative effect if it&apos;s allowed to vaporize.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This method is no longer because ammonia is harmful and has no preservative effect if it&apos;s allowed to vaporize.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>重曹</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Baking soda</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Baking soda</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Baking soda</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="37">
<j>たんぱく質を分解し食材を柔らかくする重曹の性質を利用し、高野豆腐を柔らかくする役割を持つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By utilizing the property of baking soda that can dissolve protein and soften ingredient, it serves to soften koya-dofu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By utilizing the property of baking soda, which can dissolve protein and soften ingredients, it serves to soften the koya-dofu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By utilizing the property of baking soda, which can dissolve protein and soften ingredients, it serves to soften the koya-dofu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>生の豆腐を凍結し、重曹の入った水に浸して解凍する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Freeze raw tofu and put it in the water with baking soda to thaw it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The raw, frozen tofu is placed in thawed in a solution of water and baking soda.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The raw, frozen tofu is placed in thawed in a solution of water and baking soda.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>重曹のしみこんだ豆腐の水を切り乾燥させる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Drain off tofu that is soaked into baking soda and dehydrate it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The tofu, having been soaked in baking soda, is then dehydrated.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The tofu, having been soaked in baking soda, is then dehydrated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>たんぱく質の一部が破壊されているので水戻しも早く、柔らかく煮あがる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A part of protein is destroyed, so it has short reconstituting time and is cooked softly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A portion of the protein is destroyed, so it has a short reconstituting time and will cook softly.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A portion of the protein is destroyed, so it has a short reconstituting time and will cook softly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>現在市販されているものは、ほとんどが重曹処理されたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most of koya-dofu currently on the market is processed with baking soda.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most of koya-dofu currently on the market is processed with baking soda.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most of koya-dofu currently on the market is processed with baking soda.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="42">
<j>アンモニア処理の高野豆腐と違い密封保存する必要性は無い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Unlike koya-dofu processed with ammonia, it does not need to be hermetically sealed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unlike the koya-dofu processed with ammonia, it doesn&apos;t need to be hermetically sealed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unlike the koya-dofu processed with ammonia, it doesn&apos;t need to be hermetically sealed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>また、熱湯で戻す必要も無い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, it does not need to reconstitute with hot water.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further, it doesn&apos;t need to be reconstituted with hot water.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further, it doesn&apos;t need to be reconstituted with hot water.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="44">
<j>重曹処理された高野豆腐は伝統製法のものに比べ、硬さが1/3～1/4程度で非常に柔らかく、別の食品といえるほど食感も異なる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koya-dofu processed with baking soda is 1/3 to 1/4 softer compared to the one with traditional process, and its texture is different as if it is another food.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koya-dofu processed with baking soda is one-fourth to one-third softer than the one produced through the traditional process, and its texture is so different as to suggest that it&apos;s a different kind of food.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koya-dofu processed with baking soda is one-fourth to one-third softer than the one produced through the traditional process, and its texture is so different as to suggest that it&apos;s a different kind of food.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>その柔らかさから煮崩れしやすく、伝統製法の高野豆腐と同じ感覚で調理すると形が崩れてしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is mushy due to its softness, so it loses its shape if it is cooked with traditional process.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It&apos;s mushy due to its softness, so it loses its shape if it&apos;s cooked the traditional way.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It&apos;s mushy due to its softness, so it loses its shape if it&apos;s cooked the traditional way.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>真水で煮ると崩れるので、組織を引き締め煮崩れを防ぐために初めから塩分が含まれた出汁で煮る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It loses its shape when it is simmered in pure water, so it should be simmered in saline broth to tighten its composition and to prevent from being mushy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It loses its shape when it&apos;s simmered in pure water, so it should be simmered in saline broth to tighten its composition and prevent it from being mushy.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It loses its shape when it&apos;s simmered in pure water, so it should be simmered in saline broth to tighten its composition and prevent it from being mushy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>また、重曹処理された高野豆腐は炊飯器に水と一緒に入れて炊くことによって普通の豆腐に近いものを作ることができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, by cooking koya-dofu processed with baking soda in rice cooker with water, it can make tofu close to the ordinary one.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, by cooking koya-dofu processed with baking soda in a rice cooker together with water, it can make tofu close to the ordinary type.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, by cooking koya-dofu processed with baking soda in a rice cooker together with water, it can make tofu close to the ordinary type.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>保存性</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Preservative quality</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Preservative quality</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Preservative quality</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="48">
<j>乾物のため保存性は高いが、保存期間が長くなると脂肪分が酸化し品質が劣化する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its preservative quality is high since it is dry food, but when storage life gets longer, fat content is oxidized and the quality deteriorates.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its preservative quality is high since it&apos;s a dry food, but when the storage life gets longer, the fat content is oxidized and the quality deteriorates.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its preservative quality is high since it&apos;s a dry food, but when the storage life gets longer, the fat content is oxidized and the quality deteriorates.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>味を損なわず食べられる期間は6ヶ月程度が限度である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The maximum storage life that is edible without losing its flavor is six months.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The maximum storage life over which the flavor is retained is six months.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The maximum storage life over which the flavor is retained is six months.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>また、多孔質でにおいを吸着しやすいので保存時には注意が必要である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, it is porous and can easily absorb odor, so it requires attention when it is preserved.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, it&apos;s porous and can easily absorb odor, so attention is required in preserving it.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, it&apos;s porous and can easily absorb odor, so attention is required in preserving it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>酸化防止とにおい移りを防ぐために、密封容器に入れ冷暗所に保管することが望ましい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order to prevent oxidation and odor, it is desirable to put it in the hermetically sealed container and preserve it in cold dark place.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To prevent oxidation and odor, it&apos;s preferable to put it in the hermetically sealed container and preserve it in a cold, dark place.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To prevent oxidation and odor, it&apos;s preferable to put it in the hermetically sealed container and preserve it in a cold, dark place.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Khoriuchi(id:139877), Opponent(id:720), Rusk(id:9895), Nyango(id:8484), 竃馬(id:102733), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), マクガイア(id:33346), S.S.Exp.Hashimoto(id:4001), Ncsa3809(id:28714), Kstigarbha(id:13376), 織部(id:21104), K-kazumasa(id:9265), おさかな天国(id:10703), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>