<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>宇治採茶使</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Uji saicha shi (a messenger who carries a pot of tea leaves taken in Uji)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Uji saicha shi (a messenger who carries a pot of tea leaves taken from Uji)</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Uji saicha shi</e>
<cmt>タイトルのため、括弧内の補足を削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>宇治採茶使（うじさいちゃし）は、京都府宇治市の名産品である宇治茶を徳川将軍家に献上するための茶壷を運ぶ行列のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Uji saicha shi is the procession that carried Uji tea leaves, one of the specialties of Uji City, Kyoto, in chatsubo (tea jar) to present them to Tokugawa Shogunate Family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Uji saicha shi was a procession that carried Uji tea leaves, one of the specialties of Uji City, Kyoto, in a chatsubo (tea jar) to be presented to the Tokugawa Shogunate Family.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Uji saicha shi was a procession that carried Uji tea leaves, one of the specialties of Uji City, Kyoto, in a chatsubo (tea jar) to be presented to the Tokugawa Shogunate Family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>俗に御茶壷道中という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is vulgarly called ochatsubo dochu (procession).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is commonly referred to as ochatsubo dochu (procession).</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is commonly referred to as ochatsubo dochu (procession).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>起源は慶長18年（1613年）、江戸幕府が宇治茶の献上を命じる宇治採茶師を派遣したのが始まりである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It started in 1613 when Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) dispatched Uji saicha shi to order the presentation of Uji tea leaves to the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It started in 1613 when the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) dispatched Uji saicha shi to order the presentation of Uji tea leaves to the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It started in 1613 when the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) dispatched Uji saicha shi to order the presentation of Uji tea leaves to the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>元和 (日本)年間、使番が使者に任命され宇治茶を運んでいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During Genna era (1615-1623), tsukaiban (a person responsible for order and patrol in the battle field) was appointed as an envoy to carry the tea leaves.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During Genna era (1615-1623), tsukaiban (a person responsible for inspecting and patrolling a battle field) were appointed as envoys to carry the tea leaves.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During Genna era (1615-1623), tsukaiban (a person responsible for inspecting and patrolling a battle field) were appointed as envoys to carry the tea leaves.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>徳川家光の時代の寛永9年に制度化され、寛永10年（1633年）から、幕末の慶応2年（1866年）まで続けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The system was institutionalized in 1632 of Iemitsu TOKUGAWA era and it was continued until 1866 in the end of Edo Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The system was institutionalized in 1632 during the Iemitsu TOKUGAWA era and it was continued until 1866 at the end of the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The system was institutionalized in 1632 during the Iemitsu TOKUGAWA era and it was continued until 1866 at the end of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>period 小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>行列はないが最後に江戸に茶壷を送ったのは慶応3年（1867年）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was in 1867 that the last chatsubo was sent to Edo, without the procession.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The last chatsubo was sent to Edo, without a procession, in 1867.</e>
<cmt>Word flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The last chatsubo was sent to Edo, without a procession, in 1867.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>この時は徳川慶喜が二条城に在洛中であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was when Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA was staying in Nijojo Castle in Kyoto</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this time, Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA was staying at the Nijojo Castle in Kyoto</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this time, Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA was staying at the Nijo-jo Castle in Kyoto</e>
<cmt>Nijo-jo としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>随行していた元数寄屋組頭の鈴木春碩が宇治に来て、必要なだけ御茶壺のみを宿次人足に委ねて江戸城に運んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, Shunseki SUZUKI, the former chief officer in charge of tea ceremony and tea utensil of Edo bakufu, came to Uji and asked shukutsugi ninsoku (carriers who transfer to the next staff at post) to carry the necessary number of chatsubo packed with the tea leaves to Edo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shunseki SUZUKI, the former chief officer in charge of tea ceremonies and tea utensils within the Edo bakufu, came to Uji and asked shukutsugi ninsoku (couriers who relayed packages from one messenger to another) to carry the necessary number of tea leave packed chatsubo to Edo.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shunseki SUZUKI, the former chief officer in charge of tea ceremonies and tea utensils within the Edo bakufu, came to Uji and asked shukutsugi ninsoku (couriers who relayed packages from one messenger to another) to carry the necessary number of tea leave packed chatsubo to Edo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>平成6年（1994年）、平安建都1200年記念事業で、有志により京都から東京まで徒歩で御茶壺道中が再現された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1994, as one of the events of the 1200-year anniversary of Heian&apos;s founding, ochatsubo dochu was reenacted by volunteers on foot from Kyoto to Tokyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1994, as one of the events of the 1200-year anniversary of Heian&apos;s founding, ochatsubo dochu was reenacted by volunteers on foot from Kyoto to Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1994, as one of the events of the 1200-year anniversary of Heian&apos;s founding, ochatsubo dochu was reenacted by volunteers on foot from Kyoto to Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>また、茶壷蔵のあった都留市でも毎年この行列を再現している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Tsuru City that used to have chatsubo gura (a storage for tea jar), the procession is reenacted annually.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Tsuru City, where they used to have chatsubo gura (storage for tea jars), the procession is reenacted annually.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Tsuru City, where they used to have chatsubo gura (storage for tea jars), the procession is reenacted annually.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>手順</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Procedure</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Procedure</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Procedure</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>4月下旬から5月上旬に行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It used to be held from the end of April through early May.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It used to be held from the end of April through early May.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It used to be held from the end of April through early May.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>責任者たる徒歩頭（かちがしら）が輪番でその任を務めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kachigashira (a chief of foot soldiers in the Edo Period), who was responsible for it, took the charge of carrying the tea jar by rotation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The kachigashira (men in charge of foot soldiers during the Edo Period), took responsibility of carrying the tea jar in rotation.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The kachigashira (a chief of foot soldiers in the Edo period) took responsibility of carrying the tea jar in rotation.</e>
<cmt>period 小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>茶道頭や茶道衆（茶坊主）のほか茶壷の警備の役人など、徳川吉宗の倹約令が出るまで膨れ上がり、多い時には1000人を超える大行列となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The number of the staff in the procession, such as chadogashira or chadoshu (tea server) and security officials to guard the tea jar, had swollen up to 1000 until the thrift ordinance of Yoshimune TOKUGAWA was issued.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The number of the staff in the procession, such as chadogashira or chadoshu (tea server) and security officials to guard the tea jar, had swollen up to 1000 people until Yoshimune TOKUGAWA issued new laws regulating expenditures.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The number of the staff in the procession, such as chadogashira (a head of tea ceremony for the Tokugawa Shogunate family) or chadoshu (tea server) and security officials to guard the tea jar, had swollen up to more than 1000 people until Yoshimune TOKUGAWA issued new laws regulating expenditures.</e>
<cmt>茶道頭→a head of tea ceremony for the Tokugawa Shogunate family　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>道中の総責任者は、宇治の代官の上林家が代々務めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanbayashi Family that served as daikan (magistrate) in Uji successively took all the responsibility during the procession</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kanbayashi Family that served as daikan (magistrate) in Uji took on all the responsibility of the procession for generations.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kanbayashi family that served as daikan (magistrate) in Uji took on all the responsibility of the procession for generations.</e>
<cmt>family 小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="15">
<j>100以上の将軍家伝来の茶壷に最高級の碾茶を詰めて、往路は東海道を復路は中山道・甲州街道を通った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The procession made its way through Tokaido Road in outward journey and Nakasendo Road and Koshu Road in return journey with more than 100 tea jars exclusively belonging to Shogunate Family packed with powdered green tea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The procession made its way down the Tokaido Road at the start of its journey and returned following the Nakasendo Road and Koshu Road with more than 100 tea jars exclusively belonging to Shogunate Family packed with powdered green tea.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The procession made its way down the Tokai-do Road at the start of its journey and returned following the Nakasen-do Road and Koshu-kaido Road with more than 100 tea jars exclusively belonging to Shogunate Family packed with powdered green tea.</e>
<cmt>甲州街道→Koshu-kaido Road としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>甲州街道を通った行列は甲斐国谷村（現・都留市）の勝山城の茶壷蔵に納められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The procession that went through Koshu Road stopped at Yamura, Kai Province (present Tsuru City), and the tea jars were stored in chatsubo gura in Katsuyama Castle.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The procession that passed through Koshu Road stopped at Yamura, Kai Province (present day Tsuru City), and stored the tea jars in the chatsubo gura at Katsuyama Castle.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The procession that passed through Koshu-kaido Road stopped at Yamura, Kai Province (present day Tsuru City), and stored the tea jars in the chatsubo gura at Katsuyama-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>甲州街道→Koshu-kaido Road としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>富士山の冷気にあてて熟成してから、江戸に運んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That was in order for the tea leaves to be exposed to cold wind from Mt. Fuji, and then after maturation the tea pots were carried to Edo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was in order for the tea leaves to mature by being exposed to the cold wind from Mt. Fuji, before they were carried to Edo.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was in order for the tea leaves to mature by being exposed to the cold wind from Mt. Fuji, before they were carried to Edo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="18">
<j>この御茶壷道中は、将軍が飲み徳川家祖廟に献ずるものであるから自ずからたいへん権威があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the tea leaves were for Shogun to drink and to offer to the Tokugawa family&apos;s sobyo (mausoleum containing the remains of the ancestors), the ochatsubo dochu procession was so authoritative.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the tea leaves were for the Shogun to drink and to offer to the Tokugawa family&apos;s sobyo (mausoleum containing the remains of their ancestors), the ochatsubo dochu procession was immensely authoritative.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the tea leaves were for the Shogun to drink and to offer to the Tokugawa family&apos;s sobyo (mausoleum containing the remains of their ancestors), the ochatsubo dochu procession was immensely authoritative.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>摂関家や門跡並で、御三家の行列であっても、駕籠から降りて、馬上の家臣はおりて、道を譲らねばならなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The procession was regarded the same as sekkanke (the families of Regents and Chief Advisors to Imperial family) and monseki (a temple whose head priest is a member of the Imperial family), and even the lords of Tokugawa gosanke (three privileged branches of Tokugawa family) had to get off their palanquin, their vassals dismount from their horses, and give their way to the ochatsubo dochu procession.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The procession was regarded the same as sekkanke (the families of Regents and Chief Advisors to the Imperial family) and monseki (a temple whose head priest is a member of the Imperial family), and even the lords of Tokugawa gosanke (three privileged branches of the Tokugawa family) had to get off their palanquin, their vassals dismount from their horses, to make way for the ochatsubo dochu procession.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The procession was regarded the same as sekkanke (the families of regents and chief advisors to the Imperial Family) and monzeki (temples whose head priest is a member of the Imperial family), and even the lords of Tokugawa gosanke (three privileged branches of the Tokugawa family) had to get off their palanquin, their vassals dismount from their horses, to make way for the ochatsubo dochu procession.</e>
<cmt>門跡→monzeki としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="20">
<j>行列が通る街道は、前もって入念な道普請が命ぜられ、農繁期であっても田植えは禁止された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was ordered in advance to do the elaborate michibushin (road improvement) to the roads that the precession would go through, and even in the period of busy faming rice planting was prohibited.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Elaborate michibushin (road improvement) was ordered in advance for the roads that the precession would follow, and even during the farming season rice planting was prohibited.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Elaborate michi bushin (road improvement) was ordered in advance for the roads that the precession would follow, and even during the farming season rice planting was prohibited.</e>
<cmt>michi bushin として表現を他の記事と統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>子供の戸口の出入り、たこ揚げ、屋根の置き石、煮炊きの煙も上げることは許されなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Children&apos;s going out and in through the door, kite flying, putting stones on the roof and putting out smoke from preparing meals were not allowed.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Children going in and out of houses, kite flying, putting stones on roofs and even smoke from cooking fires was not allowed.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Children going in and out of houses, kite flying, putting stones on roofs and even smoke from cooking fires was not allowed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>葬式の列さえ禁止された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even the funeral processions were prohibited.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even funeral processions were prohibited.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even funeral processions were prohibited.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>権威のあるこの行列を恐れていた沿道の庶民は、茶壷の行列が来たら、戸を閉めて閉じこもった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The common people along the roads who were afraid of the authoritative procession shut the door and kept inside when the procession came along.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Common people who lived by the roads who were afraid of the authoritative procession shut their doors and kept inside as the procession passed by.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Common people who lived by the roads who were afraid of the authoritative procession shut their doors and kept inside as the procession passed by.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>この様子は沿道の民は非常にこれを恐れていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The people along the road were so afraid of the situation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The people along the road were quite afraid of this situation.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The people along the road were quite afraid of this situation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>お茶壺が来たら、戸をぴしゃんと閉めて閉じこもった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They slammed the door and kept inside when the procession came.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They slammed their doors and kept inside as the procession approached.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They slammed their doors and kept inside as the procession approached.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>また、道で出くわしたら、土下座で行列を遣り過すしかなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And when they happened to encounter the procession on the road, they just had to kneel down on the ground and let the procession go past.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, if they happened to encounter the procession on the road, they could do nothing but kneel down on the ground and let the procession pass.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, if they happened to encounter the procession on the road, they could do nothing but kneel down on the ground and let the procession pass.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>茶壺の行列の様子は、現代でも童歌のずいずいずっころばしに良く表現されて歌い継がれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The scenes of the chatsubo procession have been sung until today in an old children&apos;s song called &quot;zuizui zukkorobashi.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even today, the scenes of the chatsubo procession are clearly expressed in an old children&apos;s song called &quot;zuizui zukkorobashi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even today, the scenes of the chatsubo procession are clearly expressed in an old children&apos;s song called &quot;zuizui zukkorobashi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kurz(id:1601), 立志堂(id:132177), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>