<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>柴漬</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shibazuke (柴漬)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shibazuke (柴漬)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shibazuke</e>
<cmt>（柴漬）を省きました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>漬物に関しては、正しくは「紫葉漬け」であり「柴漬」は誤り。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As far as Tsukemono is concerned, &apos;紫葉漬け&apos; is correct and &apos;柴漬&apos; is wrong.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As far as Tsukemono is concerned, &apos;紫葉漬け&apos; is correct and &apos;柴漬&apos; is wrong.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As far as Tsukemono is concerned, &apos;紫葉漬け&apos; is correct and &apos;柴漬&apos; is wrong.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>京都の伝統的な漬物。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is traditional Tsukemono in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is traditional tsukemono in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is traditional Tsukemono in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>漬物を大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>以下、この意味で解説する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is explained in this sense as below.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is explained in this sense as follows:</e>
<cmt>usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is explained in this sense as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>柴漬 (ふしづけ) は、柴を束ねて水に沈め、中に入った魚を捕らえる方法。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fushizuke (柴漬) is a method to catch fish inside brushwood bundled and dunked in water.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fushizuke (柴漬) is a method of catching fish inside brushwood that is bundled and dunked in water.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fushizuke (柴漬) is a method of catching fish inside brushwood that is bundled and dunked in water.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>処刑方法の一種。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A method of execution.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A method of execution</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A method of execution</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>罪人を柴で包んで縛り上げ、重りをつけて水底に沈める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A sinner is tied up covered with brushwood and sunk to the bottom of water with weight.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A sinner is tied up covered with brushwood and sunk to the bottom of water with weight.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A sinner is tied up covered with brushwood and sunk to the bottom of water with weight.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>紫葉漬け (しばづけ) とはナスを刻んだ赤シソの葉で塩漬けにした、京都の伝統的な漬物であり、「すぐき」、「千枚漬」と並んで京都の三大漬物と言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shibazuke (紫葉漬け) is chopped eggplants salted with red perilla, as traditional Tsukemono in Kyoto, and one of the three best Tsukemono in Kyoto along with &apos;Suguki&apos; and &apos;Senmaizuke.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shibazuke (紫葉漬け) is chopped eggplants salted with red perilla, as a traditional tsukemono in Kyoto and one of the three best tsukemono in Kyoto along with &apos;Suguki&apos; and &apos;Senmaizuke.&apos;</e>
<cmt>punctuation, case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shibazuke (紫葉漬け) is chopped eggplants salted with red perilla, as a traditional Tsukemono in Kyoto and one of the three best Tsukemono in Kyoto along with &apos;Suguki&apos; and &apos;Senmaizuke.&apos;</e>
<cmt>漬物を大文字に。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>紫蘇の赤紫色が鮮やかで、酸味が強い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has vivid red purple color of perilla and a strong sour taste.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has a vivid reddish-purple color of perilla and a strong sour taste.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has a vivid reddish-purple color of perilla and a strong sour taste.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>京都の漬物であるが、人気が高く日本全国ほぼどこでも売られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It&apos;s Tsukemono from Kyoto, but sold almost all over Japan because it is very popular.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is tsukemono from Kyoto, but due to the popularity of this dish it&apos;s sold nearly everywhere in Japan..</e>
<cmt>better</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is Tsukemono from Kyoto, but due to the popularity of this dish it&apos;s sold nearly everywhere in Japan..</e>
<cmt>漬物を大文字に。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="10">
<j>本来の製法で漬ける場合は、熟成まで一年近くかかるとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In case of pickling with the original process, it is supposed to take almost one year to mature.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the case of pickling with the original process, it is supposed to take nearly a year to mature.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the case of pickling with the original process, it is supposed to take nearly a year to mature.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>現在はキュウリやミョウガなどを入れる事もあり、酢漬けにされるが、本来は茄子と紫蘇の葉、そして塩を用い、酸味は乳酸菌由来のものだけで酢は使用しなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though cucumbers or Japanese gingers may be added and pickled in vinegar today, only eggplants, perilla and salt were used originally, and its sour taste comes only from lactic bacterium and no vinegar was used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though cucumbers or Japanese ginger can be added and pickled in vinegar today, originally only eggplant, perilla and salt were used; its sour taste comes only from lactic bacterium, so traditionally no vinegar was used.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although cucumbers or Japanese ginger can be added and pickled in vinegar today, originally only eggplant, perilla and salt were used; its sour taste comes only from lactic bacterium, so traditionally no vinegar was used.</e>
<cmt>Though →Although に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>現在この酢を使用しない製法のものは「生柴漬」「生紫葉漬け」などという名称で販売されることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today, the ones made in such process without using vinegar is sold mostly as &apos;Nama Shibazuke (untreated Shibazuke).&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, the ones made in such process without using vinegar are generally sold as &apos;nama shibazuke (untreated shibazuke).&apos;</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, the ones made in such process without using vinegar are generally sold as &apos;Nama Shibazuke (untreated Shibazuke).&apos;</e>
<cmt>生柴漬を大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="13">
<j>平家が滅亡した後、平家の数少ない生き残りで、京の大原に隠棲した建礼門院（平徳子）が、慰めのために持ち寄られた地元の漬物を気に入り、紫葉の入った漬物、「紫葉漬け」と名付けたという伝承がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is an legend that, after the Heike clan was destroyed, Kenreimon&apos;in (TAIRA no Tokuko), one of the few survivors of the Heike clan, who secluded in Ohara in Kyoto, liked the local Tsukemono brought for her comfort, and named the Tsukemono with perilla &apos;Shibazuke.&apos;</e>
<cmt>建礼門院（平徳子）http://100.yahoo.co.jp/detail/平徳子/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is an legend that, after the Heike clan was destroyed, Kenreimon&apos;in (TAIRA no Tokuko), one of the few survivors of the Heike, having secluded himself in Ohara, Kyoto, liked the local tsukemono brought for her comfort, and named the tsukemono with perilla &apos;shibazuke.&apos;</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is an legend that, after the Taira clan was destroyed, Kenreimonin (TAIRA no Tokuko), one of the few survivors of the Taira clan, having secluded herself in Ohara, Kyoto, liked the local Tsukemono brought for her comfort, and named the Tsukemono with perilla &apos;Shibazuke.&apos;</e>
<cmt>himself→herself　漬物名は大文字に変えました。Heike clan→Taira clanに変更しました。Heike→Taira clanに変更しました。Kenreimon&apos;in→Kenreimoninに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="14">
<j>山口美江が「紫葉漬け食べたい」と叫ぶ、フジッコ・漬物百選の有名なCMがあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was a famous commercial film of Tsukemono Hyakusen (Hundred selection of Tsukemono) by Fujicco, that Mie YAMAGUCHI shouts &apos;I want to eat Shibazuke.&apos;</e>
<cmt>山口美江http://talent.yahoo.co.jp/pf/detail/pp687フジッコhttp://www.fujicco.co.jp/index.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was a famous commercial film called &quot;Tsukemono Hyakusen (A Hundred Selections of Tsukemono)&quot; by Fujicco, in which Mie YAMAGUCHI shouts &apos;I want to eat shibazuke.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar, case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was a famous commercial film called &quot;Tsukemono Hyakusen (A Hundred Selections of Tsukemono)&quot; by Fujicco, in which Mie YAMAGUCHI shouts &apos;I want to eat Shibazuke.&apos;</e>
<cmt>柴漬けを大文字に変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 パの字(id:34188), 釣ちごちゅが(id:22605), Bergmann(id:85282), マクガイア(id:33346), Nighthawks(id:36125), あーうー(id:1140), DoWhile(id:34638), 1029man(id:93235), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>