<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>近江牛</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omigyu (beef cattle grown in Shiga prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omigyu (beef cattle grown in Shiga prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omigyu (beef cattle grown in Shiga prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>近江牛（おうみぎゅう）は、滋賀県で肥育される和牛である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omigyu is a wagyu cattle (Japanese cattle), grown in Shiga prefecture.</e>
<cmt>和牛は、用語集になかったので、wagyu cattle (Japanese cattle)としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omigyu is wagyu (Japanese beef) grown in Shiga Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>コンマの削除、表現の修正をしました。をしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omigyu is wagyu (Japanese beef) grown in Shiga Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>同じ但馬牛を素牛とする神戸牛、松阪牛と合わせ、日本三大和牛の一角を占める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is one of the three major wagyu cattle combined with Kobe beef and Matsuzaka beef that are the same breeding cattle, Tajima beef.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is one of the three major wagyu beef brands along with Kobe beef and Matsuzaka beef, all of which have the same breeding cattle, Tajima beef.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正をしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is one of the three major wagyu beef brands along with Kobe beef and Matsuzaka beef, all of which have the same breeding cattle, Tajima beef.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>歴史の古い食肉牛である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is an edible beef which has a long history.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is an edible beef which has a long history.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is an edible beef which has a long history.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>このうち近江牛は和牛の 90％ を占める黒毛和種である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among those beef, Omigyu is a Japanese black beef that accounts for 90% of wagyu cattle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among those beef brands, Omigyu is a Japanese black beef brand that accounts for 90% of wagyu.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正をしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among those beef brands, Omigyu is a Japanese black beef brand that accounts for 90% of wagyu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>牛の肥育履歴偽装事件を受け、2005年12月、近江牛の定義は、優秀な子牛を導入もしくは生産し、滋賀県内で最も長く肥育した黒毛和種でかつ、JAS法に定める原産地表示が「滋賀県産」と表示できるもの、とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After beef breed record camouflage incident, in Dec., 2005, Omigyu was defined as an excellent calf brought to or produced in the Shiga Prefecture where is the longest growing location of it, and was also defined that indication of place of origin is labeled as &quot;Shiga Prefecture&quot; under the JAS law (Act for Standardization and Proper Labeling of Agricultural and Forestry Products).</e>
<cmt>用語集では、JAS法は、Act for Standardization and Proper Labeling of Agricultural and Forestry Productsとなっていますが、コメント（出典）のリンクがエラーになり確認できませんでしたが、農林水産省のホームページhttp://search.maff.go.jp/search?as_q=JAS+law&amp;site=maff&amp;client=maff_frontend&amp;proxystylesheet=maff_frontend&amp;output=xml_no_dtdJAS law　で検索するとJAS lawと言っているようです。したがって、ここでは、JAS law (Act for Standardization and Proper Labeling of Agricultural and Forestry Products)と訳しました。原産地表示は、indication of place of origin http://www.ab.auone-net.jp/~ttt/words%20e%20and%20j%20.htmlとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the beef breed record camouflage incident, in December 2005, Omigyu was defined not only as a Japanese black beef brand raised from an excellent calf, brought to or produced in Shiga Prefecture, for the longest period in the prefecture but also as the one whose place of origin can be indicated as &apos;Shiga Prefecture&apos; under JAS law (Act for Standardization and Proper Labeling of Agricultural and Forestry Products).</e>
<cmt>表現・文法の修正をしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the beef breed record camouflage incident, in December 2005, Omigyu was defined not only as a Japanese black beef brand raised from an excellent calf, brought to or produced in Shiga Prefecture, for the longest period in the prefecture but also as the one whose place of origin can be indicated as &apos;Shiga Prefecture&apos; under JAS law (Act for Standardization and Proper Labeling of Agricultural and Forestry Products).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>江戸時代には、牛肉が「養生薬」の名目で、味噌漬や干し肉として彦根藩から将軍家へ献上、賞味されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Edo Period, beef was presented to the Shogun family in the form of misozuke (pickling in miso (fermented soybean paste)) or dried meat in the name of &quot;yojoyaku&quot; (medicine for health) by Hikone Clan, and was tasted by the Shogun family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Edo Period, beef was presented to the Shogun family by Hikone Clan in the form of misozuke (pickling in miso [fermented soybean paste]) or of dried meat in the name of &apos;yojoyaku&apos; (medicine for health).</e>
<cmt>「献上」されれば「賞味される」ことは自明なので「賞味されていた」は削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Edo Period, beef was presented to the Shogun family by Hikone Clan in the form of misozuke (pickling in miso [fermented soybean paste]) or of dried meat in the name of &apos;yojoyaku&apos; (medicine for health).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>明治になり、西洋文化の影響で牛肉食が始まり松阪牛の普及に伊勢商人が貢献したように近江商人の活躍があったためともいわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Meiji Period, western culture influenced the start of eating beef, which was said to be also influenced by the success of Omi shonin (Omi merchants) as Ise shonin (Ise merchants) contributed to the spread of Matsuzaka beef.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Meiji Period, people started to eat beef under the influence of the western culture and Omi shonin (Omi merchants) reportedly contributed to the spread of beef consumption as Ise shonin (Ise merchants) did to the spread of Matsuzaka beef.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正をしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Meiji Period, people started to eat beef under the influence of the western culture and Omi shonin (Omi merchants) reportedly contributed to the spread of beef consumption as Ise shonin (Ise merchants) did to the spread of Matsuzaka beef.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>なお、神戸牛は本来、神戸ビーフと呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, Kobegyu was called Kobe beef originally.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, Kobegyu was called Kobe beef originally.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, Kobegyu was called Kobe beef originally.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>神戸産の牛ではなく輸送のために神戸港に運ばれてきた近江牛を在留外国人が賞味し名付けたともいわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Kobe beef was not a beef produced in Kobe, but was Omigyu brought to Kobe Port for transportation and foreign residents tasted the beef and named it as Kobe beef.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that foreign residents tasted Omi beef brought to Kobe Port for transportation, believing that it was Kobe beef, and named it as Kobe beef by mistake.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正をしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that foreign residents tasted Omi beef brought to Kobe Port for transportation, believing that it was Kobe beef, and named it as Kobe beef by mistake.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>生産</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Production</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Production</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Production</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>主に滋賀県の蒲生郡、神崎郡 (滋賀県)、愛知郡 (滋賀県)（現在の近江八幡市、東近江市、竜王町など）において生産されてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has been produced mainly in Gamo County, Kanzaki County (Shiga Prefecture), and Echi County (Shiga Prefecture) (current Omihachiman City, Higashiomi City, and Ryuoh Town, etc.) in Shiga Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omi beef has been produced mainly in Gamo County, Kanzaki County (Shiga Prefecture), and Echi County (Shiga Prefecture) (currently, Omihachiman City, Higashiomi City, and Ryuoh Town, etc.) in Shiga Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正をしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omi beef has been produced mainly in Gamo County, Kanzaki County (Shiga Prefecture), and Echi County (Shiga Prefecture) (currently, Omihachiman City, Higashiomi City, and Ryuoh Town, etc.) in Shiga Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>これら一帯は米の生産やその他の農業も盛んで、このため牛を肥育するための飼料とストレスの少ない気候に恵まれたためともいわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that those areas are blessed with feedstuff for fattening cattle and a less stressful climate because production of rice and other agricultural products are active.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that those areas, as leading producers of rice and other agricultural products, are blessed with feedstuff for fattening cattle and mild climate.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正をしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that those areas, as leading producers of rice and other agricultural products, are blessed with feedstuff for fattening cattle and mild climate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>特徴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Characteristics</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Characteristics</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Characteristics</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="12">
<j>松阪牛に比べて肉の繊維や霜降りのきめが細かい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Compared with Matsuzaka beef, it is finely-textured meat fiber and marbled beef.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omi beef has more fine-textured meat fiber and marbling than Matsuzaka beef.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正をしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omi beef has more fine-textured meat fiber and marbling than Matsuzaka beef.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>脂は、融点が低くて常温で溶ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fat has a low melting point and melts at normal temperature.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fat has a low melting point and melts at normal temperature.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fat has a low melting point and melts at normal temperature.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 もね～るmoner(id:28477), Mooh(id:185556), 嫦娥(id:81469), ぱむ(id:24323), Ｋｙ進(id:59658), BUNBUN(id:63624), Licsak(id:27840), Kanai05(id:212440), Kyoww(id:126965), 1029man(id:93235), 10cm(id:147838), TibetFreedom(id:196334), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>