<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>三つ葉葵</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitsuba-aoi (Three leaves of Hollyhock)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitsuba-aoi (Three Leaves of Hollyhock)</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitsuba-aoi (Three Leaves of Hollyhock)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>三つ葉葵（みつばあおい）は日本の家紋である葵紋の一種。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitsuba-aoi is one type of aoi-mon (mallow patterns) which have been used as Japanese family crests.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitsuba-aoi is a type of aoi-mon (mallow patterns), which have been used as Japanese family crests.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitsuba-aoi is a type of aoi-mon (mallow patterns), which have been used as Japanese family crests.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>通常「三つ葉葵」といえば徳川氏の「丸に三つ葉葵」の紋を指すことが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term &quot;Mitsuba-aoi&quot;, in many cases, refers to the crest design of the &quot;Maruni Mitsuba-aoi (three leaves of Hollyhock in a circle)&quot; which shows the Tokugawa clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term &quot;Mitsuba-aoi,&quot; in many cases, refers to the crest design of the &quot;Maruni Mitsuba-aoi (three leaves of hollyhock in a circle),&quot; which indicates the Tokugawa clan.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term &quot;Mitsuba-aoi,&quot; in many cases, refers to the crest design of the &quot;Maru ni Mitsuba-aoi&quot; (three leaves of hollyhock in a circle), which indicates the Tokugawa clan.</e>
<cmt>Maru ni Mitsuba-aoiとし、クォーテーションの位置を移動</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>葵紋</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Aoi-mon</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Aoi-mon</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Aoi-mon</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>葵紋（あおいもん）はウマノスズクサ科のフタバアオイを図案化したものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Aoi-mon is designed in the motif of a futaba-aoi (two-leaf mallow) which belongs to Aristolochiaceae.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Aoi-mon is designed in the motif of a futaba-aoi (two-leaf mallow), which belongs to Aristolochiaceae.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Aoi-mon is designed in the motif of a futaba-aoi (two-leaf mallow), which belongs to Aristolochiaceae.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>その名の通り通常の葉の数は2枚である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As its name suggests, the futaba-aoi has two leaves in general.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As its name suggests, the futaba-aoi generally has two leaves.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As its name suggests, the futaba-aoi generally has two leaves.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>三つ葉のフタバアオイは稀で、三つ葉葵は架空のものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A three-leafed futaba-aoi is rare, and therefore the Mitsuba-aoi is an imaginary plant.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A three-leafed futaba-aoi is rare, and therefore the Mitsuba-aoi is an imaginary plant.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A three-leafed futaba-aoi is rare, and therefore the Mitsuba-aoi is an imaginary plant.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>葵祭に見られるように賀茂氏の象徴であり、葵紋は賀茂神社の神紋（二葉葵・加茂葵）になっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As seen in Aoi-matsuri Festival (Hollyhock flower Festival), the aoi-mon symbolizes the Kamo clan and has been used as the Kamo-jinja Shrine crest (two leaves of Hollyhock or Kamo Aoi).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As seen in the Aoi-matsuri Festival (Hollyhock Flower Festival), the aoi-mon symbolizes the Kamo clan and has been used as the Kamo-jinja Shrine crest (two leaves of hollyhock or Kamo Aoi).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As seen in the Aoi-matsuri Festival (Hollyhock Flower Festival), the aoi-mon symbolizes the Kamo clan and has been used as the Kamo-jinja Shrine crest (two leaves of hollyhock or Kamo Aoi).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>その賀茂氏とのつながりが深い三河国の武士団は、葵紋を家紋としてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bushidan (warrior bands) in Mikawa Province which had close links with the Kamo clan used the aoi-mon as their family crests.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bushidan (warrior bands) in Mikawa Province, which had close links with the Kamo clan, used the aoi-mon as their family crests.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bushidan (warrior bands) in Mikawa Province, which had close links with the Kamo clan, used the aoi-mon as their family crests.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>これにより三河武士である徳川家が葵紋を使用していることは、徳川家が清和源氏の末裔ではなく賀茂氏の末裔ではないかとの説の根拠ともなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fact supports the view that the use of the aoi-mon by the Tokugawa clan, a warrior in Mikawa means that the clan may be a descendant of the Kamo clan, not the Seiwa-Genji (Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This fact supports the view that the use of the aoi-mon by the Tokugawa clan, particularly by a warrior in Mikawa, means that the clan may be a descendant of the Kamo clan instead of the Seiwa-Genji (Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This fact supports the view that the use of the aoi-mon by the Tokugawa family, particularly by a warrior in Mikawa, means that the family may be a descendant of the Kamo clan instead of the Seiwa-Genji (Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt>the Tokugawa clan→the Tokugawa family、the clan→the familyとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>はじめは、特別な紋ではなかったが徳川家が征夷大将軍となり徳川幕府を開くにあたり、次第に他家の三つ葉葵に限らず葵紋の使用がはばかられるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Initially, the aoi-mon was not a special crest, but other families gradually started to avoid using the aoi-mon including the Mitsuba-aoi when the Tokugawa clan became the Seitaishogun (commander-in-chief of the expeditionary force against the barbarians, great, unifying leader) and established the Tokugawa shogunate.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Initially, the aoi-mon wasn&apos;t a special crest, but other families gradually started to avoid using the aoi-mon, including the Mitsuba-aoi, when the Tokugawa clan became the Seitaishogun (commander-in-chief of the expeditionary force against the barbarians; great, unifying leader) and established the Tokugawa shogunate.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Initially, the aoi-mon was not a special crest, but other families gradually started to avoid using the aoi-mon, including the Mitsuba-aoi, when the Tokugawa family became the Seii Taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) and established the Tokugawa shogunate.</e>
<cmt>wasn&apos;t→was not、the Tokugawa clan→the Tokugawa familyとし、 Seitaishogun→Seii Taishogunに修正、補足を統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>松平氏へは遠慮させ、伊奈氏には禁止させている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Tokugawa clan had the Matsudaira clan refrain from using the aoi-mon, and prohibited the Ina clan from using it.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Tokugawa clan had the Matsudaira clan refrain from using the aoi-mon and prohibited the Ina clan from using it.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tokugawa clan had the Matsudaira clan refrain from using the aoi-mon and prohibited the Ina clan from using it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>それらによっていつしか徳川家が独占するようになったが、徳川家家臣である本多氏や准家門の鳥取藩池田氏のように一部葵紋の使用を許されることもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since then, the Tokugawa clan monopolized the aoi-mon, but permission to use the aoi-mon was occasionally given to some clans such as the Honda clan, a Tokugawa&apos;s retainer and the Ikeda clan of Tottori Domain, a jun kamon (quasi-lineage) of the Tokugawa clan.</e>
<cmt>「准家門」の訳が検索できませんでしたので直訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently, the Tokugawa clan monopolized the aoi-mon, but permission to use the aoi-mon was occasionally given to some clans such as the Honda clan, a Tokugawa retainer, and the Ikeda clan of Tottori Domain, a jun kamon (quasi-lineage) of the Tokugawa clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently, the Tokugawa family monopolized the aoi-mon, but permission to use the aoi-mon was occasionally given to some clans such as the Honda clan, a Tokugawa retainer, and the Ikeda clan of Tottori Domain, a jun kamon (quasi-lineage) of the Tokugawa family.</e>
<cmt>the Tokugawa clan→the Tokugawa familyとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>天皇家は足利氏、織田信長、豊臣秀吉の例に倣い桐紋を徳川家にも与えようとしたが、徳川家はこれを固辞した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Imperial Family tried to give Kiri-mon (paulownia patterns) to the Tokugawa family to follow the precedent of the Ashikaga clan, Nobunaga ODA and Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, but the Tokugawa family refused to receive it.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Imperial Family tried to give Kiri-mon (paulownia patterns) to the Tokugawa family in order to follow the precedent of the Ashikaga clan, Nobunaga ODA and Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, but the Tokugawa family refused to receive it.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Imperial Family tried to give Kiri-mon (paulownia patterns) to the Tokugawa family in order to follow the precedent of the Ashikaga clan, Nobunaga ODA and Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, but the Tokugawa family refused to receive it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>そのため、葵紋の権威は大いに上がったとも言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, it is said that the prestige of the aoi-mon was tremendously boosted.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, it is said that the prestige of the aoi-mon was dramatically enhanced.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, it is said that the prestige of the aoi-mon was dramatically enhanced.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>三つ葉葵</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitsuba-aoi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitsuba-aoi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitsuba-aoi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="14">
<j>または三つ葵という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called Mitsu-aoi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called Mitsu-aoi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called Mitsu-aoi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>外郭が丸（輪）であるもののほかに、隅切り角（守山三つ葵・西条三つ葵など）のものや五環であるものもそういう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to its design with a circular outline, Mitsuba-aoi includes designs with angular outlines (Moriyama Mitsu-aoi, Saijo Mitsu-aoi and etc.) and gokan (五環) (five aoi-mon arranged in a circular pattern).</e>
<cmt>「隅切り角」「五環」の訳は&lt;http://www.alte-studio.com/inkan/kamon_lookup.php?s_cat_id=1&amp;retry=1&gt;を参考にしています。とくに「五環」については、読み方も分からず、調べても分からなかったので「５つ葵の模様が環状に配置されているデザイン」と解釈しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to its design with a circular outline, Mitsuba-aoi includes designs with angular outlines (Moriyama Mitsu-aoi, Saijo Mitsu-aoi, etc.) and gokan (五環) (five aoi-mon arranged in a circular pattern).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to its design with a circular outline, Mitsuba-aoi includes designs with angular outlines (Moriyama Mitsu-aoi, Saijo Mitsu-aoi, etc.) and gokan (五環) (five aoi-mon arranged in a circular pattern).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="16">
<j>徳川家、徳川御三家（尾張徳川家、紀州徳川家、水戸徳川家）では、同じような丸に三つ葉葵（まるにみつばあおい）いわゆる徳川葵（とくがわあおい）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Tokugawa clan and the Tokugawa gosanke (three privileged branches of Tokugawa family of Owari, Kishu, and Mito) had similar Maruni Mitsuba-aoi (Mitsuba-aoi in a circle), so called Tokugawa Aoi (the hollyhock trefoil coat of arms of the Tokugawa clan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Tokugawa clan and Tokugawa gosanke (three privileged branches of the Tokugawa families of Owari, Kishu and Mito) had similar Maruni Mitsuba-aoi (Mitsuba-aoi in a circle), or the so-called Tokugawa Aoi (the hollyhock trefoil coat of arms of the Tokugawa clan).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tokugawa family and Tokugawa gosanke (three privileged branches of the Tokugawa families of Owari, Kishu and Mito) had similar Maru ni Mitsuba-aoi (Mitsuba-aoi in a circle), or the so-called Tokugawa Aoi (the hollyhock trefoil coat of arms of the Tokugawa clan).</e>
<cmt>The Tokugawa family、Maru ni Mitsuba-aoiとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>徳川葵でも御三家それぞれでは、葉の模様（芯）の数の違いなどがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Each gosanke had a different Tokugawa Aoi whose leaf stripe patterns are different.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Each gosanke had a different Tokugawa Aoi, the leaf stripe patterns of which were distinct.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Each gosanke had a different Tokugawa Aoi, the leaf stripe patterns of which were distinct.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>同じ将軍家のものでも徳川三代までが一枚あたり33本で徐々に減っていき慶喜の時には13本になっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even in the same Tokugawa Shogun family, the Tokugawa Aoi of the family up to the third generation had 33 stripes per leaf, which were gradually reduced to 13 per leaf in the Yoshinobu era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even in the same Tokugawa shogun family, the Tokugawa Aoi of the family up to the third generation had 33 stripes per leaf, which were gradually reduced to 13 per leaf in the Yoshinobu era.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even in the same Tokugawa shogun family, the Tokugawa Aoi of the family up to the third generation had 33 stripes per leaf, which were gradually reduced to 13 per leaf in the Yoshinobu era.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>また、徳川綱吉、徳川吉宗は、会津葵のように、河骨の葉の図案に似た葉を用いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsunayoshi TOKUGAWA and Yoshimune TOKUGAWA used a leaf in design similar to nuphar leaf patterns used for the Aizu-aoi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsunayoshi TOKUGAWA and Yoshimune TOKUGAWA used a leaf that was similar in design to the nuphar leaf patterns used for the Aizu-aoi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunayoshi TOKUGAWA and Yoshimune TOKUGAWA used a leaf that was similar in design to the nuphar leaf patterns used for the Aizu-aoi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>ほかに葉の裏を使ったもの（丸に三つ裏葵）等の多くの変種がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are many variations such as crests using the underside of a leaf (Maruni Mitsuura-aoi [underside of the three leaves in a circle]).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are many variations, such as crests using the undersides of leaves (Maruni Mitsuura-aoi [undersides of three leaves in a circle]).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are many variations, such as crests using the undersides of leaves (Maru ni Mitsuura-aoi [undersides of three leaves in a circle]).</e>
<cmt>Maru ni Mitsuura-aoiとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>ただ、徳川一門である松平家は替紋の蔦紋や桐紋、唐団扇等を使用することがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In many cases, however, the Matsudaira family, a member of the Tokugawa clan used Tsuta-mon (ivy patterns) or Kiri-mon (paulownia patterns) which was used as a kae-mon (alternate personal crest), and Touchiwa (fan) amongst others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in many cases the Matsudaira family, a member of the Tokugawa clan, used Tsuta-mon (ivy patterns) or Kiri-mon (paulownia patterns), which was used as a kae-mon (alternate personal crest), and Touchiwa (fan), among others.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in many cases the Matsudaira family, a member of the Tokugawa clan, used Tsuta-mon (ivy patterns), Kiri-mon (paulownia patterns), or Touchiwa (fan), among others, which were used as a kae-mon (alternate personal crest).</e>
<cmt>「替紋の」は「蔦紋や桐紋」だけでなく「唐団扇」までかかると思われるため、訳文を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>由来</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Origin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Origin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Origin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="22">
<j>三つ葉葵紋の由来には以下のような幾つかの説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are various stories about the origin of the Mitsuba-aoi as stated below:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are various stories about the origin of the Mitsuba-aoi, as shown below:</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are various stories about the origin of the Mitsuba-aoi, as shown below:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="23">
<j>『改正三河後風土記』（成島司直）による</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kaisei Mikawago Fudoki (Foundation of the Tokugawa clan)&quot; (by Motonao NARUSHIMA) says that:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kaisei Mikawago Fudoki (Foundation of the Tokugawa Clan),&quot; by Motonao NARUSHIMA, states:</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Kaisei Mikawago Fudoki&quot; (Foundation of the Tokugawa Clan), by Motonao NARUSHIMA, states:</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションの位置を移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>本多中務大輔家（本多忠勝の家系）より献じたるものとも伝わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Mitsuba-aoi was presented by the Honda Nakatsukasa no taifu (Senior Assistant Minister of the Ministry of Central Affairs) family which was a lineage of Tadakatsu HONDA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Mitsuba-aoi was presented by the Honda Nakatsukasa no taifu (Senior Assistant Minister of the Ministry of Central Affairs) family, which was a lineage of Tadakatsu HONDA.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Mitsuba-aoi was presented by the Honda Nakatsukasa no taifu (Senior Assistant Minister of the Ministry of Central Affairs) family, which was a lineage of Tadakatsu HONDA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>本多の家の祖は、賀茂の社職たりしを以って、従来葵紋という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally, the Honda family used the aoi-mon because its founder served in the Kamo-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>本文章の訳は&lt;http://www.harimaya.com/kamon/column/aoi.html&gt;を参考にしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally, the Honda family used the aoi-mon because its founder served at Kamo-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally, the Honda family used the aoi-mon because its founder served at Kamo-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="26">
<j>改正三河後風土記は、江戸初期のに成立した『三河後風土記』（平岩主計親吉・著 寛永・正保年間）を原本に幕府の儒学者である成島司直により校正され天保年間に成立したものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kaisei Mikawago Fudoki&quot; was completed by Motonao NARUSHIMA, a Confucian scholar of the shogunate in the Tenpo era through his proofreading of its original, &quot;Mikawago Fudoki (The Topographical Records of Mikawa Province)&quot; (by Kazue chikayoshi HIRAIWA [平岩主計親吉] from the Kanei to the Seiho era) which was completed in the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt>「平岩主計親吉」の英語表記の順番が分かりませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kaisei Mikawago Fudoki&quot; was completed by Motonao NARUSHIMA, a Confucian scholar of the shogunate in the Tenpo era, through his proofreading of its original, &quot;Mikawago Fudoki (The Topographical Records of Mikawa Province)&quot; (by Kazue chikayoshi HIRAIWA [平岩主計親吉] from the Kanei era to the Seiho era), which was completed in the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaisei Mikawago Fudoki was completed by Motonao NARUSHIMA, a Confucian scholar of the shogunate in the Tenpo era, through his proofreading of its original, &quot;Mikawago Fudoki&quot; (The Topographical Records of Mikawa Province) (by Kazue Chikayoshi HIRAIWA [平岩主計親吉] from the Kanei era to the Seiho era), which was completed in the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション一部削除、chikayoshi→Chikayoshiに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>史書には、諸説を掲載し、どれが本当かわからないとしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This history book contains various stories, but says that it is unsure of which story is true.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This history book contains various stories but indicates there is uncertainty about which story is true.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This history book contains various stories but indicates there is uncertainty about which story is true.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>もっとも古い史書である三河後風土記には、酒井氏から由来する、とある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Mikawago Fudoki&quot;, much older history book, says that the Mitsuba-aoi was originated from the Sakai clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Mikawago Fudoki,&quot; a much older history book, states that the Mitsuba-aoi originated with the Sakai clan.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mikawago Fudoki, a much older history book, states that the Mitsuba-aoi originated with the Sakai clan.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="29">
<j>『柳営秘鑑』葵之御紋来由、『三河後風土記』『改正三河後風土記』の記述</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Aoi no Gomon Raiyu (the origin of the Tokugawa family&apos;s crest) in &quot;Ryuei Hikan&quot;, &quot;Mikawago Fudoki&quot;, and &quot;Kaisei Mikawago Fudoki&quot; say that:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Aoi no Gomon Raiyu (the origin of the Tokugawa family crest) in &quot;Ryuei Hikan,&quot; &quot;Mikawago Fudoki&quot; and &quot;Kaisei Mikawago Fudoki&quot; state:</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Aoi no Gomon Raiyu (the origin of the Tokugawa family crest) in &quot;Ryuei Hikan,&quot; &quot;Mikawago Fudoki&quot; and &quot;Kaisei Mikawago Fudoki&quot; state:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>文明七年七月（文明十一年七月とも）安祥合戦の時、酒井長衛門尉氏忠が、丸盆に葵葉三つを置き、これに、熨斗、勝栗、昆布を盛りて、三代信光に献じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July in 1475 (or July in 1479), during the Battle of Anjo, Choemon no jo Ujitada SAKAI placed three hollyhock leaves on a round tray and made Nobumitsu, the third head of Matsudaira family a present of the leaves with noshi (a thin strip of dried abalone wrapped in folded red and white paper), kachiguri (victory chestnut) and konbu (seaweed) on them.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In July 1475 (or July 1479), during the Battle of Anjo, Choemon no jo Ujitada SAKAI placed three hollyhock leaves on a round tray and made Nobumitsu, the third head of the Matsudaira family, a present of the leaves with noshi (a thin strip of dried abalone wrapped in folded red-and-white paper), kachiguri (victory chestnut) and konbu (seaweed) on them.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In July 1475 (or July 1479), during the Battle of Anjo, Choemon no jo Ujitada SAKAI placed three hollyhock leaves on a round tray and made Nobumitsu, the third head of the Matsudaira family, a present of the leaves with noshi (a thin strip of dried abalone wrapped in folded red-and-white paper), kachiguri (victory chestnut) and konbu (seaweed) on them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>この合戦勝利を得しより、この三つ葵を酒井家の紋にせよと賜りしが、五代長親の時、この紋を松平家の家紋と定め、酒井家にはこれに似たる酢漿草の紋を与えたり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Sakai was told to use the three hollyhock leaves for his family crest if they won the battle, in the Nagachika&apos;s day, the fifth head of the Matsudaira family, the Matsudaira family decided to use the Mitsuba-aoi as the family crest while the Sakai family was granted a yellow sorrel crest similar to the Mitsuba-aoi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Sakai was told to use the three hollyhock leaves for his family crest if they won the battle, in the time of Nagachika, the fifth head of the Matsudaira family, the Matsudaira family decided to use the Mitsuba-aoi as the family crest while the Sakai family was granted a yellow sorrel crest similar to the Mitsuba-aoi.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Sakai was told to use the three hollyhock leaves for his family crest if they won the battle, in the time of Nagachika, the fifth head of the Matsudaira family, the Matsudaira family decided to use the Mitsuba-aoi as the family crest while the Sakai family was granted a yellow sorrel crest similar to the Mitsuba-aoi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>またこれを家康の時とも伝えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also said that this happened in the Ieyasu era.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also said that this happened in the Ieyasu era.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also said that this happened in the Ieyasu era.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="33">
<j>『藩翰譜』（新井白石） 伊奈本多氏の項による</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The article of the Ina-Honda clan in &quot;Hankanpu (Genealogy of the Protectors of the Shogunate)&quot; (by Hakuseki ARAI) says that:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The article concerning the Ina-Honda clan in &quot;Hankanpu (Genealogy of the Protectors of the Shogunate)&quot; (by Hakuseki ARAI) states:</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The article concerning the Ina-Honda clan in &quot;Hankanpu&quot; (Genealogy of the Protectors of the Shogunate) (by Hakuseki ARAI) states:</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションの位置を移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>（改正三河後風土記にも引用されている）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(This is cited in &quot;Kaisei Mikawago Fudoki&quot; as well.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(This is also cited in &quot;Kaisei Mikawago Fudoki.&quot;)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(This is also cited in Kaisei Mikawago Fudoki.)</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>宝飯郡伊奈本多正忠が、七代清康の時に、吉田城ならびに田原を攻める際に味方した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Kiyoyasu&apos;s day, the seventh head of the Matsudaira clan, Tadamasa HONDA in Ina, Hoi District supported Kiyoyasu when he attacked Yoshida Castle and Tahara.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Kiyoyasu&apos;s day, the seventh head of the Matsudaira clan, Tadamasa HONDA in Ina, Hoi District, supported Kiyoyasu when he attacked Yoshida Castle and Tahara.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Kiyoyasu&apos;s day, the seventh head of the Matsudaira clan, Tadamasa HONDA in Ina, Hoi County, supported Kiyoyasu when he attacked Yoshida-jo Castle and Tahara.</e>
<cmt>Hoi District→Hoi Countyに修正、Yoshida-jo Castleとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>清康の凱旋を伊奈に迎えて、饗応し、三つ葉の葵に肴を盛りて、出したるに、清康喜び、汝このたび、我に味方し、合戦勝利を得たり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Tadamasa welcomed Kiyoyasu&apos;s triumphal return to Ina, entertained him with food and drink, and served him a side dish on three hollyhock leaves, Kiyoyasu was pleased and said, &quot;Thanks to your support, I gained victory in this battle.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Tadamasa welcomed Kiyoyasu&apos;s triumphal return to Ina, entertained him with food and drink, and served him a side dish on three hollyhock leaves, Kiyoyasu was pleased and said, &quot;Thanks to your support, I achieved victory in this battle.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Tadamasa welcomed Kiyoyasu&apos;s triumphal return to Ina, entertained him with food and drink, and served him a side dish on three hollyhock leaves, Kiyoyasu was pleased and said, &quot;Thanks to your support, I achieved victory in this battle.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>三つ葵は汝の家紋と聞くが、このたびの吉例により、我に与えよ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;I knew that the Mitsu-aoi is your family crest, but according to the festive custom, present it to me.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;I knew that the Mitsu-aoi is your family crest, but according to the festive custom, present it to me.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;I knew that the Mitsu-aoi is your family crest, but according to the festive custom, present it to me.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>されば岡崎随念寺に伝わる清康画像の紋は、三つ葵なりと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For that reason, the crest on the portrait of Kiyosasu in the Okazaki Zuinen-ji Temple is the Mitsu-aoi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For that reason, the crest on the portrait of Kiyosasu in the Okazaki Zuinen-ji Temple is the Mitsu-aoi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For that reason, the crest on the portrait of Kiyosasu in the Okazaki Zuinen-ji Temple is the Mitsu-aoi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="39">
<j>また、葵の紋は、もと新田氏の紋をそのまま使用したともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is another story that the aoi-mon was the former crest of the Nitta clan and used without change.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is another story that the aoi-mon was the former crest of the Nitta clan and was used without change.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is another story that the aoi-mon was the former crest of the Nitta clan and was used without change.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>諸説区々たり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are various views on its origin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are various views regarding its origin.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are various views regarding its origin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="41">
<j>岡崎市史による葵紋諸説の解説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Okazaki City History explains the origin of the aoi-mon as follows:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Okazaki City History explains the origin of the aoi-mon as follows:</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Okazaki City History explains the origin of the aoi-mon as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>元来、松平太郎左衛門家の紋なりともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The aoi-mon was originally the family crest of Taro Saemon MATSUDAIRA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The aoi-mon was originally the family crest of Taro Saemon MATSUDAIRA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The aoi-mon was originally the family crest of Tarozaemon MATSUDAIRA.</e>
<cmt>Taro Saemon→Tarozaemonに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>あるいは、松平親氏、泰親、が松平村に入りし後、賀茂明神に祈願し家紋とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Or, after Yasuchika and Chikauji MATSUDAIRA entered Matsudaira Village, they worshiped at the Kamo-myojin Shrine to pray and then started to use the aoi-mon as his family crest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Or, after Yasuchika and Chikauji MATSUDAIRA entered Matsudaira Village they worshiped at Kamo-myojin Shrine to pray and then started to use the aoi-mon as his family crest.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Or, after Yasuchika and Chikauji MATSUDAIRA entered Matsudaira Village they worshiped at Kamo-myojin Shrine to pray and then started to use the aoi-mon as his family crest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>あるいは、松平氏が、賀茂源氏また賀茂朝臣と称して葵を家紋とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also said that the Matsudaira clan used it, calling themselves Kamo-Genji (Minamoto clan) or KAMO no Asomi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also said that the Matsudaira clan used it, calling themselves Kamo-Genji (Minamoto clan) or KAMO no Asomi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also said that the Matsudaira clan used it, calling themselves Kamo-Genji (Minamoto clan) or KAMO no Asomi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="45">
<j>※三河国賀茂郡松平郷のある賀茂郡は、賀茂神社の神郡（神領地）とされ、賀茂神社の神紋である葵紋を松平郷松平家がもともと家紋としていたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">* Kamo District where Matsudaira-go, Kamo District in Mikawa Province was located was Shingun (shrine territory) for the Kamo-jinja Shrine, and the Matsudaira clan in Matsudaira-go originally used the aoi-mon, the Kamo-jinja Shrine crest as its family crest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">* The Kamo District, where Matsudaira-go, Kamo District in Mikawa Province, was located, was Shingun (shrine territory) for Kamo-jinja Shrine, and the Matsudaira clan in Matsudaira-go originally used the aoi-mon, the Kamo-jinja Shrine crest, as its own family crest.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">* The Kamo County, where Matsudaira-go, Kamo County in Mikawa Province, was located, was Shingun (shrine territory) for Kamo-jinja Shrine, and the Matsudaira clan in Matsudaira-go originally used the aoi-mon, the Kamo-jinja Shrine crest, as its own family crest.</e>
<cmt>Kamo District→Kamo Countyに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>三河国の山間部の奥三河地域には、賀茂郡賀茂郷、宝飯郡賀茂郷、設楽郡賀茂郷など賀茂の付く地名が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The mountainous Oku-mikawa area in Mikawa Province has many names of places with &quot;Kamo&quot; such as Kamo-go in Kamo District, Kamo-go in Hoi District, and Kamo-go in Shitara District.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The mountainous Oku-mikawa area in Mikawa Province has many place names with &quot;Kamo,&quot; such as Kamo-go in Kamo District, Kamo-go in Hoi District and Kamo-go in Shitara District.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The mountainous Oku-mikawa area in Mikawa Province has many place names with &quot;Kamo,&quot; such as Kamo-go in Kamo County, Kamo-go in Hoi County and Kamo-go in Shitara County.</e>
<cmt>Kamo County、Hoi County、Shitara Countyとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>そのため、松平氏、酒井氏、本多氏など、三河の土豪は葵紋を家紋とする家が多かったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For that reasons, many local clans in Mikawa such as the Matsudaira clan, the Sakai clan and the Honda clan used the aoi-mon as their family crest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For that reason, many local clans in Mikawa, such as the Matsudaira clan, the Sakai clan and the Honda clan, used the aoi-mon as their family crests.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For that reason, many local clans in Mikawa, such as the Matsudaira clan, the Sakai clan and the Honda clan, used the aoi-mon as their family crests.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="48">
<j>『日本家紋総覧』にある由来の諸説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Various views on the origin described in Nihon Kamon Soran (Complete Guide to Family Crests in Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Various views on the origin are described in Nihon Kamon Soran (Complete Guide to Family Crests in Japan).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Various views on the origin are described in &quot;Nihon Kamon Soran&quot; (Complete Guide to Family Crests in Japan).</e>
<cmt>&quot;Nihon Kamon Soran&quot;としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>以下は、日本家紋総覧にある三つ葉葵に関する由来と見られている説の一部である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The followings are a part of views on the possible origin of the aoi-mon in &quot;Nihon Kamon Soran&quot;:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following are among the views on the possible origin of the aoi-mon in &quot;Nihon Kamon Soran&quot;:</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following are among the views on the possible origin of the aoi-mon in Nihon Kamon Soran:</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせクォーテーション削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="50">
<j>酒井氏由来説。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was originated from the Sakai clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It originated with the Sakai clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It originated with the Sakai clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="51">
<j>本多氏と交換したという説。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was exchanged with the Honda clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was exchanged with the Honda clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was exchanged with the Honda clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="52">
<j>家康が自ら考案したという説。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was invented by Ieyasu himself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was invented by Ieyasu himself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was invented by Ieyasu himself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="53">
<j>松平氏を継ぎ、その家紋を踏襲したという説。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The crest of the Matsudaira clan was taken over after succession to the clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The crest of the Matsudaira clan was taken over after succession to the clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The crest of the Matsudaira clan was taken over after succession to the clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>三つ葉葵の変種</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Variations of Mitsuba-aoi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Variations of Mitsuba-aoi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Variations of Mitsuba-aoi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="54">
<j>会津葵</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Aizu-aoi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Aizu-aoi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Aizu-aoi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>会津葵（あいづあおい）・会津三つ葉葵（あいづみつばあおい）は、三つ葉葵の変種の一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Aizu-aoi or Aizu Mitsuba-aoi (trefoil hollyhock of Aizu) is one variation of the Mitsuba-aoi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Aizu-aoi or Aizu Mitsuba-aoi (trefoil hollyhock of Aizu) is one variation of the Mitsuba-aoi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Aizu-aoi or Aizu Mitsuba-aoi (trefoil hollyhock of Aizu) is one variation of the Mitsuba-aoi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>会津松平家の家紋である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is the crest of the Aizu-Matsudaira family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It&apos;s the crest of the Aizu-Matsudaira family.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is the crest of the Aizu-Matsudaira family.</e>
<cmt>It&apos;s→It isとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="57">
<j>徳川家の三つ葉葵の紋とほぼ同じ図案であるが三枚の葉はオリジナルの葵（フタバアオイ）の葉の図案ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In terms of the design, the Aizu-aoi is nearly the same as the Mitsuba-aoi of the Tokugawa family, but its three leaves are not futaba-aoi leaves (mallow leaves) used in the original.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In terms of the design, the Aizu-aoi is nearly the same as the Mitsuba-aoi of the Tokugawa family, but its three leaves aren&apos;t the futaba-aoi leaves (mallow leaves) used in the original.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In terms of the design, the Aizu-aoi is nearly the same as the Mitsuba-aoi of the Tokugawa family, but its three leaves are not the futaba-aoi leaves (mallow leaves) used in the original.</e>
<cmt>aren&apos;t→are notとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>よく似た図案である河骨（コウホネ）の葉に見えることから、会津葵は厳密には葵紋ではなく河骨紋であるとの見方もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since these leaves look like nuphar leaves similar to the futaba-aoi leaves, some scholars view the Aizu-aoi exactly as Kohone-mon (nuphar patterns), not the aoi-mon.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because these leaves look like nuphar leaves and are similar to the futaba-aoi leaves, some scholars view the Aizu-aoi precisely as Kohone-mon (nuphar patterns) instead of the aoi-mon.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because these leaves look like nuphar leaves and are similar to the futaba-aoi leaves, some scholars view the Aizu-aoi precisely as Kohone-mon (nuphar patterns) instead of the aoi-mon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 目白梅(id:141468), Aityanlove(id:203908), 与左衛門(id:159462), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), 水野白楓(id:22811), KurmUmy(id:202680), Hihi9999(id:185887), Maxima m(id:28947), Nalc(id:139567), ５１６(id:45205), Enter456(id:247777), Nakaoka7675(id:39645), ムカイ(id:72972), 松平定治(id:146386), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>