<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>虎拳</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toraken-play</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toraken Game</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toraken Game</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>虎拳（とらけん）は、襖をしめて、左右の部屋で、虎・女物・鉄砲のいずれかを身につけて待ち、襖を開くと、虎女（和藤内（＝鄭成功）の母）鉄砲（和藤内あるいは加藤清正）虎という三すくみで勝負がつく拳遊び。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toraken is a game in three Japanese rooms divided by shut Fusuma (Japanese sliding door) where people choose to wear or hand a tiger costume, women&apos;s clothes (implies Torajo, literally, a tiger woman, the mother of Watonai, another name of Seiko TEI (Zheng Chenggong)) or musket (implies Watonai or Kiyomasa KATO) which were in three-way standoff, and then open the fusuma and run off to decide who wins.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toraken is a game played in three Japanese rooms divided by closed Fusuma (Japanese sliding door) where people choose to wear or hand a tiger costume, women&apos;s clothes (impling Torajo, literally, a tiger woman, the mother of Watonai, another name of Seiko TEI - Zheng Chenggong or musket - impling Watonai or Kiyomasa KATO) the fusuma is opened and they run off to decide who wins.</e>
<cmt>grammar, wordy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toraken is a game played in three Japanese rooms divided by closed Fusuma (Japanese sliding door) where people choose to wear or hand a tiger costume, women&apos;s clothes (implying Torajo, literally, a tiger woman, the mother of Watonai, another name of Seiko TEI - Zheng Chenggong or musket - implying Watonai or Kiyomasa KATO) and wait until the fusuma is opened, and they run off to decide who wins.</e>
<cmt>襖が開くまで待ち、としました。/impling→implying</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>囃子歌から「とらとら」とも呼ばれる</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called as &apos;Tra-tra&apos; due to its words of burden sung while playing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called as &apos;Tra-tra&apos; due to the words of burden sung while playing.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called as &apos;Tora-tora&apos; due to the words of burden sung while playing.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>遊び方</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">How to Play</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">How to Play</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">How to Play</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>屏風仕立てのフリがつくお座敷遊びとしての拳遊びの中の最大規模のもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is the largest-scaled &apos;Ken Asobi (fist games)&apos; among &apos;Ozashiki-Asobi (playing games with Geisha)&apos; that uses folding screen and choreography.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is the largest-scaled &apos;Ken Asobi (fist games)&apos; among &apos;Ozashiki-Asobi (games with Geisha)&apos; that uses a folding screen and choreography.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is the largest-scaled &apos;Ken Asobi (fist games)&apos; among &apos;Ozashiki-Asobi (games with Geisha)&apos; that uses a folding screen and choreography.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>襖で仕切られた部屋3室と、虎の毛皮、女物の衣裳、鉄砲のセットが2つ必要。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Three rooms divided by fusuma, and two sets of tiger fur, female costume and musket are required to play.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Three rooms are divided by fusuma, and two sets of tiger fur, female costumes and musket are required to play.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Three rooms divided by fusuma, two sets of tiger fur, female costumes and musket are required to play.</e>
<cmt>are を削除。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>花街では部屋に屏風を立て、「虎」を四つん這い、「母」を杖を突くジェスチャー、「武将」を拳を腰に当てることで表現して遊ぶタイプのものが現在の主流である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today, instead of the above, in &apos;Hanamachi&apos; (or Kagai, geisha districts in Kyoto), they mainly use folding screen, gestures of crawling on their hands and knees to express a &quot;tiger&quot;, using a stick to express a &quot;mother&quot; and placing fists on they waist to express a &quot;Busho (an old Japanese military commander.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, instead of the above, in &apos;Hanamachi&apos; (or Kagai, geisha districts in Kyoto), they mainly use folding screen, gestures of crawling on their hands and knees to express a &quot;tiger,&quot; using a stick to express a &quot;mother&quot; and placing fists on their waist to express a &quot;Busho&quot; (an old Japanese military commander.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, instead of the above, in &apos;Hanamachi&apos; (or Kagai, geisha districts in Kyoto), they mainly use folding screen, gestures of crawling on their hands and knees to express a &quot;tiger,&quot; using a stick to express a &quot;mother&quot; and placing fists on their waist to express a &quot;Busho&quot; (an old Japanese military commander.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>この場合だと、屏風から出てきたときに相手が予想もつかない格好をしているところに面白さがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this curtailed case, it is fun to see the opponent comes out of folding screen in unexpected figure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this version, it is fun to see the opponent coming out of the folding screen as unexpected figure.</e>
<cmt>grammar, wordy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this version, it is fun to see the opponent coming out of the folding screen as unexpected figure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>（可愛らしい舞妓が虎を演じたり、恰幅のいい紳士が老女のようによろよろと歩いて見せたりする）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(It is fun that a lovely maiko plays a tiger or a man of stout build walks totteringly and plays an old woman.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(It is fun to see a lovely maiko playing a tiger or a man of stout build walking totteringly, playing an old woman.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(It is fun to see a lovely maiko playing a tiger or a man of stout build walking totteringly, playing an old woman.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>虎が老母を破り、和藤内がその虎を破って、老母は自分の息子の和藤内に勝つという三すくみ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a three-way standoff that a tiger beats an old mother, Watonai beats the tiger and the old mother beats her son Watonai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a three-way standoff where a tiger beats an old mother, Watonai beats the tiger and the old mother beats her son Watonai.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a three-way standoff where a tiger beats an old mother, Watonai beats the tiger and the old mother beats her son Watonai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>台湾の英雄・鄭成功をモデルにした近松の傑作『国姓爺合戦』のブームから採ったもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This play was derived from the boom of the masterpiece, &quot;Kokusen-ya Kassen (The Battles of Koxinga)&quot; of CHIKAMATSU which modeled the hero of Taiwan, Seiko TEI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This game was derived from the boom of the masterpiece, &quot;Kokusen-ya Kassen&quot; (The Battles of Koxinga) of CHIKAMATSU which was modeled after the hero of Taiwan, Seiko TEI.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This game was derived from the boom of the masterpiece, &quot;Kokusen-ya Kassen&quot; (The Battles of Koxinga) of CHIKAMATSU which was modeled after the hero of Taiwan, Seiko TEI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>「千里が竹の場」が原型。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its original form was &quot;Senrigatake no ba (scene of Senrigatake.)&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its original form was &quot;Senrigatake no ba&quot; (scene of Senrigatake.)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its original form was &quot;Senrigatake no ba&quot; (scene of Senrigatake.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="11">
<j>祇園では、虎退治の話なので和藤内が加藤清正に変わっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At &quot;Gion&quot;, as it is based on the story of tiger extermination, Watonai was changed to Kiyomasa KATO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At &quot;Gion,&quot; since it is based on the story of tiger extermination, Watonai was changed to Kiyomasa KATO.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At &quot;Gion,&quot; since it is based on the story of tiger extermination, Watonai was changed to Kiyomasa KATO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 BitBucket(id:30999), 桜井悠士(id:72420), 諾爾布(id:181602), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>