<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>かぶき者</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kabuki-mono</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kabuki-mono</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kabuki-mono</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>かぶき者（かぶきもの。傾奇者・歌舞伎者とも表記。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kabuki-mono (かぶき者) is also written as 傾奇者 or 歌舞伎者.</e>
<cmt>()内で分割されていたのでそれらを合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kabuki-mono (かぶき者) is also written as &quot;傾奇者&quot; or &quot;歌舞伎者.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Punctuationを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kabuki-mono (かぶき者) is also written as &quot;傾奇者&quot; or &quot;歌舞伎者.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>かぶき者は、戦国時代 (日本)末期から江戸時代初期にかけての社会風潮。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kabuki-mono was a social trend observed from the end of the Japanese Warring States period to the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kabuki-mono were the people who came out of the social trend between the end of the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States) and the early Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>I&apos;d like to say &quot;kabuki-mono&quot; are people, but I&apos;m not sure this sentence is OK or not.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kabuki-mono is the name given to people who gave rise to a particular social trend between the end of the Sengoku period (Period of Warring States) and the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt>一部変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>特に慶長から寛永年間（1596～1643）にかけて、江戸や京都などの都市部で流行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kabuki-mono was particularly in fashion from the Keicho to Kanei eras (1596-1643) in urban areas such as Edo and Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their style was particularly in fashion from the Keicho era to the Kanei era (1596-1643) in urban areas including Edo and Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Their style was particularly in fashion from the Keicho era to the Kanei era (1596-1643) in urban areas including Edo and Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>異風を好み、派手な身なりをして、常識を逸脱した行動に走る者たちのこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kabuki-mono were people who liked unusual things, dressed loudly and behaved outlandishly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They liked unusual things, dressed loudly, and behaved outlandishly.</e>
<cmt>書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They liked unusual things, dressed loudly, and behaved outlandishly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>茶道や和歌などを好む者を数寄者と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">People who enjoy the art of the tea ceremony, or waka (Japanese poetry), are referred to as suki-sha (refined people yet tinged with eccentricity).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">People who enjoy the art of the tea ceremony, or waka (Japanese poetry), are referred to as &quot;suki-sha&quot; (refined people yet tinged with eccentricity).</e>
<cmt>suki-shaを&quot;&quot;で囲みました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">People who enjoy the art of the tea ceremony, or waka (Japanese poetry), are referred to as &quot;suki-sha&quot; (refined people yet tinged with eccentricity).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>数寄者よりさらに数寄に傾いた者と言う意味である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kabuki-mono will be more inclined to suki state than suki-sha.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kabuki-mono means the people who are more eccentric than suki-sha.</e>
<cmt>&quot;suki state&quot;が分かりにくいかもしれないと感じたので訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kabuki-mono means the people who are more eccentric than suki-sha.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>当時男性の着物は浅黄や紺など非常に地味な色合いが普通だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the time, kimono for men were normally in very quiet colors, such as pale yellow or navy blue.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the time, kimono for men were normally in very quiet colors, such as pale yellow or navy blue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the time, kimono for men were normally in very quiet colors, such as pale yellow or navy blue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>しかしかぶき者は色鮮やかな女物の着物をマントのように羽織ったり、袴に動物皮をつぎはうなど常識を無視して非常に派手な服装を好んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However kabuki-mono used very bold outfits to challenge the prevailing social trends, including colorful kimonos for females casually thrown on like a cape, or a hakama (a kind of trousers, worn on a kimono) patched with animal skins.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, kabuki-mono, ignoring prevailing social trends, preferred very bold outfits, such as colorful kimonos for females worn like a cape, or a hakama (a kind of trousers, worn on a kimono) patched with animal skins.</e>
<cmt>punctuationを訂正しました。「無視して」を&quot;ignore&quot;「好んだ」を&quot;prefer&quot;にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, kabuki-mono, ignoring prevailing social trends, preferred very bold outfits, such as colorful kimonos for females worn like a cape, or a hakama (a kind of trousers, worn on a kimono) patched with animal skins.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>他にも天鵞絨(ビロード)の襟や立髪や大髭、大額、鬢きり、茶筅髪、大きな刀や脇差、朱鞘、大鍔、大煙管などの異形・異様な風体が「かぶきたるさま」として流行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally the &quot;kabuki-ing look&quot; became fashionable, consisting of unusual and bizarre items and styles such as velvet collars, tategami hairdos (long hair with the center part left unshaved), big beards, obitai hairdos (widely shaved forehead with a little hair left on the temples), binkiri hairdos (hairdo with a lock of hair running down from the temples), chasen hairdos (a hairdo modeled after a tea whisk), large swords, and oversized short swords, red colored sheaths, big sword guards, and big pipes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, unusual and bizarre items and styles were in fashion called &quot;Kabuki-taru-sama&quot;(an eccentric look) such as velvet collars, tategami hairdos (long hair with the center part left unshaved), big beards, obitai hairdos (widely shaved forehead with a little hair left on the temples), binkiri hairdos (hairdo with a lock of hair running down from the temples), chasen hairdos (a hairdo modeled after a tea whisk), large swords, and oversized short swords, red colored sheaths, big sword guards, and big pipes.</e>
<cmt>punctuationを訂正しました。「異形・異様な風体」という部分を主語にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, unusual and bizarre items and styles were in fashion called &quot;Kabuki-taru-sama&quot;(an eccentric look) such as velvet collars, tategami hairdos (long hair with the center part left unshaved), big beards, obitai hairdos (widely shaved forehead with a little hair left on the temples), binkiri hairdos (hairdo with a lock of hair running down from the temples), chasen hairdos (a hairdo modeled after a tea whisk), large swords, and oversized short swords, red colored sheaths, big sword guards, and big pipes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>彼らの行動及び趣味志向は一種の前衛芸術とも言える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Their behavior, preferences and tastes can be seen as a kind of avant-garde art.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their behavior, preferences, and tastes can be seen as a kind of avant-garde art.</e>
<cmt>punctuationを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Their behavior, preferences, and tastes can be seen as a kind of avant-garde art.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>多くは徒党を組んで行動し、飲食代を踏み倒したり因縁をふっかけて金品を奪うなどの乱暴・狼藉をしばしば働いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kabuki-mono often ganged up to refuse to pay their bill after eating and drinking, or to rob money or valuables by picking fights with people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kabuki-mono often ganged up to bilk or to rob money and valuables of people by picking fights.</e>
<cmt>「飲食代を踏み倒す」という言葉を&quot;bilk&quot;としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kabuki-mono often ganged up to bilk or to rob money and valuables of people by picking fights.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>自分の武勇を公言することも多く、それが元で喧嘩や刃傷沙汰になることもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also they often boasted about their bravery, and this could be a source for a fight or some bloodshed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, they often boasted about their bravery, and this sometimes caused fights or bloodshed.</e>
<cmt>punctuationを訂正し、&quot;a source for&quot;を&quot;cause&quot;にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, they often boasted about their bravery, and this sometimes caused fights or bloodshed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>辻斬り、辻相撲、辻踊りなど往来での無法・逸脱行為も好んで行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They enjoyed engaging in acts of hooliganism or deviant behavior on the streets, such as indiscriminately slashing at people, or staging on-the-spot sumo wrestling matches or dance sessions.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides, they enjoyed outrageous and deviant behavior on the streets, such as killing a passerby in order to test a new sword, sumo wrestling, and dancing.</e>
<cmt>I&apos;m not sure if &quot;they enjoyed…behavior&quot;is correct.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They also found pleasure in engaging in outrageous and deviant behavior on the streets, such as the killing of a passerby in order to test a new sword, sumo wrestling, and dancing.</e>
<cmt>they enjoyed outrageous and deviant behavior →they found pleasure in engaging in outrageous and deviant behavior</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>衆道や喫煙の風俗とも密接に関わっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were closely connected to the customs of homosexuality and smoking.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They also were closely connected to the customs of homosexuality and smoking.</e>
<cmt>&quot;also&quot;を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They also were closely connected to the customs of homosexuality and smoking.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>かぶき者のこうした身なりや行動は、世間の常識や権力・秩序への反発・反骨の精神の表れと見てよいだろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These kabuki-mono outfits and behavior can be seen as a physical manifestation of a spirit of repulsion and revolt against the prevailing social norms, authorities, or public order generally in society.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their outfits and behavior can be seen as an expression of their spirit of repulsion and revolt against the prevailing social norm, authorities, and public order generally in society.</e>
<cmt>&quot;physical maniｆestation&quot;という言葉はかなり専門的な用語であると判断し、&quot;expression&quot;に置き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Their outfits and behavior can be seen as an expression of their spirit of repulsion and revolt against the prevailing social norm, authorities, and public order generally in society.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>彼らはまた、仲間同士の結束と信義を重んじ、命を惜しまない気概と生き方の美学を持っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally they valued the trust and camaraderie that developed among them, and had their own set of beliefs which they prized even more than their own lives.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, they valued the trust and camaraderie that developed among them, and had their own set of beliefs which they prized even more than their own lives.</e>
<cmt>transition, punctuationを訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, they valued the trust and camaraderie that developed among them, and had their own set of beliefs which they prized even more than their own lives.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>1612年(慶長17年)に捕縛・斬首されたかぶき者の巨魁大鳥居いつ兵衛（大鳥一兵衛、同逸兵衛、逸平などとも書く）は、厳しい拷問を受けながらも仲間の名は最後まで吐かず、代わりに全国の大名の名を書き出してみせたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ichibei OTORI (大鳥居いつ兵衛, also written as 大鳥一兵衛, 大鳥逸兵衛 or 大鳥逸平), the leader of kabuki-mono, was captured and beheaded in 1612. It is said that even though he was brutally tortured he never divulged the names of his group members, instead writing down the names of national feudal lords.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, it is said that the leader of Kabuki-mono, Ichibei OTORI (大鳥居いつ兵衛: His name is also spelled &quot;大鳥一兵衛,&quot; &quot;大鳥逸兵衛&quot;and &quot;大鳥逸平&quot;), who was captured and beheaded in 1612, refused to divulge the names of the members of his group to the end, instead writing down the names of national feudal lords, even though he was brutally tortured.</e>
<cmt>この列と後列の文章は、前列の例であると解釈し、&quot;For example&quot;をつけました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, it is said that the leader of Kabuki-mono, Ichibei OTORI (大鳥居いつ兵衛: His name is also spelled &quot;大鳥一兵衛,&quot; &quot;大鳥逸兵衛&quot;and &quot;大鳥逸平&quot;), who was captured and beheaded in 1612, refused to divulge the names of the members of his group to the end, instead writing down the names of national feudal lords, even though he was brutally tortured.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>彼はまた、刀のなかごに「廿五まで　生き過ぎたりや　一兵衛」と死を恐れぬ心意気を刻んでいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He showed his spirit, fearless of death, in the phrase &apos;I have lived too long to be twenty five - Ichibei&apos; which was inscribed on the part of the sword which is buried in the hilt.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also inscribed the phrase &apos;I have lived too long to be twenty five - Ichibei&apos; on the part of the sword which is buried in the hilt to show his fearless of death.</e>
<cmt>書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also inscribed the phrase &apos;I have lived too long to be twenty five - Ichibei&apos; on the part of the sword which is buried in the hilt to show his fearless of death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="19">
<j>かぶき者になるのは、若党、中間、小者といった武家奉公人が多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">People who became kabuki-mono were mainly servants to samurai families, such as wakato (footman), chugen (rank below common soldier), or komono (lower servant).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">People who became kabuki-mono were mainly servants to samurai families, such as wakato (footman), chugen (rank below common soldier), or komono (lower servant).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">People who became kabuki-mono were mainly servants to samurai families, such as wakato (footman), chugen (rank below common soldier), or komono (lower servant).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>彼らは武士身分ではなく、武家に雇われて、槍持ち、草履取りなどの雑用をこなす者たちである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Their class was not samurai but they were hired by a samurai family and performed odd jobs such as carrying their master&apos;s lance or taking care of his shoes.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were not samurais but servants of the samurais, performing odd jobs such as carrying their masters&apos; lances, and taking care of their masters&apos; shoes.</e>
<cmt>notの後の部分ととbutの後の部分を同じ形式にするため、訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were not samurais but servants of the samurais, performing odd jobs such as carrying their masters&apos; lances, and taking care of their masters&apos; shoes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>その生活は貧しく不安定だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Their life was poor and unstable.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their life was poor and unstable.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Their life was poor and unstable.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>彼らの多くは合戦の際には足軽や人足として働きつつ、機をみて略奪行為に励み、自由で暴力的な生活を謳歌していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many of them worked as an ashigaru (common foot soldier) or a ninsoku (laborer) in times of war, actively engaging in predatory practices, seizing whatever chances they could and enjoying their lives of freedom and violence.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many of them enjoyed their life of freedom and violence, working as an ashigaru (common foot soldier) or a ninsoku (laborer) in times of war, and robbing people of their money and valuables whenever they had opportunities to do so.</e>
<cmt>「自由で暴力的な生活を謳歌していた」という文を中心に組み立てました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many of them enjoyed their life of freedom and violence, working as an ashigaru (common foot soldier) or a ninsoku (laborer) in times of war, and robbing people of their money and valuables whenever they had opportunities to do so.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>しかし、戦乱の時代が終わるとともにその居場所を狭められていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However as the time of wars came to an end, the number of kabuki-mono began to decline.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as the time of wars came to an end, they began to lose their jobs.</e>
<cmt>「居場所を狭められていった」という原文を「仕事が減った」という意味に解釈しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as the time of wars came to an end, they began to lose their jobs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>そうした時代の移り変わりがもたらす閉塞感が、彼らを反社会的で刹那的な生き方に駆り立てたという側面もあると思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From one perspective, the sense of stagnation which the changes of the times brought encouraged them to live in such an antisocial way, living only for the moment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It can be said that their feelings of entrapment due to the change of circumstances surrounding them drove them to live in such an antisocial and ephemeral way.</e>
<cmt>書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that it was the feeling of despair created by the change of circumstances experienced during this period that drove the Kubuki-mono to live in such an antisocial and ephemeral way.</e>
<cmt>一部変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="25">
<j>かぶき者たちは、一方で乱暴・狼藉を働く無法者として嫌われつつ、一方ではその男伊達な生き方が共感と賞賛を得てもいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On one hand, kabuki-mono were hated as they were seen as violent outlaws committing assaults, yet on the other hand people praised and sympathized with their masculine and gallant lifestyle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On one hand, Kabuki-mono were hated as violent outlaws committing assaults, but on the other hand, they were praised and sympathized with their lifestyle as chivalrous men.</e>
<cmt>punctuationを追加し、&quot;yet&quot;を&quot;but&quot;にしました。「男伊達」http://en.bab.la/dictionary/english-japanese/chivalrous-man</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On one hand, Kabuki-mono were hated as violent outlaws committing assaults, but on the other hand, they were praised and sympathized with their lifestyle as chivalrous men.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>武家奉公人だけでなく、町人や、れっきとした武士である旗本や御家人がかぶき者になることもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sometimes not only servants to a samurai family but also merchants and craftsmen, and bakufu hatamoto (direct retainers of a feudal government headed by a shogun) and gokenin (an immediate vassal of the shogunate), who are in the proper samurai class, become kabuki-mono.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sometimes not only servants of samurai families but also merchants, craftsmen, hatamoto(direct retainers of a feudal government headed by a shogun), and gokenin (an immediate vassal of the shogunate), who are in the proper samurai class, became Kabuki-mono.</e>
<cmt>&quot;a samurai family&quot;を&quot;samurai families&quot;にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sometimes not only servants of samurai families but also merchants, craftsmen, hatamoto(direct retainers of a feudal government headed by a shogun), and gokenin (an immediate vassal of the shogunate), who are in the proper samurai class, became Kabuki-mono.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>寛永期頃から江戸に現れる旗本奴・町奴といった無頼集団も、かぶき者の一類型と見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Groups of ruffians called hatamoto-yakko and machi-yakko appeared in the city of Edo from around the Kanei era. These groups can be seen as variants of kabuki-mono.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Groups of ruffians called hatamoto-yakko and machi-yakko, appearing in the city of Edo from around the Kanei era, were supposedly types of Kabuki-mono.</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Groups of ruffians called hatamoto-yakko and machi-yakko, appearing in the city of Edo from around the Kanei era, were supposedly types of Kabuki-mono.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>また、1603年（慶長8年）に出雲阿国(いづものおくに)がかぶき者の風俗を取り入れたかぶき踊りを創める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, in 1603, IZUMO no Okuni created a kabuki dance which introduced kabuki-mono manners and customs.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, in 1603, IZUMO no Okuni created a kabuki dance which introduced kabuki-mono manners and customs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, in 1603, IZUMO no Okuni created a kabuki dance which introduced kabuki-mono manners and customs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>するとたちまち全国的な流行となり、のちの歌舞伎の原型となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It quickly became fashionable nationwide and turned into an archetype of the later kabuki performance.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It quickly became fashionable nationwide and turned into an archetype of the later kabuki performance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It quickly became fashionable nationwide and turned into an archetype of the later kabuki performance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="30">
<j>かぶき者の文化は慶長期にその最盛期をみるも、同時にその頃から幕府や諸藩の取り締まりが厳しくなっていき、やがて姿を消していく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The kabuki-mono culture was at its peak in the Keicho era, however at the same time the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government in the Edo period headed by a shogun), and each domain under the bakufu, strengthened their crackdowns, so that kabuki-mono finally disappeared.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the kabuki-mono culture was at its peak in the Keicho era, the Edo bakufu and each domain strengthened their crackdowns at the same time, and then Kabuki-mono finally disappeared.</e>
<cmt>文中の&quot;however&quot;を&quot;although&quot;にし、文頭に持ってきました。&quot;bakufu&quot;の説明は既出なのでカットしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the kabuki-mono culture was at its peak in the Keicho era, the Edo bakufu and each domain strengthened their crackdowns at the same time, and then Kabuki-mono finally disappeared.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>しかし、その行動様式は侠客と呼ばれた無頼漢たちに、その美意識は歌舞伎という芸能の中に受け継がれていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However delinquents, known as &quot;kyokaku&quot;, inherited their form of behavior, while their aesthetic values were inherited by the performing art of kabuki.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, their form of behavior was inherited by delinquents called &quot;kyokaku,&quot; while their aesthetic values were inherited by the Kabuki performance.</e>
<cmt>&quot;while&quot;の前後の文が同じ形になるように訂正しました。Punctuationを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, their form of behavior was inherited by delinquents called &quot;kyokaku,&quot; while their aesthetic values were inherited by the Kabuki performance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 でここ(id:9565), 隠者(id:23290), Izayohi(id:13095), Alecs.bot(id:194707), 田無稲子(id:63575), PaPaPaPa(id:87231), べっ甘七みつ･たけタカひろ(id:99878), 水野白楓(id:22811), Law soma(id:45202), Nighthawks(id:36125), 日本一弱い男(id:92046), 婆娑羅(id:44173), A.0024(id:143537), KASAGI(id:24405), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>