<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>筆</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fude (ink brush)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fude (ink brush)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fude (ink brush)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>筆（ふで）とは、軸（竹筒などの細い棒）の先端に毛（繊維の束）を付けた道具であり、筆記具・画材などに使われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term &quot;fude&quot; refers to a tool made out of a stem (thin stick such as bamboo cylinder) with a brush (a bundle of fiber) on the top, which is used for writing and painting.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term &quot;fude&quot; refers to a tool made out of a stem (thin stick such as bamboo cylinder) with a brush (a bundle of fiber) on the top, which is used for writing and painting.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term &quot;fude&quot; refers to a tool made out of a stem (thin stick such as bamboo tube) with a brush (a bundle of fiber) on the top, which is used for writing and painting.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>「毛」には通常は文字どおり毛 (動物)（まれに化学繊維）が使われ、毛筆（もうひつ）という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Like the character &quot;毛,&quot; which refers to the hairs of an animal and is used in the word for &apos;brush,&apos; a coat (animal) (in rare cases, chemical fibers) is usually used.; and the letters for fude are called Mohitsu (literally, a brush made of coat).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Like the character &quot;毛,&quot; which refers to the hairs of an animal and is used in the word for &apos;brush,&apos; a coat (animal) (in rare cases, chemical fibers) is usually used.; and the letters for fude are called Mohitsu (literally, a brush made of coat).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the character &quot;毛&quot; literally means the hairs of an animal and is used in the word for &apos;brush,&apos; a coat (animal) (in rare cases, chemical fibers) is usually used.; and the letters for fude are called Mohitsu (literally, a brush made of coat).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>材料の毛は、剛毛（ウマやイタチ、タヌキ）、柔毛（羊や猫、リス）の毛などが用いられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bristles (of horse, Japanese mink and raccoon dog) and soft hairs (of sheep, cat and squirrel) are used as a material of fude.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bristles (of horse, Japanese mink and raccoon dog) and soft hairs (of sheep, cat and squirrel) are used to make fude.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bristles (of horse, Japanese mink and raccoon dog) and soft hair (of sheep, cat and squirrel) are used to make fude.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>また、「特殊筆」として、鶏や孔雀、マングースやムササビの毛、また、獣毛以外にも藁や竹を使用した筆も生産されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, chicken and peacock feathers, as well as mongoose and flying squirrel coats are used for &apos;special&apos; fude, straw and bamboo are materials which are used that are not animal in nature.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, chicken and peacock feathers, as well as mongoose and flying squirrel coats are used for &apos;special&apos; fude, straw and bamboo are materials which are used that are not animal in nature.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, chicken and peacock feathers, as well as mongoose and flying squirrel coats, and, as the materials that are not animal in nature, straw and bamboo are used for &apos;special&apos; fude.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>生産地は、いずれもそうした動物がまだ生息している地方が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most areas which produce fude are those which have animals which are used in the production of fude.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most areas which produce fude are those which have animals which are used in the production of fude.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most areas that produce fude are those which have animals which are used in the production of fude.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>最近は、胎毛筆と言って赤ちゃんの成長を願って、赤ちゃんの髪の毛でも記念に筆を作ることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Recently, &quot;taimo fude&quot; (ink brush made of newborn baby&apos;s hair) is sometimes made in order to wish newborn baby&apos;s growth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Recently, &quot;taimo fude&quot; (ink brush made of newborn baby&apos;s hair) is sometimes made in order to wish luck towards a newborn baby&apos;s growth.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Recently, &quot;taimo fude&quot; (ink brush made of newborn baby&apos;s hair) is sometimes made in order to wish the healthy growth of the newborn baby.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>剛毛の弾力と柔毛の墨含み、双方の利点を併せ持つ二種の毛を配合したものを「兼毫」と言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fude which combines both merits of the elasticity of bristles and containing much Chinese ink of soft hairs is called &apos;kengo.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A fude which combines both merits of elasticity of bristles while containing soft hairs is called &apos;kengo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A fude that offers the merits of both bristle elasticity and ink absorption in its soft hairs is called a &apos;kengo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>筒の部分を持ち、毛の部分に墨や顔料をつけ、書く対象にその毛をなすり付けることにより、文字を書いたり、絵を描いたり、化粧を行ったりできる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Holding the stem, putting Chinese ink or pigment on the brush and rubbing its brush against what is written on make it possible to write a letter, draw a picture, or make up.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The brush is used to write letters, draw pictures or apply makeup; one holds the stem, dipping the brush into Chinese ink or pigments, and brushes the head against the item the ink is to be applied to.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The brush is used to write letters, draw pictures or apply makeup; one holds the stem, dipping the brush into Chinese ink or pigments, and rub the brush against the item the ink is to be applied to.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>日本で現存している最古の筆は「天平筆（雀頭筆）」であるとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The existing oldest fude in Japan is regarded as &apos;tenpyohitsu (jakutohitsu).&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The oldest existing fude in Japan is regarded as &apos;tenpyohitsu (jakutohitsu).&apos;</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tenpyohitsu&apos; (jakutohitsu) is regarded as the oldest existing fude in Japan.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>正倉院に残されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It remains in Shosoin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It remains in Shosoin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is kept in Shosoin.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>書の筆</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Fude for writing</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fude for writing</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fude for writing</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>通常、大筆（太筆）は穂を全ておろす（ノリを落とす）が（根元に短い毛を意図的に残し、筆の弾力を高めているものに関しては根元を固めたままにすることが多い）、小筆（細筆）は穂先だけをおろすのが良い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Usually, while all part of a big brush (thick brush) is used (dissolving all glue) (in the case of the fude with remaining short coat intentionally on the root in order to strengthen the elasticity, the root of the most of the fude often remains firmed), only the top of a small brush (thin brush) is good to be used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Usually, while all parts of a big brush (thick brush) are used (involves dissolving the glue) (in the case of fude which have a coat of short hairs remaining at its root in order to strengthen its elasticity, the root is left intentionally firm), only the top of a small brush (thin brush) is good to be used.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Usually, while all of a big brush (thick brush) are used (dissolving and removing all glue) (in the case of the fude with short coat intentionally left on the root in order to strengthen the elasticity, glue is often left at the root of the fude), only the top of a small brush (thin brush) is good to be used.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>ただし、仮名用の筆に於いて、やや大きめの面相筆は根本までおろすことが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in the case of a little big menso fude among the fude for kana (the Japanese syllabary), all part of the brush is often used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, among the fude used for kana (the Japanese syllabary), all parts of the brush are often used in the case of a slightly larger menso fude.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, among the fude used for kana (the Japanese syllabary), all of the brush are often used in the case of a slightly larger menso fude.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>小筆の穂先は特に繊細なため、陸（墨を磨る部分）で穂先をまとめるために強くこすりつけることは極力避ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the top of a small brush is especially delicate, it is better to avoid to rub it against riku (a part of ink slab to grind solid Chinese ink) in order to set the top as much as possible.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the top of a small brush is especially delicate, it is better to avoid brushing it against the riku (a part of the ink slab used to grind solid Chinese ink) in order to set the top as much as possible.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the top of a small brush is especially delicate, it is better to avoid brushing it against the riku (a part of the ink slab used to grind an ink stick) in order to set the top as much as possible.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>墨などで固まった穂先を陸にこすりつけて、柔らかくしようとすることは絶対にしてはならない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It must not be done to rub the firmed top by Chinese ink against riku in order to make it softer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chinese ink should not be rubbed against the riku in order to make the hardened top softer.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The top of the brush that has been firmed by Chinese ink should not be rubbed against riku in order to make the hardened top softer.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>硯は固形墨を磨（す）るためのヤスリであり、墨液が潤滑の働きをするとは言え、そのヤスリにこすりつけることは穂先を硯で磨ることと同じであり、穂先をひどく傷めてしまうからである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is because an ink slab is a file to grind solid Chinese ink so that the rubbing a brush top against the file is as same as the grinding it on an ink slab, which hurts it hardly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is because an ink slab is a file used to grind solid Chinese ink, therefore rubbing a brush top against the file is the same as grinding it on an ink slab, which can severely damage it.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is because an ink slab is a file used to grind an ink stick, therefore rubbing a brush top against the file is the same as grinding it on an ink slab, which can severely damage it.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>大筆も硯の陸の部分で墨を調節したりするのは穂を傷めるので、大作を作る時などは、プラスチックや陶器などで作られた、ヤスリの要素だけを取り除いた「墨池（ぼくち）」というものを使うことが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the top of a big brush can also be damaged by placing it on the riku in order to adjust the amount of Chinese ink, a &apos;bokuchi,&apos; an ink slab which removes the file and is made of plastic or earthware, is often used for big pieces.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the top of a big brush can also be damaged by placing it on the riku in order to adjust the amount of Chinese ink, a &apos;bokuchi,&apos; an ink slab which removes the file and is made of plastic or earthware, is often used for big pieces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the top of a big brush can also be damaged by placing it on the riku in order to adjust the amount of Chinese ink, a &apos;bokuchi,&apos; an ink slab without the file that is made of plastic or earthenware, is often used for big pieces.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>仕組み</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Structure</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Structure</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Structure</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="17">
<j>毛はウロコ状の表皮に包まれた物体である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The coat is wrapped up by scalelike skin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The coat is wrapped with scalelike skin.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The coat is wrapped in scalelike skin.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>ウロコ状の部分をcuticle（キューティクル：表皮構成物質）と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The part of scalelike skin is called cuticle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The part of the scalelike skin is called the cuticle.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The scalelike skin part is called the cuticle.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>人毛の場合、このキューティクルの隙間は0.1ミクロンであり、水などがこの隙間から進入すると毛全体が膨らみ反る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The gap between human&apos;s cuticles is 0.1micrometer and the whole human&apos;s hair swell and roll if water enters into this gap.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The gap between a human&apos;s cuticles is 0.1micrometers and a whole human&apos;s hair will swell and roll if water enters this gap.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The gap between human&apos;s cuticles is 0.1 micrometers and a whole human&apos;s hair will swell and roll if water enters this gap.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>そのため、作られてすぐの筆は膨らんだり毛が反るので、毛や筆の性能を活かしきることができない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this reason, the brush of a new fude swells and rolls and it is impossible to take advantage of the performance of brush or fude.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this reason, the brush of a new fude swells and rolls and it is impossible to take advantage of the performance of a brush or fude.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For this reason, the brush of a newly made fude swells and rolls and it is impossible to take advantage of the performance of a brush or fude.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>ススは、元素的にはカーボン（炭素）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The element of soot is carbon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soot is in essence, a form of carbon.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soot is in essence, a form of carbon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>このスス成分が筆のキューティクルの隙間に沈着すると、水分が入れない状態になり、膨らんだり反ったりしなくなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If this element is deposited between the cuticles of fude, the brush of fude does not swell or roll because the carbon blocks water.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If this element is deposited between the cuticles of the fude, the brush of the fude will not swell or roll because the carbon blocks the water.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When this element is deposited between the cuticles of the fude, the brush of the fude will not swell or roll because the carbon blocks the water.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>また筆のコシが出て、墨の含みも良くなり、最も良い状態で筆の性能を活かすことができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, it also makes the brush more elastic and better to contain Chinese ink, and makes it possible to take advantage of the performance of brush in the best condition.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, it also makes the brush more elastic and better suited to contain Chinese ink, making it possible to maximize the brush&apos;s performance.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, it also makes the brush more elastic and better suited to load Chinese ink, making it possible to maximize the brush&apos;s performance.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>羊毛の筆は最初、透通るような白い色をしているが、使い込むに従って銀色に、さらに長年を経ると黄金色に輝き、使用者自身の書きぶりが毛の癖となって表れ、その人の体の一部の如く使いこなしやすくなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fude made of sheep wool has a translucent white color at first, but changes to silver and gold through a long use and shows the habit of user&apos;s handwriting, which makes it easier for a user to write.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fude made of sheep wool has a translucent white color at first, but changes to silver and gold through long usage, evolving to the user&apos;s handwriting habits, making it easier for a user to write with.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fude made of sheep wool has a translucent white color at first, but changes to silver and gold through long usage, evolving from the user&apos;s handwriting habits, making it easier for a user to write with.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>しかしその状態になるには、墨液よりも、摩った固形墨の方が良いと言える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it can be said that a ground solid Chinese ink is better than liquid Chinese ink in order to reach such a condition.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it can be said that solid ground Chinese ink is better than liquid Chinese ink in reaching this condition.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it can be said that ground Chinese ink stick is better than liquid Chinese ink in reaching this state.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="26">
<j>製造の途中で不揃いな毛などをすいており、書字中に抜けてくるのは抜き出し損ねた残りであって少量であれば問題ない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Irregular coats are removed in the process of production, and those which fall out during writing those which could not be removed, and do not cause a problem if there are only a small number of such hairs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Irregular coats are removed in the process of production, and those which fall out during writing those which could not be removed, and do not cause a problem if there are only a small number of such hairs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Irregular coats are removed in the process of production, and those which fall out during writing are those which could not be removed, and do not cause a problem if such hairs are only a small number.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>切れや抜けが多いと毛が減り、筆が割れを起こしたり、毛先が効かなくなって使えなくなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If many coats are cut or removed, the amount of coats decrease, which leads to a split of brush or invalidity of the top.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If many hairs are cut or removed, the amount of hairs decrease, which leads to a split brush or a brush tip which does not work as well.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If many hairs are cut or fallen, the amount of hairs decrease, which leads to a split brush or a brush tip which does not work as well.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>毛とニカワの関係について</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The relationship between fude and glue</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The relationship between fude and glue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The relationship between fude and glue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="28">
<j>前項のように、筆は使うほどに本来の筆の持つ能力が引き出されてくるが、それには墨の選び方や洗い方も大事になってくる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As mentioned above, the performance of fude becomes better in accordance with the more use, for which how to select and wash fude are important.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As mentioned above, the performance of fude becomes better the more it is used, of which it is important to know how the fude is selected and washed.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As mentioned above, a fude works better the more it is used, and to this end it is important to know in how the fude is selected and washed.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="29">
<j>墨の成分は、主にススと膠（ニカワ：コラーゲン・ゼラチン成分）から作られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ingredients of Chinese ink are mainly soot and glue (made of collagen and gelatin).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ingredients of Chinese ink are mainly soot and glue (made of collagen and gelatin).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ingredients of a Chinese ink stick are mainly soot and glue (made of collagen and gelatin).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>品質の劣悪なものは、ニカワに安価な海外の魚のコラーゲンを使うなどするため、ニカワの成分が毛に対してストレスを与え、キューティクルを傷める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the collagen of cheap overseas&apos; fish is used as the glue for the fude of inferior quality, the ingredient of the glue gives stress against the coat and hurts cuticle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the collagen of cheap overseas&apos; fish is used in glue for fude of inferior quality, the ingredients of the glue place stress on the hairs and hurt the cuticles.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the collagen of cheap overseas fish is used in glue for fude of inferior quality, the ingredients of the glue place stress on the hairs and hurt the cuticles.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>人によってはリンスやコンディショナーなどを塗布してキューティクルを守ろうとすることがあるが、前述の通り筆の毛はキューティクルの隙間にススを入れることが大事である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some people try to protect cuticle by coating rinse or conditioner on it, but as mentioned above, it is important for the coat of fude to put soot between cuticles.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some people try to protect the cuticle by coating hair conditioner on it, but as mentioned above, it is important for the coat of fude to put soot between cuticles.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some people try to protect the cuticles by coating the brush with rinse or conditioner, but as mentioned above, it is important for the fude hairs to have soot between cuticles.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>リンスやコンディショナーなどは隙間に入り込んでススを入れなくしてしまうので、筆の毛にコシを与えず逆に寿命を縮めることになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, since rinse and conditioner enter the gap and block the entering of soot, they make the life of fude shorter instead of giving an elasticity on the contrary.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, since hair conditioner enters the gap and block the entering of soot, they make the life of the fude shorter instead of giving it elasticity.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, since rinse and conditioner enter the gap and prevent soot from entering, they shorten the lifespan of the fude, and do not give it elasticity.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>洗うことについて</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">About washing</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">About washing</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Washing a fude</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="33">
<j>穂先に墨が残らないようによく水洗いする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wash fude well in order that Chinese ink remains in the top of the brush.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wash fude well in order to ensure that no Chinese ink remains in the top of the brush.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fude must be washed well in order to ensure that the Chinese ink does not remain at the top of the brush.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>ただし、作られてすぐの筆を水に長時間浸しておくと、毛に水が入り込み膨らんでキューティクルの隙間が大きく開き、毛が切れやすくなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, if a new fude is put in the water for a long time, the water enters the gap of cuticles and makes it open wide, which makes the brush easier to be cut.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, if a new fude is put in water for a long time, the water can enter the gap of cuticles and make it open wide, which makes the brush hairs easier to fall out.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, if a new fude is put in water for a long time, the water enters the gap between the cuticles and open it wide, making the brush hairs easier to cut.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>同じ理由で、筆の穂先を固めるためのノリ成分を、水に長時間さらして落とすのは適当でない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For the same reason, it is not good to remove the glue for firming the brush top of fude by putting it in the water for a long time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For the same reason, it is inadvisable to remove the glue used to firm the brush tip by placing it in the water for a long time.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For the same reason, it is improper to remove the glue used to firm the brush tip by placing it in the water for a long time.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="36">
<j>小筆を洗う場合は、筆の穂先を擦り切らせないよう気をつける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order to wash a small fude, it is necessary for the brush top not to wear.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to wash a small fude, it is necessary for the brush tip not to wear.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flowRobert: This does not makes sense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to wash a small fude, it is necessary for the brush tip not to wear out.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="37">
<j>筆の根元については、よくすすぎ、根元にニカワ分が残らないようにする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is necessary for the root of fude to be washed well in order not to remain the ingredient of glue.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is necessary for the root of the fude to be washed well in order ensure that glue does not remain within.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is necessary for the root of the fude to be washed well in order to ensure that glue does not remain within.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>ニカワ分が溜まると、膨張するなどして筆管が割れるので注意が必要である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since if an ingredient of glue remains, the stem of fude is broken by swelling or something, it is necessary to pay an attention.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It should be noted that if glue remains, the stem of the fude can swell causing the brush handle to break.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It should be noted that if glue remains, the stem of the fude could swell, causing the brush handle to break.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>ニカワは、ぬるめの湯に一番溶けやすいので、湯で洗うのが毛に最も良い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the glue can be dissolved best in the lukewarm water, it is best to wash the brush in it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The brush should be washed in lukewarm water, as glue dissolves best in it.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The brush should be washed in lukewarm water, as the glue dissolves best in it.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="40">
<j>毛の根元の墨を口で吸ったりして吸い出すことがよく行われているが、品質の良い固形墨・墨液では構わないが、品質について信用できない墨汁などを口に入れることは体に悪い可能性があるので注意する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some people often suck out Chinese ink at the root of the brush, but it needs to pay an attention because it may be bad for health to take a liquid ink of bad quality except a solid Chinese ink and a liquid ink of good quality.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some people often suck out Chinese ink at the root of the brush, but caution must be exercised since ink of low quality may adversely affect ones health, unless ink of high quality is used.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some people often suck the Chinese ink out from the root of the brush, but caution must be exercised since ink of low quality may adversely affect ones health; this does not apply if ink of high quality is used.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>前述のように海外の魚や動物の骨や皮から抽出したコラーゲンを使ったり、化学的に合成した接着剤成分などをニカワの代わりに用い、腐らせないように防腐剤が入り、工業製の香料を使っている可能性が高いため、口に入れることは不衛生であり健康被害・アレルギーなどに注意する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since some Chinese ink are highly possible to include collagen derived from the bones and skins of overseas&apos; fish and animal, use a chemical ingredient of bond instead of glue, add an antiseptic and use an industrial fragrance, it is unsanitary to put them in mouth, and it needs to pay an attention to a damage of health and allergy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since some Chinese ink use collagen derived from the bones and skins of overseas&apos; fish and animals, chemical ingredients are used as a bonding agent instead of glue, with a preservative added as well as an industrial grade fragrance, it is unsanitary to place a brush in one&apos;s mouth, and can cause health and allergy problems.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since it is highly possible that collagen derived from the bones and skins of overseas fish and animals are used as mentioned above, or that chemical ingredients may be used as a bonding agent instead of glue with an added preservative, not to mention industrial grade fragrance, it is unsanitary and can cause health and allergy problems to place a brush in one&apos;s mouth.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>また磨った墨などを作り置きして使う場合は防腐剤が入っていないため大変腐りやすいので口に入れないこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, Chinese ink which is kept long after ground goes bad very quickly because an antiseptic is not added, so that you should not put it in your mouth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, Chinese ink which is kept long after being ground can go bad very quickly due to the lack of preservatives, and should not be placed in one&apos;s mouth.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, Chinese ink which is kept long after being ground can go bad very quickly due to the lack of preservatives; therefore, it should not be placed in one&apos;s mouth, either.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="43">
<j>スス成分が溜まると筆は逆に長持ちするので、ニカワの成分だけをよく落とすのが大事である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fude which keeps soot can last long in contrast, so that it is important to wash only the ingredient of glue.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In contrast, a fude accumulates soot can last long, so it is important to only wash out the glue.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In contrast, a fude that have soot accumulated much can last long, so it is important to wash out only the glue.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="44">
<j>黒い墨の色が薄く沈着するのは筆の性能が引き出されていることを示していると言って良いので、洗いすぎて筆を傷めないよう注意する必要がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since it can be said that the deposition of the light color of black Chinese ink shows the good performance of the fude very well, it needs to pay an attention not to wash too much and hurt fude.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since it can be said that deposits of a light color of black Chinese ink are an indication of a fude&apos;s performance, attention must be given not to wash it too much, which could damage the fude.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since it can be said that deposits of a light color of black Chinese ink indicates that the performance of the fude is taken advantage of, attention must be given not to wash it too much, which could damage the fude.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>産地</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Production areas</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Production areas</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Production areas</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="45">
<j>筆の産地としては、広島県の熊野町（熊野筆）、呉市（川尻筆）、奈良県（奈良筆）、愛知県の豊橋市（豊橋筆）、宮城県の仙台市（仙台御筆）、東京都などが有名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The major famous production areas of Fude are Kumano-cho, Hiroshima Prefecture (Kumano fude), Kure City (Kawajiri fude), Nara Prefecture (Nara fude), Toyohashi City, Aichi Prefecture (Toyohashi fude), Sendai City, Miyagi Prefecture (Sendai ofude) and Tokyo Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The major famous production areas for Fude are Kumano-cho, Hiroshima Prefecture (Kumano fude), Kure City (Kawajiri fude), Nara Prefecture (Nara fude), Toyohashi City, Aichi Prefecture (Toyohashi fude), Sendai City, Miyagi Prefecture (Sendai ofude) and Tokyo Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The areas most famous for the production of Fude are Kumano-cho, Hiroshima Prefecture (Kumano fude), Kure City (Kawajiri fude), Nara Prefecture (Nara fude), Toyohashi City, Aichi Prefecture (Toyohashi fude), Sendai City, Miyagi Prefecture (Sendai ofude) and Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>Tokyo Prefecture のPrefectureは削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>いずれも職人仕事なので、特定の町内に職人の職住一致の仕事場が点在している、のが実態。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Any of them are made by craftsmen in the workplace combined with a dwelling place in specific area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">All of these are made by craftsmen in an area that combines a workplace along with living area</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As brushes are made by craftsmen, their workplaces combined with their home are scattered throughout each of these areas.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="47">
<j>特に伝統工芸品として経済産業省に認定されているのは、以下の通りである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fude made in the following cities are of special note and are certified as traditional crafts by the Ministry of Economy, Trade and Industry.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fude made in the following cities are of special note and are certified as traditional crafts by the Ministry of Economy, Trade and Industry.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fude made in the following cities are specifically certified as traditional crafts by the Ministry of Economy, Trade and Industry.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="48">
<j>豊橋筆 愛知県豊橋市</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toyohashi fude: Toyohashi City, Aichi Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toyohashi fude: Toyohashi City, Aichi Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toyohashi fude: Toyohashi City, Aichi Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="49">
<j>奈良筆 奈良県奈良市、大和郡山市</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nara fude: Nara City and Yamatokoriyama City, Nara Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nara fude: Nara City and Yamatokoriyama City, Nara Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nara fude: Nara City and Yamatokoriyama City, Nara Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="50">
<j>熊野筆 広島県熊野町</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kumano fude: Kumano-cho, Hiroshima Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kumano fude: Kumano-cho, Hiroshima Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kumano fude: Kumano-cho, Hiroshima Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="51">
<j>川尻筆 広島県呉市川尻町（旧豊田郡川尻町）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kawajiri fude: Kawajiri-cho, Kure City, Hiroshima Prefecture (former Kawajiri-cho, Toyota County)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kawajiri fude: Kawajiri-cho, Kure City, Hiroshima Prefecture (former Kawajiri-cho, Toyota County)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kawajiri fude: Kawajiri-cho, Kure City, Hiroshima Prefecture (former Kawajiri-cho, Toyota-gun)</e>
<cmt>Toyota-gun としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="52">
<j>中華人民共和国においては、浙江省呉興県善璉鎮の「湖筆」が最も名高い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the People&apos;s Republic of China, fude known as the &apos;Kohitsu&apos; of Zenrenchin, Goko Prefecture, Sekko Province are the most famous.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the People&apos;s Republic of China, fude known as the &apos;Kohitsu&apos; of Zenrenchin, Goko Prefecture, Sekko Province are the most famous.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the People&apos;s Republic of China, the &apos;Kohitsu&apos; (湖筆) in Zenrenchin, Wuxing Prefecture, Zhejiang Province is the most famous fude.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 JAnDbot(id:66507), K-king(id:72808), Hhaithait(id:37092), Sina(id:10021), Koba-chan(id:860), Taisyo(id:6896), Gsklee(id:13733), Viola(id:98352), Trilingual(id:48344), Mishika(id:276), YukkeBot(id:251107), Kaznov17(id:68122), Miyabi(id:967), Yamajy(id:14927), Redhair(id:208382), Mymelo(id:122034), Kouchiumi(id:19253), Miya(id:1881), Chobot(id:20846), Point136(id:211299), 岡部碩道(id:182846), ますめ(id:113105), Linker(id:77957), Cobe355(id:224040), Peek-poke(id:68004), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>