<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>石州流伊佐派</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Isa-ha group of the Sekishu school</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Isa-ha group of the Sekishu-ryu school (a group of Sekishu-ryu school of Japanese tea ceremony)</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Isa-ha group of the Sekishu-ryu school (a group of Sekishu-ryu school of Japanese tea ceremony)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>石州流伊佐派（せきしゅうりゅう いさは）は武家茶道。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Isa-ha group of the Sekishu school performs the buke-sado (the art of the tea ceremony of samurai families).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Isa-ha group of the Sekishu-ryu school is the buke-sado (the art of the tea ceremony of samurai families).</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Isa-ha group of the Sekishu-ryu school is the buke-sado (the art of the tea ceremony of samurai families).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>石州流の一派。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are a branch of the Sekishu school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are a branch of the Sekishu-ryu school.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are a branch of the Sekishu-ryu school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>江戸時代は幕府数奇屋頭を代々世襲し石州流嘉順派、石州流野村派とともに柳営茶道をささえた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Edo period, they had handed down a position at the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) called Sukiya-gashira (a person who is responsible for the tea room and equipment for the shogun) for generations, and they supported the Ryuei-chado (the tea ceremony for the Shogunate) in cooperation with the Kajun-ha group of the Sekishu school and the Nomura-ha group of the Sekishu school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Edo period, they had handed down a position at the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) called Sukiya-kumigashira (a person who is responsible for the tea room and equipment for the shogun) for generations, and they supported the Ryuei-chado (the tea ceremony for the Shogunate) in cooperation with the Kajun-ha group of the Sekishu-ryu school and the Nomura-ha group of the Sekishu-ryu school.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Edo period, they had handed down a position at the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) called Sukiya-kumigashira (a person who is responsible for the tea room and equipment for the shogun) for generations, and they supported the Ryuei-chado (the tea ceremony for the Shogunate) in cooperation with the Kajun-ha group of the Sekishu-ryu school and the Nomura-ha group of the Sekishu-ryu school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>維新後伊佐家が5代限りで茶道と無縁になった際に、門人だった袖山宗脩（1853年 - 1932年）によって継承され伊佐派と称している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Meiji Restoration, the Isa family retired from the tea ceremony after the fifth generation headman, but Munenaga SODEYAMA (袖山宗脩) (1853 - 1932), who was a follower of the then headman, restored the family&apos;s tea ceremony, and his group has called themselves Isa-ha since then.</e>
<cmt>「袖山宗脩」の正式な読み方が不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Meiji Restoration, the Isa family retired from the tea ceremony after the fifth generation headman, but Munenaga SODEYAMA (袖山宗脩, 1853 - 1932), who was a disciple of the school, restored the family&apos;s tea ceremony, and his group has called themselves Isa-ha group since then.</e>
<cmt>用語などを変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Meiji Restoration, the Isa family retired from the tea ceremony after the fifth generation headman, but Munenaga SODEYAMA (袖山宗脩, 1853 - 1932), who was a disciple of the school, restored the family&apos;s tea ceremony, and his group has called themselves Isa-ha group since then.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Mymelo(id:122034), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>