<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>火縄銃</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hinawaju (matchlock gun)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hinawaju (matchlock gun)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hinawaju (matchlock gun)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>火縄銃（ひなわじゅう、英語：matchlock gun）は、初期の鉄砲の形態のひとつ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hinawaju (Engllish : matchlock gun) is one form of guns in an early time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hinawaju (Engllish: matchlock gun) is one form of gun in early times.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hinawaju (English: matchlock gun) is one form of gun in early times.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>先込め式で、黒色火薬を使用する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a muzzle-loader and uses black gunpowder.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a muzzle-loader and uses black gunpowder.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a muzzle-loader and uses black gunpowder.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>火縄銃は、15世紀末にヨーロッパで発明されたと考えられ、マッチロック式銃とも言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is thought to have been invented in Europe in the end of fifteenth century and is also called a matchlock.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is thought to have been invented in Europe at the end of the fifteenth century and is also called a matchlock.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is thought to have been invented in Europe at the end of the 15th century and is also called a matchlock.</e>
<cmt>アラビア数字に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>引き金を引くと火をつけた火縄が火皿と呼ばれる部品に落ちる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If you pull a trigger, the fired match drops in the part which is called a pan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If you pull a trigger, the fired match drops into the part called the pan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If you pull a trigger, the fired match drops into the part called the pan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>火はそこから口薬（くちぐすり）と呼ばれる微粉末黒色火薬に引火し（胴薬）（どうぐすり）または玉薬（たまぐすり）と呼ばれる装薬に伝わり、そこで一気に燃焼（爆燃）、弾丸を射出する仕組みになっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fire ignites finely-powdered black gunpowder which is called kuchigusuri (gunpowder), moves to the explosive charge called dogusuri (loaded gunpowder) or tamagusuri (loaded gunpowder) and burns up at a burst (deflagration) and the bullet shoots out as a system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fire ignites fine black gunpowder which is called kuchigusuri (gunpowder), moves to the explosive charge called dogusuri (loaded gunpowder) or tamagusuri (loaded gunpowder) and burns up in a burst (deflagration) and the pressure in the barrel propels the bullet.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fire ignites fine black gunpowder which is called kuchigusuri (gunpowder), moves to the explosive charge called dogusuri (loaded gunpowder) or tamagusuri (loaded gunpowder) and burns up in a burst (deflagration) and the pressure in the barrel propels the bullet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>方式としては瞬発式火縄銃と緩発式火縄銃とがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the types, there are an instantaneous discharge matchlock and a gradual discharge matchlock.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for types, there are an instantaneous discharge matchlocks and a gradual discharge matchlocks.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for types, there are an instantaneous discharge matchlocks and a gradual discharge matchlocks.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>銃刀法の規制対象となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are subject to control of the Sword and Firearms Control Law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are subject to the Sword and Firearms Control Law.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are subject to the Sword and Firearms Control Law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>それ以前の銃器は、火種（火縄など）を手で押し付ける方式（タッチホール式）であった（宋 (王朝)の「突火槍」、明の「火竜槍」、1300年頃のロシアの「マドファ」など）ことから、扱いが難しく命中精度も低かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the firearms before that was a type where live coals (match and so on) are pushed down (a touch-hole type) (&quot;flame-spurting lance&quot; (a bamboo gun) in the Sung dynasty, &quot;a fire lance&quot; (a gunpowder weapon) in the Ming dynasty, &quot;madfa&quot; in Russia around 1300 and so on), it was difficult to handle and the accuracy of fire was low.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As previous firearms were types where live coals (matches and so on) were pushed down (a touch-hole type) (&quot;flame-spurting lance&quot; - a bamboo gun) in the Sung dynasty, &quot;a fire lance&quot; (a gunpowder weapon) in the Ming dynasty, &quot;madfa&quot; in Russia around 1300 and so on), it was difficult to handle and the firing accuracy was low.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Previous firearms were types where live coals (matches and so on) were pushed down by hands (a touch-hole type) (&apos;flame-spurting lance&apos; - a bamboo gun in the Sung dynasty, &apos;a fire lance&apos; [a gunpowder weapon] in the Ming dynasty, &apos;madfa&apos; in Russia around 1300 and so on) which was difficult to handle, and the firing accuracy was low.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　に変更しました。翻訳を一部変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>この欠点を補うため、火縄をS字型金具（サーペンタイン）ではさんで操作するサーペンタインロック式が考案され、さらに銃床など構造面の整備が進み、火縄銃が完成した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order to make up for the shortcoming, a serpentine-lock system was contrived, where a match was sandwiched between serpentines and was operated, and furthermore the adjustments of structural aspects such as a gunstock and so on advanced and a hinawaju was completed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to make up for the shortcomings, a serpentine-lock system was contrived, where a match was sandwiched between serpentines and was cocked and set off with a trigger, and changes in structural aspects such as the gunstock and so on advanced and the hinawaju was completed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to make up for the shortcomings, a serpentine-lock system was contrived, where a match was sandwiched between serpentines and was cocked and set off with a trigger, and changes in structural aspects such as the gunstock and so on advanced and the hinawaju was completed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>日本には1543年に種子島に鉄砲伝来したことから、種子島銃あるいは単に種子島と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan it was introduced in Tanegashima Island in 1543 and thus it was called a Tanegashima rifle or simply Tanegashima (as we see later, however, strictly speaking, all hinawaju were not called &quot;Tanegashima&quot; and the ones which were relatively thick and short were called that way).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan it was introduced at Tanegashima Island in 1543 and thus it was called a Tanegashima rifle or simply Tanegashima (as we&apos;ll see later, however, strictly speaking, all hinawaju were not called &quot;Tanegashima,&quot; but those that were relatively thick and short were called that way).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan it was introduced at Tanega-shima Island in 1543 and thus it was called a Tanegashima rifle or simply Tanegashima.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　に変更しました。一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>（後述、但し厳密にはすべての火縄銃を「種子島」と云わず、比較的に太く短いものをさすことが多い）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(As we&apos;ll see later, however, strictly speaking, all hinawaju were not called &apos;Tanegashima,&apos; but those that were relatively thick and short were called that way.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>マッチロック式は命中精度と射程距離の向上など銃の性能を大きく向上させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a matchlock system, the performance such as an accuracy of fire, a shooting distance and so on advanced largely.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In a matchlock mechanism, performance such as accuracy of fire, shooting distance, and so on advanced greatly.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In a matchlock mechanism, performance such as accuracy of fire, shooting distance, and so on advanced greatly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>その一方で、火種・火縄を常に持ち歩く携帯性の悪さや失火の危険、夜戦で敵にこちらの位置を教えることになる、雨天に極端に弱い等、改善すべき弱点はまだ数多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, there were many weak points to be improved, such as a bad portability where live coals and matches must be always carried, a danger of an accidental fire, an extreme vulnerability to rainy weather and so on, and at night battle the enemy could see the position of the shooter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, there were many weak points to be improved, such as poor portability where live coals and matches must be always carried, danger of an accidental fire, extreme vulnerability to rainy weather and so on, and in night battles the enemy could easily see the position of the shooter.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, there were many weak points to be improved, such as poor portability where live coals and matches must be always carried, danger of an accidental fire, extreme vulnerability to rainy weather and so on, and in night battles the enemy could easily see the position of the shooter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>これらを克服するため、ヨーロッパでは回転する鋼輪（ホイール）に黄鉄鉱片を擦り付けて着火する方式（ホイールロック式）や、燧石（火打ち石：フリント）を鉄片にぶつけて着火する方式（フリントロック式）が発明された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To make up for these, in Europe the system where a piece of pyrite was rubbed on a rotating steel circle (wheel) to ignite (wheel lock system) or the system where a firestone (flint) was hit on a piece of iron to ignite (flint gun(flintlock) system) were invented.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To make up for these, in Europe a mechanism where a piece of pyrite was struck on a rotating steel circlular (wheel) to ignite the gunpowder (wheel lock mechanism) or where a firestone (flint) was struck on a piece of iron to ignite the powder (flint gun - flintlock system) were invented.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To make up for these, in Europe a mechanism where a piece of pyrite was struck on a rotating steel circular (wheel) to ignite the gunpowder (wheel lock mechanism) or where a firestone (flint) was struck on a piece of iron to ignite the powder (flint gun - flintlock system) were invented.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>博物館の中の火縄銃と、現代のライフル銃などを比較すると、グリップ付近の形状が大きく異なる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Comparing a hinawaju in the museum with a rifle and so on in present-day, we can see a big difference between the forms near the grips.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Comparing a hinawaju in the museum with a present day rifle, we can see a big difference between the form near the grip.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Comparing a hinawaju in the museum with a present day rifle, we can see a big difference between the form near the grip.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>これは、火縄銃は火薬の大きな反動を受け止める必要がなかったクロスボウの影響を受け、その弓部分を取り払った形態にデザインされていた為と言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is said to be because a hinawaju was influenced by a crossbow which was not necessary to accept a big reaction from gunpowder and was designed into the form where the bow part was removed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is said to be because a hinawaju was influenced by the crossbow where it was not necessary to absorb a large recoil from the gunpowder exploding and it was designed into the form where the bow part was removed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is said to be because a hinawaju was influenced by the crossbow where it was not necessary to absorb a large recoil from the gunpowder exploding and it was designed into the form where the bow part was removed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>そのため、現代のいわゆるライフル銃のように台尻を肩に当てて、脇を締めて発射することはできず、弓を番えるように肘を外に張って射撃するスタイルで使用されていた（但しヨーロッパの火縄銃は肩当ストック型のものの方が多く短床型の方が少数派）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of this, the shooter cannot shoot putting the butt on the shoulder and closing the armpits like a present-day rifle and thus a matchlock gun was used in the style where the shooter shot with an elbow squared like putting an arrow on a bow (however, many of matchlock guns in Europe were the shoulder gun type and the short type was in the minority).</e>
<cmt>「短床型」をthe short typeとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of this, the shooter could not shoot with the butt against his shoulder and close his armpits like with present-day rifles and thus the matchlock gun was used in the style where the shooter shot with an elbow squared like when setting an arrow on a bow (however, many matchlock guns in Europe were the shoulder type and the short type was in the minority).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of this, the shooter could not shoot with the butt against his shoulder and close his armpits like with present-day rifles and thus the matchlock gun was used in the style where the shooter shot with an elbow squared like when setting an arrow on a bow (however, many matchlock guns in Europe were the shoulder type and the short type was in the minority).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="18">
<j>なお、日本における火縄銃が頬付け形に終始し、肩付け形の銃床にならなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Matchlock guns in Japan stuck to the cheek gun type and did not change to the gunstock of shoulder gun type.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Matchlock guns in Japan were aimed with the cheek on the gun stock type and did not change to the gunstock of shoulder gun stock type.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The gunstock of the matchlock guns in Japan remained as the cheek gun stock type and did not change to those of shoulder gun stock type.</e>
<cmt>肩付け形にならず、頬付け形に終始したのは「銃床」であると解釈し、主語をthe gunstock としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>その理由として、戦国期においては鎧武者による射撃に適さないことや鉄砲狭間からの射掛けにおいて邪魔であるという用兵上の事情、泰平期においては流儀による形態・射法の継承による硬直化等が指摘されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the reasons, it is pointed out that it was not appropriate for armored warriors to shoot during the Sengoku period (period of warring states), that it was cumbersome to shoot from gun crenels in tactics, and that during peaceful periods the form and style of shooting were inherited through the tradition and were rigidified.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for the reason, it is pointed out that it was not appropriate for armored warriors to shoot during the Sengoku period (period of warring states), that it was cumbersome to shoot from gun crenels in tactics, and during peaceful periods the form and style of shooting was inherited through tradition and were rigidified.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for the reason, it is pointed out that it was not appropriate for armored warriors to shoot during the Sengoku period (period of warring states), that it was cumbersome to shoot from gun crenels in tactics, and during peaceful periods the form and style of shooting was inherited through tradition and were rigidified.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>日本での火縄銃史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The history of matchlock guns in Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The history of matchlock guns in Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The history of matchlock guns in Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="20">
<j>従来、『鉄炮記』の記述により日本への鉄砲伝来は1543年の種子島より始まるとされてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Traditionally, according to the descriptions of &quot;Teppoki&quot; (a history book on the introduction of guns), the introduction of a gun to Japan has been considered to have begun on Tanegashima Island in 1543.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Traditionally, according to the descriptions of &quot;Teppoki&quot; (a history book on the introduction of guns), the introduction of a gun to Japan began on Tanegashima Island in 1543.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Traditionally, according to the descriptions of &quot;Teppoki&quot; (a history book on the introduction of guns), the introduction of a gun to Japan began on Tanega-shima Island in 1543.</e>
<cmt>Tanega-shima Island としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="21">
<j>しかし、近年では、東南アジアに広まっていた火器が1543年前後に倭寇勢力により日本の複数の地域に持ち込まれ、伝来当初は猟銃として用いられていたとする説も提示されている（宇田川武久説）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Recently, however, there is one theory which claims that the firearms spread across Southeast Asia were introduced in several regions in Japan by wako (Japanese pirates) around 1543 and in those days they were used as hunting guns (The theory by Takehisa UDAGAWA).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Recently, however, there is one theory which claims that the firearms spread across Southeast Asia were introduced in several regions in Japan by wako (Japanese pirates) around 1543 and in those days they were used as hunting guns (The theory of Takehisa UDAGAWA).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Recently, however, there is one theory which claims that the firearms spread across Southeast Asia were introduced in several regions in Japan by wako (Japanese pirates) around 1543 and in those days they were used as hunting guns (the theory of Takehisa UDAGAWA).</e>
<cmt>括弧のThe を小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>だが、欧米の研究家の間では、欧州の瞬発式火縄銃が日本に伝えられて改良発展したものが、逆にオランダによって日本から買い付けられて東南アジアに輸出され、それらが手本となって日本式の機構が東南アジアに広まったものとする説が有力である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, among European researchers one theory is dominant, which says that instantaneous discharge matchlocks in Europe were introduced in Japan and improvingly developed, but Holland bought them from Japan and exported them to Southeast Asia and the system of Japanese style spread across Southeast Asia as an example.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。「（宇田川武久説）」を上のセルに入れ直しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, among European researchers one theory is dominant, which says that instantaneous discharge matchlocks in Europe were introduced into Japan and improved, Holland bought them from Japan and exported them to Southeast Asia and the Japanese model spread across Southeast Asia as an example.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, among European and US researchers one theory is dominant, which says that instantaneous discharge matchlocks in Europe were introduced into Japan and improved, Holland bought them from Japan and exported them to Southeast Asia and the Japanese model spread across Southeast Asia as an example.</e>
<cmt>欧米　をEuropean and US としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>つくば科学万博においてポルトガル館で展示された「スリランカの火縄銃」は、日本製の銃に現地好みの木象嵌を銃床に施した「輸出仕様の堺筒」であるとの見方が日本の古銃研究家の間から出されており、この説を裏付ける資料とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese old gun researchers say that &quot;matchlock gun in Sri Lanka&quot; exhibited in the Portugal Pavilion of Tsukuba EXPO was &quot;Sakai gun (hinawaju made in Sakai) for export&quot; which was Japanese gun whose gunstock was decorated with marquetry, the locals&apos; favorite, which is considered as a historical material which supports the theory.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。「木象嵌」は「木象眼」marquetryとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese old gun researchers say that &quot;matchlock guns in Sri Lanka&quot; exhibited in the Portugal Pavilion of Tsukuba EXPO was &quot;Sakai gun (hinawaju made in Sakai) for export&quot; which was a Japanese gun that had a gunstock decorated with marquetry, the locals&apos; favorite, which is considered as historical material supporting the theory.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese old gun researchers say that &apos;matchlock guns in Sri Lanka&apos; exhibited in the Portugal Pavilion of Tsukuba EXPO was &apos;Sakai tsutsu (hinawaju made in Sakai) for export&apos; which was a Japanese gun that had a gunstock decorated with marquetry, the locals&apos; favorite, which is considered as historical material supporting the theory.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="24">
<j>戦国時代以降、日本では近江国の国友、同じく日野、紀州の根来寺、和泉国の堺が鉄砲の主要生産地として栄えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Senguku period in Japan, Kunitomo and Hino in Omi Province, Negoro-ji Temple in Kishu Province and Sakai in Izumi Province flourished as major production areas of guns.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Sengoku period in Japan, Kunitomo and Hino in Omi Province, Negoro-ji Temple in Kishu Province and Sakai in Izumi Province flourished as major production areas for guns.</e>
<cmt>grammar, spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Sengoku period in Japan, Kunitomo and Hino in Omi Province, Negoro-ji Temple in Kishu Province and Sakai in Izumi Province flourished as major production areas for guns.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>根来のみは織田信長・豊臣秀吉による紀州攻めの影響で安土桃山時代期以降衰退したが、国友・日野・堺はその後も鉄砲の生産地として栄え、高い技術力を誇った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Only Negoro-ji Temple declined after the Azuchi-Momoyama period because of the influence of Siege of Kishu by Nobunaga ODA and Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, but even after that, Kunitomo, Hino and Sakai flourished as production areas of guns and were proud of their high technical capabilities.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Only Negoro-ji Temple declined after the Azuchi-Momoyama period because of the influence of Siege of Kishu by Nobunaga ODA and Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, but even after that, Kunitomo, Hino and Sakai flourished as production areas for guns and they were proud of their high technical capabilities.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Only Negoro-ji Temple declined after the Azuchi-Momoyama period because of the influence of Siege of Kishu by Nobunaga ODA and Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, but even after that, Kunitomo, Hino and Sakai flourished as production areas for guns and they were proud of their high technical capabilities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="26">
<j>また、築城技術でも火縄銃の性能を活かした横矢掛かり（これ自体はすでに存在していた）などが発達し、赤穂城などに応用された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And as for technique of castle construction, battlement for a flank attack (it had already existed), exploiting the performance of a hinawaju, and so on developed and they were applied for Ako-jo Castle and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And as for technique of castle construction, battlement for a flank attack (it had already existed), exploiting the performance of hinawaju, developed and they were applied to Ako-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And as for technique of castle construction, battlement for a flank attack (it had already existed), exploiting the performance of hinawaju, developed and they were applied to Ako-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="27">
<j>日本の銃器が伝来から幕末までの永きに渡り火縄銃から進歩しなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For a long time, from the introduction of a gun to Japan to the end of Edo period, a hinawaju did not advanced.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For a long time, from the introduction of the gun to Japan to the end of Edo period, the hinawaju did not advance.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For a long time, from the introduction of the gun to Japan to the end of Edo period, the hinawaju did not advance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>その理由として、江戸時代に入って徳川綱吉によって諸国鉄砲改めによる百姓の狩猟及び銃の原則所持禁止、銃器の移動制限がなされたことや、鎖国の影響による技術進歩の停滞という通説、フリントロック式は火縄式に比べ強力なバネが装着されており、撃鉄作動時の衝撃が大きく、引金を引いてから一瞬遅れて装薬に着火する機構のため銃身がぶれ、火縄銃に比べ命中率が悪く「一発必中」を好む日本人から嫌われたらしいことのほかに、日本では良質の火打石が産出せず大量生産ができなかったこと、またおそらくはすべての武術と同じく鉄炮術も一種の競技的な要素を含んで流派形式で継承されたため、その結果必然的に器具類の改変は避けられた、という要素も大きかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reasons are as follow; that in the Edo period Tsunayoshi TOKUGAWA prohibited the hunting and possession of a gun by farmers in principle, that the transfer of a gun was limited, that, commonly believed, the technological advance of a gun was stagnated by the influence of exclusion of foreigners (national isolation), that a flint gun (flintlock system) had a stronger spring than a hinawaju and when the gunlock operating the impact was big and after triggered the gun barrel, the ignition system of explosive charge, momentarily wavered and the accuracy of fire was bad and thus Japanese who liked &quot;ippatsu hicchu&quot; (hit with one shot) disliked a flint gun, that good quality flints could not yield in Japan and could not be mass-produced, that, as a big factor, the art of gun was inherited probably in the form of school-style which included a kind of competition factor like all the martial arts and as a result, the improvement of the instruments were necessarily avoided.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reasons for this follow; in the Edo period Tsunayoshi TOKUGAWA prohibited hunting and the possession of a gun by farmers in principle, that the transfer of a gun was limited, that, commonly believed, the technological advance of guns stagnated from the influence of the exclusion of foreigners (national isolation), a flintlock gun (flintlock system) had a stronger spring than a hinawaju and when the gunlock operating the impact was big and after trigger was pulled, the ignition mechanism for the explosive charge, momentarily wavered and the accuracy of fire was bad and thus Japanese who liked to &quot;ippatsu hicchu&quot; (hit with one shot), disliked the flintlock gun, good quality flints could not be found in Japan and could not be mass-produced, that, as a big factor, the art of gun was inherited probably in the form of a school-style gun for competitions like all the martial arts and as a result, the improvement of the weapon was necessarily avoided.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reasons for this follow; in the Edo period Tsunayoshi TOKUGAWA prohibited hunting and the possession of a gun by farmers in principle; that the transfer of a gun was limited; that, commonly believed, the technological advance of guns stagnated from the influence of the exclusion of foreigners (national isolation); that a flintlock gun (flintlock system) had a stronger spring than a hinawaju and when the gunlock operating the impact was big and after trigger was pulled, the ignition mechanism for the explosive charge momentarily wavered and the accuracy of fire was bad and thus Japanese who liked to &apos;ippatsu hicchu&apos; (hit with one shot), disliked the flintlock gun; that good quality flints could not be found in Japan and could not be mass-produced; and that, as a big factor, the art of gun was inherited probably in the form of a school-style gun for competitions like all the martial arts and as a result, the improvement of the weapon was necessarily avoided.</e>
<cmt>that を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>幕末に実戦を前提として新式銃が輸入されるまでほとんどの銃器が火縄式のままであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, until new-style guns were imported for actual fights during the end of Edo period, most of guns remained matchlock guns.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, until new-model guns were imported for actual fighting during the end of the Edo period, most of guns were matchlocks.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, until new-model guns were imported for actual fighting during the end of the Edo period, most of guns were matchlocks.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="30">
<j>但し例外として、各大名諸藩で極秘裏に様々な銃器が研究されていたことも事実であり、そのバリエーションは多岐にわたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Exceptionally, however, it was a fact that various firearms were secretly studied in each daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) and each clan and the variations were huge.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Exceptionally, however, it was a fact that various firearms were secretly studied in each daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) and each clan and the variations were many.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Exceptionally, however, it was a fact that various firearms were secretly studied in each daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) and each clan and the variations were many.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>幕末新式銃渡来直前に海外事情も考慮してパーカッション式の銃器すら模造、試作されたものの他には、実用の可能性を想定していたものかどうかは何とも評しようがないものが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Just before the introduction of new-style guns during the end of Edo period, considering foreign situations, even the guns of percussion lock system were imitated and experimentally produced, but there were many guns which, we do not know how to comment, could not possibly be in practical use.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Just before the introduction of new-style guns during the end of Edo period, considering foreign situations, even the guns of percussion lock mechanism were imitated and experimentally produced, but there were many guns which, we do not know how to comment about, that could not possibly be in any practical use.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Just before the introduction of new-style guns during the end of Edo period, considering foreign situations, even the guns of percussion lock mechanism were imitated and experimentally produced, but there were many guns which, we do not know how to comment about, that could not possibly be in any practical use.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>火皿を3つ付けたものや、銃身がリボルバーのように回転する物など三連発の火縄銃や水平二連式短銃など、様々なものが試製されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Various kinds of guns were experimentally produced, such as a triple-barrel hinawaju which had three pans and whose gun barrel rotates like a revolver, a level double-barreled pistol and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Various kinds of guns were experimentally produced, such as a triple-barrel hinawaju which had three pans and whose gun barrel rotates like a revolver, a level double-barreled pistol and so on.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Various kinds of guns were experimentally produced, such as a triple-barrel hinawaju which had three pans and whose gun barrel rotates like a revolver, a level double-barreled pistol and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>日本における運用方法</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">How to use in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">How to use in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">How hinawaju was operated in Japan</e>
<cmt>翻訳を一部変更しました。</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>使用方法</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">How to use.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">How to use.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Usage</e>
<cmt>翻訳を一部変更しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="33">
<j>基本的な方法は以下のとおりである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The basic way of use is</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The basic way to use is</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The basic way to use is as follows:</e>
<cmt>和文を一部補足し、英文もそれに応じて追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="34">
<j>火縄に着火しておく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">to ignite the match.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">to ignite the match.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ignite the match.</e>
<cmt>翻訳を一部変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>複数の着火した火縄を準備することが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Several ignited matches are often prepared.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Several ignited matches are often prepared.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Several ignited matches are often prepared.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>また、火縄の両端に火をつけ、それを二つ折りにして火口を左手の指に挟み持って待機する「二口火（ふたくちび）」という方法もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And there is a way called &quot;futakuchibi&quot; where the shooter waits after igniting the both ends of match and folding it in two and having it with left hand fingers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And there is a way called &quot;futakuchibi&quot; where the shooter waits after igniting both ends of the match and folding it in two and halding it if the fingers of his left hand.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, there is a way called &apos;futakuchibi&apos; where the shooter waits after igniting both ends of the match, folding it in two and holding it in the fingers of his left hand.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="37">
<j>銃口へ発射薬である胴薬と弾丸を装填する（後に早合が発明されると装填の手間は大幅に軽減した）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Load dogusuri as gunpowder for shooting and a bullet in gun muzzle (a cartridge was invented later and the time and effort of loading largely decreased).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Load dogusuri (gunpowder) then a lead ball in gun muzzle (the cartridge was invented later and then the time and effort of loading largely decreased).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Load dogusuri (gunpowder) then a lead ball in gun muzzle (the cartridge was invented later and then the time and effort of loading largely decreased).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>火薬と弾丸はさく杖で銃身の奥へ押し固める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Push down and fix gunpowder and a bullet at the bottom of body of a gun with a ramrod.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With a ramrod, push down and fix the gunpowder and the bullet at the bottom of the barrel.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With a ramrod, push down and fix the gunpowder and the bullet at the bottom of the barrel.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="39">
<j>火皿に点火薬である口薬を入れ、火蓋を閉じ、火の点いた火縄先を火挟（ひばさみ）に挟む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Put gunpowder as an ignition agent in a pan, close the pan cover and put the lighted tip of match between metal tongs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Put some gunpowder in the pan to act as an igition agent, close the pan cover and place the lighted tip of match between metal tongs.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Put some gunpowder in the pan to act as an ignition agent, close the pan cover and place the lighted tip of match between metal tongs.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>この口薬の容器は長さ5 - 8cmの水筒型が定番であり、火薬を注いだ後、手を放すと自然に腰にぶら下がり、キャップが注ぎ口に被さる仕組みになっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for the container for gunpowder, the regular one is the cylinder type of 5 to 8 centimeters and after putting in gunpowder and putting the hand off, it hangs down from the waist naturally and the spout is covered with the cap.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for the container for gunpowder, the regular one was the cylinder type of five to eight centimeters long and after pouring the gunpowder into the barrel and letting go of the container, it hangs down from the waist naturally and the spout is covered with a cap.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for the container for gunpowder, the regular one was the cylinder type of five to eight centimeters long and after pouring the gunpowder into the barrel and letting go of the container, it hangs down from the waist naturally and the spout is covered with a cap.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>これを腰にぶら下げるのが典型スタイルである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a typical style to hang it down from the waist.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The typical container hung from the waist.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The typical container hung from the waist.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="42">
<j>目標を見定め火蓋を切る（パンカバーを開ける）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Aim at the target and cut the pan cover (open the pan cover).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Aim at the target and cut the pan cover (open the pan cover).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Aim at the target and cut the pan cover (open the pan cover).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="43">
<j>構えて狙いを付ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Get ready and aim at.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Get ready and aim at the target.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Get ready and aim at the target.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>標的の体に当る可能性を高める為に胴体の中心を狙う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Aim at the trunk of the body to increase the possibility of hitting the target body.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Aim at the trunk of the body to increase the possibility of hitting the target body.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Aim at the trunk of the body to increase the possibility of hitting the target body.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>距離は標的の目の白黒が見える位、とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The distance is long enough to be able to see the white part and black part of the eye of the target.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The correct distance is lwhen the shooter can seethe white and black part of the eyes of the target.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The correct distance is when the shooter can see the white and black part of the eyes of the target.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="46">
<j>引き金を引き発射。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Trigger and shoot.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Pull the trigger and shoot.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Pull the trigger and shoot.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="47">
<j>再装填。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reload.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reloading.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reload.</e>
<cmt>表現を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>熟練兵士なら約20秒に一発発射したという（昭和末期の実験では18秒程度）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Skillful soldiers could shoot every about twenty seconds (every eighteen seconds in the experiment during the late Showa period).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Skillful soldiers could shoot about every twenty seconds (every eighteen seconds in an experiment during the late Showa period).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that skillful soldiers could shoot about every 20 seconds (every 18 seconds in an experiment during the late Showa period).</e>
<cmt>アラビア数字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>兵士の配置</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Positions of soldiers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Positions of soldiers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Deployment of soldiers</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="49">
<j>火縄銃は、戦国時代中期以降、足軽の主要武器の一つとしてその比重を増していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hinawaju came to be increasingly used as one of major firearms for ashigaru (common foot soldier) after the middle of Sengoku period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hinawaju came to be increasingly used as one of the major firearms for ashigaru (common foot soldier) after the middle of the Sengoku period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hinawaju came to be increasingly used as one of the major firearms for ashigaru (common foot soldier) after the middle of the Sengoku period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>日本の戦国時代から江戸時代においては備ひとつに対し、鉄砲組（20 - 50名）を1、2組配しているのが基本である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the Sengoku period to the Edo period in Japan, for every preparation, one or two group(s) of matchlock infantry (20 to 50 members) were positioned basically.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the Sengoku period to the Edo period in Japan, for preparation, one or two group(s) of matchlock infantry (twenty to fifty members) were positioned.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the Sengoku period to the Edo period in Japan, for one troop, one or two group(s) of matchlock infantry (20 to 50 members) were positioned.</e>
<cmt>備（そなえ）→troop としました。アラビア数字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>戦の開始のときや、勢いに乗り突進してくる敵兵に対し一斉射撃を浴びせ進撃を止まらせるときなどに使用された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the beginning of war or against the enemies running forward in a rush, they were used to fusillade and stop the advance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the beginning of a war or against enemies charging forward in a rush, they were used to fusillade and stop the advance.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the beginning of a war or against enemies charging forward in a rush, they were used to fusillade and stop the advance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>兵士同士が密集したか否かについては議論がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is controversial whether the soldiers were close-packed or not.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is controversial whether the soldiers were closely-packed together or not.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is controversial whether the soldiers were closely-packed together or not.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>火の粉が飛び散る中で火薬を使用するので暴発しかねず、相互に安全な距離を取ったという見解がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some say that if gunpowder was used when sparks of fire were flying it might explode accidentally and thus they kept some distance for safety.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some say that if gunpowder was used when sparks of fire were flying it might explode accidentally and thus they kept some distance for safety.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is an opinion that they kept some distance for safety since gunpowder might have exploded accidentally when it was used in falling sparks.</e>
<cmt>翻訳を一部変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="54">
<j>二段撃ち：2列横隊に並び、前列が片膝をつき、後列が直立して射撃する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Two-stage shooting: soldiers line up in two rows, the front line kneels down on one knee, the back line stands up and they shoot.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Two-stage shooting: soldiers line up in two rows, the front line kneels down on one knee, the back line stands up as they shoot.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Two-stage shooting: Soldiers line up in two rows, the front line kneels down on one knee, the back line stands up as they shoot.</e>
<cmt>コロンの後の文字を大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>佐々成政が考案したという記録が残っているが、実際に採用されていたのか、上記の議論上問題がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There remains a record that it was contrived by Narimasa SASSA, but it is not sure that it was really used and doubtful as mentioned above.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There remains a record that it was contrived by Narimasa SASSA, but it is not sure these positions were really used and were doubtful as mentioned above.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There remains a record that it was contrived by Narimasa SASSA, but it is not sure these positions were really used and were doubtful as mentioned above.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="56">
<j>三段撃ち：長篠の戦いで織田軍が採用したという著名な配置。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Three-stage shooting: it is a famous positioning which ODA army applied in the Battle of Nagashino.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Three-stage shootingk, a famous positioning the ODA army applied at the Battle of Nagashino.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Three-stage shooting: Famous positioning the ODA army applied at the Battle of Nagashino.</e>
<cmt>コロンの後の文字を大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>雑賀衆が遅くとも1568年あたりまでにはすでに実戦で用いていたという説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is also one theory that Saiga-shu (the gun troop) applied it in actual fight until around 1568 at the latest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is also one theory that Saiga-shu (the gun troops) applied it in actual fighting until around 1568 at the latest.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is also one theory that Saiga-shu (the gun troops) applied it in actual fighting until around 1568 at the latest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>この三段撃ちについても大議論がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is also much debate about the three-stage shooting.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is also much debate about the three-stage shooting.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is also much debate about the three-stage shooting.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="59">
<j>1人の射撃手に数丁の火縄銃と数人の助手が付き、射撃手が射撃している間に助手が火縄銃の装填を行う方法があり、これにより素早い連射が可能である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One shooter has a few hinawaju and assistants and while the shooter is shooting, the assistants load them and thus it becomes possible to shoot serially and faster.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One shooter has a few hinawaju and assistants and while the shooter is shooting, the assistants load them and thus it becomes possible to shoot serially and faster.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One shooter has a few hinawaju and assistants and while the shooter is shooting, the assistants load them and thus it becomes possible to shoot serially and faster.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>鉄砲傭兵集団としてその名を知られた雑賀衆、根来衆の得意スタイルである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a specialty style of Saigu-shu and Negoroshu (a group of armed priests in Negoro-ji Temple), known as groups of gun mercenary.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was a special style of Saigu-shu and Negoroshu (a group of armed priests in Negoro-ji Temple), known as groups of gun mercenaries.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was a special style of Saiga-shu and Negoro-shu (a group of armed priests in Negoro-ji Temple), known as groups of gun mercenaries.</e>
<cmt>Negoro-shu として統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>石山合戦で本願寺側に付いた彼らは、織田勢を大いに苦しめた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They took the side of Hongwan-ji Temple in Ishiyama War and they anguished the side of ODA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They took the side of Hongwan-ji Temple in the Ishiyama War and they anguished the side of ODA.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They took the side of Hongwan-ji Temple in the Ishiyama War and they anguished the side of ODA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="62">
<j>この射撃手・助手を分業する射撃運用法を烏渡しの法と上杉流軍学では称したと伝えられ、また後世紀州徳川家においては薬込役という、御庭番の前身である職名にその痕跡を残している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the military science of Uesugi-ryu school, this shooting operation which divided the labor into shooters and assistants is said to have been called the way of Karasu-watashi (Crow handing) and in future generations, in Kishu Tokugawa Family, the job title of kusurikomeyaku (a gunpowder charger), which was the predecessor of Oniwaban (the shogunate&apos;s guard of the inner garden), retains the trace of it.</e>
<cmt>「烏渡し」が不明のため、Karasu-watashi (Crow handing)としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In military science of Uesugi-ryu school, this shooting method, dividing the labor into shooters and assistants is said to have been called the way of Karasu-watashi (Crow handing) and in future generations, in the Kishu Tokugawa Family, the job title of kusurikomeyaku (a gunpowder charger), the predecessor of Oniwaban (the shogunate&apos;s guard of the inner garden), retains a trace of it.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In military science of Uesugi-ryu school, this shooting method, dividing the labor into shooters and assistants is said to have been called the way of Karasu-watashi (crow handing) and in future generations, in the Kishu Tokugawa family, the job title of kusurikomeyaku (a gunpowder charger), the predecessor of Oniwaban (the shogunate&apos;s guard of the inner garden), retains a trace of it.</e>
<cmt>family 小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>発射速度</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shooting speed</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shooting speed</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shooting speed</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="63">
<j>次弾発砲までに「銃身内の火薬残滓を洗い矢で拭う」（数発撃つと銃腔にすすがこびり付き弾が入らなくなるため、槊杖の先に水に濡らした布を付けて拭う）「火穴にせせり（ヴェントピック）を通す」「銃身を冷やす」（但し、1分間に1発程度のペースで発砲するのであればこの必要は全くない）など、一般に次弾装塡の際に行うべき事は多いと言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that in general there are many things to do when loading a next bullet, such as &quot;wash the residuary gunpowder inside of a gun barrel with a cleaning rod&quot; (after shooting a few bullets the gun barrel soots and a bullet cannot be inserted, and thus it is washed with a ramrod whose point is put with a wet cloth), &quot;stick a ventpick in the fire hole,&quot; &quot;cool the gun barrel down&quot; (however, if one shoots every one minute, it is not necessary) and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that in general there are many things to do when loading the next bullet, such as &quot;clean out the residuary gunpowder from inside the gun barrel with a cleaning rod&quot; (after shooting a few bullets the gun barrel soots up and the lead shot cannot be inserted, and thus it is washed with a ramrod with a wet cloth on the end), &quot;stick a ventpick in the fire hole,&quot; &quot;cool the gun barrel down&quot; (however, if one shoots every minute, it is not necessary) and so on.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that in general there are many things to do when loading the next bullet, such as &apos;clean out the residuary gunpowder from inside the gun barrel with a cleaning rod&apos; (after shooting a few bullets the gun barrel soots up and the lead shot cannot be inserted, and thus it is washed with a ramrod with a wet cloth on the end), &apos;stick a ventpick in the fire hole,&apos; &apos;cool the gun barrel down&apos; (however, if one shoots every minute, it is not necessary) and so on.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="64">
<j>しかし、これらは後世に科学技術の進歩を強調するための「たとえ話」として語られたものであり、実際にはこの作業を1発ごとに行う必要はなく、数発に一度行えばよい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, these are told as &quot;parables&quot; to emphasize the advancement of science technology in future generations and in fact it is not necessary for these tasks to be done for each shot, but for a few shots.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, these were told as &quot;parables&quot; to emphasize the advancement of science technology in future generations and in fact it is not necessary for these tasks to be done for each shot, but for every few shots.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, these were told as &apos;parables&apos; to emphasize the advancement of science technology in future generations and in fact it is not necessary for these tasks to be done for each shot, but for every few shots.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>関流砲術では、7発位撃つと弾が入り難くなると伝えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seki&apos;s school of gunnery has taught that at about every seven shots it becomes difficult for a bullet to be inserted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seki&apos;s school of gunnery has taught that at about every seven shots it becomes difficult for a bullet to be inserted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seki&apos;s school of gunnery has taught that at about every seven shots it becomes difficult for a bullet to be inserted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>また、「劣り玉」と呼ばれる適合弾より若干径が小さい弾を使用すれば、目標への集弾性は低下するものの、10発以上の連続発射が可能である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If you use a bullet called &quot;otori-dama&quot; (inferior bullet), a bit smaller than an appropriate one, you can shoot more than ten bullets serially, though the accuracy of fire at the target decreases.</e>
<cmt>「劣り玉」を“otori-dama” (inferior bullet)としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If you use a bullet called &quot;otori-dama&quot; (inferior bullet), a bit smaller than an appropriate one, you can shoot more than ten bullets serially, though the accuracy of fire at the target decreases.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If you use a bullet called &apos;otori-dama&apos; (inferior bullet), a bit smaller than an appropriate one, you can shoot more than ten bullets serially, although the accuracy of fire at the target decreases.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>（江戸時代の射的で一般的な、射距離十五間では劣り玉でも命中率は殆ど変わらないが三十間を超えると低下が見られる）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(In the shooting distance of 15 ken (about 27 meters), which was common in the target practice during the Edo period, the accuracy of fire is almost the same even with otori-dama, but if the distance is more than 30 ken (about 54 meters), the accuracy decreases)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At a shooting distance of fifteen ken (about twenty-seven meters), common in target practice during the Edo period, the accuracy of fire is almost the same even with otori-dama, but if the distance is more than thirty ken (about fifty-four meters), the accuracy decreases)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(At a shooting distance of 15 ken [about 27 meters], common in target practice during the Edo period, the accuracy of fire is almost the same even with otori-dama, but if the distance is more than 30 ken [about 54 meters], the accuracy decreases.)</e>
<cmt>アラビア数字に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>また銃腔内や火皿の清掃は頻繁に行う必要はなく、弾が込め難い等の異常を感じたら行えば済む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And it is not necessary to clean the gun barrel and pan so often and if you see abnormalities such as difficulty of inserting a bullet and so on you clean it and as for how to clean it, you insert the cleaning rod, whose point is put with a wet piece of cloth, into the gun muzzle and move it in and out 1 to 2 times.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And it is not necessary to clean the gun barrel and pan so often and if you experience abnormalities such as difficulty inserting a lead ball, you clean it and as for how to clean it, you insert the cleaning rod, the end having a wet piece of cloth, into the gun muzzle and move it in and out 1 to 2 times.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, it is not necessary to clean the gun barrel and pan so often; it needs to be cleaned only after abnormalties are found such as difficulty inserting a lead ball.</e>
<cmt>文章を２つのセルに分けました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>その方法も、黒色火薬が水に溶けやすい特性から、洗矢の先に水で湿らせた布切れを付けたものを銃口から差込み1〜2往復させれば完了する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for the cleaning method, you insert the cleaning rod, the end having a wet piece of cloth, into the gun muzzle and move it in and out one to two times, as black gunpowder is easily soluble in water.</e>
<cmt>文章を２つのセルに分けました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>熟練した者ならば第1弾発砲から18〜20秒後に次弾発射できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Skilled persons can shoot the second bullet after 18 to 20 seconds from the first. (The experiment was done during the late Showa period)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Skilled persons can shoot a second bullet after eighteen to twenty seconds from the first. (The experiment was done during the late Showa period)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Skilled persons can shoot a second bullet after 18 to 20 seconds from the first.</e>
<cmt>アラビア数字に変更しました。一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>（昭和末期に実験済み）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(The experiment was done during the late Showa period.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>とはいえ、現代の銃に比して先込め銃は単体では連射に向かないものであることは上記のプロセスなどからも容易に窺える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, a muzzle-loader is not appropriate for serial shooting compared with a present-day gun, which is easy to understand as mentioned above.</e>
<cmt>（昭和末期に実験済み）は、上のセルに入れ直しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, a muzzle-loader is not appropriate for serial shooting compared to present-day guns, which is easy to understand as mentioned above.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, a muzzle-loader is not appropriate for serial shooting compared to present-day guns, which is easy to understand as mentioned above.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="73">
<j>この「次弾発射までに時間がかかる」という先込め式最大の問題点を改善するため、火縄銃が用いられた戦国時代 (日本)の日本では、「早合」（装塡を簡便にするための弾薬包）「複数人でチームを組む」「銃身を複数設置する」など、様々な（時には奇天烈な）発想がなされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To improve the most problematic point that &quot;it takes lots of time to shoot the next bullet&quot; of a muzzle-loader, &quot;hayago&quot; (cartridge for simplifying the loading), &quot;to make up a team with several people,&quot; &quot;to set up some gun barrels&quot; and so on were variously (sometimes bizarrely) contrived during the Sengoku period (Japan) when hinawaju was used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To improve the most problematic point that &quot;it takes lots of time to shoot the next bullet&quot; of a muzzle-loader, &quot;hayago&quot; (cartridge for simplifying the loading), &quot;to make up a team with several people,&quot; &quot;to set up some gun barrels&quot; and so on were variously (sometimes bizarrely) contrived during the Sengoku period (Japan) when hinawaju was used.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To improve the most problematic point that &apos;it takes lots of time to shoot the next bullet&apos; of a muzzle-loader, &apos;hayago&apos; (cartridge for simplifying the loading), &apos;to make up a team with several people,&apos; &apos;to set up some gun barrels&apos; and so on were variously (sometimes bizarrely) contrived during the Sengoku period (Japan) when hinawaju was used.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>西洋における火縄銃運用史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History of hinawaju operation in the West.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History of hinawaju used in the West.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History of hinawaju used in the West</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>火縄銃の登場による陣形の変遷</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Transition of battle formation by the appearance of hinawaju.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Transition of battle formations with the appearance of hinawaju.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Transition of battle formations with the appearance of hinawaju</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="74">
<j>野戦隊形における集中射撃法が実用化されたのはヨーロッパにおいてであり、最も初期のものはテルシオと呼ばれる、長槍（パイク）の密集方陣の進撃に際して四周に随伴した銃兵が相手方の方陣と至近距離まで接近し、接触寸前になった時点で発砲して第一次打撃を期待するものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was in Europe that the concentrative shooting method in open battle formation was turned into actual utilization and the earliest one was called tercio (Spanish square), where, against the advancement of a close-packed formation of pikes, fusiliers accompanying in four directions approach to the formation of the enemies at close range and just before the contact, they firstly shoot and expect the first impact blow.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was in Europe that the concentrated shooting method in open battle formation was turned into actual utilization and the earliest called tercio (Spanish square), where, against the advancement of a close-packed formation of pikes, fusiliers accompanying in four directions approach to the formation of the enemies at close range and just before contact, they firstly shoot and expect the first impact blow.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was in Europe that the concentrated shooting method in open battle formation was turned into actual utilization and the earliest called tercio (Spanish square), where, against the advancement of a close-packed formation of pikes, fusiliers accompanying in four directions approach to the formation of the enemies at close range and just before contact, they firstly shoot and expect the first impact blow.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>この方式は銃剣の発明以前であり、発砲を終えた銃兵は有効な戦力ではないから、退避行動を取ったとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As this method was used before the invention of bayonet and the fusiliers who had shot were not good war potentials, they are said to have retreated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As this method was used before the invention of the bayonet and the fusiliers who shot were not good war potentials, they are said to have retreated.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As this method was used before the invention of the bayonet and the fusiliers who shot were not good war potentials, they are said to have retreated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>実際の戦闘はパイク兵が主体であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mainly pike soldiers fought in actual fighting.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mainly pike soldiers fought in actual fighting.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mainly pike soldiers fought in actual fighting.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>射撃手前後交替の発想が見られるものとしては騎兵のカラコール戦術が対テルシオ戦法として用いられた事が挙げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The idea of the exchange of shooters between the front and the back is seen in the military caracole of horse soldiers, which was utilized against the military tercio.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The idea of the exchange of shooters between the front and rear is seen in the military caracole of horse soldiers, utilized against military tercio.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The idea of the exchange of shooters between the front and rear is seen in the military caracole of horse soldiers, utilized against military tercio.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>これは概ね1530年代頃からである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was roughly seen from around 1530s.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was roughly seen from around 1530s.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was roughly seen from around 1530s.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="79">
<j>装填に時間と防御上の弱点が生じることを解決する手段として、縦列で行進する銃兵の最前者が発砲し、発砲後直ちに最後尾に駆け戻って装填作業をしながら行進を続行するという方式が考え出されたが、それを行うには非常に訓練を必要とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a procedure to solve the weak points of taking lots of time to load and of defense aspects, one method was contrived, in which, just after the front man of fusiliers marching in a column line shot, he ran back to the end of the line with loading, but it needed much of practice to do it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To solve the weak point of the time needed to load and aspects of defenses, one method was contrived, in which, just after the front man of fusiliers marching in a column line shot, he ran back to the end of the line while loading, but it required much practice to do this.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To solve the weak point of the time needed to load and aspects of defenses, one method was contrived, in which, just after the front man of fusiliers marching in a column line shot, he ran back to the end of the line while loading, but it required much practice to do this.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>オランダ・ナッサウ伯マウリッツ (オラニエ公)がおよそこの創始者であろうと推察され、概ね1584年頃の事とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Maurice of Nassau (Prince of Orange) is conjectured to have been the originator of this method and it is considered to have been around 1584.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Maurice of Nassau (Prince of Orange) is conjectured to have been the originator of this method and it is considered to have been around 1584.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Maurice of Nassau (Prince of Orange) in Netherland is conjectured to have been the originator of this method, which is considered to have been around 1584.</e>
<cmt>オランダ　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>今日マウリッツは軍制改革の父と呼ばれているが、その功績は射撃法ではなく、それを達成する為の猛烈且つ間断なき訓練が、寄せ集め傭兵の集合体であった当時の軍隊を一種の帰属意識に基づく団結心を持った集団に変え得る予期外の効果を持つという事を発見したという点が評価されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today Maurice is called a father of the reformation of military system, but his achievement lies not in the shooting method, but in the discovery that hard and incessant practices to attain the goal could change the armies in those days, which were aggregations of mercenary, into the body whose members had a team spirit based on a sense of belonging and had an effect beyond expectation, which is highly evaluated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today Maurice is called the father of the reformation of the military system, but his achievement lies not in the shooting method, but in the discovery that hard and incessant practices to attain a goal could change the armies in those days, which were aggregations of mercenaries, into a body whose members had a team spirit based on a sense of belonging and were effective beyond expectation, which was highly evaluated.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today Maurice is called the father of the reformation of the military system, but his achievement lies not in the shooting method, but in the discovery that hard and incessant practices to attain a goal could change the armies in those days, which were aggregations of mercenaries, into a body whose members had a team spirit based on a sense of belonging and were effective beyond expectation, which was highly evaluated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>またマウリッツは、歩騎砲の三兵が連動して機動戦術を採る事を発案し且つ可能にした軍事家としても評価されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And Maurice is highly evaluated as a militarist, who thought up that three infantry men coordinated and applied a mobile tactics and who made the tactics possible.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。「歩騎砲の三兵」不明のため、three infantry menとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And Maurice is highly evaluated as a militarist, who thought up the idea to have three kinds of infantry men coordinated and apply mobile tactics and who made the tactics possible.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, Maurice is highly evaluated as a militarist, who thought up the idea to have three kinds of soldiers; infantry, cavalry and artillery coordinated in order to apply mobile tactics and who actually made the tactics possible.</e>
<cmt>歩騎砲の三兵→three kinds of soldiers; infantry, cavalry and artillery　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>ここで、個別の兵種がそれぞれ独自に機能を発揮するのではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Here, individual soldiers did not function uniquely.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Here, individual soldiers did not function uniquely.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Here, individual soldiers did not function uniquely.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>ただこの縦列交替法が大きな効果を発揮したらしい記録はなく、またこの運動方式には鈍重さが宿命的に付きまとったため、マウリッツ自身の戦死の原因をそこに求める考え方もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there is no record that the exchange method in a column line exerted a great effect and as the sluggishness was not avoided fatefully for this method of movement, some think that the cause of Maurice&apos;s death in war lied in this.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there is no record that the exchange method in a column line exerted a great effect and as the sluggishness was not avoided fatefully for this method of movement, some think that the cause of Maurice&apos;s death in war was a lie.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there is no record that the exchange method in a column line exerted a great effect; also, the sluggishness was not avoided fatefully for this method of movement, which some people think caused Maurice&apos;s death in war.</e>
<cmt>一部翻訳を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>この時代を火縄銃時代とするかどうかには疑問があるが、燧石式移行時代の終わり頃とも考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is doubtful to regard this period as that of hinawaju, but this period can be considered as the end of transferring period to the flintlock mechanism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is doubtful to regard this period as that of hinawaju, but it can be considered as the end of the transfer period to the flintlock mechanism.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is doubtful to regard this period as that of hinawaju, but it can be considered as the end of the transfer period to the flintlock mechanism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="86">
<j>実際に前後交替射撃法が実用化するのは燧石式に移行してからであり、燧石式の機能改善もそれに相当の貢献をしたと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In fact, it was not until the transference to flintlock mechanism that the shooting method of exchanging between the front and the back was put into practical use and the improvement of functions of flintlock mechanism is also considered to have contributed much to this.</e>
<cmt>「前後交替射撃法」をthe shooting method of exchanging between the front and the backとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In fact, it was not until transfering to the flintlock mechanism that the shooting method of exchanging between the front and the rear was put into practical use and the improvement in the functions of theflintlock mechanism is also considered to have contributed much to this.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact, it was not until after the mechanism was shifted to that of flintlock when the shooting method of exchanging between the front and the rear was put into practical use, which, some people think, owed much to the improvement in the functions of the flintlock mechanism.</e>
<cmt>一部翻訳を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>また銃剣の登場もこれに大きく寄与していると考えられるが、同時にこの時代は大砲の運用が飛躍的に改良されており、銃兵の交替射撃のみが戦線の状況を変革させたと論じるのは未だ大きな検討を要するであろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, the appearance of a bayonet drill is considered to have contributed much to this, but at the same times, during this period the operation of cannon was dramatically improved and it still needs much revision to argue that only the exchanging shooting of fusiliers transformed the battle line situation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, the appearance of bayonet drill is considered to have contributed much to this, but at the same time, during this period the operation of the cannon was dramatically improved and it still needs much revision to argue that only the exchange shooting of fusiliers transformed the battle line situation.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, the appearance of bayonet drill is considered to have contributed much to this, but at the same time, during this period the operation of the cannon was dramatically improved and it still needs much revision to argue that only the exchange shooting of fusiliers transformed the battle line situation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>これらは概ね17世紀末から18世紀初頭の現象である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These are roughly the phenomena from the late seventeenth century to the early eighteenth century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These were roughly phenomena from the late seventeenth century to the early eighteenth century.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These were roughly phenomena from the late 17th century to the early 18th century.</e>
<cmt>アラビア数字に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>障害物に拠る投射兵器の運用</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The operation of shooting arms based on obstacles</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The operation of shooting arms based on obstacles</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The operation of shooting arms based on obstacles</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="89">
<j>装填その他に伴う初期銃の弱点を補う為に障壁･城壁･障害物あるいは特殊な地形等によって防御された場所から、機動してくる野戦軍を射撃しようという試みは早くから行われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To make up for the weak points when loading and so on of early guns, from early on, they tried to shoot the advancing open battle army from the places protected by barriers, ramparts, obstacles, unusual land features and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To make up for the weak points when loading early guns, they tried to shoot the advancing open battle army from places protected by barriers, ramparts, obstacles, unusual land features and so on.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To make up for the weak points when loading early guns, they tried to shoot the advancing open battle army from places protected by barriers, ramparts, obstacles, unusual land features and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="90">
<j>最も著名な例は1503年イタリア戦争中、スペイン軍人ゴンサロ・フェルナンデス・デ・コルドバが行った戦法で、急造の堀とその残土を利用した土手に拠った二千名と推定されるアルケブス銃兵を指揮して、押し寄せたフランス重騎兵団を粉砕し、スペインの覇権確立の重要な要因となった戦いがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The most famous example is the tactics conducted by Spanish military personnel, Gonzalo Fernández de Córdoba during the Italian Wars in 1503, where he commanded the infantry men of arquebus, whose number is estimated to have been two thousand, positioned in hastily built fosse and the embankment made with the remaining clod, and broke up the advancing French heavy cavalry troop, and this war was an important factor leading to the establishment of Spanish hegemony.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The most famous example is the tactics conducted by Spanish military personnel, Gonzalo Fernández de Córdoba during the Italian Wars in 1503, where he commanded the infantry men using the arquebus, whose number is estimated to have been two thousand, positioned in a hastily built fosse and the embankment made with the remaining clod, that broke up the advancing French heavy cavalry troop, and these wars were an important factor leading to the establishment of Spanish hegemony.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The most famous example is the tactics conducted by Spanish military personnel, Gonzalo Fernández de Córdoba during the Italian Wars in 1503, where he commanded the Arquebusiers, whose number is estimated to have been 2000, positioned in a hastily built fosse and the embankment made with the remaining clod, that broke up the advancing French heavy cavalry troop, and these wars were an important factor leading to the establishment of Spanish hegemony.</e>
<cmt>アルケブス銃兵→Arquebusiers　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>続いてイタリア戦争においても、1522年同じくスペイン軍の傭兵隊長コロンナがミラノ郊外ビコッカにおいて、地形と急造塁壁を利用したアルケブスの反復射撃戦法で、押し寄せたスイス槍兵集団を粉砕している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also in the Italian Wars which followed, similarly in 1522, the commander of mercenary of Spanish army, Colonna broke up the advancing Swiss concentration of spearmen with tactics of repeated shooting of arquebus, using land features and hastily built ramparts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also in the Italian Wars that followed, similarly in 1522, the commander of the mercenaries in the Spanish army, Colonna broke up the advancing Swiss concentration of spearmen with tactics of repeated shooting of the arquebus, using land features and hastily built ramparts.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also in the Italian Wars that followed, similarly in 1522, the commander of the mercenaries in the Spanish army, Colonna broke up the advancing Swiss concentration of spearmen with tactics of repeated shooting of the arquebus, using land features and hastily built ramparts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>ちなみに種子島に火縄銃が伝来したとされるのはこの20年後の事である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Matchlock guns are said to have been introduced in Tanegashima Island after twenty years from this incident.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Matchlock guns are said to have been introduced on Tanegashima Island twenty years after this incident.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Matchlock guns are said to have been introduced on Tanega-shima Island 20 years after this incident.</e>
<cmt>Tanega-shima Island としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>最も古い例としてドイツで発生したフス戦争（1419 - 1436年）において、フス派信徒が円陣配置した荷車を防壁にしてハンドガンで射撃するという戦法を採ったとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the oldest example, believers of Hussites are said to have arranged the carts in circular formation, made them a protective wall and applied the tactics of shooting with handguns in Hussite Wars (1419 – 1436) which occurred in Germany.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the oldest example, believers of Hussites are said to have arranged the carts in a circular formation, made them a protective wall and applied the tactics of shooting with handguns in the Hussite Wars (1419 – 1436) that occurred in Germany.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the oldest example, believers of Hussites are said to have arranged the carts in a circular formation, made them a protective wall and applied the tactics of shooting with handguns in the Hussite Wars (1419 – 1436) that occurred in Germany.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="94">
<j>何れの戦いにおいても交替に射撃したとは言われているが、号令方式などによる統制交替射撃が行われたとする根拠はない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that they shot in rotation in any war, but there is no ground that controlled alternate shooting by command method and so on were done.</e>
<cmt>「号令方式」をcommand methodと、「統制交替射撃」をcontrolled alternate shootingとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that they shot in rotation in any war, but there are no grounds for controlled alternate shooting by command method being done.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that they shot in rotation in any war, but there are no grounds for controlled alternate shooting by command method being done.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>これら一連の戦いに共通する要素は以下のとおりである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">What is common in a series of wars is that</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">What is common in a series of wars is that</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">What is common in a series of wars is as follows:</e>
<cmt>和文を補足し、英文もそれに応じて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="96">
<j>比較的格闘戦能力に劣る部隊もしくは少数部隊が、自然もしくは人工の障害と飛び道具を利用して防戦態勢をとり、押し寄せる強力な伝統的野戦軍を破った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the troops or tiny corps which had relatively low combat capability</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">the troops or tiny corps which had relatively low combat capability</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The troops or tiny corps which had relatively low combat capability utilized natural or artificial obstacles and shooting weapons and were on the defensive, and defeated a strong surging open battle army.</e>
<cmt>和文をひとつのセルに戻し英文もつなげました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="97">
<j>この原型は中世から近世初期にかけての軍事知識として、英仏百年戦争におけるクレシーの戦い（1346年）が著名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for an archetype, Battle of Crécy (1346) in Hundred Years&apos; War between France and England is famous as military knowledge from the medieval ages to the early modern times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for an archetype, the Battle of Crécy (1346) in the Hundred Years&apos; War between France and England is notorious as military knowledge from the medieval ages to early modern times.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for an archetype, the Battle of Crécy (1346) in the Hundred Years&apos; War between France and England is notorious as military knowledge from the medieval ages to early modern times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>この戦いは火砲の使用が初めて記録された戦いとしても有名であり、また馬防柵を急造設置したらしい痕跡が現在発掘調査で明らかになりつつあると言われているが、火砲は使用されたとしても極少数であり、使用の事実及び効果に付いてはまだ今後の研究を待つ所が大きい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This battle is famous for the first record of the use of gun, and the trace of rapidly setting up horse-blocking fence is said to have been being revealed by the excavation and research, but, even though the guns were used, they were very few and the fact and effect of the use of guns still remain to be proved.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This battle is famous for the first record of the use of the gun, and of rapidly setting upa horse-blocking fence is said to have been being revealed by an excavation and research, but, even though guns were used, they were very few and the fact and effect of the use of guns still remains to be proven.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This battle is famous for the first record of the use of the gun, and it is said that the evidence of rapidly established horse-blocking fence is being revealed by an excavation and research, but, even though guns were used, they were very few and the fact and effect of the use of guns still remain to be proven.</e>
<cmt>一部翻訳を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>しかしながら、この戦いは丘陵地形を利用した弓兵集団の集中射撃によって、これまで無敵とされた重武装騎士の集団突撃を阻止粉砕するという戦果を残した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, however, in this battle, intense shooting of spearmen group, using hill landform, stopped and defeated the rush of heavily-armed knights group which were said to be invincible so far.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, however, in this battle, intense shooting of the spearmen group, from hills, stopped and defeated the rush of heavily-armed knights group which were said to had be invincible so far.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, however, in this battle, intense shooting of the spearmen group, from hills, stopped and defeated the rush of heavily-armed knights group which were said to had be invincible so far.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>さらに同戦争末期、アジャンクールの戦い（1415年）において、全く同様な事が繰り返された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And during the end of this battle, in Battle of Agincourt (1415), the totally same events were repeated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And during the end of this battle, in the Battle of Agincourt (1415), the exact same events were repeated.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And during the end of this battle, in the Battle of Agincourt (1415), the exact same events were repeated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>この時には火砲の使用に記録はないが、馬防用の先端のとがった杭の携行については、英国王ヘンリー5世 (イングランド王)の命令が記録されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time the use of gun was not recorded, but as for the carrying of pointed stakes for horse-blocking, the order of British monarch Henry V (the King of England) was recorded.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time the use of gun was not recorded, but as for the carrying of pointed stakes for horse-blocking, the order of British monarch Henry V (the King of England) was recorded.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time the use of gun was not recorded, but as for the carrying of pointed stakes for horse-blocking, the order of British monarch Henry V (the King of England) was recorded.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>これも弓兵集団と騎士団の戦闘で騎士団が全滅した戦いの例である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As an example this shows that the entire knights groups were devastated in the battle between spearman group and cavalry.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As an example this shows that the entire groups of knights were devastated in the battle between spearman groups and cavalry.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As an example this shows that the entire groups of cavalry were devastated in the battle between spearman groups and cavalry.</e>
<cmt>騎士団→groups of cavalry　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="103">
<j>これらの知識が新しく登場した特長と弱点を併せ持つ鉄砲の運用に応用された成功したのは、まず間違いはないであろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is safe to say that this knowledge was applied to the operation of guns which had both newly emerging characteristics and weak points and succeeded.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is safe to say that this knowledge was applied to the operation using guns which had both newly emerging characteristics and weak points and it succeeded.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is safe to say that this knowledge was applied to the operation using guns which had both newly emerging characteristics and weak points and it succeeded.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>日本において、信長周辺にこれらヨーロッパ軍事知識がどのように伝わっており、長篠の戦闘などに応用されたという可能性は興味深く、今後の研究が待たれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan, how European military knowledge was introduced into the vicinity of Nobunaga and the possibility that the knowledge was applied to the Battle of Nagashino were interesting and remains to be proved.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan, how European military knowledge was introduced into the vicinity of Nobunaga and the possibility that the knowledge was applied to the Battle of Nagashino is interesting and remains to be proved.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan, how European military knowledge was introduced into the people around Nobunaga and the possibility that the knowledge was applied to the Battle of Nagashino is interesting and remains to be proved.</e>
<cmt>信長周辺→people around Nobunaga としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="105">
<j>火縄銃の名称</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Names of hinawaju (matchlock gun)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Names of the hinawaju (matchlock gun)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Names of the hinawaju</e>
<cmt>既出単語の補足を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>一般に（アルケブス）もしくは同音のなまったものがよく知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In general, arquebus or the same accented sound are well-known.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In general, the arquebus or the same accented sound are well-known.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In general, the arquebus or the same accented sound are well-known.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="107">
<j>燧石式銃については（スナップハンス）（ミュクレット）（フリントロック）などの名称が知られ形式上の分別とされているが、その発祥は火縄銃同様明確な記録はない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for the guns of flintlock mechanism, the names such as &quot;snaphance,&quot; &quot;muklet,&quot; &apos;flintlock&quot; and so on are known and they are said to be classified in terms of the forms, but there is no record of the origin like hinawaju.</e>
<cmt>「ミュクレット」が不明のため、とりあえずmukletとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for the flintlocks, names such as &quot;snaphance,&quot; &quot;muklet,&quot; &apos;flintlock&quot; and so on are known and they are said to be classified in terms describing their form, but there is no record of an origin for hinawaju.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for the flintlocks, names such as &quot;snaphance,&quot; &quot;muklet,&quot; &quot;flintlock&quot; and so on are known and they are said to be classified in terms describing their form, but there is no record of an origin for hinawaju.</e>
<cmt>ダブルクォーテーションに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="108">
<j>（アルケビュス）については一つの説として、さらに初期の手砲の一形式に棒の先につけた金属筒に鉤状の突起を設け、発射時は鉤を委託物に引っかけ棒を地上に押さえ付けて発射した形式があり、これをドイツ語系で（ハーケン・ビュクセ＝鉤付筒）と呼んだだのが語源で、フランス語系で類似した（アーケン・ビュッス→アルケブス）と発音が訛化したのであろうという説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As one theory for &quot;arquebus,&quot; there is one form where, as one form of the early hand gun, hook-shaped jut was put on iron tube attached on the tip of stick and when shooting the hook was put on the other thing and the stick was pushed on the earth, and one theory says that it was called &quot;Hakenbüchse = a tube with a hook&quot; in German and became the word origin and in French the similar pronunciation (Arquen bus =&gt;arquebus) was accented.</e>
<cmt>「アーケン・ビュッス」のスペル不明で、とりあえずArquen busとしました。また、「初期の手砲の一形式に棒の先につけた金属筒に鉤状の突起を設け、発射時は鉤を委託物に引っかけ棒を地上に押さえ付けて発射した形式」とありますが、助詞の使い方が曖昧であるため、部品の配置関係が若干不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As one theory for &quot;arquebus,&quot; there is one form where, as one form of the early hand gun, hook-shaped jut was put on an iron tube attached on the tip of stick and when shooting the hook was attached to something and the stick was pushed into the earth, and one theory says that it was called &quot;Hakenbüchse = a tube with a hook&quot; in German and became the word origin and in French the similar pronunciation (Arquen bus =&gt;arquebus) was accented.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As one theory for &quot;arquebus,&quot; there is one form where, as one form of the early hand gun, hook-shaped jut was put on an iron tube attached on the tip of stick and when shooting the hook was attached to something and the stick was pushed into the earth, and one theory says that it was called &quot;Hakenbüchse = a tube with a hook&quot; in German and became the word origin and in French the similar pronunciation (Arquen bus =&gt;arquebus) was accented.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="109">
<j>さらに別の説にフランス語系の（アルク・ビュッス筒形弓）を起源とする説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And additionally there is one theory saying that the word origin was &quot;Arque bus cylinder shape arrow&quot; in French.</e>
<cmt>「アルク・ビュッス」のスペル不明で、とりあえずArque busとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And additionally there is one theory saying that the word origin was &quot;Arque bus cylinder shaped arrow&quot; in French.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And additionally there is one theory saying that the word origin was &quot;Arque bus cylinder shaped arrow&quot; in French.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="110">
<j>恐らくは両方が混在しつつ、俗称通称化したものであろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Perhaps both were mixed and existed and came to be commonly called.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Perhaps both were mixed and existed and came to be called common names.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Perhaps both were mixed and existed and came to be called common names.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>日本における分類</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Classification in Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Classification in Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Classification in Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="111">
<j>日本における火縄銃の分類として弾丸重量によるものと製作地・流派によるものの二つに大別される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The classification of hinagaju in Japan is roughly divided into the two: the one by the weight of bullet and the one by production area and the school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The classification of hinagaju in Japan is roughly divided into two: one by the weight of bullet and one according to the area where it was produced and the school.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The classification of hinawaju in Japan is roughly divided into two: one by the weight of bullet and one according to the area where it was produced and the school.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>弾丸重量による分類</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The classification by the weight of bullet</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Classification by the weight of the bullet</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Classification by the weight of the bullet</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="112">
<j>小筒</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Small tube</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Small tube</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Small barrel</e>
<cmt>一部翻訳を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="113">
<j>弾丸重量が三匁半程度のものを指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It refers to the one whose weight is about three monme (1 monme = 3.75g) and the half.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It refers to the one whose weight is about three monme (1 monme = 3.75g) and the half.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It refers to the one whose weight is about three monme (1 monme = 3.75g) and the half.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="114">
<j>威力は低いが安価で反動が少ない為、猟銃や動員兵への支給銃として用いられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The power was weak, but it was cheap and the recoil was small and thus it was used as a hunting gun or a gun supplied to a mobilized soldier.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The power was weak, but it was cheap and the recoil was light and thus it was used as a hunting gun or a gun supplied to a mobilized soldier.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The power was weak, but it was cheap and the recoil was light and thus it was used as a hunting gun or a gun supplied to a mobilized soldier.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>また、防御力の薄い明・朝鮮の兵にはこれでも十分な威力を持っていた為、文禄・慶長の役では大量に用いられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And it had a strong power for the soldiers of the Ming dynasty or Korea, whose protection powers were weak, and thus it was massively used in the Bunroku-Keicho War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And it was powerful for soldiers of the Ming dynasty or Korea, whose protective powers were weak, and thus it was massively used in the Bunroku-Keicho War.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And it was powerful for soldiers of the Ming dynasty or Korea, whose protective powers were weak, and thus it was massively used in the Bunroku-Keicho War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="116">
<j>中筒</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Middle barrel</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Middle barrel</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Middle barrel</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="117">
<j>弾丸重量が六匁程度のものを指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It refers to the one whose weight is about six monme (1 monme = 3.75g).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It refers to the one with a weight of about six monme (1 monme = 3.75g).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It refers to the one with a weight of about six monme.</e>
<cmt>既出単語の補足を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="118">
<j>小筒に比べて威力が増大した分扱いが難しい上に高価なので、臨時雇いでなく継続して主人に仕える足軽が用いる銃とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Compared with a small barrel, it had a stronger power and the handling was more difficult and expensive and thus it was regarded as a gun which was used not by temporaries but mainly by ashigaru who continuously served the master.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even with a small barrel, it was more powerful, but handling was more difficult and expensive and thus it was regarded as a gun used not by temporaries, but mainly by ashigaru who continuously served the master.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since it was more powerful, it became more difficult to handle the middle barrel compared to a small one; also, since it was expensive, it was regarded as a gun used not by temporaries, but mainly by ashigaru who continuously served the master.</e>
<cmt>一部翻訳を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="119">
<j>当世具足や竹束などの火縄銃に対応した防御装備が広まった結果、小筒に替わり主に用いられる様になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The protective equipments for hinawaju, such as Tosei-gusoku (armor), taketaba (a bamboo shield against firearms) and so on, spread and as a result, it was mainly used instead of a small barrel.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The protective equipment for defense against hinawaju, such as Tosei-gusoku (armor), taketaba (a bamboo shield against firearms) and so on, spread and as a result, it was mainly used instead of a small barrel.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The protective equipment for defense against hinawaju, such as Tosei-gusoku (armor), taketaba (a bamboo shield against firearms) and so on, spread and as a result, it was mainly used instead of a small barrel.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="120">
<j>士筒（さむらいづつ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Samurai barrel</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Samurai barrel</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Samurai barrel</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="121">
<j>弾丸重量が十匁程度のものを指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It refers to the one whose weight is about ten monme.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It refers to one with a weight of about ten monme.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It refers to one with a weight of about ten monme.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="122">
<j>威力は絶大だがあまりにも高価で扱いが難しい為、十分な鍛錬と財力を持つ侍のみが用いる事ができた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was extremely powerful and expensive and the handling was difficult and thus only those who had trained fully and had a financial power could use it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was extremely powerful and expensive and handling was difficult and thus only those who had trained fully and had the financial power could use it.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was extremely powerful, but since it was too expensive and too difficult to handle, only those who had trained fully and had the financial power could use it.</e>
<cmt>一部翻訳を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="123">
<j>彼らはこの侍筒を武家奉公人に持たせ、必要に応じて用いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They made buke hokonin (servant for a samura family) have a samurai barrel and if necessary, used it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They made buke hokonin (servant for a samura family) have a samurai barrel and if necessary, used it.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They made buke hokonin (servant for a samurai family) have a samurai barrel and if necessary, used it.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="124">
<j>短筒</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Short barrel</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Short barrel</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Short barrel</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="125">
<j>馬上筒とも言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was also called horseback barrel.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was also called horseback barrel.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was also called horseback barrel.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="126">
<j>馬上での使用や護身用に用いられていたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said to have been used on horseback or for self-defense.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said to have been used on horseback or for self-defense.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said to have been used on horseback or for self-defense.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="127">
<j>銃身が短く、片手で扱える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The gun barrel is short and can be handled with one hand.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The gun barrel was short and it could be handled with one hand.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The gun barrel was short and it could be handled with one hand.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="128">
<j>ヨーロッパの騎兵のピストルに近い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is similar to the gun of European horse soldiers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is similar to the gun used by European horse soldiers.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is similar to the gun used by European horse soldiers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="129">
<j>大鉄砲</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Odeppo (Japanese artillery)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Odeppo (Japanese artillery)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Odeppo (Japanese artillery)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="130">
<j>抱え大筒とも言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called a Japanese hand culverin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also called a Japanese hand culverin.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also called a Japanese hand culverin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="131">
<j>二十匁以上の弾丸重量を有するもので百匁クラスのものも存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The weight of a bullet is more than twenty monme and the one with more than one hundred monme exists.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The weight of the bullet is more than twenty monme and there was one with more than one hundred monme that existed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The weight of the bullet is more than 20 monme and there was one with more than 100 monme that existed.</e>
<cmt>アラビア数字に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="132">
<j>通常の弾丸の他、火矢などを用いて攻城戦・海戦で構造物を破壊する為に用いられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to usual bullets, using arrow with fire and so on, it was used to destroy structural objects in siege warfare and naval battle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to usual bullets, shooting fire arrows, and so on, they were used to destroy structural objects in siege warfare and naval battles.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to usual bullets, it was used to shoot fire arrows and so on to destroy structural objects in siege warfare and naval battles.</e>
<cmt>一部翻訳を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="133">
<j>差火点火式･地上設置型である通常の大筒と異なり、銃床とカラクリを用いた火縄銃の体裁を持つものを指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Different from a usual big barrel which is ignited by adding fire and positioned on the ground, it refers to the one which has a form of hinawaju using the gunstock and karakuri (mechanism).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Different from a usual big barrel which is ignited by adding fire and positioned on the ground, it refers to one in the form of hinawaju using the gunstock and karakuri (mechanism).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Different from a usual big barrel which is ignited by adding fire and positioned on the ground, it refers to one in the form of hinawaju using the gunstock and karakuri (mechanism).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="134">
<j>言うまでもなく反動は強烈であり、射手は射撃時に自ら転がる事で反動を吸収する程である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It goes without saying that the recoil is very strong and when shooting the shooter has to roll over by himself to absorb the recoil.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It goes without saying that the recoil is very strong and when firing the shooter has to roll over to absorb the recoil.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It goes without saying that the recoil is very strong; when firing, the shooter has to roll over to absorb the recoil.</e>
<cmt>読みやすくするためにカンマを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="135">
<j>そのため確実を期す場合は、地面に据えて擲弾筒のように撃ったり、射台に据えて用いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, to ensure the shooting, they shot by putting it on the ground like a grenade launcher or used it by putting it on the firing platform.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, to ensure the shooting, they shot by settting it up on the ground like a grenade launcher or used it by mounting it on a firing platform.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, to ensure the shooting, they shot by setting it up on the ground like a grenade launcher or used it by mounting it on a firing platform.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>製作地・流派による分類</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The classification by the production area and the school</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Classification by production area and the school</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Classification by production area and the school</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="136">
<j>主な違いとして、銃身の外形（丸、角筒）、肉厚、長さ、銃床の形状、カラクリ（内外カラクリ）、目当などがあげられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Main differences are the outer form of gun barrel (round, horn tube), the thickness, the length, the form of gunstock, the karakuri (inside and outside of karakuri), the foresight and so on.</e>
<cmt>「目当」ですが、「照星」のことと取り、foresightとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Main differences were the outer form of the gun barrel (round, horn tube), the thickness, the length, the form of gunstock, the karakuri (inside and outside of karakuri), the foresight and so on.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Main differences were the outer form of the gun barrel (round, horn tube), the thickness, the length, the form of gunstock, the karakuri (inside and outside of karakuri), the foresight and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="137">
<j>以下に記するもの以外にも多数あり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are many types except for the followings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are many types except for the following.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are many types except for the following.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="138">
<j>国友筒</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kunitomo tsutsu (gun made in Kunitomo)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kunitomo tsutsu (gun made in Kunitomo)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kunitomo tsutsu (gun made in Kunitomo)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="139">
<j>堺筒</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sakai gun (matchlock gun made in Sakai)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sakai gun (matchlock gun made in Sakai)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sakai tsutsu (matchlock gun made in Sakai)</e>
<cmt>他が「tsutsu」となっているので、これも「tsutsu」として統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="140">
<j>日野筒</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hino tsutsu (a gun made in Hino)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hino tsutsu (a gun made in Hino)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hino tsutsu (a gun made in Hino)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="141">
<j>薩摩筒</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Satsuma tsutsu (gun made in Satsuma)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Satsuma tsutsu (gun made in Satsuma)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Satsuma tsutsu (gun made in Satsuma)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="142">
<j>以上、製作地名を冠したもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The above-mentioned are the ones with the name of production area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The above-mentioned are thoes that go by the name of the production area.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The above-mentioned are those that go by the name of the production area.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="143">
<j>南蛮筒：海外より伝来した火縄銃を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imported matchlock gun: it refers to a hinawaju introduced from abroad.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imported matchlock gun: it refers to a hinawaju introduced from abroad.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imported matchlock gun: It refers to a hinawaju introduced from abroad.</e>
<cmt>コロンの後を大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="144">
<j>それを手本に国内で製造されたものは異風筒と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Copying it, they made the guns domestically, which were called foreign style matchlock gun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Copying it, they made the guns domestically, which were called foreign style matchlock guns.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Copying it, they made the guns domestically, which were called foreign style matchlock guns.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="145">
<j>稲富筒：稲富祐直の仕様に基づいて製作された鉄砲。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Inatomi gun: it refers to the guns which were made on the basis of specification by Sukenao INATOMI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Inatomi gun: it refers to guns made on the basis of specifications provided by Sukenao INATOMI.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Inatomi gun: It refers to guns made on the basis of specifications provided by Sukenao INATOMI.</e>
<cmt>コロンの後を大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="146">
<j>関流筒：関流砲術参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seki style gun: See Seki&apos;s school of gunnery.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seki style gun: See Seki&apos;s school of gunnery.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seki style gun: See Seki&apos;s school of gunnery.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>デモンストレーション</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Demonstration</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Demonstration</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Demonstration</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="147">
<j>日本各地に鉄砲隊と称しイベント時に火縄銃で空砲をうつ団体が多数できた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many groups appeared in various parts of Japan, which shot blanks with a hinawaju in the event, calling themselves musket troops.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many groups appeared in various parts of Japan, that shot blanks using a hinawaju in the event, calling themselves musket troops.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many groups appeared in various parts of Japan, that shot blanks using a hinawaju in the event, calling themselves musket troops.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="148">
<j>これは伝承砲術によっているものであるが、日本では幕末明治維新期に兵制・武器の西欧化が急速に行われたため、流派の直接伝承はすべていったん途絶えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They did it following a traditional gunnery, but in Japan, during the Meiji Restoration, the military conscription and the weapons were rapidly westernized and thus all the direct handing down of school stopped.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They did it following traditional gunnery, but in Japan, during the Meiji Restoration, the military conscription and weapons were rapidly westernized and thus all the direct handing down of the school stopped.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They did it following traditional gunnery, but in Japan, during the Meiji Restoration, the military conscription and weapons were rapidly westernized and thus all the direct handing down of the school stopped.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="149">
<j>現存する流派は伝来した古文書などを解読して後世再興したものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The existing schools revived later by deciphering traditional ancient documents and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The existing schools were revived later by deciphering traditional ancient documents and so on.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The existing schools were revived later by deciphering traditional ancient documents and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="150">
<j>古式銃団体の性格は、大まかに以下の3種に分類できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The characteristics of ancient gun group is:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The characteristics of ancient gun group are:</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The characteristics of ancient gun group can be roughly divided into the following three kinds.</e>
<cmt>和文を補足し、英文もそれに応じて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="151">
<j>伝書などに準拠し純歴史学的に再興したもの（但し1、2の流派で明治以降も祭礼等で細々と伝承されたものもある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The one which revived in terms of pure historical studies, based on densho (books on the esoterica) and so on (however, even after the Meiji period, it was obscurely inherited in rites and festivals and so on of one or two schools).</e>
<cmt>冒頭のtheを大文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One that revived in terms of pure historical studies, based on densho (books on the esoterica) and so on (however, even after the Meiji period, it was obscurely inherited in rites and festivals and so on of one or two schools).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One that revived in terms of pure historical studies, based on densho (books on the esoterica) and so on (however, even after the Meiji period, it was obscurely inherited in rites and festivals and so on of one or two schools).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="152">
<j>地域に伝わった鉄炮衆などの由来に基づき地域の特色ある武術の再現として研究されたもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The one which was studied as a re-enactment of martial art characteristic of the region, based on the origin of the unit of gun fighters and so on.</e>
<cmt>冒頭のtheを大文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One which was studied for the purpose of re-enacting martial art characteristics of a region, based on the origin of the unit of gun fighters and so on.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One which was studied for the purpose of re-enacting martial art characteristics of a region, based on the origin of the unit of gun fighters and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="153">
<j>それ以外のもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And the other ones.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And othes.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And others.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="14">
<tit>
<j>火縄銃射撃競技</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The target shooting with hinawaju</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Target shooting with hinawaju</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Target shooting with hinawaju</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="154">
<j>ヨーロッパや北アメリカなどでは盛んに火縄銃も含むマズルローダー射撃競技（前装銃射撃競技）がおこなわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Europe and North America and so on, the muzzle loader match, including a hinawaju, is actively held (the players are sent to the world championship and the Pan-Pacific Championship from Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Europe and North America and so on, muzzle loader matches, including a hinawaju, are actively held (the players are sent to the world championship and the Pan-Pacific Championship from Japan).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Europe and North America and so on, muzzle loader matches, including a hinawaju, are actively held.</e>
<cmt>括弧内にピリオドを追加しました。一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="155">
<j>（日本からも世界選手権と環太平洋選手権大会に選手を派遣している）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(The players are sent to the world championship and the Pan-Pacific Championship from Japan.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="156">
<j>日本国内では日本ライフル射撃協会傘下に日本前装銃射撃連盟があり、競技が行なわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan there is Muzzle Loaders&apos; Shooting Association of Japan under National Rifle Association of Japan, and the target shooting competition is held.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan there is Muzzle Loaders&apos; Shooting Association of Japan under National Rifle Association of Japan, and a target shooting competition is held.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan there is Muzzle Loaders&apos; Shooting Association of Japan under National Rifle Association of Japan, and a target shooting competition is held.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="157">
<j>ただし銃砲刀剣類所持等取締法や火薬類取締法などに基づく各種規制があるため、競技人口は極めて少ない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as there are various regulations based on the Firearm and Sword Control Law or the Explosives Control Law and so on, the population of players is very few.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as there are various regulations based on the Firearm and Sword Control Law or the Explosives Control Law and so on, the population of gun owners is very few.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as there are various regulations based on the Firearm and Sword Control Law or the Explosives Control Law and so on, the population of players is very small.</e>
<cmt>一部翻訳を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="158">
<j>だが、日本製の火縄銃は極めて高精度にできているため、そんな環境ながら日本の選手は国際大会で上位入賞することが多く、欧米の多くの選手も火縄銃種目では日本製の火縄銃を使って参加している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, hinawajyu made in Japan has a high-precision and thus, though the number of players is few, Japanese players often achieve a high ranking of international competition and many players from Europe and America also use hinawaju made in Japan in the hinawaju event.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, hinawajyu made in Japan has a high-precision and thus, though the number of players is few, Japanese players often achieve a high ranking in international competition and many players from Europe and America also use hinawaju made in Japan in the hinawaju event.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, hinawaju made in Japan has a high-precision and thus, although the number of players is small, Japanese players often achieve a high ranking in international competition and many players from Europe and America also use hinawaju made in Japan in the hinawaju event.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="159">
<j>アジア地域で国際前装銃連盟に加盟しているのは日本のみである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Asia region it is only Japan which joins the international muzzle loader association.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Asian region, only Japan joins the international muzzle loader association.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Asian region, only Japan joins the international muzzle loader association.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="160">
<j>日本でおこなわれる競技は、国際ルールと同じ射距離50メートルで「日本公式種子島標的（黒点径40cm）」を使用する「長筒立射」「長筒膝射」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The match in Japan uses &quot;Japan official Tanegashima target (the target diameter is 40 cm)&quot; whose shooting distance is 50 meters, same as that of international rule, which is called &quot;standing shooting with a long arm gun,&quot; &quot;kneeling shooting with a long tube.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The match in Japan uses &quot;Japan official Tanegashima target (the target diameter is fourty cm)&quot; whose shooting distance is fifty meters, same as international rules, which is called &quot;standing shooting with a long arm gun,&quot; &quot;kneeling shooting with a long tube.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The match in Japan uses &apos;Japan official Tanegashima target (the target diameter is 40 cm)&apos; whose shooting distance is 50 meters, same as international rules, which is called &apos;standing shooting with a long arm gun,&apos; &apos;kneeling shooting with a long barrel.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="161">
<j>同標的で十匁玉筒（10匁の重さの弾を使用する銃）を使用する「侍筒」（自由姿勢）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the same target, ten monme bullet tube (the gun which uses the bullet whose weight is ten monme) is used (samurai barrel, free style).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the same target, a ten monme bullet tube (gun using a bullet with the weight of ten monme) is used (samurai barrel, free style).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the same target, a ten monme bullet tube (gun using a bullet with the weight of ten monme) is used for &apos;samurai barrel&apos; (free style).</e>
<cmt>一部翻訳を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="162">
<j>「フリーピストル標的」を使用し50メートルで前装銃であれば銃種を問わない（火縄銃でなくても使用できる）「ベッテリー」も休止しているが規定上は存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Free pistol target&quot; is used and the kinds of guns do not matter if a muzzle loader is used for 50 meters (it is OK if a hinawaju is not used) and &quot;battery&quot; is halted but in the regulation it still exists (however, it has been held only in the competition in Chiba Prefecture Shooting Range).</e>
<cmt>「ベッテリー」が不明で、batteryとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Free pistol target&quot; is used and regarding the kinds of guns, it does not matter if a muzzle loader is used for fifty meters (it is OK if a hinawaju is not used) and &quot;battery&quot; is halted, but in the regulations, it still exists (however, it has been held only during competition at the Chiba Prefecture Shooting Range).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A match called &apos;battery,&apos; in which &apos;free pistol target&apos; is used and the kinds of guns do not matter as long as they are muzzle loaders (guns other than hinawaju can also be used) and the shooting distance is 50 meters, has been halted but in the regulations, it still exists.</e>
<cmt>一部翻訳を修正しました。一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="163">
<j>（但し、2005年より千葉県ライフル射場で開催される競技会に限って行っている）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(However, it has been held only during competition at the Chiba Prefecture Shooting Range.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="164">
<j>他に同標的で25メートル、短筒を片手撃ちで競う「短筒」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally there is a &quot;short barrel&quot; where the players compete with one-hand shooting of short barrel, with the same target and the shooting distance of 25 meters.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally there is a &quot;short barrel&quot; where shooters compete with one-hand shooting of a short barrel, using the same target at a shooting distance of twenty-five meters.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally there is a &apos;short barrel&apos; where shooters compete shooting a short barrel with one-hand, using the same target at a shooting distance of 25 meters.</e>
<cmt>一部翻訳を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="15">
<tit>
<j>日本独自の競技</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The matches unique to Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Matches unique to Japan</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Matches unique to Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="165">
<j>日本独自の競技として、古式に則った、8寸角板に4寸黒丸の「和的（江戸時代規格の標的）」で27メートル（江戸時代は15間）の距離で競う「古式勝ち抜き」及び、5分間に10発撃つ「早撃ち」がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the matches unique to Japan, which follows the tradition, there is a &quot;traditional tournament&quot; where the players compete using &quot;Japanese Target (a target of the Edo period standard)&quot; of 8 sun square board (1 sun = 3.03 cm) and 4 sun round black target and the shooting distance is 27 meters (15 ken during the Edo period, 1 ken = about 1.8 meters) and &quot;rapid-fire shooting&quot; where 10 bullets are shot in five minutes.</e>
<cmt>「黒丸」をround black targetとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regarding matches unique to Japan, following tradition, there is a &quot;traditional tournament&quot; where the players compete using &quot;Japanese Targets (a standard target of the Edo period)&quot; of eight sun square board (1 sun = 3.03 cm) and four sun round black target and the shooting distance is twenty-severn meters (fifteen ken during the Edo period, 1 ken = about 1.8 meters) and &quot;rapid-fire shooting&quot; where ten bullets are shot in five minutes.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regarding matches unique to Japan, following tradition, there is a &apos;traditional tournament&apos; where the players compete using &apos;Japanese Targets (a standard target of the Edo period)&apos; of eight sun square board (1 sun = 3.03 cm) with a four sun round black target, and the shooting distance is 27 meters (15 ken during the Edo period, 1 ken = about 1.8 meters); also there is a &apos;rapid-fire shooting&apos; where ten bullets are shot in five minutes.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="166">
<j>銃刀法に定める範囲の古式銃の所持は、現代銃と異なり属人的な免許・許可ではなく、属物的な登録制で、登録は都道府県教育委員会の所管（かつては文化財保護委員会であった）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As stipulated in the Firearm and Sword Control Law, possession of an ancient guns is not allowed and licensed to an individual like a modern gun, but that of an ancient gun is registered with a gun itself and the registration is under the jurisdiction of prefectural boards of education (formerly, under the jurisdiction of Commission for Protection of Cultural Properties).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As stipulated in the Firearm and Sword Control Law, possession of aancient guns generally is not allowed and must be licensed to an individual like a modern gun, but for an ancient gun, the gun is registered and registration comes under the jurisdiction of prefectural boards of education (formerly, under the jurisdiction of the Commission for the Protection of Cultural Properties).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As stipulated in the Firearm and Sword Control Law, in order to possess modern guns, he or she has to be licensed or permitted to do so, while in order to possess ancient guns, the guns themselves must be registered, which is under the jurisdiction of prefectural boards of education (formerly, under the jurisdiction of the Commission for the Protection of Cultural Properties).</e>
<cmt>全体的に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="167">
<j>登録は日本刀などと同じく銃に対してなされ、登録を受けた銃器は誰でも所持・所有できるが、実際に実弾・空包の発砲及び火薬の入手所持消費に関しては、その都度（実弾射撃を許可された者は、火薬購入については1年間、また消費は6ヶ月間限定の）所轄の警察署を通じて公安委員会の別途の許可を受ける必要がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The registration is for a gun itself like a Japanese sword and the registered gun can be possessed by anyone, but in fact, concerning the shooting of live cartridge and blank cartridge, and the purchase, possession and consumption of gunpowder, every time you need to get permission from National Public Safety Commission through the police under jurisdiction (those who get permission of live firing must purchase gunpowder within one year and consume it within six months).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The registration is for the gun, like with a Japanese sword, and a registered gun can be possessed by anyone, but in fact, concerning the shooting of live cartridges and blank cartridges, and the purchase, possession and consumption of gunpowder, every time you need to get permission from National Public Safety Commission through the police under jurisdiction (those who get permission to fire live must purchase gunpowder within one year and consume it within six months).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The registration is for the gun, like with a Japanese sword, and a registered gun can be possessed by anyone, but in fact, concerning the shooting of live cartridges and blank cartridges, and the purchase, possession and consumption of gunpowder, every time you need to get permission from National Public Safety Commission through the police under jurisdiction (those who get permission to fire live must purchase gunpowder within one year and consume it within six months).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="168">
<j>実弾射撃は指定された射撃場でしか認められない、2005年現在、公営射撃場としては神奈川県伊勢原市の県営伊勢原射撃場、千葉市若葉区の千葉県総合スポーツセンター射撃場、和歌山県海南市の和歌山県営射場、の以上3ヶ所（但し伊勢原射撃場は工事中で使用できない、また他にも私立の射場で可能な所がある）で認められている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Live firing is allowed only in the registered shooting galleys and as of 2005, as public shooting galleys, there are the three registered ones such as Kanagawa Prefectural Isehara Shooting Range in Isehara city, Kanagawa prefecture, Chiba Prefecture General Sports Center shooting galley in Chiba city Wakaba ward and Wakayama Prefecture Shooting Range in Kainan city, Wakayama prefecture (however, Isehara Shooting Range is under construction and can not be used, and in addition, there are private shooting galleys where live firings are possible).</e>
<cmt>「2005年現在」とあり、2005年はすでに過去ですが、和文の時制は現在形であるため、それに合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Live firing is allowed only in registered shooting galleries and as of 2005, as public shooting galleries, there are three registered ones such as the Kanagawa Prefectural Isehara Shooting Range in Isehara city, Kanagawa prefecture, Chiba Prefecture General Sports Center shooting galley in Chiba city Wakaba ward and Wakayama Prefecture Shooting Range in Kainan city, Wakayama prefecture (however, the Isehara Shooting Range is under construction and currently can not be used, and in addition, there are private shooting galleries where live firing is possible).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Live firing is allowed only in registered shooting galleries and as of 2005, as public shooting galleries, there are three registered ones such as the Kanagawa Prefectural Isehara Shooting Range in Isehara City, Kanagawa Prefecture, Chiba Prefecture General Sports Center shooting galley in Wakaba Ward, Chiba City and Wakayama Prefecture Shooting Range in Kainan City, Wakayama Prefecture (however, the Isehara Shooting Range is under construction and currently can not be used, and in addition, there are private shooting galleries where live firing is possible).</e>
<cmt>City, Prefecture を大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="169">
<j>古式銃とは主に前装式銃砲のことを言うが、初期の後装銃も佐賀藩の主力銃であったスペンサー銃（のちにウインチェスター銃の祖形となった）をはじめ、普仏戦争の主要銃であったシャスポー銃（後に村田式の開発の淵源となった）やドライゼ銃（ツンナール）など類種のものも相当数輸入されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An ancient gun mainly refers to a muzzle loader, but a large number of several kinds of guns were imported, such as an early breech loader, Spencer Carbine which was the main force gun of Saga clan (later it became the original form of Winchester rifle), Chassepot rifle which was the main force gun in the Franco-Prussian War (later it became the base for the development of Murata-style gun), Dreyse needle-gun (Zundnadel gun) and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An ancient gun mainly refers to a muzzle loader, but a large number of several kinds of guns were imported, such as an early breech loader, Spencer Carbine which was the main force gun of the Saga clan (later it became the original form of Winchester rifle), Chassepot rifle which was the main force gun in the Franco-Prussian War (later it became the basis for the development of the Murata-style gun), Dreyse needle-gun (Zundnadel gun) and so on.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An ancient gun mainly refers to a muzzle loader, but a large number of several kinds of guns were imported, such as an early breech loader, Spencer Carbine which was the main force gun of the Saga clan (later it became the original form of Winchester rifle), Chassepot rifle which was the main force gun in the Franco-Prussian War (later it became the basis for the development of the Murata-style gun), Dreyse needle-gun (Zundnadel gun) and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="170">
<j>ただこれらは維新後に訓練銃などとして使用されたり、外国に売却されたりして、現在国内残存数は比較的少ない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, these were used as the guns for training and so on after Meiji Restoration or were sold to foreign countries and thus at present there remains a relatively few in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, these were used for training after the Meiji Restoration or were sold to foreign countries and thus at present there remains relatively few in Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, these were used for training after the Meiji Restoration or were sold to foreign countries and thus at present there remains relatively few in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="171">
<j>日本の法律では現在のところ、古式銃とは1867年の時点で国内に存在したことが個別に証明できた国産または外国製の歴史遺物銃器の実物である、ということになっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japanese law at present, an ancient gun refers to the domestically-produced one or the real one which is foreign-produced historical relic, which are individually proved to have existed in Japan as of 1867 (thus, the replica, even though made faithfully to the real one, is not admitted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japanese law at present, an ancient gun refers to a domestically-produced one or a real foreign-produced historical relic, which have been individually proven to have existed in Japan as of 1867 (thus, the replica, even though made faithfully to the real one, is not allowed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japanese law at present, an ancient gun refers to a domestically-produced one or a real foreign-produced historical relic, which have been individually proven to have existed in Japan as of 1867.</e>
<cmt>。で終わるように、和文のつながりを一部修正しました。それに応じ、英文も修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="172">
<j>（したがって実物に忠実に作られたものであってもレプリカは認められないが、これは古式銃の登録制度が歴史史料及びその美術価値の保存を目的としていて、射撃に使用することを想定して制定されたものでないことによる。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Thus, the replica, even though made faithfully to the real one, is not allowed; this is because the registration system for ancient guns is for the purpose of the preservation of historical materials and artistic values, and is not established for shooting use.)</e>
<cmt>。で終わるように、和文のつながりを一部修正しました。それに応じ、英文も修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="173">
<j>ただし真正の古式銃であっても明治以後に新式又は現代の弾薬が使用できるように改造されたもの、あるいは現用の弾薬（装弾）が使用できる可能性のあるもの（もっとも顕著な例は坂本龍馬が使用したと言われるSW・Mk1、Mk2リボルバー）などは（現代銃に準ずる機能を有するもの）として登録審査時に排除され、したがって所有できないものがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, if it is a genuine ancient gun but is altered to be able to use a new-type or modern ammunition after the Meiji period or if it can use an actually-used ammunition (the most prominent one is, for example, SW Mk1 or Mk2 of revolver, which is said to have been used by Ryoma SAKAMOTO), it is omitted at the judgment of registration and thus can not be owned (because it has functions of a modern gun).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, if it is a genuine ancient gun, but is altered to be able to use a new-type or modern ammunition after the Meiji period or if it can use actually-used ammunition (the most prominent one is, for example, SW Mk1 or Mk2 revolver, which is said to have been used by Ryoma SAKAMOTO), it will be omitted at the judgment for registration and thus can not be owned (because it can function as a modern gun).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, if it is a genuine ancient gun, but is altered to be able to use a new-type or modern ammunition after the Meiji period or if it can use actually-used ammunition (the most prominent one is, for example, SW Mk1 or Mk2 revolver, which is said to have been used by Ryoma SAKAMOTO), it will be omitted at the judgment for registration and thus can not be owned (because it can function as a modern gun).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="174">
<j>真正の歴史遺物の国産火縄銃であれば、たとえ外国から里帰りしたものであってもほとんどはそれらの問題は無い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When it is a domestically produced hinawajyu of genuine historical relic, it has mostly no problem, even if it is brought from abroad.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When it is a domestically produced hinawajyu, a genuine historical relic, it has mostly no problem, even if it is brought from abroad.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When it is a domestically produced hinawaju, a genuine historical relic, it has mostly no problem, even if it is brought from abroad.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="175">
<j>競技用として、また空包用として使用されているものは国産火縄銃がほとんどで、すべて歴史遺物に限られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ones which are used for competition or blank cartridge are mostly domestically produced hinawaju and are limited to historical relics.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those used for competition or for firing blank cartridges are mostly domestically produced hinawaju and are limited to historical relics.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those used for competition or for firing blank cartridges are mostly domestically produced hinawaju and are limited to historical relics.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="16">
<tit>
<j>慣用句</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Proverbs</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Proverbs</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Proverbs</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="17">
<tit>
<j>火蓋を切る</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hibuta wo kiru (to cut the pan cover).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hibuta wo kiru (to cut the pan cover).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hibuta wo kiru (to cut the pan cover).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="176">
<j>「火蓋を切る」は、物事を開始するという意味で用いられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;To cut the pan cover&quot; means that you start (an argument, a battle and so on).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;To cut the pan cover&quot; means that you start (an argument, a battle and so on).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The expression &apos;hibuta wo kiru&apos; means that you start something (such as an argument, a battle and so on).</e>
<cmt>翻訳を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="177">
<j>由来には以下の説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The origins are as follow.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The origins are as follow.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The origins are as follows.</e>
<cmt>翻訳を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="178">
<j>射撃を始めるにあたって、火蓋を切る（あける）ことから。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That is because you cut (or open) the pan cover at the start of shooting.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That is because you cut (or open) the pan cover at the start of shooting.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That you cut (or open) the pan cover at the start of shooting.</e>
<cmt>翻訳を一部削除補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="179">
<j>装填したあと火蓋を縛っておいたこよりを戦闘の際に切る動作に由来する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That is because, when shooting, you cut the spill tied to the pan cover after loading.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That is because, when shooting, you cut the spill tied to the pan cover after loading.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That, when shooting, you cut the spill tied to the pan cover after loading.</e>
<cmt>翻訳を一部削除補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="18">
<tit>
<j>見当をつける、目当てがある</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kentou (guide marks) wo tsukeru (to put a guide mark), meate (end, intention) ga aru (to have an end).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kentou (guide marks) wo tsukeru (to put a guide mark), meate (end, intention) ga aru (to have an end).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kento wo tsukeru (to put a guide mark), meate ga aru (to have an end)</e>
<cmt>表現を統一しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="180">
<j>照準器のうち照門や照尺の事を見当と言い、照星を（さきのめあて）照門を（まえのめあて）と呼んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A rear sight or gun sight in the sighting device were called kentou, a front sight sakinomeate and a rear sight maenomeate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A rear sight or gun sight on the sights were called kento, a front sight sakinomeate and a rear sight maenomeate.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A rear sight or back sight on the gun sights were called &quot;kento,&quot; a front sight &quot;saki no meate&quot; and a rear sight &quot;mae no meate.&quot;</e>
<cmt>翻訳を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="181">
<j>「見当をつける」は、位置を見極めるという意味で用いられ、照準を定める動作から、位置を見極めることにひろがったと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kentou wo tsukeru&quot; is used to mean that you detect the position and from the action of fixing the sighting device, it came to meant that you detect the position.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kentou wo tsukeru&quot; is used to mean that you detect the position and from the action of sighting in, it came to meant that you have detected the position.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The expression &apos;kento wo tsukeru&apos; is used to mean that you detect the position, and from the action of sighting in, it came to mean that you have detected the position.</e>
<cmt>翻訳を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="182">
<j>早い時期から木版印刷の複数の彫板の位置併せのマークを（見当）と呼ぶことに援用され、こちらの方が広く知られることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From an early time, a mark for positioning of several wood blocks of wood block printing is called &quot;kentou&quot; and the word came to spread more widely.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From an early time, a mark for positioning of several wood blocks of wood block printing was called &quot;kentou&quot; and the word spread widely.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From an early time, a mark for positioning of several wood blocks of wood block printing was called &quot;kento&quot; and this spread more widely.</e>
<cmt>翻訳を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="183">
<j>「目当てがある」は、心積もりがあるという意味で用いられ、照準を合わせることで的に当たる期待、獲物に当たる期待が生じることから、期待できる状態を（目当てがある）（あてがある）と称する使われ方にひろがったと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Meate ga aru&apos; (to have an end) is used to mean that you have an end or intention because fixing the sighting device gives rise to the expectation of hitting the target or prey and the state of expectation is called &quot;meate ga aru or &quot;ate ga aru&apos; and such uses are thought to have spread.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Meate ga aru&apos; (to have an end) is used to mean that you have an end or intention because fixing your sights gives rise to the expectation of hitting the target or prey and the state of expectation is called &quot;meate ga aru or &quot;ate ga aru&apos; and such uses are thought to have spread.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The expression &apos;meate ga aru&apos; is used to mean that you have an end or intention because fixing your sights gives rise to the expectation of hitting the target or prey, and the state of expectation is called &quot;meate ga aru&quot; or &quot;ate ga aru&apos;&quot; and such uses are thought to have spread.</e>
<cmt>翻訳を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="184">
<j>「見当違い・見当はずれ・見当がつかない」も同義の否定的状態を示したものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kentou chigai, kentou hazure and kentou ga tsukanai&apos; refer to the negative state of the same meaning.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kentou chigai, kentou hazure and kentou ga tsukanai&apos; refer to the negative state of the same meaning.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Expressions such as &apos;kento chigai (wrong guess), kento hazure (out of register) and kento ga tsukanai (to have no clue)&apos; refer to the negative state of the same meaning.</e>
<cmt>英語の補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="19">
<tit>
<j>目星をつける、図星(ずぼし)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Meboshi wo tsukeru&quot; (to mark) and &quot;zuboshi&quot; (lucky guess)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Meboshi wo tsukeru&quot; (to mark) and &quot;zuboshi&quot; (lucky guess)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meboshi wo tsukeru (to mark down), Zuboshi (lucky guess)</e>
<cmt>英語の補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="185">
<j>｢星｣は我が国においては標識としての黒点の意味がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Hoshi&quot; has a meaning of black point as a target in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Hoshi&quot; means black point as a target in Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The word &apos;hoshi&apos; means black point as a target in Japan.</e>
<cmt>翻訳を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="186">
<j>江戸期以降火縄銃の射的に使用された木製の標的板の中央の黒点を「星」と呼ぶ習慣があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Edo period the central black point of a wooden target board used for target practice of hinawaju was called &quot;hoshi&quot; as a custom.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Edo period the central black point of a wooden target board used for target practice of hinawaju was called &quot;hoshi&quot; as a custom.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Edo period the central black point of a wooden target board used for target practice of hinawaju was called &apos;hoshi&apos; as a custom.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="187">
<j>また碁盤・将棋盤の位置見当のための黒点も「星」と呼ばれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The black point for positioning in Go board and Shogi board is also called &quot;hoshi.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The black point for positioning on a Go board and Shogi board is also called &quot;hoshi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The black point for positioning on a Go board and Shogi board is also called &apos;hoshi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="188">
<j>「目星をつける」とは目視して中心となる事物を判別することで、標的の「星」を目視・確認する動作から来ている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Meboshi wo tsukeru&apos; refers to a determination of the central object by visual inspection and it comes from the action of visually inspecting and confirming the target &quot;hoshi.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Meboshi wo tsukeru&apos; refers to a determination of the central object by visual inspection and it comes from the action of visually inspecting and confirming the target &quot;hoshi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The expression &apos;meboshi wo tsukeru&apos; refers to a determination of the central object by visual inspection and it comes from the action of visually inspecting and confirming the target &apos;hoshi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="189">
<j>「めぼしい」という形容詞もまたこれが由来である説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One theory says that the adjective &quot;meboshi&quot; comes from this.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One theory says that the adjective &quot;meboshi&quot; comes from this.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One theory says that the adjective &apos;meboshii&apos; (notable, distinguishable) comes from this.</e>
<cmt>翻訳を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="190">
<j>「図星」とは「星を正確に指す」意味でこれも射的から生じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Zuboshi&quot; means &quot;to point hoshi exactly&quot; and it also comes from target practice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Zuboshi&quot; means &quot;to point hoshi precisely&quot; and it also comes from target practice.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term &apos;zuboshi&apos; means &quot;to point hoshi precisely&quot; and it also comes from target practice.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="191">
<j>警察用語に「ホシ＝容疑者」と言う隠語がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the police term, there is a slang &quot;hoshi = crime suspect.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In police terms, there is a slang &quot;hoshi = crime suspect.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In police terms, there is a slang &apos;hoshi = crime suspect.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="192">
<j>古い刑事用語で（目星）の上略語とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the old detective term it is considered as the abbreviation of &quot;meboshi&quot; and formerly usages such as &quot;hoshi wo tsukeru = to presume a crime suspect,&quot; &quot;hoshi ga tsuku = to substantiate a charge&quot; and so on existed (Cant Dictionary, Tokyodo Publishing Co., Ltd).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the old detective term it is considered as the abbreviation of &quot;meboshi&quot; and formerly usage such as &quot;hoshi wo tsukeru = to presume a crime suspect,&quot; &quot;hoshi ga tsuku = to substantiate a charge&quot; and so on existed (Cant Dictionary, Tokyodo Publishing Co., Ltd).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the old detective term it is considered as the abbreviation of &quot;meboshi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>和文を一部変更し、英文もそれに応じました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="193">
<j>古くには「ホシをつける＝容疑者を推定する。ホシがつく＝容疑が固まる」などの用法もあった（隠語辞典・東京堂出版）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Formerly, usage such as &apos;hoshi wo tsukeru = to presume a crime suspect, hoshi ga tsuku = to substantiate a charge&apos; and so on existed (Cant Dictionary, Tokyodo Publishing Co., Ltd).</e>
<cmt>和文を一部変更し、英文もそれに応じました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 月下薄氷(id:47743), Ypacaraí(id:11031), 0null0(id:582), Eskimbot(id:29676), ポテンシャル0(id:160803), HI(id:72996), PATMAN(id:145791), 0太郎(id:7375), Kamakura(id:472), ブレイズマン(id:183852), 日陰猫Joga(id:9749), Blowback(id:173308), Kanoe(id:17203), YukkeBot2(id:251491), KH－editor(id:125369), Takobou(id:10633), いろはにほへと(id:89648), Arsenia(id:265409), Nallimbot(id:230812), Yaky(id:22711), BOT-Superzerocool(id:65015), Escarbot(id:59151), Zwobot(id:23873), BodhisattvaBot(id:185411), Rusk(id:9895), SilvonenBot(id:190970), ＮｉＫｅ(id:7512), Chlewbot(id:33904), 火縄銃(id:185833), Alexbot(id:157199), NDR(id:5500), ウミユスリカ(id:9504), Riden(id:27573), Hotsuregua(id:99069), JAnDbot(id:66507), Suguri F(id:11127), Extrahitz(id:26245), 山本伊左夫(id:25977), Diagraph01(id:25878), 建長(id:119884), Gnsin(id:12351), Toto-tarou(id:16648), Kurz(id:1601), ジュリアン・ベイショア(id:180616), Jidane(id:86850), An-chan(id:14590), Rei-bot(id:94097), Loveless(id:129239), Nopira(id:29335), Jinzuu(id:60495), Izayohi(id:13095), ひゃっこ(id:187013), ととりん(id:31982), Law soma(id:45202), Sat.K(id:3751), Yanahan(id:2437), 章奴(id:50198), Tomomori(id:143748), 岩手(id:264283), Mikeneko(id:18205), Tanuki Z(id:612), VolkovBot(id:105371), FeZn(id:444), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), TaBOT-zerem(id:257085), Louperibot(id:128971), SieBot(id:126695), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>