<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>椿餅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsubaki-mochi (a rice cake stuffed with sweet bean paste and coated with camellia leaves)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsubaki-mochi (a rice cake stuffed with sweet bean paste and coated with camellia leaves)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsubaki-mochi (a rice cake stuffed with sweet bean paste and coated with camellia leaves)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>椿餅（つばいもち）は平安時代に、軽食代わりとして食べられた餅菓子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsubaki-mochi is a rice cake sweets eaten as a light meal in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>原文で読みに「つばいもち」とあります。用語集では「つばきもち」になっています。用語集どおり、つばきもちのほう採用しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsubaki-mochi is a rice cake sweets eaten as a light meal in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsubaki-mochi is a rice cake sweets eaten as a light meal in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>平安時代の菓子は唐菓子と言って中国伝来の揚菓子がほとんどであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sweets in the Heian period were mostly fried confectioneries called togashi or karagashi (Chinese sweets) came from China.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sweets in the Heian period were mostly fried confectioneries called togashi or karagashi (Chinese sweets) came from China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sweets in the Heian period were mostly fried confectioneries called togashi or karagashi (Chinese sweets) came from China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>桜餅のように団子を植物の葉で挟む形式などが珍しく、この椿餅は日本独自のものでないかと言う見解もあるが定かではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The style that a dumpling is wrapped with plant leaves like Sakuramochi (rice cake with bean jam wrapped in a preserved cherry leaf) is uncommon and there is an opinion that Tsubaki-mochi is unique to Japan, but this is not known exactly.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The style that dumplings wrapped with plant leaves like Sakuramochi (rice cake with bean jam wrapped in a preserved cherry leaf) is uncommon and there is an opinion that Tsubaki-mochi is unique to Japan, but this is not certain.</e>
<cmt>dumplings wrapped,know exactly→certain と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The style that dumplings wrapped with plant leaves like Sakuramochi (rice cake with bean jam wrapped in a preserved cherry leaf) is uncommon and there is an opinion that Tsubaki-mochi is unique to Japan, but this is not certain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>その説に従うなら、これが和菓子の起源である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If we obey this theory, this Tsubaki-mochi is the origin of Japanese confectionery.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If we stick to this theory, this Tsubaki-mochi is the origin of Japanese confectionery.</e>
<cmt>obey→stick to と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If we stick to this theory, this Tsubaki-mochi is the origin of Japanese confectionery.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>河海抄の記述によれば、もち米を乾燥させて臼でひいて作った餅粉（現在の道明寺粉）を甘葛の汁で練って団子のようにし、椿の葉で包んだもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the description in &quot;Kakai-sho Commentary,&quot; Tsubaki-mochi was something like a dumpling made from mochi-ko (rice cake flour) (present-day domyojiko (dried and granulated glutinous rice flour)) that was made by grinding dried glutinous rice with a mill-stone, kneaded with amazura (traditional sweetener commonly used in the past), and wrapped with camellia leaves.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the description in Kakai-sho Commentary, Tsubaki-mochi was something like a dumpling made from mochi-ko (rice cake flour, present-day domyojiko [dried and granulated glutinous rice flour]) that was made by grinding dried glutinous rice with a mill-stone, kneaded with amazura (traditional sweetener commonly used in the past), and wrapped with camellia leaves.</e>
<cmt>クォーツを削除しました。カッコの結合、カッコ内を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the description in Kakai-sho Commentary, Tsubaki-mochi was something like a dumpling made from mochi-ko (rice cake flour, present-day domyojiko [dried and granulated glutinous rice flour]) that was made by grinding dried glutinous rice with a mill-stone, kneaded with amazura (traditional sweetener commonly used in the past), and wrapped with camellia leaves.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="6">
<j>現代の菓子のように日常的な間食に用いる物ではなく、貴族の館で大規模な蹴鞠の会が催されたときに参加者に配られていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsubaki-mochi was not eaten as a light meal like present-day sweets, but it was distributed to participants to big events such as kemari (a game played by aristocrats in the Heian period) at noblemen&apos;s residences.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsubaki-mochi was not eaten as a light meal like present-day sweets, but it was distributed to participants to big events such as kemari (a game played by aristocrats in the Heian period) at noblemen&apos;s residences.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsubaki-mochi was not eaten as a light meal like present-day sweets, but it was distributed to participants to big events such as kemari (a game played by aristocrats in the Heian period) at noblemen&apos;s residences.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="7">
<j>「椿い餅、ナシ、柑子やうのものども、様々に筥の蓋どもにとりまぜつつあるを、若きひとびと、そぼれとり食ふ」（源氏物語若菜 (源氏物語)上）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Young people are eating confectionery like a Tsubai-mochi, a pear and a mandarin orange mixed on the lid of a bamboo basket, frolicking.&quot; (Wakana (Young green) chapter of &quot;The Tale of Genji&quot;) vol.1</e>
<cmt>歌では、「椿い餅」「つばいもち」となっています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Young people are eating confectionery like a Tsubai-mochi, a pear and a mandarin orange mixed on the lid of a bamboo basket, frolicking.&apos; (Wakana [Young green] chapter of The Tale of Genji) vol.1.</e>
<cmt>クォーツを修正しました。カッコ内を修正しました。ピリオドを挿入しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Young people are eating confectionery like a Tsubai-mochi, a pear and a mandarin orange mixed on the lid of a bamboo basket, frolicking.&apos; (Wakana [Young green] chapter of The Tale of Genji) vol.1.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 アレシンロ(id:170344), 蛮蔵(id:156457), Masyu(id:31065), Point136(id:211299), 桜井悠士(id:72420), 竃馬(id:102733), Lime citrus soda(id:28200), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>