<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>新嘗祭</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Niinamesai</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Niinamesai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Niinamesai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>新嘗祭（にいなめのまつり、にいなめさい、しんじょうさい）とは、11月23日に、天皇が五穀の新穀を天神地祇（てんじんちぎ）に勧め、また、自らもこれを食して、その年の収穫を感謝する祭儀。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Niinamesai (Niiname no matsuri, Shinjosai) is a ritual held on 23rd November each year at which the Emperor offers newly harvested rice to the deities of heaven and earth, eats it and expresses gratitude for harvest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Niinamesai (Niiname no matsuri, Shinjosai) is a ritual held each November 23rd, in which the Emperor offers newly harvested rice to the deities of heaven and earth, eats it and expresses gratitude for the harvest.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Niinamesai (Niiname no matsuri, Shinjosai) is a ritual held each November 23, in which the Emperor offers newly harvested rice to the deities of heaven and earth, eats it and expresses gratitude for the harvest.</e>
<cmt>23rd→ 23としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>宮中三殿の近くにある神嘉殿にて執り行われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is held at Shinka-den shrine located near to Kyuchu- sanden (the Three Shrines in the Imperial Court).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is held at Shinka-den Shrine, which is located near to Kyuchu-sanden (the Three Shrines in the Imperial Court).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is held at Shinka-den Shrine, which is located near to Kyuchu-sanden (the Three Shrines in the Imperial Court).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>秋に新穀を供えて神を祭る稲作儀礼である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a ritual of rice-farming held in autumn at which the Emperor worships deities with offering newly harvested rice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a ritual of rice farming held in the autumn, at which the Emperor worships deities by offering newly harvested rice.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a ritual of rice farming held in the autumn, at which the Emperor worships deities by offering newly harvested rice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>解説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Explanation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Description</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Description</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>飛鳥時代の皇極天皇の御代に始められたと伝えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has been passed down that Niinamesai was firstly held in the Asuka period when The Emperor Kogyoku was on the throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has been passed down that Niinamesai was first held in the Asuka period, during the reign of Emperor Kogyoku.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has been passed down that Niinamesai was first held in the Asuka period, during the reign of Emperor Kogyoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>一時中断されたが、元禄時代の東山天皇の在位中に復活した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though suspended for some time, it was revived in the Genroku era when the Emperor Higashiyama was on the throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though suspended for some time, it was revived in the Genroku era during the reign of Emperor Higashiyama.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although suspended for some time, it was revived in the Genroku era (1688 - 1703) during the reign of Emperor Higashiyama.</e>
<cmt>元禄時代　の補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>1873年の太陽暦採用以前は旧暦の11月 (旧暦)の2回目の卯の日に行われていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It had been held on the second U no hi (the day of rabbit) in November (lunar calendar) until the solar calendar was adopted in 1873.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prior to the adoption of the solar calendar in 1873, it was customarily held on the second U no hi (day of the rabbit) in November (lunar calendar).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prior to the adoption of the solar calendar in 1873, it was customarily held on the second U no hi (day of the rabbit) in November (lunar calendar).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>1873年から1947年までは祝祭日となっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The day of Niinamesai was a national holiday during the period from 1873 to 1947.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The day of Niinamesai was a national holiday during the period from 1873 to 1947.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The day of Niinamesai was a national holiday during the period from 1873 to 1947.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>戦後は、勤労感謝の日として国民の祝日となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the World war Ⅱ, November 23rd was designated as a national holiday named Labor Thanksgiving Day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After World War Ⅱ, November 23rd was designated as a national holiday called Labor Thanksgiving Day.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After World War Ⅱ, November 23 was designated as a national holiday called Labor Thanksgiving Day.</e>
<cmt>23rd→ 23としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="9">
<j>新嘗祭自体は伊勢神宮及びそれに連なる神社の祭儀となり、伊勢神宮には天皇の勅使が遣わされて、大御饌（おおみけ：神が召し上がる食事）を供える形式となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since then, Niinamesai itself has become the ritual of Ise-jingu Shrine and its related shrines and on the day, the Emperor&apos;s messenger is dispatched to Ise-jingu Shrine and offers Oomike (food for deities).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since then, Niinamesai has become a ritual of Ise-jingu Shrine and its related shrines, and on that day the Emperor&apos;s messenger is dispatched to Ise-jingu Shrine and offers Oomike (food for deities).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since then, Niinamesai has become a ritual of Ise-jingu Shrine and its related shrines, and on that day the Emperor&apos;s messenger is dispatched to Ise-jingu Shrine and offers Omike (food for deities).</e>
<cmt>Oomike→ Omike としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Higashi(id:8842), Rusk(id:9895), Izayohi(id:13095), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), Nnh(id:474), 彡(id:50363), N yotarou(id:60870), Stanislaus(id:1806), D.h(id:79056), Himazin(id:22034), 伏儀(id:142093), TAMA(id:25299), ウミユスリカ(id:9504), 弥(id:61590), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>