<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>削り節</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kezuribushi (shavings of dried fish):</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kezuribushi (shavings of dried fish):</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kezuribushi (shavings of dried fish):</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>削り節（けずりぶし）とは、カツオ、サバ、イワシ等の干し魚を薄く削ったものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term &quot;kezuribushi&quot; means shavings of dried flesh of bonitos, mackerels, sardines and other fishes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term &quot;kezuribushi&quot; means shavings of dried flesh of bonitos, mackerels, sardines, and other fishes.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term &quot;kezuribushi&quot; means shavings of dried flesh of bonitos, mackerels, sardines, and other fishes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>かつては、鰹節と呼び、広く流通していたが、かつお以外を原料とするものまで混じっていたことから、商品としての誤解を避けるため、「削り節」と呼ぶこととなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Formerly, it had been popular under the name of &quot;katsuobushi&quot; which meant literally &quot;shavings of dried bonino,&quot; but since the term used to include products of other fish than bonito, too, it became to be called &quot;kezuribushi&quot; (shavings of dried fish) in order to avoid misunderstanding caused by its name.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Formerly, it had been popular under the name of &quot;katsuobushi&quot; which meant literally &quot;shavings of dried bonino,&quot; but since the term was often used to include products of fish other than bonito, it became to be called &quot;kezuribushi&quot; (shavings of dried fish) in order to avoid misunderstanding caused by its name.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Formerly, it had been popular under the name of &quot;katsuobushi&quot; which meant literally &quot;shavings of dried bonito,&quot; but since the term was often used to include products of fish other than bonito, it became to be called &quot;kezuribushi&quot; (shavings of dried fish) in order to avoid misunderstanding caused by its name.</e>
<cmt>boninoをbonitoに変更しまた。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="3">
<j>カツオを原料とした削り節の小袋（かつおパックという商品名）が家庭で手軽に使える商品として、ヒット商品となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Small packets of shavings of dried bonito have become a hit under the brand name of &quot;katsuo pack&quot; (literally, packages of dried bonito&quot;) as a convenient item for use at home.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Small packets of shavings of dried bonito have become a hit under the brand name of &quot;katsuo pack&quot; (literally, packages of dried bonito&quot;) as a convenient item for use at home.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Small packets of shavings of dried bonito have become a hit under the brand name of &quot;katsuo pack&quot; (literally, packages of dried bonito) as a convenient item for use at home.</e>
<cmt>bonitoの後の&quot;を除去しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>また、テレビでの高名な調理師が番組で鰹ダシを取る際に、鍋に山のように入れるシーンが放映されたことなどから、一段と用いられるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Their popularity was further encouraged by a TV scene, where a well-known chef feeded a huge volume of shavings out of katsuo packs into a pan to make katsuo-dashi (bouillon of bonito flesh.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their popularity was further encouraged by a TV scene, where a well-known chef fed a huge volume of shavings out of katsuo packs into a pan to make katsuo-dashi (bouillon of bonito flesh.)</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Their popularity was further encouraged by a TV scene, where a well-known chef fed a huge volume of shavings out of katsuo packs into a pan to make katsuo-dashi (bouillon of bonito flesh.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="5">
<j>静岡県の一部では、イワシ削り節がよく用いられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a part of Shizuoka Prefecture, kezuribushi of iwashi (shavings of dried sardines) are popularly used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In a part of Shizuoka Prefecture, kezuribushi of iwashi (shavings of dried sardines) are popularly used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In a part of Shizuoka Prefecture, kezuribushi of iwashi (shavings of dried sardines) are popularly used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>コクがあり、安価なため大量に使用できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those made of sardines have plenty of body and are inexpensive to be used in great quantities.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those made of sardines have plenty of body and are inexpensive to use in great quantities.</e>
<cmt>verb form</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those made of sardines have plenty of body and are inexpensive to use in great quantities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Rusk(id:9895), Otoko2008(id:238382), NDR(id:5500), マクガイア(id:33346), To0923(id:55571), Nevylax(id:38464), ウェルワィ(id:15692), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>