<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>華道</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kado</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kado</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kado</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>華道（かどう）とは、草花や樹木などの植物材料を組み合わせて構成し、鑑賞する芸術であるいけばなに、芸道としての側面を加えたもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kado is a type of Ikebana, which is an art of formation by combining vegetable materials such as flowers and trees, with the aspect of Geido (accomplishments) added thereto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kado is a type of Ikebana, an art of combining plants such as flowers and trees, with the aspect of Geido (accomplishments).</e>
<cmt>wordy, redundancy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kado is a type of Ikebana, an art of combining plants such as flowers and trees, with the aspect of Geido (accomplishments).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>日本発祥の芸術で、国際的に広がっていると言う人もいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It originated in Japan, and some say that it is spreading around the world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It originated in Japan, and is spreading around the world.</e>
<cmt>wordy, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It originated in Japan, and is spreading around the world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>花道とも表記し、またいけばなとも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also written using the kanji (Chinese characters) for &quot;the way of flowers&quot;, and it is also read as &quot;Ikebana&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also written in kanji (Chinese characters) as &quot;the way of flowers,&quot; and read as &quot;Ikebana.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kado (華道) is also written in kanji (Chinese characters) as &apos;花道&apos; (the way of flowers), and call as Ikebana.</e>
<cmt>漢字表記を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>ただし「華道」という呼称には「いけばな」よりも求道的側面が強調されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the name &quot;Kado&quot; gives more emphasis on the aspect of Gudo (seeking for the teachings of Buddha) compared to &quot;Ikebana&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, &quot;Kado&quot; places more emphasis on the aspect of Gudo (seeking for the teachings of Buddha) compared to &quot;Ikebana.&quot;</e>
<cmt>wordy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, &apos;Kado&apos; places more emphasis on the aspect of Gudo (seeking for the teachings of Buddha) than &apos;Ikebana.&apos;</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="5">
<j>さまざまな花材をいけるが、そのいけ方は華道流派によって異なる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A diverse source of flowers is arranged, and the style of flower arrangement differs in schools.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A different types of flowers are arranged in a style differs among various schools.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A different types of flowers are arranged in a style differs among various schools.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>例えば、見る方向は正面と定められている流派も多くあり、3次元の空間を、2次元で最大限に表す流派もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, while many schools set the rule wherein an object is viewed from the front, other schools try to represent, to a maximum extent, a three-dimensional space in two dimensions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, while many schools set the rule that the object is viewed from the front, other schools try to represent a three-dimensional space in two dimensions.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, while many schools set the rule that the object is viewed from the front, other schools try to represent a three-dimensional space in two dimensions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>これは日本絵画の表現方法にも通じる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This mode of representation parallels in Japanese art.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This mode of representation parallels in Japanese art.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This mode of representation parallels in Japanese art.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>欧米のフラワーデザイン(Floral Design)は、3次元のどこから見ても統一したフォルムが感じられるように生けると言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that in Western floral decoration, flowers are arranged to create a unified form when viewed from any of the three dimensions.</e>
<cmt>「フラワーデザイン（Floral Design」とありますが,「floral design」を「floral decoration」に変更させていただきました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Western floral decoration, flowers are arranged to create a unified form when viewed from any of three dimensions.</e>
<cmt>wordy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Western floral decoration, flowers are arranged to create a unified form when viewed from any of three dimensions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>また、日本のいけばな・華道では、色鮮やかな花だけでなく、枝ぶりや木の幹の美しい表情、葉や苔まで、自然植物すべてを総じて「はな」と呼び鑑賞するのも、海外のアレンジの概念とは一線を画す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, Ikebana/Kado of Japan is distinctively different from the concept of arrangement overseas, in that not only colorful flowers but also all plants such as leaves and moss, as well as beautiful expressions of foliage and tree trunks, are collectively called &quot;hana&quot; (flower) and appreciated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, Ikebana/Kado of Japan is distinctively different from the concept of flower arrangement abroad, in that not only colorful flowers, but also all plants such as leaves and moss, as well as beautiful expressions of foliage and tree trunks, are collectively called &quot;hana&quot; (flower) and are appreciated.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, Ikebana and Kado of Japan is distinctively different from the concept of flower arrangement in the Western countries, in that not only colorful flowers, but also all plants such as leaves and moss, as well as beautiful expressions of foliage and tree trunks, are collectively called &apos;hana&apos; (flower) and are appreciated.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="10">
<j>華道以前</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Background of Kado</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Background of Kado</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Background of Kado</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>華道は、仏教の伝来と発展に伴い、仏前に花を手向ける供花に由来するという説が有力である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A widely-accepted theory is that Kado originated from the floral offering of laying flowers at a Buddhist alter, along with the introduction and development of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A widely-accepted theory is that Kado originated from floral offerings being presented at a Buddhist alter, together with the introduction and development of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A widely-accepted theory is that Kado originated from floral offerings being presented at a Buddhist alter, together with the introduction and development of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="12">
<j>だが、採取した植物材料を人間の知の監督下である空間にて再構成する行為に、古代のアニミズムの流れを指摘する研究もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there is also a study which points out the trend of ancient animism in the act of reconstructing the botanical material, which has been collected, in a space under the control of human intellect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there is also a study that points out the trend of ancient animism in the act of reconstructing the botanical material, which has been collected, in a space under the control of human intellect.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there is also a study that points out the trend of ancient animism in the act of reconstructing the botanical material, which has been collected, in a space under the control of human intellect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>動物と異なり、切り落としても適切に処置すれば溌剌とした生命力を漲らせる植物になんらかの神秘を見たとしても、それは不思議なことではないであろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It comes as no surprise if one discovered some kind of mystery in plants, which differed from animals in that they recharged themselves with fresh vitality if they were treated appropriately even after they were cut down.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is not surprising that a type of mystery was seen in plants, differing from animals, in that they recharged themselves with fresh vitality if they were treated appropriately even after they were cut down.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is not surprising that a type of mystery was seen in plants, differing from animals, in that they recharged themselves with fresh vitality if they were treated appropriately even after they were cut down.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>それは常緑樹信仰にも通じ、人間の手の及ばない神秘の力を、花器の上で包括的に管理してしまおうとする試みであったかもしれない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This notion parallels in tree worship; maybe it was an attempt to control the mystic power, which is beyond human control, comprehensively in a vase.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This notion parallels in tree worship; maybe it was an attempt to control a mystic power seen as beyond human control, comprehensively in a vase.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This notion parallels in tree worship; maybe it was an attempt to control a mystic power seen as beyond human control, comprehensively in a vase.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="15">
<j>今日、「華道」といえば江戸時代後期、文化 (元号)文政の時代に流行した生花、挿花のことを指すことが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today, &quot;Kado&quot; often refers to the flower arrangement which prevailed in the Bunka-Bunsei period in the late Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, &quot;Kado&quot; often refers to flower arrangement that prevailed in the Bunka-Bunsei during the late Edo period.</e>
<cmt>redundancy, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, &apos;Kado&apos; often refers to flower arrangement that prevailed in the Bunka-Bunsei era during the late Edo period.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="16">
<j>活けた花を愛でる歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History of admiring arranged flowers</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History of admiring arranged flowers</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History of Admiring Arranged Flowers</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>一輪挿しなどに挿した花を愛でる習慣は、古くは平安時代あたりまで遡り、たとえば『枕草子』などの文献資料からたどることができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The custom of admiring flowers which were cut in vases such as a bud vase extends back to ancient times around the Heian period, and the traces can be found in literature material such as &quot;Makura no soshi&quot; (the Pillow Book).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The custom of admiring cut flowers placed in a vase like a bud vase, extends back to the Heian period, and traces can be found in literature such as &quot;Makura no soshi&quot; (the Pillow Book).</e>
<cmt>wordy, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The custom of admiring cut flowers placed in a vase like a bud vase, extends back to the Heian period, and traces can be found in literature such as &quot;Makura no soshi&quot; (the Pillow Book).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>当初は既存の器を利用していたが、後に専用の花器が製作されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Existing containers were used at first, and specials vases were manufactured later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Existing containers were used at first, and special vases were created later.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Existing containers were used at first, and special vases were created later.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="19">
<j>華道としては、室町時代中期、京都頂法寺の僧により確立された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was established as Kado in the mid Muromachi period by monks of Choho-ji Temple in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kado was established during the mid Muromachi period by monks of Choho-ji Temple in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kado was established during the mid Muromachi period by monks of Choho-ji Temple in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>代々池のほとりに住まいしていたことから「池坊（いけのぼう）」と呼ばれ、それがのちに流派の名前となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since these monks resided on the banks of ponds for generations, they were called &quot;Ikenobo&quot; (literally &quot;monks of ponds&quot;), which later became the name of the school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since these monks resided on the banks of ponds for generations, they were called &quot;Ikenobo&quot; (literally &quot;monks of ponds&quot;), which later became the name of the school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since these monks resided on the banks of ponds for generations, they were called &apos;Ikenobo&apos; (literally &quot;monks of ponds&quot;), which later became the name of the school.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>家元、宗家らによって江戸時代中期にかけて立花（たちばな、りっか 「立華」とも書く）と呼ばれる型が大成されていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The style called &quot;Tachibana/Rikka&quot; (standing flowers) was perfected over the mid Edo period by Iemoto (head family of a school), Soke (originator), and the like.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The style called &quot;Tachibana/Rikka&quot; (standing flowers) was perfected during the mid Edo period by Iemoto (head family of a school), Soke (originator), and the like.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The style called 立花 (Tachibana) (also written as &apos;立華&apos; (Rikka), literally, standing flowers) was perfected during the mid Edo period by Iemoto (head family of a school), Soke (originator), and the like.</e>
<cmt>漢字を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>その後、江戸中期から後期になるとそれまでの上流階級・または武家階級のものから広く庶民のたしなみへと変化し、生花（しょうか、せいか）を中心に広く愛された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later during the mid and late Edo period, the art, which had until then been enjoyed by the upper social class or the samurai class, changed to an accomplishment to be acquired popularly by the common people, and it was widely loved by people as Shoka/Seika (which was more free in style compared to Tachibana/Rikka).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later during the mid and late Edo period, the art, which had until then been enjoyed soley by the the samurai class, became popular among the common people as Shoka/Seika (a more free style compared to Tachibana/Rikka).</e>
<cmt>wordiness, redundancy, reduced for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later during the mid and late Edo period, the art, which had until then been enjoyed solely by the upper class or the samurai class, became popular among the common people as Shoka (also known as Seika (a more free style compared to Tachibana)).</e>
<cmt>補足し、読みを「たちばな」に統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>とくに未生流系、古流系、遠州系などの流派は技巧の達人・名手が多く登場し、多くの流派にわかれていくきっかけとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many masters in techniques appeared especially from schools such as Misho-ryu-kei (Misho school group), Ko-ryu-kei (Traditional school group), Enshu-kei (Enshu group, named after Enshu KOBORI), and this led to the separation into many other schools.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many masters in techniques appeared especially from schools such as Misho-ryu-kei (Misho school group), Ko-ryu-kei (Traditional school group), Enshu-kei (Enshu group, named after Enshu KOBORI), and this led to further separation into many other schools.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many masters in techniques appeared especially from schools such as Misho School group, Koryu (Traditional school) group, and Enshu Group, and this led to further separation into many other schools.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>江戸末期から明治時代初期の頃、世界的なニッポン文化ブームにより華道・いけばなが欧州に紹介され、ヨーロッパのフラワーデザイン(Floral Design)にラインアレンジメントの手法として影響を与えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the end of the Edo period until the early Meiji Period, Kado/Ikebana was introduced to the West as a result of the Nippon culture boom worldwide, and this had an influence on European floral decoration as a technique of vertical arrangement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the end of the Edo period until the early Meiji Period, Kado/Ikebana was introduced to the West as a result of the worldwide Nippon culture boom, and this had an influence on European floral decoration as a technique of vertical arrangement.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the end of the Edo period until the early Meiji period, Kado and Ikebana was introduced to the West as a result of the worldwide Nippon (Japanese) culture boom, and this had an influence on European floral decoration as a technique of vertical arrangement.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>国内ではやがて花姿は時代の流れに即し、なげいれ花、盛花（もりばな）などさまざまな型が編み出された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan, the flower shape eventually developed with the trend of the times; various styles such as Nageire-bana (literally &quot;throwing in flowers&quot;) and Mori-bana (literally &quot;inserting flowers&quot;) were created.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan, the flower shape eventually developed with the trends of the times; various styles such as Nageire-bana (literally &quot;throwing in flowers&quot;) and Mori-bana (literally &quot;inserting flowers&quot;) were created.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan, the flower shape eventually developed with the trends of the times; various styles such as Nageire-bana (literally &quot;throwing in flowers&quot;) and Mori-bana (literally &quot;inserting flowers&quot;) were created.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="26">
<j>江戸時代以降、池坊から枝分かれして多くの流派が誕生した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Edo period, Ikenobo branched into many other schools.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Edo period, Ikenobo branched into many other schools.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Edo period, Ikenobo branched into many other schools.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>2005年3月現在、その数は日本いけばな芸術協会に登録されているだけで392流派ある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As of March 2005, the 392 schools are registered in the Nihon Ikebana Geijutsu Kyokai (Japan Ikebana Association).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As of March 2005, the 392 schools are registered in the Nihon Ikebana Geijutsu Kyokai (Japan Ikebana Association).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As of March 2005, the 392 schools are registered in the Nihon Ikebana Geijutsu Kyokai (Japan Ikebana Association).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="28">
<j>華道の代表的流派</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Major schools of Kado</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Major schools of Kado</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Major Schools of Kado</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>五十音順</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the order of Japanese alphabet</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the order of the Japanese alphabet</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the order of the Japanese alphabet</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>池坊（いけのぼう）開祖・池坊専慶が京都の六角堂池坊の僧侶だったことに因む</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ikenobo: The name is taken after the originator, Senkei IKENOBO, who was a monk of Rokkakudo Ikenobo (Ikenobo of Rokkaku-do Hall).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ikenobo: The name is taken after the originator, Senkei IKENOBO, who was a monk of Rokkakudo Ikenobo (Ikenobo of Rokkaku-do Hall).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ikenobo: The name is taken after the originator, Senkei IKENOBO, who was a monk of Rokkakudo Ikenobo (Ikenobo of Rokkaku-do Hall).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>いけばな京花傳（いけばなきょうかでん）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ikebana-kyokaden</e>
<cmt>「いけばな京花傳」→定訳不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ikebana-kyokaden</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ikebana-kyokaden</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>小原流（おはらりゅう）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ohara-ryu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ohara-ryu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ohara School</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>華道遠州（かどうえんしゅう）江戸後期のマルチアーティスト・茶人の小堀遠州公を祖とする</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kado Enshu: The founder is Kobori ENSHU, a multi-artist and chajin (master of the tea ceremony) in the late Edo period.</e>
<cmt>「小堀遠州公」の「公」は敬称だと判断し、訳しませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kado Enshu: The founder is Kobori ENSHU, a multi-artist and chajin (master of the tea ceremony) during the late Edo period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kado Enshu: The founder was Kobori ENSHU, a multi-artist and chajin (master of the tea ceremony) during the late Edo period.</e>
<cmt>過去形にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="34">
<j>いけばなの代表的個人作家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Major artists in Ikebana</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Major artists in Ikebana</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Major Artists in Ikebana</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>柿崎順一</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Junichi KAKIZAKI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Junichi KAKIZAKI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Junichi KAKIZAKI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>假屋崎省吾</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shogo KARIYAZAKI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shogo KARIYAZAKI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shogo KARIYAZAKI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>中川幸夫</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yukio NAKAGAWA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yukio NAKAGAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yukio NAKAGAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>松田隆作</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kosaku MATSUDA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kosaku MATSUDA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kosaku MATSUDA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 窓(id:12551), AlleborgoBot(id:119729), JAnDbot(id:66507), Si-take.(id:91094), Msou(id:188968), Eskimbot(id:29676), D.h(id:79056), あお(id:33504), Jinshu(id:88538), らりた(id:1327), AlnoktaBOT(id:135808), Nevylax(id:38464), Deapy(id:191082), Ane-mone-0905(id:51469), Loveless(id:129239), Lemon(id:11234), Izayohi(id:13095), Mannequin(id:87056), Jackal1(id:122411), Avensisblue(id:159163), Nighthawks(id:36125), Escarbot(id:59151), Fryed-peach(id:63402), Thijs!bot(id:69644), Kenashida(id:86642), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), YurikBot(id:18605), SuisuiBot(id:10165), FeZn(id:444), Miya(id:1881), Fromm(id:71291), Chlewbot(id:33904), Suisui(id:69), LeonardoRob0t(id:25875), SieBot(id:126695), Wybot(id:81801), Jade0416(id:104181), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>