<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>琵琶牧々</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biwabokuboku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biwabokuboku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biwabokuboku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>琵琶牧々（びわぼくぼく）は、鳥山石燕による妖怪画集『百器徒然袋』にある日本の妖怪の一つで、琵琶の妖怪。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biwabokuboku is a Japanese specter that is introduced in &quot;Hyakki Tsurezure Bukuro&quot; (One hundred bags in idleness), a collection of specters illustrations by Sekien TORIYAMA, and it is a specter of biwa (Japanese lute).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biwabokuboku is a Japanese specter that is introduced in &quot;Hyakki Tsurezure Bukuro&quot; (One hundred bags in idleness), a collection of specters illustrations by Sekien TORIYAMA, and it is a specter of biwa (Japanese lute).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biwabokuboku is a Japanese specter that is introduced in &quot;Hyakki Tsurezure Bukuro&quot; (One hundred bags in idleness), a collection of specters illustrations by Sekien TORIYAMA, and it is a specter of biwa (Japanese lute).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>琵琶が琵琶法師に変化した姿であり、付喪神（器物が変化した妖怪）の一種とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It&apos;s form is a biwa which has transformed into a biwa-playing minstrel, and a kind of Tsukumo-gami (gods to a variety of things).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a biwa which has transformed into a biwa-playing minstrel, and a kind of Tsukumo-gami (gods to a variety of things).</e>
<cmt>It&apos;s form is a biwa → It is a biwa</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a biwa which has transformed into a biwa-playing minstrel, and a kind of Tsukumo-gami (gods to a variety of things).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>体形は人間のようだが、頭部は琵琶であり、盲目の琵琶法師のように目を閉じて杖をついている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its body form is like a human being, but its head is biwa, and like the biwa-playing minstrel, it has its eyes closed and carries a walking stick.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The body looks like a human being, but its head is biwa, and it carries a walking stick with eyes closed like the biwa-playing minstrel.</e>
<cmt>シンプル化しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The body looks like a human being, but its head is biwa, and it carries a walking stick with eyes closed like the blind biwa-playing minstrel.</e>
<cmt>「盲目の」の訳漏れに対応しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>順徳天皇自身の手による有職故実の解説書『禁秘抄』によれば、かつて「玄上（げんじょう）」と「牧馬（ぼくば）」という琵琶の名器があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the &quot;Kinpisho&quot; (about ceremonies and customs of the court, written in kanbun by Juntoku Tenno, during the Jokyu period, 1219-22) which is a explanatory note on Yusoku kojitsu (well-versed in usages or practices of the court or military households, practices), once there were famous biwa called &quot;genjo&quot; and &quot;bokuba&quot;, and there were strange occurrences especially with &quot;genjo&quot; such as its dashing by itself out of dairi when it burned down to ashes, and an ogre who was attracted to its sound had stolen it out and hanging it down with a string from Suzakumon (the main, southern gate of the Palace City).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the &quot;Kinpisho&quot; (about ceremonies and customs of the court, written in kanbun by Juntoku Tenno, during the Jokyu period, 1219-22) which is a explanatory note on Yusoku kojitsu (well-versed in usages or practices of the court or military households, practices), once there were famous biwa called &quot;genjo&quot; and &quot;bokuba&quot;, and there were strange occurrences especially with &quot;genjo&quot; such as its dashing by itself out of dairi when it burned down to ashes, and an ogre who was attracted to its sound had stolen it out and hanging it down with a string from Suzakumon (the main, southern gate of the Palace City).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the &quot;Kinpisho&quot; (Records of the history and origin of imperial court ceremonies which set forth the rules and etiquette for carrying out such ceremonies), a practical guide to Yusoku kojitsu (court and samurai rules of ceremony and etiquette) written by Emperor Juntoku, there were once famous biwa called &quot;genjo&quot; and &quot;bokuba.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>特に玄上の方は、内裏が焼失したときにひとりでに外へ飛び出したり、その音色に魅せられた鬼がこれを盗み出して、朱雀門から紐で吊り下ろしたといった不思議なことがあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Genjo&quot; in particular were involved in strange occurrences, such as when a &quot;genjo&quot; dashed out of the Imperial Palace by itself when the place was burnt down and when an ogre, who was attracted to its sound, stole a &quot;genjo&quot; and hung it by a piece of string from Suzakumon (the main, southern gate of the Palace City).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>『百器徒然袋』の解説文によれば、石燕はこの玄上と牧馬が琵琶牧々に変化したと述べている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the explanation in &quot;Hyakki Tsurezure Bukuro&quot;, Sekien states that it had been those &quot;genjo&quot; and &quot;bokuba&quot; that have transformed into Biwabokuboku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the explanation in &quot;Hyakki Tsurezure Bukuro&quot;, Sekien states that it had been those &quot;genjo&quot; and &quot;bokuba&quot; that have transformed into Biwabokuboku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the explanation in &quot;Hyakki Tsurezure Bukuro&quot;, Sekien states that it had been those &quot;genjo&quot; and &quot;bokuba&quot; that have transformed into Biwabokuboku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>また、石燕より以前、古くは室町時代の『百鬼夜行絵巻』に琵琶の妖怪が描かれていることから、石燕は『百鬼夜行絵巻』をもとに『百器徒然袋』の琵琶牧々を描いたとの説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, before Sekien, because there were specters of biwa depicted in &quot;Hyakki yagyo emaki&quot; (picture scroll of Hyakki yagyo) from the Muromachi Period, there is a theory that Sekien depicted Biwabokuboku in &quot;Hyakki Tsurezure Bukuro&quot; based on &quot;Hyakki yagyo emaki&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, since specters of biwa were depicted in &quot;Hyakki yagyo emaki&quot; (picture scroll of Hyakki yagyo) from the Muromachi Period before Sekien, there is a theory that Sekien depicted Biwabokuboku in &quot;Hyakki Tsurezure Bukuro&quot; based on &quot;Hyakki yagyo emaki&quot;.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, since the &quot;Hyakki Yagyo Emaki&quot; (a picture scroll of the demons&apos; night parade drawn in the Muromachi period, which was before Sekien&apos;s time) contains a drawing of a biwa specter, there is a theory that Sekien drew &apos;Biwabokuboku&apos;, which is introduced in the &quot;Hyakki Tsurezure Bukuro&quot;, based on the &quot;Hyakki Yagyo Emaki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 逃亡者(id:14864), Carbucketty(id:253794), Hannah(id:15935), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>