<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>小倉百人一首文化財団</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ogura Hyakunin Isshu Cultural Foundation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ogura Hyakunin Isshu Cultural Foundation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ogura Hyakunin Isshu Cultural Foundation</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>財団法人小倉百人一首文化財団（おぐらひゃくにんいっしゅぶんかざいだん）は、百人一首をテーマとして、京都文化や京都観光の発展に貢献するために京都商工会議所が設立した財団である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ogura Hyakunin Isshu Cultural Foundation was established by Kyoto Chamber of Commerce and Industry under the theme of &quot;Hyakunin Isshu&quot; (One Hundred Poems by One Hundred Poets) to contribute to the development of Kyoto Culture and Kyoto Travel.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ogura Hyakunin Isshu Cultural Foundation was established by the Kyoto Chamber of Commerce and Industry under the theme of &quot;Hyakunin Isshu&quot; (One Hundred Poems by One Hundred Poets) to contribute to the development of Kyoto Culture and Kyoto Travel.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ogura Hyakunin Isshu Cultural Foundation was established by the Kyoto Chamber of Commerce and Industry under the theme of &quot;Hyakunin Isshu&quot; (One Hundred Poems by One Hundred Poets) to contribute to the development of Kyoto Culture and Kyoto tourism.</e>
<cmt>観光　Travel→tourism</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>百人一首の歌碑建設、百人一首の殿堂時雨殿（2006年1月27日開館）の建設や、百人一首のシンポジウム、競技大会などの開催を目的としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Purposes of the foundation include construction of poetry monuments for Hyakunin Isshu, construction of Shigure-den Palace, which is the edifice for Hyakunin Isshu (inaugurated on January 27, 2006), and symposiums and contests for Hyakunin Isshu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The purpose of the foundation includes the construction of poetry monuments for Hyakunin Isshu, construction of the Shigure-den Palace, which is the edifice for Hyakunin Isshu (inaugurated on January 27, 2006), and symposiums and contests for Hyakunin Isshu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The purpose of the foundation includes the construction of poetry monuments for Hyakunin Isshu, construction of the Shigure-den Palace, which is the edifice for Hyakunin Isshu (inaugurated on January 27, 2006), and symposiums and contests for Hyakunin Isshu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>2003年11月設立。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was founded in November, 2003.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was founded in November, 2003.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was founded in November, 2003.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 ＋－(id:17104), 蒼海牧菜(id:78923), さららゆら(id:12274), Aa akogareno waga akita(id:27813), Terotako(id:11853), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>