<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>納涼床</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Noryo-yuka/Noryo-doko (breeze-enjoying floor)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Noryo-yuka/Noryo-doko (breeze-enjoying floor)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Noryo-yuka (also called as Noryo-doko - breeze-enjoying floor)</e>
<cmt>(also called as Noryo-doko - に訂正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>納涼床（のうりょうゆか、のうりょうどこ）、あるいは川床（鴨川 (淀川水系)では「かわゆか」、貴船、高雄 (京都市)では「かわどこ」と読むのが一般的）は京都の夏の風物詩の一つである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Noryo-yuka/Noryo-doko or the riverbed (In general, for Kamo-gawa River (Yodo-gawa River water system), it is pronounced as &quot;kawayuka&quot;; for Kifune or Takao in Kyoto, it is pronounced as &quot;kawadoko&quot;) is one of the poetic scenery in summer of Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Noryo-yuka/Noryo-doko or the riverbed (In general, for Kamo-gawa River (Yodo-gawa River water system), it is pronounced as &quot;kawayuka;&quot; for Kifune or Takao in Kyoto, it is pronounced as &quot;kawadoko&quot;) is one of the poetic sceneries of the Kyoto summer.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Noryo-yuka (Noryo-doko) or the riverbed (in general, for the Kamo-gawa River (Yodo-gawa River water system), it is pronounced as &apos;kawayuka;&apos; for Kifune or Takao in Kyoto, it is pronounced as &apos;kawadoko&apos;) is one of the poetic sceneries of the Kyoto summer.</e>
<cmt>() 補足しました。 Inを小文字にしました。スペース補足。原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。Kamo-gawa River→the Kamo-gawa Riverに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>料理店や茶屋が川の上や、屋外で川のよく見える位置に座敷を作り、料理を提供する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Restaurants or teahouses may set tables and offer cuisines on rivers or outdoors so that a river can be seen well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Restaurants or teahouses may set tables and offer cuisine near rivers or outdoors so that the river can be seen well.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Restaurants or teahouses may set tables and offer cuisine near rivers or outdoors so that the river can be seen well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>5月ごろから9月ごろまで、鴨川、貴船、高雄、鷹ヶ峯など京都市内各地で楽しむことができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From around May to until about September, it is possible to enjoy this in various places in Kyoto city such as Kamogawa, Kibune, Takao, and Takagamine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From around May to until about September, it is possible to enjoy this in various places in Kyoto city such as Kamogawa, Kibune, Takao, and Takagamine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From around May to September, it is possible to enjoy this in various places in Kyoto city such as Kamogawa, Kibune, Takao, and Takagamine.</e>
<cmt>until、about削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>鴨川納涼床</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kamogawa-Noryoyuka (wooden floors set by Kamo-gawa River)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kamogawa-Noryoyuka (wooden floors set by Kamo-gawa River)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kamogawa-Noryoyuka (wooden floors set by the Kamo-gawa River)</e>
<cmt>Kamo-gawa River→the Kamo-gawa Riverに変更しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>二条から五条にかけて90軒ほどの店が並ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From Nijo to Gojo, about 90 restaurants line up.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From Nijo to Gojo, about 90 restaurants are lined up.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From Nijo to Gojo, about 90 restaurants are lined up.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>京料理以外にも中華や焼肉など各国の料理が選べるので、気軽に納涼床を楽しむことができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides Kyo-ryori (local cuisine of Kyoto), because Chinese cuisine and grilled mea can be chosen, one can readily enjoy the breeze-enjoying floor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides Kyo-ryori (local cuisine of Kyoto), because Chinese cuisine and grilled mea can be selected, one can readily enjoy the breeze-enjoying floor.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides Kyo-ryori (local cuisine of Kyoto), because Chinese cuisine and grilled meat can be selected, one can readily enjoy the breeze-enjoying floor.</e>
<cmt>meatスペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>また、最近では大衆的なチェーン店であるスターバックス京都三条大橋店でも納涼床を楽しむことができ、時代の流れを感じる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover recent, the popular chain cafe Starbucks Coffee has opened the Kyoto-sanjo-ohashi branch with the breeze-enjoying floor. One can feel the flow of era there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover recently, the popular chain cafe Starbucks Coffee has opened their Kyoto-sanjo-ohashi branch utilizing a breeze-enjoying floor. One can feel the flow of the era there.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover recently, the popular chain cafe Starbucks Coffee has opened their Kyoto-sanjo-ohashi branch utilizing a breeze-enjoying floor; one can feel the flow of the era there.</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>基本的に夜の納涼床が中心であるが、5月・9月は昼の納涼床も楽しめる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Basically, the breeze-enjoying floor is mainly for enjoying the evening cool. But in May or September, one can also enjoy the daytime cool there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Basically, the breeze-enjoying floor is mainly for enjoying the cool evenings. But in May or September, one can also enjoy the coolness of the daytime as well.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Basically, the breeze-enjoying floor is mainly for enjoying the cool evenings; but in May or September, one can also enjoy the coolness of the daytime as well.</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>（食中毒防止のため、7・8月は昼の納涼床は営業しない。)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(For preventing food poisoning, the enjoying the daytime cool floor is not opened for business in July and August.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(To preventing food poisoning, the daytime cool floor is not opened for business in July and August.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(To preventing food poisoning, the daytime cool floor is not opened for business in July and August.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>貴船の川床</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Riverbed of Kibune</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kibune Riverbed</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kibune Riverbed</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="9">
<j>貴船口駅から貴船神社に向けて少し歩くと20軒ほどの店が床を並べている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Walking a little bit from Kibuneguchi Station towards Kibune-jinja Shrine, one can find about 20 restaurants displaying the floor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Walking a little bit from Kibuneguchi Station towards Kibune-jinja Shrine, one can find about 20 restaurants displaying these floors.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Walking a little bit from Kibuneguchi Station towards Kibune-jinja Shrine, one can find about 20 restaurants displaying these floors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>京料理や流しそうめんを楽しむことができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One can enjoy Kyo-ryori (Japanese cuisine of Kyoto) and Nagashi-somen (flowing somen noodles).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One can enjoy Kyo-ryori (Japanese cuisine of Kyoto) and Nagashi-somen (flowing somen noodles).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One can enjoy Kyo-ryori (Japanese cuisine of Kyoto) and Nagashi-somen (flowing somen noodles).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>自然が多く情緒溢れる床である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a floor full of nature and overflowed with emotions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a floor full of nature and overflowing with emotion.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a floor full of nature and overflowing with emotion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>高雄の川床</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Riverbed of Takao</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Takao Riverbed</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Takao Riverbed</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Opponent(id:720), TAMA(id:25299), Hadge(id:9555), Rislimric(id:54531), MIsogi(id:20599), Mochi(id:9489), Bankokuya(id:91191), Himetv(id:21833), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>