<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>春画</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shunga (erotic art)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shunga (erotic art)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shunga (erotic art)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>春画（しゅんが）とは、江戸時代に流行した性風俗（特に異性間・同性間の性行為場面）を描いた浮世絵の一種。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shunga (erotic arts) is a kind of ukiyoe (Japanese woodblock prints) that portrayed sexual culture (especially the scenes of sexual intercourse between the sexes or the same sex) that was in fashion in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shunga (erotic arts) is a kind of ukiyoe (Japanese woodblock prints) that portrayed sexual culture (especially the scenes of sexual intercourse between the sexes or the same sex) that was in fashion in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shunga (erotic arts) is a kind of ukiyoe (Japanese woodblock prints) that portrayed sexual culture (especially the scenes of sexual intercourse between the sexes or the same sex) that was in fashion in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>笑い絵や枕絵、枕草紙、秘画、ワ印とも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was also referred to as waraie (a laugh picture), makurae (a pillow picture), makura-soshi (a pillow book) and wajirushi (lit. &quot;wa&quot; mark).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was also referred to as waraie (a laugh picture), makurae (a pillow picture), makura-soshi (a pillow book), higa (pornographic picture) and wajirushi (lit. &quot;wa&quot; mark).</e>
<cmt>「秘画」を追加</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was also referred to as waraie (a laugh picture), makurae (a pillow picture), makura-soshi (a pillow book), higa (pornographic picture) and wajirushi (lit. &quot;wa&quot; mark).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>また、それほど露骨な描写でない絵は危絵（あぶなえ）とも呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, more moderate picture was referred to as abunae (lit. a dangerous picture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, more moderate picture was referred to as abunae (lit. a dangerous picture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, more moderate picture was referred to as abunae (lit. a dangerous picture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>その描写は必ずしも写実的でなく、性器が大きく描かれることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The description was not always realistic, often the size of the genitals were exaggeratingly described.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The description was not always realistic; often the size of the genitals were exaggeratingly described.</e>
<cmt>カンマ→セミコロン</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The description was not always realistic; often the size of the genitals were exaggeratingly described.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>春画の始まりは中国の医学書とともに伝えられた房中術の解説図だと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was considered that the shuga has its origin in Chinese sex manual graphics that were introduced with Chinese medical books.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was considered that the shunga has its origin in Bocchujutsu (sexual art) that was introduced with Chinese medical books.</e>
<cmt>「房中術」の訳を用語集に合わせて変更shungaのスペルミスを修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was considered that the shunga has its origin in Bocchujutsu (sexual art) that was introduced with Chinese medical books.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>日本では平安時代初期から偃息図（えんそくず、おそくず）、またはおそくずの絵と呼ばれる性的題材を描いた絵画があったとされているが（『古今著聞集』など）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan, in the early Heian Period, it is said that there was an picture known as ensokuzu, osozuzu, or osokuzu-no-e (erotic picture) that portrayed sexual theme, such as the &quot;.Kokon chomon ju&quot; (A collection of Tales Heard, Past and Present).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan, in the early Heian Period, it is said that there was an picture known as ensokuzu, osozuzu, or osokuzu-no-e (erotic picture) that portrayed sexual theme, such as the &quot;Kokon chomon ju&quot; (a collection of Tales Heard, Past and Present).</e>
<cmt>ピリオド削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan, in the early Heian period, it is said that there was an picture known as ensokuzu, osozuzu, or osokuzu-no-e (erotic picture) that portrayed sexual theme, such as the &quot;Kokon chomon ju&quot; (a collection of Tales Heard, Past and Present).</e>
<cmt>Heian Period→Heian period</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>しかし、もともと「偃息図」という言葉自体が中国からきたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the term &apos;ensokuzu&apos; itself has its origin in China.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the term &apos;ensokuzu&apos; itself has its origin in China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the term &apos;ensokuzu&apos; itself has its origin in China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>それが庶民に、室町時代から江戸時代にかけて広がり、絵師たちによって描かれるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the Muromachi Period to the Edo Period, it became popular among common people, depicted by the painters.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the Muromachi Period to the Edo Period, it became popular among common people and depicted by the painters.</e>
<cmt>カンマ→and</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the Muromachi period to the Edo period, it became popular among common people and depicted by the painters.</e>
<cmt>Muromachi Period to the Edo Period→Muromachi period to the Edo period</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>災難よけの一種のお守りとして使われるようになったり、特に枕絵の絵巻は花嫁の性教育のテキストとして使われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was used as a kind of good luck charm, especially the makurae picture scroll was used for a sexual manual for a bride.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was used as a kind of good luck charm, especially the makurae picture scroll was used for a sexual manual for a bride.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was used as a kind of good luck charm, especially the makurae picture scroll was used for a sexual manual for a bride.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>ただ、この時代は肉筆のため一部の上流階級のためのものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, because it was hand painting, the shunga was still for upper class</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, because it was hand painting, the shunga was still for the upper class.</e>
<cmt>冠詞、ピリオド</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, because it was hand painting, the shunga was still for the upper class.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="12">
<j>桃山時代、明から春宮秘戯図が伝来し出版された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Momoyama Period, Shunkyu Higizu 春宮秘戯図 (The secret plays of the court) was introduced from Ming Dynasty and published.</e>
<cmt>『春宮秘戯図』読み方不明。仮読みです。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Momoyama Period, Drawings for Secret Plays in a Bedchamber was introduced from the Ming Dynasty and published.</e>
<cmt>「春宮秘戯図」の訳を用語集に合わせて変更secretのスペルミスを修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Momoyama period, Drawings for Secret Plays in a Bedchamber was introduced from the Ming Dynasty and published.</e>
<cmt>Momoyama Period→Momoyama period</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>それに影響され日本でさかんに春画が描かれるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was influential forJapanese to depict the shunga actively.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was influential in Japan in the growth of shunga.</e>
<cmt>後半を変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was influential in Japan in the growth of shunga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="14">
<j>初期の絵師としては菱川師宣が代表的であり、彼の作品の大半が春画である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the early times, the most famous painter was Moronobu HISHIKAWA who mainly painted the shunga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the early times, the most famous painter was Moronobu HISHIKAWA who mainly painted the shunga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the early times, the most famous painter was Moronobu HISHIKAWA who mainly painted the shunga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="15">
<j>また、井原西鶴の浮世草子、好色一代男が大流行する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, Ukiyozoshi (lit. Books of the Floating World) and Koshoku ichidai otoko (Life of an amorous man) written by Saikaku IHARA became very popular.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, Ukiyozoshi (lit. Books of the Floating World) and Koshoku ichidai otoko (Life of an amorous man) written by Saikaku IHARA became very popular.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, Ukiyozoshi (lit. Books of the Floating World) and Koshoku ichidai otoko (Life of an amorous man) written by Saikaku IHARA became very popular.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>好色物と呼ばれるジャンルが流行る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, the genre called as Koshoku mono (Tales of Gallantry) became in fashion.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, the genre called as Koshoku mono (Tales of Gallantry) became in fashion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, the genre called as Koshoku mono (Tales of Gallantry) became in fashion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>それにより、春画の需要が増える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It increased demands for the shunga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It increased demands for the shunga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It increased demands for the shunga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="18">
<j>しかし享保7年（1722年）享保の改革により好色本が禁止される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in 1722, at the time of the Kyoho Reforms (the reforms made in the Kyoho era of the Edo period), erotic books were banned</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in 1722, at the time of the Kyoho Reforms (the reforms made in the Kyoho era of the Edo period), erotic books were banned</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in 1722, at the time of the Kyoho Reforms (the reforms made in the Kyoho era of the Edo period), erotic books were banned</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>それでも需要があるためこれより非公開で販売されることとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Still it was secretly sold due to its demand.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Still it was secretly sold due to its demand.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Still it was secretly sold due to its demand.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>そして、錦絵の開発により、多色刷りの春画が寛政のころから本格的に登場しだした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around 1789 to 1800, according to the development of the Nishiki-e(woodblock prints), multicolor painted shunga appeared in earnest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around 1789 to 1800, according to the development of the Nishiki-e (woodblock prints), multicolor painted shunga appeared in earnest.</e>
<cmt>スペース</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around 1789 to 1800, according to the development of the Nishiki-e (woodblock prints), multicolor painted shunga appeared in earnest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="21">
<j>江戸幕府の規定を守る必要がない春画は、通常では出版できない極彩色の作品が作られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Beyond the rules and regulations enacted by the Edo shogunate, the shuga in full color was published that was ordinarily impossible.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Beyond the rules and regulations enacted by the Edo shogunate, the shuga in full color was published that was ordinarily impossible.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Beyond the rules and regulations enacted by the Edo shogunate, the shuga in full color was published that was ordinarily impossible.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>そのため、浮世絵の最高の技術が使われているものは春画とも言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, it is said that the most significant technique of the ukiyoe was used to the shunga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, it is said that the most significant technique of the ukiyoe was used for shunga.</e>
<cmt>to the→for</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, it is said that the most significant technique of the ukiyoe was used for shunga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>有名な絵師のほとんどがこれを手がけ、狩野派・土佐派の絵師達までもが描いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most of the famous painters, even painters of the Kano School and the Tosa School painted the shunga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most of the famous painters, even painters of the Kano School and the Tosa School painted shunga.</e>
<cmt>冠詞</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most of the famous painters, even painters of the Kano School and the Tosa School painted shunga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="24">
<j>版画として大量に出回った春画は、その芸術性は高い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As woodblock paints, mass-market shunga had high artistic quality.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shunga widely-circulated as woodblock paints had high artistic quality.</e>
<cmt>「版画として」のかかりが間違っているため修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The shunga widely-circulated as woodblock paints had high artistic quality.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>性教育のため、性文化の追求、また思想、宗教的意味合いがあったかなどもわかっていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was not known if it was for sex education or for the pursuit of sex culture, or philosophical or religious implication.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was not known if it was for sex education or for the pursuit of sex culture, or philosophical or religious implication.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was not known if it was for sex education or for the pursuit of sex culture, or philosophical or religious implication.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>どういう人達に需要があり、なぜ高い技術が要求されたか、今後の研究課題ともいえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It may be a future research issue that by what kind of people it was wanted or why the high technique was required.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It may be a future research issue that by what kind of people it was wanted or why the high technique was required.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It may be a future research issue that by what kind of people it was wanted or why the high technique was required.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>また春画根付には、老男女、動物もの、聖人、果物などもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also the models of the shunga netsuke (miniature carving attached to the end of a cord hanging from a pouch) were old men and women, animals, the saints, and fruits.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also the models of shunga netsuke (miniature carving attached to the end of a cord hanging from a pouch) were old men and women, animals, the saints, and fruits.</e>
<cmt>冠詞</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also the models of shunga netsuke (miniature carving attached to the end of a cord hanging from a pouch) were old men and women, animals, the saints, and fruits.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="28">
<j>ただ、幕府による取締りの対策として、作者、絵師、版元を分からないよう画中に隠号という形で記した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, shielded from the control by the Edo Shognate, the names of the original writers, painters and publishers were expressed in the pictures as hidden signatures to disguise their identities.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, shielded from the control of the Edo Shognate, the names of the original writers, painters and publishers were expressed in the pictures as hidden signatures to disguise their identities.</e>
<cmt>control by→control of</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, shielded from the control of the Edo Shognate, the names of the original writers, painters and publishers were expressed in the pictures as hidden signatures to disguise their identities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="29">
<j>明治に入り、次第に写真に取って代わられるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Meiji Period, photographs came to replace the shunga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Meiji Period, photographs came to replace shunga.</e>
<cmt>冠詞</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Meiji period, photographs came to replace shunga.</e>
<cmt>Meiji Period→Meiji period</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>改定律令違式罪目中に、春画およびその類の諸器物を販売する者を笞罪に処し、また没収を付加した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the criminal laws 改定律令違式罪目 in the Meiji Period, those who sell the shunga or like that were punished by caning and seized it.</e>
<cmt>(改定律令違式罪目) 意味と読み方が不明です</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the criminal laws 改定律令違式罪目 in the Meiji Period, those who sell shunga or the like were punished by caning and had their shunga seized.</e>
<cmt>thatを削除seized it→had their shunga seized</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the criminal laws 改定律令違式罪目 in the Meiji period, those who sell shunga or the like were punished by caning and had their shunga seized.</e>
<cmt>Meiji Period→Meiji period</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="31">
<j>現代においては、芸術作品（エロティカ）として社会的に高く評価されており、猥褻出版物としての扱いは受けていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In these dsays, the shuga is valued at the social level as a work of art (erotica), not being regarded as pornography.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In these days, the shuga is socially valued as a work of art (erotica), not being regarded as pornography.</e>
<cmt>at the social level→sociallydaysのスペルミスを修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In these days, the shuga is socially valued as a work of art (erotica), not being regarded as pornography.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="32">
<j>幕末におきたジャポニズムによって、西洋では浮世絵がもてはやされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the end of the Edo Period, ukiyoe was valued in the West due to Japanism.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the end of the Edo Period, ukiyoe was valued in the West due to Japonism.</e>
<cmt>Japonismのスペルミスを修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the end of the Edo period, ukiyoe was valued in the West due to Japonism.</e>
<cmt>Edo Period→Edo period</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>春画は画題が猥褻であるとの理由から嫌われ、輸出には供されなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shunga was in disfavor doe to so-called its rudeness and it was not exported.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shunga was in disfavor due to its vulgarness and it was not exported.</e>
<cmt>dueのスペルミスを修正so-colledを削除rudeness→vulgarness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shunga was in disfavor due to its vulgarness and it was not exported.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>しかし、次第に外国人好みの美人画が不足していったことから、明治末期から大正にかけて局部を書き換えた春画や、複数の春画を切り張りして一枚の美人画に仕立て上げたものを輸出するようになっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, from the end of the Meiji Period to the Taisho Period, when bijinga (beautiful women&apos;s pictures) that foreigners liked gradually became out of stock, the shuga, which was partly repainted around genitals and collarged to make a woman&apos;s picture were exported.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, from the end of the Meiji Period to the Taisho Period, when bijinga (beautiful women&apos;s pictures) that foreigners liked gradually became out of stock, the shunga, which was partly repainted around genitals and collaged to make a woman&apos;s picture were exported.</e>
<cmt>collagedのスペルミスを修正shungaのスペルミスを修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, from the end of the Meiji period to the Taisho period, when bijinga (beautiful women&apos;s pictures) that foreigners liked gradually became out of stock, the shunga, which was partly repainted around genitals and collaged to make a woman&apos;s picture were exported.</e>
<cmt>Meiji Period→Meiji periodTaisho Period→Taisho period</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>こうして作られた美人画は現在も多数流通している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today such make-up bijinga were still distributed.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today such made-up bijinga were still distributed.</e>
<cmt>make-up→made-up</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today such made-up bijinga were still distributed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>真贋をめぐって裁判沙汰になったケースもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some cases had an argument about the authenticity and brought into the court.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some cases had an argument about the authenticity and brought into the court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some cases had an argument about the authenticity and brought into the court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="37">
<j>絵師と代表作</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Painters and their most important work</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Painters and their most important work</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Painters and their most important work</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>菱川師宣：『小むらさき』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moronobu HISHIKAWA &quot;Komurasaki&quot; (small purple)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moronobu HISHIKAWA &quot;Komurasaki&quot; (small purple)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moronobu HISHIKAWA &quot;Komurasaki&quot; (small purple)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>勝川春章：『絵本色好之人式』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shunsho KATSUKAWA: &quot;Ehon irogonomi no hitoshiki (絵本色好之人式) &quot; (Illustrated Rules of An Amorous Man)</e>
<cmt>『絵本色好之人式』の読み方不明　訳は用語集より</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shunsho KATSUKAWA: &quot;Ehon irogonomi no hitoshiki (絵本色好之人式) &quot; (Illustrated Rules of An Amorous Man)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shunsho KATSUKAWA: &quot;Ehon irogonomi no hitoshiki (絵本色好之人式) &quot; (Illustrated Rules of An Amorous Man)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>鳥居清長：『色道十二番』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyonaga TORII &quot;Shikido juniban&quot;(Twelve Scenes in Love Affairs)</e>
<cmt>『色道十二番』　の訳は用語集より</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyonaga TORII &quot;Shikido juniban&quot;(Twelve Scenes in Love Affairs)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyonaga TORII &quot;Shikido juniban&quot;(Twelve Scenes in Love Affairs)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>喜多川歌麿：『歌まくら』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Utamaro KITAGAWA: &quot;Utamakura&quot;(poetic pillows)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Utamaro KITAGAWA: &quot;Utamakura&quot;(poetic pillows)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Utamaro KITAGAWA: &quot;Utamakura&quot;(poetic pillows)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>歌川豊国：『逢世雁之声』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toyokuni UTAGAWA: &quot;Ose kari no koe (逢世雁之声)&quot;</e>
<cmt>『逢世雁之声』　の読み方および定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toyokuni UTAGAWA: &quot;Ose kari no koe (逢世雁之声)&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toyokuni UTAGAWA: &quot;Ose kari no koe (逢世雁之声)&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>葛飾北斎：『萬福和合神』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hokusai KATSUSHIKA: &quot;Manpukuwago-shin&quot;(happy sexual deities)</e>
<cmt>『萬福和合神』　仮訳</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hokusai KATSUSHIKA: &quot;Manpukuwago-shin&quot;(happy sexual deities)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hokusai KATSUSHIKA: &quot;Manpukuwago-shin&quot;(happy sexual deities)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>渓斎英泉：『夢多満佳話』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eisen KEISAI: &quot;Mutamagawa&quot;</e>
<cmt>『夢多満佳話』定訳不明。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eisen KEISAI: &quot;Mutamagawa&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eisen KEISAI: &quot;Mutamagawa&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>歌川国芳：『華古与見』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kuniyoshi UTAGAWA: &quot;Hanagoyomi&quot; (seasonal flowers)</e>
<cmt>『華古与見』 定訳不明。仮訳。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kuniyoshi UTAGAWA: &quot;Hanagoyomi&quot; (seasonal flowers)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kuniyoshi UTAGAWA: &quot;Hanagoyomi&quot; (seasonal flowers)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>有名な作品に、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">as famous works</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Famous works</e>
<cmt>文章形式から変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Famous works</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>醍醐『稚児双紙』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daigo-ji temple &quot;Chigo no soshi&quot; (tales of the temple acolytes)</e>
<cmt>醍醐寺の秘蔵としてtemple を補いました。定訳不明。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daigo-ji temple &quot;Chigo no soshi&quot; (tales of the temple acolytes)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daigo-ji temple &quot;Chigo no soshi&quot; (tales of the temple acolytes)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>藤原隆信</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Takanobu &quot;Shunga shokan (春画小巻)&quot; (small books of shunga)</e>
<cmt>『春画小巻』　定訳、読み方不明。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Takanobu &quot;Shunga shokan (春画小巻)&quot; (small books of shunga)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Takanobu &quot;Shunga shokan (春画小巻)&quot; (small books of shunga)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>『小柴垣草紙』（一名『野々宮絵巻』）住吉慶恩筆といい、あるいは信実筆という</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keion SUMIYOAHI or Nobuzane &quot;Koshibagaki-zoshi&quot;(lit. small brushwood fence books) (another title &quot;Nonomiya-emaki&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keion SUMIYOAHI or Nobuzane &quot;Koshibagaki-zoshi&quot;(lit. small brushwood fence books) (another title &quot;Nonomiya-emaki&quot;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keion SUMIYOAHI or Nobuzane &quot;Koshibagaki-zoshi&quot;(lit. small brushwood fence books) (another title &quot;Nonomiya-emaki&quot;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>『灌頂の巻』住吉慶恩筆といい、あるいは光信筆という</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keion SUMIYOAHI or Mitsunobu &quot;Kanjo no maki&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keion SUMIYOAHI or Mitsunobu &quot;Kanjo no maki&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keion SUMIYOAHI or Mitsunobu &quot;Kanjo no maki&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>巨勢惟久『袋法師草紙』（一名『太秦物語』）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Korehisa KOSE &quot;Fukueohoshi-soshi&quot; (The Story of Fukuro Bonze) (another title &quot;Uzumasa Monogatari&quot;or &quot;Uzumawa tales&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Korehisa KOSE &quot;Fukueohoshi-soshi&quot; (The Story of Fukuro Bonze) (another title &quot;Uzumasa Monogatari&quot;or &quot;Uzumawa tales&quot;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Korehisa KOSE &quot;Fukueohoshi-soshi&quot; (The Story of Fukuro Bonze) (another title &quot;Uzumasa Monogatari&quot;or &quot;Uzumawa tales&quot;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>『袋法師絵詞』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Fukurohoshi ekotoba&quot; (The picture book of Fukuro Bonzo)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Fukurohoshi ekotoba&quot; (The picture book of Fukuro Bonzo)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Fukurohoshi ekotoba&quot; (The picture book of Fukuro Bonzo)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>光信『四十八番春画』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitsunobu &quot;48 Shunga&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitsunobu &quot;48 Shunga&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitsunobu &quot;48 Shunga&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>狩野元信『尾花日記』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Motonobu KANO &quot;Obana-nikki&quot; (Obana Dialy)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Motonobu KANO &quot;Obana-nikki&quot; (Obana Dialy)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Motonobu KANO &quot;Obana-nikki&quot; (Obana Dialy)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="55">
<j>古くは、伝・鳥羽僧正とされる『陽物くらべ』などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Back to the old time, it included &quot;Yobutsu Kurabe&quot;(Phalluses Contest) by Toba sojo etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Back to the old time, it included &quot;Yobutsu Kurabe&quot;(Phalluses Contest) by Toba sojo etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Back to the old time, it included &quot;Yobutsu Kurabe&quot;(Phalluses Contest) by Toba sojo etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 JAnDbot(id:66507), Vhjfjhfhj(id:87448), TXiKiBoT(id:107492), Preacher(id:39996), Toto-tarou(id:16648), 寒漁夫(id:99134), 聖ザビエル(id:91074), Bluesnow(id:176583), Rokosuke(id:114496), Point136(id:211299), FlaBot(id:30804), Nopira(id:29335), Kzhr(id:131), Calvero(id:38360), Peek-poke(id:68004), Mnd(id:15140), Blizzardbreaker(id:248394), Mmma Mia!(id:21142), BitBucket(id:30999), L III (N)(id:72793), Vina-iwbot(id:56449), 東トウ(id:21350), Otoshigo(id:80102), Miya(id:1881), てつどうまん(id:126422), Macdee1985(id:163056), R28Bot(id:177951), 水平芳(id:203583), Corwin(id:973), 伏儀(id:142093), TeaServer(id:55403), Emonue(id:11273), Kurohoushi(id:17174), ヒットミン(id:52557), Katsuya(id:21306), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>