<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>京言葉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyo Language</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyo Language</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyo Language</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>京言葉（きょうことば、京ことばと表記されることも）または京都弁（きょうとべん）とは、狭義では京都府京都市旧市街、広義では京都府山城国と南丹（亀岡盆地周辺）で話される日本語の方言。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term &quot;Kyo language&quot; (written in Japanese as either &quot;京言葉&quot;,&quot;きょうことば&quot; or &quot;京ことば&quot;) or &quot;Kyoto-ben&quot; (Kyoto dialect) means a Japanese dialect spoken either in the old town area of Kyoto City, in the narrow sense, or in the area including Yamashiro Province and Nantan (around Kameoka basin), in the broad sense, both in Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term &quot;Kyo language&quot; (written in Japanese as either &quot;京言葉&quot;,&quot;きょうことば&quot; or &quot;京ことば&quot;) or &quot;Kyoto-ben&quot; (Kyoto dialect) means a Japanese dialect spoken either in the old town area of Kyoto City, in the narrow sense, or in the area including Yamashiro Province and Nantan (around Kameoka basin), in the broad sense, both in Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term Kyo language (written in Japanese as either 京言葉, きょうことば or 京ことば) or Kyoto-ben (Kyoto dialect) means a Japanese dialect spoken either in the old town area of Kyoto City, in the narrow sense, or in the area including Yamashiro Province and Nantan (around Kameoka basin), in the broad sense, both in Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>古くは京談（きょうだん）とも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In old days, &quot;Kyodan&quot; was used as an equivalent term.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the old days, &quot;Kyodan&quot; was used as an equivalent term.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the old days, Kyodan was used as an equivalent term.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>近畿方言の一種だが、別個に扱われることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyo language is a kind of Kinki dialects, but is sometimes treated separately from them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyo language is a kind of Kinki dialect, but is sometimes treated separately from them.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyo language is a kind of Kinki dialect, but is sometimes treated separately from them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>京阪式アクセントであるが、大阪弁などのアクセントとは異なることも多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its accents belong to a group of Keihan style accents, but it has still many different accents from those of Osaka dialect and other dialects of the same group.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its accents belong to a group of Keihan style accents, but it has still many different accents from those of Osaka dialect and other dialects of the same group.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its accents belong to a group of Keihan style accents, but it has still many different accents from those of Osaka dialect and other dialects of the same group.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>正確な話者は現在では少なくなりつつある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The number of correct speakers of Kyo language is now decreasing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The number of correct speakers of Kyo language is now decreasing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The number of correct speakers of Kyo language is now decreasing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>京都には長い間御所が存在していたため、宮中で話されていた御所言葉の影響を受けているとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyo language is said to have been influenced by a court language spoken at court since the Imperial palace had ever been located in Kyoto for a long period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyo language is said to have been influenced by a court language spoken at court since the Imperial palace had been located in Kyoto for a long period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyo language is said to have been influenced by a court language spoken at court since the Imperial palace had been located in Kyoto for a long period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>敬語や婉曲表現を多用し、柔らかく丁寧な口調でなるべく会話に角が立たない言い回しをするが、それが皮肉となるケースも多く、京言葉を解せない人々がコミュニケーションをとりにくい、と感じることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kyo language, honorific language and euphemistic expressions are frequently used in order to make the tone of conversation euphonic and polite avoiding any offending expression as much as possible, but it often happens to induce ironic effects or cynicism and make people who do not correctly understand Kyo language feel some difficulty in communication.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Kyo language, honorific language and euphemistic expressions are frequently used in order to make the tone of conversation euphonic and polite avoiding any offending expression as much as possible, but it often happens to induce ironic effects or cynicism and make people who do not correctly understand Kyo language feel some difficulty in communication.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Kyo language, honorific language and euphemistic expressions are frequently used in order to make the tone of conversation euphonic and polite avoiding any offending expression as much as possible, but it often happens to induce ironic effects or cynicism and make people who do not correctly understand Kyo language feel some difficulty in communication.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>ただし、それらが大阪弁と京都弁の大きな違いである優雅さの要因であるとする研究者も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, many scholars point out such way of soft expression of Kyo language is a factor of producing gracefulness, which is a major difference between Kyoto and Osaka dialects.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, many scholars point out such way of soft expression of Kyo language is a factor that produces gracefulness, which is a major difference between Kyoto and Osaka dialects.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, many scholars point out such way of soft expression of Kyo language is a factor that produces gracefulness, which is a major difference between Kyoto and Osaka dialects.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>分類</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Classification</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Classification</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Classification</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="9">
<j>京言葉は、大きく分けて御所で話された公家言葉（御所言葉）と、街中で話されるもの（町ことば）に分類される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyo language can be classified into two prominent types, one being a noble language (Court language) spoken at the Imperial palace and another being an ordinary language (town language) spoken among the people in town.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyo language can be classified into two prominent types, one being a noble language (Court language) spoken at the Imperial palace and another being an ordinary language (town language) spoken among the people in town.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyo language can be classified into two prominent types, one being a noble language (Court language) spoken at the Imperial palace and another being an ordinary language (town language) spoken among the people in town.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>ただ、近年では大阪弁の影響のほか、標準語の影響により、標準語化・東京弁化が進むと共にこれらの差異が少なくなってきているといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, since Kyo language has recently been influenced by Osaka and other dialects including the standard dialect, and has gradually transformed itself toward the standard or Tokyo dialect&apos;s direction, so that difference between these dialects has become less than ever.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, since Kyo language has recently been influenced by Osaka and other dialects including the standard dialect, and has gradually transformed itself toward the standard or Tokyo dialect&apos;s direction, so that difference between these dialects has become less.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, since Kyo language has recently been influenced by Osaka and other dialects including the standard dialect, and has gradually transformed itself toward the standard or Tokyo dialect&apos;s direction, so that difference between these dialects has become less.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="11">
<j>前者の公家言葉は、宮中や宮家、公家のあいだで室町時代の初期から女官によって話されたもので、現在では一部の社寺に残されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first one (noble language as described above) was spoken by court ladies among imperial families and court nobles within the Imprial court since Muromachi period, part of which are still being spoken within some shrines and temples of today.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first one (noble language as described above) was spoken by court ladies among imperial families and court nobles within the Imprial court since the Muromachi period, part of which are still being spoken within some shrines and temples of today.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first one (noble language as described above) was spoken by court ladies among imperial families and court nobles within the Imperial court since the Muromachi period, part of which are still being spoken within some shrines and temples of today.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>後者は、話者の職業や地域によって更に細かく分類することが出来る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The latter one (town language) can be further divided into details according to occupations and areas of the speakers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The latter one (town language) can be further divided into details according to occupations and areas of the speakers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The latter one (town language) can be further divided into details according to occupations and areas of the speakers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>中京ことば（なかぎょう-）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nakagyo Language</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nakagyo Language</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nakagyo Language</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="14">
<j>中京区を中心として、室町通の問屋街などで話される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The dialect spoken in Nakagyo Ward and its surrounding area, including the wholesaler district of Muromachi street, is called Nakagyo language.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The dialect spoken in Nakagyo Ward and its surrounding area, including the wholesaler district of Muromachi street, is called Nakagyo language.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The dialect spoken in Nakagyo-ku Ward and its surrounding area, including the wholesaler district of Muromachi-dori Street, is called Nakagyo language.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>町ことばの代表とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is regarded as the representative of the town language.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is regarded as representative of the town language.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is regarded as representative of the town language.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="16">
<j>職人ことば</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tradesman Language</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tradesman Language</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Craftsmen Language</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="17">
<j>西陣の織物産業（西陣織）に従事する人々のことば。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is a dialect spoken among the people engaged in textile industry of Nishijin (Nishijin textiel.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is a dialect spoken among people engaged in the textile industry of Nishijin (Nishijin textile.)</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is a dialect spoken among people engaged in the textile industry of Nishijin (Nishijin textile.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="18">
<j>花街ことば</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fleshpot Language</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fleshpot Language</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fleshpot Language</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="19">
<j>祇園など京の花街で、舞妓や芸妓によって話されることば。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fleshpot language is a dialect spoken among maiko (apprentice geisha) and geisha girls in Gion and other fleshpots of Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fleshpot language is a dialect spoken among maiko (apprentice geisha) and geisha girls in Gion and other fleshpots of Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fleshpot language is a dialect spoken among maiko (apprentice geisha) and geigi (a woman who gives fun with a song, a dance or a music instrument at a feast) in Gion and other fleshpots of Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>用語を他の記事と統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>簡易的な手話の様を呈する「身振り語」や、嶋原で用いられてきた伝統的な「廓言葉（なます言葉）」がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are some more dialects of Kyo language, such as &quot;gesture words&quot; similar to a simplified sign language, as well as &quot;Red-light district language (namasu language)&quot;, a traditional language spoken in Shimabara, a famous amusement area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are some more dialects of Kyo language, such as &quot;gesture words&quot; similar to a simplified sign language, as well as &quot;Red-light district language (namasu language),&quot; a traditional language spoken in Shimabara, a famous amusement area.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are some more dialects of Kyo language, such as &apos;miburi language&apos; (gesture words) similar to a simplified sign language, as well as &apos;namasu language&apos; (Red-light district language), a traditional language spoken in Shimabara, a famous amusement area.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションの位置などを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="21">
<j>伝統工芸語</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Languages for Traditional Arts and Crafts</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Languages for Traditional Arts and Crafts</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Languages for Traditional Arts and Crafts</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="22">
<j>京焼、京友禅などの現場で話される職業語。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Vocational languages are spoken at various field sites of traditional arts and crafts like Kyoyaki porcelain, Kyoyuzen dyed fabrics and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Vocational languages are spoken at various field sites of traditional arts and crafts like Kyoyaki porcelain, Kyoyuzen dyed fabrics and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Vocational languages are spoken at various field sites of traditional arts and crafts like Kyoyaki porcelain, Kyoyuzen dyed fabrics and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="23">
<j>農家ことば</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Farmers Language</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Farmers Language</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Farmers Language</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="24">
<j>大原や口丹波など京都周辺の農村部で話されることば。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A farmers languge is spoken in rural areas around Kyoto City, such as Ohara and Kuchitanba.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A farmers languge is spoken in rural areas around Kyoto City, such as Ohara and Kuchitanba.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A farmers language is spoken in rural areas around Kyoto City, such as Ohara and Kuchitanba.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>発音</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Pronunciation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Pronunciation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Pronunciation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="25">
<j>京言葉は、多くの人々によって「優雅である」という評価がなされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many people recognize Kyo language as &quot;being elegant.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many people recognize Kyo language as &quot;being elegant.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many people recognize Kyo language as &apos;being elegant.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>これの一要因として、京言葉の持つ発音、アクセントがあげられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such recognition may be attributed to its pronunciation and accents.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such recognition may be attributed to its pronunciation and accents.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such recognition may be attributed to its pronunciation and accents.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="27">
<j>長母音やウ音便を多用することから、全般的にテンポが遅く、ゆったりとした柔らかい印象を与えるのが特徴的である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Generally speaking, it is characterized by frequent use of long vowels and euphonic changes &quot;u&quot;, giving an impression of being slow-paced, unstrained and floppy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Generally speaking, it is characterized by frequent use of long vowels and euphonic changes &quot;u,&quot; giving an impression of being slow-paced, unstrained and floppy.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Generally speaking, it is characterized by frequent use of long vowels and euphonic changes &apos;u,&apos; giving an impression of being slow-paced, unstrained and floppy.</e>
<cmt>分かりやすくするために、原文にはないクォーテーションを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>母音</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Vowels</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Vowels</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Vowels</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="28">
<j>長母音の「う」や「お」を短く発音し、「学校」（がっこう）を「ガッコ」と、「山椒」（さんしょう）を「サンショ」とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Long vowels of &quot;u&quot; and &quot;o&quot; are cut short, modifying, for example, &quot;gakkou&quot; (school) to &quot;gakko&quot;, &quot;sanshou&quot; (Japanese pepper) to &quot;sansho.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Long vowels of &quot;u&quot; and &quot;o&quot; are cut short, modifying, for example, &quot;gakkou&quot; (school) to &quot;gakko,&quot; &quot;sanshou&quot; (Japanese pepper) to &quot;sansho.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Long vowels of &apos;u&apos; and &apos;o&apos; are cut short, modifying, for example, &apos;gakkou&apos; (school) to &apos;gakko,&apos; &apos;sanshou&apos; (Japanese pepper) to &apos;sansho.&apos;</e>
<cmt>長音表記「ou」を「o」とすると意味が分かりにくくなるため、「ou」のまま表記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="29">
<j>また、名詞や動詞の音素文字を長く伸ばすことも行われ、「蚊」（か）を「カア」と、「野」（の）を「ノオ」とすることがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Phonemic letters of nouns and verbs are sometimes long drawn in pronunciation, altering, for example, &quot;ka&quot; (mosquito) to &quot;ka-a&quot;, and &quot;no&quot; (field) to &quot;no-o.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Phonemic letters of nouns and verbs are sometimes long drawn in pronunciation, altering, for example, &quot;ka&quot; (mosquito) to &quot;ka-a,&quot; and &quot;no&quot; (field) to &quot;no-o.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Phonemic letters of nouns and verbs are sometimes long drawn in pronunciation, altering, for example, &apos;ka&apos; (mosquito) to &apos;ka-a,&apos; and &apos;no&apos; (field) to &apos;no-o.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="30">
<j>さらに、訛として i の母音を e に転化させ「虱」（しらみ）を「シラメ」とするものがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, some people convert pronunciation of vowel &quot;i&quot; into &quot;e&quot; as a dialect, and pronounce, for example, &quot;shirame&quot; instead of &quot;shirami (louse).&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further, some people convert pronunciation of vowel &quot;i&quot; into &quot;e&quot; as a dialect, and pronounce, for example, &quot;shirame&quot; instead of &quot;shirami (louse).&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further, some people convert pronunciation of vowel &apos;i&apos; into &apos;e&apos; as a dialect, and pronounce, for example, &apos;shirame&apos; instead of &apos;shirami&apos; (louse).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>その他にも、 e を i に、 u を o に、 o を u と転化させる場合がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, occasional conversions may be made from &quot;e&quot; to &quot;i&quot;, from &quot;u&quot; to &quot;o&quot; and from &quot;o&quot; to &quot;u.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, occasional conversions may be made from &quot;e&quot; to &quot;I,&quot; from &quot;u&quot; to &quot;o&quot; and from &quot;o&quot; to &quot;u.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, occasional conversions may be made from &apos;e&apos; to &apos;i,&apos; from &apos;u&apos; to &apos;o&apos; and from &apos;o&apos; to &apos;u.&apos;</e>
<cmt>分かりやすくするために、原文にはないクォーテーションを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="32">
<j>連母音をなまらせ「見える」を「メール」とするケースもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In other cases, a series of vowels may be combined, to pronounce, for example, &quot;meru&quot; instead of &quot;mieru (literally, &quot;can be seen&quot; or &quot;look like.&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In other cases, a series of vowels may be combined, to pronounce, for example, &quot;meru&quot; instead of &quot;mieru (literally, &quot;can be seen&quot; or &quot;look like.&quot;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In other cases, a series of vowels may be combined, to pronounce, for example, &apos;meru&apos; instead of &apos;mieru&apos; (literally, &apos;can be seen&apos; or &apos;look like&apos;).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>子音</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Consonants</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consonants</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consonants</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="33">
<j>「シ」[ʃi]を「ヒ」[çi]に転化して「失礼」（しつれい）を「ヒツレイ」としたり、[s] を [ʃi] に、[m] を [b] に転化させる例などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are some examples to change pronunciation of &quot;shi&quot; (&amp;amp643i) to &quot;hi&quot; (&amp;amp231i), as in the case of &quot;hitsurei&quot; instead of &quot;shitsurei&quot; (literally, &quot;excuse me&quot;), as well as &quot;s&quot; to &quot;&amp;amp643i&quot; and &quot;m&quot; to &quot;b.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are some examples to change pronunciation of &quot;shi&quot; (&amp;amp643i) to &quot;hi&quot; (&amp;amp231i), as in the case of &quot;hitsurei&quot; instead of &quot;shitsurei&quot; (literally, &quot;excuse me&quot;), as well as &quot;s&quot; to &quot;&amp;amp643i&quot; and &quot;m&quot; to &quot;b.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are some examples to change pronunciation of &apos;shi&apos; [ʃi] to &apos;hi&apos; [çi], as in the case of &apos;hitsurei&apos; instead of &apos;shitsurei&apos; (literally, &apos;excuse me&apos;), as well as &apos;s&apos; to [ʃi] and &apos;m&apos; to [b].</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>音便</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Euphonic Changes</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Euphonic Changes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Euphonic Changes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="34">
<j>語呂を滑らかにするための関西特有の音便が多用される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order to smoothen the combination of sounds, euphonic changes typical to Kansai region are often applied to Kyo language.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to smoothen the combination of sounds, euphonic changes typical to the Kansai region are often applied to Kyo language.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to smoothen the combination of sounds, euphonic changes typical to the Kansai region are often applied to Kyo language.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="35">
<j>ウ音便</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Euphonic Changes &quot;U&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Euphonic Changes &quot;U&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Euphonic Changes &apos;U&apos;</e>
<cmt>分かりやすくするために、原文にはないクォーテーションを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="36">
<j>明るくなる→明るうなる、美しく咲く→美しゅう咲く</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Akaruku naru&quot; (literally, &quot;become bright&quot;) =&gt;&quot;Akaru-u naru&quot;; &quot;utsukusiku saku&quot; (literally, &quot;blossom beautifully&quot;)=&gt;&quot;utsukushu-u saku&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Akaruku naru&quot; (literally, &quot;become bright&quot;) =&gt;&quot;Akaru-u naru;&quot; &quot;utsukusiku saku&quot; (literally, &quot;blossom beautifully&quot;)=&gt;&quot;utsukushu-u saku&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akaruku naru&apos; (literally, become bright) converts into &apos;akaru-u naru,&apos; &apos;utsukushiku saku&apos; (literally, blossom beautifully) into &apos;utsukushu-u saku.&apos;</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="37">
<j>オ音便</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Euphonic Changes &quot;O&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Euphonic Changes &quot;O&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Euphonic Changes &apos;O&apos;</e>
<cmt>分かりやすくするために、原文にはないクォーテーションを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="38">
<j>「オ」と発音するが、表記は「う」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Euphonic changes &quot;o&quot; are often applied to the description of &quot;u.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Euphonic changes &quot;o&quot; are often applied to the description of &quot;u.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Euphonic changes &apos;o&apos; are often applied to the description of &apos;u.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="39">
<j>眠たくて仕方ない→眠とうて仕方ない、赤く染まる→赤う染まる</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Nemutakute shikatanai&quot; (literally, &quot;desperately sleepy&quot;)=&gt;&quot;Nemutoute shikatanai&quot;; &quot;akaku somaru&quot; (literally, &quot;become reddish&quot;)=&gt;&quot;akou somaru&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Nemutakute shikatanai&quot; (literally, &quot;desperately sleepy&quot;)=&gt;&quot;Nemutoute shikatanai;&quot; &quot;akaku somaru&quot; (literally, &quot;become reddish&quot;)=&gt;&quot;akou somaru&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nemutakute shikatanai&apos; (literally, desperately sleepy) converts into &apos;nemutote shikatanai,&apos; &apos;akaku somaru&apos; (literally, become reddish) into &apos;ako somaru.&apos;</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="40">
<j>促音便</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bursting Euphonic Changes</e>
<cmt>促音便→bursting euphonic changes　[定訳未詳]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bursting Euphonic Changes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bursting Euphonic Changes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="41">
<j>えらいことや→えらいこっちゃ　おきばりやす→おきばりやっしゃ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Erai kotoya&quot; (literally, &quot;It&apos;s too bad&quot;)=&gt;&quot;Erai koccha&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Erai kotoya&quot; (literally, &quot;It&apos;s too bad&quot;)=&gt;&quot;Erai koccha&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Erai kotoya&apos; (literally, &apos;It&apos;s too bad&apos;) converts into &apos;erai kotcha,&apos; &apos;okibari yasu&apos; into &apos;okibari yassha.&apos;</e>
<cmt>補足し表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="42">
<j>撥音便</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Flipping Euphonic Changes</e>
<cmt>撥音便→flipping euphonic changes　[定訳未詳]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Flipping Euphonic Changes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Flipping Euphonic Changes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="43">
<j>つかぬことを→つかんことを　ぼうさん→ぼんさん</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Tsukanu kotowo&quot; (literally, &quot;By the way&quot;)=&gt;&quot;Tsukan kotowo&quot;; &quot;bousan&quot; (literally, &quot;Buddhist monk&quot;)=&gt;&quot;bonsan&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Tsukanu kotowo&quot; (literally, &quot;By the way&quot;)=&gt;&quot;Tsukan kotowo;&quot; &quot;bousan&quot; (literally, &quot;Buddhist monk&quot;)=&gt;&quot;bonsan&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsukanu kotowo&apos; (literally, &apos;By the way&apos;) converts into &apos;Tsukan kotowo,&apos; &apos;bosan&apos; (literally, Buddhist monk) into &apos;bonsan.&apos;</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>語法</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Usages</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Usages</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Usages</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>活用</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Conjugation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Conjugation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Conjugation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="44">
<j>五段動詞の命令形では、標準語と同様の命令形に加えてい段で活用するものがあり、これは「～なさい」を省略したものと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperative forms of some godan doshi (5-grade conjugation verbs) conjugate at &quot;i-dan&quot;(i-grade), being considered as an abbreviation of &quot;--nasai&quot; and may be used in addition to normal forms of the standard Japanese.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperative forms of some godan doshi (5-grade conjugation verbs) conjugate at &quot;i-dan&quot;(i-grade), being considered as an abbreviation of &quot;--nasai&quot; and may be used in addition to normal forms of the standard Japanese.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperative forms of some godan doshi (5-grade conjugation verbs) conjugate at &apos;i&apos; dan (i-grade), being considered as an abbreviation of &apos;nasai&apos; and may be used in addition to normal forms of the standard Japanese.</e>
<cmt>分かりやすくするために、原文にはないクォーテーションを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="45">
<j>（例）「走り」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Example) &quot;Hashiri&quot; (literally, &quot;Run!!&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Example) &quot;Hashiri&quot; (literally, &quot;Run!!&quot;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Example) &apos;Hashiri&apos; (literally, &apos;run&apos;)</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="46">
<j>五段動詞の否定は、あ段で活用する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Negative forms of godan doshi (five-grade verbs) conjugate at &quot;a-dan&quot; (a-grade).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Negative forms of godan doshi (five-grade verbs) conjugate at &quot;a-dan&quot; (a-grade).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Negative forms of godan doshi conjugate at &apos;a&apos; dan (a-grade).</e>
<cmt>前出補足をのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="47">
<j>（例）「あらへん」、「走らへん」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Examples) &quot;arahen&quot; (literally, &quot;there is no --&quot;): &quot;hashirahen&quot; (literally, &quot;-- do not run&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Examples) &quot;arahen&quot; (literally, &quot;there is no --&quot;): &quot;hashirahen&quot; (literally, &quot;-- do not run&quot;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Examples) &apos;arahen&apos; (literally, &apos;there is no...&apos;), &apos;hashirahen&apos; (literally, &apos;... do not run&apos;)</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="48">
<j>「走れへん」とすると、標準語と同じく「走れない」の意味になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The wording of &quot;Hashirehen&quot; instead of &quot;hashirahen&quot; means &quot;-- cannot run,&quot; the same way as in the standard Japanese.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The wording of &quot;Hashirehen&quot; instead of &quot;hashirahen&quot; means &quot;-- cannot run,&quot; the same way as in the standard Japanese.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The wording of &apos;Hashirehen&apos; instead of &apos;hashirahen&apos; means &apos;... cannot run,&apos; the same way as in the standard Japanese.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="49">
<j>他の近畿方言では「～らへん」「～れへん」を区別しないことが多く、コミュニケーションギャップが生じやすい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In other Kinki dialects, many people do not discriminate between &quot;--rahen&quot; and &quot;--rehen&quot;, which frequently causes communication gaps among speakers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In other Kinki dialects, many people do not discriminate between &quot;--rahen&quot; and &quot;--rehen,&quot; which frequently causes communication gaps among speakers.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In other Kinki dialects, many people do not discriminate between &apos;... rahen&apos; and &apos;... rehen,&apos; which frequently causes communication gaps among speakers.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="50">
<j>さ行変格活用、か行変格活用の否定は、い段で活用することが多く、その場合否定の助詞は「ひん」となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Negative forms of SA-gyo and KA-gyo henkaku katsuyo (SA-row and KA-row irregular conjugation group verbs) conjugate frequently at &quot;i-dan&quot;(i-grade,) in which cases &quot;hin&quot; shall be fixed as a relevant postpositional particle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Negative forms of SA-gyo and KA-gyo henkaku katsuyo (SA-row and KA-row irregular conjugation group verbs) conjugate frequently at &quot;i-dan&quot;(i-grade,) in which cases &quot;hin&quot; shall be fixed as a relevant postpositional particle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Negative forms of SA-gyo and KA-gyo henkaku katsuyo (SA-row and KA-row irregular conjugation group verbs) conjugate frequently at &apos;i&apos; dan (i-grade,) in which cases &apos;hin&apos; shall be fixed as a relevant postpositional particle.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>現在は、大阪他の言い方に従って、え段+「へん」などと言う事も増えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Presently, such wording as e-dan (e-grade) conjugative group verbs with postfix &quot;hen&quot; are increasingly used, due to the influence of Osaka and other dialects.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Presently, such wording as e-dan (e-grade) conjugative group verbs with postfix &quot;hen&quot; are increasingly used, due to the influence of Osaka and other dialects.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Presently, such wording as &apos;e&apos; dan (e-grade) conjugative group verbs with postfix &apos;hen&apos; are increasingly used, due to the influence of Osaka and other dialects.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>い段+「ひん」、え段+「へん」ともに、未然形+「やへん」が変化したものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such forms as i-dan (i-grade) conjugation plus postfix &quot;hin&quot; and e-dan (e-grade) plus &quot;hen&quot; are both the convertion from imperfective forms plus &quot;yahen.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such forms as i-dan (i-grade) conjugation plus postfix &quot;hin&quot; and e-dan (e-grade) plus &quot;hen&quot; are both the convertion from imperfective forms plus &quot;yahen.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such forms as i-dan (i-grade) conjugation plus postfix &apos;hin&apos; and &apos;e&apos; dan (e-grade) plus &apos;hen&apos; are both the conversion from imperfective forms plus &apos;yahen.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="53">
<j>（例）「しーひん」（しない）、「きーひん」（来ない）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Examples) &quot;shi-hin&quot; (shinai, literally &quot;do not do&quot;)&quot;; &quot;ki-hin (konai, literally &quot;do not come&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Examples) &quot;shi-hin&quot; (shinai, literally &quot;do not do&quot;);&quot; &quot;ki-hin (konai, literally &quot;do not come&quot;)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Examples) &apos;shi-hin&apos; (shinai, literally &apos;do not do&apos;), &apos;ki-hin&apos; (konai, literally &apos;do not come&apos;).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="54">
<j>五段動詞で勧誘を示す場合、お段で伸ばさない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order to have godan doshi (5-grade conjugation verbs) express inducement, its o-dan (o-grade) syllable is not streched long.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to have godan doshi (5-grade conjugation verbs) express inducement, its o-dan (o-grade) syllable is not streched long.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to have godan doshi express inducement, its &apos;o&apos; dan (o-grade) syllable is not stretched long.</e>
<cmt>前出補足をのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>一段動詞の場合は短く「よ」を付けるが、「する」は「しょう」と伸ばす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order to make ichidan doshi (1-grade conjugation verbs) express inducement, a short postfix &quot;yo&quot; is added but for the verb &quot;suru&quot; (literally, &quot;do&quot;) which changes itself to long pronunciation of &quot;sho.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to make ichidan doshi (1-grade conjugation verbs) express inducement, a short postfix &quot;yo&quot; is added but for the verb &quot;suru&quot; (literally, &quot;do&quot;) which changes itself to long pronunciation of &quot;sho.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to make ichidan doshi (1-grade conjugation verbs) express inducement, a short postfix &apos;yo&apos; is added but for the verb &apos;suru&apos; (literally, &apos;do&apos;) which changes itself to long pronunciation of &apos;sho.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="56">
<j>（例）「走ろ」、「行こ」、「見よ」、「寝よ」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Examples) &quot;hashiro&quot; (literally, &quot;Let&apos;s run&quot;), &quot;iko&quot; (literally, &quot;Let&apos;s go&quot;), &quot;miyo&quot; (literally, &quot;Let&apos;s see&quot;), &quot;neyo&quot; (literally, &quot;Let&apos;s go to bed&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Examples) &quot;hashiro&quot; (literally, &quot;Let&apos;s run&quot;), &quot;iko&quot; (literally, &quot;Let&apos;s go&quot;), &quot;miyo&quot; (literally, &quot;Let&apos;s see&quot;), &quot;neyo&quot; (literally, &quot;Let&apos;s go to bed&quot;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Examples) &apos;hashiro&apos; (literally, &apos;Let&apos;s run&apos;), &apos;iko&apos; (literally, &apos;Let&apos;s go&apos;), &apos;miyo&apos; (literally, &apos;Let&apos;s see&apos;), &apos;neyo&apos; (literally, &apos;Let&apos;s go to bed&apos;)</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>可能表現</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Epressions of Ability</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Expressions of Ability</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Expressions of Ability</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="57">
<j>標準語同様に「れる」、「られる」を付けて言える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As in the standard Japanese, the postfixes of &quot;reru&quot; and &quot;rareru&quot; are used to express ability.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As in the standard Japanese, the postfixes of &quot;reru&quot; and &quot;rareru&quot; are used to express ability.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As in the standard Japanese, the postfixes of &apos;reru&apos; and &apos;rareru&apos; are used to express ability.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>不可能を表す形は「～れへん」「～られへん」がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Negative expression of ability is made by adding &quot;--rehen&quot;and &quot;--rarehen&quot; to each verb.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Negative expression of ability is made by adding &quot;--rehen&quot;and &quot;--rarehen&quot; to each verb.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Negative expression of ability is made by adding &apos;... rehen&apos; and &apos;... rarehen&apos; to each verb.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="59">
<j>（例）「走れる」、「寝られる」、「走れへん」、「寝られへん」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Examples) &quot;hashireru&quot; (literally, &quot;can run&quot;), &quot;nerareru&quot; (literally &quot;can sleep&quot;), &quot;hashirehen&quot; (literally, &quot;cannot run&quot;), &quot;nerarehen&quot; (literally, &quot;cannot sleep&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Examples) &quot;hashireru&quot; (literally, &quot;can run&quot;), &quot;nerareru&quot; (literally &quot;can sleep&quot;), &quot;hashirehen&quot; (literally, &quot;cannot run&quot;), &quot;nerarehen&quot; (literally, &quot;cannot sleep&quot;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Examples) &apos;hashireru&apos; (literally, &apos;can run&apos;), &apos;nerareru&apos; (literally, &apos;can sleep&apos;), &apos;hashirehen&apos; (literally, &apos;cannot run&apos;), &apos;nerarehen&apos; (literally, &apos;cannot sleep&apos;)</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="60">
<j>「～れへん」形は誤解を招きやすいが、京都では多く使われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though open to misunderstanding, the expression of &quot;--rehen&quot; is often used in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though open to misunderstanding, the expression of &quot;--rehen&quot; is often used in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Alhough open to misunderstanding, the expression of &apos;... rehen&apos; is often used in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。 &quot;Though&quot; -&gt; &quot;Although&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="61">
<j>不可能を言う場合、「よう～ん」、「よう～ひん」の形を取ることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Expressions of inabiltiy, or negative expressions of ability, often take a form of &quot;yo --n&quot; or &quot;yo --hin.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Expressions of inabiltiy, or negative expressions of ability, often take a form of &quot;yo --n&quot; or &quot;yo --hin.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Expressions of inability, or negative expressions of ability, often take a form of &apos;yo... n&apos; or &apos;yo... hin.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="62">
<j>（例）「よう走らん」、「よう寝ん」、「よう起きひん」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Examples) &quot;yo hashiran&quot; (literally, &quot;cannot run&quot;), &quot;yo nen&quot; (literally, &quot;cannot sleep&quot;), &quot;yo okihin&quot; (literally, &quot;cannot get up&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Examples) &quot;yo hashiran&quot; (literally, &quot;cannot run&quot;), &quot;yo nen&quot; (literally, &quot;cannot sleep&quot;), &quot;yo okihin&quot; (literally, &quot;cannot get up&quot;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Examples) &apos;yo hashiran&apos; (literally, &apos;cannot run&apos;), &apos;yo nen&apos; (literally, &apos;cannot sleep&apos;), &apos;yo okihin&apos; (literally, &apos;cannot get up&apos;)</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>敬語</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Respectful Languages</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Respectful Languages</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Respectful Languages</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="63">
<j>…はる</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;--haru&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;--haru&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">... Haru</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="64">
<j>「なさる」の変形で、「なはる」とも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Nasaru (standard respectful form of &quot;do&quot;) may be modified to &quot;naharu.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Nasaru (standard respectful form of &quot;do&quot;) may be modified to &quot;naharu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nasaru&apos; (standard respectful form of &apos;do&apos;) may be modified to &apos;naharu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>日常的に多用される尊敬語表現で、関西の他地域よりも使用頻度が高いと同時に敬意度は低くなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Compared with other Kansai areas, this form of respectful expression is more mundanely used in Kyoto, but with less degrees of respect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Compared with other Kansai areas, this form of respectful expression is more mundanely used in Kyoto, but with less degrees of respect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Compared with other Kansai areas, this form of respectful expression is more mundanely used in Kyoto, but with less degrees of respect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>（例）「乗って来はるわ」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Example) &quot;notte kiharuwa&quot; (literally, &quot;Look, they are getting on&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Example) &quot;notte kiharuwa&quot; (literally, &quot;Look, they are getting on&quot;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Example) &apos;notte kiharuwa&apos; (literally, &apos;Look, they are getting on&apos;)</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="67">
<j>丁寧語として客観的立場から表現する用法もあり、これは京都周辺のみの表現である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Only in the surrounding areas of Kyoto, some polite languages are used to make an expression objective.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Only in the surrounding areas of Kyoto, some polite languages are used to make an expression objective.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Only in the surrounding areas of Kyoto, some polite languages are used to make an expression objective.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>（例）「うちの子ぉ、よう泣かはるやろ」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Example) &quot;Uchino Ko-o, yo-u nakaharuyaro&quot; (literally, &quot;As you see, our child cries very much&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Example) &quot;Uchino Ko-o, yo-u nakaharuyaro&quot; (literally, &quot;As you see, our child cries very much&quot;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Example) &apos;Uchino Ko-o, yo-u nakaharuyaro&apos; (literally, &apos;As you see, our child cries very much&apos;)</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="69">
<j>お…やす</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;o--yasu&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;o--yasu&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">O... yasu</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="70">
<j>敬意を伴った軽い命令表現で、挨拶などに用いる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is a light imperative expression with implied respects, and is used as greetings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is a light imperative expression with implied respects, and is used as greetings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is a light imperative expression with implied respects, and is used as greetings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>（例）「お越しやす」、「おかけやしとおくれやす」（どうぞお掛けくださいませ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Examples) &quot;Okoshiyasu&quot; (literelly, &quot;Welcome, here&quot;), &quot;okakeyashitookureyasu&quot; (dozo okakekudasaimase, literally, &quot;please take your seat&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Examples) &quot;Okoshiyasu&quot; (literelly, &quot;Welcome, here&quot;), &quot;okakeyashitookureyasu&quot; (dozo okakekudasaimase, literally, &quot;please take your seat&quot;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Examples) &apos;Okoshiyasu&apos; (literally, &apos;Welcome, here&apos;), &apos;okakeyashitookureyasu&apos; (also referred as dozo okakekudasaimase, literally, &apos;please take your seat&apos;)</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションなどを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="72">
<j>…といやす</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;--toiyasu&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;--toiyasu&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">... Toiyasu</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="73">
<j>「ておいやす」の変形。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is a converted form of &quot;--teoiyasu.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is a converted form of &quot;--teoiyasu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is a converted form of &apos;... teoiyasu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションなどを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>（例）「しといやした」（してらっしゃいました）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Example) &quot;--shitoiyasita&quot; (--shiterasshaimashita, literally &quot;you were kindly doing --&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Example) &quot;--shitoiyasita&quot; (--shiterasshaimashita, literally &quot;you were kindly doing --&quot;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Example) &apos;... shitoiyashita&apos; (... shiterasshaimashita, literally &apos;you were kindly doing...&apos;)</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションなどを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="75">
<j>…ておみ、とおみ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;--teomi, toomi&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;--teomi, toomi&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">... Teomi, Toomi</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="76">
<j>漢字で書くと「て御見」となり、共通語の「てごらん」に相当。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This can be written in Kanji as &quot;て御見&quot; which corresponds to the common language of &quot;tegoran&quot; (literarlly, &quot;You had better try to --.&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This can be written in Kanji as &quot;て御見&quot; which corresponds to the common language of &quot;tegoran&quot; (literarlly, &quot;You had better try to --.&quot;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This can be written in Kanji as &apos;て御見&apos; which corresponds to the common language of &apos;tegoran&apos; (literally, &apos;You had better try to....&apos;)</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションなどを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>（例）「見とおみ」（見てごらん）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Example) &quot;Mitoomi&quot; (Mitegoran, literally &quot;Would you look at --?&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Example) &quot;Mitoomi&quot; (Mitegoran, literally &quot;Would you look at --?&quot;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Example) &apos;Mitoomi&apos; (also referred as Mitegoran, literally &apos;Would you look at... ?&apos;)</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションなどを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="78">
<j>…よし</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;--yoshi&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;--yoshi&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">... Yoshi</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="79">
<j>同等・目下に対して用いる命令表現。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is an imperative expression used toward the equal or lower rank persons.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is an imperative expression used toward equal or lower ranking persons.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is an imperative expression used toward equal or lower ranking persons.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>（例）「はよ行きよし」（早く行きなさい）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Example) &quot;hayo ikiyoshi&quot; (hayaku ikinasai, literally &quot;you must go quickly&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Example) &quot;hayo ikiyoshi&quot; (hayaku ikinasai, literally &quot;you must go quickly&quot;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Example) &apos;hayo ikiyoshi&apos; (hayaku ikinasai, literally &apos;you must go quickly&apos;)</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションなどを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="81">
<j>…おす</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;--osu&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;--osu&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">... Osu</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="82">
<j>「ある」の丁寧語で、大阪の「おま（す）」に相当。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is a polite form of &quot;--aru&quot; (literally, &quot;(there) is/are,&quot; which is equivalent to &quot;--omasu&quot; in Osaka dialect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is a polite form of &quot;--aru&quot; (literally, &quot;(there) is/are,&quot; which is equivalent to &quot;--omasu&quot; in Osaka dialect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is a polite form of &apos;... aru&apos; (literally, &apos;(there) is,&apos; which is equivalent to &apos;... omasu&apos; in Osaka dialect.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションなどを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>形容詞の後ろにもつく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is also used by putting it after adjectives.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is also used by putting it after adjectives.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is also used by putting it after adjectives.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>（例）「誰もおへん」、「おいしおすなぁ」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Examples) &quot;daremo ohen&quot; (literally, &quot;nobody is there&quot;; &quot;oishiosu na&quot; (literally, &quot;this is very delicious, isn&apos;t it?&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Examples) &quot;daremo ohen&quot; (literally, &quot;nobody is there&quot;; &quot;oishiosu na&quot; (literally, &quot;this is very delicious, isn&apos;t it?&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Examples) &apos;daremo ohen&apos; (literally, &apos;nobody is there&apos;), &apos;oishiosu na&apos; (literally, &apos;this is very delicious, isn&apos;t it?&apos;)</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションなどを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="85">
<j>…どす</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;--dosu&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;--dosu&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">... Dosu</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="86">
<j>断定の丁寧語で、東京の「です」、大阪の「だす」に相当する良く知られた京言葉。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is one of well-known Kyo language as a polite form of decisive expression, corresponding to &quot;--desu&quot; in Tokyo dialect and &quot;--dasu&quot; in Osaka dialect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is one example of the well-known Kyo language as a polite form of decisive expression, corresponding to &quot;--desu&quot; in Tokyo dialect and &quot;--dasu&quot; in Osaka dialect.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is one example of the well-known Kyo language as a polite form of decisive expression, corresponding to &apos;... desu&apos; in Tokyo dialect and &apos;... dasu&apos; in Osaka dialect.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションなどを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>「でおす」の変形で、「どふ」とも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is a conversion from &quot;--deosu&quot;, and may be said as &quot;--dofu&quot;, too.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is a conversion from &quot;--deosu,&quot; and may be said as &quot;--dofu,&quot; too.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is a conversion from &apos;... deosu,&apos; and may be said as &apos;... dofu,&apos; too.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションなどを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>江戸末期から昭和にかけて男女とも用いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This expression were used by both men and women from the late Edo period to Showa era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This expression was used by both men and women from the late Edo period to the Showa era.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This expression was used by both men and women from the late Edo period to the Showa period.</e>
<cmt>用語を他の記事と統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>（例）「おめでとうさんどす」、「明日行かはるんどすか」、「そうどした」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Examples) &quot;Omedetosandosu&quot; (literally, &quot;Congratulation&quot;; &quot;Asu ikaharun dosuka&quot; (literally, &quot;Are you leaving tomorrow?&quot;); &quot;so dosita&quot; (literally, &quot;so you have told&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Examples) &quot;Omedetosandosu&quot; (literally, &quot;Congratulations;&quot; &quot;Asu ikaharun dosuka&quot; (literally, &quot;Are you leaving tomorrow?&quot;); &quot;so dosita&quot; (literally, &quot;so you have told&quot;)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Examples) &apos;Omedetosandosu&apos; (literally, &apos;congratulations&apos;), &apos;Asu ikaharun dosuka&apos; (literally, &apos;Are you leaving tomorrow?&apos;), &apos;so doshita&apos; (literally, &apos;so you have told&apos;)</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションなどを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>婉曲</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Euphemism</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Euphemism</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Euphemism</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="90">
<j>依頼や辞退を表すときには、直接的な言い方は避け、婉曲的で非断定的な言い回しを好む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the case of request or declination, Kyo language prefers euphemistic and indecisive expressions and avoids straightforward words.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the case of request or declination, Kyo language prefers euphemistic and indecisive expressions and avoids straightforward words.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the case of request or declination, Kyo language prefers euphemistic and indecisive expressions and avoids straightforward words.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="91">
<j>例えば「～して下さい」という要求をする時も、「～してもらわしまへんやろか」（～してもらえはしませんでしょうか）のような遠回しな否定疑問を用いる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, in order to make a request for somebody to &quot;do something&quot;, negative interrogatives by insinuation are used, such as &quot;-- shite morawashimahen yaroka&quot; (--shite moraewashimasen deshoka, literally &quot;Won&apos;t you kindly do --?&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, in order to make a request for somebody to &quot;do something,&quot; negative interrogatives by insinuation are used, such as &quot;-- shite morawashimahen yaroka&quot; (--shite moraewashimasen deshoka, literally &quot;Won&apos;t you kindly do --?&quot;)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, in order to make a request for somebody to &apos;do something,&apos; negative interrogatives by insinuation are used, such as &apos;... shite morawashimahen yaroka&apos; (... shite moraewashimasen deshoka, literally &apos;Won&apos;t you kindly do... ?&apos;).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションなどを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="92">
<j>辞退する時も、「おおきに」「考えときまっさ」などと曖昧な表現をすることによって、勧めてきた相手を敬った表現をする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When declining any solicitation, too, shadowy expressions are used, like &quot;ookini&quot; (literally, &quot;thank you&quot;), &quot;kangaetoki massa&quot; (literally, &quot;let me consider&quot;) and so on, which expressions are considered respectful to the solicitors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When declining any solicitation, too, shadowy expressions are used, like &quot;ookini&quot; (literally, &quot;thank you&quot;), &quot;kangaetoki massa&quot; (literally, &quot;let me consider&quot;) and so on, which expressions are considered respectful to the solicitors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When declining any solicitation, too, shadowy expressions are used, like &apos;ookini&apos; (literally, &apos;thank you&apos;), &apos;kangaetoki massa&apos; (literally, &apos;let me consider&apos;) and so on, which expressions are considered respectful to the solicitors.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションなどを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>また、「主人に訊かなければ分からない」などと他人を主体化させ、丁重に断る方法も良く用いられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another way used frequently to decline any request politely is to subjectify other persons like your husband, saying, for example, &quot;I have to ask for my husband&apos;s opinion.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another way used frequently to decline any request politely is to subjectify other persons like your husband, saying, for example, &quot;I have to ask for my husband&apos;s opinion.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another way used frequently to decline any request politely is to subjectify other persons like your husband, saying, for example, &apos;I have to ask for my husband&apos;s opinion.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="94">
<j>後述する「ぶぶ漬け」も、そのような直接的表現を嫌う風土によるものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As is described below, a story of &quot;bubu zuke&quot; was created in such a climate as people disliked any direct expression.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As is described below, a story of &quot;bubu zuke&quot; was created in such a climate as people disliked any direct expression.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As is described below, a story of &apos;bubu zuke&apos; was created in such a climate as people disliked any direct expression.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>ぶぶ漬け</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bubu zuke</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bubu zuke</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bubu Zuke</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="95">
<j>京都における非言語的コミュニケーション（ノンバーバル・コミュニケーション）を物語る上でよく用いられるのが、「ぶぶ漬け」（茶漬け）の例である（他に玄関先での「座布団」と寒い日の「火鉢」の例もある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a typical example of non-verbal communicatons in Kyoto, a story of &quot;bubu zuke&quot; (cha-zuke, literally &quot;a bowl of rice doused in hot tea&quot;) is often cited, though there are many other examples such as &quot;zabuton&quot; (literally, &quot;a cusion&quot;) on a doorstep and &quot;a hibachi brazier&quot; in a cold day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a typical example of non-verbal communicatons in Kyoto, a story of &quot;bubu zuke&quot; (cha-zuke, literally &quot;a bowl of rice doused in hot tea&quot;) is often cited, though there are many other examples such as &quot;zabuton&quot; (literally, &quot;a cusion&quot;) on a doorstep and &quot;a hibachi brazier&quot; in a cold day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a typical example of non-verbal communications in Kyoto, a story of &apos;bubu zuke&apos; (also referred as cha-zuke, literally &apos;a bowl of rice doused in hot tea&apos;) is often cited, although there are many other examples such as &apos;zabuton&apos; (literally, &apos;a cushion&apos;) on a doorstep and &apos;a hibachi brazier&apos; in a cold day.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。 &quot;though&quot; -&gt; &quot;although&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>これは、他人の家を訪問した際、その家の人にぶぶ漬けを勧められたら、それは帰宅をさりげなく促しているというものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This story of bubu zuke tells that, when you visit somebody and are offered bubu zuke, you must understand you are casually induced to leave soon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This story of bubu zuke tells that, when you visit somebody and are offered bubu zuke, you must understand you are casually induced to leave soon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This story of bubu zuke tells that, when you visit somebody and are offered bubu zuke, you must understand you are casually induced to leave soon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>その場合、家人はお茶漬の準備など全くしていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In that case, the host has never prepared any bubu zuke for you.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In that case, the host has never prepared any bubu zuke for you.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In that case, the host has never prepared any bubu zuke for you.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="98">
<j>一般に「今日はぶぶ漬け程度の粗食しかおもてなし出来ないので、日を改めてまた来てくれ」という意味に解釈されているが、角が立たないように自分の意思を伝える一種の取り決めごととも言えることで、京都という独特の閉鎖的社会だからこそ成り立った習慣である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the one hand, this story is generally interpreted as the host&apos;s apology to say,&quot;I cannot entertain you with anything more than bubu zuke today, so please come on the other day, if you like,&quot; but at the same time this is considered as a kind of communication rules to express the host&apos;s intention without giving bitter feelings, that is a special custom available only in such closed society as Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the one hand, this story is generally interpreted as the host&apos;s apology to say,&quot;I cannot entertain you with anything more than bubu zuke today, so please come on the other day, if you like,&quot; but at the same time this is considered as a kind of communication rules to express the host&apos;s intention without giving bitter feelings, that is a special custom available only in such closed society as Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the one hand, this story is generally interpreted as the host&apos;s apology to say, &apos;I cannot entertain you with anything more than bubu zuke today, so please come on the other day, if you like,&apos; but at the same time this is considered as a kind of communication rules to express the host&apos;s intention without giving bitter feelings, that is a special custom available only in such closed society as Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>そもそも「食事を勧められる」ということは、客がそのような食事時に訪問しているか、あるいは食事時まで居続けているということであり、常識的に考えれば失礼な行為に当たる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the first place, &quot;being offered any meal&quot;means that you are visiting him at mealtime or you have extended your stay until mealtime, and this kind of action should be regarded as unmannerly from a common-sense.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the first place, &quot;being offered any meal&quot;means that you are visiting him at mealtime or you have extended your stay until mealtime, and this kind of action should be regarded as unmannerly from common-sense.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the first place, &apos;being offered any meal&apos; means that you are visiting him at mealtime or you have extended your stay until mealtime, and this kind of action should be regarded as unmannerly from common-sense.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>家人が「食事を勧める」ことで、訪問者は時間を自覚でき、家人側も相手に対して失礼を犯さずに帰宅を要求することができる、という社交的な効果があると考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The host may expect a sociable effect of &quot;offering meals&quot; that reminds any guest of lapse of time and urges him to leave without discourteousness.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The host may expect a sociable effect of &quot;offering meals&quot; that reminds any guest of lapse of time and urges him to leave without discourteousness.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The host may expect a sociable effect of &apos;offering meals&apos; that reminds any guest of lapse of time and urges him to leave without discourteousness.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="101">
<j>この場合の理想的なやり取りとしては、家人がぶぶ漬けを勧めてきたら、客人は一旦はこれを固辞し、少なくとも2回断ってもまだ勧めてくるようだったら有難く家の中に上がって頂く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The most ideal case of such communications might be that, after once or twice the host offers bubu zuke which the guest declines, the host still offers it so that the guest may accept it and get into the house to take it with gratitude.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The most ideal case of such communications might be that, after once or twice the host offers bubu zuke which the guest declines, the host still offers it so that the guest may accept it and get into the house to take it with gratitude.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The most ideal case of such communications might be that, after once or twice the host offers bubu zuke which the guest declines, the host still offers it so that the guest may accept it and get into the house to take it with gratitude.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペースをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>ぶぶ漬けを勧められても一旦はこれを断るのは常識であり、もし遠慮も無く真に受けて食べてしまうと、家人に｢あの人は厚かましい｣という印象を抱かれてしまいかねない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered as a common-sense for a visitor to once decline an offer of bubu zuke, and, therefore, if he accepts the offer and takes it without reserve, he will give an impression to the host that &quot;he is bold.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered as a common-sense for a visitor to once decline an offer of bubu zuke, and, therefore, if he accepts the offer and takes it without reserve, he will give an impression to the host that &quot;he is bold.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered as a common-sense for a visitor to once decline an offer of bubu zuke, and, therefore, if he accepts the offer and takes it without reserve, he will give an impression to the host that &apos;he or she is bold.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="103">
<j>もっとも大抵の場合、1回または2回断った時点で家人はぶぶ漬けを勧めるのをあっさりやめるので、客人は｢ほな、この辺でお暇致します。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in most cases, the host will not continue to offer bubu zuke more than once or twice, and then the visitor may say &quot;Well, I have to leave now.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in most cases, the host will not continue to offer bubu zuke more than once or twice, and then the visitor may say &quot;Well, I have to leave now.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in most cases, the host will not continue to offer bubu zuke more than once or twice, and then the visitor may say &apos;Well, I have to leave now.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>今日はおおきに。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Thank you for your meeting me.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Thank you for meeting me.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thank you for meeting me.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>｣と家を引き取る行動を起こすのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, the visitor may take action of departure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, the visitor may take action to depart.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, the visitor may take action to depart.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>このとき家人が何らかの行動を起こして、さりげなく客人に帰るよう促すこともある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Otherwise, the host may sometimes take an action to casually induce the visitor to leave.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Otherwise, the host may sometimes take an action to casually induce the visitor to leave.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Otherwise, the host may sometimes take an action to casually induce the visitor to leave.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="107">
<j>ただし、実際にぶぶ漬けを用意して、他意なくご馳走しようとしている場合もあるので、相手の真意を探るには阿吽の呼吸とも言える絶妙なテクニックが必要となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nevertheless, since it is possible that some hosts might actually wish to entertain his guest by bubu zuke, visitors are required to be skilled in the technique of rhythmic breathing to understand the host&apos;s real intent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nevertheless, since it is possible that some hosts might actually wish to entertain his guest with bubu zuke, visitors are required to be skilled in the technique of rhythmic breathing to understand the host&apos;s real intent.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nevertheless, since it is possible that some hosts might in fact wish to entertain his guest with bubu zuke, visitors are required to be skilled in the technique of rhythmic breathing to understand the host&apos;s real intent.</e>
<cmt>&quot;actually&quot; -&gt; &quot;in fact&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="108">
<j>もちろん、「ぶぶ漬け」はあくまで喩えであり、その他の日常生活においても、京都ではコミュニケーションにおける伝統的な暗黙の了解事項が多々存在しており、一言では到底説明し切れない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Needless to say, the story of &quot;bubu zuke&quot; is just a parable of one of so many traditional implicit communications existing in the daily life of the people living in Kyoto that may never be explained in a simple sentence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Needless to say, the story of &quot;bubu zuke&quot; is just a parable of one of so many traditional implicit communications existing in the daily life of the people living in Kyoto that may never be explained in a simple sentence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Needless to say, the story of &apos;bubu zuke&apos; is just a parable of one of so many traditional implicit communications existing in the daily life of the people living in Kyoto that may never be explained in a simple sentence.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションなどを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="109">
<j>実際に京都で生活していないと分からない感覚なのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This kind of sense is very special which can never be felt unless actually living in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This kind of sense is very special which can never be felt unless having the experience of actually living in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>word spacing, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This kind of sense is very special which can never be felt unless having the experience of in fact living in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>&quot;actually&quot; -&gt; &quot;in fact&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="110">
<j>どちらにせよ、古くからの慣習によって成り立っているそのコミュニケーションに慣れていない非京都圏の人々には全く意図が伝わらず、慌てて実際に料理を用意しなければならない場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Any of such communication ways of Kyoto people as established through their traditional customs is usually unfamiliar to the people of non-Kyoto area, and causes various troubles of miscommunication; for example, a host might be compelled to prepare any meal in a hurry.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Any of such ways of communication of Kyoto people as established through their traditional customs is usually unfamiliar to the people of non-Kyoto areas, and causes various troubles of miscommunication; for example, a host might be compelled to prepare any meal in a hurry.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Any of such ways of communication of Kyoto people as established through their traditional customs is usually unfamiliar to the people of non-Kyoto areas, and causes various troubles of miscommunication; for example, a host might be compelled to prepare any meal in a hurry.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペースをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>また、逆に非京都圏の客人が単に「帰っておくれやす。」の意味としてだけ知っていた場合、客人の心証を害す等、余計なトラブルを招きかねないので、気心知れた相手以外には用いないことが奨められる戦略である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another example of such trouble is to give an unfavorable impression to any guest who knows the implication of bubu zuke simply as &quot;kaette okure yasu&quot; (literally, &quot;please leave here,&quot;) which may possibly lead them to any unnecessary conflict; and, such being the case, bubu zuke and other typical communication ways of traditional Kyoto people are not recommended to use except between congenial persons.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another example of such trouble is to give an unfavorable impression to any guest who knows the implication of bubu zuke simply as &quot;kaette okure yasu&quot; (literally, &quot;please leave here,&quot;) which may possibly lead them to an unnecessary conflict; and, such being the case, bubu zuke and other typical communication ways of traditional Kyoto people are not recommended to use except for between congenial persons.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another example of such trouble is to give an unfavorable impression to any guest who knows the implication of bubu zuke simply as &apos;kaette okure yasu&apos; (literally, &apos;please leave here&apos;), which may possibly lead them to an unnecessary conflict; and, such being the case, bubu zuke and other typical communication ways of traditional Kyoto people are not recommended to use except for between congenial persons.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペースをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="112">
<j>なお「ぶぶ漬け」に関するエピソードを扱った小説には北森鴻『ぶぶ漬け伝説の謎』（同名の短編集に収められている）が存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An episode concerning &quot;bubu zuke&quot; is cited in a novel &quot;Mystery of bubu-zuke legend&quot; by Ko KITAMORI (contained in a collection of short stories of the same title.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An episode concerning &quot;bubu zuke&quot; is cited in a novel &quot;Mystery of bubu-zuke legend&quot; by Ko KITAMORI (contained in a collection of short stories of the same title.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An episode concerning &apos;bubu zuke&apos; is cited in a novel &quot;Mystery of bubu-zuke legend&quot; by Ko KITAMORI (contained in a collection of short stories of the same title).</e>
<cmt>一部クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="113">
<j>北森はこの小説の中で登場人物に次のような内容を語らせている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this novel, the author has let a character speak as follows:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this novel, the author has a character speak as follows:</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this novel, the author has a character speak as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="114">
<j>「ぶぶ漬け伝説は非常によく知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Bubu zuke legend is widely known.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Bubu zuke legend is widely known.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bubu zuke legend is widely known.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>しかし、現実にそのとおりの体験をした人となると聞かない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But, I&apos;ve never heard of any person who has actually experienced it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But, I&apos;ve never heard of any person who has actually experienced it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But, I&apos;ve never heard of any person who has in fact experienced it.</e>
<cmt>&quot;actually&quot; -&gt; &quot;in fact&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="116">
<j>京都の人に聞いても、そういった仕打ちをしたという人もいない」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nor, any one living in Kyoto told me to have treated a guest in that way.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nor, any one living in Kyoto told me about having treated a guest in that way.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nor, any one living in Kyoto told me about having treated a guest in that way.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>語彙</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Vocabulary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Vocabulary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Vocabulary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="117">
<j>「～なはい」や「～や」、「～え」などの接語の他にも、独特の表現や語彙が存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to such typical clitics as --nahai&quot; and &quot;--e&quot;, many distinctive expressions and vocabularies are used in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to such typical clitics as --nahai&quot; and &quot;--e&quot;, many distinctive expressions and vocabularies are used in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to such typical clitic words as &apos;... nahai,&apos; &apos;... ya&apos; and &apos;... e,&apos; many distinctive expressions and vocabularies are used in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>補足し、クォーテーションなどを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="118">
<j>また、「駄々をこねる子」のことを「ダダコ」と表現したりと、別の品詞から名詞を作り出して用いるパターンが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kyo language, there are many patterns creating new nouns from other word classes, like &quot;dadako&quot; which is made from &quot;dadawo koneru ko&quot; (a child who throws a terrible tantrum.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Kyo language, there are many patterns creating new nouns from other word classes, like &quot;dadako&quot; which is made from &quot;dadawo koneru ko&quot; (a child who throws a terrible tantrum.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Kyo language, there are many patterns creating new nouns from other word classes, like &apos;dadako&apos; which is made from &apos;dadawo koneru ko&apos; (a child who throws a terrible tantrum).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="119">
<j>また、名詞（主に生活に関するもの）に関して用いられる「お～」や「お～さん（はん）」があり、以下のように利用される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As well, some nouns (mainly concerned to a daily life) are modified to &quot;o--&quot; and &quot;o--san (han)&quot; to be used in the following ways:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As well, some nouns (mainly concerned to a daily life) are modified to &quot;o--&quot; and &quot;o--san (han)&quot; to be used in the following ways:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As well, some nouns (mainly concerned to a daily life) are modified to &apos;o...&apos; and &apos;o... san (han)&apos; to be used in the following ways:</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションなどを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="120">
<j>「おつむ」 - 頭</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;otsumu&quot; -- atama (head)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;otsumu&quot; -- atama (head)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">otsumu: atama (head)</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="121">
<j>「おつくり」 - 刺身</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;otsukuri&quot; -- sashimi (sliced raw fish)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;otsukuri&quot; -- sashimi (sliced raw fish)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">otsukuri: sashimi (sliced raw fish)</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="122">
<j>「おねもじ」 - ネギ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;onemoji&quot; -- negi (leeks)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;onemoji&quot; -- negi (leeks)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">onemoji: negi (leeks)</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="123">
<j>「おあげさん」 - 油揚げ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;oagesan&quot;--aburaage (deep fried bean curd)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;oagesan&quot;--aburaage (deep fried bean curd)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">oagesan: aburaage (deep fried bean curd)</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="124">
<j>「おくどさん」 - 竃（かまど）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;okudosan&quot; -- kamado (furnace)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;okudosan&quot; -- kamado (furnace)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">okudosan: kamado (furnace)</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>畳語</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Folding Words</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Folding Words</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Folding Words</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="125">
<j>同じ言葉を繰り返して、意味を強調する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By repeating the same word, its meaning is emphasized.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By repeating the same word, its meaning is emphasized.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By repeating the same word, its meaning is emphasized.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="126">
<j>「承りましてございますでございます」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Uketamawarimashite gozaimasu de gozaimasu&quot; (literally, &quot;I have respectfully acknowledged it&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Uketamawarimashite gozaimasu de gozaimasu&quot; (literally, &quot;I have respectfully acknowledged it&quot;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Uketamawarimashite gozaimasu de gozaimasu&apos; (literally, &apos;I have respectfully acknowledged it&apos;)</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="127">
<j>「キツキツ言う」（強く言う）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kitsu-kitsu iu&quot; (tsuyoku iu, literally, &quot;say strongly&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kitsu-kitsu iu&quot; (tsuyoku iu, literally, &quot;say strongly&quot;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kitsu-kitsu iu&apos; (also referred as tsuyoku iu, literally, &apos;say strongly&apos;)</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="128">
<j>「赤こ赤こ（あこあこ）なってきてますえ」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Ako-ako natte kimasue&quot; (literally, &quot;it will become richly red&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Ako-ako natte kimasue&quot; (literally, &quot;it will become richly red&quot;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ako-ako natte kimasue&apos; (literally, &apos;it will become richly red&apos;)</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="129">
<j>など。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And so on.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="14">
<tit>
<j>擬音語・擬態語</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Onomatopoeia and Mimetic Words</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Onomatopoeia and Mimetic Words</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Onomatopoeia and Mimetic Words</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="130">
<j>京言葉では修辞技法（オノマトペ）を多用し、リズム感を構成する一因となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyo language uses many rhetorical techniques (onomatopoeia) to compose an element of rhythmic structure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyo language uses many rhetorical techniques (onomatopoeia) to compose an element of rhythmic structure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyo language uses many rhetorical techniques (onomatopoeia) to compose an element of rhythmic structure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="131">
<j>「ガタガタ」、「ミルミル」などというようなものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Gata gata&quot;, &quot;miru miru&quot;, and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Gata gata,&quot; &quot;miru miru,&quot; and others.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gata gata,&apos; &apos;miru miru,&apos; and others.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="132">
<j>また、「はんなり」のような2音節目に「ん」、4音節目に「り」を持つ擬態語（「ぐんなり」、「ちんまり」など）が多く存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also many mimetic words are used like &quot;gunnari&quot;(literally, &quot;limb (adjective)&quot;), &quot;chinmari&quot; (literally, &quot;very small&quot;) and so on, which have &quot;n&quot; at the second syllable and &quot;ri&quot; at the fourth syllable as in the word &quot;hannari.&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also many mimetic words are used like &quot;gunnari&quot; (literally, &quot;limb&quot; - adjective), &quot;chinmari&quot; (literally, &quot;very small&quot;) and so on, which have &quot;n&quot; at the second syllable and &quot;ri&quot; at the fourth syllable as in the word &quot;hannari.&quot;.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also many mimetic words are used like &apos;gunnari&apos; (literally, &apos;limb&apos;), &apos;chinmari&apos; (literally, &apos;very small&apos;) and so on, which have &apos;n&apos; at the second syllable and &apos;ri&apos; at the fourth syllable as in the word &apos;hannari.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="133">
<j>「はんなり」の語源は「花」であるが、これはけばけばしい「華やかさ」を表しているわけではなく、つつましく可憐な様子を表す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though the word &quot;hannari&quot; originates from &quot;flower&quot;, it means humble and pretty appearances rather than &quot;flamboyant&quot; ones.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though the word &quot;hannari&quot; originates from &quot;flower,&quot; it means humble and pretty appearances rather than &quot;flamboyant&quot; ones.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though the word &apos;hannari&apos; originates from &apos;flower,&apos; it means humble and pretty appearances rather than &apos;flamboyant&apos; ones.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Snow rabbit(id:95634), Kkkdc(id:32227), Enirac Sum(id:12090), とーととと(id:165841), Hhaithait(id:37092), FAT26(id:9460), まったけ(id:130042), Kyoww(id:126965), Rainbow(id:10288), Flénu(id:159955), TAMA(id:25299), 榎(id:91458), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>