<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>践祚</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Senso (to Become New Emperor)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Senso (to Become New Emperor)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Senso (to Become New Emperor)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>践祚（せんそ）とは、天子の位を受け継ぐことであり、それは先帝の崩御あるいは譲位によって行われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term &quot;Senso&quot; means to succeed the position of Tenshi emperor upon the demise of the previous emperor or his abdication from the position.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term &quot;Senso&quot; means to succeed the position of Tenshi emperor upon the demise of the previous emperor or his abdication from the position.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term &quot;Senso&quot; means to succeed the position of Tenshi (emperor) upon the demise of the previous emperor or his abdication from the position.</e>
<cmt>Tenshi emperor→Tenshi (emperor)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>古くは「践阼」と書き、「践」とは位に就くこと、「阼」は天子の位を意味する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In ancient times, this term was written in kanji script as &apos;践阼,&apos; while &apos;践&apos; means to take an official position and &apos;阼&apos; means the position of the Tensi emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In ancient times, this term was written in kanji script as &apos;践阼,&apos; while &apos;践&apos; means to take an official position and &apos;阼&apos; means the position of the Tensi emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In ancient times, this term was written in kanji script as &apos;践阼,&apos; while &apos;践&apos; means to take an official position and &apos;阼&apos; means the position of the Tensi emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>これに続いて位に就いた事を内外に明らかにする事を即位という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Senso is followed by relevant proclamation, which is called enthronement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Senso is followed by a relevant proclamation, which is called enthronement.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Senso is followed by a relevant proclamation, which is called enthronement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>日本に於いては古く、桓武天皇以前は即位と同義であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before the reign of Kanmu, the term Senso had been used in the same meaning as enthronement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before the reign of Kanmu, the term Senso had been used to mean enthronement.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before the reign of Kanmu, the term Senso had been used to mean enthronement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>第51代天皇である平城天皇は、即位に先立ってこの践祚を行い、その後に即位式を行っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">51st Emperor Heijo had executed this Senso prior to the enthronement, and then the coronation followed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">51st Emperor Heijo had executed Senso prior to the enthronement, and then the coronation followed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fifty-first Emperor, Heijo had executed Senso prior to the enthronement, and then the coronation followed.</e>
<cmt>51st Emperor→The fifty-first Emperor,に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>これ以後、践祚と即位の区別がなされるようになったと思われる（このため、践祚のみで即位式が行われなかった仲恭天皇は、「半帝」と呼ばれて太上天皇号も崩御後の諡号も贈られる事も無かった（「仲恭」の諡号が贈られたのは実に崩御から636年後の事であった））。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Subsequently, the term Senso was likely distinguished from that of enthronement and coronation, and for this reason Emperor Chukyo, who had become the emperor by Senso without enthronement ceremony or coronation, was called Hantei (halfway emperor) and was bestowed no daijo-tenno-go (name of the retired emperor) after his retirement nor any shigo (posthumous name) after his demise (his shigo was given 636 years later after his death.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently, the term Senso was likely distinguished from that of enthronement and coronation, and for this reason Emperor Chukyo, who had become the emperor by Senso without an enthronement ceremony or coronation, was called Hantei (halfway emperor) and was not bestowed no daijo-tenno-go (name of the retired emperor) after his retirement nor any shigo (posthumous name) after his demise (his shigo was given 636 years after his death.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently, the term Senso was likely distinguished from that of enthronement and coronation, and for this reason Emperor Chukyo, who had become the emperor by Senso without an enthronement ceremony or coronation, was called Hantei (halfway emperor) and was not bestowed no daijo-tenno-go (name of the retired emperor) after his retirement nor any shigo (posthumous name) after his demise (his shigo was given 636 years after his death.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>践祚にかかる儀式を『践祚の儀』といい、先帝崩御後直ちに行われる『剣璽』及び新帝が即位後初めて三権の長（内閣総理大臣、衆議院議長、参議院議長、最高裁判所長官）を引見される『即位後朝見の儀』は共に国事行為とされ、先帝の諒闇が明けて行われる即位の礼と続く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A series of ceremonies related to the Senso are called &quot;Senso-no-gi (ceremonies to become a new emperor)&quot; which are regarded as a part of emperor&apos;s constitutional functions, being composed of the first ceremony named Kenji (ceremony for imperial succession) to be executed immediately after the demise of previous emperor, and the second ceremony named Sokuigo Choken-no-gi (ceremony to have an audience with the emperor after enthronement) for the Sanken-no-cho (chiefs of three organizations of power, namely the prime minister, the chairmen of House of Representatives and the House of Councillors, and the Chief Justice,) and being followed by the next ceremony named Sokui-no-rei (ceremony of the enthronement) which is to be held after the end of ryoan (period to mourn for the passing of emperor.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A series of ceremonies related to Senso are called &quot;Senso-no-gi (ceremonies to become a new emperor)&quot; which are regarded as a part of the emperor&apos;s constitutional functions, being composed of the first ceremony named Kenji (ceremony for imperial succession) to be executed immediately after the demise of the previous emperor, and the second ceremony named Sokuigo Choken-no-gi (ceremony to have an audience with the emperor after enthronement) for the Sanken-no-cho (chiefs of three organizations of power, namely the prime minister, the chairmen of House of Representatives and the House of Councillors, and the Chief Justice,) and being followed by the next ceremony named Sokui-no-rei (ceremony of the enthronement) which is to be held after the end of ryoan (period to mourn for the passing of emperor.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A series of ceremonies related to Senso are called &quot;Senso-no-gi (ceremonies to become a new emperor)&quot; which are regarded as a part of the emperor&apos;s constitutional functions, being composed of the first ceremony named Kenji (ceremony for imperial succession) to be executed immediately after the demise of the previous emperor, and the second ceremony named Sokuigo Choken-no-gi (ceremony to have an audience with the emperor after enthronement) for the Sanken-no-cho (chiefs of three organizations of power, namely the prime minister, the chairmen of House of Representatives and the House of Councillors, and the Chief Justice,) and being followed by the next ceremony named Sokui-no-rei (ceremony of the enthronement) which is to be held after the end of ryoan (period to mourn for the passing of emperor.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>践祚し皇位を継承するには『三種の神器』を先帝から受け継ぐことが要求される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial succession requires for a new emperor to inherit the three sacred imperial treasures from the previous emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial succession requires for a new emperor to inherit the three sacred imperial treasures from the previous emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial succession requires for a new emperor to inherit the three sacred imperial treasures from the previous emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>三種の神器は八咫鏡・八尺瓊勾玉・天叢雲剣で構成されるが、その内八咫鏡は祀られている賢所を含む宮中三殿を相続する事によって受継ぎ、八尺瓊勾玉・天叢雲剣を受継ぐ儀式が剣璽となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The three sacred imperial treasures are composed of Yata-no-Kagami mirror, Yasakani-no-Magatama (comma-shaped jewel) and Ama-no-Murakumo-no-Tsurugi sword, each of which is enshrined in the Kyuchu-sanden (three sacred shrines in the imperial palace) including Kashiko-dokoro where Yata-no-Kagami mirror is stored, while all of which, both jewels and shrines, are succeeded by the new emperor and the above said Kenji ceremony is held as a ritual for succession of Yasakani-no-Magatama and Ama-no-Murakumo-no-Tsurugi sword.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The three sacred imperial treasures are composed of Yata-no-Kagami mirror, Yasakani-no-Magatama (comma-shaped jewel) and Ama-no-Murakumo-no-Tsurugi sword, each of which is enshrined in the Kyuchu-sanden (three sacred shrines in the imperial palace) including Kashiko-dokoro where the Yata-no-Kagami mirror is stored, while all of which, both jewels and shrines, are succeeded by the new emperor and the above said Kenji ceremony is held as a ritual for succession of Yasakani-no-Magatama and Ama-no-Murakumo-no-Tsurugi sword.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The three sacred imperial treasures are composed of Yata-no-Kagami mirror, Yasakani-no-Magatama (comma-shaped jewel) and Ama-no-Murakumo-no-Tsurugi sword, each of which is enshrined in the Kyuchu-sanden (three sacred shrines in the imperial palace) including Kashiko-dokoro where the Yata-no-Kagami mirror is stored, while all of which, both jewels and shrines, are succeeded by the new emperor and the above said Kenji ceremony is held as a ritual for succession of Yasakani-no-Magatama and Ama-no-Murakumo-no-Tsurugi sword.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>皇位そのものの証明は三種の神器の所持を以て挙げられるため、南北朝正閏論に於いては神器が無いまま即位した北朝 (日本)の正当性が否定される根拠の一つとなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the imperial throne itself may be approved by retention of the three sacred imperial treasures, the Nanbokucho-Seijunron (argument on legitimacy of either Northern or Southern Court) has a base of its denial of orthodoxy of Hokucho (Northern court) which ascended to the throne without three sacred imperial treasures.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the imperial throne itself may be approved by the retention of the three sacred imperial treasures, the Nanbokucho-Seijunron (argument on legitimacy of either Northern or Southern Court) has a basis for its denial of orthodoxy of Hokucho (Northern court) which ascended to the throne without the three sacred imperial treasures.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the imperial throne itself may be approved by the retention of the three sacred imperial treasures, the Nanbokucho-Seijunron (argument on legitimacy of either Northern or Southern Court) has a basis for its denial of orthodoxy of Hokucho (Northern court) which ascended to the throne without the three sacred imperial treasures.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="12">
<j>現行の皇室典範は、次のように定めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the Imperial House Act, the followings are ordained:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the Imperial House Act, the following are ordained:</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the Imperial House Act, the following are ordained:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>第四条　天皇が崩じたときは、皇嗣が、直ちに即位する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Article 4. When the emperor has demised, the crown prince shall immediately assume the throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Article 4. When the emperor has demised, the crown prince shall immediately assume the throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Article 4. When the emperor has demised, the crown prince shall immediately assume the throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="14">
<j>第二十四条　皇位の継承があつたときは、即位の礼を行う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Article 24. When imperial throne is succeeded, the Sokui-no-rei (ceremony of the enthronement) shall be held.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Article 24. When imperial throne is succeeded, the Sokui-no-rei (ceremony of the enthronement) shall be held.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Article 24. When imperial throne is succeeded, the Sokui-no-rei (ceremony of the enthronement) shall be held.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="15">
<j>ここにいう「即位」は、平城天皇から昭和天皇までの「践祚」と同じ概念である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term &quot;Sokui (enthronement)&quot; specified herein has the same concept as the term &quot;Senso (to become a new emperor&quot; used for the emperors from Emperor Heijo to Emperor Showa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term &quot;Sokui (enthronement)&quot; specified herein has the same concept as the term &quot;Senso (to become a new emperor&quot; used for the emperors from Emperor Heijo to Emperor Showa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term &apos;Sokui (enthronement)&apos; specified herein has the same concept as the term &apos;Senso (to become a new emperor)&apos; used for the emperors from Emperor Heijo to Emperor Showa.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に)補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>昭和天皇までの「即位」は、現行皇室典範の「即位の礼」に当たるものと解される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term &quot;Sokui (enthronement)&quot; applied to the consecuutive lineage of emperors upto Emperor Showa is understood equivalent to &quot;Sokui-no-rei (ceremony of the enthronement)&quot; specified in the current Imperial House Act.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term &quot;Sokui (enthronement)&quot; applied to the consecuutive lineage of emperors up to Emperor Showa is understood as equivalent to &quot;Sokui-no-rei (ceremony of the enthronement)&quot; specified in the current Imperial House Act.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term &apos;Sokui (enthronement)&apos; applied to the consecuutive lineage of emperors up to Emperor Showa is understood as equivalent to &apos;Sokui-no-rei (ceremony of the enthronement)&apos; specified in the current Imperial House Act.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Poe(id:16973), พริกขี้หนู(id:131976), Fryed-peach(id:63402), Nnh(id:474), MIsogi(id:20599), 代言人(id:33675), 水野白楓(id:22811), くっちゃめ(id:86793), Veinte(id:16767), 伏儀(id:142093), Hatsune(id:26654), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>