<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>天保暦</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tenpo-reki (Tenpo calendar)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tenpo-reki (Tenpo calendar)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tenpo-reki (Tenpo calendar)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>天保暦（てんぽうれき）とは、かつて日本において使用された太陰太陽暦の暦法である和暦である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tenpo-reki (Tenpo calendar) is rekiho (method of making calendars) of Japanese calendar of the lunar solar calendar, which used to be used in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tenpo-reki (Tenpo calendar) is rekiho (method of making calendars) of Japanese calendar for the lunar solar calendar, used in old Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tenpo-reki (or Tenpo calendar) is a Japanese calendar based on the lunar solar calendar used in old Japan.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>正式には天保壬寅元暦（てんぽうじんいんげんれき）と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Officially it is called Tenpo jiningenreki.</e>
<cmt>天保壬寅元暦→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Officially it is called Tenpo jiningenreki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Officially, it is called Tenpo jiningenreki.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>これは過去に中国で用いられた暦法にも同名の天保暦が存在するためである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is called above since there used to be Tenpo-reki (Tenpo calendar) of rekiho (method of making calendars) which was used in China in the past.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is called as above since there used to be Tenpo-reki (Tenpo calendar) of rekiho (method of making calendars) used in China in the past.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is because the calendar of the same name Tenpo-reki was previously used in China.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>日本の旧暦は、広義にはグレゴリオ暦導入以前の和暦日本で使用された暦・紀元一覧をさすが、狭義にはこの天保暦をさす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a wide sense, Japanese old calendar means the calendar, the list of era which were used in Japan before introducing the Gregorian calendar, but in a narrow sense it means this Tenpo-reki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In a wide sense, Japanese old calendar means a calendar, that lists eras used in Japan before introducing the Gregorian calendar, but in a narrow sense it means Tenpo-reki.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In a wide sense, Japanese old calendar means all the calendars and eras adopted in Japan before the Gregorian calendar was introduced, but in a narrow sense, it means Tenpo-reki.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>注意</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Attention</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Attention</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Attention</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>西暦と明治6年以降の日付は、グレゴリオ暦。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Christian Era and the date after 1873 is in the Gregorian calendar style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Christian Era and dates after 1873 are in the Gregorian calendar style.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Christian Era and dates after 1873 are in the Gregorian calendar system.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>使用期間</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The period when the Tenpo calendar was used</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The period when the Tenpo calendar was used</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The period when the Tenpo calendar was used</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>天保15年1月1日 (旧暦)（1844年2月18日）に寛政暦から改暦され、明治5年12月2日 (旧暦)（1872年12月31日）まで約29年間使用された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 18, 1844(the old calendar), it was changed from Kansei-reki (Kansei calendar) and was used for about twenty nine years until December 31, 1872.(the old calendar)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 18, 1844 it (the old calendar), was changed from the Kansei-reki (Kansei calendar) and used for about twenty nine years until December 31, 1872. (the old calendar)</e>
<cmt>spacing, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 18, 1844, it was changed from the Kansei calendar and used for about twenty nine years until December 31, 1872.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>明治6年（1873年）1月1日、グレゴリオ暦（太陽暦）に改暦される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 1, 1873, it was changed to the Gregorian calendar (solar calendar).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 1, 1873, it was changed to the Gregorian calendar (solar calendar).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 1, 1873, it was changed to the Gregorian calendar (solar calendar).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="9">
<j>渋川景佑らが西洋天文学の成果を取り入れて完成させた暦で、実施された太陰太陽暦としてはそれまでで最も精密なものであるとして評価されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kagesuke SHIBUKAWA completed this calendar after he introduced the content of western astronomy, it was considered the most accurate calendar as the lunar solar calendar which was practically being used so far.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kagesuke SHIBUKAWA completed this calendar after he introduced western astronomy to Japan, it was considered the most accurate lunar solar calendar and has been practically used so far.</e>
<cmt>grammar, wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kagesuke SHIBUKAWA completed this calendar after he introduced western astronomy to Japan, and the calendar was considered the most accurate lunar solar calendar which had been practically used.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>平山清次の計算によれば、平均太陽年365.24219日・平均朔望月29.530589日に対して、天保暦の太陽年は365.24223日・朔望月29.530588日であり、グレゴリオ暦の太陽年365.2425日よりも誤差が小さいとされている（『暦法及時法』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the calculation of Kiyotsugu HIRAYAMA, a solar years of Tenpo-reki is 365,24223 days, synodic month of 29.530588 days, on the contrary to the average solar year of 365.24219, the average syndic month of 29.530589 days, it is said the difference is smaller than the number of 365.2425 days which came from the Gregorian calendar. (&quot;Rekiho oyobi Jiho&quot;) (calendar and timetable method)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the calculation of Kiyotsugu HIRAYAMA, a solar year of Tenpo-reki is 365.24223 days, synodic month of 29.530588 days, on the contrary to the average solar year of 365.24219, the average syndic month of 29.530589 days, it is said the difference is smaller than the number of 365.2425 days that came from the Gregorian calendar. (&quot;Rekiho oyobi Jiho&quot;) (calendar and timetable method)</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the calculation of Kiyotsugu HIRAYAMA,a solar year of Tenpo-reki is 365.24223 days and a synodic month is 29.530588 days, whereas the average solar year is 365.24219 and the average synodic month is 29.530589 days; it is said the difference is smaller than the solar year of 365.2425 days of the Gregorian calendar (&quot;Rekiho oyobi Jiho&quot; (calendar and timetable method).)</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="11">
<j>寛政暦までは、二十四節気を1年間を等分（時間分割）して計算する「平気法」が使用されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before Kansei-reki (Kansei calendar) was introduced, &apos; Heikiho&apos; (a way of expressing 24 divisions of the old calendar) was used which was calculated by dividing one year equally (divided by time), 24 divisions of the old calendar.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before the Kansei-reki (Kansei calendar) was introduced, &apos; Heikiho&apos; (a way of expressing 24 divisions of the old calendar) was used and was calculated by dividing one year equally (divided by time), into 24 divisions of the old calendar.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before the Kansei-reki (Kansei calendar) was introduced, &apos; Heikiho&apos; (a way of expressing 24 divisions of the old calendar) was used and was calculated by dividing one year equally (divided by time), into 24 divisions of the old calendar.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>天保暦では太陽の位置を計算し、天球上の太陽の軌道を24等分（空間分割）して二十四節気を求める「定気法」を採用した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Tenpo-reki, Teikiho (a way of expressing 24 divisions of the old calendar) was used, which is the method to calculate the position of the sun and divide the orbit of the sun on the the celestial sphere by twenty four (divide in the space) to come up with 24 divisions of the old calendar.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Tenpo-reki, Teikiho (a way of expressing 24 divisions of the old calendar) was used, which is the method to calculate the position of the sun and divide the orbit of the sun on the the celestial sphere by twenty four (divide in the space) to come up with 24 divisions of the old calendar.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Tenpo-reki, Teikiho (a way of expressing 24 divisions of the old calendar) was used, which is the method to calculate the position of the sun and divide the orbit of the sun on the celestial sphere by twenty-four (divide in the space) to obtain 24 divisions of the old calendar.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>しかし、定気法の採用については置閏法（閏月の置き方）がかえって複雑になったとの批判がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However there is some criticism of introducing Teikiho, since it made Chijun-ho (a calendar technique of setting leap month and leap day) (how to place a leap month) more complicated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However there was some criticism about introducing Teikiho, since it made Chijun-ho (a calendar technique of setting the leap month and leap day) (how to place a leap month) more complicated.</e>
<cmt>grammar, word spacing,</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However there was some criticism about introducing Teikiho, since it made Chijun-ho (a calendar system of setting the leap month) more complicated.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>これにより2033年の日付がおかしくなるという問題（定義通り運用すると9月の次が11月になってしまう）が報告されている（旧暦2033年問題）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to this, there is a report that there will be an issue of having date confused in 2033 (if it is used in accordance with its definition, month of November will come after September) (the issue of the old calendar 2033)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of this, there is a report that says there will be an issue with having the date confused in 2033 (if it is used in accordance with its definition, the month of November will come after September) (the issue of the old calendar 2033)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of this, it is reported that the date will be confused in 2033 (if it is used in accordance with its definition, the month of November will come after September) (the issue of the old calendar 2033).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>また、中国や西洋の流れに反して不定時法を暦法において公式に導入したことに関しても強い批判がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also there is a strong criticism for officially introducing Futei-jiho (Japanese classical Timetable Method) in rekiho (method of making calendars), which was going against the influence of China and Europe.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also there is a strong criticism for officially introducing Futei-jiho (Japanese classical Timetable Method) in rekiho (method of making calendars), going against the influence of China and Europe.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also there is a strong criticism for officially introducing the Japanese classical Timetable Method in the calendar, going against the influence of China and Europe.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="16">
<j>なお明治維新の際、陰陽寮・土御門晴雄が太陽暦導入に反対して、太陰太陽暦に基づく改暦を企図したが、明治2年に晴雄の急逝により計画が中止されたために、天保暦が日本における最後の太陰太陽暦となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By the way, Onmyoryo (Bureau of Divination), Haruo TSUCHIMIKADO was against introducing solar calendar and suggested the plan to change the calendar of the lunar solar calendar during the period of Meiji Restoration, however after he died suddenly, this plan was cancelled and Tenpo-reki became the last lunar solar calendar in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Onmyoryo&apos;s (Bureau of Divination), Haruo TSUCHIMIKADO was against introducing the solar calendar and suggested a plan to change the calendar of the lunar solar calendar during the period of the Meiji Restoration, however after he died suddenly, this plan was cancelled and the Tenpo-reki became the last lunar solar calendar in Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Haruo TSUCHIMIKADO of the Bureau of Divination was against introducing the solar calendar and suggested a plan to change the calendar of the lunar solar calendar during the period of the Meiji Restoration, however after he died suddenly, this plan was cancelled and the Tenpo-reki became the last lunar solar calendar in Japan.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>グレゴリオ暦への改暦</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The change into the Gregorian calendar</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The change into the Gregorian calendar</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The transition into the Gregorian calendar</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="17">
<j>明治5年11月9日 (旧暦)（1872年12月9日）、突如としてグレゴリオ暦への改暦の布告が明治天皇の詔書と太政官布告339号によって行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 9, 1872 (the old calendar), there was Shosho (imperial edict, decree) and edict of Daijokan (The Grand Council of State), No. 339 were issued to change the existing calendar to Gregorian calendar by the Emperor Meiji suddenly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 9, 1872 (the old calendar), the Shosho (imperial edict, decree) and the edict of Daijokan (The Grand Council of State), No. 339 were issued to suddenly change the existing calendar to a Gregorian calendar by the Emperor Meiji.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December 9, 1872, the Imperial edict of the Emperor Meiji and the edict of the Grand Council of State No. 339 were suddenly issued to change the existing calendar to a Gregorian calendar.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="18">
<j>そのため布告された翌月の12月が、わずか2日となり、その翌日が明治6年（1873年）1月1日（グレゴリオ暦）となることを知らされた当時の人々の間に、混乱が生じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to this there was confusion among people since they were told there was only two days in December, which was the following month after the change of the calendar was announced, and the next day was going to be January, 1, 1873. (Gregorian calendar)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to this there was confusion among people since they were told there were only two days in December, which was the following month after the change of the calendar was announced, the next day was going to be January 1, 1873. (Gregorian calendar)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was confusion among people since they were told that there were only two days in December, the next month of the announcement, and the next day was going to be January 1, 1873. (Gregorian calendar) due to the change.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="19">
<j>改暦にともなう混乱の詳細は、「グレゴリオ暦日本におけるグレゴリオ暦導入」の節を参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Please refer to the details of the confusion in relation to change the calendar to the section of &apos;introducing the Gregorian calendar to Japan.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Please refer to the details of the confusion in relation to changing the calendar, to the section of &apos;introducing the Gregorian calendar to Japan.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For the details of the confusion due to the change of the calendar, refer to the section &apos;introducing the Gregorian calendar to Japan.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>改暦以後の旧暦</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The old calendar after changing the calendar</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The old calendar after changing the calendar</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The old calendar after the change of the calendar</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="20">
<j>日本では、新暦への改暦以来現在まで「旧暦」という名前の太陰太陽暦が暦書やカレンダーなどに記載されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan, in some calendar it said &apos;the old calendar&apos; of lunar-solar calendar or Rekisho (Expository books about calendar) after the change of the new calendar occurred until the present.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan, in some calendars say &apos;the old calendar&apos; of the lunar-solar calendar or Rekisho (Expository books about calendar) after the change of the new calendar, occurred until the present.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan, after the change to the new calendar up to the present, the lunar-solar calendars called &apos;the old calendar&apos; were described in calendars and expository books about calendar.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>これは現代天文学による月と太陽の動きから朔と二十四節気を計算し置閏法のみ天保暦と同じにしたものであり、厳密には天保暦ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Strictly speaking this is not Tenpo-reki, first day of the month and 24 divisions of the old calendar were calculated from the movement of moon and sun of the modern astronomy, and only Chemung-ho was decided to be the same as Tenpo ho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Strictly speaking this is not Tenpo-reki, first day of the month and 24 divisions of the old calendar were calculated from the movement of the moon and the sun of modern astronomy, and only Chemung-ho was decided to be the same as Tenpo ho.</e>
<cmt>spacing, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Strictly speaking, they are not Tenpo-reki; the, first day of the month and 24 divisions of the old calendar were calculated from the movement of the moon and the sun of modern astronomy, and to the result of which, only the Chijun-ho was applied like Tenpo ho.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Caviler(id:256245), Resto1578(id:168692), Izayohi(id:13095), Peehyoro Acala(id:170), R-h(id:46562), Tietew(id:4054), Nnh(id:474), Polyester(id:9559), 水野白楓(id:22811), Philolo(id:17346), 春野秋葉(id:36725), Hayabusa future(id:21110), Hukuuchi(id:82116), CLUB910(id:24308), Katsuya(id:21306), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>