<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>大和魂</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamato-damashi (the Japanese spirit)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yamato-damashi (the Japanese spirit)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamato-damashii (the Japanese spirit)</e>
<cmt>damashi→damshii</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>世事に対応し、社会のなかでものごとを円滑に進めてゆくための常識や世間的な能力。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The common sense and social skills required to make things go smoothly in society.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The common sense and social skills required to make things go smoothly in society.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The common sense and social skills required to know the stream and make things go smoothly in society.</e>
<cmt>「世事に対応し」の部分を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>特に各種の専門的な学問・教養・技術などを社会のなかで実際に役立ててゆくための才能や手腕。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In particular, the ability and competence to make actual use of various types of technical knowledge, culture, and skills in society.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In particular, the ability and competence to make actual use of various types of specialist knowledge, education, and skills in society.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In particular, the ability and competence to make actual use of various types of specialist knowledge, education, and skills in society.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="3">
<j>外国（中国）の文化や文明を享受するうえで、それと対になるべき（日本人の）常識的・日本的な対応能力。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The commonsensical Japanese ability (of the Japanese people) to respond, which should go hand-in-hand with foreign (Chinese) culture and civilization in enjoying them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The commonsensical, typically Japanese ability (of the Japanese people) to respond to situations, which should go hand-in-hand with an appreciation of foreign (Chinese) culture and civilization.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The commonsensical, typically Japanese ability (of the Japanese people) to respond to situations, which should go hand-in-hand with an appreciation of foreign (Chinese) culture and civilization.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>やまとごころ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamato-gokoro (the Japanese mind).</e>
<cmt>大和魂と区別するために、用語集とは違った用語を採用しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yamato-gokoro (the Japanese mind).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamato-gokoro (the Japanese mind).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="5">
<j>知的な論理や倫理ではなく、感情的な情緒や人情によってものごとを把握し、共感する能力・感受性。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The sensibility and ability to grasp things with emotions and human kindness, instead of an intellectual logic or ethics, and to empathize.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sensibility and ability to grasp things with emotions and human kindness, instead of intellectual logic or ethics, and to empathize.</e>
<cmt>Article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sensibility and ability to grasp things with emotions and human kindness, instead of intellectual logic or ethics, and to empathize.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>もののあはれ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mono no aware (the sadness or pathos of things).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mono no aware (the sadness or pathos of things).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mono no aware (the sadness or pathos of things).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="7">
<j>複数の女性を同時に愛してしかもすべてを幸福にしうる、艶福とそれを可能にしうる恋愛生活での調整能力。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Good fortune in love and the adjusting ability in a love life that enables it, which make it possible to love multiple women at the same time and furthermore to make all of them happy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Flexibility in one&apos;s love life and the success that brings, making it possible to love many women at the same time and furthermore to make all of them happy.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Flexibility in one&apos;s love life and the success that brings, making it possible to love many women at the same time and furthermore to make all of them happy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>いろごのみ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Iro-gonomi (lechery).</e>
<cmt>用語集の用語がこの文脈に合っており最適なものか分かりませんが、他の用語が思い浮かばないため、ここではそのまま使用しています。。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Iro-gonomi (lechery).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Iro-gonomi (lechery).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="9">
<j>以上の根底となるべき、優れた人物のそなえる霊的能力。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The spiritual ability possessed by a remarkable individual, which should form the basis of the above.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The spiritual ability possessed by a remarkable individual which should form the basis of the above.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The spiritual ability possessed by a remarkable individual which should form the basis of the above.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="10">
<j>日本民族固有（のものと考えられていた）勇敢で、潔く、特に主君・天皇に対して忠義な気性・精神性・心ばえ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The brave, heroic, and loyal nature, spirit, and disposition, especially with regard to the lord and the Emperor, (which were considered something) unique to the Japanese race.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The brave, heroic, and loyal nature, spirit, and disposition, especially with regard to lords and the Emperor, (which were considered) unique to the Japanese race.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The brave, heroic, and loyal nature, spirit, and disposition, especially with regard to lords and the Emperor, (which were considered) unique to the Japanese race.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>（近世国学以来の新解釈）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(A new interpretation since the modern study of Japanese classical literature)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(A new interpretation resulting from the modern study of Japanese classical literature)</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(A new interpretation resulting from the modern study of Japanese classical literature)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="12">
<j>大和魂（やまと-だましい）は、外来の学問・知識を日本に採り入れる際に必要な判断力・能力、または情緒（もののあはれ）を理解する心などを指す用語・概念。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamato-damashi is a term and concept referring to the judgment and ability that are necessary in accepting foreign scholarship and knowledge in Japan, a heart to understand feelings (mono no aware), etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yamato-damashi is a term and concept referring to the judgment and ability that are necessary in accepting foreign scholarship and knowledge in Japan, as well as the heart to appreciate feelings (mono no aware), etc.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamato-damashii is a term and concept referring to the judgment and ability that are necessary in accepting foreign scholarship and knowledge in Japan, as well as the heart to appreciate feelings (mono no aware), etc.</e>
<cmt>damashi→damshii</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>右記に示すとおり、性格・能力・品性もしくはそうした性質そのものを指す極めて広い概念・用語である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As indicated above, it is a very broad term and concept, which denotes personality, ability, character, and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As indicated above, it is a very broad term and concept, which denotes personality, ability, character, and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As indicated above, it is a very broad term and concept, which denotes personality, ability, character, and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="14">
<j>平安時代中期ごろから「才」「漢才」と対比的に使われはじめた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It began to be used as a contrast to &apos;sai&apos; (intelligence) and &apos;karazae&apos; (ability to write Chinese poems skillfully with a thorough knowledge of Chinese classics) from the middle of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。用語集の用語はこの文脈では合わないので、変更しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It began to be used from the middle of the Heian period as a contrast to &apos;zae&apos; (scholarship) and &apos;karazae&apos; (Chinese learning).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity - I get the feeling &quot;才&quot; and &quot;漢才&quot; are more like synonyms here. Also I think &quot;才&quot; might be pronounced &apos;zae&apos; in this case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It began to be used from the middle of the Heian period as a contrast to &apos;zae&apos; (scholarship) and &apos;karazae&apos; (Chinese learning).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>上記のような諸内容を包含するきわめてひろい概念であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was an extremely broad concept having various implications as described above.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was an extremely broad concept having various implications as described above.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was an extremely broad concept having various implications as described above.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>しかし、江戸時代中期以降の国学の流れのなかで、「漢意」と対比されることが多くなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the study of Japanese classical literature beginning in the middle of the Edo period, however, it was often contrasted with &apos;kara-gokoro&apos; (Chinese mindedness).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the study of Japanese classical literature beginning in the middle of the Edo period, however, it was often contrasted with &apos;kara-gokoro&apos; (Chinese mindedness).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the study of Japanese classical literature beginning in the middle of the Edo period, however, it was often contrasted with &apos;kara-gokoro&apos; (Chinese mindedness).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>そして、「日本古来から伝統的に伝わる固有の精神」「万邦無比の優れた日本の精神性」「日本国家のために尽くす清い心」といった誤用がむしろ主流となっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And it became rather mainstream to misuse it to mean &apos;the unique spirit traditionally going back to Japanese ancient times,&apos; &apos;superior Japanese spirituality unequaled in any other country,&apos; and &apos;a pure mind to render good service to the Japanese nation.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The misuse of the term to mean &apos;the unique spirit traditionally going back to Japanese ancient times,&apos; &apos;superior Japanese spirituality unequaled in any other country,&apos; and &apos;a pure mind to render good service to the Japanese nation&apos; became rather mainstream</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The misuse of the term to mean &apos;the unique spirit traditionally going back to Japanese ancient times,&apos; &apos;superior Japanese spirituality unequaled in any other country,&apos; and &apos;a pure mind to render good service to the Japanese nation&apos; became rather mainstream</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>この傾向は明治時代以降、ナショナリズムや民族主義の興隆とともに過剰な意味が付与されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This tendency became more marked from the Meiji period, and the term &apos;yamato-damashi&apos; was given an excessive meaning with the rise of nationalism and racism.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This tendency became more marked from the Meiji period onwards and, with the rise of nationalism and racism, the term &apos;yamato-damashi&apos; became heavily loaded.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This tendency became more marked from the Meiji period onwards and, with the rise of nationalism and racism, the term &apos;yamato-damashii&apos; became heavily loaded.</e>
<cmt>damashi→damshii</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>第二次世界大戦期には軍国主義的な色彩を強く帯び、現状を打破し突撃精神を鼓舞する意味で使われることが主となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It took on a militaristic tinge during World War II, and it was mainly used to signify encouraging an offensive spirit to break the status quo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It took on a militaristic tinge during World War II, and it was mainly used with the meaning of encouraging an offensive spirit to break the status quo.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It took on a militaristic tinge during World War II, and it was mainly used with the meaning of encouraging an offensive spirit to break the status quo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>そのため日本の敗戦後は、日本の文化・思想界の主潮流から追いやられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a consequence, it has been excluded from the prevailing currents of Japanese thought and culture since Japan&apos;s defeat in the war.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a consequence, it has been excluded from the prevailing currents of Japanese thought and culture since Japan&apos;s defeat in the war.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a consequence, it has been excluded from the prevailing currents of Japanese thought and culture since Japan&apos;s defeat in the war.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>沿革</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="21">
<j>大和魂の語の初出は、『源氏物語』の『少女』帖とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term yamato-damashi is said to have made the first appearance in Chapter &quot;Otome&quot; (Maiden) of &quot;Genji Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of Genji).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term yamato-damashi is said to have first appeared in the &quot;Otome&quot; (Maiden) chapter of &quot;Genji Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of Genji).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term yamato-damashii is said to have first appeared in the &quot;Otome&quot; (Maiden) chapter of &quot;Genji Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of Genji).</e>
<cmt>damashi→damshii</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>大和魂の語・概念は、漢才という語・概念と対のものとして生まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term and concept of yamato-damashi emerged as a contrast to those of karazae.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term and concept of yamato-damashi emerged as a contrast to those of karazae.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term and concept of yamato-damashii emerged as a contrast to those of karazae.</e>
<cmt>damashi→damshii</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>和魂漢才と言うこともあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The expression wakon-kansai (Japanese spirit with Chinese learning) was also sometimes used.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The expression wakon-kansai (Japanese spirit with Chinese learning) was also sometimes used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The expression wakon-kansai (Japanese spirit with Chinese learning) was also sometimes used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>漢才、すなわち中国などから流入してきた知識・学問をそのまま日本へ移植するのではなく、あくまで基礎的教養として採り入れ、それを日本の実情に合わせて応用的に政治や生活の場面で発揮することが大和魂とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamato-damashi was to adopt karazae -- that is, the scholarship and knowledge introduced from China and other countries -- as a basic education and apply it to politics and other aspects of life in accordance with the actual condition of Japan, instead of transplanting it as it is in the country.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yamato-damashi was to adopt karazae -- that is, the scholarship and knowledge introduced from China and other countries -- as a basic education and apply it to politics and other aspects of life in accordance with the actual condition of Japan, instead of transplanting it as it is in the country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamato-damashii was to adopt karazae -- that is, the scholarship and knowledge introduced from China and other countries -- as a basic education and apply it to politics and other aspects of life in accordance with the actual condition of Japan, instead of transplanting it as it is in the country.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>『源氏物語』が生まれた平安中期は、国風文化という日本独特の文化が興った時代である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The unique culture of Japan called Kokufu Bunka (the original national culture of Japan) thrived in the middle of the Heian period, during which &quot;Genji Monogatari&quot; was born.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。用語集の用語はこの文脈では合わないので、変更しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The mid-Heian period, when &quot;Genji Monogatari&quot; was written, saw the flourishing of Japan&apos;s own unique culture, known as Kokufu Bunka.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The mid-Heian period, when &quot;Genji Monogatari&quot; was written, saw the flourishing of Japan&apos;s own unique culture, known as Kokufu Bunka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>しかし、当時の人々の中には、中国から伝来した知識・文化が基盤となって、日本風に味付けしているのだ、という認識が存在していたと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it is believed that some people at that time recognized it was built on the basis of Chinese knowledge and culture, which were translated into a culture that fit the Japanese style.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is believed that some people at that time recognized it was founded on Chinese knowledge and culture, which had been altered to make it more Japanese.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is believed that some people at that time recognized it was founded on Chinese knowledge and culture, which had been altered to make it more Japanese.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>そのうち、大和魂は、机上の知識を現実の様々な場面で応用する判断力・能力を表すようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamato-damashi soon began to signify the judgment and ability to put book knowledge to practical use in various actual situations.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yamato-damashi soon began to signify the judgment and ability to put written knowledge to practical use in different real-life situations.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamato-damashii soon began to signify the judgment and ability to put written knowledge to practical use in different real-life situations.</e>
<cmt>damashi→damshii</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>主として「実務能力」の意味で用いられるとともに、「情緒を理解する心」という意味でも用いられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was mainly used to mean &apos;business ability&apos;, but it was also used to stand for &apos;a heart to understand feelings&apos;.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was mainly used to mean &apos;business ability&apos;, but it was also used to stand for &apos;a heart to understand feelings&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was mainly used to mean &apos;business ability&apos;, but it was also used to stand for &apos;a heart to understand feelings&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="29">
<j>こうした用法はながらく続いていたが、江戸時代中期に現れた本居宣長によって、大和魂は「日本固有の心」という意味が付与されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These usages continued long, but Norinaga MOTOORI, who appeared in the middle of the Edo period, gave the meaning of &apos;a unique Japanese spirit&apos; to yamato-damashi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These usages continued for a long time, but Norinaga MOTOORI, who appeared in the middle of the Edo period, gave the meaning of &apos;a unique Japanese spirit&apos; to the term.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These usages continued for a long time, but Norinaga MOTOORI, who appeared in the middle of the Edo period, gave the meaning of &apos;a unique Japanese spirit&apos; to the term.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>さらに江戸後期になると国学者によって、大和魂の語は、日本の独自性を主張するための政治的な用語として使われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The word yamato-damashi was additionally used as a political term to advocate Japanese uniqueness by the scholars of Japanese classical literature in the later Edo period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yamato-damashi&apos; was additionally used as a political term to advocate Japanese uniqueness by scholars of Japanese classical literature in the late Edo period.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamato-damashii was additionally used as a political term to advocate Japanese uniqueness by scholars of Japanese classical literature in the late Edo period.</e>
<cmt>damashi→damshii</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>そうした中で、遣唐使廃止を建言した菅原道真が、大和魂の語の創始者に仮託されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this context, SUGAWARA no Michizane who urged the abolition of kentoshi (Japanese envoys to Tang Dynasty China) was made and used as the creator of the word yamato-damashi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this context, SUGAWARA no Michizane, who had urged the abolition of the Japanese diplomatic missions to Tang Dynasty China, was promoted as the creator of the word yamato-damashi.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this context, SUGAWARA no Michizane, who had urged the abolition of the Japanese diplomatic missions to Tang Dynasty China, was promoted as the creator of the word yamato-damashii.</e>
<cmt>damashi→damshii</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="32">
<j>明治時代に入り、西洋の知識・学問・文化が一気に流入するようになると、岡倉天心らによって、それらを日本流に摂取すべきという主張が現れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The influx of Western knowledge, scholarship, and culture at once during the Meiji period led Tenshin OKAKURA and others to claim that they should be assimilated to the Japanese style.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sudden influx of Western knowledge, scholarship, and culture during the Meiji period led Tenshin OKAKURA and others to claim that they should be assimilated into the Japanese style.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sudden influx of Western knowledge, scholarship, and culture during the Meiji period led Tenshin OKAKURA and others to claim that they should be assimilated into the Japanese style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>そして、大和魂とともに和魂洋才という語が用いられるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And the word wakon-yosai (Japanese spirit with Western learning) began to be used with yamato-damashi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The word wakon-yosai (Japanese spirit with Western learning) also began to be used with yamato-damashi.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The word wakon-yosai (Japanese spirit with Western learning) also began to be used with yamato-damashii.</e>
<cmt>damashi→damshii</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>この語は、和魂漢才のもじりであり、大和魂の本来的な意味を含んでいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This expression was a parody of wakon-kansai, and it contained the original meaning of yamato-damashi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This expression was a parody of wakon-kansai, and it contained the original meaning of yamato-damashi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This expression was a parody of wakon-kansai, and it contained the original meaning of yamato-damashii.</e>
<cmt>damashi→damshii</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>しかし、一方では西洋の知識・文化を必要以上に摂取する事への抵抗感も併せもっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it also implied resistance to the excessive adoption of Western knowledge and culture.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it also implied resistance to the excessive adoption of Western knowledge and culture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it also implied resistance to the excessive adoption of Western knowledge and culture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="36">
<j>その後、大正・昭和と下るに連れて、日本のナショナリズム・民族主義が強まっていくと、大和魂の語には日本への強い意識が込めらるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the Japanese nationalism and racism intensified later in the Taisho and Showa periods, the word yamato-damashi began to connote strong Japanese consciousness.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, as Japanese nationalism and racism intensified during the Taisho and Showa periods, the word yamato-damashi began to connote a strong Japanese consciousness.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, as Japanese nationalism and racism intensified during the Taisho and Showa periods, the word yamato-damashii began to connote a strong Japanese consciousness.</e>
<cmt>damashi→damshii</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>国家への犠牲的精神とともに他国への排外的な姿勢を含んだ語として、用いられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was used as a term suggesting a sacrificial spirit for the nation as well as an anti-foreign attitude.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was used as a term suggesting a sacrificial spirit for the nation as well as an anti-foreign attitude.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was used as a term suggesting a sacrificial spirit for the nation as well as an anti-foreign attitude.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>そして、大和魂が元々持っていた「外来の知識を摂取して、柔軟に応用する」という意味と正反対の受け止められ方をされていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was taken to be antithetical to the original meaning of yamato-damashi, that is, &apos;adopting foreign knowledge and applying it flexibly&apos;.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As such, it took on a meaning that was the complete oppostite of the original &apos;adopting foreign knowledge and applying it flexibly&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As such, it took on a meaning that was the complete opposite of the original &apos;adopting foreign knowledge and applying it flexibly&apos;.</e>
<cmt>スペース、スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>こうして、大和魂の本来の姿を見失った日本は、第二次世界大戦で亡国寸前の敗北を喫することとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This way Japan, which lost sight of the true color of yamato-damashi, suffered the defeat, which almost ruined the country, in World War II.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This way Japan, which had lost sight of the true meaning of yamato-damashi, was defeated and almost ruined in World War II.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This way Japan, which had lost sight of the true meaning of yamato-damashii, was defeated and almost ruined in World War II.</e>
<cmt>damashi→damshii</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>敗戦後、大和魂の語は軍国主義に結びつくものとして忌避される傾向にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The tendency after the defeat in the war is to avoid using the word yamato-damashi because of its link to militarism.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The tendency after the war has been to avoid using the word yamato-damashi because of its link to militarism.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The tendency after the war has been to avoid using the word yamato-damashii because of its link to militarism.</e>
<cmt>damashi→damshii</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>また、本来的な意味に着目されることも少なくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, less attention is being paid to its original meaning.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, less attention is being paid to its original meaning.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, less attention is being paid to its original meaning.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>和歌</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Waka (traditional Japanese poems of thirty-one syllables)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Waka (traditional Japanese poems of thirty-one syllables)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Waka (traditional Japanese poems of thirty-one syllables)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="42">
<j>敷島の大和心を人問はば　朝日に匂ふ　山桜花（本居宣長）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If I am asked about the meaning of yamato-gokoro, I will answer it is the blossoms of yamazakura (mountain cherry trees) shining in the rising sun (Norinaga MOTOORI).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If I am asked about the meaning of yamato-gokoro, I will answer it is the blossoms of yamazakura (mountain cherry trees) shining in the rising sun (Norinaga MOTOORI).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If I am asked about the meaning of yamato-gokoro, I will answer it is the blossoms of yamazakura (mountain cherry trees) shining in the rising sun (Norinaga MOTOORI).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>かくすればかくなるものと知りながら　やむにやまれぬ大和魂（吉田松陰）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If I do this I know that coming, but I have to do this because of yamato-damashi (Shoin YOSHIDA).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">I knew that it would end so if I acted thus, but I am compelled by yamato-damashi (Shoin YOSHIDA).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">I knew that it would end so if I acted thus, but I am compelled by yamato-damashii (Shoin YOSHIDA).</e>
<cmt>damashi→damshii</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>身はたとひ　武蔵の野辺に朽ちぬとも　留め置かまし大和魂（吉田松陰）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even if I let my body rust away in the Musashino Plain, I will hold on to yamato-damashi for the future of Japan (Shoin YOSHIDA).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even if my body rots in the Musashino Plain, I will forever have yamato-damashi (Shoin YOSHIDA).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even if my body rots in the Musashino Plain, I will forever have yamato-damashii (Shoin YOSHIDA).</e>
<cmt>damashi→damshii</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>剣道は　神の教への道なれば　大和心をみがくこの技（高野佐三郎）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Being a michi (way) taught by God, Kendo (the Japanese art of fencing) hones yamato-gokoro (Sasaburo TAKANO).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Way of the Sword, being a path taught by the gods, hones yamato-gokoro (Sasaburo TAKANO).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Way of the Sword, being a path taught by the gods, hones yamato-gokoro (Sasaburo TAKANO).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 釣ちごちゅが(id:22605), 橄欖岩(id:24996), 怪蘇(id:45514), Loveless(id:129239), Nekosuki600(id:21263), Shimoxx(id:9332), 神風(id:47887), Nightingale(id:13166), S19991002(id:185302), Chuta(id:10457), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>