<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>大喜利</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ogiri (Professional rakugo storytellers play on words.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ogiri (Professional rakugo storytellers play on words.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ogiri (Professional rakugo storytellers play on words.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>大喜利（おおぎり、おおきり）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ogiri (pronounced as ogiri or okiri)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ogiri (pronounced as ogiri or okiri)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ogiri (pronounced as ogiri or okiri)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>興行において、その日の最後に出る演目。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An item that is presented at the end of the day&apos;s performance.</e>
<cmt>興行：show business (出典：http://www.eudict.com/）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An item that is presented at the end of the day&apos;s performance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An item that is presented at the end of the day&apos;s performance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>キリは終りの意で、縁起をかついで佳字をあてる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiri (the concluding segment of a Noh play which combines chant and dance) means the end, and the word Kiri is expressed in writing by using Chinese characters of good meanings with a superstitious view of bringing good fortune.</e>
<cmt>佳字：Chinese characters of good meanings (佳客：good visitor, 佳境：best partなどから類推しました。これらの出典：http://tangorin.com/words/）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiri (the concluding segment of a Noh play which combines chant and dance) means the end, and the word Kiri is expressed in writing by using Chinese characters of good meanings with a superstitious view of bringing good fortune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiri (the concluding segment of a Noh play which combines chant and dance) means the end, and the word Kiri is expressed in writing by using Chinese characters of good meanings with a superstitious view of bringing good fortune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>歌舞伎では特に所作事を出す場合が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kabuki (traditional drama performed by male actors), shosagoto (dance in Kabuki) is especially presented in most cases.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Kabuki (traditional drama performed by male actors), shosagoto (a dance in Kabuki) is especially presented in most cases.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Kabuki (traditional drama performed by male actors), shosagoto (a dance in Kabuki) is especially presented in most cases.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>寄席で、トリを落語・講談が取らない場合、しばしばその代りに行われた演芸。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Yose (storyteller theater), a theatrical entertainment that was performed last often as an alternative to rakugo (comic story telling) or kodan storytelling when the last performer does not play neither of them.</e>
<cmt>トリ：（取り：the last performer 出典：PDIC ver5.0.15)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Yose (storyteller theater), a theatrical entertainment is performed last often as an alternative to rakugo (comic story telling) or kodan storytelling when the last performer does neither of them.</e>
<cmt>re-wrote the sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Yose (storyteller theater), a theatrical entertainment is performed last often as an alternative to rakugo (comic story telling) or kodan storytelling when the last performer does neither of them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>複数人でおこなわれ、お題をうけて小咄やなぞ掛けなどを行うことが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was played by two or more performers, and a brief (comic) story or a riddle was performed in response to a given topic.</e>
<cmt>小咄：brief (comic) story (出典：http://tangorin.com)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was played by two or more performers, and a brief story (comic) or a riddle was performed in response to a given topic.</e>
<cmt>re-wrote the sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was played by two or more performers, and a brief story (comic) or a riddle was performed in response to a given topic.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>司会者を伴うこともある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is sometimes performed in the presence of an emcee.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is sometimes performed in the presence of an emcee.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is sometimes performed in the presence of an emcee.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>本項で詳述する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The details are described in this section.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The details are described in this section.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The details are described in this section.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>元来は、寄席において観客へのサービスとして行われていたもので、最後の演目として複数の出演者が再び登場し、観客から題目をもらって互いに芸を競い合う余興であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was originally performed last as service for audience in the theater and was a sideshow act in which more than one performers come on stage again after all other performance, and compete with each other in their performance played in accordance with the topic given from the audience.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was originally performed last as a bonus for the audience in the theater and was a sideshow act in which more than one performer came on the stage again after all the other performances, and competed with each other on their performance based on a topic given by the audience.</e>
<cmt>re-wrote the sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was originally performed last as a bonus for the audience in the theater and was a sideshow act in which more than one performer came on the stage again after all the other performances, and competed with each other on their performance based on a topic given by the audience.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="11">
<j>これはコンサートなどにおけるアンコールに相当し、現在の演芸の舞台でもよく耳にする「お客様方のご機嫌を伺いたいと思います」というフレーズは、このサービスという観念に由来するものと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is relevant to encore in concerts, and such a phrase as &quot;We would like to ask you the audience how you liked the show&quot;, which is still often heard on the stage of theatrical entertainment today, may be originated from the concept of the service.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is relevant for encores in concerts, and phrases such as &quot;We would like to ask you the audience how you liked the show&quot;, which is still often used on the stage in present theatrical entertainment, may have originated from the concept of the bonus.</e>
<cmt>re-wrote the sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is relevant for encores in concerts, and phrases such as &apos;We would like to ask you the audience how you liked the show,&apos; which is still often used on the stage in present theatrical entertainment, may have originated from the concept of the bonus.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;カンマ位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="12">
<j>大喜利という名は能・浄瑠璃・歌舞伎といった古典芸能の舞台で、最後の演目を意味する言葉として使われる「大切り」に由来する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name &quot;Ogiri&quot; derives from a word &quot;ogiri&quot; or &quot;okiri&quot; in different Chinese characters meaning the last item of the show in classical Japanese popular performing arts including Noh (traditional masked dance-drama), Joruri (ballad drama), and Kabuki.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name &quot;Ogiri&quot; is derived from a word &quot;ogiri&quot; or &quot;okiri&quot; according to the Chinese characters and means the last item of the show in classical Japanese popular performing arts including Noh (traditional masked dance-drama), Joruri (ballad drama), and Kabuki.</e>
<cmt>re-wrote the sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name Ogiri is derived from a word &apos;ogiri&apos; or &apos;okiri&apos; according to the Chinese characters and means the last item of the show in classical Japanese popular performing arts including Noh (traditional masked dance-drama), Joruri (ballad drama), and Kabuki.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>尚、「切り」は「ピンからキリまで」の「キリ」で、最後の意。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Actually, the word &quot;kiri&quot; comes from the phrase &quot;from the start to the last&quot; and means &quot;the last&quot;.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処　(21行目と22行目に記載）　原文では、一文の中に、”（「切り」は「ピンからキリまで」の「キリ」で、最後の意）”と、括弧（）内にさらにかぎ括弧「」がありましたため、2文に分けさせていただきました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Actually, the word &quot;kiri&quot; comes from the phrase &quot;from the start to the last&quot; and means &quot;the last&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Actually, the word &apos;kiri&apos; comes from the phrase &apos;from the start to the last&apos; and means &apos;the last.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;ピリオド位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>「喜利」は客も喜び、演者も利を得るという意味の当て字である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Chinese characters for &quot;kiri&quot; were just applied to hold the meanings that the audience enjoys the play and the performer enjoys the profit.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Chinese characters for &quot;kiri&quot; were applied just to signify that the audience enjoys the play and the performers enjoy the profit.</e>
<cmt>re-wrote the sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Chinese characters for &apos;kiri&apos; were applied just to signify that the audience enjoys the play and the performers enjoy the profit.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="15">
<j>現在「大喜利」といえば、テレビ番組『笑点』（日本テレビ放送網）のコーナーの「大喜利 (笑点)」がイメージされるだろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In these days, the word &quot;Ogiri&quot; is associated with the item &quot;Ogiri&quot; in Shoten (a TV program of entertainment show such as rakugo stories or manzai, comic dialogues) broadcasted by Nippon Television Network Corporation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In these days, the word &quot;Ogiri&quot; is associated with the item &quot;Ogiri&quot; in Shoten (a TV entertainment program that presents shows such as rakugo stories or manzai, and comic dialogues) that is broadcasted by Nippon Television Network Corporation.</e>
<cmt>re-wrote the sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In these days, the word &apos;Ogiri&apos; is associated with the item &apos;Ogiri&apos; in &quot;Shoten&quot; (a TV entertainment program that presents shows such as rakugo stories or manzai, and comic dialogues) that is broadcasted by Nippon Television Network Corporation.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;&quot;補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>またここから派生して、多くのバラエティ番組やお笑いイベントなどでは「大喜利形式」と称し、お笑い芸人やタレント、落語家達が用意された様々なお題に対して、面白い答えを出し合い、互いのお笑いセンスを競っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, an item called &quot;the Ogiri style&quot; was derived from that program and has been prevalent among many variety programs and Owarai (comedians show) events where comedians, entertainers, and Rakugo story tellers are giving comical responses to various topics prepared in advance and compete with each other in their sense of Owarai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, an item called &quot;the Ogiri style&quot; was derived from that program and has been popular among many variety programs and Owarai (comedians show) events where comedians, entertainers, and Rakugo story tellers give comical responses to various topics they had prepared in advance and compete with each other on their sense of Owarai.</e>
<cmt>re-wrote the sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, an item called &apos;the Ogiri style&apos; was derived from that program and has been popular among many variety programs and Owarai (comedians show) events where comedians, entertainers, and Rakugo story tellers give comical responses to various topics they had prepared in advance and compete with each other on their sense of Owarai.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>良い答えを出した人に座布団が与えられるシステムやフリップや小道具等の使用なども「笑点」によって一般的になった形式である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Based on the program Shoten, the idea of providing one more zabuton (traditional Japanese cushions used to sit on the floor) to the performer who has given a good response and the use of a flip chart and prop, etc., have become common.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based on the program called Shoten, the idea of giving one more zabuton (traditional Japanese cushions used to sit on the floor) to a performer that gives a good comical response and the use of a flip chart and prop, etc., have become common.</e>
<cmt>re-wrote the sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based on the program called Shoten, the idea of giving one more zabuton (traditional Japanese cushions used to sit on the floor) to a performer that gives a good comical response and the use of a flip chart and prop, etc., have become common.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="18">
<j>大喜利でよく行われるもの</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Popular topics in Ogiri</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Popular topics in Ogiri</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Popular topics in Ogiri</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>あいうえお作文</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">AIUEO compositions</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">AIUEO compositions</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">AIUEO compositions</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>なぞかけ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Playing riddles</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Playing riddles</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Playing riddles</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>川柳・短歌・都々逸など</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Senryu (humorous or ironical haiku), Tanka, and Dodoitsu (a type of Japanese songs), etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Senryu (humorous or ironical haiku), Tanka, and Dodoitsu (a type of Japanese songs) etc.</e>
<cmt>re-wrote the sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Senryu (humorous or ironical haiku), Tanka, and Dodoitsu (a type of Japanese songs) etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>イラスト・歌</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Illustrations and songs</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Illustrations and songs</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Illustrations and songs</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>あったら嫌なもの・あったらいいものなどを使ったもの</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Stories in which the last thing that you might want to have or those things that you might like to have are mentioned</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Stories in which the last thing that you might want to have or those things that you might like to have are mentioned</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Stories in which the last thing that you might want to have or those things that you might like to have are mentioned</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>豊竹屋</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toyotakeya</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toyotakeya</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toyotakeya</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>「○○のようで○○でない、△△のようで△△でない、それは何かと尋ねれば、□□、□□」のように、AでもなくBでもないCを問うもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Stories in which a question about C, which is neither A nor B, is made; for example, &quot;This seems like such and such but is not such and such, and it seems like such and such but is not such and such; now I ask what it is, and the answer is thus and thus.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Stories in which a question about C, which is neither A nor B, is made; for example, &quot;This seems like such and such but is not such and such, and it seems like such and such but is not such and such; now I will ask what it is, and the answer is thus and thus.&quot;</e>
<cmt>added &quot;will&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Stories in which a question about C, which is neither A nor B, is made; for example, &apos;This seems like such and such but is not such and such, and it seems like such and such but is not such and such; now I will ask what it is, and the answer is thus and thus.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>合いの手として、「ベンベン」（義太夫の三味線の音色に由来）と入れることから、上方ではこの名がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is named so in Kamigata (the Kyoto-Osaka region) because a phrase &quot;Benben.&quot;, an onomatopoetic expression of Gidayu shamisen (shamisen used for Gidayu, reciting dramatic narratives), is uttered as an interjection.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That is what it is called in Kamigata (the Kyoto-Osaka region) because the phrase &quot;Benben.&quot;, an onomatopoetic expression of Gidayu shamisen (shamisen used for Gidayu when reciting dramatic narratives), is uttered as an interjection.</e>
<cmt>re-wrote the sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That is what it is called in Kamigata (the Kyoto-Osaka region) because the phrase &quot;Benben,&quot; an onomatopoetic expression of Gidayu shamisen (shamisen used for Gidayu when reciting dramatic narratives), is uttered as an interjection.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 興味津々ノ助(id:29699), 経済準学士(id:22656), Cprobot(id:97843), 9PgUp(id:24726), えむえすじょー(id:89544), ShikiH(id:181574), やきとり(id:126941), L0 0l(id:119980), Fryed-peach(id:63402), 崎宏(id:64519), Ponta2(id:129030), Dr jimmy(id:111486), Ｋｙ進(id:59658), コネ(id:15481), Koegeki(id:46093), ねむりねずみ(id:127692), Point136(id:211299), Mana1127(id:57619), Satok0195(id:193106), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>