<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>雪月花</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Setsugetsuka</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Setsugetsuka</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Setsugetsuka</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>雪月花（せつげつか、ゆきつきはなとも）は、白居易の漢詩「寄殷協律」の一句「雪月花時最憶君」による語。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Setsugetsuka (雪月花, or pronounced as Yukitsuki no Hana) is a word from the phrase, &quot;Setsugetsuka no toki mottomo kimi wo omou (I remember you especially when snow, the moon or flowers is beautiful)&quot; in an old Chinese poem, &quot;IN Kyoritsu ni yosu (A poem sent to IN Kyoritsu)&quot; composed by Juyi BAI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Setsugetsuka (雪月花, or pronounced as Yukitsuki no Hana) is a word from the phrase, &quot;Setsugetsuka no toki mottomo kimi wo omou (I remember you especially when snow, the moon or flowers are beautiful)&quot; in an old Chinese poem, &quot;IN Kyoritsu ni yosu (A poem sent to IN Kyoritsu)&quot; composed by Juyi BAI.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Setsugetsuka (or pronounced as Yuki Tsuki Hana (Snow, the Moon and Flowers)), is a word from the phrase, &apos;Setsugetsuka no toki mottomo kimi wo omou (I remember you especially when snow, the moon or flowers are beautiful)&apos; in an old Chinese poem, &apos;In Kyoritsu ni yosu (A poem sent to In Kyoritsu)&apos; composed by Juyi BAI.</e>
<cmt>雪月花の定訳（漢字と括弧内のnoは削除）&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;IN→In （姓名ではないので）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>雪・月・花という自然の美しい景物を指す語である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Setsugetsuka (snow, the moon, and flower)&quot; is a collective word to refer to beautiful objects of nature.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Setsugetsuka (snow, the moon, and flower)&quot; is a collective word to refer to beautiful objects of nature.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Setsugetsuka (snow, the moon, and flower)&quot; is a collective word to refer to beautiful objects of nature.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>日本においてはこの語句が格別に愛好され、以下に述べる含みを持つ語として使われるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan, the word &quot;setsugetsuka&quot; became very poular, and has been used by itself, having acquired some new meanings as shown below.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan, the word &quot;setsugetsuka&quot; became very popular, and has been used by itself, having acquired some new meanings as shown below.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan, the word &apos;setsugetsuka&apos; became very popular, and has been used by itself, having acquired some new meanings as shown below.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>また「雪月花」 (せつげっか) は楽曲の曲名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Setsugetsuka&quot; also is a music title.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Setsugetsuka&quot; is also a music title.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Setsugetsuka&apos; is also a music title.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>殷協律は白居易が江南にいたときの部下であり、長安からこの詩を贈ったものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When he was in Jiangnan, Juyi BAI had a subordinate, IN Kyoritsu; later when Juyi BAI moved to Changan, he sent the above poem to IIN.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When he was in Jiangnan, Juyi BAI had a subordinate, IN Kyoritsu; later when Juyi BAI moved to Changan, he sent the above poem to IIN.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When he was in Jiangnan, Juyi BAI had a subordinate, In Kyoritsu; later when Juyi BAI moved to Changan, he sent the above poem to In.</e>
<cmt>IN→InIIN→In</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>「雪月花の時」は、この詩においては、それぞれの景物の美しいとき、すなわち四季折々を指す語であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The original meaning of the phrase &quot;time of setsugetsuka&quot; in the poem was the time when snow, the moon, or floweris beautiful, that is, different seasons of a year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The original meaning of the phrase &quot;time of setsugetsuka&quot; in the poem was the time when snow, the moon, or flower are beautiful, that is, different seasons of a year.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The original meaning of the phrase &apos;time of setsugetsuka&apos; in the poem was the time when snow, the moon, or flowers are beautiful, that is, different seasons of a year.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;flower→flowers</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>そうした折々に、遠く江南にいる殷協律を思うというのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He described in the poem that at different times of a year, when nature is beautiful, he thought of Kyoritsu IN, who was far away in Jiangnan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the poeme he described that at different times of the year, when nature is beautiful, he thought about Kyoritsu IN, who was far away in Jiangnan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the poem he described that at different times of the year, when nature is beautiful, he thought about In Kyoritsu, who was far away in Jiangnan.</e>
<cmt>poeme→poemKyoritsu IN→In Kyoritsu （他のセルと合わせました）</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>しかし「雪月花」は日本の詩和歌においては、これら三種を一度に取り合わせたものを指すものとしてしばしば用いられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japanese poetry, on the other hand, &quot;setsugetsuka&quot; is sometimes used to describe a scenery or an object which contains all the three natural elements, snow, the moon, and flower, at the same time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japanese poetry, on the other hand, &quot;setsugetsuka&quot; is sometimes used to describe scenery or an object which contains all three natural elements, snow, the moon, and flowers, at the same time.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japanese poetry, on the other hand, &apos;setsugetsuka&apos; is sometimes used to describe scenery or an object which contains all three natural elements, snow, the moon, and flowers, at the same time.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>日本語における初出は『万葉集』、大伴家持の和歌である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The earliest appearance of setsugetsuka in Japanese language is in one of Yakamochi OTOMO&apos; s poem, which was selected in &quot;Manyoshu&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The earliest appearance of setsugetsuka in Japanese language is in one of Yakamochi OTOMO&apos; s poem, which was selected in &quot;Manyoshu&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The earliest appearance of setsugetsuka in Japanese language is in one of Yakamochi OTOMO&apos; s poem, which was selected in &quot;Manyoshu&quot; (Collection of Ten Thousand Leaves).</e>
<cmt>万葉集の定訳</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>宴席の題詠として雪月梅花が詠まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In celebration banquets, poetry was composed on fixed topics including &quot;setsugetsubaika (snow, the moon, plum and flower).&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At celebration banquets, poetry was composed on fixed topics including &quot;setsugetsubaika&quot; (snow, the moon, plums and flowers).</e>
<cmt>punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At celebration banquets, poetry was composed on fixed topics including &quot;setsugetsubaika&quot; (snow, the moon, plums and flowers).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>すなわち月の明るい折に、雪と花をあわせたものを提示するという遊戯的な設定を和歌の題材としたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Waka poems were composed under the playful setting in which an object consisting of the elements of snow and flower is presented in the moonlighted setting.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Waka poems were composed under a playful setting where the object, consisting of the elements of snow and flowers, is presented under the moonlight.</e>
<cmt>grammar and punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Waka poems were composed under a playful setting where the object, consisting of the elements of snow and flowers, is presented under the moonlight.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>この取り合わせは『枕草子』の一節に村上天皇の挿話として見え、日本の宮廷文化においては、しばしば珍しい取り合わせとして、また「最君憶」（最も君を憶う）との連想において好まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This combination was mentioned in a paragraph of &quot;Makura no Soshi (The Pillow Book)&quot; as an anecdote about Emperor Murakami; the combination was preferred by the aristocrats in Japan as an unusual combination, or as a word that reminds of a phrase &quot;I remember you especially.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This combination was mentioned in a paragraph of &quot;Makura no Soshi (The Pillow Book)&quot; as an anecdote about Emperor Murakami; the combination was preferred by the aristocrats in Japan as an unusual combination, or as a word that is reminiscent of the phrase &quot;I remember you especially.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This combination was mentioned in a paragraph of &quot;Makura no Soshi (The Pillow Book)&quot; as an anecdote about Emperor Murakami; the combination was preferred by the aristocrats in Japan as an unusual combination, or as a word that is reminiscent of the phrase &quot;I remember you especially.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>「雪月花時最憶君」は『和漢朗詠集』交友の部に前句とともに採られており、先に触れた村上天皇の挿話もこの連想を下敷きにしたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Together with the preceding line, &quot;Setsugetsuka no toki mottomo kimi o omou&quot; is inluded in the Chapter of Friendship in &quot;Wakan Roei Shu (Collection of Sung Japanese and Chinese poems);&quot; and the anecdote about Emperor Murakami mentioned above also was based on the association between &quot;setsugetsuka no toki&quot; and &quot;mottomo kimi o omou.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Together with the preceding line, &quot;Setsugetsuka no toki mottomo kimi o omou&quot; is inluded in the Chapter of Friendship in &quot;Wakan Roei Shu&quot; (Collection of Sung Japanese and Chinese poems); and the anecdote about Emperor Murakami mentioned above also was based on the association between &quot;setsugetsuka no toki&quot; and &quot;mottomo kimi o omou.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Together with the preceding line, &apos;Setsugetsuka no toki mottomo kimi o omou&apos; is inluded in the Chapter of Friendship in &quot;Wakan Roeishu&quot; (Japanese and Chinese poems to sing); and the anecdote about Emperor Murakami mentioned above also was based on the association between &apos;setsugetsuka no toki&apos; and &apos;mottomo kimi o omou.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;和漢朗詠集の定訳</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="14">
<j>時代が下ると、雪月花は主に雪・月・桜の取り合わせとして理解され、この三種の景物、さらにはそうした景物をめでる風流な態度そのものを示す語句として理解されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later on, &quot;setsugetsuka&quot; was recognized primarily as the combination of snow, the moon, and cherry blossoms; &quot;setsugetsuka&quot; was used as the word that refers to these three objects themselves, or further including the elegant stances themselves when enjoing these objects.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later on, &quot;setsugetsuka&quot; was recognized primarily as the combination of snow, the moon, and cherry blossoms; &quot;setsugetsuka&quot; referred to these three objects themselves, or further included the elegant stances themselves when enjoing these objects.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later on, &quot;setsugetsuka&quot; was recognized primarily as the combination of snow, the moon, and cherry blossoms; &quot;setsugetsuka&quot; referred to these three objects themselves, or further included the elegant stances themselves when enjoing these objects.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>日本三景や日本三名園がこれに相当する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These include the three most scenic spots in Japan and three outstanding gardens in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These include the three most scenic spots and three outstanding gardens in Japan.</e>
<cmt>redundancy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These include the three most scenic spots and three outstanding gardens in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="16">
<j>日本三景：雪-天橋立、月-松島、花（紅葉を花に見立てる）-宮島</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The three most scenic spots in Japan: snow in Amanohashidate; the moon in Matsushima; and flowers in Miyajima (autumn leaves are likened to flowers).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The three most scenic spots in Japan: snow in Amanohashidate; the moon in Matsushima; and flowers in Miyajima (autumn leaves are likened to flowers).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The three most scenic spots in Japan: snow in Amanohashidate; the moon in Matsushima; and flowers in Miyajima (autumn leaves are likened to flowers).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>日本三名園：雪-兼六園、月-後楽園、花（ウメ）-偕楽園</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The three outstanding gardens in Japan: snow in Kenroku-en garden; the moon in Koraku-en garden; and flowers (Japanese plum) in Kairaku-en garden.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The three outstanding gardens in Japan: snow in Kenroku-en garden; the moon in Koraku-en garden; and flowers (Japanese plum) in Kairaku-en garden.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The three outstanding gardens in Japan: snow in Kenroku-en garden; the moon in Koraku-en garden; and flowers (Japanese plums) in Kairaku-en garden.</e>
<cmt>plum→plums</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="18">
<j>音楽作品としてもいくつかの楽曲がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are several pieces of music about setsugetsuka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are several pieces of music about setsugetsuka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are several pieces of music about setsugetsuka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="19">
<j>『雪月花』 (箏組歌・三橋検校作曲)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Setsugetsuka&quot; (kotokumiuta, or koto suites of songs, composed by Kengyo Mitsuhashi)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Setsugetsuka&quot; (kotokumiuta, or koto suites of songs, composed by Kengyo Mitsuhashi)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Setsugetsuka&quot; (kotokumiuta, or koto suites of songs, composed by Kengyo MITSUHASHI)</e>
<cmt>Mitsuihashi→MITSUHASHI</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="20">
<j>『新雪月花』 (箏曲・吉沢検校作曲)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Shin-setsugetsuka&quot; (koto music, composed by Kengyo Yoshizawa)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Shin-setsugetsuka&quot; (koto music, composed by Kengyo Yoshizawa)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Shin-setsugetsuka&quot; (koto music, composed by Kengyo YOSHIZAWA)</e>
<cmt>Yoshizawa→YOSHIZAWA</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="21">
<j>現代では伝統的な日本の美の感覚を連想させる語として、詩や流行歌、あるいは和風レストランの屋号などに用いられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today &quot;setsugetsuka&quot; is used in poems, popular songs, or Japanese cuisine restaurant names to add the feeling of traditional senses of Japanese beauty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today &quot;setsugetsuka&quot; is used in poems, popular songs, or Japanese cuisine restaurant names to add the feeling of traditional senses of Japanese beauty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today &quot;setsugetsuka&quot; is used in poems, popular songs, or Japanese cuisine restaurant names to add the feeling of traditional senses of Japanese beauty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="22">
<j>また1914年の創設以来、今日ではエンターテイメントの一角を担うまでに有名になった宝塚歌劇団の組の花・月・雪という組分けもここから来ている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takarazuka Revue, which became renowned as one of the major entertaining groups since the establishment in 1914, has three groups: Flower, Moon, and Snow, which also derived from setsugetsuka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takarazuka Revue, that became renowned as one of the major entertaining groups since the establishment in 1914, has three groups: Flower, Moon, and Snow, which also derived from setsugetsuka.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takarazuka Revue, that became renowned as one of the major entertaining groups since the establishment in 1914, has three groups: Flower, Moon, and Snow, which also derived from setsugetsuka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="23">
<j>・また、バンダイナムコゲームスから、プリント倶楽部（通称・プリクラ、プリ）花鳥風月シリーズ「雪月花」、「雪月花2」、「雪月花3」が発売されており、どれも期間限定ものが多く、花吹雪シリーズ（花吹雪、花吹雪2、花吹雪NEW）と、1、2を争う人気となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Print Club (generally called Pricla, or Pri) Kacho-fugetsu Series &quot;Setsugetsuka,&quot; &quot;Setsugetsuka 2&quot;and &quot;Setsugetsuka 3&quot; are released from Bandai Namco Games, mostly limited-time offer; the series is very poplular vying with Hanafubuki Series (Hanafubuki, Hanafubuki 2, and Hanafubuki New) for the top sales.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Print Club (generally called Pricla, or Pri) Kacho-fugetsu Series &quot;Setsugetsuka,&quot; &quot;Setsugetsuka 2&quot;and &quot;Setsugetsuka 3&quot; are released from Bandai Namco Games, mostly limited-time offer; the series is very poplular vying with Hanafubuki Series (Hanafubuki, Hanafubuki 2, and Hanafubuki New) for the top sales.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Print Club (generally called Pricla, or Pri) Kacho-fugetsu Series &apos;Setsugetsuka,&apos; &apos;Setsugetsuka 2&apos; and &apos;Setsugetsuka 3&apos; are released from Bandai Namco Games, mostly limited-time offer; the series is very poplular vying with Hanafubuki Series (Hanafubuki, Hanafubuki 2, and Hanafubuki New) for the top sales.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Rusk(id:9895), Πrate(id:11329), K66星雲(id:16609), Cprobot(id:97843), Metatron(id:64025), Nighthawks(id:36125), 汲平(id:18186), Aphaia(id:3132), Kamuin(id:5241), 詠狸庵(id:41048), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>