<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>乳鉢坊</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nyubobachi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nyubachibo</e>
<cmt>スペルミス修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nyubachibo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>乳鉢坊（にゅうばちぼう）とは、芝居の鳴り物に使う銅盤が変化して生まれた日本の妖怪である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nyubobachi refers to Japanese specter that was transmuted from a copper disk used as a musical instruments for a play.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A Nyubachibo (literally, mortar [a bowl-shaped vessel] bonze) is one of Japanese yokai (ghosts, spirits and monsters) that was transmuted from a copper disk (cymbal) used as a musical instrument for theatrical performance.</e>
<cmt>スペルミス修正、補足訳、文法調整</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nyubachibo (literally, mortar [a bowl-shaped vessel] bonze) is one of Japanese yokai (ghosts, spirits and monsters) that was transmuted from a copper disk (cymbal) used as a musical instrument for theatrical performance.</e>
<cmt>A Nyubachibo→Nyubachibo</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>付喪神の一種とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered as a kind of tsukumo-gami (gods to a variety of things).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered to be a kind of tsukumogami (a type of Japanese spirits that originate in items or artifacts that have reached their 100th birthday and become alive).</e>
<cmt>補足訳修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered to be a kind of tsukumogami (a type of Japanese spirits that originate in items or artifacts that have reached their 100th birthday and become alive).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>鳥山石燕 の「画図百器徒然袋」では、銅盤を頭にかぶった人のような姿で、瓢箪の妖怪である瓢箪小僧と共に描かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With Hyotankozo (gourd boy), a specter of a gourd, Nyubobachi is portrayed in a human-like figure wearing a copper disk on the head in Sekien TORIYAMA&apos;s &quot;Hyakki Tsurezure Bukuro&quot; (One hundred bags in idlenss).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sekien TORIYAMA&apos;s &quot;Gazu Hyakki Tsurezure Bukuro&quot; (The Illustrated Bag of One Hundred Random Demons; the term &apos;hyakki&apos; in its title is a pun on the usual hyakki, replacing the character for demon which is written as &quot;鬼&quot; in Japanese with a character for vessel written as &quot;器,&quot; and sure enough, most of the yokais shown in this book are tsukumogami) portrays the Nyubachibo in a human-like figure wearing a copper disk (or cymbal) on the head, along with a Hyotan-kozo (a calabash or bottle-gourd boy) which is a specter of bottle gourds.</e>
<cmt>原文に「画図」を補足のうえ再訳出しました。流れ調整、用語選択。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sekien TORIYAMA&apos;s &apos;Gazu Hyakki Tsurezure Bukuro&apos; (The Illustrated Bag of One Hundred Random Demons; the term &apos;hyakki&apos; in its title is a pun on the usual hyakki, replacing the character for demon which is written as &quot;鬼&quot; in Japanese with a character for vessel written as &quot;器,&quot; and sure enough, most of the yokais shown in this book are tsukumogami) portrays the Nyubachibo in a human-like figure wearing a copper disk (or cymbal) on the head, along with a Hyotan-kozo (a calabash or bottle-gourd boy) which is a specter of bottle gourds.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot; → &apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>室町時代の『百鬼夜行絵巻』にも同じような銅盤状の妖怪が描かれているので、これがモデルになったという説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since similar copper disk specter was portrayed in &quot;Hyakki Yagyo (Night Parade of One Hundred Demons) Picture Scroll&quot; in Muromachi period, some say that Nyubobachi was modeled on this copper disk specter.</e>
<cmt>「銅版」は「銅盤」の誤植と思われます</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since a similar copper disk (or cymbal) yokai was depicted in &quot;Hyakki Yagyo Emaki&quot; (The &apos;Night Parade of One Hundred Demons&apos; Picture Scroll) in the Muromachi period, some believe that Nyubachibo was modeled on it.</e>
<cmt>原文を「銅盤」に修正しました。補足訳、用語選択、スペル修正。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since a similar copper disk (or cymbal) yokai was depicted in &quot;Hyakki Yagyo Emaki&quot; (The &apos;Night Parade of One Hundred Demons&apos; Picture Scroll) in the Muromachi period, some believe that Nyubachibo was modeled on it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>大きな音を鳴らして人を驚かせるという説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some also say that Nyubobachi frightens people by making loud sound.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One theory has it that the Nyubachibo scares people by making a loud sound.</e>
<cmt>スペルミス修正、用語選択、冠詞</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One theory has it that the Nyubachibo scares people by making a loud sound.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 逃亡者(id:14864), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>