<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>元服</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Genpuku (celebrate one&apos;s coming of age)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Genpuku (celebrate one&apos;s coming of age)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genpuku (celebrate one&apos;s coming of age)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>元服（げんぶく、げんぷく）とは、平安時代以降、公家・武家の間で行われた男子の成人式という通過儀礼である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Genpuku was a coming-of-age celebration for boys, which was a rite of passage that was held among Court nobles and samurai families since the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Genpuku was a coming-of-age celebration for boys, a rite of passage held among Court nobles and samurai families since the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genpuku was a coming-of-age celebration for boys, a rite of passage held among Court nobles and samurai families since the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>加冠（初冠）ともいわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was also called as kakan or uikoburi (put a crown on a young man&apos;s head on a genpuku ceremony).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was also called kakan or uikoburi (crowning a young man during the genpuku ceremony).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was also called kakan or uikoburi (crowning a young man during the genpuku ceremony).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>江戸時代以降は行われなくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the Edo period, this rite was lost.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the Edo period, this rite was lost.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the Edo period, this rite was lost.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>一般に15歳（数え年）に達した男子が成人したことを表すために行われ、氏神の社前で大人の服に改め、総角（角髪（みずら））と呼ばれる子供の髪型を改めて大人の髪（冠下の髻（かんむりしたのもとどり））を結い、烏帽子親により冠をつける（公家、及び、平氏系の武家では、厚化粧、引眉にお歯黒も付ける、源氏系は付けない場合が多かった）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In general, Genpuku was held in order to declare that a boy, who became 15 years old (age by the traditional Japanese system), reached manhood, and in the rite, the boy changed into adult clothes in front of the shrine of his ujigami (a guardian god or spirit of a particular place in the Shinto religion), changed his hairstyle from the hairstyle for children called agemaki (mizura: trefoil knots) to the hairstyle for adults called kanmurisita no motodori (the hair is bundled up on the top of the head and made stood up to put on a crown), and was put a crown by eboshioya (a person who put on an eboshi in the case of genpuku ceremony); in Court nobles and the Taira families of samurai, the boy often had heavy makeup, hikimayu (painted eyebrows) and ohaguro (black painted teeth), while in the Genji families of samurai, the boy mostly did not have any makeup.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In general, Genpuku was held in order to declare that a boy, who became 15 years old (age according to the traditional Japanese system), reached manhood, and in the rite, the boy changed into adult clothes in front of the shrine of his ujigami (a guardian god or spirit of a particular place in the Shinto religion), changed his hairstyle from the hairstyle for children called agemaki (mizura: trefoil knots) to the hairstyle for adults called kanmurisita no motodori (the hair is bundled up on the top of the head and made to stand up to accomodate a crown), and was crowned by eboshioya (a person who put on an eboshi during the genpuku ceremony); in Court nobles and the Taira families of samurai, the boy often had heavy makeup, hikimayu (painted eyebrows) and ohaguro (black painted teeth), while in the Genji families of samurai, the boy mostly did not have any makeup.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In general, Genpuku was held in order to declare that a boy, who became 15 years old (age according to the traditional Japanese system), reached manhood, and in the rite, the boy changed into adult clothes in front of the shrine of his ujigami (a guardian god or spirit of a particular place in the Shinto religion), changed his hairstyle from the hairstyle for children called agemaki (mizura: trefoil knots) to the hairstyle for adults called kanmurisita no motodori (the hair is bundled up on the top of the head and made to stand up to accomodate a crown), and was crowned by eboshioya (a person who put on an eboshi (formal headwear for court nobles) during the genpuku ceremony); in Court nobles and the Taira families of samurai, the boy often had heavy makeup, hikimayu (painted eyebrows) and ohaguro (black painted teeth), while in the Minamoto families of samurai, the boy mostly did not have any makeup.)</e>
<cmt>烏帽子の説明追記Genji→Minamoto</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>それまでの幼名を廃して烏帽子名（元服名・諱）を新たに付ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The childhood name fell into disuse, and the eboshi name (the genpuku name, imina (personal name)) was given newly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The childhood name fell into disuse, and the eboshi name (the genpuku name, imina or personal name) was newly given.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The childhood name fell into disuse, and the eboshi name (the genpuku name, imina or personal name) was newly given.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>室町時代以降は民間にも普及した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the Muromachi period, this rite became widespread among the private sector.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the Muromachi period, this rite became widespread among the private sector.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the Muromachi period, this rite became widespread among ordinary people.</e>
<cmt>この「民間」は private sector ではないと思います。ordinary people としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>民間においては褌親（へこおや）の元で、初めてふんどしを付け、性に関する知識を授かる褌祝（ふんどしいわい）と呼ばれる儀式がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the private sector, there was a rite called Fundoshi-iwai that a boy wore Fundoshi (loincloth) for the first time under heko-oya (acting parents asked for Fundoshi iwai), and was taught the knowledge about sex.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the private sector, there was a rite called Fundoshi-iwai when a boy wore Fundoshi (loincloth) for the first time under heko-oya (acting parents asked for Fundoshi iwai), and was taught about sex.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In ordinary people, there was a rite called Fundoshi-iwai when a boy wore Fundoshi (loincloth) for the first time under heko-oya (acting parents asked for Fundoshi iwai), and was taught about sex.</e>
<cmt>the private sector→ordinary people</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>なお、貴族の女子の成人式は「裳着（もぎ）」という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The coming-of-age celebration for noble girls was called &apos;Mogi.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The coming-of-age celebration for noble girls was called &apos;Mogi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The coming-of-age celebration for noble girls was called &apos;Mogi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>江戸時代以降は女性も元服と称し、結婚と同時に、未婚でも18～20才くらいで行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the Edo period, women also described their celebration as Genpuku, and they had it simultaneously with the marriage, and even if they were single, they had the ceremony at around the age from 18 to 20.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the Edo period, women also described their celebration as Genpuku, and they experienced it simultaneously with marriage, and even if they were single, they held the ceremony at around the age 18 to 20.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the Edo period, women also described their celebration as Genpuku, and they experienced it simultaneously with marriage, and even if they were single, they held the ceremony at around the age 18 to 20.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>女性で元服という場合は、地味な着物を着て、日本髪の髪形を丸髷、両輪、又は先笄に替え、元服前より更に厚化粧になり、鉄漿親（かねおや）によりお歯黒を付けてもらい、引眉する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the case where a woman hold Genpuku, she wore modest kimono, changed her hairstyle to marumage (rounded hair style of a married woman), ryowa (two knots are made and fixed with a stick called &quot;kogai&quot; with the remaining hair rolled up), or sakko fashion (Maiko&apos;s hairstyle), and had heavier makeup than that of a girl before Genpuku, was put ohaguro by kaneoya (godmother of kanetsuke), and had hikimayu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When a woman celebrated Genpuku, she wore modest kimono, changed her hairstyle to marumage (rounded hair style of a married woman), ryowa (two knots are made and fixed with a stick called &quot;kogai&quot; with the remaining hair rolled up), or sakko fashion (Maiko&apos;s hairstyle), and wore heavier makeup and ohaguro was put on by kaneoya (godmother of kanetsuke), and had hikimayu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When a woman celebrated Genpuku, she wore modest kimono, changed her hairstyle to marumage (rounded hair style of a married woman), ryowa (two knots are made and fixed with a stick called &quot;kogai&quot; with the remaining hair rolled up), or sakko fashion (Maiko&apos;s hairstyle), and wore heavier makeup and ohaguro was put on by kaneoya (godmother of kanetsuke), and had hikimayu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>お歯黒を付けるが引眉しない場合は半元服と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the case where the woman had ohaguro but did not have hikimayu, it was called hangempuku (attaining womanhood informally).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the case where the woman had ohaguro, but did not have hikimayu, it was called hangempuku (attaining womanhood informally).</e>
<cmt>gramamr</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the case where the woman had ohaguro, but did not have hikimayu, it was called hangempuku (attaining womanhood informally).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>半元服の習慣は現在でも祇園の舞妓、嶋原の太夫等、一部の花街に残る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The custom of hangempuku still remains even now in a part of Hanamachi (geisha districts in Kyoto), for example among Maiko (an apprentice geisha) in Gion, Tayu (a high ranking courtesan) in Shimabara, and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The custom of hangempuku still remains even now in a part of Hanamachi (geisha districts in Kyoto), for example among Maiko (an apprentice geisha) in Gion, Tayu (a high ranking courtesan) in Shimabara, and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The custom of hangempuku still remains even now in a part of Hanamachi (geisha districts in Kyoto), for example among Maiko (an apprentice geisha) in Gion, Tayu (a high ranking courtesan) in Shimabara, and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Lonicera(id:20638), Izayohi(id:13095), Nnh(id:474), YurikBot(id:18605), 経済準学士(id:22656), NDR(id:5500), FlaBot(id:30804), 三日月(id:19540), Greenland4(id:114494), Mikomaid(id:56139), 弥(id:61590), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>