<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>本直し</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Honnaoshi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Honnaoshi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Honnaoshi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>本直し（ほんなおし）は、アルコール飲料の一種。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Honnaoshi is a kind of alcoholic drinks.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Honnaoshi is a kind of alcoholic drink.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Honnaoshi is a kind of alcoholic drink.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>直しとも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called naoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called naoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called naoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>調味料でもある甘味の強いみりんに焼酎を加えて甘味を抑え、飲みやすくしたもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a product which is produced by blending mirin (sweet sweet rice wine), which is very sweet and used usually as seasoning, with shochu so that the product becomes less sweet and easy to drink.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It&apos;s a product made by blending mirin (sweet rice wine), which is very sweet and is usually employed as a seasoning, with shochu so that the product becomes less sweet and is therefore easy to drink.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It&apos;s a product made by blending mirin (sweet rice wine), which is very sweet and is usually employed as a seasoning, with shochu so that the product becomes less sweet and is therefore easy to drink.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>柳蔭（やなぎかげ）と美称されることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Using a good name, honnaoshi is sometimes called yanagikake.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the complimentary sense, honnaoshi is sometimes called yanagikake.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the complimentary sense, honnaoshi is sometimes called yanagikake.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>「飲みにくい酒を手直しする」というニュアンスから「直し」という呼称が発生した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its name &quot;naoshi &quot; (literally improve) derived from &quot;improve the taste of difficult-to drink alcoholic drink&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its name &quot;naoshi &quot; (literally, improve) is derived from &quot;improve the taste of a difficult-to drink alcoholic beverage.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its name &apos;naoshi&apos; (literally, improve) is derived from &apos;improve the taste of a difficult-to drink alcoholic beverage.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>江戸時代には焼酎の亜種としてよく飲まれていたが、現在では一般にはマイナーな存在である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although it was drunk by many people in the Edo period as a subspiecies of shochu, it is a minor alcoholic drink at present.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although it was drunk by many people in the Edo period as a subtype of shochu, today it has minor status.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it was drunk by many people in the Edo period as a subtype of shochu, today it has minor status.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>かつては夏の暑気払いとして、井戸で冷やされて楽しまれ、高級品として扱われていたことが、上方落語の「青菜」に伺える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fact that it was drunk in summer season after cooled in a well and was treated as luxury good is seen from the story of &quot;Aona&quot;, a program of kamigata-rakugo (traditional Japanese storytelling performed in Kyoto-Osaka region).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fact that it was drunk in the summer season after being cooled in a well and was treated as luxury product is seen from the story of &quot;Aona,&quot; a program of kamigata-rakugo (traditional Japanese storytelling performed in the region of Kyoto and Osaka).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fact that it was drunk in the summer season after being cooled in a well and was treated as luxury product is seen from the story of &apos;Aona,&apos; a program of kamigata-rakugo (traditional Japanese storytelling performed in the region of Kyoto and Osaka).</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>また正月の屠蘇のベースとして用いられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was also used as the principal material of toso (spiced sake which is used for celebrating a New year).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was also used as the principal material of toso (a spiced sake that is used in celebration of the New Year).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was also used as the principal material of toso (a spiced sake that is used in celebration of the New Year).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>法的には「飲用みりん」と言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Legally, it is called &quot;drinking mirin&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Legally, it&apos;s called &quot;drinking mirin.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Legally, it&apos;s called &apos;drinking mirin.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>かつては酒税法上、「本みりん」とは区別され、飲用みりんは本みりんより課税額が安かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the Liquor Tax Act, it was distinguished from &quot;hon-mirin&quot; (pure mirin) in the past and its tax rate was lower than that of hon-mirin.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the Liquor Tax Act, it was once distinguished from &quot;hon-mirin (pure mirin),&quot; and its tax rate was lower than that of hon-mirin.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the Liquor Tax Act, it was once distinguished from &apos;hon-mirin&apos; (pure mirin), and its tax rate was lower than that of hon-mirin.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>しかし、のちには一本化された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, they were unified later.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, they were later unified.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, they were later unified.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>1990年代に世界貿易機関の勧告により、ウィスキーの酒税が下がる一方で焼酎の酒税は上昇した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the wake of WTO recommendation issued in the 1990s, whisky&apos;s tax rate was lowered while shochu&apos; tax rate was raised.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the wake of a WTO recommendation issued in the 1990s, the tax rate for whisky was lowered while the rate for shochu was raised.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the wake of a WTO recommendation issued in the 1990s, the tax rate for whisky was lowered while the rate for shochu was raised.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>しかし、料理酒と同一視された本直しは看過され、相対的に低い税率に抑えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, honnaoshi was overlooked since it was identified with cooking liquor and its tax rate was left relatively low.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, honnaoshi was overlooked since it was identified with cooking liquor, and its tax rate was left relatively low.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, honnaoshi was overlooked since it was identified with cooking liquor, and its tax rate was left relatively low.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>そこで一部の焼酎・みりん製造業者は、発泡酒同様の「節税焼酎」として本直しに着目した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under such circumstances, some manufacturers of shochu/mirin aimed at honnaoshi as &quot;tax-saving chochu&quot;, like the case of low-malt beer.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under such circumstances, some manufacturers of shochu/mirin aimed at honnaoshi as &quot;tax-saving chochu,&quot; as in the case of low-malt beer.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under such circumstances, some manufacturers of shochu/mirin aimed at honnaoshi as &apos;tax-saving shochu,&apos; as in the case of low-malt beer.</e>
<cmt>shochu としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>その結果、1990年代末期には飲用酒としての販売量が急激に増加した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, its sales amount as alcoholic drink increased rapidly toward the end of 1990s.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, its sales as an alcoholic beverage increased rapidly toward the end of the 1990s.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, its sales as an alcoholic beverage increased rapidly toward the end of the 1990s.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="16">
<j>しかし大蔵省（現・財務省）はこれを見逃さず、2000年には酒税改正を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the Ministry of Finance (the Finance Ministry) didn&apos;t overlook such situation and amended the Liquor Tax Act in 2000.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the Ministry of Finance (the Finance Ministry) didn&apos;t overlook the situation, and in 2000 it amended the Liquor Tax Act.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the Finance Ministry (current Ministry of Finance) didn&apos;t overlook the situation, and in 2000 it amended the Liquor Tax Act.</e>
<cmt>財務省→Ministry of Finance　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>これにより、焼酎を多く加えた飲用みりん（アルコール分23度以上、またはエキス分8度未満）については焼酎と同じ税率となり、直しへの需要は急激に廃れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of this amendment, tax rate of drinking mirin which contain shochu in large amount (the products whose alcoholicity is 23 proof or above, or the products whose content of extracted component is below 8%) was raised to the the same level with that of shochu and as a result, demand for naoshi declined steeply.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of that amendment, the tax rate of drinking mirin containing a large amount of shochu (the products whose alcohol content is 23 proof or above, or the products whose content of extracted component is below 8%) was raised to the same level at that of shochu, and consequently there was a sharp drop in the demand for naoshi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of that amendment, the tax rate of drinking mirin containing a large amount of shochu (the products whose alcohol content is 23 proof or above, or the products whose content of extracted component is below 8%) was raised to the same level at that of shochu, and consequently there was a sharp drop in the demand for naoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>現在の本直しは、比較的限られた業者が製造・販売している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Currently, limited number of manufacturers are manufacturing and selling honnaoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Currently, honnaoshi is produced and sold by a limited number of manufacturers.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Currently, honnaoshi is produced and sold by a limited number of manufacturers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Roger(id:9883), Izayohi(id:13095), Kazov(id:9237), Starbacks(id:1018), Jingmouyinghung(id:150853), Suisui(id:69), Johncapistrano(id:969), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>