<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>四条派</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shijo school</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shijo school</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shijo school</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>四条派（しじょうは）は、日本画界でも大きな派閥である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shijo school is a large group among those of the Japanese painting world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Shijo school is a large group among those of the Japanese painting world.</e>
<cmt>冠詞</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Shijo school is a large group among those of the Japanese painting world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>江戸中期頃、松村呉春を祖とし、岡本豊彦や松村景文らが発展させ、京都画壇で一大勢力となり、その後塩川文麟、幸野楳嶺、竹内栖鳳、西山翠嶂、堂本印象などと現代まで続いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around Mid-Edo period Goshun MATSUMURA founded it and Toyohiko OKAMOTO, Keibun MATSUMURA and others developed it to a force of Kyoto art circlesand then Bunrin SHIOKAWA, Bairei KONO, Seiho TAKEUCHI, Suisho NISHIYAMA, Insho DOMOTO and others took over and it has been going until now.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around the Mid-Edo period, Goshun MATSUMURA founded it and Toyohiko OKAMOTO, Keibun MATSUMURA and others developed it to a force of the Kyoto painting circles, then Bunrin SHIOKAWA, Bairei KONO, Seiho TAKEUCHI, Suisho NISHIYAMA, Insho DOMOTO and others took over and it continues to this day.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除「京都画壇」の訳を変更「現代まで続いている」の訳を変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around the Mid-Edo period, Goshun MATSUMURA founded it and Toyohiko OKAMOTO, Keibun MATSUMURA and others developed it to a force of the Kyoto painting circles, then Bunrin SHIOKAWA, Bairei KONO, Seiho TAKEUCHI, Suisho NISHIYAMA, Insho DOMOTO and others took over and it continues to this day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>四条派は、松村呉春を祖とする画家集団から始まる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shijo school started as a painter group founded by Goshun MATSUMURA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Shijo school started as a painter group founded by Goshun MATSUMURA.</e>
<cmt>冠詞</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Shijo school started as a painter group founded by Goshun MATSUMURA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>当初、呉春は与謝蕪村について、俳諧や文人画（南画）を学ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the beginning Goshun studied Haikai (amusing and playful waka) and literati painting (Nanga: a school of Chinese painting) under Buson YOSA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the beginning Goshun studied Haikai (amusing and playful waka) and literati painting (Nanga: a school of Chinese painting) under Buson YOSA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the beginning Goshun studied Haikai (amusing and playful waka) and literati painting (Nanga: a school of Chinese painting) under Buson YOSA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>その後一時、現在の大阪府池田市に滞在するものの、京都へ戻り円山応挙の門をたたくが、応挙は固辞して受けず、親友として待遇した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, he stayed in Ikeda City, Osaka Prefecture at one time and then went back to Kyoto to be a pupil of Okyo MARUYAMA, but Okyo refused the request and treat him as his best friend.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, he stayed in Ikeda City, Osaka Prefecture at one time and then went back to Kyoto to be a pupil of Okyo MARUYAMA, but Okyo refused the request and treat him as his best friend.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, he stayed in Ikeda City, Osaka Prefecture at one time and then went back to Kyoto to be a pupil of Okyo MARUYAMA, but Okyo refused the request and treat him as his best friend.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>そのため呉春は応挙の写実性の薫陶を受け、独特の画風を構築していく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then Goshun studied the realism of Okyo under him and built the unique painting style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then Goshun studied the realism of Okyo under him and built the unique painting style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then Goshun studied the realism of Okyo under him and built the unique painting style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>呉春の弟子である岡本豊彦や実弟で弟子でもある松村景文などが、四条通周辺に居を構えたことから、「四条派」と呼ばれるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toyohiko OKAMOTO, A pupil of Goshun and Keibun MATSUMURA, a younger brother and pupil of Goshun and others built their residences on the Shijo street and therefore they were called &quot;Shijo school&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toyohiko OKAMOTO, a pupil of Goshun, and Keibun MATSUMURA, a younger brother and pupil of Goshun, and other pupils built their residences on the Shijo street and therefore they were called &quot;Shijo school&quot;</e>
<cmt>aを小文字に修正カンマを追加</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toyohiko OKAMOTO, a pupil of Goshun, and Keibun MATSUMURA, a younger brother and pupil of Goshun, and other pupils built their residences on the Shijo street and therefore they were called &quot;Shijo school&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>この頃から、宮中に出入りする一方で、京都の町衆の支持も受け、四条派は大きく発展していくことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From that period, they started to visit the Imperial Court and on the other hand they had the support of people in Kyoto, which developed Shijo school further.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From that period, they started to visit the Imperial Court and on the other hand they had the support of people in Kyoto, which developed the Shijo school further.</e>
<cmt>冠詞</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From that period, they started to visit the Imperial Court and on the other hand they had the support of people in Kyoto, which developed the Shijo school further.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="9">
<j>豊彦や景文は多くの弟子を持ち、その中でも豊彦の弟子である塩川文麟が突出した才能を示したため、四条派の後継者となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the many pupils of Toyohiko and Keibun, Bunrin SHIOKAWA, a pupil of Toyohiko showed unusual talent, so he became the successor of Shijo school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the many pupils of Toyohiko and Keibun, Bunrin SHIOKAWA, a pupil of Toyohiko, showed unusual talent, so he became the successor of the Shijo school.</e>
<cmt>冠詞カンマを追加</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the many pupils of Toyohiko and Keibun, Bunrin SHIOKAWA, a pupil of Toyohiko, showed unusual talent, so he became the successor of the Shijo school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="10">
<j>明治以後文麟は西洋画の手法を取り入れ、それが四条派の画風を変えるきっかけとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Meiji period, Bunrin adopted the techniques of Western paintings, which changed the painting style of Shijo school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Meiji period and after, Bunrin adopted the techniques of Western paintings, which changed the painting style of the Shijo school.</e>
<cmt>冠詞「明治以降」の表記を変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Meiji period and after, Bunrin adopted the techniques of Western paintings, which changed the painting style of the Shijo school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>それは文麟の後継者となる幸野楳嶺にも伝えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He taught Bairei KONO the techniques who became the successor of Bunrin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He taught Bairei KONO the techniques who became the successor of Bunrin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He taught Bairei KONO the techniques who became the successor of Bunrin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>幸野楳嶺は、画家と言うよりも教育者としての側面が強く、竹内栖鳳や菊池芳文をはじめとする多くの弟子たちを育てた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bairei KONO had the stronger side as a teacher than a painter and trained a lot of pupils of him like Seiho TAKEUCHI, Hobun KIKUCHI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bairei KONO was more of a teacher than a painter and trained a lot of pupils such as Seiho TAKEUCHI and Hobun KIKUCHI.</e>
<cmt>「側面が強い」の訳を変更of himを削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bairei KONO was more of a teacher than a painter and trained a lot of pupils such as Seiho TAKEUCHI and Hobun KIKUCHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="13">
<j>明治に入り、実質的に竹内栖鳳が四条派を継ぐことになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Meji period, Seiho TAKEUCHI succeeded Shijo school practically.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Meji period, Seiho TAKEUCHI succeeded the Shijo school practically.</e>
<cmt>冠詞</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Meji period, Seiho TAKEUCHI succeeded the Shijo school practically.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>栖鳳は狩野派や西洋画の写実画法などを積極的に取り入れ、再び四条派の画風を変えることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He adopted the technique of realism from Kano school and Western paintings willingly and changed the painting style of Shijo school again.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He adopted the technique of realism from the Kano school and Western paintings willingly and changed the painting style of the Shijo school again.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除冠詞</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He adopted the technique of realism from the Kano school and Western paintings willingly and changed the painting style of the Shijo school again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="15">
<j>この頃からは、多くの弟子たちが個別に活躍するようになり、上村松園や西山翠嶂をはじめ、西村五雲、土田麦僊、小野竹喬、池田遙邨などが活躍した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since that period, a lot of pupils started to work actively and individually like Shoen UEMURA, Suisho NISHIYAMA and others like Goun NISHIMURA, Bakusen TSUCHIDA, Chikkyo ONO, Yoson IKEDA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that time, a lot of pupils started to work actively and individually like Shoen UEMURA, Suisho NISHIYAMA and others like Goun NISHIMURA, Bakusen TSUCHIDA, Chikkyo ONO, Yoson IKEDA.</e>
<cmt>「この頃から」の訳を変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that time, a lot of pupils started to work actively and individually like Shoen UEMURA, Suisho NISHIYAMA and others like Goun NISHIMURA, Bakusen TSUCHIDA, Chikkyo ONO, Yoson IKEDA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="16">
<j>またその後は、堂本印象、上村松篁、中村大三郎らが活躍し、現在に至っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that Insho DOMOTO, Shoko UEMURA, Daizaburo NAKMURA and others played active roles and Shijo school continued up to the present.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, Insho DOMOTO, Shoko UEMURA, Daizaburo NAKMURA and others played active roles and the Shijo school continued up to the present.</e>
<cmt>「その後は」の表記を変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, Insho DOMOTO, Shoko UEMURA, Daizaburo NAKMURA and others played active roles and the Shijo school continued up to the present.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>黎明期（江戸時代）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The earliest days (Edo period)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The earliest days (Edo period)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The earliest days (Edo period)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="17">
<j>「概要」にある程度書いたように、四条派は円山派の流れをくんではいるが、松村呉春は円山応挙と対立したわけではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As already written some in the summary above, Shijo school is derived from Maruyama school, but it doesn&apos;t mean that Goshun MATSUMURA conflicted with Okyo MARUYAMA.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As already written in the summary above, the Shijo school is derived from the Maruyama school, but it doesn&apos;t mean that Goshun MATSUMURA conflicted with Okyo MARUYAMA.</e>
<cmt>冠詞someを削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As already written in the summary above, the Shijo school is derived from the Maruyama school, but it doesn&apos;t mean that Goshun MATSUMURA conflicted with Okyo MARUYAMA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>蕪村から学んだ文人画（南画）を基礎とし、応挙の写生画風を取り入れ、独自の形で発展させ、四条派を作り上げる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He rather took the realism of Okyo in his own style and developed it uniquely on the basis of literati painting (Nanga) learned from Buson and built up Shijo school.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He rather took the realism of Okyo in his own style and developed it uniquely on the basis of literati painting (Nanga) learned from Buson and built up the Shijo school.</e>
<cmt>冠詞</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He rather took the realism of Okyo in his own style and developed it uniquely on the basis of literati painting (Nanga) learned from Buson and built up the Shijo school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>つまり、円山派の発展形のひとつが四条派と言うことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In other words, Shijo school is one of the developed styles of Maruyama school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In other words, the Shijo school is one of the developed styles of the Maruyama school.</e>
<cmt>冠詞</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In other words, the Shijo school is one of the developed styles of the Maruyama school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="20">
<j>呉春は器用な人物で、独自の画風を簡単に作り上げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Goshun is so efficient that he built up his own painting style easily.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Goshun was so efficient that he built up his own painting style easily.</e>
<cmt>is→wasに変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Goshun was so efficient that he built up his own painting style easily.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>そして、それに学ぼうと多くの弟子が集まる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And a lot of people came to him to be his pupils to learn the style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A lot of people came to him to be his pupils and to learn the style.</e>
<cmt>andを追加文頭のAndを削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A lot of people came to him to be his pupils and to learn the style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>代表的なのは、実弟の松村景文、備中国水江村から出てきた岡本豊彦、備前国から出てきた柴田義董、長門国赤間関から出てきた小田海僊らである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The leading people are Keibun MATSUMURA of his younger brother, Toyohiko OKAMOTO from Mizue Village in Bicchu Province, Gito SHIBATA from Bizen Province, Kaisen ODA from Akamagaseki in Nagato Province and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The leading people are Keibun MATSUMURA, his younger brother, Toyohiko OKAMOTO from Mizue Village in Bicchu Province, Gito SHIBATA from Bizen Province, Kaisen ODA from Akamagaseki in Nagato Province.</e>
<cmt>and othersを削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The leading people are Keibun MATSUMURA, his younger brother, Toyohiko OKAMOTO from Mizue Village in Bicchu Province, Gito SHIBATA from Bizen Province, Kaisen ODA from Akamagaseki in Nagato Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="23">
<j>呉春の弟子たちは、互いに切磋琢磨しあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those pupils of Goshun learned from each other using friendly competition.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The pupils of Goshun improved together through friendly rivalry.</e>
<cmt>「お互いから学んだ」とは記述されていないため変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The pupils of Goshun improved together through friendly rivalry.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>特に豊彦と景文が頭角をあらわし、「花鳥は景文、山水は豊彦」と言われるまでになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among them, especially Toyohiko and Keibun stood out as the painters told &quot;birds and flowers of Keibun, landscapes of Toyohiko&quot;.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among them, Toyohiko and Keibun especially stood out; people often said &quot;the birds and flowers of Keibun or the landscapes of Toyohiko&quot;.</e>
<cmt>as the paiｎnters を削除told→to be toldに変更especiallyの位置を変更「「花鳥は景文、山水は豊彦」と言われるまでになる。」の部分を変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among them, Toyohiko and Keibun especially stood out; people often said &quot;the birds and flowers of Keibun or the landscapes of Toyohiko&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="25">
<j>また、景文も豊彦も多くの弟子を持ち、景文の弟子には西山芳園、長谷川玉峰、横山清暉などがおり、豊彦の弟子には塩川文麟、岡本亮彦、柴田是真、田中日華などがいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keibun and Toyohiko also accepted a lot of pupils: Keibun&apos;s pupils including Hoen NISHIYAMA, Gyokuho Hasegawa, Seiki YOKOYAMA and others, Toyohiko&apos;s pupils including Bunrin SHIOKAWA, Sukehiko OKAMOTO, Zeshin SHIBATA, Nikka TANAKA and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keibun and Toyohiko also accepted a lot of pupils: Keibun&apos;s pupils include Hoen NISHIYAMA, Gyokuho HASEGAWA and Seiki YOKOYAMA, and Toyohiko&apos;s pupils include Bunrin SHIOKAWA, Sukehiko OKAMOTO, Zeshin SHIBATA and Nikka TANAKA.</e>
<cmt>名字を大文字に変更and othersを削除includingの箇所の構成を変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keibun and Toyohiko also accepted a lot of pupils: Keibun&apos;s pupils include Hoen NISHIYAMA, Gyokuho HASEGAWA and Seiki YOKOYAMA, and Toyohiko&apos;s pupils include Bunrin SHIOKAWA, Sukehiko OKAMOTO, Zeshin SHIBATA and Nikka TANAKA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>どちらも、一門を抱えるほどであったが、四条派を継いだのは豊彦の方であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They both had a large number of people of the school, but after all Toyohiko succeeded Shijo school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They both had a large number of people of the school, but Toyohiko succeeded the Shijo school.</e>
<cmt>after allを削除冠詞</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They both had a large number of people of the school, but Toyohiko succeeded the Shijo school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="27">
<j>豊彦は、有栖川宮家と親交があり、宮中にも出入りし、修学院離宮にも作品が残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because Toyohiko was friends with Arisugawa no miya imperial family and used to visit the Imperial Court, his works remain in Shugakuin Imperial Villa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toyohiko was associated with the Arisugawa no miya imperial family and used to visit the Imperial Court, and his works remain in Shugakuin Imperial Villa.</e>
<cmt>「親交がある」の表記を変更構成を変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toyohiko was associated with the Arisugawa no miya imperial family and used to visit the Imperial Court, and his works remain in Shugakuin Imperial Villa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>また、弟子で養子の岡本亮彦は、安政2年（1855年）の京都御所再建時に、障壁画を任されるほどだった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And therefore Sukehiko OKOMOTO, a pupil and adopted son of Toyohiko was requested fusuma (a thick papered sliding door for partitioning rooms in a Japanese house) paintings when the Kyoto Imperial Palace was rebuilt in 1855.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, Sukehiko OKOMOTO, a pupil and adopted son of Toyohiko, was requested fusuma (a thick papered sliding door for partitioning rooms in a Japanese house) paintings when the Kyoto Imperial Palace was rebuilt in 1855.</e>
<cmt>文頭を変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, Sukehiko OKOMOTO, a pupil and adopted son of Toyohiko, was requested fusuma (a thick papered sliding door for partitioning rooms in a Japanese house) paintings when the Kyoto Imperial Palace was rebuilt in 1855.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="29">
<j>豊彦の弟子の中でも、特に才覚をあらわしたのが塩川文麟である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among those pupils of Toyohiko, Especially Bunrin SHIOKAWA showed the talent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among those pupils of Toyohiko, especially Bunrin SHIOKAWA showed the talent.</e>
<cmt>eを小文字に変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among those pupils of Toyohiko, especially Bunrin SHIOKAWA showed the talent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>彼は呉春に褒められるほど、幼少の頃から才気だったところがあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was so talented that Goshun praised him already when he was a child.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was so talented that Goshun praised him when he was a child.</e>
<cmt>alreadyを削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was so talented that Goshun praised him when he was a child.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>また、文麟は豊彦の肖像画も描いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bunrin also drew a portrait of Toyohiko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bunrin also drew a portrait of Toyohiko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bunrin also drew a portrait of Toyohiko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>文麟が四条派を継いだのは自然な流れだったのかもしれない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It may be natural that Bunrin succeeded Shijo school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It may have been natural that Bunrin succeeded the Shijo school.</e>
<cmt>冠詞時制</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It may have been natural that Bunrin succeeded the Shijo school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>発展期（明治・大正）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The developing period (Meiji and Taisho period)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The developing period (Meiji and Taisho period)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The developing period (Meiji and Taisho period)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="33">
<j>塩川文麟が、明治になって積極的に西洋画の画法を取り入れた事によって、四条派の画風にも変化が起きる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because Bunrin SHIOKAWA took the techniques of Western paintings willingly, the painting style of Shijo school changed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because Bunrin SHIOKAWA adopted the techniques of Western paintings willingly, the painting style of the Shijo school changed in the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>「明治になって」を追加</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because Bunrin SHIOKAWA adopted the techniques of Western paintings willingly, the painting style of the Shijo school changed in the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>それまでの構図や彩色法の型を破って、水彩画法を応用して従来の日本画になかった色彩を横長の画面で表現した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He broke the traditional style of composition and coloring and adopted watercolour technique and expressed colors which had never seen in the traditional Japanese paintings, in rectangular picture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He broke the traditional style of composition and coloring, adopted watercolor techniques and expressed colors which had never seen in the traditional Japanese paintings in a landscape-oriented picture.</e>
<cmt>冠詞カンマを削除「横長」の訳を変更watercolorのスペルミスを修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He broke the traditional style of composition and coloring, adopted watercolor techniques and expressed colors which had never seen in the traditional Japanese paintings in a landscape-oriented picture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>そう言った意味では、文麟は時代の先覚者であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In that sense, Bunrin was a pioneer of the times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In that sense, Bunrin was a pioneer of the times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In that sense, Bunrin was a pioneer of the times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="36">
<j>文麟も多くの弟子を持ったが、その中で後継者となったのは幸野楳嶺だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also Bunrin accepted a lot of pupils and among them Bairei KONO became the successor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bunrin also accepted a lot of pupils and among them Bairei KONO became the successor.</e>
<cmt>alsoの位置を変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bunrin also accepted a lot of pupils and among them Bairei KONO became the successor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>楳嶺の画風にはそれほど見るべき点は無いが、文麟が作り上げた画風を忠実に受けつぎながらも、幅広い画域を誇った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The painting style of Bairei had no striking features, but he followed the style created by Bunrin faithfully and also had an ability in a wide variety of paintings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The painting style of Bairei had no striking features, but he followed the style created by Bunrin faithfully and also had an ability in a wide variety of painting styles.</e>
<cmt>paintingsｙ→painting stylesに変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The painting style of Bairei had no striking features, but he followed the style created by Bunrin faithfully and also had an ability in a wide variety of painting styles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="38">
<j>しかし、楳嶺の本領は教育の分野で発揮された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But Bairei showed him at his best in the field of education.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But Bairei showed himself at his best in the field of education.</e>
<cmt>him→himselfに変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But Bairei showed himself at his best in the field of education.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>京都府知事に画学校の設立を建議し「京都府画学校（後の「京都市立芸術大学」）」を設立し、教鞭をとっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He proposed the governor of Kyoto Prefecture to establish Kyoto Prefectural School of Painting (future Kyoto City University of Arts) and taught there after it was established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He proposed the governor of Kyoto Prefecture to establish Kyoto Prefectural School of Painting (future Kyoto City University of Arts) and taught there.</e>
<cmt>after it was establishedを削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He proposed the governor of Kyoto Prefecture to establish Kyoto Prefectural School of Painting (future Kyoto City University of Arts) and taught there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>また、私塾を開き多くの弟子たちを育てた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also trained a lot of pupils in his own private school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also trained a lot of pupils in his own private school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also trained a lot of pupils in his own private school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>その中に「楳嶺四天王」と呼ばれる竹内栖鳳や菊池芳文、都路華香、谷口香嶠たちがおり、その他にも上村松園（楳嶺の死後は栖鳳の下で学ぶ）がいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among them there were so called &quot;The big four of Bairei&quot; including Seiho TAKEUCHI, Hobun KIKUCHI, Kako TSUJI, Kokyo Taniguchi and also Shoen UEMURA who studied under Seiho after the death of Bairei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among them there were so called &quot;the big four of Bairei&quot; including Seiho TAKEUCHI, Hobun KIKUCHI, Kako TSUJI, Kokyo TANIGUCHI and also Shoen UEMURA who studied under Seiho after the death of Bairei.</e>
<cmt>名字を大文字に変更記号を半角に変更theを小文字に変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among them there were so called &quot;the big four of Bairei&quot; including Seiho TAKEUCHI, Hobun KIKUCHI, Kako TSUJI, Kokyo TANIGUCHI and also Shoen UEMURA who studied under Seiho after the death of Bairei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>楳嶺の教育方針は、基礎を徹底的に叩き込んだ後で、自由にさせるというもので、最初は弟子たちからは恐れられていたが、結構面倒見は良かったようで、常に弟子たちを引き立てるようにしていたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On his educational policy, first Bairei trained them to the basics thoroughly and then set them free, so they were afraid of Bairei first, but actually he took care of them well and always tried to cheer them up.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On his educational policy, Bairei first trained them in the basics thoroughly and then set them free, so they were afraid of Bairei first, but actually he took care of them well and always tried to cheer them up.</e>
<cmt>firstの位置を変更to→inに変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On his educational policy, Bairei first trained them in the basics thoroughly and then set them free, so they were afraid of Bairei first, but actually he took care of them well and always tried to cheer them up.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="43">
<j>楳嶺の死後、「楳嶺四天王」の中でも竹内栖鳳が特に頭角をあらわし、京都府画学校を修了した後、京都の若手画家の先鋭として名を挙げていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Bairei died, among &quot;The big four of Bairei&quot; Seiho TAKEUCHI showed the talent especially and after graduated from Kyoto Prefectural School of Painting he became famous as a leader of young painters in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Bairei died, among &quot;the big four of Bairei&quot; Seiho TAKEUCHI showed the talent especially, and after graduated from Kyoto Prefectural School of Painting he became famous as a leader of young painters in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>カンマを挿入theを小文字に変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Bairei died, among &quot;the big four of Bairei&quot; Seiho TAKEUCHI showed the talent especially, and after graduated from Kyoto Prefectural School of Painting he became famous as a leader of young painters in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>また「帝室技芸員」にも選ばれ、第1回の文化勲章を受章し、名実共に京都画壇の筆頭となっていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also he was selected as a &quot;Teishitsu Gigeiin (selected artist by Imperial Household Ministry)&quot; and won the 1st Order of Culture and became the top of Kyoto painting circles both in name and reality.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was selected as a &quot;Teishitsu Gigeiin&quot; (selected artist by Imperial Household Ministry) and won the first Order of Culture and became the top of Kyoto painting circles both in name and reality.</e>
<cmt>Alsoを削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was selected as a &quot;Teishitsu Gigeiin&quot; (selected artist by Imperial Household Ministry) and won the first Order of Culture and became the top of Kyoto painting circles both in name and reality.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="45">
<j>その後は、栖鳳や菊池芳文の弟子たちが、個別に活躍していく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that the pupils of Seiho and Hobun KIKUCHI played active roles of their own.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that the pupils of Seiho and Hobun KIKUCHI played active roles of their own.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that the pupils of Seiho and Hobun KIKUCHI played active roles of their own.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="46">
<j>有名なところでは、上村松園や西山翠嶂をはじめ、西村五雲、土田麦僊、小野竹喬、池田遙邨、谷口香嶠、橋本関雪、菊池契月などが活躍した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Famous people among them are Shoen UEMURA, Suisho NISHIYAMA and others like Goun NISHIYAMA, Bakusen TSUCHIDA, Chikkyo ONO, Yoson IKEDA, Kokyo TANIGUCHI, Kansetsu HASHIMOTO, Keigetsu KIKUCHI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Famous people among them are Shoen UEMURA, Suisho NISHIYAMA and others like Goun NISHIMURA, Bakusen TSUCHIDA, Chikkyo ONO, Yoson IKEDA, Kokyo TANIGUCHI, Kansetsu HASHIMOTO, Keigetsu KIKUCHI.</e>
<cmt>NISHIYAMA→NISHIMURAに変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Famous people among them are Shoen UEMURA, Suisho NISHIYAMA and others like Goun NISHIMURA, Bakusen TSUCHIDA, Chikkyo ONO, Yoson IKEDA, Kokyo TANIGUCHI, Kansetsu HASHIMOTO, Keigetsu KIKUCHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>安定期（昭和・平成）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The stabilized period (Showa and Heisei period)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The stabilized period (Showa and Heisei period)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The stabilized period (Showa and Heisei period)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="47">
<j>昭和に入ると戦争の足音が響くようになり、栖鳳は軍部に協力することもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Showa period, because of the war cloud Seiho sometimes cooperated with the military.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Showa period, because of the threat of war Seiho sometimes cooperated with the military.</e>
<cmt>「戦争の足音が響くようになり」の訳を変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Showa period, because of the threat of war Seiho sometimes cooperated with the military.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="48">
<j>しかし、戦後になると文化勲章受章者の堂本印象や上村松篁、それ以外にも中村大三郎、宇田荻邨らが活躍し、またその弟子たちが現在活躍するに至っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But after the war, Insho DOMOTO and Shoko Uemura who both won Order of Culture and others like Daizaburo NAKAMURA and Tekison UDA played active roles and then their pupils are also active now.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But after the war, Insho DOMOTO and Shoko Uemura who both won Order of Culture and others like Daizaburo NAKAMURA and Tekison UDA played active roles, and their pupils are active now.</e>
<cmt>thenを削除alsoを削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But after the war, Insho DOMOTO and Shoko Uemura who both won Order of Culture and others like Daizaburo NAKAMURA and Tekison UDA played active roles, and their pupils are active now.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 松茸(id:27535), Kimihiko Ozaki(id:293258), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>