<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>犬追物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Inuou-mono (dog-hunting event, a skill of an archery)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Inuoumono (dog-hunting event, a skill of an archery)</e>
<cmt>Inuou-mono→Inuoumono （用語集、ウェブ上にてこちらのスペルを確認しました）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Inuoumono (dog-hunting event, a skill of an archery)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>犬追物（いぬおうもの）は鎌倉時代から始まったとされる日本の弓術の作法の一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Inuou-mono is one of the manners of the art of Japanese archery that started from the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Inuoumono is one of the manners of the art of Japanese archery that started from the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>Inuou-mono→Inuoumono と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Inuoumono is one of the manners of the art of Japanese archery that started from the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>流鏑馬、笠懸と共に騎射三物の一つに数えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is one of the Kisha-Mitsumono (three archeries with riding a horse, Inuou-mono, Kasagake, and Yabusame) along with Yabusame (horseback archery) and Kasagake (horseback archery competition).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is one of the Kisha-Mitsumono (three archeries with riding a horse), along with Yabusame (horseback archery) and Kasagake (horseback archery competition).</e>
<cmt>Inuou-mono, Kasagake, and Yabusame を削除しました。（同文中にて重複のため）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is one of the Kisha-Mitsumono (three archeries with riding a horse), along with Yabusame (horseback archery) and Kasagake (horseback archery competition).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>作法</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Manners</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Manners</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Manners</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>競技場として40間四方の平坦なスペースを準備し、そこを「馬場」とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A flat space of about 120m square is prepared as a field and is used as &quot;baba&quot; (a horse-riding ground).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A flat space of about 132㎡ is prepared and is used as &apos;umaba&apos; (a horse-riding ground).</e>
<cmt>120m square→132㎡ と修正しました。（一間四方＝3.3㎡）baba→umaba （「うまば」、「ばば」の両方の読み方を確認しましたが『大辞林』、&quot;umaba&quot; での使用をウエブ上で認めましたのでこちらに修正しました）クォーツを修正しました。as a field を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A flat space of about 132㎡ is prepared and is used as &apos;umaba&apos; (a horse-riding ground).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>その馬場に36騎の騎手（12騎を1組とする）、2騎の検分者（「検見」といわれる）、2騎の喚次、150匹の犬を投入し、所定の時間内に騎手が何匹犬を射たかで争う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">36 horsemen (one unit consists of 12 horsemen), two kenbunsha (a person for judgment) who are also called an inspector, and two persons for calling, and 150 dogs also enter the baba, and horsemen compete each other how many dogs they shoot at within a given time period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">36 horsemen (one unit consists of 12 horsemen), 2 judges (called &apos;kenmi&apos; an inspector), and 2 people for calling, and 150 dogs also enter the umaba, and horsemen compete each other how many dogs they shoot at within a given time period.</e>
<cmt>検分者はタイトル名ではないと理解し、修正し、”「検見」といわれる”という部分を補いました。「検見」の読み方は家訓済みです。two→2,two persons→2 people,baba→umaba と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">36 horsemen (one unit consists of 12 horsemen), 2 judges (called &apos;kenmi&apos; an inspector), and 2 people for calling, and 150 dogs also enter the umaba, and horsemen compete each other how many dogs they shoot at within a given time period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>しかし実際に犬を打ち抜くことは無く、「犬射引目」（いぬうちひきめ）という特殊な矢を使用した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, they did not actually shoot dogs but used a specially designed arrow called &quot;inuuchihikime&quot; arrow (an arrow for dog-shooting).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, they did not actually harm dogs but used specially designed arrows called &apos;inuuchihikime&apos; arrow (an arrow for dog-shooting).</e>
<cmt>shoot→harm と修正しました。クォーツを修正しました。a arrow→arrows と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, they did not actually harm dogs but used specially designed arrows called &apos;inuuchihikime&apos; arrow (an arrow for dog-shooting).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>ただ単に犬に矢を当てればいいと言う物ではなく、相撲の決め手のように打ち方や命中した場所によっていくつもの技が存在した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was not merely about shooting at dogs but there were many techniques depending on how to shoot or what part of the dog an arrow hit, like a winning move in a sumo tournament.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was not merely about shooting at dogs but there were many techniques according to how to shoot or what part of the dog an arrow hit, such as winning moves in sumo.</e>
<cmt>depending on→according to,like a winning move in a sumo tournament の部分を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was not merely about shooting at dogs but there were many techniques according to how to shoot or what part of the dog an arrow hit, such as winning moves in sumo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>この判定のために検見や喚次が必要となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To judge these techniques, inspectors and persons for calling were needed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To judge these techniques, inspectors and persons for calling were needed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To judge these techniques, inspectors and persons for calling were needed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>鎌倉時代に武士が平時の武芸の鍛錬のために始めた物と言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Inuou-mono was started by samurais in the Kamakura period to train and improve their military arts skills.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Inuoumono was started by samurai in the Kamakura period to train and improve their military arts skills.</e>
<cmt>Inuou-mono→Inuoumono,samurais→samurai と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Inuoumono was started by samurai in the Kamakura period to train and improve their military arts skills.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>当時は獣類をウマで追い騎射をする競技を総称して「追物射」（おうものい）と言い、牛を追う「牛追物」などもあったが、犬を追う「犬追物」だけが残った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, the hunting that horsemen did Kisha (to shoot an arrow with riding a horse) at animals was called &quot;oumonoi&quot; and there were also other games such as &quot;Ushioumono&quot; (cows-hunting event, a skill of an archery) but only Inuou-mono had been preserved.</e>
<cmt>用語集では oumonoyumi となっていますが、「追物射」（おうものい）とありますので、oumonoi とします。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, the hunting that horsemen did Kisha (to shoot an arrow with riding a horse) at animals was called &apos;oumonoi,&apos; and there were also other games such as &apos;Ushioumono&apos; (cows-hunting event, a skill of an archery) but only &apos;Inuoumono&apos; had been preserved.</e>
<cmt>クォーツ,Inuou-mono を修正しました。クォーツ、カンマを挿入しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, the hunting that horsemen did Kisha (to shoot an arrow with riding a horse) at animals was called &apos;oumonoi,&apos; and there were also other games such as &apos;Ushioumono&apos; (cows-hunting event, a skill of an archery) but only &apos;Inuoumono&apos; had been preserved.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>北条氏得宗家（宗家）最後の当主北条高時が闘犬や犬追物にはまって政治を省みなくなり、鎌倉幕府滅亡の原因となったとする伝説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Legend has it that Inuou-mono was the reason of the fall of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) because the last head of the Tokuso Family of the Hojo clan (Soke, (head of family, originator)), Takatoki HOJO, devoted himself in dogfight and Inuou-mono and neglected politics.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Legend has it that Inuoumono was the reason of the down fall of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) because the last head of the Tokuso Family of the Hojo clan (Soke, [head of family, originator]), Takatoki HOJO, devoted himself in dogfights and Inuoumono then neglected the politics.</e>
<cmt>Inuou-mono→Inuoumono,fall→down fall,in dogfight→to dogfights,and→then,カッコ内を修正しました。the を挿入しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Legend has it that Inuoumono was the reason of the down fall of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) because the last head of the Tokuso Family of the Hojo clan (Soke, [head of family, originator]), Takatoki HOJO, devoted himself in dogfights and Inuoumono then neglected the politics.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>戦国時代 (日本)に入ると、作法を保持していた有力な守護大名・守護代が次々と滅び、江戸時代まで作法を継承できたのは島津氏と小笠原氏だけとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States) (Japan), dominant Shugo daimyo (Japanese territorial lord as provincial constable) and Shugodai (the acting Military Governor) who preserved Inuou-mono manners perished one after another, and those who could maintain the manner even in the Edo period were only the Shimazu clan and the Ogasawara clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States) (Japan), dominant Shugo daimyo (Japanese territorial lord as provincial constable) and Shugodai (the acting Military Governor) who were preserving Inuoumono manners perished one after another, and those who could maintain the manner even to the Edo period were only the Shimazu clan and the Ogasawara clan.</e>
<cmt>preserved→were preserving,in→to,Inuou-mono→Inuoumono と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States) (Japan), dominant Shugo daimyo (Japanese territorial lord as provincial constable) and Shugodai (the acting Military Governor) who were preserving Inuoumono manners perished one after another, and those who could maintain the manner even to the Edo period were only the Shimazu clan and the Ogasawara clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>その後、薩摩藩では一時生類憐みの令による中断を除き、世子の元服の時など慶事のおりに開催していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, in the Satsuma clan, Inuou-mono was held at auspicious events such as heirs&apos; genpuku (celebrate one&apos;s coming of age), except the period when it was suspended by the law prohibiting cruelty to animals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, in the Satsuma clan, Inuoumono was held at auspicious events such as heirs&apos; genpuku (celebrate one&apos;s coming of age), except during the interruption by the law prohibiting cruelty to animals.</e>
<cmt>Inuou-mono→Inuoumono,the period when it was suspended の部分を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, in the Satsuma clan, Inuoumono was held at auspicious events such as heirs&apos; genpuku (celebrate one&apos;s coming of age), except during the interruption by the law prohibiting cruelty to animals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>また、島津光久が徳川家綱のために興行したこともある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitsuhisa SHIMAZU once held the event for Ietsuna TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitsuhisa SHIMAZU once held the event for Ietsuna TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitsuhisa SHIMAZU once held the event for Ietsuna TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="16">
<j>明治維新の後幕藩体制が崩壊、幕府、薩摩藩という庇護者を失った犬追物は技術保持が困難となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Meiji Restoration and the demise of the feudal system characteristic of the shogunate, Inuou-mono lost its patrons such as bakufu and the Satsuma clan and become difficult to maintain its techniques.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Meiji Restoration and the demise of the feudal system characteristic of the shogunate, Inuoumono lost its patrons such as the bakufu and the Satsuma clan and become difficult to maintain its techniques.</e>
<cmt>Inuou-mono→Inuoumono,bakufu→the bakufu,</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Meiji Restoration and the demise of the feudal system characteristic of the shogunate, Inuoumono lost its patrons such as the bakufu and the Satsuma clan and become difficult to maintain its techniques.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>当時日本の伝統文化を軽視する風潮があったことにくわえ、広大なスペースと大勢の競技者が必要な犬追物は、興行にも、その稽古にも多大な費用を必要としたからである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to the climate of making light of Japanese traditional culture at that time, Inuou-mono required a huge space and tremendous amounts of money to hold its event and its training and practice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because, in addition to the tendency of ignoring Japanese traditional culture at that time, Inuoumono which required a huge space and many participants needed also tremendous amounts of money to hold its event and its training and practice.</e>
<cmt>Because を挿入しました。climate of making light of→tendency of ignoring, Inuou-mono→Inuoumono,後半部分を必要に応じて修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because, in addition to the tendency of ignoring Japanese traditional culture at that time, Inuoumono which required a huge space and many participants needed also tremendous amounts of money to hold its event and its training and practice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>明治14年、島津忠義は明治天皇の前で犬追物の天覧を行ったが、これが史上最後の犬追物興行となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1881, Tadayoshi SHIMAZU held an Inuou-mono event with the Emperor Meiji in attendance and this was the last Inuou-mono event in Inuou-mono history.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1881, Tadayoshi SHIMAZU held an Inuoumono event with the Emperor Meiji in attendance and this was the last Inuoumono event in Inuoumono history.</e>
<cmt>Inuou-mono→Inuoumono と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1881, Tadayoshi SHIMAZU held an Inuoumono event with the Emperor Meiji in attendance and this was the last Inuoumono event in Inuoumono history.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>現在、島津家関係の史料（国宝「島津家文書」など）や小笠原流の資料により作法は伝わっているが、実演の方は動物愛護との絡みもあり、今後も復興されるみこみはない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today, the technique has been handed down in historical materials related to the Shimazu family (a national treasure &quot;the archives of the House of Shimazu&quot;) and the Ogasawara school, but its demonstration will not be restored in the future in relation to animal welfare.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, the manner has been handed down in the historical materials related to the Shimazu family (a national treasure &apos;the archives of the House of Shimazu&apos;) and the Ogasawara school, but the demonstration will not be restored in the future due to animal welfare.</e>
<cmt>technique→manner,historical→the historical,its→the,in relation→due, クォーツを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, the manner has been handed down in the historical materials related to the Shimazu family (a national treasure &apos;the archives of the House of Shimazu&apos;) and the Ogasawara school, but the demonstration will not be restored in the future due to animal welfare.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 竹速(id:136689), 福太郎(id:132415), Point136(id:211299), こぶまき(id:38278), Kaba(id:17904), ブレイズマン(id:183852), 堀五郎右衛門(id:84263), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>