<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>風呂吹き大根</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furofuki Daikon</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furofuki Daikon</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furofuki Daikon</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>風呂吹き大根（ふろふきだいこん）は、ダイコンを柔らかくゆで、練り味噌などをつけて食べる料理。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furofuki daikon is simmered Daikon radish, which is often served with Miso sauce.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furofuki daikon is simmered Daikon radish, which is often served with Miso sauce.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furofuki daikon is simmered Japanese radish, which is often served with Miso sauce.</e>
<cmt>Japanese radishに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>カブ、トウガンなどで作られることもあり、その際は単に風呂吹きと呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This simmered dish is called as merely Furofuki when another vegetable such as turnip or wax gourd is used instead of radish.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This simmered dish is called as merely Furofuki when another vegetable such as turnip or wax gourd is used instead of radish.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This simmered dish is called as merely Furofuki when another vegetable such as turnip or wax gourd is used instead of radish.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>名前の由来</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Origin of the name</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Origin of the name</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Origin of the name</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>名前の由来には諸説ある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are several views on the origin of the name.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are several views on the origin of the name.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are several views on the origin of the name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>一説によると、漆器職人が冬になると漆の乾きが悪くて困っていたところ、ある僧から風呂（漆器の貯蔵室のこと）に大根のゆで汁を吹き込み、そこで乾かすとよいと教えられ、その通りにするとうまくいった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to one of them, when an Urushi-ware craftsman tried to shorten the time period required to dry urushi-ware in winter time, he was advised by a Buddhist monk to dry urushi-ware in Furo (store room for urushi-ware) filled with water vapor of boiling water used to simmer radish, and succeeded in it by following the advice..</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to one of them, when an Urushi-ware craftsman tried to shorten the time period required to dry urushi-ware in winter time, he was advised by a Buddhist monk to dry urushi-ware in Furo (store room for urushi-ware) filled with water vapor from boiling water used to simmer radish, and succeeded in it by following this advice..</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to one of them, when an Urushi-ware (Japanese lacquerware) craftsman tried to shorten the time period required to dry urushi-ware in winter time, he was advised by a Buddhist monk to dry urushi-ware in Furo (store room for urushi-ware) filled with water vapor from boiling water used to simmer Japanese radish, and succeeded in it by following this advice.</e>
<cmt>Japanese radishに訂正しました。不要なピリオドを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>この時、大量のゆで汁を取るため、ゆでた大根も大量に余ったので近所に配った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A large amount of simmered radish which were produced to generate the large amount of water vapor was then distributed to neighbors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A large amount of simmered radish which was produced to generate a large amount of water vapor was then distributed to neighbors.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A large amount of simmered Japanese radish which was produced to generate a large amount of water vapor was then distributed to neighbors.</e>
<cmt>Japanese radishに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>すると、これがおいしいと評判になり、風呂にゆで汁を吹き込んだ残りの大根であることから、「風呂吹き大根」の名前が生まれた、というもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the neighbors found the simmered radish delicious and the simmered radish was named as &quot;Furofuki daikon&quot; after its associated process in which the water vapor of the boiling water used to simmer radish was blown into the Furo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the neighbors found the simmered radish delicious and the simmered radish was named as &quot;Furofuki daikon&quot; after its associated process in which the water vapor of the boiling water used to simmer radish was blown into the Furo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the neighbors found the simmered Japanese radish delicious and the simmered Japanese radish was named as &apos;Furofuki daikon&apos; after its associated process in which the water vapor of the boiling water used to simmer Japanese radish was blown into the Furo.</e>
<cmt>Japanese radishに訂正しました。原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>ただし「風呂」とは本来、サウナ風呂のことを指し、蒸気を満たした「室（むろ）」が語源であることを考えると、上の説は前後が逆転している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, because Furo is originally a term used to refer to a sauna bath and its original form was &quot;Muro&quot;, which is a space filled with water vapor, the relationship between the cause and the result seems to have been reversed in this view.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, because Furo is originally a term used to refer to a sauna bath and its original form was &quot;Muro&quot;, which is a space filled with water vapor, the relationship between the cause and the result seems to have been reversed in this view.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, because &apos;Furo&apos; is originally a term used to refer to a sauna bath and its original form was &apos;Muro,&apos; which is a space filled with water vapor, the relationship between the cause and the result seems to have been reversed in this view.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>もともと漆器の乾燥室である風呂に湿気を与えるために沸かす湯が勿体ないため、大根を茹でるのに使った――という説のほうが信憑性は高い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another view, which claims that boiling water used to provide the furo (drying room for urushi-ware) with moisture was utilized to simmer radish for energy saving, is more realistic.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another view, which claims that boiling water used to provide the furo (drying room for urushi-ware) with moisture was utilized to simmer radish for energy saving, is more realistic.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another view, which claims that boiling water used to provide the furo (drying room for urushi-ware) with moisture was utilized to simmer Japanese radish for energy saving, is more realistic.</e>
<cmt>Japanese radishに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>作り方</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Recipe</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Recipe</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Recipe</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="9">
<j>大根は厚さ４㎝ほどに切って皮を剥き、面取りをする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cut radish into 4 cm thick rounds, peel them, and peel a very thin strip from edges of each slice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cut radish into 4 cm thick rounds, peel them, and peel a very thin strip from the edges of each slice.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cut Japanese radish into 4 cm thick rounds, peel them, and peel a very thin strip from the edges of each slice.</e>
<cmt>Japanese radishに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>その後、米の研ぎ汁（なければひと握りの米粒）と一緒に下ゆでをしておくと、きれいな白色に仕上げることができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, in order to make the finished color white, cover them with rice rising water (or water with a handful of rice) and cook.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, in order to make the finished color white, cover them with rice water washings (or water with a handful of rice) and cook.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, in order to make the finished color white, cover them with rice water washings (or water with a handful of rice) and cook.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="11">
<j>鍋の底にコンブを敷き、その上に大根を乗せてたっぷりの水を注ぎ、大根が柔らかくなるまでゆっくり煮る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the bottom of a saucepan, place kombu (kelp) first and then the cooked radish, and simmer them with sufficient water until the radish become tender.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the bottom of a saucepan, place kombu (kelp) first and then the cooked radish, and simmer them with sufficient water until the radish becomes tender.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the bottom of a saucepan, place kombu (kelp) first and then the cooked Japanese radish, and simmer them with sufficient water until the radish becomes tender.</e>
<cmt>Japanese radishに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>よく煮えた大根に、用意しておいた味噌だれなどをつけて食べる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The well-cooked radish is served with separately prepared Miso sauce</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The well-cooked radish is served with separately prepared Miso sauce</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The well-cooked Japanese radish is served with separately prepared Miso sauce</e>
<cmt>Japanese radishに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>残った昆布や出し汁は、そのまま食したり他の料理に転用してもよい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The remaining kombu and soup can be taken as-is or can also be used for other foods.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The remaining kombu and soup can be taken as-is or can also be used for other foods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The remaining kombu and soup can be taken as-is or can also be used for other foods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Sum(id:10953), Point136(id:211299), Babi Hijau(id:40709), 竹麦魚(id:11012), Corwin(id:973), マクガイア(id:33346), 無花果(id:117005), 死郎(id:1683), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>