<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>裸祭り</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The naked festival</e>
<cmt>用語集にはthe naked festival (a Japanese festival in which the men go naked except for fundoshi loincloths)とありましたが、ここでは次の文章が()内にあたる説明になっているため、()内の内容は削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The naked festival</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The naked festival</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>裸祭り（はだかまつり）とは、参加者が裸体で参加する祭である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The naked festival is a Japanese festival in which the participants go naked.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The naked festival is a Japanese festival in which the participants go naked.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The naked festival is a Japanese festival in which the participants go naked.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Overview</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>Overview→Summary と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="3">
<j>裸祭とは五穀豊穣を願う祭として成人男性が裸体で競い合う祭とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The naked festival is regarded as a festival to wish for the productiveness of grain in which adult men go naked and compete with each other.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The naked festival is regarded as a festival to wish for the productiveness of grain in which adult men go naked and compete with each other.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The naked festival is regarded as a festival to wish for the productiveness of grain in which adult men go naked and compete with each other.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="4">
<j>農機具などが近代化される前の日本の農耕社会においては、強い働き手となる逞しい男性の存在が農家に最も求められる最重要課題であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the agrarian society in Japan where farming equipment had not been modernized, it was the most necessary and important issue for farmer&apos;s families to have a strong and tough man who worked hard.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the agrarian society in Japan where farming equipment had not been modernized, it was the most necessary and important issue for farmer&apos;s families to have strong and tough men who worked hard.</e>
<cmt>a strong and tough man→strong and tough men と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the agrarian society in Japan where farming equipment had not been modernized, it was the most necessary and important issue for farmer&apos;s families to have strong and tough men who worked hard.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>家督の維持、子孫の繁栄には強く逞しい男性の存在が欠かせなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order to maintain the family estate and family prosperity, strong and tough men were imperative.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to maintain the family estate and family prosperity, strong and tough men were imperative.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to maintain the family estate and family prosperity, strong and tough men were imperative.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>裸祭を通じて、男性は裸体を村の長老や女性に披露することで、結婚相手となる嫁や自家への入婿を探す男女の出会いの場として、裸祭は村の行事では最重要の位置付けとされていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The festival was regarded as the most important event in the village because the event in which men showed their naked body to the patriarch and women in the village turned into a meeting place for men looking for their future wives and for the parents of young women looking for irimuko (man who is adopted as the husband for a daughter).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The festival was regarded as the most important event in the village, because the event in which men showed their naked body to the patriarch and women in the village turned into a meeting place for men looking for their future wives and for the parents of young women looking for irimuko (man who is adopted as the husband for a daughter).</e>
<cmt>カンマを挿入しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The festival was regarded as the most important event in the village, because the event in which men showed their naked body to the patriarch and women in the village turned into a meeting place for men looking for their future wives and for the parents of young women looking for irimuko (man who is adopted as the husband for a daughter).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>特に、家督を継げない次男、三男にとっては入り婿先に招かれる重要な機会であるだけに、自己の逞しさを演出する唯一の場であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially for the second and third sons in a family who could not succeed the family estate, it was an important chance to be invited by the families who were looking for irimuko, and was also the only chance to show their strength.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Especially for the second and third sons in a family who could not succeed the family estate, it was an important chance to be invited by the families who were looking for irimuko, and was also the only chance to show their sturdiness.</e>
<cmt>strength→sturdiness と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Especially for the second and third sons in a family who could not succeed the family estate, it was an important chance to be invited by the families who were looking for irimuko, and was also the only chance to show their sturdiness.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>また、男手を失った後家にとっても再婚相手を探す場でもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was also a place for widows to meet new husbands.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was also a place for widows to look for new husbands.</e>
<cmt>meet→look for と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was also a place for widows to look for new husbands.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="9">
<j>裸祭に神木の取り合い等の闘争が多いのも、闘争能力の高さが男性の強さや生殖能力を象徴し、農家でより強い働き手であることを示すものでもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The naked festival often involves battles such as battles over a sacred tree because the ability to win in such a battle symbolizes the strength and the reproductive capability and such ability suggests that the man can make a better worker in a farmer&apos;s family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The naked festival often involves battles such as a battle over a sacred tree and so on, because the ability to win in such a battle symbolizes the strength and the reproductive capability and such ability suggests that the man can make a better worker in a farmer&apos;s family.</e>
<cmt>スペースの修正をしました。battles over a sacred tree→a battle over a sacred tree and so on と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The naked festival often involves battles such as a battle over a sacred tree and so on, because the ability to win in such a battle symbolizes the strength and the reproductive capability and such ability suggests that the man can make a better worker in a farmer&apos;s family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>それだけに、伝統的に裸祭の参加は成人男性に限定されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, the participants in the naked festival were limited to adult men.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the participants in the naked festival were limited to adult men.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the participants in the naked festival were limited to adult men.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="11">
<j>裸祭は禊（水行）の後、お堂の内外で神木、玉、等、その祭の象徴を奪い合う会陽を始めとして休耕となる真冬を中心に開催されるものが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the naked festivals, an event called eyo is held where men fight over the symbol of the festival, such as a sacred tree or a ball in or outside the main hall of the shrine.</e>
<cmt>原文では「～をはじめとして」とありますが、この表現は日本語として少し不自然に思います。（原文を２文に分けたため、さらにその不自然さが際立ってしまっている気がします。）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the naked festivals, an event called eyo is held where men fight over the symbol of the festival, such as a sacred tree or a ball in or outside the main hall of the shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The naked festival, which includes an event in which men who have performed misogi (a cold-water purification ceremony) fight over the symbol of the festival (such as a sacred tree or a ball) in or outside the main hall of the shrine, is often held around midwinter time when the farmland lies idle.</e>
<cmt>原文・訳文を一文に戻して訳出</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>これは冬場の娯楽の少ない農耕社会で鬱積した気分を解消させることを目的としていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since there is not much entertainment in winter in agrarian society, the festival was aimed for releasing the pent-up feelings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since there is not much entertainment in winter in agrarian society, the festival was aimed for releasing the pent-up feelings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since there is not much entertainment in winter in agrarian society, the festival was aimed for releasing the pent-up feelings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>男性の闘争本能を呼び起こさせることで、地域社会の若者層の暴走を抑えることであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By evoking men&apos;s combative instinct, the festival could keep the young people from burning up.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By evoking men&apos;s combative instinct, the festival could keep the young people from rampages.</e>
<cmt>burning up→rampages と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By evoking men&apos;s combative instinct, the festival could keep the young people from rampages.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>厳しい冬の寒さの中を裸で立ち向かわせることで、逞しい男らしさを演出させることであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also by letting men fight against each other in the severe cold weather, they could present themselves as strong.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also by letting men fight against each other naked in the severe cold weather, they could present themselves as strong.</e>
<cmt>”裸で”という部分を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also by letting men fight against each other naked in the severe cold weather, they could present themselves as strong.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="15">
<j>また、真夏に、漁師を主体とした神輿を担ぐ祭、春から秋に掛けて神輿や山車を担いだり曳いたりする祭りもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are also festivals held in summer in which fishermen carry a portable shrine, or held around spring through fall in which men carry or pull a portable shrine or a festival car (float).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are also festivals held in summer such as fishermen carry a portable shrine, or festivals held around spring through fall such as men carry or pull a portable shrine or a festival car (float).</e>
<cmt>in which→such as,festivals を挿入しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are also festivals held in summer such as fishermen carry a portable shrine, or festivals held around spring through fall such as men carry or pull a portable shrine or a festival car (float).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>なお、神社によっては岡山県の鏡野町（旧上齋原村）の上齋原村神社などは裸祭を廃止し、女相撲に変えたところもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some shrines such as the Kamisaibara-jinja Shrine in Kagamino-cho (former Kamisaibarason Village), Okayama Prefecture, abolished the traditional naked festival and switched to female sumo wrestling.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some shrines such as Kamisaibara-jinja Shrine in Kagamino-cho (former Kamisaibarason Village), Okayama Prefecture, abolished the traditional naked festival and switched to female sumo wrestling.</e>
<cmt>the を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some shrines such as Kamisaibara-jinja Shrine in Kagamino-cho (former Kamisaibarason Village), Okayama Prefecture, abolished the traditional naked festival and switched to female sumo wrestling.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Nekomarukun(id:186899), もね～るmoner(id:28477), AlleborgoBot(id:119729), Izayohi(id:13095), Catnemesis(id:154045), Julius Caesar(id:181760), 天然ガス(id:98149), Ikazuchi(id:92573), ワイドビューなんこ(id:176938), Morigen(id:22906), かげろん(id:202674), Hide-sp(id:145562), TAMA(id:25299), Phronimos(id:293969), 甲武讃(id:98731), ぼったる(id:155519), Rusk(id:9895), 超閑散(id:235733), VolkovBot(id:105371), ゴリラッパ(id:38264), A. J. Kuonji(id:68661), KAMUI(id:9330), Penes(id:186308), Knua(id:66861), Point136(id:211299), Masabb(id:71275), K. Takeda(id:119013), 北極熊(id:182750), ヘロン(id:96518), Saaki(id:43602), Mikomaid(id:56139), 弥(id:61590), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>