<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>だし巻き卵</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dashi-maki Tamago (Rolled Omelet)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dashi-maki Tamago</e>
<cmt>タイトルなので補足を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dashi-maki Tamago</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>だし巻き卵（だしまきたまご）は、卵焼きの一種で、溶き卵にだし汁を混ぜて焼き固める料理である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dashi-maki Tamago is a kind of an omelet (a Japanese style omelet) and a dish of baked beaten eggs mixed with dashi broth soup.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dashi-maki Tamago is a kind of an omelet (a Japanese style omelet) and a dish of fried beaten eggs mixed with dashi broth soup.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dashi-maki Tamago is a kind of an omelet (a Japanese style omelet) and a dish of fried beaten eggs mixed with dashi broth soup.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>単にだし巻きとも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is sometimes simply called Dashi-maki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is sometimes simply called Dashi-maki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is sometimes simply called Dashi-maki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>作り方は卵は黄身・白身を混ぜ（黄身は割りほぐして白身とよく混ぜ合わせる）、それにダシを加え、油を敷いたフライパンなどを使って焼く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">How to make Dashi-maki Tamago: mix egg yolk and white (beat egg yolk lightly with egg white), add dashi broth soup, and bake in an oily pan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">How to make Dashi-maki Tamago: Mix egg yolk and white (beat egg yolk lightly with egg white), add dashi broth soup, and fry in an oily pan.</e>
<cmt>表記、用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">How to make Dashi-maki Tamago: Mix egg yolk and white (beat egg yolk lightly with egg white), add dashi broth soup, and fry in an oily pan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>焼く際には「巻き焼き鍋」と呼ばれる銅製の四角い鍋を使うことが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For baking, a box-shaped copper pan called makiyakinabe (a square pan made from copper) is often used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For frying, a box-shaped copper pan called &apos;makiyakinabe&apos; (a square pan made from copper) is often used.</e>
<cmt>表記、用語を変えました。NR: The meaning of makiyakinabe is described twice here. I would delete the information in parentheses (i.e. &quot;a square pan made from copper&quot;).</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For frying, a box-shaped copper pan called &apos;makiyakinabe&apos; is often used.</e>
<cmt>括弧内は重複表現なので、削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>関東では関西よりも幾分横幅が大きく、縦幅が小さい巻き焼き鍋を使う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Kanto region, a makiyakinabe that is a little wider in width and shorter in length than the one in the Kansai region is used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The makiyakinabe used in the Kanto region is slightly wider in width and shorter in length than that in the Kansai region.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The makiyakinabe used in the Kanto region is slightly wider in width and shorter in length than that in the Kansai region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>また、より簡単に巻ける底が波形になったフッ素樹脂加工された鍋なども市販されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Pans such as resin-treatment with Fluorocarbon Polymer with a corrugated bottom are marketed and you can roll eggs easily with these pans.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other types of pans are also available, such as a fluororesin-coated pan with a corrugated bottom that enables you to roll up the egg more easily.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせて訳文を修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other types of pans are also available, such as a fluororesin-coated pan with a corrugated bottom that enables you to roll up the egg more easily.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>厚焼き卵もだし巻き卵とほぼ同じ作り方をする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Atsuyakitamago (a thick omelet) and Dashi-maki Tamago are made almost in the same way.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Atsuyaki Tamago (a thick omelet) and Dashi-maki Tamago are made almost in the same way.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Atsuyaki Tamago (a thick omelet) and Dashi-maki Tamago are made almost in the same way.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>だし巻き卵との違いは必ずしも明確ではないが、1つには厚焼き卵は砂糖で甘味を強めに付けるのに対し、だし巻き卵はみりんのみで甘さを抑えるということがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Differences from Dashi-maki Tamago are not always clear but one difference is that Atsuyakitamago is sweetened up with sugar while Dashi-maki Tamago cuts down on the sweetness using only mirin (sweet cooking rice wine).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Differences from Dashi-maki Tamago are not always clear, however, Atsuyaki Tamago is sweeter adding sugar than Dashi-maki Tamago only adding mirin (sweet cooking rice wine).</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Differences from Dashi-maki Tamago are not always clear, however, Atsuyaki Tamago is sweeter adding sugar than Dashi-maki Tamago only adding mirin (sweet cooking rice wine).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>関東地方では厚焼き卵が、関西地方ではだし巻き卵が主流となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Atsuyakitamago is more preferred in the Kanto region and Dashi-maki Tamago in the Kansai region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Atsuyaki Tamago is more preferred in the Kanto region and Dashi-maki Tamago in the Kansai region.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Atsuyaki Tamago is more preferred in the Kanto region and Dashi-maki Tamago in the Kansai region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Alljal(id:46858), Kim-wilson(id:34721), 穴子(id:148357), 1029man(id:93235), Sheepech(id:111676), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>