<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>皿屋敷</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sarayashiki (The Haunted Plate House)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sarayashiki (The Haunted Plate House)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sarayashiki (The Haunted Plate House)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>皿屋敷（さらやしき）は、お菊という女性の亡霊が皿を数えることで有名な怪談話の総称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sarayashiki is a general term for Kaidan telling (Ghost Stories telling) famous for a woman&apos;s ghost named Okiku counting plates.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sarayashiki is a general term for Kaidan telling (Ghost Stories telling) famous for a woman&apos;s ghost named Okiku counting plates.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sarayashiki is a general term for Kaidan telling (Ghost Stories telling) famous for a woman&apos;s ghost named Okiku counting plates.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>播磨国（現・兵庫県）姫路市が舞台の『播州皿屋敷』（ばんしゅう-）、江戸番町が舞台の『番町皿屋敷』（ばんちょう-、ばんまち-）が広く知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Banshu Sarayashiki&quot; (Sarayashiki in Banshu) whose stage is Himeji City of Harima Province (presently Hyogo Prefecture) and &quot;Bancho (or Banmachi) Sarayashiki&quot; whose stage is Bancho, Edo, are widely known.</e>
<cmt>「播磨国（現・兵庫県）姫路市」という書き方は変ではないでしょうか。「播磨国」（明治以前）と「姫路市」（現代）という呼び名が両立しないという気がしますが、原文どおりに訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Banshu Sarayashiki&quot; (Sarayashiki in Banshu) whose stage is Himeji City of Harima Province (presently Hyogo Prefecture) and &quot;Bancho (or Banmachi) Sarayashiki&quot; whose stage is Bancho, Edo, are widely known.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Banshu Sarayashiki&quot; (Sarayashiki in Banshu) whose stage is Himeji City of Harima Province (presently Hyogo Prefecture) and &quot;Bancho (or Banmachi) Sarayashiki&quot; whose stage is Bancho, Edo, are widely known.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>他に群馬県甘楽郡の2町1村・滋賀県彦根市・兵庫県尼崎市・島根県松江市・高知県幡多郡の2町1村・福岡県嘉麻市・長崎県五島列島の福江島など日本各地において類似の話が残っており、それらが相互に影響しあいながら成立したものであろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Similar stories also remain all over Japan: In two towns and one village of Kanra-gun, Gunma Prefecture; Hikone City, Shiga Prefecture; Amagasaki City, Hyogo Prefecture; Matsue City, Shimane Prefecture; two towns and one village of Hata County, Kochi Prefecture; Kama City, Fukuoka Prefecture; the Island of Fukue, Goto-retto Island, Nagasaki Prefecture: Those would come into the world, having a mutual influence on each other.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Similar stories also remain all over Japan: In two towns and one village of Kanra-gun, Gunma Prefecture; Hikone City, Shiga Prefecture; Amagasaki City, Hyogo Prefecture; Matsue City, Shimane Prefecture; two towns and one village of Hata County, Kochi Prefecture; Kama City, Fukuoka Prefecture; the Island of Fukue, Goto-retto Island, Nagasaki Prefecture: and it is assumed that those stories were made with a mutual influence on each other.</e>
<cmt>最後の部分の意味がわかりにくいので、修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Similar stories also remain all over Japan: In two towns and one village of Kanra-gun, Gunma Prefecture; Hikone City, Shiga Prefecture; Amagasaki City, Hyogo Prefecture; Matsue City, Shimane Prefecture; two towns and one village of Hata County, Kochi Prefecture; Kama City, Fukuoka Prefecture; the Island of Fukue, Goto-retto Island, Nagasaki Prefecture: and it is assumed that those stories were made with a mutual influence on each other.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>井戸の中からお菊の亡霊が「お皿が一枚……二枚……」「九枚……一枚足りない……」と恨めしげな声で語る、というのが、怪談やお化け屋敷などで登場するときのパターンである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Out of the well, Okiku&apos;s ghost narrates in a reproachful voice, &apos;One plate, two plate …&apos; &apos;Nine plate, … one is missing …&apos;; it is a typical way when she appears in Kaidan or a haunted house, and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Out of the well, Okiku&apos;s ghost narrates in a reproachful voice, &apos;One plate, two plate …&apos; &apos;Nine plate, … one is missing …&apos;; it is a typical way when she appears in Kaidan or a haunted house, and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Out of the well, Okiku&apos;s ghost narrates in a reproachful voice, &apos;One plate, two plate …&apos; &apos;Nine plate, … one is missing …&apos;; it is a typical way when she appears in Kaidan or a haunted house, and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="5">
<j>江戸時代にはこれらの話が浄瑠璃・歌舞伎の題材とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Edo period these stories were taken up as a theme of Joruri (a dramatic narrative chanted to a samisen accompaniment) and Kabuki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Edo period these stories were taken up as a theme of Joruri (a dramatic narrative chanted to a samisen accompaniment) and Kabuki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Edo period these stories were taken up as a theme of Joruri (a dramatic narrative chanted to a samisen accompaniment) and Kabuki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>播州皿屋敷</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Banshu Sarayashiki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Banshu Sarayashiki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Banshu Sarayashiki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>姫路市の十二所神社 (姫路市)に伝わる、姫路城にまつわる「播州皿屋敷実録」が原型とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Banshu-Sarayashiki Jitsuroku (The Fact of The Haunted Plate House in Banshu) which has been handed down to Junisho-jinja Shrine (Himeji City) of Himeji City and is related to Himeji-jo Castle is said to be its prototype.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The prototype of Sarayashiki is Banshu-Sarayashiki Jitsuroku (The Fact of The Haunted Plate House in Banshu) which has been handed down to Junisho-jinja Shrine (Himeji City) of Himeji City and is related to Himeji-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>主部が長すぎて読みにくので、順番を逆にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The prototype of Sarayashiki is Banshu-Sarayashiki Jitsuroku (The Fact of The Haunted Plate House in Banshu) which has been handed down to Junisho-jinja Shrine (Himeji City) of Himeji City and is related to Himeji-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>永正年間（つまり現在の姫路城が出来る前）、姫路城第9代城主小寺則職の家臣青山鉄山が主家乗っ取りを企てていたが、これを衣笠元信なる忠臣が察知、自分の妾だったお菊という女性を鉄山の家の女中にし鉄山の計略を探らせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Eisho era (that is, before the present Himeji-jo Castle was built), Tetsuzan AOYAMA, a vassal of Norimoto KODERA, the ninth lord of Himeji-jo Castle, was plotting to take over his master&apos;s castle, which a loyal subject named Motonobu KINUGASA perceived, and sent his mistress Okiku into Tetsuzan&apos;s house as a maid to spy on his plot.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Eisho era (that is, before the present Himeji-jo Castle was built), Tetsuzan AOYAMA, a vassal of Norimoto KODERA, the ninth lord of Himeji-jo Castle, was plotting to take over his master&apos;s castle, however, a loyal subject named Motonobu KINUGASA sensed it and sent his mistress Okiku into Tetsuzan&apos;s house as a maid to spy on his plot.</e>
<cmt>関係代名詞「which」以降が読みにくいので、「which」を「however」に変更しました。「which」を残して、「which was perceived by a loyal subject…」とするべきか迷いましたが、その次の文章をつなげやすい「however」にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Eisho era (that is, before the present Himeji-jo Castle was built), Tetsuzan AOYAMA, a vassal of Norimoto KODERA, the ninth lord of Himeji-jo Castle, was plotting to take over his master&apos;s castle, however, a loyal subject named Motonobu KINUGASA sensed it and sent his mistress Okiku into Tetsuzan&apos;s house as a maid to spy on his plot.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>そして、元信は、青山が増位山 (兵庫県)の花見の席で則職を毒殺しようとしていることを突き止め、その花見の席に切り込み、則職を救出、家島に隠れさせ再起を図る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then Motoharu found out that Aoyama was going to kill Norimoto by poisoning on the occasion of cherry-blossom viewing at Mt. Masuiyama (Hyogo Prefecture), so he stormed into the viewing and rescued Norimoto, to hide him in Ieshima Island for attempting a comeback.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then Motoharu found out that Aoyama was going to kill Norimoto by poisoning him during cherry-blossom viewing at Mt. Masuiyama (Hyogo Prefecture), so he stormed into the viewing, rescued Norimoto and hid him in Ieshima Island for attempting a comeback.</e>
<cmt>最後の部分の「to」を「and」 に変更。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then Motoharu found out that Aoyama was going to kill Norimoto by poisoning him during cherry-blossom viewing at Mt. Masuiyama (Hyogo Prefecture), so he stormed into the viewing, rescued Norimoto and hid him in Ieshima Island for attempting a comeback.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>乗っ取りに失敗した鉄山は家中に密告者がいたとにらみ、家来の町坪弾四朗に調査するように命令した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tetsuzan, failing in the takeover, suspected that there had been a betrayer in his house and ordered his vassal Danshiro CHONOTSUBO to inquire into it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tetsuzan, failing in the takeover, suspected that there had been a betrayer in his house and ordered his vassal Danshiro CHONOTSUBO to inquire into it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tetsuzan, failing in the takeover, suspected that there had been a betrayer in his house and ordered his vassal Danshiro CHONOTSUBO to inquire into it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>程なく弾四朗は密告者がお菊であったことを突き止めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soon Danshiro found out that the betrayer was Okiku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soon Danshiro found out that the betrayer was Okiku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soon Danshiro found out that the betrayer was Okiku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>そこで、以前からお菊のことが好きだった弾四朗は妾になれと言い寄った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then Danshiro, as he had been in love with Okiku, approached her to get her as his mistress.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then Danshiro, as he had been in love with Okiku, approached her to get her as his mistress.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then Danshiro, as he had been in love with Okiku, approached her to get her as his mistress.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>しかし、お菊は拒否した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Okiku refused him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Okiku refused him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Okiku refused him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>その態度に立腹した弾四朗は、お菊が管理を委任されていた10枚揃えないと意味のない家宝の毒消しの皿のうちの一枚をわざと隠してお菊にその因縁を付け、とうとう責め殺して古井戸に死体を捨てた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Danshiro, offended at her attitude, hid one of the ten poison-neutralizing plates of the family treasure which were committed to Okiku&apos;s management and worthless unless all the plates were completely reserved, on purpose to blame her to death and dumped her body in an old unused well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Danshiro, offended at her attitude, hid one of the ten poison-neutralizing plates of the family treasure which were committed to Okiku&apos;s management and worthless unless all the plates were completely reserved, on purpose to blame her, and he finally strangled her to death and dumped her body in an old unused well.</e>
<cmt>「とうとう責め殺して」の訳が抜けていたので、追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Danshiro, offended at her attitude, hid one of the ten poison-neutralizing plates of the family treasure which were committed to Okiku&apos;s management and worthless unless all the plates were completely reserved, on purpose to blame her, and he finally strangled her to death and dumped her body in an old unused well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="14">
<j>以来その井戸から夜な夜なお菊が皿を数える声が聞こえたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It says that since then Okiku&apos;s voice counting plates was heard from the well night after night.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It says that since then, Okiku&apos;s voice counting plates was heard from the well night after night.</e>
<cmt>カンマを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It says that since then, Okiku&apos;s voice counting plates was heard from the well night after night.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>やがて衣笠元信達小寺の家臣によって鉄山一味は討たれ、姫路城は無事、則職の元に返った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before long Tetsuzan and his followers were destroyed by Odera&apos;s vassals such as Motonobu KINUGASA, and Himeji-jo Castle was safely returned to Norimoto&apos;s hand.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before long, Tetsuzan and his followers were destroyed by Odera&apos;s vassals such as Motonobu KINUGASA, and Himeji-jo Castle was safely returned to Norimoto.</e>
<cmt>カンマを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before long, Tetsuzan and his followers were destroyed by Odera&apos;s vassals such as Motonobu KINUGASA, and Himeji-jo Castle was safely returned to Norimoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>その後、則職はお菊の事を聞き､その死を哀れみ､十二所神社の中にお菊を「お菊大明神」として祀ったと言い伝えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has been said that hearing about Okiku, Norimoto felt sorry for her death and enshrined her as &apos;Okiku-Daimyojin Shrine&apos; in Junisho-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has been said that hearing about Okiku, Norimoto felt sorry for her death and enshrined her as &apos;Okiku-Daimyojin Shrine&apos; in Junisho-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has been said that hearing about Okiku, Norimoto felt sorry for her death and enshrined her as &apos;Okiku-Daimyojin Shrine&apos; in Junisho-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>その後300年程経って城下に奇妙な形をした虫が大量発生し、人々はお菊が虫になって帰ってきたと言っていたといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also it is said that about three hundred years since then, when a plague of insects with a strange shape occurred in the castle town, people said that Okiku returned in the form of a insect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also said that about three hundred years later, a plague of strange-shaped insects appeared in the castle town, and people said that Okiku returned in the form of the insects.</e>
<cmt>読みにくいので、「since then, when」を「later」に変更。「in the form of a insect」を「in the form of the insects」に変更。「in the form of a insect」を使用する場合は、「a」を「an」に修正する必要あり。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also said that about three hundred years later, a plague of strange-shaped insects appeared in the castle town, and people said that Okiku returned in the form of the insects.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="18">
<j>小寺・青山の対立という史実を元に脚色された物と考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This has been considered to be a dramatized version based on a historical fact of antagonism between Odera and Aoyama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This story is considered to be a dramatized version of a historical fact, the antagonism between Odera and Aoyama.</e>
<cmt>読みにくいので、前置詞などを変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This story is considered to be a dramatized version of a historical fact, the antagonism between Odera and Aoyama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="19">
<j>姫路城に「お菊井戸」が現存する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Himeji-jo Castle &apos;Okiku-ido&apos; (Okiku&apos;s well) still exists.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Himeji-jo Castle, &apos;Okiku-ido&apos; (Okiku&apos;s well) still remains.</e>
<cmt>一部変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Himeji-jo Castle, &apos;Okiku-ido&apos; (Okiku&apos;s well) still remains.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="20">
<j>バリエーションとして以下のような物もある：</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are also following versions as variations :</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following are the other variations of this story:</e>
<cmt>一部変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following are the other variations of this story:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>お菊は衣笠元信なる忠臣の妾で、鉄山を討ったのは衣笠であったというもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Okiku was a mistress of a loyal subject Motonobu KINUGASA, and it was Kinugasa that destroyed Tetsuzan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Okiku was a mistress of a loyal subject, Motonobu KINUGASA, and it was Kinugasa who destroyed Tetsuzan.</e>
<cmt>カンマを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Okiku was a mistress of a loyal subject, Motonobu KINUGASA, and it was Kinugasa who destroyed Tetsuzan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="22">
<j>お菊は船瀬三平なる忠臣の妻で、お菊の呪いが鉄山を滅ぼしたというもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Okiku was a wife of a loyal subject Sanpei FUNASE and Okiku&apos;s curses ruined Tetsuzan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Okiku was a wife of a loyal subject, Sanpei FUNASE and Okiku&apos;s curses ruined Tetsuzan.</e>
<cmt>カンマを追加しました。船瀬三平の妻が一人であれあば、「the wife of」に修正したほうがいいと思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Okiku was a wife of a loyal subject, Sanpei FUNASE and Okiku&apos;s curses ruined Tetsuzan.</e>
<cmt>a wife→the wife</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="23">
<j>お菊の最後の姿に似た「お菊虫」なる怪物によって鉄山が殺されたというもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tetsuzan was killed by a monster called &apos;Okiku Mushi&apos; (Okiku Insect) similar to Okiku&apos;s last figure.</e>
<cmt>用語集では「お菊虫」は&apos;Okiku-Mushi (worm in the shape of Okiku)&apos;となっていますが、本文中に「お菊の最後の姿に似た」という解説がありますので、ここでは単に&apos;Okiku Insect&apos;としました。前列で「虫」としてinsectを使いましたので、用語を統一しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tetsuzan was killed by a monster called &apos;Okiku Mushi&apos; (Okiku Insect) that looked like Okiku at the end of her life.</e>
<cmt>「similar to Okiku&apos;s last figure」では不自然な気がするので、「that looked like Okiku at the end of her life」に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tetsuzan was killed by a monster called &apos;Okiku Mushi&apos; (Okiku Insect) that looked like Okiku at the end of her life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="24">
<j>お菊虫の元になったのは1795年に大量発生したアゲハチョウの幼虫ではないかと考えられており、このことにちなんで姫路市の市蝶はジャコウアゲハである（姫路藩主池田氏の家紋は平家由来の揚羽蝶である）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">What originated Okiku Mushi is considered to be larvae of swallow-tailed butterflies of which a plague occurred in 1795, and this has brought Atrophaneura alcinous as the city butterfly of Himeji City (the crest of the Ikeda clan, the lord of Himeji Domain, is a swallow-tailed butterfly which dates back to the time of the Heike clans.).</e>
<cmt>「ジャコウアゲハ」は用語集ではAtrophaneura alcinousとなっていますが、学名なのでイタリックにしました。また研究社『新英和大辞典』ではByasa alcinousというようです。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The origin of Okiku Mushi is believed to be the larvae of swallow-tailed butterflies of which a plague occurred in 1795, and this brought Atrophaneura alcinous as the city butterfly of Himeji City (the crest of the Ikeda clan, the lord of Himeji Domain, is a swallow-tailed butterfly which dates back to the time of the Heike clans).</e>
<cmt>出だしを読みやすく修正しました。イタリックでの記載は必要ないと判断し、修正しました。重複ピリオド削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The origin of Okiku Mushi is believed to be the larvae of swallow-tailed butterflies of which a plague occurred in 1795, and this brought Atrophaneura alcinous as the city butterfly of Himeji City (the crest of the Ikeda clan, the lord of Himeji Domain, is a swallow-tailed butterfly which dates back to the time of the Heike clans).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>番町皿屋敷</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bancho Sarayashiki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bancho Sarayashiki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bancho Sarayashiki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="25">
<j>番町は牛込御門内番町（現在の千代田区飯田橋付近か?）とも、現在の千代田区一番町～六番町ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bancho refers to both Ushigome-Gomon 内番町 (presently near Idabashi, Chiyoda Ward?) and one bancho to six bancho of present Chiyoda Ward.</e>
<cmt>「牛込御門内番町」は用語集では&apos;Bancho in Ushigome-Gomon&apos; ですが、固有名詞ですので途中でinを使わず、&apos;Ushigome-Gomon 内番町&apos;としました。おそらくUchibanchoと思いますが確認がとれず、「読み方不明」です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bancho refers to both Ushigome-Gomon 内番町 (presently near Idabashi, Chiyoda Ward?) and one bancho to six bancho of present Chiyoda Ward.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bancho refers to both Ushigome-Gomon 内番町 (presently near Idabashi, Chiyoda Ward?) and one bancho to six bancho of present Chiyoda Ward.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>ただし後者は『東海道四谷怪談』の舞台とされる一帯の近くでもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The latter, however, is also near a zone regarded as a stage of &quot;Tokaido Yotsuya Kaidan&quot; (Tokaido Yotsuya Ghost Stories).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The latter, however, is also near an area regarded as a stage of &quot;Tokaido Yotsuya Kaidan&quot; (Tokaido Yotsuya Ghost Stories).</e>
<cmt>「zone」は合わない気がするので、「area」に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The latter, however, is also near an area regarded as a stage of &quot;Tokaido Yotsuya Kaidan&quot; (Tokaido Yotsuya Ghost Stories).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="27">
<j>お菊の奉公する主人は青山主膳。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A master who Okiku works for is Shuzen AOYAMA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A master who Okiku works for is Shuzen AOYAMA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A master who Okiku works for is Shuzen AOYAMA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>家宝の皿を割ってしまうか誰かに割られるかしたため、殺されて井戸に投げ込まれたか自ら井戸に飛び込んだか、というバリエーションがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are some variations: As she broke a plate of the family treasure or had the plate broken by someone, she was killed and thrown into a well, or jumped into a well herself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are some variations: As she broke a plate of the family treasure or had the plate broken by someone, she was killed and thrown into a well, or jumped into a well herself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are some variations: As she broke a plate of the family treasure or had the plate broken by someone, she was killed and thrown into a well, or jumped into a well herself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>主膳がお菊を責め立てる際にその指を一本切り落としたため、後に生まれた主膳の子には手の指が一本足りなかったともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also said that when Shuzen blamed Okiku, he cut off one of her fingers, for which Shuzen&apos;s child who was born later had one finger missing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also said that since Shuzen cut off one of Okiku&apos;s fingers when blaming her, his child, who was born later, had one finger missing.</e>
<cmt>「for which～」が読みにくい気がするので、「since」に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also said that since Shuzen cut off one of Okiku&apos;s fingers when blaming her, his child, who was born later, had one finger missing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="30">
<j>東京都内にはお菊の墓というものがいくつか見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">What is referred to Okiku&apos;s graveyards can be seen in some places in Tokyo Metropolis.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">What is referred to as Okiku&apos;s graveyards can be seen in some places in Tokyo Metropolis.</e>
<cmt>「referred to」の後ろに「as」を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">What is referred to as Okiku&apos;s graveyards can be seen in some places in Tokyo Metropolis.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>現在東海道本線平塚駅近く、明石町公園内にもお菊塚と刻まれた自然石の石碑がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is also a tombstone, made of natural stone and engraved as Okiku&apos;s Tumulus, in the Akashicho Square near present Hiratsuka Station of the JR Tokaido Main Line.</e>
<cmt>用語集では「お菊塚」は&apos;the tumulus of Okiku&apos;となっていますが、墓碑銘として彫られていると考えられますので、&apos;Okiku&apos;s Tumulus&apos;としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is also a tombstone, made of natural stone and engraved as Okiku&apos;s Tumulus, in the Akashicho Square near present Hiratsuka Station of the JR Tokaido Main Line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is also a tombstone, made of natural stone and engraved as Okiku&apos;s Tumulus, in the Akashicho Square near present Hiratsuka Station of the JR Tokaido Main Line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>元々ここに彼女の墓が有ったが、戦後近隣の晴雲寺内に移動したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They say that originally there used to be her graveyard here but it was moved to neighboring Seiun-ji Temple after World War II.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They say that originally there used to be her graveyard here but it was moved to neighboring Seiun-ji Temple after World War II.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They say that originally there used to be her graveyard here but it was moved to neighboring Seiun-ji Temple after World War II.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>尼崎のお菊伝説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The legend of Okiku in Amagasaki City</e>
<cmt>「尼崎」はAmagasaki Cityとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The legend of Okiku in Amagasaki City</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The legend of Okiku in Amagasaki City</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="33">
<j>青山播磨守の家臣・喜多玄蕃の屋敷に奉公していたお菊が、食事の中に針が混じっていたことを理由に折檻され井戸へ投げ込まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Okiku who worked in a residence of Genban KITA, a vassal of Aoyama Harima no Kami (the governor of Harima Province), was beaten and thrown into a well on the ground that a needle had been mixed in a meal.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Okiku who worked in a residence of Genban KITA, a vassal of Aoyama Harima no Kami (the governor of Harima Province), was beaten and thrown into a well on the ground that a needle had been mixed in a meal.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Okiku who worked in a residence of Genban KITA, a vassal of Aoyama Harima no Kami (the governor of Harima Province), was beaten and thrown into a well on the ground that a needle had been mixed in a meal.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>その後お菊の最後の姿に似た虫が大量に現れ、玄蕃の家を呪い滅ぼしたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that a large number of insects looking like Okiku&apos;s last figure appeared and cursed Genban&apos;s house to ruin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, a large number of insects that looked like Okiku at the end of her life appeared and cursed Genban&apos;s house to ruin.</e>
<cmt>「Okiku&apos;s last figure」を「Okiku at the end of her life」に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, a large number of insects that looked like Okiku at the end of her life appeared and cursed Genban&apos;s house to ruin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>岡本綺堂『番町皿屋敷』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Bancho Sarayashiki&quot; by Kido OKAMOTO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Bancho Sarayashiki&quot; by Kido OKAMOTO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Bancho Sarayashiki&quot; by Kido OKAMOTO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="35">
<j>1916年（大正5年）作の戯曲。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A drama written in 1916.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A drama written in 1916.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A drama written in 1916.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>怪談ではなく悲恋物語の形を取る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It takes a form of a tragic love story not a ghost story.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It takes a form of a tragic love story not a ghost story.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It takes a form of a tragic love story not a ghost story.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="37">
<j>旗本青山播磨と腰元は相思相愛の仲であったが身分の違いから叶わない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A hatamoto (direct retainers of the bakufu, which is a form of Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) Harima AOYAMA and a chamber maid are in love with each other, but they are hopeless due to a difference of their birth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A hatamoto (direct retainers of the bakufu, which is a form of Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) Harima AOYAMA and a chamber maid are in love with each other, but they cannot be together due to a difference of their status.</e>
<cmt>「身分の違いから叶わない」を「they cannot be together due to a difference of their status」に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A hatamoto (direct retainers of the bakufu, which is a form of Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) Harima AOYAMA and a chamber maid are in love with each other, but they cannot be together due to a difference of their status.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>やがて播磨に縁談が持ち込まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soon an offer of marriage is brought to Harima.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soon, an offer of marriage is brought to Harima.</e>
<cmt>カンマを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soon, an offer of marriage is brought to Harima.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>彼の愛情を試そうとしたお菊は青山家の家宝の皿を一枚割るが、播磨はお菊を不問に付す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Trying to test his love, Okiku breaks one of the plates of the family treasure of the Aoyama family, but Harima overlooks Okiku&apos;s fault.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Trying to test his love, Okiku breaks one of the plates of the family treasure of the Aoyama family, but Harima overlooks Okiku&apos;s fault.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Trying to test his love, Okiku breaks one of the plates of the family treasure of the Aoyama family, but Harima overlooks Okiku&apos;s fault.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>ところが周りの者が、お菊がわざと皿を割った瞬間を目撃していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, someone surrounding her witnesses the moment Okiku breaks the plate on purpose.</e>
<cmt>「目撃していた」とありますが、劇のあらすじですので、現在形で統一しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, someone surrounding her witnesses the moment Okiku breaks the plate on purpose.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, someone surrounding her witnesses the moment Okiku breaks the plate on purpose.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>これを知った播磨は、自分がそんなに信じられないのかと激怒、お菊を斬ってしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Learning this, Harima gets furious suspecting that she can&apos;t believe him that much, and kills Okiku with his sword.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Learning this, Harima gets furious suspecting that she can&apos;t believe him that much, and kills Okiku with his sword.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Learning this, Harima gets furious suspecting that she can&apos;t believe him that much, and kills Okiku with his sword.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>そして播磨の心が荒れるのに合わせるかのように、青山家もまた荒れ果ててゆくのだった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And as Harima&apos;s mind goes wild, the Aoyama family also goes to utter ruin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And as Harima&apos;s mind goes wild, the Aoyama family also goes to utter ruin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And as Harima&apos;s mind goes wild, the Aoyama family also goes to utter ruin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="43">
<j>1963年（昭和38年）に大映で市川雷蔵 (8代目)、藤由紀子主演で『手討』が製作された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1963 a movie &quot;Teuchi&quot; (capital punishment administered personally by one&apos;s master) was produced by Daiei Motion Picture Company starring Raizo ICHIKAWA (eighth) and Yukiko FUJI.</e>
<cmt>『手討ち』の説明を短く入れました（研究社『新和英大辞典第五版』）。「大映」の英語名称は&apos;Daiei Motion Picture Company&apos;のようです。http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/149824/Daiei-Motion-Picture-Company</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1963, a movie &quot;Teuchi&quot; (capital punishment administered personally by one&apos;s master) was produced by Daiei Motion Picture Company starring Raizo ICHIKAWA (eighth) and Yukiko FUJI.</e>
<cmt>カンマを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1963, a movie &quot;Teuchi&quot; (capital punishment administered personally by one&apos;s master) was produced by Daiei Motion Picture Company starring Raizo ICHIKAWA (eighth) and Yukiko FUJI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>ただしすぐお菊の後を追う形で、青山播磨も切腹に向かう所で終わる、より悲恋物語の性格が強い作品である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is, however, a film characteristic of more tragic love story which ends at a scene where Harima AOYAMA goes to seppuku (suicide by disembowelment) in the form of immediately following Okiku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is, however, a film characteristic of more tragic love story which ends at a scene where Harima AOYAMA goes to seppuku (suicide by disembowelment) in the form of immediately following Okiku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is, however, a film characteristic of more tragic love story which ends at a scene where Harima AOYAMA goes to seppuku (suicide by disembowelment) in the form of immediately following Okiku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>ビデオ、DVDになっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is on video and DVD.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is on video and DVD.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is on video and DVD.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>落語の『皿屋敷』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Sarayashiki&quot; of rakugo (traditional comic storytelling)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Sarayashiki&quot; of rakugo (traditional comic storytelling)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Sarayashiki&quot; of rakugo (traditional comic storytelling)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="46">
<j>落語の中に皿屋敷を題材にした話がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rakugo includes a story on the theme of Sarayashiki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rakugo includes a story on the theme of Sarayashiki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rakugo includes a story on the theme of Sarayashiki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>題名は『お菊の皿』、またはそのままの『皿屋敷』。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its title is &quot;Okiku&apos;s Plates&quot; or just &quot;Sarayashiki&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its title is &quot;Okiku&apos;s Plates&quot; or just &quot;Sarayashiki&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its title is &quot;Okiku&apos;s Plates&quot; or just &quot;Sarayashiki&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="48">
<j>町内の若者達が番町皿屋敷へお菊の幽霊見物に出かける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Young folks in a neighborhood go to Bancho Sarayashiki to see Okiku&apos;s ghost.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Young folks in a neighborhood go to Bancho Sarayashiki to see Okiku&apos;s ghost.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Young folks in a neighborhood go to Bancho Sarayashiki to see Okiku&apos;s ghost.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>出かける前に隠居からお菊の皿を数える声を九枚まで聞くと死んでしまうから六枚ぐらいで逃げ出せと教えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before they leave, they are suggested by a retired old man that they might die if they hear Okiku&apos;s voice count places up to nine, so it&apos;s better to run off when they hear Okiku count them up to six or so.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before they leave, they are warned by a retired old man that they might die if they hear Okiku&apos;s voice count plates up to nine, so it&apos;s better to run off when they hear Okiku count them up to about six.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正(places→plates）「up to six or so」を「up to about six」に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before they leave, they are warned by a retired old man that they might die if they hear Okiku&apos;s voice count plates up to nine, so it&apos;s better to run off when they hear Okiku count them up to about six.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>若者達は隠居の教えを守り、六枚まで聞いたところで皿屋敷から逃げ出してきたが、お菊があまりにもいい女だったので若者達は翌日も懲りずに皿屋敷へ出かけていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Following the old man&apos;s suggestion, the young folks escape from Sarayashiki when they hear her counting up to six, but Okiku is such a beautiful woman that they go there the next day again without learning a lesson.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Following the old man&apos;s suggestion, the young folks escape from Sarayashiki when they hear her counting up to six, but Okiku is such a beautiful woman that they go there the next day again without learning a lesson.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Following the old man&apos;s suggestion, the young folks escape from Sarayashiki when they hear her counting up to six, but Okiku is such a beautiful woman that they go there the next day again without learning a lesson.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>数日もすると人々に噂が伝わり、見物人は百人にまで膨れ上がった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a few days a rumor spreads among people and spectators swell up to a hundred.</e>
<cmt>「膨れ上がった」とありますが、落語のあらすじですので、現在形で統一しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In a few days a rumor spreads among people and spectators swell up to a hundred.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In a few days a rumor spreads among people and spectators swell up to a hundred.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="52">
<j>それだけ人が増えると六枚目で逃げるにも逃げられず、九枚まで数える声をまで聞いてしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Once the number of people increases that much, they cannot escape at the time of counting the sixth plate even if they want to, so they have to hear her voice even counting up to nine.</e>
<cmt>「六枚目で」のところを&apos; at the time of counting the sixth plate&apos;とし、言葉を少し追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Once the number of people increases that much, they cannot escape at the time of counting the sixth plate even if they want to, so they have to hear her voice even counting up to nine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Once the number of people increases that much, they cannot escape at the time of counting the sixth plate even if they want to, so they have to hear her voice even counting up to nine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>しかし聞いた者は死なず、よく聞くとお菊が九枚以降も皿を数え続けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, not only those who hear her do not die but also Okiku, when they listen carefully, continues to count the plates even after the ninth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, not only those who hear her do not die but also Okiku, when they listen carefully, continues to count the plates even after the ninth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, not only those who hear her do not die but also Okiku, when they listen carefully, continues to count the plates even after the ninth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>お菊は十八枚まで数えると「これでおしまい」と言って井戸の中に入ろうとするので見物人の一人が「お菊の皿は九枚と決まっているだろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Okiku counts up to 18 plates she is going to enter the well saying, &apos;That&apos;s all.&apos;, so one of the spectators says, &apos;It&apos;s the rule that Okiku&apos;s plates consist of nine.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Okiku counts up to 18 plates, she is going to enter the well saying, &apos;That&apos;s all.&apos;, so one of the spectators says, &apos;It&apos;s the rule that Okiku&apos;s plates consist of nine.&apos;</e>
<cmt>カンマを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Okiku counts up to 18 plates, she is going to enter the well saying, &apos;That&apos;s all.&apos;, so one of the spectators says, &apos;It&apos;s the rule that Okiku&apos;s plates consist of nine.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>何故十八枚も数えるんだ」と訊くと、お菊は「明日はお休みだから明日の分まで数えた」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the spectator asks &apos;Why do you count 18 plates?&apos;, Okiku replies, &quot;As tomorrow is a holiday, I counted even my duty for tomorrow.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the spectator asks &apos;Why do you count 18 plates?&apos;, Okiku replies, &quot;As tomorrow is a holiday, I counted even my duty for tomorrow.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the spectator asks &apos;Why do you count 18 plates?&apos;, Okiku replies, &quot;As tomorrow is a holiday, I counted even my duty for tomorrow.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Takobou(id:10633), Izayohi(id:13095), 桂鷺淵(id:151322), Haguii(id:1313), Nnh(id:474), ウース(id:31355), B612(id:96270), D.h(id:79056), TXiKiBoT(id:107492), さららゆら(id:12274), Pontafon(id:33761), Har-Poon-SSM(id:72987), Isopuh(id:154165), ラッパ食堂(id:255123), Y440(id:33809), Chiew(id:39745), Loveless(id:129239), Point136(id:211299), Alexbot(id:157199), NDR(id:5500), Louperibot(id:128971), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>