<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>葛切り</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kudzukiri (noodles made from kudzu flour and sugar)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kudzukiri (noodles made from kudzu flour and sugar)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kudzukiri (noodles made from kudzu flour and sugar)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>葛切り（くずきり）は、葛粉を水で溶かしてから加熱し、冷却して板状に固めたものをうどんのように細長く切った麺状の食べ物。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kudzukiri, a noodles like eating, is made as follows: Heated kudzu flour which was dissolved in water is set into a board shape by cooling, and then it is cut thin and long like udon (Japanese wheat noodle).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kudzukiri, a noodle for eating, is made with heated kudzu flour that has been dissolved in water and then set into a board shape by cooling, after which it is cut into long, thin forms udon (Japanese wheat noodles).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kudzukiri, a noodle for eating, is made with heated kudzu flour that has been dissolved in water and then set into a board shape by cooling, after which it is cut into long, thin forms udon (Japanese wheat noodles).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>冷して蜜をかけて食べたり、乾燥したものを鍋料理の具として用いたりする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kudzukiri is enjoyed in many ways such as Japanese style sweets in which syrup is poured on the cooled one, and ingredients of the pot dish in which dried one is used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kudzukiri is enjoyed in many ways such as Japanese-style sweets in which syrup is poured over the cooled noodles, and as an ingredient in pot dishes, in which dried type is used.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kudzukiri is enjoyed in many ways such as Japanese-style sweets in which syrup is poured over the cooled noodles, and as an ingredient in pot dishes, in which dried type is used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="3">
<j>鍋料理の具としては、昨今、葛を原料に用いず、代わりに廉価なジャガイモ澱粉などを原料にして葛切りを模した食材も一般的に使われるようになってきている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Recently, foodstuff imitating Kudzukiri, which is made from other cheaper materials like potato starch instead of kudzu flour, has also been used as ingredients of the pot dish commonly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Recently, foodstuff imitating Kudzukiri, which is made from cheaper materials like potato starch instead of kudzu flour, has become common as an ingredient in pot dishes.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Recently, foodstuff imitating Kudzukiri, which is made from cheaper materials like potato starch instead of kudzu flour, has become common as an ingredient in pot dishes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>本葛粉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hon-kudzu-ko (genuine kudzu flour)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hon-kudzu-ko (genuine kudzu flour)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hon-kudzu-ko (genuine kudzu flour)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>クズの根から作られる粉は本葛粉と呼ばれ、なめらかで口当たりが良いが、本来多少の苦味を伴う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The flour made from the root of the kudzu vine is called &quot;Hon-kudzu-ko&quot;, which has smooth and pleasant taste with some bitterness.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The flour made from the root of the kudzu vine is called &quot;Hon-kudzu-ko,&quot; which has a smooth and pleasant taste with some bitterness.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The flour made from the root of the kudzu vine is called &quot;Hon-kudzu-ko,&quot; which has a smooth and pleasant taste with some bitterness.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>この苦味が薄いと薬効が落ちるとも言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Hon-kudzu-ko with less bitterness has less medicinal efficacy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Hon-kudzu-ko with less bitterness has less medicinal efficacy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Hon-kudzu-ko with less bitterness has less medicinal efficacy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>本葛粉は生産量が少なく高価であるため、現在「本葛粉」として市販されている物でさえコムギやジャガイモ、サツマイモ（甘藷）やなどのデンプンを混入した物が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Hon-kudzu-ko is expensive due to its small production, not a few goods come onto the market include starch extracted from wheat, potato, sweet potato and others, even if they are labeled &quot;Hon-kudzu-ko&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because Hon-kudzu-ko is expensive due to its small production, various goods that have come onto the market include starch extracted from wheat, potato, sweet potato and others, even if they are labeled &quot;Hon-kudzu-ko.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because Hon-kudzu-ko is expensive due to its small production, various goods that have come onto the market include starch extracted from wheat, potato, sweet potato and others, even if they are labeled &apos;Hon-kudzu-ko.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>（ジャガイモは、体を冷やす作用がある）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(The starch extracted from potato cools the body.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(The starch extracted from potato cools the body.)</e>
<cmt>sp</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(The starch extracted from potato cools the body.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>ただし、西日本、特に産地の多い近畿や九州では本葛粉が比較的手に入りやすい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Hon-kudzu-ko is comparatively easy to obtain in the western Japan, especially in Kinki region and Kyushu region, in which there are many kudzu vine-producing area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Hon-kudzu-ko is relatively easy to obtain in western Japan, especially in the Kinki and Kyushu regions, in which there are many kudzu vine-producing areas.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Hon-kudzu-ko is relatively easy to obtain in western Japan, especially in the Kinki and Kyushu regions, in which there are many kudzu vine-producing areas.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>本葛粉の生産の現状</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Current situation of producing Hon-kudzu-ko</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Current state of Hon-kudzu-ko production</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Current state of Hon-kudzu-ko production</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="9">
<j>本葛粉の生産はクズの根を掘り出す人の高齢化と天然資源の減少によって、現在、国内で出回る本葛粉にしめる中国製の割合が高まっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ratio of Hon-kudzu-ko made in China to that coming onto the domestic market has risen recently because of decreasing domestic production of Hon-kudzu-ko, which was caused by the aging of the experts who dig out the root of kudzu vine, as well as by the decreasing natural kudzu vine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ratio of Hon-kudzu-ko made in China to that coming onto the domestic market has risen recently due to the decreases domestic production of Hon-kudzu-ko, which has been caused by the aging of the experts who dig out the root of the kudzu vine, as well as by the decreasing amount of natural kudzu vine.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ratio of Hon-kudzu-ko made in China to that coming onto the domestic market has risen recently due to the decreases domestic production of Hon-kudzu-ko, which has been caused by the aging of the experts who dig out the root of the kudzu vine, as well as by the decreasing amount of natural kudzu vine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>中国製については、中国から寒根葛（葛）の根を輸入し国内で製造した物を国産本葛と表示しているケースがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kudzu flour produced in domestic factories by using the root of kudzu vine imported from China is often labeled &quot;Hon-kudzu-ko made in Japan&quot;.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The kudzu flour produced in domestic factories by using the root of kudzu vines imported from China is often labeled as &quot;Hon-kudzu-ko made in Japan.&quot;</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The kudzu flour produced in domestic factories by using the root of kudzu vines imported from China is often labeled as &quot;Hon-kudzu-ko made in Japan.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>さらに国産本葛と中国産葛を混ぜ合わせて国産本葛としている事が多々見受けられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, not a few manufacturers also apply a label &quot;Hon-kudzu-ko made in Japan&quot; on the mixture of domestic kudzu flour and Chinese-made kudzu flour.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, various manufacturers also apply a label &quot;Hon-kudzu-ko made in Japan&quot; to the mixture of domestic kudzu flour and Chinese-made kudzu flour.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, various manufacturers also apply a label &quot;Hon-kudzu-ko made in Japan&quot; to the mixture of domestic kudzu flour and Chinese-made kudzu flour.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>中国産の寒根葛（葛）の根のポストハーベスト（残留農薬）の危険性が問題になっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Recently, the toxicity of the pesticide residue remaining in the root of kudzu vine grown in China has become a problem.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Recently, the toxicity of the pesticide residue remaining in the root of kudzu vine grown in China has become a problem.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Recently, the toxicity of the pesticide residue remaining in the root of kudzu vine grown in China has become a problem.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>国内産本葛の大生産地は、現在、鹿児島である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A large producing area of the domestic kudzu flour is Kagoshima Prefecture at present.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kagoshima Prefecture is currently a large producing area for domestic kudzu flour.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kagoshima Prefecture is currently a large producing area for domestic kudzu flour.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>南九州産を原料とする三軒は、信頼のおける生産者といえるだろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Above all, three manufacturers using the root of kudzu vine grown in Southern Kyushu are credible.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Particularly significant are three manufacturers using the root of the kudzu vine grown in southern Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Particularly significant are three manufacturers using the root of the kudzu vine grown in southern Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>※　台湾産の葛根はタイワンクズ、中国産の葛根はシナノクズであり、日本産の葛根とは植物学的には同種類ではない</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">*The root of kudzu vine grown in Japan, Taiwan and China each belongs to the separate species botanically.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">*The kudzu vines grown in Japan, Taiwan and China each represent a separate species, botanically.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">*The kudzu vines grown in Japan, Taiwan and China each represent a separate species, botanically.</e>
<cmt>全角削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="16">
<j>本葛の原料原産地名表示の現状</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Current situation of how the details of raw materials and producing areas are displayed on the package of kudzu flour</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The current situation of how the details of raw materials and producing areas are displayed on packages of kudzu flour</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The current situation of how the details of raw materials and producing areas are displayed on packages of kudzu flour</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="17">
<j>現在、本葛には、原料原産地名の表示義務がない為、本葛の表示があっても国産とは限らないのが現状である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Displaying the details of raw materials and producing areas on the package of kudzu flour is not an obligation, therefore, the kudzu flour with a label of &quot;Hon-kudzu-ko&quot; is not always made from the root of kudzu vine grown in Japan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is not a requirement to display the details of raw materials and producing areas on the package of kudzu flour, so the kudzu flour with a label of &quot;Hon-kudzu-ko&quot; isn&apos;t always made from the root of kudzu vine grown in Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is not a requirement to display the details of raw materials and producing areas on the package of kudzu flour, so the kudzu flour with a label of &quot;Hon-kudzu-ko&quot; isn&apos;t always made from the root of kudzu vine grown in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>よって商品内容表示に原料原産地名の表示のない物については、外国産が混じっていると言える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Accordingly, there is a high probability that the package of kudzu flour without the details of raw materials and producing areas contains the kudzu flour made in other countries.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Accordingly, there is a high probability that the package of kudzu flour without the details of raw materials and producing areas contains kudzu flour that has originated in other countries.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Accordingly, there is a high probability that the package of kudzu flour without the details of raw materials and producing areas contains kudzu flour that has originated in other countries.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Opponent(id:720), マクガイア(id:33346), Charenji(id:7908), Nighthawks(id:36125), Roger(id:9883), Corwin(id:973), NDR(id:5500), 黒毛金眼九尾猫(id:112621), Kjwnxdsaz(id:160046), 1029man(id:93235), Johncapistrano(id:969), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>