<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>采女装束</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Uneme Costume</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Uneme Costume</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Uneme Costume</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>采女装束（うねめしょうぞく）とは、全国の豪族から選抜されて天皇の給仕係などとして上古の宮中に勤めた女官である采女の衣装。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Uneme costume is a costume of Uneme, a court lady who were selected among Gozoku (local ruling family) and served in the inner palace as a wait staff of an emperor in ancient times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Uneme costume is a costume for Uneme, a court lady selected among Gozoku (local ruling families) who served in the inner palace as a waiting staff of the emperor in ancient times.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Uneme costume is a costume for Uneme, a court lady selected among Gozoku (local ruling families) who served in the inner palace as a waiting staff of the emperor in ancient times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>装束になったのは江戸時代後期である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was in the latter half of Edo period that Uneme started to wear the costume.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was during the latter half of Edo period that Uneme started to wear a costume.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was during the latter half of Edo period that Uneme started to wear a costume.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>同じ宮中の女官といっても、基本的に頭脳労働中心の女房が身に着ける十二単に比べて、立ち働きが多いため丈が短く活動的にできている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Compared with juni-hitoe (twelve-layered ceremonial kimono) that were worn by nyobo (a court lady) who mainly worked as a brainworker in the same inner palace, Uneme costume was short-length, allowing mobility for Uneme who worked walking around.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Compared with juni-hitoe (twelve-layered ceremonial kimono) worn by nyobo (a court lady) who mainly worked as a brainworker in the same inner palace, the Uneme costume was short-length, allowing mobility for Uneme who worked while walking around.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Compared with juni-hitoe (twelve-layered ceremonial kimono) worn by nyobo (a court lady) who mainly worked as a brainworker in the same inner palace, the Uneme costume was short-length, allowing mobility for Uneme who worked while walking around.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>ちなみに時代祭での小野小町は平安時代初期の采女の装束を身に着けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">ONO no Komachii in Jidai-matsuri Festival was in Uneme costume in the early Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">ONO no Komachii during the Jidai-matsuri Festival wore an Uneme costume during the early Heian period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">ONO no Komachii during the Jidai-matsuri Festival wore an Uneme costume during the early Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>簡素で活動的なことから、現代の女性神職装束はこの采女装束を参考にしていると言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Uneme costume was simple with mobility, it is said that present-day costume for female Shinto priest was based on Uneme costume.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the Uneme costume was simple allowing mobility, it is said that present-day costume for female Shinto priest was based on the Uneme costume.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the Uneme costume was simple allowing mobility, it is said that present-day costume for female Shinto priest was based on the Uneme costume.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="6">
<j>ここでは明治以降の神事で采女が身に着ける装束について解説する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Here we will explain the costume that Uneme wear in Shinto rituals after Meiji period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">We will describe the costume that Uneme wore in Shinto rituals after Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">We will describe the costume that Uneme wore in Shinto rituals after the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>冠詞</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>装束</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Costume</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Costume</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Costume</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>下から</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the bottom to the top</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the bottom to the top</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the bottom to the top</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>襪（しとうず）：絹製の白い靴下。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shitozu: White socks made of silk.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shitozu: White socks made of silk.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shitozu: White socks made of silk.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>足袋と違って指先は分かれない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Unlike tabi, the toes of Shitoz are not parted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unlike tabi, the toes of Shitoz are not parted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unlike tabi, the toes of Shitozu are not parted.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>単（ひとえ）：裏の無い着物。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hitoe: Kimono without a lining.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hitoe: Kimono without a lining.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hitoe: Kimono without a lining.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>裾を袴の中に入れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The hem of Hitoe should be tucked into Hakama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The hem of Hitoe should be tucked into Hakama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The hem of Hitoe should be tucked into Hakama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>切袴（きりばかま）：足の甲にかかるくらいの丈の、幅の広いズボン形の袴。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">kiri-hakama (short fringe hakama): Hakama whose hems almost reached to instep and it is like a wide-legged trousers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">kiri-hakama (short fringe hakama): Hakama with hems almost reaching the instep and it is like a wide-legged trousers.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">kiri-hakama (short fringe hakama): Hakama with hems almost reaching the instep and it is like a wide-legged trousers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>捩襠（ねじまち）といって縁を縫わずに巻いて糊でとめており、襞は上の部分にしかない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiri-hakama was made to use nejimachi method; the hems are rolled up and glued instead of sewing while the upper part was tucked.</e>
<cmt>定訳不明のため、捩襠（ねじまち）→nejimachi methodと訳出しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiri-hakama was made to use nejimachi method; the hems are rolled up and glued instead of sewing while the upper part was tucked.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiri-hakama was made to use nejimachi method; the hems are rolled up and glued instead of sewing while the upper part was tucked.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="14">
<j>絵衣（えぎぬ）：雲や松、椿の模様を描いた白い練絹に萌黄色の生絹（すずし/生糸で織った薄い織物）の裏地をつけた丈の短い表衣（うえのきぬ）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eginu (silk canvas): a white short-length ue no kinu (silk robe) with patterns of clouds, pines, and Camellia with a suzushi (raw silk products that were thinly made) lining in moegiiro (light green) color.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eginu (silk canvas): a white short-length ue no kinu (silk robe) with patterns of clouds, pine trees, and Camellia with a suzushi (raw silk products that were thinly made) lining in moegiiro (light green) color.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eginu (silk canvas): a white short-length ue no kinu (silk robe) composed of white neriginu (glossy silk) with patterns of clouds, pine trees, and Camellia and a suzushi (raw silk products that were thinly made) lining in moegiiro (a light green color).</e>
<cmt>補足しました。チェックお願いしますNR: Without explanation, &quot;neriginu&quot; would have no meaning to a native speaker of English so I have added the definition that appears in the SunFlare glossary.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>単と同形だが袴の上に出して着る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eginu&apos;s shape was same as that of Hitoe; it was tucked out when it was worn.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shape of Hginu was same as that of Hitoe; it was tucked out when worn.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The shape of Eginu was same as that of Hitoe; it was tucked out when worn.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="16">
<j>唐衣（からぎぬ）：女房装束でも使われる丈の短い上着。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Karaginu: a short-length jacket that was used as a part of costumes for nyobo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Karaginu: a short-length jacket that was used as a part of the costume for nyobo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Karaginu: a short-length jacket that was used as a part of the costume for nyobo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>采女は白地に青で青海波の模様があるものを着用して、苧麻（ちょま）の帯を腰に締める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Uneme put on Karaginu in white color with patterns of blue water waves, and tied up choma (hemp) obi (long draping sash) around her waist.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Uneme wore Karaginu in white with patterns of blue water waves, and tied up choma (hemp) obi (long draping sash) around her waist.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Uneme wore Karaginu in white with patterns of blue water waves, and tied up choma (hemp) obi (long draping sash) around her waist.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="18">
<j>千早（ちはや）：襟元を着物の打ち合わせのように仕立てた白い薄絹の貫頭衣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chihaya (Japanese coat for female priests): a white thin silk top which was pulled over one&apos;s head, and its collars were layered like Kimono.</e>
<cmt>貫頭衣→頭からかぶる衣服 と考え訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chihaya (Japanese coat for female priests): a white thin silk top which was pulled over one&apos;s head, and its collars were layered like Kimono.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chihaya (Japanese coat for female priests): a white thin silk top which was pulled over one&apos;s head, and its collars were layered like Kimono.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>巫女が身に着けるものと違って袖が無い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">sleeveless unlike the top that is worn by miko (a shrine maiden).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">sleeveless unlike the top that is worn by miko (shrine maiden).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is sleeveless unlike the top that is worn by miko (shrine maiden).</e>
<cmt>文にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="20">
<j>髪上具（かみあげのぐ）：雛人形の髪飾りでおなじみの平額・釵子・櫛のワンセット。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">kamiage no gu (a set of hair ornaments): hirabitai ornament, sashi (ornate hairpin), a comb, as those used for a doll displayed at the Girls&apos; Festival.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">kamiage no gu (a set of hair ornaments): hirabitai ornament, sashi (ornate hairpin), a comb, like those used for a doll display during the Girls&apos; Festival.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">kamiage no gu (a set of hair ornaments): hirabitai ornament, sashi (ornate hairpin), a comb, like those used for a doll display during the Girls&apos; Festival.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>采女装束の場合は心葉というウメの枝と「日陰の糸」という顔の横に下げる糸状の髪飾りを装着する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">a branch of camellia called Kokoroba and thread-like hair ornaments called `hikage no ito&apos; which was hanged beside one&apos;s face were adhered to Kamiage no gu in Uneme costume.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">a branch of camellia called Kokoroba and thread-like hair ornaments called `hikage no ito&apos; which was hung beside one&apos;s face were attached to Kamiage no gu in Uneme costume.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A branch of plum called Kokoroba and thread-like hair ornaments called `hikage no ito&apos; which was hung beside one&apos;s face were attached to Kamiage no gu in Uneme costume.</e>
<cmt>梅　plum</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="22">
<j>などで構成される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those consisting of Uneme costume were above mentioned.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The description of the Uneme costume is mentioned above.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The description of the Uneme costume is mentioned above.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 こぶまき(id:38278), 桜井悠士(id:72420), Kamuin(id:5241), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>