<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>怨霊</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Onryo (Revengeful Ghost)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Onryo (Revengeful Ghost)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Onryo (Revengeful Ghost)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>怨霊（おんりょう）とは一般的に、人間の目には見えず、人間に対して敵意や悪意を抱いているとされる、超自然的、あるいは霊的存在。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Onryo are commonly supernatural or ghostly phenomenon that cannot be seen by human eyes and harbor ill will and vengeance towards humans.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Onryo are common supernatural or ghostly phenomenon that cannot be seen by human eyes that harbor ill will and vengeance towards humans.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Onryo are common supernatural or ghostly phenomenon that cannot be seen by human eyes that harbor ill will and vengeance towards humans.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>その性格上、悪霊に分類される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to these attributes, they are classified as evil spirits.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to these attributes, they are classified as evil spirits.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to these attributes, they are classified as evil spirits.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>ある人間が、事故や事件、争乱、刑罰や処刑、他者からの過度な精神的または肉体的圧迫などによって死に至った場合、いわゆる昇天や成仏をせず、強い念（＝怨念。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Onryo refers to supernatural phenomenon and the religious idea (in some parts) or spiritual notion that if a person dies in an accident or incident, dispute, suffers punishment or execution, or dies after suffering from excessive mental or physical stress caused by another person, and does not reach heaven or nirvana, but remains in this world saddled with strong feelings (grudge, described below),</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Onryo refers to supernatural phenomenon and the religious idea (in some parts) or spiritual notion that if a person dies in an accident or incident, dispute, suffers punishment or execution, or dies after suffering from excessive mental or physical stress caused by another person, and does not reach heaven or nirvana, but remains in this world saddled with strong feelings (grudges, described below),</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Onryo refers to supernatural phenomenon and the religious idea (in some parts) or spiritual notion that if a person dies in an accident or incident, dispute, suffers punishment or execution, or dies after suffering from excessive mental or physical stress caused by another person, and does not reach heaven or nirvana, but remains in this world saddled with strong feelings (grudges, described below),</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>後述）を抱いたままこの世に留まり、自らを死に至らしめた相手を呪い、時にはその相手を死にまで至らしめることによって、自らの仕返しの思いを遂げるという、（一部の）宗教上あるいは心霊上での概念やその超自然的存在自体を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the spirit may curse the person who caused their death and in some cases drive that person to death, and in this way seek retaliation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">the spirit may curse the person who caused their death and in some cases drive that person to death, and in this way seek retaliation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">the spirit may curse the person who caused their death and in some cases drive that person to death, and in this way seek retaliation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>またそれらをテーマとした講談、マンガ、映画、ドラマなどで用いられる用語であり、こういったフィクションなどではその効果を高めるために怨霊の物質化が描写されることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also a term used in storytelling, comics, movies and dramas with these themes and in this kind of fiction the spirits are portrayed with physical presences in order to heighten the effectiveness of the story.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also a term used in storytelling, comics, movies, and dramas and in this kind of fiction the spirits are portrayed as having a physical presence in order to heighten the effectiveness of the story.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also a term used in storytelling, comics, movies, and dramas and in this kind of fiction the spirits are portrayed as having a physical presence in order to heighten the effectiveness of the story.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="6">
<j>怨念</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Onnen (Grudge)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Onnen (Grudge)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Onnen (Grudge)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>怨念（おんねん）とは、その超自然的存在のもつ、あるいはその超自然的存在そのものである、「祟りの結果として表面化し、相手に影響を及ぼすに至る」とされる「思念」を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Onnen (Grudge) indicates a feeling held by a supernatural being that results in a curse surfacing and affecting another person.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Onnen (Grudge) indicates a feeling held by a supernatural being that results in a curse that affects another person.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Onnen indicates a feeling held by a supernatural being that results in a curse that affects another person.</e>
<cmt>怨念既出のため説明削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="8">
<j>著名な事例</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Notable examples</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Notable examples</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Notable examples</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>日本においては、平安時代の菅原道真や崇徳天皇の祟りや、江戸時代に「田宮家で実際に起こった、妻のお岩にまつわる一連の事件」を、四世鶴屋南北が怪談として脚色した「東海道四谷怪談」などが挙げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan, examples include the curses of Michizane Sugawara and Emperor Sutoku in the Heian Period, and in the Edo Period Tsuruya Nanboku used the &apos;incident of a wife&apos;s murder which actually happened in the Tamura household&apos; as a ghost story in his play &apos;Tokaido Yotsuya Ghost Stories&apos;.</e>
<cmt>田宮家で実際に起こった、妻のお岩にまつわる一連の事件 &apos;incident of a wife&apos;s murder which actually happened in the Tamura household&apos;</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan, examples include the curses of Michizane Sugawara and Emperor Sutoku during the Heian and Edo Periods Tsuruya Nanboku used the &apos;incident of a wife&apos;s murder which actually happened in the Tamura household&apos; as a ghost story in his play &apos;Tokaido Yotsuya Ghost Stories.&apos;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan, examples include the curses of SUGAWARA no Michizane and Emperor Sutoku during the Heian period and during the Edo period Nanboku TSURUYA, the fourth used the &apos;incident of a wife, Oiwa&apos;s murder which in fact happened in the Tamiya fafmily&apos; as a ghost story in his play &apos;Tokaido Yotsuya Ghost Stories.&apos;</e>
<cmt>菅原道真の表記変更Heian の後に period 追記Tamura household→Tamiya family「四世」追記して、Nanboku TSURUYA としました。「お岩」も追記したのでご確認願います。Edo の前に during the 追記Periods→periodactually →in factに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="10">
<j>また、明治時代に東京で起きたとされる、某・旧省庁内における「平将門の『首塚(くびづか)』移転などにまつわる数々の祟り」など、怨霊に関する、不特定多数の人間によって確認されたとされる現象もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, there were also phenomenon which were reportedly witnessed by an unspecified number of people in connection with onryo ghosts such as the reported happenings in Tokyo in the Meiji Period in connection with the transfer of the tomb for the head of Tairano Masakado inside an old undisclosed ministry and related curses.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, there were also phenomenon reportedly witnessed by an unspecified number of people in connection with onryo ghosts such as the reported happenings in Tokyo during the Meiji Period in connection with the transfer of a tomb for the head of Tairano Masakado inside an old undisclosed ministry and related curses.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, there were also phenomenon reportedly witnessed by an unspecified number of people in connection with onryo ghosts such as the reported happenings in Tokyo during the Meiji Period in connection with the transfer of &quot;a tomb for the head&quot; of TAIRA no Masakado inside an old undisclosed ministry and related curses.</e>
<cmt>Tairano→TAIRA no&apos; &apos; は文の構成上付けられず、 &quot; &quot; のみ『』の部分につけました。ご確認願います。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>しかし、呪術と同様に、科学的にはなお実証不可能である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as with magic, it is impossible to find scientific proof.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, like with magic, it is impossible to find scientific proof.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, like with magic, it is impossible to find scientific proof.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="12">
<j>民俗学的背景</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Folkloric Background</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Folkloric Background</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Folkloric Background</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>概して、「その怨霊化したとされる者の死んだ場所や墓所を荒らしたり、不用意にそういった場所の近くを通りかかっただけの生きた人間に対してさえも祟りが降りかかる場合がある」といった見解がとられることも多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The usual understanding is that there are cases where the place or grave where the person who is said to have became an onryo(revengeful ghost) died is vandalized or that people who merely inadvertently pass such places become cursed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The usual understanding is that there are cases where the place or grave where the person who is said to have became an onryo (revengeful ghost) died, is vandalized or people who merely inadvertently pass such a place become cursed.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The usual understanding is that &apos;there are cases where the place or grave where the person who is said to have became an onryo died, is vandalized or people who merely inadvertently pass such a place become cursed.&apos;</e>
<cmt>怨霊の説明既出のため削除&apos; &apos; をつけました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="14">
<j>日本の各時代や地域によっても「死者は聖なる存在」「死者は忌み嫌うべき存在」「自然死以外は、悪霊化し、生者に祟る」など様々な見解がとられていたといわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that there have been different viewpoints throughout the ages in Japan and across different regions including that &apos;the dead become sacred beings&apos;, &apos;the dead become beings to be abhorred&apos; or that &apos;people who die of unnatural causes become revengeful ghosts and curse the living.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that there have been different viewpoints throughout the ages in Japan and across different regions including that &apos;the dead become sacred beings&apos;, &apos;the dead become beings to be abhorred&apos; or that &apos;people who die of unnatural causes become revengeful ghosts and curse the living.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that there have been different viewpoints throughout the ages in Japan and across different regions including that &apos;the dead become sacred beings&apos;, &apos;the dead become beings to be abhorred&apos; or that &apos;people who die of unnatural causes become revengeful ghosts and curse the living.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>「江戸時代に至ってもなお、庶民は一般的に怨霊に対する畏怖感、恐怖感を抱いていた」という民俗学上の分析もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some analysis of folklore suggests that even into the Edo Period people generally harbored feelings of awe and fear with respect to the dead.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some analysis of folklore suggests that even during the Edo Period people generally harbored feelings of awe and fear with respect to the dead.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some analysis of folklore suggests that &apos;even during the Edo Period people generally harbored feelings of awe and fear to the dead.&apos;</e>
<cmt>with respect は原文にないので削除し、「」部分に &apos; &apos; を付けました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>上に挙げた死者の霊は両義的側面を持っていることが分かるが、怨霊と反対に祝い祀られているのが祖霊である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As can be seen from the above explanation the spirits of the deceased have some ambiguous aspects and the opposite of revengeful ghosts are the ancestral spirits which are honored.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As can be seen from the above explanation the spirits of the deceased have some ambiguous aspects and in contrast to revengeful ghosts are the ancestral spirits which are honored.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As can be seen from the above explanation the spirits of the deceased have some ambiguous aspects and in contrast to revengeful ghosts are the ancestral spirits which are honored.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>また民俗学と全く関係ないわけでもないが哲学者の梅原猛は日本史を怨霊鎮めの観点から捉えた「怨霊史観」で著名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also while not completely unrelated to folklore, the philosopher Takeshi Umehara is noted for his work &apos;History of Onryo&apos; which looks at history from the point of view of appeasement of revengeful ghosts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also while not completely unrelated to folklore, the philosopher Takeshi Umehara is noted for his work &apos;History of Onryo&apos; which looks at history from the point of view of the appeasement of revengeful ghosts.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also while not completely unrelated to folklore, the philosopher Takeshi UMEHARA is noted for his work &apos;History of Onryo&apos; which looks at Japanese history from the point of view of the appeasement of revengeful ghosts.</e>
<cmt>history→Japanese historyUmehara→UMEHARA</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="18">
<j>インドの仏教では人は7日に1度ずつ7回の転生の機会があり、例外なく49日以内に全員が転生すると考えられているために人間の怨霊は存在しない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Indian Buddhism there are no revengeful ghosts as there are seven opportunities for reincarnation, one each seven days after death, so all the deceased without exception are thought to be reincarnated within 49 days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Indian Buddhism there are no revengeful ghosts as there are seven opportunities for reincarnation, one each seven days after death, so all the deceased without exception are thought to be reincarnated within 49 days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Indian Buddhism there are no revengeful ghosts as there are seven opportunities for reincarnation, one each seven days after death, so all the deceased without exception are thought to be reincarnated within 49 days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>しかし、日本では神仏習合が幅広く行われているため、日本の仏教の僧侶・尼のなかには除霊などを収入源としている者も存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However in Japan a mixture of Buddhism and Shinto is widespread so some Japanese Buddhist monks and nuns find a source of income in such practices as exorcising spirits.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However in Japan a mixture of Buddhism and Shinto is widespread so some Japanese Buddhist monks and nuns find a source of income in such practices as exorcising spirits.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However in Japan a mixture of Buddhism and Shinto is widespread so some Japanese Buddhist monks and nuns find a source of income in such practices as exorcising spirits.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>平安時代以前の怨霊とみられるものとしては、大和政権が征服を進める際に敵方の霊を弔ったという隼人塚がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Examples of appearance of onryo prior to the Heian Period include the Hayatozuka historical site at which it is said the Yamato Crown mourned the spirits killed in enemy territory during its conquest of the region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Examples of appearance of onryo prior to the Heian Period include the Hayatozuka historical site at which it is said the Yamato Crown mourned the spirits killed in enemy territory during its conquest of the region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Examples of appearance of onryo prior to the Heian Period include the Hayato burial mound at which it is said the Yamato Government mourned the spirits of the enemy during its conquest of the region.</e>
<cmt>Crown→Government「敵方の霊」「隼人塚」の訳を訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="21">
<j>怨霊の神格化</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Deification of onryo (revengeful ghosts)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Deification of onryo (revengeful ghosts)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Deification of onryo</e>
<cmt>既出のため説明削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>また、いくつかの神社などにおいて、実在した歴史上の人物（一部の皇族や武将を除く）が、神として祀られている場合でも、「当初、その（祀られている）人物が、暗殺や反乱などによって殺害されたもので、それが怨霊化して祟りをなすことを畏怖して、祀った結果によるもの」という見解を持つ研究者も少なくない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, quite a few researchers hold the view that at various shrines and temples, even in the case of historic figures who once lived and are now enshrined (excepting some imperial family members and shoguns), at first the enshrined people were murdered or died in rebellions and the people were fearful of these people becoming ghosts and placing curses so they deified them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, quite a few researchers hold the view that at various shrines and temples, even in the case of historic figures who once lived and are now enshrined (excepting some imperial family members and shoguns), at first the enshrined people were murdered or died in rebellions and the people were fearful of these people becoming ghosts and placing curses so they deified them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, quite a few researchers hold the view that at various shrines and temples, even in the case of historic figures who once lived and are now enshrined (excepting some imperial family members and warriors), &apos;at first the enshrined people were murdered or died in rebellions and the people were fearful of these people becoming ghosts and placing curses so they deified them.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「」に　&apos; &apos; 付けました。「武将」がshogunsとなっていますが、warriorsとしました。ご確認願います。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="23">
<j>実際に、日本三大怨霊とされる、菅原道真は、太宰府天満宮（福岡県太宰府市）や北野天満宮（京都市上京区）、平将門は、築土神社（東京都千代田区）や神田明神（東京都千代田区）、崇徳天皇は、白峯神宮（京都市上京区）にそれぞれ祀られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Actually, the three greatest onryo (revengeful ghosts) and the places at which they are enshrined include: Michizane Sugawara, at Dazaifu Tenmangu (Dazaifu City, Fukuoka Prefecture) and Kitano Tenmangu (Kamigyo Ward, Kyoto), Taira-no-Masakado at Tsukudo Shrine (Chiyoda Ward, Tokyo) and Kanda Myojin Shrine (Chiyoda Ward, Tokyo) and Emperor Sutoku at Shiramine Shrine (Kamigyo Ward, Kyoto).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Actually, the three greatest onryo (revengeful ghosts) and the places at which they are enshrined include: Michizane Sugawara, at Dazaifu Tenmangu (Dazaifu City, Fukuoka Prefecture) and Kitano Tenmangu (Kamigyo Ward, Kyoto), Taira-no-Masakado at Tsukudo Shrine (Chiyoda Ward, Tokyo) and Kanda Myojin Shrine (Chiyoda Ward, Tokyo) and Emperor Sutoku at Shiramine Shrine (Kamigyo Ward, Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact, the three greatest onryo and the places at which they are enshrined include: SUGAWARA no Michizane, at Dazaifu Tenmangu Shrine (Dazaifu City, Fukuoka Prefecture) and Kitano Tenmangu Shrine (Kamigyo Ward, Kyoto), TAIRA no Masakado at Tsukudo-jinja Shrine (Chiyoda Ward, Tokyo) and Kanda Myojin Shrine (Chiyoda Ward, Tokyo) and Emperor Sutoku at Shiramine-jingu Shrine (Kamigyo Ward, Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>怨霊の説明削除菅原道真の表記変更神社名にShrine 追記平将門の表記変更築土神社に jinja 追記jingu 追記Actually→In factに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 釣ちごちゅが(id:22605), Nnh(id:474), Stanislaus(id:1806), 逃亡者(id:14864), STBot(id:137943), TXiKiBoT(id:107492), Memosa(id:131221), WR(id:4432), Kamui99(id:107396), Mikeneko(id:18205), Geist(id:6907), Hotneko(id:38627), クロサキ(id:169477), 廬舎那憂(id:168188), GURAX(id:107578), Muneco(id:30867), Loveless(id:129239), Corwin(id:973), Suisui(id:69), Caminante(id:39410), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>