<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>ふんどし</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fundoshi (traditional Japanese underwear)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fundoshi (traditional Japanese underwear)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fundoshi (traditional Japanese underwear)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>褌（ふんどし）は、日本をはじめとする地域での伝統的な男性用の下着である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Fundoshi&quot; is traditional underwear for men in Japan and other areas.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Fundoshi&quot; is a traditional underwear for men in Japan and other areas.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Fundoshi&quot; is a traditional underwear for men in Japan and other areas.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>英語では loincloth と表記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In English, it is described as &quot;loincloth.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In English, it is described as &quot;loincloth.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In English, it is described as &quot;loincloth.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>祭りの中において褌は下着ではなく、晴れ着として扱われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the occasion of festivals, fundoshi is not treated as underwear but as festive dress.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On festival occasions, fundoshi is not treated as underwear but as a festive dress.</e>
<cmt>Rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On festival occasions, fundoshi is not treated as underwear but as a festive dress.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>百貨店、呉服、武具、祭、通信販売などで販売されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It can be bought in department stores, kimono shops (drapers), armorer&apos;s shops, festival sites and mail-order markets.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It can be bought in department stores, kimono shops (drapers), armorer&apos;s shops, festival sites and mail-order markets.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It can be bought in department stores, kimono shops (drapers), armorer&apos;s shops, festival sites and mail-order markets.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>コロン削除</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>「褌」の漢字は「衣」偏に「軍」と書くように、戦闘服に由来する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As kanji (a Chinese character used in Japanes writing) for &quot;fundoshi&quot; consists of a radical &quot;衣&quot; (&quot;koromo&quot; meaning &quot;vesture&quot;) at left-hand side and &quot;軍&quot; (&quot;gun&quot; meaning &quot;military&quot;) at right-hand side, a fundoshi loincloth traces back to battle dress.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As kanji (a Chinese character used in Japanese writing) for &quot;fundoshi&quot; consists of a radical &quot;衣&quot; (&quot;koromo&quot; meaning &quot;vesture&quot;) on the left-hand side and &quot;軍&quot; (&quot;gun&quot; meaning &quot;military&quot;) on the right-hand side, a fundoshi loincloth traces back to battle dresses.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As kanji (a Chinese character used in Japanese writing) for &quot;fundoshi&quot; consists of a radical &quot;衣&quot; (&quot;koromo&quot; meaning &quot;vesture&quot;) on the left-hand side and &quot;軍&quot; (&quot;gun&quot; meaning &quot;military&quot;) on the right-hand side, a fundoshi loincloth traces back to battle dresses.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>昔は布が高価であったことから、戦国時代 (日本)では戦死者の身分は褌の有無で見分けを行っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Sengoku period (the period of Warring States) in Japan, it was possible to discern ranks of warriors killed in war by checking whether they were wearing fundoshi loincloths or not, since cloths at that time were generally expensive.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Sengoku period (the period of Warring States) in Japan, it was possible to discern the ranks of warriors killed in war by checking whether they were wearing fundoshi loincloths or not, since cloths at that time were generally expensive.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Sengoku period (the period of Warring States) in Japan, it was possible to discern the ranks of warriors killed in war by checking whether they were wearing fundoshi loincloths or not, since cloths at that time were generally expensive.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>当時は麻が主流であったが、江戸時代に入り木綿に代り、武士の他に一般庶民にも普及するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In those days hemps were mostly used, but later in the Edo period they were replaced by cottons which made fundoshi loincloths popular among the common people beside warriors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In those days hemps were mostly used, but later in the Edo period they were replaced by cotton which made fundoshi loincloths popular among the common people beside warriors.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In those days hemps were mostly used, but later in the Edo period they were replaced by cotton which made fundoshi loincloths popular among the common people beside warriors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>一部の上流階層は縮緬などを用いていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some upper class people wore fundoshi loincloths made of chirimen (crepe fabrics).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some upper class people wore fundoshi loincloths made of chirimen (crepe fabrics).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some upper class people wore fundoshi loincloths made of chirimen (crepe fabrics).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>第二次世界大戦までは日本人成人男性の主な下着となっていたが、戦後、洋装化が進んだことや、ブリーフ、トランクス等の新しい下着が出現したことで、急速に廃れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Until World War II, fundoshi loincloths had been main underwear for adult men, but, since the end of the war, they fell rapidly into disuse because of emergence of new style underwear such as briefs, trunks and so on along with westernization of men&apos;s wear.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Until World War II, fundoshi loincloths had been the main underwear for adult men, but, since the end of the war, they fell rapidly into disuse because of the emergence of new style underwear such as briefs, trunks and so on along with the westernization of men&apos;s wear.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Until World War II, fundoshi loincloths had been the main underwear for adult men, but, since the end of the war, they fell rapidly into disuse because of the emergence of new style underwear such as briefs, trunks and so on along with the westernization of men&apos;s wear.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>褌の由来は南方伝来説と大陸伝来説があるが、定説はない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">No theory is established yet about the origin of fundoshi loincloths, although there are two conflicting ideas that they had come to Japan either from southern countries or through the Continent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">No theory has been established yet about the origin of fundoshi loincloths, although there are two conflicting ideas that they had come to Japan either from southern countries or through the Continent.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">No theory has been established yet about the origin of fundoshi loincloths, although there are two conflicting ideas that they had come to Japan either from southern countries or through the Continent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>南方伝来説の根拠は、東南アジア、ポリネシアや南アメリカ地区で六尺褌とほぼ同形状のものがあることから言われる説である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The idea that fundoshi loincloths were brought in from south is based on the fact that there are found some items that resemble in shape to a rokushaku fundoshi loincloth (a long loincloth of about 2.4 meter length) in Southeast Asia, Polynesia and South America.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The idea that fundoshi loincloths were brought in from the south is based on the fact that some items that resemble in shape to a rokushaku fundoshi loincloth (a long loincloth of about 2.4 meter length) were found in Southeast Asia, Polynesia and South America.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The idea that fundoshi loincloths were brought in from the south is based on the fact that some items that resemble in shape to a rokushaku fundoshi loincloth (a long loincloth of about 2.4 meter length) were found in Southeast Asia, Polynesia and South America.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>一方、大陸伝来説は、中国大陸に「特鼻褌」（とくびこん）と呼ばれる、男性の局部が牛の鼻のように見える褌が日本に伝来したとの説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the otherhand, another idea that fundoshi loincloths were introduced from the Continent claims that there existed in the Chinese Continent a special fundoshi loincloth called &quot;tokubi-kon&quot; with which men&apos;s privates appear like a nose of bovine.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the otherhand, another idea that fundoshi loincloths were introduced from the Continent claims that there existed in the Chinese Continent a special fundoshi loincloth called &quot;tokubi-kon&quot; with which men&apos;s privates appeared like the nose of a cow.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the otherhand, another idea that fundoshi loincloths were introduced from the Continent claims that there existed in the Chinese Continent a special fundoshi loincloth called &quot;tokubi-kon&quot; with which men&apos;s privates appeared like the nose of a cow.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>日本の祭事に六尺褌が多いのは、南方伝来の六尺褌が根底文化にあり、大陸文化との折衷が始まり、時代を経て簡略化された越中褌が生まれたとの説が一部で唱えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is partly claimed that roku-shaku fundoshi (a long rectangular loincloth of about 2.4 meter length) is now largely worn on the occasion of festivals in Japan because the roku-shaku fundoshi imported from south had been incorporated into the basic culture of Japan, and then the Continental culture began fusing into the Japanese culture, while fundoshi itself became simplified through ages to the present form of Ecchu fundoshi (a simple rectangular loincloth with strings).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is partly claimed that roku-shaku fundoshi (a long rectangular loincloth of about 2.4 meter length) is now largely worn on the festive occasions in Japan because the roku-shaku fundoshi imported from the south had been incorporated into the basic culture of Japan, and then the Continental culture began fusing into the Japanese culture, while fundoshi itself became simplified through the ages to the present form of Ecchu fundoshi (a simple rectangular loincloth with strings).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is partly claimed that roku-shaku fundoshi (a long rectangular loincloth of about 2.4 meter length) is now largely worn on the festive occasions in Japan because the roku-shaku fundoshi imported from the south had been incorporated into the basic culture of Japan, and then the Continental culture began fusing into the Japanese culture, while fundoshi itself became simplified through the ages to the present form of Etchu fundoshi (a simple rectangular loincloth with strings).</e>
<cmt>Ecchu→Etchuとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>語源</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Origin of the word:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Origin of the word:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Origin of the Word</e>
<cmt>コロン削除、頭文字を大文字に変更</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="14">
<j>「踏通（ふみとおし）」「踏絆（ふもだし）、馬や犬を繋ぎ止める綱」「絆す（ほだす）、動かないよう縄等で繋ぎ止める」から由来するという説が一般的である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The word &quot;fundoshi&quot; is commonly believed to have come from &quot;fumitoshi&quot; (meaning &quot;to outthrust both legs&quot;), or from &quot;fumodashi&quot; (meaning &quot;a rope to tie down a horse or a dog&quot;), or from &quot;hodasu&quot; (meaning &quot;to tie down something by a rope in order not to move freely&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The word &quot;fundoshi&quot; is commonly believed to have come from &quot;fumitoshi&quot; (meaning &quot;to outthrust both legs&quot;), or from &quot;fumodashi&quot; (meaning &quot;a rope to tie down a horse or a dog&quot;), or from &quot;hodasu&quot; (meaning &quot;to tie down something by a rope so that it will not move freely&quot;).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The word &quot;fundoshi&quot; is commonly believed to have come from &quot;fumitoshi&quot; (meaning &quot;to outthrust both legs&quot;), or from &quot;fumodashi&quot; (meaning &quot;a rope to tie down a horse or a dog&quot;), or from &quot;hodasu&quot; (meaning &quot;to tie down something by a rope so that it will not move freely&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>元来日本語には「ん」という発音の言葉がなかったことから、漢語の「褌衣」を韓国語化した「Hun-t-os,（フントス）」からくるという説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another conception suggests that the word &quot;fundoshi&quot; originates from &quot;Hun-t-os&quot; (pronounced as &quot;funtos&quot;) that is a Koreanized word of Chinese &quot;kon-i&quot; (literally, &quot;fundoshi wear&quot;), as Japanese language had primitively no word including a pronunciation of &quot;n.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another conception suggests that the word &quot;fundoshi&quot; originates from &quot;Hun-t-os&quot; (pronounced as &quot;funtos&quot;) that is a Koreanized word of Chinese &quot;kon-i&quot; (literally, &quot;fundoshi wear&quot;), as Japanese language had primitively no word including a pronunciation of &quot;n.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another conception suggests that the word &quot;fundoshi&quot; originates from &quot;Hun-t-os&quot; (pronounced as &quot;funtos&quot;) that is a Koreanized word of Chinese &quot;kon-i&quot; (literally, &quot;fundoshi wear&quot;), as Japanese language had primitively no word including a pronunciation of &quot;n.&quot;</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース消去</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>また古語においてはふんどしは「犢鼻褌（たふさぎ）」といった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In ancient words, fundoshi was called &quot;tafusagi.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In ancient language, fundoshi was called &quot;tafusagi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>rewrote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In ancient language, fundoshi was called &quot;tafusagi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>これの由来についても「股塞ぎ（またふさぎ）」「布下げ（たふさげ）」「タブ（樹皮布）裂き」など諸説ある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This ancient word &quot;tafusagi&quot; is also conceived to have originated in various archaism such as &quot;mata-fusagi&quot; (meaning &quot;crotch covering&quot;), &quot;tafusage&quot; (meaning &quot;draping cloth&quot;), &quot;tabu-saki&quot; (meaning &quot;torn cloth made of a bark&quot; and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This ancient language &quot;tafusagi&quot; is also conceived to have originated in various archaisms such as &quot;mata-fusagi&quot; (meaning &quot;crotch covering&quot;), &quot;tafusage&quot; (meaning &quot;draping cloth&quot;), &quot;tabu-saki&quot; (meaning &quot;torn cloth made of a bark&quot; and so on.</e>
<cmt>rewrote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This ancient language &quot;tafusagi&quot; is also conceived to have originated in various archaisms such as &quot;mata-fusagi&quot; (meaning &quot;crotch covering&quot;), &quot;tafusage&quot; (meaning &quot;draping cloth&quot;), &quot;tabu-saki&quot; (meaning &quot;torn cloth made of a bark&quot;) and so on.</e>
<cmt>カッコ不足分追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>アイヌ語で「テパ」(tepa)と呼ぶのも同じ語源からくるのではないかと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Tepa&quot; in the Ainu language seems to have shared the same origin with the ancient Japanese word &quot;tafusagi.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Tepa&quot; in the Ainu language seems to have shared the same origin with the ancient Japanese word &quot;tafusagi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Tepa&quot; in the Ainu language seems to have shared the same origin with the ancient Japanese word &quot;tafusagi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>九州の方言で「兵児帯」（へこおび）と呼ぶのは「へのこ」（陰茎の意）からくる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Hekoobi&quot; (meaning &quot;an undress belt&quot;) in Kyushu dialect is a word derived from &quot;henoko&quot; (meaning &quot;penis&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Hekoobi&quot; (meaning &quot;an undress belt&quot;) in Kyushu dialect is a word derived from &quot;henoko&quot; (meaning &quot;penis&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Hekoobi&quot; (meaning &quot;an undress belt&quot;) in Kyushu dialect is a word derived from &quot;henoko&quot; (meaning &quot;penis&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>材質</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Quality of materials:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Quality of materials:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Quality of Materials</e>
<cmt>コロン削除、頭文字を大文字に変更</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="20">
<j>一般的には木綿の晒布が多く使用される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Generally, most of fundoshi are made of bleached cotton cloth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Generally, most of fundoshi are made of bleached cotton cloth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Generally, most of fundoshi are made of bleached cotton cloth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>他に、新モス、スフ、絹（シルク）、麻 (繊維)等も使用される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other materials such as muslin, silk and hemp are also used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other materials such as muslin, silk and hemp are also used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other materials such as muslin, silk and hemp are also used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>着装感は生地の目が粗いものが柔らかく、生地が細かいものは硬めの感触となり、下着には目の粗い生地が用いられている方が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Coarse mesh cloth is used for underwear more than fine mesh cloth, because the former gives softer feeling while the latter gives rather rigid feeling.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Coarse mesh cloth is used for underwear more so than fine mesh cloth, because the former gives a softer feeling while the latter gives a rather rigid feeling.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Coarse mesh cloth is used for underwear more so than fine mesh cloth, because the former gives a softer feeling while the latter gives a rather rigid feeling.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>色は白色が多いが、赤、青などの色生地も使用されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">White is the dominant color but red, blue and other colors are also used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">White is the dominant color but red, blue and other colors are also used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">White is the dominant color but red, blue and other colors are also used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>、他に柄物などもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, patterned cloths are also used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, patterned cloths are also used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, patterned cloths are also used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>種類</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinds:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kinds:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinds</e>
<cmt>コロン削除</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="25">
<j>褌の種類は六尺褌、越中褌、畚（もっこ）褌、割褌、黒猫褌などの種類があり、締め方や形状が大きく異なる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are many kinds of fundoshi loincloth, such as roku-shaku fundoshi (a long rectangular loincloth of about 2.4 meters length), ecchu-fundoshi (a simple rectangular loincloth with strings), mokko fundoshi (a basket-like stringed loincloth), wari fundoshi (a rectangular loincloth partly split for tying), kuroneko fundoshi (a kind of jockstrap) and so on, each of which differs considerably in shape and in the way of tying.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are many kinds of fundoshi loincloth, such as roku-shaku fundoshi (a long rectangular loincloth of about 2.4 meters in length), ecchu-fundoshi (a simple rectangular loincloth with strings), mokko fundoshi (a basket-like stringed loincloth), wari fundoshi (a rectangular loincloth partly split for tying), kuroneko fundoshi (a kind of jockstrap) and so on, each of which differs considerably in shape and in the way of tying.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are many kinds of fundoshi loincloth, such as roku-shaku fundoshi, Etchu fundoshi, mokko fundoshi (a basket-like stringed loincloth), wari fundoshi (a rectangular loincloth partly split for tying), kuroneko fundoshi (a kind of jockstrap) and so on, each of which differs considerably in shape and in the way of tying.</e>
<cmt>roku-shaku fundoshi→既出のため補足削除、表記統一のため、ecchu-fundoshi→Etchu fundoshiとし補足削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>柄や色のある物も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are also many colored and patterned fundoshi loincloths.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are also many colored and patterned fundoshi loincloths.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are also many colored and patterned fundoshi loincloths.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>医療用の下着である越中褌T字帯も褌に含まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ecchu fundoshi T-jitai (T-shaped bandage) that is used as underwear for medical purpose is also included in the category of fundoshi loincloth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ecchu fundoshi T-jitai (T-shaped bandage) that is used as underwear for medical purposes is also included in the category of fundoshi loincloth.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Etchu fundoshi T-jitai (T-shaped bandage) that is used as underwear for medical purposes is also included in the category of fundoshi loincloth.</e>
<cmt>Etchu fundoshiとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>六尺褌</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rokushaku fundoshi (a long rectangular loincloth of about 2.4 meter length):</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rokushaku fundoshi (a long rectangular loincloth of about 2.4 meter in length):</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Roku-shaku Fundoshi</e>
<cmt>他の表記に合わせ、Roku-shaku Fundoshiとし補足削除、コロン削除</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="28">
<j>六尺褌は、長さ約180cm～300cm程度、幅約34cm～16cmのさらしの布を用いた日本人男性用の下着。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Rokushaku fundoshi&quot; is a kind of underwear for Japanese men, made of bleached cloth of about 180 - 300cm in length and 34 - 16cm in width.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Rokushaku fundoshi&quot; is a kind of underwear for Japanese men, made of bleached cloth of about 180 - 300cm in length and 34 - 16cm in width.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Rokushaku fundoshi&quot; is a kind of underwear for Japanese men, made of bleached cloth of about 180 - 300cm in length and 34 - 16cm in width.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>臀部が露出していることに特徴がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is characterized by exposing buttocks.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is characterized by exposing the buttocks.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is characterized by exposing the buttocks.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>現在では、下着に用いられるよりも、主に祭事や水着などで使用されることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today, it is often worn as festival wear and swimming wear rather than underwear.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, it is often worn as festival wear and swimming wear rather than underwear.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, it is often worn as festival wear and swimming wear rather than underwear.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>詳細は六尺褌を参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For details, please refer to the article &quot;Rokushaku Fundoshi.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For details, please refer to the article &quot;Rokushaku Fundoshi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For details, please refer to the article &quot;Roku-shaku Fundoshi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Roku-shakuとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>越中褌</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ecchu Fundoshi:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ecchu Fundoshi:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Etchu Fundoshi</e>
<cmt>Ecchu→Etchuとし、コロン削除</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="32">
<j>越中褌は、長さ100cm程度、幅34cm程度の布の端に紐をつけた下着。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Ecchu fundoshi&quot; is a kind of underwear made of a rectangular cloth of about 100cm in length and about 34cm in width with strings on both sides.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Ecchu fundoshi&quot; is a kind of underwear made of a rectangular cloth of about 100cm in length and about 34cm in width with strings on both sides.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Etchu fundoshi&quot; is a kind of underwear made of a rectangular cloth of about 100cm in length and about 34cm in width with strings on both sides.</e>
<cmt>Ecchu→Etchuとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>一部では和製英語の越中褌クラシックパンツ、サムライパンツとも呼ばれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In some quarter, it is called &quot;ecchu fundoshi classic pants&quot; or &quot;samurai pants,&quot; both in wasei-eigo (English words coined in Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In some quarters, it is called &quot;ecchu fundoshi classic pants&quot; or &quot;samurai pants,&quot; both in wasei-eigo (English words coined in Japan).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In some quarters, it is called &quot;Etchu fundoshi classic pants&quot; or &quot;samurai pants,&quot; both in wasei-eigo (English words coined in Japan).</e>
<cmt>Etchu fundoshiとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>医療用の下着である越中褌T字帯も越中褌の一種。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ecchu fundoshi T-jitai (T-shaped bandage) being used for medical purpose is regarded as a kind of ecchu fundoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ecchu fundoshi T-jitai (T-shaped bandage) is being used for medical purpose and is regarded as a kind of ecchu fundoshi.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Etchu fundoshi T-jitai (T-shaped bandage) is being used for medical purpose and is regarded as a kind of Etchu fundoshi.</e>
<cmt>Etchu fundoshiとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>禊の時に使われる場合が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is often worn on the occasion of misogi (a purification ceremony).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is often worn on the occasion of misogi (a purification ceremony).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is often worn on the occasion of misogi (a purification ceremony).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>その他、一部の裸祭りでは六尺褌に代って、こちらが使われる場合がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, it is used in some hadaka-matsuri (a Japanese festival in which the men go naked except for fundoshi loincloth) instead of roku-shaku fundoshi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, it is used in some hadaka-matsuri (a Japanese festival in which the men go naked except for fundoshi loincloth) instead of roku-shaku fundoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, it is used in some hadaka-matsuri (a Japanese festival in which the men go naked except for fundoshi loincloth) instead of roku-shaku fundoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>詳細は越中褌を参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For details, please refer to the article &quot;Ecchu Fundoshi.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For details, please refer to the article &quot;Ecchu Fundoshi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For details, please refer to the article &quot;Etchu Fundoshi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Ecchu→Etchuとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>畚（もっこ）褌</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mokko Fundoshi:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mokko Fundoshi:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mokko Fundoshi</e>
<cmt>コロン削除</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="38">
<j>長さ70cm程度、幅34cm程度の布の両端に紐を通したもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Mokko fundoshi&quot; is a kind of fundoshi loincloth made of a cloth of about 70cm in length and 34cm in width with strings put on two opposite sides of the cloth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Mokko fundoshi&quot; is a kind of fundoshi loincloth made of a cloth of about 70cm in length and 34cm in width with strings put on two opposite sides of the cloth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Mokko fundoshi&quot; is a kind of fundoshi loincloth made of a cloth of about 70cm in length and 34cm in width with strings put on two opposite sides of the cloth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>土木工事等で土を運ぶ畚に形状が似ているためこの名がついたといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This fundoshi resembles mokko (a straw basket) for carrying earth at a site of civil works, after that it is said to have been named.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This fundoshi resembles mokko (a straw basket) for carrying earth at a site of civil works, after which it is said to have been named.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This fundoshi resembles mokko (a straw basket) for carrying earth at a site of civil works, after which it is said to have been named.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>歌舞伎の女形は、普段から、これを着用。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kabuki actors for female roles regularly wear this mokko fundoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kabuki actors of female roles regularly wear this mokko fundoshi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kabuki actors of female roles regularly wear this mokko fundoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>割褌</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wari Fundoshi:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wari Fundoshi:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wari Fundoshi</e>
<cmt>コロン削除</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="41">
<j>六越褌、とも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its another name is &quot;rokkoshi fundoshi.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its another name is &quot;rokkoshi fundoshi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its another name is &quot;rokkoshi fundoshi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>長さ150～160cm幅30～40cm程度の布を使用し、片一方の布端を約55～60cm程真中から切ってある褌。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is made of a cloth of 150cm - 160cm in length and 30cm - 40cm in width, a part of which is cut into two from the end of the cloth upto 55cm - 60cm in lengthwise direction.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is made of a cloth that is 150cm - 160cm in length and 30cm - 40cm in width, a part of which is cut into two from the end of the cloth upto 55cm - 60cm in the lengthwise direction.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is made of a cloth that is 150cm - 160cm in length and 30cm - 40cm in width, a part of which is cut into two from the end of the cloth upto 55cm - 60cm in the lengthwise direction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>切った部分を腰に巻く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The cut parts of the cloth are used to wrap around the waist.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The cut parts of the cloth are used to wrap around the waist.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The cut parts of the cloth are used to wrap around the waist.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>六尺褌と越中褌の中間的な物。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It goes miday between rokushaku fundoshi and ecchuu fundoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is midway between rokushaku fundoshi and ecchuu fundoshi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is midway between roku-shaku fundoshi and Etchu fundoshi.</e>
<cmt>roku-shakuとし、ecchuu→Etchuに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>戦国～江戸時代に掛けて一部の武将や大名に愛用された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was used habitually by some busho (Japanese military commanders) and daimyo (Japanese feudal lords) from the Sengoku period (the period of warring states) partially through the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was used habitually by some busho (Japanese military commanders) and daimyo (Japanese feudal lords) from the Sengoku period (the period of warring states) to partially through the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was used habitually by some busho (Japanese military commanders) and daimyo (Japanese feudal lords) from the Sengoku period (the period of warring states) to partially through the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース消去、Periodの頭文字を小文字に変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>黒猫褌</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kuroneko Fundoshi:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kuroneko Fundoshi:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kuroneko Fundoshi</e>
<cmt>コロン削除</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="46">
<j>戦前の水泳の授業などで使われた子供用の水褌（水着としての褌）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is equivalent to &quot;suikon&quot; (fundoshi loincloth used as swimming pants) that was used by children for their swimming lessons at school before World War II.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is equivalent to &quot;suikon&quot; (fundoshi loincloth used as swimming pants) that was used by children for their swimming lessons at school before World War II.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is equivalent to &quot;suikon&quot; (fundoshi loincloth used as swimming pants) that was used by children for their swimming lessons at school before World War II.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>広島県、長崎県では「キンツリ」、「三角兵子」と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called &quot;kintsuri&quot; and &quot;sankaku-heko&quot; in Hiroshima and Nagasaki Prefectures.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called &quot;kintsuri&quot; and &quot;sankaku-heko&quot; in Hiroshima and Nagasaki Prefectures.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called &quot;kintsuri&quot; and &quot;sankaku-heko&quot; in Hiroshima and Nagasaki Prefectures.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>畚（もっこ）褌の一種でTバックになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a kind of mokko fundoshi with a T-shaped back.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a kind of mokko fundoshi with a T-shaped back.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a kind of mokko fundoshi with a T-shaped back.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>大人はサポーターとして用いる場合が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For adults, it is often used as a jockstrap.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For adults, it is often used as a jockstrap.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For adults, it is often used as a jockstrap.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="50">
<j>昭和初期頃より登場し、簡易褌と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It became used since the beginning of the Showa period, being called &quot;kani-kon&quot; (literally, &quot;a simple fundoshi loincloth&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It became used since the beginning of the Showa period, being called &quot;kani-kon&quot; (literally, &quot;a simple fundoshi loincloth&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It became used since the beginning of the Showa period, being called &quot;kani-kon&quot; (literally, &quot;a simple fundoshi loincloth&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>生地は黒色の麻が用いられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As its material, black hemp cloths are used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As its material, black hemp cloth is used.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As its material, black hemp cloth is used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>名称の由来や出現は不明であるが、「黒猫」の名称は生地の黒色に由来している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though it is unknown from where and when the name &quot;kuroneko&quot; (literally, &quot;a black cat&quot;) came for use, it seems to have originated in the black color of the material fabric.</e>
<cmt>原文に矛盾があります。「由来や出現は不明である」としながら「黒色に由来している」と断定しています。ここでは、「由来しているようである」と読み替えて英訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though it is unknown from where and when the name &quot;kuroneko&quot; (literally, &quot;a black cat&quot;) came to be used, it seems to have originated from the black color of the material fabric.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though it is unknown from where and when the name &quot;kuroneko&quot; (literally, &quot;a black cat&quot;) came to be used, it seems to have originated from the black color of the material fabric.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>国民皆泳が叫ばれ水泳が学校の教科として取り上げられたことで、幼児～小学生用の水着として全国に普及し、昭和30年代頃まで各地で散見されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since swimming practice was widely encouraged as an universal movement throughout the nation and a swimming lesson was included in an official curriculum at primary schools, this kuroneko fundoshi loincloth became popular across the country as a swimming pants for children covering from infants to students of elementary schools and it could be found here and there in Japan untill around 1955.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since swimming practice was widely encouraged as anuniversal movement throughout the nation and swimming lessons were included in the official curriculum of primary schools, this kuroneko fundoshi loincloth became popular across the country as swimming pants for children covering from infants to students of elementary schools and it could be found here and there in Japan until around 1955.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since swimming practice was widely encouraged as anuniversal movement throughout the nation and swimming lessons were included in the official curriculum of primary schools, this kuroneko fundoshi loincloth became popular across the country as swimming pants for children covering from infants to students of elementary schools and it could be found here and there in Japan until around 1955.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>廻し</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mawashi:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mawashi:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mawashi</e>
<cmt>コロン削除</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="54">
<j>廻しは、日本の国技・相撲や一部の裸祭り、奉納相撲に使われる特殊な褌。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Mawashi&quot; is a particular kind of fundoshi loincloth typically used for sumo wrestling, a Japanese national sport, and for some hadaka-matsuri (a naked festival in which men go naked except for fundoshi loincloth) as well as for hono-sumo (a ritual sumo match held at a shrine).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Mawashi&quot; is a particular kind of fundoshi loincloth typically used for sumo wrestling, a Japanese national sport, and for some hadaka-matsuri (a naked festival in which men go naked except for fundoshi loincloth) as well as for hono-sumo (a ritual sumo match held at a shrine).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Mawashi&quot; is a particular kind of fundoshi loincloth typically used for sumo wrestling, a Japanese national sport, and for some hadaka-matsuri (a naked festival in which men go naked except for fundoshi loincloth) as well as for honozumo (a ritual sumo match held at a shrine).</e>
<cmt>hono-sumo→honozumoに修正 (用語集およびhttp://kotobank.jp/word/%E5%A5%89%E7%B4%8D%E7%9B%B8%E6%92%B2)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>色・材質・締め方が他の褌とは異なる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mawashi is different from other fundoshi loincloths in its color, material and a way of fastening.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mawashi is different from other fundoshi loincloths in its color, material and way of fastening.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mawashi is different from other fundoshi loincloths in its color, material and way of fastening.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>詳細は廻しを参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For details, please refer to the article &quot;Mawashi.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For details, please refer to the article &quot;Mawashi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For details, please refer to the article &quot;Mawashi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>締め込み</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shimekomi :</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shimekomi :</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shimekomi</e>
<cmt>コロン削除</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="57">
<j>福岡市博多区で毎年7月に行われる博多祇園山笠や、その他の裸祭りの装束として使われる褌。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Shimekomi&quot; is another kind of fundoshi loincloth used as a costume for hadaka-matsuri (naked festivals) including Hakata Gion Yamagasa, a summer festival held in July every year at Hakata Ward, Fukuoka City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Shimekomi&quot; is another kind of fundoshi loincloth used as a costume for hadaka-matsuri (naked festivals) including Hakata Gion Yamagasa, a summer festival held in July every year at Hakata Ward, Fukuoka City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Shimekomi&quot; is another kind of fundoshi loincloth used as a costume for hadaka-matsuri (naked festivals) including Hakata Gion Yamagasa, a summer festival held in July every year at Hakata Ward, Fukuoka City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>締め方や材質は、博多では廻しに近い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This shimekomi loincloth used in Hakata festival is similar to a mawashi loincloth in its material and fastening method.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This shimekomi loincloth used in Hakata festival is similar to the mawashi loincloth in its material and method of fastening.</e>
<cmt>rewrote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This shimekomi loincloth used in Hakata festival is similar to the mawashi loincloth in its material and method of fastening.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>.但し、生地の厚さは晒と廻しの中間くらい、薄めの帆布や重ねた木綿の洋服地に近い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, thickness of its material cloth stands in between those of sarashi and mawashi loincloths, being similar to rather thin canvas or superimposed cotton fabrics for cotton dress.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the thickness of its material cloth is between those of the sarashi and mawashi loincloths, being similar to rather thin canvas or superimposed cotton fabrics for cotton dress.</e>
<cmt>rewrote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the thickness of its material cloth is between those of the sarashi and mawashi loincloths, being similar to rather thin canvas or superimposed cotton fabrics for cotton dress.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>前垂れを出す場合が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It often hangs maedare (an apron).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It often hangs maedare (an apron).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It often hangs maedare (an apron).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>博多以外では5mの、さらしを廻しと同様に締め込む場合が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In other places than Hakata, people often tie up a sarashi loincloth of five meter long in the same way as a mawashi loincloth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In other places than Hakata, people often tie up a sarashi loincloth of five meters long in the same way as a mawashi loincloth.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In other places than Hakata, people often tie up a sarashi loincloth of five meters long in the same way as a mawashi loincloth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>何れの場合も横褌の幅を広くし(7～12cm)、後の結び目を廻しと同様にする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In any case, the width of loincloth at both sides of body should be kept wide (between seven and twelve centimeters) and a knot at the rear should be tied in the same way as a mawashi loincloth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In any case, the width of the loincloth on both sides of body should be kept wide (between seven and twelve centimeters) and a knot at the rear should be tied in the same way as a mawashi loincloth.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In any case, the width of the loincloth on both sides of body should be kept wide (between seven and twelve centimeters) and a knot at the rear should be tied in the same way as a mawashi loincloth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>廻し、六尺褌、九尺褌、晒一反を指す場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In some cases, the word &quot;shimekomi&quot; may indicate mawashi, rokushaku fundoshi, kyuushaku fundoshi and sarashi ittan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In some cases, the word &quot;shimekomi&quot; may indicate mawashi, rokushaku fundoshi, kyuushaku fundoshi and sarashi ittan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In some cases, the word &quot;shimekomi&quot; may indicate mawashi, roku-shaku fundoshi, kyu-shaku fundoshi and sarashi ittan.</e>
<cmt>roku-shaku、kyu-shakuとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>晒一反</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sarashi Ittan:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sarashi Ittan:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sarashi Ittan</e>
<cmt>コロン削除</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="64">
<j>下帯、とも呼ばれる、さらし1反分(10m)を、丸ごと使うふんどし。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Sarashi ittan,&quot; which is also called &quot;shitaobi,&quot; is one of fundoshi loincloths using a full bolt (10 meters) of bleached cloth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Sarashi ittan,&quot; which is also called &quot;shitaobi,&quot; is one of fundoshi loincloths where a full bolt (10 meters) of bleached cloth is used.</e>
<cmt>rewrote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Sarashi ittan,&quot; which is also called &quot;shitaobi,&quot; is one of fundoshi loincloths where a full bolt (10 meters) of bleached cloth is used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>1枚の布で褌と腹巻きを兼ねる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One piece of cloth serves for both fundoshi and haramaki (a bellyband).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One piece of cloth serves as both fundoshi and haramaki (a bellyband).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One piece of cloth serves as both fundoshi and haramaki (a bellyband).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>着物用の下着として使われる他、玉せせりや、愛知県等の真冬の裸祭りで使われる場合が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">People wear it as underwear for kimono as well as a costume for the Tamaseseri festival and other naked winter festivals in Aich Prefecture and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">People wear it as underwear for kimono as well as a costume for the Tamaseseri festival and other naked winter festivals in Aich Prefecture and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">People wear it as underwear for kimono as well as a costume for the Tamaseseri festival and other naked winter festivals in Aich Prefecture and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>褌と兼用せず、越中褌、締め込み、ステテコと併用する場合も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Instead of its dual-use for both fundoshi and haramaki, it is often worn separately in parallel with ecchu fundoshi loincloth, shimekomi loincloth and suteteko (half-long undershorts).</e>
<cmt>「ステテコ」は用語集では単に&quot;men&apos;s underwear&quot;となっていますが、ここではより具体的に&quot;half-long undershorts&quot;としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Instead of its dual-use for both fundoshi and haramaki, it is often worn separately in parallel with ecchu fundoshi loincloth, shimekomi loincloth and suteteko (semi-long undershorts).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Instead of its dual-use for both fundoshi and haramaki, it is often worn separately in parallel with Etchu fundoshi loincloth, shimekomi loincloth and suteteko (semi-long undershorts).</e>
<cmt>Etchu fundoshiとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>九尺褌</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyushaku Fundoshi:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyushaku Fundoshi:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyu-shaku Fundoshi</e>
<cmt>コロン削除、Kyu-shakuとしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="68">
<j>長崎県雲仙市（旧・国見町 (長崎県)）の伝統芸能「鳥刺し踊り」に使われる褌。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kyushaku fundoshi&quot; (a longer fundoshi loincloth of about 3.6 meter length) is worn for the traditional art &quot;Torisashi dancing&quot; being performed in Unzen City, Nagasaki Prefecture (former Kunimi Town, Nagasaki Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kyushaku fundoshi&quot; (a longer fundoshi loincloth of about 3.6 meter in length) is worn for the traditional art &quot;Torisashi dancing&quot; that is performed in Unzen City, Nagasaki Prefecture (former Kunimi Town, Nagasaki Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Kyu-shaku fundoshi&quot; (a longer fundoshi loincloth of about 3.6 meter in length) is worn for the traditional art &quot;Torisashi dancing&quot; that is performed in Unzen City, Nagasaki Prefecture (former Kunimi Town, Nagasaki Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>Kyu-shakuとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>股間を通した布を胸まで引き上げて締める独特の形をしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is tied in an unique style that a loincloth through one&apos;s groin is pulled up to be tightened at the position of one&apos;s breast.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is tied in a unique style where a loincloth that goes through one&apos;s groin is pulled up to be tightened at the position of one&apos;s breast.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is tied in a unique style where a loincloth that goes through one&apos;s groin is pulled up to be tightened at the position of one&apos;s breast.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>本来は漁師が着用したふんどしで、廻しと同様に着用。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was originally worn by fishermen in the same way as a mawashi loincloth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was originally worn by fishermen in the same way as a mawashi loincloth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was originally worn by fishermen in the same way as a mawashi loincloth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="14">
<tit>
<j>サイジ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saiji:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saiji:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saiji</e>
<cmt>コロン削除</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="71">
<j>石川県舳倉島の海人が身につけていた褌。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Saiji&quot; was a fundoshi loincloth worn by woman divers of Hegurajima island, Ishikawa Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>「海女」を&quot;woman divers&quot;としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Saiji&quot; was a fundoshi loincloth worn by female divers of Hegurajima island, Ishikawa Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Saiji&quot; was a fundoshi loincloth worn by female divers of Hegura-jima Island, Ishikawa Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>Hegurajima island→Hegura-jima Islandとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>非常に布面積の小さい越中褌の一種で現在のTバックに近い形状。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was a kind of ecchu fundoshi loincloth made of a very small size cloth, similar to a current T-back swim suit.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was a kind of ecchu fundoshi loincloth made of a very small sized cloth, similar to the current T-back swim suit.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was a kind of Etchu fundoshi loincloth made of a very small sized cloth, similar to the current T-back swim suit.</e>
<cmt>Etchu fundoshiとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>前垂れ、前袋にあたる部分は3角形の刺し子で、残りはロープ状。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It consisted of an apron or front sack of a triangle quilted cloth and the rest parts in a ropelike shape.</e>
<cmt>「刺子」を&quot;a quilted cloth&quot;としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It consisted of an apron or front sack made of a triangle quilted cloth and the rest parts in a ropelike shape.</e>
<cmt>rewrote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It consisted of an apron or front sack made of a triangle quilted cloth and the rest parts in a ropelike shape.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>横褌を巻きつけたあと、前垂れの部分を外から横褌に巻きつける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After tightening yokomitsu (parts of fundoshi loincloth at right and left sides of the body), a part of apron is tucked into yokomitsu from outside.</e>
<cmt>「横褌」は訳文のとおりに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After tightening the yokomitsu (parts of fundoshi loincloth on the right and left sides of the body), a part of the apron is tucked into the yokomitsu from outside.</e>
<cmt>rewrote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After tightening the yokomitsu (parts of fundoshi loincloth on the right and left sides of the body), a part of the apron is tucked into the yokomitsu from outside.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="15">
<tit>
<j>下がり</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sagari:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sagari:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sagari</e>
<cmt>コロン削除</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="75">
<j>歌舞伎や時代劇の衣装(股道具)として作られた、最初から見せることを目的に作られた特殊なふんどし。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Sagari&quot; is a special fundoshi loincloth made particularly for showing purpose as a costume (crotch gear) for players of Kabuki and jidaigeki (period dramas) on stage.</e>
<cmt>①「股道具」を「股に付ける衣装」という意味に解釈し、&quot;crotch gear&quot;と訳しました。②「下がり」は用語集では&quot;a (sumo wrestler&apos;s) string apron&quot;（『新和英大辞典』）とされていますが、ここでは該当しません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Sagari&quot; is a special fundoshi loincloth made particularly for showing purpose as a costume (crotch gear) for players of Kabuki and jidaigeki (period dramas) on stage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Sagari&quot; is a special fundoshi loincloth made particularly for showing purpose as a costume (crotch gear) for players of Kabuki and jidaigeki (period dramas) on stage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>歌舞伎ではマタギ、素人歌舞伎ではキン隠しと呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is called &quot;matagi&quot; in Kabuki and &quot;kin-kakushi&quot; in amateur Kabuki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is called &quot;matagi&quot; in Kabuki and &quot;kin-kakushi&quot; in amateur Kabuki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is called &quot;matagi&quot; in Kabuki and &quot;kin-kakushi&quot; in amateur Kabuki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>越中に似ているが、前垂れと股間の布(晒し)が別々になっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It resembles ecchu loincloth except that its apron is separated from the crotch covering cloth (bleached cloth).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It resembles ecchu loincloth except that its apron is separated from the cloth covering the crotch (bleached cloth).</e>
<cmt>rewrote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It resembles Etchu loincloth except that its apron is separated from the cloth covering the crotch (bleached cloth).</e>
<cmt>Etchuとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>前垂れは武士役は白の方形の羽二重や縮緬、「粋な江戸の色男」役では赤の方形の羽二重や縮緬、町人役は白の三角形の晒しとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A performer of the role of samurai puts on an apron made of a white rectangular cloth of habutae (thick silk fabrics) or chirimen (silk crepe fabrics), and a performer of the role of &quot;a stylish playboy in Edo&quot; wears an apron made of a red rectangular cloth of habutae or chirimen, while a performer of the role of a common townsman wears an apron of a white bleached triangle cloth..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A performer that plays the role of a samurai puts on an apron made of a white rectangular cloth of habutae (thick silk fabrics) or chirimen (silk crepe fabrics), and a performer that plays the role of &quot;a stylish playboy in Edo&quot; wears an apron made of a red rectangular cloth of habutae or chirimen, while a performer that plays the role of a common townsman wears an apron of a white bleached triangle cloth..</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A performer that plays the role of a samurai puts on an apron made of a white rectangular cloth of habutae (thick silk fabrics) or chirimen (silk crepe fabrics), and a performer that plays the role of &quot;a stylish playboy in Edo&quot; wears an apron made of a red rectangular cloth of habutae or chirimen, while a performer that plays the role of a common townsman wears an apron of a white bleached triangle cloth.</e>
<cmt>余分なピリオド削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>荒事や繻子奴、等、勇猛な男性の役では伊達下がりと呼ばれる廻し化粧廻しに似た豪華で重厚な下がりになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A player of the role of a dauntless man such as aragoto (a Kabuki player featuring exagerated gruffness of samurai etc.) and shusu-yakko (a man who is good at fight and favorite with women but basically faithful and serious) wears a gorgeous and massive sagari loincloth called &quot;Date-sagari&quot; which looks like kesho-mawashi (a sumo wrestler&apos;s ceremonial apron).</e>
<cmt>①一原文一訳文の例外対処　②「荒事」は単語登録では&quot;aragoto (Kabuki play featuring exaggerated posture, makeup, and costume)&quot;と訳されていますが、「武士などの荒々しさを誇張して演じる役＝荒事師）の意味に解釈して訳しました。 ③「繻子奴」は「ケンカ強くて忠義に厚く、女にモテて軽いところもあるけど根は真面目ないいやつ」という意味に解釈して訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A player of the role of a dauntless man such as aragoto (a Kabuki player featuring exaggerated gruffness of samurai etc.) and shusu-yakko (a man who is good at fighting and a favorite with women but basically faithful and serious) wears a gorgeous and massive sagari loincloth called &quot;Date-sagari&quot; which looks like kesho-mawashi (a sumo wrestler&apos;s ceremonial apron).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A player of the role of a dauntless man such as aragoto (a Kabuki player featuring exaggerated gruffness of samurai etc.) and shusu-yakko (a man who is good at fighting and a favorite with women but basically faithful and serious) wears a gorgeous and massive sagari loincloth called &quot;Date-sagari&quot; which looks like kesho-mawashi (a sumo wrestler&apos;s ceremonial apron).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>一部の祭り・郷土芸能でも着用。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This gorgeous sagari loincloth is also worn in some festivals and local performing arts.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This gorgeous sagari loincloth is also worn in some festivals and local performing arts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This gorgeous sagari loincloth is also worn in some festivals and local performing arts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>肉襦袢、または下着の褌の上に着用。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is worn on niku-juban (fleshings) or over fundoshi loincloth worn as underwear.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is worn on niku-juban (fleshings) or over fundoshi loincloth that is worn as underwear.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is worn on niku-juban (fleshings) or over fundoshi loincloth that is worn as underwear.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="82">
<j>また着用する役者、俳優によって二重に仕立てた下がりの下の部分の左右に鉛のおもりを入れて(五円玉が適当な重さ)、きれいに垂れ下がるように見せている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Depending on players or actors, an apron of the sagari loincloth is made in double layers, at the bottom of which two lead weights (each weight of five yen coin is appropriate) are put at the right and left ends, in order to show the apron droop down smartly.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Depending on the players or actors, an apron of the sagari loincloth is made in double layers, at the bottom of which two lead weights (each weight of five yen coin is appropriate) are put on the right and left ends, in order to make the apron droop down neatly.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Depending on the players or actors, an apron of the sagari loincloth is made in double layers, at the bottom of which two lead weights (each weight of five yen coin is appropriate) are put on the right and left ends, in order to make the apron droop down neatly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>その形も少し「丸み」ができるように「分銅状」の形にしたりsしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, the shape of apron is modified into that of sash weight in order to round off the apron.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, the shape of the apron is modified into that of a sash weight in order to round off the apron.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, the shape of the apron is modified into that of a sash weight in order to round off the apron.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>このように、股を割ったとき、いかに下がりがきれいに見えるかという様々な工夫が見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, various ideas are devised to make the apron of sagari loincloth hang down beautifully when a player or actor spreads his legs to squat.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, various ideas have been devised to make the apron of sagari loincloth hang down beautifully when a player or actor spreads his legs to squat.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, various ideas have been devised to make the apron of sagari loincloth hang down beautifully when a player or actor spreads his legs to squat.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="85">
<j>時代劇のふんどしも参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also please refer to the article of &quot;Fundoshi for Period Dramas.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also please refer to the article of &quot;Fundoshi for Period Dramas.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also please refer to the article of &quot;Fundoshi for Period Dramas.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="16">
<tit>
<j>半タコ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hantako:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hantako:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hantako</e>
<cmt>コロン削除</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="86">
<j>半タコは褌ではないが、ここで取り上げておく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though &quot;Hantako&quot; is not regarded as a kind of fundoshi loincloth, we take it up here for explanation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though &quot;Hantako&quot; is not regarded as a kind of fundoshi loincloth, we take it up here for explanation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though &quot;Hantako&quot; is not regarded as a kind of fundoshi loincloth, we take it up here for explanation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>日本版トランクス。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hantako is a Japanese version of trunks.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hantako is a Japanese version of trunks.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hantako is a Japanese version of trunks.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>猿股、ステテコ、木股とも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called sarumata, suteteko and kimata.</e>
<cmt>「木股」の意味不詳。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called sarumata, suteteko and kimata.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called sarumata, suteteko and kimata.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>明治以降に一般化した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the Meiji period, it became popular.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It became popular since the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It became popular since the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>時代劇や素人歌舞伎で使われる場合が多いが、時代考証上は誤りとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is now often worn by players of jidai-geki (period dramas) and amateur Kabuki, but the result of historical research denies the credibility of their background to wear hantako.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is now often it is worn by players of jidai-geki (dramas on the eras) and amateur Kabuki, but the result of historical research denies the credibility of their background of wearing hantako.</e>
<cmt>rewrote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is now often it is worn by players of jidai-geki (dramas on the eras) and amateur Kabuki, but the result of historical research denies the credibility of their background of wearing hantako.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>裸祭り(褌を着用しない場合)で多用される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is often used on the occasion of naked festivals (unless fundoshi loincloths are used.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is often used on the occasion of naked festivals (unless fundoshi loin cloths are used.)</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is often used on the occasion of naked festivals (unless fundoshi loin cloths are used).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>祭りによっては、御輿の担ぎ手に褌を禁止し、半タコ着用を指示する場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some festivals prohibit carriers of a portable shrine to wear fundoshi loincloths and instruct them to wear hantako trunks.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some festivals prohibit carriers of a portable shrine to wear fundoshi loincloths and instruct them to wear hantako trunks.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some festivals prohibit carriers of a portable shrine to wear fundoshi loincloths and instruct them to wear hantako trunks.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="17">
<tit>
<j>通過儀礼</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rite of Passage:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rite of Passage:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rite of Passage</e>
<cmt>コロン削除</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="93">
<j>日本の一部の地方では、通過儀礼として、一定年齢に達すると、成人を迎えた証として初めて褌を締める「褌祝」と言われる私的祭事がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In some regions in Japan, people celebrate a private festival called &quot;fundoshi iwai&quot; that is a rite of passage, where persons who reached a certain age would wear fundoshi loincloth for the first time as proof of attaining adulthood.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In some regions in Japan, people celebrate a private festival called &quot;fundoshi iwai&quot; that is a rite of passage, where persons who reached a certain age would wear fundoshi loincloth for the first time as proof of attaining adulthood.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In some regions in Japan, people celebrate a private festival called &quot;fundoshi iwai&quot; that is a rite of passage, where persons who reached a certain age would wear fundoshi loincloth for the first time as proof of attaining adulthood.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>褌は陰部を覆うことから性的機能を持ったものの象徴として扱われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A fundoshi loincloth, which covers genitals, is treated as a simbol of sexual ability.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A fundoshi loincloth, which covers the genitals, is treated as a symbol of sexual ability.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A fundoshi loincloth, which covers the genitals, is treated as a symbol of sexual ability.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>歌舞伎の演技の中で、着物の裾をはしょり、見得を切る場面などは、陰部や臀部を見せて褌を締めていることを表すことで、自分は成人した者であるとの証を象徴したものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On a Kabuki stage, a player who kilts hems of kimono to make a proud gesture is presenting himself as an adult by showing his pubic region and buttocks covered by a fundoshi loincloth.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On a Kabuki stage, a player who kilts hems of kimono to make a proud gesture is presenting himself as an adult by showing his pubic region and buttocks covered by a fundoshi loincloth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On a Kabuki stage, a player who kilts hems of kimono to make a proud gesture is presenting himself as an adult by showing his pubic region and buttocks covered by a fundoshi loincloth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>昔から、褌は成人の下着として位置付けられており、一定年齢に満たない幼児や子供が下着として褌を使用することはなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A fundoshi loincloth has always been regarded as adults&apos; underwear, and no infant nor child has worn it as underwear.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A fundoshi loincloth has always been regarded as adults&apos; underwear, and no infant nor child has worn it as underwear.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A fundoshi loincloth has always been regarded as adults&apos; underwear, and no infant nor child has worn it as underwear.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>幼児や子供は金太郎のような腹掛けが一般的だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Infants and children have generally worn bibs like Kintaro (a hero of a fairy tale) did.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Infants and children generally wore bibs like Kintaro (a hero of a fairy tale) did.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Infants and children generally wore bibs like Kintaro (a hero of a fairy tale) did.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>但し、福岡県では7歳で男児は「へこかき」、女児は「ゆもじかき」（湯文字）、と言う成人仕様の下着を初めて身につける地区がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in some districts in Fukuoka Prefecture, boys wear adults&apos; underwear called &quot;hekokaki&quot; and girls wear the same underwear called &quot;yumojikaki,&quot; when they become seven years old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in some districts in Fukuoka Prefecture, boys wear the adult&apos;s underwear called &quot;hekokaki&quot; and girls wear the same underwear called &quot;yumojikaki,&quot; when they become seven years old.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in some districts in Fukuoka Prefecture, boys wear the adult&apos;s underwear called &quot;hekokaki&quot; and girls wear the same underwear called &quot;yumojikaki,&quot; when they become seven years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>時代が洋装化に向かったことで、子供はパッチ（ステテコ）を使用するようになったが、第二次世界大戦前までは、成人してからは褌に代えるのが一般的だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before World War II, boys and girls in general used to change their underwear to fundoshi loincloth when they entered adulthood, though children had already begun wearing tight-fitting drawers (suteteko pants) along with the tendency toward westernizing style of dress.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before World War II, boys and girls in general used to change their underwear to fundoshi loincloth when they entered adulthood, though children had already begun wearing tight-fitting draws (suteteko pants) along with the tendency toward westernizing style of dress.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before World War II, boys and girls in general used to change their underwear to fundoshi loincloth when they entered adulthood, though children had already begun wearing tight-fitting draws (suteteko pants) along with the tendency toward westernizing style of dress.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="100">
<j>近代に入り、明治政府が徴兵令を制定し、国民皆兵が義務付けられ、徴兵検査を受けることが成人男子の証として社会的に認知されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the modern age, since the Meiji government instituted a conscription ordinance and made universal conscription compulsory, it became widely acknowledged in the society as proof of being manhood to undergo an examination for conscription.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the modern age, since the Meiji government instituted a conscription ordinance and made a universal conscription compulsory; it became widely acknowledged in the society as proof of reaching manhood to undergo an examination for conscription.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the modern age, since the Meiji government instituted a conscription ordinance and made a universal conscription compulsory; it became widely acknowledged in the society as proof of reaching manhood to undergo an examination for conscription.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>この徴兵検査の際に白い越中褌の着用が指導されることで、擬似的な「褌祝」に相当するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This examination for conscription became a pseudo &quot;fundoshi iwai,&quot; because the government instructed the people to wear a white ecchu fundoshi loincloth at all examination for conscription.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This examination for conscription became a pseudo &quot;fundoshi iwai,&quot; because the government instructed the people to wear a white ecchu fundoshi loincloth at all examinations for conscription.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This examination for conscription became a pseudo &quot;fundoshi iwai,&quot; because the government instructed the people to wear a white Etchu fundoshi loincloth at all examinations for conscription.</e>
<cmt>Etchu fundoshiとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>軍隊に入隊すると、白い越中褌が支給され、使用を強制された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Upon entering the military, every body was supplied with a white ecchu fundoshi and forced to use it..</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Upon entering the military, every body was supplied with a white ecchu fundoshi and was forced to use it..</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Upon entering the military, every body was supplied with a white Etchu fundoshi and was forced to use it.</e>
<cmt>余分なピリオド削除、Etchu fundoshiとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>こうして、当時の日本人成人男子は通過儀礼として誰もが「褌」を締めなければならない環境下に置かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, every Japanese adult man at that time was put under the circumstances that he had to wear &quot;fundoshi loincloth&quot; as a rite of passage.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, it was mandatory for every Japanese adult man had to wear &quot;fundoshi loincloth&quot; as a rite of passage.</e>
<cmt>rewrote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, it was mandatory for every Japanese adult man had to wear &quot;fundoshi loincloth&quot; as a rite of passage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="18">
<tit>
<j>愛好家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Devotees:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Devotees:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Devotees</e>
<cmt>コロン削除</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="104">
<j>一般に昔の下着と考えられがちだが、現在でも愛好家は存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though fundoshi loincloth is generally considered as the underwear of old days, there still exist devotees for it even today..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though fundoshi loincloth is generally considered as the underwear of olden days, some people are still devoted to using it even today.</e>
<cmt>rewrote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though fundoshi loincloth is generally considered the underwear of olden days, some people are still devoted to using it even today.</e>
<cmt>considered as→consideredとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>褌は、パンツのようにゴムを使わず、風呂敷のように、単純な一枚の布で機能が完結する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Unlike underpants, fundoshi loincloth includes no rubber, and like furoshiki (a wrapping cloth), it is made of just one sheet of simple cloth to complete its function.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unlike underpants, fundoshi loincloth includes no rubber, and like furoshiki (a wrapping cloth), it is made of just one sheet of simple cloth and that completes its function.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unlike underpants, fundoshi loincloth includes no rubber, and like furoshiki (a wrapping cloth), it is made of just one sheet of simple cloth and that completes its function.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>その「潔さ」が、日本人が古来から持つ「美意識」と共通するものがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This feeling of &quot;integrity&quot; of fundoshi loincloth shares the same interest with traditional Japanese &quot;aesthetic feeling,&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This perception that the fundoshi loincloth is &quot;gracious&quot; is the same perception shared by the traditional Japanese of an &quot;aesthetic sensation.&quot;</e>
<cmt>rewrote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This perception that the fundoshi loincloth is &quot;gracious&quot; is the same perception shared by the traditional Japanese of an &quot;aesthetic sensation.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>また、日本の古典的な理想の男子像にも例えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also likened to a Japanese classical ideal man&apos; image.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also likened to the image of a &quot;classical ideal Japanese man&quot;.</e>
<cmt>rewrote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also likened to the image of a &quot;classical ideal Japanese man.&quot;</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を移動、余分なスペース消去</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="108">
<j>褌を着用することで、虚飾を排し、時流に流されることなく本質を求道する理想の日本人男子像を具現化するものとして、褌にこだわりを抱く愛好家は少なくない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are a lot of devotees who consider that wearing of fundoshi loincloth is the way to realize an ideal image of Japanese men who pursue essences without being influenced by the flow of times, doing away with all ostentation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are a lots of devotees who consider that wearing the fundoshi loincloth is the way to portray the ideal image of a Japanese man who pursues essence without being influenced by the flow of times, doing away with all ostentation.</e>
<cmt>rewrote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are lots of devotees who consider that wearing the fundoshi loincloth is the way to portray the ideal image of a Japanese man who pursues essence without being influenced by the flow of times, doing away with all ostentation.</e>
<cmt>a lots of→lots ofに修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="109">
<j>これまでの愛好家は父親や祖父が愛用していたことで、近親者に勧められて本人も愛用するようになる受動的な例が多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the past, many became the passive devotees of fundoshi loincloth by following recommendations by close relatives including their fathers and grand fathers who regularly used fundoshi loincloth.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the past, many became passive devotees to the fundoshi loincloth by following the recommendations given by close relatives including their fathers and grand fathers who regularly used fundoshi loincloth.</e>
<cmt>rewrote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the past, many became passive devotees to the fundoshi loincloth by following the recommendations given by close relatives including their fathers and grand fathers who regularly used fundoshi loincloth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>新たな愛好家は、従前の例ではなく、周囲に愛用する者がいない中で、能動的に初めて褌を着用する例となっていることである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But, the newly emerged devotees are positive, unlike the precedented cases, in enjoying fundoshi loincloth for the first time even among the people who do not wear it.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But, the newly emerging devotees are positive, unlike their predecessors, in enjoying fundoshi loincloth for the first time even among the those who do not wear it.</e>
<cmt>rewrote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But, the newly emerging devotees are positive, unlike their predecessors, in enjoying fundoshi loincloth for the first time even among the those who do not wear it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>従来からの愛好家の高齢化が進み、高齢世代の愛好家人口は減少している一方で、新たな愛好家となるブリーフやトランクスしか知らない世代が出現している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While traditional devotees to fundoshi loincloth are aging and their population is decreasing, new devotees are emerging from the generation who knows only briefs and trunks.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While traditional devotees to fundoshi loincloth are now aging and their population is decreasing, new devotees are emerging from the generation that knows only briefs and trunks.</e>
<cmt>rewrote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While traditional devotees to fundoshi loincloth are now aging and their population is decreasing, new devotees are emerging from the generation that knows only briefs and trunks.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>諸外国にもない、日本独自の存在が新鮮な感覚を呼んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Uniqueness of fundoshi loincloth that does not exist in other countries than Japan is attracting fresh sensitivity of the people in the world..</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The uniqueness of fundoshi loincloth that does not exist in any country other than Japan is attracting fresh sensitivity of the people around the world..</e>
<cmt>rewrote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The uniqueness of fundoshi loincloth that does not exist in any country other than Japan is attracting fresh sensitivity of the people around the world.</e>
<cmt>余分なピリオド削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="113">
<j>新たな下着として褌の持つ機能や効能が着目されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fundoshi loincloth is calling public attention to its function and efficacy as a new underwear.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fundoshi loincloth is attracting public attention to its function and efficacy as a new underwear.</e>
<cmt>rewrote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fundoshi loincloth is attracting public attention to its function and efficacy as a new underwear.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="114">
<j>個性化の時代を迎えて、個人の主張が容認される成熟した社会となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Now the matured society has come, where any individual advocacy is generally accepted, along with the movement of individualization.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Now, the Japanese socieity is mature and so any individual advocacy is generally accepted, along with movements for individualization.</e>
<cmt>rewrote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Now, the Japanese socieity is mature and so any individual advocacy is generally accepted, along with movements for individualization.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース消去</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>新しい世代は褌を「過去の下着」としての旧来の偏見を持たなくなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The people of new generation have no longer any conventional prejudice to consider the fundoshi loincloths as &quot;underwear in the past.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The people of the new generation no longer have any conventional prejudices towards the fundoshi loincloths being used as &quot;underwear in the past.&quot;</e>
<cmt>rewrote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The people of the new generation no longer have any conventional prejudices towards the fundoshi loincloths being used as &quot;underwear in the past.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="116">
<j>これらのことが、新たな世代の愛好家を呼ぶ下地となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under such circumstances, new devotees for the fundoshi loincloths are uprising from the new generation..</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under such circumstances, new devotees to the fundoshi loincloths are arising from the new generation..</e>
<cmt>rewrote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under such circumstances, new devotees to the fundoshi loincloths are arising from the new generation.</e>
<cmt>余分なピリオド削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="117">
<j>日本人の洋装化が進んでも、日本の高温多湿な気候の中で褌の持つ下着としての優れた機能や効能からくる満足度はブリーフやトランクスよりも高い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">No matter how far the westernization might go through the Japanese dressing, high temperature and humidity in Japan would make the fundoshi loincloths more attractive and satisfactory than the briefs and trunks in their function and efficiency as underwear.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">No matter how far westernization might infiltrate Japanese way of dressing, the high temperatures and humidity in Japan would make the fundoshi loincloths more attractive and satisfactory than the briefs and trunks in their function and efficiency as underwear.</e>
<cmt>rewrote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">No matter how far westernization might infiltrate Japanese way of dressing, the high temperatures and humidity in Japan would make the fundoshi loincloths more attractive and satisfactory than the briefs and trunks in their function and efficiency as underwear.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="118">
<j>そのことや、独特の着装感から、新世代の愛好家が生まれるものと推測される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to such advantages of fundoshi loincloths, their unique feeling to wear is supposed to bring forth new devotees for them from the new generation.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to such advantages of fundoshi loincloths, their unique feeling when worn is supposed to bring forth new devotees for them from the new generation.</e>
<cmt>rewrote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to such advantages of fundoshi loincloths, their unique feeling when worn is supposed to bring forth new devotees for them from the new generation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="119">
<j>これまでは、戦前のように自家で縫製して使用するような環境でなくなり、また、一般の店頭にも並ぶこともなく入手性に難があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before World War II, fundoshi loincloth had been mostly homemade, but its circumstances changed so that no more homemade was available and it was also difficult to obtain at the shop.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before World War II, the fundoshi loincloth was mostly homemade, but circumstances changed so it is no longer homemade but it is also difficult to obtain it at the shop.</e>
<cmt>rewrote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before World War II, the fundoshi loincloth was mostly homemade, but circumstances changed so it is no longer homemade but it is also difficult to obtain it at the shop.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="120">
<j>しかし、インターネットの出現とそれに伴うインターネット通販の発達で、褌の製造販売を行う専門の業者等が生まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, recently, internet services have developed various mail order business among which evolved some dealers who are specialized in manufacturing and selling fundoshi loincloth.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, recently, various mail order businesses have developed due to internet services among which are some dealers who are specialized in manufacturing and selling fundoshi loincloth.</e>
<cmt>rewrote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, recently, various mail order businesses have developed due to internet services among which are some dealers who are specialized in manufacturing and selling fundoshi loincloth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="121">
<j>こうして、褌は容易に入手できるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, it has now become easy for us to obtain fundoshi loincloth.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, it has now become easy for us to obtain fundoshi loincloth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, it has now become easy for us to obtain fundoshi loincloth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="122">
<j>ネットワーク社会の到来と共に、褌に関する情報がネット等を通じて提供されるようになった。。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Networked society has also made it possible to offer any information on fundoshi loincloth through internet and other services.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The presence of network societies has also made it possible to offer any information on fundoshi loincloth through the internet and other services.</e>
<cmt>rewrote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The presence of network societies has also made it possible to offer any information on fundoshi loincloth through the internet and other services.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="123">
<j>こうして、現在でも数多くの愛好家が存在することが確認されるようになったことで、孤立がちな新たな世代の愛好家には、価値観を共有することで連帯感に似た心情を持つようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this way, many devotees of fundoshi loincloth are now surely existing everywhere in Japan, so that each devotee of the new generation is feeling no more isolated but sharing the common concept of value, accelerating a kind of the sense of unity.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this way, there are certainly many devotees of fundoshi loincloth everywhere in Japan, so, devotees of the new generation are no longer feeling isolated but are sharing the common concept of the value, and accelerating a kind of sense of unity.</e>
<cmt>rewrote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this way, there are certainly many devotees of fundoshi loincloth everywhere in Japan, so, devotees of the new generation are no longer feeling isolated but are sharing the common concept of the value, and accelerating a kind of sense of unity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="124">
<j>こうして、こだわりの愛好家を生む環境となっているようだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, the circumstances are now arranged to bring about new devotees with peculiar tastes.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, the present circumstances are such that new devotees with peculiar tastes are arising.</e>
<cmt>rewrote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, the present circumstances are such that new devotees with peculiar tastes are arising.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="125">
<j>六尺褌愛好者、越中褌愛好者も参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Please refer also to the articles &quot;Rokushaku Fundoshi Aikosha&quot; (devotees of rokushaku fundoshi loincloth) and &quot;Ecchu Fundoshi Aikosha&quot; (devotees of ecchu fundoshi loincloth).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Please refer also to the articles &quot;Rokushaku Fundoshi Aikosha&quot; (devotees to rokushaku fundoshi loincloth) and &quot;Ecchu Fundoshi Aikosha&quot; (devotees to ecchu fundoshi loincloth).</e>
<cmt>rewrote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Please refer also to the articles &quot;Roku-shaku Fundoshi Aikosha&quot; (devotees to roku-shaku fundoshi loincloth) and &quot;Etchu Fundoshi Aikosha&quot; (devotees to Etchu fundoshi loincloth).</e>
<cmt>Roku-shaku、roku-shaku、Etchuとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="19">
<tit>
<j>水着としての褌</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fundoshi Loincloths as Swimming Wear:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fundoshi Loincloths as Swim Wear:</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fundoshi Loincloths as Swim Wear</e>
<cmt>コロン削除</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="126">
<j>戦前までは日本人男性の水着は、褌が一般的であり、ほとんどが六尺褌であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before World War II, Japanese men&apos;s swimmin clothes were generally fundoshi loincloths, mostly rokushaku fundoshi loincloths.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before World War II, Japanese men&apos;s swim clothes were generally fundoshi loincloths, mostly rokushaku fundoshi loincloths.</e>
<cmt>rewrote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before World War II, Japanese men&apos;s swim clothes were generally fundoshi loincloths, mostly roku-shaku fundoshi loincloths.</e>
<cmt>roku-shaku fundoshiとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="127">
<j>六尺褌水着としての六尺褌も参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Please refer also to the article &quot;Rokushaku Fundoshi Mizugi tosite no Rokushaku Fundoshi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>「六尺褌水着としての六尺褌」の意味不明。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Please refer also to the article &quot;Rokushaku Fundoshi Mizugi tosite no Rokushaku Fundoshi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Please refer also to the article &quot;Roku-shaku Fundoshi Mizugi tosite no Roku-shaku Fundoshi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Roku-shaku Fundoshiとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="20">
<tit>
<j>時代劇の褌</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fundoshi Loincloths for Period Drama:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fundoshi Loincloths for Period Drama:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fundoshi Loincloths for Period Drama:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="128">
<j>かつて無声映画といわれた頃の時代劇映画では、ふんどしを露に見せての剣戟が盛んだった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In various period dramas made in the age of silent pictures, many sword fighting scenes were screened, where players used to demonstrate blatantly his fundoshi loincloth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In dramas on the various eras that were made in the age of silent pictures, many sword fighting scenes were screened, where players used to blatantly display their fundoshi loincloth.</e>
<cmt>rewrote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In dramas on the various eras that were made in the age of silent pictures, many sword fighting scenes were screened, where players used to blatantly display their fundoshi loincloth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="129">
<j>当時の人気スター、市川百之助による意識的にふんどしを見せるサービスに女性ファンは大喜びし、「フンドシももちゃん」と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Momonosuke ICHIKAWA, a popular star at the time, showed consciously his own fundoshi loincloth, with which services women admirers of him were much pleased and called him &quot;Fundoshi Momo-chan.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Momonosuke ICHIKAWA, a popular star at the time, showed consciously his own fundoshi loincloth, for which his female admirers were much pleased and called him &quot;Fundoshi Momo-chan.&quot;</e>
<cmt>rewrote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Momonosuke ICHIKAWA, a popular star at the time, showed consciously his own fundoshi loincloth, for which his female admirers were much pleased and called him &quot;Fundoshi Momo-chan.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="130">
<j>同様の立ち回りは、若い頃の市川右太衛門や、片岡千恵蔵、阪東妻三郎、羅門光三郎なども行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Similar fighting scenes were played by Utaemon ICHIKAWA (when he was young,) Chiezo KATAOKA, Tsumasaburo BANDO, Mitsusaburo RAMON and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Similar fighting scenes were played by Utaemon ICHIKAWA (when he was young,) Chiezo KATAOKA, Tsumasaburo BANDO, Mitsusaburo RAMON and others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Similar fighting scenes were played by Utaemon ICHIKAWA (when he was young), Chiezo KATAOKA, Tsumasaburo BANDO, Mitsusaburo RAMON and others.</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置を移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="131">
<j>特に市川右太衛門の「浄魂」の大剣戟シーンのふんどしを露にしての剣戟や、阪妻の「決闘高田馬場」の尻はしょりのふんどし、最近ではテレビ映画「森の石松」で中村勘三郎 (18代目)がふんどしを見せての剣戟が知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among others, most well-known were the scene of great sword fighting in the silent movie &quot;Jokon&quot; performed by Utaemon ICHIKAWA exposing his fundoshi loincloth, and the scene of a sword fight in the &quot;Ketto Takada no Baba&quot; played by Tsumasaburo BANDO kilting up the back of his kimono to show his fundoshi loincloth, as well as the sword fighting scene in the recent TV cinema &quot;Mori no Ishimatsu&quot; where Kanzaburo NAKAMURA (the 18th generation) played a sword fight showing his fundoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among others, most well-known were the scene of great sword fighting in the silent movie &quot;Jokon&quot; performed by Utaemon ICHIKAWA exposing his fundoshi loincloth, and the scene of a sword fight in the &quot;Ketto Takada no Baba&quot; played by Tsumasaburo BANDO kilting up the back of his kimono to show his fundoshi loincloth, as well as the sword fighting scene in the recent TV cinema &quot;Mori no Ishimatsu&quot; where Kanzaburo NAKAMURA (the 18th generation) played a sword fight showing his fundoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among others, most well-known were the scene of great sword fighting in the silent movie &apos;Jokon&apos; performed by Utaemon ICHIKAWA exposing his fundoshi loincloth, and the scene of a sword fight in the &apos;Ketto Takada no Baba&apos; played by Tsumasaburo BANDO kilting up the back of his kimono to show his fundoshi loincloth, as well as the sword fighting scene in the recent TV cinema &apos;Mori no Ishimatsu&apos; where Kanzaburo NAKAMURA (the 18th generation) played a sword fight showing his fundoshi.</e>
<cmt>作品名のクォーテーションをシングルに変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="21">
<tit>
<j>女性の褌</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fundoshi Loincloth for Women:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fundoshi Loincloth for Women:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fundoshi Loincloth for Women</e>
<cmt>コロン削除</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="132">
<j>一般に女性と褌は縁がないと思われがちだが、決してそうではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is generally believed that women have nothing to do with fundoshi loincloth, but it is not correct.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is generally believed that women have nothing to do with fundoshi loincloth, but that is not correct.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is generally believed that women have nothing to do with fundoshi loincloth, but that is not correct.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="133">
<j>古くは『日本書紀』にも女性が褌を着用した記述を確認することができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Descriptions of women wearing fundoshi loincloths are confirmed in &quot;the Nihon Shoki&quot; (&quot;the Chronicle of Japan&quot;) of ancient times.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Descriptions of women wearing fundoshi loincloths are confirmed in &quot;the Nihon Shoki&quot; (&quot;the Chronicle of Japan&quot;) of ancient times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Descriptions of women wearing fundoshi loincloths are confirmed in the &quot;Nihon Shoki&quot; (&quot;the Chronicle of Japan&quot;) of ancient times.</e>
<cmt>統一リストに基づき、the &quot;Nihon Shoki&quot;に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="134">
<j>一部では腰巻も含めた下穿きの総称として「褌」という言葉が使われていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In some areas in Japan at that time, the term &quot;fundoshi&quot; was used to mean collectively whole underwear including koshimaki loincloths (waist cloths).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In some areas in Japan at that time, the term &quot;fundoshi&quot; was used to mean collectively, whole underwear including koshimaki loincloths (waist cloths).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In some areas in Japan at that time, the term &quot;fundoshi&quot; was used to mean collectively, whole underwear including koshimaki loincloths (waist cloths).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="135">
<j>タンポンやナプキンなどの生理用品が普及する以前は、越中褌やもっこ褌が「お馬」と呼ばれ生理帯として長い間使用されてきたという歴史がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before tampons and napkins became commonly used, women had used ecchu fundoshi and mokko fundoshi loincloths as sanitary goods called &quot;ouma&quot; for a long period in the history.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before tampons and napkins became commonly used, women had used ecchu fundoshi and mokko fundoshi loincloths as sanitary towels called &quot;ouma&quot; for a long period in the history.</e>
<cmt>rewrote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before tampons and napkins became commonly used, women had used Etchu fundoshi and mokko fundoshi loincloths as sanitary towels called &quot;ouma&quot; for a long period in the history.</e>
<cmt>Etchu fundoshiとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="136">
<j>だが、生理中の女性を穢れたものとして忌み嫌う風習があったことから、あまりおおっぴらに語られることがなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But, people have not openly talked about this because of their custom to hold menstruants in detestation as a disgrace.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But, people have not openly talked about this because of their custom to hold menstruants in detestation as a disgrace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But, people have not openly talked about this because of their custom to hold menstruants in detestation as a disgrace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="137">
<j>江戸時代から戦後にかけては見世物としての女相撲興行が盛んに行われていたし、大衆演劇の世界では男装した女役者が着物をはしょり、ふんどしを見せながらの剣戟を演じて客の喝采を浴びたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the Edo period to the postwar period, women&apos;s sumo exhibitions were actively performed as an entertainment show, and in the society of popular dramas, a female player wearing men&apos;s dress performed sword fights kilting her kimono and showing her fundoshi loincloth to gain plaudits from audience for her performance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the Edo period to the postwar period, women&apos;s sumo exhibitions were actively performed as an entertainment show, and in the society of popular dramas, a female player wearing men&apos;s dress performed sword fights kilting her kimono and showing her fundoshi loincloth to gain plaudits from the audience for her performance.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the Edo period to the postwar period, women&apos;s sumo exhibitions were actively performed as an entertainment show, and in the society of popular dramas, a female player wearing men&apos;s dress performed sword fights kilting her kimono and showing her fundoshi loincloth to gain plaudits from the audience for her performance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="138">
<j>またサイジのように一部の海女が身につける褌も存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also there exist other fundoshi loincloths for women, like a saiji loincloth for some female divers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also there are other fundoshi loincloths for women, like a saiji loincloth for some female divers.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also there are other fundoshi loincloths for women, like a saiji loincloth for some female divers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="139">
<j>下着といえば褌か腰巻しかなかった時代には、女性も必要に応じてふんどしを締めることに抵抗がなかったと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In such times as underwear was limited either to fundoshi loincloths or koshimaki loincloths (waist cloths), it seems that women had no feeling of resistance against wearing fundoshi loincloths as the occasion demands.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In such times, as underwear was limited either to fundoshi loincloths or koshimaki loincloths (waist cloths), it seems that women felt no resistance towards wearing fundoshi loincloths as the occasion demands.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In such times, as underwear was limited either to fundoshi loincloths or koshimaki loincloths (waist cloths), it seems that women felt no resistance towards wearing fundoshi loincloths as the occasion demands.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="140">
<j>昨今の褌ブームの影響か、男性はもとより広く女性をも対象にした商品が市場に現れている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reflecting the current boom of fundoshi loincloths, a wide range of fundoshi items, not only for men but also for women, are being sold in the market.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reflecting the current boom of fundoshi loincloths, a wide range of fundoshi items, not only for men but also for women, are being sold in the market.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reflecting the current boom of fundoshi loincloths, a wide range of fundoshi items, not only for men but also for women, are being sold in the market.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="141">
<j>中には「パンドルショーツ」という名称で発売されている物も在る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among them, a brand of &quot;pandoru shotsu&quot; is included.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among them, a brand of &quot;pandoru shotsu&quot; is included.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among them, a brand of &quot;pandoru shotsu&quot; is included.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="142">
<j>「パンドル」とはフランス語で、「垂れる」と言う意味。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term &quot;pandoru&quot; is French meaning &quot;droop&quot; in English.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term &quot;pandoru&quot; is French meaning &quot;droop&quot; in English.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term &quot;pandoru&quot; is French meaning &quot;droop&quot; in English.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="143">
<j>女優の益戸育江がTV番組の取材で手作りの越中褌を愛用していると発言して話題を呼んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ikue MASUDO, an actress, attracted public attention by telling in a TV program that she is habitually using a handmade ecchu fundoshi loincloth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ikue MASUDO, an actress, attracted public attention by telling on a TV program that she is habitually using a handmade ecchu fundoshi loincloth.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ikue MASUDO, an actress, attracted public attention by telling on a TV program that she is habitually using a handmade Etchu fundoshi loincloth.</e>
<cmt>Etchu fundoshiとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="22">
<tit>
<j>セクシャル</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sexuality:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sexuality:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sexuality</e>
<cmt>コロン削除</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="144">
<j>褌は下着の一種である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fundoshi loincloth is a kind of underwear.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fundoshi loincloth is a kind of underwear.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fundoshi loincloth is a kind of underwear.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="145">
<j>特に六尺褌は局部だけを覆うだけなので、余計に股間部が強調され、臀部も露出していることから、一部のゲイに人気がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially rokushaku fundoshi is popular among some gays because it covers the private parts only so that it emphasizes crotch part unnecessarily and also exposes buttocks.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Especially rokushaku fundoshi is popular among some gays because it covers the private parts only so that it exaggerate the crotch part and also exposes the buttocks.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Especially roku-shaku fundoshi is popular among some gays because it covers the private parts only so that it exaggerate the crotch part and also exposes the buttocks.</e>
<cmt>roku-shaku fundoshiとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="146">
<j>ゲイ向けのグラビアやアダルトビデオ、また、ゲイ向けの褌サイトには逞しい、あるいは、肥満した男性が褌を締めた姿も一部見受けられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In photogravures for gays, in adult videos, and in web sites of fundoshi loincloths for gay, pictures of some muscular or stout men wearing fundoshi loincloths can be seen.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In photogravures for gays, in adult videos, and in web sites of fundoshi loincloths for gays, pictures of some muscular or stout men wearing fundoshi loincloths can be seen.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In photogravures for gays, in adult videos, and in web sites of fundoshi loincloths for gays, pictures of some muscular or stout men wearing fundoshi loincloths can be seen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="147">
<j>またゲイバーには褌バーというカテゴリも存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some gay bars belong to a special category named fundoshi bar.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some gay bars belong to a special category named fundoshi bar.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some gay bars belong to a special category named fundoshi bar.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="148">
<j>ゲイには裸祭りの愛好者も多く、積極的に全国の裸祭りに参加しているらしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many of the gays are devoted to the naked festivals and are reportedly very positive in participating in any naked festival held across the country.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many of the gays are devoted to the naked festivals and are reportedly very positive in participating in any naked festival held across the country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many of the gays are devoted to the naked festivals and are reportedly very positive in participating in any naked festival held across the country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="149">
<j>やおいの女性の中には褌少年を題材にインターネットで活動する者もいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some of female writers for Yaoi (female-oriented fictional media that focus on homo-sexual male relationships usually created by female authors) are actively contributing to internet media with their pictures and articles on the subject of boys wearing fundoshi loincloths.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some female writers of Yaoi (female-oriented fictional media that focus on homo-sexual male relationships usually created by female authors) are actively contributing to the internet media with their pictures and articles on the subject of boys wearing fundoshi loincloths.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some female writers of Yaoi (female-oriented fictional media that focus on homo-sexual male relationships usually created by female authors) are actively contributing to the internet media with their pictures and articles on the subject of boys wearing fundoshi loincloths.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="150">
<j>褌を締めた男性キャラクターの画像などを掲載し、一部では褌キャラ・ふんどしキャラと表現している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On web pages, they post pictures of male characters wearing fundoshi loincloths, which they call fundoshi-kyara (fundoshi-character).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On web pages, they post pictures of male characters wearing fundoshi loincloths, which they call fundoshi-kyara (fundoshi-character).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On web pages, they post pictures of male characters wearing fundoshi loincloths, which they call fundoshi-kyara (fundoshi-character).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="151">
<j>また同性愛者に限らず、女性の褌姿を愛好する男性や褌を愛好する女性も一部に存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is not limited to homosexuals, but there are some men who love to watch figures of women wearing fundoshi loincloths as well as some women who love to wear loincloths.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is not limited to homosexuals, but there are some men who love to watch figures of women wearing fundoshi loincloths as well as some women who love to wear loincloths.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is not limited to homosexuals, but there are some men who love to watch figures of women wearing fundoshi loincloths as well as some women who love to wear loincloths.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="152">
<j>団鬼六や沼正三を輩出した伝説的雑誌『奇譚クラブ』においては「女斗美」（「女闘美」とも表記）と呼ばれ女相撲を熱狂的に愛好する作者による小説が定期的に発表されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The legendary magazine &quot;Kitan Club,&quot; that threw up famous writers, Oniroku DAN and Shozo NUMA, had regularly published novels written by an author who loved fanatically women&apos;s sumo wrestling called &quot;metomi.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The legendary magazine &quot;Kitan Club,&quot; that publishes works of famous writers such as Oniroku DAN and Shozo NUMA, had regularly published articles written by an author who was a fanatic of women&apos;s sumo wrestling called &quot;metomi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>rewrote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The legendary magazine &quot;Kitan Club,&quot; that publishes works of famous writers such as Oniroku DAN and Shozo NUMA, had regularly published articles written by an author who was a fanatic of women&apos;s sumo wrestling called &apos;metomi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一部シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="153">
<j>エログロ描写で当時大ヒットした石井輝男監督の「徳川女系図」(1968)などのピンク映画には女相撲シーンがあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Women&apos;s sumo wrestling scenes were screened in various pink-eiga (blue films) including a hit movie &quot;Tokugawa Onna Keizu&quot;(1968) by director Teruo ISHII that became a blockbuster by its erotic and grotesque depictions.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Women&apos;s sumo wrestling scenes were screened in various pink-eiga (blue films) including a hit movie &quot;Tokugawa Onna Keizu&quot;(1968) by director Teruo ISHII that became a blockbuster due to its erotic and grotesque depictions.</e>
<cmt>rewrote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Women&apos;s sumo wrestling scenes were screened in various pink-eiga (blue films) including a hit movie &apos;Tokugawa Onna Keizu&apos; (1968) by director Teruo ISHII that became a blockbuster due to its erotic and grotesque depictions.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更、スペース追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="154">
<j>また、谷ナオミ主演のにっかつロマンポルノ作品にもしばしば褌は登場している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Figures with fundoshi loincloths appeared frequently also in Nikkatsu roman-porno films with Naomi TANI as a leading character.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Figures with fundoshi loincloths appeared frequently also in Nikkatsu roman-porno films with Naomi TANI as a leading character.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Figures with fundoshi loincloths appeared frequently also in Nikkatsu roman-porno films with Naomi TANI as a leading character.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="155">
<j>また近年では宮沢りえが1989年に発表したカレンダーのふんどし姿が話題を呼び、女性の褌姿を収録した写真集、アダルトビデオなども数多く出されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In recent years, Rie MIYAZAWA attracted public attentions by publishing her figure in a fundoshi loincloth on a calendar of 1989, which was followed by a stream of various photo albums, adult videos and so on, containing pictures of women in fundoshi loincloths.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In recent years, Rie MIYAZAWA has attracted public attentions by publishing her figure in a fundoshi loincloth in a 1989 calendar, which was followed by a stream of various photo albums, adult videos and so on, containing pictures of women in fundoshi loincloths.</e>
<cmt>rewrote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In recent years, Rie MIYAZAWA has attracted public attentions by publishing her figure in a fundoshi loincloth in a 1989 calendar, which was followed by a stream of various photo albums, adult videos and so on, containing pictures of women in fundoshi loincloths.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="156">
<j>21世紀に入ってからは博多祇園山笠や、その他の裸祭り、奉納相撲に参加する褌・廻し・締め込み姿の少年少女画像がネット上で広まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After moving into the 21st century, the internet has propagated various graphic images of boys and girls in fundoshi, mawashi and shimekomi loincloths, participating in Hakata Gion Yamagasa summer festival and other festivals as well as various honozumo (ritual sumo matches held at a shrine).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After moving into the 21st century, the internet has propagated various graphic images of boys and girls in fundoshi, mawashi and shimekomi loincloths, participating in Hakata Gion Yamagasa summer festival and other festivals as well as various honozumo (ritual sumo matches held at a shrine).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After moving into the 21st century, the internet has propagated various graphic images of boys and girls in fundoshi, mawashi and shimekomi loincloths, participating in Hakata Gion Yamagasa summer festival and other festivals as well as various honozumo.</e>
<cmt>honozumo→既出のため補足削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="157">
<j>本来、粋、勇猛、精悍、ダンディズム、というイメージを持つ褌を、これらとは対照的な可憐な少年少女(特に少女)が締めると、却って可憐な魅力が強調される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When a fundoshi loincloth that keeps essential images of chic, bravery, virility and dandyism is worn by a pretty boy or girl (especially a girl) who has a contrast image, the fundoshi loincloth may accelerate the effect of wearers&apos; prettiness.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When a fundoshi loincloth that keeps essential images of chic, bravery, virility and dandyism is worn by a pretty boy or girl (especially a girl) who has a contrasting image, the fundoshi loincloth may accelerate the effect of the wearers&apos; prettiness.</e>
<cmt>rewrote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When a fundoshi loincloth that keeps essential images of chic, bravery, virility and dandyism is worn by a pretty boy or girl (especially a girl) who has a contrasting image, the fundoshi loincloth may accelerate the effect of the wearers&apos; prettiness.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="158">
<j>ここのところに一部のマニア（主に可憐系を愛する者）が注目、褌姿の少年少女をテーマにした同人誌、フィギュア、ホームページ、ブログ、画像掲示板等が相次いで登場した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This point drew attention of some manias (mainly, lovers of prettiness line,) who then began creating consistently coterie magazines, figures (or figurines,) home pages, blogs, gazo-keijiban (graphic billboards) and others on the subject of boys and girls wearing fundoshi loincloth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This point brought about the development of some manias (mainly, lovers of the prettiness line) that led to the consisten creation of coterie magazines, figures (or figurines,) home pages, blogs, gazo-keijiban (graphic billboards) and others on the subject of boys and girls wearing fundoshi loincloth.</e>
<cmt>rewrote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This point brought about the development of some manias (mainly, lovers of the prettiness line) that led to the consistent creation of coterie magazines, figures (or figurines), home pages, blogs, gazo-keijiban (graphic billboards) and others on the subject of boys and girls wearing fundoshi loincloth.</e>
<cmt>consisten→consistentに修正、余分なスペース消去、カンマの位置を移動、</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="23">
<tit>
<j>文学・漫画・アニメ・テレビ番組の中の褌</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fundoshi Loincloth in Literature, Comics, Animated Cartoons and TV Programs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fundoshi Loincloth in Literature, Comics, Animated Cartoons and TV Programs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fundoshi Loincloth in Literature, Comics, Animated Cartoons and TV Programs</e>
<cmt>ピリオド削除</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="24">
<tit>
<j>古典落語</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koten Rakugo:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koten Rakugo:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koten Rakugo</e>
<cmt>コロン削除</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="159">
<j>古典落語では、褌を締めていた時代なので褌に関連した話題には事欠かない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koten rakugo (classical comic storytelling) had a plenty of talks associated with fundoshi loincloths because most of the contemporary people were wearing fundoshi loincloths.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koten rakugo (classical comic storytelling) had plenty of comedic stories associated with fundoshi loincloths because most of the contemporary people were wearing fundoshi loincloths.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koten rakugo (classical comic storytelling) had plenty of comedic stories associated with fundoshi loincloths because most of the contemporary people were wearing fundoshi loincloths.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="160">
<j>『錦の袈裟』『蛙茶番』などが挙げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its typical examples are &quot;Nishiki no Kesa&quot; and &quot;Kawazu-chaban.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Typical examples are &quot;Nishiki no Kesa&quot; and &quot;Kawazu-chaban.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Typical examples are &quot;Nishiki no Kesa&quot; and &quot;Kawazu-chaban.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="25">
<tit>
<j>川柳</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Senryu (humorous and ironical haiku poem):</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Senryu (humorous and ironical haiku poem):</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Senryu (humorous and ironical haiku poem)</e>
<cmt>コロン削除</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="161">
<j>江戸庶民の暮らしを生き生きと描写した川柳にも褌はよく登場する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fundoshi loincloths often appear also in senryu poems depicting vivid lives of common people in the Edo period..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fundoshi loincloths often appear also in senryu poems depicting the vivid lives of common people in the Edo period..</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fundoshi loincloths often appear also in senryu poems depicting the vivid lives of common people in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>余分なピリオド削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="162">
<j>代表的なものをいくつか例に挙げると、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some typical examples are cited as follows:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some typical examples are cited as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some typical examples are cited as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="163">
<j>庶民の日常生活を詠んだもの</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Senryu poems concerning commoners&apos; daily lives:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Senryu poems on commoners&apos; daily lives:</e>
<cmt>re-worded</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Senryu poems on commoners&apos; daily lives</e>
<cmt>コロン削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="164">
<j>「越中がはづれて隣りの国を出し」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Ecchu ga hazurete tonarino kuni wo dasi&quot; (&quot;Pubic region appears from beside the unfastened ecchu fundoshi&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Ecchu ga hazurete tonarino kuni wo dasi&quot; (&quot;Pubic region appears from beside the unfastened ecchu fundoshi&quot;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Etchu ga hazurete tonarino kuni wo dasi&quot; (&quot;Pubic region appears from beside the unfastened Etchu fundoshi&quot;)</e>
<cmt>Etchuとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="165">
<j>「ふんどしをひねくり廻し一分出し」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Fundoshi wo hinekuri mawasi iti-bu dasi&quot; (&quot;Twiddling a fundoshi loincloth to expose a part of my privates&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Fundoshi wo hinekuri mawasi iti-bu dasi&quot; (&quot;Twiddling a fundoshi loincloth to expose a part of my privates&quot;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Fundoshi wo hinekuri mawasi ichi-bu dasi&quot; (&quot;Twiddling a fundoshi loincloth to expose a part of my privates&quot;)</e>
<cmt>iti-bu→ichi-buに修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="166">
<j>褌に絡めて関取の暮らしを詠んだもの</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Senryu poems related to fundoshi loincloths, reflecting the lives of sekitori sumo wrestlers:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Senryu poems related to fundoshi loincloths, reflecting the lives of sekitori sumo wrestlers:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Senryu poems related to fundoshi loincloths, reflecting the lives of sekitori sumo wrestlers</e>
<cmt>コロン削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="167">
<j>「褌の強いはやがて幕になり」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Fundoshi no tsuyoi wa yagate maku ni nari&quot; (&quot;Tightly fastened fundoshi loincloth will make the wrestler strong to be promoted to maku-uchi or top division of sumo ranking&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Fundoshi no tsuyoi wa yagate maku ni nari&quot; (&quot;Tightly fastened fundoshi loincloth will make the wrestler strong enough to be promoted to maku-uchi or top division of sumo ranking&quot;)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Fundoshi no tsuyoi wa yagate maku ni nari&quot; (&quot;Tightly fastened fundoshi loincloth will make the wrestler strong enough to be promoted to maku-uchi or top division of sumo ranking&quot;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="168">
<j>「褌を故郷へ飾る角力取」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Fundoshi wo kokyo e kazaru sumo-tori&quot; (&quot;A sumo wrestler goes home loaded with honorable fundoshi loincloth&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Fundoshi wo kokyo e kazaru sumo-tori&quot; (&quot;A sumo wrestler goes home loaded with honorable fundoshi loincloths&quot;)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Fundoshi wo kokyo e kazaru sumo-tori&quot; (&quot;A sumo wrestler goes home loaded with honorable fundoshi loincloths&quot;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="169">
<j>褌が生理帯としても使用されていたことをしのばせるもの</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Senryu poems suggesting that a fundoshi loincloth was used as a sanitary belt for women:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Senryu poems suggesting that a fundoshi loincloth was used as a sanitary belt for women:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Senryu poems suggesting that a fundoshi loincloth was used as a sanitary belt for women</e>
<cmt>コロン削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="170">
<j>「越中を女房がすると事を欠き」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Ecchu wo nyobo ga suruto koto wo kaki&quot; (&quot;When my wife wears an ecchu fundoshi loincloth, there is no way to have sex with her&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Ecchu wo nyobo ga suruto koto wo kaki&quot; (&quot;When my wife wears an ecchu fundoshi loincloth, there is no way to have sex with her&quot;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Etchu wo nyobo ga suruto koto wo kaki&quot; (&quot;When my wife wears an Etchu fundoshi loincloth, there is no way to have sex with her&quot;)</e>
<cmt>Etchuとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="171">
<j>「十三四 姫はお馬をのりならひ」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Juusan-shi hime wa ouma wo norinarai&quot; (&quot;A girl of thirteen or fourteen years old is practicing a horse riding for the first time&quot; (which depict a scene of a young girl undergoing menstruation for the first time in a toilet));</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Juusan-shi hime wa ouma wo norinarai&quot; (&quot;A girl of thirteen or fourteen years old is practicing horse riding for the first time&quot; (which depicts a scene of a young girl undergoing menstruation for the first time in a toilet));</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Jusan-shi hime wa ouma wo norinarai&quot; (&quot;A girl of thirteen or fourteen years old is practicing horse riding for the first time&quot; [which depicts a scene of a young girl undergoing menstruation for the first time in a toilet])</e>
<cmt>Juusan-shi→Jusan-shiに修正、カッコ表記修正、セミコロン削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="172">
<j>などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">and others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">and others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="26">
<tit>
<j>文学</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Literature:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Literature:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Literature</e>
<cmt>コロン削除</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="173">
<j>夏目漱石は、『虞美人草』の中で夏の風物詩として褌を取り上げている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In his novel &quot;Gubijinso&quot;, Soseki NATSUME referred to fundoshi loincloth as a special feature of summer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In his novel &quot;Gubijinso&quot;, Soseki NATSUME referred to fundoshi loincloth as a special feature of summer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In his novel &quot;Gubijinso&quot; (The Poppy), Soseki NATSUME referred to fundoshi loincloth as a special feature of summer.</e>
<cmt>Gubijinsoの英訳表記追加 (用語集参照)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="174">
<j>「夏は褌を洗う」など、夏の季語のような用法を使用している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He used the word &quot;fundoshi&quot; like a season word for summer, writing for example as &quot;Natsu wa fundoshi wo arau&quot; (literally, &quot;In summer, I wash my fundoshi loincloth&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He used the word &quot;fundoshi&quot; like a seasonal word for summer, writing for example as &quot;Natsu wa fundoshi wo arau&quot; (literally, &quot;In summer, I wash my fundoshi loincloth&quot;).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He used the word &quot;fundoshi&quot; like a seasonal word for summer, writing for example as &quot;Natsu wa fundoshi wo arau&quot; (literally, &quot;In summer, I wash my fundoshi loincloth&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="175">
<j>堺利彦の『獄中生活 (文学)』では、堺が巣鴨監獄（のちの巣鴨プリズン、巣鴨拘置所）に入獄したおりの官給の褌の感想がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In his novel &quot;Gokuchu Seikatsu&quot; (literally, &quot;the life in prison&quot;), Toshihiko SAKAI wrote his sentiment about the government-furnished fundoshi loincloth supplied to him when he went to Sugamo Kangoku (later renamed to Sugamo Prison and to Sugamo Kochisho).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In his novel &quot;Gokuchu Seikatsu&quot; (literally, &quot;Life in prison&quot;), Toshihiko SAKAI wrote his sentiments about the government-furnished fundoshi loincloth supplied to him when he went to Sugamo Kangoku (later renamed as Sugamo Prison and to Sugamo Kochisho).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In his novel &quot;Gokuchu Seikatsu&quot; (literally, &quot;Life in prison&quot;), Toshihiko SAKAI wrote his sentiments about the government-furnished fundoshi loincloth supplied to him when he went to Sugamo Kangoku (later renamed as Sugamo Prison and to Sugamo Kochisho).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="176">
<j>「いずれも柿色染であるが、手拭と褌とは縦に濃淡の染分けになって、多少の美をなしているからおかしい。」（三 巣鴨監獄）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Tenugui (towel) and fundoshi (loincloth) are both dyed persimmon color, but, interestingly, they are dyed in different shades in longitudinal direction, constituting some beauty.&quot; (No.3 Sugamo Kangoku)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Tenugui (towel) and fundoshi (loincloth) are both dyed the color of persimmon, but, interestingly, they are dyed in different shades in the longitudinal direction, constituting some beauty.&quot; (No.3 Sugamo Kangoku)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Tenugui (towel) and fundoshi (loincloth) are both dyed the color of persimmon, but, interestingly, they are dyed in different shades in the longitudinal direction, constituting some beauty.&quot; (No.3 Sugamo Kangoku)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="177">
<j>泉鏡花『いろ扱ひ』は、作者の少年時の乱読癖を振り返った私小説。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Iro-atsukai&quot; of Kyoka IZUMI is an &quot;I&quot; novel (a novel based on author&apos;s own life), recalling his habit to read books excursively in his childhood.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Iro-atsukai&quot; of Kyoka IZUMI is an &quot;I&quot; novel (a novel based on author&apos;s own life), recalling his habit of reading books excursively in his childhood.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Iro-atsukai&quot; of Kyoka IZUMI is an &quot;I&quot; novel (a novel based on author&apos;s own life), recalling his habit of reading books excursively in his childhood.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="178">
<j>厳しい塾の下宿から、貸本屋へ外出する方便として、「褌を外して袂へ忍ばせて置く」裏技を開陳している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There, he explained a trick to go out to a book-lending shop from a severely controlled boarding house of private tutoring school, that was &quot;to hide my fundoshi loincloth inside of kimono&apos;s tamoto (a sleeve)&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There, he explained a trick on how to go out to a book-lending shop from a strictly controlled boarding house of a private school, and that was &quot;to hide my fundoshi loincloth inside of kimono&apos;s tamoto (a sleeve)&quot;.</e>
<cmt>rewrote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There, he explained a trick on how to go out to a book-lending shop from a strictly controlled boarding house of a private school, and that was &quot;to hide my fundoshi loincloth inside of kimono&apos;s tamoto (a sleeve).&quot;</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース消去、カンマの位置を移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="179">
<j>「何のためだと云ふと、其塾の傍に一筋の小川が流れて居る、其小川へ洗濯に出ましたと斯（か）う答へるんです。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;The reason for doing so was to explain later to a landlord (or landlady) that I went out to wash my fundoshi loincloth at a brook near the school,&quot; he wrote.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;The reason for doing so was to explain later to a landlord (or landlady) that I went out to wash my fundoshi loincloth at a brook near the school,&quot; he wrote.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;The reason for doing so was to explain later to a landlord (or landlady) that I went out to wash my fundoshi loincloth at a brook near the school,&quot; he wrote.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="180">
<j>さうすると剣突を喰つて、『どうも褌を洗ひに行きますと云ふのは、何だか申上げ悪（にく）いから黙つて出ました。』と言ひ抜ける積りさ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He continued, &quot;If I am harshly scolded, I would give an evasive answer &apos;I didn&apos;t tell you anything because I hesitated to tell anything about such a nasty matter as washing fundoshi loincloth.&apos;&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He continued, &quot;If I am harshly scolded, I would give an evasive answer &apos;I didn&apos;t tell you anything because I hesitated to tell anything about such a nasty matter as washing a fundoshi loincloth.&apos;&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He continued, &quot;If I am harshly scolded, I would give an evasive answer &apos;I didn&apos;t tell you anything because I hesitated to tell anything about such a nasty matter as washing a fundoshi loincloth.&apos;&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="181">
<j>芥川龍之介『玄鶴山房』では、肺結核の床に就いている主人公・玄鶴が、褌で縊れ死ぬことを夢想する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the novel &quot;Genkaku-sanbo&quot; written by Ryunosuke AKUTAGAWA, a leading character GENKAKU, who is in bed suffering lung tuberculosis, dreams of his own death by hanging himself by his fundoshi loincloth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the novel &quot;Genkaku-sanbo&quot; written by Ryunosuke AKUTAGAWA, a leading character, GENKAKU, who is in bed suffering lung tuberculosis, dreams of his own death by hanging himself by his fundoshi loincloth.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the novel &quot;Genkaku-sanbo&quot; (Genkaku&apos;s House) written by Ryunosuke AKUTAGAWA, a leading character, Genkaku, who is in bed suffering lung tuberculosis, dreams of his own death by hanging himself by his fundoshi loincloth.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Genkaku-sanbo&quot;の英訳追加 (参照: http://books.google.co.jp/books?id=rUo7AAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA97&amp;dq=genkaku-sanbo&amp;hl=ja&amp;ei=ED1ZTMCfEcGHccXIpMII&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=10&amp;ved=0CE8Q6AEwCQ#)GENKAKU→Genkakuに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="182">
<j>「玄鶴はそっと褌を引き寄せ、彼の頭に巻きつけると、両手にぐっと引っぱるようにした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;GENKAKU pulled lightly his fundoshi loincloth and wound it around his head pulling it forcefully by both hands&quot; he wrote.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;GENKAKU pulled lightly his fundoshi loincloth and wound it around his head pulling it forcefully by both hands&quot;, he wrote.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Genkaku pulled lightly his fundoshi loincloth and wound it around his head pulling it forcefully by both hands,&quot; he wrote.</e>
<cmt>GENKAKU→Genkakuに修正、カンマの位置を移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="183">
<j>/そこへ丁度顔を出したのはまるまると着膨（きぶく）れた武夫だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;At that point, it was Takeo who showed up wearing heavy clothes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;At that point, it was Takeo who showed up wearing heavy clothes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;At that point, it was Takeo who showed up wearing heavy clothes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="184">
<j>/やあ、お爺さんがあんなことをしていらあ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&apos;Yah, grandpa is doing that&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&apos;Yah, grandpa is doing that&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yah, grandpa is doing that.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオド追加、スペース消去</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="185">
<j>/武夫はこう囃（はや）しながら、一散に茶の間へ走って行った。」（五）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He jeered at GENKAKU and ran away like a rabbit toward the living room.&quot; (No.5)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He jeered at GENKAKU and ran away like a rabbit toward the living room.&quot; (No.5)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He jeered at GENKAKU and ran away like a rabbit toward the living room.&quot; (No.5)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="186">
<j>「死ぬときはきれいな身なりで」という美意識は、近代社会において、人口に膾炙していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In modern society, people were familiar with such sense of beauty as &quot;a man should be neat and tidy when he dies.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In modern society, people were familiar with the sense of beauty that &quot;a man should be neat and tidy when he dies.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In modern society, people were familiar with the sense of beauty that &quot;a man should be neat and tidy when he dies.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="187">
<j>芥川龍之介『追憶』にはこうある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In his novel &quot;Tsuioku,&quot; Ryunosuke AKUTAGAWA wrote, &quot;this &apos;oshisho-san&apos; (master) lived a long life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In his novel &quot;Tsuioku,&quot; Ryunosuke AKUTAGAWA wrote, &quot;this &apos;oshisho-san&apos; (master) lived a long life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In his novel &quot;Tsuioku&quot; (Remembrance), Ryunosuke AKUTAGAWA wrote as follows:</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」&quot;Tsuioku&quot;の英訳追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="188">
<j>「この「お師匠さん」は長命だった。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;This &apos;oshisho-san&apos; (master) lived a long life.&quot;</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="189">
<j>「なんでも晩年味噌（みそ）を買いに行き、雪上がりの往来で転んだ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When he went out to buy miso (fermented soybean paste,) he tumbled over the snow on a road.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When he went out to buy miso (fermented soybean paste,) he tumbled over the snow on a road.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;When he went out to buy miso (fermented soybean paste), he tumbled over the snow on a road.&quot;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション追加、カンマの位置を移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="190">
<j>「そして、やっと家（うち）へ帰ってくると、「それでもまあ褌（ふんどし）だけ新しくってよかった」と言ったそうである。」（一九 宇治紫山）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But, when he returned home, he is said to have commented, &apos;Fortunately, I was wearing a new fundoshi loincloth when I fell down.&apos;&quot; (No. 19 Ujishizan)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But, when he returned home, he is said to have made the comment, &apos;Fortunately, I was wearing a new fundoshi loincloth when I fell down.&apos;&quot; (No. 19 Ujishizan)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;But, when he returned home, he is said to have made the comment, &apos;Fortunately, I was wearing a new fundoshi loincloth when I fell down.&apos;&quot; (No. 19 Ujishizan)</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション追加、余分なスペース消去</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="191">
<j>小林多喜二『蟹工船』では、密閉空間に置かれた船員達の、荒れた風景の小道具として描かれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In his novel &quot;Kanikosen,&quot; Takiji KOBAYASHI wrote of fundoshi loincloth as a prop to describe a nasty scene of sailors confined in an enclosed space.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In his novel &quot;Kanikosen,&quot; Takiji KOBAYASHI wrote of fundoshi loincloth as a prop to describe a nasty scene of sailors confined in an enclosed space.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In his novel &quot;Kanikosen&quot; (The Crab Factory Ship), Takiji KOBAYASHI wrote of fundoshi loincloth as a prop to describe a nasty scene of sailors confined in an enclosed space.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Kanikosen&quot;の英訳追加 (参照: http://books.google.co.jp/books?id=1cfO-Rrnx0EC&amp;pg=PA83&amp;dq=kani-kosen&amp;hl=ja&amp;ei=aEJZTMCUJYfGcK-VkfcI&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=8&amp;ved=0CFAQ6AEwBw#v=onepage&amp;q=kani-kosen&amp;f=false)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="192">
<j>「夢精をするのが何人もいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;A number of sailors had wet dreams.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;A number of sailors had wet dreams.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;A number of sailors had wet dreams.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="193">
<j>誰もいない時、たまらなくなって自涜をするものもいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some of them gave way to masterbation when nobody is around him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some of them gave way to masterbation when nobody was around him.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some of them gave way to masterbation when nobody was around him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="194">
<j>――棚の隅にカタのついた汚れた猿又や褌が、しめっぽく、すえた臭いをして円められていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the corners of a shelf, dirty sarumata shorts and fundoshi loincloths with semen spots were left crumpled up, which were exuding wet and sour smell.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the corners of a shelf, dirty sarumata shorts and fundoshi loincloths with semen spots were left crumpled up and were exuding wet and sour smell.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the corners of a shelf, dirty sarumata shorts and fundoshi loincloths with semen spots were left crumpled up and were exuding wet and sour smell.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="195">
<j>学生はそれを野糞のように踏みつけることがあった。」（四）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Students sometimes tramped on them like feces lying on the ground.&quot; (No.4)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Students sometimes tramped on them like feces lying on the ground.&quot; (No.4)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Students sometimes tramped on them like feces lying on the ground.&quot; (No.4)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="196">
<j>小林多喜二『独房』では、政治犯としての入所体験において、外界との違いを褌に見つける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In his novel &quot;Dokubo,&quot; Takiji KOBAYASHI noted some difference in fundoshi loincloth between inside and outside of prison according to his experience of imprisonment as a political crime.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In his novel &quot;Dokubo,&quot; Takiji KOBAYASHI noted some differences in the fundoshi loincloth between the inside and outside of a prison based on his experience of imprisonment for a political crime.</e>
<cmt>rewrote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In his novel &quot;Dokubo&quot; (Solitary Cell), Takiji KOBAYASHI noted some differences in the fundoshi loincloth between the inside and outside of a prison based on his experience of imprisonment for a political crime.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Dokubo&quot;の英訳追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="197">
<j>「青い着物を着、青い股引（ももひき）をはき、青い褌（ふんどし）をしめ、青い帯をしめ、ワラ草履（ぞうり）をはき、――生れて始めて、俺は「編笠（あみがさ）」をかぶった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Wearing blue kimono, blue momohiki (long underpants), blue fundoshi loincloth, blue belt, and straw sandals---and I wore &apos;amigasa&apos; (a braided hat) for the first time in my life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;I wore a blue kimono, blue momohiki (long underpants), blue fundoshi loincloth, blue belt, and straw sandals---and I wore &apos;amigasa&apos; (a braided hat) for the first time in my life.</e>
<cmt>rewrote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;I wore a blue kimono, blue momohiki (long underpants), blue fundoshi loincloth, blue belt, and straw sandals---and I wore &apos;amigasa&apos; (a braided hat) for the first time in my life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="198">
<j>だが、俺は褌まで青くなくたっていゝだろうと思った。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But, I thought that fundoshi loincloth should not necessarily be blue.&quot; he wrote.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But, I thought that fundoshi loincloth should not necessarily be blue.&quot; he wrote.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But, I thought that fundoshi loincloth should not necessarily be blue,&quot; he wrote.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド→カンマに変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="199">
<j>高村光太郎『回想録』には、近世の風俗の名残が、近代の流れに洗われてゆく風情を描く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In his writing &quot;Kaisoroku,&quot; Kotaro TAKAMURA depicted fading relics of early-modern folkways in the tide of the modern times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In his writing of &quot;Kaisoroku,&quot; Kotaro TAKAMURA depicted fading relics of early-modern folkways in the tide of the modern times.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In his writing of &quot;Kaisoroku&quot; (Memoirs), Kotaro TAKAMURA depicted fading relics of early-modern folkways in the tide of the modern times.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Kaisoroku&quot;の英訳追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="200">
<j>「祖父は丁髷（ちょんまげ）をつけて、夏など褌（ふんどし）一つで歩いていたのを覚えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;I remember my grandfather with chonmage (a topknot) on his head who walked around wearing nothing but fundoshi loincloth in the summer season.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;I remember my grandfather wore a chonmage (a topknot) on his head and walked around wearing nothing but the fundoshi loincloth in the summer season.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;I remember my grandfather wore a chonmage (a topknot) on his head and walked around wearing nothing but the fundoshi loincloth in the summer season.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="201">
<j>その頃裸体禁止令が出て、お巡りさんが「御隠居さん、もう裸では歩けなくなったのだよ。」と言って喧（やかま）しい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, since the government issued a ban on people&apos;s naked appearances, a cop was loud to instruct my grandfather saying &apos;Goinkyo-san (an honorific title for retired men), nobody is now allowed to walk around naked.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, since the government issued a ban on people appearing naked, a cop was loud to instruct my grandfather saying &apos;Goinkyo-san (an honorific title for retired men), now, nobody is allowed to walk around naked.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, since the government issued a ban on people appearing naked, a cop was loud to instruct my grandfather saying &apos;Goinkyo-san (an honorific title for retired men), now, nobody is allowed to walk around naked.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="202">
<j>そしたら着物を着てやろうというので蚊帳（かや）で着物を拵え素透（すどお）しでよく見えるのに平気で交番の前を歩いていた。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, my grandfather followed the cop&apos;s request, and began to wear kimono which was, however, made of transparent kaya fabricks (a mosquito net for bed) and did not hesitate to walk in it in front of the police station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, my grandfather obeyed the cop&apos;s request, and began to wear kimono which was, however, made of transparent kaya fabricks (a mosquito net for bed) and did not hesitate to walk in it in front of the police station.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, my grandfather obeyed the cop&apos;s request, and began to wear kimono which was, however, made of transparent kaya fabricks (a mosquito net for bed) and did not hesitate to walk in it in front of the police station.&quot;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="203">
<j>坂口安吾『青鬼の褌を洗う女』では、性別役割分業として「褌を洗う女私」を登場させている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ango SAKAGUCHI wrote a novel &quot;Ao-oni no fundoshi wo arau onna&quot; in which he described &quot;fundoshi wo arau onna = watashi&quot; (literally, &quot;I am a woman who washes men&apos;s fundoshi loincloth&quot;) as a symbol case of job-sharing between men and women.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ango SAKAGUCHI wrote a novel &quot;Ao-oni no fundoshi wo arau onna&quot; in which he described &quot;fundoshi wo arau onna = watashi&quot; (literally, &quot;I am a woman who washes men&apos;s fundoshi loincloth&quot;) as a symbolic case of job-sharing between men and women.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ango SAKAGUCHI wrote a novel &quot;Ao-oni no fundoshi wo arau onna&quot; (The Woman Who Washes the Blue Demon&apos;s Loincloth) in which he described &quot;fundoshi wo arau onna = watashi&quot; (literally, &quot;I am a woman who washes men&apos;s fundoshi loincloth&quot;) as a symbolic case of job-sharing between men and women.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Ao-oni no fundoshi wo arau onna&quot;の英訳追加 (参考: http://www.aasianst.org/absts/1997abst/japan/j96.htm)余分なスペース消去</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="204">
<j>三島由紀夫の褌姿は有名だ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A figure of Yukio MISHIMA in fundoshi loincloth is widely known.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A figure of Yukio MISHIMA in fundoshi loincloth is widely known.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A figure of Yukio MISHIMA in fundoshi loincloth is widely known.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="205">
<j>市谷駐屯地での割腹事件の数年前から褌姿で切腹する写真や映画『憂国』を残している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since several years before his harakiri suicide at Camp Ichigaya, Yukio MISHIMA had made and left pictures of his own image of committing suicide in fundoshi loincloth as well as a movie &quot;yukoku.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since several years before his harakiri suicide at Camp Ichigaya, Yukio MISHIMA had made and left pictures of his own image of committing suicide in fundoshi loincloth as well as a movie titled &quot;yukoku.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since several years before his harakiri suicide at Camp Ichigaya, Yukio MISHIMA had made and left pictures of his own image of committing suicide in fundoshi loincloth as well as a movie titled &quot;Yukoku&quot; (Patriotism).</e>
<cmt>&quot;Yukoku&quot;とし、英訳補足追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="206">
<j>三島由紀夫と交流のあった稲垣足穂は、ふんどしをはいた奇行で有名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taruho INAGAKI, a novelist who had kept contact with Yukio MISHIMA, is famous for his eccentricities in fundoshi loincloth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taruho INAGAKI, a novelist who had kept contact with Yukio MISHIMA, is famous for his eccentricities on fundoshi loincloth.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taruho INAGAKI, a novelist who had kept contact with Yukio MISHIMA, is famous for his eccentricities on fundoshi loincloth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="207">
<j>彼には、三島同様に男色趣味があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As in the case of Yukio MISHIMA, Taruho INAGAKI had a taste for sodomy.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As in the case of Yukio MISHIMA, Taruho INAGAKI had a taste for sodomy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As in the case of Yukio MISHIMA, Taruho INAGAKI had a taste for sodomy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="208">
<j>そのため、足穂はふんどしでインタビューに応じたり、若い男をくどいたりしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Accordingly, he sometimes wore fundoshi loincloth in interviews and also made advances toward young men.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Accordingly, he sometimes wore fundoshi loincloth to interviews and also made advances towards young men.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Accordingly, he sometimes wore fundoshi loincloth to interviews and also made advances towards young men.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="27">
<tit>
<j>漫画・アニメ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Comics and Animations:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Comics and Animations:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Comics and Animations</e>
<cmt>コロン削除</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="209">
<j>現代を舞台にした作品の場合、古風だが強い意志を持った男子というキャラクターを強調するアイテムとして使用されることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the works set in the background of modern times, a fundoshi loincloth is often used as an item to emphasize male characters with an archaic but strong will.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the works set in the background of modern times, a fundoshi loincloth is often used as an item to emphasize the male character as archaic but strong will.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the works set in the background of modern times, a fundoshi loincloth is often used as an item to emphasize the male character as archaic but strong will.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="210">
<j>また、ギャグとしての意味合いも強い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has also a clear implication of gag.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has also a clear implication of being a gag.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has also a clear implication of being a gag.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="211">
<j>例外的に香坂しぐれ、きくりのような女性キャラも存在するが、この場合も武道の達人、くノ一や男装趣味といった特殊な設定のキャラクターであることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As exceptional examples, there exist some female characters in fundoshi loincloths, like Shigure KOSAKA and Kikuri, but most of them are specially designed as particular characters such as an expert in marshal arts, a female ninja, a devotee of wearing men&apos;s clothes and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As exceptional examples, there are some female characters in fundoshi loincloths, like Shigure KOSAKA and Kikuri, but most of them are specially designed for particular characters such as an expert in marshal arts, a female ninja, a devotee of wearing men&apos;s clothes and so on.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As exceptional examples, there are some female characters in fundoshi loincloths, like Shigure KOSAKA and Kikuri, but most of them are specially designed for particular characters such as an expert in marshal arts, a female ninja, a devotee of wearing men&apos;s clothes and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="212">
<j>また、博多を舞台にした青春劇画『博多っ子純情』（長谷川法世）では、博多祇園山笠が重要なイベントとして描かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The &quot;Hakatakko Junjo,&quot; one of seishun-gekiga (story comics of youths), written by Hosei HASEGAWA, having its setting in Hakata, depicts Hakata Gion Yamagasa summer festival as an important event.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Hakatakko Junjo,&quot; a seishun-gekiga (story comics of youths), written by Hosei HASEGAWA, having its setting in Hakata, depictsthe Hakata Gion Yamagasa summer festival as an important event.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &quot;Hakatakko Junjo,&quot; a seishun-gekiga (story comics of youths), written by Hosei HASEGAWA, having its setting in Hakata, depicts the Hakata Gion Yamagasa summer festival as an important event.</e>
<cmt>depictsthe→depicts theに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="213">
<j>『六尺ふんどし』（青柳裕介）、『匠のふんどし』（山崎大紀）、『ふんどし刑事ケンちゃんとチャコちゃん』（徳弘正也）、『赤褌鈴乃介』（永井豪、『赤胴鈴之助』のパロディ）といったタイトルに使用している作品もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are also comics whose titles contain the word of &quot;fundoshi&quot; such as &quot;Rokushaku Fundoshi&quot; by Yusuke AOYAGI, &quot;Takumi no Fundoshi&quot; by Daiki YAMAZAKI, &quot;Fundoshi Keiji Ken-chan to Chako-chan&quot; by Masaya TOKUHIRO, &quot;Akafundoshi Suzunosuke&quot; (a parody of &quot;Akado Suzunosuke&quot;) by Go NAGAI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are also comics where the title contains the word &quot;fundoshi&quot; such as &quot;Rokushaku Fundoshi&quot; by Yusuke AOYAGI, &quot;Takumi no Fundoshi&quot; by Daiki YAMAZAKI, &quot;Fundoshi Keiji Ken-chan to Chako-chan&quot; by Masaya TOKUHIRO, and &quot;Akafundoshi Suzunosuke&quot; (a parody of &quot;Akado Suzunosuke&quot;) by Go NAGAI.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are also comics where the title contains the word &quot;fundoshi&quot; such as &quot;Roku-shaku Fundoshi&quot; by Yusuke AOYAGI, &quot;Takumi no Fundoshi&quot; by Daiki YAMAZAKI, &quot;Fundoshi Keiji Ken-chan to Chako-chan&quot; by Masaya TOKUHIRO, and &quot;Akafundoshi Suzunosuke&quot; (a parody of &quot;Akado Suzunosuke&quot;) by Go NAGAI.</e>
<cmt>Roku-shaku Fundoshiとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="214">
<j>褌はパンツと違いその種類や締め方が多岐にわたるため、絵的な表現が難しい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Unlike undershorts, fundoshi loincloths of a variety of different kinds and different ways of tying are difficult to depict in the picturesque way.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unlike undershorts, fundoshi loincloths are of a wide variety and have different ways of tying that are difficult to depict in a picturesque way.</e>
<cmt>rewrote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unlike undershorts, fundoshi loincloths are of a wide variety and have different ways of tying that are difficult to depict in a picturesque way.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="215">
<j>そのため漫画やアニメに登場する褌は、作者の知識不足もあって六尺、越中といった描き分けが明確でないことが非常に多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That is the main reason why many of rokushaku, ecchu and other individual fundoshi loincloths are very often indistinguishably drawn in comics and animations, as well as due to writers&apos; lack of knowledges.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That is the main reason why many of rokushaku, ecchu and other individual fundoshi loincloths are very often drawn in a way that they cannot be distinguised in comics and animations, and this is also due to the lack of knowledge of the writers.</e>
<cmt>rewrote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That is the main reason why many of roku-shaku, Etchu and other individual fundoshi loincloths are very often drawn in a way that they cannot be distinguised in comics and animations, and this is also due to the lack of knowledge of the writers.</e>
<cmt>roku-shaku、Etchuとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="28">
<tit>
<j>褌に関する言葉・都市伝説など</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wordings and Urban Legends concerned to Fundoshi Loincloths:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wordings and Urban Legends on Fundoshi Loincloths:</e>
<cmt>rewrote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wordings and Urban Legends on Fundoshi Loincloths</e>
<cmt>コロン削除</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="216">
<j>褌を含むことわざとして以下のものなどがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Followings are Japanese proverbs containing the word of fundoshi:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following are Japanese proverbs containing the word &quot;fundoshi&quot;:</e>
<cmt>rewrote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following are Japanese proverbs containing the word &quot;fundoshi&quot;:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="217">
<j>「褌を締めてかかる」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;To tighten one&apos;s fundoshi loincloth before doing something new&quot; (corresponding to the western proverb &quot;to roll up one&apos;s sleeves&quot; or &quot;to pull up one&apos;s socks&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;To tighten one&apos;s fundoshi loincloth before doing something new&quot; (corresponding to the western proverb &quot;to roll up one&apos;s sleeves&quot; or &quot;to pull up one&apos;s socks&quot;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;To tighten one&apos;s fundoshi loincloth before doing something new&quot; (corresponding to the western proverb &quot;to roll up one&apos;s sleeves&quot; or &quot;to pull up one&apos;s socks&quot;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="218">
<j>「義理と褌欠かされぬ」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Both giri (obligations) and fundoshi loincloths are essential for men&apos;s life&quot; (corresponding to the western proverb &quot;asses scratch one another&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Both giri (obligations) and fundoshi loincloths are essential for men&apos;s life&quot; (corresponding to the western proverb &quot;asses scratch one another&quot;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Both giri (obligations) and fundoshi loincloths are essential for men&apos;s life&quot; (corresponding to the western proverb &quot;asses scratch one another&quot;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="219">
<j>「人の褌で相撲を取る」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;To fight a sumo wrestling wearing another&apos;s fundoshi loincloth&quot; (corresponding to the western proverb &quot;to plough with another&apos;s calf&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;To fight a sumo wrestler wearing another&apos;s fundoshi loincloth&quot; (corresponding to the western proverb &quot;to plough with another&apos;s calf&quot;)</e>
<cmt>spelling error</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;To fight a sumo wrestler wearing another&apos;s fundoshi loincloth&quot; (corresponding to the western proverb &quot;to plough with another&apos;s calf&quot;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="220">
<j>「帯に短し襷に長し褌には丁度良い」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Too short for obi belt for kimono, and too long for tasuki cord to tuck up sleeves of kimono, but just good for a fundoshi loincloth&quot; (corresponding to the western proverb &quot;too much for one, and not enough for two&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Too short for an obi belt for a kimono, and too long for a tasuki cord to tuck up the sleeves of a kimono, but just good for a fundoshi loincloth&quot; (corresponding to the western proverb &quot;too much for one, and not enough for two&quot;)</e>
<cmt>rewrote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Too short for an obi belt for a kimono, and too long for a tasuki cord to tuck up the sleeves of a kimono, but just good for a fundoshi loincloth&quot; (corresponding to the western proverb &quot;too much for one, and not enough for two&quot;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="221">
<j>成人を意味する褌親（へこおや）がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a word &quot;Heko-oya&quot; that means acting parents asked for Fundoshi-iwai (a coming-of-age celebration for a boy wearing a fundoshi loincloth).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a word &quot;Heko-oya&quot; that means acting parents asked for Fundoshi-iwai (a coming-of-age celebration for a boy wearing a fundoshi loincloth).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a word &quot;Heko-oya&quot; that means acting parents asked for Fundoshi-iwai (a coming-of-age celebration for a boy wearing a fundoshi loincloth).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="222">
<j>カニの腹節は俗に褌と呼ばれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An abdominal part of crab is commonly called fundoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The abdominal part of crab is commonly called fundoshi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The abdominal part of crab is commonly called fundoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="223">
<j>北陸地方ではカニのえら（食用に不適）を指し、茹でるカニの甲羅を開けたのちに先ず取り除く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Hokuriku region, the term fundoshi means gills of crab (inedible), which are removed first after opening a shell of crab to be boiled.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Hokuriku region, the term fundoshi means gills of crab (inedible), which are removed first after opening a shell of crab to be boiled.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Hokuriku region, the term fundoshi means gills of crab (inedible), which are removed first after opening a shell of crab to be boiled.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="224">
<j>食卓にカニを出された男性がカニではなく自分の褌を外す、という民話がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to a folklore, a man served with a dish of crab had mistakenly unfastened his fundoshi loincloth instead of removing the crab&apos;s fundoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to a folklore, a man served with a dish of crab had mistakenly unfastened his fundoshi loincloth instead of removing the crab&apos;s fundoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to a folklore, a man served with a dish of crab had mistakenly unfastened his fundoshi loincloth instead of removing the crab&apos;s fundoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="225">
<j>褌を含む四字熟語は「緊褌一番」がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of four-character idioms including a word of fundoshi is &quot;kinkon-ichiban&quot; (literally, &quot;to tighten one&apos;s fundoshi loincloth to give another try&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of four-character idioms that includes the word &quot;fundoshi&quot; is &quot;kinkon-ichiban&quot; (literally, &quot;to tighten one&apos;s fundoshi loincloth to try again&quot;).</e>
<cmt>rewrote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of four-character idioms that includes the word &quot;fundoshi&quot; is &quot;kinkon-ichiban&quot; (literally, &quot;to tighten one&apos;s fundoshi loincloth to try again&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="226">
<j>飛脚のふんどしという都市伝説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of urban legends is &quot;hikyaku no fundoshi&quot; (literally, a fundoshi loincloth of an express messenger).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One urban legends is &quot;hikyaku no fundoshi&quot; (literally, a fundoshi loincloth of an express messenger).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One urban legends is &quot;hikyaku no fundoshi&quot; (literally, a fundoshi loincloth of an express messenger).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="227">
<j>雅楽にも褌が付く曲がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even in gagaku (ancient Japanese court dance and music), there are some tunes including the word of fundoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even in gagaku (ancient Japanese court dance and music), there are some tunes that contain the word &quot;fundoshi&quot;.</e>
<cmt>rewrote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even in gagaku (ancient Japanese court dance and music), there are some tunes that contain the word &quot;fundoshi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="228">
<j>何れも相撲の時の曲らしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They seem to have been played on the occasion of sumo exhibitions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They seem to have been played at sumo exhibitions.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They seem to have been played at sumo exhibitions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="229">
<j>輪鼓褌脱（太食調）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rinko-kodatsu (Taishiki-cho) (a tune of gagaku music corresponding to Taishiki-cho tune of togaku music).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rinko-kodatsu (Taishiki-cho) (a tune of gagaku music corresponding to the Taishiki-cho tune of togaku music).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rinko-kodatsu (Taishiki-cho) (a tune of gagaku music corresponding to the Taishiki-cho tune of togaku music).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="230">
<j>剣気褌脱（盤渉調）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kenki-kotatsu (Banshiki-cho) (a tune of gagaku music corresponding to Banshiki-cho tune of togaku music).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenki-kotatsu (Banshiki-cho) (a tune of gagaku music corresponding to the Banshiki-cho tune of togaku music).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenki-kotatsu (Banshiki-cho) (a tune of gagaku music corresponding to the Banshiki-cho tune of togaku music).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="231">
<j>昔から妊婦に関して「夫のふんどし（六尺）(地方によっては裸祭り参加者のふんどし)を腹巻にすると安産できる」と言う言い伝えがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A legend about a pregnant woman has always been believed that she may have an easy delivery if she wears as her belly-band the rokushaku fundoshi loincloth of her husband (or of someone who participated in a naked festival, depending on regions.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a legend on the belief that a pregnant woman may have an easy delivery if she wears as her belly-band the rokushaku fundoshi loincloth of her husband (or of someone who participated in a naked festival, depending on regions.)</e>
<cmt>re-wrote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a legend on the belief that a pregnant woman may have an easy delivery if she wears as her belly-band the roku-shaku fundoshi loincloth of her husband (or of someone who participated in a naked festival, depending on regions).</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース消去、ピリオドの位置を移動、roku-shaku fundoshiとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="232">
<j>徳川家康は倹約家で自身は浅黄に染めたふんどしを常に使用し、家臣にもそれを勧めていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, an economical person, was reportedly wearing always a fundoshi loincloth dyed in pale yellow, and also encouraged his retainers to do so.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, an economical person, was reportedly always wearing a fundoshi loincloth dyed in pale yellow, and also encouraged his retainers to do so.</e>
<cmt>re-wrote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, an economical person, was reportedly always wearing a fundoshi loincloth dyed in pale yellow, and also encouraged his retainers to do so.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="233">
<j>しかし、いかに骨太の三河武士でも下帯だけは真白のものを使用したとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But, he used a white fundoshi loincloth when he wore it as underwear to cover his privates, however big-boned samurai warrior from Mikawa province he was.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But, he used a white fundoshi loincloth as underwear to cover his privates, however, he was a big-boned samurai warrior from Mikawa province.</e>
<cmt>re-wrote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But, he used a white fundoshi loincloth as underwear to cover his privates, even though he was a big-boned samurai warrior from Mikawa Province.</e>
<cmt>however, →even thoughとし、余分なスペース消去、provinceの頭文字を大文字に変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 AlleborgoBot(id:119729), Los688(id:12316), Iyasaka77(id:236678), 0null0(id:582), CommonsDelinker(id:84593), Lupinoid(id:68), フンドシ王子(id:137860), Preacher(id:39996), Ultratomio(id:1090), Hephaistos(id:203283), Greenland4(id:114494), Kamawanu(id:20537), ＋－(id:17104), Dr jimmy(id:111486), A. J. Kuonji(id:68661), ふんどし(id:109181), Point136(id:211299), YukkeBot2(id:251491), Mikomaid(id:56139), ウンチマン(id:19007), LoL045(id:162762), MIO(id:31681), HiCULTURE(id:69227), TEy(id:32722), YANCHARIKA(id:96809), Rusk(id:9895), Alecs.bot(id:194707), Baioextra(id:164616), Fthong(id:21987), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), Sparta Praha(id:18054), Kinchan(id:54982), Sionnach(id:21673), R28Bot(id:177951), ウッでやんす高橋(id:11540), Alexbot(id:157199), Elthy(id:5957), フンドシ(id:185687), 釣ちごちゅが(id:22605), 西原恭次(id:190768), クモハモハ大王(id:185685), Tokyo Watcher(id:95142), Hachikou(id:10676), TXiKiBoT(id:107492), Yatobi(id:9686), September rain(id:237830), Kimisea(id:107834), Coffee coffee(id:144411), Loveless(id:129239), Annie(id:28656), Izayohi(id:13095), Usadasuki(id:106795), Jbot(id:181157), 逃亡者(id:14864), Damena(id:90772), Aboshi(id:9318), Nekosuki(id:20825), 竃馬(id:102733), VolkovBot(id:105371), YurikBot(id:18605), Fromm(id:71291), アセルス(id:87426), Kan1234(id:158649), こいつぅ(id:2105), 北極熊(id:182750), 博多商人コイツミ(id:63820), Ete(id:28565), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>