<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>時代祭</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jidai matsuri (Festival of the Ages)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jidai matsuri (Festival of the Ages)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jidai matsuri (Festival of the Ages)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>時代祭（じだいまつり）は、京都、平安神宮の祭り。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jidai matsuri, or Festival of the Ages, is a festival for celebrating the establishement of Heian Jingu Shrine in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jidai matsuri, or Festival of the Ages, is a festival for celebrating the establishement of Heian Jingu Shrine in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jidai matsuri is a festival of Heian-Jingu Shrine in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>その創建を祝うためのものであり京都三大祭りの一つである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The festival is one of the three most renowned festivals in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The festival is one of the three most renowned festivals in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is for celebrating the establishment of the shrine and one of the three most renowned festivals in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>起源</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Origin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Origin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Origin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>神宮の管理と保存のための市民組織として、平安講社が作られ、「祭り」はその記念事業として始まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Heian Kosha was established as a civil organization for the management and preservation of the shrine, and the festival was started as a project to celebrate anniversary.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Heian Kosha was established as a civil organization for the management and preservation of the shrine, and the festival was started as a project to celebrate it&apos;s anniversary.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Heian Kosha was established as a civil organization for the management and preservation of the Heian-jingu Shrine, and &apos;the festival&apos; was started as a project to celebrate its anniversary.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>その中で祭りを盛大にするため、東京奠都以前の京都の風俗を、時代を遡って行列を行うことが提案されたので、この祭りが「時代祭り」と呼ばれるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An idea to augument the mood of the festival was that having a procession in Kyoto styles representing each historical period, from the newest to the oldest, prior to the transfer of capital to Tokyo; and the festival started to be called &quot;Jidai matsuri,&quot; or Festival of the Ages.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An idea to augument the mood of the festival was to have a procession in Kyoto style representing each historical period, from the newest to the oldest, prior to the transfer of capital to Tokyo; and the festival started to be called &quot;Jidai matsuri,&quot; or the Festival of the Ages.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An idea to augment the mood of the festival was to have a procession in Kyoto style representing each historical period, from the newest to the oldest, prior to the transfer of capital to Tokyo; and the festival started to be called &apos;Jidai matsuri.&apos;</e>
<cmt>用語などを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>初回は、創建されたばかりの平安神宮への参拝として明治28年（1895年）10月25日に行われ、その次の回からは、「祭神である桓武天皇と孝明天皇の二柱の御霊が、住まいであった御所から街の繁栄を見ながら行列のお供を従へて神宮へ行く」形となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first festival was held on October 25, 1895 as a worship to the newly built Heian Jingu Shrine; from the next year, the festival took a form in which &quot;the two great spirits of Emperor Kanmu and Emperor Komei, who are the objects of worship, visit the shrine from Kyoto Imperial House, which used to be the residence, with a long line of attendants following in the procession, enjoying the view of the flourishing towns.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first festival was held on October 25, 1895 to worship the newly built Heian Jingu Shrine; from the following year, the festival took a form in which two great spirits of Emperor Kanmu and Emperor Komei, who are the objects of worship, visit the shrine from the Kyoto Imperial Household, which used to be their residence, with a long line of attendants following in the procession, enjoying the view of the flourishing towns.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first festival was held on October 25, 1895 to worship the newly built Heian-jingu Shrine; from the following year, the festival took a form in which &apos;two great spirits of Emperor Kanmu and Emperor Komei, who are the objects of worship, visit the shrine from the Kyoto Imperial Household, which used to be their residence, with a long line of attendants following in the procession, enjoying the view of the flourishing towns.&apos;</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>開催日も桓武天皇が長岡京から都を移し新しい都に入ったとされる日、すなわち京都の誕生日とも言える10月22日となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The date of the festival was decided to be the day Emperor Kanmu was believed to enter Kyoto, that is, on October 22, therefore, it is the &quot;birthday&quot; of Kyoto, the city he decided to be the capital moving from Nagaokakyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The date of the festival was decided to be the day Emperor Kanmu was believed to enter Kyoto, on October 22, therefore, it is the &quot;birthday&quot; of Kyoto, the city that he decided to become the capital after moving from Nagaokakyo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The date of the festival was decided to be the day Emperor Kanmu was believed to enter Kyoto, on October 22, therefore, it is the birthday of Kyoto, the city that he decided to become the capital after moving from Nagaoka-kyo (the ancient capital of Nagaoka).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>祭り自体は10月15日の参役宣状祭（行列の役柄任命）から、23日の後日祭までの期間行われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The festival starts on October 15, with Sanyaku senjosai ceremony, in which the roles in the procession are declared, and ends with the closing ceremony which is held on October 23.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The festival starts on October 15, with the Sanyaku senjosai ceremony, whereby the roles in the procession are declared, and ends with the closing ceremony held on October 23.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The festival starts on October 15, with the Sanyaku Senjosai ceremony (whereby the roles in the procession are declared), and ends with the closing ceremony held on October 23.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>行列の構成</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Structure of procession</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Structure of procession</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Structure of Procession</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>行列は7つの時代、18の列でそれぞれに時代を再現した衣装や道具を身につけた人々で行われ、最初は明治維新、ついで江戸時代、安土桃山時代、吉野、鎌倉時代、藤原、延暦と時代を遡って続く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The procession consists of performers who are dressed and have instruments and objects, forming18 sections representing seven periods, starting with Meiji Restoration, followed by Edo, Azuchi-Momoyama, Yoshino, Kamakura, Fujiwara eras, ending with Enryaku era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The procession consists of performers who are dressed and have instruments and objects, forming18 sections representing seven periods, starting with the Meiji Restoration, followed by Edo, Azuchi-Momoyama, Yoshino, Kamakura, Fujiwara eras, ending with the Enryaku era.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The procession consists of performers who are dressed and have instruments and objects, forming18 sections representing seven periods, starting with the Meiji Restoration, followed by Edo, Azuchi-Momoyama, Yoshino, Kamakura, Fujiwara periods, ending with the Enryaku era.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>参加人数は約2000人、長さは2kmに及び約3時間の行程となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The number of performers are 2,000 with the total length being 2 km, and the procession lasts about 3 hours.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The number of performers are 2,000 with the total length being 2 km, and the procession lasts about 3 hours.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The number of performers are 2,000 with the total length being 2 km, and the procession lasts about 3 hours.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>先頭の名誉奉行は京都府知事、京都市長らが務める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The head of the procession is meiyo-bugyo (the honorable comissione), which is served by the Governor of Kyoto Prefecture or Mayor of Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The head of the procession is meiyo-bugyo (the honorable comissione), which is served by the Governor of Kyoto Prefecture or Mayor of Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The head of the procession is meiyo-bugyo (the honorable commissioner), which is served by the Governor of Kyoto Prefecture, Mayor of Kyoto City, and others.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>また時代行列の後には祭り本来の主役である神幸列などが続く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinkoretsu, or the procession of the shrine deity, which is the main figure of the festival, is on the rear of the Jidai procession.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinkoretsu, or the procession of the shrine deity, which is the main figure of the festival, is at the rear of the Jidai procession.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinkoretsu (the procession of the shrine god), which is the main figure of the festival, is at the rear of the Jidai procession.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="12">
<j>行列前方、明治維新・維新勤王隊列の鼓笛隊は官軍の山国隊で、明治28年の第1回から大正時代までは生存していた元隊士が行列に参加していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The drum and bundle corps for the procession of Meiji Restoration and Restoration royalists, which are at the front part of the Jidai procession, are conscripted farmer army of loyalists, Yamaguni platoon used to be composed of actual veterans from the first festival in 1895 to sometime in Taisho era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The drum and bugle corps for the procession of Meiji Restoration and Restoration royalists, which are in the forward part of the Jidai procession, are conscripted army of farmer loyalists, Yamaguni platoon used to be composed of actual veterans from the first festival in 1895 to sometime in Taisho era.</e>
<cmt>terminology, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The drum and bugle corps for the procession of Meiji Restoration and Restoration royalists, which are in the forward part of the Jidai procession, are conscripted army of farmer loyalists, Yamaguni platoon used to be composed of actual veterans from the first festival in 1895 to sometime in the Taisho period.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>室町時代ではなく「吉野時代」列であったが、平成19年（2007年）より桓武天皇1200年記念大祭を機に室町時代列が新たに行列に加わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was only &quot;Yoshino era&quot; procession, which represents only the early Muromachi period (from mid to late 1300s); the procession for Muromachi period (representing the time period lasting till mid 1500s) has been added to the Jidai procession since 2007, after having reviewed at the opportunity of the 1200 Anniversary of the demise of Emperor Kanmu.</e>
<cmt>室町時代および吉野時代のおおよその期間を加えました。また、「桓武天皇1200年記念大祭を機に・・」は「桓武天皇1200年記念大祭を機会に見直し・・」と意訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There used to be only the &quot;Yoshino era&quot; procession, which represents only the early Muromachi period (from mid to late 1300s); the procession for the Muromachi period (representing the time period lasting till mid 1500s) had been added to the Jidai procession as of 2007, after having been reviewed at the opportunity of the 1200 Anniversary of the demise of Emperor Kanmu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There used to be only the &apos;Yoshino era&apos; procession, which represents only the early Muromachi period; the procession for the Muromachi period had been added to the Jidai procession as of 2007, after having been reviewed at the opportunity of the 1200 Anniversary of the demise of Emperor Kanmu.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションなどを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>行列のコース</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Procession route</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Procession route</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Procession Route</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="14">
<j>正午に京都御所を出発。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The procession takes off Kyoto Imperial House at noon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The procession starts at Kyoto Imperial Household at noon.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The procession starts at Kyoto Imperial Palace at noon.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>丸太町通から烏丸通に入り南下、 御池通、河原町通 と京都の中心部を練り歩き、最後は三条通から神宮通に入って平安神宮に至る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The procession goes on Maruta-machi dori street and southward on Karasuma dori street, then moves through the downtown Kyoto, from Oike-dori street to Kawaramachi dori street, and Sanjo dori street, and heading north on Jingu dori street to go back to Heian Jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It proceeds along Maruta-machi dori street and southward on Karasuma dori street, then moves through downtown Kyoto, from Oike-dori street to Kawaramachi dori street, and Sanjo dori street, heading north on Jingu dori street to return to Heian Jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It proceeds along Marutamachi-dori street and southward on Karasuma-dori street, then moves through the center of Kyoto City, from Oike-dori street to Kawaramachi-dori street, and Sanjo-dori street, heading north on Jingu-dori street to return to Heian-jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>約4.5キロ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The total route of the procession is about 4.5 km.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The total route of the procession is about 4.5 km.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The total route of the procession is about 4.5 km.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Zenzai-Doji(id:98967), ＋－(id:17104), VolkovBot(id:105371), Si-take.(id:91094), Nnh(id:474), 玄史生(id:43670), Cookie4869(id:21927), MEIJISAN(id:81096), Maxima m(id:28947), うら(id:40695), Maechan0360(id:40038), 商事品川(id:68669), Louperibot(id:128971), Hatsune(id:26654), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>