<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>天狗</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tengu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tengu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tengu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>天狗（てんぐ）は、日本の伝説の生物一覧。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tengu are Japanese legendary creatures.</e>
<cmt>原文の「一覧」の意味不明、訳出できず。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tengu are legendary Japanese creatures.</e>
<cmt>usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tengu are legendary Japanese creatures.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>一般的に山伏の服装で赤ら顔で鼻が高く、翼があり空中を飛翔するとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is generally said that they wear Yamabushi monk outfit, have a red face and long nose, and fly in the air with wings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is generally said that the Tengu is clothed as a Yamabushi monk, has a red face and long nose, and flies on wings through the air.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is generally said that the Tengu is clothed as a Yamabushi monk, has a red face and long nose, and flies on wings through the air.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>俗に人を魔道に導く魔物とされ、外法様ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are commonly said to be a devil to lead people to the path of evil, and also called Geho-sama.</e>
<cmt>外法様http://www1.tcn-catv.ne.jp/sugizaki/tontinkan/i_kemono.htm</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Tengu are commonly said to be devils that lead people to the path of evil, and are also called Geho-sama.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tengu are commonly said to be devils that lead people to the path of evil, and are also called Geho-sama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>また後白河天皇の異名でもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Go-Shirakawa was also called Tengu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Go-Shirakawa was also called Tengu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Go-Shirakawa was also called Tengu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>由来と成立</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Origin and Formation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Origin and Formation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Origin and Formation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>中国由来</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Origin in China</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Origin in China</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Origin in China</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>元来は中国の物怪で、流星または彗星の尾の流れる様子が狗（いぬ）に似ていることから、天の狗、すなわち天狗と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were originally Chinese monsters, and the way a shooting star or a comet tail passes looked like a canine, which was called Tengu, meaning a canine of the sky.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The tengu were originally Chinese monsters, and the way a shooting star or a comet tail passes looked like a canine, which was called &quot;tengu,&quot; meaning a canine of the sky.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tengu were originally Chinese monsters; correspondingly, the way a shooting star or a comet tail passes looked like a canine, which was called &quot;Tengu,&quot; meaning a canine of the sky.</e>
<cmt>天狗を大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>また、中国の奇書『山海経』西山経3巻の章莪山の項に、「獣あり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Chapter Gazan, volume 3, Seizankyo of &quot;Sankaikyo&quot;, a Chinese curiosa mentions, &apos;There is a beast.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Chapter Gazan in Volume 3, &quot;Seizankyo,&quot; of &quot;Sankaikyo,&quot; a Chinese curiosa mentions, &apos;There is a beast.</e>
<cmt>punctuation, case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Chapter Gazan in Volume 3, &quot;Seizankyo,&quot; of &quot;Sankaikyo,&quot; a Chinese curiosa mentions, &apos;There is a beast.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>その状狸（山猫を指すと考えられる）の如く、白い首、名は天狗。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It looks like a raccoon dog (this is considered to indicate a wildcat) with a white neck, whose name is Tengu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It looks like a raccoon dog (this is considered to indicate a wildcat) with a white neck, whose name is Tengu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It looks like a raccoon dog (this is considered to indicate a wildcat) with a white neck, whose name is Tengu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>その声は榴榴の様。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its voice is like a wildcat.</e>
<cmt>榴榴http://www-cc.gakushuin.ac.jp/~ori-www/suwa-f08/suwa77.htm</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its voice is like that of a wildcat.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its voice is like that of a wildcat.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>凶をふせぐによろし」とあるように天狐、アナグマにも例えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It&apos;s good to prevent misfortune,&apos; they are also compared to a fox of the sky and a badger.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It&apos;s good to prevent misfortune,&apos; and they are also compared to a fox of the sky or a badger.</e>
<cmt>conjunction</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It&apos;s good to prevent misfortune,&apos; and they are also compared to a fox of the sky or a badger.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>なお仏教では、経論律の三蔵には、本来、天狗という言葉はない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for Buddhism, Pali Canon with Sutra, Discipline and Special teachings doesn&apos;t have the word Tengu originally.</e>
<cmt>三蔵http://buddhism.about.com/od/thetripitaka/a/tripitakahistor.htm</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for Buddhism, the &quot;Pali Canon with Sutra, Discipline and Special Teachings&quot; didn&apos;t originally have the word &quot;tengu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for Buddhism, the Pali Canon with Sutra, Discipline and Special Teachings didn&apos;t originally contain the word &quot;Tengu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>ダブルクォーテーションを省き、天狗を大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>しかし、『正法念経』19には「一切身分光燄騰赫。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, &quot;Shohonengyo&quot; volume 19 mentions, &apos;Flames were burning brightly from all over the body.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, &quot;Shohonengyo,&quot; Volume 19, mentions, &apos;Flames were burning brightly from all over the body.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, &quot;Shohonengyo,&quot; Volume 19, mentions, &apos;Flames were burning brightly from all over the body.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>見此相者皆言憂流迦下。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Everybody who saw this said Ulkā came down.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Everybody who saw this said, &quot;Ulkā came down.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Everybody who saw this said, &quot;Ulkā came down.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>魏言天狗下」とあり、これは古代インドのサンスクリット語のUlkā（漢訳音写：憂流迦）という彗星の名を、天狗と翻訳したものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It means Tengu came down in Chinese,&apos; and this Tengu was translated from Ulkā (憂流迦 in Chinese character), a comet name in Sanskrit of ancient India.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It means that Tengu came down in Chinese,&apos; and this &quot;tengu&quot; was translated from Ulkā (憂流迦 in Chinese characters), a name for a comet in the Sanskrit of ancient India.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It means &apos;Tengu came down in Chinese,&apos; and this Tengu was translated from Ulkā (憂流迦 in Chinese characters), a name for a comet in the Sanskrit of ancient India.</e>
<cmt>ダブルクォーテーションを省き、天狗を大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>日本において天狗の言葉が初めて見られるのは『日本書紀』で、634年、怪音をたてて空を飛来するもの（かなり地表まで落下した流星か）を唐から来た人が、「流星にあらず、これ天狗アマキツネなり」と呼んだという記載がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan, the word Tengu was seen in &quot;Nihon-shoki&quot; for the first time, and it mentions that, in 634, a person from Tang called something flying in the sky with strange noise (it might be a shooting star which fell pretty close to the ground) &apos;it is not a shooting star, it is Tengu-Amakitsune.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan, the word &quot;Tengu&quot; was seen in &quot;Nihon Shoki&quot; for the first time, and it mentions that, in 634, a person from Tang said of something flying in the sky with a strange noise (it might be a shooting star, which fell fairly close to the ground), &apos;It is not a shooting star, it is Tengu-Amakitsune.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan, the word &quot;Tengu&quot; was seen in &quot;Nihon Shoki&quot; for the first time, and it mentions that, in 634, a person from Tang said of something flying in the sky with a strange noise (it might be a shooting star, which fell fairly close to the ground), &apos;It is not a shooting star, it is Tengu-Amakitsune.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>奈良～平安時代初期における天狗とは、『山海経』の形状の通り天狐であり、やはり彗星あるいは流星を指したと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tengu from the Nara era to the early Heian era meant a fox of the sky as the shape described in &quot;Sankaikyo&quot;, and it is considered to indicate a comet or shooting star after all.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tengu from the Nara period to the early Heian period meant a fox of the sky as the shape described in &quot;Sankaikyo,&quot; so ultimately it is considered to indicate a comet or a shooting star.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tengu from the Nara period to the early Heian period meant a fox of the sky as the shape described in &quot;Sankaikyo,&quot; so ultimately it is considered to indicate a comet or a shooting star.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>付会と俗信</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Stretch and Superstition</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Stretching and Superstition</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Stretching and Superstition</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="16">
<j>空海や円珍などにより密教が日本に伝えられると、後にこれが胎蔵界曼荼羅に配置される星辰・星宿信仰と付会（ふかい）され、また奈良時代から役行者より行われていた山岳信仰とも相まっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Kukai and Enchin introduced esoteric Buddhism to Japan, this is stretched to worship of constellation on Womb World Mandala, and also combined with mountain worship having done by Ennogyoja since the Nara era.</e>
<cmt>胎蔵界曼荼羅http://www2.bremen.de/info/nepal/Gallery-3/Cosmos/9-6/garbhadatu-0.htm円行者http://100.yahoo.co.jp/detail/役行者/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Kukai and Enchin introduced esoteric Buddhism to Japan, it was extended to the worship of the constellations on the Womb World Mandala, and was also combined with mountain worship, having been performed by Ennogyoja since the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Kukai and Enchin introduced esoteric Buddhism to Japan, it was extended to the worship of the constellations on the Womb World Mandala, and was also combined with mountain worship, having been performed by Ennogyoja since the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>そして鎌倉時代になると、修験道の山伏（山伏）をも天狗と呼ぶようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Kamakura era, Yamabushi monks of Shugendo were also called Tengu.</e>
<cmt>（山伏）は不要と判断、訳出せず。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Kamakura period, the Yamabushi monks of Shugendo were also called tengu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Kamakura period, the Yamabushi monks of Shugendo were also called Tengu.</e>
<cmt>天狗を大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>これは、その風体や修行法が独特であることから、既成の宗派から軽蔑されて呼んだものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is because their appearance and trainings were unique, and existent religious schools called them so with contempt.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is because their appearance and training were unique, and the existent religious schools called them so with an inference of contempt.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is because their appearance and training were unique, and the existing religious schools called them so with contempt.</e>
<cmt>文法間違い。“the existent religious”=&gt;” the existing religious” “an inference of”は削除。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>山伏は名利を得んとする傲慢で我見の強い者として、死後に転生し、魔界の一種として天狗道が、一部に想定されて解釈された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A Yamabushi monk was supposed to be worldly-minded, arrogant and self-centered, and to transmigrate after death, and some people assumed and interpreted the realm of Tengu as a sort of devildom.</e>
<cmt>天狗道http://www.onmarkproductions.com/html/tengu-scholarship-pop.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A Yamabushi monk was supposed to be worldly minded, arrogant and self-centered, and was supposed to transmigrate after death, but some people assumed and interpreted the realm of tengu as a sort of devildom.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A Yamabushi monk was supposed to be worldly minded, arrogant and self-centered, and was supposed to transmigrate after death, but some people assumed and interpreted the realm of Tengu as a sort of devildom.</e>
<cmt>天狗を大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>一方民間では、平地民が山地を異界として畏怖し、そこで起きる怪異な現象を天狗のイメージに付託した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile among the public, people living in flatlands were in awe of mountains as a different world, and they referred mysterious phenomena happening there to the image of Tengu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, among the public, people living in flatlands were in awe of the mountains as a different world, and they associated the mysterious phenomena happening there with the image of Tengu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, among the public, people living in flatlands were in awe of the mountains as a different world, and they associated the mysterious phenomena happening there with the image of Tengu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>ここから天狗を山の神と見なす傾向が生まれ、各種天狗の像を目して狗賓（ぐひん）、山人、山の神などと称する地域が現在でも存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This caused tendency to consider Tengu as Mountain God, and some regions regarding the image of various Tengu as Guhin, Yamando, Mountain God still exist.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This brought forth a tendency to consider Tengu as a mountain god, and in some regions the aspect regarding the image of various tengu as Guhin, Yamando (Mountain God) still exists.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This brought forth a tendency to consider Tengu as a mountain god, and in some regions the aspect regarding the image of various Tengu as &quot;Guhin,&quot; &quot;Yamando&quot; or &quot;a mountain god&quot; still exists.</e>
<cmt>天狗を大文字にしました。「狗賓（ぐひん）、山人、山の神」を原稿どおり並列に表記。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="22">
<j>したがって、今日、一般的に伝えられる、鼻が高く（長く）赤ら顔、山伏の装束に身を包み、一本歯の高下駄を履き、葉団扇を持って自在に空を飛び悪巧みをするといった性質は、中世以降に解釈されるようになったもので、本来まったく性質の異なったものが習合された俗信であるとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, their natures generally passed on today, such as a long nose, a red face, wearing Yamabushi monk outfit, wearing wooden clogs with single support, flying freely in the sky with a leaf fan and having evil design, have been interpreted since the middle ages, and it is considered to be superstition blending of originally quite different natures.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the characteristics that have generally been passed on till today--a long nose and red face, wearing the attire of a Yamabushi monk, and wearing wooden clogs with single support, flying freely in the sky with a leaf fan and having evil design--have been interpreted since the middle ages, and it is considered to be the superstitious blending of originally quite different characteristics.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the characteristics that have generally been passed on till today--a long nose and red face, wearing the attire of a Yamabushi monk, and wearing wooden clogs with single support, flying freely in the sky with a leaf fan and having evil design--have been interpreted since the middle ages, and it is considered to be the superstitious blending of originally quite different characteristics.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="23">
<j>事実、当時の天狗の形状姿は一定せず、多くは僧侶形で、時として童子姿や鬼形をとることもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In fact, the figure of the Tengu of the day was not fixed, and most of them looked like a monk and some were like a child figure or goblin figure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In fact, the figure of the Tengu of the period was not fixed; most often it would resemble a monk, but some had the figure of a child or a goblin.</e>
<cmt>punctuation, article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact, the figure of the Tengu of the period was not fixed; most often it would resemble a monk, but some had the figure of a child or a goblin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>また、空中を飛翔することから、鳶（とび）のイメージで捉えられることも多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since they flew in the air, they were often viewed as the image of kite.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since they flew through the air, they were often perceived in the image of a kite.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since they flew through the air, they were often perceived in the image of a kite.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>さらに尼の転生した者を「尼天狗」と呼称することもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, the one transmigrated from a nun was sometimes called &apos;Ama Tengu.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the one that transmigrated from a nun was sometimes called &apos;Ama Tengu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the one that transmigrated from a nun was sometimes called &apos;Ama Tengu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>平安末期成立の『今昔物語集』には、空を駆け、人に憑く「鷹」と呼ばれる魔物や、顔は天狗、体は人間で、一対の羽を持つ魔物など、これらの天狗の説話が多く記載された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Tales of Times Now Past&quot; written in the late Heian era described a lot of tales of Tengu such as a devil flying in the sky and possessing people called &apos;Hawk,&apos; and one having a face of Tengu, a body of human and a pair of wings.</e>
<cmt>今昔物語集http://eow.alc.co.jp/今昔物語/UTF-8/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Tales of Times Now Past,&quot; written during the late Heian period, described many tales of Tengu, such as a devil called &apos;Hawk&apos; that would fly through the sky and possess people, and one having the face of Tengu with a human body and a pair of wings.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Tales of Times Now Past,&quot; written during the late Heian period, described many tales of Tengu, such as a devil called &apos;Hawk&apos; that would fly through the sky and possess people, and one having the face of Tengu with a human body and a pair of wings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>これは1296年（永仁4年）に『天狗草子』として描写作成された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was described and created as &quot;Tengu-zoshi&quot; in 1296.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was created and described as &quot;Tengu-zoshi&quot; in 1296.</e>
<cmt>syntax</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was created and described as &quot;Tengu-zoshi&quot; in 1296.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>ここには当時の興福寺や東大寺など7大寺の僧侶が堕落した姿相が風刺として描かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The corrupted image of the monks of the seven major temples of the day including Kofuku-ji Temple and Todai-ji Temple is depicted as a satire.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The corrupted image of the monks of the seven major temples of the day, including Kofuku-ji Temple and Todai-ji Temple, is depicted as a satire.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The corrupted image of the monks of the seven major temples of the day, including Kofuku-ji Temple and Todai-ji Temple, is depicted as a satire.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>これら天狗の容姿は、室町時代に成立したとされる『御伽草子・天狗の内裏』の、鞍馬寺の護法魔王尊あるいは鞍馬天狗などが、その初期の原型であり、おそらく室町時代初期以降に変化したものと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gohomao-son or Kurama Tengu of Kurama-dera Temple in &quot;Otogi-zoshi, Tengu no Dairi&quot; allegedly made in the Muromachi era was the first model of the appearance of these Tengu, and it is considered to have probably changed after the early Muromachi era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gohomao-son, or Kurama Tengu of Kurama-dera Temple, in &quot;Otogi-zoshi, Tengu no Dairi,&quot; allegedly made during the Muromachi era, was the first model of the appearance of these tengu, and it is considered to have probably changed after the early Muromachi era.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gohomao-son, or Kurama Tengu of Kurama-dera Temple, in &quot;Otogi-zoshi, Tengu no Dairi,&quot; allegedly created during the Muromachi era, was the first model of the appearance of these Tengu, but it is considered to have probably changed after the early Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>天狗を大文字にしました。era→periodに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="30">
<j>『平家物語』では、「人にて人ならず、鳥にて鳥ならず、犬にて犬ならず、足手は人、かしらは犬、左右に羽根はえ、飛び歩くもの」とあり、鎌倉時代になると、験力を誇示する天台僧らに、仏教の超越性を証明する為の標的とされ、『是害坊絵巻』を始めとする書物に、天台の僧に戦いを挑み、無残に敗退する天狗の物語が伝えられるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;The Tale of the Heike&quot; describes, &apos;It&apos;s a human but not a human, a bird but not a bird, a dog but not a dog, and it has human arms and legs, a dog&apos;s head, a pair of wings and it flies,&apos; and in the Kamakura era, Tendai monks flaunting miraculous efficacy made it a target to prove transcendency of Buddhism, and some books including &quot;Zegaibo Emaki&quot; mention stories that Tengu challenged a Tendai monk to a fight and got defeated miserably.</e>
<cmt>平家物語http://www.gotterdammerung.org/books/reviews/t/tale-of-the-heike.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;The Tale of the Heike&quot; describes, &apos;It&apos;s a human but not a human, a bird but not a bird, a dog but not a dog, and it has human arms and legs, a dog&apos;s head and a pair of wings, and it flies&apos;; moreover, in the Kamakura era Tendai monks flaunting miraculous efficacy made it an objective to prove the transcendence of Buddhism, and some books, including &quot;Zegaibo Emaki,&quot; mention stories that Tengu challenged a Tendai monk to a fight and was defeated in misery.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tale of the Heike describes, &apos;It&apos;s a human but not a human, a bird but not a bird, a dog but not a dog, and it has human arms and legs, a dog&apos;s head and a pair of wings, and it flies&apos;; moreover, in the Kamakura period Tendai monks flaunting miraculous efficacy made it an objective to prove the transcendence of Buddhism, and some books, including &quot;Zegaibo Emaki,&quot; mention stories that Tengu challenged a Tendai monk to a fight and was defeated miserably.</e>
<cmt>慣用句が不自然。 “was defeated in misery.” =&gt; “was defeated miserably.”era→periodに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>また、林羅山の『神社考』「天狗論」、また平田篤胤の『古今妖魅考』に、京都市上京区に存在する「白峯神宮」の祭神である金色の鳶と化した讃岐院（崇徳上皇）、長い翼を持つ沙門となった後鳥羽上皇、龍車を駆る後醍醐天皇ら、『太平記』に登場する御霊が天狗として紹介される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, &apos;Comments on Tengu&apos; of &quot;A Study on Shrines&quot; by Razan HAYASHI and &quot;A Study on Monsters of All Ages&quot; by Atsutane HIRATA describe the souls appeared in &quot;Taiheiki&quot; including Sanuki-in （Ex-Emperor Sutoku) having turned into a gold kite as the God enshrined in &apos;Shiramine jingu Shrine&apos; in Kamigyo Ward, Kyoto City, Ex-Emperor Go-toba having turned into a Shamon with long wings, and Emperor Go-Daigo driving Ryusha (Emperor&apos;s car), as Tengu.</e>
<cmt>林羅山http://100.yahoo.co.jp/detail/林羅山/平田篤胤 http://www.kurihiko.com/iwamaannai/tengu/hirata/hirata.html太平記http://www.ninpo.org/historicalrecords/taiheiki1.html白峯神宮http://www.kamimoude.org/jinjya/kyoto-city/kamigyou/k-shiramine/index.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, &apos;Comments on Tengu&apos; of &quot;A Study on Shrines&quot; by Razan HAYASHI and &quot;A Study on Monsters of All Ages&quot; by Atsutane HIRATA describe the souls that appeared in &quot;Taiheiki,&quot; including Sanuki-in （former Emperor Sutoku) having turned into a gold kite as the god enshrined in &apos;Shiramine jingu Shrine&apos; in Kamigyo ward, Kyoto City, former Emperor Go-toba having turned into a Shamon with long wings, and Emperor Go-Daigo driving Ryusha (an Emperor&apos;s car), as tengu.</e>
<cmt>grammar, case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, &apos;Comments on Tengu&apos; in &quot;A Study on Shrines,&quot; by Razan HAYASHI, and &quot;A Study on Monsters of All Ages,&quot; by Atsutane HIRATA, describe the souls that appeared in &quot;Taiheiki,&quot; including Sanuki-in （the Retired Emperor Sutoku) having turned into a gold kite as the god enshrined in &apos;Shiramine jingu Shrine&apos; in Kamigyo Ward, Kyoto City, the Retired Emperor Gotoba having turned into a shamon with long wings, and Emperor Go-Daigo driving Ryusha (an Emperor&apos;s car), as Tengu.</e>
<cmt>天狗を大文字にしました。the former Emperor Sutoku→the Retired Emperor Sutokuに変更しました。the former Emperor Go-toba→the Retired Emperor Gotobaに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="32">
<j>天狗は、慢心の権化とされ、鼻が高いのはその象徴である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tengu is conceit personified, and its long nose represents it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tengu is the personification of conceit, as represented by its long nose.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tengu is the personification of conceit, as represented by its long nose.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>これから転じて「天狗になる」と言えば自慢が高じている様を表す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By extension, &apos;become Tengu&apos; means boasting too much.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By extension, &apos;become tengu&apos; means boasting too much.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By extension, &apos;becoming Tengu&apos; means being excessively boastful.</e>
<cmt>天狗を大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>彼等は総じて教えたがり魔である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They want to teach in general.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Generally, they seek to teach.</e>
<cmt>better</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Generally, they seek to teach.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>中世には、仏教の六道のほかに天狗道があり、仏道を学んでいる為地獄に堕ちず、邪法を扱うため極楽にも行けない無間（むげん）地獄と想定、解釈された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the middle age, there was the realm of Tengu other than Six realms of Buddhism, which was assumed and interpreted as Avici for those who were not going to fall into the hell because they learned Buddhism, and not going to the heaven either because they did wrong.</e>
<cmt>六道http://buddhism.about.com/od/basicbuddhistteachings/tp/Six-Realms-of-Existence.htm無間地獄http://www.answers.com/topic/avici</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Middle Ages there was the realm of tengu other than the six realms of Buddhism, which was assumed and interpreted as Avici for those who were not going to fall into Hell because they had learned Buddhism, but were not going to Heaven either because they had done wrong.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Middle Ages there was the realm of Tengu other than the six realms of Buddhism, which was assumed and interpreted as Avici for those who were not going to fall into Hell because they had learned Buddhism but were not going to Heaven either because they had done wrong.</e>
<cmt>天狗を大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>天狗の種類</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Types of Tengu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Types of Tengu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Types of Tengu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="36">
<j>前述のように、天狗が成立した背景には複数の流れがあるため、その種類や姿もさまざまである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As described above, there are more than one stream in the background of forming Tengu, so their types and appearance vary.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As described above, there is more than one stream contributing to the formation of the tengu, so they vary in type and appearance.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As described above, there is more than one stream contributing to the formation of the Tengu, so they vary in type and appearance.</e>
<cmt>天狗を大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>一般的な姿は修験者の様相で、その顔は赤く、鼻が高い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Generally they look like a Shugendo practitioner with a red face and a long nose.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Generally, they look like Shugendo practitioners with red faces and long noses.</e>
<cmt>plural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Generally, they look like Shugendo practitioners with red faces and long noses.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>翼があり空中を飛翔するとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are supposed to have wings to fly in the sky.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are supposed to have wings that enable them to fly through the sky.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are supposed to have wings that enable them to fly through the sky.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>このうち、鼻の高いのを「大天狗」、鼻先が尖ったのは「小天狗」あるいは｢烏天狗｣という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among them, the ones with a long nose are called &apos;Great Tengu,&apos; and the ones with a sharp nose &apos;Small Tengu&apos; or &apos;Crow Tengu.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among them, the ones with long noses are called &apos;Great Tengu&apos; and the ones with sharp noses are called &apos;Small Tengu&apos; or &apos;Crow Tengu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among them, the ones with long noses are called &apos;Great Tengu&apos; and the ones with sharp noses are called &apos;Small Tengu&apos; or &apos;Crow Tengu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="40">
<j>種類としては、天狗として世にあだなし、業尽きて後、再び人身を得ようとする「波旬」、自尊心と驕慢を縁として集う「魔縁」と解釈される場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for types, some are interpreted as &apos;Hajun&apos; which try to regain human body after living as infamous Tengu, or &apos;Maen&apos; which gather linked with pride and arrogance.</e>
<cmt>波旬新選古語辞典</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for types, some are interpreted as &apos;Hajun,&apos; which try to regain human form after living as infamous Tengu; or as &apos;Maen,&apos; which gather together, linked by pride and arrogance.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for types, some are interpreted as &apos;Hajun,&apos; which try to regain human form after living in infamy as Tengu; or as &apos;Maen,&apos; which gather together, linked by pride and arrogance.</e>
<cmt>「天狗ととして世にあだなし」の部分をよりクリアにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="41">
<j>またその伝承も各地に伝わっており、変わったものとして、紀州に伝わる、山伏に似た白衣を着、自由自在に空を飛ぶ「空神」、岩手県南部では「スネカ」、北部では「ナゴミ」「ナゴミタクリ」という、小正月に怠け者のすねにできるという火まだらをはぎとりに現われる天狗などが伝えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its folklore has been handed down in many regions, and as rare ones, &apos;Kujin (Flying God)&apos; wearing white clothes like a Yamabushi monk is handed down in Kishu, and &apos;Suneka&apos; in the southern Iwate Prefecture, &apos;Nagomi&apos; or &apos;Nagomitakuri&apos; in the northern Iwate Prefecture, which shows up to rip a spot that is believed to appear on a lazy person&apos;s shin on the fifteenth day of the new year, is handed down.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its folklore has been handed down in many regions, but among the more rare are &apos;Kujin (flying god)&apos; wearing white clothes like a Yamabushi monk, as described in Kishu, and &apos;Suneka&apos; in southern Iwate Prefecture, &apos;Nagomi&apos; or &apos;Nagomitakuri&apos; in northern Iwate Prefecture, which shows up to rip a spot that is believed to appear on a lazy person&apos;s shin on the fifteenth day of the new year.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its folklore has been handed down in many regions, but among the more rare are &apos;Kujin (flying god),&apos; which wears white clothing like a Yamabushi monk and flies freely in the sky, as described in Kishu; and &apos;Suneka&apos; in southern Iwate Prefecture, &apos;Nagomi&apos; or &apos;Nagomitakuri&apos; in northern Iwate Prefecture, which appears in order to rip a spot that is believed to appear on a lazy person&apos;s shin on the fifteenth day of the new year.</e>
<cmt>「自由自在に空を飛ぶ」の部分の訳を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>姿を見た者はいないが、五月十五日の月夜の晩に太平洋から飛んでくる「アンモ」もこの類で、イロリにばかりあたっている怠け童子の脛には、茶色の火班がついているので、その皮を剥ぎにくるという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Anmo,&quot; flying from the Pacific ocean and coming on the moonlit night on May 15th, which nobody has seen, is also this sort, and it is said to come and rip the skin with a brown spot which a lazy child only warming himself at the hearth has at his shin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Anmo,&quot; which flies from the Pacific Ocean and arrives unseen on the moonlit night of May 15th, is also of this sort, and it is said to come and rip the skin with a brown spot which a lazy child simply warming himself at the hearth will have on his shin.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Anmo,&quot; which flies from the Pacific Ocean and arrives unseen on the moonlit night of May 15th, is also of this sort, and it is said to come and rip the skin with a brown spot which a lazy child simply warming himself at the hearth will have on his shin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>弱い子供を助けてくれ、病気で寝ている子はアンモを拝むと治るという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Anmo helps weak children, and praying for it makes a sick child in bed cured.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Anmo helps weak children and that praying for it can cure a bedridden child.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Anmo helps weak children and that praying for it can cure a bedridden child.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>静岡県大井川では、『諸国里人談』に、一名を「境鳥」といい、顔は人に似て正面に目があり、翼を広げるとその幅約6尺、人間と同じような容姿、大きさで、嘴を持つ「木の葉天狗」が伝えられており、夜更けに川面を飛び交い魚を取っていたと記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Shokoku Satobitodan&quot; mentions, in Oi-gawa River, Shizuoka Prefecture, &apos;Konoha Tengu&apos; also known as &apos;Sakaidori,&apos; having eyes on the front face like human, 180cm long wings when spread, similar appearance and size with human, and a beak, and describes it was flying over the river and catching fish late at night.</e>
<cmt>大井川http://100.yahoo.co.jp/detail/大井川（静岡県の川）/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Shokoku Satobitodan&quot; mentions, in the Oi-gawa River, Shizuoka Prefecture, &apos;Konoha Tengu&apos; also known as &apos;Sakaidori,&apos; having eyes on the front of the face like a human, 180cm long wings when spread, and a size and appearance similar to a human, but with a beak, and describes it as flying over the river late at night, catching fish.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Shokoku Satobitodan&quot; mentions, in the Oi-gawa River, Shizuoka Prefecture, &apos;Konoha Tengu&apos; also known as &apos;Sakaidori,&apos; having eyes on the front of the face like a human, 180cm long wings when spread, and a size and appearance similar to a human, but with a beak, and describes it as flying over the river late at night, catching fish.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>また、鳥のくちばしと翼を持った鳥類系天狗の形状を色濃く残す「烏天狗」は有名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Crow Tengu&apos; which has a bird&apos;s beak and wings and is strongly influenced by the shape of avian Tengu is famous.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Crow Tengu&apos; is famous, having a bird&apos;s beak and wings and is strongly influenced by the shape of an avian tengu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The famous &apos;Crow Tengu,&apos; with its bird&apos;s beak and wings, is strongly influenced by the shape of an avian Tengu.</e>
<cmt>天狗を大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>有名な是害坊天狗などもこの種で、多くの絵巻にその姿が残されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The famous Zegaibo Tengu is also this sort, and its figure can be found in numbers of picture scrolls.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The famous Zegaibo Tengu is also of this sort, and its figure can be found in numerous picture scrolls.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The famous Zegaibo Tengu is also of this sort, and its figure can be found in numerous picture scrolls.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>尼がなった「女天狗」や、狼の姿をした狗賓という天狗もいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were also &apos;Female Tengu&apos; transmigrated from a nun, and Tengu in the shape of a wolf called Guhin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were also the &apos;female tengu&apos; transmigrated from a nun and a tengu in the shape of a wolf called Guhin.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were also the &apos;female Tengu,&apos; having transmigrated from a nun and a Tengu in the shape of a wolf called Guhin.</e>
<cmt>天狗を大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>神としての天狗</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tengu as God</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tengu as a god</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tengu as a god</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="48">
<j>神として信仰の対象となる程の大天狗には名が付いており、愛宕山の太郎坊、鞍馬山の僧正坊（鞍馬天狗）、比良山の次郎坊の他、比叡山法性坊、英彦山豊前坊、富士山太郎坊、白峰山相模坊、等が知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Major Tengu which become the object of religion as God have names, and famous one include Tarobo of Mount Atago, Sojobo of Mount Kurama (Kurama Tengu), Jirobo of Mount Hira, as well as Hoshobo of Mount Hiei, Buzenbo of Mount Ehiko, Tarobo of Mount Fuji and Sagamibo of Mount Shiramine.</e>
<cmt>僧正坊http://www.geocities.jp/mythmaster/soujoubou.htm</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The major tengu that became objects of religion as gods have names, and famous ones include Tarobo of Mount Atago, Sojobo of Mount Kurama (Kurama Tengu) and Jirobo of Mount Hira, as well as Hoshobo of Mount Hiei, Buzenbo of Mount Ehiko, Tarobo of Mount Fuji and Sagamibo of Mount Shiramine.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The major Tengu that became objects of religion as gods have names, and famous ones include Tarobo of Mount Atago, Sojobo of Mount Kurama (Kurama Tengu) and Jirobo of Mount Hira, as well as Hoshobo of Mount Hiei, Buzenbo of Mount Ehiko, Tarobo of Mount Fuji and Sagamibo of Mount Shiramine.</e>
<cmt>天狗を大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>滋賀県高島市では「グヒンサン」と言い、大空を飛び、祭見物をしたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The one in Takashima City, Shiga Prefecture is called &apos;Guhinsan&apos; and is said to have flown in the sky and visited a festival.</e>
<cmt>高島市http://100.yahoo.co.jp/detail/高島（市）/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The one in Takashima City, Shiga Prefecture, is called &apos;Guhinsan&apos; and is said to have flown through the sky and visited a festival.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The one in Takashima City, Shiga Prefecture, is called &apos;Guhinsan&apos; and is said to have flown through the sky and visited a festival.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>高島町大溝に火をつけにいったが、隙間がなくて失敗したという話が伝わっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that it went to Omizo, Takashima Cho to set fire, but failed because there was no space.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that it went to Omizo, Takashima Cho in order to set a fire but failed because there was no space.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that it went to Omizo, Takashima Cho in order to set a fire but failed because there was no space.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>鹿児島県奄美大島でも、山に住む「テンゴヌカミ」が知られ、大工の棟梁であったが、嫁迎えのため六十畳の家を一日で作るので藁人形に息を吹きかけて生命を与えて使い、二千人を山に、二千人を海に帰したと言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Amamioshima, Kagoshima Prefecture, &apos;Tengonukami&quot; living in a mountain is well-known, and it is said that a master carpenter gave life to straw men by blowing in order to have them work to build a house with 60 mats for his bride in a day, and had two thousand men go back to the mountain and another two thousand to the sea.</e>
<cmt>奄美大島http://100.yahoo.co.jp/detail/奄美大島/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Amamioshima, Kagoshima Prefecture, the one well-known as &apos;Tengonukami&quot; lives in a mountain, and it is said that a master carpenter gave life to straw men by blowing forth in order to have them work to build a house with 60 mats for his bride in a day, and had 2,000 men go back to the mountain and another 2,000 to the sea.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Amamioshima, Kagoshima Prefecture, the one well-known as &apos;Tengonukami&quot; lives in a mountain, and it is said that a master carpenter gave life to straw men by blowing forth in order to have them work to build a house with 60 mats for his bride in a day, and had 2,000 men go back to the mountain and another 2,000 to the sea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>愛媛県石鎚山では、六歳の男の子が山頂でいなくなり、いろいろ探したが見つからず、やむなく家に帰ると、すでに子供は戻っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Mount Ishizuchi, Ehime Prefecture, a 6-year old boy got lost at the mountaintop, and after people looked for him everywhere and didn&apos;t find him and gave up and went back home, the boy was already back home.</e>
<cmt>石鎚山http://100.yahoo.co.jp/detail/石鎚山/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At Mount Ishizuchi, Ehime Prefecture, a six-year-old boy got lost at the mountaintop, but after people looked for him everywhere and didn&apos;t find him and gave up and went back home, it was discovered that the boy was already back home.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At Mount Ishizuchi, Ehime Prefecture, a six-year-old boy got lost at the mountaintop, but after people looked for him everywhere and didn&apos;t find him and gave up and went back home, it was discovered that the boy was already back home.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>子に聞くと、山頂の祠の裏で小便をしていると、真っ黒い大男が出てきて子供をたしなめ、「送ってあげるから目をつぶっておいで」と言い、気がつくと自分の家の裏庭に立っていたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When asked, he explained; when he was having a piss in the back of the shrine at the mountaintop, a big inky man came out and reproved him, and said &apos;I will take you home, so close your eyes,&apos; then he found himself standing in the backyard of his own home.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When asked, he explained that while he was urinating at the back of the shrine on the mountaintop, a &apos;big, inky man&apos; came out and reproved him, saying, &apos;I will take you home, so close your eyes,&apos; whereupon he found himself standing in the backyard of his own home.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When asked, he explained that while he was urinating at the back of the shrine on the mountaintop, a &apos;big, inky man&apos; came out and reproved him, saying, &apos;I will take you home, so close your eyes,&apos; whereupon he found himself standing in the backyard of his own home.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>山神としての天狗</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tengu as Mountain God</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tengu as a mountain god</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tengu as a mountain god</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="54">
<j>天狗はしばしば輝く鳥として描かれ、松明丸、魔縁とも呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tengu was often depicted as a shiny bird, and also called Taimatsumaru or Maen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tengu has often been depicted as a shiny bird and has also been called Taimatsumaru or Maen.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tengu has often been depicted as a shiny bird and has also been called Taimatsumaru or Maen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>怨霊となった崇徳上皇が、天狗の王として金色の鷲として描かれるのはこのためである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is why Ex-Emperor Sutoku turned into a ghost was depicted as a gold kite as the Tengu king.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is why the former Emperor Sutoku turned into a ghost and was depicted as a golden kite as the Tengu king.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is why the Retired Emperor Sutoku turned into a ghost and was depicted as a golden eagle as the Tengu king.</e>
<cmt>「金色の鷲」　の「鷲」の訳語をeagleに修正しました。the former Emperor Sutoku→the Retired Emperor Sutokuに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>また、山神との関係も深く、霊峰とされる山々には、必ず天狗がいるとされ（それゆえ山伏の姿をしていると考えられる）、実際に山神を天狗（ダイバ）とする地方は多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is deeply related with Mountain God, and sacred mountains are always supposed to have Tengu (therefore, they are considered to be in the shape of a Yamabushi monk), and many regions actually have Tengu (Daiba) as Mountain God.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is deeply related to the mountain god, and sacred mountains are always supposed to have tengu (thus they are considered to be in the shape of a Yamabushi monk), and many regions actually have tengu (daiba) as mountain gods.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is deeply related to the mountain god, and sacred mountains are always supposed to have Tengu (thus they are considered to be in the shape of a Yamabushi monk); moreover, various regions in fact have Tengu (daiba) as mountain gods.</e>
<cmt>天狗を大文字にしました。actually →in factに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>現在でも、山形県最上郡の伝承にみえる天狗は白髪の老人である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even in the present time, the Tengu in the folklore in Mogami Gun, Yamagata Prefecture is an old man with white hair.</e>
<cmt>最上郡http://map.goo.ne.jp/route/address_list.php?depa=&amp;dest=&amp;SN=1&amp;C1=06&amp;A1=山形県&amp;M1=E140.21.59.820N38.14.14.930&amp;kana=1</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even in the present time, the tengu in the folklore in Mogami Gun, Yamagata Prefecture is an old man with white hair.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even in the present time, the Tengu in the folklore in Mogami Gun, Yamagata Prefecture is an old man with white hair.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>山伏を中心とする天狗の信仰は、民間の仏教と、古代から続く山の神秘観山岳信仰に結びついたもので、極めて豊富な天狗についての伝説は山岳信仰の深さを物語るものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Worship of Tengu mainly with a Yamabushi monk is connected with local Buddhism, and mysteriousness of mountains and mountain worship, and quite various legends of Tengu explain the depth of mountain worship.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Worship of the tengu, mainly with a Yamabushi monk&apos;s attire, is connected with local Buddhism, as well as with the mysteriousness of mountains and mountain worship, and various legends of tengu explain the depth of mountain worship.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Worship of the Tengu, mainly among Yamabushi monks, is connected with local Buddhism, as well as with the mysteriousness of mountains and mountain worship, and various legends of Tengu explain the depth of mountain worship.</e>
<cmt>天狗を大文字にしました。「山伏を中心とする」＝「mainly among Yamabushi monks」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="59">
<j>山形県などでは、夏山のしげみの間にある十数坪の苔地や砂地を、「天狗のすもう場」として崇敬し、神奈川県の山村では、夜中の、木を切ったり、「天狗倒し」と呼ばれる、山中で大木を切り倒す不思議な音、山小屋が、風もないのにゆれたりすることを山天狗の仕業としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Yamagata Prefecture, they adore a mossy or sandy area of about 40 square meters in the bushes in mountains in summer as &apos;Sumo ring of Tengu,&apos; and in mountain villages in Kanagawa Prefecture, they regard mysterious sound of cutting trees at midnight or one of cutting a big tree in a mountain called &apos;Tengu&apos;s felling&apos; and a hut&apos;s shaking without wind as tricks of Mountain Tengu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Yamagata Prefecture, they adore a mossy or sandy area of about 40 square meters in the bushes in mountains in summer as &apos;the sumo ring of Tengu,&apos; and in mountain villages in Kanagawa Prefecture they regard the mysterious sound of cutting trees at midnight or one of cutting a big tree on a mountain called &apos;Tengu&apos;s felling&apos; and a hut&apos;s shaking without wind as a trick of the mountain tengu.</e>
<cmt>grammar, case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Yamagata Prefecture, they adore a mossy or sandy area of about 40 square meters in the bushes in mountains in summer as &apos;the sumo ring of Tengu,&apos; and in mountain villages in Kanagawa Prefecture they regard the mysterious sound of cutting trees at midnight or one of cutting a big tree on a mountain called &apos;Tengu&apos;s felling&apos; and a hut&apos;s shaking without wind as a trick of the mountain Tengu.</e>
<cmt>天狗を大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>鉄砲を三つ撃てばこうした怪音がやむという説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also said that firing three shots makes this kind of mysterious sound stop.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also said that firing three shots will make this mysterious sound stop.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also said that firing three shots will make this mysterious sound stop.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>その他、群馬県利根郡では、どこからともなく笑い声が聞こえ、構わず行くと更に大きな声で笑うが、今度はこちらが笑い返すと、前にもまして大声で笑うという「天狗笑い」、山道を歩いていると突然風が起こり、山鳴りがして大きな石が飛んでくる「天狗礫」（これは天狗の通り道だという）、「天狗田」、「天狗の爪とぎ石」、「天狗の山」、「天狗谷」など、天狗棲む場所、すなわち「天狗の領地」、「狗賓の住処」の伝承がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides these, in Tone Gun, Gunma Prefecture, there is some folklore; &apos;Tengu&apos;s laugh,&apos; a laughter comes out of nowhere, and the laughter becomes louder if you go further, then it becomes much louder than before if you laugh back; &apos;Tengu&apos;s stones (it is said to be a path of Tengu),&apos; when you walk in the mountain, a gust blasts and big stones fly over with rumbling of the mountain; &apos;Tengu&apos;s rice field&apos;; &apos;Tengu&apos;s nail-polishing rock&apos;; &apos;Tengu&apos;s mountain&apos;; &apos;Tengu&apos;s valley&apos;; &apos;Tengu&apos;s domain,&apos; where Tengu lives; &apos;Guhin&apos;s home.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides these, in Tone Gun, Gunma Prefecture, there is some folklore: with &apos;Tengu&apos;s laugh,&apos; a laughter comes out of nowhere, and the laughter becomes louder if you go further, then it becomes much louder than before if you laugh back; &apos;Tengu&apos;s stones (it is said to be a path of Tengu),&apos; as when you walk in the mountain a gust blasts and big stones fly over with the rumbling of the mountain; and &apos;Tengu&apos;s rice field&apos;; &apos;Tengu&apos;s nail-polishing rock&apos;; &apos;Tengu&apos;s mountain&apos;; &apos;Tengu&apos;s valley&apos; and &apos;Tengu&apos;s domain,&apos; where Tengu lives; as well as &apos;Guhin&apos;s home.&apos;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides these, in Tone Gun, Gunma Prefecture, there is some folklore: with &apos;Tengu&apos;s laugh,&apos; a laughter comes out of nowhere, and the laughter becomes louder if you go further, then it becomes much louder than before if you laugh back; &apos;Tengu&apos;s stones (it is said to be a path of Tengu),&apos; as when you walk in the mountain a gust blasts and big stones fly over with the rumbling of the mountain; and &apos;Tengu&apos;s rice field&apos;; &apos;Tengu&apos;s nail-polishing rock&apos;; &apos;Tengu&apos;s mountain&apos;; &apos;Tengu&apos;s valley&apos; and &apos;Tengu&apos;s domain,&apos; where Tengu lives; as well as &apos;Guhin&apos;s home.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>金沢市の繁華街尾張町では、宝暦五年(1755)に『天狗つぶて』が見られたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Owari Cho, downtown Kanazawa City, it is said that they saw &quot;Tengu&apos;s pebbles&quot; in 1755.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Owari Cho, downtown Kanazawa City, it is said that people saw &quot;Tengu&apos;s pebbles&quot; in 1755.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Owari Cho, downtown Kanazawa City, it is said that people saw &quot;Tengu&apos;s pebbles&quot; in 1755.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>静岡県の小笠山では夏に山中から囃子の音が聞こえる怪異「天狗囃子」があり、小笠神社の天狗の仕業だという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Mount Ogasa, Shizuoka Prefecture, they have a mysterious happening called &quot;Tengu&apos;s music&quot; that music is heard from the mountain in summer, which is said to be a trick of Tengu of Ogasa Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Mount Ogasa, Shizuoka Prefecture, they have a mysterious occurrence called &quot;Tengu&apos;s music&quot; in which music is heard from the mountain in summer, which is said to be a trick of the tengu of Ogasa Shrine.</e>
<cmt>grammar, case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Mount Ogasa, Shizuoka Prefecture, there is a mysterious occurrence called &quot;Tengu&apos;s music&quot; in which music is heard from the mountain in summer, which is said to be a trick of the Tengu of Ogasa Shrine.</e>
<cmt>天狗を大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>佐渡島（新潟県佐渡市）でも同様に「山神楽」（やまかぐら）といって、山中から神楽のような音が聞こえる怪異を天狗の仕業という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Sadogashima Island (Sado City, Nigata Prefecture) as well, a mysterious happening called &quot;Yama Kagura,&quot; that music like Kagura is heard from the mountain, is considered as a trick of Tengu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, on Sadogashima Island (Sado City, Nigata Prefecture) there is a mysterious happening called &quot;Yama Kagura,&quot; where music like Kagura is heard from the mountain; this is considered a trick of the tengu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, on Sadogashima Island (Sado City, Nigata Prefecture) there is a mysterious happening called &quot;Yama Kagura,&quot; where music like Kagura is heard from the mountain; this is considered to be a trick of the Tengu.</e>
<cmt>天狗を大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>岐阜県揖斐郡徳山村 (岐阜県)（現・揖斐川町）では「天狗太鼓」といって、山から太鼓のような音が聞こえると雨の降る前兆だという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Tokuyama Mura, Ibi Gun, Gifu Prefecture (the present Ibigawa Cho), sound like a drum, called &quot;Tengu&apos;s drum,&quot; heard from the mountain is considered as a sign of rain to come.</e>
<cmt>（岐阜県）は不要と判断、訳出せず</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Tokuyama Mura, Ibi Gun, Gifu Prefecture (the present Ibigawa Cho), a sound like a drum, called &quot;Tengu&apos;s drum,&quot; as heard from the mountain, is considered a sign of impending rain.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Tokuyama Mura, Ibi Gun, Gifu Prefecture (the present Ibigawa Cho), a sound like a drum, called &quot;Tengu&apos;s drum,&quot; heard from the mountain, is considered a sign of impending rain.</e>
<cmt>“as heard from the mountain”-&gt;”heard from the mountain”</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="66">
<j>特に、鳥のように自由に空を飛び回る天狗が住んでいたり、腰掛けたりすると言われている天狗松（あるいは杉）の伝承は日本各地にあり、山伏の山岳信仰と天狗の相関関係を示す好例である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially folklore with Tengu freely flying in the sky like a bird, or Tengu pine (or cedar) on which they say Tengu sits exists all over Japan, which provides a good example to show correlation between mountain worship of Yamabushi Monk and Tengu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Particularly, there is folklore with Tengu flying through the sky like a bird, or the Tengu pine (or cedar) on which they say the tengu sits exists all over Japan, which provides a good example to show the correlation between the mountain worship of the Yamabushi Monks and the tengu.</e>
<cmt>syntax</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Particularly, there is folklore with Tengu flying through the sky like a bird, or that the Tengu pine (or cedar), on which they say the Tengu sits, exists all over Japan, thus providing a good example to show the correlation between the mountain worship of the Yamabushi monks and the tengu.</e>
<cmt>天狗を大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>樹木は神霊の依り代とされ、天狗が山の神とも信じられていたことから、天狗が樹木に棲むと信じられたと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since trees were supposed to be dwellings of spirits, and Tengu was believed to be Mountain God, Tengu was believed to live in trees.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because trees were supposed to be dwellings of spirits, and tengu was believed to be a mountain god, the tengu were believed to live in trees.</e>
<cmt>syntax</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because trees were supposed to be dwellings of spirits, and Tengu was believed to be a mountain god, the Tengu were believed to live in trees.</e>
<cmt>天狗を大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>こうした木の周囲では、天狗の羽音が聞こえたり、風が唸ったりするという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that flap of Tengu&apos;s wing is heard or the wind roars around such trees.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the flapping of tengu&apos;s wing can be heard, or that the wind roars around such trees.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the flapping of Tengu&apos;s wings can be heard, or that the wind roars around such trees.</e>
<cmt>天狗を大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>風が音をたてて唸るのは、天狗の声だと考えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that roaring of the wind was voice of Tengu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that the roaring of the wind was the voice of the tengu.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that the roaring of the wind was the voice of the Tengu.</e>
<cmt>天狗を大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>愛知県宝飯郡にある大松の幹には天狗の巣と呼ばれる大きな洞穴があり、実際に天狗を見た人もいると云う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The trunk of a big pine tree in Hoi Gun, Aichi Prefecture has a big cave called &apos;Tengu&apos;s Nest,&apos; where they say some people actually saw Tengu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Near the trunk of a big pine in Hoi Gun, Aichi Prefecture, there is a big cave called &apos;Tengu&apos;s Nest,&apos; where it is said that some people actually saw the tengu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Near the trunk of a big pine in Hoi Gun, Aichi Prefecture, there is a big cave called &apos;Tengu&apos;s Nest,&apos; where it is said that some people in fact saw the Tengu.</e>
<cmt>天狗を大文字にしました。actually →in factに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>また埼玉県児玉郡では、天狗の松を伐ろうとした人が、枝から落ちてひどい怪我を負ったが、これは天狗に蹴落とされたのだという話である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kodama Gun, Saitama Prefecture, someone who tried to cut Tengu pine fell off from a branch and got severely injured, which is believed to have happened because Tengu kicked him down.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Kodama Gun, Saitama Prefecture, someone who tried to cut down a Tengu pine fell off a branch and was seriously injured; this is believed to have happened because Tengu kicked him out of the tree.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Kodama Gun, Saitama Prefecture, someone who tried to cut down a Tengu pine fell off a branch and was seriously injured; this is believed to have happened because Tengu kicked him out of the tree.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>天狗の木と呼ばれる樹木は枝の広がった大木や、二枝に岐れまた合わさって窓形になったもの、枝がコブの形をしたものなど、著しく異形の木が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Trees which are called Tengu trees are mostly big trees with the branches widespread and trees with an extremely strange shape such as one branched into two and put back together having a window-like shape and one with a branch in the shape of a bump.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Trees that are called Tengu trees are mostly big trees with widespread branches and trees with an extremely strange shape such as one branched into two and put back together having a window-like shape, or one with a branch in the shape of a bump.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Trees that are called Tengu trees are mostly big trees with widespread branches and trees with an extremely strange shape such as one branched into two and put back together having a window-like shape, or one with a branch in the shape of a bump.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>天狗に因む生物名</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Animal named after Tengu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Animals named after tengu</e>
<cmt>grammar, plural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Animals named after Tengu</e>
<cmt>天狗を大文字にしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="73">
<j>生物の和名として天狗が登場することがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tengu sometimes makes an appearance as a Japanese name of a creature.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tengu sometimes appears as the Japanese name of a creature.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tengu sometimes appears as the Japanese name of a creature.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>動物についていえば鼻、または類似器官が突き出た外見に因むものが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for animals, most are related to an appearance with a prominent nose or a similar organ.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for animals, most references are related to those having a prominent nose or a similar organ.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for animals, most references are related to those having a prominent nose or a similar organ.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="75">
<j>哺乳類 - テングザル、テングコウモリ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mammals - Tengu zaru, Tengu komori</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mammals - Tengu zaru, Tengu komori</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mammals - Tengu zaru, Tengu komori</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="76">
<j>魚類 - テングハギ、ウミテング</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fish - Tengu hagi, Umi Tengu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fish - Tengu hagi, Umi Tengu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fish - Tengu hagi, Umi Tengu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="77">
<j>昆虫類 - テングチョウ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Insects - Tengu cho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Insects - Tengu cho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Insects - Tengu cho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="78">
<j>植物 - テングクワガタ、ハリギリ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Plants - Tengu kuwagata, Harigiri</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Plants - Tengu kuwagata, Harigiri</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Plants - Tengu kuwagata, Harigiri</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="79">
<j>菌類 - テングタケ類</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fungi - Tengu take</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fungi - Tengu take</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fungi - Tengu take</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>天狗を主題にした創作</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Creation with Tengu Motif</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Creation with Tengu Motif</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Creation with Tengu Motif</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="80">
<j>大日本天狗党絵詞（黒田硫黄による漫画）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Dainihon Tengu To Ekotoba&quot; (cartoon by Io KURODA)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Dainihon Tengu To Ekotoba&quot; (cartoon by Io KURODA)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Dainihon Tengu To Ekotoba&quot; (cartoon by Io KURODA)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="81">
<j>Tactics (漫画)（木下さくらと東山和子による漫画）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tactics (Cartoon by Sakura KINOSHITA and Kazuko HIGASHIYAMA)</e>
<cmt>最初の（漫画）は不要と判断、訳出せず</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tactics (cartoon by Sakura KINOSHITA and Kazuko HIGASHIYAMA)</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tactics (cartoon by Sakura KINOSHITA and Kazuko HIGASHIYAMA)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="82">
<j>町でうわさの天狗の子（岩本ナオによる漫画）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Child of Tengu Rumored in Town (Cartoon by Nao IWAMOTO)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Child of Tengu Rumored in Town (cartoon by Nao IWAMOTO)</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Child of Tengu Rumored in Town (cartoon by Nao IWAMOTO)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 MD242(id:11277), Tomzo(id:16777), Suguri F(id:11127), Nnh(id:474), 深志(id:34508), ノトス(id:42992), Snake Head 1995(id:146125), 経済準学士(id:22656), Cprobot(id:97843), Eskimbot(id:29676), Fooke(id:6585), Rai koku(id:1661), Qazzx(id:8772), Spyle135(id:48034), Greenland4(id:114494), Locus(id:132168), Swind(id:30993), らりた(id:1327), NORN(id:52924), Dendai(id:121364), Rei-bot(id:94097), Loveless(id:129239), うぃき野郎(id:53567), Yas(id:739), 天狗堂二十貫(id:213750), GENMEI(id:31879), Mamasaid(id:2903), Camelia(id:112815), Toroia(id:31889), ロリ(id:613), Izayohi(id:13095), Stanislaus(id:1806), 逃亡者(id:14864), Seibuabina(id:37532), お掃除大好き(id:99320), Saburo(id:18511), Hiro-o(id:8534), Zwobot(id:23873), Escarbot(id:59151), Kamitani(id:30757), 文姫(id:66661), Rusk(id:9895), VolkovBot(id:105371), Boca samba(id:137526), クロサキ(id:169477), SuisuiBot(id:10165), MS472(id:58603), 上(id:14148), 松岡明芳(id:122110), TANUKI(id:28527), Corwin(id:973), SieBot(id:126695), Cpro(id:28341), 小太刀(id:18154), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>