<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>天女</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tennyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tennyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tennyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>天女（てんにょ）は日本の伝説上の存在。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tennyo are legendary existence in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tennyo are legendary existence in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tennyo are legendary beings in Japan.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;existence&quot; to &quot;beings&quot;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>日本の伝承</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese tradition</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese tradition</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japanese Legend</e>
<cmt>added &quot;The&quot;; changed &quot;tradition&quot; to &quot;Legend&quot;</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>天女は、天部に住むとされる女性のことで、天帝などに仕えているとされる女官の総称である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tennyo are females which are said to be living in heaven (天部), and is the collective term for ladies-in-waiting who are said to be serving for God of Hosts and others.</e>
<cmt>天部とは神々そのものを指すのでここでは誤用されているように思われます。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tennyo are females which are said to be living in heaven (天部), and is the collective term for ladies-in-waiting who are said to be serving for God of Hosts and others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tennyo is a general term for women who are said to live in heaven and serve as ladies-in-waiting for the gods.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;collective term&quot; to &quot;general term&quot;; rearranged the sentence to eliminate the comma and double usage of &quot;are said to be&quot;; I see that 英治郎 gives only two options for &quot;天帝&quot;: &quot;God of Hosts&quot; and &quot;Lord of Hosts&quot; Both of these seem closely tied with Christianity, so I think a simple &quot;gods&quot; works best here</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>人間界においては容姿端麗であることを除けば人と大きく変わるところはない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In human world, they don&apos;t have much difference with human beings except that they have very beautiful looks, and they are said to fly in the sky with clothing called hagoromo (robe of feathers), and there is a story about a tennyo, who had her hagoromo robbed and had became to be unable to go back to the sky, getting married to a man on the ground, (hagoromo legend) handed down.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In human world, they don&apos;t have much difference with human beings except that they have very beautiful looks, and they are said to fly in the sky with clothing called hagoromo (robe of feathers), and there is a story about a tennyo, who had her hagoromo robbed and had became to be unable to go back to the sky, then marrying a man on the ground (hagoromo legend), has been handed down.</e>
<cmt>getting married to→then marrying, カンマの位置を修正しました。has been を挿入しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the human world, there is very little difference between tennyo and humans aside from their beautiful appearance.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処; changed &quot;looks&quot; to &quot;appearance&quot;; fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>羽衣と呼ばれる衣服で空を飛ぶとされるが、この羽衣を奪われたばかりに空に帰れなくなり、地上の男性と結婚する話（羽衣伝説）などが伝えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although they are said to fly in the sky wearing clothing called hagoromo (heavenly kimono), stories passed down about them include one about a tennyo whose hagoromo gets stolen, making her unable to return to the sky, and marries a man living on the earth (the hagoromo legend).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処; used the definition for &quot;hagoromo&quot; from the English wiki article: heavenly kimono of tennin, tennyo, tenshi; changed &quot;and&quot; to &quot;Although&quot; since there is a contrast between the first and second clause; fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>羽衣伝説は日本（北海道から沖縄県まで）や朝鮮半島などの各地に伝説が伝わっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hagoromo legend is handed down in various places in Japan (from Hokkaido through Okinawa Prefecture) and in Korean Peninsula, and on one hand in folkloristic, there are theories regarding it as a story about foreign visitors from overseas, or regarding it as a kind of Hakucho shojo setsuwa (Swan maiden story), which is one of tales of marriage between a human and a nonhuman being, but on the other hand, there is even a theory by the believers of OOPARTS and overtechnologies regarding tennyo as space aliens.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hagoromo legends are handed down in various places in Japan (from Hokkaido through Okinawa Prefecture) and in Korean Peninsula, and on one hand in folkloristic, there are theories regarding it as a story about foreign visitors from overseas, or regarding it as a kind of Hakucho shojo setsuwa (Swan maiden story), which is one of tales of marriage between a human and a nonhuman being, but on the other hand, there is even a theory by the believers of OOPARTS and overtechnologies regarding tennyo as space aliens.</e>
<cmt>legend is→legends are と修正しました。”オーバーテクノロジー”については用語の定訳等が確認できません。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The hagoromo legend is handed down in various places in Japan (from Hokkaido to Okinawa Prefecture) and the Korean Peninsula.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処added &quot;the&quot; before &quot;hagoromo&quot;; changed &quot;through&quot; to &quot;to&quot;; added &quot;the&quot; before &quot;Korean Peninsula&quot;;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>民俗学の上では渡来人説から異類婚姻譚の一つである白鳥処女説話の一種とする説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Within the study of folklore, there is a theory that the legend is a variation on the story of the Swan Maiden, brought to Japan by visitors from overseas, about a marriage between a human and a non-human being.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処; changed &quot;in folkloristic&quot; to &quot;Within the study of folklore&quot;; eliminated &quot;Hakucho shojo setsuwa&quot; since it appeared to be a direct translation and used &quot;Swan Maiden&quot; instead; It seems to me that &quot;渡来人から&quot; is implying that the legend was brought to Japan by the visitors, not that the story was &quot;about&quot; them, so I changed the translation;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>一方で、果てはオーパーツ / オーバーテクノロジー信奉者らによる宇宙人と見なす説までみられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, there is a theory by those who believe in out-of-place-artifacts (OOPArt) and super technology (technology beyond our current capabilities, mainly in science fiction) that goes so far as to regard tennyo as beings from outer space.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処; changed &quot;OOPARTS&quot; to &quot;out-of-place-artifacts (OOPArt)&quot;; changed &quot;overtechnology&quot; to &quot;super technology&quot; and added a description; changed &quot;space aliens&quot; to &quot;beings from outer space&quot;; I split this sentence into three because I could not find a way to make all three work as one or two sentences in any combination.</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>仙人（仙人の女性）との相関性も伝承中には見出せるが、両者の差異は曖昧である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Relation with hermits (female hermits) can be seen in the tradition, too, but the difference in between the two is vague.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The correlation between tennyo and hermits (female hermits) can be seen in the tradition also, but the difference in between the two is vague.</e>
<cmt>Relation with→The correlation between tennyo,, too→also, と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it is also possible to make a correlation between tennyo and hermits (female hermits) within folklore, the difference between the two is ambiguous.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;but&quot; to &quot;Although&quot; and used at the beginning of the sentence; changed &quot;in the tradition&quot; to &quot;within folklore&quot;; changed &quot;can be seen&quot; to &quot;it is also possible&quot;; changed &quot;vague&quot; to &quot;ambiguous&quot;; fixed grammar</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>民間信仰における女性の神格性（女神）とは些か趣を異としており、天女自身が超常の力を持つという描写は少なく、地上へは専ら何らかの連絡か個人的な用事（水浴びなど）のために訪れるというだけで、その存在自体は比較的俗である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has a bit different taste compared to deification of females (goddess) among fold beliefs, having less description about tennyo herself having supernatural powers, and because tennyo comes to human world solely for contact and personal affairs (such as bathing), her existence itself if comparatively mundane.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has a slight different meaning compared to deification of females (goddess) among folk beliefs, there is less description about tennyo herself having supernatural powers, and because tennyo comes to human world solely for contacts and personal affairs (such as bathing), her existence itself is comparatively mundane.</e>
<cmt>taste→meaning (”趣：意図する内容”として修正しました)bit→slight,fold beliefs→folk beliefs,having→there is,contact→contacts,if→is,</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a slight difference in meaning between tennyo and the deification of females (goddesses) in folk beliefs; tennyo themselves are rarely portrayed as having supernatural powers, and because they visit the human world only to give messages and to take care of personal tasks (such as bathing), their existence itself is relatively mundane.</e>
<cmt>changed comma after &quot;folk beliefs&quot; to a semi-colon; changed &quot;solely for contacts&quot; to &quot;only to give messages&quot;; changed &quot;comparatively&quot; to &quot;relatively&quot;; fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="10">
<j>西洋における伝承中では、自然霊的な精霊ないし妖精（フェアリー）のうち女性の姿をとるものがこのイメージに近しいため、しばしば同一視される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since natural spirits and sprites (fairies) having female looks in Western traditions have similar image to tennyo, they are often seen as the same existence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since natural spirits and sprites (fairies) having female looks in Western traditions have similar image to tennyo, they are often seen as the same existence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tennyo are often identified as natural spirits and sprites (fairies) from Western folklore since they have a female form and a similar image.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;often seen as the same existence&quot; to &quot;often identified&quot; for &quot;同一視される&quot;; rearranged sentence to read more naturally and fixed grammar accordingly</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>飛天との関係</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Relationship with hiten</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Connection with hiten</e>
<cmt>Relationship→Connection と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Relationship to Hiten</e>
<cmt>capitalized &quot;Hiten&quot; since this is a section title</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>飛天は仏教美術にしばしば登場する「空を飛ぶ人物」で、特に女性形の者は天女と同一視される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hiten is &apos;flying person&apos; who often appears in Buddhist arts, and ones having female form is often seen as the same existence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hiten is a &apos;flying person&apos; who often appears in Buddhist arts, and ones having female form is often seen as the same existence.</e>
<cmt>a を挿入しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hiten are &quot;people who fly in the sky&quot; who often appear in Buddhist art, and those with a female form are often identified as tennyo.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;flying person&quot; to &quot;people who fly in the sky&quot;; Buddhist arts→Buddhist art; changed &quot;ones having&quot; to &quot;those with&quot;; changed &quot;seen as the same existence&quot; to &quot;identified as tennyo&quot;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>インド方面を起源とする説と、オリエント・ペルシャに起源を求める説があるが、後者のほうは元々、有翼人種（亜人ないし精霊の一種）として描かれていたと推測されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are theories seeking its origin in India or in Oriental Persia, but people in the latter theory are estimated to have been originally drawn as winged people (kind of semi-human or spirit).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are theories seeking its origin in India or in Oriental Persia, but people in the latter theory are conjectured to have been originally drawn as winged people (kind of semi-human or spirit).</e>
<cmt>estimated→ conjectured と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is one theory that the origin of hiten is in India and another theory claiming that it is in Oriental Persia, but in the latter, it is conjectured that these were people who were originally drawn as a race of winged humans (a form of semi-human or spirit).</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;its origin&quot; to &quot;the origin of hiten&quot;; fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>これが西洋方面に伝播する過程で天使に、東洋方面に伝播する過程で飛天から天女へと変化していったと目されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has been believed that they changed to angels along their ways to be propagated to Western side, and changed to hiten and then to tennyo along their ways to be propagated to Eastern side.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has been regarded that they changed to angels along their ways to be propagated Westwards, and changed to hiten and then to tennyo along their ways to be propagated Eastwards.</e>
<cmt>believed→regarded （”目す：みなす”として修正しました）西洋方面、東洋方面をそれぞれ修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that in the process of the idea spreading to the West, they were changed to angels, and in the process of spreading to the East, they changed to hiten and then to tennyo.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;propagated&quot; to &quot;spreading&quot; for &quot;伝播する&quot;; rearranged sentence and fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>他の文化圏の対応物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Corresponding existences in other cultural regions</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Corresponding existences in other cultural regions</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Corresponding existences in other cultural regions</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="14">
<j>インドの精霊緊那羅は男性形が馬頭人身の姿をしているが、女性形のキンナリーは天女としてのイメージを持つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Spirits in India, Kinnara, have appearance of heads of horses and bodies of humans in male form, but Kinnari, having female form, have image as tennyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Spirits in India, Kinnara, have appearance of heads of horses and bodies of humans in male form, but Kinnari, having female form, have the image as tennyo.</e>
<cmt>image→the image と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although kinnara spirits in India have the body of a human and the head of a horse in their male form, the female form of kinnari have the image of tennyo.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;but&quot; to &quot;Although&quot; and used at the beginning of the sentence; made &quot;kinnara&quot; and &quot;kinnari&quot; lowercase; fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>またインド神話では天女は神格を持つ存在の一種であり、アプサラスなども天女の一種に分類される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also in Indian mythology, tennyo is a kind of existence having godship, and Apsaras and others are classified as a kind of tennyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also in Indian mythology, tennyo is a kind of existence having divinity, and Apsaras and others are classified as a kind of tennyo.</e>
<cmt>godship→divinity と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Within Indian mythology as well, tennyo have a form of divine existence and Apsaras are also classified as a kind of tennyo.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;is a kind of existence having divinity&quot; to &quot;having a form of divine existence;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>ただアプサラスはニュンペー（ニンフ：水の精霊）とも同一視される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Apsaras is also seen as the same existence as Nympe (Nymph : spirit of water).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Apsaras is also seen as the same existence as Nympe (Nymph : spirit of water).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Apsaras, however, are also identified as nymphs (spirits of water).</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;seen as the same existence&quot; to &quot;identified&quot; for &quot;同一視&quot;; changed &quot;Nympe&quot; to &quot;nymph&quot; and changed the description to only (spirit of water); fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="17">
<j>イスラム教ではフーリーが天女と同一視される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Islamism, Huri is seen as the same existence as tennyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Islamism, Huri is seen as the same existence as tennyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Islam, Houri are regarded in the same light as tennyo.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;Huri&quot; to &quot;Houri&quot;; changed &quot;is seen as the same existence as tennyo&quot; to &quot;are regarded in the same light as tennyo&quot; for &quot;同一視される&quot;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>フーリーは永遠の処女であり、敬虔なイスラム教徒は死後に天国 (イスラーム)で彼女らの歓待を受けるとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Huri is an eternal virgin, and devout Muslim, after death, is said to receive hospitable treatment in heaven (Islam) by them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Houri is an eternal virgin, and devout Muslims, after their death, is said to receive hospitable treatment in heaven (Islam) by them.</e>
<cmt>Huri→Houri,Muslim→Muslims,after death→after their death と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Houri are eternal virgins, and devout muslims are said to receive hospitable treatment from them in heaven (Islam) after death.</e>
<cmt>rearranged words and fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="19">
<j>余禄とはなるが、北欧神話におけるワルキューレも、主神オーディンの命を受け、戦って死んだ勇者を天界（ヴァルハラ）に導く存在であり、ある意味では他の文化圏における天女に近しいイメージがあるが、北欧神話の観点ではあまり関連付けては扱われない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This will be a digression, but Valkyrie in Scandinavian myth is also an existence to lead hero who had died in a battle to heaven (Walhalla) under the order of chief god, Odin, and in a sense, she has a similar image with tennyo in other cultural regions, but as a respect from Scandinavian myth, they are not treated as related ones.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, Valkyries in Scandinavian myth are also an existence to lead hero who had died in a battle to heaven (Walhalla) under the order of chief god, Odin, and in a sense, they have a similar image with tennyo in other cultural regions, but as a respect from Scandinavian myth, they are not treated as related ones.</e>
<cmt>This will be a digression→In addition （”余禄：余分の利得”＝この場合は情報、として修正しました）Valkyries are と修正しました。but を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, valkyries in Norse mythology are beings who, under orders of the god Odin, lead men of valor who died in battle to heaven (Valhalla); in a sense, they have a similar image with tennyo in other cultural regions, but from the Norse mythology point of view are not considered to be related.</e>
<cmt>made &quot;valkyries&quot; lowercase&quot;; changed &quot;Scandinavian myth&quot; to &quot;Norse mythology&quot; for &quot;北欧神話&quot;; changed (Walhalla) to (Valhalla); changed comma to a semi-colon after (Valhalla); fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>比喩表現として</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As figure of speech</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As figurative expression</e>
<cmt>figure of speech→figurative expression と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a figurative expression</e>
<cmt>added &quot;a&quot;</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="20">
<j>美しい女性を天女と例えることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sometimes beautiful woman is compared to tennyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sometimes a beautiful woman is compared to tennyo.</e>
<cmt>a を挿入しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Beautiful women are sometimes figuratively referred to as tennyo.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;woman&quot; to &quot;women&quot;; changed &quot;compared to&quot; to &quot;figuratively referred to&quot;; fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>ただこれは女神などと形容する場合と同様に、崇拝に値するという意味であり、それ自体は美貌を唯一基準とする個人崇拝の一種である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, like expressing woman as a goddess, it means that the woman deserves to be adored, and the expression itself is a kind of personal worshipping having the beauty as the sole standard.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, same as expressing a woman as a goddess, it means that the woman deserves to be adored, and the expression itself is a kind of personal worshiping having the beauty as the sole standard.</e>
<cmt>like→same as,woman→a woman,worshipping→worshiping</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, this is similar to describing a woman as a goddess, meaning she is worthy of idolization, with the expression itself being a form of personal worship based solely on beauty.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;same&quot; to &quot;this is similar&quot;; changed &quot;expressing&quot; to &quot;describing&quot;; changed &quot;deserves to be adored&quot; to &quot;worthy of idolization&quot;; fixed grammar</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Dinosaur(id:99960), 言(id:187210), Locahunt(id:18828), Blazer(id:186151), Ash(id:15625), Tiyoringo(id:70026), うぃき野郎(id:53567), Fievarsty(id:201483), Misakawa(id:208485), ぽえこ(id:88711), Yatobi(id:9686), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>