<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>野槌</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nozuchi (a kind of Japanese ghost)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nozuchi</e>
<cmt>後段で詳しく説明されていますので括弧内説明は不要です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nozuchi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>野槌（のづち）は、日本に伝わる妖怪。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nozuchi is a specter that exists in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nozuchi is a specter that exists in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nozuchi is a specter that exists in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>その名は「野の精霊（野つ霊）」の意。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its name means &apos;the spirit of fields (notsurei).&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its name means &apos;field&apos;s spirit&apos; (&apos;no野&apos; means &apos;field;&apos; &apos;zuづ&apos; and &apos;tsuつ&apos; mean &apos;of;&apos; &apos;chi霊&apos; means &apos;spirit&apos; or &apos;ghost&apos;).</e>
<cmt>「霊」は「ち」と読みます。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its name means &apos;field&apos;s spirit&apos; (&apos;no野&apos; means &apos;field;&apos; &apos;zuづ&apos; and &apos;tsuつ&apos; mean &apos;of;&apos; &apos;chi霊&apos; means &apos;spirit&apos; or &apos;ghost&apos;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>ヘビのようだが、直径15センチ、体長1メートルくらいで、太さの割りに短い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It looks like a snake, having a diameter of about 15cm and a length of about 1m, and it is short for its thickness.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It looks like a snake, having a diameter of about 15cm and a length of about 1m, and it is short for its thickness.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It looks like a snake, having a diameter of about 15cm and a length of about 1m, and it is short for its thickness.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>頭のてっぺんに口がある以外は目も鼻もなく、ちょうど柄のない槌のような形をしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other than a mouth at the top of its head, there are no eyes or a nose and it looks almost like a hammer without a grip.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other than a mouth at the top of its head, there are no eyes or a nose and it looks almost like a hammer (&apos;tsuchiつち&apos; or &apos;zuchiづち&apos;) without a grip.</e>
<cmt>日本人なら「のづち」は「野槌」hammer of fieldかと気付く記述になっていますが、詳しい説明は邪魔なのではぶきます。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other than a mouth at the top of its head, there are no eyes or a nose and it looks almost like a hammer (&apos;tsuchiつち&apos; or &apos;zuchiづち&apos;) without a grip.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>深山に棲み子ウサギやリスを食べる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It lives in a place deep in the mountains and eats baby rabbits and squirrels.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It lives deep in the mountains and eats baby rabbits and squirrels.</e>
<cmt>簡略化します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It lives deep in the mountains and eats baby rabbits and squirrels.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>時には人を喰うとされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was considered that it sometimes eats humans.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was considered that it sometimes eats humans.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was considered that it sometimes eats humans.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>奈良時代の歴史書『古事記』や『日本書紀』では草の女神カヤノヒメの別名とされ、山野の精とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters) and the &quot;Nihon Shoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan) which are history books compiled during the Nara Period, Nozuchi was considered to be a name for Goddess of grass, Kayanohime, and was considered as the spirit of fields and mountains.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the history books compiled during the Nara Period including &quot;Kojiki&quot; (Records of Ancient Matters) and &quot;Nihon Shoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), Nozuchi is a nickname of Kaya no Hime (the goddess of grass) and a spirit of fields and of mountains.</e>
<cmt>用語を統一、わかりやすくしました。（用語リストを参照。用語集の間違いは無視します。）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the history books compiled during the Nara Period including &quot;Kojiki&quot; (Records of Ancient Matters) and &quot;Nihon Shoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), Nozuchi is a nickname of Kaya no Hime (the goddess of grass) and a spirit of fields and of mountains.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>記紀神話にはカヤノヒメを蛇とする記述は見られないものの、夫のオオヤマツミを蛇体とする説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although there are no descriptions on Kayanohime being a snake in the &quot;Kiki-shinwa&quot; (the Kojiki, Nihonshoki and mythology), there is a theory that her husband, Oyamatsumi, was in a form of a snake.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the myths recorded in &quot;Kojiki&quot; and in &quot;Nihon Shoki&quot; do not mention Kaya no Hime as a goddess with a snake&apos;s body, according to some myth her husband Oyamatsumi no Kami (the god of mountains) has a snake&apos;s body.</e>
<cmt>誤訳です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the myths recorded in &quot;Kojiki&quot; and in &quot;Nihon Shoki&quot; do not mention Kaya no Hime as a goddess with a snake&apos;s body, according to some myth her husband Oyamatsumi no Kami (the god of mountains) has a snake&apos;s body.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>後に仏教が普及すると、カヤノヒメが霧の神、暗闇の神、惑わしの神を産んだとされることから、野槌は妖怪変化を産む神とみなされ、野槌自体も次第に妖怪視された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Kayanohime gave birth to Kiri no kami (God of fog), Kurayami no kami (God of darkness), and Madowashi no kami (God of delusion), when Buddhism spread later on, Nozuchi was considered to be a god that gave birth to specters, and Nozuchi itself gradually began to be seen as a specter.</e>
<cmt>「霧の神」「暗闇の神」「惑わしの神」、いずれも定訳不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Buddhism spread in Japan, Kaya no Hime began to be considered to have been the mother of the god of fog, of the god of darkness and of the god of worldly desires, therefore, Nozuchi began to be considered to be a god bearing various specters, and Nozuchi itself was gradually considered to be a specter or a govlin.</e>
<cmt>「霧の神」云々はオリジナル著者による現代語訳ですので日本名を書かずそのまま英語に訳すのが無難です。「惑」は仏教の煩悩を意味します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Buddhism spread in Japan, Kaya no Hime began to be considered to have been the mother of the god of fog, of the god of darkness and of the god of worldly desires, therefore, Nozuchi began to be considered to be a god bearing various specters, and Nozuchi itself was gradually considered to be a specter or a govlin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>また仏教説話中にも取り入れられており、鎌倉時代の仏教説話集『沙石集』には、徳のない僧侶は深山に住む槌型の蛇に生まれ変わり、生前に口だけが達者で智慧の眼も信の手も戒めの足もなかったため、野槌は口だけがあって目や手足のない姿だとある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, it is included in preaching stories of Buddhism, and in &quot;Shasekishu&quot;, a collection of Buddhist stories compiled during the Kamakura Period, that a priest without virtue will be born again as a hammer shaped snake that lives in a place deep in the mountains, and since he was only glib without Chie no Me (wisdom-eye), Shin no te (hands for sincerity), and Imashinme no ashi (feet for admonition), Nozuchi is in the form with only a mouth, and no eyes, hands and feet.</e>
<cmt>「信の手」と「戒めの足」の定訳不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is found in Buddhist stories; according to &quot;Shaseki-shu,&quot; a collection of Buddhist stories compiled in the Kamakura period, a priest without virtue was born again as a hammer-shaped snake living deep in the mountains, and the priest had had a glib tongue while he had not have the eyes of the wisdom nor the hands of the piety nor the legs of the commandment, so Nozuchi he became had only a mouth and did not have eyes nor hands nor legs.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくします。仏教限定なので仏教関係記事で使用される用語を選びます。「手」はお祈りに使う部分なのでhand、「足」は普通にlegが良いです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is found in Buddhist stories; according to &quot;Shaseki-shu,&quot; a collection of Buddhist stories compiled in the Kamakura period, a priest without virtue was born again as a hammer-shaped snake living deep in the mountains, and the priest had had a glib tongue while he had not have the eyes of the wisdom nor the hands of the piety nor the legs of the commandment, so Nozuchi he became had only a mouth and did not have eyes nor hands nor legs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>江戸時代の百科事典『和漢三才図会』によれば、大和国（現・奈良県）吉野山中の菜摘川（夏実川）や清明滝（蜻螟滝）でよく見かけるもので、野槌の名は槌に似ていることが由来とある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the &quot;Wakan sansai zue&quot;, an encyclopedia compiled during the Edo period, Nozuchi was seen frequently in Natsumi-gawa River and Seimei-daki Waterfall in the Yoshino-yama mountains, and its name derives from its resemblance to a hammer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Wakan Sansai Zue,&quot; an encyclopedia compiled during the Edo period, Nozuchi was often seen in Natsumi-gawa River and Seimei-daki Waterfall in Yoshino-yama mountain range, and its name originated from its resemblance to a hammer (&apos;tsuchi&apos; or &apos;zuchi&apos;).</e>
<cmt>用語を統一します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Wakan Sansai Zue,&quot; an encyclopedia compiled during the Edo period, Nozuchi was often seen in Natsumi-gawa River and Seimei-daki Waterfall in Yoshino-yama mountain range, and its name originated from its resemblance to a hammer (&apos;tsuchi&apos; or &apos;zuchi&apos;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>深山の木の穴に住み、大きいものでは体長3尺（約90センチメートル）、直径5寸（約15センチメートル）、人を見ると坂を転がり下って人の足に噛みつくが、坂を登るのは遅いので、出くわしたときには高いところへ逃げると良いという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It lives in a tree hole deep in the mountains, and a large one is as big as three jaku (about 90cm) long and five sun (about 15cm) in diameter; on seeing a human being, it comes down the hill and bites his/her leg, but since it is slow in climbing up hill, it is good to run to a high place if one encounters Nozuchi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to it, Nozuchi lives in holes of trees deep in the mountains, and a large one is 3 jaku (about 90cm) long and 5 sun (about 15cm) in diameter; on seeing a human being, it comes down the hill and bites his/her on the leg, however, since it cannot crawl up hills fast, when encountering Nozuchi, it can be dodged by running away to a higher place.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくします。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to it, Nozuchi lives in holes of trees deep in the mountains, and a large one is 3 jaku (about 90cm) long and 5 sun (about 15cm) in diameter; on seeing a human being, it comes down the hill and bites his/her on the leg, however, since it cannot crawl up hills fast, when encountering Nozuchi, it can be dodged by running away to a higher place.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>民俗伝承においては奈良県のほかにも徳島県、北陸地方、中部地方に伝承されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In terms of folklore, other than Nara Prefecture, it is handed down in Tokushima Prefecture, Hokuriku regions and Chubu regions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other than Nara Prefecture, in Tokushima Prefecture, in Hokuriku region and in Chubu region remain the legends of Nozuchi.</e>
<cmt>文法ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other than Nara Prefecture, in Tokushima Prefecture, in Hokuriku region and in Chubu region remain the legends of Nozuchi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>また、シカを一飲みにする、転がってくる野槌に当たると死ぬ、野槌に見つけられただけでも病気を患ったり、高熱を発して死ぬともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also said that Nozuchi eats a deer in one gulp, or that one would die if hit by Nozuchi rolling down hill, or even just seen by a Nozuchi will make one sick or die of high fever.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also said that Nozuchi eats a deer in one gulp, and that a person, who was hit by Nozuchi which had been rolling off, would die, and that a person, who was even just found by Nozuchi, would contract some disease or even suffer from a bad fever and die.</e>
<cmt>andとorを直します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also said that Nozuchi eats a deer in one gulp, and that a person, who was hit by Nozuchi which had been rolling off, would die, and that a person, who was even just found by Nozuchi, would contract some disease or even suffer from a bad fever and die.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>鳥山石燕は『今昔画図続百鬼』で、全身毛だらけの野槌がウサギを食べる様子を描いており、解説文で「草木の精をいふ」と述べ、その形状を『沙石集』からの引用で「目も鼻もなき物也といへり」と述べている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Konjaku Gazu Zoku Hyakki&quot; (Continued Illustrations of the Many Demons Past and Present), Sekien TORIYAMA depicts Nozuchi with its entire body covered in hair and eating a rabbit; in the explanatory note, he says &apos;Nozuchi is a spirit of grasses and trees&apos;, and by quoting from &quot;Shasekishu&quot; he describes its shape as &apos;a thing with no eyes or nose.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;Konjaku Gazu Zoku Hyakki&quot; (Ancient and Modern Illustrations of Various Demons, Continued), Sekien TORIYAMA depicts Nozuchi with its entire body covered in hair and eating a rabbit; in the comment, he says &apos;Nozuchi is a spirit of grasses and trees&apos;, and by quoting from &quot;Shaseki-shu&quot; he describes its shape as &apos;a thing with no eyes nor nose.&apos;</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくします。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;Konjaku Gazu Zoku Hyakki&quot; (Ancient and Modern Illustrations of Various Demons, Continued), Sekien TORIYAMA depicts Nozuchi with its entire body covered in hair and eating a rabbit; in the comment, he says &apos;Nozuchi is a spirit of grasses and trees&apos;, and by quoting from &quot;Shaseki-shu&quot; he describes its shape as &apos;a thing with no eyes nor nose.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="16">
<j>ツチノコは、野槌に似ていることから名づけられた名前である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Tsuchinoko&quot; is a name that was given from its resemblance to Nozuchi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name of Tsuchinoko (an imaginary creature of Japan, its name means &apos;hammer&apos;s child&apos;) originated from its resemblance to Nozuchi.</e>
<cmt>ツチノコがいきなり出てきますので説明を加えます。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name of Tsuchinoko (an imaginary creature of Japan, its name means &apos;hammer&apos;s child&apos;) originated from its resemblance to Nozuchi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>あるいは一説に、ノヅチの伝説の元になった実在の生物ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Or, Tsuchinoko is regarded as the real living creature that became the basis of the legend of Nozuchi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Someone says that Tsuchinoko is a real living creature on which had been based, the legends of Nozuchi had been formed.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくします。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Someone says that Tsuchinoko is a real living creature on which had been based, the legends of Nozuchi had been formed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>昭和40年頃には、野槌の伝承はツチノコとしてほぼ統一されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around 1965, the legend of Nozuchi is unified to Tsuchinoko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around 1965, almost all the legends of Nozuchi had been changed to the legends of Tsuchinoko.</e>
<cmt>誤訳です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around 1965, almost all the legends of Nozuchi had been changed to the legends of Tsuchinoko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="19">
<j>黄表紙『妖怪仕内評判記』（ばけものしうちひょうばんき）にも野槌が登場するが、こちらは伝説・伝承と異なり、のっぺらぼうのように目鼻のない人型の化け物で、頭の上の大きな口で物を食べる姿として描かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nozuchi also appears in &quot;Bakemono shichi hyobanki &quot;(books of public estimation on various matters of ghosts), a kibyoshi (an illustrated book of popular fiction whose cover is yellow), but unlike the legend and folklores, it is a monster in a human form with no eyes and nose like an expressionless face, and eats with its big mouth on the top of its head.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In a kibyoshi (illustrated book of popular fiction in the Edo period) &quot;Bakemono Shiuchi Hyobanki&quot; (Reputations of Various Ghosts), Nozuchi is also found; however, unlike the legend and folklores, Nozuchi depicted in the book is a monster in the shape of a man with no eyes and no nose like Nopperabo (a monster), and it eats food using its big mouth on the top of its head.</e>
<cmt>「のっぺらぼう」はお化けです。「仕内」は細かく訳さずvarious ghostsで大丈夫です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In a kibyoshi (illustrated book of popular fiction in the Edo period) &quot;Bakemono Shiuchi Hyobanki&quot; (Reputations of Various Ghosts), Nozuchi is also found; however, unlike the legend and folklores, Nozuchi depicted in the book is a monster in the shape of a man with no eyes and no nose like Nopperabo (a monster), and it eats food using its big mouth on the top of its head.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 逃亡者(id:14864), Point136(id:211299), VolkovBot(id:105371), Misakawa(id:208485), Ttkkss(id:119005), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>