<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>玉川遠州流</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tamagawa Enshu School (Tea Ceremony and Green Tea Ceremony)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tamagawa Enshu-ryu School (A school of Tea and Green Tea Ceremony)</e>
<cmt>補足を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tamagawa Enshu-ryu School (A school of Tea and Green Tea Ceremony)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>玉川遠州流（たまがわえんしゅうりゅう、ぎょくせん-）は茶道および煎茶道の流派。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Tamagawa (Gyokusen) Enshu school is a school of tea ceremony and green tea ceremony.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Tamagawa (also known as Gyokusen) Enshu-ryu school is a school of tea and green tea ceremony.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tamagawa (also known as Gyokusen) Enshu-ryu school is a school of tea and green tea ceremony.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>玉川流とも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also referred to as the Tamagawa school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also referred to as the Tamagawa school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also referred to as the Tamagawa school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>初代大森漸斎は京都の人で、若い頃は剣術を好んでしたが、後に小堀遠州の門に入る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zansai OMORI, the first-generation head of the Tamagawa Enshu school, whose home town was Kyoto, preferably practiced kenjutsu (the art of swordsmanship) when young; he subsequently entered the Kobori Enshu school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zansai OMORI, the first-generation head of the school, whose home town was Kyoto, preferably practiced kenjutsu (the art of swordsmanship) when young; he subsequently became the disciple of Enshu KOBORI.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zansai OMORI, the first-generation head of the school, whose home town was Kyoto, preferably practiced kenjutsu (the art of swordsmanship) when young; he subsequently became the disciple of Enshu KOBORI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>「玉川」は霊元天皇に竹二重切花入を献上した際に賜った号である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The presentation of a &apos;take niju giri hana ire (bamboo vase)&apos; to Emperor Reigen brought him go (a pseudonym), &apos;Tamagawa.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His go (a pseudonym) &apos;Tamagawa&apos; was received by Emperor Reigen on the presentation of &apos;take niju giri hana ire&apos; (bamboo vase).</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His go (a pseudonym) &apos;Tamagawa&apos; was received by Emperor Reigen on the presentation of &apos;take niju giri hana ire&apos; (bamboo vase).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>2代杖信は閑院宮の茶頭を務め、以降公家との関わりが強かったが、3代有斐の亡きあと嗣子の礼座が早世したため断絶する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With Joshin, the second tea master, serving as a sado (a person in charge of the tea ceremony) for Kainnomiya (one of the Imperial families), the relationship with court nobles had deepened since then, but after the death of the third head, Yuri, the premature death of the following heir Reiza caused the extinction of the Omori family line.</e>
<cmt>用語集で読み方不明の人名は玉川会本部に問い合わせました。礼座→Reiza</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With Joshin, the second tea master, serving as a sado (a person in charge of the tea ceremony) for Kaninnomiya (one of the Imperial families), the relationship with court nobles had deepened since then, but after the death of the third head, Yuri, the premature death of the following heir Reiza caused the extinction of the Omori family line.</e>
<cmt>読みを変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With Joshin, the second tea master, serving as a sado (a person in charge of the tea ceremony) for Kaninnomiya (one of the Imperial families), the relationship with court nobles had deepened since then, but after the death of the third head, Yuri, the premature death of the following heir Reiza caused the extinction of the Omori family line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>およそ30年の空白期間を経て、3代有斐より皆伝を受けた閑院宮美仁親王の意により橘正之が大森家を復興し4代宗震となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the absence of the head of the school for thirty years, Masayuki TACHIBANA revived the Omori family to become the fourth-generation head, Soshin, under instructions of Imperial Prince Kainnomiya Haruhito, who had been certified as full proficiency from the third head, Yuri.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the absence of the head of the school for 30 years, Masayuki TACHIBANA revived the Omori family to become the fourth head, Soshin, under instructions of Imperial Prince Kaninnomiya Haruhito, who had been certified as full proficiency from the third head, Yuri.</e>
<cmt>アラビア数字にし読みを変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the absence of the head of the school for 30 years, Masayuki TACHIBANA revived the Omori family to become the fourth head, Soshin, under instructions of Imperial Prince Kaninnomiya Haruhito, who had been certified as full proficiency from the third head, Yuri.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>橘正之は花山院家の家司で従五位下に叙せられていたが、美仁親王の家臣である南部主悦を通して伝を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ordained as Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade), Masayuki TACHIBANA, who was a keishi (household superintendent) of the Kazanin family, was instructed by Shuetsu NANBU, a vassal of Prince Haruhito.</e>
<cmt>南部主悦→Shuetsu NANBU</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ordained as Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade), Masayuki TACHIBANA, who was a keishi (household superintendent) of the Kazanin family, was instructed by Shuetsu NANBU, a vassal of Imperial Prince Haruhito.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ordained as Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade), Masayuki TACHIBANA, who was a keishi (household superintendent) of the Kazanin family, was instructed by Shuetsu NANBU, a vassal of Imperial Prince Haruhito.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>もともと2代杖信の弟子で西勝寺の皆乗院公道が秋田に茶道を普及していた縁があり、宗震は4回にわたって秋田を訪れ伝道に携わり、それ以来秋田を中心に東北地方に広まっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The earliest connection with Kodo Kaijoin of Saisho-ji Temple, who was a disciple of the second-generation head, Joshin, and who spread tea ceremony in Akita, led Soshin to visit it four times and to assist in promoting the school of tea ceremony; therefore, the Tamagawa Enshu school has spread over the Tohoku region, especially in Akita since then.</e>
<cmt>西勝寺→Saisho-ji Temple　/皆乗院公道→Kodo Kaijoin</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the edge of the earlier connections that Kodo KAIJOIN of Saisho-ji Temple who was a disciple of the second head, Joshin, spread tea ceremony in Akita, Soshin visited Akita four times to involve in the promotion and the school has known over the Tohoku region, especially in Akita since then.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the edge of the earlier connections that Kodo KAIJOIN of Saisho-ji Temple who was a disciple of the second head, Joshin, spread tea ceremony in Akita, Soshin visited Akita four times to involve in the promotion and the school has known over the Tohoku region, especially in Akita since then.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>5代宗龍のとき明治維新を迎え、東京に移って有栖川宮の茶頭を務めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Meiji Restoration saw Soryu, the fifth-generation head, move to Tokyo and serve as a sado for Arisugawa no Miya.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Meiji Restoration saw Soryu, the fifth-generation head, move to Tokyo and serve as a sado for Arisugawanomiya.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Meiji Restoration saw Soryu, the fifth-generation head, move to Tokyo and serve as a sado for Arisugawanomiya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>宗龍は明治19年（1886年）に玉川遠州流と称し、伝来の法をもとにして玉川遠州流煎茶法を完成させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1886, Soryu called his way of tea ceremony as Tamagawa Enshu school and completed the Tamagawa Enshu school of sencha-ho (green tea method) based on the method handed from their ancestors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1886, Soryu called his way of tea ceremony as Tamagawa Enshu school and completed the Tamagawa Enshu school of sencha-ho (green tea method) based on the method handed from their ancestors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1886, Soryu called his way of tea ceremony as Tamagawa Enshu school and completed the Tamagawa Enshu school of sencha-ho (green tea method) based on the method handed from their ancestors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>6代岑尾は5代宗龍の娘で、京都で高等女学校の英語教師をしていたが、晩年になって茶道の伝道に努めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mineo, the sixth head of the school, was a daughter of the fifth head, Soryu, and an English teacher of a girls &apos;high school in Kyoto; however, she promoted the Tamagawa Enshu school of tea ceremony in her late years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mineo, the sixth head of the school, was a daughter of the fifth head, Soryu, and an English teacher of a girls&apos; high school in Kyoto; however, she promoted the Tamagawa Enshu school of tea ceremony in her late years.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mineo, the sixth head of the school, was a daughter of the fifth head, Soryu, and an English teacher of a girls&apos; high school in Kyoto; however, she promoted the Tamagawa Enshu school of tea ceremony in her late years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>6代岑尾のあとは、弟子の中野賢子（大森柳庵）の夫が家元を継ぎ7代宗夢となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Succeeding to the iemoto (the head family of a school) after Mineo, the husband of Masako NAKANO, one of Mineo&apos;s disciples, become the seventh head, Somu.</e>
<cmt>岑尾→Mineo /　中野賢子→Masako NAKANO</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Succeeding to the iemoto (the head family of a school) after Mineo, the sixth, the husband of Masako NAKANO (also known as Ryuan OMORI), a Mineo&apos;s disciple, became the seventh head, Somu.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ。「6代」「大森柳庵」を補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Succeeding to the iemoto (the head family of a school) after Mineo, the sixth, the husband of Masako NAKANO (also known as Ryuan OMORI), a Mineo&apos;s disciple, became the seventh head, Somu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Mzaki(id:61977), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>