<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>千社札</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Senjafuda or Senshafuda (a votive card)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Senjafuda or Senshafuda (a votive card)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Senjafuda (a votive card)</e>
<cmt>Senshafuda削除して次の項で説明。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>千社札（せんしゃふだ、せんじゃふだ）とは、神社や仏閣に参拝をした記念として貼る、自分の名前入りの札のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Senjafuda is a card or slip stuck to shrines and temples on which visitor&apos;s name is printed as a memorial of the visit.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Senjafuda is a card or slip stuck to shrines and temples on which visitor&apos;s name is printed as a memorial of the visit.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Senjafuda (also referred to as Senshafuda) is a card or slip stuck to shrines and temples on which visitor&apos;s name is printed as a memorial of the visit.</e>
<cmt>Senshafuda を括弧書きで入れました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>元来は銅板で作られていたが、江戸時代以降は紙が用いられることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally, it was a strip made of copper, however, in and after Edo period, usually paper was used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally, it was a strip made of copper, however, during and after the Edo period, paper was usually used.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally, it was a strip made of copper, however, during and after the Edo period, paper was usually used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>更に、ごく最近ではシール状になっているものも多く、これらはゲームセンター等に設置されている専用の作成機で、名前等を入力した上で作成することが出来る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, sticker type is often used most recently and this is made by special machines placed at penny arcade and so on with which one can input his name, etc. on it and make a card.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Recently sticker types are most often used and this is made with special vending machines where one can input his name and make a card.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Recently sticker types are often used and this is made with special vending machines where one can input his name and make a card.</e>
<cmt>most often→often</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>また、手軽に作成できるようになり、本来の用途とは外れた様々な用途に使用されることが増えてきている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As it becomes easy to make this senjafuda, people use it in many ways out of the original purpose.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As it has become easy to make senjafuda, people use them in many ways other than for the original purpose.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As it has become easy to make senjafuda, people use them in many ways other than for the original purpose.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>千社札には、幅が一寸六分 (数)（58ミリメートル）、高さが四寸八分（173ミリメートル）の一丁札が用いられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For senjafuda, a strip called iccho-fuda (a 1 cho-sized card) of 58mm in width and 173mm in length is used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For senjafuda, a strip called iccho-fuda (a 1 cho-sized card) of 58mm in width and 173mm in length is used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For senjafuda, a strip called iccho-fuda (a 1 cho-sized card) of 58mm in width and 173mm in length is used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>この中に描いた子持ち枠と呼ばれる枠の中に文字などを記入する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A frame called komochi-waku (an inner frame where characters are printed in) is printed on the card and inside of it, characters such as name and so on are described.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A frame called komochi-waku (inner frame where characters are printed within) is printed on the card and inside, characters such as name and so on are printed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A frame called komochi-waku (inner frame where characters are printed within) is printed on the card and inside, characters such as name and so on are printed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>なお、この子持ち枠のサイズは1887年に外寸法で幅48ミリメートル、高さ144ミリメートルに定められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, the komochi-waku was stipulated in 1887 to make in width 48mm by length 144mm as the outside size.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, in 1887 the komochi-waku was stipulated to be a width of 48mm and a length 144mm.</e>
<cmt>wordy, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, in 1887 the komochi-waku was stipulated to be a width of 48mm and a length 144mm.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>通常、神社や仏閣に奉納するための札は墨による単色刷りだが、交換や蒐集、鑑賞などの目的のために、多色刷りされた色札が作成されることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Normally, senjafuda dedicated to shrines and temples are claro obscuro of India ink, however, multiple color printed &apos;irofuda (literally, colored card)&apos; are often made for exchange, collection and appreciation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Normally, senjafuda dedicated to shrines and temples are done in India ink, however, multiple color printed &apos;irofuda (literally, colored card)&apos; are often made for exchange, collection, and appreciation.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Normally, senjafuda dedicated to shrines and temples are done in India ink, however, multiple color printed &apos;irofuda (literally, colored card)&apos; are often made for exchange, collection, and appreciation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>愛好家同士で納札交換会を催して楽しむこともある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fanciers sometimes hold and enjoy a gathering of votive cards exchanges.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fanciers sometimes hold and enjoy a gathering for exchanging cards.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fanciers sometimes hold and enjoy a gathering for exchanging cards.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>また京都の花街などでは名刺の代わりに図柄入りの千社札もあり花名刺とも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &apos;Hanamachi (or &apos;Kagai&apos;, geisha districts)&apos; in Kyoto, they use patterned senjafuda instead of business card which is called &apos;Hanameishi (literally, flower business card.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &apos;Hanamachi (or &apos;Kagai&apos;, geisha districts)&apos; in Kyoto, they use patterned senjafuda instead of a business card called &apos;Hanameishi (literally, flower business card.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &apos;Hanamachi (or &apos;Kagai&apos;, geisha districts)&apos; in Kyoto, they use patterned senjafuda instead of a business card called &apos;Hanameishi (literally, flower business card.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>近年用いられるのは、主に後者のものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">What used mainly theses days is the latter one.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Presently these are mainly used.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Presently these are mainly used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>文字には主に江戸文字が用いられ、錦絵と同じ江戸版画によって印刷される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The letters are mainly in characters designed in Edo era, and senjafuda is printed in the same way as &apos;Edo-hanga&apos;, a wood block prints produced in and around Edo era which is used to print nishiki-e (a color woodblock print.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The letters are mainly characters designed during the Edo era, and senjafuda are printed in the same way as &apos;Edo-hanga&apos; wood block prints that were produced in and around the Edo era when nishiki-e were printed (a colored woodblock print.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The letters are mainly characters designed during the Edo period, and senjafuda are printed in &apos;Edo-hanga&apos; (wood block prints that were produced in and around the Edo period) in the same way as nishiki-e (a colored woodblock print).</e>
<cmt>era→period「that were produced in and around the Edo period」この説明は必要でしょうか？後半書き換えましたのでご確認願います。NR: I think it makes sense to put the explanation of &quot;Edo-hanga&quot; in parentheses.</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="13">
<j>奉納の際には通常目立つところに貼るが、隠し貼りといって風雨に晒されず目立たないところに貼ることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Usually, senjafuda is stuck to conspicuous place of the buildings of shrines or temples when dedicated, however, it is sometimes stuck to by-place not to exposed to rain and wind which is called &apos;kakuhsi-bari (secret pasting.)&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Usually, senjafuda is stuck to conspicuous place on the buildings of shrines or temples when dedicated, however, it is sometimes stuck in places not exposed to wind and rain and this is called &apos;kakuhsi-bari (secret pasting.).&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Usually, senjafuda is stuck to conspicuous place on the buildings of shrines or temples when dedicated, however, it is sometimes stuck in places not exposed to wind and rain and this is called &apos;kakuhsi-bari (secret pasting.).&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>抜け</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nuke (survived part of senjafuda)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nuke (remains of senjafuda)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nuke (remains of senjafuda)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="14">
<j>神社や仏閣に奉納した千社札は、天井や壁に貼られてゆき、長い年月が経過して紙の空白部分が腐食すると、墨の印刷された部分のみが残る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When senjafuda dedicated to shrines and temples were stuck to ceilings and walls and long time has passed, the vacant part of the paper became eroded and gone out, and only printed or written part by India ink or so are left.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When senjafuda dedicated to shrines and temples were stuck to ceilings and walls and a long time had passed, the blank part of the paper became tattered and, and only the printed or written area in India ink or such are left.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When senjafuda dedicated to shrines and temples were stuck to ceilings and walls and a long time had passed, the blank part of the paper became tattered and, and only the printed or written area in India ink or such are left.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>これを抜けという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This left part is called &apos;Nuke.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This area remaining is called &apos;Nuke.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This area remaining is called &apos;Nuke.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>近年における千社札</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today&apos;s Senjafuda</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Present Day Senjafuda</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Present Day Senjafuda</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="16">
<j>最近では、手軽に作れるシール形式の千社札が急増しており、宗教的な用途以外にも、名札の代わりにしたり、気合を込めるの意味で太鼓の達人のプレイに使用する自作の撥に貼り付けたりと、様々な用途が生み出されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Recently, easily-made sticker type senjafuda is increased and used other than religious purposes such as a business card and some kind of amulet stuck to &apos;bachi&apos; (drumsticks) of a drum master to stir himself when he performs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Recently, easily-made sticker type senjafuda have increased and are used other than for religious purposes such as for business cards and some kind of amulet stuck to &apos;bachi&apos; (drumsticks) of a drum master to inspire himself when he performs.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Recently, easily-made sticker type senjafuda have increased and are used other than for religious purposes such as for business cards and some kind of amulet stuck to &apos;bachi&apos; (drumsticks) of a drum master to inspire himself when he performs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>しかし、その反面、神社などではマナーに欠けた参拝者の貼り付けを迷惑行為として、千社札の奉納自体を禁じている場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, some shrines, etc prohibit visitors from dedicating senjafuda as a disruptive behavior by visitors who breach manners.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, some shrines, etc prohibit visitors from dedicating senjafuda in what is considered a disruptive behavior by visitors who breach protocol.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, some shrines, etc prohibit visitors from dedicating senjafuda in what is considered a disruptive behavior by visitors who breach protocol.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>迷惑とされる行為</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Behavior Reagrded as Disruptive</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Behavior Reagrded as Disruptive</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Behavior Reagrded as Disruptive</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="18">
<j>シールによる千社札の普及が、古くからある千社札の伝統や決まりを乱していると批判の対象になっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prevalence of sticker type senjafuda became a focus of criticism that it is violating the traditions and rules of senjafuda.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prevalence of sticker type senjafuda has become a focus of criticism that it is violating the traditions and rules governing senjafuda.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prevalence of sticker type senjafuda has become a focus of criticism that it is violating the traditions and rules governing senjafuda.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="19">
<j>他人の千社札の上に貼る</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sticking own senjafuda on other&apos;s senjafuda.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sticking personal senjafuda on other&apos;s senjafuda.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sticking personal senjafuda on other&apos;s senjafuda.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>特に、「抜け」た跡に貼る場合などは、自覚無しに上貼りされることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In particular, sticking new one onto the &apos;nuke&apos; of patterns and characters left are sometimes done without being aware of it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In particular, sticking new one onto the &apos;nuke&apos; of patterns and characters still remaining are sometimes done without being aware of it.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In particular, sticking new one onto the &apos;nuke&apos; of patterns and characters still remaining are sometimes done without being aware of it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="21">
<j>色札を貼る</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sticking colored senjafuda.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sticking colored senjafuda.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sticking colored senjafuda.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>本来は墨の単色刷りのもののみを貼るべきであり、目立つこのような札は貼るべきではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally, when senjafuda is stuck, it should be claro obscuro of India ink and too much appealing colored card should be avoided.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally, when senjafuda is stuck, it should be those done in India ink and loud appealing colored cards should be avoided.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally, when senjafuda is stuck, it should be those done in India ink and loud appealing colored cards should be avoided.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>さらに、悪質なものでは必要以上に名前以外の文字・絵を描いて宣伝に利用される場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">More aggravated thing seen today is to use senjafuda as a media of an advertisement by printing characters and pictures other than visitor&apos;s name beyond necessity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seen today is more aggravating behavior of those using senjafuda as advertising media by printing unnecessary characters and pictures other than visitor&apos;s name.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seen today is more aggravating behavior of those using senjafuda as advertising media by printing unnecessary characters and pictures other than visitor&apos;s name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="24">
<j>はがしにくいシールを用いる</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Using hard to detach senjafuda</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Using hard to detach senjafuda</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Using hard to detach senjafuda</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>千社札は、施設の都合により剥がされることもあることを考慮に入れ、そのような場合でも建物を傷つけない接着物を用いる必要がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taking it to consideration that senjafuda is sometimes peeled off for certain reasons of the facilities of shrines and temples, it is necessary to use adhesive harmless to the buildings even in such case.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Considerating that senjafuda are sometimes peeled off to maintain the facilities of shrines and temples, it is necessary to use an adhesive that is harmless to the buildings.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Considerating that senjafuda are sometimes peeled off to maintain the facilities of shrines and temples, it is necessary to use an adhesive that is harmless to the buildings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kkkdc(id:32227), 江口磐世☆(id:168037), Nnn(id:26535), Fromm(id:71291), Kstigarbha(id:13376), 海獺(id:153448), Mojipro(id:115347), 京都人(id:177312), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>