<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>纏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Matoi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Matoi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Matoi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>纏（まとい）とは、江戸時代に町火消が用いた、自分たちの組であることを示すもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Matoi was used by fire brigade in the Edo Period and expressed their own kumi (brigade).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Matoi were used by fire brigades in the Edo Period, and it expressed their own &quot;kumi&quot; (brigade).</e>
<cmt>kumiに&quot;&quot;をつけました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Matoi were used by fire brigades in the Edo Period, and it expressed their own &quot;kumi&quot; (brigade).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>纏は各組により様々な意匠が凝らしてある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Design of Matoi was elaborated by each brigade in various ways.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Design of Matoi is elaborated by each brigade in various ways.</e>
<cmt>現在形にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Design of Matoi is elaborated by each brigade in various ways.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>概ね、上部に組を表す頭があり、馬簾と呼ばれる房飾りがついている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In general, Matoi had head which showed its kumi on its top and tassel decoration which was referred to as baren.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In general, Matoi has a head which shows its brigade on the top and tassel decoration which was referred to as &quot;baren.&quot;</e>
<cmt>barenに&quot;&quot;をつけました。現在形にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In general, Matoi has a head which shows its brigade on the top and tassel decoration which was referred to as &quot;baren.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>下部は木の棒になっていて手に持って使う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bottom part of Matoi is made of wood and they used it in their hands.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bottom part of Matoi is a wood stick to hold in the hands.</e>
<cmt>「棒」を訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bottom part of Matoi is a wood stick to hold in the hands.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>江戸時代の江戸では、武家屋敷で発生した火災は大名と旗本が消火活動にあたり、町人の住む地域で火災は町人の手による消火活動が行われていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At Edo in the Edo Period, daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) and hatamoto (direct retainers of the bakufu, which is a form of Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) battled the fires occurred at samurai residence, while towns people did that the fires occurred at the regions where they lived.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At Edo in the Edo Period, daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) and hatamoto (direct retainers of the bakufu, which is a form of Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) battled the fires occurred at samurai residence, while merchants and craftsmen battled the fires occurred at the regions where they lived.</e>
<cmt>「町人」を&quot;marchants and craftsmen&quot;としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At Edo in the Edo Period, daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) and hatamoto (direct retainers of the bakufu, which is a form of Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) battled the fires occurred at samurai residence, while merchants and craftsmen battled the fires occurred at the regions where they lived.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>江戸の大半を焼失する明暦の大火後の1658年（万治元年）に江戸中定火之番（定火消）が設置された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1658, after the Great Fire of Meireki in which most part of Edo was burned down, Edonakajobinoban (jobikeshi (fire department under the direct control of the Edo bakufu)) was established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1658, after the Great Fire of Meireki in which most part of Edo was burned down, Edonakajobinoban (jobikeshi [fire department under the direct control of the Edo bakufu]) was established.</e>
<cmt>（）の中の（）を[]になおしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1658, after the Great Fire of Meireki in which most part of Edo was burned down, Edonakajobinoban (jobikeshi [fire department under the direct control of the Edo bakufu]) was established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>火災時には旗本が火消屋敷に常駐している臥煙と呼ばれる消防員の指揮をとり出動していたが、その際に用いた馬印が、纏の始まりになったといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the time of fire, hatamoto led firefighters referred to as Gaen who were stationed in firehouse and went into action, and it is said that umajirushi (commander&apos;s battle standard) used at that time was the origin of Matoi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the time of fire, hatamoto led firefighters referred to as &quot;Gaen&quot; who were stationed in firehouse and went into action, and it is said that umajirushi (commander&apos;s battle standard) used at that time was the origin of Matoi.</e>
<cmt>Gaenを&quot;&quot;で囲みました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the time of fire, hatamoto led firefighters referred to as &quot;Gaen&quot; who were stationed in firehouse and went into action, and it is said that umajirushi (commander&apos;s battle standard) used at that time was the origin of Matoi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>消火活動においては、「纏持ち」と呼ばれる火消がこれを持ち、風下の屋根の上にあがり、放水や建物の破壊など消火活動の目印としてなどして用いられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During fire fighting, firefighters referred to as &quot;Matoimochi&quot; climbed onto the roof on the lee side with holding Matoi, and Matoi was used for signs of firefighting such as water-discharge and destruction of buildings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During fire fighting, firefighters referred to as &quot;Matoimochi&quot; climbed onto the roof on the lee side with holding Matoi, and Matoi was used for signs of firefighting such as water-discharge and destruction of buildings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During fire fighting, firefighters referred to as &quot;Matoimochi&quot; climbed onto the roof on the lee side with holding Matoi, and Matoi was used for signs of firefighting such as water-discharge and destruction of buildings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Avanzare(id:34657), Alecs.bot(id:194707), 伏儀(id:142093), Milsan(id:43412), Cpro(id:28341), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>