<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>色目</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Color Combinations</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Color Combinations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Irome (color combinations)</e>
<cmt>Iromeを追加</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>色目（いろめ）とは十二単などにおける色の組み合わせをいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It refers to color combinations used in juni-hitoe (the ceremonial attire of a Japanese court lady consisting originally of twelve layers of unlined kimono worn one on top of another).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It refers to color combinations used in juni-hitoe (the ceremonial attire of a Japanese court lady consisting originally of twelve layers of unlined kimono worn one on top of another).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Irome refers to color combinations used in juni-hitoe (the ceremonial attire of a Japanese court lady consisting originally of twelve layers of unlined kimono worn one on top of another) and so on.</e>
<cmt>and so onを追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>衣を表裏に重ねるもの、複数の衣を重ねるもの、経糸と緯糸の違いによるものなどがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Color combinations are created by various methods including using the outer and lining materials of different colors, layering the multiple dresses and using warp and weft of different colors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Color combinations are created by various methods including using the outer and lining materials of different colors, layering multiple dresses and using warp and weft of different colors.</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Irome are created by various methods including using the outer and lining materials of different colors, layering multiple dresses and using warp and weft of different colors.</e>
<cmt>Iromeに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>代表的なものは表裏に重ねるものでこれをとくに襲の色目（かさねのいろめ）という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The typical method is the layering of dress inside out which is specifically referred to as the color combinations for female court attire.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The typical method is the layering of dresses inside out, which is specifically referred to as the color combinations for female court attire.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The typical method is the layering of dresses inside out, which is specifically referred to as the Kasane no irome (color combinations for female court attire).</e>
<cmt>Kasane no Iromeに修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>平安時代中期には確立しており、源氏物語や枕草子に言及が見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The foregoing color combination was well established by the mid Heian Period and it is mentioned in Genji Monogatari (the Tale of Genji) and Makura no Soshi (The Pillow Book).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The foregoing color combination was well established by the mid Heian Period and it is mentioned in the Tale of Genji and Makura no Soshi (The Pillow Book).</e>
<cmt>shortened a bit</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The foregoing irome was well established by the mid Heian Period and it is mentioned in the Tale of Genji and Makura no Soshi (The Pillow Book).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>色目は季節毎に分類され、用いる時期もほぼ季節に対応する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Color combinations are broken down by the season and the time of the year to use each of the categories approximately corresponds to the respective season.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Color combinations are broken down by the season and the time of the year, each category used approximately according to the season.</e>
<cmt>rephrased the last half</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Irome are broken down by the season and the time of the year, each category used approximately according to the season.</e>
<cmt>Iromeに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>通年用いる事が可能な通季のものもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some color combinations can be used all year round.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some color combinations can be used all year round.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some color combinations can be used all year round.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>色目の名は多く季節の風物にちなみ、紅梅、桜、山吹、朽葉、松などの植物名がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Color combinations were often named in connection with seasonal features such as flora including kobai (rose plums), cherry blossoms, forsythias, fallen leaves and pines.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Color combinations were often named in connection with seasonal features such as flora including kobai (rose plums), cherry blossoms, forsythias, fallen leaves and pines.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Irome were often named in connection with seasonal features such as flora including kobai (rose plums), cherry blossoms, japanese rose, fallen leaves and pines.</e>
<cmt>Iromeに修正用語集に統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>また、玉虫色などの昆虫名、氷、初雪などの地象などによる他、白襲、赤色などの色名、枯野など景物にちなむものもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other seasonal features that color combinations were name after include insects such as iridescence, terrestrial phenomena such as ice and the first snow of the year, in addition to colors such as shiragasane (white layers) and akairo (red color) as well as landscape such as kareno (withered fields).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other seasonal features that color combinations were named after include insects such as jewel beetle, terrestrial phenomena such as ice and the first snow of the year, in addition to colors such as shiragasane (white layers) and akairo (red color) as well as landscapes such as kareno (withered fields).</e>
<cmt>“iridescence” would in some circumstances be a good rendering of 玉虫色, but in this instance the reference is to the insect, more so than to the color</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other seasonal features that irome were named after include insects such as jewel beetle, terrestrial phenomena such as ice and the first snow of the year, in addition to colors such as shiragasane (white layers) and akairo (red color) as well as landscapes such as kareno (withered fields).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>大抵は2色から3色の組み合わせを用いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In most cases, 2 or 3 colors are combined.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In most cases, 2 or 3 colors are combined.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In most cases, 2 or 3 colors are combined.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>表裏2色の組み合わせが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Combinations of 2 different colors of the outer and lining materials were often used.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Combinations of 2 different colors of the outer and lining materials were often used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Combinations of 2 different colors of the outer and lining materials were often used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>また、同じ色の組み合わせでも表と裏のどちらに用いるかで名称が異なる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, when the same color combination was used, depending on which side of dress those 2 colors were used, i.e., outer or lining, it was regarded as 2 different color combinations being identified by different names.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, when the same color combination was used, depending on which side those 2 colors were used, i.e. outer or lining, it was regarded as 2 different color combinations being identified by different names.</e>
<cmt>deleted “of dress”</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, when the same color combination was used, depending on which side those 2 colors were used, i.e. outer or lining, it was regarded as 2 different color combinations being identified by different names.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>たとえば春の柳襲は表が白、裏が萌黄であるが、表が萌黄、裏が白のものは木賊襲といい、通年用いる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, the outer material was white and the lining was moegiiro (light green color) for yanagigasane (the willow color combination) for the springtime, whereas, if the outer material was light green and the lining was white, it was called tokusagasane (the tokusa (scouring rush) color combination) which was used year round.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, the outer material was white and the lining was moegiiro (light green color) for yanagigasane (the willow color combination) for the springtime, whereas, if the outer material was light green and the lining was white, it was called tokusagasane (the scouring rush color combination) which was used year round.</e>
<cmt>nested parentheses</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, the outer material was white and the lining was moegiiro (light green color) for yanagigasane (the willow color combination) for the springtime, whereas, if the outer material was light green and the lining was white, it was called tokusagasane (the scouring rush color combination) which was used year round.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>また同じ組み合わせを季節によって違う名で呼ぶこともある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, the same color combinations were sometimes called differently depending on the season</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, the same color combinations were sometimes called differently depending on the season.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, the same color combinations were sometimes called differently depending on the season.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>たとえば春の柳襲と夏の卯の花襲はともに表が白、裏が萌黄となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, the outer material was white and the lining was light green for both the yanagigasane (willow) color combination for the spring and the unohana (deutzia flower) color combination for the summer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, the outer material was white and the lining was light green for both the yanagigasane (willow) color combination for the spring and the unohana (deutzia flower) color combination for the summer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, the outer material was white and the lining was light green for both the yanagigasane for the spring and the unohanagasane (deutzia flower color combination) for the summer.</e>
<cmt>用語集に統一(willow) color combination を削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>色目の名と実際の組み合わせの対応は、有職故実のひとつであり、江戸期にかけて整理された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keeping the names of color combinations and the actual color combinations accurately corresponded with one another was part of Yusoku kojitsu (the court and samurai rules of ceremony and etiquette) and they were organized until the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keeping the names and the actual color combinations accurately corresponding with one another was part of Yusoku kojitsu (the court and samurai rules of ceremony and etiquette) and they were organized until the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>removed repetitive phrasing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keeping the names and the actual color combinations accurately corresponding with one another was part of Yusoku kojitsu (the court and samurai rules of ceremony and etiquette) and they were organized until the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>有職故実家によって若干組み合わせが異なるものがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some color combinations slightly vary depending on the Yusoku kojitsu expert.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some color combinations slightly vary depending on the Yusoku kojitsu expert.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some color combinations slightly vary depending on the Yusoku kojitsu expert.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="17">
<j>現代の衣服などの着こなしに於いても参考にされる事が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those color combinations often serve as useful reference for dressing today.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those color combinations often serve as a useful reference for dressing today.</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those color combinations often serve as a useful reference for dressing today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="18">
<j>襲の色目の例</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Examples of color combinations for female court attire</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Examples of color combinations for female court attire</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Examples of Kasane no irome (color combinations for female court attire)</e>
<cmt>Kasane no iromeを追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 釣ちごちゅが(id:22605), Masyu(id:31065), 赤ペン先生(id:137031), Aphaia(id:3132), Blue-comet(id:192801), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), Cpro(id:28341), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>