<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>拳遊び</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ken Asaobi (fist play)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ken Asaobi (fist play)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ken Asobi (fist play)</e>
<cmt>AsaobiをAsobiに変更しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>拳遊び（けんあそび）は、二人で手の開閉または指の屈伸などによって勝負を争う遊戯の事。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ken asobi is a competitive game between two people that uses spread or closed hand or the reflection of fingers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ken asobi is a competitive game between two people that uses spread or closed hands or the reflection of fingers.</e>
<cmt>plural hands</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ken asobi is a competitive game between two people that uses spread or closed hands or the reflection of fingers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>後に、三人以上であったり、手だけでなく体全体を用いたりするものも現れたが、基本的に形によって勝敗を決める遊びである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This chooses the winner and looser basically with shape and the game that used three players or whole body instead of just hands started to appear later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This chooses the winner and loser basically with shape and the game that used three players or whole body instead of just hands started to appear later.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This chooses the winner and loser basically with shape and the game that used three players or whole body instead of just hands started to appear later.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>酒宴で行われる遊びだったが、そのうちのいくつかは子供の間でも行われるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was the game that was originally played during sake (Japanese rice wine) drinking parties, but some of them started to be played among children.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was the game that was originally played during drinking parties, but some of them started to be played among children.</e>
<cmt>deleted “sake (Japanese rice wine)”</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was the game that was originally played during drinking parties, but some of them started to be played among children.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>日本・中国など東アジアを中心に数多くの拳遊びがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are many ken asobi centering around east Asian nations such as Japan and China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are many kinds of ken asobi, mainly in east Asian nations such as Japan and China.</e>
<cmt>centering around-&gt;mainly in</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are many kinds of ken asobi, mainly in east Asian nations such as Japan and China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>拳遊びは大別して「数拳」と「三すくみ拳」があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Main Ken Asobi were &apos;kazuken&apos; (finger number game) and &apos;sansukumi-ken&apos; (a three-cornered deadlock finger game).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Main Ken Asobi were &apos;kazuken&apos; (finger number game) and &apos;sansukumi-ken&apos; (a three-cornered deadlock finger game).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Main Ken Asobi were &apos;kazuken&apos; (finger number game) and &apos;sansukumi-ken&apos; (a three-cornered deadlock finger game).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>数拳は2人が互いに片手の指で数を示すと同時に双方の出した数の合計を言い、当たった方が勝ちというもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The kazuken was played by two people using finger signals with one hand to show number at the same time as calling out the sum of both players&apos; numbers, and the one who gave out the correct answer became the winner.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The kazuken was played by two people using finger signals with one hand to show a number at the same time as calling out the sum of both players&apos; numbers, and the one who gave out the correct answer became the winner.</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The kazuken was played by two people using finger signals with one hand to show a number at the same time as calling out the sum of both players&apos; numbers, and the one who gave out the correct answer became the winner.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>中国が発祥地で日本では18世紀の初めから広がった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It originated from China and spread to Japan from the start of 18th century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It originated from China and spread to Japan from the start of 18th century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It originated from China and spread to Japan from the start of 18th century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>16世紀の後半に長崎から入ってきた遊びなので本拳・長崎拳・崎陽拳ともよばれた（崎陽は漢学者たちによる長崎の異称のこと）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the game was imported through Nagasaki during latter half of 16th century, it was called as honken, Nagasakiken, or kiyoken (Kiyo was the alias of Nagasaki used by Chinese scholars).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the game was imported through Nagasaki during the latter half of 16th century, it was called honken, Nagasakiken, or kiyoken (Kiyo was the word for Nagasaki used by Chinese scholars).</e>
<cmt>articles; prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the game was imported through Nagasaki during the latter half of 16th century, it was called honken, Nagasakiken, or kiyoken (Kiyo was the word for Nagasaki used by Chinese scholars).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>江戸時代の天保年間までは、これが大人の拳遊びの中心だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was the center of ken asobi of adults until the Tenpo years (1830-1843) in Edo Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was the center of adult ken asobi until the Tenpo years (1830-1843) in the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>word order; articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was the center of adult ken asobi until the Tenpo years (1830-1843) in the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>現代でも九州では球磨拳などの数拳が行われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The kazuken such as kumaken are currently played even now in Kyushu region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The kazuken such as kumaken are currently played even now in the Kyushu region.</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The kazuken such as kumaken are currently played even today in the Kyushu region.</e>
<cmt>nowをtodayに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>子供の遊びにも、数拳によく似た遊びがある（→手を用いた遊び数字を指定する遊び）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are games for children similar to kazuken (the game that points out the number using hands).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are games for children similar to kazuken (the game that points out the number using hands).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are games for children similar to kazuken (the game that points out the number using hands).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>三すくみ拳は東アジアに古くから分布し日本にも平安時代には存在し和風化されて遊ばれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sansukumi-ken was present in various areas of eastern Asia from long ago, and it existed and played in Japan from Heian Period after being adapted to the Japanese way.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sansukumi-ken was present in various areas of eastern Asia from long ago, and it existed and was played in Japan from the Heian Period after being adapted to the Japanese way.</e>
<cmt>articles; added “was”</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sansukumi-ken was present in various areas of eastern Asia from long ago, and it existed and was played in Japan from the Heian Period after being adapted to the Japanese way.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>日本での代表的な三すくみ拳は虫拳でヘビ、カエル、ナメクジの三すくみ（人さし指はヘビ、親指はカエル、小指はナメクジ）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The representative sansukumi-ken of Japan was mushiken (insect fist) and sansukumi with snake, frog, and slug (index finger is snake, thumb is frog, and little finger is slug).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The representative sansukumi-ken of Japan was mushiken (insect fist) and sansukumi with snake, frog, and slug (index finger is snake, thumb is frog, and little finger is slug).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The representative sansukumi-ken of Japan was mushiken (insect fist) and sansukumi with snake, frog, and slug (index finger is snake, thumb is frog, and little finger is slug).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>江戸時代後期には天竺徳兵衛をモデルにした自来也ものが読本・浄瑠璃・歌舞伎で当たりし、児雷也の蝦蟇への大変身が話題となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jiraiya modeled after Tokube TENJIKU became popular in books, Joruri (dramatic narrative chanted to a samisen accompaniment), and kabuki during late Edo Period, and the transformation of Jiraiya into gama no abura (oil of toad) became a popular topic for discussion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jiraiya modeled after Tokube TENJIKU became popular in books, Joruri (dramatic narrative chanted to a samisen accompaniment), and kabuki during late Edo Period, and the transformation of Jiraiya into gama no abura (oil of toad) became a popular topic for discussion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jiraiya modeled after Tokube TENJIKU became popular in books, Joruri (dramatic narrative chanted to a shamisen accompaniment), and kabuki during late Edo Period, and the transformation of Jiraiya into gama no abura (oil of toad) became a popular topic of conversation.</e>
<cmt>samisenをshamisenに変更しました。for discussionをof conversationに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>そこでカエル・ナメクジ・ヘビの「蛇拳（じゃけん）」というものが流行し、幕末には狐拳という三すくみ拳が流行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, &apos;Jaken&apos; (snake fist) that used frog, slug, and snake and sansukumi-ken called kitsuneken (fox finger game) became popular at the end of Bakufu (government by shogunate) period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, &apos;Jaken&apos; (snake fist) that used frog, slug, and snake and sansukumi-ken called kitsuneken (fox finger game) became popular at the end of Bakufu (government by shogunate) period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, &apos;Jaken&apos; (snake fist) that used frog, slug, and snake and sansukumi-ken called kitsuneken (fox finger game) became popular at the end of Bakufu (government by shogunate) period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>明治になり数拳と三すくみ拳からの現代行われているじゃんけんが考案されたと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that janken that derived from kazuken and sansukumi-ken played nowadays was invented when entering Meiji Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that janken that derived from the kazuken and sansukumi-ken played nowadays was invented at the start of the Meiji Period.</e>
<cmt>when entering-&gt;at the start of the</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that janken that derived from the kazuken and sansukumi-ken played nowadays was invented in the Meiji Period.</e>
<cmt>at the start of をinに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 移動用アカウント(id:87382), Fouinarret(id:89185), Kunipoo(id:35872), 諾爾布(id:181602), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>