<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>毬杖</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Giccho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Giccho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Giccho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>毬杖（ぎっちょう）は、木製の槌（つち）をつけた木製の杖を振るい、木製の毬を相手陣に打ち込む遊びのことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Giccho is a game, in which one party smashes a wooden ball aiming at the other party&apos;s side by swinging wooden cane applied a wooden mallet on the end.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Giccho is a game in which one party smashes a wooden ball aimed at the other party&apos;s side by swinging a wooden cane with a wooden mallet head at the end.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Giccho is a game in which one party smashes a wooden ball aimed at the other party&apos;s side by swinging a wooden cane with a wooden mallet head at the end.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>またはその杖をいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Giccho also indicates the wooden cane used in the game.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Giccho also indicates the wooden cane used in the game.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Giccho also indicates the wooden cane used in the game.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>振々毬杖（ぶりぶりぎっちょう）、玉ぶりぶりとも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Giccho is also called &quot;buriburi-giccho&quot; or &quot;tama-buriburi&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Giccho is also called &quot;buriburi-giccho&quot; or &quot;tama-buriburi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Giccho is also called &quot;buriburi-giccho&quot; or &quot;tama-buriburi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>杖には色糸をまとう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The cane is decorated with color thread.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The cane is decorated with colored thread.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The cane is decorated with colored thread.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>平安時代に童子の遊びとして始まり、後に庶民の間に広まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Developed as a game for children in the Heian period, Giccho later became popular among the people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Giccho evolved during the Heian period as a game for children, but later it became popular with people of all generations.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Giccho evolved during the Heian period as a game for children, but later it became popular with people of all generations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>その後は形骸化し、江戸時代頃まで正月儀式として残った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The game gradually became obsolete, however, it remained as a ritual of the New Year until around the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The game gradually became obsolete, but it remained as a New Year ritual until around the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The game gradually became obsolete, but it remained as a New Year ritual until around the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>現在では、地域における文化体験の一環として時たま楽しまれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At present, people occasionally enjoy this game as a part of regional hands-on cultural learning experience.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, people occasionally enjoy this game as part of regional hands-on cultural learning experiences.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, people occasionally enjoy this game as part of regional hands-on cultural learning experiences.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>左利きの人が毬杖を左手に持ったことから、ひだりぎっちょうの語源とする説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A theory suggests that the word &quot;hidari-giccho&quot; (lefty) was derived from the matter that lefties held Giccho (wooden cane) in their left hands.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A theory suggests that the term &quot;hidari-giccho&quot; (lefty) was derived from the matter that a left-handed person would hold Giccho (wooden cane) in the left hand.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A theory suggests that the term &quot;hidari-giccho&quot; (lefty) was derived from the matter that a left-handed person would hold Giccho (wooden cane) in the left hand.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>『本朝俚諺』には、「俗間に、左の手の利きたる人をぎっちょといへるは、左義長といふ意、左専（もっぱ）らききたるに準（なら）ふ」とある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Honchorigen&quot; suggests another etymology in its description that &quot;The reason why lefties are generally called &quot;giccho&quot; is in the Chinese character &quot;左義長&quot; (Sagicho (ritual bonfire of New Year&apos;s decorations)), which also means people who mainly use their left hand&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Honchorigen&quot; suggests another etymology in its description that &quot;the reason lefties are generally called &quot;giccho&quot; is in the Chinese character &quot;左義長&quot; (Sagicho (ritual bonfire of New Year&apos;s decorations)), which also means people who mainly use the left hand.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Honchorigen&quot; suggests another etymology in its description that &apos;the reason lefties are generally called &quot;giccho&quot; is in the Chinese character &quot;左義長&quot; (Sagicho (ritual bonfire of New Year&apos;s decorations)), which also means people who mainly use the left hand.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Noririty(id:2936), Point136(id:211299), Textex(id:27452), Yas(id:739), Nighthawks(id:36125), Annogoo(id:127074), Hatsune(id:26654), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>