<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>缶コーヒー</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Canned coffee</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Canned coffee</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Canned Coffee</e>
<cmt>語頭大文字</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>缶コーヒー（かんコーヒー）とは、缶に入っていて、すぐに飲むことのできるコーヒーである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Canned coffee means coffee which is packed into a can and can be drunk without preparation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Canned coffee means coffee in a can ready to drink without any preparation.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Canned coffee means coffee in a can ready to drink without any preparation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>主に自動販売機やコンビニエンスストアなどで販売されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is mainly sold from vending machines and at convenience stores.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is mainly sold from vending machines and at convenience stores.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is mainly sold from vending machines and at convenience stores.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>チルドカップやペットボトル入りの製品と総括してReady To Drinkコーヒーとも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ii is also called ready-to-drink coffee collectively with products packed in a chilled cup or a PET bottle (Polyethylene terephtalate bottle).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ii is also called ready-to-drink coffee collectively with products packed in a chilled cup or a PET bottle (Polyethylene terephtalate bottle).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ii is also called ready-to-drink coffee collectively with products packed in a chilled cup or a PET bottle (Polyethylene terephtalate bottle).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>缶コーヒーはコーヒーを加工して作られる様々な二次産品（コーヒー風味の菓子やパンなど）の一つで、工業用コーヒー市場の製品に分類される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Canned coffee is one of the various secondary products made from by processing coffee (.coffee-flavored candies and bread) and is categorized as a product of industrial coffee market.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Canned coffee is one of the various secondary products made from by processing coffee (.coffee-flavored candies and bread) and is categorized as a product of industrial coffee market.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Canned coffee is one of the various secondary products made from by processing coffee (.coffee-flavored candies and bread) and is categorized as a product of industrial coffee market.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>同じ保存食であるインスタントコーヒーの簡便性がさらに高められ、屋外でも容易に消費可能である点が特徴。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is higher in convenience than instant coffee which belongs to the same preserved food category and is characterized by easiness of outdoor use.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is higher in convenience than instant coffee which belongs to the same preserved food category and is characterized by easy outdoor use.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is higher in convenience than instant coffee which belongs to the same preserved food category and is characterized by easy outdoor use.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>日本では喫茶店ブーム、インスタントコーヒーブームを経て本格的に商品化され、自動販売機の発達とともに飛躍的な成長を遂げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was commercialized on a full scale in Japan through the coffee shop boom and the instant coffee boom and grew by leaps and bounds with development of vending machines.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was commercialized on a full scale in Japan during the coffee shop and instant coffee boom and grew by leaps and bounds with the development of vending machines.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was commercialized on a full scale in Japan during the coffee shop and instant coffee boom and grew by leaps and bounds with the development of vending machines.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>以降も市場は拡大を続け、2008年時点で日本での清涼飲料水におけるシェアは3割を超えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, too, the market continued to expand and in 2008 the market share of canned coffee exceeded 30% in the whole soft drink market in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, too, the market continued to expand and in 2008 the market share of canned coffee exceeded 30% in the whole soft drink market in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, too, the market continued to expand and in 2008 the market share of canned coffee exceeded 30% in the whole soft drink market in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>郊外のスーパーマーケットやディスカウントストアなどでは、24～30本入りの箱単位で売られることも多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In supermarkets and discount stores in the suburb, canned coffee is in many occasions sold in cases of 24-30 cans.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In supermarkets and discount stores in the suburbs, canned coffee is sold in cases of twenty-four to thirty-cans.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In supermarkets and discount stores in the suburbs, canned coffee is sold in cases of twenty-four to thirty-cans.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>清涼飲料に使用される容器の構成は1999年頃にポリエチレンテレフタラートと缶の割合が逆転し、2000年代においてペットボトルが全体の88.1%となっており缶の使用は大きく減退している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Component ratio between can and polyethylene terephtalate (PET) for soft-drink container use was reversed around 1999 and the ratio of PET bottles became 88.1% of the whole in the 2000s with the use of cans being considerably reduced.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Component ratio between cans and polyethylene terephtalate (PET) for soft-drink containers use was reversed around 1999 and the ratio of PET bottles became 88.1% of the whole during the 2000s with the use of cans being considerably reduced.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Component ratio between cans and polyethylene terephtalate (PET) for soft-drink containers use was reversed around 1999 and the ratio of PET bottles became 88.1% of the whole during the 2000s with the use of cans being considerably reduced.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>コーヒー系清涼飲料に限れば逆となっており、2000年代における容器の構成は缶が71.5％と大きく占めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as only for coffee-type soft drinks, the situation is reverse, or cans largely accounted for 71.5% of containers in the 2000s.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, just for coffee-type soft drinks, the situation is reversed, cans largely accounted for 71.5% of containers during the 2000s.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, just for coffee-type soft drinks, the situation is reversed, cans largely accounted for 71.5% of containers during the 2000s.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>理由として、食品衛生法で定められた高温・高圧での殺菌を行う（ただし、特性上完全な殺滅は困難。詳細は缶コーヒーの成分の節参照）ため、スチール缶が強度的な面から多用される状況、と全国清涼飲料工業会は見解を示している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is, as Japan Soft Drinks Association explains, sterilization under high temperature and humidity required by Food Sanitation Act should be conducted (Perfect sterilization is difficult to be done due to its characteristics, though. For details, refer to the chapter on the ingredients of canned coffee) and so steel cans are used in large numbers due to its intensity.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the Japan Soft Drink Association explains, sterilization under high temperature and humidity required by the Food Sanitation Act should be conducted (Perfect sterilization is difficult, though. For details, refer to the chapter on the ingredients of canned coffee) and so steel cans are used in large numbers.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the Japan Soft Drink Association explains, sterilization should be conducted under the high temperature and humidity conditions required by the Food Sanitation Act (perfect sterilization is difficult, however; for details, refer to the section on ingredients for canned coffee) so, due to their strength, steel cans are used in large quantities.</e>
<cmt>「強度的な面から」がＮＣで抜けたので対応しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>日本にて缶コーヒーに関する各種調査が行われており各種項目において首位に選出されることが多いブランドは「ジョージア (缶コーヒー)」となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Various surveys have been conducted on the canned coffee in Japan and &apos;Georgia (canned coffee)&apos; is the brand which has been many times selected as No.1 in various items.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Various surveys have been conducted on canned coffee in Japan and &apos;Georgia (canned coffee)&apos; is the brand often selected as number one in various categories.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Various surveys have been conducted on canned coffee in Japan and &apos;Georgia (canned coffee)&apos; is the brand often selected as number one in various categories.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="13">
<j>缶コーヒーが持つ、独特の風味・嗅覚・味が発生する要因として、スチール缶など容器ごと行う殺菌工程、添加剤成分（缶コーヒーの成分）、コーヒーが本来持つ香りが熱や時間が経つことで飛んでしまう特性（缶コーヒーの成分）、などが挙げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The unique flavor, smell and taste of canned coffee are created by the sterilization process together with a container like a steel can, the ingredients of an additive (an ingredient of canned coffee), the property of coffee that the natural aroma of coffee disappear due to heat or a lapse of time (an ingredient of canned coffee) and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The unique flavor, smell and taste of canned coffee are created by the sterilization process together with a container like a steel can, the ingredient of additives (ingredients of canned coffee), the property of coffee where the natural aroma disappears due to heat or lapse of time.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The unique flavor, smell and taste of canned coffee are created by the sterilization process together with a container like a steel can, the ingredient of additives (ingredients of canned coffee), the property of coffee where the natural aroma disappears due to heat or lapse of time.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>また、コーヒー飲み物としてのコーヒーと差があると感じる人も存在するため、それに匹敵する味を求めて絶えず改良が行われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As there are some people who feel canned coffee tastes different from usually-served coffee, improvement efforts are always made to meet those people&apos;s tastes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As there are some people who feel canned coffee tastes different from usually-served coffee, effort to improvethe taste is always being made to meet their expectations.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As there are some people who feel canned coffee tastes different from usually-served coffee, effort to improve the taste is always being made to meet their expectations.</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="15">
<j>飲み方に個々の嗜好が強く反映されるコーヒーを一様にパッケージして販売する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Each individual&apos;s taste is strongly reflected on drinking way of coffee, but canned coffee is uniformly packed and sold.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Each individual&apos;s taste is strongly reflected on the way they \drink their coffee, but canned coffee is uniformly canned and sold.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Each individual&apos;s taste is strongly reflected on the way they drink their coffee, but canned coffee is uniformly canned and sold.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>という特異性ゆえに、長らく日本独特の飲料とみられていたが、90年代からは欧米など日本以外の国でも一部製造販売されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to this peculiarity, canned coffee has been long regarded as a special Japanese drink, but from the 1990s it started being manufactured and sold in some countries other than Japan like Western countries.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to this peculiarity, canned coffee has been long regarded as a special Japanese drink, but from the 1990s it started being manufactured and sold in some countries other than Japan like in Western countries.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to this peculiarity, canned coffee has been long regarded as a special Japanese drink, but from the 1990s it started being manufactured and sold in some countries other than Japan like in Western countries.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>特に東南アジアにおける販売伸張が目立つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">More especially, the sale of canned coffee is remarkably increased in Southeast Asian countries.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">More especially, the sale of canned coffee has remarkably increased in Southeast Asian countries.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">More especially, the sale of canned coffee has remarkably increased in Southeast Asian countries.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>日本</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="18">
<j>1958年（昭和33年） - 外山食品が『ダイヤモンド缶入りコーヒー』を発売したとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1958 - Toyama Shokuhin is understood to have started selling &quot;Coffee in Diamond can.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1958 - Toyama Shokuhin is understood to have started selling &quot;Coffee in Diamond labeled cans.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1958 - Toyama Shokuhin is understood to have started selling &quot;Coffee in Diamond labeled cans.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>しかし同社は1964年に倒産してしまったため詳細は不明。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Details are unknown due to its bankruptcy in 1964.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Details are unknown due to bankruptcy in 1964.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Details are unknown due to bankruptcy in 1964.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="20">
<j>1965年（昭和40年） - 島根県浜田市のコーヒー店主・三浦義武によって開発された『ミラ・コーヒー』が世界初の缶コーヒーともいわれるが短期間で生産中止となっており、これも詳細は不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1965 - &quot;Mira Coffee&quot; was developed by Yoshitake MIURA, storekeeper of the coffee shop in Hamada city, Shimane Prefecture, which is said to be the first canned coffee in the world, but it went out of production in a short time and so details are unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1965 - &quot;Mira Coffee&quot; was developed by Yoshitake MIURA, storekeeper of the coffee shop in Hamada city, Shimane Prefecture, which is said to be the first canned coffee in the world, but it went out of production in a short time and so details are unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1965 - &quot;Mira Coffee&quot; was developed by Yoshitake MIURA, storekeeper of the coffee shop in Hamada City, Shimane Prefecture, which is said to be the first canned coffee in the world, but it went out of production in a short time and so details are unknown.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>当時、浜田市中において盛んだった製缶技術を駆使して製造されたもので、半年後に開缶しても混濁する事がなかったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The product was manufactured utilizing can-making technology which was then prosperous in Hamada City, and it is said that it didn&apos;t show muddiness when the can is opened even a half year later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The product was manufactured utilizing can-making technology then prosperous in Hamada City, and it is said that it didn&apos;t show muddiness even when the can was opened a half year later.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The product was manufactured utilizing can-making technology then prosperous in Hamada City, and it is said that it didn&apos;t show muddiness even when the can was opened a half year later.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="22">
<j>1969年（昭和44年） - 上島珈琲本社（現：UCC上島珈琲）が、コーヒー牛乳にヒントを得て日本初のミルク入り缶コーヒー『UCCコーヒー ミルク入り』を発売した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1969 - Ueshima Coffee Head Office (Currently: UCC Ueshima Coffee) put on the market &quot;UCC COFFEE Milk &amp; Coffee,&quot; the first canned coffee with milk, taking a hint from coffee milk.</e>
<cmt>&quot;UCC COFFEE Milk &amp; Coffee&quot;は、下記UCCのサイトから引用した現在の名称です。1969年当時の英語の正式名称が見つからないので現在のものにしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1969 - Ueshima Coffee Head Office (Currently: UCC Ueshima Coffee) put on the market &quot;UCC COFFEE Milk &amp; Coffee,&quot; the first canned coffee with milk, taking a hint from coffee milk.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1969 - Ueshima Coffee Head Office (Currently: UCC Ueshima Coffee) put on the market &quot;UCC COFFEE Milk &amp; Coffee,&quot; the first canned coffee with milk, taking a hint from coffee milk.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>当時は瓶入りのコーヒー牛乳が外出先で購入できる一般的なコーヒー飲料であったが、缶コーヒーの登場によって人々は自由にコーヒー飲料を持ち歩くことができるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In those days, bottled coffee milk was a general coffee drink which was available away from home or office, but upon arrival of canned coffee on the market, people came to be able to carry coffee drink freely.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In those days, bottled coffee milk was a general coffee drink available away at home or office, but with the arrival of canned coffee on the market, people were able to carry coffee freely.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In those days, bottled coffee milk was a general coffee drink available away at home or office, but with the arrival of canned coffee on the market, people were able to carry coffee freely.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>ただし、UCCの缶コーヒーは、乳固形分の比率が高く乳飲料に該当する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, canned coffee of UCC is categorized as milk beverage due to its high ratio of milk solid.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, UCC canned coffee is categorized as a milk beverage due to its high ratio of milk solids.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, UCC canned coffee is categorized as a milk beverage due to its high ratio of milk solids.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>コーヒー5g以上というコーヒー規格の缶コーヒーは、1972年に発売されたポッカコーポレーション（当時）の『コーヒープレミアムタイプ』である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Canned coffee comprising with the coffee standard of more than 5g of coffee content was &quot;Coffee Premium Type&quot; put on the market by Pokka Corporation (of those days) in 1972.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Canned coffee comprising of standard coffee of more than 5g of coffee content was &quot;Coffee Premium Type&quot; put on the market by Pokka Corporation in 1972.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Canned coffee comprising of standard coffee of more than 5 g of coffee content was &quot;Coffee Premium Type&quot; put on the market by Pokka Corporation in 1972.</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="26">
<j>1973年（昭和48年） - コーヒーは温めても冷やしても飲まれることに目をつけたポッカは、冷却と加熱の切り替えが可能な、ホットオアコールド式自動販売機を開発した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1973 - Pokka, paying attention to the fact that coffee can be drunk warmed or chilled, developed a hot-or-cold-type vending machine by which switchover is possible between cooling and heating.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1973 - Pokka, concious of the fact that coffee can be drunk warmed or chilled, developed a hot-or-cold-type vending machine by which switchover is possible between cooling and heating.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1973 - Pokka, conscious of the fact that coffee can be drunk warmed or chilled, developed a hot-or-cold-type vending machine by which switchover is possible between cooling and heating.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>この自動販売機の普及によって、夏の飲み物であった缶コーヒーは通年商品となり、市場は大きく拡大した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As this vending machine came into wide use, canned coffee which had been a summer drink became a year-round product, which considerably expanded the market.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As this vending machine came into wide use, canned coffee, that had been considered a summer drink became a year-round product, and this considerably expanded the market.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As this vending machine came into wide use, canned coffee, that had been considered a summer drink became a year-round product, and this considerably expanded the market.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="28">
<j>1975年（昭和50年） - 日本コカ・コーラ社『ジョージア (缶コーヒー)』で市場参入。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1975 - Coca-Cola (Japan) Company, Limited entered into the market with &quot;Georgia (Canned coffee).&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1975 - Coca-Cola (Japan) Company, Limited entered into the market with &quot;Georgia (Canned coffee).&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1975 - Coca-Cola (Japan) Company, Limited entered into the market with &quot;Georgia (Canned coffee).&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="29">
<j>1983年（昭和58年） には1億ケースを突破。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The shipment in 1983 exceeded 100 million cases.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shipment in 1983 exceeded 100 million cases.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The shipment in 1983 exceeded 100 million cases.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="30">
<j>1986年（昭和61年） 頃から、アサヒ飲料・キリンビバレッジ・サントリーといったビール系企業が本格参入。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From around 1986, beer brewery-affiliated companies like Asahi soft Drinks, Kirin Beverage and Suntory entered the market on a full scale.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From around 1986, beer brewery-affiliated companies like Asahi soft Drinks, Kirin Beverage, and Suntory entered the market on a full scale.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From around 1986, beer brewery-affiliated companies like Asahi soft Drinks, Kirin Beverage, and Suntory entered the market on a full scale.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>豆の品種や製法に焦点をあてたイメージ戦略で清涼飲料系缶コーヒーとの差別化を図る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They aimed at differentiation from soft-drink-type canned coffee through the image marketing strategy focusing on kinds of coffee beans and manufacturing process.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They aimed at differentiation from soft-drink-type canned coffee through an image marketing strategy focusing on kinds of coffee beans and manufacturing process.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They aimed at differentiation from soft-drink-type canned coffee through an image marketing strategy focusing on kinds of coffee beans and manufacturing process.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="32">
<j>1990年（平成2年） には3億ケース（1ケース＝30本）を突破。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1990, the shipment exceeded 300 million cases (30 cans/case)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1990, the shipment exceeded 300 million cases (30 cans/case)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1990, the shipment exceeded 300 million cases (30 cans/case).</e>
<cmt>ピリオド補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>飲料市場における缶コーヒーの割合は全体の約4分の1に達した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ratio of canned coffee in the beverage market achieved the level of approximately one fourth of the whole.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ratio of canned coffee in the beverage market achieved a level of approximately one fourth of the whole.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ratio of canned coffee in the beverage market achieved a level of approximately one fourth of the whole.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="34">
<j>2001年（平成13年） 頃から、300g前後のボトル缶が登場。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From around 2001, 300g or so bottle cans appeared on the market.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From around 2001, 300g or so bottle cans appeared on the market.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From around 2001, 300 g or so bottle cans appeared on the market.</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="35">
<j>2003年（平成15年） 頃から、190gの寸胴型ボトル缶が登場しており、主にプレミアム志向のコーヒーがやや高めの価格設定（1本140円前後）で販売されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From around 2003, 190g cylindrical bottle cans appeared on the market and they were mainly used for premium-oriented coffee which was sold at comparatively high prices (approximately 140 yen/can).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From around 2003, 190g cylindrical bottly type cans appeared on the market mainly used for premium-oriented coffee sold at comparatively high prices (approximately 140 yen/can).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From around 2003, 190 g cylindrical bottle type cans appeared on the market mainly used for premium-oriented coffee sold at comparatively high prices (approximately 140 yen/can).</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>これらボトル缶は、缶に直接口をつけることに抵抗感のある女性向けに開発されたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These types of bottle cans were developed for female persons who feel uncomfortable drinking directly from a can.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These types of bottle cans were developed for female persons who felt uncomfortable drinking directly from a can.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These types of bottle cans were developed for female persons who felt uncomfortable drinking directly from a can.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>また、リキャップが可能であり、190g寸胴型ボトルでは熱を通しにくいシュリンクを採用し、持ちやすさなどの工夫もなされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, it is possible to recap and, in the case of 190g cylindrical bottles, shrink technology is adopted to prevent heat transfer, which makes them to be comfortably held.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, it is possible to recap them and, in the case of 190g cylindrical bottles, shrink technology is adopted to prevent heat transfer, which allows them to be comfortably held.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, it is possible to recap them and, in the case of 190 g cylindrical bottles, shrink technology is adopted to prevent heat transfer, which allows them to be comfortably held.</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="38">
<j>2000年代中盤頃から、メタボリックシンドロームが話題となるなど健康志向が高まっていることや、エスプレッソなど苦みの強いコーヒーを提供するカフェが普及した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From around the mid 2000s, people became health-conscious with topics like metabolic syndrome being talked about and cafes where bitter coffee like espresso were served spread.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From around the mid 2000s, people became health-conscious with topics like metabolic syndrome being talked about and cafes serving bitter coffee like espresso spread.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From around the mid 2000s, people became health-conscious with topics like metabolic syndrome being talked about and cafes serving bitter coffee like espresso spread.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>これらが影響し、糖分の少ないコーヒーが好まれるようになった傾向によって微糖・無糖コーヒーの需要・市場が伸びている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to the tendency, low-sugar-content coffee came to be preferred and the demand/market for trace-sugar or sugar-free coffee are growing.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to the tendency, low-sugar-content coffee came to be preferred and the demand/market for trace-sugar or sugar-free coffee is growing.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to the tendency, low-sugar-content coffee came to be preferred and the demand/market for trace-sugar or sugar-free coffee is growing.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>無糖コーヒーはボトル缶使用による利便性の向上や味の向上によって改良された商品が増えてきている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As far as sugar-free coffee is concerned, upgraded products have been increasing with improved level of convenience by use of bottle cans and with improved tastes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As far as sugar-free coffee is concerned, upgraded products have been increasing with the improved level of convenient use of bottle cans with improved flavor.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As far as sugar-free coffee is concerned, upgraded products have been increasing with the improved level of convenient use of bottle cans with improved flavor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="41">
<j>2000年代前半から中盤における缶コーヒーの市場規模は推定約3億5000万ケースと横ばい～微減状態で停滞気味に推移している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The market size of canned coffee from the beginning to the mid 2000s hovered around with an estimated amount of 350 million cases leveling off or slightly decreasing.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The market size for canned coffee from the beginning to the mid 2000s hovered around an estimated 350 million cases, leveling off or slightly decreasing.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The market size for canned coffee from the beginning to the mid 2000s hovered around an estimated 350 million cases, leveling off or slightly decreasing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>要因としては消費者の嗜好変化によるチルドカップコーヒーへの移行、健康志向の拡大により主軸商品であるミルク・砂糖入りのカテゴリーの苦戦やそれの影響による低糖・微糖・無糖コーヒーの需要拡大による差分埋め合わせ、が挙げられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As factors in the situation, the following facts are mentioned, i.e., the shift to chilled cup coffee due to the change of consumers&apos; tastes and hard-fought struggles the main product, canned coffee with milk and sugar was forced to engage in due to people&apos;s expanded health consciousness, for which efforts were made to increase the demand for low-sugar, trace-sugar and sugar-free canned coffee to make up for the loss of sales.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As factors in the situation, the following facts are mentioned, i.e., the shift to chilled cup coffee due to the change of consumers&apos; tastes and the hard-fought struggle for the main product, canned coffee with milk and sugar due to people&apos;s expanded health consciousness, for which efforts were made to increase the demand for low-sugar, trace-suga,r and sugar-free canned coffee to make up for the loss of sales.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As factors in the situation, the following facts are mentioned, i.e., the shift to chilled cup coffee due to the change of consumers&apos; tastes and the hard-fought struggle for the main product, canned coffee with milk and sugar due to people&apos;s expanded health consciousness, for which efforts were made to increase the demand for low-sugar, trace-sugar and sugar-free canned coffee to make up for the loss of sales.</e>
<cmt>カンマ削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="43">
<j>2008年（平成20年）、 前述の低糖・微糖・無糖コーヒーの需要拡大が功を奏し、2007年比1.5％増と久々に上昇傾向に転じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 2008, the market size of canned coffee took an upward turn and made an 1.5% increase compared with 2007.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 2008, the market size of canned coffee took an upward turn and made an 1.5% increase compared with 2007.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 2008, the market size of canned coffee took an upward turn thanks to the above-mentioned increase the demand for low-sugar, trace-sugar and sugar-free canned coffee and made an 1.5% increase compared with 2007.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>世界</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">World</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">World</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">World</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="44">
<j>1876年 米国のenChase &amp; Sanborn Coffee Company（Chase &amp; Sanborn Coffee Company）が開発とも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some say that Chase &amp; Sanborn Coffee Company in the United States developed it in 1876.</e>
<cmt>http://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E7%BC%B6%E3%82%B3%E3%83%BC%E3%83%92%E3%83%BCでは、「1876年 米国のチェイス・アンド・サンボーンカンパニー（Chase &amp; Sanborn Coffee Company）が開発[8]とも。」となっています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some say that Chase &amp; Sanborn Coffee Company in the United States developed it in 1876.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some say that Chase &amp; Sanborn Coffee Company in the United States developed it in 1876.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>なお、米国特許商標庁の特許文献検索では製缶会社による1940年代の缶コーヒー製造法特許を確認することができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If you search the website of the United States Patent and Trademark Office for some patent documents, you can find 1940s process patents of the 1940s for canned coffee by can manufacturing companies.</e>
<cmt>複数の製缶会社による複数の特許と解釈した訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If you search the website of the United States Patent and Trademark Office for some patent documents, you can find process patents from the 1940s for canned coffee by can manufacturing companies.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If you search the website of the United States Patent and Trademark Office for some patent documents, you can find process patents from the 1940s for canned coffee by can manufacturing companies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="46">
<j>1977年 日本のポッカコーポレーション、シンガポールに子会社（Pokka Corporation (Singapore) Pte. Ltd.）を設立。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1977, Pokka Corporation of Japan established its subsidiary (Pokka Corporation (Singapore) Pte. Ltd.) in Singapore.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1977, Pokka Corporation of Japan established its subsidiary (Pokka Corporation (Singapore) Pte. Ltd.) in Singapore.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1977, Pokka Corporation of Japan established its subsidiary (Pokka Corporation (Singapore) Pte. Ltd.) in Singapore.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>現地工場にて缶コーヒーの生産を開始。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It started manufacturing canned coffee in the local plant.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It started manufacturing canned coffee in a local plant.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It started manufacturing canned coffee in a local plant.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>1979年からは日本、香港へと輸出。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1979, it started exporting canned coffee to Japan and Hong Kong.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1979, it started exporting canned coffee to Japan and Hong Kong.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1979, it started exporting canned coffee to Japan and Hong Kong.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="49">
<j>1982年 台湾の食品会社zh金車公司（King Car Food Industrial Co.）、台湾市場において缶コーヒー『enMr. Brown Coffee』の販売を開始。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1982, A food company in Taiwan, King Car Food Industrial Co. started selling canned coffee, &quot;Mr. Brown Coffee&quot; in the Taiwan market.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1982, A food company in Taiwan, King Car Food Industrial Co. started selling canned coffee, &quot;Mr. Brown Coffee&quot; in the Taiwan market.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1982, a food company in Taiwan, King Car Food Industrial Co. started selling canned coffee, &quot;Mr. Brown Coffee&quot; in the Taiwan market.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="50">
<j>1991年 スイスの世界的食品企業enNestle（Nestle）、enThe Coca-Cola Company（The Coca-Cola Company）社と合弁事業し Coca-Cola &amp;Nestle Refreshments を設立（のち enBeverage Partners Worldwide へ改称。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1991, a Swiss global food company, Nestle and The Coca-Cola Company set up a joint venture, Coca-Cola &amp;Nestle Refreshments (Changed it name later to Beverage Partners Worldwide.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1991, a Swiss global food company, Nestle and The Coca-Cola Company set up a joint venture, Coca-Cola &amp; Nestle Refreshments (Changed it&apos;s name later to Beverage Partners Worldwide.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1991, a Swiss global food company, Nestle and The Coca-Cola Company set up a joint venture, Coca-Cola &amp; Nestle Refreshments (Changed it&apos;s name later to Beverage Partners Worldwide.)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除)補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>（2007年にネスレへ販売権返還）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 2007, it returned its dealership to Nestle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 2007, it returned its dealership to Nestle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(In 2007, it returned its dealership to Nestle.)</e>
<cmt>()補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>アジアを中心に世界各国で『ネスカフェ』ブランドの缶コーヒーが販売されるようになる（米国では1996年から販売）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Canned coffee with the brand name of &quot;NESCAFE&quot; came to be sold around the world centering on Asian countries (In the United States, it was put on the market in 1996).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Canned coffee under the brand name of &quot;NESCAFE&quot; came to be sold around the world centering on Asian countries (In the United States, it was put on the market in 1996).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Canned coffee under the brand name of &quot;NESCAFE&quot; came to be sold around the world centering on Asian countries (In the United States, it was put on the market in 1996).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="53">
<j>1994年 米国のコーヒー店チェーン・enStarbucks（Starbucks Coffee Company）社、enPepsiCo（PepsiCo, Inc.）社とパートナーシップを締結。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1994, a chain of coffee shops in the United States, Starbucks Coffee Company formed a partnership with PepsiCo, Inc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1994, a chain of coffee shops in the United States, Starbucks Coffee Company formed a partnership with PepsiCo, Inc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1994, a chain of coffee shops in the United States, Starbucks Coffee Company formed a partnership with PepsiCo, Inc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>以降、米国内における缶コーヒー『Starbucks DoubleShot』の発売（2002）や、加温可能な自社ブランドの自動販売機導入など積極的な市場展開を進める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, it actively developed the market by putting on the US market canned coffee, &quot;Starbucks Double Shot&quot; (2002) and by introducing heating vending machines for its own brand products.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, it actively developed the market by putting on the US market canned coffee, &quot;Starbucks Double Shot&quot; (2002) and by introducing heating vending machines for its own brand products.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, it actively developed the market by putting on the US market canned coffee, &quot;Starbucks Double Shot&quot; (2002) and by introducing heating vending machines for its own brand products.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="55">
<j>2008年 コカ・コーラ社はイタリアの大手コーヒーロースター・イッリカッフェ（Illycaffè）と提携を結び、オーストリア、クロアチア、ギリシャなど欧州10カ国で缶コーヒー『Illy issimo』を販売。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 2008, The Coca-Cola Company tied up with a major coffee roaster in Italy, Illycaffe and sold canned coffee, &quot;Illy issimo&quot; in 10 European countries including Austria, Croatia and Greece.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 2008, The Coca-Cola Company tied up with a major coffee roaster in Italy, Illycaffe and sold canned coffee, &quot;Illy issimo&quot; in 10 European countries including Austria, Croatia and Greece.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 2008, The Coca-Cola Company tied up with a major coffee roaster in Italy, Illycaffe and sold canned coffee, &quot;Illy issimo&quot; in 10 European countries including Austria, Croatia and Greece.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>表示の定義</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Definition of labels</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Definition of labels</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Definition of labels</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="56">
<j>「コーヒー」「コーヒー飲料」などの表示の定義はしばらく存在しなかったが、1977年 業界団体は製造規約を制定、のちに公正取引委員会が正式に告示した『参考文献・リンク』に基づき次の3種類に区分された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the labels like &quot;Coffee,&quot; &quot;Coffee beverage&quot; and so on had not been defined for some time the trade organization laid down manufacturing rules in 1977 and classified the products into the three types below according to &quot;Bibliography and links&quot; which was officially announced by Japan Fair Trade Commission later.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」 『参考文献・リンク』=「Bibliography and links」は、直訳しました。公式の訳はサイトでも見つけられませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the labels like &quot;Coffee,&quot; &quot;Coffee beverage,&quot; and so on, had not been defined for some time, the trade organization laid down manufacturing rules in 1977 and classified the products into the three types below according to &quot;Bibliography and links&quot; officially announced by Japan Fair Trade Commission later.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the labels like &quot;Coffee,&quot; &quot;Coffee beverage,&quot; and so on, had not been defined for some time, the trade organization laid down manufacturing rules in 1977 and classified the products into the three types below according to &quot;Bibliography and links&quot; officially announced by Japan Fair Trade Commission later.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>これは、自販機の普及による販売競争激化に加え、1975年に発生したブラジル大霜害の影響で生豆価格が高騰していたことから、極端に低濃度の製品や代替物を使用した粗悪品が市場に流通してしまう恐れが生じたことによる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was caused by the intensified sales competition due to the spread of vending machines and the fears that extremely low-concentrated products or inferior products containing substitute ingredients might be distributed on the market in view of rising prices of unroasted beans due to the great frost damage in Brazil in 1975.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was caused by an intensified sales competition due to the spread of vending machines and the fears that extremely low-concentrated products or inferior products containing substitute ingredients might be distributed on the market in view of rising prices of unroasted beans due to great frost damage in Brazil during 1975.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was caused by an intensified sales competition due to the spread of vending machines and the fears that extremely low-concentrated products or inferior products containing substitute ingredients might be distributed on the market in view of rising prices of unroasted beans due to great frost damage in Brazil during 1975.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="58">
<j>製品内容量100グラム中の生豆使用量</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Unroasted beans content per 100g of products</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unroasted beans content per 100g of products</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unroasted beans content per 100 g of products</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="59">
<j>コーヒー</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Coffee</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Coffee</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Coffee</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="60">
<j>5グラム以上</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">5g or more</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">5g or more</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">5 g or more</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="61">
<j>コーヒー飲料</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Coffee beverage</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Coffee beverage</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Coffee beverage</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="62">
<j>2.5グラム以上5グラム未満</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">2.5g or more and less than 5g</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">2.5g or more and less than 5g</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">2.5 g or more and less than 5 g</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="63">
<j>コーヒー入り清涼飲料</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Coffee-containing soft drinks</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Coffee-containing soft drinks</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Coffee-containing soft drinks</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="64">
<j>1グラム以上2.5グラム未満</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1g or more and less than 2.5g</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1g or more and less than 2.5g</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1 g or more and less than 2.5 g</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="65">
<j>喫茶店などで供されるコーヒーの場合、1杯(100〜150ml)あたりの生豆使用量は約10グラム程度とされるため、濃度規格をもっと上げるべきだという意見も挙げられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As unroasted beans content for coffee served at coffee shops is understood to be approximately 10g per one cup (100 to 150ml), there were opinions that the concentrations in the standard should be higher.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As unroasted bean content for coffee served at coffee shops is understood to be approximately 10g per one cup (100 to 150ml), there were opinions prevailing that concentrations for the standard should be higher.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As unroasted bean content for coffee served at coffee shops is understood to be approximately 10 g per one cup (100 to 150 ml), there were opinions prevailing that concentrations for the standard should be higher.</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>しかし、飲用するシチュエーションが異なる缶コーヒーとレギュラーコーヒーを同列で比較するのは無理がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as the drinking situations are different between canned coffee and regular coffee, it would be unreasonable to compare the two types on the same stage.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as the drinking situation is different between canned coffee and regular coffee, it would be unreasonable to compare the two types on the same level.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as the drinking situation is different between canned coffee and regular coffee, it would be unreasonable to compare the two types on the same level.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>この観点から、当範囲内に収めるのが妥当という結論に至っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From this viewpoint, it came to the conclusion that it be appropriate to leave the levels as they are.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From this viewpoint, the conclusion was that it is appropriate to leave the levels as they were.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From this viewpoint, the conclusion was that it is appropriate to leave the levels as they were.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>また、複雑化を避けるため当初は2区分にとどめる予定であったが、低濃度の瓶入りコーヒーも対象に含まれることになり3区分へと範囲が拡げられることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, it was originally intended to be classified into two levels to avoid complication, but low-concentrated coffee packed in bottles came to be included and it was expanded in the scope to three classes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, it was originally intended to be classified into two levels to avoid complication, but low-concentrated coffee in bottles came to be included and it was expanded in scope to three classes.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, it was originally intended to be classified into two levels to avoid complication, but low-concentrated coffee in bottles came to be included and it was expanded in scope to three classes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>その他の定義</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other definitions</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other definitions</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other definitions</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="69">
<j>製品に乳固形分を3%以上を含むものは『乳及び乳製品の成分規格等に関する省令』に基づき「乳飲料」となる（『カフェ・オ・レ』『カフェ・ラッテ』『コーヒー牛乳』など）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Any product containing 3% or more of milk solid is to be categorized as &apos;milk beverages&apos; according to &quot;Ordinance regarding standard of element, etc. of milk and dairy products&quot; (&quot;Café au lait&quot; &quot;Caffè Latte&quot; &quot;Coffee milk&quot; and so on).</e>
<cmt>『乳及び乳製品の成分規格等に関する省令』は、http://www.japaneselawtranslation.go.jp　を参考に訳しました。公式英文名ではありません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Any product containing three percent or more of milk solids is to be categorized as &apos;milk beverages&apos; according to &quot;Ordinance regarding standard of element, etc. of milk and dairy products&quot; (&quot;Café au lait&quot; &quot;Caffè Latte&quot; &quot;Coffee milk&quot; and so on).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Any product containing three percent or more of milk solids is to be categorized as &apos;milk beverages&apos; according to &quot;Ordinance regarding standard of element, etc. of milk and dairy products&quot; (&quot;Café au lait&quot; &quot;Caffè Latte&quot; &quot;Coffee milk&quot; and so on).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="70">
<j>糖類、乳製品、乳化された油脂を使用したものに「ブラック」と表示してはならない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is not permitted to label products containing sugars, dairy products or emulsified fats as &apos;Black.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is not permitted to label products containing sugars, dairy products or emulsified fats as &apos;Black.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is not permitted to label products containing sugars, dairy products or emulsified fats as &apos;Black.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>ただし糖類のみを使用したものに限り「加糖」と併記することで「ブラック」と表示する事ができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, products containing only sugars are permitted to be labeled as &apos;Black&apos; with a description of &apos;Sweetened.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, products containing only sugars are permitted to be labeled as &apos;Black&apos; with a description of &apos;Sweetened.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, products containing only sugars are permitted to be labeled as &apos;Black&apos; with a description of &apos;Sweetened.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="72">
<j>「無糖」「微糖」は健康増進法の栄養表示基準に基づき従った内容であれば無条件、もしくは条件付きで表示可能。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The labels, &apos;Sugar-free&apos; and &apos;trace-sugar&apos; are unconditionally or conditionally permitted to be labeled, if a product complies with the nutrition label standards of Health Promotion Law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The labels, &apos;Sugar-free&apos; and &apos;trace-sugar&apos; are unconditionally or conditionally permitted to be labeled, if a product complies with the nutrition label standards of the Health Promotion Law.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The labels, &apos;Sugar-free&apos; and &apos;trace-sugar&apos; are unconditionally or conditionally permitted to be labeled, if a product complies with the nutrition label standards of the Health Promotion Law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>「無糖」は糖類0.5g以下の場合、使用可能。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The label, &apos;Sugar-free&apos; can be used if the content of sugars is 0.5g or less.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The label, &apos;Sugar-free&apos; can be used if the content of sugars is 0.5g or less.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The label, &apos;Sugar-free&apos; can be used if the content of sugars is 0.5 g or less.</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>「微糖」が無条件で使用可能なのは絶対表示の場合のみである。、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The label, &apos;Trace-sugar&apos; can be unconditionally used only by the absolute labeling method.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The label, &apos;Trace-sugar&apos; can be unconditionally used only by the absolute labeling method.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The label, &apos;Trace-sugar&apos; can be unconditionally used only by the absolute labeling method.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>「100gあたり糖類2.5g以下」を満たすことによって「微糖」「低い」「少ない」「控えめ」等の表現が自由に使用可能。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such labels as &apos;Trace-sugar,&apos; &apos;Low,&apos; &apos;little,&apos; &apos;Moderate&apos; and so on can be freely used by complying with &apos;2.5g or less per 100g.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such labels as &apos;Trace-sugar,&apos; &apos;Low,&apos; &apos;little,&apos; &apos;Moderate&apos; and so on can be freely used by complying with &apos;2.5g or less per 100g.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such labels as &apos;Trace-sugar,&apos; &apos;Low,&apos; &apos;little,&apos; &apos;Moderate&apos; and so on can be freely used by complying with &apos;2.5 g or less per 100 g.&apos;</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>「微糖」が条件付きで使用可能なのは、相対表示の場合である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The label, &apos;Trace-sugar&apos; can be conditionally used by the relative labeling method.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The label, &apos;Trace-sugar&apos; can be conditionally used by the relative labeling method.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The label, &apos;Trace-sugar&apos; can be conditionally used by the relative labeling method.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>各社が独自に定めた糖類量の「標準値」からマイナス2.5g/100ml未満の場合『当社標準品に比較』という注意書き付きで「微糖」「低い」「少ない」「控えめ」等の表現が使用可能となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such labels as &apos;Trace-sugar,&apos; &apos;Low,&apos; &apos;little,&apos; &apos;Moderate&apos; and so on can be used by putting a warning label, &quot;Compared with our standard product,&quot; if the content equals each company&apos;s own &apos;Standard value&apos; of sugars minus less than 2.5g/100ml.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such labels as &apos;Trace-sugar,&apos; &apos;Low,&apos; &apos;little,&apos; &apos;Moderate&apos; and so on can be used by attaching a warning label, &quot;Compared with our standard product,&quot; if the content equals each company&apos;s own &apos;Standard value&apos; of sugars minus less than 2.5g/100ml.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such labels as &apos;Trace-sugar,&apos; &apos;Low,&apos; &apos;little,&apos; &apos;Moderate&apos; and so on can be used by attaching a warning label, &quot;Compared with our standard product,&quot; if the content equals each company&apos;s own &apos;Standard value&apos; of sugars minus less than 2.5 g/100 ml.</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>この場合、日本コーヒー飲料協会の調査値や「飲料以外の食品」の基準に基づく「100mlあたり糖類5g以下」が準用されているケースが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The value of &apos;5g or less of sugars per 100ml&apos; on the basis of the surveyed value of Japan Coffee Beverage Association and the standard of &apos;Foods other than beverages&apos; is applied mutatis mutandis in many cases.</e>
<cmt>「日本コーヒー飲料協会」の訳は直訳で、公式ではありません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The value of &apos;5g or less of sugars per 100ml&apos; on the basis of the surveyed value of Japan Coffee Beverage Association and the standard of &apos;Foods other than beverages&apos; is applied mutatis mutandis in many cases.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The value of &apos;5 g or less of sugars per 100 ml&apos; on the basis of the surveyed value of Japan Coffee Beverage Association and the standard of &apos;Foods other than beverages&apos; is applied mutatis mutandis in many cases.</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="79">
<j>缶に「ミルク入り」などと表示する場合は、乳脂肪分3%以上、無脂乳固形分8%以上の成分を有する乳製品がコーヒー飲料の内容重量に対し5%以上使用されていなければならない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A label of &apos;Milk-containing&apos; and so on cannot be put on cans unless a coffee beverage contains 5% or more by weight of a dairy product containing 3% or more of milk fat and 8% or more of nonfat milk solid.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A label showing &apos;Milk-containing&apos; and so on cannot be put on cans unless a coffee beverage contains five percent or more by weight of a dairy product containing three percent or more of milk fat and eight percent or more of nonfat milk solids.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A label showing &apos;Milk-containing&apos; and so on cannot be put on cans unless a coffee beverage contains five percent or more by weight of a dairy product containing three percent or more of milk fat and eight percent or more of nonfat milk solids.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="80">
<j>『ブルーマウンテン』のように特定種のコーヒー名を表記した場合は、他種のコーヒーを混合してはならない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If a specific name of coffee like &quot;Blue Mountain&quot; is to be labeled, no other type of coffee may be mixed with it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If a specific name for coffee like &quot;Blue Mountain&quot; is to be labeled, no other type of coffee may be mixed with it.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If a specific name for coffee like &quot;Blue Mountain&quot; is to be labeled, no other type of coffee may be mixed with it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="81">
<j>『モカ・ブレンド』のように特定種のコーヒー名と混合した表記の場合は、その種のコーヒーを51%以上使用していなければならない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If a name meaning a blend with a specific type of coffee like &quot;Mocha Blend&quot; is to be labeled, 51% or more of that type of coffee should be contained.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If a name meaning a blend of a specific type of coffee like &quot;Mocha Blend&quot; is to be labeled, fifty-one percent or more of that type of coffee should be contained.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If a name meaning a blend of a specific type of coffee like &quot;Mocha Blend&quot; is to be labeled, fifty-one percent or more of that type of coffee should be contained.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="82">
<j>「早挽き」「深煎り」「デミタス」の表示には特に規定が無く、メーカー側の判断によって使用されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For the labels of &apos;Freshly-ground,&apos; &apos;Deeply-roasted&apos; and &apos;Demitasse,&apos; there is no rule and so manufacturers are using these labels according to their own judgments.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For the labels indicating &apos;Freshly-ground,&apos; &apos;Deeply-roasted&apos; and &apos;Demitasse,&apos; there are no rules and manufacturers are using these labels based upon their own judgment.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For the labels indicating &apos;Freshly-ground,&apos; &apos;Deeply-roasted&apos; and &apos;Demitasse,&apos; there are no rules and manufacturers are using these labels based upon their own judgment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>缶の種類</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Types of cans</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Types of cans</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Types of cans</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="83">
<j>ショート缶</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Short cans</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Short cans</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Short cans</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="84">
<j>190g前後の缶を使用したコーヒー。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is coffee packed in 190g or so cans</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Coffee in 190g cans</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Coffee in 190 g cans</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>1980年代後半以降は最も一般的な容量となっているため、ショート缶と呼称される機会は減っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As this volume was the most common after the last half of the 1980s, occasions for this can being called short can have been decreasing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As this volume was the most common after the last half of the 1980s, the occasion for this can being called a short can have been decreasing.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As this volume was the most common after the last half of the 1980s, the occasion for this can being called a short can have been decreasing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="86">
<j>ロング缶</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tall cans</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tall cans</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tall cans</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="87">
<j>250g前後の細長い缶を使用したコーヒー。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is coffee packed in 250g or so tall cans</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is coffee packed in 250g or so tall cans</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is coffee packed in 250 g or so tall cans.</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入ピリオド補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>「コーヒー」は少なく、「コーヒー飲料」が主流となる（まれに「コーヒー入り清涼飲料」の場合も）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This type is used less for &apos;Coffee&apos; and becomes mainly for &apos;Coffee beverages&apos; (In rare cases, for &apos;Coffee-containing soft drink&apos;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This type is used less for &apos;Coffee&apos; and is mainly for &apos;Coffee beverages&apos; (In rare cases, for &apos;Coffee-containing soft drink&apos;).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This type is used less for &apos;Coffee&apos; and is mainly for &apos;Coffee beverages&apos; (In rare cases, for &apos;Coffee-containing soft drink&apos;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>流行がショート缶へと移り変わる過渡期には、長さが190gサイズと同等でありながら横幅が広い「太缶」といわれる250g缶も散見された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a period of transition of trends to short cans, 250g cans called &apos;Fat can&apos; which were equally tall as 190g size cans and fat were found.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the period of transition of trends to short cans, 250g cans called &apos;Fat can&apos; that were equally tall as 190g size cans and equal in diameter were found.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the period of transition of trends to short cans, 250 g cans called &apos;Fat can&apos; that were equally tall as 190 g size cans and wider in diameter were found.</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入原文に合うように修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="90">
<j>エスプレッソ缶</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Espresso cans</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Espresso cans</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Espresso cans</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="91">
<j>170g前後の缶を使用したコーヒー。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is coffee packed in 170g or so cans</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Coffee in 170g cans</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Coffee in 170 g cans</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>但し、190g缶のデミタスもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there are also 190g demitasse.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there is also 190g demitasse.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there is also 190 g demitasse.</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="93">
<j>ボトル缶</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bottle cans</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bottle cans</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bottle cans</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="94">
<j>ペットボトルのリシール（再栓）機能とアルミ缶のリサイクル性を兼ね備えており、俗にリキャップ缶とも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are also commonly called recap cans, being resealable as PET bottles and recyclable as aluminum cans.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are also commonly called recap cans, being resealable as PET bottles and recyclable as aluminum cans.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are also commonly called recap cans, being resealable as PET bottles and recyclable as aluminum cans.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>190g前後で細めの寸胴状のもの（TEC缶 - 東洋製罐　WORC - 大和製罐）と、300g前後・400-500g程度の寸胴な集乳缶形状（ニューボトル缶 - 大和製罐・ユニバーサル製缶）をしたものがあり、飲み口が広いことから飲用時の香り受けが非常に良い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are 190g or so narrow and cylindrical cans (TEC cans-Toyo Seikan, WORC-Daiwa Can) and 300g or so/400g-500g cylindrical, milk-can-shaped cans (New bottle cans-Daiwa Can/Universal Can), wide opening of which makes aroma and flavor of coffee more enjoyable when drinking.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are 190g or so narrow and cylindrical cans (TEC cans-Toyo Seikan, WORC-Daiwa Can) and 300g or so/400g-500g cylindrical, milk-can-shaped cans (New bottle cans-Daiwa Can/Universal Can), with wide opennings making the aroma and flavor of coffee more enjoyable when drinking.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are 190 g or so narrow and cylindrical cans (TEC cans-Toyo Seikan, WORC-Daiwa Can) and 300 g or so/400 g-500 g cylindrical, milk-can-shaped cans (New bottle cans-Daiwa Can/Universal Can), with wide openings making the aroma and flavor of coffee more enjoyable when drinking.</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="96">
<j>350g缶</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">350g cans</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">350g cans</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">350 g cans</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="97">
<j>コスト的な影響から「コーヒー」としての350g缶は稀で「コーヒー飲料」としても極少数に留まる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to their cost, 350g cans are rarely used for &apos;coffee&apos; and extremely less even for &apos;Coffee beverages.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to their cost, 350g cans are rarely used for &apos;coffee&apos; and extremely less for &apos;Coffee beverages.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to their cost, 350 g cans are rarely used for &apos;coffee&apos; and extremely less for &apos;Coffee beverages.&apos;</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>徳用感があり止渇飲料としての量的欲求に適合するため夏場における販売比重が高い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since they give a sense of economy and meet a quantitative desire for thirst-quenching beverage, more emphasis is placed on their sales in the summer season.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since they give a sense of economy and meet a quantitative desire for a thirst-quenching beverage, more emphasis is placed on their sales during the summer season.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since they give a sense of economy and meet a quantitative desire for a thirst-quenching beverage, more emphasis is placed on their sales during the summer season.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="99">
<j>樽型缶</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Barrel-shaped cans</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Barrel-shaped cans</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Barrel-shaped cans</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="100">
<j>樽の形状をしており一種の高級感がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are barrel-shaped and have a kind of high-quality sense.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are barrel-shaped and present an image of high-quality.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are barrel-shaped and present an image of high-quality.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>もとは缶ビール用として開発されたもので、のちに缶コーヒー用へと改良された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were originally developed for canned beer and afterward modified for canned coffee.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were originally developed for canned beer and afterwards modified for canned coffee.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were originally developed for canned beer and afterwards modified for canned coffee.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>本格志向へと流行が移行し始めた頃に生まれ、その雰囲気作りに一役買っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were created around the time when the trend started changing to authenticity-oriented coffee and played a part in producing the atmosphere.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were created around the time when the trend started changing to authentically-oriented coffee and played a part in creating the atmosphere.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were created around the time when the trend started changing to authentically-oriented coffee and played a part in creating the atmosphere.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="103">
<j>ウエストウェーブ缶</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Waist-shaped cans</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Waist-shaped cans</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Waist-shaped cans</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="104">
<j>日本たばこ産業が販売する缶コーヒー『ルーツ (缶コーヒー)』シリーズで採用されている缶。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is the can type used for &quot;Roots (Canned coffee)&quot; series sold by Japan Tobacco.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is the can type used for &quot;Roots (Canned coffee)&quot; series sold by Japan Tobacco.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is the can type used for &quot;Roots (Canned coffee)&quot; series sold by Japan Tobacco.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>缶胴下部に殺菌時の熱効率を上げる括れ加工が施されており、コーヒーカップを思わせる独特の形状をしている（MC缶 - 北海製罐）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its lower part is compressed to make a waist for higher thermal efficiency in sterilization and its unique shape resembles a coffee cup (MC can-Hokkai Can).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its lower part is compressed to make a waist for higher thermal efficiency during sterilization and its unique shape resembles a coffee cup (MC can-Hokkai Can).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its lower part is compressed to make a waist for higher thermal efficiency during sterilization and its unique shape resembles a coffee cup (MC can-Hokkai Can).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="106">
<j>ビード缶</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bead cans</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bead cans</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bead cans</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="107">
<j>缶材が薄くても外圧に耐えられるよう、ドラム缶のような輪帯（ビード）加工が施され表面が波打っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Embossed beads as on drums are added to the middle of the can body for the thin-walled can body plate to resist the external pressure and so the plate is corrugated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Embossed beads like those found on a drum are incorporated into the middle of the can body for the thin-walled can body plate to resist external pressure and the can is corrugated.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Embossed beads like those found on a drum are incorporated into the middle of the can body for the thin-walled can body plate to resist external pressure and the can is corrugated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>鋼材高騰を背景にコスト面で優れていたが、デザイン上難があったため80年代しか普及しなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While they were advantageous in cost under the soaring cost of steel, there were drawbacks in design and they were used only in the 1980s.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While they had a cost advantage under the soaring cost of steel, there were drawbacks in design and they were used only in the 1980s.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While they had a cost advantage under the soaring cost of steel, there were drawbacks in design and they were used only in the 1980s.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="109">
<j>セルフヒーティング缶</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Self-heating cans</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Self-heating cans</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Self-heating cans</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="110">
<j>20世紀初頭に発明された自己発熱機構を備える食品缶。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are food cans equipped with the self-heating device invented at the beginning of the 20th century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are food cans equipped with the self-heating device invented at the beginning of the twentieth century.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are food cans equipped with the self-heating device invented at the beginning of the twentieth century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>1940年代の欧米にはこの機構を採用したコーヒーがすでに存在していたが使用状況は限られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Canned coffee with this device already existed in the Western countries in the 1940s but was of limited use.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Canned coffee with this device already existed in Western countries during the 1940s but was of limited use.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Canned coffee with this device already existed in Western countries during the 1940s but was of limited use.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>2000年頃から加温可能な自動販売機の代替として再び注目されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From around 2000, it started receiving attention again as an alternative to heating vending machines.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From around 2000, it started receiving attention again as an alternative to heated vending machines.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From around 2000, it started receiving attention again as an alternative to heated vending machines.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="113">
<j>普通の缶飲料より割高な点がデメリット。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A disadvantage of this is comparatively more expensive than the conventional-type canned beverages.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A disadvantage, it was comparatively more expensive than the conventional-type canned beverages.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A disadvantage, it was comparatively more expensive than the conventional-type canned beverages.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>自動販売機</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Vending machines</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Vending machines</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Vending machines</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="114">
<j>缶コーヒーの需要を飛躍的に伸ばした要因に冷温可能な自動販売機の普及がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Factors for the rapidly-increased demand of canned coffee include the spread of vending machines which can perform both heating and cooling.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Factors for the rapidly-increased demand of canned coffee include the spread of vending machines which can perform both heating and cooling.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Factors for the rapidly-increased demand of canned coffee include the spread of vending machines which can perform both heating and cooling.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="115">
<j>ホットorコールド自販機</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hot or cold vending machines</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hot or cold vending machines</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hot or cold vending machines</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="116">
<j>加温と冷蔵の選択ができる自販機。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a type of vending machines on which one can choose hot or cold drink.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is a type of vending machine from which one can choose hot or cold drinks.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is a type of vending machine from which one can choose hot or cold drinks.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="117">
<j>1972年にサンデンによって開発され、ポッカが初めて導入した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was developed by Sanden in 1972 and first introduced by Pokka.</e>
<cmt>「サンデン」＝「Sanden」は、下記サイトから引用しました。http://www.sanden.co.jp/index.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was developed by Sanden in 1972 and first introduced by Pokka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was developed by Sanden in 1972 and first introduced by Pokka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="118">
<j>ホット&amp;コールド自販機</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hot and cold vending machines</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hot and cold vending machines</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hot and cold vending machines</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="119">
<j>一台で加温と冷蔵の両方を同時に販売できる自販機で、1976年に三洋電機によって開発された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a type of vending machines which can dispense both hot and cold drinks simultaneously by a machine, which was developed by SANYO Electric in 1976.</e>
<cmt>「三洋電機」＝「SANYO Electric」は、下記サイトから引用しました。http://sanyo.com/corporate/profile/outline.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is a type of vending machine that can dispense both hot and cold drinks simultaneously by a machine, developed by SANYO Electric in 1976.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is a type of vending machine that can dispense both hot and cold drinks simultaneously by a machine, developed by SANYO Electric in 1976.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="120">
<j>IH自販機</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">IH vending machines</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">IH vending machines</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">IH vending machines</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="121">
<j>電磁誘導電磁誘導加熱装置（Induction Heating）が搭載されている自販機。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a type of vending machines which is equipped with Induction Heating.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is a type of vending machine equipped with Induction Heating.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is a type of vending machine equipped with Induction Heating.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="122">
<j>待機時は常温（あるいは低温）で缶飲料を保管し、販売時のみ選択商品を急速加熱して提供する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They store canned beverages at normal room temperature (or lower temperature) on standby and rapidly heat up a selected drink at the time of dispensing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They store canned beverages at normal room temperature (or lower temperature) on standby and rapidly heat up a selected drink druing the process of dispensing.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They store canned beverages at normal room temperature (or lower temperature) on standby and rapidly heat up a selected drink during the process of dispensing.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="123">
<j>250ml缶なら1分未満で約140度まで加熱可能。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is possible to heat up to 140 degrees or so within less than one minute in the case of a 250ml can.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is possible to raise the heat up to 140 degrees or so in less than one minute in the case of a 250ml can.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is possible to raise the heat up to 140 degrees or so in less than one minute in the case of a 250 ml can.</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="124">
<j>この機能により温度維持に消費されていた電力を削減、製品の劣化スピードが抑制され補充管理にかかる負荷も軽減した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This function made it possible to reduce electric power which had been consumed to maintain the temperature and to control deteriorating speed of products which lightened the burden of reloading management.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This function made it possible to reduce electric power consumed to maintain the temperature and to control the deteriorating speed of products which lightened the burden of reloading management.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This function made it possible to reduce electric power consumed to maintain the temperature and to control the deteriorating speed of products which lightened the burden of reloading management.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="125">
<j>このように、従来のホット自販機の問題点を大幅に解消している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As above, this type has considerably cleared up problems of conventional heating vending machines.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As above, this type has considerably cleared up the problem of conventional type heating vending machines.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As above, this type has considerably cleared up the problem of conventional type heating vending machines.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="126">
<j>日本国内では1993年に富士電機ホールディングスが開発し、ダイドーが導入した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan, it was developed by Fuji Electric Holdings Co., Ltd in 1993 and introduced by Dydo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan, it was developed by Fuji Electric Holdings Co., Ltd in 1993 and introduced by Dydo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan, it was developed by Fuji Electric Holdings Co., Ltd in 1993 and introduced by Dydo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="127">
<j>米国のスターバックス社が導入した自販機はこの機構を取り入れているとみられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The particular type of vending machine which Starbucks Corporation in U.S. introduced is understood to be the one which adopts this system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The particular type of vending machine which Starbucks Corporation in U.S. introduced is understood to be one adopting this system.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The particular type of vending machine which Starbucks Corporation in U.S. introduced is understood to be one adopting this system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>日本における概略</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Outline of situations in Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Outline of the situation in Japan</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Outline of the situation in Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="128">
<j>1975年頃から「白ベンダー業者（ノーブランド自販機の訪問販売業者）」が台頭する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From around 1975, off-brand distributors of vending machine (door-to-door peddlers) started appearing on the scene.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From around 1975, off-brand distributors of vending machines (door-to-door peddlers) started appearing on the scene.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From around 1975, off-brand distributors of vending machines (door-to-door peddlers) started appearing on the scene.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="129">
<j>いわゆる自販機ビジネスの先がけとなった商売で、斬新な商法と販売力で設置台数を拡大させていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were the pioneers of the so-called Vending machine business and kept expanding the number of the machine installed by their innovative business practice and selling power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were the pioneers of the so-called Vending machine business and kept expanding the number machines installed by their innovative business practice and selling power.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were the pioneers of the so-called Vending machine business and kept expanding the number of machines installed by their innovative business practice and selling power.</e>
<cmt>of補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="130">
<j>70年代末には全国に700社以上もの業者が存在していたといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that there were no less than 100 dealers across the nation at the end of the 1970s.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that there were no less than 100 dealers across the nation at the end of the 1970s.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that there were no less than 700 dealers across the nation at the end of the 1970s.</e>
<cmt>数字修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="131">
<j>ホット&amp;コールド自販機の誕生と重なるこの時期は業者間の競争も激化した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this period which coincided with the time when hot and cold vending machines were invented, competition among dealers was intensifying.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During this period, that coincided with the time when hot and cold vending machines were invented, competition among dealers was intensifying.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During this period, that coincided with the time when hot and cold vending machines were invented, competition among dealers was intensifying.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="132">
<j>その将来性が見込まれて製造メーカーには注文が殺到。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Vending-machine manufacturers were flooded with orders, as the machines were regarded promising.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Vending-machine manufacturers were flooded with orders, as the machines were regarded promising.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Vending-machine manufacturers were flooded with orders, as the machines were regarded promising.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="133">
<j>奇抜なデザインや購買意欲を刺激する付加要素を備えた自販機が多く登場し缶コーヒーの売り上げに拍車をかける一因となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Vending machines with wild design or with factors stirring up customer interests appeared in large numbers, which contributed to the accelerated sales of canned coffee.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Vending machines with wild design or with factors stirring up customer interests appeared in large numbers, contributing to accelerated sales of canned coffee.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Vending machines with wild design or with factors stirring up customer interests appeared in large numbers, contributing to accelerated sales of canned coffee.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="134">
<j>のちにこの自販機ビジネスは飲料メーカーからも注目を浴びて提携が組まれるようになり、商標入りの自販機が取扱いの主流になってゆく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, the vending-machine business attracted the attention of beverage makers, some of which started establishing business alliance with the former, and vending machines labeled with trade marks of beverage makers became the main current of the vending machine business.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, the vending-machine business attracted the attention of beverage makers, some that started establishing business alliance with the former, and vending machines labeled with trade marks of beverage makers became the main current of the vending machine business.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, the vending-machine business attracted the attention of beverage makers, some that started establishing business alliance with the former, and vending machines labeled with trade marks of beverage makers became the main current of the vending machine business.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>世界における普及状況</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Penetration in the world</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Penetration throughout the world</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Penetration throughout the world</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="135">
<j>日本のように屋外に大量の自動販売機が設置されている国は他に類をみない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is no country in which many of vending machines are installed outdoors like in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is no country with as many of vending machines installed outdoors like in Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is no country with as many of vending machines installed outdoors like in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="136">
<j>欧米においては1960年代以降、清涼飲料の容器が瓶や缶へと移り変わっていったが、コーヒーの販売機だけはカップ式が依然主流のままであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Western countries, containers for soft drinks were changing to bottles and cans after the 1960s, but the cup-dispensing method remained as mainstream only in the case of vending machines.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Western countries, containers for soft drinks were changing to bottles and cans after the 1960s, but the cup-dispensing method remained as mainstream only in the case of vending machines.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Western countries, containers for soft drinks were changing to bottles and cans after the 1960s, but the cup-dispensing method remained as mainstream only in the case of vending machines.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="137">
<j>日本の缶コーヒー市場における成功に倣いホット自販機を取り入れる試みが過去に行われたが、市場の関心は薄かったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In view of a success in the canned coffee market in Japan, introduction of heating vending machines was attempted in the past, but there was low level of interest in the market.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In view of the success in the canned coffee market in Japan, introduction of heating vending machines was attempted in the past, but there was a low level of interest in the market.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In view of the success in the canned coffee market in Japan, introduction of heating vending machines was attempted in the past, but there was a low level of interest in the market.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>缶コーヒーの成分</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ingredients of canned coffee</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ingredients of canned coffee</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ingredients of canned coffee</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="138">
<j>低酸性飲料であるコーヒー飲料は細菌汚染による変質リスクが炭酸飲料と比べて高い（ブラックコーヒーは除く）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Coffee beverages, a type of subacid drinks involve higher risk of spoilage due to bacterial pollution as compared with carbonated drinks (except black coffee).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Coffee beverages, a type of sub-acid drink involving a higher risk of spoilage due to bacterial pollution as compared with carbonated drinks (except for black coffee).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Coffee beverages, a type of sub-acid drink involving a higher risk of spoilage due to bacterial pollution as compared with carbonated drinks (except for black coffee).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="139">
<j>乳成分を含んでいることや加温販売されることも細菌の育成条件に適っているため、添加される成分は保存性に重きがおかれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Importance is attached to storage stability of ingredients to be added due to the fact that milk constituent and hot dispensing create propagating conditions for bacteria.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Importance is attached to storage stability of ingredients added due to the fact that milk constituent and hot dispensing create propagating conditions for bacteria.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Importance is attached to storage stability of ingredients added due to the fact that milk constituent and hot dispensing create propagating conditions for bacteria.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="140">
<j>水</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Water</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Water</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Water</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="141">
<j>水はコーヒーの抽出に必要な成分。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Water is necessary to extract coffee.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Water is necessary to extract coffee.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Water is necessary to extract coffee.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="142">
<j>硬度 (水)は高いほど苦みやロースト感に作用し、低いほど酸味やマイルド感に作用する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The higher water hardness is, the more it affects bitterness and sense of roasting, and the lower water hardness is, the more it affects acid taste and sense of mildness.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The higher the water hardness is, the more it affects bitterness and the sense of roasting, and the lower the water hardness is, the more it affects the acid taste and sense of mildness.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The higher the water hardness is, the more it affects bitterness and the sense of roasting, and the lower the water hardness is, the more it affects the acid taste and sense of mildness.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="143">
<j>ただしカルシウムやマグネシウムの含有量が高すぎると乳成分が不安定になるため硬度150ppm未満が望ましいとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, if it contains an excessively high amount of calcium and magnesium, milk constituent becomes unstable, and so hardness of less than 150ppm is considered to be desirable.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, if it contains an excessively high amount of calcium and magnesium, milk constituents become unstable, and so hardness of less than 150ppm is considered to be desirable.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, if it contains an excessively high amount of calcium and magnesium, milk constituents become unstable, and so hardness of less than 150 ppm is considered to be desirable.</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="144">
<j>また、塩類を多く含む水はコーヒーの香味を阻害し乳成分の熱安定性にも悪影響を及ぼすという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, it is said that water containing high level of salts may interfere with flavor of coffee and also adversely affect the thermal stability of milk constituent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, it is said that water containing a high level of salts may interfere with coffee flavor and also adversely affect thermal stability of milk constituents.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, it is said that water containing a high level of salts may interfere with coffee flavor and also adversely affect thermal stability of milk constituents.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>コーヒー</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Coffee</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Coffee</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Coffee</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="145">
<j>コーヒーは缶コーヒーの主となる成分。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Coffee is the main ingredient of canned coffee.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Coffee is the main ingredient of canned coffee.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Coffee is the main ingredient of canned coffee.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="146">
<j>ミルクコーヒーが全盛だった時代はミルクにコーヒーの風味が打ち消されないよう、安価でえぐ味の強い『コーヒーノキロブスタ種』を強焙煎することで苦みと焙煎臭を生かしていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While white coffee was at its height, less-expensive and strongly-harsh &apos;Coffee tree Robsta&apos; heavily roasted was used to bring out the bitterness and roasting aroma which prevent milk from removing the flavor of coffee.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While white coffee was at its height, less-expensive, and strongly-harsh &apos;Coffee tree Robsta&apos; heavily roasted was used to bring out the bitterness and roasting aroma which prevents milk from removing the flavor of coffee.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While white coffee was at its height, less-expensive, and strongly-harsh &apos;Coffee tree Robsta&apos; heavily roasted was used to bring out the bitterness and roasting aroma which prevents milk from removing the flavor of coffee.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="147">
<j>しかし本格志向へと流行が移り、乳成分の比率が抑えられてからは上品な芳香を持つ『コーヒーノキアラビカ種』をメインにした缶コーヒーが多数となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, after the trend changed to authenticity-oriented coffee and the ratio of milk constituent came to be kept lower, canned coffee mainly using elegantly-aromatic &apos;Coffee tree Arabica&apos; became quite large in number.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, after the trend changed to authenticity-oriented coffee and the ratio of milk constituents were kept lower, canned coffee mainly using elegant aromatic &apos;Coffee tree Arabica&apos; became quite large in number.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, after the trend changed to authenticity-oriented coffee and the ratio of milk constituents were kept lower, canned coffee mainly using elegant aromatic &apos;Coffee tree Arabica&apos; became quite large in number.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="148">
<j>コーヒー液は主にドリップ式によって抽出される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Coffee liquid is extracted mainly by the drip method.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Coffee liquid is extracted mainly by the drip method.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Coffee liquid is extracted mainly by the drip method.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="149">
<j>インスタントコーヒーや濃縮抽出液（コーヒーエキス）が使用される場合もあるが主流ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Instant coffee or concentrated coffee extract is sometimes used but not the mainstream.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Instant coffee or concentrated coffee extract is sometimes used, but is not mainstream.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Instant coffee or concentrated coffee extract is sometimes used, but is not mainstream.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="150">
<j>抽出後のコーヒー液は酸度が上昇（水素イオン指数5.0〜5.5付近）する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The acidity of coffee liquid increases after extraction (around 5.0 to 5.5 in the hydrogen-ion exponent).</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The acidity of coffee in liquid form increases after extraction (around 5.0 to 5.5 in hydrogen-ion exponents).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The acidity of coffee in liquid form increases after extraction (around 5.0 to 5.5 in hydrogen-ion exponents).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="151">
<j>乳成分がクロロゲン酸などの有機酸群と反応するとタンパク質が不安定になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Milk constituent reacts with group of organic acids including chlorogenic acid to make protein unstable.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Milk constituents react with a group of organic acids including chlorogenic acid to make protein unstable.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Milk constituents react with a group of organic acids including chlorogenic acid to make protein unstable.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="152">
<j>そのため、凝集・沈殿の可能性が生じてしまうため、重曹などで中性寄り（pH6.0〜6.5付近）に調整が施される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, aggregation and precipitation would possibly occur, and so pH is adjusted as close to neutral value by adding sodium bicarbonate and so on.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, aggregation and precipitation may possibly occur so, pH is adjusted as close to neutral value by adding sodium bicarbonate.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, aggregation and precipitation may possibly occur so, pH is adjusted as close to neutral value (around pH 6.0 - pH 6.5) by adding sodium bicarbonate.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="153">
<j>経時による風味劣化の抑制には『ビタミンC』などの酸化防止剤が添加される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Antioxidants such as &quot;Vitamin C&quot; are added to control flavor deterioration by the lapse of time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Antioxidants such as &quot;Vitamin C&quot; are added to control flavor deterioration over the lapse of time.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Antioxidants such as &quot;Vitamin C&quot; are added to control flavor deterioration over the lapse of time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>乳成分</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Milk constituent</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Milk constituent</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Milk constituent</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="154">
<j>乳成分は缶コーヒーをマイルドな口あたりにするが、その比率が高まるほど「コーヒーらしさ」から離れる傾向がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While milk constituent makes the taste of canned coffee mild, the higher its ratio is, the more the flavor tends to get away from &apos;something coffee-like.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While milk constituent makes the taste of canned coffee mild, the higher its ratio, the more the flavor tends to differ from &apos;something coffee-like.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While milk constituent makes the taste of canned coffee mild, the higher its ratio, the more the flavor tends to differ from &apos;something coffee-like.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="155">
<j>缶コーヒーに使用される乳成分は牛乳のほか粉乳、煉乳などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Milk constituent to be used for canned coffee includes not only cow&apos;s milk but powdered milk, evaporated milk and so on.</e>
<cmt>http://www.japaneselawtranslation.go.jpでは、「牛乳」＝　　「cow&apos;s milk」、「粉乳」＝　　「milk powder」、「煉乳」＝　　「condensed milk」となっております。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Milk constituents used for canned coffee includes not only fresh cow&apos;s milk, but powdered milk, evaporated milk, and so on.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Milk constituents used for canned coffee includes not only fresh cow&apos;s milk, but powdered milk, evaporated milk, and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="156">
<j>その扱いは乳及び乳製品の成分規格等に関する省令に基づき厳しい管理がなされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Milk constituent is strictly controlled according to &quot;Ordinance regarding standard of element, etc. of milk and dairy products.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Milk constituents are strictly controlled according to the &quot;Ordinance regarding standard of element, etc. of milk and dairy products.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Milk constituents are strictly controlled according to the &quot;Ordinance regarding standard of element, etc. of milk and dairy products.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="157">
<j>『牛乳』は供給元から低温輸送されたのち貯蔵されるが、変質しやすいため保管に細心の注意が必要とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While &quot;Cow&apos;s milk&quot; is stored after refrigerated transport from a producer, it is necessary to take particular care to control storage due to its being quickly changeable in quality.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While &quot;Cow&apos;s milk&quot; is stored after refrigerated transport from a producer, it is necessary to take particular care to control storage due to its being quickly changeable in quality.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While &quot;Cow&apos;s milk&quot; is stored after refrigerated transport from a producer, it is necessary to take particular care to control storage due to its being quickly changeable in quality.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="158">
<j>牛乳や生クリームの配合率を上げると風味は向上するが脂肪分の分離を招く危険性がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although higher combination ratio of cow&apos;s milk or fresh cream makes the flavor improved, there is the risk of causing fat separation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although a higher combination ratio of cow&apos;s milk or fresh cream improves the flavor, there is the risk of causing fat separation.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although a higher combination ratio of cow&apos;s milk or fresh cream improves the flavor, there is the risk of causing fat separation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="159">
<j>『粉乳』は保存性に優れるため輸送や保管が容易だが、ミルク本来の風味とはギャップを生じる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although &quot;powdered milk&quot; is easily transported and stored due to its high storage stability, it is away from essential flavor of milk.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although &quot;powdered milk&quot; is easily transported and stored due to its high storage stability, it is unlike the essential flavor of milk.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although &quot;powdered milk&quot; is easily transported and stored due to its high storage stability, it is unlike the essential flavor of milk.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="160">
<j>『煉乳』は調達コストの安さと濃厚な味わいで初期の缶コーヒーに多用されていたが、本格志向へと流行が移った90年代以降は主流から外れている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Evaporated milk&quot; had been frequently used for early canned coffee due to its low procurement cost and rich flavor, but after the 1990s during which the trend changed to authenticity-oriented coffee, was removed from the mainstream.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Evaporated milk&quot; had been frequently used for early canned coffee due to its low procurement cost and rich flavor, but after the 1990s when the trend changed to authentically-oriented coffee, it was removed from the mainstream.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Evaporated milk&quot; had been frequently used for early canned coffee due to its low procurement cost and rich flavor, but after the 1990s when the trend changed to authentically-oriented coffee, it was removed from the mainstream.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="161">
<j>これらの乳成分は加温販売時の熱によって酸化し、経時によって劣化が進めば特有の臭気を発するため『ビタミンE』などの酸化防止剤が添加される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If these milk constituents are oxidized by heat at the time of hot dispensing and become well deteriorated by the lapse of time, they give off an offensive smell, and so antioxidants including &quot;Vitamin E&quot; are added.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If these milk constituents are oxidized by heat at the time of hot dispensing and become well deteriorated over a lapse of time, they give off an offensive smell, and so antioxidants including &quot;Vitamin E&quot; are added.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If these milk constituents are oxidized by heat at the time of hot dispensing and become well deteriorated over a lapse of time, they give off an offensive smell, and so antioxidants including &quot;Vitamin E&quot; are added.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="162">
<j>いずれにせよ加温による風味の寿命は1〜2週間程度（通常の賞味期限は製造日から1年程度）と長くない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At any rate, the flavor remains unchanged under heating about for one to two weeks (Usually, the best before date is about one year after making), which is not long.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At any rate, the flavor remains unchanged when heated within one to two weeks (Usually, the best before the coffee stored for one year after making), which is not long.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At any rate, the flavor remains unchanged when heated within one to two weeks (Usually, the best before the coffee stored for one year after making), which is not long.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="14">
<tit>
<j>甘味料</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sweeteners</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sweeteners</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sweeteners</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="163">
<j>甘味料は缶コーヒーに甘みを与える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sweeteners give sweetness to canned coffee.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sweeteners give sweetness to canned coffee.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sweeteners give sweetness to canned coffee.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="164">
<j>缶コーヒーにおける標準使用量は日本コーヒー飲料協会にて業界標準値を100mlあたり砂糖7.5gと定めており、「糖分○○％カット」などといった表示はこれを基準に行われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The standard amount of usage of sweeteners for canned coffee is 7.5g of sugar per 100ml as the industry&apos;s standard value established by Japan Coffee Beverage Association and labels like &apos;Sugar content reduced by so and so %&apos; is put according to this rule.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The standard amount of usage of sweeteners for canned coffee is 7.5g of sugar per 100ml as the industry&apos;s standard value established by the Japan Coffee Beverage Association and labels like &apos;Sugar content reduced by so and so percentage&apos; is put in accordance with this rule.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The standard amount of usage of sweeteners for canned coffee is 7.5 g of sugar per 100 ml as the industry&apos;s standard value established by the Japan Coffee Beverage Association and labels like &apos;Sugar content reduced by so and so percentage&apos; is put in accordance with this rule.</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="165">
<j>近年では砂糖の使用量は減少傾向にあり、250g缶では現在でも標準使用量に近いものが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In recent years, the amount of usage of sugar has been on a declining trend and many of 250g cans contain close to the standard amount even today.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In recent years, the amount of usage of sugar has been on a declining trend and many 250g cans contain close to the standard amount even today.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In recent years, the amount of usage of sugar has been on a declining trend and many 250 g cans contain close to the standard amount even today.</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="166">
<j>しかし、190g缶では標準が100mlあたり6g台、「低糖・甘さ控えめ」は4g台、「微糖」は2g前後が一般的な使用量の水準となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in the case of 190g cans, the general criteria are standard one contains the 6g range, &apos;Low-sugar/moderated-sugar&apos; the 4g range and &apos;Trace-sugar&apos; 2g or so.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in the case of 190g cans, the general criteria are that standard cans contains the 6g range, &apos;Low-sugar/moderated-sugar&apos; the 4g range and &apos;Trace-sugar&apos; 2g or so.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in the case of 190 g cans, the general criteria are that standard cans contains the 6 g range, &apos;Low-sugar/moderated-sugar&apos; the 4 g range and &apos;Trace-sugar&apos; 2 g or so.</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="167">
<j>これら微糖・低糖タイプの缶コーヒーは砂糖単独では甘味や成分の安定性が不足するため人工甘味料と併用されることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the case of these trace-sugar/low-sugar type canned coffee, artificial sweeteners are many times used in combination with sugar because its sweetness and constituent may lack in stability when used alone.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the case of these trace-sugar/low-sugar type canned coffee, artificial sweeteners are used many times in combination with sugar because its sweetness and constituents may lack stability when used alone.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the case of these trace-sugar/low-sugar type canned coffee, artificial sweeteners are used many times in combination with sugar because its sweetness and constituents may lack stability when used alone.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="168">
<j>「味が薄い」と感じるユーザーも存在するため、微糖ニーズの高まりに合わせて様々な改良が行われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As there are some consumers who feel &apos;short on the taste,&apos; various efforts for improvement have been made to respond to increased trace-sugar needs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As there are some consumers who feel a &apos;lack of taste,&apos; various efforts for improvement have been made to respond to increased trace-sugar needs.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As there are some consumers who feel a &apos;lack of taste,&apos; various efforts for improvement have been made to respond to increased trace-sugar needs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="169">
<j>『砂糖』は最もナチュラルな甘味だが、原料の段階で耐熱性細菌の汚染源となる可能性がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While sugar has the most natural sweetness, it may possibly become a contaminant source of thermotolerant bacterium at the unprocessed stage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While sugar has the most natural sweetness, it may possibly become a contaminant source of thermotolerant bacterium during the unprocessed stage.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While sugar has the most natural sweetness, it may possibly become a contaminant source of thermotolerant bacterium during the unprocessed stage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="170">
<j>健康面においてはカロリーの心配や、う蝕（虫歯）・血糖値上昇の原因要素になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the health aspect, causes of concern include high calorie, dental caries (cavity) and high blood sugar level.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the health aspect, causes of concern include high calorie, dental caries (cavities) and high blood sugar levels.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the health aspect, causes of concern include high calorie, dental caries (cavities) and high blood sugar levels.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="171">
<j>使用される糖種はテンサイが多く、上白糖は輸送上の問題から使用されることは殆どない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While the type of sugar which is mainly used is sugar beet, superfine sugar is hardly used due to its transportation problems.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While the type of sugar mainly used is from the sugar beet, superfine sugar is hardly used due to its problems of transport.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While the type of sugar mainly used is from the sugar beet, superfine sugar is hardly used due to its problems of transport.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="172">
<j>炭酸飲料などによく使用される『異性化糖』はアミノ酸に反応しやすく、加熱時に独特の臭味を発生させる（ストレッカー分解）可能性がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Isomerized sugar&quot; which is frequently used for carbonated drinks and so on easily reacts with amino acid and it may possibly generate a typical unpleasant smell when heated (Strecker degradation).</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Isomerized sugar&quot; frequently used for carbonated drinks and so on easily reacts with amino acid and may possibly generate a typical unpleasant smell when heated (Strecker degradation).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Isomerized sugar&quot; frequently used for carbonated drinks and so on easily reacts with amino acid and may possibly generate a typical unpleasant smell when heated (Strecker degradation).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="173">
<j>そのため、使用されてもその成分比率は低い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, even if it is used, its component ratio is low.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, even if it is used, its component ratio is low.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, even if it is used, its component ratio is low.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="174">
<j>また、温度によって甘味の変化が激しい点も缶コーヒーと相性が悪い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, it severely changes its sweetness according to temperature, which is incompatible with canned coffee.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, sweetness severely changes according to temperature, which is incompatible with canned coffee.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, sweetness severely changes according to temperature, which is incompatible with canned coffee.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="175">
<j>主に微糖コーヒーの甘みを補うために使用されている『アセスルファムカリウム』や『スクラロース』のような人工甘味料は酵素や微生物に対しても非常に強く、成分の安定性も高い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Artificial sweeteners like &quot;acesulfame-K&quot; and &quot;sucralose&quot; mainly used to add sweetness for trace-sugar coffee are considerably resistant to enzymes and microorganisms and highly stable in their constituent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Artificial sweeteners like &quot;acesulfame-K&quot; and &quot;sucralose&quot; mainly be used to add sweetness because trace-sugar coffee is considerably resistant to enzymes and microorganisms and are highly stable in their constituents.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Artificial sweeteners like &quot;acesulfame-K&quot; and &quot;sucralose&quot; mainly be used to add sweetness because trace-sugar coffee is considerably resistant to enzymes and microorganisms and are highly stable in their constituents.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="176">
<j>ノンカロリーという点も時流に適しており、近年ではブラックとは異なり甘みのある「無糖コーヒー」という新たなジャンルの開拓にも寄与している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Their calorie-free characteristic is something trendy and, in recent years, contribute to development of a new category named &apos;Sugar-free coffee&apos; with sweetness different from black coffee.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The calorie-free characteristics are trendy and, in recent years, there was contribution to the development of a new category &apos;Sugar-free coffee&apos; with sweetness different from black coffee.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The calorie-free characteristics are trendy and, in recent years, there was contribution to the development of a new category &apos;Sugar-free coffee&apos; with sweetness different from black coffee.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="177">
<j>また、他の甘味料と併用すれば少量でも甘味が増す特性があるので、結果的に総量を減らすことができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, as it has the property of increasing sweetness if it is used even small amount together with other sweeteners, the total amount of sweeteners can consequently be reduced.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, as it has the property of increasing sweetness if it is used in even small amounts together with other sweeteners, the total amount of sweeteners can consequently be reduced.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, as it has the property of increasing sweetness if it is used in even small amounts together with other sweeteners, the total amount of sweeteners can consequently be reduced.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="178">
<j>一方で味わいに対しては好みが別れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, there is a difference between the kind of tastes people like.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, there are differences between the kinds of flavors people like.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, there are differences between the kinds of flavors people like.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="179">
<j>特に缶コーヒーのような雰囲気が重視される商品の場合、ケミカルな印象がマイナスイメージにもなりえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">More especially, in the case of such a product for which the atmosphere is valued as canned coffee, chemical-like impression may become a negative image.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">More especially, in products where the atmosphere is valued as canned coffee, a chemical-like impression may give a negative impression.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">More especially, in products where the atmosphere is valued as canned coffee, a chemical-like impression may give a negative impression.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="15">
<tit>
<j>香料</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Flavoring agents</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Flavoring agents</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Flavoring agents</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="180">
<j>香料は缶コーヒーの性格を決定する大きな要素となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Flavoring agents are considered to be an important factor determining the nature of canned coffee.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Flavoring agents are considered to be an important factor determining the nature of canned coffee.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Flavoring agents are considered to be an important factor determining the nature of canned coffee.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="181">
<j>コーヒーの香り自体が熱に対して非常に弱く揮発しやすい（特に焙煎感の消失が著しい）デリケートなものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The flavor of coffee is delicate in that it is considerably vulnerable to heat and volatile (more especially, heavy elimination of roasting-flavor).</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The flavor of coffee is delicate in that it is considerably vulnerable to heat and is volatile (especially, the heavy elimination of roasting-flavor).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The flavor of coffee is delicate in that it is considerably vulnerable to heat and is volatile (especially, the heavy elimination of roasting-flavor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="182">
<j>そのため、製造時の熱処理が多い缶コーヒーにおいては、香料による補完の必要性が生じる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, it becomes necessary to supplement the lost flavor by flavoring agents in the case of canned coffee which passes through several heat-treatment processes.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, it becomes necessary to supplement the lost flavor by flavoring agents in the case of canned coffee which passes through several heat-treatment processes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, it becomes necessary to supplement the lost flavor by flavoring agents in the case of canned coffee which passes through several heat-treatment processes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="183">
<j>そのためコーヒー液そのものの香りというよりは「挽きたての豆の香りが充満した部屋」のようなイメージで調合されることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In many cases, coffee liquid is prepared under the image of a &apos;room which is filled with flavor of freshly-roasted beans&apos; rather than flavor of coffee liquid itself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In many cases, coffee is prepared under the image of a &apos;room filled with the aroma of freshly-roasted beans&apos; rather than flavor of coffee drink itself.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In many cases, coffee is prepared under the image of a &apos;room filled with the aroma of freshly-roasted beans&apos; rather than flavor of coffee drink itself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="184">
<j>通常、焙煎豆から水や溶剤あるいは超臨界抽出装置を用いて抽出したエキスやエッセンスなどがベースとして精製され、必要に応じ合成香料と調合して使用される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Usually, a refined product as a base from the extract, essence and so on which are extracted from roasted beans by water, solvents or supercritical extraction equipment, is mixed with an amount of synthetic flavoring agents as required.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Usually, a refined product as a base from the extract, essence extracted from roasted beans with water, solvents or supercritical extraction equipment, is mixed with an amount of synthetic flavoring agents as required.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Usually, a refined product as a base from the extract, essence extracted from roasted beans with water, solvents or supercritical extraction equipment, is mixed with an amount of synthetic flavoring agents as required.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="185">
<j>また、高温殺菌の際に生じるレトルト臭をカバーする目的で添加されたり、乳成分のミルク感を向上させるため補助的にミルクフレーバーが使用される場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Flavoring agents are sometimes added to cover retort odor generated in the high-temperature pasteurization and milk-flavor agents is supplementarily used to improve milk-taste of milk constituent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Flavoring agents are sometimes added to cover retort odor generated during high-temperature pasteurization and milk-flavor agents are supplementarily used to improve the taste of the milk constituents.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Flavoring agents are sometimes added to cover retort odor generated during high-temperature pasteurization and milk-flavor agents are supplementally used to improve the taste of the milk constituents.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="16">
<tit>
<j>乳化剤</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emulsifiers</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emulsifiers</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emulsifiers</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="186">
<j>乳化剤は乳成分とコーヒー液の分離を妨ぐ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emulsifiers prevent separation between milk constituent and coffee liquid.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emulsifiers prevent separation between milk constituent and coffee liquid.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emulsifiers prevent separation between milk constituent and coffee liquid.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="187">
<j>初期の缶コーヒーは乳成分が分離することがよくあった（缶の内部に付着するため「リング」と呼ばれた）ため、よく振ってから飲用しなければならなかったが、乳化剤の発達により振る必要はほぼ無くなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As milk constituent used to be frequently separated in the case of earlier canned coffee (It was called &apos;Ring&apos; due to the constituent being attached to the interior wall of cans), cans had to be shaked before drinking, which became almost unnecessary due to development of emulsifiers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As milk constituent is used to be frequently separated in the case of earlier canned coffee (called &apos;Ring&apos; due to the constituent being attached to the interior wall of cans), cans had to be shaked before drinking, which became almost unnecessary due to the development of emulsifiers.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As milk constituent is used to be frequently separated in the case of earlier canned coffee (called &apos;Ring&apos; due to the constituent being attached to the interior wall of cans), cans had to be shaked before drinking, which became almost unnecessary due to the development of emulsifiers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="188">
<j>また、自販機による加温販売に伴い、耐熱性細菌(クロストリジウム属)による酸敗事故が発生するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rancidity accident caused by thermotolerant bacterium (genus Clostridium) came to occur following the introduction of hot dispensing by vending machines.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Accidental rancidity caused by thermotolerant bacterium (genus Clostridium) occurred following the introduction of hot dispensing by vending machines.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Accidental rancidity caused by thermotolerant bacterium (genus Clostridium) occurred following the introduction of hot dispensing by vending machines.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="189">
<j>しかし、加熱殺菌による殺滅は実質不可能なため『エマルション（成分表記上は乳化剤）』の添加による抑制がとられるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as it is substantially impossible to sterilize by heat, control came to be kept by adding &quot;Emulsion (Emulsifier on label).&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as it is substantially impossible to sterilize by heat, control was maintained by adding &quot;Emulsion (Emulsifier on label).&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as it is substantially impossible to sterilize by heat, control was maintained by adding &quot;Emulsion (Emulsifier on label).&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="17">
<tit>
<j>日本の主なメーカーと主要銘柄</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Major manufacturers in Japan and major brands</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Major manufacturers in Japan and major brands</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Major manufacturers in Japan and major brands</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="190">
<j>缶コーヒー市場占有率における首位銘柄は「ジョージア」となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Georgia&apos; is understood to be the top brand in market share of canned coffee.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Georgia&apos; is understood to be the top brand in market share of canned coffee.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Georgia&apos; is understood to be the top brand in market share of canned coffee.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="18">
<tit>
<j>日本の主なパッカー</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Major packers in Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Major producers in Japan</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Major producers in Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="191">
<j>パッカーとは受託充填工場のことをいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A packer means a contracted packing plant.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A producer means a contracted canning plant.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A producer means a contracted canning plant.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="192">
<j>缶コーヒーを含めた清涼飲料水の製造はメーカーの自社工場によるものと、パッカーにOEMされるものとに分かれており、その生産比率はほぼ半分にまで達している（2008年）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Manufacture of soft drinks including canned coffee is divided into two categories, one by manufacturers&apos; captive plants and the other by contracted OEM packers, and the production came to be almost in equal proportions (2008).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Manufacture of soft drinks including canned coffee is divided into two categories, one by manufacturers&apos; captive plants and the other by contracted OEM producer, and production came to be almost in equal proportions (2008).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Manufacture of soft drinks including canned coffee is divided into two categories, one by manufacturers&apos; captive plants and the other by contracted OEM producer, and production came to be almost in equal proportions (2008).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="193">
<j>原則としてメジャーブランドやプライベートブランドの製品製造に携わったパッカーの社名が表に出る事は殆ど無いが、一部のパッカーは自社ブランド製品なども展開させている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While company names of packers which manufacture the products of major brands and private brands hardly appear on the labels in principle, some packers develop their own brand products and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While company names of producers that manufacture major and private brands hardly appear on the labels in principle, some producers develop their own brand name products.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While company names of producers that manufacture major and private brands hardly appear on the labels in principle, some producers develop their own brand name products.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="194">
<j>これらパッカーは飲料生産に必要不可欠な存在であるとともに、缶コーヒーが急成長した歴史とも深く関係している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These packers are not only indispensable presence for beverage production but closely related to the history of rapid growth of canned coffee.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These producers are not only an indispensable presence for beverage production, but are closely related to the history of the rapid growth of canned coffee.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These producers are not only an indispensable presence for beverage production, but are closely related to the history of the rapid growth of canned coffee.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="19">
<tit>
<j>缶コーヒーのユーザー層</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">User category of canned coffee</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">User category of canned coffee</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">User category of canned coffee</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="20">
<tit>
<j>1980年代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The 1980s</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The 1980s</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The 1980s</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="195">
<j>クラシエホールディングスが1980年に行なった調査では、男性は20代〜30代、女性は20代前半の飲用率が高い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A survey conducted by Kracie Holdings, Ltd. In 1980 showed that men from their twenties to their thirties and women in their early twenties were high in drinking rate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A survey conducted by Kracie Holdings, Ltd. In 1980 showed that men from twenty to thirty and women in their early twenties had a high drinking rate.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A survey conducted by Kracie Holdings, Ltd. in 1980 showed that men from twenty to thirty and women in their early twenties had a high drinking rate.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="196">
<j>本数は月間1〜2本程度が最も多く、20代の中には月に6本以上を飲用するヘビーユーザーも若干数存在した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">People who drank one or two cans a month were largest in number and some heavy users in their twenties drank six or more cans a month.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">People who drank one or two cans a month were largest in number and some heavy users in their twenties drank six or more cans a month.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">People who drank one or two cans a month were largest in number and some heavy users in their twenties drank six or more cans a month.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="197">
<j>また、嗜好調査では10代から最も高い支持を得ていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, a preference survey showed the highest support was given by teenagers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, a preference survey showed the highest support was given by teenagers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, a preference survey showed the highest support was given by teenagers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="198">
<j>このように若者主体型の商品であったことから、中高年への需要喚起が今後の検討課題とされていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As above, canned coffee was preferred mainly by young people and so stimulating demand by middle-aged and elderly persons was considered to be an issue for the future.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As above, canned coffee was shown to be preferred mainly by young people and so stimulating demand by middle-aged and elderly persons was considered to be an issue for the future.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As above, canned coffee was shown to be preferred mainly by young people and so stimulating demand by middle-aged and elderly persons was considered to be an issue for the future.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="21">
<tit>
<j>1990年代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The 1990s</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The 1990s</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The 1990s</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="199">
<j>1992年、サントリーは新ブランド『BOSSコーヒー』の開発にあたって徹底的な消費者調査を行う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1992, Suntory conducted a full-scale consumer survey before their development of a new brand &quot;BOSS coffee.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1992, Suntory conducted a full-scale consumer survey before their development of a new brand &quot;BOSS coffee.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1992, Suntory conducted a full-scale consumer survey before their development of a new brand &quot;BOSS coffee.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="200">
<j>その結果、購入者の80%は男性で、中でも1日に1本以上飲用するヘビーユーザーが全消費の6割を占めていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The survey showed that male persons accounted for 80% of users and, among them, consumption by heavy users who drank one or more cans a day accounted for 60% of the total consumption.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The survey showed that male persons accounted for eighty percent of consummers and, among them, consumption by heavy drinkers who drank one or more cans a day accounted for sixty percent of the total consumption.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The survey showed that male persons accounted for eighty percent of consumers and, among them, consumption by heavy drinkers who drank one or more cans a day accounted for sixty percent of the total consumption.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="201">
<j>このことから缶コーヒーの販売にはヘビーユーザーの獲得が不可欠であることがわかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It became clear from the above that acquiring heavy users was essential for sales of canned coffee.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It became clear from the above that acquiring heavy drinkers was essential for the sales of canned coffee.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It became clear from the above that acquiring heavy drinkers was essential for the sales of canned coffee.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="202">
<j>ヘビーユーザー像</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Heavy-user image</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Heavy-user image</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Heavy-user image</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="203">
<j>25〜35歳前後で身体を動かすような職業</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are about 25 to 35 years old engaging in physical- labor occupations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are about twenty-five to thirty-five years old engaged in physical- labor occupations.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are about twenty-five to thirty-five years old engaged in physical-labor occupations.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="204">
<j>基本的に仕事熱心で割と規則正しい生活</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are basically work-minded and lead comparatively well-regulated lives.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are basically work-minded and lead comparatively well-regulated lives.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are basically work-minded and lead comparatively well-regulated lives.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="205">
<j>テレビをよく見る</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are frequent viewers of television.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are frequent viewers of television.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are frequent viewers of television.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="206">
<j>甘いものが嫌いではなく、缶コーヒーの味覚の違いがわかる</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They don&apos;t feel any particular disliking in sweets and know the difference in canned coffee tastes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They don&apos;t have any particular disliking of sweets and know the difference in the tastes of canned coffee.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They don&apos;t have any particular disliking of sweets and know the difference in the tastes of canned coffee.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="207">
<j>普段飲む主飲ブランドと、時々飲む次飲ブランドを持つ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They distinguish brands into the main ones which they drink every day and the secondary ones which they sometimes drink.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They distinguish brands ias the main ones they drink daily and secondary ones they sometimes drink.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They distinguish brands as the main ones they drink daily and secondary ones they sometimes drink.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="208">
<j>選好性はショート缶のほうが高く、ブランドへのこだわりも強い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In preference, they choose more of short cans and have determination with the brands.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In preference, they choose more of the short cans and have determined the brands.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In preference, they choose more of the short cans and have determined the brands.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="209">
<j>自販機での購入が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They purchase more from vending machines.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They purchase more from vending machines.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They purchase more from vending machines.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="210">
<j>新製品が出たらとりあえず試し、口に合わなければ次からは買わない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As soon as a new predict appears on the market, they try it, and if disagreeable, they will not buy it any more.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As soon as a new predict appears on the market, they try it, and if disagreeable, they will not buy it again.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As soon as a new predict appears on the market, they try it, and if disagreeable, they will not buy it again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="211">
<j>缶コーヒーとレギュラーコーヒーはあくまでも別物であると認識している</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They clearly understand that canned coffee is one thing, and regular coffee another.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They clearly understand that canned coffee is one thing, and regular coffee another.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They clearly understand that canned coffee is one thing, and regular coffee another.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="212">
<j>飲む状況</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When to drink</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When to drink</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When to drink</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="213">
<j>通勤途中</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They drink it on their way to work.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They drink it on their way to work.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They drink it on their way to work.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="214">
<j>仕事中や休憩中</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They drink it at work or on a break.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They drink it at work or on a break.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They drink it at work or on a break.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="215">
<j>タバコを吸いながら</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They drink it during smoking.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They drink it during smoking.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They drink it during smoking.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="216">
<j>この働く男性をターゲットとした販売戦略は成功を収め、以降の市場における方向性に影響を与えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This marketing strategy targeting working male persons was a success, which influenced the orientation on the market after that.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This marketing strategy targeting working males was a success, which influenced market orientation.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This marketing strategy targeting working males was a success, which influenced market orientation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="22">
<tit>
<j>2000年代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The 2000s</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The 2000s</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The 2000s</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="217">
<j>缶コーヒーを求めるヘビーユーザーのリピーターは安定傾向である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The situation of heavy-user repeaters who buy canned coffee is on stabilization trend.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The situation of heavy-consummer repeaters who buy canned coffee is on a stabilization trend.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The situation of heavy-consumer repeaters who buy canned coffee is on a stabilization trend.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="218">
<j>その一方で女性や若年層には広がりをみせず、メーカーはその層の取り込みを模索することになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, canned coffee did not become widespread among female persons and young people, and so manufacturers came to search a way to capture the category of customers.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, canned coffee has not become widespread among females and young people so, manufacturers searched for a way to capture this category of customers.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, canned coffee has not become widespread among females and young people so, manufacturers searched for a way to capture this category of customers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="219">
<j>2003年に初採用され2004年に多数使用された190g広口ボトル缶商品は再度蓋ができる機能とデザインで女性に人気を得た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The products in 190g wide-mouth bottle cans which was first adopted in 2003 and used many in 2004 became popular among female persons due to its recapping function and design.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The products in 190g wide-mouth bottle cans first adopted in 2003 and used many in 2004 became popular among females due to its recapping function and design.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The products in 190 g wide-mouth bottle cans first adopted in 2003 and used many in 2004 became popular among females due to its recapping function and design.</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="220">
<j>しかし、一時的なもので定着せずに縮小していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it was temporary, did not take hold and kept decreasing.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it was temporary, did not take hold and kept decreasing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it was temporary, did not take hold and kept decreasing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="221">
<j>また、1993年に発売開始となったチルド飲料チルドカップコーヒーはスターバックスなどに代表されるシアトル系コーヒーブームの影響で、缶コーヒーよりも店舗の味わいに近かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, chilled-cup coffee of chilled drink which was put on the market in 1993 was closer to coffee-shop tastes than canned coffee was, through the influence of the Seattle-type coffee boom, represented by Starbucks Coffee.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, chilled-cup coffee put on the market in 1993 was closer to coffee-shop flavors than canned coffee was, through the influence of the Seattle-type coffee boom, represented by Starbucks Coffee.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, chilled-cup coffee put on the market in 1993 was closer to coffee-shop flavors than canned coffee was, through the influence of the Seattle-type coffee boom, represented by Starbucks Coffee.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="222">
<j>それにより、女性に選択され市場規模が拡大し、缶コーヒー市場停滞の一因となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to the above situation, the product was chosen by female persons and the market was expanded, which contributed to stagnated market of canned coffee.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to the above, the product was chosen by females and the market expanded, which was a positive contributed to a stagnated canned coffee market.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to the above, the product was chosen by females and the market expanded, which was a positive contributed to a stagnated canned coffee market.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="223">
<j>2008年時点において、缶コーヒーのメインユーザーは30-40代の男性となっており、ヘビーユーザーの定義は「一日3本程度飲む人」となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As of 2008, main users of canned coffee were considered to be male persons from their thirties to forties and heavy users were defined as &apos;Persons who drink about three cans a day.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As of 2008, main consummers of canned coffee were considered to be males from their thirties to forties and heavy consummers were defined as &apos;Persons who drink about three cans a day.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As of 2008, main consumers of canned coffee were considered to be males from their thirties to forties and heavy consumers were defined as &apos;Persons who drink about three cans a day.&apos;</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="224">
<j>また、ユーザーの高齢化が進行しており、若い男性や女性層の取り込みが引き続いて課題となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, as canned coffee users are aging, it continues to be an issue to capture the young male and female customers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, as canned coffee consummers are aging, it continues to be an issue to capture the young male and female customers.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, as canned coffee consumers are aging, it continues to be an issue to capture the young male and female customers.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="23">
<tit>
<j>缶コーヒーとリサイクル</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Canned coffee and recycle</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Canned coffee and recycling</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Canned coffee and recycling</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="225">
<j>缶コーヒーを生産する飲料工場から排出される産業廃棄物の大半は抽出後の「コーヒーかす」である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The industrial wastes discharged from beverage plants manufacturing canned coffee are mostly coffee grounds generated by an extraction process.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Industrial wastes discharged from beverage plants manufacturing canned coffee are mostly coffee grounds generated by the extraction process.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Industrial wastes discharged from beverage plants manufacturing canned coffee are mostly coffee grounds generated by the extraction process.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="226">
<j>工場の規模によっては排出量が中途半端なため、処理業者に処分を依頼せざるを得ない場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the case of some small-scale plants, the amount discharged may not be enough to dispose by themselves and so they are sometimes compelled to ask some contractor to do so.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the case of some small-scale plants, the amount discharged may not be enough to dispose by themselves and so they are sometimes compelled to ask a contractor to do this.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the case of some small-scale plants, the amount discharged may not be enough to dispose by themselves and so they are sometimes compelled to ask a contractor to do this.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="227">
<j>かすが発生しないインスタントコーヒーやコーヒーエキスなどに原料としての期待が寄せられた時期もあったが、品質の点でドリップ方式に劣るため主流になることはなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was a certain period of time during which hopes were placed on instant coffee and coffee extracts which generate no grounds as raw materials, but they never became mainstream due to their being inferior to drip method in quality.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was a certain period of time during which hopes were placed upon instant coffee and coffee extracts that generate no grounds as raw materials, but they never became mainstream due to their being inferior to the drip method in quality.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was a certain period of time during which hopes were placed upon instant coffee and coffee extracts that generate no grounds as raw materials, but they never became mainstream due to their being inferior to the drip method in quality.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="228">
<j>コーヒーかすの処理については公害が社会問題として表面化する1970年代にはすでに懸念材料となっており、近代に至るまでその有効利用法が模索されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The matter of coffee grounds disposal had already become a cause of concern in the 1970s when environmental pollution became an issue as a social problem and effective usage has been searched until today.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The matter of coffee grounds disposal had already become a concern in the 1970s when environmental pollution became an issue as a social problem and effective usage has been searched for until today.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The matter of coffee grounds disposal had already become a concern in the 1970s when environmental pollution became an issue as a social problem and effective usage has been searched for until today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="229">
<j>同じ嗜好飲料でもビール製造時に排出される麦芽やビール酵母などは再利用価値が高いことに比べ、コーヒーかすは用途の幅があまり広くない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While malt and beer yeast discharged during the manufacturing process of beer which belongs to one and the same category of taste-oriented beverages are high in the reusable value, the usage range of coffee grounds is not so wide.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While malt and beer yeast discharged during the manufacturing process of beer belongs to one and the same category of taste-oriented beverages are high in reusable value, the usaable range of coffee grounds is not as wide.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While malt and beer yeast discharged during the manufacturing process of beer belongs to one and the same category of taste-oriented beverages are high in reusable value, the usable range of coffee grounds is not as wide.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="230">
<j>ポピュラーな手段として土壌改良剤への再利用があるが、排出量と再利用量にギャップがありすぎるため必ずしも有効というわけではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a popular measure, there is reuse of coffee grounds as a soil improvement agent, but it is not necessarily effective due to an excessive gap between the amount discharged and the amount of reuse.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a popular measure, there is the reuse of coffee grounds as a soil improvement agent, but it is not necessarily effective due to an excessive gap between the amount discharged and the amount reused.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a popular measure, there is the reuse of coffee grounds as a soil improvement agent, but it is not necessarily effective due to an excessive gap between the amount discharged and the amount reused.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="231">
<j>再利用の例</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Examples of reuse</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Examples of reuse</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Examples of reuse</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="232">
<j>堆肥（土壌改良剤）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Compost (soil improvement agent)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Compost (soil improvement agent)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Compost (soil improvement agent)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="233">
<j>バイオ燃料（バイオコークス・バイオディーゼル）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biofuel (Biocoke/biodiesel)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biofuel (Biocoke/biodiesel)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biofuel (Biocoke/biodiesel)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="234">
<j>鋳型の素材</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Raw material of mold</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Raw material for mold</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Raw material for mold</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="235">
<j>活性炭（使い捨てカイロ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Activated charcoal (Disposable body warmer)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Activated charcoal (Disposable body warmer)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Activated charcoal (Disposable body warmer)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="24">
<tit>
<j>缶コーヒーのバリエーション</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Variation of canned coffee</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Variation of canned coffee</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Variation of canned coffee</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="236">
<j>コーヒー入り炭酸飲料</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Coffee-containing carbonated drinks</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Coffee-containing carbonated drinks</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Coffee-containing carbonated drinks</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="237">
<j>コーヒー入り炭酸飲料は世界各国で周期的に発売される傾向がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Coffee-containing carbonated drinks tend to be put on the market periodically around the world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Coffee-containing carbonated drinks tend to be put on the market periodically around the world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Coffee-containing carbonated drinks tend to be put on the market periodically around the world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="238">
<j>その個性的な風味は好き嫌いが極端に別れるため、好奇心や目新しさで話題を呼ぶものの、定番化まで至らず販売終了となることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although it furnished a topic of conversation due to its novelty and people&apos;s curiosity, personal preferences on its distinctive taste were sharply divided, and so it frequently finished sales without becoming a standard product.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although it furnished a topic of conversation due to its novelty and people&apos;s curiosity, personal preferences on its distinctive taste were sharply divided, and so it frequently finished selling without becoming a standard product.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it furnished a topic of conversation due to its novelty and people&apos;s curiosity, personal preferences on its distinctive taste were sharply divided, and so it frequently finished selling without becoming a standard product.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="239">
<j>古くは1954年に東京の鳥井飲料が『コーヒーサイダー』の名で商品化しており、「一家揃って晩餐後楽しめるもの」として好評を博したといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Formerly in 1954, Torii Inryo produced it on a commercial basis under the name of &quot;Coffee Cider,&quot; which is said to have gained public favor as &apos;A drink a whole family can enjoy after dinner.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Formerly in 1954, Torii Inryo produced it on a commercial basis under the name of &quot;Coffee Cider,&quot; which is said to have gained public favor as &apos;A drink a whole family can enjoy after dinner.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Formerly in 1954, Torii Inryo produced it on a commercial basis under the name of &quot;Coffee Cider,&quot; which is said to have gained public favor as &apos;A drink a whole family can enjoy after dinner.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="240">
<j>缶入りでは1975年にアートコーヒーが『コーヒースカッシュ』の名で発売。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a canned product, Art Coffee put it on the market under the name of &quot;Coffee Squash&quot; in 1975.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a canned product, Art Coffee put it on the market under the name of &quot;Coffee Squash&quot; in 1975.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a canned product, Art Coffee put it on the market under the name of &quot;Coffee Squash&quot; in 1975.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="241">
<j>2005年にもリバイバル販売された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was sold as a remodeled product in 2005.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was sold as a remodeled product in 2005.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was sold as a remodeled product in 2005.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="242">
<j>ほかに、ネスレ日本『コーヒースカッシュ』（1989）、『スパークリング・カフェ』（2006）など。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, Nestlé Japan &quot;Coffee Squash&quot; (1989), &quot;Sparkling Café&quot; (2006) and so on were put on the market.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, Nestlé Japan &quot;Coffee Squash&quot; (1989), &quot;Sparkling Café&quot; (2006) and so on were put on the market.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, Nestlé Japan &quot;Coffee Squash&quot; (1989), &quot;Sparkling Café&quot; (2006) and so on were put on the market.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="243">
<j>日本国外ではコーラ (飲料)との融合が多く、ペプシコ『Pepsi-Kona』（1995）、『Pepsi Kaffe』（2004）、コカ・コーラ『enCoca-Cola Blāk』（2006）などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Outside Japan, it commonly became merged with Cola (Beverages) and PepsiCo &quot;Pepsi-Kona&quot; (1995), &quot;Pepsi Kaffe&quot; (2004), Coca-Cola &quot;Coca-Cola Blāk&quot; (2006) and so on were put on the market.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Outside Japan, it commonly became merged with Cola (Beverages) and PepsiCo &quot;Pepsi-Kona&quot; (1995), &quot;Pepsi Kaffe&quot; (2004), Coca-Cola &quot;Coca-Cola Blāk&quot; (2006) and so on were put on the market.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Outside Japan, it commonly became merged with Cola (Beverages) and PepsiCo &quot;Pepsi-Kona&quot; (1995), &quot;Pepsi Kaffe&quot; (2004), Coca-Cola &quot;Coca-Cola Blāk&quot; (2006) and so on were put on the market.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="244">
<j>フレーバー缶コーヒー</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Flavored canned coffee</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Flavored canned coffee</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Flavored canned coffee</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="245">
<j>デザートコーヒーなどとも称される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called Dessert Coffee and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called Dessert Coffee and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called Dessert Coffee and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="246">
<j>欧米を発端とするグルメコーヒー・ブームに呼応して、日本でも1995年頃からアーモンドやヘーゼルナッツの風味を効かせたフレーバー缶コーヒーが販売されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Flavored canned coffee with flavors of almond or hazelnuts started being sold also in Japan around 1995 following the gourmet-coffee boom which had started in the West.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Flavored canned coffee with the flavor of almond or hazelnuts started being sold also in Japan around 1995 following the gourmet-coffee boom which had started in the West.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Flavored canned coffee with the flavor of almond or hazelnuts started being sold also in Japan around 1995 following the gourmet-coffee boom which had started in the West.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="247">
<j>しかしいずれもジャンルの一角を形成したといえるほどの成功には至らず、むしろこの流行はチルドカップ市場で発達している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">None in this category achieved such a success as making up a part of the genre and this particular trend rather developed on the chilled-cup market.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">None in this category achieved a success in making up a part of the genre and this particular trend rather developed in the chilled-cup market.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">None in this category achieved a success in making up a part of the genre and this particular trend rather developed in the chilled-cup market.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="248">
<j>サッポロ『ヘーゼルナッツ風味コーヒー・オレ』（1995）、ダイドー『カフェ・ア・ラ・モード』（1995）、キリンビバレッジ『ファイア メンソール』（2008）、日本コカ・コーラ『ジョージア 塩キャラメル・コーヒー』（2008）など。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This category includes Sapporo &quot;Hazelnuts flavored Coffee au Lait&quot; (1995), Dydo &quot;Café a la Mode&quot; (1995), Kirin Beverage &quot;Fire Menthol&quot; (2008) and Coca-Cola (Japan) &quot;Georgia Salt Caramel Coffee&quot; (2008).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This category includes Sapporo &quot;Hazelnuts flavored Coffee au Lait&quot; (1995), Dydo &quot;Café a la Mode&quot; (1995), Kirin Beverage &quot;Fire Menthol&quot; (2008) and Coca-Cola (Japan) &quot;Georgia Salt Caramel Coffee&quot; (2008).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This category includes Sapporo &quot;Hazelnuts flavored Coffee au Lait&quot; (1995), Dydo &quot;Café a la Mode&quot; (1995), Kirin Beverage &quot;Fire Menthol&quot; (2008) and Coca-Cola (Japan) &quot;Georgia Salt Caramel Coffee&quot; (2008).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="249">
<j>珈琲豆入り缶コーヒー</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Canned coffee with coffee beans</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Canned coffee with coffee beans</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Canned coffee with coffee beans</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="250">
<j>1977年に『ベルミーコーヒー・ビーンズパック』の名でクラシエフーズより発売された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kracie Foods started selling it under the name of &quot;Bellme coffee beans pack&quot; in 1977.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kracie Foods started selling this under the name of &quot;Bellme coffee beans pack&quot; in 1977.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kracie Foods started selling this under the name of &quot;Bellme coffee beans pack&quot; in 1977.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="251">
<j>内部がフィルターで仕切られた二層構造になっており、缶底に仕込まれた本物のコーヒー豆から自販機の加温を利用して直接コーヒーを抽出する仕組み。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The can inside was separated by filter making it double layer structure with real coffee beans being enclosed on the bottom, where coffee directly extracted from the beans when heated by vending machine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The can inside was separated with a filter making it a double layer structure with real coffee beans being enclosed on the bottom, where coffee was directly extracted from the beans when heated in a vending machine.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The can inside was separated with a filter making it a double layer structure with real coffee beans being enclosed on the bottom, where coffee was directly extracted from the beans when heated in a vending machine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="252">
<j>1999年に『豆入りコーヒー』の名で宝ホールディングスより発売された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1999, Takara Holdings started selling it under the name of &quot;Coffee with coffee beans.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1999, Takara Holdings started selling it under the name of &quot;Coffee with coffee beans.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1999, Takara Holdings started selling it under the name of &quot;Coffee with coffee beans.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="253">
<j>あらかじめ缶の中にコーヒー液やミルクと一緒にコーヒー豆を封入しておく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Coffee beans are to be enclosed into the can in advance together with coffee liquid and milk.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Coffee beans are enclosed in the can in advance together with coffee liquid and milk.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Coffee beans are enclosed in the can in advance together with coffee liquid and milk.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="254">
<j>そして、製造時の加熱殺菌を利用してコーヒーを抽出することで香りや旨みが缶内に封じ込められるという製法。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, coffee is to be extracted from the beans when heated by heat sterilization during the manufacturing process, by which the flavor and taste can be confined in the can.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, coffee is extracted from the beans when heated by heat sterilization during the manufacturing process, by which the flavor and taste can be confined in the can.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, coffee is extracted from the beans when heated by heat sterilization during the manufacturing process, by which the flavor and taste can be confined in the can.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="255">
<j>加熱機能付き缶コーヒー</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Canned coffee with heating function</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Canned coffee with a heating function</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Canned coffee with a heating function</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="256">
<j>1987年に『だんだんあつあつコーヒー』の名で味の素ゼネラルフーヅより発売された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1987, Ajinomoto General Foods put it on the market under the name of &quot;Dandan Atsuatsu Coffee&quot; (Gradually heated coffee).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1987, Ajinomoto General Foods put it on the market under the name of &quot;Dandan Atsuatsu Coffee&quot; (Gradually heated coffee).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1987, Ajinomoto General Foods put it on the market under the name of &quot;Dandan Atsuatsu Coffee&quot; (Gradually heated coffee).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="257">
<j>日本酒の特殊容器に使用されていた加熱機構を缶コーヒーに採用したもので、酸化カルシウムと水を反応させて発熱を起こす仕掛けが施されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The heating system used for special containers of Japanese sake was adopted for canned coffee, which is designed to generate heat by inducing a reaction between calcium oxide and water.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The heating system used for special containers of Japanese sake was adopted for canned coffee, which is designed to generate heat by inducing a reaction between calcium oxide and water.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The heating system used for special containers of Japanese sake was adopted for canned coffee, which is designed to generate heat by inducing a reaction between calcium oxide and water.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="258">
<j>烏龍茶入り缶コーヒー</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Canned coffee containing oolong tea</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Canned coffee containing oolong tea</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Canned coffee containing oolong tea</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="259">
<j>1988年に『烏龍珈琲』の名で森永製菓より発売された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1988, Morinaga seika started selling it under the name of &quot;Oolong coffee.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1988, Morinaga seika started selling this product under the name of &quot;Oolong coffee.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1988, Morinaga seika started selling this product under the name of &quot;Oolong coffee.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="25">
<tit>
<j>世界の普及状況</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Penetration in the world</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Penetration throughout the world</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Penetration throughout the world</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="260">
<j>缶コーヒーは日本などアジアが市場の主流で、欧米では極小規模の範囲で留まっており、日本でいう350ml相当の缶にミルク・糖分多めの商品が日系やアジア系のメーカーから数種発売されている程度である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Asian countries including Japan form the main market of canned coffee, the Western countries remain very small-scale as a market, where only a few types of coffee containing a little extra milk and sugar in cans equal to Japanese 350ml ones sold by Japanese- and Asian-affiliated manufacturers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While Asian countries including Japan form the main market of canned coffee, Western countries remain a very small-scale market, where only a few types of coffee containing a little extra milk and sugar in cans equal to Japanese 350ml cans sold by Japanese- and Asian-affiliated manufacturers.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While Asian countries including Japan form the main market of canned coffee, Western countries remain a very small-scale market, where only a few types of coffee containing a little extra milk and sugar in cans equal to Japanese 350 ml cans sold by Japanese- and Asian-affiliated manufacturers.</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="261">
<j>これは日本のように、屋外にも莫大な数の自動販売機（清涼飲料用）が設置されている国が世界的に類がなく、また「アイスコーヒー」という文化があまり馴染みがないためでもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That may have been caused by the fact that Japan is globally unparalleled country where the huge number of vending machines (selling soft drinks) installed outdoors and the fact that in the Western countries the culture of &apos;Ice coffee&apos; (Hot coffee prevails in the West.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That may have been caused by the fact that Japan is a globally unparalleled country where a huge number of vending machines (selling soft drinks) installed outdoors and the fact that in the Western countries the culture of &apos;Ice coffee&apos; (Hot coffee prevails in the West.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That may have been caused by the fact that Japan is a globally unparalleled country where a huge number of vending machines (selling soft drinks) installed outdoors and the fact that in the Western countries the culture of &apos;Ice coffee&apos; is not familiar.</e>
<cmt>後列と原文を調整し、一文にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="262">
<j>（欧米ではホットで飲むことが主流。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, cold coffee has recently become established in urban areas of the United States as a result of a success of Starbucks Coffee) is not familiar.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, cold coffee recently became established in urban areas of the United States as a result of the success of Starbucks Coffee) is not familiar.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Hot coffee prevails in the West.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="263">
<j>（但し、近年米国においてはスターバックスの成功により、都市部では定着している。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(However, cold coffee recently became established in urban areas of the United States as a result of the success of Starbucks Coffee.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="264">
<j>アメリカでは、コーヒー豆をミルで挽いた粉状のもの（レギュラーコーヒー）を缶詰にしたものを「Can Coffee」と呼ぶ（⇒和製英語）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the United States, mill-ground coffee beans n a powdery state (Regular coffee) which is canned is called &apos;Can Coffee&apos; (=&gt;Waseieigo (Japanese word constructed of elements from one or more English terms)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the United States, mill-ground coffee beans in a powdery state (Regular coffee) and canned is called &apos;Can Coffee&apos; (=&gt;Waseieigo Japanese word constructed of elements from one or more English terms).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the United States, mill-ground coffee beans in a powdery state (Regular coffee) and canned is called &apos;Can Coffee&apos; (=&gt;Waseieigo Japanese word constructed of elements from one or more English terms).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="265">
<j>なお、米国において、缶紅茶は、ごく一般的な飲料として普及している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Canned black tea is widespread as a very popular beverage in the United States.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Canned black tea is widespread as a very popular beverage in the United States.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Canned black tea is widespread as a very popular beverage in the United States.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="26">
<tit>
<j>缶コレクター</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Can collectors</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Can collectors</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Can collectors</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="266">
<j>日本には海外のビール缶コレクターズクラブ『Brewery Collectibles Club of America』のようなコーヒー缶コレクター団体は存在しない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are no collector organizations for coffee cans in Japan as there are collector clubs for beer cans overseas including &quot;Brewery Collectibles Club of America.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are no collector organizations for coffee cans in Japan as there are collector clubs for beer cans overseas including &quot;Brewery Collectibles Club of America.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are no collector organizations for coffee cans in Japan as there are collector clubs for beer cans overseas including &quot;Brewery Collectibles Club of America.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="267">
<j>しかし個人単位でコレクターは数多く存在し、Web上などでそのコレクションの一部を見る事ができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there are many of individual collectors and a part of their collections can be seen on websites and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there are many of individual collectors and a part of their collections can be seen on websites and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there are many of individual collectors and a part of their collections can be seen on websites and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="268">
<j>しかし、希少な缶が高い金銭価値を持っていたとしても、それらが詳しく体系化されるような活動はあまり盛んではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even if some cans have scarcity value, however, movement for detailed systematization has not been active.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even if some cans have a scarce value, however, movement for detailed systematization has not been active.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even if some cans have a scarce value, however, movement for detailed systematization has not been active.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="269">
<j>また、日本以外の国においてコーヒー缶コレクターが存在する可能性があるが、存在したとしてもごく少数にとどまると推測される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, although there may be some coffee-can collectors in other countries than Japan, they are estimated to be limited in extremely small number.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, although there may be some coffee-can collectors in other countries than Japan, they are estimated to be limited in extremely small number.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, although there may be some coffee-can collectors in other countries than Japan, they are estimated to be limited in extremely small number.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="27">
<tit>
<j>参考</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reference</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reference</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reference</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="270">
<j>缶コーヒーは限定的な普及状況（世界の普及状況）のため、その飲み方で日本人であるかどうか知られてしまう事がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to the limited penetration (Penetration in the world) of canned coffee, Japanese drinking practices sometimes end up identifying a drinking person as a Japanese.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to the limited penetration (Penetration in the world) of canned coffee, Japanese drinking practices sometimes end up identifying a drinking person as a Japanese.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to the limited penetration (Penetration in the world) of canned coffee, Japanese drinking practices sometimes end up identifying a drinking person as a Japanese.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="271">
<j>大韓航空機爆破事件の際の金賢姫は、派遣された日本の外交官が差し入れた熱い缶コーヒーを、息で「ふーふー」吹いてから飲もうとしたために正体を見破られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the time of Korean Air Lines bombing incident, Kim Hyun-Hee&apos;s identity was discovered when she, before drinking, blew on her hot canned coffee received from a dispatched Japanese diplomat.</e>
<cmt>「ふーふー」の擬音語はサイトをあちこち探しましたが、見つかりませんでした。[研究社　新和英大辞典第５版]では、「ふうふう吹く」＝「blow on 《one&apos;s coffee》」となっています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the time of the Korean Air Lines bombing incident, Kim Hyun-Hee&apos;s identity was discovered when, before drinking, she blew on her hot canned coffee received from a dispatched Japanese diplomat.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the time of the Korean Air Lines bombing incident, Kim Hyun-Hee&apos;s identity was discovered when, before drinking, she blew on her hot canned coffee received from a dispatched Japanese diplomat.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="272">
<j>本当に飲み慣れた日本人であれば熱くても吹くような習慣は乏しい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Any Japanese regular drinker rarely blows on his/her coffee even if it is hot.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Any Japanese regular drinkers rarely blow on his/her coffee even if it is hot.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Any Japanese regular drinkers rarely blow on his/her coffee even if it is hot.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="273">
<j>シチューなどの食べ方については定着していない欧米式マナー「吹かずに冷めるのを待つ」飲み方が、缶コーヒーについては逆に定着している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The eating practice &apos;To wait until cooling off without blowing,&apos; the Western manner for eating stew and so on which has not been established here in Japan conversely take hold for canned coffee.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The practice &apos;To wait until cooling off without blowing,&apos; the Western manner for eating stew and so on which has not been established here in Japan is conversely taking hold for canned coffee.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The practice &apos;To wait until cooling off without blowing,&apos; the Western manner for eating stew and so on which has not been established here in Japan is conversely taking hold for canned coffee.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Ligar(id:12623), AlleborgoBot(id:119729), Tomzo(id:16777), RiceCracker(id:4809), Stay on tab(id:82191), Sillago(id:187189), Shoppe(id:10574), Hokahoka(id:37244), Rio-ver(id:272197), Gonorego2004(id:30859), ITA-ATU(id:90254), Goch(id:17164), Fumipon(id:46816), An-chan(id:14590), デジタルチョコ(id:27299), IwaimBot(id:190695), Point136(id:211299), Red Star Belgrade(id:25968), Starbacks(id:1018), Sat.K(id:3751), ZZZ(id:9462), TEy(id:32722), 茶務(id:48052), 視力0.1以下(id:119355), MDR-SK(id:192066), Interregnum(id:25269), Gleam(id:4760), Kanibaketu(id:147610), Rislimric(id:54531), 曖(id:41245), E257-500(id:9366), やすとし(id:63220), MaxPowr(id:203568), You-kan(id:33117), Mkawam(id:91511), ホイップ(id:44812), Nog(id:53565), Jcoffee(id:13421), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>