<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>干しいも</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hoshi-imo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hoshi-imo</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hoshi-imo (dried sweet potatoes)</e>
<cmt>「干し芋」補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>干しいも（ほしいも、干し芋）はサツマイモを蒸して乾燥させた食品である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hoshi-imo (dried sweet potatoes) is made from sweet potato through the processing of steaming and then drying.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hoshi-imo (dried sweet potatoes) is made from sweet potato through the processing of steaming and then drying.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hoshi-imo is made from sweet potato through the processing of steaming and then drying.</e>
<cmt>干し芋　既出のため、補足を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>日本においては全国各地で作られているが、産業としては8割以上が茨城県で生産されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Hoshi-imo is produced nationwide in Japan, more than 80 percent of hoshi-imo is produced in Ibaraki Prefecture for the industrial purpose.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While Hoshi-imo is produced nationwide in Japan, more than 80 percent of hoshi-imo is indutrially produced in Ibaraki Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While hoshi-imo is produced nationwide in Japan, more than 80 percent of hoshi-imo is industrially produced in Ibaraki Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>「乾燥芋（かんそういも、かんそいも）」「蒸し切り干し」「きっぽし」「いもかち」などとも呼ばれることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called, &apos;kanso-imo&apos; (dried sweet potato), &apos;mushi-kirihoshi&apos; (steamed, cut and dried sweet potato), &apos;kibboshi,&apos; &apos;imokachi&apos; and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called, kanso-imo (dried sweet potato), mushi-kirihoshi (steamed, cut and dried sweet potato), kibboshi, imokachi, and so on.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called, &apos;kanso-imo&apos; (dried sweet potato), &apos;mushi-kirihoshi&apos; (steamed, cut and dried sweet potato), &apos;kibboshi,&apos; &apos;imokachi,&apos; and so on.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>色は暗い黄緑がかった褐色をしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its color is brown inclined to dark yellowish green.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its color is brown inclined to dark yellowish green.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its color is brown inclined to dark yellowish green.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>大きさは作る人によって様々だが、一般的に店頭で販売されているものは一片が長さ10～15cm、幅5cm程度の細長く薄い板状をしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though the size of the hoshi-imo is various depending on the person who makes it, the piece generally sold at shops has a long and narrow and thin tabular shape with around 10-15cm length and 5cm width.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the size of hoshi-imo varies depending on the person who makes it, the piece generally sold at shops has a long and narrow tubular shape with length around 10-15 cm and width around 5 cm.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the size of hoshi-imo varies depending on the person who makes it, the piece generally sold at shops has a long and narrow tubular shape with length around 10-15 cm and width around 5 cm.</e>
<cmt>イタリック体になっている箇所を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>適度な水分を含む為、粘度のある噛み応えとサツマイモらしい甘味が特徴的である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its gummy texture and sweet taste peculiar to the sweet potato are unique, both of which are produced by the moderate moisture contained in it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its gummy texture and sweet taste peculiar to the sweet potato are unique, both of which are produced by the moderate moisture content.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its gummy texture and sweet taste peculiar to the sweet potato are unique, both of which are produced by the moderate moisture content.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>また整腸作用のあるアルカリ食品としても優秀で、様々な栄養素を含む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, hoshi-imo is an excellent alkaline food with a virtue of keeping bowels in good condition, containing various nourishment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, hoshi-imo is an excellent alkaline food with a virtue of keeping the bowels in good condition, containing various nutrients.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, hoshi-imo is an excellent alkaline food with a virtue of keeping the bowels in good condition, containing various nutrients.</e>
<cmt>イタリック体になっている箇所を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>そのまま生で食べてもよいが、火であぶるとやわらかく甘味も増す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">You can not only eat it raw but also eat it after toasting, because toasting makes hoshi-imo softer and sweeter.</e>
<cmt>一例文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">You can not only eat it raw but also eat it after toasting, because toasting makes hoshi-imo softer and sweeter.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">You can not only eat it raw but also eat it after toasting, because toasting makes hoshi-imo softer and sweeter.</e>
<cmt>イタリック体になっている箇所を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>また表面を軽く焦がすことにより、香ばしさが生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, slightly scorching provides you with nice-smelling.</e>
<cmt>一例文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, slightly scorching provides you with pleasant aroma.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, slightly scorching provides you with pleasant aroma.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>シンプルな製法のため家庭でも作られることが多いが、蒸し方にはある程度のコツが必要となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although hoshi-imo is frequently made at home due to its simple recipe, some tricks are required in steaming.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although hoshi-imo is frequently made at home due to its simple recipe, some tricks are required in steaming.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although hoshi-imo is frequently made at home due to its simple recipe, some tricks are required in steaming.</e>
<cmt>イタリック体になっている箇所を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>先述のとおり複雑な製法ではないが時間と手間がかかる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Making hoshi-imo is not complicated as stated above, but it takes time and labor.</e>
<cmt>一例文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As stated above, making hoshi-imo is not complicated, but it takes time and labor.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As stated above, making hoshi-imo is not complicated, but it takes time and labor.</e>
<cmt>イタリック体になっている箇所を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>そのため価格は1袋500gで1000円程度するものもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, some manufacturers offer about 1000 yen for a 500g pack of hoshi-imo.</e>
<cmt>一例文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, some manufacturers offer a 500g pack of hoshi-imo for about 1000 yen.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, some manufacturers offer a 500-gram pack of hoshi-imo for about 1000 yen.</e>
<cmt>a 500-gram pack　と表現を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>また製造時の端切れを集めたものを「せっこう」と言い、通常品の半値程度で販売されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, a group of hoshi-imo left over after cutting fine slices is called &apos;sekko&apos;, sold at about half the usual price.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, a group of hoshi-imo left over after cutting fine slices is called sekko, sold at about half the usual price.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, a group of hoshi-imo left over after cutting fine slices is called &apos;sekko,&apos; sold at about half the usual price.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>形が整っていないために二級品扱いで安価ではあるが、味は変わらない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Despite its low price because sekko is categorized in the second class due to the irregularity of the hoshi-imo contained in the pack, the taste of the hoshi-imo is the same as that sold in the usual pack.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Despite its low price due to sekko being categorized in the second class due to the irregularity of the hoshi-imo contained in the pack, the taste of the hoshi-imo is the same as that sold in the usual pack.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Despite its low price due to sekko being categorized in the second class due to the irregularity of the hoshi-imo contained in the pack, the taste of the hoshi-imo is the same as that sold in the usual pack.</e>
<cmt>イタリック体になっている箇所を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>他に、干しいもの表面が白い粉で覆われている場合がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, you may sometimes find the surface of hoshi-imo covered with white powder.</e>
<cmt>一例文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, you may sometimes find the surface of hoshi-imo covered with white powder.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, you may sometimes find the surface of hoshi-imo covered with white powder.</e>
<cmt>イタリック体になっている箇所を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>これは芋の自己分解で生まれた糖分が表面に出て結晶化したものでカビではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This white powder is not mold but crystallized sugar coming to the surface after formed through the autolysis process in potato.</e>
<cmt>一例文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This white powder is not mold but crystallized sugar coming to the surface after being formed through the autolysis process in potato.</e>
<cmt>aded &quot;being&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This white powder is not mold but crystallized sugar coming to the surface after being formed through the autolysis process in potato.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>製法</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Processing</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Processing</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Processing</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="17">
<j>収穫直後のサツマイモを、皮をつけたまま2時間ほど蒸しあげる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fresh sweet potato in its skin is steamed for about two hours.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fresh sweet potato in its skin is steamed for about two hours.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fresh sweet potato in its skin is steamed for about two hours.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>蒸し器から出した後、皮をむき、すだれに広げ冬場の寒風を利用して天日で1週間程度干す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After put out from the steamer, the steamed sweet potato is peeled and expanded on bamboo screens, dried in the sun for about a week utilizing chilly wind peculiar to the winter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After being put out from the steamer, the steamed sweet potato is peeled and expanded on bamboo screens, and dried in the sun for about a week utilizing chilly wind peculiar to the winter.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After being put out from the steamer, the steamed sweet potato is peeled and expanded on bamboo screens, and dried in the sun for about a week utilizing chilly wind peculiar to the winter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>そのまま干されることもあるが、ピアノ線などを使って1センチ程度の厚さに切られてから干されることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While some steamed sweet potatoes are dried entirely, most of them are dried after being sliced in one centimeter thick.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While some steamed sweet potatoes are dried entirely, most of them are dried after being sliced to one centimeter thickness.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While some steamed sweet potatoes are dried entirely, most of them are dried after being sliced to one centimeter thickness using such tools as piano wires.</e>
<cmt>ピアノ線　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>切らずにそのまま干したものは「丸干しいも」と呼ばれ20日ほどの乾燥が必要になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The steamed sweet potato dried entirely without being cut is called &apos;maru-hoshiimo&apos; (uncut whole piece of dried sweet potato), which requires about twenty days to be dried up.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The steamed sweet potato dried entirely without being cut is called maru-hoshiimo (uncut whole piece of dried sweet potato), which requires about twenty days to dry.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The steamed sweet potato dried entirely without being cut is called &apos;maru-hoshiimo&apos; (uncut whole piece of dried sweet potato), which requires about 20 days to dry.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="21">
<j>サツマイモの甘味を増やすため、サツマイモを収穫後に糖化させるなどの工夫もしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Various technique are adopted, including the saccharification method of the flesh sweet potato which enhances sweetness.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Various technique are adopted, including the saccharification method of the fresh sweet potato, which enhances sweetness.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Various technique are adopted, including the saccharification method of the fresh sweet potato, which enhances sweetness.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="22">
<j>近年は、衛生確保のためビニールハウスや網を張って乾燥させてることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the hygienic viewpoint, plastic greenhouses and nets are used when sweet potato is dried these days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the hygienic viewpoint, plastic greenhouses and nets are used when sweet potato is dried these days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the hygienic viewpoint, plastic greenhouses and nets are used when sweet potato is dried these days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>また機械乾燥で大量生産されたものもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, some manufacturers have introduced machines for drying the sweet potato aiming at mass production.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, some manufacturers have introduced machines for drying the sweet potato, aiming at mass production.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, some manufacturers have introduced machines for drying the sweet potato, aiming at mass production.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>ゆでたものを干す場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some sweet potatoes are dried after being boiled.</e>
<cmt>一例文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some sweet potatoes are dried after being boiled.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some sweet potatoes are dried after being boiled.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>この場合デンプンが糊化しないので蒸したものより堅くなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hoshi-imo made from the boiled sweet potato becomes harder than that from steamed sweet potato, because starch contained in the sweet potato would not be changed into an adhesive material</e>
<cmt>一例文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hoshi-imo made from the boiled sweet potato becomes harder than that from steamed sweet potato, because starch contained in the sweet potato is not changed into an adhesive material</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hoshi-imo made from the boiled sweet potato becomes harder than that from steamed sweet potato, because starch contained in the sweet potato is not changed into an adhesive material.</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを追加ｈしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="26">
<j>原料となるサツマイモの品種は玉豊種（農林22号）やいずみ種が多く使用される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sweet potato sorted into Tamayutaka-kind (agricultural and forestry No. 22) and Izumi-kind are frequently used as a raw material.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sweet potato sorted into Tamayutaka-kind (agricultural and forestry No. 22) and Izumi-kind are frequently used as a raw material.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sweet potato sorted into Tamayutaka-kind (agricultural and forestry No. 22) and Izumi-kind are frequently used as a raw material.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>玉豊種は他のサツマイモと比べて大型で、外皮、肉色とも白く、食感はホクホクではなくネットリしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Tamayutaka-kind is larger than other kinds with whitish skin and substance, tasting sticky rather than flaky.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Tamayutaka-kind is larger than other kinds with whitish skin and substance, tasting sticky rather than flaky.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tamayutaka-kind is larger than other kinds with whitish skin and substance, tasting sticky rather than flaky.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="28">
<j>サツマイモの収穫直後に製造されるため、必然的に干しいもの製造は冬季から初春に行われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hoshi-imo is produced in winter through early spring as a logical consequence of using fresh sweet potato.</e>
<cmt>一例文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hoshi-imo is produced in winter through early spring as a logical consequence of using fresh sweet potato.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hoshi-imo is produced in winter through early spring as a logical consequence of using fresh sweet potato.</e>
<cmt>イタリック体になっている箇所を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>しかし冷凍保存されたものが一年を通じて流通している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, hoshi-imo kept in freezers are sold throughout a year.</e>
<cmt>一例文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, hoshi-imo kept in freezers are sold throughout a year.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, hoshi-imo kept in freezers are sold throughout a year.</e>
<cmt>イタリック体になっている箇所を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>産地</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Production area</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Production area</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Production area</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="30">
<j>県別の生産高では茨城県（ひたちなか市、東海村）が全国第一位となっているほか、冬のからっ風が強い群馬県、明治時代に産業化が始められた静岡県、長崎県などで生産が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides Ibaraki Prefecture (Tokai-mura, Hitachinaka City), which boasts the largest output among all prefectures in Japan, Gunma Prefecture blessed with downdraft blown down from the top of mountains in winter, and Shizuoka Prefecture and Nagasaki Prefecture, where the manufacturing the hoshi-imo was industrialized in the Meiji period, produce lots of hoshi-imo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides Ibaraki Prefecture (Tokai-mura, Hitachinaka City), which boasts the largest output among all prefectures in Japan, Gunma Prefecture, blessed with downdraft blown down from the top of mountains in winter, and Shizuoka Prefecture and Nagasaki Prefecture, where the manufacture of the hoshi-imo was industrialized in the Meiji period, produce lots of hoshi-imo.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides Ibaraki Prefecture (Tokai-mura, Hitachinaka City), which boasts the largest output among all prefectures in Japan, Gunma Prefecture, blessed with downdraft blown down from the top of mountains in winter, and Shizuoka Prefecture and Nagasaki Prefecture, where the manufacture of the hoshi-imo was industrialized in the Meiji period, produce lots of hoshi-imo.</e>
<cmt>イタリック体になっている箇所を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>最近では茨城県の業者による技術指導の下、中華人民共和国産も出回っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under the technical instruction of manufacturers in Ibaraki Prefecture, hoshi-imo is also produced in the People&apos;s Republic of China, which is coming onto the market in Japan.</e>
<cmt>一例文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the technical instruction of manufacturers in Ibaraki Prefecture, hoshi-imo is also produced in the People&apos;s Republic of China, which is coming onto the market in Japan.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the technical instruction of manufacturers in Ibaraki Prefecture, hoshi-imo is also produced in the People&apos;s Republic of China, which is coming onto the market in Japan.</e>
<cmt>イタリック体になっている箇所を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>しかし国産に比べ甘味や食感に差異がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there are differences in sweetness and texture between China-made hoshi-imo and domestic.</e>
<cmt>一例文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there are differences in sweetness and texture between China-made hoshi-imo and domestic.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there are differences in sweetness and texture between China-made hoshi-imo and domestic.</e>
<cmt>イタリック体になっている箇所を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>保存方法</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">How to preserve</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">How to preserve</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">How to preserve</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="33">
<j>室温保存も可能であるが、保存料等は使われておらず、さらに最近のものは食感を良くするため乾燥しすぎないようにしているのでカビが発生しやすい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hoshi-imo can be preserved at room temperature, however, it easily gets mildewed because of its manufacturing method without using preservatives and other chemical products, in addition to the latest technique for preventing hoshi-imo from being over dehydrated aiming at better texture.</e>
<cmt>一例文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hoshi-imo can be preserved at room temperature; however, it easily gets mildewed because of its manufacturing method without using preservatives and other chemical products, in addition to the latest technique for preventing hoshi-imo from being over dehydrated, aiming at better texture.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hoshi-imo can be preserved at room temperature; however, it easily gets mildewed because of its manufacturing method without using preservatives and other chemical products, in addition to the latest technique for preventing hoshi-imo from being over dehydrated, aiming at better texture.</e>
<cmt>イタリック体になっている箇所を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>そのためクレームの多い食品の一つである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, hoshi-imo is cited as one of foodstuffs suffering from lots of complaints.</e>
<cmt>一例文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, hoshi-imo is cited as one of foodstuffs suffering from lots of complaints.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, hoshi-imo is cited as one of foodstuffs suffering from lots of complaints.</e>
<cmt>イタリック体になっている箇所を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>このため冷蔵庫での保存が好ましい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is recommendable to keep it in refrigerator.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is recommendable to keep it in refrigerator.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is recommendable to keep it in refrigerator.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>冷凍にすれば長期保存が可能である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Frozen hoshi-imo can be preserved for a long period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Frozen hoshi-imo can be preserved for a long period.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Frozen hoshi-imo can be preserved for a long period.</e>
<cmt>イタリック体になっている箇所を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="37">
<j>店頭販売用の干しいもは、バリア性の高いフィルムで作られた包装袋にほしいもと脱酸素剤を同封し、日持ち向上させる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hoshi-imo sold at stores is usually packed with deoxidizer into a bag made of wrapping material with high shielding properties for long-term storage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hoshi-imo sold at stores is usually packed with deoxidizer into a bag made of wrapping material with high shielding properties for long-term storage.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hoshi-imo sold at stores is usually packed with deoxidizer into a bag made of wrapping material with high shielding properties for long-term storage.</e>
<cmt>イタリック体になっている箇所を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Weihuajin(id:18206), LoL045(id:162762), PeachLover(id:56909), Bandalgom(id:31841), Mannequin(id:87056), Papakuro(id:21241), 水野白楓(id:22811), Minestrone(id:108968), Web comic(id:70956), Izumikairaku(id:115091), Halfd(id:145364), TAMA(id:25299), Jnr bus(id:33651), 1029man(id:93235), Green tea(id:38860), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>