<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>襟立衣</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eritategoromo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eritategoromo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eritategoromo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>襟立衣（えりたてごろも）は、鳥山石燕の妖怪画集『画図百器徒然袋』にある日本の妖怪。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eritategoromo refers to a Japanese specter portrayed in Sekien TORIYAMA&apos;s book of specter paintings,&quot;Hyakki Tsurezure Bukuro&quot; (One hundred bags in idlenss).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An Eritate-goromo (literally, standing-collar robe) is one of Japanese yokai (ghosts, spirits and monsters) that was portrayed in Sekien TORIYAMA&apos;s yokai art collection book: &quot;Gazu Hyakki Tsurezure Bukuro&quot; (The Illustrated Bag of One Hundred Random Demons; the term &apos;hyakki&apos; in its title is a pun on the usual hyakki, replacing the character for demon which is written as &quot;鬼&quot; in Japanese with a character for vessel written as &quot;器,&quot; and sure enough, most of the yokais shown in this book are tsukumogami [a type of Japanese spirits that originate in items or artifacts that have reached their 100th birthday and become alive]).</e>
<cmt>原文に「画図」を補足のうえ再訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An Eritate-goromo (literally, standing-collar robe) is one of Japanese yokai (ghosts, spirits and monsters) that was portrayed in Sekien TORIYAMA&apos;s yokai art collection book: &quot;Gazu Hyakki Tsurezure Bukuro&quot; (The Illustrated Bag of One Hundred Random Demons; the term &apos;hyakki&apos; in its title is a pun on the usual hyakki, replacing the character for demon which is written as &quot;鬼&quot; in Japanese with a character for vessel written as &quot;器,&quot; and sure enough, most of the yokais shown in this book are tsukumogami [a type of Japanese spirits that originate in items or artifacts that have reached their 100th birthday and become alive]).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>天狗の首領である日本八大天狗の1人、鞍馬山僧正坊の身に纏っている僧衣の襟立衣が妖怪化したものとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It allegedly mutated from the robe of Priest Shobo of Mount Kurama (Kurama tengu), who was one of tengu&apos;s chieftain, i. e., Great Tengu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sojobo of Mount Kurama (also called Kurama Tengu), one of the eight greatest Japanese tengu (long-nosed goblins), used to wear a clerical robe with a standing collar, which reportedly transmuted into a yokai and was thus named the Eritate-goromo.</e>
<cmt>原文「大天狗」はリンク先表示であり、wiki上の原文に基づいて修正しました。流れ調整、用語選択、補足訳。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sojobo of Mt. Kurama (also called Kurama Tengu), one of the eight greatest Japanese tengu (long-nosed goblins), used to wear a clerical robe with a standing collar, which reportedly transmuted into a yokai and was thus named the Eritate-goromo.</e>
<cmt>Mount→Mt.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>衣に目や髭が生じ、尖った襟が鼻となった姿で描かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its eyes and mustache are portrayed on the priest&apos;s robe, and the sharp collar is drawn as the nose.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the portrayal, it has the eyes and beard appearing on a Buddhist priest&apos;s robe, and a sharp collar is put in the place of the nose.</e>
<cmt>表現調整、用語選択（絵から察するに、髭はmustacheではなくbeardと思われます）http://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E8%A5%9F%E7%AB%8B%E8%A1%A3</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In TORIYAMA&apos;s book, the Buddhist priest&apos;s robe worn by Sojobo has eyes and a beard on it, and its sharp collar forms the Eritate-goromo&apos;s nose.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせて修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>鞍馬山僧正坊はもとは人間の高僧であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The priest of Mount Kurama allegedly used to be a human high priest.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sojobo of Mount Kurama used to be a human high priest.</e>
<cmt>原文の「僧山坊」は「僧正坊」の誤植ですので、修正の上再訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sojobo of Mt. Kurama used to be a human high priest.</e>
<cmt>Mount→Mt.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>修行途中にもかかわらず悟りを得たと思い違えために死後も成仏できなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since he mistakenly thought he was enlightened in the middle of the ascetic practice, he could not attain Buddhahood after the death.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to a legend, Sojobo mistakenly believed that he suddenly realized Buddhahood in the middle of ascetic practices, thereby failing to become Buddha after death.</e>
<cmt>表現調整</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to a legend, Sojobo mistakenly believed that he suddenly realized Buddhahood in the middle of ascetic practices, thereby failing to become Buddha after death.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>驕りの代名詞ともいえる天狗に生まれ変わったとする説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to one view, he was reincarnated as tengu, which is a synonym for arrogance.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to one view, he was reincarnated as tengu, which is a synonym for arrogance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to one view, he was reincarnated as tengu, which is a synonym for arrogance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>天狗となってもなお僧の位階に固執するかのように僧衣を身に纏い続けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although he became a tengu, he still wore the priest&apos;s robe as if he persisted in the dignity as a priest.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although he became a tengu, he still wore the priest&apos;s robe as if he persisted in the dignity as a priest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although he became a tengu, he still wore the priest&apos;s robe as if he persisted in the dignity as a priest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>この僧衣は、いわば彼の驕り高ぶりの証ともいえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The robe may be a proof of his arrogance.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The robe may be a proof of his arrogance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The robe may be a proof of his arrogance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>この驕り高ぶりの業、もしくは何らかの霊の憑依によって衣から変化したものが、妖怪の襟立衣とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that his arrogance or some kind of possessing spirit turned the robe into the specter, Eritategoromo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is supposedly either Sojo&apos;s fatal arrogance or the possession by an evil spirit that caused the robe to turn into a yokai: the Eritate-goromo.</e>
<cmt>表現調整</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is supposedly either Sojo&apos;s fatal arrogance or the possession by an evil spirit that caused the robe to turn into a yokai: the Eritate-goromo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 逃亡者(id:14864), Uijgf(id:150999), Cprobot(id:97843), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>