<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>浴衣</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yukata (a kind of traditional Japanese clothes)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yukata (a kind of traditional Japanese clothing)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yukata (a kind of traditional Japanese clothing)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>浴衣（ゆかた）は和服の一種である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Yukata&quot; is a kind of wafuku (traditional Japanese clothes).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Yukata&quot; is a kind of wafuku (traditional Japanese clothing).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yukata is a kind of wafuku (traditional Japanese clothing).</e>
<cmt>文頭の &quot;&quot; 削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>平安時代の湯帷子(ゆかたびら)がその原型とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has reportedly originated in yukatabira (a light garment for bathing) in the Heian Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reportedly, it originated in the yukatabira (a light garment for bathing) of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reportedly, it originated in the yukatabira (a light garment for bathing) of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>湯帷子は、平安中期に成立した倭名類聚抄(わみょうるいじゅしょう)によると、内衣布で沐浴するための衣とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Wamyo-ruijusho (a Japanese encyclopedia) edited in the middle of the Heian Period, yukatabira was a kind of inner cloth worn for bathing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Wamyo-ruijusho (a Japanese encyclopedia) edited in the middle of the Heian period, yukatabira was a kind of inner cloth worn for bathing.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Wamyo-ruijusho (a Japanese encyclopedia) edited in the middle of the Heian period, yukatabira was a kind of inner cloth worn for bathing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>この時代、複数の人と入浴する機会があったため、汗取りと裸を隠す目的で使用されたものと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In those days, while a person occasionally took a bath together with others, he is assumed to have worn the cloth in a bath to wipe off the sweat and also to hide his naked body.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In those days, while a person occasionally took a bath together with others, he is assumed to have worn the cloth in a bath to wipe off the sweat and also to hide his naked body.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In those days, while a person occasionally took a bath together with others, he or she is assumed to have worn the cloth in a bath to wipe off the sweat and also to hide his naked body.</e>
<cmt>he→he or she</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>素材は、水に強く水切れの良い麻が使われていたという説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The material of the cloth was water-resistant hemp of good drainage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The material of the cloth was water-resistant hemp of good drainage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The material of the cloth was water-resistant hemp of good drainage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>安土桃山時代頃から、湯上りに着て肌の水分を吸い取らせる目的でひろく用いられるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since around the Azuchi-Momoyama Period, the said cloth became widely worn to absorb sweat off skin after a bath.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since around the Azuchi-Momoyama period, the cloth became widely worn to absorb sweat off the skin after a bath.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since around the Azuchi-Momoyama period, the cloth became widely worn to absorb sweat off the skin after a bath.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>これが江戸時代に入って庶民の愛好する衣類の一種となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Edo Period, it evolved to be a kind of clothes favorably worn by common people.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Edo period, it evolved into a kind of clothing favorably worn by common people.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Edo period, it evolved into a kind of clothing favorably worn by common people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>「ゆかた」の名は「ゆかたびら」の略である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term &quot;yukata&quot; is an abbreviation of &quot;yukatabira&quot; (a light garment used for bathing in the Heian Period).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term &quot;yukata&quot; is an abbreviation of &quot;yukatabira&quot; (a light garment used for bathing in the Heian period).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term &apos;yukata&apos; is an abbreviation of &apos;yukatabira&apos;.</e>
<cmt>既出単語の説明削除&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>通常は木綿地の単衣物で、和服の中で最も単純かつ基本的な構造となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Usually, yukata is an unlined cotton garment of the simplest and the most basic structure.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Usually, the yukata is an unlined cotton garment of the simplest, most basic structure.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Usually, the yukata is an unlined cotton garment of the simplest, most basic structure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>このため戦後のある時期まで家庭 (教科)の授業では浴衣を縫うことが多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this reason, yukata-making was often a subject of home economics lesson at primary schools until sometime in the postwar period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this reason, yukata-making was often a subject of home economics lesson at primary schools until sometime in the postwar period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For this reason, yukata-making was often a subject of home economics lesson at primary schools until sometime in the postwar period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>着用の場合には、本来は素肌の上に直接着るものとされており、近年では下着を着用することが多くなったが、それでも和装用スリップや肌襦袢程度である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under normal circumstances, yukata is supposed to be worn direct to the skin, but, in these years, many people put on yukata on underwear which is, however, no more than an underslip for kimono or hadajuban (an undershirt with tie strings to be worn beneath kimono).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under normal circumstances, the yukata is supposed to be worn direct to the skin, but nowadays many people put on yukata as underwear which is, however, no more than an underslip for kimono or hadajuban (an undershirt with tie strings to be worn beneath the kimono).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under normal circumstances, the yukata is supposed to be worn direct to the skin, but nowadays many people put on underwear which is, however, no more than an underslip for kimono or hadajuban (an undershirt with tie strings to be worn beneath the kimono) underneath the yukata.</e>
<cmt>ＮＣ訳は原文と異なるのでオリジナル訳に戻し一部変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>生地が薄く、開放的で風通しがよいことから、もっぱら夏場や湯上り、あるいは寝巻きとしての用途が主である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of its thin fabrics, and open and airy construction, yukata is mostly worn in summer season, or after a bath, or as night clothes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of its thin fabric and its open, airy construction, the yukata is mostly worn in summer season, after a bath or as nighttime clothing.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of its thin fabric and its open, airy construction, the yukata is mostly worn in summer season, after a bath or as nighttime clothing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>また、男子は三尺帯、女子は半幅帯で着るのが古風であるが、明治以降兵児帯（へこおび）が流行したこともあって、これを用いることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a conservative style for men to wear sanjaku-obi (a short waistband) and for women to wear hanhaba-obi (a half-width waistband), but heko-obi (an undress belt) may also be put on because it was once popularly worn after the Meiji Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It&apos;s a conservative style for men to wear sanjaku-obi (a short waistband) and for women to wear hanhaba-obi (a half-width waistband), but heko-obi (an non-dress belt) may also be put on because it was once popularly worn after the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It&apos;s a conservative style for men to wear sanjaku-obi (a short waistband) and for women to wear hanhaba-obi (a half-width waistband), but heko-obi (an non-dress belt) may also be put on because it was once popularly worn after the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>さらに最近では男子は角帯を用いることも多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore in these days, many men tend to put on kaku-obi (a stiff sash for men) on yukata.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, nowadays many men tend to add a kaku-obi (a stiff sash for men) to the yukata.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, nowadays many men tend to add a kaku-obi (a stiff sash for men) to the yukata.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>角帯は元来浴衣には合わせないものとされていたが、この意識は薄れつつあるように見受けられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kakuobi was originally regarded unsuitable for yukata, but this idea seems now receding.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kakuobi was originally regarded as unsuitable for yukata, but it seems this idea is receding.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaku-obi was originally regarded as unsuitable for yukata, but it seems this idea is receding.</e>
<cmt>角帯は他と合わせてハイフンを入れました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>事実、浴衣と角帯のセットで販売されることも珍しくない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In fact, it is not uncommon to offer yukata and heko-obi in one set.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In fact, it&apos;s fairly common to offer yukata and heko-obi in one set.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact, it&apos;s fairly common to offer yukata and haku-obi in one set.</e>
<cmt>heko→kaku</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="17">
<j>浴衣に合わせる履物は、素足に下駄が一般的である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most popular footwear for yukata is a pair of wooden clogs for bare feet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The most popular footwear for yukata is a pair of wooden clogs for bare feet.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The most popular footwear for yukata is a pair of wooden clogs for bare feet.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>浴衣と下駄はセットでも販売されているが、もちろん下駄は好みのデザイン・鼻緒でよい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although yukata and wooden clogs are sold in one set, it is possible, of course, to select any clogs with thongs of your favorite color and design.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although yukata and wooden clogs are sold in one set, it is possible, of course, to select any clogs with thongs of your favorite color and design.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although yukata and wooden clogs are sold in one set, it is possible, of course, to select any clogs with thongs of your favorite color and design.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>最近では浴衣に足袋をはいて草履や雪駄を履くこともしばしば見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Recently, you may often see people wearing yukata with tabi (Japanese digitated socks) and zori (Japanese sandals) or setta (Japanese sandals with leather soles).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Recently, you may often see people wearing yukata with tabi (Japanese digitated socks) and zori (Japanese sandals) or setta (Japanese sandals with leather soles).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Recently, you may often see people wearing yukata with tabi (Japanese digitated socks) and zori (Japanese sandals) or setta (Japanese sandals with leather soles).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>さらにはビーチサンダルや洋服用のサンダルを合わせる人もいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, some people in yukata are also found even with beach sandals or with sandals for western clothes.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, some people in yukata are also found even with beach sandals or with sandals for Western clothing.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, some people in yukata are also found even with beach sandals or with sandals for Western clothing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="21">
<j>元来が略装の最たるものであるから、浴衣で出かけられるのは気取らない場所にかぎり、この格好で人と会うのは失礼とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because yukata has been the utmost casual wear from the beginning and it is regarded as impolite if you wear yukata and meet others, any place where you can go in yukata is limited to very candid spaces.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because the yukata has been the utmost casual wear from the beginning and it&apos;s regarded as impolite if one wears yukata to meet others, one can only wear a yukata to the most casual places.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because the yukata has been the utmost casual wear from the beginning and it&apos;s regarded as impolite if one wears yukata to meet others, one can only wear a yukata to the most casual places.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>ただし現在では和装そのものが稀になりつつあることもあり、こうしたしきたりをあまり感じない人も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, at present, many people are not very conscious of such yukata-related customs, partly because kimono-style itself is becoming rare.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, however, many people aren&apos;t very conscious of such yukata-related customs, partly because the kimono style itself is becoming rare.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, however, many people aren&apos;t very conscious of such yukata-related customs, partly because the kimono style itself is becoming rare.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>むしろ、夏の祭りなどの行事に浴衣をわざわざ着て行く以外に、習慣として和服を着る機会が少なくなっている現在、浴衣の着る機会の多い若い女性を中心に、浴衣は略装であるという感覚も失われつつある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also because of today&apos;s fewer opportunity to wear wafuku (Japanese traditional clothes) on a regular basis except for summer festivals and other events where you wear yukata purposely, yukata is no longer being considered even as informal wear largely by young women with comparatively frequent chances to wear yukata among others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, because there are fewer opportunities to wear wafuku (Japanese traditional clothing) on a regular basis except for summer festivals and other events where one would intentionally wear yukata, it&apos;s no longer being considered even as informal wear largely by young women with comparatively frequent chances to wear yukata, among others.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, because there are fewer opportunities to wear wafuku on a regular basis except for summer festivals and other events where one would intentionally wear yukata, it&apos;s no longer being considered even as informal wear largely by young women with comparatively frequent chances to wear yukata, among others.</e>
<cmt>既出単語の説明削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="24">
<j>現代の日本の生活で浴衣が用いられるのは、主に花火・縁日・盆踊りなどの夏の行事である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the modern life in Japan, people wear yukata primarily for such occasions as fireworks, temple festivals, Bon festival dances and other summer events.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the modern life in Japan, people wear yukata primarily for such occasions as fireworks, temple festivals, Bon festival dances and other summer events.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the modern life in Japan, people wear yukata primarily for such occasions as fireworks, temple festivals, Bon festival dances and other summer events.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>また温泉街では浴衣を着て下駄を履くのが雰囲気を出すのに重要として、浴衣着用を前提としたまちづくりをしてあるところもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some hot-spring resort areas are making their own development plans on the premise of wearing yukata and geta (Japanese wooden clogs), which they acknowledge as an important factor to create an atmosphere of hot-springs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some hot-spring resort areas are making their own development plans on the premise of wearing yukata and geta (Japanese wooden clogs), which they acknowledge as an important element in creating a &quot;hot springs&quot; atmosphere.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some hot-spring resort areas are making their own development plans on the premise of wearing yukata and geta, which they acknowledge as an important element in creating a &quot;hot springs&quot; atmosphere.</e>
<cmt>既出単語の説明削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>浴衣は色鮮やかで、下駄も音が好まれるため、祭り、温泉とも華やかな雰囲気になるとして、浴衣・下駄着用前提の取り組みは増えつつある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bright colors of yukata and pattering sounds of geta (wooden clogs) are most liked as they produce a gorgeous atmosphere of festivals and hot springs, under which acknowledgement people are increasing their involvement in their towns&apos; development plans on the premise of wearing yukata and geta.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bright colors of yukata and pattering sounds of geta (wooden clogs) are most liked, as they produce a gorgeous atmosphere of festivals and hot springs, under which acknowledgment people are increasing their involvement in their towns&apos; development plans on the premise of wearing yukata and geta.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bright colors of yukata and pattering sounds of geta are most liked, as they produce a gorgeous atmosphere of festivals and hot springs, under which acknowledgment people are increasing their involvement in their towns&apos; development plans on the premise of wearing yukata and geta.</e>
<cmt>既出単語の説明削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>デパートや商業施設、観光関係やサービス業の従業員など夏の制服として着用する例も多くなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also increasing are the cases where employees of department stores and other commercial establishments, tourism and other entertainment services began to wear yukata as their uniform for summer season.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also increasing are cases where the employees of department stores and other commercial establishments, tourism and entertainment services are beginning to wear yukata as a uniform for the summer season.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also increasing are cases where the employees of department stores and other commercial establishments, tourism and entertainment services are beginning to wear yukata as a uniform for the summer season.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>近年女性用ではミニスカートのように裾が膝より高いタイプも存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Recent years, some yukata are with hems positioned higher than knees, like mini skirts..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In recent years, some yukata have hems above the knee, like a miniskirt.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In recent years, some yukata have hems above the knee, like a miniskirt.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="29">
<j>最近では、温泉街や祭りなどを鮮やかにするため、みんなで気軽に浴衣姿になってもらおうと努力している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Lately, in order to brighten hot-spring areas and festivals, people are encouraged to wear yukata without constraint.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Lately, in order to brighten hot-spring areas and festivals, people are encouraged to wear yukata without constraint.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Lately, in order to brighten hot-spring areas and festivals, people are encouraged to wear yukata without constraint.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>そのため、旅館で宿泊客に浴衣と下駄を貸し出したりプレゼントする、観光施設で浴衣を貸し出すところも出ている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this purpose, some ryokan (Japanese style hotels) are lending or presenting yukata and geta to their guests, and some tourist facilities are lending them out, too.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this purpose, some ryokan (Japanese-style hotels) are lending or presenting yukata and geta to their guests, and some tourist facilities are lending them out too.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For this purpose, some ryokan (Japanese-style hotels) are lending or presenting yukata and geta to their guests, and some tourist facilities are lending them out too.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>このように、浴衣は人気があり、浴衣が温泉地の一種のリゾートウェアとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, yukata has become popular as a kind of resort wear in hot-spring areas.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the yukata has become popular as a kind of resort wear in hot-spring areas.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the yukata has become popular as a kind of resort wear in hot-spring areas.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="32">
<j>また日本独特の風習として、旅館やホテルに寝巻きとして客用の浴衣が用意してある場合が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, many of ryokan and hotels prepare yukata for their guests as nightclothes, which is an unique custom in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, many ryokan and hotels prepare yukata for their guests as night clothing, which is a unique custom in Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, many ryokan and hotels prepare yukata for their guests as night clothing, which is a unique custom in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="33">
<j>また、日本舞踊などのお稽古着として使用されることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, yukata may be used as practice wear of nihon-buyo (classical Japanese dance).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, yukata may be used as practice wear for nihon-buyo (classical Japanese dance).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, yukata may be used as practice wear for nihon-buyo (classical Japanese dance).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="34">
<j>浴衣はもともと白地の木綿をアイ (植物)で染抜くのが原則で、柄も大胆なものが多かった（右図参照）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally, yukata was made principally of indigo-dyed plain cotton cloth leaving undyed patterns.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally, the yukata was made principally of indigo-dyed plain cotton cloth in which undyed patterns were left.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally, the yukata was made principally of indigo-dyed plain cotton cloth in which undyed patterns were left and daring patterns were laid on the yukata (see the picture on the right.)</e>
<cmt>（右図参照）等、この文章に入るべきものが次の文頭にきているため、原文どおりこの文末に追記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>近年では和服を着る唯一の機会が浴衣ということも多くなり、華やかな色合いと柄のものなど多様化してきている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, daring patterns were laid on yukata as shown in the right picture, but in recent years they are diversified into various gorgeous colors and designs since yukata offers the only chance to wear traditional Japanese clothes in many cases.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, daring patterns were laid on the yukata (as shown in the picture on the right), but in recent years they have diversified into various gorgeous colors and designs because, in many cases, yukata offers the only chance to wear traditional Japanese clothing.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But in recent years they have diversified into various gorgeous colors and designs because, in many cases, yukata offers the only chance to wear traditional Japanese clothing.</e>
<cmt>文頭の部分に訂正を加えて前文に移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>生地も、浴衣本来の木綿ではなく、麻 (繊維)を混ぜたものやポリエステルなどを用いたものも多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many of yukata fabrics have also changed from cotton as of original yukata to those containing hemp and polyester.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many of the yukata fabrics have also changed from cotton, as of original yukata, to those containing hemp and polyester.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many of the yukata fabrics have also changed from cotton, as of original yukata, to those containing hemp and polyester.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>浴衣の多様化によって、かつては一目瞭然であった浴衣以外の着物との境界は極めて曖昧になっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Diversification of yukata has made the boundary between yukata and other clothes indistinct.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The dDiversification of yukata has made the boundary between yukata and other clothing less distinct.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The diversification of yukata has made the boundary between yukata and other clothing less distinct.</e>
<cmt>dDiversification→diversification</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>柄によってはひとえの着物として着用できるものも現れている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, some yukata may be worn as unlined kimono, depending on their patterns.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, some yukata may be worn as unlined kimono, depending on their patterns.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, some yukata may be worn as unlined kimono, depending on their patterns.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="39">
<j>和服のなかでは比較的安価であることから、別誂えの反物を染めて歌舞伎役者などが贔屓への配りものとすることも多かったが、最近ではこうした風習も徐々に少なくなりつつある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since yukata is comparatively inexpensive among Japanese clothes, kabuki players used to present to their patrons specially ordered rolls of dyed cloth for yukata, although such custom has recently been gradually decreasing in frequency.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because the yukata is comparatively inexpensive among the various kinds of Japanese clothing, kabuki players used to present to their patrons specially ordered rolls of dyed cloth for yukata, although in recent years that custom has become less frequently employed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because the yukata is comparatively inexpensive among the various kinds of Japanese clothing, kabuki players used to present to their patrons specially ordered rolls of dyed cloth for yukata, although in recent years that custom has become less frequently employed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>角界にはまだかろうじて、関取が自分の名前の入った浴衣生地を贔屓筋や他の相撲部屋に贈るという風習が残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the world of sumo (Japanese style wrestling), there still remain by a narrow margin such custom as ranking wrestlers present specially ordered cloth for yukata with their names printed on it to their patrons and to other sumo stables.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the world of sumo (Japanese-style wrestling), there remain by a narrow margin such customs as ranking wrestlers present specially ordered cloth for yukata, imprinted with their names, to their patrons and other sumo stables.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the world of sumo (Japanese-style wrestling), there remain by a narrow margin such customs as ranking wrestlers present specially ordered cloth for yukata, imprinted with their names, to their patrons and other sumo stables.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>もちろん、自分の気に入った柄で、オリジナルな浴衣を仕立てる力士もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Of course, some of the wrestlers may specially order to make up their original yukata using the cloths of their favorite patterns.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Of course, some of the wrestlers may specially order their original yukata using cloth in their favorite patterns.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Of course, some of the wrestlers may specially order their original yukata using cloth in their favorite patterns.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>ちなみに関取か否かを問わず、現役力士は浴衣が正装であり、浴衣を着ずに外出してはならない規定がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By the way, there is a regulation that no wrestler at work, whether a ranking wrestler or not, may go out without yukata which is a formal attire for sumo wrestlers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By the way, there is a regulation that no wrestler at work, whether a ranking wrestler or not, may go out without yukata, which is formal attire for sumo wrestlers.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By the way, there is a regulation that no wrestler at work, whether a ranking wrestler or not, may go out without yukata, which is formal attire for sumo wrestlers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="43">
<j>乞巧奠（きっこうてん）の慣習と織女祭に因み、日本ゆかた連合会により7月7日がゆかたの日と制定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nippon Yukata Rengokai (literally, a Joint Association of Japanese Yukata Industry) instituted the day of yukata on July 7 after the custom of Tanabata Star Festival (the festival of weavers) and Shokujo-sai (the festival for female weavers).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nippon Yukata Rengokai (literally, the Joint Association of the Japanese Yukata Industry) instituted the day of yukata on July 7 after the custom of the Tanabata Star Festival (the festival of weavers) and Shokujo-sai (the festival for female weavers).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nippon Yukata Rengokai (literally, the Joint Association of the Japanese Yukata Industry) instituted the day of yukata on July 7 after the custom of the Tanabata Star Festival (the festival of weavers) and Shokujo-sai (the festival for female weavers).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="44">
<j>着付けも普通の和服に比べて比較的安易で、かつ安価であることから、民族衣装として、手頃なお土産物や通販などで外国人にも人気がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since yukata is easier in wearing compared with the other kimono-wearing, in addition to being inexpensive to buy, yukata is enjoying high popularity among foreigners, too, as an ethnic costume and a reasonable souvenir or an article for mail order.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because the yukata is easier to wear than other kimono clothing, in addition to being inexpensive, it enjoys high popularity among foreigners as an ethnic costume and a reasonable souvenir or an article for mail order.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because the yukata is easier to wear than other kimono clothing, in addition to being inexpensive, it enjoys high popularity among foreigners as an ethnic costume and a reasonable souvenir or an article for mail order.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>そしてもちろん、日本人に現在も愛され続ける伝統文化の一つである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And, needless to say, it is one of the traditional Japanese cultures being loved for ever by all Japanese people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Needless to say, it&apos;s one of the traditional Japanese cultures that will forever be loved by Japanese people.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Needless to say, it is one of the traditional Japanese cultures that have been loved by Japanese people.</e>
<cmt>後半部分が原文と異なるため訂正しました。it&apos;s→it is</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 ととりん(id:31982), Nnh(id:474), Eno(id:18745), Suemi(id:34711), Eskimbot(id:29676), Complex01(id:10454), PixelBot(id:166734), MIO(id:31681), Syrotyna(id:21563), Meisen(id:200991), Mishika(id:276), Mayo(id:23467), Dusk00(id:48236), Synthebot(id:123032), Vina-iwbot(id:56449), Hashar(id:3639), Xqbot(id:273540), たぬき(id:27723), Hana-p(id:133035), SuisuiBot(id:10165), Fromm(id:71291), Goki(id:7107), ミナ(id:71704), Almabot(id:280069), Rei-bot(id:94097), TheMPD(id:17762), Bit(id:2197), Louperibot(id:128971), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>