<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>花輪違</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hanawachigai</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hanawachigai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hanawachigai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>花輪違（はなわちがい）とは、日本の家紋である輪違紋の一種。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hanawachigai is a kind of Wachigai-mon which is a Japanese family crest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hanawachigai is a type of wachigai-mon (emblem with geometric design), which is a Japanese family crest.</e>
<cmt>&quot;kind&quot; replaced with &quot;type&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hanawachigai is a type of wachigai-mon (emblem with geometric design), which is a Japanese family crest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>「七宝輪違（しっぽうわちがい）」「十方七宝（じっぽうしっぽう）」「玉輪違（たまわちがい）」ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called &apos;Shippo wachigai&apos;, &apos;Jippo Shippo&apos;, or &apos;Tamawachigai&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called &quot;shippo wachigai&quot; (&quot;seven treasures&quot; wachigai), &quot;jippo shippo&quot; (ten directions, seven treasures) or &quot;tamawachigai.&quot;</e>
<cmt>commas and period placed within the quotation marks, &quot;shippo&quot; and &quot;jippo&quot; explanations added</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called &quot;shippo wachigai&quot; (&quot;seven treasures&quot; wachigai), &quot;jippo shippo&quot; (ten directions, seven treasures) or &quot;tamawachigai.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>七宝の中に花角を入れたもので、七宝紋の「七宝に花角（しっぽうにはなかく）」と同一の紋である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a pattern of Hanakaku placed in the center of Shippo, and the same pattern as Shppo with Hanakaku, a kind of Shippo-mon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a design made of hanakaku (a flower design) placed in the center of shippo (a geometrical design with circles intersecting a circular frame), and it is identical to &quot;shippo ni hanakaku&quot; (shippo with hanakaku) crest.</e>
<cmt>sentence reworded, &quot;pattern&quot; は「繰り返される」 という意味が含まれているので &quot;design&quot; に変えました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a design made of hanakaku (a flower design) placed in the center of shippo (a geometrical design with circles intersecting a circular frame), and it is identical to &quot;shippo ni hanakaku&quot; (shippo with hanakaku) crest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>元は大陸から伝来た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was originally introduced into Japan from the (Asian) continent, then extracted from Yusoku pattern named &apos;Wachigai&apos;, which repeates motifs like a chain, and used as Kuruma-mon (pattern of a wheel) in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was originally introduced to Japan from the (Asian) continent.</e>
<cmt>OK, 一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was originally introduced to Japan from the (Asian) continent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>有職の「輪違い」という鎖型に連続した文様から抜き取られたもので、平安時代には車紋として用いられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was isolated from &quot;wachigai,&quot; which is a chain-like yusoku design pattern (traditional design motifs of court nobles), and used as kuruma-mon (pattern of wheels or rings) in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>sentence reworded, 一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was isolated from &quot;wachigai,&quot; which is a chain-like yusoku design pattern (traditional design motifs of court nobles), and used as kuruma-mon (pattern of wheels or rings) in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>江戸時代以降、2つの輪を交叉させた文様を特に「輪違」と呼ぶようになったため、それと区別する意味で「唐花の入った輪違」という形状から「花輪違」というようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Edo period, patterns with two wheels intersected one another were especially called &apos;Wachigai&apos;, therefore, &apos;Wachigai pattern with kara-hana (a kind of Chinese arabesque pattern) &apos; came to be called &apos;Hanawachigai&apos;.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the Edo period, designs with two intersecting rings were specifically called &quot;wachigai,&quot; and therefore, &quot;wachigai pattern with kara-hana (Chinese arabesque pattern)&quot; came to be called &quot;hanawachigai.&quot;</e>
<cmt>sentence reworded</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the Edo period, designs with two intersecting rings were specifically called &quot;wachigai,&quot; and therefore, &quot;wachigai pattern with kara-hana (Chinese arabesque pattern)&quot; came to be called &quot;hanawachigai.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>ちなみに、輪違紋と同様の図案である金輪（かなわ）紋は、五徳の輪を図案化したものであり、輪違紋の輪より細く描かれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Incidentally, Kanawa-mon, which resembles Wachigai-mon, depicts a ring part of Gotoku (three or four-legged kettle stand) the line of which is thinner than that of Wachigai-mon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Incidentally, kanawa-mon, which resembles wachigai-mon, is a design based on the circular part of gotoku (three or four-legged kettle stand), and the line used for the design is thinner than that of wachigai-mon.</e>
<cmt>sentence reworded</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Incidentally, kanawa-mon, which resembles wachigai-mon, is a design based on the circular part of gotoku (three or four-legged kettle stand), and the line used for the design is thinner than that of wachigai-mon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>用例</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Examples of Users</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Examples of use</e>
<cmt>&quot;users&quot; changed to &quot;use&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Examples of use</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>出雲源氏佐々木義清が自らの紋としたため、その後裔である、隠岐氏、塩冶氏、佐々木義泰、高岡氏、佐世氏などが用いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Yoshikiyo SASAKI of the Izumo-Genji clan employed Hanawachigai-mon as his family crest, his descendants such as the Oki clan, the Enya clan, Yoshiyasu SASAKI, the Takaoka clan, the Sase clan also used it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Yoshikiyo SASAKI of the Izumo-Genji clan used hanawachigai-mon as his family crest, his descendants such as the Oki clan, the Enya clan, Yoshiyasu SASAKI, the Takaoka clan, and the Sase clan also used it.</e>
<cmt>&quot;employed&quot; changed to &quot;used,&quot; &quot;and&quot; added before &quot;the Sase clan&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Yoshikiyo SASAKI of the Izumo-Genji clan used hanawachigai-mon as his family crest, his descendants such as the Oki clan, the Enya clan, Yoshiyasu SASAKI, the Takaoka clan, and the Sase clan also used it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>また全く別流であるが、高氏の高師直や、秋田城介の嫡流である城氏 (平氏)もこの紋を使用している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">KO no Moronao of the Ko clan and the Jo (Taira) clan, which was the direct descendant of Akita-jo no suke (provincial governor of Akita-jo castle) also used Hanawachigai-mon although their family line were different from those above.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though unrelated to the families above, KO no Moronao of the Ko clan and the Jo (Taira) clan, the direct descendant of Akitajo no suke (provincial governor of Akita-jo castle), also used hanawachigai-mon.</e>
<cmt>sentence reworded</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though unrelated to the families above, KO no Moronao of the Ko clan and the Jo (Taira) clan, the direct descendant of Akitajo no suke (provincial governor of Akita-jo castle), also used hanawachigai-mon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>日向高鍋藩の秋月氏の裏紋もこの紋である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Akizuki clan of Takanabe domain, Hyuga Province also used Hanawachigai-mon as its Ura-mon (secondary family crest used in informal occasions).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Akizuki clan of the Takanabe domain, Hyuga Province, also used hanawachigai-mon as its ura-mon (secondary family crest used at informal occasions).</e>
<cmt>&quot;the&quot; added before &quot;Takanabe domain,&quot; comma added after &quot;Province,&quot; &quot;in&quot; changed to &quot;at&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Akizuki clan of the Takanabe domain, Hyuga Province, also used hanawachigai-mon as its ura-mon (secondary family crest used at informal occasions).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>文様</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">patterns</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Design</e>
<cmt>&quot;pattern&quot; changed to &quot;design&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Design</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>輪違という文様は、幾つもの輪を交差させたものをいい、有職文様では、同様のものを七宝ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wachigai is a pattern of many circles intersected one another, and Yusoku-monyo (traditional design motifs, used either in single units or repeated to create patterns, based on designs from Heian courtly decoration) has a similar pattern called Shippo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wachigai refers to a design that consists of many intersecting circles, and in yusoku-monyo (traditional design motifs, used either in single units or repeated to create patterns, based on designs from Heian courtly decoration) has a similar pattern called shippo.</e>
<cmt>sentence reworded</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wachigai refers to a design that consists of many intersecting circles, and in yusoku-monyo (traditional design motifs, used either in single units or repeated to create patterns, based on designs from Heian courtly decoration) has a similar pattern called shippo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>花輪違の花角を取り除きつなげたものを「七宝つなぎ」という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shippo tsunagi&apos; is made by erasing hanakaku from Hanawachigai motif, and arranging the motifs in rows and columns.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Shippo tsunagi&quot; is a pattern made by removing hanakaku from hanawachigai motif and arranging the motif in a repeating pattern.</e>
<cmt>sentence reworded</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Shippo tsunagi&quot; is a pattern made by removing hanakaku from hanawachigai motif and arranging the motif in a repeating pattern.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>古くは「四方襷（しほうたすき）」という呼び名もあり、その「四方（しほう）」が「七宝（しっぽう）」へと変化したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In ancient times, this motif is said to have been called &apos;Shiho tasuki&apos; then the name changed from &apos;Shiho&apos; to &apos;Shippo&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In ancient times, this motif was called &quot;shiho tasuki&quot; (cross-bracing in four directions) then the name changed from &quot;shiho&quot; (four directions) to &quot;shippo.&quot;</e>
<cmt>sentence reworded, 原文の「四方」とは「四つの方向」という意味だと思います</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In ancient times, this motif was called &quot;shiho tasuki&quot; (cross-bracing in four directions) then the name changed from &quot;shiho&quot; (four directions) to &quot;shippo.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>無限に連鎖する平和や円満を意味する輪の交叉から成る文様のため、「世界中の財宝」と、「無限の子孫繁栄」を表す吉祥文様として家紋・屏風の裏紙の模様などに用いられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Shippo tsunagi is a pattern of repeating motifs of many intersected circles which symbolizes endless peace and hapiness, it is used as patterns of family crests, and backing paper of Byobu (holding screens) as auspicious omens motif, representing &apos;treasures all over the world&apos; and &apos;infinite fertility and family prosperity&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because shippo tsunagi is a pattern of repeating motifs of many intersecting circles that symbolizes endless peace and happiness, it was used as a design of auspicious omen representing &quot;treasures from all over the world&quot; and &quot;infinite fertility and family prosperity,&quot; and it was used in family crests as well as on backing paper of byobu (folding screens).</e>
<cmt>sentence reworded</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because shippo tsunagi is a pattern of repeating motifs of many intersecting circles that symbolizes endless peace and happiness, it was used as a design of auspicious omen representing &quot;treasures from all over the world&quot; and &quot;infinite fertility and family prosperity,&quot; and it was used in family crests as well as on backing paper of byobu (folding screens).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>七宝つなぎの種類は七宝の中央に花を入れたものを「花七宝（はなしっぽう）」、鳥と花菱を組み合わせて七宝形にしたものを「鳥襷（とりだすき）」、幾つかが繋がった形で部分的に用いたものを「破れ七宝（やぶれしっぽう）」という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are several variations of Shippo Tsunagi, such as &apos;Hana Shippo&apos; which is a Shippo pattern with a flower motif in the center, &apos;Toridasuki&apos; which is a Shippo pattern with a combination of birds and Hanabishi motifs, &apos;Yabure Shippo&apos; in which some Shippo motifs are partially arranged and others are missing, and another type of Shippo Tsunagi is called &apos;Hoshi Shippo&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are several variations of shippo tsunagi, such as &quot;hana shippo,&quot; which is a shippo pattern with a flower motif in the center, &quot;toridasuki,&quot; which is a shippo pattern with a combination of birds and hanabishi motifs, and &quot;yabure shippo,&quot; in which the shippo pattern is interrupted.</e>
<cmt>sentence reworded, 一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are several variations of shippo tsunagi, such as &quot;hana shippo,&quot; which is a shippo pattern with a flower motif in the center, &quot;toridasuki,&quot; which is a shippo pattern with a combination of birds and hanabishi motifs, and &quot;yabure shippo,&quot; in which the shippo pattern is interrupted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>ほかに「星七宝（ほししっぽう）」というものもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, a shippo tsunagi pattern called &quot;hoshi shippo&quot; also exists.</e>
<cmt>sentence reworded, 一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, a shippo tsunagi pattern called &quot;hoshi shippo&quot; also exists.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="17">
<j>ちなみに「七宝」とは仏教では、『無量寿経』によると、「金、銀、瑠璃（るり）、玻璃（はり）、シャコ、珊瑚（さんご）、瑪瑙（めのう）の七種の宝」のことで、世界中の財宝を表し、また『法華経』では、「金、銀、瑠璃、真珠、シャコ、マイ瑰（まいかい）、瑪瑙の七種」のことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Muryoju-kyo&quot;(Sutra of Immeasurable Life) of Buddhism, &apos;Shippo&apos; means &apos;seven treasures of gold, silver, lapis lazuli, crystal, squilla, coral, and agate&apos;, which represents treasures of all over the world, and in Hokke-kyo Sutra, they are &apos; gold, silver, lapis lazuli, pearl, squilla,マイ瑰, and agate&apos; however, a connection between this Shippo pattern and the Buddhist term &apos;Shippo&apos; is unknown.</e>
<cmt>マイ瑰→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Muryoju-kyo&quot; (Sutra of Immeasurable Life) in Buddhism, &quot;shippo&quot; means &quot;seven treasures of gold, silver, lapis lazuli, crystal (quartz), giant clamshells, coral, and agate,&quot; which represent treasures from all over the world, and in &quot;Hokke-kyo&quot; (Lotus Sutra), they are &quot;gold, silver, lapis lazuli, pearl, giant clamshell, maikai, and agate.&quot;</e>
<cmt>quotation marks changed from single to double, period and commas placed within the quotation marks, 一原文一訳文の例外対処, マイ瑰→定訳不明, 「シャコ」は &quot;squilla&quot; と訳されてますが、シャコ貝のことだと思われるので、 &quot;giant clamshell&quot; にしておきました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Muryoju-kyo&quot; (Sutra of Immeasurable Life) in Buddhism, &quot;shippo&quot; means &quot;seven treasures of gold, silver, lapis lazuli, crystal (quartz), giant clamshells, coral, and agate,&quot; which represent treasures from all over the world, and in &quot;Hokke-kyo&quot; (Lotus Sutra), they are &quot;gold, silver, lapis lazuli, pearl, giant clamshell, maikai, and agate.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>しかし、この文様と仏教用語の「七宝」との関係については不明である</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the connection between this shippo pattern and the Buddhist term &quot;shippo&quot; is unknown.</e>
<cmt>&quot;a connection&quot; changed to &quot;the connection,&quot; quotation marks changed from single to double, 一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the connection between this shippo pattern and the Buddhist term &quot;shippo&quot; is unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Tajima73(id:243513), 小者(id:172526), ムカイ(id:72972), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>