<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>洛南高等学校・附属中学校</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rakunan High School / Rakuna Junior High School</e>
<cmt>洛南高等学校・附属中学校：http://www.rakunan-h.ed.jp/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rakunan High School / Rakuna Junior High School</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rakunan High School / Rakuna Junior High School</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>洛南高等学校・附属中学校（らくなんこうとうがっこう・ふぞくちゅうがっこう）は、京都市南区 (京都市)にある私立学校中学校・高等学校である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rakunan High School / Rakuna Junior High School are a private junior and senior high school, which located in Minami key, Kyoto city.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rakunan High School and Rakuna Junior High School are respectively private junior and senior high schools located in Minami key, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rakunan High School and Rakunan Junior High School are private junior and senior high schools, respectively, located in Minami-ku, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>洛南のスペル、区の表記を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Outline</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Outline</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>統一用語</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>設置者は、古義真言宗系14本山（仁和寺、宝山寺、朝護孫子寺、勧修寺、大覚寺、醍醐寺、中山寺 (宝塚市)、西大寺 (奈良市)、東寺、清荒神清澄寺、泉涌寺、善通寺、須磨寺及び大本山随心院）が経営に参画し、真言宗智山派、真言宗豊山派及び新義真言宗の3派が教育振興に協力する学校法人真言宗京都学園。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Organizers were Kogi Shingon Shukei 14 Honzan (Ninna-ji Temple, Hozan-ji Temple, Chogosonshi-ji Temple, Kaju-ji Temple, Daikaku-ji Temple, Daigo-ji Temple, Nakayama-dera Temple (Takarazuka city), Saidai-ji Temple (Nara city), To-ji Temple, Kiyoshikojin Seicho-ji Temple, Sennyu-ji Temple, Zentsu-ji Temple, Suma-dera Temple and Daihonzan Zuishin-in Temple), these temples runs school, and three sects which is Chisan Sect of Shingon, Buzan Sect of Shingon and New Shingon corporate with educational promotion for Gakkohojin Shingon-shu Kyoto Gakuen.</e>
<cmt>古義真言宗：http://www.eudict.com/?lang=engjpk&amp;word=Kogi%20Shingon%20(, 真言宗智山派： http://www.eudict.com/?lang=engjpk&amp;word=Kogi%20Shingon%20(, 真言宗豊山派：http://www.eudict.com/?lang=engjpk&amp;word=Kogi%20Shingon%20(, 新義真言宗： 定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The organizers were Kogi Shingon Shukei 14 Honzan (Ninna-ji Temple, Hozan-ji Temple, Chogosonshi-ji Temple, Kaju-ji Temple, Daikaku-ji Temple, Daigo-ji Temple, Nakayama-dera Temple (Takarazuka City), Saidai-ji Temple (Nara City), To-ji Temple, Kiyoshikojin Seicho-ji Temple, Sennyu-ji Temple, Zentsu-ji Temple, Suma-dera Temple and Daihonzan Zuishin-in Temple); these temples run the school, and three sects (the Chisan Sect of Shingon, the Buzan Sect of Shingon, and New Shingon) cooperate with the program of educational promotion for Gakkohojin Shingon-shu Kyoto Gakuen.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The organizers were Kogi Shingon Shukei 14 Honzan (Ninna-ji Temple, Hozan-ji Temple, Chogosonshi-ji Temple, Kaju-ji Temple, Daikaku-ji Temple, Daigo-ji Temple, Nakayama-dera Temple (Takarazuka City), Saidai-ji Temple (Nara City), To-ji Temple, Kiyoshikojin Seicho-ji Temple, Sennyu-ji Temple, Zentsu-ji Temple, Suma-dera Temple and Daihonzan Zuishin-in Temple); these temples run the school, and three sects (the Chisan Sect of Shingon, the Buzan Sect of Shingon, and New Shingon) cooperate with the program of educational promotion for Gakkohojin Shingon-shu Kyoto Gakuen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>学校は東寺の境内にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The school located inside of To-ji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The school is located in To-ji.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The school is located in To-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>Templeを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>正式名称は「洛南高等学校」および「洛南高等学校附属中学校」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Official Name is &apos;Rakunan High School&apos; and &apos;Junior High School of Rakunan High School&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The official names are &apos;Rakunan High School&apos; and &apos;Junior High School of Rakunan High School&apos;</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The official names are &apos;Rakunan High School&apos; and &apos;Junior High School of Rakunan High School&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>同じ学校法人が経営する大学として種智院大学がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Same educational foundation runs Shuchiin University as four years college.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The same educational foundation runs Shuchiin University as a four-year college.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The same educational foundation runs Shuchiin University as a four-year college.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>種々の学校改革を断行し、1980年代より急激に大学進学実績を伸長させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They carried out various school reforms, and their achievements of number of student who goes to university increased in 1980&apos;s.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They carried out various school reforms, and in the 1980s they achieved record numbers of students who went on to the university level.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They carried out various school reforms, and in the 1980s they achieved record numbers of students who went on to the university level.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>また、バスケットボールやバレーボール、体操、陸上競技、吹奏楽などの部活動も盛んである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And the school activity is also very active which are basketball club, volleyball club track and field club and brass band.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The school offers many activities, including the basketball club, volleyball club, track-and-field club and brass band.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The school offers many activities, including a basketball club, a volleyball club, a track-and-field club and a brass band.</e>
<cmt>文法が不自然。 &apos;the&apos; を &apos;a&apos; に変え、すべてのクラブ名に関しても &apos;a&apos;を加えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>長らく男子校であったが、平成18年から男女共学になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">School had been a boy&apos;s school for a long time, but in 2006, reorganized as a coeducational school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It had been a boys&apos; school for a long time, but in 2006 it was reorganized as a coeducational school.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It had been a boys&apos; school for a long time, but in 2006 it was reorganized as a coeducational school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>将来は附属小学校も設置する計画がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Planning to establish an elementary school which attached to a university in the future.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The plan for the future was to establish an elementary school attached to a university.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The plan for the future was to establish an elementary school attached to a university.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>III類（内部進学）、III類（高校入学）、I類一般、I類推薦（スポーツ・吹奏楽等）などで別々のクラスとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">III class (candidate from Rakunan junior high school), III class (candidate from other junior high school), I class scholarship (sports, brass band) etc. separated to each class.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Class III (candidate from Rakunan junior high school), class III class (candidate from other junior high school), class I scholarship (sports, brass band), etc., separated into each class.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Class III (candidate from Rakunan Junior High School), class III (candidate from another junior high school), class I general, class I scholarship (sports, brass band), etc., with students separated by class.</e>
<cmt>I類一般を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>近年、III類（内部進学）には高校受験で若干の編入がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Recently, II class (candidate from Rakunan junior high school) has some transferred students by high school entrance examination.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Recently, class II (candidates from Rakunan junior high school) has received some transferred students as a result of the high school entrance examination.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Recently, class III (candidates from Rakunan junior high school) has received transferred students as a result of the high school entrance examination.</e>
<cmt>数字を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>校章</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">School badge</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">School emblem</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">School emblem</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="12">
<j>毘沙門亀甲</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bishamon Kikko</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bishamon Kikko</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bishamon Kikko</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>校訓</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">School precepts</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">School precepts</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">School precepts</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="13">
<j>自己を尊重せよ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Respect yourself</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Respect yourself</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Respect yourself</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="14">
<j>真理を探究せよ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Search for the truth</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Search for the truth</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Search for the truth</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="15">
<j>社会に献身せよ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Contribute to the society</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Contribute to society</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Contribute to society</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>沿革</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>Background?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Background</e>
<cmt>クエスチョンマークを削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="16">
<j>洛南高等学校は、空海が平安時代の828年（天長5年）に庶民教育のために設立した綜芸種智院に端を発するとしているが、綜芸種智院は空海の死後、廃れ、廃された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rakunan High School is founded by Kukai in 828 in Heian period which started in Syugeisyuchiin for education for citizen, but Shugei Shuchiin disgraced and closed after Kukai&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rakunan High School was founded by Kukai in 828, during the Heian period, having started in Syugeisyuchiin for the education of citizens; however, Shugei Shuchiin was eventually disgraced and closed after Kukai&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rakunan High School was founded by Kukai in 828, during the Heian period, having started in Shugei Shuchiin for the education of citizens; however, Shugei Shuchiin was eventually disgraced and closed after Kukai&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>綜芸種智院のスペルを統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>現在の洛南高校の源流は、1881年（明治14年）、明治の真言僧である釈雲照が真言宗の教育機関として設立した総黌である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The origin of Rakunan High School is Soko which established as educational organization for Singon-syu in 1881 (Meiji period 14) by SHAKU Unsho who was priest of Shingon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The origin of Rakunan High School is Soko, which was established as an educational organization for Singon-syu in 1881 (Meiji period 14) by SHAKU Unsho, who was priest of Shingon.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The origin of Rakunan High School is Soko, which was established in 1881 (Meiji 14) by SHAKU Unsho, a priest of Shingon, as an educational organization for Shingon-shu.</e>
<cmt>真言宗のスペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>総黌は幾多の変遷を経て、戦前の高等教育機関の真言宗京都専門学校及び中等教育機関の東寺中等学校の両学となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soko had changed several times, and became prewar high educational organization of Shingon-shu Kyoto Senmon Gakko (Shingon-shu Kyoto Technical School) and junior educational organization of To-ji Chuto Gakko (To-ji Middle School).</e>
<cmt>真言宗京都専門学校：定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soko had changed several times, becoming a prewar high educational organization of Shingon-shu Kyoto Senmon Gakko (Shingon-shu Kyoto Technical School) and a junior educational organization of To-ji Chuto Gakko (To-ji Middle School).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soko had changed several times, becoming a prewar high educational organization of Shingon-shu Kyoto Senmon Gakko (Shingon-shu Kyoto Technical School) and a junior educational organization of To-ji Chuto Gakko (To-ji Middle School).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>戦後、新学制の下、真言宗京都学園が設立した東寺高等学校が直接の前身である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the war, under new educational system, To-ji Kotogakko (To-ji Senior High School) established by Shingon-shu Kyoto Gakuen which became Rakunan High School.</e>
<cmt>東寺高等学校：定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the war, under the new educational system, To-ji Kotogakko (To-ji Senior High School), established by Shingon-shu Kyoto Gakuen, became Rakunan High School.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the war, under the new educational system, To-ji Kotogakko (To-ji Senior High School), established by Shingon-shu Kyoto Gakuen, became Rakunan High School.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="20">
<j>1960年代（昭和30年代後半）、底辺校として不良の溜まり場になっていた東寺高校に対して、当時の副校長三浦俊良らが中心になって学校内の改革を決断。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1960, Toji High School became a lower ranked school where the bad students were assembled, Shunryo MIURA, the vice principal took the lead and decided to reform the school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1960, Toji High School became a lower-ranked school to which poor students were assembled, but Shunryo MIURA, the vice principal, took the lead and decided to reform the school.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1960, Toji High School became a lower-ranked school to which poor students were sent, but Shunryo MIURA, the vice principal, took the lead in deciding to reform the school.</e>
<cmt>文法間違いと不自然さ ? 変更点： &apos;to which poor students were sent&apos; &apos;took the lead in deciding&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>校名を洛南高等学校と改称するだけでなく、校則を厳しくし不良生徒を退学などの処分を含めて大幅に取り締まり、また特別進学コースを設置して優秀な生徒を集めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">School renamed to Rakunan High School and also made strict school regulations and controlled measures of bad students including withdrew from school, and otherwise made a special academic advancement course to gathered intelligence students.</e>
<cmt>特別進学コース:定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The school was renamed as Rakunan High School, enacting strict school regulations and control measures for poor students, including withdrawal from school, but otherwise it instituted a special academic advancement course designed to attract intelligent students.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The school was renamed as Rakunan High School, enacting strict school regulations and control measures for poor students, including withdrawal from school, but otherwise it instituted a special academic advancement course designed to attract intelligent students.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>改革後の洛南高等学校は、風紀は堅く守られ、又、学問、スポーツともに成績全国トップクラスの進学校として生まれ変わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After all reforms, students obey the school discipline, Rakunan High School became a high ranked school which is well educated and also has great sports teams.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After all the reforms, students began to obey the code of school discipline and Rakunan High School became a high-ranked school in terms of its educational offering and sports teams.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After all the reforms, students began to obey the code of school discipline and Rakunan High School became a high-ranked school in terms of its educational offering and sports teams.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>21世紀になって緩くなったとはいえ、洛南高校は校則が厳しいことで知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rakunan High School has known to have strict school regulations even it got lax in 21 century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rakunan High School has long been known for its strict school regulations, even though it has become more lax in the twenty-first century.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rakunan High School has long been known for its strict school regulations, even though it has become more lax in the twenty-first century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>同様に底辺校から急成長した例として東大寺学園とよく比較される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also often compared with Todai-ji Gakuen this is also known as a fast growing school from lower rank.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though often compared with Todai-ji Gakuen, it is also known as a fast-growing school from the lower rank.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though often compared with Todai-ji Gakuen, it is also known as a fast-growing school from the lower rank.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>現在では京都一の受験難易度と認知されている学校へと変わっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Now, school has changed into the well known as a most difficult school to get requirements for admission in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today the school is well known as a most difficult school in terms of the requirements for admission in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today the school is well known as a most difficult school in terms of the requirements for admission in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>年表</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chronology</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chronology</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Timeline</e>
<cmt>スポットチェックによる統一</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="26">
<j>1881年（明治14年） - 総黌創立</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1881: Soko was established</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1881: Soko was established.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1881: Soko was established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>1902年（明治35年） -　私立古義真言宗聯合高等中学校に改称</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1902: Renamed Shiritsu Kogi Shingon-shu Sogo Koto Chugakko (Private Kogi Shingon-shu Sogo Higher Middle School)</e>
<cmt>私立古義真言宗聯合高等中学校：定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1902: It was renamed as Shiritsu Kogi Shingon-shu Sogo Koto Chugakko (Private Kogi Shingon-shu Sogo Higher Middle School).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1902: It was renamed as Shiritsu Kogi Shingon-shu Sogo Koto Chugakko (Private Kogi Shingon-shu Sogo Higher Middle School).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>1917年（大正6年） - 真言宗京都大学(後の種智院大学)・真言宗京都中学に分離改称</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1917: Divided to two schools and renamed Shingon-shu Kyoto University (became Syuchiin University) and Shingon-shu Kyoto Middle School</e>
<cmt>真言宗京都大学：定訳不明、真言宗京都中学：定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1917: It was divided into two schools and renamed Shingon-shu Kyoto University (which became Syuchiin University) and Shingon-shu Kyoto Middle School.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1917: It was divided into two schools and renamed Shingon-shu Kyoto University (which became Syuchiin University) and Shingon-shu Kyoto Middle School.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>1926年（大正15年） - 真言宗京都中学は東寺中学校に改称</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1926: Shingon-shu Kyoto Middle School renamed to To-ji Middle School</e>
<cmt>東寺中学校：定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1926: Shingon-shu Kyoto Middle School was renamed as To-ji Middle School.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1926: Shingon-shu Kyoto Middle School was renamed as To-ji Middle School.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>1948年（昭和23年） - 東寺高等学校に改称</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1948: Renamed To-ji Senior High School</e>
<cmt>東寺高学校：定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1948: It was renamed as To-ji Senior High School.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1948: It was renamed as To-ji Senior High School.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>1962年（昭和37年）6月 - 洛南高等学校に改称</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1962 June: Renamed Rakunan High School</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1962, June: It was renamed as Rakunan High School</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1962, June: It was renamed as Rakunan High School.</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>1975年（昭和40年）4月 - 自動車コース、特別進学コース創設</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1975 April: Automobile Course, Special academic advancement course was established</e>
<cmt>自動車コース：定訳不明、特別進学コース:定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1975 April: The automobile course, a special academic advancement course, was established</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1975, April: The automobile course, a special academic advancement course, was established.</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>1978年（昭和53年）4月 - 準特別進学コース創設</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1975 April: Semi-special academic advancement course was established</e>
<cmt>準特別進学コース：定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1975 April: The semi-special academic advancement course was established</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1975, April: The semi-special academic advancement course was established.</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>1982年（昭和57年）4月 - コース呼称変更普通科→I類、普通科（自動車コース）→II類、普通科（特別進学コース・準特別進学コース）→III類（特別進学コース→III類A、準特別進学コース→III類B）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1982 April: Renamed courses General Course - I class, General Course (Automatable course) - II Class, General Course (Special academic advancement course and Semi-special academic advancement course) - III Class (Special academic advancement course - IIIA class, Semi-special academic advancement course - IIIB Class)</e>
<cmt>特別進学コース:定訳不明、準特別進学コース：定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1982 April: Courses were renamed as General Course - I class, General Course (academic course) - II Class, General Course (Special academic advancement course and Semi-special academic advancement course) - III Class (Special academic advancement course - IIIA class and Semi-special academic advancement course - IIIB Class)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1982, April: Courses were renamed as General Course, class I; General Course (Automobile course), class II; General Course (special academic advancement course and semi-special academic advancement course), class III (special academic advancement course, class IIIA, and semi-special academic advancement course, class IIIB).</e>
<cmt>自動車コースに修正しました。ピリオドを補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>1985年（昭和60年）4月 - 洛南高等学校附属中学校開校（2クラス）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1985 April: Junior High School of Rakunan High School (two classes) was opened</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1985 April: The Junior High School of Rakunan High School (two classes) was opened</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1985, April: The Junior High School of Rakunan High School (two classes) was opened.</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>1993年（平成5年）4月 - II類（自動車コース）募集停止</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1993 April: II class (Automobile course) Stop accepting applicants</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1993 April: The II class (automobile course) stopped accepting applicants</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1993, April: The II class (automobile course) stopped accepting applicants.</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>1996年（平成8年）4月 - 洛南高等学校附属中学校2クラス増設</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1996 April: Junior High School of Rakunan High School added two more classes</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1996 April: The Junior High School of Rakunan High School added two more classes</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1996, April: The Junior High School of Rakunan High School added two more classes.</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>2001年（平成13年）4月 - 体育着（夏）がランニングシャツから半袖シャツへの移行が始ま</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">2001 April: Gym class uniform shifted from no sleeve shirts to short sleeve shirts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">2001 April: The gym class uniform shifted from sleeveless shirts to short-sleeve shirts.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">2001 April: The gym class uniform shifted from sleeveless shirts to short-sleeve shirts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>2002年（平成14年）4月 - 洛南高等学校附属中学校5クラスに（1クラス増設）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">2002 April: Junior High School of Rakunan High School became five classes (added one class)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">2002, April: The Junior High School of Rakunan High School became five classes (with the addition of a class).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">2002, April: The Junior High School of Rakunan High School became five classes (with the addition of a class).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>2003年（平成15年）4月 - 皮膚の弱い生徒に配慮し学生服が廃止され、ブレザーの制服（ネクタイは学年ごとに色が違う）への移行が始まる</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">2003 April: abolished school uniform for students who has sensitive skin, started to shift blazer uniform (each grade has different color of tie)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">2003, April: The school uniform was abolished for students with sensitive skin, and the shift to a blazer uniform started (each grade has a different color tie).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">2003, April: The school uniform was abolished for students with sensitive skin, and the shift to a blazer uniform started (each grade has a different color tie).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>2005年（平成17年）4月 - 制服がブレザーに完全移行</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">2005 April: Completely shifted blazer uniform.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">2005, April: It completely shifted to the use of blazer uniforms.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">2005, April: It completely shifted to the use of blazer uniforms.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>2006年（平成18年）4月 - 共学化</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">2006 April: Became an coeducational school</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">2006, April: It became an coeducational school.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">2006, April: It became an coeducational school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="43">
<j>実績</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Achievements</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Achievements</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Achievements</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>大学合格実績</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Result of University examination</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Results of university examinations</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Results of university examinations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="44">
<j>1991年から2008年まで、京都大学合格者数は18年連続全国第1位である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From 1991 to 2008, for 18 years continued to be the number one school that most students passed Kyoto University examination.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For 18 years consecutive years from 1991 to 2008, it had the most students pass the Kyoto University examination.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For 18 years consecutive years from 1991 to 2008, it had the most students pass the Kyoto University examination.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>その他実績</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other results</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other results</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other results</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="45">
<j>バスケットボール部は全国高等学校総合体育大会でここ30年以上京都代表に選出され続け、日本の高校ではトップクラスの1校となっている（ウィンターカップで2年連続、全国制覇）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Basketball team selected to Kyoto team of All Inter-high school championships for more than 30 years, and became one of the top class school (champion of Winter Cup in 2 years)</e>
<cmt>ウィンターカップ：http://wintercup.jabba-net.com/2008/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The basketball team has for more than 30 years been selected to participate as the Kyoto team in the All Inter-High School Championships, and has become one of the top-class schools (having won the Winter Cup in two different years).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The basketball team has for more than 30 years been selected to participate as the Kyoto team in the All Inter-High School Championships, and has become one of the top-class school teams (having won the Winter Cup in two different years).</e>
<cmt>文法修正。「バスケットボール部」が「トップクラスの１校」となったという構成になってしまっているので、「トップクラスの学校チーム」となる様、訂正。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>体操部も大阪の清風中学校・高等学校と実績を二分する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gymnastic team also the one of best team which divided the title with Seifu Junior &amp; Senior High School.</e>
<cmt>清風中学校：http://www.seifu.ac.jp/english/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The gymnastics team, a top squad, shared the title with Seifu Junior &amp; Senior High School.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The gymnastics team, a top squad, shared the title with Seifu Junior &amp; Senior High School, of Osaka.</e>
<cmt>「大阪の」を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>また、国際物理オリンピックの京都初の代表もここの出身である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And also the first representative of Kyoto for International Physics Olympic is also from this school.</e>
<cmt>国際物理オリンピック：http://www.jyu.fi/tdk/kastdk/olympiads/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, the first representative of Kyoto for the International Physics Olympics is from this school.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, the first representative of Kyoto for the International Physics Olympics is from this school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>アクセス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Access</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Access</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Access</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="48">
<j>JR京都駅(八条口)から徒歩15分</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">15 minutes walk from JR Kyoto station (Hachijo Exit)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It&apos;s a 15-minute walk from JR Kyoto Station (Hachijo exit).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It&apos;s a 15-minute walk from JR Kyoto Station (Hachijo exit).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>近鉄京都線東寺駅徒歩10分</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">15 minutes walk from Kintetsu Kyoto line To-ji station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It&apos;s a 15-minute walk from the Kintetsu Kyoto Line&apos;s To-ji Station.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It&apos;s a 10-minute walk from the Kintetsu Kyoto Line&apos;s To-ji Station.</e>
<cmt>「徒歩10分」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>京都市営バス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto City Bus</e>
<cmt>京都市営バス：http://www.city.kyoto.jp/koho/eng/access/transport.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto City Bus</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto City Bus</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>姉妹校</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sister school</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sister school</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sister school</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="51">
<j>種智院大学</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Syuchiin University</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Syuchiin University</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shuchiin University</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Leelee360(id:124701), ゴンボ(id:22207), T@ka(id:12814), BJP039(id:47469), 0null0(id:582), Kstigarbha(id:13376), 右衛門(id:79716), Lupinoid(id:68), Co.kyoto(id:79296), Poporonbomber(id:8192), Kazuhiro Watanabe(id:85247), Toto-tarou(id:16648), Yamajy(id:14927), さららゆら(id:12274), 文太(id:138302), 日本一弱い男(id:92046), Masabb(id:71275), カキクケ子(id:111143), 竹麦魚(id:11012), ざざむし(id:9415), Ogeshi(id:80487), Yamabig(id:21134), 目蒲東急之介(id:34741), Marobashi(id:74184), 翰林硯士(id:99377), Jkr2255(id:16760), Ogny(id:13549), １０３系西九条行き(id:99687), F-21(id:59339), Basedview(id:182448), HAH00735(id:67997), たね(id:10372), Cheebot(id:14114), Balmung0731(id:99201), 弾丸野郎(id:163223), Project(id:11782), Hideki1976(id:106957), BitBucket(id:30999), Taisyo(id:6896), MIO(id:31681), Xbeta(id:69259), Rentaro2521(id:159641), Bravel(id:155993), たなつね(id:36863), Rusk(id:9895), Kanjy(id:36859), Metya1013(id:43768), Suisui(id:69), Gwkaakun(id:108135), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>