<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>番組小学校</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bangumi Elementary Schools</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bangumi Elementary Schools</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bangumi Elementary Schools</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>番組小学校（ばんぐみしょうがっこう）は、明治維新後の1869年（明治2年）、京都の町衆たちの手によって、当時の住民自治組織であった「番組（町組）」を単位として創設された、64の小学校を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bangumi elementary schools refer to the sixty-four elementary schools established by the towns people in Kyoto in 1869, two years after the Meiji Restoration, based on the then extant municipal-level autonomous administraitive unit known as the &quot;bangumi&quot; (a neighborhood unit).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bangumi elementary schools refer to the sixty-four elementary schools established by the towns people in Kyoto in 1869, two years after the Meiji Restoration, based on the then extant municipal-level autonomous administraitive unit known as the &quot;bangumi&quot; (a neighborhood unit).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bangumi elementary schools refer to the sixty-four elementary schools established by the towns people in Kyoto in 1869, two years after the Meiji Restoration, based on the then extant municipal-level autonomous administrative unit known as the &apos;bangumi&apos; (a neighborhood unit).</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>これらの小学校は、1872年（明治5年）の、国家による学校制度（学制）の創設に先立つ、日本で最初の学区制小学校であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These elementary schools became the first school district elementary schools under the National Education System ofJapan (school system) introduced in 1872.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These elementary schools became the first school district elementary schools under the National Education System ofJapan (school system) introduced in 1872.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These elementary schools became the first school district elementary schools under the National Education System of Japan (school system) introduced in 1872.</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Overview</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Overview</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>近世、京都には「町組」という住民自治の組織があったが、明治維新の前後に、町組は「上京（下京）第○○番組」という通し番号のついた地域的なまとまりを持つ組織に再編され、「番組」と呼ばれるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Edo period, Kyoto was organized into autonomous administrative units called &quot;machigumi&quot;, composed of local residents; however, at or about the time of the Meiji Restoration, the machigumi were reorgainzed under a system in which they were designated as belonging to either the northern part of Kyoto, &quot;Kamigyo&quot;, or the southern part, &quot;Shimogyo&quot;, followed by bangumi number, such as Kamigyo, bangumi number 12&quot;, and were referred to as &quot;bangumi&quot; from that point.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Edo period, Kyoto was organized into autonomous administrative units called &quot;machigumi&quot;, composed of local residents; however, at or about the time of the Meiji Restoration, the machigumi were reorgainzed under a system in which they were designated as belonging to either the northern part of Kyoto, &quot;Kamigyo&quot;, or the southern part, &quot;Shimogyo&quot;, followed by bangumi number, such as Kamigyo, bangumi number 12&quot;, and were referred to as &quot;bangumi&quot; from that point.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Edo period, Kyoto was organized into autonomous administrative units called &apos;machigumi,&apos; composed of local residents; however, at or about the time of the Meiji Restoration, the machigumi were reorganized under a system in which they were designated as belonging to either the northern part of Kyoto, &apos;Kamigyo,&apos; or the southern part, &apos;Shimogyo,&apos; followed by bangumi number, such as &apos;Kamigyo, bangumi number 12,&apos; and were referred to as &apos;bangumi&apos; from that point.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>1869年（明治2年）には、27程度の町を1番組として、上京に33の番組、下京に32の番組、合計65（同年、下京で1番組が分離し、番組の数は66となった。）に再編されました。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In1869, approximately 27 &quot;machi&quot; (a neighborhod) formed a single bangumi, of which there were thirty-three in Kamigyo and thrty-two in Shimo-gyo, for a toltal of sixty-five (during the same year, a bangumi in Shimogyo was split, bringing the total to sisty-six).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In1869, approximately 27 &quot;machi&quot; (a neighborhod) formed a single bangumi, of which there were thirty-three in Kamigyo and thrty-two in Shimo-gyo, for a toltal of sixty-five (during the same year, a bangumi in Shimogyo was split, bringing the total to sisty-six).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1869, approximately 27 &quot;machi&quot; (a neighborhood) formed a single bangumi and the system was again reorganized in the same year, in which there were thirty-three in Kamigyo and thirty-two in Shimo-gyo, for a total of sixty-five (during the same year, a bangumi in Shimogyo was split, bringing the total to sixty-six).</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入次のセルにかかっていた原文を調整しました。スペル原文の修正に合わせ、訳文も調整しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>1つの番組に対して自治会所機能を併せ持つ小学校が1つ作られることになり、同年中に64校の小学校が開校された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The system was again reorganized in (????), in a manner such that each bangumi was provided with an administrative building and an elementary school, and sixty-four elementary schools were opened that same year.</e>
<cmt>something is mising, including the date, in the Japanese text.</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The system was again reorganized in (????), in a manner such that each bangumi was provided with an administrative building and an elementary school, and sixty-four elementary schools were opened that same year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Each bangumi was provided with an administrative building and an elementary school, and sixty-four elementary schools were opened that same year.</e>
<cmt>文頭を前のセルに移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>（番組の数が66であるのに対して、小学校数が64校なのは、番組2つで1つの小学校を設置したところが2箇所あったため。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(The reason that there were only sixty-four schools for sixty-six bangumi is that there were two groups of two bangumi each that decided to establish a single school to share between themselves.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(The reason that there were only sixty-four schools for sixty-six bangumi is that there were two groups of two bangumi each that decided to establish a single school to share between themselves.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(The reason that there were only sixty-four schools for sixty-six bangumi is that there were two groups of two bangumi each that decided to establish a single school to share between themselves.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>京都府は、各番組に対して、新築校舎の模範設計を示している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The prefectural government of Kyoto released model plans for a new schoolhouses for each of the bangumi.</e>
<cmt>unclear as to what the verb means and to what the &quot;model plan(s)&quot; refers.</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The prefectural government of Kyoto released model plans for a new schoolhouses for each of the bangumi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The prefectural government of Kyoto released model plans for a new schoolhouses for each of the bangumi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>校舎は2階建てであり、1階中央の玄関を入ると、左右に大小の差のある男女の筆道場が配置されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Each schoolhouse was to have two floors, with separate writing practice rooms of slightly different constructions for boys and girls arrranged to the right and left as one entered the central entrance on the first floor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Each schoolhouse was to have two floors, with separate writing practice rooms of slightly different constructions for boys and girls arrranged to the right and left as one entered the central entrance on the first floor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Each schoolhouse was to have two floors, with separate writing practice rooms of slightly different constructions for boys and girls arranged to the right and left as one entered the central entrance on the first floor.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>2階には広間の講堂、出勤場（職員室）、算術教室が置かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The second floor included a large classroom, a faculty room, and a character brushwork instruction room.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The second floor included a large classroom, a faculty room, and a character brushwork instruction room.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The second floor included a large classroom, a faculty room, and a character brushwork instruction room.</e>
<cmt>広間＝hall</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>建設費は、各番組に対して、京都府から800円が貸与され、半額が無利子の10年年賦で返済の予定とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kyoto prefectural government provided a loan of 800 yen for construction costs of each bangumi school, half of which was scheduled to be repaid in yearly installments over a period of ten years with no interest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kyoto prefectural government provided a loan of 800 yen for construction costs of each bangumi school, half of which was scheduled to be repaid in yearly installments over a period of ten years with no interest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kyoto prefectural government provided a loan of 800 yen for construction costs of each bangumi school, half of which was scheduled to be repaid in yearly installments over a period of ten years with no interest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>また、各番組の全戸別に対して、半年に1分の軒金が課せられ、有志による寄付と合わせて、恒久的な運営費に充当するものとされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, along with philanthropic donations, each bangumi school was alloted a portion of the building costs semiannually for permanent operational expenses.</e>
<cmt>what? Not a field with which I&apos;m familiar.</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, along with philanthropic donations, each bangumi school was alloted a portion of the building costs semiannually for permanent operational expenses.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, along with philanthropic donations, each bangumi houses was allotted a portion of the building costs semiannually for permanent operational expenses.</e>
<cmt>「全戸」は学校ではなく、番組内の各家のことだと思われますので、housesにしました。「軒金」は意味が調べられませんでしたが、&quot;a portion of the building costs&quot;というよりは、「分担金」のようなものと解釈しました。スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>各番組では、「上(下)京○○番会社」を設立して、資金運用に当たった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Every bangumi school was named according to the classification system designated by &quot;Kami- (Shimo-) gyo&quot;, followed by a two digit number, and funding was alloted to each school using this system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Every bangumi school was named according to the classification system designated by &quot;Kami- (Shimo-) gyo&quot;, followed by a two digit number, and funding was alloted to each school using this system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Every bangumi school was named according to the classification system designated by &apos;Kami- (Shimo-) gyo,&apos; followed by a one or two digit number, and funding was allotted to each school using this system.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせて赤字に変更しました。スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>1870年（明治3年）正月、各番組小学校において「稽古はじめ」式が催され、授業が開始された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On New Year&apos;s in 1870, each bangumi elemetary school held a ceremony commemorating the start of instruction at the school, and lessons were begun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On New Year&apos;s in 1870, each bangumi elemetary school held a ceremony commemorating the start of instruction at the school, and lessons were begun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On New Year&apos;s in 1870, each bangumi elementary school held a ceremony commemorating the start of instruction at the school, and lessons were begun.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>京都府が作成した式次第によれば、孔子と菅原道真の2学神像が祀られたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the program of the ceremony, which was drawn up by the Kyoto prefectural government, students were to venerate two gods of scholarship and learning, Confucious and SUGAWARA no Michizane.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the program of the ceremony, which was drawn up by the Kyoto prefectural government, students were to venerate two gods of scholarship and learning, Confucious and SUGAWARA no Michizane.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the program of the ceremony, which was drawn up by the Kyoto prefectural government, students were to venerate two gods of scholarship and learning, Confucius and SUGAWARA no Michizane.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>京都市学校歴史博物館には、下京第7番組小学校の像が展示されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An image of the Shimogyo bangumi school 07 is displayed at the Kyoto Municipal Museum of School History.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An image of the Shimogyo bangumi school 07 is displayed at the Kyoto Municipal Museum of School History.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An image of the Shimogyo bangumi school 07 is displayed at the Kyoto Municipal Museum of School History.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>授業科目は、「句読」「暗誦」「習字」「算術」の4科であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The subjects of the lessons the students studied were &quot;gammar and punctuation&quot;, &quot;recitation from memory&quot;, &quot;calligraphy&quot;, and &quot;arithmetic&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The subjects of the lessons the students studied were &quot;gammar and punctuation&quot;, &quot;recitation from memory&quot;, &quot;calligraphy&quot;, and &quot;arithmetic&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The subjects of the lessons the students studied were &apos;grammar and punctuation,&apos; &apos;recitation from memory,&apos; &apos;calligraphy,&apos; and &apos;arithmetic.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;カンマ、ピリオド位置移動スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="17">
<j>この番組は1872年（明治5年）には「区」として再編され、さらに1879年（明治12年）郡区町村編制法により上京区・下京区が置かれると、「組」と改められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term &quot;bangumi&quot; was revised to &quot;-ku&quot; (district) in 1872, and again revised to &quot;-gumi&quot; in 1879 upon the promulgation of the Gun-ku-cho-son Henseiho (Act for the alignment of local government system), under which Kamigyo and Shimogyo became Kamigyoku and Shimogyoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term &quot;bangumi&quot; was revised to &quot;-ku&quot; (district) in 1872, and again revised to &quot;-gumi&quot; in 1879 upon the promulgation of the Gun-ku-cho-son Henseiho (Act for the alignment of local government system), under which Kamigyo and Shimogyo became Kamigyoku and Shimogyoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term &quot;bangumi&quot; was revised to &apos;-ku&apos; (ward) in 1872, and again revised to &apos;-gumi&apos; in 1879 upon the promulgation of the Gun-ku-cho-son Henseiho (Act for the alignment of local government system), under which Kamigyo and Shimogyo became Kamigyo Ward and Shimogyo Ward.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="18">
<j>市制によって誕生した京都市が、1892年（明治25年）に学区制度を確立。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The birth of Kyoto City brough about by the municapity system resulted in the creation of a school disctrict system in 1892.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The birth of Kyoto City brough about by the municapity system resulted in the creation of a school disctrict system in 1892.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The birth of Kyoto City brought about by the municipality system resulted in the creation of a school district system in 1892.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>番組をルーツとする学区は、1893年（明治26年）に上京区28学区、下京区32学区となり、この形は1941年（昭和16年）の国民学校令により学区による小学校の運営が廃止されるまで存続した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under the school district system, which had been established based on the bangumi school system, the were twenty-eight schoold districts in Kamigyoku and thirty-two school districts in Shimoguoku; the school district system remained intact operating under this form until it was abolished in 1941 by the Kokumin gakko rei (Act of elementary schools).</e>
<cmt>no access to online dictionary…</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the school district system, which had been established based on the bangumi school system, the were twenty-eight schoold districts in Kamigyoku and thirty-two school districts in Shimoguoku; the school district system remained intact operating under this form until it was abolished in 1941 by the Kokumin gakko rei (Act of elementary schools).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the school district system, which had been established based on the bangumi school system, there were twenty-eight school districts in Kamigyoku and thirty-two school districts in Shimogyoku in 1893; the school district system remained intact operating under this form until it was abolished in 1941 by the Kokumin gakko rei (Act of elementary schools).</e>
<cmt>年号補足スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="20">
<j>その後、戦後の6・3・3・4制になり、もとの小学校を新制中学の校舎に利用するなどによって小学校の通学区の変化があったが、戦前の学区制度廃止前の学区は「京都の元学区」という住民自治の単位として現在も生き残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Subsequently, with the introduction of the 6/3/3/4 system of education after the war, due to measures such as the appropriation of the buildings that had been used for the elementary schools for use as middle schools and the like, although the districts used to define the elementary school to be attended by local residents changed, the school district system remains intact to this day as the &quot;Kyoto Original School Districts&quot;, which are automonous school districts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently, with the introduction of the 6/3/3/4 system of education after the war, due to measures such as the appropriation of the buildings that had been used for the elementary schools for use as middle schools and the like, although the districts used to define the elementary school to be attended by local residents changed, the school district system remains intact to this day as the &quot;Kyoto Original School Districts&quot;, which are automonous school districts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently, with the introduction of the 6/3/3/4 system of education after the war, due to measures such as the appropriation of the buildings that had been used for the elementary schools for use as middle schools and the like, although the districts used to define the elementary school to be attended by local residents changed, the school district system remains intact to this day as the &apos;Kyoto Original School Districts,&apos; which are autonomous resident districts.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;　スペルOK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>番組小学校と元学区の対応一覧</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">List of the bangumi elementary schools original school districts</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">List of the bangumi elementary schools original school districts</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Corresponding list of the bangumi elementary schools and original school districts</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせて修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="21">
<j>番組小学校の学校名は、当初「上京第○○番組小学校」などと番組名を用いて名付けられたが、その後地域の歴史に基づくものや、中国の古典に基づくものに改称され、その名称は元学区の名称に継承されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The names of the bangumi elementary schools were at first designated according to the system described above as &quot;Kami- (Shimo-) gyo ##); however, the schools subsequently renamed themselves based on local history, Chinese classics and the like, and those names were inhereted by the original school districts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The names of the bangumi elementary schools were at first designated according to the system described above as &quot;Kami- (Shimo-) gyo ##); however, the schools subsequently renamed themselves based on local history, Chinese classics and the like, and those names were inhereted by the original school districts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The names of the bangumi elementary schools were at first designated according to the system described above as &apos;Kami- (Shimo-) gyo ##); however, the schools subsequently renamed themselves based on local history, Chinese classics and the like, and those names were inherited by the original school districts.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;　スペルOK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kansai explorer(id:48975), Straysheep(id:42448), Mooko(id:36162), うら(id:40695), Tribot(id:186681), Htks(id:24185), Ko-ken(id:49348), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>