<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>私塾立命館</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shijuku Ritsumeikan (Ritsumeikan Private Academy)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shijuku Ritsumeikan (Ritsumeikan Private Academy)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shijuku Ritsumeikan (Ritsumeikan Private Academy)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>私塾立命館（しじゅくりつめいかん）は、西園寺公望が1869年に京都御所内の私邸に開設した家塾。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shijuku Ritsumeikan was a private academy that Kinmochi SAIONJI established in his private residence in Kyoto Imperial Palace in 1869.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shijuku Ritsumeikan was a private academy that Kinmochi SAIONJI established in his private residence in the Kyoto Imperial Palace in 1869.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shijuku Ritsumeikan was a private academy that Kinmochi SAIONJI established in his private residence in the Kyoto Imperial Palace in 1869.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>賓師</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Guest teachers</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Guest teachers</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Guest teachers</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>私塾立命館の賓師として迎えられたのは、当時の著名漢学者たちであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was prominent scholars of the Chinese classics of the day who were invited as the guest teachers of Shijuku Ritsumeikan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prominent scholars of Chinese classics in the day were invited as guest teachers for the Shijuku Ritsumeikan.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prominent scholars of Chinese classics in the day were invited as guest teachers for the Shijuku Ritsumeikan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>西園寺公望は、「教師には朱子学者、水戸学の儒者をむかえ、文章家として聞こえた人もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinmochi SAIONJI mentioned, &apos;We invited Neo-Confucian scholars and Confucians of Mitogaku (the scholarship and academic traditions that arose in the Mito Domain) as teachers, and some of them were famous as good writers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kinmochi SAIONJI mentioned, &apos;We invited Neo-Confucian scholars and Confucians of Mitogaku (the scholarship and academic traditions that arose in the Mito Domain) as teachers, and some of them were famous as good writers.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinmochi SAIONJI mentioned, &apos;We invited Neo-Confucian scholars and Confucians of Mitogaku (the scholarship and academic traditions that arose in the Mito Domain) as teachers, and some of them were famous as good writers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>（略）京都にいる漢学者のえらい所をぬき集めたという形だった」と述べている（木村毅編『西園寺公望自伝』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Snip) It was like a selection of the elite of scholars of the Chinese classics in Kyoto&apos; (&quot;Autobiography of Kinmochi SAIONJI&quot; edited by Ki KIMURA).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Snip) It was like a bonzana of elite scholars of Chinese classics in Kyoto&apos; (&quot;Autobiography of Kinmochi SAIONJI&quot; edited by Ki KIMURA).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Snip) It was like a bonzana of elite scholars of Chinese classics in Kyoto&apos; (&quot;Autobiography of Kinmochi SAIONJI&quot; edited by Ki KIMURA).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>実際に、賓師として確認されているのは、江馬天江、広瀬青邨、松本士竜（松本巌）、富岡鉄斎、神山鳳陽（四郎）らである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is Tenko EMA, Seison HIROSE, Shiryu MATSUMOTO (Iwao MATSUMOTO) (松本 士竜(松本巌)), Tessai TOMIOKA and Hoyo (Shiro) GOYAMA who were actually known as guest teachers.</e>
<cmt>松本士竜(松本巌)は、読み不明のため、人名として一般的な読みにしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is Tenko EMA, Seison HIROSE, Shiryu MATSUMOTO (Iwao MATSUMOTO) (松本 士竜(松本巌)), Tessai TOMIOKA and Hoyo (Shiro) GOYAMA who were actually known as guest teachers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is Tenko EMA, Seison HIROSE, Shiryu MATSUMOTO (Iwao MATSUMOTO), Tessai TOMIOKA and Hoyo (Shiro) GOYAMA who were in fact known as guest teachers.</e>
<cmt>(松本 士竜（松本巌）)削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>1870年、広瀬青邨が西園寺の詩文会に招かれたとき同席していた者には、尊攘運動に加わって岩倉具視の知遇をえていた山中静逸、江馬天功の実兄で、池田屋事件で投獄される板倉槐堂（淡海竹洲）、本草学者山本亡羊の子で漢方医だった山本秀五郎（秀夫）や浜崎廉太郎（直全）らがあったほか谷口靄山らも参加していたとされるから、この中にも賓師として迎えられたものがあったと思われる（「青邨公手沢日記」）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1870, when Seison HIROSE was invited to a poem meeting by Saionji, Aizan TANIGUCHI was also present as well as Seiitsu YAMANAKA who joined movement of Sonno Joi (slogan advocating reverence for the Emperor and the expulsion of foreigners) and enjoyed Tomomi IWAKURA&apos;s favor, Kaido ITAKURA (Chikushu OMI) who was a real brother of Tenko EMA and would be put in prison for the Ikedaya Incident, Hidegoro (Hideo) YAMAMOTO who was a son of a scholar of herbalism Boyo YAMAMOTO and a Chinese medicine doctor, and Rentaro (Chokuzen) HAMASAKI, so it is considered that some of these were also invited as guest teachers (&quot;Seison-ko Shutaku Nikki (青邨公手沢日記) (Cherised Diary of Prince Seison)&quot;).</e>
<cmt>青邨公手沢日記は登録では読み不明でしたので、一般的な読みにしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1870, when Seison HIROSE was invited to a poem meeting by Saionji, Aizan TANIGUCHI was also present as well as Seiitsu YAMANAKA who joined movement of Sonno Joi (slogan advocating reverence for the Emperor and the expulsion of foreigners) and enjoyed Tomomi IWAKURA&apos;s favor, Kaido ITAKURA (Chikushu OMI) who was a real brother of Tenko EMA and would be put in prison for the Ikedaya Incident, Hidegoro (Hideo) YAMAMOTO who was a son of a scholar of herbalism Boyo YAMAMOTO and a Chinese medicine doctor, and Rentaro (Chokuzen) HAMASAKI, so it is considered that some of these were also invited as guest teachers (&quot;Seison-ko Shutaku Nikki (青邨公手沢日記) (Cherised Diary of Prince Seison)&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1870, when Seison HIROSE was invited to a poem meeting by Saionji, Aizan TANIGUCHI was also present as well as Seiitsu YAMANAKA who joined movement of Sonno Joi (slogan advocating reverence for the Emperor and the expulsion of foreigners) and enjoyed Tomomi IWAKURA&apos;s favor, Kaido ITAKURA (Chikushu OMI) who was a real brother of Tenko EMA and would be put in prison for the Ikedaya Incident, Hidegoro (Hideo) YAMAMOTO who was a son of a scholar of herbalism Boyo YAMAMOTO and a Chinese medicine doctor, and Rentaro (Chokuzen) HAMASAKI, so it is considered that some of these were also invited as guest teachers (&quot;Seison-ko Shutaku Nikki&quot; (Cherised Diary of Prince Seison)).</e>
<cmt>スペース調整 (青邨公手沢日記) 削除&quot;の位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>塾の性格と規模</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Character and scale of the academy</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Character and scale of the academy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Character and scale of the academy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>西園寺公望自身が、「大いに勤王家を養成するという抱負」で塾を設立したと述べている通り、私塾立命館は他の公家家塾とは異なり、初めから一般的な教育機関としての性格を備えていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Kinmochi SAIONJI himself mentioned that he established the academy with &apos;big ambitions to foster people of loyalty to the Emperor,&apos; Shijuku Ritsumeikan had character as a general educational institute from the start, different form other private academies of court nobles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Kinmochi SAIONJI himself mentioned that he established the academy with &apos;big ambitions to foster people loyal to the Emperor,&apos; Shijuku Ritsumeikan was a general educational institute from the start, and different form other private academies of court nobles.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Kinmochi SAIONJI himself mentioned that he established the academy with &apos;big ambitions to foster people loyal to the Emperor,&apos; Shijuku Ritsumeikan was a general educational institute from the start, and different form other private academies of court nobles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>そのため、開設当初は平穏な詩会の場に過ぎなかったのが、塾の噂が各地に広がるにつれ、多くの若者が集まって内外の時事問題を議論する場へと変化、ついには校舎を増築する程までに成長している（木村毅編『西園寺公望自伝』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, although it only offered opportunities for peaceful poem meetings when it was established, as the talk of the academy spread nationwide, many young people gathered, and it became to offer opportunities to discuss domestic and international current events, and eventually grew to build an additional building (&quot;Autobiography of Kinmochi SAIONJI&quot; edited by Ki KIMURA).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, although it only offered opportunities for peaceful poem meetings when it was established, as talk of the academy spread nationwide, many young people gathered, and it became to offer opportunities to discuss domestic and international current events, and eventually grew, adding an additional building (&quot;Autobiography of Kinmochi SAIONJI&quot; edited by Ki KIMURA).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, although it only offered opportunities for peaceful poem meetings when it was established, as talk of the academy spread nationwide, many young people gathered, and it became to offer opportunities to discuss domestic and international current events, and eventually grew, adding an additional building (&quot;Autobiography of Kinmochi SAIONJI&quot; edited by Ki KIMURA).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>西園寺自身の回想によると、西園寺および門客・家臣以外にも、諸藩からもかなりの塾生が集まっていたようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the recollection of Saionji himself, a large number of students gathered from various domains as well as the Saionji clan and its retainers and vassals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the recollection of Saionji himself, a large number of students gathered from various domains as well as the Saionji clan and its retainers and vassals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the recollection of Saionji himself, a large number of students gathered from various domains as well as the Saionji clan and its retainers and vassals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>塾の評判が高くなるにつれてさらに多くの若者が集まるようになり、ついには100人程度までにふくれあがったことが知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the academy developed its reputation, much more young people gathered, and it is known that it eventually expanded up to about 100 students.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the academy developed its reputation, much more young people gathered, and it is known that it eventually expanded up to about 100 students.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the academy developed its reputation, much more young people gathered, and it is known that it eventually expanded up to about 100 students.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>塾の閉鎖とその背景</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Closing of the academy and its background</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Closing of the academy and its background</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Closing of the academy and its background</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>1870年4月23日、塾のあり方に不穏を感じた京都府庁（太政官複都制）が差留命令を下し、私塾立命館はわずか1年弱で閉鎖されることになる（開設は1869年9月23日前後とされる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 23, 1870, Kyoto Prefectural Office (Dual capital system by Grand Council of State), which found the state of the academy disturbing, issued an injunction, which made Shijuku Ritsumeikan closed only after a little less than a year (the establishment was supposed to be around September 23, 1869).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 23, 1870, Kyoto Prefectural Office (Dual capital system by Grand Council of State), which found the state of the academy disturbing, issued an injunction, which closed Shijuku Ritsumeikan after a little less than a year (the establishment was supposed to be around September 23, 1869).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On April 23, 1870, Kyoto Prefectural Office (Dual capital system by Grand Council of State), which found the state of the academy disturbing, issued an injunction, which closed Shijuku Ritsumeikan after a little less than a year (the establishment was supposed to be around September 23, 1869).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>このとき西園寺公望自身はフランス留学の準備のため長崎県にいたため何もできないまま閉塾を受け入れるほかなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, Kinmochi SAIONJI himself was in Nagasaki Prefecture to prepare for studying in France, so he had no choice but to accept the closing of the academy without doing anything.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, Kinmochi SAIONJI himself was in Nagasaki Prefecture to prepare for studying in France, so he had no choice but to accept the closing of the academy without doing anything.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, Kinmochi SAIONJI himself was in Nagasaki Prefecture to prepare for studying in France, so he had no choice but to accept the closing of the academy without doing anything.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>後に私塾の閉鎖について感想を求められた西園寺公は、「立命館の諸生が高談放論するのを、革命思想とでも勘ちがいして、ぬきうちに止めよと云ってきたらしく、塾はよほど盛んになっていて惜しかったけれど、廃校にした」と述べている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, asked to give his comments on the closing of the private academy, Prince Saionji mentioned &apos;It seemed that they misunderstood that letting the students of Ritsumeikan speak freely is from a revolutionary idea and ordered to close without notice, and it was a shame, because the academy was quite active, but I closed it.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, asked to give his comments on the closing of the private academy, Prince Saionji mentioned &apos;It seemed that they misunderstood that letting the students of Ritsumeikan speak freely was a revolutionary idea, but they asked that it be stopped, and while it was a shame, since the academy was quite active, I closed it.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, asked to give his comments on the closing of the private academy, Prince Saionji mentioned &apos;It seemed that they misunderstood that letting the students of Ritsumeikan speak freely was a revolutionary idea, but they asked that it be stopped, and while it was a shame, since the academy was quite active, I closed it.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="17">
<j>塾に対する閉鎖命令は、太政官が複都制に出した「京都大学校取り建て中止」の通達とも深く関係している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The closing order against the academy was deeply related to the notice of &apos;Cancellation of building of Kyoto University&apos; that the Grand Council of State issued for the Dual capital system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The closing order against the academy was deeply related to the notice of &apos;Cancellation of building of Kyoto University&apos; that the Grand Council of State issued by the Dual capital system.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The closing order against the academy was deeply related to the notice of &apos;Cancellation of building of Kyoto University&apos; that the Grand Council of State issued by the Dual capital system.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>明治維新後の東京都では「昌平黌」を再興し、学制中央機関として「大学校」を設置することが決定していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Tokyo Metropolis after the Meiji Restoration, it was decided to rebuild &apos;Shoheiko (a school run by Edo shogunate)&apos; and to establish a &apos;university&apos; as a central organization of the educational system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Tokyo Metropolis after the Meiji Restoration, it was decided that the &apos;Shoheiko (a school run by Edo shogunate)&apos; would be rebuilt that a &apos;university&apos; would be established as a central organization of the educational system.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Tokyo Metropolis after the Meiji Restoration, it was decided that the &apos;Shoheiko&apos; (a school run by Edo shogunate) would be rebuilt that a &apos;university&apos; would be established as a central organization of the educational system.</e>
<cmt>位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>これにより京都にあった「大学校」は必要なくなったして、1869年11月に廃止通達が出されたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, as the &apos;university&apos; existed in Kyoto became unnecessary, the notice of abolition was issued in November in 1869.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, as the &apos;university&apos; existed in Kyoto became unnecessary, the notice of abolition was issued in November in 1869.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, as the &apos;university&apos; existed in Kyoto became unnecessary, the notice of abolition was issued in November in 1869.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>既に京都大学校建て替え準備に入っていた京都大学校関係者たちはこの通達を事実上無視し、通達翌月には「京都大学校代（仮大学校）」として大学校開校を強行した（京都留守官の通達では「京都学校」とされた）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The authorities of Kyoto University, who had already started to prepare to rebuilt Kyoto University, virtually ignored this notice, and in the following month of the notice, went ahead with the opening of the university as &apos;Provisional Kyoto University (temporary university)&apos; (It was referred to as &apos;Kyoto School&apos; in the notice by Kyoto rusukan (officer for the emperor who was out of Kyoto)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The authorities of Kyoto University, who had already started to prepare to rebuild Kyoto University, virtually ignored this notice, and in the following months of the notice, went ahead with the opening of the university as &apos;Provisional Kyoto University (temporary university)&apos; (It was referred to as &apos;Kyoto School&apos; in the notice by Kyoto rusukan (officer for the emperor who was out of Kyoto)).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The authorities of Kyoto University, who had already started to prepare to rebuild Kyoto University, virtually ignored this notice, and in the following months of the notice, went ahead with the opening of the university as &apos;Provisional Kyoto University&apos; (temporary university) (It was referred to as &apos;Kyoto School&apos; in the notice by Kyoto rusukan (officer for the emperor who was out of Kyoto)).</e>
<cmt>スペース削除&apos;の位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>東京の太政官は既成事実として「京都大学校代」の存在を認め、京都留守官の管轄の下で学校は存続されたが、結局は教官の引き抜きなど諸般の事情により1870年（明治3）年7月には廃止されてしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Grand Council of State in Tokyo accepted the existence of &apos;Provisional Kyoto University&apos; as an accomplished fact, and the school continued under the jurisdiction of Kyoto rusukan, but it ended up to be abolished in July in 1870, due to various reasons including headhunting of the teachers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Grand Council of State in Tokyo accepted the existence of &apos;Provisional Kyoto University&apos;, and the school continued under the jurisdiction of Kyoto rusukan, but ended up being abolished in July in 1870, due to various reasons including headhunting of the teachers.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Grand Council of State in Tokyo accepted the existence of &apos;Provisional Kyoto University,&apos; and the school continued under the jurisdiction of Kyoto rusukan, but ended up being abolished in July in 1870, due to various reasons including headhunting of the teachers.</e>
<cmt>コンマ位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>当時「京都大学校代」は寺町今出川西入ル（現在の同志社大学構内南東端）に位置し、京都御所内の「私塾立命館」とは目と鼻の先であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, &apos;Provisional Kyoto University&apos; was located at Nishi-iru, Imadegawa, Tera-machi (in the southeast end of present Doshisha University campus), and just around the corner of &apos;Shijuku Ritsumeikan&apos; in Kyoto Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, &apos;Provisional Kyoto University&apos; was located at Nishi-iru, Imadegawa, Tera-machi (in the southeast end of present Doshisha University campus), and just around the corner of &apos;Shijuku Ritsumeikan&apos; in Kyoto Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, &apos;Provisional Kyoto University&apos; was located at Nishi-iru, Imadegawa, Tera-machi (in the southeast end of present Doshisha University campus), and just around the corner of &apos;Shijuku Ritsumeikan&apos; in Kyoto Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>京都留守官が威信をかけて設立した「京都大学校代」がわずか300人ばかり学生しか集められずに開校から8ヶ月余りで廃止に追い込まれたのに対し、わずか徒歩10分程度のところにある一私塾が100人もの塾生を抱えきれず増築までして対応しているということが京都留守官の逆鱗に触れたことは想像に難くない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While &apos;&apos;Provisional Kyoto University,&apos; of which Kyoto rusukan put his prestige on the establishment, barely collected no more than 300 students, and was forced to close after a little more than eight months, a private academy, which was about 10-minue walk away, built an additional building to handle no less than 100 students, so it is easy to imagine that this brought Kyoto rusukan&apos; anger.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While &apos;&apos;Provisional Kyoto University,&apos; of which Kyoto rusukan put his prestige on the establishment, they barely collected more than 300 students, and was forced to close after a little more than eight months, while a private academy, which was about a 10-minute walk away, built an additional building to handle no less than 100 students, so it is easy to imagine that this brought the Kyoto rusukan&apos; anger.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While &apos;Provisional Kyoto University,&apos; of which Kyoto rusukan put his prestige on the establishment, they barely collected more than 300 students, and was forced to close after a little more than eight months, while a private academy, which was about a 10-minute walk away, built an additional building to handle no less than 100 students, so it is easy to imagine that this brought the Kyoto rusukan&apos; anger.</e>
<cmt>削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>のちに西園寺公望は、私塾立命館への「差留命令」が京都留守長官の「嫌疑」か「妬心」から出たものに違いないと述べるとともに、しばらくは閉塾に応じるが、再興の時期を待ちたいと賓師に宛てた手紙のなかで述べている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, Kinmochi SAIONJI mentioned that the &apos;injunction&apos; against Shijuku Ritsumeikan must have been issued out of the head of Kyoto rusukan&apos;s &apos;suspicion&apos; or &apos;envy,&apos; and also mentioned that he would accept the closing of the academy for a while, but would like to wait for the time of the rebuilding in a letter to guest teachers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, Kinmochi SAIONJI mentioned in a letter to guest teachers, that the &apos;injunction&apos; against Shijuku Ritsumeikan must have been issued out of the head of Kyoto rusukan&apos;s &apos;suspicion&apos; or &apos;envy,&apos; and also mentioned that he would accept the closing of the academy for a while, but would like to wait for its rebuilding.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, Kinmochi SAIONJI mentioned in a letter to guest teachers, that the &apos;injunction&apos; against Shijuku Ritsumeikan must have been issued out of the head of Kyoto rusukan&apos;s &apos;suspicion&apos; or &apos;envy,&apos; and also mentioned that he would accept the closing of the academy for a while, but would like to wait for its rebuilding.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>その年の12月、西園寺公望は留学先フランスへ出発。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In December in the same year, Kinmochi SAIONJI departed for France where he was going to study.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In December in the same year, Kinmochi SAIONJI departed for France where he was going to study.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In December in the same year, Kinmochi SAIONJI departed for France where he was going to study.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>1880年まで日本を離れることになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was away from Japan until 1880.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was away from Japan until 1880.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was away from Japan until 1880.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="27">
<j>明治時代に入り西園寺家が東京に移った後、かつて私塾が置かれた西園寺邸跡には、「白雲神社」が建立され現在に至っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Saionji Family moved to Tokyo in the Meiji Period, &apos;Shirakumo-jinja Shrine&apos; was established in the Saionji residence site where the private academy used to be, which still exists now.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Saionji Family moved to Tokyo in the Meiji Period, &apos;Shirakumo-jinja Shrine&apos; was established in the Saionji residence site where the private academy used to be, which still exists now.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Saionji family moved to Tokyo in the Meiji Period, &apos;Shirakumo-jinja Shrine&apos; was established in the Saionji residence site where the private academy used to be, which still exists now.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="28">
<j>私塾立命館閉鎖後</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the closing of Shijuku Ritsumeikan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the closing of Shijuku Ritsumeikan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the closing of Shijuku Ritsumeikan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="29">
<j>フランス留学から帰国した西園寺は東洋自由新聞社長を経て政界入りするが、その間も教育に対する情熱を失うことはなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Coming back to Japan from France where he studied, Saionji went into politics after serving as the president of Toyo Jiyu Shinbun journal, and he never lost his passion for education all that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Coming back to Japan from France where he studied, Saionji went into politics after serving as the president of Toyo Jiyu Shinbun journal, and he never lost his passion for education.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Coming back to Japan from France where he studied, Saionji went into politics after serving as the president of Toyo Jiyu Shinbun journal, and he never lost his passion for education.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>1880年には岸本辰雄、宮城浩蔵、矢代操らが明治法律学校を設立するのを援助したほか、1894年文部大臣に就任すると井上毅らが作った「教育勅語」に反対し、明治天皇から「教育勅語」改定の許可を得て第二の教育勅語の草案作成にも取り組んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1880, he supported Tatsuo KISHIMOTO, Kozo MIYAGI and Misao YASHIRO to establish Meiji Law School, and when he became the Minister of Education in 1894, he opposed the &apos;Imperial Rescript on Education&apos; made by Kowashi INOUE and others, and worked on a draft of the second Imperial Rescript on Education with Emperor Meiji&apos;s permission to revise the &apos;Imperial Rescript on Education.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1880, he supported Tatsuo KISHIMOTO, Kozo MIYAGI and Misao YASHIRO to establish Meiji Law School, and when he became the Minister of Education in 1894, he opposed the &apos;Imperial Rescript on Education&apos; made by Kowashi INOUE and others, and worked on a draft of the second Imperial Rescript on Education with Emperor Meiji&apos;s permission to revise the &apos;Imperial Rescript on Education.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1880, he supported Tatsuo KISHIMOTO, Kozo MIYAGI and Misao YASHIRO to establish Meiji Law School, and when he became the Minister of Education in 1894, he opposed the &apos;Imperial Rescript on Education&apos; made by Kowashi INOUE and others, and worked on a draft of the second Imperial Rescript on Education with Emperor Meiji&apos;s permission to revise the &apos;Imperial Rescript on Education.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>結局、西園寺の大臣退任により教育勅語の改正実現には至らなかったが「もっとリベラルの方へ向けて教育の方針を立つべきものだと思った」と回想している（白柳秀湖『西園寺公望伝』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the end, due to Saionji&apos;s retirement from the position of the Minister of Education, the revise of the Imperial Rescript on Education was not realized, but he reflected, &apos;I believed that the educational policy should be developed for more liberal way&apos; (&quot;Biography of Kinmochi SAIONJI&quot; by Shuko SHIRAYANAGI).</e>
<cmt>登録では『西園寺公望伝』がSaionji Kinmochi den (story)となっていますが、Biography of Kinmochi SAIONJIにしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the end, due to Saionji&apos;s retirement as Minister of Education, the revision of the Imperial Rescript on Education was not realized, but he reflected, &apos;I believed that the educational policy should be developed for more liberal way&apos; (&quot;Biography of Kinmochi SAIONJI&quot; by Shuko SHIRAYANAGI).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the end, due to Saionji&apos;s retirement as Minister of Education, the revision of the Imperial Rescript on Education was not realized, but he reflected, &apos;I believed that the educational policy should be developed for more liberal way&apos; (&quot;Biography of Kinmochi SAIONJI&quot; by Shuko SHIRAYANAGI).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>また文部大臣として東京帝国大学に対して「自由」な校風の帝国大学を作ろうと「京都帝国大学」の創設を実現している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the Minister of Education, he tried to build an imperial university with &apos;free&apos; school environment, compared to Tokyo Imperial University, and realized the establishment of &apos;Kyoto Imperial University.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Minister of Education, he tried to build an imperial university with a &apos;free&apos; school environment, compared to Tokyo Imperial University, and realized the establishment of &apos;Kyoto Imperial University.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Minister of Education, he tried to build an imperial university with a &apos;free&apos; school environment, compared to Tokyo Imperial University, and realized the establishment of &apos;Kyoto Imperial University.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>京都帝国大学の創設には、終生側近として仕える文部省官僚・中川小十郎が初代事務局長としてその中心的役割を担っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For the establishment of Kyoto Imperial University, Kojuro NAKAGAWA, an official of the Ministry of Education, who served as his lifelong aid, played a central role as the first Secretary General.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For the establishment of Kyoto Imperial University, Kojuro NAKAGAWA, an official of the Ministry of Education, who served as his lifelong aid, played a central role as the first Secretary General.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For the establishment of Kyoto Imperial University, Kojuro NAKAGAWA, an official of the Ministry of Education, who served as his lifelong aid, played a central role as the first Secretary General.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>この他、1901年、「女子を先ず人として教育する」の理念のもと成瀬仁蔵が創設する日本女子大学の設立発起人にも名を連ねている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides, he took his place among the promoters of the establishment of Japan Women&apos;s University, which Jinzo NARUSE established in 1901 with philosophy to &apos;educate a woman first as a person.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides, he took his place among the promoters for the establishment of the Japan Women&apos;s University, which Jinzo NARUSE established in 1901 with philosophy to &apos;educate a woman first as a person.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides, he took his place among the promoters for the establishment of the Japan Women&apos;s University, which Jinzo NARUSE established in 1901 with philosophy to &apos;educate a woman first as a person.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="35">
<j>京都法政学校への継承</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Inheritance to Kyoto Hosei (law and politics) School</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Inheritance to Kyoto Hosei (law and politics) School</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Inheritance to Kyoto Hosei (law and politics) School</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>西園寺文部大臣秘書官として京都帝国大学創設の中心に関わった中川小十郎は、大学創設実務が一段落すると官界を去り経済界に身を移した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kojuro NAKAGAWA, who got involved in the core of the establishment of Kyoto Imperial University as a secretary to the Education Minister Saionji, left the government and move to the business world after the practical business of the university establishment was settled.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kojuro NAKAGAWA, who was central to the establishment of Kyoto Imperial University as a secretary to the Education Minister Saionji, left the government and later moved to the business world after the university establishment was settled.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kojuro NAKAGAWA, who was central to the establishment of Kyoto Imperial University as a secretary to the Education Minister Saionji, left the government and later moved to the business world after the university establishment was settled.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>しかし、京都帝国大学が制度上旧制高等学校卒業生しか受け入れることができず、西園寺公望が提唱した「能力と意欲のある人に国として（教育の）機会を与えるべき」という教育理念からもかけ離れている実態に限界を感じ、自ら私学を興すことを思い立つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, since Kyoto Imperial University could only allowed graduates of old-education-system high schools due to its institution, which was actually far from the educational philosophy to &apos;give an (educational) opportunity to people with ability and motivation as a nation&apos; that Kinmochi SAIONJI proposed, he realized limitations and decided to establish a private school himself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, since Kyoto Imperial University could only allow graduates of old-education-system high schools due to its institution, which was actually far from the educational philosophy proposed by Kinmochi SAIONJI to &apos;give an (educational) opportunity to people with ability and motivation as a nation&apos;, he realized its limitations and decided to establish a private school himself.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, since Kyoto Imperial University could only allow graduates of old-education-system high schools due to its institution, which was in fact far from the educational philosophy proposed by Kinmochi SAIONJI to &apos;give an (educational) opportunity to people with ability and motivation as a nation,&apos; he realized its limitations and decided to establish a private school himself.</e>
<cmt>コンマ位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>中川は政財界の主要人物や学界人脈から後援を得るとともに、西園寺公望の実弟・末弘威麿らの協力を得て、上京区三本木通にあった料亭「清輝楼（旧・吉田屋）」を間借りして三年制の夜間学校を設立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nakagawa gained the cooperation from Takemaro SUEHIRO, a younger brother of Kinmochi SAIONJI, as well as the backing from key figures of the political and business worlds, and the network of the academy, and established a three-year night school by taking a room of &apos;Seikiro (former Yoshidaya),&apos; a restaurant in Sanbongi-dori Street, Kamigyo-ku Ward.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nakagawa gained cooperation from Takemaro SUEHIRO, a younger brother of Kinmochi SAIONJI, as well as backing from key figures in the political and business worlds, as well as the network of the academy, and established a three-year night school by taking a room of &apos;Seikiro (former Yoshidaya),&apos; a restaurant in Sanbongi-dori Street, Kamigyo-ku Ward.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nakagawa gained cooperation from Takemaro SUEHIRO, a younger brother of Kinmochi SAIONJI, as well as backing from key figures in the political and business worlds, as well as the network of the academy, and established a three-year night school by taking a room of &apos;Seikiro (former Yoshidaya),&apos; a restaurant in Sanbongi-dori Street, Kamigyo Ward.</e>
<cmt>住所表記</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>これが「京都法政学校」である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was &apos;Kyoto Hosei School.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was &apos;Kyoto Hosei School.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was &apos;Kyoto Hosei School.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>京都法政学校は、西園寺公望の教育への理想を体現する形で設置が進んだ京都帝国大学の補完的役割を担うという名目で設置された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Hosei School was established in order to take a supplemental role for Kyoto Imperial University, which was established to embody Kinmochi SAIONJI&apos;s educational ideal.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Hosei School was established in order to take a supplemental role for Kyoto Imperial University, which was established to embody Kinmochi SAIONJI&apos;s educational ideal.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Hosei School was established in order to take a supplemental role for Kyoto Imperial University, which was established to embody Kinmochi SAIONJI&apos;s educational ideal.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>事実、講義のほぼ全てが京都帝国大学教授により行われていたほか、京都法政学校を母体にのちに設立される「財団法人立命館」の寄付行為には、財団解散時には所有財産の全てが京都帝国大学に寄付されることなどが明記されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In fact, almost all the lectures were given by professors of Kyoto Imperial University, and the endowment act of &apos;Ritsumeikan Foundation,&apos; which would be established later based on Kyoto Hosei School, specified that all the holdings would be donated to Kyoto Imperial University when the Foundation dissolved.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In fact, almost all the lectures given by professors of Kyoto Imperial University, and the endowment act of &apos;Ritsumeikan Foundation,&apos; which would be established later based on Kyoto Hosei School, specified that all holdings would be donated to Kyoto Imperial University when the Foundation dissolved.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact, almost all the lectures given by professors of Kyoto Imperial University, and the endowment act of &apos;Ritsumeikan Foundation,&apos; which would be established later based on Kyoto Hosei School, specified that all holdings would be donated to Kyoto Imperial University when the Foundation dissolved.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="42">
<j>京都法政学校はその校名が示すとおり、当初は法律科と政治科との二学科を置くのみであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As its school name showed, Kyoto Hosei School only had two departments at first - law department and politics department.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As its school name showed, Kyoto Hosei School only had two departments at first - law department and politics department.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As its school name showed, Kyoto Hosei School only had two departments at first - law department and politics department.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>しかしながら、ゆくゆくは医学科・文学科などを置いて総合学園とすることを視野に入れており、京都法政学校という名称が実体を反映するものでなかった（詳細は「京都法政学校」を参照）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, creating a comprehensive university with medical department and literature department ultimately was brought into view, so the name Kyoto Hosei School did not reflect its substance (See &apos;Kyoto Hosei School for details).</e>
<cmt>登録では「総合学園」がintegrated school（定訳不明）ですが、comprehensive universityにしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, creating a comprehensive university with medical and literature departments was ultimately brought into view, so the name Kyoto Hosei School did not reflect its substance (See &apos;Kyoto Hosei School for details).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, creating a comprehensive university with medical and literature departments was ultimately brought into view, so the name Kyoto Hosei School did not reflect its substance (See &apos;Kyoto Hosei School for details).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>1904（明治37）年には大学部に経済科が設置され教学内容が法政学校としての域を越えると、実体を体現する新たな名称が必要になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1904, when economics department was established, and its teaching contents went beyond the limit as a law and politics school, it needed a new name to embody its substance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1904, when the economics department was established, and its teaching contents went beyond the limit as a law and politics school, it needed a new name to embody its substance.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1904, when the economics department was established, and its teaching contents went beyond the limit as a law and politics school, it needed a new name to embody its substance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>そこで西園寺公望が京都帝国大学設立に託した、政治権力から一線を画したリベラルでアカデミックな学風という理念の源流にある「私塾立命館」の名称の継承を申し出、西園寺がこれを快諾した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, it made an offer to inherit the name &apos;Shijuku Ritsumeikan&apos; the source of the philosophy as liberal and academic school environment separated from the political power, which Kinmochi SAIONJI left with the establishment of Kyoto Imperial University, and Saionji kindly agreed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, it made an offer to inherit the name &apos;Shijuku Ritsumeikan&apos;, embodying the spirit of being a liberal and academic school environment separated from political power, which Kinmochi SAIONJI left with the establishment of Kyoto Imperial University, and Saionji kindly agreed.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, it made an offer to inherit the name &apos;Shijuku Ritsumeikan,&apos; embodying the spirit of being a liberal and academic school environment separated from political power, which Kinmochi SAIONJI left with the establishment of Kyoto Imperial University, and Saionji kindly agreed.</e>
<cmt>コンマの位置</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>このとき西園寺は1869（明治2）年の私塾開設と同時に自身で揮毫した「立命館」の大書を送るとともに、自ら次のような扁額をしたためて寄贈している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, Saionji sent a big sign of &apos;Ritsumeikan&apos; that he had written by himself when the private academy was established in 1869, as well as giving the following framed motto he wrote by himself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, Saionji sent a big sign with the letters &apos;Ritsumeikan&apos; that he had written himself when the private academy was established in 1869, as well as giving the following framed motto he wrote himself.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, Saionji sent a big sign with the letters &apos;Ritsumeikan&apos; that he had written himself when the private academy was established in 1869, as well as giving the following framed motto he wrote himself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="47">
<j>立命館</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ritsumeikan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ritsumeikan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ritsumeikan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>-　往年、余は一校を興し名づけて立命館という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">- Once, I established a school named Ritsumeikan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">- Once, I established a school named Ritsumeikan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">- Once, I established a school named Ritsumeikan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>泰西に遊学するに及んで、校廃し名存す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While studying in the West, the school closed but the name remained.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While studying in the West, the school closed but the name remained.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While studying in the West, the school closed but the name remained.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>この頃京都法政学校学員来り、その名を襲用することを請う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time the staff of Kyoto Hosei School came and ask for inheriting the name.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time the staff of Kyoto Hosei School came and asked to inherit the name.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time the staff of Kyoto Hosei School came and asked to inherit the name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>余は名の実を得ることを喜び、すなわち扁額を書してもってこれを与う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">I was delighted that the name would get its substance, and would write and give a framed motto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">I was delighted that the name would live out its meaning, and as such I hereby write and present this framed motto.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">I was delighted that the name would live out its meaning, and as such I hereby write and present this framed motto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>孟子いわく、殀寿貳わず、身を修めて以て之を俟つは、命を立つる所以なりと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mencius said that our longevity was determined by a fate, and waiting for the fate with cultivating the mind would fulfill our duties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mencius said that our longevity was determined by fate, and waiting for our fate to befall us while cultivating the mind would fulfill our duties.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mencius said that our longevity was determined by fate, and waiting for our fate to befall us while cultivating the mind would fulfill our duties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>蓋し学問の要はここに在り。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is exactly the point of learning.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is exactly the point of learning.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is exactly the point of learning.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>明治三十八年四月　侯爵 西園寺公望</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April in 1905, Prince Kinmochi SAIONJI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April in 1905, Prince Kinmochi SAIONJI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April in 1905, Prince Kinmochi SAIONJI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="55">
<j>1905（明治5）年、西園寺公望から「私塾立命館」の名称の継承を許された「京都法政学校」は、1913（大正2）年に「財団法人立命館」を設置するとともに、大学名を「立命館大学」、中学校名を「立命館中学校・高等学校」と改称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1905, &apos;Kyoto Hosei School,&apos; which was allowed to inherit the name &apos;Shijuku Ritsumeikan&apos; by Kinmochi SAIONJI, established &apos;Ritsumeikan Foundation&apos; in 1913, and renamed the university &apos;Ritsumeikan University&apos; and the junior high school &apos;Ritsumeikan Junior/Senior High Schools.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1905, &apos;Kyoto Hosei School,&apos; which was allowed to inherit the name &apos;Shijuku Ritsumeikan&apos; by Kinmochi SAIONJI, established &apos;Ritsumeikan Foundation&apos; in 1913, and renamed the university &apos;Ritsumeikan University&apos; and the junior high school &apos;Ritsumeikan Junior/Senior High Schools.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1905, &apos;Kyoto Hosei School,&apos; which was allowed to inherit the name &apos;Shijuku Ritsumeikan&apos; by Kinmochi SAIONJI, established &apos;Ritsumeikan Foundation&apos; in 1913, and renamed the university &apos;Ritsumeikan University&apos; and the junior high school &apos;Ritsumeikan Junior/Senior High Schools.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>西園寺は公人として特定の私学に肩入れすることをよしとしなかったが、最後まで立命館学園の発展に有形無形の支援を続けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though Saionji frowned on commitment to a specific private school as a public figure, he continued to give tangible and intangible support to the development of Ritsumeikan Gakuen (academy) for the rest of his life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though Saionji frowned on committing to a specific private school as a public figure, he continued to give tangible and intangible support to the development of Ritsumeikan Gakuen (academy) for the rest of his life.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though Saionji frowned on committing to a specific private school as a public figure, he continued to give tangible and intangible support to the development of Ritsumeikan Gakuen (academy) for the rest of his life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>「立命館」の由来</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Origin of &apos;Ritsumeikan&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Origin of &apos;Ritsumeikan&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Origin of &apos;Ritsumeikan&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="57">
<j>「立命」は中国の孟子の一節『殀壽不貳　修身以俟之　所以立命也』から採られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ritsumei (立命)&apos; originated from a line, &quot;殀壽不貳 修身以俟之 所以立命也,&quot; by Mencius in China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ritsumei (立命)&apos; originated from a line, &quot;殀壽不貳 修身以俟之 所以立命也,&quot; by Mencius in China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ritsumei (立命)&apos; originated from a line, &quot;殀壽不貳 修身以俟之 所以立命也,&quot; by Mencius in China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>これは、「人間の寿命は、天命によって決められている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This means &apos;Our longevity is determined by a fate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This means &apos;Our longevity is determined by fate.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This means &apos;Our longevity is determined by fate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>修養に努めてその天命を待つのが人間の本分の全うである」という意味である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Waiting for the fate with cultivating the mind will fulfill our duties.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Waiting for our fate to befall us while cultivating the mind will fulfill our duties.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Waiting for our fate to befall us while cultivating the mind will fulfill our duties.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 西山東男(id:73339), J o(id:26533), Straysheep(id:42448), Ganman(id:96316), Mixtures(id:29234), 表現等規制委員会(id:61918), まったけ(id:130042), Kaznov17(id:68122), ごまふあざ(id:36855), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>