<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>八坂女紅場学園</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasaka Nyokoba Gakuen</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasaka Nyokoba Gakuen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasaka Nyokoba Gakuen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>八坂女紅場学園（やさかにょこうばがくえん）（祇園女子技芸学校（ぎおんじょしぎげいがっこう））は、京都市東山区祇園甲部にある舞妓・芸妓のための教育施設。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasaka Nyokoba Gakuen (Gion Joshi Gikei School) is an educational institution of Maiko and Geiko which located in Kobe Gion Higashiyama-ku Kyoto city.</e>
<cmt>祇園女子技芸学校: 定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasaka Nyokoba Gakuen (Gion Joshi Gikei School) is an educational institution of Maiko and Geiko that is located in Kobe Gion, Higashiyama-ku, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasaka Nyokoba Gakuen (Gion Joshi Gigei School) is an educational institution of Maiko and Geiko located in Kobu Gion, Higashiyama-ku, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>甲部=Kobu 技芸=Gigei</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Outline</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Outline</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>統一用語</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>明治5年に創設された八坂女紅場を母体に、昭和26年創立。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1951, established the school that was based on Yasaka Nyokouba that established in 1916.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1951the school was established based on Yasaka Nyokouba, which was established in 1916.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1951, the school was established based on Yasaka Nyokoba, which was founded in 1916.</e>
<cmt>Nyokouba→Nyokoba</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>都をどりで知られる祇園甲部歌舞練場（ぎおんこうぶかぶれんじょう）に付属するように看板があがっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The billboard is attached to Gionkobu Kaburenjo which is famous about Miyako dance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The billboard is attached to Gionkobu Kaburenjo, which is famous in regard to the Miyako dance.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The billboard is attached to Gionkobu Kaburenjo, which is famous in regard to the Miyako dance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>通称「にょこば」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Commonly known as &apos;Nyokoba&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is commonly known as &apos;Nyokoba.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is commonly known as &apos;Nyokoba.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="6">
<j>必須科目は井上流、鳴物、茶道、三味線。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The required subjects are Inoue-ryu, narimono, sado and shamisen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The required subjects are inoue-ryu, narimono, sado and shamisen.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The required subjects are Inoue-ryu, Narimono, Sado and Shamisen.</e>
<cmt>大文字</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>その他、能楽・長唄・一中節・常磐津・清元・地唄・浄瑠璃・小唄・笛・華道・書道・日本画などを学ぶことができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also able to learn nogaku, nagauta, icchubushi, tokiwazu, kiyomoto, jiuta, joruri, kouta, fue (flute), kado (flower arrangement), shodo (calligraphy) and nihonga (Japanese painting).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One can also learn nogaku, nagauta, icchubushi, tokiwazu, kiyomoto, jiuta, joruri, kouta, fue (flute), kado (flower arrangement), shodo (calligraphy) and nihonga (Japanese painting).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One can also learn Nogaku, Nagauta, Icchubushi, Tokiwazu, Kiyomoto, Jiuta, Joruri, Kouta, Fue (flute), Kado (flower arrangement), Shodo (calligraphy) and Nihonga (Japanese painting).</e>
<cmt>大文字</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>「学園」とつくが、学制外の施設である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It calls &apos;Gakuen&apos; but it&apos;s not an educational institute.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It it called &apos;Gakuen&apos; but it isn&apos;t an educational institution.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is called &apos;Gakuen (school)&apos; but it isn&apos;t an educational institution.</e>
<cmt>GakuenはSchoolとして意味を示さなければ、文自体が無意味になると思われます。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>生徒は祇園の芸・舞妓の全員で、年齢は15歳から80過ぎまでと幅広い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">All the students of Gei of Gion and Maiko are age wide from 15 years old to 18 years old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The students of Gei of Gion and Maiko range from 15 to 18 years of age.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The students of Geiko and Maiko of Gion range from 15 to over 80 years of age.</e>
<cmt>芸・舞妓＝げいこ・まいこ「80過ぎ」に修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="10">
<j>八坂女紅場学園は財団法人で、お茶屋の並ぶ祇園町南側界隈の「地主」でもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Yasaka Nyokouba Gakuen is zaidan-hojin (foundation) and also the &apos;landowner&apos; of the neighborhood of Minami-gawa Gion-machi where the ochaya are lined up.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Yasaka Nyokouba Gakuen is zaidan-hojin (foundation) and also the &apos;landowner&apos; of the neighborhood of Minami-gawa Gion-machi, in which the ochaya are located.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Yasaka Nyokouba Gakuen is Zaidan-hojin (foundation) and also the &apos;landowner&apos; of the neighborhood of Minami-gawa Gion-machi, in which the Ochaya are located.</e>
<cmt>大文字</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="11">
<j>参考図書：『コモンズとしての地域空間－新たな住まい方をめざして』平竹耕三著　2002年</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reference book: “Local area commons: For a new way of living” by Kozo HIRATAKE in 2002.</e>
<cmt>『コモンズとしての地域空間－新たな住まい方をめざして』: http://ci.nii.ac.jp/naid/110002963238/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reference book: “Local Area Commons: For a New Way of Living,” by Kozo HIRATAKE (2002)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reference book: “Local Area Commons: For a New Way of Living,” by Kozo HIRATAKE (2002)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="12">
<j>「女紅場」（じょこうば）は、明治初期、全国でにつくられた女子のための習い事の施設。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jokoba&apos; is the class to take some lessons for girl in Japan early Meiji period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jokoba&apos; was the class in which girls of the early Meiji period could receive instruction.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jokoba&apos; was the class in which girls of the early Meiji period could receive instruction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>のちにこの言葉は用いられなくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, this word was not used anymore.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This word eventually became obsolete</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This word eventually became obsolete.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Mnd(id:15140), Umzk555(id:33692), Miya(id:1881), OiOiO(id:94238), Ultratomio(id:1090), MT.Stone(id:2812), NDR(id:5500), 秋の虹(id:18259), 満月(id:82772), ShikiH(id:181574), 今紫(id:9521), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>