<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>五条坂</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gojo-zaka</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gojo-zaka</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gojo-zaka</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>五条坂（ごじょうざか）は、京都市内の通りの一つである五条通の東端部分の別名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gojo-zaka is the different name of the east end section of the Gojo-dori Street.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gojo-zaka is another name for the eastern section of Gojo-dori Street, a street running inside Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gojo-zaka is another name for the eastern section of Gojo-dori Street, a street running inside Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>および東大路通との交差点の名称（五条坂交差点）を表す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It also refers to the name of a crossing (Gojozaka crossing) with the Higashioji-dori Street.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It also refers to the name of a crossing (Gojozaka crossing) with Higashioji-dori Street.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It also refers to the name of a crossing (Gojozaka crossing) with Higashioji-dori Street.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>本項では両方を記述する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This article describes the both.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This article describes both.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This section describes both.</e>
<cmt>&quot;article&quot; -&gt; &quot;section&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>通りとしての五条坂</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gojo-zaka as a street</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gojo-zaka as a street</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gojo-zaka as a street</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>五条通の東端部分の別名であり、東大路通（五条坂交差点）から清水寺へ向かって清水道（松原通の東端部分の別名）までの坂道を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gojo-zaka is the different name of the east end section of the Gojo-dori Street, referring to a slope heading toward Kiyomizu-dera Temple from the Higashioji-dori Street (Gojozaka crossing) to Kiyomizu-michi (Matsubara-dori Street).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gojo-zaka is another name for the eastern section of Gojo-dori Street, referring to a slope heading toward Kiyomizu-dera Temple from the Higashioji-dori Street (Gojozaka crossing) to Kiyomizu-michi (Matsubara-dori Street).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gojo-zaka is another name for the eastern section of Gojo-dori Street, referring to a slope heading toward Kiyomizu-dera Temple from the Higashioji-dori Street (Gojozaka crossing) to Kiyomizu-michi (Matsubara-dori Street).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>また、五条大橋東詰（京阪五条駅 (京阪)）から東大路通に掛けての五条通（国道1号）も含めた区間を指していう場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some refer to the section including the section of Gojo-dori Street (National Highway Route No. 1) from Gojo-ohashi Higashizume (east foot of Gojo-Ohashi bridge) to the Gojo-dori Street.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some refer to the section as including the section of Gojo-dori Street (National Highway Route No. 1) from Gojo-ohashi Higashizume (east foot of Gojo-Ohashi bridge) to Gojo-dori Street.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some refer to the section as including the section of Gojo-dori Street (National Highway Route No. 1) from Gojo-ohashi Higashizume (east foot of Gojo-Ohashi bridge) to Higashioji-dori Street.</e>
<cmt>道名修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>五条坂交差点以東の部分については、京都でも有数の観光地である清水寺への第一のアクセスになっているため、清水焼や土産物を売る店が並ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The section from the Gojozaka crossing is lined with shops dealing in kiyomizu-ware, because it provides the primary access to Kiyomizu-dera Temple, one of the most popular tourist spots</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The section from Gojozaka crossing is lined with shops dealing in kiyomizu-ware, because it provides primary access to Kiyomizu-dera Temple, one of the most popular tourist spots</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The section from Gojozaka crossing is lined with shops dealing in kiyomizu-ware and souvenir, because it provides primary access to Kiyomizu-dera Temple, one of the most popular tourist spots in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>in Kyoto補足and souvenior補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>観光バスがすれ違うのがやっとの道幅であり、春や秋の観光シーズンには、東大路通から歩く観光客がここを通り、門前近くの駐車場へ向かう観光バス・タクシー・自家用車とあわせ、混雑が激しい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The street, which is barely wide enough for two sightseeing basses to pass each other, is crowded with tourists walking up from the Higashioji-dori Street together with sightseeing busses, taxis, and private cars going to parking lots near the gate in spring and autumn sightseeing seasons.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The street, which is barely wide enough for two sightseeing buses to pass each other, is crowded with tourists walking up from Higashioji-dori Street together with sightseeing busses, taxis, and private cars going to parking lots near the gate during the spring and autumn sightseeing seasons.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The street, which is barely wide enough for two sightseeing buses to pass each other, is crowded with tourists walking up from Higashioji-dori Street together with sightseeing busses, taxis, and private cars going to parking lots near the gate during the spring and autumn sightseeing seasons.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>2005年11月には初めて観光ピーク時の土・日曜日および休日に通行禁止とする実験的措置がとられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In November, 2005, an experimental measures were taken to close vehicles on week ends and holidays of sightseeing for the first time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In November, 2005, temporary measures were taken to close vehicle access during weekends and holidays in peak sighseeing season.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In November 2005, temporary measures were taken to close vehicle access during weekends and holidays in peak sightseeing season.</e>
<cmt>,削除スペルを修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="10">
<j>2007年は、そのような措置は取られず、観光ピーク時の土・日曜日および休日には、東大路通南行きから五条坂への左折が禁止されるにとどまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 2007, such a measures was not taken: instated, only left turn into Gojo-zaka was prohibited at Gojo-ohashi Higashizume on week ends and holidays of sightseeing for the first time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 2007, the measures were not taken: instead only a left turn into Gojo-zaka was prohibited at Gojo-ohashi Higashizume during weekends and holidays in peak sighseeing season.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 2007, the measures were not taken: instead only a left turn into Gojo-zaka was prohibited at Gojo-ohashi Higashizume during weekends and holidays in peak sightseeing season.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="11">
<j>五条大橋東詰から東大路通に掛けての区間も含めて、毎年8月上旬に「陶器まつり (東山区)」（山科区の清水焼団地で7月第4週に開催される陶器まつり (山科区)とは別のものである）が開催される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toki Matsuri (Ceramic Work Festival) is held in early August every year on the street between the section between Gojozaka crossing and Higashioji-dori Street and its surroundings (The Toki Masuril held at Kiyomizuyaki-danchi in the Yamashina Ward on the fourth week of July has no relation).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toki Matsuri (Ceramic Work Festival) is held in early August every year on the street in the section located between Gojozaka crossing and Higashioji-dori Street and its surroundings (The Toki Matsuri held at Kiyomizuyaki-danchi in the Yamashina Ward on the fourth week of July has no relation).</e>
<cmt>Robert: This translator has a ton of spelling errors: advise him to use spell check.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toki Matsuri (Ceramic Work Festival) (Higashiyama Ward) is held in early August every year on the street in the section located between Gojo-ohashi Higashizume and Higashioji-dori Street and its surroundings (The Toki Matsuri held at Kiyomizuyaki-danchi in the Yamashina Ward on the fourth week of July has no relation).</e>
<cmt>Gojozaka crossing→Gojo-ohashi Higashizume(Higashiyama Ward)補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="12">
<j>この五条大橋-東大路通の区間は第二次世界大戦末期の建物疎開により拡幅された片側4車線の広い通りである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The section between Gojo-ohashi and the Higashioji-dori Street was widened through building evacuation at the end of World War II, resulting into a street having 4 lane for traffic in each direction.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The section between Gojo-ohashi and the Higashioji-dori Street was widened through building demolition at the end of World War II, resulting in each street having 4 lanes for traffic in each direction.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The section between Gojo-ohashi and the Higashioji-dori Street was widened through building demolition at the end of World War II, resulting in each street having 4 lanes for traffic in each direction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="13">
<j>また、大和大路通五条交差点北側には「是より五條坂」と記された碑が建つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A monument saying &quot;This is Gojo-zaka from here&quot; stands on the left side of Yamato-oji-dori Gojo crossing,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A monument saying &quot;This is Gojo-zaka from here&quot; stands on the left side of Yamato-oji-dori Gojo crossing,</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A monument saying &apos;This is Gojo-zaka from here&apos; stands on the north side of Yamato-oji-dori Gojo crossing,</e>
<cmt>left→north</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>沿道の施設</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Facilities long the Street</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Facilities along the street</e>
<cmt>Spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Facilities along the street</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="14">
<j>京都陶磁器会館</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Tojiki Kaikan (Kyoto Ceramic Center)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Tojiki Kaikan (Kyoto Ceramic Center)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Tojiki Kaikan (Kyoto Ceramic Center)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="15">
<j>清水寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyomizu-dera Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyomizu-dera Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyomizu-dera Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="16">
<j>地主神社（縁結びの神様）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jishu-jinja Shrine (deity of marriage)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jishu-jinja Shrine (deity of marriage)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jishu-jinja Shrine (deity of marriage)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="17">
<j>茶わん坂</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chawan-zaka slope</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chawan-zaka slope</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chawan-zaka Slope</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="18">
<j>産寧坂（三年坂）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sannei-zaka Slope (Sannen-zaka slope)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sannei-zaka Slope (Sannen-zaka slope)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sannei-zaka Slope (Sannen-zaka Slope)</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="19">
<j>二寧坂（二年坂）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ninen-zaka slope (Ninen-zaka slope)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ninen-zaka slope (Ninen-zaka slope)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ninen-zaka Slope (Ninen-zaka Slope)</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="20">
<j>六波羅蜜寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rokuharamitsu-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rokuharamitsu-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rokuharamitsu-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="21">
<j>五条坂交差点</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gojo-zaka Crossing</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gojo-zaka Crossing</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gojo-zaka Crossing</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>京都市東山区に位置し、東大路通と五条坂の交差点にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Located in the Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City, it is the crossing between the Higashioji-dori Street and Gojo-zaka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Located in the Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City, it is a crossing between Higashioji-dori Street and Gojo-zaka.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Located in the Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City, it is a crossing between Higashioji-dori Street and Gojo-zaka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>東大路通のすぐ南に東山五条交差点が位置し、連続した交差点を形成している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It constitutes successive crossings together with the Higashiyama Gojo crossing immediately south on the Higashioji-dori Street.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is constituted of successive crossings with Higashiyama Gojo crossing immediately south on Higashioji-dori Street.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is constituted of successive crossings with Higashiyama Gojo crossing immediately south on Higashioji-dori Street.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>清水寺への最寄りバス停留所が位置するため、多くの観光客を見ることができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many tourists can be found because the nearest bus stop from Kiyomizu-dera Temple is located at the crossing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many tourists can be found because the nearest bus stop from Kiyomizu-dera Temple is located at the crossing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many tourists can be found because the nearest bus stop from Kiyomizu-dera Temple is located at the crossing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="25">
<j>交通</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Transportation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Transportation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Transportation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="26">
<j>京阪バス（五条坂停留所）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keihan Bus Co.,Ltd. (Gojozaka stop)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keihan Bus Co.,Ltd. (Gojozaka stop)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keihan Bus Co., Ltd. (Gojozaka stop)</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="27">
<j>京都市営バス（五条坂停留所）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto City Bus (Gojozaka stop)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto City Bus (Gojozaka stop)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto City Bus (Gojozaka stop)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="28">
<j>京都バス（東山五条停留所）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Bus Co.,Ltd. (Higashiyama-Gojo stop)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Bus Co.,Ltd. (Higashiyama-Gojo stop)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Bus Co., Ltd. (Higashiyama-Gojo stop)</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Miyuki h(id:84952), うら(id:40695), Nakadati(id:26815), Chi-Ham(id:143515), 金山銀山銅山(id:163855), 目蒲東急之介(id:34741), Jade0416(id:104181), Hatsune(id:26654), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>