<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>醒ヶ井通</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Samegai-Doori Street</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Samegai-Doori Street</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Samegai-dori Street</e>
<cmt>&quot;-dori Street&quot;に修正</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>醒ヶ井通（さめがいどおり）は京都市内の南北の通りの一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Samegai-doori street is one of the streets running from north to south in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Samegai-doori street is a street running north-south through Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Samegai-dori Street is a street running north-south through Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>&quot;-dori Street&quot;に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>北は六角通から南は五条通まで。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Samegai-doori street runs from Rokkaku-doori street at its north end to Gojo-doori street at its south end.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Samegai-doori street runs from Rokkaku-doori street at its north end to Gojo-doori street at its south end.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Samegai-dori Street runs from Rokkaku-dori Street at its north end to Gojo-dori Street at its south end.</e>
<cmt>&quot;-dori Street&quot;に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>途中蛸薬師通と錦小路通の間で京都市立堀川高等学校敷地により分断されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Samegai-doori street is divided in the middle of itself by the premises of Kyoto Municipal Horikawa High School between Takoyakushi-doori street and Nishikikoji-doori street.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Samegai-doori street is divided in the middle by Kyoto Municipal Horikawa High School between Takoyakushi-doori street and Nishikikoji-doori street.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Samegai-dori Street is divided in the middle by Kyoto Municipal Horikawa High School between Takoyakushi-dori Street and Nishikikoji-dori Street.</e>
<cmt>&quot;-dori Street&quot;に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>五条通以南では、西隣の堀川通が東よりに拡張されたためにこれと重なり消滅した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A section of Samegai-doori street in the south of a point on Gojo-doori street vanished because Horikawa-doori street which is located next to the street and in the west of the street was expanded eastward and overlapped the section.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A section of Samegai-doori street south of Gojo-doori street vanished because Horikawa-doori street which is located next to and west of the street was expanded eastward and overlapped the section.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A section of Samegai-dori Street south of Gojo-dori Street vanished because Horikawa-dori Street which is located next to and west of the street was expanded eastward and overlapped the section.</e>
<cmt>&quot;-dori Street&quot;に修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>平安京には存在せず、豊臣秀吉による天正の地割で新設された通りである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This street did not exist in Heiankyo and was newly constructed in the land division in Tensho ordered by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This street did not exist in Heiankyo and was newly constructed according to the Tensho land division ordered by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow/Robert: Check red portion, original translation was kind of unclear</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This street did not exist in Heiankyo and was newly constructed according to the Tensho no Jiwari (land allotment system in Tensho era) ordered by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI.</e>
<cmt>「天正の地割」の意味を明確にするため表記を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>堀川五条にあり名水として知られた井戸「佐女牛井」（さめがい）が通り名の由来である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Samegai-doori street was named after a well &quot;Samegai&quot; which was located in Horikawagojo and whose water was famous as excellent quality water.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Samegai-doori street was named after the well &quot;Samegai&quot; which was located in Horikawagojo and whose water was famous for its excellent quality.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Samegai-dori Street was named after the well &apos;Samegai&apos; which was located in Horikawagojo and whose water was famous for its excellent quality.</e>
<cmt>&quot;-dori Street&quot;に修正、シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Matsukaze(id:51778), 0null0(id:582), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>