<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>下鴨本通</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shimogamohon-dori Street</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shimogamohon-dori Street</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shimogamohon-dori Street</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>下鴨本通（しもがもほんどおり）は京都市の南北の主要な通りの一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shimogamohon-dori Street is one of the main street at north and south in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shimogamohon-dori Street is a main street running north-sout though Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shimogamohon-dori Street is a main street running north-sout though Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>左京区下鴨の中央を南北に貫き、南は鴨川 (淀川水系)に架かる新葵橋を介してそのまま河原町通に続く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The street runs through center of Shimogamo, Sakyo-Ward to south east, and it continues to run to Kawaramachi-dori Street through the Shin-Aoi Bridge which is on the Kamo River (Yodo River series).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The street runs through the center of Shimogamo, Sakyo-Ward, south east, and continues to run up to Kawaramachi-dori Street through the Shin-Aoi Bridge which is on the Kamo River (Yodo River series).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The street runs through the center of Shimogamo, Sakyo Ward, south east, and continues to run up to Kawaramachi-dori Street through the Shin Aoi-bashi Bridge which is on the Kamo-gawa River (Yodo-gawa River series).</e>
<cmt>Sakyo Ward, Shin Aoi-bashi Bridge, Kamo-gawa River, Yodo-gawa Riverとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="3">
<j>同じく下鴨を南北に貫く下鴨東通・下鴨中通・下鴨西通と異なり4車線と広く直線的である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The street has wide and straight line with 4 car lines which is different from the street which also runs through north and south from Shimogamo, which is Shimogamohigashi-dori Street, Shimogamonaka-dori Street, and Shimogamonishi-dori Street.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The street runs wide and straight with 4 car lanes, which differs from the other streets running north-south from Shimogamo, such as Shimogamohigashi-dori Street, Shimogamonaka-dori Street, and Shimogamonishi-dori Street.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The street runs wide and straight with four car lanes, which differs from the other streets running north-south from Shimogamo, such as Shimogamohigashi-dori Street, Shimogamonaka-dori Street, and Shimogamonishi-dori Street.</e>
<cmt>4をスペルアウト</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="4">
<j>北大路通（バス停留所で京都府立洛北中学校・高等学校前（当時のバス停は市電洛北高校前、鉄道駅は洛北高校前）、交差点では下鴨本通北大路）から南は京都市電河原町線が1978年まで走っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto City Railway, Kawaramachi Line used to run from Kitaoji-dori Street (bus stop was at Kyoto Prefectural Rakuhoku High School), (at that time, bus stop was Shiden Rakuhokukoko mae, and train station was Rakuhokukoko-mae), Shimogamohon-dori Kitaoji-dori Street at intersection) at south until 1978.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto City Railway, Kawaramachi Line used to run from Kitaoji-dori Street (the bus stop was located at Kyoto Prefectural Rakuhoku High School), (at that time, the bus stop was known as Shiden Rakuhokukoko mae, and the train station was known as Rakuhokukoko-mae), and intersecting with Shimogamohon-dori Kitaoji-dori Street) to the south until 1978.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto City Railway, Kawaramachi Line used to run from Kitaoji-dori Street (the bus stop was located at Kyoto Prefectural Rakuhoku High School), (at that time, the bus stop was known as Shiden Rakuhokukoko-mae, and the train station was known as Rakuhokukoko-mae), and intersecting with Shimogamohon-dori Kitaoji-dori Street) to the south until 1978.</e>
<cmt>表記をRakuhokukoko-maeに統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="5">
<j>賀茂御祖神社（下鴨神社）はこの沿道にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kamo mioyajjinja Shrine (Shimogamo Jinja Shrine) is located on this street.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kamo mioyajjinja Shrine (Shimogamo Jinja Shrine) is located on this street.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kamo Mioya-jinja Shrine (Shimogamo-jinja Shrine) is located on this street.</e>
<cmt>スペルミスを訂正し、表記をKamo Mioya-jinja Shrine, Shimogamo-jinja Shrineとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>交差する道路</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Crossing roads.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cross roads</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cross Roads</e>
<cmt>頭文字を大文字にしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>上側が北側、下側が南側。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Upper side is north, down side is south.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The upper side is considered the northern portion, while the lower side is considered the southern portion.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The upper side is considered the northern portion, while the lower side is considered the southern portion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>左側が西側、右側が東側。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Left side is west, and right side is east.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The left side is considered the western portion, while the right side is considered the east portion.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The left side is considered the western portion, while the right side is considered the east portion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>交差する道路の特記がないものは市町村道。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The crossing roads without sign belong to the municipality&apos;s road.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cross roads with signs belong to the city.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cross roads with signs belong to the city.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>沿道の主な施設</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Main facilities on the roadside</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Main road side facilities</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Main Roadside Facilities</e>
<cmt>road side→roadsideとし、頭文字を大文字に修正</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="9">
<j>京都ノートルダム女子大学・ノートルダム学院小学校 北山通角</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Notre Dame University, Notre Dame Elementary School, Kitayama-dori Street</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Notre Dame University, Notre Dame Elementary School, Kitayama-dori Street</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Notre Dame University, Notre Dame Elementary School, Kitayama-dori Street</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>京都府立洛北中学校・高等学校</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Prefectural Rakuhoku High School</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Prefectural Rakuhoku High School</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Prefectural Rakuhoku High School</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>賀茂御祖神社（下鴨神社）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kamo mioyajjinja Shrine (Shimogamo Jinja Shrine)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kamo mioyajjinja Shrine (Shimogamo Jinja Shrine)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kamo Mioya-jinja Shrine (Shimogamo-jinja Shrine)</e>
<cmt>Kamo Mioya-jinja Shrine, Shimogamo-jinja Shrineとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>京都家庭裁判所 新葵橋西詰</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Family Court Shinaoibashi Nishi-zume</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Family Court Shinaoibashi Nishi-zume</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Family Court, Shin Aoi-bashi Bridge Nishi-zume</e>
<cmt>カンマを追加、前出の表記に合わせ、Shin Aoi-bashi Bridgeとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Miyuki h(id:84952), Hideyuki(id:9577), Y3006(id:155535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>