<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>長辻通</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagatsuji-dori Street</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagatsuji-dori Street</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagatsuji-dori Street</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>長辻通（ながつじどおり）は、京都市内の通りの一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagatsuji-dori Street is one of the street in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagatsuji-dori Street is a street in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagatsuji-dori Street is a street in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>南は渡月橋北詰から北は嵯峨釈迦堂前（清凉寺仁王門前）まで、京都の景勝地の一つ嵐山の中心部を貫き、観光利用による交通量が人、車両ともに多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This street runs from Togetsu Bridge at south to in front of Saga Shaka-do at north (in front of Nio Gate at Seiryo-ji Temple), and runs through the center of Arashiyama which is one of the picturesque place in Kyoto, and there is heavy traffic from people and cars for sightseeing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This street runs from Togetsu Bridge in the south to the front of Saga Shaka-do in the north (in front of Nio Gate at Seiryo-ji Temple), and runs through the center of Arashiyama which is a picturesque place in Kyoto, and contains heavy traffic caused by sighseers.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This street runs from the north end of Togetsu-kyo Bridge in the south to the front of Saga Shaka-do in the north (in front of Nio-mon Gate at Seiryo-ji Temple), and runs through the center of Arashiyama which is a picturesque place in Kyoto, and contains heavy traffic caused by sighseers.</e>
<cmt>Togetsu-kyo Bridge, Nio-mon Gateとし、「北詰」を訳出</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>渡月橋から天龍寺あたりが最も人通りが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The area from Togetsu Brigde to Tenryu-ji Temple is the busiest place.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The busies area is from Togetsu Brigde to Tenryu-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The busies area is from Togetsu-kyo Brigde to Tenryu-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>Togetsu-kyo Bridgeとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>三条通と丸太町通（新丸太町通）の区間では、近年、秋の観光シーズンに車両の北行一方通行の規制を行う交通社会実験が行われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Recently, the traffic examination which is the one-way traffic rule for north direction in fall sightseeing season is held at the section between Sanjo-dori Street and Marutamachi-dori Street (Shinmarutamachi-dori Street).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Recently, a regulation making all north bound traffic one-way was implemented during the fall sightseeing seasion for he section beteen Sanjo-dori Street and Marutamachi-dori Street (Shinmarutamachi-dori Street).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Recently, a regulation making all north bound traffic one-way was implemented during the fall sightseeing seasion for he section beteen Sanjo-dori Street and Marutamachi-dori Street (Shinmarutamachi-dori Street).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>丸太町通以北は車も人も減り、清凉寺（嵯峨釈迦堂）の仁王門をアイストップとするまっすぐな道が続いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is less traffic with car and people to north from Marutamachi-dori Street, and a straight street is continues to Nio Gate of Seiryo-ji Temple as ice-top.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is less vehicle and pedestrian traffic north bound from Marutamachi-dori Street, and a straight street continues up until the Nio Gate of Seiryo-ji Temple as an ice-top.</e>
<cmt>Robert: &quot;Ice-top&quot; doesn’t make sense. / Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is less vehicle and pedestrian traffic north bound from Marutamachi-dori Street, and a straight street continues up until the Nio-mon Gate of Seiryo-ji Temple (Saga Shaka-do) as an eyestop.</e>
<cmt>（嵯峨釈迦堂）を訳出、Nio-mon Gateとしました。 ice-top→&quot;eyestop&quot;に訂正 (参照: http://www.weblio.jp/content/%E3%82%A2%E3%82%A4%E3%82%B9%E3%83%88%E3%83%83%E3%83%97)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="6">
<j>嵯峨釈迦堂前から西に進んだ突き当たりが二尊院であり、そこから北へ向かう道は鳥居本を経て愛宕山（愛宕神社 (京都市)）へと続いており、愛宕街道とも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The end of the street from in front of Saga Shaka-do to west is Nison-in, the street toward to north goes through Toriimoto and continues to Atagoyama, it&apos;s called Atago Kaido.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the end of the street in front of Saga Shaka-do to the west, the street is known as Nison-in, while the street northbound which goes through Toriimoto and continues to Atagoyama, is called Atago Kaido.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the end of the street in front of Saga Shaka-do to the west, the street is known as Nison-in Temple, while the street northbound which goes through Toriimoto and continues to Mt. Atago, is called Atago kaido.</e>
<cmt>Nison-in Temple, Mt. Atago, Atago kaidoとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="7">
<j>南は、渡月橋を渡り嵯峨街道となり桂川右岸を南に進む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The south goes through Togetu Bridge and became Saga kaido and runs to south at right side shore of Katrura River.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the south, it goes through Togetu Bridge and becomes Saga kaido and runs south on the right side shore of Katrura River.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the south, it goes through Togetu-kyo Bridge and becomes Saga kaido and runs south on the right side shore of the Katsura-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>Togetsu-kyo Bridge, Katsura-gawa Riverに修正&quot;Katsura-gawa&quot;→&quot;the Katsura-gawa&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="8">
<j>ルート</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Route</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Route</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Route</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>嵯峨釈迦堂前</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In front of Saga Shaka-do</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In front of Saga Shaka-do</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In front of Saga Shaka-do</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>－交差点－（丸太町通）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Crossing- (Marutamachi-dori Street)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Crossing- (Marutamachi-dori Street)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">- Crossing - (Marutamachi-dori Street)</e>
<cmt>スペース、ハイフンを追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>－渡月橋交差点－ （三条通）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Togetsu Bridge Crossing - (Sanjo-dori Street)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Togetsu Bridge Crossing - (Sanjo-dori Street)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">- Togetsu-kyo Bridge Crossing - (Sanjo-dori Street)</e>
<cmt>スペース、ハイフンを追加、Togetsu-kyo Bridgeとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>渡月橋－嵯峨街道</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Togetsu Bridge - Saga kaido</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Togetsu Bridge - Saga kaido</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Togetsu-kyo Bridge - Saga kaido</e>
<cmt>Togetsu-kyo Bridgeとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 うら(id:40695), 武嶋(id:89475), 本屋(id:125948), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>