<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>第二京阪道路</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daini-Keihan-Doro Bypass</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daini-Keihan-Doro Bypass</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daini-Keihan-Doro Bypass</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>第二京阪道路（だいにけいはんどうろ）は、京都府京都市伏見区から大阪府門真市に至る一般国道1号バイパス道路である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Daini-Keihan-Doro Bypass is a bypass of the general National Highway Road No. 1, which extends from Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture to Kadoma City, Osaka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>http://www.excite.co.jp/map/address/27/読みは訳し出しして「いません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Daini-Keihan-Doro Bypass is a bypass of the general National Highway Road No. 1, which extends from Fushimi ward in Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture, to Kadoma City in Osaka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Daini-Keihan-Doro Bypass is a bypass of the general National Highway Road No. 1, which extends from Fushimi Ward in Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture, to Kadoma City in Osaka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>wを大文字に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>4 - 6車線の専用部（自動車専用道路）と側道に当たる2 - 4車線の一般部（一般道路）からなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is composed of 4 to 6 lanes of the Exclusive Section (expressway) and 2 to 4 lanes of the General Section (general road) as the side roads.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is comprised of four to six lanes of the exclusive section (expressway) and two to four lanes of the general section (general road) as side roads.</e>
<cmt>grammar, number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is comprised of four to six lanes of the exclusive section (expressway) and two to four lanes of the general section (general road) as side roads.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>飽和状態にある京阪国道および近畿自動車道の吹田ジャンクション・吹田インターチェンジと門真インターチェンジ (近畿自動車道) 間の渋滞緩和（加えて、これに付随する名神高速道路の天王山トンネル付近と京都南インターチェンジ付近の渋滞緩和）を目的として整備が進んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The development of this bypass is being promoted to relieve congestions on the Keihan National Highway, whose traffic volume has exceeded its capacity, and on the section between Suita Junction /Suita Interchange of the Kinki Jidoshado Expressway and Kadoma Interchange (the Kinki Jidoshado Expressway) (as well as in addition congestions occurred around the Tennouzan tunnel and Kyoto Minami Interchange in association with the heavy traffic in the section above)</e>
<cmt>http://www.wdic.org/w/GEO/近畿自動車道%20(高速道)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The development of this bypass is being promoted in order to relieve congestion on the Keihan National Highway, whose traffic volume has exceeded its capacity, and on the section between the Suita Junction/Suita Interchange of the Kinki Jidoshado Expressway and the Kadoma Interchange (the Kinki Jidoshado Expressway) (as well as the congestion occurring around the Tennouzan Tunnel and the Kyoto Minami Interchange, as associated with the heavy traffic in the section mentioned above).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The development of this bypass is being promoted in order to relieve congestion on the Keihan National Highway, whose traffic volume has exceeded its capacity, and on the section between the Suita Junction/Suita Interchange of the Kinki Jidoshado Expressway and the Kadoma Interchange (the Kinki Jidoshado Expressway) (as well as the congestion occurring around the Tennouzan Tunnel and the Kyoto Minami Interchange of the Meishin Expressway, as associated with the heavy traffic in the section mentioned above).</e>
<cmt>of Meishin Expressway補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>沿道環境への対策として、道路の両脇に副道・植栽帯・自転車歩行者道からなる環境施設帯を設置している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a measure to improve roadside environment, environmental facilities are provided along the both sides of the road, which include side roads, planted zones, and pedestrian and cycler lanes.</e>
<cmt>http://www.mlit.go.jp/index.html一原文一訳文の例外対処緑立つ道の訳をカッコ内につけてあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a measure to improve the roadside environment, environmental facilities are provided along both sides of the road, which include side roads, planted zones, and lanes for cyclists and pedestrians.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a measure to improve the roadside environment, environmental facilities are provided along both sides of the road, which include side roads, planted zones, and lanes for cyclists and pedestrians.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>国土交通省は「緑立つ道」の愛称を付けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ministry of Land, Infrastructure, Transport, and Tourism has nicknamed this bypass “Midori-tatsu-michi!” (a road with fresh foliage sprouting)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ministry of Land, Infrastructure, Transport and Tourism has nicknamed this bypass “Midori-tatsu-michi (a road with fresh foliage sprouting).&quot;</e>
<cmt>Transport, and→Transport and</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ministry of Land, Infrastructure, Transport and Tourism has nicknamed this bypass &apos;Midori-tatsu-michi (a road with fresh foliage sprouting).&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせて&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="6">
<j>ここでは、一般有料道路としての営業路線では第二京阪道路に含まれる洛南連絡道路（地域高規格道路）についても合わせて記述する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Here below the Rakunan Renraku Road (local high-standard highway) is described together, because it is included in the service route of the Daini-Keihan-Doro Bypass as a general toll road.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Rakunan Renraku Road (local high-standard highway) is hereunder described collectively, because it&apos;s included in the service route of the Daini-Keihan-Doro Bypass as a general toll road.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Rakunan Renraku Road (local high-standard highway) is hereunder described collectively, because it is included in the service route of the Daini-Keihan-Doro Bypass as a general toll road.</e>
<cmt>it&apos;s→it is</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>専用部</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Exclusive Section</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Exclusive Section</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Exclusive Section</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>延長約28.3キロメートルの自動車専用道路であり、地域高規格道路の計画路線に指定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a 28.3 km long road exclusive for automobiles, designated as a planning route of local high-standard highways.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It&apos;s a 28.3-kilometer road for exclusive use by automobiles, and is designated as a planning route for the local high-standard highways.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It&apos;s an approximately 28.3-kilometer extended road for exclusive use by automobiles, and is designated as a planning route for the local high-standard highways.</e>
<cmt>an approximately 28.3-kilometer extended road としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>一般有料道路としての営業路線では、阪神高速道路8号京都線接続部から門真ジャンクションまでの区間が第二京阪道路である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The service route of the Daini-Keihan-Doro Bypass, as the general toll road, is the section from the joint with the Hanshin Expressway Kyoto Line to Kadoma Junction.</e>
<cmt>http://www.wdic.org/w/GEO/阪神高速道路「残りの部分」をわかりやすいように加えてあります。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The service route of the Daini-Keihan-Doro Bypass, as the general toll road, is the section from the union with the Hanshin Expressway Kyoto Line to Kadoma Junction.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The service route of the Daini-Keihan-Doro Bypass, as the general toll road, is the section from the union with the Hanshin Expressway Route No. 8 Kyoto Line to Kadoma Junction.</e>
<cmt>Route No. 8補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>地域高規格道路の路線では、巨椋池インターチェンジから門真JCTまでの区間（延長約27.4km）が第二京阪道路であり、阪神高速道路8号京都線接続部から巨椋池ICまでの区間（延長約0.9km）は洛南連絡道路（らくなんれんらくどうろ）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the local high-standard highway, it covers the (27.4 km long) section from Oguraike Interchange to Kadoma Junction, and the remaining section from the joint with the Hanshin Expressway Route No. 8 Kyoto Line to Oguraike Interchange is the Rakuan Renraku Road.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the local high-standard highway, it covers the (27.4-kilometer) section from the Oguraike Interchange to Kadoma Junction, and the remaining section from the union with the Hanshin Expressway Route No. 8 Kyoto Line to the Oguraike Interchange is the Rakuan Renraku Road.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the local high-standard highway, it covers the (approximately 27.4-kilometer extended) section from the Oguraike Interchange to Kadoma Junction, and the remaining (approximately 0.9-kilometer extended) section from the union with the Hanshin Expressway Route No. 8 Kyoto Line to the Oguraike Interchange is the Rakunan Renraku Road.</e>
<cmt>Rakuan→Rakunanapproximately 27.4-kilometer extended としました。approximately 0.9-kilometer extended を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Overview</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Overview</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Overview</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>起点 阪神高速道路8号京都線接続部</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Origin: The joint with the Hanshin Expressway Route No. 8 Kyoto Line</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Origin: The joint with the Hanshin Expressway Route No. 8 Kyoto Line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Origin: The joint with the Hanshin Expressway Route No. 8 Kyoto Line</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="11">
<j>終点 門真JCT</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Terminus: Kadoma Junction</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Terminus: Kadoma Junction</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Terminus: Kadoma Junction</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>道路構造令等 2種2級60キロメートル毎時、1種3級80km/h</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Government Order on Road Design Standards, etc.: Type 2 Class 2, 80 km /h</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Government Order on Road Design Standards, Etc.: Type 2 Class 2, 80 km /h</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Government Order on Road Design Standards, Etc.: Type 2 Class 2, 60 km/h, Type 1 Class 3, 80 km/h</e>
<cmt>80→60Type 1 Class 3, 80 km/h補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>車線数 4車線、6車線</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Lanes: 4 lanes, 6 lanes</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Lanes: 4 lanes, 6 lanes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Lanes: 4 lanes, 6 lanes</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="14">
<j>公共事業・有料道路事業の合併施行方式 (道路整備)で建設されており、建設工事の途中で国土交通省から西日本高速道路に移管され、西日本高速道路株式会社が一般有料道路として管理する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This construction is being promoted under the (road construction) method of merging public works and toll road projects, where West Nippon Expressway Company Limited takes over the control from Ministry of Land, Infrastructure, Transport, and Tourism during construction and operates the road as a general toll road</e>
<cmt>http://www.w-nexco.co.jp/http://www.mlit.go.jp/index.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This construction is being promoted under the (road construction) method of merging public works and toll-road projects, whereby the West Nippon Expressway Company Limited assumes control from the Ministry of Land, Infrastructure, Transport and Tourism during construction and operates the road as a general toll road.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This construction is being promoted under the (road construction) method of merging public works and toll-road projects, whereby the West Nippon Expressway Company Limited assumes control from the Ministry of Land, Infrastructure, Transport and Tourism during construction and operates the road as a general toll road.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="15">
<j>阪神高速道路8号京都線接続部は一般部の起点よりも約1.4km南の淀川左岸（南岸）付近にあるため、専用部の延長距離は一般部のそれよりも短くなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Exclusive Section is a little bit shorter than the General Section, because the joint of the Exclusive Section with the Hanshin Expressway Route No. 8 Kyoto Line is near the left (southern) bank of the Yodo-gawa River, 1 4 km south of the origin of the General Section.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The exclusive section is slightly shorter than the general section because the union of the exclusive section with the Hanshin Expressway Route No. 8 Kyoto Line is near the left (southern) bank of the Yodo-gawa River, 1.4 km south of the origin of the general section.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The exclusive section is slightly shorter than the general section because the union of the exclusive section with the Hanshin Expressway Route No. 8 Kyoto Line is near the left (southern) bank of the Yodo-gawa River, 1.4 km south of the origin of the general section.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="16">
<j>巨椋池本線料金所以北は4車線（第2種第2級・設計速度60km/h）、巨椋池本線料金所から久御山ジャンクションまでは4車線（第1種第3級・設計速度80km/h）、久御山JCT以南は6車線（第1種第3級・設計速度80km/h）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The section stretching north of the Oguraike Tollbooth has 4 lanes (Type 2 Class2, design speed of 60 km/h), the section from the Oguraike Tollbooth to Kumiyma Junction has 4 lines (Type 1 Class 3, Design speed of 80 km/h), and the section stretching south of Kumiyama Junction has 6 lines (Type 1 Class3, Design speed of 80 km/h).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The section stretching north of the Oguraike Tollbooth has four lanes (Type 2 Class 2; design speed 60 km/h), the section from the Oguraike tollbooth to Kumiyma Junction has four lines (Type 1 Class 3; design speed 80 km/h), and the section stretching south of Kumiyama Junction has six lines (Type 1 Class 3; design speed 80 km/h).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The section stretching north of the Oguraike tollbooth has four lanes (Type 2 Class 2; design speed 60 km/h), the section from the Oguraike tollbooth to Kumiyama Junction has four lines (Type 1 Class 3; design speed 80 km/h), and the section stretching south of Kumiyama Junction has six lines (Type 1 Class 3; design speed 80 km/h).</e>
<cmt>Kumiyma→Kumiyama</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>現在は、京田辺本線料金所以南も4車線であるが、門真JCTまでの開通時に6車線化される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The section south of Kyotanabe Tollgate, which has now 4 lines, will have 6 lanes when the section up to the Kadoma Junction is completed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The section south of the Kyotanabe toll gate, which now has four lanes, will have six lanes when the section up to Kadoma Junction is complete.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The section south of the Kyotanabe toll gate, which now has four lanes, will have six lanes when the section up to Kadoma Junction is complete.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="18">
<j>2003年3月30日に最初の区間として巨椋池ICから枚方東インターチェンジが部分開通した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The section from Oguraike Interchange to Hirakata-higashi Interchange was the first to open, and with this opening, the Daini-Keihan-Doro Bypass was partially opened to traffic on March 30, 2003,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The section from the Oguraike Interchange to the Hirakata-higashi Interchange was the first to open, and consequently the Daini-Keihan-Doro Bypass was partially opened to traffic on March 30, 2003.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The section from the Oguraike Interchange to the Hirakata-higashi Interchange was the first to open, and consequently the Daini-Keihan-Doro Bypass was partially opened to traffic on March 30, 2003.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>巨椋池IC以北の区間は、阪神高速道路8号京都線と同時に2008年1月19日開通した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The section north of Oguraike Interchange opened on January, 19, 2008, upon the opening of the Hanshin Expressway Kyoto Line</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The section north of the Oguraike Interchange became accessible on January, 19, 2008 with the opening of the Hanshin Expressway Kyoto Line.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The section north of the Oguraike Interchange became accessible on January 19, 2008 with the opening of the Hanshin Expressway Route No. 8 Kyoto Line.</e>
<cmt>Route No. 8補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>枚方東IC以南の区間については、2007年度中の開通を目標としていたが、用地買収の遅れや道路が通る周辺住民の反対運動等で、現在は2010年春開通予定で建設が進められている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The section south of Hirakata-higashi Interchange was planned to be opened within fiscal 2007, but is still under construction and scheduled for completion in the spring of 2010 because of a delay of land acquisition and oppositions from the neighborhood.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The section south of the Hirakata-higashi Interchange was scheduled to open within fiscal 2007, but it is still under construction and scheduled for completion in the spring of 2010 due to a delay in land acquisition and opposition from the neighborhood.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The section south of the Hirakata-higashi Interchange was scheduled to open within fiscal year 2007, but it is still under construction and scheduled for completion in the spring of 2010 due to a delay in land acquisition and opposition from the neighborhood.</e>
<cmt>&quot;fiscal&quot; -&gt; &quot;fiscal year&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>通過市町村</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Traversed Municipalities</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Traversed Municipalities</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Traversed Municipalities</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="21">
<j>京都府</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>京都市伏見区 - 久世郡久御山町 - 八幡市 - 京田辺市 - 八幡市 - 京田辺市 - 八幡市 -</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fushimi Ward Kumiyama Town -Kumiyama-cho, Kuse-gun -Yawata City - Kyotanabe City - Yawata City - Kyotanabe City - Yawata City</e>
<cmt>http://www.town.kumiyama.kyoto.jp/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fushimi Ward Kumiyama Town - Kumiyama-cho, Kuse-gun - Yawata City - Kyotanabe City - Yawata City - Kyotanabe City - Yawata City</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City - Kumiyama-cho, Kuse-gun - Yawata City - Kyotanabe City - Yawata City - Kyotanabe City - Yawata City</e>
<cmt>Kumiyama Town -削除Kyoto City補足</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="22">
<j>大阪府</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Osaka Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Osaka Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Osaka Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="23">
<j>枚方市 - （ここから右は建設中） - 交野市 - 寝屋川市 - 四條畷市 - 寝屋川市 - 門真市</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hirakata City – (under construction from here) – Katano City – Neyagawa City - Shijonawate City – Kadoma City</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hirakata City – (under construction from here) – Katano City – Neyagawa City - Shijonawate City – Kadoma City</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hirakata City – (under construction from here) – Katano City – Neyagawa City - Shijonawate City – Kadoma City</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>インターチェンジなど</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">List of Interchanges and Facilities</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">List of Interchanges and Facilities</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">List of Interchanges and Facilities</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="24">
<j>IC番号欄の背景色が■である部分については道路が供用済みの区間を示している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sections having Interchanges with a highlight in ■ have been in service.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sections having interchanges highlighted in ■ have been in service.</e>
<cmt>grammar, case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sections having interchanges highlighted in green have been in service.</e>
<cmt>■ は実際のウェブでは緑色になっていましたので、そのように訳しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>また、施設名欄の背景色が■である部分は施設が供用されていない、または完成していないことを示す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The facilities with a highlight in ■ have not been established or completed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The facilities highlighted in ■ have not been established or completed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The facilities highlighted in ash have not been established or completed.</e>
<cmt>■ は実際のウェブでは灰色になっていましたので、そのように訳しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="26">
<j>未開通のIC/JCT名は仮称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tentative names are given for the sections to be opened.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tentative names are given for the sections to be opened.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tentative names are given for the sections to be opened.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="27">
<j>第二京阪道路の距離標は巨椋池ICを起点に門真JCTに向かって付けられており、洛南連絡道路区間のキロポストは阪神高速道路8号京都線接続部を起点に「洛0.5」のように付けられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the Daini-Keihan-Doro Bypass, the distance marked on the distance signs originates from Oguraike Interchange in the direction of Kadoma Junction, while on the Rakunan Renraku Road, the distance on kilometer posts, for example “洛0.5”, originates from the joint with the Hanshin Expressway Route No. 8 Kyoto Line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the Daini-Keihan-Doro Bypass, the distance marked on each respective sign originates from the Oguraike Interchange in the direction of Kadoma Junction, while on the Rakunan Renraku Road the distance on kilometer posts, for example “洛0.5,” which originates from the union with the Hanshin Expressway Route No. 8 Kyoto Line.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the Daini-Keihan-Doro Bypass, the distance marked on each respective sign originates from the Oguraike Interchange in the direction of Kadoma Junction, while on the Rakunan Renraku Road the distance on kilometer posts, for example “洛0.5,” which originates from the union with the Hanshin Expressway Route No. 8 Kyoto Line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>開通区間</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Opened Sections</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Opened Sections</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Opened Sections</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="28">
<j>阪神高速道路8号京都線接続部から枚方東IC</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the joint with the Hanshin Expressway Route No. 8 Kyoto Line to Hirakata-higashi Interchange</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the union with the Hanshin Expressway Route No. 8 Kyoto Line to the Hirakata-higashi Interchange</e>
<cmt>grammar, article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the union with the Hanshin Expressway Route No. 8 Kyoto Line to the Hirakata-higashi Interchange</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="29">
<j>2003年3月30日 巨椋池IC - 枚方東IC開通</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 30, 200: Oguraike Interchange – Hirakata-higashi Interchange opened</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 30, 200: The Oguraike Interchange – Hirakata-higashi Interchange opened.</e>
<cmt>punctuation, article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 30, 2003: The Oguraike Interchange – Hirakata-higashi Interchange opened.</e>
<cmt>200→2003</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="30">
<j>2008年1月19日 阪神高速道路8号京都線接続部 - 巨椋池IC開通</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 19, 200: From the joint with the Hanshin Expressway Route No. 8 Kyoto Line to Oguraike Interchange opened.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 19, 200: The section from the union with the Hanshin Expressway Route No. 8 Kyoto Line to the Oguraike Interchange opened.</e>
<cmt>article, space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 19, 2008: The section from the union with the Hanshin Expressway Route No. 8 Kyoto Line to the Oguraike Interchange opened.</e>
<cmt>200→2008</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>開通予定年度</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Scheduled Opening Year</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Scheduled Opening Year</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Scheduled Opening Year</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="31">
<j>2010年3月 枚方東IC - 門真JCT</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 2010: Hirakata-higashi Interchange - Kadoma Interchange</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 2010: Hirakata-higashi Interchange - Kadoma Interchange</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 2010: Hirakata-higashi Interchange - Kadoma Junction</e>
<cmt>Interchange→Junction</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>料金</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tolls</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tolls</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tolls</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="32">
<j>下記の3区間に分けて定められている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The toll system differs among the following 3 sections.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The toll system differs among the following three sections:</e>
<cmt>punctuation, number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The toll system differs among the following three sections:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="33">
<j>A区間（京都市伏見区向島大黒（起点） - 京田辺松井IC） 各インターチェンジ等相互間による料金</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tolls for A Section (Mukaijima-daikoku, Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City (origin) – Kyotanabe-matsui Interchange): Distance-based toll between interchanges or facilities.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tolls for the A section (Mukaijima-daikoku, Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City (origin) – Kyotanabe-matsui Interchange): distance-based toll between interchanges or facilities.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tolls for the A section (Mukaijima-daikoku, Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City (origin) – Kyotanabe-matsui Interchange): distance-based toll between interchanges or facilities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="34">
<j>A区間の全区間を通行した場合の料金は下記の通り。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tolls for travelling the whole A Section are as follows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The tolls for traveling the entire A section are as follows:</e>
<cmt>punctuation, article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The tolls for traveling the entire A section are as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="35">
<j>軽自動車等 350円 (通貨)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Light Vehicle: 350 yen (currency)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Light vehicle: 350 yen (currency)</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Light vehicle: 350 yen (currency)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="36">
<j>普通自動車 400円</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Standard Vehicle: 400 yen</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Standard vehicle: 400 yen</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Standard vehicle: 400 yen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="37">
<j>中型自動車 500円</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mid-size Vehicle: 500 yen</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Midsize vehicle: 500 yen</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Midsize vehicle: 500 yen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="38">
<j>大型自動車 700円</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oversized Vehicle: 700 yen</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oversize vehicle: 700 yen</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oversize vehicle: 700 yen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="39">
<j>特定大型車 1,150円</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Extra Large Vehicle: 1,150 yen</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Extra-large vehicle: 1,150 yen</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Extra-large vehicle: 1,150 yen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="40">
<j>B区間（京田辺松井IC - 交野市星田北（交野南IC）） この区間の料金。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tolls for B Section (Kyotanabe-matsui Interchange - Hoshida-kita, Katano City (Katano-minami Interchange))</e>
<cmt>http://www.excite.co.jp/map/address/27/230/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tolls for the B section (Kyotanabe-matsui Interchange - Hoshida-kita, Katano City (Katano-minami Interchange))</e>
<cmt>Tolls for B Section→Tolls for the B section</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tolls for the B section (Kyotanabe-matsui Interchange - Hoshida-kita, Katano City (Katano-minami Interchange))</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>全線供用開始の前日までは括弧内。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tolls in parenthesis are applied until the completion of the entire route.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The tolls in parentheses will apply till the completion of the entire route.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The tolls in parentheses will apply till the completion of the entire route.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="42">
<j>軽自動車等 350円（200円）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Light Vehicle: 350 yen (200 yen)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Light vehicle: 350 yen (200 yen)</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Light vehicle: 350 yen (200 yen)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="43">
<j>普通車 450円（200円）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Standard Vehicle: 460 yen (200 yen)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Standard vehicle: 460 yen (200 yen)</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Standard vehicle: 450 yen (200 yen)</e>
<cmt>460→450</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="44">
<j>中型車 500円（250円）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mid-size Vehicle: 500 yen (250 yen)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Midsize vehicle: 500 yen (250 yen)</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Midsize vehicle: 500 yen (250 yen)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="45">
<j>大型車 700円（300円）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oversized Vehicle: 700 yen (300 yen)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oversize vehicle: 700 yen (300 yen)</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oversize vehicle: 700 yen (300 yen)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="46">
<j>特大車 1,200円（400円）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Extra Large Vehicle: 1,200 yen (400 yen)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Extra-large vehicle: 1,200 yen (400 yen)</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Extra-large vehicle: 1,200 yen (400 yen)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="47">
<j>C区間（交野市星田北（交野南IC） - 門真市大字稗島（門真JCT）） この区間の料金</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tolls for C Section (Hoshida-kita, Katano City (Katano-minami Interchange) - Hiejima, Kadoma City (Kadoma Junction)): Flat fare</e>
<cmt>http://www.excite.co.jp/map/address/27/223/53/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tolls for the C section (Hoshida-kita, Katano City (Katano-minami Interchange) - Hiejima, Kadoma City (Kadoma Junction)): flat fare</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tolls for the C section (Hoshida-kita, Katano City (Katano-minami Interchange) - Hiejima, Kadoma City (Kadoma Junction)): flat fare</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="48">
<j>軽自動車等 350円</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Light Vehicle: 350 yen</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Light vehicle: 350 yen</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Light vehicle: 350 yen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="49">
<j>普通車 450円</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Standard Vehicle: 450 yen</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Standard vehicle: 450 yen</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Standard vehicle: 450 yen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="50">
<j>中型車 550円</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mid-size Vehicle: 550 yen</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Midsize vehicle: 550 yen</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Midsize vehicle: 550 yen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="51">
<j>大型車 750円</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oversized Vehicle: 750 yen</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oversize vehicle: 750 yen</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oversize vehicle: 750 yen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="52">
<j>特大車 1,250円</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Extra Large Vehicle: 1,250 yen</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Extra-large vehicle: 1,250 yen</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Extra-large vehicle: 1,250 yen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>交通量</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Traffic Volume</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Traffic Volume</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Traffic Volume</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="53">
<j>2005年度（平成17年度道路交通センサスより）平日24時間交通量（台）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fiscal 2005 Average Weekday 24-hour Road Traffic Volume Census (numbers)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fiscal year 2005 Average Weekday 24-Hour Road Traffic Volume Census (Statistical)</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fiscal year 2005 Average Weekday 24-Hour Road Traffic Volume Census (Statistical)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="54">
<j>巨椋池IC - 久御山JCT 6,334</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oguraike Interchange - Kumiyama Junction: 6,334</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oguraike Interchange - Kumiyama Junction: 6,334</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oguraike Interchange - Kumiyama Junction: 6,334</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="55">
<j>久御山JCT - 久御山南IC 12,543</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kumiyama Junction - Kumiyama-minami interchange: 12,543</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kumiyama Junction - Kumiyama-minami interchange: 12,543</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kumiyama Junction - Kumiyama-minami Interchange: 12,543</e>
<cmt>interchange→Interchange</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="56">
<j>久御山南IC - 八幡東IC 14,044</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kumiyama-minami Interchange - Yawata-higashi Interchange: 14,044</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kumiyama-minami Interchange - Yawata-higashi Interchange: 14,044</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kumiyama-minami Interchange - Yawata-higashi Interchange: 14,044</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="57">
<j>八幡東IC - 京都府・大阪府境 7,045</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yawata-higashi Interchange - Kyoto-Osaka prefectural border: 7,045</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yawata-higashi Interchange - Kyoto-Osaka prefectural border: 7,045</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yawata-higashi Interchange - Kyoto-Osaka prefectural border: 7,045</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>一般部</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">General Section</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">General Section</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">General Section</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="58">
<j>延長約29.7kmの一般道路である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This section is a 29.7 km long general road.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This section is a general road 29.7 kilometers in length.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This section is a general road 29.7 kilometers in extended length.</e>
<cmt>extended を補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="59">
<j>都市計画上の名称及び国土交通省の事業名称は、洛南道路（京都府内の京滋バイパス以北・延長約3.3km）・京都南道路（京都府内の京滋バイパス以南・延長約8.8km）・大阪北道路（大阪府内・延長約17.6km）となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The road names under the city planning and the projects of the Ministry of Land, Infrastructure, Transport, and Tourism are Rakunann Road (the 3.3 km section north of the Keiji Bypass in Kyoto city), Kyoto Minami Road (the 8.8 km section north of the Keiji Bypass in Kyoto City), and Osaka-kita Road (the 17.6 km section in Osaka Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>http://www.wdic.org/w/GEO/京都南道路</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The road names under the city planning and the projects of the Ministry of Land, Infrastructure, Transport and Tourism are Rakunann Road (the 3.3-km section north of the Keiji Bypass in Kyoto City), Kyoto Minami Road (the 8.8-km section north of the Keiji Bypass in Kyoto City) and Osaka-kita Road (the 17.6-km section in Osaka Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The road names under the city planning and the projects of the Ministry of Land, Infrastructure, Transport and Tourism are Rakunan Road (the approximately 3.3-km extended section north of the Keiji Bypass in Kyoto Prefecture), Kyoto Minami Road (the approximately 8.8-km extended section south of the Keiji Bypass in Kyoto Prefecture) and Osaka-kita Road (the approximately 17.6-km extended section in Osaka Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>Rakunann→RakunanCity→Prefectureスペース削除north→south「延長約」の意味をそれぞれ補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Overview</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Overview</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Overview</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="60">
<j>起点 京都市伏見区横大路下三栖</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Origin; Yokooji-shimomisu, Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City</e>
<cmt>http://www.excite.co.jp/map/address/26/109/?start=600</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Origin: Yokooji-shimomisu, Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Origin: Yokooji-shimomisu, Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="61">
<j>終点 門真市大字稗島</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Terminus: Hiejima, Kadoma City</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Terminus: Hiejima, Kadoma City</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Terminus: Hiejima, Kadoma City</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="62">
<j>規格等 3種1級60km/h、3種2級60km/h</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Road Design Standard: Type 3 Class 1 60km/h, Type 3 Class 2 60km/h</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Road design standards: Type 3 Class 1, design speed 60km/h; Type 3 Class 2, design speed 60km/h</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Road design standards: Type 3 Class 1, design speed 60 km/h; Type 3 Class 2, design speed 60 km/h</e>
<cmt>単位の前にスペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="63">
<j>車線数 4車線、2車線</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Lanes: 4 lanes, 2 Lanes</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Lanes: 4 lanes, 2 Lanes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Lanes: 4 lanes, 2 Lanes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="64">
<j>事業主体・道路管理者とも国土交通省である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ministry of Land, Infrastructure, Transport, and Tourism is both implementing the project and managing the road.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ministry of Land, Infrastructure, Transport and Tourism is implementing the project and managing the road.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ministry of Land, Infrastructure, Transport and Tourism is implementing the project and managing the road.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="65">
<j>一般部は専用部の「側道」の位置づけであり、専用部インターチェンジと主要道路との連絡と、沿道地域間交通での利用が想定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The General Section is regarded as &quot;side roads&quot; of the Highway Section, so it is designed to serve as a connection route with interchanges of the Exclusive Sections and provide interregional transportation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The general section is regarded as the &quot;side roads&quot; of the highway section, so it is designed to serve as a connection route with the interchanges of the exclusive sections as well as to provide interregional transportation.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The general section is regarded as the &apos;side roads&apos; of the highway section, so it is designed to serve as a connection route with the interchanges of the exclusive sections as well as to provide interregional transportation.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせて&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>このため、周辺地域に設置されている道路標識では、「国道1号」の表示で枚方バイパスへ、自動車専用道路を示す緑色の「第二京阪」の表示で第二京阪道路の一般部を経由して専用部へ誘導されるようになっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the neighborhood, therefore, the traffic guide sign “National Highway Route No.1” guide drivers to the Hirakata Bypass, while the expressway-dedicated green sign “the Daini-Keihan-Doro Bypass“ guide them to the Expressway Section through the General Section.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Accordingly, in the neighborhood the traffic guide sign “National Highway Route No. 1” directs drivers to the Hirakata Bypass, while the expressway-dedicated green sign “Daini-Keihan-Doro Bypass“ directs them to the expressway section via the general section.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Accordingly, in the neighborhood the traffic guide sign &apos;National Highway Route No. 1&apos; directs drivers to the Hirakata Bypass, while the expressway-dedicated green sign &apos;Daini-Keihan-Doro Bypass&apos; directs them to the expressway section via the general section.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせて&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="67">
<j>起点は専用部の起点よりも約1.4km北の京都外環状線交点であるため、一般部の延長距離は専用部のそれよりも長くなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The General Section is a little bit longer than the Exclusive Section, because its origin is the joint with the Kyoto-sotokanjo-sen Belt Line, 1.4 km north of the Exclusive Section’s origin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The general section is slightly longer than the exclusive section because its origin is the union with the Kyoto-sotokanjo-sen Belt Line, 1.4 km north of the exclusive section&apos;s origin.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The general section is slightly longer than the exclusive section because its origin is the union with the Kyoto-sotokanjo-sen Belt Line, approximately 1.4 km north of the exclusive section&apos;s origin.</e>
<cmt>approximately 1.4 km としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="68">
<j>京田辺松井IC以北と国道170号交点以南は片側2車線（第3種第1級・設計速度60km/h）、京田辺松井ICから国道170号交点までは片側1車線（第3種第2級・設計速度60km/h）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The section north of Kyotanabe-matsui Interchange and the section south of the intersection with the National Highway Route No, 170 have 2 lanes in each direction (Type 3 Class 1, design speed of 60 km/h), and the section from Kyotanabe-matsui Interchange to the intersection with the National Highway route No, 170 (Type 3 Class 2, Design speed of 60 km/h) has one lane in each direction.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The section north of the Kyotanabe-matsui Interchange and the section south of the intersection with National Highway Route No. 170 have two lanes in each direction (Type 3 Class 1; design speed of 60 km/h), and the section from the Kyotanabe-matsui Interchange to the intersection with National Highway Route No. 170 (Type 3 Class 2; design speed of 60 km/h) has one lane in each direction.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The section north of the Kyotanabe-matsui Interchange and the section south of the intersection with National Highway Route No. 170 have two lanes in each direction (Type 3 Class 1; design speed of 60 km/h), and the section from the Kyotanabe-matsui Interchange to the intersection with National Highway Route No. 170 (Type 3 Class 2; design speed of 60 km/h) has one lane in each direction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>ただし、京田辺松井ICから国道170号交点までの区間でも、枚方東ICから国道307号交点（専用部のインターチェンジから主要道路交差点まで）は片側2車線となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the section between Kyotanabe-matsui Interchange and the intersection with the National Highway Route No, 170, however, the number of lanes is 2 from Hirakata-higashi Interchange to the intersection with National Highway No.207</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in the section between the Kyotanabe-matsui Interchange and the intersection with National Highway Route No. 170, there are two lanes is two from the Hirakata-higashi Interchange to the intersection with National Highway No. 207.</e>
<cmt>grammar, space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in the section between the Kyotanabe-matsui Interchange and the intersection with National Highway Route No. 170, there are two lanes in each direction from the Hirakata-higashi Interchange to the intersection with National Highway No. 307 (from the interchange of an exclusive section to a crossing of a major highway).</e>
<cmt>is two削除each direction補足207→307 (from Interchange of exclusive section to a crossing of major highway)補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="70">
<j>京滋バイパス以南については、堀割構造である京田辺松井IC付近から枚方東IC付近、枚方南IC付近から交野北IC付近を除き、道路の両脇に副道（一方通行で1車線）・自転車歩行者道・植栽帯からなる環境施設帯を設置している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the section south of the Keiji Bypass, environmental facilities zones are provided along the both sides of the road, which are made up of side lanes (one lane and one way traffic), pedestrian and cycler lanes, and planted zones, except along the sections built in a canal structure found between Kyotanabe-matsui Interchange and Hirakata-higashi Interchange, and between Hirakata-minami Interchange and Katano-kita Interchange.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the section south of the Keiji Bypass, zones for environmental facilities are provided along both sides of the road, consisting of side lanes (one lane and one-way traffic), lanes for cyclists and pedestrians, and planted zones, except along the sections built in a canal structure found between the Kyotanabe-matsui and Hirakata-higashi interchanges and between the Hirakata-minami and Katano-kita interchanges.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the section south of the Keiji Bypass, zones for environmental facilities are provided along both sides of the road, consisting of side lanes (one lane and one-way traffic), lanes for cyclists and pedestrians, and planted zones, except along the sections built in a canal structure found between the Kyotanabe-matsui and Hirakata-higashi interchanges and between the Hirakata-minami and Katano-kita interchanges.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>原則として主要道路以外には副道を経由して接続している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In principle, it is connected to other roads through side lanes unless connected to major highways.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Principally, it is connected to other roads through side lanes unless it is connected to a major highway.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Principally, it is connected to other roads through side lanes unless it is connected to a major highway.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="72">
<j>当初は、一般部は片側2車線の本線と片側2車線の側道からなっており、京阪国道の機能を完全に代替する計画であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was initially planned to have 2 main lanes and 2 side lanes in each direction so that it can completely take over the function of the Keihan National Highway.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was initially planned to have two main lanes and two side lanes in each direction so that it could fully assume the function of the Keihan National Highway.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was initially planned to have two main lanes and two side lanes in each direction so that it could fully assume the function of the Keihan National Highway.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>しかし、沿線住民の反対運動などもあり、側道部分を環境施設帯に変更するとともに、住宅地の中を通過する京田辺松井ICから国道170号交点までの区間では本線部分も片側1車線に変更し、枚方バイパスの機能を補完するという現在の形になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the plan was changed because of oppositions of people living in the neighborhood; environmental facility zones were provided instead of the side lane, and the number of the lane in the main lanes between Kyotanabe-matsui Interchange and the intersection with the National Highway Route No. 170 was reduced into one in each direction. As the result, it is supplementing the function of the Hirakata Bypass.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the plan was changed due to opposition from people living in the neighborhood; therefore, environmental facility zones were provided instead of the side lane, and the number of main lanes between the Kyotanabe-matsui Interchange and the intersection with National Highway Route No. 170 was reduced to one in each direction so that it now supplements the function of the Hirakata Bypass.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the plan was changed due to opposition from people living in the neighborhood; therefore, environmental facility zones were provided instead of the side lane, and the number of main lanes between the Kyotanabe-matsui Interchange and the intersection with National Highway Route No. 170 was reduced to one in each direction so that it now supplements the function of the Hirakata Bypass.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="74">
<j>未開通の木津川 (京都府)渡河部（久御山南ICから京都府道22号八幡木津線交点まで）と国道307号以南の区間は、専用部の全線開通と同時に2010年春開通予定で建設が進められている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Uncompleted sections - the section crossing the Kizu River (Kyoto Prefecture) (between kumiyama Minami Interchange and the intersection with Kyoto prefectural road No. 22 Yawata-Kizu-sen), and the section south of National Highway No. 307 - are under construction and scheduled to be opened in the spring of 2002 upon the opening of the entire exclusive Section.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Uncompleted sections - the section crossing the Kizu River (Kyoto Prefecture) (between the Kumiyama-minami Interchange and the intersection with Kyoto Prefectural Road No. 22, Yawata-Kizu-sen) and the section south of National Highway No. 307 are under construction but were scheduled to open in the spring of 2002 upon the opening of the entire exclusive section.</e>
<cmt>syntax</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Uncompleted sections - The section crossing the Kizu-gawa River (Kyoto Prefecture) (between the Kumiyama-minami Interchange and the intersection with Kyoto Prefectural Road No. 22, Yawata-Kizu-sen) and the section south of National Highway No. 307 are under construction but were scheduled to open in the spring of 2010 upon the opening of the entire exclusive section.</e>
<cmt>Kizu→Kizu-gawa2002→2010</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>通過市町村</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Traversed Municipalities</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Traversed Municipalities</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Traversed Municipalities</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="75">
<j>京都府</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="14">
<tit>
<j>京都市伏見区 - 久世郡久御山町 - （この間は建設中） - 八幡市 - 京田辺市 - 八幡市 - 京田辺市 - 八幡市 -</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City – Kumiyama-cho Kuse-gun – (Under construction) – Hawata City – Kyotanabe City – Yawata City</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City – Kumiyama-cho Kuse-gun – (Under construction) – Hawata City – Kyotanabe City – Yawata City</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City – Kumiyama-cho Kuse-gun – (Under construction) – Yawata City – Kyotanabe City – Yawata City - Kyotanabe City – Yawata City</e>
<cmt>Hawata→YawataKyotanabe City – Yawata City補足</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="76">
<j>大阪府</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Osaka Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Osaka Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Osaka Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="77">
<j>枚方市 - （ここから右は建設中） - 交野市 - 寝屋川市 - 四條畷市 - 寝屋川市 - 門真市</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hirakata city – (under construction from here) – Katano City – Neyagawa City - Shijonawate City – Kadoma City</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hirakata City – (under construction from here) – Katano City – Neyagawa City - Shijonawate City – Kadoma City</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hirakata City – (under construction from here) – Katano City – Neyagawa City - Shijonawate City – Neyagawa City - Kadoma City</e>
<cmt>Neyagawa City補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="15">
<tit>
<j>交差する道路</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Traversed Roads</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Traversed Roads</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Traversed Roads</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="16">
<tit>
<j>開通区間</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Opened Sections</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Opened Sections</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Opened Sections</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="78">
<j>京都市伏見区横大路下三栖里ノ内（京都外環状線及び油小路通交点）から久御山南IC</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From Yokooji-shimomisu, Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City (Intersection with Kyoto-sotokanjo-sen Belt Line and Abura-no-koji dori Street) to Kumiyama-minami Interchange</e>
<cmt>http://www.excite.co.jp/map/address/26/109/?start=600</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From Yokooji-shimomisu in Fushimi ward, Kyoto City (Intersection with Kyoto-sotokanjo-sen Belt Line and Abura-no-koji dori Street) to the Kumiyama-minami Interchange</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From Satonouchi Yokooji-shimomisu in Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City (Intersection with Kyoto-sotokanjo-sen Belt Line and Abura-no-koji dori Street) to the Kumiyama-minami Interchange</e>
<cmt>Satonouchi 補足ｗを大文字に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="79">
<j>八幡市上津屋八王子（京都府道22号八幡木津線交点）から枚方市津田東町3丁目（国道307号交点）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From Kozuya-hachioji, Yawata City (the intersection with Kyoto prefectural road No. 22 Yawata-Kizu-sen) to Tsudahigashi-machi, Hirakata City</e>
<cmt>http://www.excite.co.jp/map/address/26/210/http://www.excite.co.jp/map/address/27/210/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From Kozuya-hachioji, Yawata City (the intersection with Kyoto Prefectural Road No. 22, Yawata-Kizu-sen) to Tsudahigashi-machi, Hirakata City</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From Kozuya-hachioji, Yawata City (the intersection with Kyoto Prefectural Road No. 22, Yawata-Kizu-sen) to 3-chomeTsudahigashi-machi, Hirakata City (the intersection with National Highway Route No. 307)</e>
<cmt>3-chome補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="80">
<j>門真市大字三ツ島から門真市大字稗島（大阪府道2号大阪中央環状線交点）（副道のみ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From Oaza-Mitsushima, Kadoma City to Hiejima, Kadoma City (the intersection with the Osaka-chuo-kanjo-sen Belt Line) (Only sidle leines)</e>
<cmt>http://www.excite.co.jp/map/address/27/223/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From Oaza-Mitsushima, Kadoma City, to Hiejima, Kadoma City (the intersection with the Osaka-chuo-kanjo-sen Belt Line) (only side lanes)</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From Oaza-Mitsushima, Kadoma City, to Hiejima, Kadoma City (the intersection with Osaka Prefectural Road No. 2, Osaka-chuo-kanjo-sen Belt Line) (only side lanes)</e>
<cmt>Osaka Prefectural Road No. 2補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="17">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="81">
<j>1997年9月 門真市大字三ツ島から門真市大字稗島（大阪府道2号大阪中央環状線交点）開通（環境施設帯のモデル区間として環境施設帯のみ開通）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">September 1997: Opening from Oaza-Mitsushima, Kadoma City to Hiejima, Kadoma City (the intersection with Osaka Prefectural Road No. 2 Osaka-chuo-kanjo-sen Belt Line) (only environmental facility zones only as a model for environmental facility zone)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">September 1997: Opening from Oaza-Mitsushima, Kadoma City to Hiejima, Kadoma City (the intersection with Osaka Prefectural Road No. 2 Osaka-chuo-kanjo-sen Belt Line) (only environmental facility zones as a model for environmental facility zones)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September 1997: Opening from Oaza-Mitsushima, Kadoma City to Hiejima, Kadoma City (the intersection with Osaka Prefectural Road No. 2 Osaka-chuo-kanjo-sen Belt Line) (only environmental facility zones as a model for environmental facility zones)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="82">
<j>2003年3月30日 久御山町佐山美ノケ薮（京都府道15号宇治淀線交点）から久御山南IC、八幡市上津屋八王子（京都府道22号八幡木津線交点）から八幡市内里松ケ外（京都府道282号内里城陽線交点）、京田辺市松井口仲谷（京都府道736号交野久御山線交点）から枚方市津田東町3丁目（国道307号交点）開通</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 30, 2003: Opening from Sayama Koaza-minoga-yabu, Kumiyama Town (the intersection with Kyoto Prefectural Road No. 15 Ujiyodo Line) to Kumiyama-minami Interchange, from Kozuya-hachioji, Yawata City (the intersection with Kyoto prefectural road No. 22 Yawata-Kizu-sen) to Uchizato-matsugasoto, Yawata City (the intersection with Kyoto prefectural road No. 282 Uchizato-joyo-sen), and from Matsuiguchi-hirotani, Kyotanabe City (the intersection with Kyoto prefectural road No. 736 Katanokumiyama-sen Line to Tsuda-higashi 3-chome Hirakata City)the intersection with National Highway route 307)</e>
<cmt>http://www.excite.co.jp/map/address/26/322/佐山小字美ノケ薮</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 30, 2003: Opening from Sayama Koaza-minoga-yabu, Kumiyama Town (the intersection with Kyoto Prefectural Road No. 15 Ujiyodo Line) to the Kumiyama-minami Interchange, from Kozuya-hachioji, Yawata City (the intersection with Kyoto Prefectural Road No. 22, Yawata-Kizu-sen) to Uchizato-matsugasoto, Yawata City (the intersection with Kyoto Prefectural Road No. 282, Uchizato-joyo-sen), and from Matsuiguchi-hirotani, Kyotanabe City (the intersection with Kyoto Prefectural Road No. 736, Katanokumiyama-sen Line to Tsuda-higashi 3-chome, Hirakata City) the intersection with National Highway Route 307)</e>
<cmt>punctuation, space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 30, 2003: Opening from Sayama Koaza-minoga-yabu, Kumiyama Town (the intersection with Kyoto Prefectural Road No. 15 Ujiyodo Line) to the Kumiyama-minami Interchange, from Kozuya-hachioji, Yawata City (the intersection with Kyoto Prefectural Road No. 22, Yawata-Kizu-sen) to Uchizato-matsugasoto, Yawata City (the intersection with Kyoto Prefectural Road No. 282, Uchizato-joyo-sen), and from Matsuiguchi-hirotani, Kyotanabe City (the intersection with Kyoto Prefectural Road No. 736, Katanokumiyama-sen Line) to Tsuda-higashi 3-chome, Hirakata City (the intersection with National Highway Route 307)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除()の位置調整</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="83">
<j>2005年6月19日 久御山町森北大内（久御山JCT）から久御山町佐山美ノケ薮（京都府道15号宇治淀線交点）開通</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">June 19, 2005: Opening from Mori Kitaouchi, Kumiyama Town (Kumiyama Junction) to Sayama Koaza-minoga-yabu, Kumiyama Town (the intersection with Kyoto Prefectural Road No. 15 Ujiyodo Line)</e>
<cmt>http://www.excite.co.jp/map/address/26/322/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">June 19, 2005: Opened from Mori Kitaouchi, Kumiyama Town (Kumiyama Junction) to Sayama Koaza-minoga-yabu, Kumiyama Town (the intersection with Kyoto Prefectural Road No. 15 Ujiyodo Line)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">June 19, 2005: Opened from Mori Kitaouchi, Kumiyama Town (Kumiyama Junction) to Sayama Koaza-minoga-yabu, Kumiyama Town (the intersection with Kyoto Prefectural Road No. 15 Ujiyodo Line)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="84">
<j>2007年3月24日 八幡市内里松ケ外（京都府道282号内里城陽線交点）から京田辺市松井口仲谷（京都府道736号交野久御山線交点）開通</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 24, 2007: Opening from Uchizato-matsugasoto, Yawata City (the intersection with Kyoto Prefectural Road No. 282 Uchizato-Joyo sen) to Matsuiguchi-hirotani, Kyotanabe City (the intersection with Kyoto Prefectural road No. 736 Katanokumiyama-sen)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 24, 2007: Opened from Uchizato-matsugasoto, Yawata City (the intersection with Kyoto Prefectural Road No. 282, Uchizato-Joyo sen) to Matsuiguchi-hirotani, Kyotanabe City (the intersection with Kyoto Prefectural Road No. 736, Katanokumiyama-sen)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 24, 2007: Opened from Uchizato-matsugasoto, Yawata City (the intersection with Kyoto Prefectural Road No. 282, Uchizato-Joyo sen) to Matsuiguchi-hirotani, Kyotanabe City (the intersection with Kyoto Prefectural Road No. 736, Katanokumiyama-sen)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="18">
<tit>
<j>交通量</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Traffic Volume</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Traffic Volume</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Traffic Volume</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="85">
<j>2005年度（平成17年度道路交通センサスより）平日24時間交通量（台）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fiscal 2005 Average Weekday 24-hour Road Traffic Volume Census (numbers)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fiscal year 2005 Average Weekday 24-Hour Road Traffic Volume Census (Statistical)</e>
<cmt>grammar, case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fiscal year 2005 Average Weekday 24-Hour Road Traffic Volume Census (Statistical)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="86">
<j>京都市伏見区横大路下三栖里ノ内 45,803</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Satonouchi, Yokooji-shimomisu, Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City; 45,803</e>
<cmt>http://www.excite.co.jp/map/address/26/109/?start=600</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Satonouchi, Yokooji-shimomisu, Fushimi ward, Kyoto City: 45,803</e>
<cmt>punctuation, case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Satonouchi, Yokooji-shimomisu, Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City: 45,803</e>
<cmt>ｗを大文字に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="87">
<j>久世郡久御山町東一口 37,812</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Higashi-imoarai, Kumiyama Town 37,812</e>
<cmt>http://www.excite.co.jp/map/address/26/322/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Higashi-imoarai, Kumiyama Town: 37,812</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Higashi-imoarai, Kumiyama Town Kuze-gun: 37,812</e>
<cmt>Kuze-gun補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="88">
<j>久世郡久御山町佐山字新開地 9,119</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sayama Koaza-shinkaichi, Kumiyama Town: 9,119</e>
<cmt>http://www.excite.co.jp/map/address/26/322/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sayama Koaza-shinkaichi, Kumiyama Town: 9,119</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sayama Koaza-shinkaichi, Kumiyama Town Kuze-gun: 9,119</e>
<cmt>Kuze-gun補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="89">
<j>枚方市長尾台 20,172</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagaodai, Hirakata City: 20,172</e>
<cmt>http://www.excite.co.jp/map/address/27/210/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagaodai, Hirakata City: 20,172</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagaodai, Hirakata City: 20,172</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="19">
<tit>
<j>沿線</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Facilities along the Bypass</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Facilities along the Bypass</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Facilities along the Bypass</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="90">
<j>ジャスコ久御山ショッピングセンター</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">JASCO Kumiyama shopping center</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">JASCO Kumiyama Shopping Center</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">JASCO Kumiyama Shopping Center</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="91">
<j>京阪東ローズタウン</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keihan-higashi Rose Town</e>
<cmt>http://www.keihan-ert.jp/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keihan-higashi Rose Town</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keihan-higashi Rose Town</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="92">
<j>大阪国際大学</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Osaka International University</e>
<cmt>http://www.oiu.ac.jp/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Osaka International University</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Osaka International University</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Hideyuki(id:9577), KAZU2000(id:96278), Washisama(id:9333), Pixan(id:24280), K5528(id:151617), Purupurupuru(id:27352), Out go 7(id:8199), はてなさま(id:103001), Yassy0411(id:203358), Ce2(id:2439), Uguisu794(id:24248), Special rapid(id:96013), Sunen(id:10700), Sasima(id:163392), Umashika(id:25964), Nevylax(id:38464), Misola(id:36747), Topgun1997(id:32246), Ayers Rock(id:49390), Ritsuka(id:6464), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>