<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>両替町通</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryogaemachi-dori Street</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryogaemachi-dori Street</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryogaemachi-dori Street</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>両替町通（りょうがえまちどおり）は京都市内の南北の通りの一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ryogaemachi-dori Street is a north-south running street in Kyoto city.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ryogaemachi-dori Street is a street running north-south through Kyoto city.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ryogaemachi-dori Street is a street running north-south through Kyoto city.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>北は丸太町通から南は三条通まで、烏丸通の一筋西を走る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It extends from the Marutamachi-dori Street in the north to the Sanjo-dori Street in the south, running a block west of the Karasuma-dori Street.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It extends from Marutamachi-dori Street in north to Sanjo-dori Street in the south, running a block west of Karasuma-dori Street.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It extends from Marutamachi-dori Street in north to Sanjo-dori Street in the south, running a block west of Karasuma-dori Street.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>南の延長線上を諏訪町通（すわんちょうどおり）が走る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Suwancho-dori Street runs along its southern extension.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Suwancho-dori Street runs along its southern extension.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Suwancho-dori Street runs along its southern extension.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>由来と歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Origin and History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Origin and History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Origin and History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>平安京には存在せず、豊臣秀吉による天正の地割で新設された通りである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It did not exist in Heiankyo and was built by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI according to his Tensho zoning.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It did not exist in Heiankyo and was built by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI according to his Tensho zoning policy.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It did not exist in Heiankyo and was built by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI according to his Tensho zoning policy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>1600年（慶長5年）、押小路通との交差点付近に徳川家康によって金座 (歴史)が設けられ、さらに1608年（慶長13年）には銀座 (歴史)が伏見から金座の南に移転した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A kinza (history) was established by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA around the crossing with the Oshikoji-dori Street in 1600 and a ginza (history) was moved from Fushimi to an area south of the kinza in 1608.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A kinza (history) was established by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA around the intersection with Oshikoji-dori Street in 1600 and a ginza (history) was moved from Fushimi to an area south of the kinza in 1608.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A kinza (literally, gold za, or gold mint) was established by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA around the intersection with Oshikoji-dori Street in 1600 and a ginza (literally, silver za, or silver mint) was moved from Fushimi to an area south of the kinza in 1608.</e>
<cmt>金座、銀座の表記を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>このため通り沿いには金融や金銀細工に携わる業者が集中した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore many financial dealers and gold- and silver-smiths were concentrated along the street.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore many financial dealers and gold- and silver-smiths were concentrated along the street.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore many financial dealers and gold- and silver-smiths were concentrated along the street.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="8">
<j>現状</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Current Status</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Current Status</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Current Status</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>金融業は烏丸通に移り、現在は中心街の狭い通りである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because financial institutions were relocated to the area along the Karasuma-dori Street, the current Ryogaemachi-dori Street is only a downtown narrow street.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because financial institutions were relocated to the area along Karasuma-dori Street, the current Ryogaemachi-dori Street is only a narrow downtown street.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because financial institutions were relocated to the area along Karasuma-dori Street, the current Ryogaemachi-dori Street is only a narrow downtown street.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="10">
<j>諏訪町通</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Suwancho-dori Street</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Suwancho-dori Street</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Suwancho-dori Street</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>諏訪町通（すわんちょうどおり）は両替町通を南へ延長した線上にあり、北は高辻通から南は東本願寺の北端の花屋町通まで。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Suwancho-dori Street, located along the southern extension of the Ryogaemachi-dori Street, runs from the Takatsuji-dori Street in the north to the Hanayacho-dori Street at the northern end of Higashihongan-ji Temple in the south.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Suwancho-dori Street, located along the southern extension of the Ryogaemachi-dori Street, runs from Takatsuji-dori Street in the north to Hanayacho-dori Street at the northern end of Higashihongan-ji Temple in the south.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Suwancho-dori Street, located along the southern extension of the Ryogaemachi-dori Street, runs from Takatsuji-dori Street in the north to Hanayacho-dori Street at the northern end of Higashihongan-ji Temple in the south.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="12">
<j>的場通との交差点付近にある諏訪神社が通り名の由来である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name of the street comes from Suwa Jinja Shrine, which is near the crossing with the Matoba-dori Street.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name of the street comes from Suwa Jinja Shrine, which is near the intersection with Matoba-dori Street.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name of the street comes from Suwa-jinja Shrine, which is near the intersection with Matoba-dori Street.</e>
<cmt>Suwa-jinja Shrineとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="13">
<j>六条通付近には江戸時代初期に「六条三筋町」の遊郭が設けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the early Edo era brothels were established in Rokujo misujimachi around the Rokujo-dori Street</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the early Edo era brothels were established in Rokujo misujimachi around Rokujo-dori Street</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the early Edo period brothels were established in Rokujo misujimachi around Rokujo-dori Street</e>
<cmt>Edo periodとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Miyuki h(id:84952), Matsukaze(id:51778), Tinecici(id:192914), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>