<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>三条通</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanjo-dori Street</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanjo-dori Street</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanjo-dori Street</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>三条通（さんじょうどおり）は京都府京都市の主要な東西の通りの一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Sanjo-dori Street　is one of the major east-west running streets in Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanjo-dori Street is one of the major east-west streets in Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>grammar, space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanjo-dori Street is one of the major east-west streets in Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>平安京の三条大路に相当する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It corresponds to the Sanjo-oji Street in Heiankyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It corresponds to Sanjo-oji Street in Heiankyo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It corresponds to Sanjo-oji Street in Heiankyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>また、鴨川 (淀川水系)に架かる三条大橋が東海道東海道五十三次の終点だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Sanjo-ohashi Bridge over the Kamo-gawa River (Yodo-gawa water system) was the end point of the Tokaido Gojusan-tsugi (fifty-three stages in Tokaido Road) of the Tokaido.</e>
<cmt>http://www.mutsunohana.net/miyako/oji-koji/sanjo-oji.htm「また」は訳し出ししていません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sanjo-ohashi Bridge over the Kamo-gawa River (Yodo-gawa water system) was the end point of the Tokaido Gojusan-tsugi (fifty-three stages in Tokaido Road) of the Tokaido.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sanjo-ohashi Bridge over the Kamo-gawa River (Yodo-gawa water system) was the end point of the Tokaido Gojusan-tsugi (fifty-three stages in Tokaido Road) of the Tokaido.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Overview</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Overview</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Overview</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>東は山科区四宮から西は右京区の嵐山（渡月橋）に至る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ｔｈｅ Sanjo-dori Street runs east to west from Shinomiya, Yamashina Ward to (Togetukyo Bridge) Arashiyama, Ukyo Ward.</e>
<cmt>http://kaiwai.city.kyoto.jp/search/view_sight.php?ManageCode=3000071&amp;InforKindCode=1</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ｔｈｅ Sanjo-dori Street runs east to west from Shinomiya in Yamashina ward to (Togetukyo Bridge) Arashiyama in Ukyo ward.</e>
<cmt>grammar, case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanjo-dori Street runs east to west from Shinomiya in Yamashina Ward to (Togetukyo Bridge) Arashiyama in Ukyo Ward.</e>
<cmt>wを大文字に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>東海道の京の出入口の部分は「京の七口」の一つの「粟田口」と呼ばれ、近くにある粟田神社は「旅立ちの神」として信仰された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The entry and exit points of the Tokaido was called “Awataguchi,” which is one of the “Seven Gates of Kyoto,” and nearby Awata-jinja Shrine was worshiped as a “God of Journey.”</e>
<cmt>http://kaiwai.city.kyoto.jp/search/view_sight.php?ManageCode=8000009&amp;InforKindCode=4&amp;whole=truehttp://www5e.biglobe.ne.jp/~hidesan/sanjyo-st.htmhttp://www5e.biglobe.ne.jp/~hidesan/awata-jinjya.htm</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The entry and exit points of the Tokaido was called “Awataguchi,” which is one of the seven gates of Kyoto, and the nearby Awata-jinja Shrine was worshiped as a “god of journeys.”</e>
<cmt>grammar, case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The entry and exit points of the Tokaido in Kyo was called &apos;Awataguchi,&apos; which is one of the seven gates of Kyoto, and the nearby Awata-jinja Shrine was worshiped as a &apos;god of journeys.&apos;</e>
<cmt>in Kyo補足原文の「」にあわせて&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>山科区内では、東海道の旧道と、現在は京都府道143号四ノ宮四ツ塚線になっている旧国道1号のどちらも三条通と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Yamashina Ward, both the old Tokaido and the Old National Highway route No. 1, present Shinomiya-Yotsuzuka-sen Kyoto Fudo 143 Go (Kyoto Prefectural Road 143), are called Sanjo-dori Street.</e>
<cmt>「東海道上」と判断し訳出しました。カッコ内一原文一訳文の例外対処http://kaiwai.city.kyoto.jp/search/view_sight.php?ManageCode=3000047&amp;InforKindCode=1&amp;whole=true</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Yamashina Ward, both the old Tokaido and the Old National Highway Route No. 1, the present-day Shinomiya-Yotsuzuka-sen Kyoto Fudo 143 Go (Kyoto Prefectural Road 143), are called Sanjo-dori Street.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Yamashina Ward, both the old Tokaido and the Old National Highway Route No. 1, the present-day Shinomiya-Yotsuzuka-sen Kyoto Fudo 143 Go (Kyoto Prefectural Road 143), are called Sanjo-dori Street.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>（東海道場の旧道の方は、旧三条通といわれることも多い）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(The Old Tokaido is often called Old Sanjo-dori. Street, too.)</e>
<cmt>カッコ内一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(The Old Tokaido is often called Old Sanjo-dori. Street too.)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(The Old Tokaido is often called Old Sanjo-dori. Street too.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>両者は日ノ岡峠の山科区側で合流し、蹴上を経て三条大橋で鴨川を渡る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The both streets join on the Yamashina Ward side of Hinoka-toge, pass through Keage, and cross the Kamogawa River by the Sanjo-ohashi Bridge.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Both streets join on the Yamashina ward side of Hinoka-toge, pass through Keage and cross the Kamogawa River by the Sanjo-ohashi Bridge.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Both streets join on the Yamashina Ward side of Hinoka-toge, pass through Keage and cross the Kamo-gawa River by the Sanjo-ohashi Bridge.</e>
<cmt>wを大文字にKamogawa→Kamo-gawa</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>東海道として延伸していた部分は、山科区内を中心に三条街道とも呼ばれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The road that extended as the Tokaido is called Sanjo-kaido Road particularly in Yamashina Ward.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The road that extended as the Tokaido is called Sanjo-kaido Road, particularly in Yamashina Ward.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The road that extended as the Tokaido is called Sanjo-kaido Road, particularly in Yamashina Ward.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>河原町通から寺町通にかけては三条名店街商店街と呼ばれるアーケードの商店街。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the Kawaramachi-dori Street to the Teramachi-dori Street, the Sanjo-dori Street is a shopping arcade called Sanjo Meitengai Shopping Street.</e>
<cmt>http://kaiwai.city.kyoto.jp/search/view_sight.php?ManageCode=3000027&amp;InforKindCode=1&amp;whole=true</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Froawaramachi-dori Street to Teramachi-dori Street, Sanjo-dori Street is a shopping arcade known as Sanjo Meitengai Shopping Street.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Froawaramachi-dori Street to Teramachi-dori Street, Sanjo-dori Street is a shopping arcade known as Sanjo Meitengai Shopping Street.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>寺町通から烏丸通にかけては一方通行の狭い道路だが、明治時代はメインストリートだったので、旧日本銀行京都支店（現在は京都文化博物館の別館）や中京郵便局などの近代建築が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Between the Teramachi-dori Street and the Karasuma-dori Street, it is now a narrow one-way street, but many modern architectures are found along it, such as Old Kyoto Branch, Bank of Japan (present Museum of Kyoto Annex) and Nakagyo Post Office, because it was the main street in the Meiji era.</e>
<cmt>http://web.kyoto-inet.or.jp/people/kurituka/torina.htmhttp://www.boj.or.jp/http://www.jp-network.japanpost.jp/storesearch/detail/index.php?id=300101441530</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Between Teramachi-dori Street and Karasuma-dori Street, it is now a narrow one-way street, but many modern-era architectural structures are found along it, such as the Old Kyoto Branch, Bank of Japan (present Museum of Kyoto Annex) and the Nakagyo Post Office, because it was the main street in the Meiji era.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Between Teramachi-dori Street and Karasuma-dori Street, it is now a narrow one-way street, but many modern-era architectural structures are found along it, such as the Old Kyoto Branch, Bank of Japan (present Museum of Kyoto Annex) and the Nakagyo Post Office, because it was the main street in the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>&quot;era&quot; -&gt; &quot;period&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>郡区町村編制法により上京区・下京区が置かれたとき、この三条通を境として北が上京区、南が下京区とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Kamigyo Ward and Simogyo Ward were established under Gun-ku-cho-son Henseiho (Act for the alignment of local government system), the Sanjo-dori Street was used as the boundary between the 2 Wards; Kamibyo Ward was difiend as north of it and Shimogyo Ward as south of it.</e>
<cmt>http://100.yahoo.co.jp/detail/郡区町村編制法/http://www.excite.co.jp/map/address/26/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Kamigyo and Simogyo wards were established under Gun-ku-cho-son Henseiho (Act for the Alignment of Local Government Systems), Sanjo-dori Street was used as the boundary between the two wards; Kamibyo ward was defined as being north of it and Shimogyo ward was defined as being south of it.</e>
<cmt>grammar, spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Kamigyo and Simogyo wards were established under Gun-ku-cho-son Henseiho (Act for the Alignment of Local Government Systems), Sanjo-dori Street was used as the boundary between the two wards; Kamigyo Ward was defined as being north of it, and Shimogyo Ward was defined as being south of it.</e>
<cmt>wを大文字にKamibyo→kamigyo</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>烏丸通との交差点には、京都市道路元標が残されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A Road Origin Marker of Kyoto City has still remained at the crossing with the Karasuma-dori Street.</e>
<cmt>http://kaiwai.city.kyoto.jp/search/view_sight.php?ManageCode=3000025&amp;InforKindCode=1&amp;whole=true</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A road-origin marker of Kyoto City can still be seen at the crossing with Karasuma-dori Street.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A road-origin marker of Kyoto City can still be seen at the crossing with Karasuma-dori Street.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>堀川通から千本通にかけては再びアーケードの三条会商店街となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Between the Horikawa-dori Street and the Senbon-dori Street, the street becomes an arcade of Meitengai Shopping Street again..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Between Horikawa-dori Street and Senbon-dori Street, the street again becomes the Meitengai Shopping Street arcade.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Between Horikawa-dori Street and Senbon-dori Street, the street again becomes the Meitengai Shopping Street arcade.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>千本通から西は京都府道112号二条停車場嵐山線となり、幹線道路となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">West of the Senbon-dori Street, it is a highway, Nijoteishajo-Arashiyama-sen Kyoto Fudo 112 Go (Kyoto Prefectural Road 112).</e>
<cmt>http://web.kyoto-inet.or.jp/people/kurituka/torina.htm</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">West of Senbon-dori Street it&apos;s a highway, Nijoteishajo-Arashiyama-sen Kyoto Fudo 112 Go (Kyoto Prefectural Road 112).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">West of Senbon-dori Street it&apos;s a highway, Nijoteishajo-Arashiyama-sen Kyoto Fudo 112 Go (Kyoto Prefectural Road 112).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="16">
<j>西は、西大路通から葛野大路通までの京福電気鉄道嵐山本線併用軌道区間を越えると北西に進み、旧二条通（太子道）と合流すると再び西に向かい、太秦（広隆寺前）、帷子辻を経て、桂川 (淀川水系)左岸で罧原通と合流し嵐山（渡月橋）に至る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the westward direction, through the section sharing lanes with the Arashiyama Main Line, Keifuku Electric Railroad from the Nishioji-dori Street to the Kadonoji-dori Street, it turns northwest, merges with the Old Nijo-dori Street, runs west again, passes through Uzumasa (Koryujimae) and Katabiranotsuji, merges with the Fushihara-dori Street in the left bank of the Katsura-gawa River (the Yodogawa Water System), and leads to (the Togetukyo Bridge) Arashiyama.</e>
<cmt>http://web.kyoto-inet.or.jp/people/kurituka/torina.htmhttp://web.kyoto-inet.or.jp/people/kurituka/torina.htmhttp://www.mutsunohana.net/miyako/oji-koji/musano-koji.htmhttp://kaiwai.city.kyoto.jp/search/view_sight.php?ManageCode=3000083&amp;InforKindCode=1&amp;whole=truehttp://www.katsuragi-nara.jp/aruko_02_05.htmlhttp://www.linkclub.or.jp/~mcyy/kyo/names/fushihara.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the westward direction, through the section sharing lanes with the Arashiyama Main Line, Keifuku Electric Railroad from Nishioji-dori Street to Kadonoji-dori Street, it turns northwest, merges with Old Nijo-dori Street, runs west again, passes through Uzumasa (Koryujimae) and Katabiranotsuji, merges with Fushihara-dori Street on the left bank of the Katsura-gawa River (Yodogawa Water System) and leads to Arashiyama (the Togetukyo Bridge).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the westward direction, through the section sharing lanes with the Arashiyama Main Line, Keifuku Electric Railroad from Nishioji-dori Street to Kadonoji-dori Street, it turns northwest, merges with Old Nijo-dori Street (Taishimichi (the road that Prince Shotoku took)), runs west again, passes through Uzumasa (Koryujimae) and Katabiranotsuji, merges with Fushihara-dori Street on the left bank of the Katsura-gawa River (Yodo-gawa water system) and leads to Arashiyama (Togetukyo Bridge).</e>
<cmt>(Taishimichi (the road where Prince Shotoku took))補足Yodogawa→Yodo-gawa</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>嵐山付近は観光シーズンには慢性的な渋滞が生じている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around Arashiyama, chronic traffic congestions occur during tourist seasons.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around Arashiyama, chronic traffic congestion occurs during tourist seasons.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around Arashiyama, chronic traffic congestion occurs during tourist seasons.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="18">
<j>三条大橋東詰から烏丸通までが路上喫煙等禁止区域である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The section between the Sanjo-ohashi Higashizume east end and the Karasuma-dori street is designated as a public non-smoking area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The section between the eastern end of Sanjo-ohashi Higashizume and Karasuma-dori Street is designated as a public non-smoking area.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The section between the eastern end of Sanjo-ohashi Higashizume and Karasuma-dori Street is designated as a public non-smoking area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>路面電車</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Streetcar</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Streetcar</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Streetcar</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="19">
<j>明治の初期からメインストリートだったために、市街地での拡幅は限られていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Road widening has its limitation because it has been a main street since the early Meiji era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Road widening has its limitations, because it has been a main street since the early Meiji era.</e>
<cmt>better</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Road widening has its limitations, because it has been a main street since the early Meiji era.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>しかし、東と西の郊外では主要幹線として拡幅され、路面電車が通された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the eastern and western suburbs, however, the road was widened as a main highway and the streetcar started to run on it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in the eastern and western suburbs the road was widened as a main highway and the streetcar started running on it.</e>
<cmt>better</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in the eastern and western suburbs the road was widened as a main highway and the streetcar started running on it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="21">
<j>東側は、京阪電気鉄道京阪京津線が三条大橋（鉄道駅の位置は多少変化している）から蹴上までと、日ノ岡の西方から御陵まで路上を併用軌道で走っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the east, the streetcar of the Keihan Keishin Line of Keihan Electric Railway ran from the Sanjo-ohashi Bridge (the location of the station is changed a little) to Keage and from the west side of Hinoka to Misasagi sharing a traffic lane.</e>
<cmt>京阪電鉄HP (http://www.keihan.co.jp/)http://www.keihan.co.jp/english_site/pdf/sightseeing-7.pdfhttp://www.keihan.co.jp/english_site/pdf/sightseeing-7.pdf</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the east, the streetcar of the Keihan Keishin Line of Keihan Electric Railway ran from the Sanjo-ohashi Bridge (the location of the station has changed slightly) to Keage and from the west side of Hinoka to Misasagi, sharing a traffic lane.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the east, the streetcar of the Keihan Keishin Line of Keihan Electric Railway ran from the Sanjo-ohashi Bridge (the location of the station has changed slightly) to Keage and from the west side of Hinoka to Misasagi, sharing a traffic lane.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>現在はほぼ同じ区間を京都市営地下鉄京都市営地下鉄東西線が走っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Now the Tozai Line of Kyoto Municipal Subway/Kyoto City Subway roughly takes the same route.</e>
<cmt>http://www.city.kyoto.jp/koho/eng/access/transport.html路線図には&quot;Kyoto City Subway Line&quot;と表記http://www.city.kyoto.jp/kotsu/tikadia/tikatime.htm</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today the Tozai Line of Kyoto Municipal Subway/Kyoto City Subway takes roughly the same route.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today the Tozai Line of Kyoto Municipal Subway/Kyoto City Subway takes roughly the same route.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="23">
<j>西側は、西大路通から葛野大路通までの区間を、嵐電（らんでん）と通称される京福電気鉄道嵐山本線が現在も路上を併用軌道で走っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the west, the street car of the Arashiyama Main Line, Keifuku Electric Railroad, commonly known as Randen, still runs from the Nishioji-dori Street to Kadonoji-dori Street, sharing a traffic lane</e>
<cmt>http://www.keifuku.co.jp/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the west, the streetcar of the Arashiyama Main Line, Keifuku Electric Railroad, commonly known as Randen, still runs from Nishioji-dori Street to Kadonoji-dori Street, sharing a traffic lane.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the west, the streetcar of the Arashiyama Main Line, Keifuku Electric Railroad, commonly known as Randen, still runs from Nishioji-dori Street to Kadonoji-dori Street, sharing a traffic lane.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>交差する道路</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Crossing Roads</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Crossing Roads</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Crossing Roads</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="24">
<j>上側が東側、下側が南側。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">East is upper and south is lower.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">East is upper, and south is lower.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">East is upper, and south is lower.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>左側が北側、右側が南側。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">North is left and south is right.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">North is to the left, and south is to the right.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">North is to the left, and south is to the right.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="26">
<j>交差する道路の特記がないものは市町村道。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Roads unless specified are operated by local municipalities.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Roads are operated by the local municipalities unless otherwise indicated.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Roads are operated by the local municipalities unless otherwise indicated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>交通量</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Traffic Volume</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Traffic Volume</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Traffic Volume</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="27">
<j>2005年度の平日24時間交通量（台）（平成17年度道路交通センサスより）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fiscal 2005 Average Weekday 24-hour Traffic Volume (numbers) (Road Traffic Census)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fiscal 2005 Average Weekday 24-Hour Traffic Volume (Statistical) (Road Traffic Census)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fiscal year 2005 Average Weekday 24-Hour Traffic Volume (Statistical) (Road Traffic Census)</e>
<cmt>&quot;Fiscal&quot; -&gt; &quot;Fiscal year&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="28">
<j>山科区日ノ岡朝田町：34,576</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hinoka-asadacho, Yamashina Ward: 34,576</e>
<cmt>http://www.excite.co.jp/map/address/26/110/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hinoka-asadacho, Yamashina ward: 34,576</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hinoka-asadacho, Yamashina Ward: 34,576</e>
<cmt>ｗを大文字に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="29">
<j>右京区西院春栄町：17,432</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sainshunei-cho, Ukyo Ward: 17,432</e>
<cmt>http://www.excite.co.jp/map/address/26/108/?start=900</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sainshunei-cho, Ukyo ward: 17,432</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sainshunei-cho, Ukyo Ward: 17,432</e>
<cmt>ｗを大文字に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>沿道の主な施設</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Main Facilities along the Street</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Main facilities along the street</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Main facilities along the street</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="30">
<j>京都薬科大学</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Pharmaceutical University</e>
<cmt>http://www.kyoto-phu.ac.jp/index_esc.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Pharmaceutical University</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Pharmaceutical University</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="31">
<j>琵琶湖疏水</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biwako Sosui (Channel)</e>
<cmt>http://kodomo.bunka.go.jp/1hogo/shoukai/main.asp{0fl=show&amp;id=1000000860&amp;clc=1000000153&amp;cmc=1000000171&amp;cli=1000000221&amp;cmi=1000000833{9.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biwako Sosui (Channel)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biwako Sosui (Channel)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="32">
<j>京都市水道局蹴上浄水場</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keage Purification Plant, Kyoto City Waterworks Bureau</e>
<cmt>http://tabitano.main.jp/7keage.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keage Purification Plant, Kyoto City Waterworks Bureau</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keage Purification Plant, Kyoto City Waterworks Bureau</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="33">
<j>都ホテル</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Miyako Hotels &amp; Resorts</e>
<cmt>http://www.miyakohotels.ne.jp/tokyo/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Miyako Hotels &amp; Resorts</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Miyako Hotels &amp; Resorts</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="34">
<j>南禅寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nanzen-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nanzen-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nanzen-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="35">
<j>高山彦九郎皇居望拝像</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The statue of Hikokuro TAKAYAMA viewing and bowing the knee to the Imperial Palace</e>
<cmt>http://www.kyototsuu.jp/History/HumanTakayamaHikokurou.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The statue of Hikokuro TAKAYAMA viewing and bowing the knee to the Imperial Palace</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The statue of Hikokuro TAKAYAMA viewing and bowing the knee to the Imperial Palace</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="36">
<j>三条京阪</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanjo-keihan</e>
<cmt>http://www.keihan.co.jp/english_site/pdf/sightseeing-7.pdf</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanjo-keihan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanjo-keihan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="37">
<j>三条大橋（鴨川 (淀川水系)）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanjo-ohashi Bridge (Kamogawa (Yodagawa Water system))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanjo-ohashi Bridge (Kamogawa (Yodagawa Water system))</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanjo-ohashi Bridge (Kamo-gawa River (Yoda-gawa water system))</e>
<cmt>Kamogawa→Kamo-gawa RiverYodogawa Water system→Yodo-gawa water system</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="38">
<j>京都文化博物館</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Museum of Kyoto</e>
<cmt>http://www.bunpaku.or.jp/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Museum of Kyoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Museum of Kyoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="39">
<j>旧日本銀行京都支店 - 明治時代の建築（現在は博物館別館として使用）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Old Kyoto Branch, Bank of Japan - an architecture in the Meiji era (now used as Museum of Kyoto Annex)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Old Kyoto Branch, Bank of Japan is an example of architecture from the Meiji era (now used as the Museum of Kyoto Annex).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Old Kyoto Branch, Bank of Japan is an example of architecture from the Meiji period (now used as the Museum of Kyoto Annex).</e>
<cmt>era -&gt; &quot;period&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="40">
<j>中京郵便局 - 外観のみ明治建築が残されている</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nakagyo Post Office - Only the outer appearance of Meiji Architectures has been preserved.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Only the outer appearance of Meiji architecture has been preserved at the Nakagyo Post Office.</e>
<cmt>structure</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Only the outer appearance of Meiji architecture has been preserved at the Nakagyo Post Office.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="41">
<j>西日本電信電話京都支店</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto office, NTT West</e>
<cmt>http://www.ntt-west.co.jp/index_e2.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto office, NTT West</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto office, NTT West</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>新風館 - 複合商業施設（京都市登録有形文化財） ※NTTの北隣にある</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">SHIN-PUH-KAN - (Commercial Complex (registared tangible cultural properties of Kyoto City) ※next to NTT in the south</e>
<cmt>http://www.shin-puh-kan.com/index.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">SHIN-PUH-KAN (a commercial complex registered as a tangible cultural property of Kyoto City) ※next to NTT in the south</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">SHIN-PUH-KAN (a commercial complex registered as a tangible cultural property of Kyoto City) * next to NTT in the north</e>
<cmt>※→*south→north</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="42">
<j>みずほ銀行京都中央支店</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Chuo Branch, Mizuho Bank</e>
<cmt>http://vip.mapion.co.jp/c/f?uc=4&amp;pg=1&amp;ino=BA339167&amp;grp=mizuho</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Chuo Branch, Mizuho Bank</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Chuo Branch, Mizuho Bank</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="43">
<j>旧第一銀行京都支店 - 明治時代の建築（復元建築）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Old Kyoto Branch, Daichi Bank - an architecture in the Meiji era (Reconstructed building)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Old Kyoto Branch, Daichi Bank (a reconstructed building) is another example of architecture from the Meiji era.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Old Kyoto Branch, Daichi Bank (a reconstructed building) is another example of architecture from the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>era -&gt; &quot;period&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="44">
<j>三条会商店街</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanjo Meitengai Shopping Street.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanjo Meitengai Shopping Street</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanjo Meitengai Shopping Street</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="45">
<j>立命館大学朱雀キャンパス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Suzaku Campus of Ritsumeikan Asia Pacific University</e>
<cmt>http://www.ritsumei.jp/index_j.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Suzaku Campus of Ritsumeikan Asia Pacific University</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Suzaku Campus of Ritsumeikan Asia Pacific University</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="46">
<j>島津製作所本社</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Headquarters office, Shimadzu Corporation, Headquarters</e>
<cmt>http://www.shimadzu.co.jp/aboutus/company/access/sanjo.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Headquarters office, Shimadzu Corporation</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Headquarters office, Shimadzu Corporation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="47">
<j>東映太秦映画村</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Uzumasa Eigamura (Toei Movie Land)</e>
<cmt>http://www.eigamura30.com/index.shtml</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Uzumasa Eigamura (Toei Movie Land)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Uzumasa Eigamura (Toei Movie Land)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="48">
<j>広隆寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koryu-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>http://kaiwai.city.kyoto.jp/search/view_sight.php?ManageCode=1000064&amp;InforKindCode=1&amp;whole=true</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koryu-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koryu-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="49">
<j>京都市右京区役所</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ukyo Ward Office, Kyoto City</e>
<cmt>http://www.city.kyoto.lg.jp/ukyo/index.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ukyo Ward Office, Kyoto City</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ukyo Ward Office, Kyoto City</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="50">
<j>右京警察署</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ukyo Police Office</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ukyo Police Station</e>
<cmt>usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ukyo Police Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="51">
<j>京都嵯峨芸術大学</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Saga University of Arts</e>
<cmt>http://www.kyoto-saga.ac.jp/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Saga University of Arts</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Saga University of Arts</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="52">
<j>京都西郵便局</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto-nishi Post Office</e>
<cmt>https://www.jp-network.japanpost.jp/storesearch/detail/index.php?id=300101442980</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto-nishi Post Office</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto-nishi Post Office</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="53">
<j>嵐山</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Arashiyama</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Arashiyama</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Arashiyama</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="54">
<j>瑞泉寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zuisen-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>http://dic.yahoo.co.jp/dsearch?enc=UTF-8&amp;p=瑞泉寺&amp;dtype=0&amp;dname=0na&amp;stype=0&amp;pagenum=1&amp;index=11328609761400</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zuisen-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zuisen-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="55">
<j>京都市営地下鉄京都市営地下鉄東西線 太秦天神川駅 - 三条京阪駅 - 東山駅 (京都府) - 蹴上駅 - 御陵駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto subwa Line, Tozai Line: Uzumasa-tenjingawa Station - Sanjo-keihan Station - Higashiyama station (Kyoto Prefecture) = Keage Station - Misasagi Station</e>
<cmt>http://www.keihan.co.jp/english_site/pdf/sightseeing-7.pdfhttp://www.keihan.co.jp/english_site/pdf/sightseeing-7.pdfhttp://www.city.kyoto.jp/kotsu/tikadia/hyperdia/menu0132.htm京都市営地下鉄は、重複しているので一度のみ訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Subway Line, Tozai Line: Uzumasa-tenjingawa Station - Sanjo-keihan Station - Higashiyama Station (Kyoto Prefecture) = Keage Station - Misasagi Station</e>
<cmt>case, spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Subway Line, Tozai Line: Uzumasa-tenjingawa Station - Sanjo-keihan Station - Higashiyama Station (Kyoto Prefecture) - Keage Station - Misasagi Station</e>
<cmt>&quot;=&quot; を &quot;-&quot; にしました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="56">
<j>京阪電気鉄道京阪本線・京阪鴨東線 三条駅 (京都府)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keihan Oto Line, and Keihan Main Line, Keihan Electric Railway : Sanjo Station (Kyoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>http://www.keihan.co.jp/http://www.keihan.co.jp/english_site/pdf/sightseeing-7.pdf</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keihan Oto Line, and Keihan Main Line, Keihan Electric Railway: Sanjo Station (Kyoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keihan Oto Line, and Keihan Main Line, Keihan Electric Railway: Sanjo Station (Kyoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="57">
<j>京福電気鉄道京福電気鉄道嵐山本線 帷子ノ辻駅 - 太秦広隆寺駅 - 蚕ノ社駅 - 嵐電天神川駅 - 山ノ内駅 (京都府) - 西大路三条駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Arashiyama Main Line, Keifuku Electric Railroad: Katabiranotsuji StationUzumasa - Uzumasa- koryuji Station - Kaikonoyashiro Station - Randen-Tenjingawa Station - Yamanouchi Station (Kyoto Prefecure) - Nishiojisanjo Station</e>
<cmt>http://www.keifuku.co.jp/randen/katabira-no-tsuji/timetable.htmlhttp://www.keifuku.co.jp/randen/uzumasa-koryuji/timetable.htmlhttp://www.keifuku.co.jp/randen/kaikonoyashiro/timetable.htmlhttp://www.keifuku.co.jp/randen/randen-tenjingawa/timetable.htmlhttp://www.keifuku.co.jp/randen/information.htmlhttp://www.keifuku.co.jp/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Arashiyama Main Line, Keifuku Electric Railroad: Katabiranotsuji Station Uzumasa - Uzumasa- koryuji Station - Kaikonoyashiro Station - Randen-Tenjingawa Station - Yamanouchi Station (Kyoto Prefecture) - Nishiojisanjo Station</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Arashiyama Main Line, Keifuku Electric Railroad: Katabiranotsuji Station - Uzumasa-koryuji Station - Kaikonoyashiro Station - Randen-Tenjingawa Station - Yamanouchi Station (Kyoto Prefecture) - Nishiojisanjo Station</e>
<cmt>Uzumasa繰り返し、１つ削除スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 J o(id:26533), Hideyuki(id:9577), るなあるてみす(id:168261), Si-take.(id:91094), Nnh(id:474), ととりん(id:31982), Carbuncle(id:346), Ignis(id:28979), ポピュラーポプラ(id:157724), 月夜野ほたる(id:7183), 春野秋葉(id:36725), Miyuki h(id:84952), Rusk(id:9895), Root253(id:196221), Ktr(id:30468), 油谷サトシ(id:27516), 金山銀山銅山(id:163855), Mochi(id:9489), うら(id:40695), PuzzIeBacheIor(id:18744), Ogeshi(id:80487), ちょろ(id:17218), Sokyo(id:55425), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>