<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>新間之町通</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinai-no-machi-doori Street</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinai-no-machi-doori Street</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shin Ainomachi-dori Street</e>
<cmt>Shinai-no-machi-doori→Shin Ainomachi-doriとしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>新間之町通（しんあいのまちどおり）は京都市内の南北の通りの一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinai-no-machi-doori street is one of the streets running from north to south in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinai-no-machi-doori street is a street running from north - south through Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shin Ainomachi-dori Street is a street running from north - south through Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>Shin Ainomachi-dori Streetとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>鴨川 (淀川水系)の東、左京区の二条通と仁王門通の間の１区画のみの短い通り。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinai-no-machi-doori street is a short street spanning over only one block in the east of Kamo River (in Yodo River system) between Nijo-doori street and Niomon-doori street in Sakyo Ward.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinai-no-machi-doori street is a short street spanning only one block in the east of Kamo River (in Yodo River system) between Nijo-doori street and Niomon-doori street in Sakyo Ward.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shin Ainomachi-dori Street is a short street spanning only one block in the east of the Kamo-gawa River (in Yodo-gawa River system) between Nijo-dori Street and Niomon-dori Street in Sakyo Ward.</e>
<cmt>Shin Ainomachi-dori Street, Kamo-gawa River, Yodo-gawa River, Nijo-dori Street, Niomon-dori Streetとしました。&quot;Kamo-gawa River&quot;→&quot;the Kamo-gawa River&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>南の延長は新堺町通と名前が変わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The southward extended portion of Shinai-no-machi-doori street has a different name, Shinsakaicho-doori street.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The southward extended portion of Shinai-no-machi-doori street has a different name, Shinsakaicho-doori street.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The southward extended portion of Shin Ainomachi-dori Street has a different name, Shin Sakaimachi-dori Street.</e>
<cmt>Shin Ainomachi-dori Streetとし、Shinsakaicho-doori street→Shin Sakaimachi-dori Streetに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>町屋が並ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many pieces of machiya (a type of residences and stores in the central part of a city) line Shinai-no-machi-doori street.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many pieces of machiya (a type of residence or store in the central part of a city) line Shinai-no-machi-doori street.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many pieces of machiya (a type of residence or store in the central part of a city) line Shin Ainomachi-dori Street.</e>
<cmt>Shin Ainomachi-dori Streetとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>京都御所の拡張により間之町通の丸太町通以北の住民が（当時新開地であった）鴨川の東の現在地に移住したためにこの名が付いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name, Shinai-no-machi-doori street was given because the residents living in an area along and in the north of Marutamacih-doori street along Ai-no-machi-doori street moved to the current site which was in the east of Kamo River (and which was a newly developed area) due to the expansion of the Imperial Palace in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name, Shinai-no-machi-doori street was given because the residents living in an area along and in the north of Marutamacih-doori street along Ai-no-machi-doori street moved to the current site which was in the east of Kamo River (and which was a newly developed area) due to the Imperial Palace&apos;s expansion in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name, Shin Ainomachi-dori Street was given because the residents living in an area along and in the north of Marutamacih-dori Street along Ainomachi-dori Street moved to the current site which was in the east of Kamo-gawa River (and which was a newly developed area) due to the Imperial Palace&apos;s expansion in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>Shin Ainomachi-dori Street, Marutamacih-dori Street, Ainomachi-dori Street, Kamo-gawa Riverとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Miyuki h(id:84952), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>