<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>東海道</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokaido</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokaido</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokaido</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>東海道（とうかいどう、うみつみち）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokaido (or Umitsu-Michi)</e>
<cmt>２つの読み方のみ記載しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokaido (or Umitsu-Michi)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokaido (or Umitsu-Michi) can mean:</e>
<cmt>Thought needs to be given to the way the information is laid out on the actual page. This is clearly meant to introduce the two possible meanings of Tokaido.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>五畿七道の一つで、本州太平洋側の中部を指す行政区分。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of the Goki-Shichido, referring to a region on the Taiheiyo side of central Honshu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is one of the Goki-Shichido, referring to a region on the Taiheiyo side of central Honshu.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of the Goki-Shichido, an ancient administrative area, on the Pacific Ocean side of central Honshu.</e>
<cmt>The structure used here needs to conform to that of the introductory sentence above.</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>五畿七道の東海道を通る幹線道路。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A highway traversing Tokaido of Goki-Shichido</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This highway traverses Tokaido, of Goki-Shichido.</e>
<cmt>Completed</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of two highways that traverse the above-mentioned Tokaido region.</e>
<cmt>Again, this seems to be introducing two highways that bear the name Tokaido.</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>律令制時代に整備されたもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A road developed in the Ritsuryo era</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This road was developed during the Ritsuryo era.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A highway that was built during the Ritsuryo period.</e>
<cmt>structure</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="5">
<j>江戸時代に整備されたもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A road developed in the Edo era</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This road was developed during the Edo era.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A highway that was built during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>structure</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>五街道の一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of the Go-kaido</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is one of the Go-kaido.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This highway was one of the Go-kaido (the collective name given to the five principal routes used during the Edo period).</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくするために訳を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="7">
<j>行政区画としての東海道</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokaido as an admistrative division</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokaido is considered an admistrative division in this case.</e>
<cmt>Completed</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Administrative division</e>
<cmt>I realize this deviates from the Japanese a little but as this is a heading, I think simply &quot;Administrative division&quot; would be sufficient.</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="8">
<j>行政区分の東海道は、畿内から東に伸びる、本州太平洋側の中部を指した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokaido as an administrative division referred to a region of Central Honshu extending east of Kinai and along the Taiheiyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokaido, as an administrative division, referred to a region of Central Honshu extending east of Kinai and along the Taiheiyo.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As an administrative division, Tokaido referred to a region of Central Honshu extending east of Kinai and along the Taiheiyo.</e>
<cmt>No real problems but I think this reads a little more smoothly.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>これは、現在の三重県から茨城県に至る太平洋沿岸の地方に相当する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This corresponds to regions from present-day Mie Prefecture to Ibaraki Prefecture along the Pacific coast.</e>
<cmt>http://www.pref.ibaraki.jp/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This corresponds to the regions from present-day Mie Prefecture to Ibaraki Prefecture along the Pacific coast.</e>
<cmt>Article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This corresponds to the regions stretching from present-day Mie Prefecture to Ibaraki Prefecture along the Pacific coast.</e>
<cmt>Again, this just reads a little more smoothly, I think.</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="10">
<j>伊賀国（三重県の西部）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Iga-no-kuni (western Mie Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Iga-no-kuni (western Mie Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Iga-no-kuni (western Mie Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="11">
<j>伊勢国（三重県の中部）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Iga-no-kuni (central Mie Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Iga-no-kuni (central Mie Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ise-no-kuni (central Mie Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>名称間違え</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="12">
<j>志摩国（三重県の東部と愛知県の伊良子岬付近）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shima-no-kuni (eastern Mie Prefecture and the vicinity of Irako Cape in Aichi Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shima-no-kuni (eastern Mie Prefecture and the vicinity of the Irako Cape, in Aichi Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shima-no-kuni (eastern Mie Prefecture and the vicinity of the Irako Cape, in Aichi Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="13">
<j>尾張国（愛知県の西部）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Owari-no-kuni (western Aichi Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>http://100.yahoo.co.jp/detail/尾張国/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Owari-no-kuni (western Aichi Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Owari-no-kuni (western Aichi Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="14">
<j>三河国（愛知県の中部と東部）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mikawa-no-kuni (central and eastern Aichi Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mikawa-no-kuni (central and eastern Aichi Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mikawa-no-kuni (central and eastern Aichi Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="15">
<j>遠江国（静岡県の概ね西部）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toto-umi-no-kuni (roughly western Shizuoka Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toto-umi-no-kuni (generally, western Shizuoka Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>Better</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toto-umi-no-kuni (mainly western Shizuoka Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>I don&apos;t think &quot;generally&quot; communicates quite the same meaning as &quot;概ね&quot;.</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="16">
<j>駿河国（静岡県の概ね中部及び富士山周辺）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Suruga-no-kuni (roughly Central ShizuokaPrefecture and the vicinity of Mt. Fuji)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Suruga-no-kuni (roughly Central ShizuokaPrefecture and the vicinity of Mt. Fuji)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Suruga-no-kuni (mainly Central ShizuokaPrefecture and the vicinity of Mt. Fuji)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="17">
<j>伊豆国（伊豆半島及び伊豆諸島）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Izu-no-kuni (Izu Peninsula and Izu Island chain)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Izu-no-kuni (Izu Peninsula and the Izu island chain)</e>
<cmt>capitalization</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Izu-no-kuni (Izu Peninsula and the Izu island chain)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="18">
<j>甲斐国（山梨県）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kai-no-kuni (Yamanashi Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kai-no-kuni (Yamanashi Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kai-no-kuni (Yamanashi Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="19">
<j>相模国（神奈川県）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sagami-no-kuni (Kanagawa Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sagami-no-kuni (Kanagawa Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sagami-no-kuni (Kanagawa Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="20">
<j>武蔵国（東京都と埼玉県、神奈川県の一部。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Musashi-no-kuni (Tokyo Prefecture and part of Saitama and Kanagawa Prefectures,</e>
<cmt>http://100.yahoo.co.jp/detail/武蔵国/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Musashi-no-kuni (Tokyo Prefecture and part of Saitama and Kanagawa Prefectures,</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Musashi-no-kuni (Tokyo Prefecture and part of Saitama and Kanagawa Prefectures,</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>初めは東山道）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Initially belonging to Tozando</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Initially belonging to Tozando</e>
<cmt>To complete the above cell</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">initially belonging to Tozando).</e>
<cmt>If this is completing the above cell, the first word should be lower case and this should end in a close parenthesis followed by a period.</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="22">
<j>安房国（千葉県の南部）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Awa-no-kuni (southern Chiba Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Awa-no-kuni (southern Chiba Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Awa-no-kuni (southern Chiba Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="23">
<j>上総国（千葉県の中部）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kazusa-no-kuni (Central Chiba Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kazusa-no-kuni (Central Chiba Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kazusa-no-kuni (central Chiba Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>大文字</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="24">
<j>下総国（東京都の隅田川東岸、千葉県の北部、茨城県の一部）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shimo-usa-no-kuni (the east of the Sumida River in Tokyo Prefecture, northern Chiba Prefecture, part of Ibaraki Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shimo-usa-no-kuni (east of the Sumida River in Tokyo Prefecture, northern Chiba Prefecture and part of Ibaraki Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shimo-usa-no-kuni (east of the Sumida River in Tokyo Prefecture, northern Chiba Prefecture and part of Ibaraki Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="25">
<j>常陸国（茨城県）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hitachi-no-kuni (Ibaraki Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hitachi-no-kuni (Ibaraki Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hitachi-no-kuni (Ibaraki Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>道（みち）としての東海道</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokaido as a Road</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokaido as a road</e>
<cmt>Capitalization</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Highway</e>
<cmt>I realize this deviates from the Japanese a little but as this is a heading, I think simply &quot;Highway&quot; would be sufficient.</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>律令時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ritsuryo Era</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ritsuryo Period</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ritsuryo Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="26">
<j>律令制の東海道は、東海道の諸国の国府を駅路で結ぶ物であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Tokaido in the Ritsuryo era is a road linking Kokufu of Tokaido regions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Ritsuryo period the Tokaido was a road linking the Kokufu and Tokaido regions.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Ritsuryo period the Tokaido was a road linking the Kokufu and Tokaido regions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>七道の一つで、五畿七道の中路である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Tokaido, one of the Shichido, is in the middle grade among Goki-Shicido.</e>
<cmt>中路をmiddle-grade roadと訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Tokaido, one of the Shichido, is in the middle grade among the Goki-Shicido.</e>
<cmt>Article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tokaido, one of the Shichido, is in the middle grade among the Goki-Shichido.</e>
<cmt>スペルミス</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>律令時代の東海道の道幅は、中世や江戸時代の物より広く、直線的に建設された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Tokaido in the Ritsuryo era was developed wider and straighter than that in the Middle Ages and the Edo era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Ritsuryo period the Tokaido was developed to be wider and straighter than that of the middle ages and the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Ritsuryo period the Tokaido was developed to be wider and straighter than that of the middle ages and the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>中世に大半が廃れたため、正確な道筋については議論されているが、以下の箇所を除いては近世の東海道とおおむね同様の径路と考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A question remains as to what is the exact route because the road was out of use and disappeared over the Middle Ages, but its route is thought to be almost the same as the modern Tokaido, except the following areas:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A question remains as to what the exact route would have been because the road was no longer used and had disappeared over the middle ages, but its route is thought to be nearly the same as the modern Tokaido except for the following areas:</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A question remains as to what the exact route would have been because the road was no longer used and had disappeared over the middle ages, but its route is thought to be nearly the same as the modern Tokaido except for the following areas:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="30">
<j>平城京（奈良）から東に伊賀国府を経由して鈴鹿関に至る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the area east from Heijo-kyo (Nara) until Suzuka-no-Seki Checkpoint via Iga Kokufu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">the area east from Heijo-kyo (Nara) until the Suzuka-no-Seki checkpoint via Iga Kokufu</e>
<cmt>Article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The area east from Heijo-kyo (Nara) up to the Suzuka-no-Seki checkpoint via Iga Kokufu</e>
<cmt>小文字</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="31">
<j>沼津から御殿場を経由して足柄峠を越え、関本に至る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the area from Numazu to Sekimoto via Gotenba and Ashigara-toge</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The area from Numazu to Sekimoto via Gotenba and Ashigara-toge</e>
<cmt>capitalization</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The area from Numazu to Sekimoto via Gotenba and Ashigara-toge</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="32">
<j>当時は「東海道」の本筋であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In those days, the Tokaido was the main road in &quot;Tokaido&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In those days the Tokaido was the main road in &quot;Tokaido.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In those days the Tokaido was the main road in &quot;Tokaido.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>800年頃、富士山の噴火によって足柄が通行不能になって「箱根路」が拓かれると「東海道矢倉沢往還」と称されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Ashikagaji was closed because of an eruption of Mt. Fuji around 800, the &quot;Hakone-ji&quot; was developed and called &quot;Tokaido Yagurazawa Okan&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Ashikagaji was closed in about 88 due to an eruption of Mt. Fuji, the &quot;Hakone-ji&quot; was developed and called &quot;Tokaido Yagurazawa Okan.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Ashikagaji was closed in about 800 due to an eruption of Mt. Fuji, the &quot;Hakone-ji&quot; was developed and called &quot;Tokaido Yagurazawa Okan.&quot;</e>
<cmt>年号間違え</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>なお箱根路は急峻なため、足柄路が復興され、中世までは主要な街道筋であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, because the route of the Hakone-ji had steep slopes, the Ashigara-ji was repaired and reopened and continued to be a major highway until the Middle Ages.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, because the route of the Hakone-ji had steep slopes the Ashigara-ji was repaired and reopened, and it continued to be a major highway until the Middle Ages.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, because the route of the Hakone-ji had steep slopes, the Ashigara-ji was repaired and reopened, and it continued as a major highway until the middle ages.</e>
<cmt>中世の大文字他と統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="35">
<j>相模国国府以東。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">East of Saggami-no-kuni Kokufu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">East of Saggami-no-kuni Kokufu</e>
<cmt>SaGGami? Sagami?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">East of Sagami-no-kuni Kokufu</e>
<cmt>相模スペルミス</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>海を渡ってから房総半島を北上し、常陸国から菊多関を経由して陸奥国に入り、今の宮城県南部で東山道に合する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After crossing the sea, the Tokaido ran north in the Boso Peninsula, went through Hitachi-no-kuni and the Kikuta-no-seki Checkpoint into Mutsu-no-kuni, and merged with theTozando in present-day Miyagi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After crossing the sea, the Tokaido ran north along the Boso Peninsula, went through Hitachi-no-kuni and the Kikuta-no-seki checkpoint into Mutsu-no-kuni, and merged with the Tozando in what is now Miyagi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After crossing the sea, the Tokaido ran north along the Boso Peninsula, went through Hitachi-no-kuni and the Kikuta-no-seki checkpoint into Mutsu-no-kuni, and merged with the Tozando in what is now Miyagi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="37">
<j>相模国では、多摩川を渡る地点までは現在の矢倉沢往還（国道246号）の経路にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Sagami-no-kuni, it took the route of the present Yagurazawa-okan (National Highway 246) until the point of crossing the Tama-gawa River.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Sagami-no-kuni it took the route of the present Yagurazawa-okan (National Highway 246) until the point of crossing the Tama-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Sagami-no-kuni it took the route of the present Yagurazawa-okan (National Highway 246) until the point of crossing the Tama-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>矢倉沢往還の旧道では、律令時代の東海道の道筋がそのまま現在でも用いられている箇所がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In some section of the Old way of the Yagurazawa-okan., the roadway of the Tokaido in the Ritsuryo era has been used</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In some sections of the old route of the Yagurazawa-okan, the roadway of the Tokaido in the Ritsuryo period, has been used.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In some sections of the old route of the Yagurazawa-okan, the roadway of the Tokaido in the Ritsuryo period has been used.</e>
<cmt>カンマを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="39">
<j>武蔵国と下総国の境の中川低地付近は古代には陸化が進んでおらず低湿地で通行に適さず、元来武蔵国が北隣の上野国の豪族の影響下にありその関係が密接であった（武蔵国造の乱を参照のこと）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In ancient times, a border area between Musashi-no-kuni and Shimo-usa-no-kuni called Nakagawa Lowlands had not become a solid land and were unsuitable for people to travel and Musash-no-kuni belonged to Tozando under traditional influence of powerful families of its northern nabor Ueno-no-kuni and with a close relation with them. (Refer to Musashi-no-kuni-nomiyatuko-no-ran).</e>
<cmt>http://100.yahoo.co.jp/detail/武蔵国造の反乱/一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In ancient times a border area between Musashi-no-kuni and Shimo-usa-no-kuni, called the Nakagawa Lowlands, had not become solid land and was therefore unsuitable for people to travel, but Musash-no-kuni belonged to Tozando under the traditional influence of powerful families of its northern neighbor Ueno-no-kuni, and had a close relationship with them. (Refer to Musashi-no-kuni-nomiyatuko-no-ran).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In ancient times a border area between Musashi-no-kuni and Shimo-usa-no-kuni, called the Nakagawa Lowlands, had not become solid land and was therefore unsuitable as a travel route, but Musashi-no-kuni belonged to Tozando under the traditional influence of the powerful families of its northern neighbor Ueno-no-kuni, and had a close relationship with them (see the article on Musashi-no-kuni-nomiyatuko-no-ran).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置訳を補いました。スペルミス</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>そのため、当初の東海道は相模国の三浦半島から海路で房総半島の上総国（安房国分立は718年）に渡るルートとなっており、武蔵国は東山道に属していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">So the initial Tokaido crossed water from the Miura Peninsula of Sagami-no-kuni to the Boso Peninsula of Kazusa-no-kuni.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳出の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">So, the initial Tokaido crossed water from the Miura Peninsula of Sagami-no-kuni to the Boso Peninsula of Kazusa-no-kuni.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Accordingly, the initial Tokaido crossed water from the Miura Peninsula of Sagami-no-kuni to the Boso Peninsula of Kazusa-no-kuni (Awa-no-kuni became independent in 718).</e>
<cmt>訳を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>現・千葉県である安房国（房総半島先端）はともかくとして、上総国（房総半島中部）と下総国（房総半島根本部）の位置が「現代感覚から見て逆転している」のはこのためである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is because, apart from Awa-no-kuni, present-day Chiba Prefecutre (the tip area of Boso Peninsula), Kazusa no kuni (the central Boso Penisula) having a kanji meaning &quot;upper&quot; was actually below Shimosa-no-kuni (upper part of the Penisula) having a kanji meaning &quot;lower&quot;, which makes some feel strange from today&apos;s conception of &quot;upper&quot; and &quot;lower&quot;.</e>
<cmt>この部分は直訳するとわかりにくいので、わかりやすいように意訳してあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is because, apart from Awa-no-kuni, present-day Chiba Prefecture (the tip area of the Boso Peninsula), Kazusa no kuni (the central Boso Penisula), having the kanji meaning &quot;upper,&quot; was actually below Shimosa-no-kuni (the upper part of the penisula), having a kanji meaning &quot;lower,&quot; which makes some feel strange from today&apos;s concept of &quot;upper and lower.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Grammar, Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is because, apart from Awa-no-kuni, present-day Chiba Prefecture (the tip of the Boso Peninsula), Kazusa-no-kuni (the central Boso Peninsula), having the kanji meaning &quot;upper,&quot; was in fact below Shimousa-no-kuni (the upper part of the peninsula), having a kanji meaning &quot;lower,&quot; which may feel confusing by comparison to the modern concept of &quot;upper and lower.&quot;</e>
<cmt>ハイフン入スペルミススペース削除&quot;actually&quot; -&gt; &quot;in fact&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="42">
<j>武蔵国はその後、海路の不安定さや蝦夷討伐の際の輸送の効率性を重視する観点から、771年（宝亀2年）旧10月27日に東海道に移された（続日本紀）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, on October 27 in 771 (Japanese old calendar), Musashi-no-kuni was transferred to Tokaido with a consideration of an insecure water route and an importance of efficient transportation in sending an expedition to Ezo (according to Shoku-Nihongi)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, on October 27, 771 (on the old Japanese calendar), Musashi-no-kuni was transferred to Tokaido in consideration of an insecure water route and the importance of efficient transportation in sending an expedition to Ezo (according to Shoku-Nihongi).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, on October 27, 771 (on the old Japanese calendar), Musashi-no-kuni was transferred to Tokaido in consideration of an insecure water route and the importance of efficient transportation in sending an expedition to Ezo (according to Shoku-Nihongi).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>なお、「東海道」の呼称は上記の相模 - 上総のルートとともに、三河国から伊勢湾を経由して伊勢国に渡る別ルートという海上ルートを含んでいたために、「ヤマノミチ（東山道）」に対する「ウミノミチ」の意味で命名されたと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that the name of the Tokaido with the meaning of &quot;Umino-michi (sea route)&quot;in contrast to &quot;Yama-no-michi (mountain road) (Tozando)&quot;came from its water route of crossing the Ise Bay from Mikawa-no-kuni to Ise-no-kuni, which was different route from the Sagami to Kazusa route as explained above.</e>
<cmt>「なお」は特に訳出していません。一原文一訳出の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that the name of the Tokaido with the meaning of &quot;Umino-michi (sea route)&quot;in contrast to &quot;Yama-no-michi (mountain road) (Tozando)&quot;came from its water route of crossing the Ise Bay from Mikawa-no-kuni to Ise-no-kuni, which was a different route than the Sagami to Kazusa route as explained above.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that the name &quot;Tokaido&quot; includes the meaning &quot;Umi-no-michi&quot; (literally, &quot;sea road&quot;) rather than &quot;Yama-no-michi&quot; (literally, &quot;mountain road,&quot; which is the meaning that the name &quot;Tozando&quot; includes) because, in addition to the route from Sagami to Kazusa mentioned above, it also provides a route across the sea at Ise Bay from Mikawa-no-kuni to Ise-no-kuni.</e>
<cmt>「---とともに」の意味合いが訳されていない。---(which was a different route)than ---訳しなおし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>海上ルートは延喜式にも記された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The water route was described in Engi-shiki.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳出の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The water route was described in Engi-shiki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The water route was described in Engi-shiki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="45">
<j>東海道は地域としての東海道最後の国である常陸国の国府に達してからもさらに北上し、菊多関から陸奥国に入った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Tokaido, after reaching its terminal region, Hitachi-no-kuni, further extended north to Mutsu-no-kukni via the Kikuta-no-seki Checkpoint.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Tokaido, after reaching its terminal region of Hitachi-no-kuni, further extended north to Mutsu-no-kukni via the Kikuta-no-seki checkpoint.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, capitalization</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tokaido, after reaching its terminal region of Hitachi-no-kuni, was extended further north to Mutsu-no-kuni via the Kikuta-no-seki checkpoint.</e>
<cmt>スペルミス</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>今の福島県の海岸地方（浜通り）を通って、宮城県の岩沼市あたりで東山道に合流した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It continued along the coastal area of present-day Fukushima Prefecture (along Hama dori-street) to merged with the Tosando in Iwanuma City, Miyagi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It continued along the coastal area of present-day Fukushima Prefecture (along Hama dori street) and merged with the Tosando in Iwanuma City, Miyagi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It continued along the coastal area of the present-day Fukushima Prefecture (along Hama-dori street) and merged with the Tosando in Iwanuma City, Miyagi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>ハイフン入</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>陸奥は東山道に属するので、この東海道はそれに対する副線である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Tokaido in Mutsu is a secondary route because Mutsu belonged to Tozando.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Tokaido in Mutsu is a secondary route, because Mutsu belonged to Tozando.</e>
<cmt>Clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tokaido in Mutsu is a secondary route, because Mutsu belonged to Tozando.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>それより北にも各地に東海道と呼ばれる道が断片的に存在し、それが古代の名残りだとすると、さらに北でも支線として存在した可能性が高い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In regions north of Mutsu, roads named Tokaido are found here and there.If they are legacies of ancient times, it is likely that the Tokaido existed as a branch line in further northern regions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In regions north of Mutsu, roads with the Tokaido name are found here and there. If they are legacies of ancient times, it is likely that the Tokaido existed as a branch line in regions farther north.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In regions north of Mutsu, roads with the Tokaido name are found here and there. If they are legacies of ancient times, it is likely that the Tokaido existed as a branch line in regions farther north.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>史料に山道に対する海道として現れるものは、多賀城の国府から海側の牡鹿郡・桃生郡へ向かう支線として設定されたと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The roads described in historical papers as a sea route in contrast to a mountain route are believed to have been developed as a branch line. extending from Kokufu of Tagajo toward Oshika-gun/Monou-gun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The roads described in historical papers as sea routes (by contrast to mountain routes) are believed to have been developed as branch lines extending from Kokufu of Tagajo toward Oshika-gun/Monou-gun.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The roads described in historical papers as sea routes (in contrast to mountain routes) are believed to have been developed as branch lines extending from Kokufu of Tagajo toward Oshika-gun/Monou-gun.</e>
<cmt>スペース削</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>また現在の仙台市にある東海道（あずまかいどう）も、古代に連なる可能性がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, Azuma-kaido Street in present-day Sendai may have a story that goes back to an ancient time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, Azuma-kaido Street in present-day Sendai may have a story that goes back to ancient times.</e>
<cmt>Better</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, Azuma-kaido Street in present-day Sendai may have a story that goes back to ancient times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>中世</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Middle Ages</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Middle Ages</e>
<cmt>As a heading</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Middle Ages</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="51">
<j>源頼朝が相模国鎌倉市に鎌倉幕府を樹立すると、東海道は京都と鎌倉を結ぶ幹線として機能するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Kamakura Shogunate was established by MIYAMOTO Yoritomo, Tokaido began to serve as an arterial highway linking Kyoto with Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>http://dic.yahoo.co.jp/dsearch?enc=UTF-8&amp;p=源頼朝&amp;stype=0&amp;dtype=0</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Kamakura Shogunate was established by Yoritomo Miyamoto, the Tokaido began to serve as an arterial highway linking Kyoto with Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Once the Kamakura shogunate was established by MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, the Tokaido began to serve as an arterial highway linking Kyoto and Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>shogunateとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="52">
<j>海道記とあるように、この頃、海道といえば、東海道そのものを指していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In those days, Umimichi referred to the Tokaido, as was described in a book titled Kaidoki.</e>
<cmt>http://etext.virginia.edu/japanese/kaidoki/AnoKaid.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In those days Umimichi referred to the Tokaido, as described in a book entitled &quot;Kaidoki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In those days Umimichi referred to the Tokaido, as described in a book entitled &quot;Kaidoki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>江戸時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Edo Era</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Edo Period</e>
<cmt>As a heading</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Edo Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="53">
<j>江戸時代になり、事実上の首都が江戸に移ると、東海道は五街道の一つとされ、京都と江戸を結ぶ、日本の中で最も重要な街道となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the beginning of the Edo period, when the admistrative capital was transferred to Edo (Tokyo), the Tokaido was regarded as one of the 5 major highways and became the most important highway linking Kyoto and Edo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the beginning of the Edo era, when the admistrative capital was transferred to Edo (Tokyo), the Tokaido was regarded as one of the five major highways and thus became the most important highway linking Kyoto and Edo.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the beginning of the Edo period, when the administrative capital was transferred to Edo (Tokyo), the Tokaido was regarded as one of the five major highways and thus became the most important route linking Kyoto and Edo.</e>
<cmt>スペース削スペルミス</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>日本橋 (東京都中央区)（江戸）から三条大橋（京都市）に至る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It extended from Nihonbashi (Chuo Ward, Tokyo Prefecture) (Edo) to Sanjo-ohashi (Kyoto).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It extended from Nihonbashi (the Chuo ward of Tokyo Prefecture) (Edo) to Sanjo-ohashi (Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It extended from Nihonbashi (Chuo Ward, Tokyo Prefecture) (Edo) to Sanjo-ohashi (Kyoto City).</e>
<cmt>市表記ルール</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>宿駅は53箇所（→東海道五十三次）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were fifty-three Yadoeki. (Refer to Toakaido Gojusan Tsugi)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were fifty-three yadoeki (refer to Toakaido Gojusan Tsugi).</e>
<cmt>A sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were 53 yadoeki (see &quot;Tokaido Gojusan Tsugi&quot;).</e>
<cmt>スペルミス</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>当初は、主に軍用道路として整備された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mainly for a military purpose, the Tokaido was improved at first.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Military activity was the original purpose of the improvement of the Tokaido.</e>
<cmt>Better Eng</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Military activity was the original purpose of the improvement of the Tokaido.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>途中に箱根町と新居町に関所を設けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Checkpoints were set on the way in Hakone Town and Arai Town.</e>
<cmt>http://www.town.hakone.kanagawa.jp/http://archive.hp.infoseek.co.jp/kd_tokaido.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Checkpoints were established along the way in Hakone Town and Arai Town.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Checkpoints were established along the way in Hakone Town and Arai Town.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="58">
<j>京都から延長して大阪市に至る京街道（宿駅4箇所）も、東海道の一部とすることがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some may regard the Tokaido the Kyo-kaido (with 4 checkpoints), which extended from Kyoto to Osaka, as part of the Tokaido.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some may regard the Tokaido the Kyo-kaido (with four checkpoints), which extended from Kyoto to Osaka, as part of the Tokaido.</e>
<cmt>Num</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some may regard the Kyo-kaido (with four checkpoints), which extended from Kyoto to Osaka, as part of the Tokaido.</e>
<cmt>It seems a little strange to me that &quot;Kyo-kaido&quot; is hyphenated but &quot;Tokaido&quot; isn&apos;t. I&apos;ve left this as is for the time being, though.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>江戸方面から大坂へ向かう場合は、大津宿から京都には入らずに伏見区に入る大津街道が追分駅 (滋賀県)付近から分岐する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the way from the direction of Edo to Osaka, the Otsu-Kaido branched off at Oiwake Station (Shiga Prefecture) to enter Fushimi ward instead of entering Kyoto at Otsu-juku.</e>
<cmt>http://www.okeihan.net/eki/detail.php?station_no=61</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the way, in the direction from Edo to Osaka, the Otsu-Kaido branched off at Oiwake Station (Shiga Prefecture) to enter the Fushimi ward instead of entering Kyoto at Otsu-juku.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the way, in the direction from Edo to Osaka, the Otsu-kaido branched off at Oiwake Station (Shiga Prefecture) to enter Fushimi Ward instead of entering Kyoto at Otsu-juku.</e>
<cmt>大文字</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="60">
<j>東海道を扱った作品</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Work Pieces Featuring Tokaido</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Work Pieces Featuring Tokaido</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Work Pieces Featuring Tokaido</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="61">
<j>歌川広重作「東海道五十三次」（浮世絵）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokaido Gojusan Tsugi by Hiroshige UTAGAWA (Ukiyoe picture)</e>
<cmt>http://dic.yahoo.co.jp/dsearch?enc=UTF-8&amp;p=歌川広重&amp;stype=0&amp;dtype=2</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokaido Gojusan Tsugi, by Hiroshige Utagawa (a ukiyoe picture)</e>
<cmt>Grammar, capitalization</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokaido Gojusan Tsugi, by Hiroshige UTAGAWA (a ukiyoe picture)</e>
<cmt>名字大文字</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="62">
<j>十返舎一九作「東海道中膝栗毛」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokaidochu Hizakurige by Ikku JUPPENSHA</e>
<cmt>http://dic.yahoo.co.jp/dsearch?enc=UTF-8&amp;p=歌川広重&amp;stype=0&amp;dtype=2</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokaidochu Hizakurige, by Ikku Juppensha</e>
<cmt>by the Ikku Juppensha?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokaidochu Hizakurige, by Ikku Juppensha</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>明治時代以後</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meiji Era and Onward</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Meiji Period and Onward</e>
<cmt>As a heading</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Meiji Period and Onward</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="63">
<j>明治政府は、幹線道路の呼称に番号付きの国道を用いるようになり、地方制度としての令制国も廃止した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meiji Government began to assign road numbers to national arterial highways and abolished Ryoseikoku as it a regional division system.</e>
<cmt>http://100.yahoo.co.jp/detail/国府（令制）/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Meiji government began to assign road numbers to national arterial highways and thereby abolished Ryoseikoku as a regional division system.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Meiji government began to assign road numbers as the names of national arterial highways, and thereby it abolished Ryoseikoku as a regional division system.</e>
<cmt>I think most native speakers of English would have interpreted the translation according to the meaning of the Japanese, but the above should resolve any concerns.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>幹線道路としての実質的機能と位置は現在の国道15号及び国道1号に受け継がれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its proper function and location of the highway were taken over by presen National Highway 15 and 1.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳出の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The proper function and location of the highway were taken over by the present National Highway 15 and 1.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The proper function and location of the highway were taken over by the present national highways 15 and 1.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>部分的に異なる経路を歩むが、東日本と西日本（関東地方と近畿地方）を結ぶ機能は律令時代から同じであり、現在においても東海道の径路は、日本に必要なものであることを示している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the current Tokaido takes a different route in some sections, its function of linking East Japan with West Japan (or Kanto region with Kansai region) has not been the same since the Ritsuryo era, which means that the route of the Tokaido is still indispensable for Japan today..</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳出の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the current Tokaido takes a different route in some sections, its function of linking eastern Japan with western Japan (or the Kanto region with the Kansai region) has not been the same since the Ritsuryo era, which means the route of the Tokaido is still indispensable for Japan today.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the current Tokaido takes a different route in some sections, its function of linking eastern Japan with western Japan (or the Kanto region with the Kansai region) has been the same since the Ritsuryo period, which means the route of the Tokaido is still indispensable for Japan today.</e>
<cmt>not取りました。スペース削</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="66">
<j>現代において「東海道」と言うときには、江戸時代の東海道の道筋と、その頃の東海道に属した諸国の範囲を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When people say &quot;Tokaido&quot; today, they refer to its route in the Edo era and the areas that belonged to the region of Tokaido in those days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When people say &quot;Tokaido&quot; today, they refer to its route in the Edo era and the areas that belonged to the region of Tokaido in those days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When people say &quot;Tokaido&quot; today, they refer to its route in the Edo era and the areas that belonged to the region of Tokaido in those days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>従って、東海道の東端は、律令時代では北茨城市、江戸時代以後は特別区（江戸）ということになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore the east end of Tokaido was Kitaibaraki City in the Ritsuryo era and Special word (Edo) in the Edo era and after afterwards.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the east end of Tokaido was Kitaibaraki City in the Ritsuryo era and the special word (Edo) in the Edo era and later.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the east end of Tokaido was Kitaibaraki City in the Ritsuryo era and the special word (Edo) in the Edo era and later.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>鉄道の「東海道」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokaido as a Railway</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokaido as a Railway</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokaido as a Railway</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="68">
<j>なお、「東海道」の名をつけた東海道本線および東海道新幹線は、東京－熱田間と草津－京都間ではほぼ江戸時代の東海道に沿っているが、その間は中山道（加納宿－草津宿）と美濃路（宮宿－垂井宿）に沿ったルートとなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Tokaido Main Line and Tokaido Shinkansen, which include &quot;Tokaido&quot; in their names, roughly follow the Tokaido between Tokyo and Atami and between Kusatsu and Kyoto but take a route along the Nakasenndo (between Kano-juku and Kusatsu-juku) and Mino-ji highway (between Miyashuku and Tarui-juku) in the middle.</e>
<cmt>http://archive.hp.infoseek.co.jp/kd_nakasendo.htmlhttp://100.yahoo.co.jp/detail/稲沢（市）/http://archive.hp.infoseek.co.jp/kd_tokaido.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Tokaido Main Line and Tokaido Shinkansen, which include &quot;Tokaido&quot; in their names, roughly follow the Tokaido between Tokyo and Atami and between Kusatsu and Kyoto, but they take a route along the Nakasenndo (between Kano-juku and Kusatsu-juku) and Mino-ji Highway (between Miyashuku and Tarui-juku) in the middle.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, capitalization</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tokaido Main Line and Tokaido Shinkansen, which both include &quot;Tokaido&quot; in their names, roughly follow the Tokaido between Tokyo and Atsuta and between Kusatsu and Kyoto, but between these two sections of the route, they follow the Nakasen-do (between Kano-juku and Kusatsu-juku) and then the Mino-ji Highway (between Miya-juku and Tarui-juku).</e>
<cmt>I assume that the route followed by the Tokaido Main Line and Tokaido Shinkansen is as follows:the Tokaido between Tokyo and Atsuta → the Nakasen-do → the Mino-ji Highway → the Tokaido between Kusatsu and Kyoto</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>現在「東海道」というと、しばしばこの両鉄道沿いのルートが江戸時代のそれであると誤解され、紹介されることもあるほどである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today some people misunderstand and even show others that the route taken by these 2 railways is that of the &quot;Tokaido&quot;of the Edo era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today some people misunderstand and even show others that the route taken by these two railways is that of the &quot;Tokaido&quot;of the Edo era.</e>
<cmt>Num</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today some people misunderstand and even show others that the route taken by these two railways is that of the &quot;Tokaido&quot; of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>後述する通り、本来の街道としての東海道は名古屋－亀山－草津という、現在の鉄道路線ならば関西本線と草津線のルートに近いものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As explained below, the true Tokaido as a historical highway roughly follows the route of Nagoya - Kameyama - Kusatsu, which is rather closer to the route taken by the present Kansai Main Line and Kusatsu Line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As explained below, the true Tokaido as an historical highway roughly follows the route of Nagoya - Kameyama - Kusatsu, which is somewhat closer to the route taken by the present Kansai Main Line and the Kusatsu Line.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As explained below, the true Tokaido as an historical highway roughly follows the route of Nagoya - Kameyama - Kusatsu, which is somewhat closer to the route taken by the present Kansai Main Line and the Kusatsu Line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="71">
<j>これは東西両京を結ぶ鉄道線を敷設するに当たって、東海道と中山道のいずれに通すかを巡って明治初期に論争があり、その結果中山道経由に一時は決定してその一部に該当する路線が開業したものの、後に碓氷峠を越える区間など山岳地域での工事の長期化・費用増、開業後の輸送量制限を考慮して、やはり東海道の方が優れているということになり、急遽岐阜（加納）以東のルートが東海道経由に変更されたことに起因している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Behind this lies a construction plan early Meiji era; there were divided opinions over which route is better for the construction, Tokaido or Nakasen-do Street. At first the government accepted the route along the Nakasen-do Street and started service of some sections, but later realized that the route along the Tokaido is better considering the earlier plan&apos;s estimated higher costs and longer period for construction as well as restricted transportations in mountanous areas, in particular areas across Usui-toge, and then finally shifted its route east of Kano (Gifu Prefecture) to the route along the Tokaido,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Behind this lies a construction plan of the early Meiji era, and there were divided opinions over which route--Tokaido or Nakasen-do Street--was better for construction. At first the government accepted the route along the Nakasen-do Street and started service in some sections, but later it realized that the route along the Tokaido was better considering the earlier plan&apos;s estimated higher costs and longer period for construction as well as restricted transportation in mountanous areas (particularly those across the Usui-toge) and then finally shifted its route east of Kano (Gifu Prefecture) to the route along the Tokaido.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Behind this lies a construction plan of the early Meiji period, and there were divided opinions over which route--Tokaido or Nakasen-do Street--would be preferable for construction. Initially the government accepted the route along Nakasen-do Street and started service in some sections, but later it realized that the route along the Tokaido was better, considering the earlier plan&apos;s higher estimated costs and longer construction period, as well as the restricted transportation in mountainous areas (particularly those across the Usui-toge), so ultimately the route was shifted east of Kano (Gifu Prefecture) to the route along the Tokaido.</e>
<cmt>スペルミス</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="72">
<j>計画変更が決まった時には、既に神戸駅 (兵庫県)から大阪駅・京都駅を経て大津駅に至る鉄道と、長浜駅から岐阜駅・名古屋駅を経て武豊駅までの鉄道が開業していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When they decided to change the plan, the line of Kobe Station (Hyogo Prefecture) - Osaka Station - Kyoto-Station - Otsu Station and the line of Nihama Station - Gifu Station - Nagoya Station -Taketoyo Station had been opened.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When they decided to change the plan, the line of Kobe Station (Hyogo Prefecture) - Osaka Station - Kyoto-Station - Otsu Station and the line of Nihama Station - Gifu Station - Nagoya Station -Taketoyo Station had been opened.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When it was decided that the plan would be changed, the line of Kobe Station (Hyogo Prefecture) - Osaka Station - Kyoto-Station - Otsu Station and the line of Nagahama Station - Gifu Station - Nagoya Station -Taketoyo Station had already been opened.</e>
<cmt>地名間違え</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>これと琵琶湖の鉄道連絡船（大津－長浜）を用いることによって武豊－名古屋－京都－神戸間の連絡が図られていたため、両京を結ぶ鉄道はこれを最大限に活用して早期に完成させるべきであるとの判断がなされ、これにより現行ルートが定まることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They also thought it better to construct the trunk line connecting ancient and then new capitals as early as possible by making use of already-built lines and ferry service on Biwa Lake. In this way the current route was established.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They also thought it would be better to construct the trunk line connecting the ancient capitals and new capitals as early as possible by making use of already-built lines and ferry service on Lake Biwa, thereby establishing the present route.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They also thought it would be better to construct the trunk line connecting the ancient capitals and new capitals as early as possible by making use of already-built lines and ferry service on Lake Biwa (Otsu - Nagahama), thereby establishing the present route.</e>
<cmt>訳を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="74">
<j>結果、日本の鉄道開業である新橋駅－横浜駅間もその東西幹線に組み入れる形となた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the result, Japan&apos;s first railway line from Shinbashi to Yokohama was also incorporated into this east-west trunk line.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the result, Japan&apos;s first railway line from Shinbashi to Yokohama was incorporated into this east-west trunk line.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the result, Japan&apos;s first railway line from Shinbashi to Yokohama was incorporated into this east-west trunk line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>明治10年代末より横浜から静岡駅を経て大府駅に至る区間と関ヶ原駅から米原駅を経て大津に至る区間が建設され、1889年（明治22年）7月に全通、これにより現在の東海道本線の原型が完成した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The construction started in the section from Yokohama Station to Obu Station via Shizuoka Station and the section from Sekigahara Station to Otsu Station via Maibara Station in mid 1880&apos;s and the entire line was opened in July, 1889, when the prototype of current Tokaido Main Line was completed.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The construction started in the section from Yokohama Station to Obu Station via Shizuoka Station and in the section from Sekigahara Station to Otsu Station via Maibara Station in the mid-1880s, and in July 1889 the entire line was opened with the completion of the prototype for the current Tokaido Main Line.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The construction started in the section from Yokohama Station to Obu Station via Shizuoka Station and in the section from Sekigahara Station to Otsu Station via Maibara Station in the mid-1880s, and in July 1889 the entire line was opened with the completion of the prototype for the current Tokaido Main Line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="76">
<j>なお熱田から四日市宿を経て草津に至る、江戸時代の東海道のうち上記の東西幹線から外れた区間に関しては、明治中期になって関西鉄道がその沿線の振興を目的に鉄道を敷設し、現在の草津線と関西本線の一部（柘植駅－名古屋）になっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the area from Atsuta to Kusatsu via Yokaichi-juku, which is deviated from East-West truck line above, Kansai Railway Company set up rails in the middle of Meiji era for the purpose of promoting the development of the area,, and the line has become part of current Kansai Main line (from Tsuge Station to Nagoya)</e>
<cmt>http://www.rtri.or.jp/japanrail/History1_E.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the middle of the Meiji, for the area from Atsuta to Kusatsu via Yokaichi-juku, which is deviated from the east-west truck line above, Kansai Railway Company set up rails for the purpose of promoting the development of the area, and subsequently it has become part of the current Kansai Main line (from Tsuge Station to Nagoya).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the middle of the Meiji, for the area from Atsuta to Kusatsu via Yokkaichi-juku, which diverges from the east-west truck line above, Kansai Railway Company set up rails for the purpose of promoting the area&apos;s development, and subsequently it became part of the current Kansai Main Line (from Tsuge Station to Nagoya).</e>
<cmt>スペルミス小文字</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="77">
<j>また新幹線に関しては、当初は名古屋から京都まで鈴鹿山脈を一直線にトンネルで抜けるルートでの敷設も計画されていたが、トンネルが長大になり建設に時間・費用を要すること、それに米原が北陸本線（旧：北陸道）との接続点になっていたこともあって、最終的には東海道本線に沿う現行ルートで敷設された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the construction of Shinkansen, although the initial plan was to build a straight tunnel under the Suzuka Sanmyaku Mountains, the current route along the Tokaido Main line was finally accepted considering a time- and money-consuming task of making such a tunnel and the role of Maibara Station as a junction to Hokuriku Main line (former Hokuriku-do)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the construction of the Shinkansen, although the initial plan was to build a straight tunnel under the Suzuka Sanmyaku mountain range, the current route of the Tokaido Main Line was finally accepted in consideration of the costly and time-consuming task of making such a tunnel and the role of Maibara Station as a junction to the Hokuriku Main line (formerly Hokuriku-do).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the construction of the Shinkansen, although the initial plan was to build a straight tunnel under the Suzuka Sanmyaku mountain range, the current route of the Tokaido Main Line was finally accepted in consideration of the costly and time-consuming task of making such a tunnel and the role of Maibara Station as a junction to the Hokuriku Main line (formerly Hokuriku-do).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="78">
<j>以上の経緯については、中山道及び鉄道と政治の項目も参照のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Please refer to the sections of &quot;Nakasen-do Street&quot; and &quot;Railways and Politics&quot; for more details.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Please refer to the &quot;Nakasen-do Street&quot; and &quot;Railways and Politics&quot; sections for additional details.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Please refer to the &quot;Nakasen-do Street&quot; and &quot;Railways and Politics&quot; sections for additional details.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 伊賀123(id:181679), AlleborgoBot(id:119729), Nnh(id:474), Πrate(id:11329), Reggaeman(id:6214), Eskimbot(id:29676), Maxima m(id:28947), Mintleaf(id:2216), Njt(id:11249), Mietyan(id:198616), Tara123(id:130635), Mop(id:12061), Johncapistrano(id:969), Natunohi(id:6550), Sunen(id:10700), 肉球ぷりん(id:92929), Kinori(id:443), IwaimBot(id:190695), Chobot(id:20846), Kone(id:377), Ficbot(id:156903), Shimoxx(id:9332), Yas(id:739), Mkoba(id:9856), Bankokuya(id:91191), ウィキ豊(id:82961), Guretaro(id:163381), もね～るmoner(id:28477), 元禄三百年生まれ(id:157908), G(id:21), ガウス(id:6519), Cyuuritsu Na Shitenn(id:102276), たね(id:10372), Stanislaus(id:1806), 水野白楓(id:22811), ぽえこ(id:88711), Escarbot(id:59151), Shinkansen(id:13703), Interregnum(id:25269), Rusk(id:9895), Kafuka1964(id:105407), Mochi(id:9489), N yotarou(id:60870), 木林森(id:10796), Ribbon(id:172), Ash(id:15625), Shinya(id:7356), ばろむわん(id:262), Safkan(id:423), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>