<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>下立売通</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shimotachiuri-dori/Shimodachiuri-dori Street</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shimotachiuri-dori/Shimodachiuri-dori Street</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shimotachiuri-dori Street</e>
<cmt>タイトルのため、表記を一つにしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>下立売通（しもたちうりどおり、しもだちうりどおり）は京都市内の東西の通りの一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shimotachiuri-dori/Shimodachiuri-dori Street is one of the east and west street in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shimotachiuri-dori/Shimodachiuri-dori Street is a street running east-west through Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shimotachiuri-dori (also called Shimodachiuri-dori) Street is a street running east-west through Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>Shimotachiuri-dori/Shimodachiuri-dori→Shimtachiuri-dori (also called Shimodachiuri-dori)としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>東は京都御苑西縁の烏丸通から、西は右京区嵯峨瀬戸川町に至る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This street runs from Karasuma-dori Street at Nishi suberi of Kyoto Gyogoen (Kyoto Imperial Garden) at east to Saga Setogawacho, Ukyo-Ward at west.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the east, this street runs from Karasuma-dori Street at Nishi suberi of Kyoto Gyogoen (Kyoto Imperial Garden) to Saga Setogawacho, Ukyo-Ward in the west..</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the east, this street runs from Karasuma-dori Street at Nishi suberi of Kyoto Gyoen (Kyoto Imperial Garden) to Saga Setogawa-cho, Ukyo-Ward in the west..</e>
<cmt>Gyogoen→Gyoenに修正、余分なスペースを削除、ハイフンを入れSetogawa-choとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>一部は、平安京の勘解由小路（かでのこうじ）にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A part of street used to be Kadenokoji in Heiankyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A part of the street used to be Kadenokoji in Heiankyo.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A part of the street used to be Kadenokoji in Heiankyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>沿道には、釜座通との交差点に京都府庁、紙屋川東入に通称達磨寺（法輪寺 (京都市上京区)）、右京区花園に妙心寺、法金剛院などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the street, there is the Kyoto Prefectural Government at the crossing at Kamana-dori Street, (Horin-ji Temple (Kamigyo-Ward, Kyoto City)) that is known as Daruma-ji Temple at Kamiyagawa Higashi-iru, Myoshin-ji Temple and Hokongo-in Temple at Hanazono Ukyo-ku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kyoto Prefectural Government is located at the intersection with Kamana-dori Street, Daruma-ji Temple (Horin-ji Temple (Kamigyo-Ward, Kyoto City)) is located at Kamiyagawa Higashi-iru, while Myoshin-ji Temple and Hokongo-in Temple is located at Hanazono Ukyo-ku.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kyoto Prefectural Government is located at the intersection with Kamanza-dori Street, Daruma-ji Temple (Horin-ji Temple (Kamigyo Ward, Kyoto City)) is located at Kamiyagawa Higashi-iru, while Myoshin-ji Temple and Hokongo-in Temple is located at Hanazono, Ukyo Ward.</e>
<cmt>Kamana-dori→Kamanza-doriに修正、Kamigyo-Wardのハイフンを消去、「右京区花園」の表記を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>下ノ下立売通</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shimono-Shimotachiuri-dori Street</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shimono-Shimotachiuri-dori Street</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shimono-Shimotachiuri-dori Street</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>途中御前通を東端として、この通りの一本北に走る妙心寺道を上ノ下立売通（かみのしもたちうりどおり）、略称「かみのしもだち」とよぶことがあり、その対として並行する下立売通のこの区間を下ノ下立売通（しものしもたちうりどおり）、略称「しものしもだち」とよぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Onmae-dori street is as the edge of east on the way, Kamino-shimotachiuri-dori Street which is known as &apos;Kamino-Shimodachi&apos; that is one street north from Myoshinjimichi, and the section between Simono-Shimotauchi-dori Street which runs side by side with it is called as &apos;Shimono-Shimodachi&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taking a part of Onmae-dori street as the eastern edge, Myoshinjimichi is known as Kamino-shimotachiuri-dori Street or &apos;Kamino-Shimodachi&apos; for short, and the section between Simono-Shimotauchi-dori Street which runs side by side with it is called &apos;Shimono-Shimodachi&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taking a part of Onmae-dori street as the eastern edge, Myoshinjimichi road is known as Kamino-shimotachiuri-dori Street or &apos;Kamino-Shimodachi&apos; for short, and the section between Simono-Shimotauchi-dori Street which runs side by side with it is called &apos;Shimono-Shimodachi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Myoshinjimichi roadとし、ピリオドの位置を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>下ノ下立売通は、右京区花園で丸太町通に合流する地点を西端とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The spot which connects to Marutamachi-dori street at Hanazono, Ukyo-Ward is the of edge of west on Simono-Shimotachiuri-dori Street.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The spot which connects Marutamachi-dori street at Hanazono, Ukyo-Ward forms the western edge of Shimono-Shimotachiuri-dori Street.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The spot which connects Marutamachi-dori street at Hanazono, Ukyo Ward forms the western edge of Shimono-Shimotachiuri-dori Street.</e>
<cmt>Ukyo-Wardのハイフン消去</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>上ノ下立売通</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kamino-Shimotachiuri-dori street</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kamino-Shimotachiuri-dori street</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kamino-Shimotachiuri-dori street</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>一方、上ノ下立売通は、妙心寺正門前を通って法金剛院西側を南下、丸太町通と交差する地点までいったん進む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, Kamino-Shimotachiuri-dori Stret runs to the spot which connects with Marutamachi-dori Street where runs through in front of the main gate of Myoshin-ji Temple, and goes to south at the west side of Hokongo-in Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, Kamino-Shimotachiuri-dori Stret runs to a spot which connects Marutamachi-dori Street that runs in front of the main gate of Myoshin-ji Temple, and heads south on the west side of Hokongo-in Temple.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, Kamino-Shimotachiuri-dori Street runs to a spot which connects Marutamachi-dori Street that runs in front of the main gate of Myoshin-ji Temple, and heads south on the west side of Hokongo-in Temple.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペースを削除、Streetのスペルミスを修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>一旦ここで途切れ、新たに花園駅 (京都府)前から山陰本線南を沿うように作られた新道を進んで、天神川通の花園黒橋陸橋をくぐり、常盤方面へ抜けて右京区嵯峨瀬戸川町まで続いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It stopped here at once, and it runs again on the new road which is established along the south of Sanin Honsen Line from in front of the Hanazono Station (Kyoto Prefecture), and goes through under the Hanazono Kurobashi (Hanazono Kuro Bridge) on Tenjingawa-dori Street and continues to Saga Setogawacho, Ukyo-Ward though Tokiwa direction.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is then interrupted, but once continues on a newroad established along the south of the Sanin Honsen Line in front of the Hanazono Station (Kyoto Prefecture), and goes through the Hanazono Kurobashi (Hanazono Kuro Bridge) on Tenjingawa-dori Street and continues to Saga Setogawacho, Ukyo-Ward headed towards Tokiwa.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is then interrupted, but once continues on a new road established along the south of the Sanin Main Line in front of the Hanazono Station (Kyoto Prefecture), and goes through the Hanazono Kuro-bashi Bridge on Tenjingawa-dori Street and continues to Saga Setogawa-cho, Ukyo Ward headed towards Tokiwa.</e>
<cmt>スペースを追加、 住所表記を修正、 Hanazono Kuro-bashi Bridge, Sanin Main Lineとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="11">
<j>この丸太町通との交差点での上ノ下立売通の途切れは、山陰本線の二条駅〜花園駅 (京都府)間複線高架化に伴い、それまで交差点を直進して踏切となっていた道路部分が盛土のために廃止されたことで、生じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The stop at Kamino-Shimotachiuri-dori Street at the crossing with Marutamachi-dori Street occurred with building a elevated railroad between Nijo Station and Hanazono Station of Sanin Honsen Line, which is from a part of the road that was abolished for the fill of the railway crossing which used to run straight at the crossing point.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The interruption at Kamino-Shimotachiuri-dori Street located at the intersection with Marutamachi-dori Street occurred together with the construction of an elevated railroad between Nijo Station and Hanazono Station of the Sanin Honsen Line, whereby a part of the road which used to run straight through the intersection was eliminated and replaced with a railway crossing.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The interruption at Kamino-Shimotachiuri-dori Street located at the intersection with Marutamachi-dori Street occurred together with the construction of an elevated railroad between Nijo Station and Hanazono Station of the Sanin Main Line, whereby a part of the road which used to run straight through the intersection was eliminated and replaced with a railway crossing.</e>
<cmt>Sanin Main Lineとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="12">
<j>かつて丸太町通が西大路通との交差点である西ノ京円町を西端としていた当時、この通りは右京区へ伸びる生活上重要な道路として活用されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Nishinokyo Enmachi which is the crossing point with Nishioji-dori Street was used to be the edge of east on Marutamachi-dori Street, this street was used as an important road for living which continues to Sakyo-Ward.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Nishinokyo Enmachi, the intersection with Nishioji-dori Street, used to be the western edge for Marutamachi-dori Street, acted as an important road for facilitiating daily life in Sakyo-Ward.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Nishinokyo Enmachi, the intersection with Nishioji-dori Street, used to be the western edge for Marutamachi-dori Street, Kamino-Shimotachiuri-dori Street acted as an important road for facilitiating daily life that continued to Ukyo Ward.</e>
<cmt>Sakyo-Ward→Ukyo Wardに修正、原文の内容に沿わない箇所を一部訳し直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>しかし、ほぼ全区間、自動車同士のすれ違いに苦労するほど道幅が狭かったため、特に路線バスなどが通過する際に渋滞が発生することも多発。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But, it was very difficult even when bicycles passed each other, and especially when bus had to pass through the traffic jam was occurred, because almost all of road had narrow width.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the street was extremely narrow in all sections, making it difficult for vehicles to pass each other, and traffic jams occuring when buses passed through.</e>
<cmt>Robert: This translator mistranslated &quot;自動車&quot; as &quot;bicycle&quot;/Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the street was extremely narrow in all sections, making it difficult for vehicles to pass each other, and traffic jams occuring when buses passed through.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>この状況の解消は丸太町通の西延まで待たなければならなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To clear this situation was waiting to Nishionbe on Marutamachi-dori Street.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The traffic jams would extend to Nishionbe on Marutamachi-dori Street.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The traffic jams were not cleard until the Marutamachi-dori Street was extended to the west.</e>
<cmt>文脈より「西延」→&quot;Nishinobe&quot;という地名ではなく「西への延長」と解釈し、訳文が原文の内容に沿うよう全体を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>沿道の主な施設</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Main facilities on the street</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Main roadside facilities</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Main Roadside Facilities</e>
<cmt>頭文字を大文字に変更</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="15">
<j>京都御苑</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Gyoen(Kyoto Imperial Garden)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Gyoen(Kyoto Imperial Garden)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Gyoen (Kyoto Imperial Garden)</e>
<cmt>カッコの前のスペースを追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="16">
<j>平安女学院中学校・高等学校</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Heian Jogakuin St. Agnes&apos; Junior High School/High School</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Heian Jogakuin St. Agnes&apos; Junior High School/High School</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Heian Jogakuin St. Agnes&apos; Junior High School/High School</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="17">
<j>京都府警察</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Prefectural Police Department</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Prefectural Police Department</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Prefectural Police Department</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="18">
<j>京都府庁</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Prefectural Government</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Prefectural Government</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Prefectural Government</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="19">
<j>法輪寺 (京都市上京区)（だるま寺）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Horin-ji Temple (Kamigyo-Ward, Kyoto City) (Daruma-ji Temple)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Horin-ji Temple (Kamigyo-Ward, Kyoto City) (Daruma-ji Temple)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Horin-ji Temple (Kamigyo-Ward, Kyoto City) (Daruma-dera Temple)</e>
<cmt>だるま寺→Daruma-dera Templeに修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="20">
<j>京都上労働基準監督署</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Labor Standards Inspection Office</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Labor Standards Inspection Office</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Labor Standards Inspection Office</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="21">
<j>花園中学校・高等学校</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hanazono Junior and Senior High School</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hanazono Junior and Senior High School</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hanazono Junior and Senior High School</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="22">
<j>妙心寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Myoshin-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Myoshin-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Myoshin-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="23">
<j>法金剛院</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hokongo-in Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hokongo-in Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hokongo-in Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="24">
<j>花園駅 (京都府)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hanazono Station (Kyoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hanazono Station (Kyoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hanazono Station (Kyoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="25">
<j>京都府立嵯峨野高等学校</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Prefecture Sagano High School</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Prefecture Sagano High School</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Prefecture Sagano High School</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="26">
<j>嵯峨嵐山駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saga-Arashiyama Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saga-Arashiyama Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saga-Arashiyama Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Miyuki h(id:84952), Imefw(id:121222), Ktr(id:30468), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>