<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>京街道 (大坂街道)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyo-kaido Road</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyo-kaido Road</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyo-kaido Road</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>京街道（きょうかいどう）または大坂街道（おおさかかいどう）とは、大坂（大阪）の京橋（後に高麗橋）から淀川左岸に沿って進み、淀を経て京（京都）に向かう街道である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyo-kaido Road, or Osaka-kaido Road, is a street that starts from Kyobashi (later Kyobashi) of Osaka, runs along the left bank of the Yodo-gawa River, and leads to Kyo (Kyoto) via Yodo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyo-kaido Road, or Osaka-kaido Road, is a street that starts from Kyobashi (later Kyobashi) of Osaka, runs along the left bank of the Yodo-gawa River and leads to Kyo (Kyoto) via Yodo.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyo-kaido Road, or Osaka-kaido Road, is a street that starts from Kyobashi (later moving to Koraibashi) of Osaka, runs along the left bank of the Yodo-gawa River and leads to Kyo (Kyoto) via Yodo.</e>
<cmt>Koraibashiとしました。 Later moved to を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>文禄3年（1594年）に伏見城築造に着手した豊臣秀吉が、文禄5年（1596年）2月に毛利一族に命じて淀川左岸に築かせた「文禄堤」が起源である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It originates from Bunrokutei Bank, which Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI made Mori Family build at the left bank of the Yodo-gawa River in1596 as a part of building Fushimi Castle he started in 1594.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It originates from Bunrokutei Bank, which Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI had the Mori Family build at the left bank of the Yodo-gawa River in 1596 as a part of building Fushimi Castle, which he had started in 1594.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It originates from Bunrokutei Bank, which Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI had the Mori ｆamily build at the left bank of the Yodo-gawa River in February 1596 as a part of the Fushimi Castle construction, which he had started in 1594.</e>
<cmt>Mori ｆamilyとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>淀から京都の間は大きく2つのルートが取られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The road has taken 2 major different routes between Yodo and Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The road has taken two significantly different routes between Yodo and Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The road has taken two significantly different routes between Yodo and Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>1つは桂川左岸を進む鳥羽街道であり、もう1つは現在の宇治川右岸の淀堤を経て伏見に至り、伏見から伏見街道あるいは竹田街道を経て京都中心部に達する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One is the Toba-kaido Road; the other runs along the right bank of Uji-gawa River, Yodo-tsutsumi bank, to Fushimi and then to the heart of Kyoto via either the Fushimi-kaido Road or Takeda-kaido Road.</e>
<cmt>http://www.nichibun.ac.jp/meisyozue/kyoto/50/yo.htmlhttp://dic.yahoo.co.jp/dsearch?enc=UTF-8&amp;p=伏見&amp;dtype=0&amp;dname=0na&amp;stype=0&amp;pagenum=1&amp;index=18699416074000http://web.kyoto-inet.or.jp/people/kurituka/torina.htm</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One is the Toba-kaido Road, and the other runs along the right bank of Uji-gawa River, Yodo-tsutsumi bank, to Fushimi and then to the heart of Kyoto via either the Fushimi-kaido Road or Takeda-kaido Road.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One is the Toba-kaido Road which runs along the left bank of the Katsura-gawa River, and the other runs along the right bank of the present-day Uji-gawa River, Yodo-tsutsumi bank, to Fushimi and then to the heart of Kyoto via either the Fushimi-kaido Road or Takeda-kaido Road.</e>
<cmt>桂川左岸、present-dayを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>伏見から大阪までの道のりは、五街道の一つである東海道の延長として道中奉行の管轄下に置かれ、伏見宿 (京街道)、淀宿、枚方宿、守口宿の4宿場が設けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The section between Fushimi and Osaka was under control of Dochu-bugyo (magistrate of major roads) as the extension of one of the Go-kaido Roads, and 4 stages were established along it; Fushimi-shuku, Yodo-shuku, Hirakata-shuku, and Moriguchi-shuku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The section between Fushimi and Osaka was under the control of Dochu-bugyo (magistrate of major roads) as the extension of one of the Go-kaido roads, and four stages were established along it: Fushimi-shuku, Yodo-shuku, Hirakata-shuku and Moriguchi-shuku.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The section between Fushimi and Osaka was under the control of Dochu-bugyo (magistrate of major roads) as the extension of one of the Go-kaido roads (major five roads that started from Edo (now Tokyo)), and four stages were established along it: Fushimi-shuku (along the Kyo-kaido Road), Yodo-shuku, Hirakata-shuku and Moriguchi-shuku.</e>
<cmt>五街道の説明を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>東海道の大津宿から髭茶屋追分で京都・三条大橋へ向かう道と分かれ、京都を通らず大津街道を通りこれら4宿場を経て大坂に至る道のりは、参勤交代の経路としても用いられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Sankin-kotai (daimyo&apos;s alternate-year residence in Edo), some took this route without passing through Kyoto; at Higechaya-oiwake (Higashichaya bisection) after Otsu-shuku of the Tokaido, they separated away from the route toward Sanjo-ohashi of Kyoto and travelled along Otsu-kaido Road to Osaka via these 4 stages.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Sankin-kotai (daimyo&apos;s alternate-year residence in Edo), some took this route without passing through Kyoto; at Higechaya-oiwake (Higashichaya bisection) after Otsu-shuku of the Tokaido, they separated from the route toward Sanjo-ohashi of Kyoto and traveled along Otsu-kaido Road to Osaka via these four stages.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Sankin-kotai (daimyo&apos;s (feudal lord) alternate-year residence in Edo), some took this route without passing through Kyoto; at Higechaya-oiwake (Higechaya bisection) after leaving Otsu-shuku of the Tokaido, they separated from the route toward Sanjo-ohashi of Kyoto and traveled along Otsu-kaido Road to Osaka via these four stages.</e>
<cmt>leaving を追加しました。Higashichaya→Higechaya bisection</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>東海道五十三次東海道五十七次と呼ぶこともある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some call the route Tokaido Gojusan Tsugi (fifty-three stages in Tokaido Road) Tokaido Gojunana Tsugi (fifty-seven stages in Tokaido Road).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some call the route Tokaido Gojusan Tsugi (53 stages of the Tokaido Road) or Tokaido Gojunana Tsugi (57 stages of the Tokaido Road).</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some call the route Tokaido Gojusan Tsugi (53 stages of the Tokaido Road) or Tokaido Gojunana Tsugi (57 stages of the Tokaido Road).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>また、淀宿と枚方宿の間に橋本という遊郭を持った間の宿が設けられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is also an unofficial stage named Hashimoto between Yodo-shuku and Hirakata-shuku, which had a prostitution quarter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is also an unofficial stage called Hashimoto between Yodo-shuku and Hirakata-shuku, which once had a prostitution quarter.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is also an unofficial stage called Hashimoto between Yodo-shuku and Hirakata-shuku, which once had a prostitution quarter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>伏見・大坂間は淀川を利用した舟運が盛んであり、陸路の利用は大坂からの上り客が多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">River traffic on the Yodo-gawa River was busy from Fushimi to Osaka, while land traffic is busy from Osaka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">River traffic on the Yodo-gawa River was busy from Fushimi to Osaka, while land traffic was busy from Osaka.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">River traffic on the Yodo-gawa River was busy from Fushimi to Osaka, while land traffic was busy from Osaka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="10">
<j>明治時代に入ると、鳥羽街道を経るルートが大阪街道とされ、京都・大阪間の国道（旧京阪国道）も伏見を通らないこちらのルートが選択された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Meiji era, the route via Toba-kaido Road began to be recognized as Osaka-kaido Road, and a national highway between Kyoto and Osaka (Old Keihan-kokudo national road) chosen this route rather than the route via Fushimi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Meiji era the route via Toba-kaido Road began to be recognized as Osaka-kaido Road, and this route was chosen as a national highway between Kyoto and Osaka (Old Keihan-kokudo National Road) instead of the route via Fushimi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Meiji period the route via Toba-kaido Road began to be recognized as Osaka-kaido Road, and this route was chosen as a national route between Kyoto and Osaka (Old Keihan-kokudo National Road) instead of the route via Fushimi.</e>
<cmt>national routeとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="11">
<j>伏見を含む4つの宿場に沿っては、京阪電気鉄道京阪本線が通っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keihan Electric Railway runs following thses 4 stages including Fushimi.</e>
<cmt>京阪電鉄HP (http://www.keihan.co.jp/)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Keihan Electric Railway follows these four stages, including Fushimi.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Keihan Electric Railway follows these four stages, including Fushimi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Rusk(id:9895), Hideyuki(id:9577), Washisama(id:9333), Nnh(id:474), Blueroses5327(id:97718), Buckstars(id:8767), Aoiya(id:44787), ブレービー(id:108476), うら(id:40695), ぽえこ(id:88711), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>