<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>竹田街道</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takeda-kaido Road</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takeda-kaido Road</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takeda-kaido Road</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>竹田街道（たけだかいどう）は、京（京都市中心部）と伏見（京都市伏見区）をつなぐ街道の一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Takeda-kaido Road is one of roads linking Kyo (the heart of Kyoto City) and Fushimi (the Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Takeda-kaido Road is one of the roads which links Kyo (the heart of Kyoto City) and Fushimi (the Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Takeda-kaido Road is one of the roads which links Kyo (the heart of Kyoto City) and Fushimi (the Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>京の七口の一つとしてあげられることもある竹田口から、旧紀伊郡竹田村（京都市伏見区竹田）を通り、伏見港へとつながっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It extended from the Takeda-guchi exit, which can be cited as one of the Seven Exits of Kyoto, to the Fushimi Port via former Takeda-mura, Kii-gun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It extended from the Takeda-guchi exit, which can be cited as one of the Seven Exits of Kyoto, to the Fushimi Port via the formerTakeda-mura, Kii-gun.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It extended from the Takeda-guchi exit, which can be cited as one of the Seven Exits of Kyoto, to the Fushimi Port via the former Takeda-mura, Kii-gun (present day Takeda, Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City).</e>
<cmt>(present day Takeda, Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City)補足スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>奈良街道や京街道の一部とも位置づけられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is regarded as a part of the Nara-kaido Road or the Kyo-kaido Road.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is regarded as a part of Nara-kaido Road or Kyo-kaido Road.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is regarded as a part of Nara-kaido Road or Kyo-kaido Road.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>現在でもなお京都市中心部と伏見市街を結ぶとともに、奈良市方面へとつながる国道24号の一部として主要な幹線道路となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today it still links the heart of Kyoto City with Fushimi City and serves as a main arterial highway as a part of the National Highway Route No. 24 leading to Nara City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today it still links the heart of Kyoto City with Fushimi City and serves as a primary highway and is part of the National Highway Route No. 24 leading to Nara City.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today it still links the heart of Kyoto City with Fushimi City and serves as a primary highway and is part of the National Highway Route No. 24 leading to Nara City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>沿革</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>竹田街道は、江戸時代に拓かれたと言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Takeda-kaido Road is said to have been built during the Edo era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Takeda-kaido Road is said to have been built during the Edo era.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Takeda-kaido Road is said to have been built during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>era→peirod</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>車石が敷かれ、牛車による物資の輸送が行われていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was covered with Kuruma-ishi Paving stones for transportation of goods by cow carriage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was paved with Kuruma-ishi stones, and goods were transported by carriages pulled by cattle.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was paved with Kuruma-ishi stones, and goods were transported by carriages pulled by cattle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>その車石の一部が陶化小学校に残されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some Kuruma-ishi Paving stones were left in Toka Elementary School.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some Kuruma-ishi stones were left in Toka Elementary School.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some Kuruma-ishi stones were left in Toka Elementary School.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>1895年に日本で初めての営業用の電気鉄道が、京都電気鉄道の手によってほぼ竹田街道に沿って京都駅から京橋京都市の間に敷設された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1895 Japan&apos;s first commercial electric railroad was built roughly along the Takeda-kaido Street by Kyoto Denki Tetsudo (Kyoto Electric Railway) between Kyoto Station and.Kyobashi, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1895 Japan&apos;s first commercial electric railroad was built roughly along Takeda-kaido Street by Kyoto Denki Tetsudo (Kyoto Electric Railway) between Kyoto Station and Kyobashi, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1895 Japan&apos;s first commercial electric railroad was built roughly along Takeda-kaido Road by Kyoto Denki Tetsudo (Kyoto Electric Railway) between Kyoto Station and Kyobashi, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>Street →Road</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>この路線は京都市電に引き継がれたが、1970年に市電全廃に先駆けて廃止された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The railroad was taken over by Kyoto-Shiden (Kyoto Municipal Steetcar), which was abolished in 1970 ahead of the total abolition of the city tram.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The railroad was taken over by Kyoto-Shiden (Kyoto Municipal Steetcar), which was stopped in 1970 before the city tram was completely abolished.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The railroad was taken over by Kyoto-Shiden (Kyoto Municipal Streetcar), which was stopped in 1970 before the city tram was completely abolished.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>翌1971年に竹田街道は国道24号に指定された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the following year 1970 the Takeda-kaido Road was designated as the National Highway Route No. 24.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1970, the following year, Takeda-kaido Road was designated as National Highway Route No. 24.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1971, the following year, Takeda-kaido Road was designated as National Highway Route No. 24.</e>
<cmt>数字修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>現在の道のり</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Current Route</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Current Route</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Current route</e>
<cmt>文頭のみ大文字に</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>現在は京都府道115号伏見港京都停車場線（竹田街道十条通より深草加賀屋敷町までは国道24号との重複）が竹田街道と呼ばれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today Fushimi-ko-Kyoto-Teishajo-sen, Kyoto Fudo 115 Go (Kyoto Prefectural Road 115) (with the section from Takeda-kaido Jujo-dori to Fukakusa-kagayashiki-cho overlapping with the National Highway Route No. 24) is called Takeda-kaido Road.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today Fushimi-ko-Kyoto-Teishajo-sen, Kyoto Fudo 115 Go (Kyoto Prefectural Road 115) (with the section from Takeda-kaido Jujo-dori to Fukakusa-kagayashiki-cho overlapping with the National Highway Route No. 24) is called Takeda-kaido Road.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today Fushimi-ko-Kyoto-Teishajo-sen, Kyoto Fudo 115 Go (Kyoto Prefectural Road 115) (with the section from Takeda-kaido Jujo-dori to Fukakusa-kagayashiki-cho overlapping with the National Highway Route No. 24) is called Takeda-kaido Road.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>同府道は、竹田街道八条通から伏見区の京都外環状線までを結んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kyoto Fudo 115 Go runs from the Takeda-kaido Hachijo-dori to the Kyoto-sotokanjo-sen Belt Line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kyoto Fudo 115 Go runs from Takeda-kaido Hachijo-dori to the Kyoto-sotokanjo-sen Belt Line.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kyoto Fudo 115 Go runs from Takeda-kaido Hachijo-dori to the Kyoto-sotokanjo-sen Belt Line in Fushimi Ward.</e>
<cmt>Fushimi Ward補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>東洞院通の延長上にあるが現在は京都駅で断絶しているため、京都駅の北側へは高倉陸橋（通称・たかばし）によって塩小路高倉で高倉通とつながっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though it runs on the extension line of the Higashi-no-Toin-dori Street, Kyoto Station interrupt it today halfway; Takakura Rikkyo overpass (nicknamed Takabashi) joins it with the Takakura-dori Street at Shiokoji-Takakura to allow it to go to the northern side of Kyoto Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though it runs on the extension line of Higashi-no-Toin-dori Street, today, Kyoto Station interrupts it halfway; Takakura Rikkyo overpass (nicknamed Takabashi) joins it with Takakura-dori Street at Shiokoji-Takakura, allowing it to connect with the northern side of Kyoto Station.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though it runs on the extension line of Higashinotoin-dori Street, today, Kyoto Station interrupts it halfway; Takakura Rikkyo overpass (nicknamed Takabashi) joins it with Takakura-dori Street at Shiokoji-Takakura, allowing it to connect with the northern side of Kyoto Station.</e>
<cmt>道の表記を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>約1キロメートル東の山沿いを伏見街道が並行している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Fushimi-kaido Road parallels about 1 km east of it along the foot of mountains.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fushimi-kaido Road runs parallel about 1 km east of the Road along the foot of mountains.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fushimi-kaido Road runs parallel about 1 km east of the Road along the foot of mountains.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>交差する道路など</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Crossing Roads</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cross Roads</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cross roads</e>
<cmt>文頭のみ大文字に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="16">
<j>交差する道路などの特記がないものは市町村道。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Roads unless specified are operated by local municipalities.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Roads unless specified are operated by local municipalities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Roads unless specified are operated by local municipalities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Aoiya(id:44787), うら(id:40695), Kagetudo(id:163875), Jade0416(id:104181), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>