<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>下鴨西通</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shimogamo-nishi-doori Street</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shimogamo-nishi-doori Street</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shimogamo Nishi-dori Street</e>
<cmt>Shimogamo-nishi-doori→Shimogamo Nishi-doriとしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>下鴨西通（しもがもにしどおり）は京都市左京区の南北の通りの一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shimogamo-nishi-doori street is one of the streets running from north to south in Sakyo Ward in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shimogamo-nishi-doori street is a street running north-south in Sakyo Ward in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shimogamo Nishi-dori Street is a street running north-south in Sakyo Ward in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>Shimogamo Nishi-dori Streetとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>鴨川 (淀川水系)の東岸を葵橋東詰の下鴨本通から北へ京都府立植物園正門まで。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shimogamo-nishi-doori street runs northward on the east bank of Kamo River (in Yodo river system) from the east end of Aoi-bashi bridge on Shimogamo-hondoori street to the front gate of Kyoto Prefectural Botanical Garden.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shimogamo-nishi-doori street runs northward on the east bank of Kamo River (in Yodo river system) from the east end of Aoi-bashi bridge on Shimogamo-hondoori street to the front gate of Kyoto Prefectural Botanical Garden.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shimogamo Nishi-dori Street runs northward on the east bank of the Kamo-gawa River (in Yodo-gawa River system) from the east end of Aoi-bashi Bridge on Shimogamo Hon-dori Street to the front gate of Kyoto Prefectural Botanical Garden.</e>
<cmt>Shimogamo Nishi-dori Street, Kamo-gawa River, Yodo-gawa River, Aoi-bashi Bridge, Shimogamo Hon-dori Streetとしました。&quot;Kamo-gawa River&quot;→&quot;the Kamo-gawa River&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>一筋東の下鴨中通の北大路通から御蔭通と異なり、対面通行可能である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Walking facing the traffic is allowed on Shimogamo-nishi-doori street being different from the section from a point on Kitaoji-doori street to a point on Mikage-doori street of Shimogamo-naka-doori street which is located by one street in the east of Shimogamo-nishi-doori street.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Walking towards incoming traffic is allowed on Shimogamo-nishi-doori street as opposed to the section from a point on Kitaoji-doori street to a point on Mikage-doori street of Shimogamo-naka-doori street which is located one street east of Shimogamo-nishi-doori street.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Walking towards incoming traffic is allowed on Shimogamo Nishi-dori Street as opposed to the section from a point on Kitaoji-dori Street to a point on Mikage-dori Street of Shimogamo Naka-dori Street which is located one street east of Shimogamo Nishi-dori Street.</e>
<cmt>○○通の表記をすべて&quot;-dori Street&quot;に修正、Shimogamo-nishi-doori→Shimogamo Nishi-dori、Shimogamo-naka-doori→Shimogamo Naka-doriとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>沿道は住宅街で、京都財界の著名人が居を構えたこともあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The area along Shimogamo-nishi-doori street is a residential area and some celebrities in the business and financial world of Kyoto used to live there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The area along Shimogamo-nishi-doori street is a residential area and some celebrities in the business and financial world of Kyoto used to live there.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The area along Shimogamo Nishi-dori Street is a residential area and some celebrities in the business and financial world of Kyoto used to live there.</e>
<cmt>Shimogamo Nishi-dori Streetとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>沿道の主な施設</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Main facilities along Shimogamo-nishi-doori street</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Main facilities along Shimogamo-nishi-doori street</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Main Facilities along Shimogamo Nishi-dorii Street</e>
<cmt>頭文字を大文字に変更、Shimogamo Nishi-dori Streetとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>京都家庭裁判所　葵橋東詰</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kyoto Family Court at east end of Aoi Bridge</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kyoto Family Court at the east end of Aoi Bridge</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kyoto Family Court at the east end of Aoi-bashi Bridge</e>
<cmt>Aoi-bashi Bridgeとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>京都市立下鴨小学校</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Municipal Shimogamo Elementary School</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Municipal Shimogamo Elementary School</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Municipal Shimogamo Elementary School</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>京都府立植物園</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Prefectural Botanical Garden</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Prefectural Botanical Garden</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Prefectural Botanical Garden</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Miyuki h(id:84952), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>