<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>師団街道</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shidan-kaido Road</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shidan-kaido Road</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shidan-kaido Road</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>師団街道（しだんかいどう）は、京都市の南北の通りの一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Shidan-kaido Road is a north-south running street in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Shidan-kaido Road is a street running north-south in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Shidan-kaido Road is a street running north-south in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>竹田街道の東に位置し、京阪電鉄京阪本線の西側を並行している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Located east of the Takeda-kaido Road, it parallels to the west of the Keihan Main Line of Keihan Electric Railway.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Located east of the Takeda-kaido Road, it parallels the west of the Keihan Main Line of Keihan Electric Railway.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Located east of the Takeda-kaido Road, it parallels the west of the Keihan Main Line of Keihan Electric Railway.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>北は塩小路橋東詰（塩小路通）で川端通につながり、南は国道24号を越えると伏見市街の京町通 (伏見)につながる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the north it is connected to the Kawabata-dori Street at Shiokojibashi-higashizume (the east foot of Shiokoji-bashi bridge), and in the south it crosses the National Highway Route No. 24 and is connected to the Kyomachi-dori Street (Fushimi) in downtown Fushimi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the north it is connected to Kawabata-dori Street at Shiokojibashi-higashizume (the east foot of Shiokoji-bashi bridge), and in the south it crosses National Highway Route No. 24 and is connected to Kyomachi-dori Street (Fushimi) in downtown Fushimi.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the north it is connected to Kawabata-dori Street at Shiokojibashi-higashizume (the east foot of Shiokoji-bashi Bridge), and in the south it crosses National Highway Route No. 24 and is connected to Kyomachi-dori Street (Fushimi) in downtown Fushimi.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>師団街道竜大前交差点から名神高速道路付近までは片側2車線の道路だが、大岩街道以南は南向きの一方通行となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The section from the Ryu-dai-mae crossing up to an area near the Meishin Expressway has 2 lanes in each direction, but the section north from the Oiwa-kaido Road is one way traffic heading south.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The section from the Ryu-dai-mae crossing up to an area near the Meishin Expressway has 2 lanes in each direction, but the section north from the Oiwa-kaido Road consists of one way traffic heading south.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The section from the Ryu-dai-mae crossing up to an area near the Meishin Expressway has 2 lanes in each direction, but the section south from the Oiwa-kaido Road consists of one way traffic heading south.</e>
<cmt>north→south</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="5">
<j>現在の伏見区深草の地にあった大日本帝国陸軍第16師団 (日本軍)に因む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It originates from Dai Juroku Shidan (16th division) of the Imperial Japanese Army (Japanese troops), which was located in Fukakusa, Fushimi Ward.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It originates from Dai Juroku Shidan (16th division) of the Imperial Japanese Army (Japanese troops), which was located in Fukakusa, Fushimi Ward.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It originates from Dai Juroku Shidan (16th division) of the Imperial Japanese Army (Japanese troops), which was located in Fukakusa, Fushimi Ward.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="6">
<j>墨染寺（上野岑雄が詠んだ墨色伝説の地。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bokusen-ji Temple (place of the Legend of Sumiiro (the legend that the color of the cherry blossoms turned into Sumiiro, light ink black, by KAMITSUKE no Mineo composing the poem))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bokusen-ji Temple (place of the Legend of Sumiiro (the legend that the color of the cherry blossoms turned into Sumiiro, light ink black, a poem composed by KAMITSUKE no Mineo))</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bokusen-ji Temple (place of the Legend of Sumiiro (the legend that the color of the cherry blossoms turned into Sumiiro, light ink black, a poem composed by KAMITSUKE no Mineo))</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>伏見区墨染町）に通じていることから、かつては墨染通（すみぞめどおり）と呼ばれたが、現在はあまり使われていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was once also called Sumizome-dori Street, because it leads to Sumizome-cho Fushimi Ward--the name is rarely used today.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was once also called Sumizome-dori Street, because it leads to Sumizome-cho Fushimi Ward--the name is rarely used today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was once also called Sumizome-dori Street, because it leads to Sumizome-cho Fushimi Ward--the name is rarely used today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>沿革</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>陸軍第16師団の設置に伴い、明治44年（1911年）に京都市街から師団司令部に至る国道として指定された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the establishment of Dai Juroku Shidan (16th division) of the Imperial Japanese Army, it was designated a national highway that connected downtown Kyoto and the Army&apos;s divisional headquarters.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the establishment of Dai Juroku Shidan (16th division) of the Imperial Japanese Army, it was designated a national highway that connected downtown Kyoto and the Army&apos;s divisional headquarters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the establishment of Dai Juroku Shidan (16th division) of the Imperial Japanese Army, it was designated a national highway that connected downtown Kyoto and the Army&apos;s divisional headquarters in 1911.</e>
<cmt>in 1911補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>終戦後に国道24号に指定されたが、昭和46年に国道24号は竹田街道に移った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After World war Two it was designated National Highway Route No. 24, though it was subsequently taken over by the Takeda-kaido. Road.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After World War Two it was designated National Highway Route No. 24, though it was subsequently taken over by Takeda-kaido Road.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After World War II it was designated National Highway Route No. 24, though it was subsequently taken over by Takeda-kaido Road in 1971.</e>
<cmt>Two→IIin 1971補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>第一軍道、第二軍道、第三軍道</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daiichi Gundo (first military road), Daini Gundo (second military road), Daisan Gundo (third military road)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daiichi Gundo (first military road), Daini Gundo (second military road), Daisan Gundo (third military road)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daiichi Gundo (first military road), Daini Gundo (second military road), Daisan Gundo (third military road)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>陸軍第16師団の設置に伴い、直違橋通（本町通 (京都)）沿いにも師団司令部などの軍の施設が位置することになり、師団街道と直違橋通を結ぶために琵琶湖疏水（鴨川運河）と京阪電車を橋によって越える3つの東西の道路が陸軍によって敷設された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the establishment of Dai Juroku Shidan (16th division) of the Imperial Japanese Army, military facilities were established along the Sujikaibashi-dori Street and as the result three east-west roads were built by the Army to connect the Shidan-kaido Road and the Sujikaibashi-dori Street through bridges over the Biwako Sosui (channel) (Kamo-gawa Canal) and the Keihan Electric Railway,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the establishment of Dai Juroku Shidan (16th division) of the Imperial Japanese Army, military facilities were established along Sujikaibashi-dori Street and as a result three east-west roads were built by the Army to connect Shidan-kaido Road and Sujikaibashi-dori Street through bridges over the Biwako Sosui (channel) (Kamo-gawa Canal) and the Keihan Electric Railway,</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the establishment of Dai Juroku Shidan (16th division) of the Imperial Japanese Army, military facilities were established along Sujikaibashi-dori Street (Honmachi-dori Street) and as a result three east-west roads were built by the Army to connect Shidan-kaido Road and Sujikaibashi-dori Street through bridges over the Biwako Sosui (channel) (Kamo-gawa Canal) and the Keihan Electric Railway,</e>
<cmt>(Honmachi-dori Street)補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>北からそれぞれ、第一軍道、第二軍道、第三軍道と呼ばれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The roads were individually called from the north Daiichi Gundo, Daini Gundo, and Daisan Gundo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the north, the roads were individually called Daiichi Gundo, Daini Gundo, and Daisan Gundo.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the north, the roads were individually called Daiichi Gundo, Daini Gundo, and Daisan Gundo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="12">
<j>軍道の開設は1909年、師団司令部設置（1908年）の翌年とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Gundo is said to open in 1909, a year after the divisional headquarters were established (in 1908).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Gundo is said to have been opened in 1909, a year after the divisional headquarters were established (in 1908).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Gundo is said to have been opened in 1909, a year after the divisional headquarters were established (in 1908).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>第一軍道</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daiichi Gundo (first military road)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daiichi Gundo (first military road)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daiichi Gundo (first military road)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="13">
<j>京都兵器支廠と京都練兵場の間を通る道路であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It extended between Kyoto Heiki-shisho (Kyoto branch of the Heikisho, organization of former Japanese army) and Kyoto Drill Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It extended between Kyoto Heiki-shisho (Kyoto branch of the Heikisho, organization of former Japanese army) and Kyoto Drill Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It extended between Kyoto Heiki-shisho (Kyoto branch of the Heikisho, organization of former Japanese army) and Kyoto Drill Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="14">
<j>砂川橋と西砂川橋で疏水と京阪電車をまたぎ、直違橋通（深草直違橋九丁目）と師団街道（師団街道竜大前交差点）とをつないでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It crosses the Sosui (channel) and the Keihan Electric Railway by the Sunagawa-bashi bridge and the Nishi-sunagawa-bashi bridge to connect the Sujikaibashi-dori Street (9 Chome, Fukakusa-Sujikaibashi) and the Shidan-kaido Road (Shidan-kaido Road Ryu-dai-mae crossing).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It crosses the Sosui (channel) and the Keihan Electric Railway by the Sunagawa-bashi bridge and the Nishi-sunagawa-bashi bridge to connect Sujikaibashi-dori Street (9 Chome, Fukakusa-Sujikaibashi) and Shidan-kaido Road (Shidan-kaido Road Ryu-dai-mae crossing).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It crosses the Sosui (channel) and the Keihan Electric Railway by the Sunagawa-bashi bridge and the Nishi-sunagawa-bashi bridge to connect Sujikaibashi-dori Street (9 Chome, Fukakusa-Sujikaibashi) and Shidan-kaido Road (Shidan-kaido Road Ryu-dai-mae crossing).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>現在は府道（京都府道201号中山稲荷線）の一部となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today it belongs to a prefectural road (Nakayama-Inari-sen, Kyoto Fudo 201 Go (Kyoto Prefectural Road 201)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today it belongs to a prefectural road (Nakayama-Inari-sen, Kyoto Fudo 201 Go (Kyoto Prefectural Road 201)).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today it belongs to a prefectural road (Nakayama-Inari-sen, Kyoto Fudo 201 Go (Kyoto Prefectural Road 201)).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>第二軍道</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daini Gundo (second military road)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daini Gundo (second military road)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daini Gundo (second military road)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="16">
<j>京都練兵場の正門に面する道路であり、師団司令部（現在の聖母学院本館の位置）につながる道として特に重要視された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The road, among others, was regarded important, because it ran in front of Kyoto Drill Court and led to the divisional headquarters (present-day Honkan (main building of Kyoto/Fujimori Campus), Seibo Gakuin School.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The road, among others, was regarded important, because it ran in front of Kyoto Drill Court and led to divisional headquarters (present-day Honkan (main building of Kyoto/Fujimori Campus), Seibo Gakuin School.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The road, among others, was regarded important, because it ran in front of Kyoto Drill Court and led to divisional headquarters (present-day Honkan (main building) of Kyoto/Fujimori Campus), Seibo Gakuin School.</e>
<cmt>)補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="17">
<j>師団橋と西師団橋で疏水と京阪電車をまたぎ、直違橋通（深草直違橋六丁目）と師団街道（深草野田町）とをつないでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It crosses the Sosui (channel) and the Keihan Electric Railway by the Shidan-bashi bridge and the Nishi-Shidan-bashi bridge to connect the Sujikaibashi-dori Street (6 Chome, Fukakusa-Sujikaibashi) and the Shidan-kaido Road (Fukakusa-Noda-cho).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It crosses the Sosui (channel) and the Keihan Electric Railway by Shidan-bashi bridge and Nishi-Shidan-bashi bridge to connect Sujikaibashi-dori Street (6 Chome, Fukakusa-Sujikaibashi) and Shidan-kaido Road (Fukakusa-Noda-cho).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It crosses the Sosui (channel) and the Keihan Electric Railway by Shidan-bashi Bridge and Nishi-Shidan-bashi Bridge to connect Sujikaibashi-dori Street (6 Chome, Fukakusa-Sujikaibashi) and Shidan-kaido Road (Fukakusa-Noda-cho).</e>
<cmt>スペース削除スペルを修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>疏水をまたぐ師団橋の橋桁には陸軍のシンボルであった五芒星が記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A Gobosei (pentacle) mark-a symbol of Army--remains on a girder of the Shidan-bashi bridge over the the Sosui (channel).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A Gobosei (pentacle) mark-a symbol of the Army--remains on a girder of the Shidan-bashi bridge over the the Sosui (channel).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A Gobosei (pentacle) mark-a symbol of the Army--remains on a girder of the Shidan-bashi Bridge over the Sosui (channel).</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正the削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>第三軍道</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daisan Gundo (third military road)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daisan Gundo (third military road)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daisan Gundo (third military road)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="19">
<j>野砲兵隊の正門に面する道路であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It faced the front gate of Yaho-heitai (field gun crew).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It faced the front gate of Yaho-heitai (field gun crew).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It faced the front gate of Yaho-heitai (field gun crew).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="20">
<j>中之郷橋と西中之郷橋で疏水と京阪電車をまたぎ、直違橋通（直違橋一丁目交差点）と師団街道（深草飯食町交差点）とをつないでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It crosses the Sosui (channel) and the Keihan Electric Railway by the Nakanogo-hashi bridge and the Nishi Nakanogo-hashi bridge to connect the Sujikaibashi-dori Street (the Sujikai-bashi 1 Chome crossing) and the Shidan-kaido Road (the Fukakusa-Nishiijiki-cho crossing).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It crosses the Sosui (channel) and the Keihan Electric Railway by the Nakanogo-hashi bridge and the Nishi Nakanogo-hashi bridge to connect Sujikaibashi-dori Street (the Sujikai-bashi 1 Chome crossing) and Shidan-kaido Road (the Fukakusa-Nishiijiki-cho crossing).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It crosses the Sosui (channel) and the Keihan Electric Railway by the Nakanogo-hashi Bridge and the Nishi Nakanogo-hashi Bridge to connect Sujikaibashi-dori Street (the Sujikai-bashi 1 Chome crossing) and Shidan-kaido Road (the Fukakusa-Nishiijiki-cho crossing).</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>現在は大岩街道（滋賀県道・京都府道35号大津淀線）の一部となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today it belongs to the Oiwa-kaido Road (Otsu-Yodo-sen, Kyoto Fudo 35 Go (Kyoto Prefectural Road 35)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today it belongs to Oiwa-kaido Road (Otsu-Yodo-sen, Kyoto Fudo 35 Go (Kyoto Prefectural Road 35)).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today it belongs to Oiwa-kaido Road (Shiga Prefectural road and Otsu-Yodo-sen, Kyoto Fudo 35 Go (Kyoto Prefectural Road 35)).</e>
<cmt>Shiga Prefectural road補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>沿道の主な施設</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Facilities along the Street</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Facilities along the Street</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Facilities along the Street</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="22">
<j>龍谷大学深草キャンパス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fukakusa Campus, Ryukoku University</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fukakusa Campus, Ryukoku University</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fukakusa Campus, Ryukoku University</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="23">
<j>京都府警察</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Police</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Police</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Police</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Aoiya(id:44787), Hideyuki(id:9577), はらぐろ(id:82902), うら(id:40695), Ogeshi(id:80487), 代言人(id:33675), Amagiri(id:101077), Felicemente(id:43126), Ritsuka(id:6464), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>