<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>一条通</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ichijo-dori Street</e>
<cmt>http://dic.yahoo.co.jp/dsearch?enc=UTF-8&amp;p=いちじょうどおり&amp;stype=0&amp;dtype=0</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ichijo-dori Street</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ichijo-dori Street</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>一条通（いちじょうどおり）は京都市の主要な東西の通りの一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ichijo-dori Street is one of the major east-west running streets in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ichijo-dori Street is one of the major east-west running streets in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ichijo-dori Street is one of the major east-west streets in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>表現を統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>平安京の一条大路にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It corresponds to the Ichijo-oji Street of Heiankyo.</e>
<cmt>http://www.mutsunohana.net/miyako/oji-koji/ichijo-oji.htm</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It corresponds to the Ichijo-oji Street of Heiankyo.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It corresponds to Ichijo-oji Street of Heian-kyo.</e>
<cmt>Heian-kyoとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>東端は烏丸通。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its east end is the Karasuma-dori Street.</e>
<cmt>http://kaiwai.city.kyoto.jp/search/view_sight.php?ManageCode=3000025&amp;InforKindCode=1&amp;whole=true</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its eastern end is Karasuma-dori Street.</e>
<cmt>east end→eastern end</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its eastern end is Karasuma-dori Street.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>西は右京区花園付近までだが、さらに西に延長して嵯峨野の清凉寺（嵯峨釈迦堂）までを一条通と呼ぶこともある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the west, it ends around Hanazono, Ukyo Ward, but some refer to the street extended west to Seiryo-ji Temple Saga-Shakado in Sagano as the Ichijo Street.</e>
<cmt>http://www.excite.co.jp/map/address/26/108/?start=900http://kaiwai.city.kyoto.jp/search/view_sight.php?ManageCode=1000139&amp;InforKindCode=1&amp;whole=truehttp://kaiwai.city.kyoto.jp/search/view_sight.php?ManageCode=9000353&amp;InforKindCode=4&amp;whole=true</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the west, it ends around Hanazono, Ukyo ward, but some refer to the street that extends west to Seiryo-ji Temple Saga-Shakado in Sagano as Ichijo Street.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the west, it ends around Hanazono in Ukyo Ward, but some refer to the street, which extends west to Seiryo-ji Temple (Saga-Shakado) in Sagano, as Ichijo-dori Street.</e>
<cmt>括弧追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>また宇多野で分岐して周山街道にも通じている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It also branches at Utano and leads to the Shuzan-kaido Road.</e>
<cmt>http://kaiwai.city.kyoto.jp/search/view_sight.php?InforKindCode=4&amp;ManageCode=6000010http://web.kyoto-inet.or.jp/people/kurituka/torina.htm</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It also branches at Utano and leads to Shuzan-kaido Road.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It also branches at Utano and leads to Shuzan-kaido Road.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>平安京の北端の通りであったが、平安時代中期以降は一条大路を越えて北へ市街地が拡大した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though the the Ichijo-oji Street formed the northern edge of Heiankyo, the downtown area expanded across it after the middle of Heian era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though the Ichijo-oji Street formed the northern edge of Heiankyo, the downtown area expanded across it after the middle of Heian era.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though Ichijo-oji Street formed the northern edge of Heian-kyo, the downtown area expanded across it northward after the mid-Heian period.</e>
<cmt>Heian-kyo, period　に修正 northward追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>京都御所の北端の大路という位置付けは現在、その北側を走る今出川通が果たしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Imadegawa-dori Street, which runs along the north side of the Ichi-dori Street, now acts as the north edge of Kyoto Gosho (Old Imperial Palace).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imadegawa-dori Street, which runs along the north side of Ichi-dori Street, now acts as the northern boundary of Kyoto Gosho (Old Imperial Palace).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imadegawa-dori Street now acts as the northern boundary of Kyoto Gosho (Old Imperial Palace), which runs along its north side.</e>
<cmt>原文どおりに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>現在は市中心部では一方通行の狭い通りである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Now, the Ichijo-dori Street in the central Kyoto City is a narrow one-way.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ichijo-dori Street, in central Kyoto City, is a narrow one-way road.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ichijo-dori Street, in central Kyoto City, is a narrow one-way road.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>堀川 (京都府)にかかる一条戻橋が有名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ichijomodori-bashi Bridge over Horikawa is well known.</e>
<cmt>http://web.kyoto-inet.or.jp/people/kurituka/torina.htm</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ichijomodori-bashi Bridge over Horikawa is well known.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ichijomodori-bashi Bridge, which spans the Hori-kawa River (Kyoto Prefecture), is well known.</e>
<cmt>(Kyoto Prefecture) 追加 Hori-kawa Riverとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>東一条通</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Higashi-Ichijo-dori Street</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Higashi-Ichijo-dori Street</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Higashi-Ichijo-dori Street</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>東一条通（ひがしいちじょうどおり）は鴨川 (淀川水系)を挟んで一条通の延長線上にあり、西は川端通から東は吉田神社鳥居前まで。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Higashi-Ichijo-dori Street, which forms a extended line of the ichijo-dori Street across the Kamo-gawa River (Yodo-gawa water system), runs from the Kawabata-dori Street in the west to Yoshida-jinja Shrine Torimae in the east.</e>
<cmt>http://web.kyoto-inet.or.jp/people/kurituka/torina.htm</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Higashi-Ichijo-dori Street, which forms an extended line of Ichijo-dori Street across the Kamo-gawa River (Yodo-gawa Water System), runs from Kawabata-dori Street in the west to Yoshida-jinja Shrine Torimae in the east.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Higashi-Ichijo-dori Street, which forms an extended line of Ichijo-dori Street across the Kamo-gawa River (Yodo-gawa River system), runs from Kawabata-dori Street in the west to the gate (Torii) of Yoshida-jinja Shrine in the east.</e>
<cmt>Yodo-gawa River system,　gate (Torii) of the Yoshida-jinja Shrine　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>東大路通から東は吉田神社の参道であり、節分祭の折りになると露店でにぎわう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The east of the Higashioji Street is the approach to Yoshida-jinja Shrine, along which there are many street stalls with a lively atmosphere during the Setsubun Festival, the bean-throwing festival of celebrating the coming of spring.</e>
<cmt>http://kaiwai.city.kyoto.jp/search/view_sight.php?ManageCode=1000230&amp;InforKindCode=1&amp;whole=true英辞郎 on the WEB</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The east of Higashioji Street is the approach to Yoshida-jinja Shrine, along which there are many street stalls with a lively atmosphere during the Setsubun Festival, the bean-throwing festival to celebrate the coming of spring.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The east of Higashi-ichijo Street is the approach to Yoshida-jinja Shrine, along which there are many street stalls with a lively atmosphere during the Setsubun Festival, the bean-throwing festival to celebrate the coming of spring.</e>
<cmt>東大路通から ではなく、　東一条通り　ではないかと解釈し、修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>またこの区間の両側は京都大学のキャンパスであり、正門も東一条通に面している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The both sides of this section is the campus of Kyoto University, whose main gate also faces the Higashi-Ichijo-dori Street.</e>
<cmt>http://www.kyoto-u.ac.jp/ja</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Both sides of this section comprise the campus of Kyoto University, whose main gate also faces Higashi-Ichijo-dori Street.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Both sides of this section comprise the campus of Kyoto University, whose main gate also faces Higashi-Ichijo-dori Street.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>4月の入学シーズンには京都大学の課外活動へ勧誘する立て看板が林立する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In every April when new students enter the university, many sign boards are erected for recurring students to extracurricular activities.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Each April, when new students enter the university, many signboards are erected to remind returning students of extracurricular activities.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Each April, when new students enter the university, many signboards are erected to remind returning students of extracurricular activities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="15">
<j>交差する道路</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Crossing Roads</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Crossing roads</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Crossing roads</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="16">
<j>ここでは、市中心部の一方通行の狭い通りについては記述しない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Roads unless specified are operated by local municipalities.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Roads are operated by local municipalities unless otherwise specified.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The narrow, one-way roads running in the center of the city aren&apos;t mentioned here.</e>
<cmt>訳修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="17">
<j>上側が東側、下側が西側。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">East is upper and west is lower.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">East is upper, and west is lower.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">East is upper, and west is lower.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>左側が北側、右側が南側。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">North is left and south is right.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">North is to the left, and south is to the right.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">North is to the left, and south is to the right.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Lupinoid(id:68), Hideyuki(id:9577), Matsukaze(id:51778), Ktr(id:30468), ちょろ(id:17218), A-keita(id:10120), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>