<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>五条通</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gojo-dori Street</e>
<cmt>http://kaiwai.city.kyoto.jp/search/view_sight.php?ManageCode=3000043&amp;InforKindCode=1&amp;whole=true</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gojo-dori Street</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gojo-dori Street</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>五条通（ごじょうどおり）は京都市の主要な東西の通りの一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Gojo-dori Street is one of the major east-west running streets in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gojo-dori Street is one of the major east-west streets in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gojo-dori Street is one of the major east-west streets in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Overview</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Overview</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Overview</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>都市の中心部を東西に貫き、ほとんどの区間で一般国道に指定されている主要幹線である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The street, running east and west through the center of the city, is main arterial highway with most of the section designated as general national highways.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The street, which runs east and west through the center of the city, is the main arterial highway with most of the section designated as a general national highway.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The street, which runs east and west through the center of the city, is the main arterial highway with most of the section designated as a general national highway.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>国道の名称としては堀川五条以東は国道1号であり、烏丸五条以西は国道9号（烏丸五条-堀川五条は国道1号と重複）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The east of Horikawa Gojo is National Highway Route 1 and the west of Karasumaru Gojo is National Highway route No.9 (The section between.Karasuma Gojo and Horikawa Gojo is shared by National Highway Route No. 1.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The east of Horikawa Gojo is National Highway Route No. 1, and the west of Karasumaru Gojo is National Highway Route No. 9 (the section between.Karasuma Gojo and Horikawa Gojo is shared with National Highway Route No. 1).</e>
<cmt>grammar, case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The east of Horikawa Gojo is National Highway Route No. 1, and the west of Karasumaru Gojo is National Highway Route No. 9 (the section between Karasuma Gojo and Horikawa Gojo is shared with National Highway Route No. 1).</e>
<cmt>文中のピリオド削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>また国道8号（烏丸五条以東）、国道162号（天神川五条-西大路五条）の重複区間でもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also it is shared by the National Highway Route No. 8 (east of Karasuam Gojo) and National Highway Route No.162 (between Tenjin Gojo and Nishioji Gojo).</e>
<cmt>http://www.city.kyoto.jp/html/kotsu/busdia/hyperdia/ni.htm</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, it is shared by National Highway Route No. 8 (east of Karasuma Gojo) and National Highway Route No. 162 (between Tenjin Gojo and Nishioji Gojo).</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, it is shared by National Highway Route No. 8 (east of Karasuma Gojo) and National Highway Route No. 162 (between Tenjingawa Gojo and Nishioji Gojo).</e>
<cmt>Tenjin→Tenjingawa</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>通りの東は東大路通との交差点である五条坂交差点付近から五条坂と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the east, the street starting around Gojozaka Crossing with the Higashioji-dori Street is called Gojozaka.</e>
<cmt>http://www.city.kyoto.jp/html/kotsu/busdia/hyperdia/ko.htm一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the east, the street starting around Gojozaka Crossing with Higashioji-dori Street is called Gojozaka.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the east, the street starting around Gojozaka Crossing with Higashioji-dori Street is called Gojozaka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>五条坂交差点からは清水寺に向かう細い道となり、松原通（松原通の東端部）と合流する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The street from Gojozaka crossing is narrow toward Kiyomizudera Temple and merges with the Matsubara-dori Street (at the eastern end of the Matsubara-dori Street).</e>
<cmt>http://kaiwai.city.kyoto.jp/search/view_sight.php?ManageCode=1000047&amp;InforKindCode=1&amp;whole=truehttp://web.kyoto-inet.or.jp/people/kurituka/torina.htm一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The street from Gojozaka Crossing is narrow toward Kiyomizudera Temple and merges with Matsubara-dori Street (at the eastern end of Matsubara-dori Street).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The street from Gojozaka Crossing is narrow toward Kiyomizu-dera Temple but merges with Matsubara-dori Street (at the eastern end of Matsubara-dori Street).</e>
<cmt>ハイフン挿入し他の記事と統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>なお、国道1号は東大路通を立体交差で越えて五条バイパスとなり、渋谷通と合流して東山 (京都府)を越え山科盆地へ続く(この山科区における五条バイパスも含めて、ひろく五条通と呼ばれることもある)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">National Highway Route No. 1, after crossing over the Higashioji-dori Street, becomes the Gojo Bypass, merges with the Shibuya-dori Street, runs across Higashiyama (Kyoto Prefecture), and continues to Yamashina Basin. (The Gojo Bypass running in Yamashina Ward may be widely referred to as the Gojo-dori Street.)</e>
<cmt>http://web.kyoto-inet.or.jp/people/kurituka/torina.htmhttp://www.nihonjiten.com/data/45482.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">National Highway Route No. 1, after crossing over Higashioji-dori Street, becomes the Gojo Bypass, merges with Shibuya-dori Street, runs across Higashiyama (Kyoto Prefecture) and continues to Yamashina Basin (the Gojo Bypass running in Yamashina ward is widely referred to as Gojo-dori Street.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">National Highway Route No. 1, after it crosses Higashioji-dori Street, becomes the Gojo Bypass, merges with Shibutani-dori Street, runs through Higashiyama (Kyoto Prefecture) and continues to Yamashina Basin (the Gojo Bypass running in Yamashina Ward is widely referred to as Gojo-dori Street).</e>
<cmt>Shibuya→Shibutaniピリオドを)から出す</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>西は国道9号として、桂川 (淀川水系)の西大橋を経て桂から京都縦貫自動車道沓掛インターチェンジに繋がる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the west, the street, as National Highway Route No.9, crosses the Nishiohashi Bridge, goes to Katsura, and leads to Kutsukake Interchange of Kyoto Jukan Jidoshado Expressway.</e>
<cmt>http://www1.river.go.jp/cgi/SiteInfoNew.exe?ID=406041286606210http://www.kyo-miti.jp/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the west the street, designated as National Highway Route No. 9, crosses the Nishiohashi Bridge, goes to Katsura and leads to the Kutsukake Interchange of the Kyoto Jukan Jidoshado Expressway.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the west the street, designated as National Highway Route No. 9, crosses the Nishiohashi Bridge of Katsura River (Yodo-gawa water system), goes to Katsura and leads to the Kutsukake Interchange of the Kyoto Jukan Jidoshado Expressway.</e>
<cmt>of Katsura River (Yodo-gawa water system)補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>平安京の六条坊門小路にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The street corresponds to the Rokujo-bomon-koji Street in Heiankyo.</e>
<cmt>http://www.mutsunohana.net/miyako/oji-koji/rokujobomon-koji.htm</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The street corresponds to Rokujo-bomon-koji Street in Heiankyo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The street corresponds to Rokujo-bomon-koji Street in Heiankyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>豊臣秀吉が、方広寺参拝のため、鴨川 (淀川水系)に架かる五条大橋を六条坊門小路に移設したため、この通りが五条通となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The street started to be called the Gojo-dori street because Gojo-ohashi Bridge crossing across the Kamogawa-River (Yodogawa water system) was moved to the Rokujo-bomon-koji Street by Hideyoshi Toyotomi, who wanted to visit Hokoji Temple.</e>
<cmt>http://kaiwai.city.kyoto.jp/search/view_sight.php?ManageCode=2000055&amp;InforKindCode=6&amp;whole=truehttp://www.civilnet.or.jp/gallery/bridge/kyoto/html/gojo.html一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was originally called Gojo-dori Street because the Gojo-ohashi Bridge crossing the Kamogawa-River (Yodogawa water system) was moved to Rokujo-bomon-koji Street by Hideyoshi Toyotomi, who wanted to visit Hokoji Temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was originally called Gojo-dori Street because the Gojo-ohashi Bridge crossing the Kamo-gawa River (Yodo-gawa water system) was moved to Rokujo-bomon-koji Street by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, who wanted to visit Hoko-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>Kamogawa-River→Kamo-gawa River 他の記事とあわせる。Yodogawa→Yodo-gawaToyotomi→TOYOTOMIHokoji→Hoko-ji</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>元の五条大路は松原通と呼ばれるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The former Gojo-oji Street began to be called Matsubara Street.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The former Gojo-oji Street began to be called Matsubara Street.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The former Gojo-oji Street began to be called Matsubara Street.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="14">
<j>唱歌「牛若丸」の歌い出しには「京の五条の橋の上」とあり、現在の五条大橋の西詰、五条通の中央分離帯に牛若丸と弁慶の像が置かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Ushiwakamaru,&quot; the school song starts with “on a bridge of Gojo in Kyoto,” and the statues of Ushiwakamaru and Benkei stand at the west end of the Gojo-ohashi Bridge and on the median strip of the street.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The school anthem &quot;Ushiwakamaru&quot; begins with “on a bridge of Gojo in Kyoto,” and the statues of Ushiwakamaru and Benkei stand at the western end of the Gojo-ohashi Bridge and on the median strip of the street.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The school anthem &apos;Ushiwakamaru&apos; begins with, &apos;On a bridge of Gojo in Kyoto,&apos; and the statues of Ushiwakamaru and Benkei stand at the western end of the Gojo-ohashi Bridge and on the median strip of the street.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」にあわせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>なお、牛若丸と弁慶の時代の五条大橋は、元の五条大路である松原通の方に架かる橋にあたるため、時代考証上の不備のように思われるが、牛若丸と弁慶の出会いはもともと五条大橋とは別の場所であったものを、後年作り話として「五条の橋の上」と設定したものに過ぎない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Considering that the Gojo-ohashi Bridge in the era of Ushiwakamaru and Benkei were located on the former Gojo-oji Street, the present-day Matsubara-dori Street, historical evidence may not be properly examined, but the encounter of Ushiwakamaru with Benkei on the Gojo-ohashi Bridge, which in fact occurred in different place, may have been a story made up.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Considering that the Gojo-ohashi Bridge in the era of Ushiwakamaru and Benkei was located on the former Gojo-oji Street (the present-day Matsubara-dori Street), the historical evidence may not be properly examined, but the encounter of Ushiwakamaru with Benkei on Gojo-ohashi Bridge, which in fact occurred in a different place, may have been a contrived tale.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Considering that the Gojo-ohashi Bridge in the era of Ushiwakamaru and Benkei was located on the former Gojo-oji Street (the present-day Matsubara-dori Street), the historical evidence may not be properly examined, but the encounter of Ushiwakamaru with Benkei on Gojo-ohashi Bridge, which in fact occurred in a different place, may have been a contrived tale.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="16">
<j>東大路通から千本通までの区間は御池通や堀川通同様、第二次世界大戦末期に防火帯形成のため建物疎開が行われ、戦後、その用地を利用して幅員約50mに道路が整備された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During World War II, houses along the section between Higashioji Street and Senbon-dori Street were forced to move to build a fire blocking belt, like in the Horikawa-dori Street; after the war, the street were widened to about 50 meter using the site.</e>
<cmt>http://web.kyoto-inet.or.jp/people/kurituka/torina.htmhttp://kaiwai.city.kyoto.jp/search/view_sight.php?ManageCode=3000014&amp;InforKindCode=1&amp;whole=truehttp://web.kyoto-inet.or.jp/people/kurituka/torina.htm</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During World War II, houses along the section between Higashioji Street and Senbon-dori Street were forced to move in order to build a fire-blocking belt, like in Horikawa-dori Street; however, after the war, the street was widened to about 50 meters using the site.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During World War II, houses along the section between Higashioji Street and Senbon-dori Street were forced to move in order to build a fire-blocking belt, like in Oike-dori Street and Horikawa-dori Street; however, after the war, the street was widened to about 50 meters using the site.</e>
<cmt>Oike-dori Street and 補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>現在、西大路通まで50mに拡幅する工事が事業中である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Now road widening works are under way to extend 50 meter wide lanes to the Nishioji-dori Street.</e>
<cmt>http://web.kyoto-inet.or.jp/people/kurituka/torina.htm</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Road-widening work is now under way to extend the 50-meter-wide lanes to Nishioji-dori Street.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Road-widening work is now under way to extend the 50-meter-wide lanes to Nishioji-dori Street.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>交差する道路など</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Crossing Road</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Crossing Roads</e>
<cmt>plural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Crossing Roads</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="18">
<j>交差する道路などの特記がないものは市町村道。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Roads unless specified are operated by local municipalities.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Roads are operated by local municipalities unless otherwise specified.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Roads are operated by local municipalities unless otherwise specified.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>交通量</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Traffic Volume</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Traffic Volume</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Traffic Volume</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="19">
<j>2005年度（平成17年度道路交通センサスより）平日24時間交通量（台）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fiscal 2005 Average Weekday 24-hour Traffic Volume (numbers) (Road Traffic Census)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fiscal year 2005 Average Weekday 24-Hour Traffic Volume (Statistical) (Road Traffic Census)</e>
<cmt>grammar, case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fiscal year 2005 Average Weekday 24-Hour Traffic Volume (Statistical) (Road Traffic Census)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="20">
<j>京都市下京区大津町：64,436</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Otsucho, Shimogyo Ward, Kyoto City: 64,436</e>
<cmt>http://www.excite.co.jp/map/address/26/106/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Otsucho, Shimogyo ward, Kyoto City: 64,436</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Otsucho, Shimogyo Ward, Kyoto City: 64,436</e>
<cmt>ｗ大文字に、他の記事と統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="21">
<j>京都市右京区西京極新明町：54,289</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nishi Kyogoku-shinmeicho, Ukyo Ward, Kyoto City: 54,289</e>
<cmt>http://www.excite.co.jp/map/address/26/108/?start=900</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nishi Kyogoku-shinmeicho, Ukyo ward, Kyoto City: 54,289</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nishi Kyogoku-shinmeicho, Ukyo Ward, Kyoto City: 54,289</e>
<cmt>ｗ大文字に、他の記事と統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="22">
<j>沿道の主な施設</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Main Facilities along Street</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Main facilities along the street</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Main facilities along the street</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="23">
<j>清水寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyomizu-dera Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyomizu-dera Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyomizu-dera Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="24">
<j>西大谷本廟</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nishiotani Honbyo Mausoleum (Otani Honbyo Mausoleum of Hongan-ji Temple, Honganji group of Jodoshin-shu sect)</e>
<cmt>http://kaiwai.city.kyoto.jp/search/view_sight.php?ManageCode=1000115&amp;InforKindCode=1&amp;whole=true</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nishiotani Honbyo Mausoleum (Otani Honbyo Mausoleum of Hongan-ji Temple, of the Honganji group of the Jodoshin-shu sect)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nishiotani Honbyo Mausoleum (Otani Honbyo Mausoleum of Hongan-ji Temple, of the Honganji group of the Jodoshin-shu sect)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="25">
<j>東山郵便局 (京都府)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Higashiyama Post Office</e>
<cmt>http://www.jp-network.japanpost.jp/storesearch/detail/index.php?id=300101440150</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Higashiyama Post Office</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Higashiyama Post Office</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="26">
<j>京阪電気鉄道京阪本線 - 五条駅 (京阪)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keihan Electric Railway - Gojo Station (Keihan)</e>
<cmt>京阪電鉄HP (http://www.keihan.co.jp/)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keihan Electric Railway - Gojo Station (Keihan)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keihan Electric Railway - Gojo Station (Keihan)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="27">
<j>五条大橋(鴨川 (淀川水系))</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gojo-ohashi Bridge (Kamo-gawa River (Yodogawa water system)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gojo-ohashi Bridge (Kamo-gawa River (Yodogawa Water System)</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gojo-ohashi Bridge (Kamo-gawa River (Yodo-gawa Water System)</e>
<cmt>Yodogawa→Yodo-gawa</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="28">
<j>五条楽園</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gojo Rakuen</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gojo Rakuen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gojo Rakuen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="29">
<j>朝日神明宮 - 石門心学の故地</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Asahi Shinmeigu - the former site of Sekimon Shingaku</e>
<cmt>http://kaiwai.city.kyoto.jp/search/view_sight.php?ManageCode=9000284&amp;InforKindCode=4&amp;whole=truehttp://dic.yahoo.co.jp/dsearch?enc=UTF-8&amp;p=石門心学&amp;dtype=0&amp;dname=0na&amp;stype=0&amp;pagenum=1&amp;index=12019310338000</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Asahi Shinmeigu - the former site of Sekimon Shingaku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Asahi Shinmeigu - the former site of Sekimon Shingaku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="30">
<j>京都市営地下鉄烏丸線 - 五条駅 (京都市営地下鉄)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Karasuma-Sen (Karasuma Line), Kyoto City Subway - Gojo Station (Kyoto City Subway)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Karasuma-Sen (Karasuma Line), Kyoto City Subway - Gojo Station (Kyoto City Subway)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Karasuma-Sen (Karasuma Line), Kyoto City Subway - Gojo Station (Kyoto City Subway)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="31">
<j>烏丸五条</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Karasma Gojo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Karasma Gojo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Karasuma Gojo</e>
<cmt>Karasma→Karasuma</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="32">
<j>堀川五条</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Horikawa Gojo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Horikawa Gojo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Horikawa Gojo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="33">
<j>山陰本線（嵯峨野線） - 丹波口駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">San&apos;in Main Line (Sagano Line) - Tambaguchi Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">San&apos;in Main Line (Sagano Line) - Tambaguchi Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">San&apos;in Main Line (Sagano Line) - Tanbaguchi Station</e>
<cmt>&quot;Tambaguchi&quot; -&gt; &quot;Tanbaguchi&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="34">
<j>京都市中央卸売市場第一市場</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">First market, Kyoto City central wholesale market</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first market: Kyoto City Central Wholesale Market</e>
<cmt>punctuation, case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first market, Kyoto City Central Wholesale Market</e>
<cmt>:を,に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="35">
<j>京都リサーチパーク</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Research Park</e>
<cmt>http://www.krp.co.jp/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Research Park</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Research Park</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="36">
<j>京都市立病院</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto City Hospital</e>
<cmt>http://www.city.kyoto.lg.jp/city-hosp/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto City Hospital</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto City Hospital</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="37">
<j>ローム</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">ROHM, Co. Ltd</e>
<cmt>http://www.rohm.com/index.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">ROHM, Co. Ltd</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">ROHM, Co. Ltd</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="38">
<j>ダイヤモンドシティ・ハナ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">DIAMOND CITY Hana</e>
<cmt>http://hana.diamondcity.co.jp/html/access.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">DIAMOND CITY Hana</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">DIAMOND CITY Hana</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="39">
<j>京都光華女子大学</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Koka Women&apos;s University</e>
<cmt>http://www.koka.ac.jp/index.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Koka Women&apos;s University</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Koka Women&apos;s University</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="40">
<j>京都市西京極総合運動公園</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto City Nishi Kyogoku General Playground</e>
<cmt>http://www.city.kyoto.jp/koho/kids/06_institution/26/index.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto City Nishi Kyogoku General Playground</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto City Nishi Kyogoku General Playground</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="41">
<j>京都市西京極総合運動公園陸上競技場兼球技場</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto City Nishi Kyogoku General Playground Track field and Ball park</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto City Nishi Kyogoku General Playground, Track, Field and Ball Park</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto City Nishi Kyogoku General Playground, Track, Field and Ball Park</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="42">
<j>京都市西京極総合運動公園野球場</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto City Nishi Kyogoku General Playground. Ball park</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto City Nishi Kyogoku General Playground and Ballpark</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto City Nishi Kyogoku General Playground and Baseball Field</e>
<cmt>ballpark→Baseball field 前出の球技場と区別するため</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Hideyuki(id:9577), Dummyoscar(id:26399), たね(id:10372), Urania(id:7213), Wei Yuan(id:13342), お掃除大好き(id:99320), ＋－(id:17104), Miyuki h(id:84952), Matsukaze(id:51778), Ktr(id:30468), 油谷サトシ(id:27516), 金山銀山銅山(id:163855), Mochi(id:9489), Ko-ken(id:49348), Baba(id:2635), うら(id:40695), Haruno Akiha(id:107628), ちょろ(id:17218), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>