<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>花屋町通</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hanayacho-dori Street</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hanayacho-dori Street</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hanayacho-dori Street</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>花屋町通（はなやちょうどおり）は京都市の通りの一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hanayacho-dori Street is one of the streets in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hanayacho-dori Street is a street in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hanayacho-dori Street is a street in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>花屋町通は東西は葛野大路通・西京極駅から富小路通まで。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hanayacho-dori Street runs from Nishi-Kyogoku Station on Kadonooji-dori Streetat east and west, to Tominokoji-dori Street.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hanayacho-dori Street runs from Nishi-Kyogoku Station on Kadonooji-dori Street east and west, to Tominokoji-dori Street.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hanayacho-dori Street runs from Nishi-Kyogoku Station on Kadonooji-dori Street east and west, to Tominokoji-dori Street.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>南北は六条通と旧花屋町通の間にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The south and north is between Rokujo-dori Street and former Hanayacho-dori Street.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">North and south, it is between Rokujo-dori Street and the former Hanayacho-dori Street.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">North and south, it is between Rokujo-dori Street and the former Hanayacho-dori Street.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>旧花屋町通は新町通から堀川通まで並列している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Former Hanayacho-dori Street lines up from Shinmachi-dori Street to Horikawa-dori Street.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The former Hanayacho-dori Street runs parallel from Shinmachi-dori Street to Horikawa-dori Street.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The former Hanayacho-dori Street runs parallel from Shinmachi-dori Street to Horikawa-dori Street.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>この間では花屋町通は新花屋町通と呼ぶこともある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sometimes Hnayacho-dori Street is called Shin-Hanayacho-dori Street in this area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sometimes Hnayacho-dori Street is called Shin-Hanayacho-dori Street in this area.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sometimes Hanayacho-dori Street is called Shin-Hanayacho-dori Street in this area.</e>
<cmt>Hnayacho-dori→Hanayacho-doriに修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>堀川通から西側は花屋町通1本になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">West side from Horikawa-dori Street became one street, Hanayacho-dori Street.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">West from Horikawa-dori Street, it merges into one street, Hanayacho-dori Street.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">West from Horikawa-dori Street, it merges into one street, Hanayacho-dori Street.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>また丹波口駅にある京都市中央卸売市場第一市場があるため道は中断される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also the street is stopped because there is the first market of Central Wholesale Market of Kyoto City at Tanbaguchi Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also the street is interrupted by the First Central Wholesale Market of Kyoto City at Tanbaguchi Station.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also the street is interrupted by the First Central Wholesale Market of Kyoto City at Tanbaguchi Station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>烏丸通から富小路通までは西行きの一方通行の道だが、烏丸通から西は一部を除きほぼ片側1車線の両方通行の道路になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The street from Karasuma-dori Street to Tomikoji-dori Street is one-way street which goes to east, but the street toward west from Karasuma-dori Street became 2-way street with one driveway on each side, except one part.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The street from Karasuma-dori Street to Tomikoji-dori Street is a one-way street which heads east, but the street west from Karasuma-dori Street becomes a 2-way street with one lane on each side, except for one part.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The street from Karasuma-dori Street to Tomikoji-dori Street is a one-way street which heads east, but the street west from Karasuma-dori Street becomes a two-way street with one lane on each side, except for one part.</e>
<cmt>2-way→two-wayとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>ちなみに七本松通との交差点はかなり広い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By the way, the crossing with Shicihonmatsu-dori Street is very wide.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The intersection with Shicihonmatsu-dori Street is very wide.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The intersection with Shicihonmatsu-dori Street is very wide.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="10">
<j>読み方に関してははなやまちと読んでも間違いないが、はなやちょうのほうが浸透している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It&apos;s not wrong to read Hahanayamachi, but reading Hanaya-cho is better known.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While it is sometimes known as Hahanayamachi, it is better known as Hanaya-cho.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While it is sometimes known as Hanayamachi, it is better known as Hanaya-cho.</e>
<cmt>Hahanayamachi→Hanayamachiに修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="11">
<j>由来は生花商の店が多かったことからこの名がついた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name came from that many flower shops used to be there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name stems from the fact that many flower shops used to populate the area.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name stems from the fact that many flower shops used to populate the area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 MDR-SK(id:192066), Kansai explorer(id:48975), スフィンクス(id:162663), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>