<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>東高野街道</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Higasih-Koya-Kaido Road</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Higasih-Koya-Kaido Road</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Higashi Koya-Kaido Road</e>
<cmt>Higashiのスペルミスを修正、ハイフンを一部とりました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>東高野街道（ひがしこうやかいどう）とは、かつて京都から高野山への参詣道として用いられた街道。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Higashi-koya-kaido road was a road which was used as an entrance path to visit Mt. Koya from Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Higashi-koya-kaido road was a road used to visit Mt. Koya from Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Higashi Koya-kaido road was a road used to visit Mt. Koya from Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>Higashi Koya-kaido roadとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>数ある高野街道のうち、いちばん東側に位置する道筋。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Of many Koya-kaido roads, Higashi-koya-kaido road was located at the eastmost position.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Of the many Koya-kaido roads, Higashi-koya-kaido road was located at the eastern most location.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Of the many Koya-kaido roads, Higashi Koya-kaido road was located at the eastern most location.</e>
<cmt>Higashi Koya-kaido roadとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>八幡（京都府八幡市）で京街道 (大坂街道) と別れ、河内国の東部を通り、長野（大阪府河内長野市）で西高野街道と合流し、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Higashi-Koya-kaido road parted from Kyo-kaido road (Osaka-kaido road) at Yahata (Yahata City, Kyoto Prefecture), ran through the eastern part of Kawachi-no-kuni province, and joined Nishi-Koya-kaido road at Nagano (Kawachi-nagano City, Osaka Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Higashi-Koya-kaido road parted from Kyo-kaido road (Osaka-kaido road) at Yahata (Yahata City, Kyoto Prefecture), ran through the eastern part of Kawachi-no-kuni province, and joined Nishi-Koya-kaido road at Nagano (Kawachi-nagano City, Osaka Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Higashi Koya-kaido road parted from Kyo-kaido road (Osaka-kaido road) at Yahata (Yahata City, Kyoto Prefecture), ran through the eastern part of Kawachi Province, and joined Nishi Koya-kaido road at Nagano (Kawachi-nagano City, Osaka Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>Higashi Koya-kaido road, Kawachi Province, Nishi Koya-kaido roadとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>以南は高野街道として紀見峠、橋本、高野山へ至る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The section of Higashi-Koya-kaido road in the south of Nagano led to Kimi-toge ridge, Hashimoto, and Mt. Koya as Koya-kaido road.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The section of the Higashi-Koya-kaido road in the south of Nagano led to Kimi-toge ridge, Hashimoto, and Mt. Koya in the form of the Koya-kaido road.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The section of the Higashi Koya-kaido road in the south of Nagano led to Kimi-toge ridge, Hashimoto, and Mt. Koya in the form of the Koya-kaido road.</e>
<cmt>Higashi Koya-kaido roadとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="6">
<j>いつ頃に形成されたかは定かでない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is not sure when Higashi-Koya-kaido road was formed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Exactly when Higashi-Koya-kaido road was established is unknown.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Exactly when Higashi Koya-kaido road was established is unknown.</e>
<cmt>Higashi Koya-kaido roadとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>既存の集落を経ず、出来るだけ直線になるように通されており、自然発生的に形成された道ではなく、計画に基づいて建設された日本の古代道路であると言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Higashi-Koya-kaido road was constructed as straight as possible without passing any then-existing settlements and, therefore, it is said that this road was not a road which had been spontaneously formed but a Japanese ancient road which was constructed according to a plan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Higashi-Koya-kaido road was constructed as straight as possible without passing through any then-existing settlements and, therefore, it is said that this road was not a road which had been spontaneously formed but an ancient Japanese road which was constructed according to a plan.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Higashi Koya-kaido road was constructed as straight as possible without passing through any then-existing settlements and, therefore, it is said that this road was not a road which had been spontaneously formed but an ancient Japanese road which was constructed according to a plan.</e>
<cmt>Higashi Koya-kaido roadとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="8">
<j>淀川水系の河川や、かつて存在した巨大な河内湖（深野池）周辺の湿地帯を避けて生駒山地の麓を通り、河内国府（現在の藤井寺市）付近で大和川を越えると石川 (大阪府)の左岸に沿って通った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Higashi-Koya-kaido road passed through the foot of Ikoma mountains bypassing the rivers in Yodo River system and wetlands around Kawachi Lake (Fukano-ike pond) which used to exist, and the road ran along the left bank of Ishi River after crossing Yamato River around Kawachi-Kokufu (presently, Fujiidera City).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Higashi-Koya-kaido road passed through the foot of the Ikoma mountains bypassing the rivers in the Yodo River system and wetlands which used to exist around Kawachi Lake (Fukano-ike pond), and ran along the left bank of Ishi River after crossing Yamato River around Kawachi-Kokufu (presently, Fujiidera City).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Higashi Koya-kaido road passed through the foot of the Ikoma mountain range bypassing the rivers in the Yodo-gawa River system and wetlands which used to exist around Lake Kawachi (Fukano-ike pond), and ran along the left bank of the Ishi-kawa River after crossing the Yamato-gawa River around Kawachi-Kokufu (presently, Fujiidera City).</e>
<cmt>Higashi Koya-kaido road, Ikoma mountain range, Lake Kawachiとし、「 ○○川」の表記を&quot;-gawa River&quot;としました。&quot;Ishi-kawa River&quot;→&quot;the Ishi-kawa River&quot;に変更しました。&quot;Yamato-gawa River&quot;→&quot;the Yamato-gawa River&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="9">
<j>平安時代には駅が設置され、京と河内国府を結ぶ官道としても重要であったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Heian period, stations were provided on Higashi-Koya-kaido road and the road was also important as an administrative road connecting between Kyoto and Kawachi-Kokufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Heian period, stations existed on the Higashi-Koya-kaido road and was also important as an administrative road connecting Kyoto and Kawachi-Kokufu.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Heian period, stations existed on the Higashi Koya-kaido road and was also important as an administrative road connecting Kyoto and Kawachi-Kokufu.</e>
<cmt>Higashi Koya-kaido roadとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="10">
<j>その後は官道としての重要性は薄れたものの、仏教信仰の一般化に伴い、高野山参りが盛んになると参拝道として賑わうようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though the importance of Higashi-Koya-Kaido road reduced after Heian period, the road became thronged as an entrance path to Mt. Koya when visitors to Mt. Koya increased with the spread of belief in Buddha in the general public.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though the importance of the Higashi-Koya-Kaido road declined after the Heian period, it became crowded with people at the entrance to Mt. Koya as visitors to Mt. Koya increased due to the spread of the Buddhist belief among the general public.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the importance of the Higashi Koya-kaido road declined after the Heian period, it became crowded with people at the entrance to Mt. Koya as visitors to Mt. Koya increased due to the spread of the Buddhist belief among the general public.</e>
<cmt>Higashi Koya-kaido roadとしました。&quot;Though&quot;→&quot;Although&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="11">
<j>現在では、大阪府道・京都府道735号長尾八幡線、枚方バイパス、大阪府道18号枚方交野寝屋川線、大阪府道20号枚方富田林泉佐野線と国道170号（旧道）各道の大半に相当または平行する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today, the route of Higashi-Koya-kaido road corresponds to or runs in parallel to most of each of Nagao-Yahata Line which is an Osaka prefectural road and Kyoto Prefectural Road No. 735, Hirakata Bypass, Hirakata-Kono-Neyagawa Line which is Osaka Prefectural Road No. 18, Hirakata-Tondabayashi-Izumisano Line which is Osaka Prefectural Road No. 20, and National Road No. 170 (old road).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, the route for the Higashi-Koya-kaido road corresponds to or runs in parallel to most of the Nagao-Yahata Line which is an Osaka prefectural road and Kyoto Prefectural Road No. 735, Hirakata Bypass, Hirakata-Kono-Neyagawa Line which is Osaka Prefectural Road No. 18, Hirakata-Tondabayashi-Izumisano Line which is Osaka Prefectural Road No. 20, and National Road No. 170 (old road).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, the route for the Higashi Koya-kaido road corresponds to or runs in parallel to most of the Nagao-Yahata Line which is an Osaka prefectural road and Kyoto Prefectural Road No. 735, Hirakata Bypass, Hirakata-Katano-Neyagawa Line which is Osaka Prefectural Road No. 18, Hirakata-Tondabayashi-Izumisano Line which is Osaka Prefectural Road No. 20, and National Road No. 170 (old road).</e>
<cmt>Higashi Koya-kaido roadとし、「交野(かたの)」の読みの誤りを訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kansai explorer(id:48975), Rusk(id:9895), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>