<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>花見小路通</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hanamikoji-Doori Street</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hanamikoji-Doori Street</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hanamikoji-dori Street</e>
<cmt>Hanamikoji-dori Streetとしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>花見小路通（はなみこうじどおり）は、京都市の南北の通りの一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hanamikoji-doori street is one of the streets running from east to west in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hanamikoji-doori street is a street running east-west through Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hanamikoji-dori Street is a street running east-west through Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>Hanamikoji-dori Streetとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>北は三条通から南は安井北門通まで約1km、祇園の中心を通るメインストリートである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hanamikoji-doori street spans over the length of about 1 km from Sanjo-doori street at its north end to Yasuikita-doori street at its south end, and is the main street passing through the central zone of Gion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hanamikoji-doori street spans a length of about 1 km from Sanjo-doori street at its north end to Yasuikita-doori street at its south end, and is the main street passing through the central zone of Gion.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hanamikoji-dori Street spans a length of about 1 km from Sanjo-dori Street at its north end to Yasui Kitamon-dori Street at its south end, and is the main street passing through the central zone of Gion.</e>
<cmt>Hanamikoji-dori Street, Sanjo-dori Streetとし、Yasuikita-doori street→Yasui Kitamon-dori Streetに修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>四条通以南は明治以降発展し、茶屋や料理屋が立ち並ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The section of Hanamikoji-doori street in the south of a point on Shijo-doori street started to develop in Meiji period and tea rooms and restaurants line the road.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The section of Hanamikoji-doori street south of Shijo-doori street started to develop during the Meiji period with tea rooms and restaurants lining the road.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The section of Hanamikoji-dori Street south of Shijo-dori Street started to develop during the Meiji period with tea rooms and restaurants lining the road.</e>
<cmt>Hanamikoji-dori Street, Shijo-dori Streetに修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>沿道の施設</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Facility along Hanamikoji-doori street</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Facility along Hanamikoji-doori street</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Facility along Hanamikoji-dori Street</e>
<cmt>Hanamikoji-dori Streetに修正</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>建仁寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kennin-ji temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kennin-ji temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kennin-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>templeの頭文字を大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Aoiya(id:44787), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>