<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>塔ノ段通</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To-no-dan-doori Street</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To-no-dan-doori Street</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tonodan-dori Street</e>
<cmt>Tonodan-dori Streetとしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>塔ノ段通（とうのだんどおり）は京都市内の南北の通りの一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To-no-dan-doori street is one of the streets running from north to south in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To-no-dan-doori street is a street running north-south through Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tonodan-dori Street is a street running north-south through Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>Tonodan-dori Streetとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>北は上京区桜木町から南は今出川通まで、延長およそ600m。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To-no-dan-doori street runs from Sakuragi-cho in Kamikyo Ward at its north end to Imadegawa-doori street to its south end, spanning over a length of about 600 m.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To-no-dan-doori street runs from Sakuragi-cho in Kamikyo Ward at its north end to Imadegawa-doori street to its south end, spanning a length of about 600 m.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tonodan-dori Street runs from Sakuragi-cho in Kamigyo Ward at its north end to Imadegawa-dori Street to its south end, spanning a length of about 600 m.</e>
<cmt>Tonodan-dori Street, Imadegawa-dori Streetとし、Kamikyo→Kamigyoに修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>ほぼ住宅のみの並ぶ通りで、商店も数少ない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Only residences mainly line To-no-dan-doori street and just a few stores also line the street.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Residences mainly line To-no-dan-doori street with a few stores as well.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Residences mainly line Tonodan-dori Street with a few stores as well.</e>
<cmt>Tonodan-dori Streetとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>名称の由来は、相国寺の七重の塔が建っていたところであるため。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name of the street, To-no-dan (stage for a tower) comes from the site where a seven-storey pagoda of Sokoku-ji temple stood.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name of the street, To-no-dan (stage for a tower) comes from the site where a seven-storey pagoda of Sokoku-ji temple used to stand.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name of the street, Tonodan (stage for a tower) comes from the site where a seven-storey pagoda of Shokoku-ji temple used to stand.</e>
<cmt>Tonodanとし、相国寺(しょうこくじ)の読みの誤りを訂正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="5">
<j>この塔は京都で現存している塔でもっとも高い教王護国寺よりも高かったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the seven-storey pagoda was higher than the pagoda of Kyoogokoku-ji temple which is the highest pagoda of all the exisitng pagodas in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the seven-storey pagoda was higher than the pagoda of Kyoogokoku-ji temple which is the highest pagoda of all the exisitng pagodas in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the seven-storey pagoda was higher than the pagoda of Kyoogokoku-ji Temple which is the highest pagoda of all the exisitng pagodas in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>templeの頭文字を大文字に変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>主な沿道の施設</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Main facilities along To-no-dan-doori street</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Main facilities along To-no-dan-doori street</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Main Facilities along Tonodan-dori Street</e>
<cmt>Tonodan-dori Streetとし、頭文字を大文字に変更</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>同志社女子中学校・高等学校</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Doshisha Women&apos;s Jr.-High and High Schools</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Doshisha Women&apos;s Jr.-High and High Schools</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Doshisha Girls&apos; Junior and Senior High School</e>
<cmt>学校ウェブサイトの表記に変更(参照: http://www.girls.doshisha.ac.jp/)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Miyuki h(id:84952), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>