<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>八幡愚童訓</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hachiman Gudokun (Exegesis of Hachimanshin (God of War) Legends for the Ignorant and Children)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hachiman Gudokun (Exegesis of Hachimanshin Legends for the Ignorant and Children)</e>
<cmt>nested parentheses</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hachiman Gudokun (Exegesis of Hachimanshin Legends for the Ignorant and Children)</e>
<cmt>Hachiman Gudokun (Tales of the God of War told to the Simple)</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>八幡愚童訓（はちまんぐどうくん）は、鎌倉時代中期・後期に成立したと思われる八幡神の霊験・神徳を説いた寺社縁起。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hachiman Gudokun is a history of temples and shrines that narrates the miracle and divine virtue of Hachimanshin (Shinto god of War), which is considered to have been compiled in the middle or late Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hachiman Gudokun is a history of temples and shrines that narrates the miracle and divine virtue of Hachimanshin (Shinto god of War), which is considered to have been compiled in the middle or late Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Hachiman Gudokun&quot; is a history of temples and shrines that narrates the miracle and divine virtue of Hachimanshin (Shinto god of War), which is considered to have been compiled in the middle or late Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>Hachiman Gudokun にダブルコーテーションを追記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>「愚童訓」とは八幡神の神徳を「童蒙にも理解出来るように説いた」の意味である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The word &quot;gudokun&quot; refers to &quot;exegesis for ignorant persons and children&quot; and (in this case) easy explanations of the divine virtue of Hachimanshin for children and the ignorant.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The word &quot;gudokun&quot; refers to &quot;exegesis for ignorant persons and children&quot; and, in this case, easy explanations of the divine virtue of Hachimanshin for children and the ignorant.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The word &apos;gudokun&apos; refers to &apos;exegesis for ignorant persons and children&apos; and, in this case, easy explanations of the divine virtue of Hachimanshin for them.</e>
<cmt>ダブルコーテーションをシングルコーテーションに修正しました。for children and the ignorant を for them に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>著者は不明であるが、石清水八幡宮の社僧の作と考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is unclear who the author is, but it is considered that the exegesis was authored by a shaso (Buddhist monk attached to a shrine) of Iwashimizu Hachimangu Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is unclear who the author is, but it is thought that the exegesis was authored by a shaso (Buddhist monk attached to a shrine) of Iwashimizu Hachimangu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>consider-&gt;think</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is unclear who the author is, but it is thought that the exegesis was authored by a shaso (Buddhist priest attached to a shrine) of Iwashimizu Hachimangu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>monk を priest に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>諸本に書かれた書名によって『八幡大菩薩愚童訓』『八幡愚童記』などともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Depending on the titles of books of different variety, it is also known as &quot;Hachiman Daibosatsu (Hachiman the Great Bodhisattva) Gudokun&quot; or &quot;Hachiman Gudo-ki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Depending on the titles of different kinds of books, it is also known as &quot;Hachiman Daibosatsu (Hachiman the Great Bodhisattva) Gudokun&quot; or &quot;Hachiman Gudo-ki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>books of different variety-&gt;different kinds of books</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Depending on the titles of different kinds of books, it is also known as &quot;Hachiman Daibosatsu (Hachiman the Great Bodhisattva) Gudokun&quot; or &quot;Hachiman Gudo-ki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>江戸時代初期に作成されたものの表題に附された訓に基づいて「はちまんぐどうきん」とも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, it is sometimes called &quot;Hachiman Gudo-kin&quot; based on the title of the book compiled in the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, it is sometimes called &quot;Hachiman Gudo-kin&quot; based on the title of the book compiled in the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, it is sometimes called &quot;Hachiman Gudo-kin&quot; based on the title of the book compiled in the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>蒙古襲来についての記録としても有名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also famous as records of Mongol invasions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also famous as records of Mongol invasions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also famous as records of Mongol invasions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>分類</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Classification</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Classification</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Classification</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>本書は同系統ながら内容にやや差異のある2種に大別されており、分類上、甲種・乙種と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hachiman Gudokun is roughly divided into two categories, which are conventionally called &apos;the first category&apos; and the &apos;second category&apos;-despite the same origin, there is a slight difference between the two.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hachiman Gudokun is roughly divided into two categories, which are conventionally called &apos;the first category&apos; and the &apos;second category&apos; - despite the shared origin, there is a slight difference between the two.</e>
<cmt>same-&gt;shared; spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hachiman Gudokun is roughly divided into two categories, which are conventionally called &apos;the first category&apos; and the &apos;second category&apos; - despite the shared origin, there is a slight difference between the two.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>成立年代については、甲種は延慶 (日本)元年から文保2年以前（1308年 - 1318年）と考えられ、乙種は正安年間（1299年 - 1302年）頃の成立という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The birth date of the first category is considered to be prior to the period between 1308 and 1318 while that of the second category is said to be around the Shoan era (1299-1302).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The date of the first category is considered to be prior to 1308 while that of the second category is said to be around the Shoan era (1299-1302).</e>
<cmt>deleted “birth” and “the period from”</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The date of the first category is considered to be between 1308 and 1318 while that of the second category is said to be around the Shoan era (1299-1302).</e>
<cmt>「延慶 (日本)元年から文保2年以前（1308年 - 1318年）」誤訳のためprior to 1308 を between 1308 and 1318 に修正して対応しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>甲乙ともに上下二巻本で構成されるが、元来は一本であったとも考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Both the first and second categories come in two volumes (book I and II), but it is also likely that they were originally one book.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Both the first and second categories come in two volumes (book I and II), but it is also likely that they were originally one book.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Both the first and second categories come in two volumes (book I and II), but it is also likely that they were originally one book.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>(万治3年（1660年）書写のいわゆる柳原旧蔵本は下巻を欠いているが上巻と中巻があり、三巻本が存在したとも言われている）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(It is also said that the 1660 transcription, the so-called &apos;Yanagihara old stock,&apos; had three volumes because book 1 of 3 and book 2 of 3 are preserved, although no book 3 of 3 remained.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(It is also said that the 1660 transcription, the so-called &apos;Yanagihara old stock,&apos; had three volumes because book 1 of 3 and book 2 of 3 are preserved, although nothing book 3 of 3 remained.)</e>
<cmt>no-&gt;nothing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(It is also said that the 1660 transcription, the so-called &quot;Yanagihara Kyuzobon&quot; (a collection of books once possessed by the Yanagihara family), had three volumes because book 1 of 3 and book 2 of 3 are preserved, although nothing book 3 of 3 remained.)</e>
<cmt>Yanagihara old stock&apos; を&quot;Yanagihara Kyuzobon&quot; (a collection of books once possessed by the Yanagihara family) に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="11">
<j>また、特に甲種本は一類・二類に分類される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, the first category is divided into category A and category B, in particular.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, the first category is divided into category A and category B, in particular.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, the first category is divided into category A and category B, in particular.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>一類は前文が具体的な内容になっており、元寇文永の役についても元 (王朝)・高麗連合軍による対馬国・壱岐国の侵攻が明記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The preface of the category A features detailed descriptions, whereby the attacks to Tsusima and Iki Provinces by the coalition army of the Yuan Dynasty and Goguryeo are described in detail as the explanation of Bunei War, one of Genko (Mongol invasion attempts against Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The preface of category A features detailed descriptions, whereby the attacks on Tsusima and Iki Provinces by the coalition army of the Yuan Dynasty and Goguryeo are described in detail as the explanation of Bunei War, one of Genko (Mongol invasion attempts against Japan).</e>
<cmt>articles; prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The preface of category A features detailed descriptions, whereby the attacks on Tsusima and Iki Provinces by the coalition army of the Yuan Dynasty and Goguryeo are described in detail as the explanation of Bunei War, one of Genko (Mongol invasion attempts against Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>一方、二類は前文が抽象的であり、対馬・壱岐の侵攻についての記載が殆どない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The preface of the category B, meanwhile, consists of abstract contents, whereby there are few descriptions about invasion to Tushima and Iki Provinces.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The preface of category B, meanwhile, consists of abstract contents, whereby there are few descriptions about the invasion to Tushima and Iki Provinces.</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The preface of category B, meanwhile, consists of abstract contents, whereby there are few descriptions about the invasion to Tushima and Iki Provinces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>内容</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Contents</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Contents</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Contents</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="14">
<j>上述のように、甲乙本ではそれぞれ内容に差異があるが、以下はその概観を述べる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As mentioned above, there is a slight difference between the first and second category books, whose outline is given below.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As mentioned above, there is a slight difference between the first and second category books, whose outline is given below.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As mentioned above, there is a slight difference between the first and second category books, whose outline is given below.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>甲種本</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">First category books</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">First category books</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">First category books</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="15">
<j>上下二巻。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Book I and Book II</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Book I and Book II</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They consist of Book I and Book II.</e>
<cmt>主語と述語を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>甲種本は、史上の異敵とその降伏（こうぶく）に関する事蹟が述べられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first category books describe invasions by foreign enemies and their defeats in history.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first category books describe invasions by foreign enemies and their defeats in history.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first category books describe invasions by foreign enemies and their defeats in history.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>上巻においては神功皇后のいわゆる「三韓征伐」、皇后の皇子であり八幡大菩薩とされる応神天皇の事蹟、元寇文永の役における蒙古軍の襲来、対馬・壱岐への侵攻、九州上陸と九州御家人勢との戦闘の状況、箱崎八幡宮（筥崎八幡宮）の焼亡などが記される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Book I introduces the following episodes: the so-called &apos;sankan-seibatsu&apos; (the conquest of three countries in old Korea) by Empress Jingu; the achievements of Emperor Ojin, the son of Empress Jingu, who was regarded as Hachiman Daibosatsu (Great Bodhisattva Hachiman); and the attacks of Mongol army, invasions into Tsushima and Iki Provinces, Mongol army&apos;s landing on Kushyu island, battle between Mongol army and Kyushu warriors, and the burning of Hakozaki Hachiman-gu Shrine during Bunei War.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Book I introduces the following episodes: the so-called &apos;sankan-seibatsu&apos; (the conquest of three countries in old Korea) by Empress Jingu; the achievements of Emperor Ojin, the son of Empress Jingu, who was regarded as Hachiman Daibosatsu (Great Bodhisattva Hachiman); and the attacks of Mongol army, invasions into Tsushima and Iki Provinces, Mongol army&apos;s landing on Kushyu island, battle between Mongol army and Kyushu warriors, and the burning of Hakozaki Hachiman-gu Shrine during Bunei War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Book I introduces the following episodes: the so-called &apos;sankan-seibatsu&apos; (the conquest of three countries in old Korea) by Empress Jingu; the achievements of Emperor Ojin, the son of Empress Jingu, who was regarded as Hachiman Daibosatsu (Great Bodhisattva Hachiman); and the attacks of Mongol army, invasions into Tsushima and Iki Provinces, Mongol army&apos;s landing on Kushyu island, battle between Mongol army and Kyushu warriors, and the burning of Hakozaki Hachiman-gu Shrine during the Bunei War.</e>
<cmt>during Bunei War を during the Bunei War に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>下巻は元寇弘安の役における思円上人・叡尊の祈祷、蒙古退却の奇瑞などを記述する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Book II introduces episodes such as Buddhist monk Eison&apos;s (aka &apos;Shien&apos;) prayers and auspicious sign of Mongol army&apos;s retreat during Koan War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Book II introduces episodes such as Buddhist monk Eison&apos;s (aka &apos;Shien&apos;) prayers and the auspicious sign of Mongol army&apos;s retreat during the Koan War.</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Book II introduces episodes such as Buddhist priest Eison&apos;s (aka &apos;Shien Shonin&apos;) prayers and the auspicious sign of Mongol army&apos;s retreat during the Koan War.</e>
<cmt>monk を priest に修正しました。Shien を Shien Shonin に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="19">
<j>甲種本の特徴としては、文永の役におけるモンゴル・高麗連合軍である蒙古軍の対馬・壱岐侵攻に関するほぼ唯一の史料である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first category books are almost only extant historical documents about the invasions of Mongol army, namely, the coalition force of Mongolia and Goguryeo, into Tsushima and Iki Provinces during Bunei War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first category books are almost the only extant historical documents about the invasions of the Mongol army, namely the coalition force of Mongolia and Goguryeo, into Tsushima and Iki Provinces during Bunei War.</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first category books are almost the only extant historical documents about the invasions of the Mongol army, namely the coalition force of Mongolia and Goguryeo, into Tsushima and Iki Provinces during the Bunei War.</e>
<cmt>during Bunei War を during the Bunei War に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>また、箱崎八幡による奇瑞や神威の顕現によって度々蒙古軍が撃退されたことが述べられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The books explain that Mongol army was often beaten back by the auspicious spells and divine power of Hakozaki Hachiman.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The books explain that the Mongol army was often beaten back by the auspicious spells and divine power of Hakozaki Hachiman.</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The books explain that the Mongol army was often beaten back by the auspicious spells and divine power of Hakozaki Hachiman.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>さらに、叡尊の祈祷による霊験の成果が強調されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, the influence of miracle caused by Buddhist monk Eison&apos;s prayers is emphasized in the books.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, the influence of miracles caused by Buddhist monk Eison&apos;s prayers is emphasized in the books.</e>
<cmt>plural miracles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, the influence of miracles caused by Buddhist priest Eison&apos;s prayers is emphasized in the books.</e>
<cmt>monk を priest に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>本書の成立に社寺の祈祷に対する朝廷からの恩賞問題が関わっていた可能性が指摘されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From this fact, it is pointed out the there is a possibility that the birth of the books had something to do with prizes given by Imperial Court to shrines and temples for their prayers.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From this fact, it is pointed out the there is a possibility that the birth of the books had something to do with prizes given by Imperial Court to shrines and temples for their prayers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From this fact, it is pointed out the there is a possibility that the birth of the books had something to do with prizes given by Imperial Court to shrines and temples for their prayers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>（群書類従 第一輯 神祇部 巻十三　収録）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(&quot;Gunsho ruiju&quot;(Collection of historical documents compiled by Hokiichi HANAWA)/ First Series/ Jingi (gods of heaven and earth) Section/ Volume 13)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(&quot;Gunsho ruiju&quot; Collection of historical documents compiled by Hokiichi HANAWA, First Series, Jingi - gods of heaven and earth - Volume 13)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Included in the Gunsho ruiju [Collection of historical documents compiled by Hokiichi HANAWA], First Series, Jingi - gods of heaven and earth - Volume 13)</e>
<cmt>「収録」訳漏れのため&quot;Gunsho ruiju&quot; Collection of historical documents compiled by Hokiichi HANAWA をIncluded in the Gunsho ruiju [Collection of historical documents compiled by Hokiichi HANAWA] に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>乙種本</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The second category books</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The second category books</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The second category books</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="24">
<j>上下二巻。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Book I and Book II</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Book I and Book II</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They consist of Book I and Book II.</e>
<cmt>主語と述語を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>乙種本は、八幡大菩薩の霊験・神徳について14章にわたって述べ、阿弥陀信仰との習合を説いた教義書的性格を持つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The second category books explain the miracle and divine virtue of Hachiman Daibosatsu in fourteen chapters, which have doctrinaire characteristics and preach merger with Amida Buddha worship.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The second category books explain the miracle and divine virtue of Hachiman Daibosatsu in fourteen chapters, which have doctrinaire characteristics and preach merger with Amida Buddha worship.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The second category books explain the miracle and divine virtue of Hachiman Daibosatsu in fourteen chapters, which have doctrinaire characteristics and preach merger with the worship of Amida.</e>
<cmt>Amida Buddha worship を the worship of Amida に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="26">
<j>序にはじまり、垂迹、名号、遷坐、御躰、本地、王位、氏人、慈悲、放生会、受戒、正直、不浄、仏法、後世の十四章からなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The books comprises preface and the following fourteen chapters: Suijaku (syncretism of Shinto with Buddhism), Myogo (name of the Buddha), Senza (travels), Gotai (body), Honji (original ground or true nature), Oi (imperial power), Ujibito (clan members), Jihi (mercy), Hojoe (the ritual for releasing captivated animals for mercy), Jukai (receiving the religious precept), Seichoku (honesty), Fujo (sins), Buppo (Buddhism), and Gose (afterworld).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The books comprises a preface and the following fourteen chapters: Suijaku (synthesis of Shinto and Buddhism), Myogo (name of the Buddha), Senza (travels), Gotai (body), Honji (original ground or true nature), Oi (imperial power), Ujibito (clan members), Jihi (mercy), Hojoe (the ritual for releasing captivated animals for mercy), Jukai (receiving the religious precept), Seichoku (honesty), Fujo (sins), Buppo (Buddhism), and Gose (afterworld).</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The books comprises a preface and the following fourteen chapters: Suijaku (synthesis of Shinto and Buddhism), Myogo (name of the Buddha), Senza (travels), Gotai (body), Honji (original ground or true nature), Oi (imperial power), Ujibito (clan members), Jihi (mercy), Hojoe (the ritual for releasing captivated animals for mercy), Jukai (receiving the religious precept), Seichoku (honesty), Fujo (uncleanliness), Buppo (Buddhism), and Gose (afterworld).</e>
<cmt>sins を uncleanliness に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>各項目にわたり広大無辺なる八幡大菩薩の神徳霊験が述べられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In each chapter, the limitless divine virtue and miracle of Hachiman Daibosatsu is elucidated.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In each chapter, the limitless divine virtue and miracle of Hachiman Daibosatsu is elucidated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In each chapter, the limitless divine virtue and miracle of Hachiman Daibosatsu is elucidated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>（続群書類従 第二輯 神祇部 巻三十）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(&quot;Zoku Gunshoruiju&quot; (The Collection of Historical Sources, continued)/ Second Series/ Jingi (gods of heaven and earth) Section/ Volume 30)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(&quot;Zoku Gunshoruiju&quot; The Collection of Historical Sources, continued, Second Series, Jingi - gods of heaven and earth - Volume 30)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Zoku Gunshoruiju [The Collection of Historical Sources, continued], Second Series, Jingi - gods of heaven and earth - Volume 30)</e>
<cmt>&quot;Zoku Gunshoruiju&quot; The Collection of Historical Sources, continued をZoku Gunshoruiju [The Collection of Historical Sources, continued] に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Los688(id:12316), Haydar(id:56911), 水野白楓(id:22811), 弥(id:61590), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>