<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>笠縫邑</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kasanuimura</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kasanuimura</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kasanuimura</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>笠縫邑（かさぬいむら、かさぬいのむら）とは、崇神天皇6年に、宮中に奉祀していた天照大神を移し、豊鍬入姫命に託して祀らせた場所。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kasanuimura, or Kasanui no mura, is the place where Toyosuki iribime no mikoto, who was given the responsibility, enshrined Amaterasu Omikami (the Sun Goddess) after she was transferred from her place of enshrinement at the Imperial Court in the 6th year of Emperor Sujin&apos;s reign.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kasanuimura, or Kasanui no mura, is the place where Toyosuki iribime no mikoto, who was given responsibility, enshrined Amaterasu Omikami (the Sun Goddess) after she was transferred from her place of enshrinement at the Imperial Court in the 6th year of Emperor Sujin&apos;s reign.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kasanuimura, or Kasanui no mura, is the place where Toyosuki iribime no Mikoto, who was given responsibility, enshrined Amaterasu Omikami (the Sun Goddess) after she was transferred from her place of enshrinement at the Imperial Court in the sixth year of Emperor Sujin&apos;s reign.</e>
<cmt>神名表現を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>同時に宮中を出された倭大国魂神は渟名城入媛命に託して、後に大和神社に祀った、とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamatonookuni tamanokami, who was removed from the Imperial court at the same time, was enshrined at Oyamato-jinja Shrine by Nunaki iribime no mikoto, who was given the responsibility.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yamatonookuni tamanokami, who was removed from the Imperial court at the same time, was enshrined at Oyamato-jinja Shrine by Nunaki iribime no mikoto, who was given responsibility.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamatonookuni tama no Kami, who was removed from the Imperial Court at the same time, was enshrined at Oyamato-jinja Shrine by Nunaki iribime no Mikoto, who was given responsibility.</e>
<cmt>神名表現を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>笠縫邑は大嘗祭、豊明節会の起源に関係する土地との説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kasanuimura, according to one theory, is associated with the place of origin of Daijosai (first ceremonial offering of rice by newly-enthroned Emperor) and Toyoakari no sechie (one of the ceremonies at a seasonal holiday).</e>
<cmt>大嘗祭の訳は用語集に複数あります。豊明節会は定訳不明。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kasanuimura, according to one theory, is associated with the place of origin of Daijosai (first ceremonial offering of rice by newly-enthroned Emperor) and Toyoakari no sechie (one of the ceremonies at a seasonal holiday).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kasanuimura, according to one theory, is associated with the place of origin of Daijo-sai festival (first ceremonial offering of rice by newly-enthroned Emperor) and Toyoakari no sechie (one of the ceremonies at a seasonal holiday).</e>
<cmt>Daijo-sai festival としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>比定地については、檜原神社（桜井市 三輪）、多神社（磯城郡 田原本町多）、笠縫神社（磯城郡田原本町秦荘、秦楽寺境内南東隅）、笠山荒神社（桜井市笠）、多神社摂社の姫皇子神社、志貴御県坐神社（桜井市金屋）、小夫天神社（桜井市小夫）、穴師坐兵主神社（桜井市穴師）、飛鳥坐神社（高市郡 明日香村飛鳥）、磯城の厳橿の本（垂仁天皇紀5年3月条：所在地不詳）、等々。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are various candidates for its presumed locations: Hibara-jinja Shrine (Miwa, Sakurai City), O-jinja Shrine (O, Tawaramoto-cho, Shiki-gun), Kasanui-jinja Shrine (Hananosho, Tawaramoto-cho, Shiki-gun, the southeast corner of the grounds of Jinraku-ji Temple), Kasayamako-jinja Shrine (Kasa, Sakurai City), Himemiko-jinja Shrine which is a sessha (an auxiliary shrine dedicated to a deity closely related to that of a main shrine) of O-jinja Shrine, Shiki no miagata niimasu-jinja Shrine (Kanaya, Sakurai City), Obuten-jinja Shrine (Obu, Sakurai City), Anashi niimasuhyozu-jinja Shrine (Anashi, Sakurai City), Asuka niimasu-jinja Shrine (Asuka, Asuka-mura, Takaichi-gun), the foot of the Itsukashi in Shiki (noted in March of the fifth year of Emperor Suinin&apos;s reign: the address is unknown), and others.</e>
<cmt>垂仁天皇紀5年3月条は定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are various candidates for its presumed locations: Hibara-jinja Shrine (Miwa, Sakurai City), O-jinja Shrine (O, Tawaramoto-cho, Shiki-gun), Kasanui-jinja Shrine (Hananosho, Tawaramoto-cho, Shiki-gun, the southeast corner of the grounds of Jinraku-ji Temple), Kasayamako-jinja Shrine (Kasa, Sakurai City), Himemiko-jinja Shrine which is a sessha (an auxiliary shrine dedicated to a deity closely related to that of a main shrine) of O-jinja Shrine, Shiki no miagata niimasu-jinja Shrine (Kanaya, Sakurai City), Obuten-jinja Shrine (Obu, Sakurai City), Anashi niimasuhyozu-jinja Shrine (Anashi, Sakurai City), Asuka niimasu-jinja Shrine (Asuka, Asuka-mura, Takaichi-gun), the foot of the Itsukashi in Shiki (noted in March of the fifth year of Emperor Suinin&apos;s reign: the address is unknown), and others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are various candidates for its presumed locations: Hibara-jinja Shrine (Miwa, Sakurai City), O-jinja Shrine (O, Tawaramoto-cho, Shiki-gun), Kasanui-jinja Shrine (Hananosho, Tawaramoto-cho, Shiki-gun, the southeast corner of the grounds of Jinraku-ji Temple), Kasayamako-jinja Shrine (Kasa, Sakurai City), Himemiko-jinja Shrine which is a sessha (an auxiliary shrine dedicated to a deity closely related to that of a main shrine) of O-jinja Shrine, Shiki no miagata niimasu-jinja Shrine (Kanaya, Sakurai City), Obuten-jinja Shrine (Obu, Sakurai City), Anashi niimasuhyozu-jinja Shrine (Anashi, Sakurai City), Asuka niimasu-jinja Shrine (Asuka, Asuka-mura, Takaichi-gun), the foot of the Itsukashi in Shiki (noted in March of the fifth year of Emperor Suinin&apos;s reign: the address is unknown), and others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="5">
<j>檜原神社、笠山荒神社、小夫天神社（笠山荒神社よりもさらに東の山間部）、穴師坐兵主神社等はまさに山の中である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hibara-jinja Shrine, Kasayamako-jinja Shrine, Obuten-jinja Shrine (in the mountains further east of Kasayamako-jinja Shrine), Anashi niimasuhyozu-jinja Shrine are literally in the mountains.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hibara-jinja Shrine, Kasayamako-jinja Shrine, Obuten-jinja Shrine (in the mountains further east of Kasayamako-jinja Shrine), Anashi niimasuhyozu-jinja Shrine are literally in the mountains.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hibara-jinja Shrine, Kasayamako-jinja Shrine, Obuten-jinja Shrine (in the mountains further east of Kasayamako-jinja Shrine), Anashi niimasuhyozu-jinja Shrine are literally in the mountains.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="6">
<j>また、笠縫神社に関係する秦楽（じんらく）という名が、築山古墳 (大和高田市)（大和高田市築山字城山）の前方部眼下に広がる平地にも神楽（じんらく）という名で存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, the name Jinraku (秦楽) related to Kasanui-jinja Shrine exists in the flatland called Jinraku (神楽) that spreads in front of and just below the Tsukiyama Kofun (ancient tomb) (Yamatotakada City) (Aza Tsukiyama, Tsukiyama, Yamatotakada City).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, the name Jinraku (秦楽) related to Kasanui-jinja Shrine exists in the flatland called Jinraku (神楽) that spreads in front of and just below the Tsukiyama Kofun (ancient tomb) (Yamatotakada City) (Aza Tsukiyama, Tsukiyama, Yamatotakada City).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, the name Jinraku (秦楽) related to Kasanui-jinja Shrine exists in the flatland called Jinraku (神楽) that spreads in front of and just below the Tsukiyama Kofun (ancient tomb) (Yamatotakada City) (Aza Tsukiyama, Tsukiyama, Yamatotakada City).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>この神楽は、古くは秦楽と書いたとの説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to one theory this Jinraku (神楽) was written as Jinraku (秦楽) in the olden days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to one theory this Jinraku (神楽) was written as Jinraku (秦楽) in the olden days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to one theory this Jinraku (神楽) was written as Jinraku (秦楽) in the olden days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>何らかの関係を示唆しているかも知れない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It may be suggesting that they are related somehow.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It may suggest that they are related somehow.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It may suggest that they are related somehow.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="9">
<j>多神社から、摂社の屋就神命神社（やつぎかみのみことじんじゃ、やつき？しんめいじんじゃ：祭神 天明豊玉命）の方角を見ると、神楽、築山古墳の方角となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Yatsugikami no mikoto-jinja Shrine (also Yatsuki? Shinmei-jinja Shrine: the enshrined deity is Amenoakaru Toyotama no mikoto) is viewed from O-jinja Shrine, it is the direction in which Jinraku and Tsukiyama Kofun are located.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Yatsugikami no mikoto-jinja Shrine (also Yatsuki? Shinmei-jinja Shrine: the enshrined deity is Amenoakaru Toyotama no mikoto) is viewed from O-jinja Shrine, it is the direction in which Jinraku and Tsukiyama Kofun are located.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Yatsugikami no mikoto-jinja Shrine (also presumably Yatsuki Shinmei-jinja Shrine: the enshrined deity is Amenoakaru Toyotama no Mikoto) is viewed from O-jinja Shrine, it is the direction in which Jinraku and Tsukiyama Kofun are located.</e>
<cmt>?→presumably としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>実際には、理由はよく判らないが地元住民によって大切に残された「矢継ぎの森（やつぎのもり：屋就神命神社の杜でもある）」に隠されて見えない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In reality, however, they cannot be seen for some unknown reason because they are hidden by &apos;Yatsugi no Mori&apos; (Yatsugi Forest: the forest of Yatsugikami no mikoto-jinja Shrine), which has been protected with care by the local residents.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In reality, however, they cannot be seen for some unknown reason because they are hidden by &apos;Yatsugi no Mori&apos; (Yatsugi Forest: the forest of Yatsugikami no mikoto-jinja Shrine), which has been protected with care by the local residents.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In reality, however, they cannot be seen for some unknown reason because they are hidden by &apos;Yatsugi no Mori&apos; (Yatsugi Forest: the forest of Yatsugikami no mikoto-jinja Shrine), which has been protected with care by the local residents.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="11">
<j>また、もしかすると、昔は、多神社から姫皇子神社の方向を見ると、箸墓が見えたのかもしれない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Or, it is possible that Hashihaka was seen from O-jinja Shrine when viewed in the direction of Himemiko-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>箸墓とは箸墓古墳のことだと思われますが、原文通りにそのまま「箸墓」のみにしておきました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Or, it is possible that Hashihaka was seen from O-jinja Shrine when viewed in the direction of Himemiko-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Or, it is possible that Hashihaka (Kofun) was seen from O-jinja Shrine when viewed in the direction of Himemiko-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>箸墓（古墳）　と補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>元々、姫皇子神社は、多神社の奥（北：上座）に位置していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Himemiko-jinja Shrine was originally located further back (to the north: Kamiza (upper seat, seat of honor)) of O-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Himemiko-jinja Shrine was originally located further back (to the north: Kamiza (upper seat, seat of honor)) of O-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Himemiko-jinja Shrine was originally located further back (to the north: Kamiza (upper seat, seat of honor)) of O-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>前（南：下座）に移転させられている可能性がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, there is a possibility that it was relocated to the front (south, shimoza (lower seat)).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, there is a possibility that it was relocated to the front (south, shimoza (lower seat)).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, there is a possibility that it was relocated to the front (south, shimoza (lower seat)).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="14">
<j>多神社を笠縫邑の位置と比定するなら、これら古墳が、鏡に映した様に南北及び東西が逆になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If O-jinja were to be the presumed location of Kasanuimura, these ancient tombs&apos; locations would be a mirror image, with the south and the north, and the east and the west switched.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If O-jinja were to be the presumed location of Kasanuimura, these ancient tombs&apos; locations would be a mirror image, with the south and the north, and the east and the west switched.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If O-jinja Shrine were to be the presumed location of Kasanuimura, these ancient tombs&apos; locations would be a mirror image, with the south and the north, and the east and the west switched.</e>
<cmt>O-jinja Shrine としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>しかし、大嘗祭の悠紀殿（千木は伊勢神宮外宮の様に外削ぎ）、主基殿（千木は伊勢神宮内宮の様に内削ぎ）の起源とも関係している可能性がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it may be related to the origin of the Yuki-den building (the chigi (ornamental crossbeams on the gable of a Shinto shrine) is in the sotosogi (the ends of the chigi are terminated with a vertical cut) form just like in the Gegu (outer shrine) of Ise-jingu Shrine), and the Suki-den building (the chigi is in the uchisogi (the ends of the chigi are terminated with a horizontal cut) form, just as in the Naigu (inner shrine) of Ise-jingu Shrine) of Daijosai.</e>
<cmt>原文からは何が主語がなのか不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it may be related to the origin of the Yuki-den building (the chigi (ornamental crossbeams on the gable of a Shinto shrine) in the sotosogi (the ends of the chigi are terminated with a vertical cut) form just like in the Gegu (outer shrine) of Ise-jingu Shrine), and the Suki-den building (the chigi is in the uchisogi (the ends of the chigi are terminated with a horizontal cut) form, just as in the Naigu (inner shrine) of Ise-jingu Shrine) of Daijosai.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it may be related to the origin of the Yuki-den building (the chigi (ornamental crossbeams on the gable of a Shinto shrine) in the sotosogi (the ends of the chigi are terminated with a vertical cut) form just like in the Gegu (outer shrine) of Ise-jingu Shrine), and the Suki-den building (the chigi is in the uchisogi (the ends of the chigi are terminated with a horizontal cut) form, just as in the Naigu (inner shrine) of Ise-jingu Shrine) of Daijo-sai festival.</e>
<cmt>Daijo-sai festival としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="16">
<j>大阪の笠縫島</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kasanui-jima Island in Osaka</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kasanui-jima Island in Osaka</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kasanui-jima Island in Osaka</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>深江稲荷神社（大阪市 東成区深江南）には、付近の深江は笠縫氏の居住地で、大和の笠縫邑から移住してきた、との伝承がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A lore at Fukae Inari-jinja Shrine (Fukae-minami, Higashinari Ward, Osaka City) says that Fukae in the vicinity was the Kasanui family&apos;s residence, and that the family migrated from Kasanuimura in Yamato.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A legend at Fukae Inari-jinja Shrine (Fukae-minami, Higashinari Ward, Osaka City) says that Fukae in the vicinity was the Kasanui family&apos;s residence, and that the family migrated from Kasanuimura in Yamato.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A legend at Fukae Inari-jinja Shrine (Fukae-minami, Higashinari Ward, Osaka City) says that Fukae in the vicinity was the Kasanui family&apos;s residence, and that the family migrated from Kasanuimura in Yamato.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>万葉歌人高市黒人（たけちのくろと）が「四極山（しはつやま） うち越え見れば笠縫の島　漕ぎ隠る　棚無し小舟」と詠んだ様に、古代には、笠縫島といわれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As TAKECHI no Kuroto, a Manyo kajin (poet of Manyoshu (Collection of Ten Thousand Leaves)), read in his poem, &apos;Climbing over Mt. Shihatsu I see Kasanui Island and a simple little rowing forth to disappear,&apos; the area was called Kasanui-jima Island in the ancient times.</e>
<cmt>「四極山（しはつやま） うち越え見れば笠縫の島　漕ぎ隠る　棚無し小舟」定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As TAKECHI no Kuroto, a Manyo kajin (poet of Manyoshu (Collection of Ten Thousand Leaves)), read in his poem, &apos;Climbing over Mt. Shihatsu I see Kasanui Island and a simple little rowing forth to disappear,&apos; the area was called Kasanui-jima Island in the ancient times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As TAKECHI no Kuroto, a Manyo kajin (poet of Manyoshu (Collection of Ten Thousand Leaves)), read in his poem, &apos;Climbing over Mt. Shihatsu I see Kasanui Island and a simple little rowing forth to disappear,&apos; the area was called Kasanui-jima Island in the ancient times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>笠縫島は、現在の深江から東大阪市足代にかけて、入江に浮かんだ島であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kasanui-jima Island was an island located in an inlet between the present-day Fukae to Ajiro, Higashiosaka City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kasanui-jima Island was an island located in an inlet between the present-day Fukae to Ajiro, Higashiosaka City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kasanui-jima Island was an island located in an inlet between the present-day Fukae to Ajiro, Higashiosaka City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>笠の材料の確保のため、笠縫氏は島に住んだと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that the Kasanui family lived on the island in order to secure the materials for straw hats.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that the Kasanui family lived on the island in order to secure the materials for straw hats.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that the Kasanui family lived on the island in order to secure the materials for straw hats.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>もともと大和の笠縫邑も、同じような低湿地か、島状の土地だったのではないかとも推測される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, it is speculated that the original Kasanuimura in Yamato was either a low-lying wetland or a land shaped like an island.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, it is speculated that the original Kasanuimura in Yamato was either a low-lying wetland or a land shaped like an island.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, it is speculated that the original Kasanuimura in Yamato was either a low-lying wetland or a land shaped like an island.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="22">
<j>現在も大嘗祭に使用する笠は、この深江から天皇家へ献上されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even to this day, the straw hats used at Daijosai is presented to the Imperial Family from Fukae.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even to this day, the straw hats used at Daijosai is presented to the Imperial Family from Fukae.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even to this day, the straw hats used at Daijo-sai festival is presented to the Imperial Family from Fukae.</e>
<cmt>Daijo-sai festival としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>また、深江は、皇祖の御神鏡に関係する鋳物師とも関係が深い土地とのことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, Fukae is said to be a region that is closely associated with a caster related to the goshinkyo mirror (sacred mirror) of the Imperial ancestor.</e>
<cmt>御神鏡は定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, Fukae is said to be a region that is closely associated with a caster related to the goshinkyo mirror (sacred mirror) of the Imperial ancestor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, Fukae is said to be a region that is closely associated with a caster related to the goshinkyo mirror (sacred mirror) of the Imperial ancestor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>鏡作神社（磯城郡田原本町八尾　等周辺）とも関係の可能性がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a possibility that it is also related to Kagamitsukuri-jinja Shrine (including areas around Yao, Tawaramoto-cho, Shiki-gun).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a possibility that it is also related to Kagamitsukuri-jinja Shrine (including areas around Yao, Tawaramoto-cho, Shiki-gun).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a possibility that it is also related to Kagamitsukuri-jinja Shrine (including areas around Yao, Tawaramoto-cho, Shiki-gun).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Tiyoringo(id:70026), Point136(id:211299), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>