<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>長髄彦</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagasunehiko</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagasunehiko</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagasunehiko</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>長髄彦（ながすねひこ）は、日本神話に登場する人物。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagasunehiko is a character that appears in Japanese mythology.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagasunehiko is a character that appears in Japanese mythology.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagasunehiko is a character that appears in Japanese mythology.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>『古事記』では那賀須泥毘古と表記され、また登美能那賀須泥毘古（トミノナガスネヒコ）、登美毘古（トミビコ）とも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;The Kojiki&quot; (Records of Ancient Matters) he is written as Nagasunehiko, but he is also called Tominonagasunehiko as well as Tomibiko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;The Kojiki&quot; (Records of Ancient Matters) he is written as Nagasunehiko, but he is also called Tominonagasunehiko as well as Tomibiko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;The Kojiki&quot; (Records of Ancient Matters) he is written as Nagasunehiko, but he is also called Tominonagasunehiko as well as Tomibiko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>神武東征の場面で、大和国地方で東征に抵抗した豪族の長として描かれている人物。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is portrayed in the scene of Jinmu Tosei (Emperor Jinmu&apos;s expedition to the east) as the head of a local ruling family in the Yamato Province area who opposed Jinmu&apos;s expedition to the east.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is portrayed in the scene of Jinmu Tosei (Emperor Jinmu&apos;s expedition to the east) as the head of a local ruling family in the Yamato Province area who opposed Jinmu&apos;s expedition to the east.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is portrayed in the scene of Jinmu Tosei (Emperor Jinmu&apos;s expedition to the east) as the head of a local ruling family in the Yamato Province area who opposed Jinmu&apos;s expedition to the east.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>神武天皇が浪速国青雲の白肩津に到着したのち、孔舎衛坂（くさえのさか）で迎え撃ち、このときの戦いで天皇の兄の五瀬命は矢に当たって負傷し、後に死亡している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He attacked the invading enemies at Kusaenosaka after Emperor Jinmu arrived at Shirakata no tsu (Bay of Shirakata) in 青雲, Namihaya Province, and Emperor&apos;s older brother, Itsuse no Mikoto, was injured by a shot of an arrow during this battle, and he later died.</e>
<cmt>「青雲」読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He attacked the invading enemies at Kusaenosaka after Emperor Jinmu arrived at Shirakata no tsu (Bay of Shirakata) in 青雲, Namihaya Province, and the Emperor&apos;s older brother, Itsuse no Mikoto, was injured by an arrow during this battle, and later died.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He attacked the invading enemies at Kusaenosaka after Emperor Jinmu arrived at Shirakata no tsu (Bay of Shirakata) in 青雲, Namihaya Province, and the Emperor&apos;s older brother, Itsuse no Mikoto, was injured by an arrow during this battle, and later died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>その後、八十梟帥や兄磯城を討った皇軍と再び戦うことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He later fought again, against the Imperial army who killed Yasotakeru and Eshiki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He later fought again, against the Imperial army who killed Yasotakeru and Eshiki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He later fought again, against the Imperial army who killed Yasotakeru and Eshiki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>このとき、金色の鳶が飛んできて、神武天皇の弓弭に止まり、長髄彦の軍は眼が眩み、戦うことができなくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time, a golden kite flew by and perched itself on the nock of Emperor Jinmu&apos;s bow, and Nagasunehiko&apos;s army was blinded and could not fight.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this time, a golden kite flew by and perched itself on the nock of Emperor Jinmu&apos;s bow, and Nagasunehiko&apos;s army was blinded and could not fight.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this time, a golden kite flew by and perched itself on the nock of Emperor Jinmu&apos;s bow, and Nagasunehiko&apos;s army was blinded and could not fight.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>長髄彦は神武天皇に「昔、天つ神の子が天の磐船に乗って降臨した。名を櫛玉饒速日命という。私の妹の三炊屋媛を娶わせて、可美真手という子も生まれた。ゆえに私は饒速日命を君として仕えている。天つ神の子がどうして二人いようか。どうして天つ神の子であると称して人の土地を奪おうとしているのか」とその疑いを述べた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagasunehiko addressed his question to Emperor Jinmu, &quot;Long ago, a child of Amatsu kami (god of heaven) descended, riding on Ame no iwafune (rock boat of heaven). His name was Kushitama Nigihayahi no Mikoto. He married my younger sister, Mikashigiyahime, and a child named Umashimade was born. Therefore, I serve Nigihayahi no Mikoto as my lord. How could there be 2 children of God. How can you try to steal other people&apos;s land when you call yourself Amatsu kami&apos;s son?&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagasunehiko addressed his question to Emperor Jinmu, &quot;Long ago, a child of Amatsu kami (god of heaven) descended, riding on Ame no iwafune (rock boat of heaven). His name was Kushitama Nigihayahi no Mikoto. He married my younger sister, Mikashigiyahime, and a child named Umashimade was born. Therefore, I serve Nigihayahi no Mikoto as my lord. How could there be 2 children of God. How can you try to steal other people&apos;s land when you call yourself Amatsu kami&apos;s son?&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagasunehiko addressed his question to Emperor Jinmu, &quot;Long ago, a child of Amatsu kami (god of heaven) descended, riding on Ame no iwafune (rock boat of heaven). His name was Kushitama Nigihayahi no Mikoto. He married my younger sister, Mikashigiyahime, and a child named Umashimade was born. Therefore, I serve Nigihayahi no Mikoto as my lord. How could there be 2 children of God. How can you try to steal other people&apos;s land when you call yourself Amatsu kami&apos;s son?&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>天皇は天つ神の子である証拠として、天の羽羽矢と歩靱を見せ、長髄彦は恐れ畏まったが、改心することはなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emperor showed Ame no haha ya (the heavenly feathered arrows) and Kachiyuki (Japanese quiver) as his proof of being Amatsu kami&apos;s son, and even though Nagasunehiko was awed, he did not reform himself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emperor showed Ame no haha ya (the heavenly feathered arrows) and Kachiyuki (Japanese quiver) as his proof of being Amatsu kami&apos;s son, and even though Nagasunehiko was awed, he did not reform himself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emperor showed Ame no haha ya (the heavenly feathered arrows) and Kachiyuki (Japanese quiver) as his proof of being Amatsu kami&apos;s son, and even though Nagasunehiko was awed, he did not change his views.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>そのため、間を取り持つことが無理だと知った饒速日命（ニギハヤヒノミコト）に殺された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, he was killed by Nigihayahi no Mikoto, who realized that it was impossible to mediate between the Emperor and Nagasunehiko.</e>
<cmt>原文の「間を取り持つ」は「天皇と長髄彦の間を取り持つ」として訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, he was killed by Nigihayahi no Mikoto, who realized that it was impossible to mediate between the Emperor and Nagasunehiko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, he was killed by Nigihayahi no Mikoto, who realized that it was impossible to mediate between the Emperor and Nagasunehiko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>饒速日命の手によって殺された、或いは失脚後に故地に留まり死去したともされているが、実際は同胞である和邇氏（海神族）の協力を経て北上し、時の畿内の有力豪族安日彦（アビヒコ）とともに青森県は弘前に落ち着いたという説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that he was killed by the hands of Nigihayahi no Mikoto, and alternatively, it is also said that he died after remaining in the area where he eventually died after his failure, but there are theories that imply that in actuality, he advanced north with the support of the Wani clan (Watatsumi family), who was his sibling clan, and he settled in Hirosaki, Aomori Prefecture, with Abihiko, who was a powerful ruling clan in Kinai region then, and there is a lore regarding the potential site of his death that hints the possibility of his involvement in the eastern expedition because he performed a Shinto ritual, due to the political instability prior to the eastern expedition, in which an arrow was aimed toward the sun, and there is also a theory that says that he committed suicide because of the Yaoi clan who claimed to be the descendant.</e>
<cmt>原文が長く、訳文の意味が読み取れにくくなってます。適切な場所で区切らないと意味が伝わりません。「東征前に」で始まる文章、意味不明。「自らを後裔と主張する」は誰の後裔なのか意味不明。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that he was killed by the hands of Nigihayahi no Mikoto, and alternatively, it is also said that he died after remaining in the area where he eventually died after his failure, but there are theories that imply that in actuality, he advanced north with the support of the Wani clan (Watatsumi family), who was his sibling clan, and he settled in Hirosaki, Aomori Prefecture, with Abihiko, who was a powerful ruling clan in Kinai region then, and there is a lore regarding the potential site of his death that hints the possibility of his involvement in the eastern expedition because he performed a Shinto ritual, due to the political instability prior to the eastern expedition, in which an arrow was aimed toward the sun, and there is also a theory that says that he committed suicide because of the Yaoi clan who claimed to be the descendant.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that he was killed by the hands of Nigihayahi no Mikoto, and alternatively, it is also said that he eventually died after his failure at his homeland, but there are theories that imply that in actuality, he advanced north with the support of the Wani clan (Watatsumi family), who was his sibling clan, and he settled in Hirosaki, Aomori Prefecture, with Abihiko, who was a powerful regional ruler in the Kinai region at that time.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>また、東征前に政情不安から太陽に対して弓を引く神事を行ったという東征にも関与していた可能性をも匂わせる故地の候補地の伝承、自らを後裔と主張する矢追氏による自死したという説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is also lore regarding the potential site of his death that hints at the possibility of his involvement in the eastern expedition because he performed a Shinto ritual prior to the eastern expedition in which an arrow was aimed toward the sun to solve political instability and there is also a theory passed down by Yaoi clan, who claim to be his descendants, that says he committed suicide.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="12">
<j>旧添下郡鳥貝郷（現生駒市北部・奈良市富雄駅地方）付近、あるいは桜井市付近に勢力を持った豪族という説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is also a theory that says that he was from a local ruling clan that had power in the area around what was formerly Torikai-go, Soejimo-gun (present-day northern Ikoma City, area around Tomio Station, Nara City), or in the area near Sakurai City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is also a theory that says that he was from a local ruling clan that had power in the area around what was formerly Torikai-go, Soejimo-gun (present-day northern Ikoma City, area around Tomio Station, Nara City), or in the area near Sakurai City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is also a theory that says that he was from a local ruling clan that had power in the area around what was formerly Torikai-go, Soejimo-gun (present-day northern Ikoma City, area around Tomio Station, Nara City), or in the area near Sakurai City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>なお、長髄とは記紀では邑の名であるとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kiki (the Kojiki and Nihonshoki), Nagasune is said to be the name of a large village.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Kiki (the Kojiki and Nihonshoki), Nagasune is said to be the name of a large village.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Kiki (the Kojiki and Nihonshoki), Nagasune is said to be the name of a large village.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="14">
<j>登美夜毘売（トミヤヒメ）、あるいは三炊屋媛（ミカシギヤヒメ）ともいう自らの妹を、天の磐舟で、斑鳩の峰白庭山に降臨した饒速日命（ニギハヤヒノミコト）の妻とし、仕えるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He made his younger sister, Tomiyahime, also known as Mikashigiyahime, the wife of Nigihayahi no Mikoto, who rode Amano iwafune and descended down on a mountain in Ikaruga called Mt. Shiraniwa, and Nagasunehiko began to serve him.</e>
<cmt>原文にはありませんが、「仕えるようになる」は「長髄彦が（饒速日命に）使えるようになる」と訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He made his younger sister, Tomiyahime, also known as Mikashigiyahime, the wife of Nigihayahi no Mikoto, who rode Amano iwafune and descended down on a mountain in Ikaruga called Mt. Shiraniwa, and Nagasunehiko began to serve him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He made his younger sister, Tomiyahime, also known as Mikashigiyahime, the wife of Nigihayahi no Mikoto, who rode a Amano iwafune(boat) and descended down on a mountain in Ikaruga called Mt. Shiraniwa, and Nagasunehiko began to serve him.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="15">
<j>この子孫が聖徳太子と共に物部守屋を討った迹見赤檮（トミノイチイ）だとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that his descendant was Tominoichii who defeated MONONOBE no Moriya with Prince Shotoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that his descendant was Tominoichii who defeated MONONOBE no Moriya with Prince Shotoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that his descendant was Tominoichii who defeated MONONOBE no Moriya with Prince Shotoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>中世、戦国の武将山形の織田家（後に織田信長を輩出）や仙台の伊達家が長髄彦の子孫であると言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the Oda family (which later turned out Nobunaga ODA) of Yamagata, and the Date family of Sendai, who were both busho (Japanese military commanders) during the Middle Ages and the Period of Warring Sates, were Nagasunehiko&apos;s descendants.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the Oda family (which later turned out Nobunaga ODA) of Yamagata, and the Date family of Sendai, who were both busho (Japanese military commanders) during the Middle Ages and the Period of Warring Sates, were Nagasunehiko&apos;s descendants.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the Oda family (which later turned out Nobunaga ODA) of Yamagata, and the Date family of Sendai, who were both busho (Japanese military commanders) during the Middle Ages and the Period of Warring Sates, were Nagasunehiko&apos;s descendants.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 MIK(id:61548), Sat666(id:127263), Jitaku(id:27778), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), Nnh(id:474), 代言人(id:33675), 水野白楓(id:22811), Shimoxx(id:9332), 味っ子(id:17086), 冨中仙人(id:11065), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>