<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>シオツチノオジ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shiotsuchinooji</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shiotsuchinooji</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shiotsuchinooji</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>シオツチノオジ（シホツチノヲヂ）は、日本神話に登場する神 (神道)であり塩竈明神とも言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shiotsuchinooji (Shihotsuchinooji) ia a deity (Shinto religion) who appears in the Japanese Mythology and he is also called Shiogama-myojin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shiotsuchinooji (Shihotsuchinooji) is a deity (in the Shinto religion) who appears in the Japanese Mythology and is also called Shiogama-myojin.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。スペルミスを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shiotsuchinooji (Shihotsuchinooji) is a deity (in the Shinto religion) who appears in the Japanese Mythology and is also called Shiogama-myojin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>古事記では塩椎神（しおつちのかみ）、日本書紀では塩土老翁・塩筒老翁、先代旧事本紀では塩土老翁と表記する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His name is written as 塩椎神 (Shiotsuchinokami) in Kojiki (The Record of Ancient Matters), 塩土老翁 (Shitsuchinooji) or 塩筒老翁 (Shiotsutsunooji) in Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan) and 塩土老翁 (Shiotsuchinooji) in Sendai Kyujihongi (Ancient Japnese History) respectively.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His name is written as Shiotsuchinokami in Kojiki (The Record of Ancient Matters), Shitsuchinooji or Shiotsutsunooji in Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan), and Shiotsuchinooji in Sendai Kyujihongi (Ancient Japnese History) respectively.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。漢字を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His name is written as Shiotsuchinokami in Kojiki (The Record of Ancient Matters), Shitsuchinooji or Shiotsutsunooji in Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan), and Shiotsuchinooji in Sendai Kyujihongi (Ancient Japanese History) respectively.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>別名 事勝因勝長狭神（ことかつくにかつなぎさ）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His another name is Kotokatsukunikatsunagisa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His is also called Kotokatsukunikatsunagisa.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His is also called Kotokatsukunikatsunagisa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>神話での記述</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Description in the Mythology</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Description in Mythology</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Description in Mythology</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>日本書紀の天孫降臨の説話において、日向の高千穂の峰に天降ったニニギが笠狭崎に至った時に事勝因勝長狭神が登場し、ニニギに自分の国を奉っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the story of tensonkorin (the descent to earth of the grandson of sun goddess) described in Nihonshoki, when Ninigi arrived at Kasasa-no-misaki Cape after descending to Takachiho-no-mine in Hyuga, Kotokatsukunikatsunagisa appeared and presented his own province to Ninigi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the story of tensonkorin (the descent to earth of the grandson of sun goddess) described in Nihonshoki, when Ninigi arrived at Kasasa-no-misaki Cape after descending to Takachiho-no-mine in Hyuga, Kotokatsukunikatsunagisa appeared and presented his own province to Ninigi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the story of tensonkorin (the descent to earth of the grandson of sun goddess) described in Nihonshoki, when Ninigi arrived at Kasasa-no-misaki Cape after descending to Takachiho no mine in Hyuga, Kotokatsukunikatsunagisa appeared and presented his own province to Ninigi.</e>
<cmt>ハイフン削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>一書では、事勝因勝長狭神の別名が塩土老翁で、イザナギの子であるとしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Issho (a book quoted in Nihonshoki), Shiotsuchinooji is the another name of Kotokatsukunikatsunagisa and he is regarded as a son of Izanagi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Issho (a book quoted in Nihonshoki), Shiotsuchinooji is another name of Kotokatsukunikatsunagisa and he is regarded as being a son of Izanagi.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Issho (a book quoted in Nihonshoki), Shiotsuchinooji is another name of Kotokatsukunikatsunagisa and he is regarded as being a son of Izanagi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>海幸山幸の説話においては、ホデリ（海幸彦）の釣針を失くして悲嘆にくれるホオリ（山幸彦）の前に現れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the story of Umisachi Yamasachi, he appeared in front of Hoori (Yamasachihiko) who was involved in grief for losing Hoderi&apos;s (Umisachihiko&apos;s) fishhook.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the story of Umisachi Yamasachi, he appeared in front of Hoori (Yamasachihiko) who was grieving after losing Hoderi&apos;s (Umisachihiko&apos;s) fishhook.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the story of Umisachi Yamasachi, he appeared in front of Hoori (Yamasachihiko) who was grieving after losing Hoderi&apos;s (Umisachihiko&apos;s) fishhook.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>ホオリから事情を聞くと小舟（または目の詰まった竹籠）を出してホオリを乗せる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After hearing the state of things from Hoori, he gave Hoori a ride on a small boat (or a banboo basket that is closely stitched).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After hearing the situation from Hoori, he gave Hoori a ride on a small boat (or a tightly woven bamboo basket).</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After hearing the situation from Hoori, he gave Hoori a ride on a small boat (or a tightly woven bamboo basket).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>そして、そのまま進めば良い潮路に乗って海神の宮に着くから、宮の前の木の上で待っていれば、あとはワタツミが良いようにしてくれると告げる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, he gave advice to Hoori by saying &quot;Go ahead and you will reach at the palace of Watatsumi no kami with the help of favorable tide, and you only need to wait on the tree situated in front of the palace until Watatsumi takes action in favor of you&quot;.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, he gave advice to Hoori by saying &quot;Go ahead and you will reach the palace of Watatsumi no kami with the help of a favorable tide, and you only need to wait on top of the tree situated in front of the palace until Watatsumi takes action in favor of you&quot;.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, he gave advice to Hoori by saying &quot;Go ahead and you will reach the palace of Watatsumi no kami with the help of a favorable tide, and you only need to wait on top of the tree situated in front of the palace until Watatsumi takes action in favor of you.&quot;</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>日本書紀本文の神武東征の記述では、塩筒老翁が東に良い土地があると言ったことから神武天皇は東征を決意したとある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the story of Jinmu tosei (story in Japanese myth about the first generation of the Imperial family), the Emperor Jinmu made up his mind to go to east because Shiotsutsunooji said that there was good land in east.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the story of Jinmu tosei (a story in Japanese mythology about the first generation of the Imperial family), the Emperor Jinmu made up his mind to go to East because Shiotsutsunooji said that there was good land in the East.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the story of Jinmu tosei (a story in Japanese mythology about the first generation of the Imperial family) of Nihonshoki, the Emperor Jinmu made up his mind to go to East because Shiotsutsunooji said that there was good land in the East.</e>
<cmt>of Nihonshoki補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="11">
<j>解説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Explanation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Explanation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Explanation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>名前の「シホツチ」は「潮つ霊」「潮つ路」であり、潮流を司る神、航海の神である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As indicated by his name &quot;Shihotsuchi&quot;, which means &quot;shiotsutama (soul of tide)&quot; and/or &quot;shiotsuji (route of tide)&quot;, he is a deity presiding tide, namely a deity of navigation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As indicated by his name &quot;Shihotsuchi&quot;, which means &quot;shiotsutama (soul of tides)&quot; and/or &quot;shiotsuji (route of tides)&quot;, he is a deity presiding over the tides, namely a deity of navigation.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As indicated by his name &apos;Shihotsuchi,&apos; which means &apos;shiotsutama (soul of tides)&apos; and/or &apos;shiotsuji (route of tides),&apos; he is a deity presiding over the tides, namely a deity of navigation.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;にコンマを&apos;の中に移動</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="13">
<j>記紀神話におけるシオツチノオジは、登場人物に情報を提供し、とるべき行動を示すという重要な役割を持っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kiki shinwa (the mythology described in Kojiki and Nihonshoki), Shiotsuchinooji plays an important role of providing information to the characters and suggesting the way they should take.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Kiki shinwa (the mythology described in Kojiki and Nihonshoki), Shiotsuchinooji plays an important role of providing information to the characters and suggesting the way they should take.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Kiki shinwa (the mythology described in Kojiki and Nihonshoki), Shiotsuchinooji plays an important role of providing information to the characters and suggesting the way they should take.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>海に関する神が知恵を授けるという説話には、ギリシャ神話などに登場する「海の老人」との類似が見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such story in which a sea-related deity provides a suggestion is similar to the story of &quot;The Old Man of Sea&quot; which appears in the Greek Mythology etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such a story in which a sea-related deity provides a suggestion is similar to the story of &quot;The Old Man of the Sea&quot; which appears in Greek Mythology etc.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such a story in which a sea-related deity provides a suggestion is similar to the story of &apos;The Old Man of the Sea&apos; which appears in Greek Mythology etc.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="15">
<j>また、シオツチノオジは製塩の神としても信仰されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, Shiotsuchinooji is worshipped as a deity of salt manufacture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, Shiotsuchinooji is also worshipped as the deity of salt manufacture.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, Shiotsuchinooji is also worshipped as the deity of salt manufacture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>シオツチノオジを祀る神社の総本社である鹽竈神社（宮城県塩竈市）の社伝では、タケミカヅチとフツヌシは、塩土老翁の先導で諸国を平定した後に塩竈にやってきたとする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the shrine history of Shiogama-jinja Shrine (Shiogama City, Miyagi Prefecture), the head shrine of shrines that enshrine Shiotsuchinooji, Takemikazuchi and Futsunushi came to Shiogama after they had conquered various provinces with the guidance of Shiotsuchinooji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the shrine history of Shiogama-jinja Shrine (Shiogama City, Miyagi Prefecture), the head shrine of shrines that enshrine Shiotsuchinooji, Takemikazuchi and Futsunushi came to Shiogama after they had conquered various provinces with the guidance of Shiotsuchinooji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the shrine history of Shiogama-jinja Shrine (Shiogama City, Miyagi Prefecture), the head shrine of shrines that enshrine Shiotsuchinooji, Takemikazuchi and Futsunushi came to Shiogama after they had conquered various provinces with the guidance of Shiotsuchinooji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>武甕槌神と経津主神はすぐに去って行くが塩土老翁はこの地にとどまり、人々に漁業や製塩法を教えたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that although Takemikazuchi-no kami and Futsunushi-no-kami left Shiogama soon, Shiotsuchinooji remained there and taught people fishery and the technology of salt manufacture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that although Takemikazuchi-no kami and Futsunushi-no-kami soon left Shiogama, Shiotsuchinooji remained there and taught people fishery and the method of manufacturing salt.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that although Takemikazuchi no kami and Futsunushi no kami soon left Shiogama, Shiotsuchinooji remained there and taught people fishery and the method of manufacturing salt.</e>
<cmt>ハイフン削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="18">
<j>海の神、製塩の神、呪術・予言の神などとして信仰されており、各地の塩釜神社で祀られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is worshipped as a deity of sea, a deity of salt manufacture as well as a deity of magic/prediction and is being enshrined at Shiogama-jinja Shrines in various places.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is worshipped as a deity of sea, a deity of salt manufacture as well as a deity of magic/prediction and is enshrined at Shiogama-jinja Shrines in various places.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。不要な動詞を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is worshipped as a deity of sea, a deity of salt manufacture as well as a deity of magic/prediction and is enshrined at Shiogama-jinja Shrines in various places.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Izayohi(id:13095), Nnh(id:474), Tribot(id:186681), Htks(id:24185), 沢田(id:40580), Hatsune(id:26654), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>