<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>賀茂建角身命</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kamo Taketsunumi no mikoto</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kamo Taketsunumi no mikoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kamo Taketsunumi no mikoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>賀茂建角身命（かもたけつぬみのみこと）は、日本神話に登場する神 (神道)である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kamo Taketsunumi no mikoto&quot; is a god (Shinto) appearing in Japanese myths.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kamo Taketsunumi no mikoto&quot; is a god (Shinto) appearing in Japanese mythology.</e>
<cmt>terminalogy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Kamo Taketsunumi no mikoto&quot; is a god (Shinto) appearing in Japanese mythology.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>山城国の賀茂氏（賀茂県主）の始祖であり、賀茂御祖神社（下鴨神社）の祭神として知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is the originator of the Kamo clan (Kamo no Agatanushi) in Yamashiro Province, and is known as the enshrined deity of Kamomioya-jinja Shrine (Shimogamo-jinja Shrine).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is the originator of the Kamo clan (Kamo no Agatanushi) in Yamashiro Province, and is known as the enshrined deity of Kamomioya-jinja Shrine (the Shimogamo-jinja Shrine).</e>
<cmt>inserted &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is the originator of the Kamo clan (Kamo no Agatanushi) in Yamashiro Province, and is known as the enshrined deity of Kamomioya-jinja Shrine (the Shimogamo-jinja Shrine).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>『新撰姓氏録』によれば、賀茂建角身命はカミムスビ（かみむすびのみこと）の孫である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the &quot;Shinsen Shoji Roku,&quot; Kamo Taketsunumi no mikoto is the grandchild of Kamimusubi no mikoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the &quot;Shinsen Shoji Roku,&quot; Kamo Taketsunumi no mikoto is the grandchild of Kamimusubi no mikoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the &quot;Shinsen Shoji Roku,&quot; Kamo Taketsunumi no mikoto is the grandchild of Kamimusubi no mikoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>神武東征の際、タカミムスビ・天照大神の命を受けて日向の曾の峰に天降り、大和国の葛木山に至り、八咫烏に化身して神武天皇を先導した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Jinmu tosei (story in Japanese myth about the first generation of the Imperial family), he was ordered by Takamimusubi no mikoto and Amaterasu Omikami to descend from heaven in Hinomine, Yamato Province, to arrive in the Katsuragi-san Mountain in Yamato Province, and incarnated as a Yatagarasu (mythical raven who aided Emperor Jinmu on his eastern expedition) to lead Emperor Jinmu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Jinmu tosei (story in Japanese mythology about the first generation of the Imperial family), he was ordered by Takamimusubi no mikoto and Amaterasu Omikami to descend from heaven in Hinomine, Yamato Province, to arrive on Mount Katsuragi-san in Yamato Province, and was incarnated as a Yatagarasu (mythical raven who aided Emperor Jinmu on his eastern expedition) and to lead Emperor Jinmu.</e>
<cmt>wording corrected for clarity and correctness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Jinmu tosei (story in Japanese mythology about the first generation of the Imperial family), he was ordered by Takamimusubi no mikoto and Amaterasu Omikami to descend from heaven in Hinomine, Yamato Province, to arrive on Mount Katsuragi-san in Yamato Province, and was incarnated as a Yatagarasu (mythical raven who aided Emperor Jinmu on his eastern expedition) and to lead Emperor Jinmu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>『山城国風土記』（逸文）によれば、大和の葛木山から山代の岡田の賀茂（岡田鴨神社がある）に至り、葛野河（高野川）と賀茂河（鴨川）が合流する地点（下鴨神社がある）に鎮まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Yamashiro no kuni Fudoki&quot; (lost writings), he went from Katsuragi-san Mountain in Yamato Province to Okada no kamo in Yamashiro Province (where Okada kamo-jinja Shrine is), and settled where the Kadono-gawa River (Takano-gawa River) and Kamo-gawa River meet (where Shimogamo-jinja Shrine is located).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Yamashiro no kuni Fudoki&quot; (lost writings), he went from Mount Katsuragi-san in Yamato Province to Okada no kamo in Yamashiro Province (where the Okada kamo-jinja Shrine is), and settled where the Kadono-gawa River (Takano-gawa River) and Kamo-gawa River meet (where Shimogamo-jinja Shrine is located).</e>
<cmt>wording corrected for clarity and correctness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Yamashiro no kuni Fudoki&quot; (lost writings), he went from Mount Katsuragi-san in Yamato Province to Okada no kamo in Yamashiro Province (where the Okada kamo-jinja Shrine is), and settled where the Kadono-gawa River (Takano-gawa River) and Kamo-gawa River meet (where Shimogamo-jinja Shrine is located).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>賀茂建角身命には建玉依比古命と建玉依比売命の2柱の御子神がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kamo Taketsunumi no mikoto has two mikogami (the child god in a shrine where parent-child gods are enshrined), Taketamayorihiko no mikoto and Taketamayorihime no mikoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kamo Taketsunumi no mikoto has two mikogami (the child god in a shrine where parent-child gods are enshrined), Taketamayorihiko no mikoto and Taketamayorihime no mikoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kamo Taketsunumi no mikoto has two mikogami (the child god in a shrine where parent-child gods are enshrined), Taketamayorihiko no mikoto and Taketamayorihime no mikoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>建玉依比古命は後に賀茂県主となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taketamayorihiko no mikoto later becomes Kamo no Agatanushi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taketamayorihiko no mikoto later becomes Kamo no Agatanushi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taketamayorihiko no mikoto later becomes Kamo no Agatanushi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>タマヨリビメ他のタマヨリビメは、大山咋神が丹塗矢に化身して賀茂別雷命（賀茂別雷神社の祭神）を産ませたとの記述がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Regarding Tamayoribime, it is described that Oyamakui no kami, who incarnated as a red arrow, made her give birth to Kamowake ikazuchi no mikoto (enshrined deity of Kamowake Ikazuchi-jinja Shrine).</e>
<cmt>「タマヨリビメ他のタマヨリビメは」は「タマヨリビメは」と読み替えて訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regarding Tamayoribime, it is described as Oyamakui no kami, who incarnated as a red arrow, and this made her give birth to Kamowake ikazuchi no mikoto (the enshrined deity of Kamowake Ikazuchi-jinja Shrine).</e>
<cmt>revised wording for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &quot;Yamashiro no kuni Fudoki&quot; also describes how Oyamakui no kami appeared to Tamayoribime in the form of a red arrow and made her give birth to Kamowake ikazuchi no mikoto (the enshrined deity of Kamowake Ikazuchi-jinja Shrine).</e>
<cmt>和文が不鮮明ですが、できるかぎり明確になるように訳し直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Nnh(id:474), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>