<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>神社局</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bureau of Shinto shrines</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bureau of Shinto shrines</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bureau of Shrines (Jinja kyoku)</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>神社局（じんじゃきょく）は、明治政府に置かれた局の一つである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bureau of Shinto shrines was one of the bureaus of the Meiji government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bureau of Shinto shrines was one of the bureaus of the Meiji government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Bureau of Shrines was one of the bureaus of the Meiji government.</e>
<cmt>Bureau of Shinto shrines を The Bureau of Shrines に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>内務省 (日本)に置かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bureau was established in the prewar Ministry of Home Affairs (Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bureau was established in the prewar Ministry of Home Affairs (Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bureau was established in the prewar Ministry of Home Affairs (Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>神社および神官、神職に関する行政事項をつかさどった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It took charge of administrative matters relating to Shinto shrines, Shinto priests and Shinto priesthood.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It took charge of administrative matters relating to Shinto shrines, Shinto priests and Shinto priesthood.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It took charge of administrative matters relating to Shinto shrines, Shinto priests and Shinto priesthood.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>明治33年4月26日、内務省社寺局が廃され、その事務は神社局と宗教局とにわかれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 26, 1900 after the Bureau of shrines and temples was discontinued, the work was divided into Bureau of Shinto shrines and Bureau of Religions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 26, 1900, after the Bureau of shrines and temples was discontinued, the work was divided into Bureau of Shinto shrines and Bureau of Religions.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On April 26, 1900, after the Bureau of Shrines and Temples, the Ministry of Home Affairs was discontinued, the work was divided into the Bureau of Shrines and the Bureau of Religions.</e>
<cmt>Bureau of shrines and temples を Bureau of Shrines and Temples に修正しました。※出典：http://www2.kokugakuin.ac.jp/ijcc/wp/glossary/def_S.html「内務省」訳漏れのため the Ministry of Home Affairs を追記して対応しました。Bureau of Shrines, Bureau of Religions の前にそれぞれ定冠詞を追記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>すなわち、内務省官制を改正し、同省に7局を置き、地方局の前に神社局を加え、社寺局を改めて宗教局とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In other words, the Ministry of Home Affairs were reorganized, to establish seven bureaus in the ministry, add Bureau of Shinto shrines to Bureau of Areas, and renamed Bureau of shrines and temples as Bureau of Religions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In other words, the Ministry of Home Affairs was reorganized to establish seven bureaus in the ministry, add Bureau of Shinto shrines to Bureau of Areas, and rename Bureau of shrines and temples as Bureau of Religions.</e>
<cmt>were-&gt;was; renamed-&gt;rename</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In other words, the Ministry of Home Affairs was reorganized to establish seven bureaus in the ministry, add Bureau of Shrines to Bureau of Areas, and rename Bureau of Shrines and Temples as Bureau of Religions.</e>
<cmt>Bureau of shrines and temples を Bureau of Shrines and Temples に修正しました。※出典：http://www2.kokugakuin.ac.jp/ijcc/wp/glossary/def_S.html</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="6">
<j>局長1人、書記官1人、考証官1人、技師2人、事務官1人、考証官補2人などの職員が置かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bureau included the staff of one director, one secretary, one investigator, one engineer, one clerk, and two assistant investigators.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bureau&apos;s staff included one director, one secretary, one investigator, one engineer, one clerk and two assistant investigators.</e>
<cmt>the bureau&apos;s staff; punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bureau&apos;s staff included one director, one secretary, one investigator, two engineers, one clerk and two assistant investigators.</e>
<cmt>one engineer を two engineers に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="7">
<j>1940年(昭和15年)11月9日、神祇院設置に伴い廃止。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On November 9, 1940, the bureau was discontinued upon the establishment of Jingiin (Institute of Divinities).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 9, 1940, the bureau was discontinued upon the establishment of Jingiin (Institute of Divinities).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On November 9, 1940, the bureau was discontinued upon the establishment of Jingiin (Institute of Divinities).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kafuka1964(id:105407), Tomzo(id:16777), Component(id:146478), 弥(id:61590), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>