<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>山岳信仰</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sangaku-shinko Faith</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sangaku-shinko Faith</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sangaku-shinko Faith</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>山岳信仰（さんがくしんこう）とは、山を神聖視し崇拝の対象とする信仰。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Sangaku-shinko Faith&quot; is a faith worshipping mountains as something sacred.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Sangaku-shinko Faith&quot; is a faith worshipping mountains as being sacred.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Sangaku-shinko faith&quot; is a faith worshipping mountains as being sacred.</e>
<cmt>Faith→faithにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>自然崇拝の一種で、狩猟民族などの山岳と関係の深い民族が山岳地とそれに付帯する自然環境に対して抱く畏敬の念、雄大さや厳しい自然環境に圧倒され恐れ敬う感情などから発展した宗教形態であると思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a kind of nature worship, and is believed to be a form of religion developing from the feeling of awe towards mountainous areas and its accompanying natural environment and the feeling of being overwhelmed, fear, and respect with the magnificence and harshness of natural environment that people such as the hunting people with deep relationship with mountains had.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a kind of nature worship, and is believed to be a form of religion developing from the feeling of awe towards mountainous areas and its accompanying natural environment and the feeling of being overwhelmed, fear, and respect with the magnificence and harshness of the natural environment that hunters had in their deep relationship with mountains..</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a kind of nature worship, and is believed to be a form of religion developing from the feeling of awe towards mountainous areas and its accompanying natural environment and the feeling of being overwhelmed, fear, and respect with the magnificence and harshness of the natural environment that hunters had in their deep relationship with mountains..</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>山岳地に霊的な力があると信じ、自らの生活を律するために山の持つ圧倒感を利用する形態が見出される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They believed that mountainous areas had spiritual powers, and utilized the overwhelmingness of the mountains to bring discipline to their lives.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They believed that mountainous areas had spiritual powers, and utilized the overwhelming awe of the mountains to bring discipline to their lives.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They believed that mountainous areas had spiritual powers, and utilized the overwhelming awe of the mountains to bring discipline to their lives.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>形態</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Forms</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Forms</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Forms</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>これらの信仰は主に、内陸地山間部の文化に強く見られ、その発生には人を寄せ付けない程の険しい地形を持つ山が不可欠とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These faiths are strong in cultures of inland mountainous regions and a mountain with a terrain almost inaccessible for humans is indispensable for it to emerge.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These faiths are strong in the cultures of inland mountainous regions and a mountains with a terrain almost inaccessible for humans is indispensable for it to emerge.</e>
<cmt>grammer</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These faiths are strong in the cultures of inland mountainous regions and a mountains with a terrain almost inaccessible for humans is indispensable for it to emerge.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>そのような信仰形態をもつ地域では、山から流れる河川や、山裾に広がる森林地帯に衣食住の全てに渡って依存した生活を送っており、常に目に入る山からの恩恵に浴している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In areas with such religious forms, their lives including food, clothing, and shelter are entirely dependent on the rivers from the mountain and the forest area at the skirt of the mountain, and are blessed by the mountain constantly in sight.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In areas where such religion forms, life&apos;s necessities, including food, clothing, and shelter, is entirely dependent upon the rivers that flow from the mountain and through the forest area at the skirt of the mountain, and they feel blessed by the mountain being constantly in sight.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In areas where such religion forms, life&apos;s necessities, including food, clothing, and shelter, are entirely dependent upon the rivers that flow from the mountain and through the forest area at the skirt of the mountain, and they feel blessed by the mountain being constantly in sight.</e>
<cmt>necessitiesに合わせ&quot;is&quot;→&quot;are&quot;としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>その一方で、これらの信仰をもつ人々は、険しい地形や自然環境により僅かな不注意でも生命を奪われかねない環境にあることから、危険な状況に陥る行為を「山の機嫌を損ねる」行為として信仰上のタブーとし、自らの安全を図るための知識として語り継いでいると考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, people with these faiths are in environments where due to the harsh landscape and natural environment, slight carelessness can lead to death, and therefore, are believed to consider dangerous actions as acts &apos;offending the mountain&apos; and a religious taboo, and hand it down as knowledge for achieving one&apos;s own safety.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, people with this faith are living in an environment where due to the harsh landscape, slight carelessness can lead to death, and therefore, consider dangerous actions as acts &apos;offending the mountain&apos; and are religious taboos, and they hand down their knowledge for achieving one&apos;s own safety.</e>
<cmt>grammar, redudancy, wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, people with this faith are living in an environment where due to the harsh landscape, slight carelessness can lead to death, and therefore, consider dangerous actions as acts &apos;offending the mountain&apos; and are religious taboos, and they hand down their knowledge for achieving one&apos;s own safety.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>なお今日では、各種防寒装備や登山用品の発達に伴い、従来は人跡未踏の地とされた地帯に人間が入り込んでも生存しつづける事が可能ではあるが、山岳信仰を尊ぶ地域住民の感情を非常に害する事もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today, with the development of various protective gear for cold weather and climbing, people can survive if they enter areas previously considered unbeaten, but may deeply offend the feelings of local residents who value sangaku shinko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, with the development of various protective gear for cold weather and climbing, people can survive if they enter areas previously considered unbeatable, but they may deeply offend the feelings of local residents who value sangaku shinko.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, with the development of various protective gear for cold weather and climbing, people can survive if they enter areas previously considered unbeatable, but they may deeply offend the feelings of local residents who value the Sangaku-shinko faith.</e>
<cmt>他の表記に合わせ、&quot;the Sangaku-shinko faith&quot;としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>登山者が山の機嫌を損ねるとされている行為を犯すと、民俗学的な意味での呪術の類型として、登山者が山に入る事を看過した地元の住民が罰せられると信じ、山をなだめようと大規模な祭を行うケースも報告されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If a climber commits an act considered to offend the mountain, it is believed that the local residents who allowed the climber to enter the mountain unnoticed would be punished by a kind of witchcraft in terms of folklore, and there are reported cases of large scale festivals held to soothe the mountain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If a climber commits an act considered to offend the mountain, it is believed that the local residents who allowed the climber to enter the mountain unnoticed will be punished by a kind of witchcraft according to folklore, and there are reported cases of large scale festivals held to soothe the mountain.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If a climber commits an act considered to offend the mountain, it is believed that the local residents who allowed the climber to enter the mountain unnoticed will be punished by a kind of witchcraft according to folklore, and there are reported cases of large scale festivals held to soothe the mountain.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="10">
<j>その一方で、これら山岳信仰のある地域で、しばしば近代的な装備を過信した者が、無謀な行動の結果、重大な危険に直面したり、逆に大量の物資を持ち込んでそのゴミを放置するといった、過剰な自己防衛に基づく自然への攻撃を行ってしまうケースも散見され、近年では改めて自然と共存するために培われた山岳信仰が、その精神性において見直されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, in regions where Sangaku-shinko Faith exists, people placing too much confidence on modern gear, facing serious danger as a result of reckless acts, or conversely attacking nature due to excessive self-defense, by for instance, bringing in a large amount of goods and leaving the garbage behind, are seen here and there, drawing a fresh look at the spirituality of Sangaku-shinko Faith, which was cultivated for coexisting with nature.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, in regions where the Sangaku-shinko faith exists, people placing too much confidence in modern gear, facing serious danger as a result of reckless acts, or conversely attacking nature due to excessive self-defense, by for instance, bringing in a large amount of goods and leaving the garbage behind, seen here and there, draws a fresh look at the spirituality of the Sangaku-shinko faith, which was cultivated for the purpose of coexisting with nature.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, in regions where the Sangaku-shinko faith exists, people placing too much confidence in modern gear, facing serious danger as a result of reckless acts, or conversely attacking nature due to excessive self-defense, by for instance, bringing in a large amount of goods and leaving the garbage behind, seen here and there, draws a fresh look at the spirituality of the Sangaku-shinko faith, which was cultivated for the purpose of coexisting with nature.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>日本の山岳信仰</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sangaku-shinko Faith in Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sangaku-shinko faith in Japan</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sangaku-shinko faith in Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>日本においても、水源・狩猟の場・鉱山・森林などの経済的条件、雄大な容姿や火山などの地質的条件から山が重要視され、古来から山は神霊が宿る、あるいは降臨する場所と信じられ祭祀が行われてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan, mountains were valued due to economic reasons such as source of water, hunting ground, mine, forest, and geological reasons such as its magnificent appearance and volcanoes, and religious services were performed based on belief since ancient times that mountains are places where divine spirit resides or descends.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan, mountains were valued due to economic reasons such as a source of water, hunting grounds, mines, forest, and for geological reasons such as their majestic appearance and volcanoes, and religious services were performed based upon belief since ancient times that mountains are places where divine spirits reside or descend to.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan, mountains were valued due to economic reasons such as a source of water, hunting grounds, mines, forest, and for geological reasons such as their majestic appearance and volcanoes, and religious services were performed based upon belief since ancient times that mountains are places where divine spirits reside or descend to.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>また、死者の魂（祖霊）が山に帰る「山上他界」という考えもある（この他は海上他界、地中他界など）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, there is a concept called &apos;sanjo takai&apos; (in addition to this, there are kaijo takai, chichu takai, etc), which means the spirits of the dead (ancestral spirit) return to the mountain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, there is a concept called &apos;sanjo takai&apos; (in addition to this, there are kaijo takai, chichu takai, etc), which means that the spirits of the dead (ancestral spirit) return to the mountain.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, there is a concept called &apos;sanjo takai&apos; (in addition to this, there are kaijo takai, chichu takai, etc), which means that the spirits of the dead (ancestral spirit) return to the mountain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>これらの伝統は神道に繋がり、長野県諏訪大社や奈良県三輪山のように、山そのものを信仰する流れが生まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These traditions led to Shinto, and gave rise to a trend of faith towards mountains themselves, as in Suwa Taisha Shrine in Nagano Prefecture and Miwa-yama Mountain in Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These traditions led to Shinto, and gave rise to a trend of faith towards mountains, as in the Suwa Taisha Shrine in Nagano Prefecture and Mount Miwa-yama in Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These traditions led to Shinto, and gave rise to a trend of faith towards mountains, as in the Suwa Taisha Shrine in Nagano Prefecture and Mt. Miwa in Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Mt. Miwa&quot;としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>農村部では水源であることと関連して、春になると山の神が里に降りて田の神となり、秋の収穫を終えると山に帰るという信仰もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In rural areas, because mountains are a source of water, there are beliefs that god of mountains descends to the village and becomes god of rice fields in spring, and returns to the mountain in fall after harvest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In rural areas, because mountains are a source of water, there are beliefs that god of the mountain descends to the village and becomes the god of the rice fields in spring, and returns to the mountain in fall after the harvest.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In rural areas, because mountains are a source of water, there are beliefs that god of the mountain descends to the village and becomes the god of the rice fields in spring, and returns to the mountain in fall after the harvest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>日本人ではないのだが、カールブッセの詩「山の彼方の空遠く、幸い住むと人のいう」という言葉が、日本人の山岳信仰の信仰観を表しているだろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although it is not by a Japanese, the words &apos;Over the mountains, far to travel, people say, happiness dwells&apos; in a poem by Carl Busse describe the view of Japanese Sangaku-shinko Faith.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although not written by a Japanese, the words &apos;Over the mountains, too far to travel, people say, happiness dwells&apos; in the poem by Carl Busse describing the view of Japanese Sangaku-shinko Faith.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although not written by a Japanese, the words &apos;Over the mountains, too far to travel, people say, happiness dwells&apos; in the poem by Carl BUSSE describing the view of Japanese Sangaku-shinko faith.</e>
<cmt>Carl BUSSE, Faith→faithに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="16">
<j>また仏教でも、世界の中心には須弥山（しゅみせん）という高い山がそびえていると考えられ、空海が高野山を、最澄が比叡山を開くなど、山への畏敬の念は、より一層深まっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Buddhism, it was believed that there is a high mountain called Shumi-sen Mountain at the center of the world, and awe for mountains deepened further as Kukai founded a temple on Koya-san Mountain and Saicho on Hiei-zan Mountain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Buddhism, it was believed that there is a high mountain called Mount Shumi-sen at the center of the world, and awe for mountains deepened further as Kukai founded a temple on Mount Koya-san and Saicho on Mount Hiei-zan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Buddhism, it was believed that there is a high mountain called Mt. Sumeru at the center of the world, and awe for mountains deepened further as Kukai founded a temple on Mt. Koya and Saicho on Mt. Hiei.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Shume-sen&quot;は須弥山の日本語読みのため、&quot;Mt. Sumeru&quot;に修正、およびMt. Koya, Mt. Hieiとしました。(参考: http://tangorin.com/words/%E9%A0%88%E5%BC%A5%E5%B1%B1)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>平地にあっても仏教寺院が「○○山△△寺」と号するのはそのような理由からである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is why Buddhist temples are called &apos;OO Mountain △△ Temple&apos; even if they are on flatlands.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is why Buddhist temples are called &apos;OO Mountain △△ Temple&apos; even if they are on flatlands.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is why Buddhist temples are called &apos;OO Mountain △△ Temple&apos; even if they are on flatlands.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="18">
<j>チベット仏教でも聖なる山は信仰の対象であるが、信仰は山自体に捧げられ、その山に登るのは禁忌とされる場合が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sacred mountains are also objects of faith in Tibetan Buddhism, but faith is often for the mountain itself, and it is often a taboo to climb such mountains.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sacred mountains are also objects of faith in Tibetan Buddhism, but faith is often for the mountain itself, and it is often a taboo to climb such mountains.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sacred mountains are also objects of faith in Tibetan Buddhism, but faith is often for the mountain itself, and it is often a taboo to climb such mountains.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>一方で日本では、山頂に達することが重要視されるのは注目すべきである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile in Japan, it should be noted that emphasis is placed on reaching the summit.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile in Japan, it should be noted that emphasis is placed on reaching the summit.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile in Japan, it should be noted that emphasis is placed on reaching the summit.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>日本人の場合、山自体を信仰する気持ちももちろんあるのだが、そこから早朝に拝まれるご来光を非常にありがたがる傾向が強く、山頂のさらにその先（彼方）にあるもの（あの世）を信仰していることが原因であろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese people definitely have faith for the mountain itself, but tend to greatly appreciate the rising sun viewed from there early in the morning, which may be due to the fact that their object of faith is what lies ahead of (beyond) the summit (the other world).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese people definitely have faith for the mountain itself, but tend to greatly appreciate the rising sun viewed from there early in the morning, which may be due to the fact that their object of faith is what lies ahead of (beyond) the summit (the other world).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese people definitely have faith for the mountain itself, but tend to greatly appreciate the rising sun viewed from there early in the morning, which may be due to the fact that their object of faith is what lies ahead of (beyond) the summit (the other world).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>日本ではアニミズムとしての太陽信仰と山岳信仰が結びついているのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan, Taiyo-shinko Faith (sun worshipping) and Sangaku-shinko Faith as forms of animism are interconnected.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan, Taiyo-shinko Faith (sun worshipping) and Sangaku-shinko Faith as forms of animism are interconnected.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan, Taiyo-shinko faith (sun worshipping) and Sangaku-shinko faith as forms of animism are interconnected.</e>
<cmt>Faith→faithとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="22">
<j>その後、密教、道教の流れをくんだ修験者や山伏たちが、俗世との関わりを絶ち、悟りを開くために山深くに入り修行を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, mountaineering ascetics and mountain priests who were of the school of Esoteric Buddhism and Taoism, detached themselves from this world, and went deep in the mountains and practiced asceticism to achieve enlightenment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, mountaineering ascetics and mountain priests who were of the school of Esoteric Buddhism and Taoism, detached themselves from this world, and went deep into the mountains and practiced asceticism to achieve enlightenment.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, mountaineering ascetics and mountain priests who were of the school of Esoteric Buddhism and Taoism, detached themselves from this world, and went deep into the mountains and practiced asceticism to achieve enlightenment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>これは、後に修験道や呪術的宗教などを生み出している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This later led to the birth of Shugendo (Japanese mountain asceticism-shamanism incorporating Shinto and Buddhist concepts) and witchcraft religion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This later led to the birth of Shugendo (Japanese mountain asceticism-shamanism incorporating Shinto and Buddhist concepts) and witchcraft religion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This later led to the birth of Shugendo (Japanese mountain asceticism-shamanism incorporating Shinto and Buddhist concepts) and witchcraft religion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="24">
<j>山岳信仰は、もともとが自然崇拝のアニミズム的信仰から発展してきただけに、江戸末期まで神仏習合の形態を取ってきたが、神仏習合が明治以後の神仏分離令により禁止されて以後、もともと真言密教系の修験道が強かった出羽三山も含め、寺と神社が分けられ、信仰の本体の多くは神社の形態を取って存続した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Sangaku-shinko Faith originally developed from a form of animism faith worshipping nature, it took the form of syncretism of Shinto and Buddhism until the end of Edo period, but since this syncretism was banned under the order for the separation of Buddhism and Shintoism in the Meiji era, temples and shrines, including Dewa-sanzan Mountain, where Shugendo of the Shingon Sect was strong, were separated, many of the main faith continued in shrines.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Sangaku-shinko Faith originally developed from a form of animism faith worshipping nature, it took the form of syncretism of Shinto and Buddhism until the end of Edo period, but since this syncretism was banned under the order for the separation of Buddhism and Shintoism in the Meiji era, temples and shrines, including Dewa-sanzan Mountain, where Shugendo of the Shingon Sect was strong, were separated, many of the main faith continued in shrines.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Sangaku-shinko faith originally developed from a form of animism faith worshipping nature, it took the form of syncretism of Shinto and Buddhism until the end of Edo period, but since this syncretism was banned under the order for the separation of Buddhism and Shintoism in the Meiji period, temples and shrines, including Dewa-sanzan Mountain, where Shugendo of the Shingon Esoteric Buddhism was strong, were separated, many of the main faith continued in shrines.</e>
<cmt>Faith→faith, Meiji era→Meiji periodとしました。「真言密教系」を訳出するため一部文章を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="25">
<j>山が神界として信仰の対象となっていた一方で、死者の霊の集まる他界として、イタコの口寄せをはじめとする先祖霊供養にも発展をみせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While mountains were the object of faith as the divine world, it was also a place where memorial services for the spirit of ancestors, such as spiritualism by itako (shrine maiden performing spiritualism) evolved, as the next world where spirits of the dead gather.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While mountains were the object of faith as the divine world, it was also a place where memorial services for the spirit of ancestors, such as spiritualism by itako (shrine maiden performing spiritualism) evolved, as the next world where spirits of the dead gather.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While mountains were the object of faith as the divine world, it was also a place where memorial services for the spirit of ancestors, such as spiritualism by itako (shrine maiden performing spiritualism) evolved, as the next world where spirits of the dead gather.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>なお、民衆の間でも信仰の顕れとして登山を行う習慣があり、現在でも、霊場といわれる山岳をはじめとして、山には多くの人々が登っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, it is a custom among the people to climb mountains as a sign of faith, and even today, many people climb mountains including those considered sacred grounds.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, it is a custom among the people to climb mountains as a sign of faith, and even today, many people climb mountains including those considered sacred grounds.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, it is a custom among the people to climb mountains as a sign of faith, and even today, many people climb mountains including those considered sacred grounds.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="27">
<j>山岳信仰のある地域</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Regions where Sangaku-shinko Faith exist</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regions where the Sangaku-shinko Faith exist</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regions where the Sangaku-shinko faith exist</e>
<cmt>Faith→faithとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>チベット</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tibet</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tibet</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tibet</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>ネパール</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nepal</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nepal</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nepal</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>ラダック（インド）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ladakh (India)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ladakh (India)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ladakh (India)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>アブラハムの宗教の流れを汲む宗教信徒全般の居住地（旧約聖書におけるシナイ山・十戒）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Habitats of the followers in general of religions descending from Abraham (Mount Sinai in the Old Testament, Decalogue)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Habitats of the followers in general of religions descending from Abraham (Mount Sinai in the Old Testament, Decalogue)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Habitats of the followers in general of religions descending from Abraham (Mt. Sinai in the Old Testament, Decalogue)</e>
<cmt>Mt. Sinaiとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>韓国、朝鮮民主主義人民共和国、中国延辺朝鮮族自治州（中国。他、同国内の満州族居住地）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Korea, Democratic People&apos;s Republic of Korea, Yanbian Korean Autonomous Prefecture in China (China. Other areas in the country where Manchu people live)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Korea, Democratic People&apos;s Republic of Korea, Yanbian Korean Autonomous Prefecture in China (China. Other areas in the country where Manchu people live)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Korea, Democratic People&apos;s Republic of Korea, Yanbian Korean Autonomous Prefecture in China (China. Other areas in the country where Manchu people live)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="33">
<j>ペルー</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Peru</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Peru</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Peru</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Tommy6-bot(id:171289), こたつ狼(id:27622), Nnh(id:474), Libertas(id:40611), GcG(id:27111), Stanislaus(id:1806), Ginz(id:31584), イシャはどこだ(id:152484), Siyajkak(id:9402), Tjan(id:17305), Saburo(id:18511), Yrogetac(id:87379), Yatobi(id:9686), Akiyoshi&apos;s Room(id:146283), Nakadati(id:26815), Shimoxx(id:9332), 三日月(id:19540), 弥(id:61590), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>