<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>イワサク・ネサク</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Iwasaku and Nesaku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Iwasaku and Nesaku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Iwasaku and Nesaku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>イワサク（イハサク）・ネサクは、日本神話に登場する神 (神道)である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Iwasaku (also called Ihasaku) and Nesaku were the gods (Shinto religion) appeared in Japanese Mythology.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Iwasaku (also called Ihasaku) and Nesaku were gods (Shinto religion) appeared in Japanese Mythology.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Iwasaku (also called Ihasaku) and Nesaku were gods (Shinto religion) appeared in Japanese Mythology.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>古事記では石析神・根析神、日本書紀では磐裂神・根裂神と表記される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Their names were written as 石析神 and 根析神 in Kojiki (The Records of Ancient Matters) and 磐裂神 and 根裂神 in Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan).</e>
<cmt>漢字が焦点となっているため、漢字表記を訳文に残しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their names were written as 石析神 and 根析神 in Kojiki (The Records of Ancient Matters) and 磐裂神 and 根裂神 in Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Their names were written as 石析神 and 根析神 in Kojiki (The Records of Ancient Matters) and 磐裂神 and 根裂神 in Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>古事記の神産みの段でイザナギが十束剣で、妻のイザナミの死因となった火神カグツチの首を斬ったとき、剣の先についた血が岩について化生した神で、その次にイワツツノオ（磐筒男神）が化生している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the chapter of kamiumi (bearing gods between Izanagi and Izanami) in Kojiki, when Izanagi cut down the head of Kagutsuchi, the god of fire, who was the cause of his wife, Izanami&apos;s death, they metamorphosed into the gods when the blood on the sword stuck to the rock, and Iwatsutsunoo metamorphosed next.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the chapter of kamiumi (bearing gods between Izanagi and Izanami) in Kojiki, when Izanagi cut off the head of Kagutsuchi, the god of fire, who was the cause of his wife Izanami&apos;s death, they metamorphosed into gods when the blood on the sword stuck to the rock, and Iwatsutsunoo metamorphosed next.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the chapter of kamiumi (bearing gods between Izanagi and Izanami) in Kojiki, when Izanagi cut off the head of Kagutsuchi, the god of fire, who was the cause of his wife Izanami&apos;s death with his Totsuka no tsurugi sword, they metamorphosed into gods when the blood on the sword stuck to the rock, and Iwatsutsunoo metamorphosed next.</e>
<cmt>with his Totsuka no tsurugi sword補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>日本書紀同段の第六の一書も同様である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was same for the sixth alternate writing in the same chapter in Nihonshoki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was same for the sixth alternate writing in the same chapter in Nihonshoki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was same for the sixth alternate writing in the same chapter in Nihonshoki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>第七の一書では磐裂神・根裂神の子として磐筒男神・磐筒女神が生まれたとし、この両神の子が経津主神であるとしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the seventh alternate writing, it said that Iwatsutsu-no-onokami and Iwatsutsu-no-menokami were born as the children of Iwasaku and Nesaku, and the child of those gods was Futsunushi no kami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the seventh alternate writing, it said that Iwatsutsu-no-onokami and Iwatsutsu-no-menokami were born as the children of Iwasaku and Nesaku, and the child of those gods was Futsunushi no kami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the seventh alternate writing, it said that Iwatsutsu no onokami and Iwatsutsu no menokami were born as the children of Iwasaku and Nesaku, and the child of those gods was Futsunushi no kami.</e>
<cmt>ハイフン削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>古事記伝では、「石根析」というべき所を2つに分けて名附けた神名とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kojikiden (Commentaries on the Kojiki), it said that their name should have written as &apos;石根析&apos; (Iwanesaku) but it was divided into two and named their Shinmyo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処漢字が焦点となっているため、漢字表記を訳文に残しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Kojikiden (Commentaries on the Kojiki), it said that their name should have written as &apos;石根析&apos; (Iwanesaku) but it was divided into two and named their Shinmyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Kojikiden (Commentaries on the Kojiki), it said that their name should have written as &apos;石根析&apos; (Iwanesaku) but it was divided into two and named their Shinmyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>「サク」は祝詞の「磐根木根踏みさくみて」の「さく」で、岩に凹凸があることを指したものとしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saku&apos; was from Norito (Shinto prayer) of &apos;Iwane Kine Fumisakumite,&apos; and it indicated that there was roughness on the rock.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saku&apos; was from Norito (Shinto prayer) of &apos;Iwane Kine Fumisakumite,&apos; and it indicated that there was a rough patch on the rock.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saku&apos; was from Norito (Shinto prayer) of &apos;Iwane Kine Fumisakumite,&apos; and it indicated that there was a rough patch on the rock.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>橘守部は、「サク」を「裂く」と解して、「岩根さえも裂く剣の威力」を表すものと解釈している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TACHIBANA no Moribe picked out &apos;Saku&apos; as &apos;裂く&apos; (pronounced as saku, meaning tear) and interpreted that it described &apos;the power of sword to tear even the root of the rock.&apos;</e>
<cmt>漢字が焦点となっているため、漢字表記を訳文に残しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TACHIBANA no Moribe picked out &apos;Saku&apos; as &apos;裂く&apos; (pronounced as saku, meaning tear) and interpreted that it described &apos;the power of sword to tear even the root of the rock.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TACHIBANA no Moribe picked out &apos;Saku&apos; as &apos;裂く&apos; (pronounced as saku, meaning tear) and interpreted that it described &apos;the power of sword to tear even the root of the rock.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Nnh(id:474), Tribot(id:186681), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>