<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>天之御中主神</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ame no Minakanushi no Kami (天之御中主神)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ame no Minakanushi no Kami (天之御中主神)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ame no Minakanushi no Kami</e>
<cmt>漢字表記は削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>天之御中主神（アメノミナカヌシノカミ）は、日本神話に登場する神 (神道)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ame no Minakanushi no Kami is one of the gods who appear in Japanese mythology (Shinto)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ame no Minakanushi no Kami is one of the gods who appear in Japanese mythology (Shinto)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ame no Minakanushi no Kami is one of the gods (Shinto) who appear in Japanese mythology.</e>
<cmt>(神道）の位置を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>天地創造に関わった五柱の別天津神（ことあまつかみ）の一柱。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is one of the five pillars of Kotoamatsukami (literally, separate heavenly gods) who were involved in the Creation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is one of the five pillars of Kotoamatsukami (literally, separate heavenly gods) who were involved in the Creation.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is one of the five pillars of Kotoamatsukami (literally, separate heavenly gods) who were involved in the Creation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="3">
<j>古事記の天之御中主神</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ame no Minakanushi no Kami as described in &quot;Kojiki&quot; (the Records of Ancient Matters)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ame no Minakanushi no Kami as described in &quot;Kojiki&quot; (the Records of Ancient Matters)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ame no Minakanushi no Kami as described in &quot;Kojiki&quot; (the Records of Ancient Matters)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>古事記では、天地開闢 (日本神話)の際に高天原に最初に出現した神であるとしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kojiki, Ame no Minakanushi no Kami is described as the first god who made an appearance in &quot;Takamagahara&quot; (the Plain of High Heaven or the Japanese Olympus) at the time of the creation of heaven and earth (Japanese mythology).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Kojiki, Ame no Minakanushi no Kami is described as the first god who made an appearance in &quot;Takamagahara&quot; (the Plain of High Heaven or the Japanese Olympus) at the time of the creation of heaven and earth (Japanese mythology).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Kojiki, Ame no Minakanushi no Kami is described as the first god who made an appearance in &quot;Takamagahara&quot; (the Plain of High Heaven or the Japanese Olympus) at the time of the creation of heaven and earth (Japanese mythology).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>その後タカミムスビ、カミムスビが現れ、すぐに姿を隠したとしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kojiki further describes that a couple of kami appeared later and soon disappeared, namely Takamimusubi and Kamimusubi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kojiki further describes that a couple of kami appeared later and soon disappeared, namely Takamimusubi and Kamimusubi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kojiki further describes that a couple of kami appeared later and soon disappeared, namely Takamimusubi and Kamimusubi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>この三柱の神を造化三神といい、性別のない「独神」（ひとりがみ）という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These three pillars of gods are called &quot;Zoka-sanshin&quot; (three kami of creation), who are said to be genderless &quot;hitorigami&quot;(solitary kami).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These three pillars of gods are called &quot;Zoka-sanshin&quot; (three kami of creation), who are said to be genderless &quot;hitorigami&quot;(solitary kami).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These three pillars of gods are called &quot;Zoka-sanshin&quot; (three kami of creation), who are said to be genderless &apos;hitorigami&apos; (god without gender).</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。独神→&apos;hitorigami&apos; (god without gender)　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>日本書紀の天御中主尊</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ame no Minakanushi no Kami as described in &quot;Nihon Shoki&quot; (the Chronicles of Japan)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ame no Minakanushi no Kami as described in &quot;Nihon Shoki&quot; (the Chronicles of Japan)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ame no Minakanushi no Kami as described in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (The Chronicles of Japan)</e>
<cmt>Nihonshoki としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>日本書紀では本文には記述はなく、第一段で6つ書かれている一書のうちの第四の一書にのみ登場する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are no description of this kami in the main version of Nihon Shoki, and one is found only in the fourth of the six &quot;alternate writings&quot; quoted in its Section 1.</e>
<cmt>日本書紀における「段」とは各「巻=Chapter」の小区分のようです。正確には「巻第一の第一段」すなわち&apos;..Section 1, Chapter 1&apos;という表記のほうがいいと思われますが、勝手に加えてはいけないということなのでコメントにとどめます。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are no description of this kami in the main version of Nihon Shoki, and one is found only in the fourth of the six &quot;alternate writings&quot; quoted in its Section 1.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is no description of this kami in the main version of Nihonshoki, and one is found only in the fourth of the six &quot;alternate writings&quot; quoted in its Section 1.</e>
<cmt>Nihonshoki としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>そこでは、まず国之常立神、次に国狭槌尊が表れたと書き、その次に「また、高天原においでになる神の名を天御中主尊（あめのみなかぬしのみこと）という」と書かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is stated there that a kami called Kuninotokotachi no Kami first appeared and then did another by the name of Kuninosatsuchi no Mikoto. Then follows a statement that &apos;the god in Takamagahara is called Ame no Minakanushi no Mikoto.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is stated there that a kami called Kuninotokotachi no Kami first appeared and then did another by the name of Kuninosatsuchi no Mikoto. Then follows a statement that &apos;the god in Takamagahara is called Ame no Minakanushi no Mikoto.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is stated there that a kami called Kuninotokotachi no Kami first appeared and then did another by the name of Kuninosatsuchi no Mikoto; then follows a statement that &apos;the god in Takamagahara is called Ame no Minakanushi no Mikoto.&apos;</e>
<cmt>セミコロンを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>この記述からは、前に書かれた二神とどちらが先に現れたのかはわからない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From these descriptions it is not clear which god came into being first.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From these descriptions it is not clear which god came into being first.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From these descriptions it is not clear which god came into being first.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>なお、他の一書では、最初に現れた神は国常立尊（本文、第一、第四、第五）、ウマシアシカビヒコヂ（第二、第三）、天之常立神（第六）としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other alternate writings quoted in Nihon Shoki state differently about the god who first appeared; Kuni no Tokotachi no Mikoto (main version, the first, the fourth and the fifth alternate writing); Umashiashikabihikoji (the second and the third alternate writing); Ame no Tokotachi no Kami (the sixth alternate writing)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other alternate writings quoted in Nihon Shoki state differently about the god who first appeared; Kuni no Tokotachi no Mikoto (main version, the first, the fourth and the fifth alternate writing); Umashiashikabihikoji (the second and the third alternate writing); Ame no Tokotachi no Kami (the sixth alternate writing)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other alternate writings quoted in Nihonshoki state differently about the god who first appeared; Kuni no Tokotachi no Mikoto (main version, the first, the fourth and the fifth alternate writing); Umashiashikabihikoji (the second and the third alternate writing); Ame no Tokotachi no Kami (the sixth alternate writing)</e>
<cmt>Nihonshoki としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="12">
<j>諸説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Various theories</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Various theories</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Various theories</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>神名は、天（高天原）の中央に座する主宰神という意味である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name of this kami implies that it is the presiding god sitting in the middle of heaven (Takamagahara).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name of this kami implies that it is the presiding god sitting in the middle of heaven (Takamagahara).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name of this kami implies that it is the presiding god sitting in the middle of heaven (Takamagahara).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>宇宙の根源の神であり、宇宙そのものであるともされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is regarded as the origin of the cosmos or as the cosmos itself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is regarded as the origin of the cosmos or as the cosmos itself.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is regarded as the origin of the cosmos or as the cosmos itself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="15">
<j>古事記、日本書紀とも、その後の事績は全く書かれておらず、「中空神」とも言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">No mention whatsoever is made either in Kojiki or Nihon Shoki of this kami&apos;s subsequent deed, and this kami is said to be 中空神.</e>
<cmt>「中空神」という単語は広辞苑、明鏡国語辞典、新漢語林、大辞泉、ブリタニカ国際百科事典のいずれにも見あたりません。またインターネットの使用例では、この原文である和文Wikipediaからの引用が大半です。ひょっとするとhollow godの直訳かとも思われますが、このhollow godそのものも、ネット上の一般的使用例こそかなり出てくるものの、まともな英語表現とは思えない節があります。例えばCorpus (US)に一件のみ、Corpus (UK)にはゼロ、各種英和辞典、英英辞典（Oxford, Collins およびOxford Sentence Dic）での検索においても全くヒットしません。あるいは&apos;imaginary god&apos;がいいかとも考えましたが、自信がなくそのままにしてあります。&apos;hollow god&apos;という用語が変なニュアンスを持つものかどうかをネイティブチェッカーの方にご判断いただき、おかしくないとなればそれでもいいかとも思います。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">No mention whatsoever is made either in Kojiki or Nihon Shoki of this kami&apos;s subsequent deed, and this kami is said to be 中空神.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">No mention whatsoever is made either in Kojiki or Nihonshoki of this kami&apos;s subsequent deeds, and this kami is said to be &apos;Chukushin&apos; (literally, a god without form).</e>
<cmt>Nihonshoki としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>記紀神話が形成される上で創造された観念的な神と考えられ、それには中国の天帝の思想が影響したものと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered that this kami is a conceptual god created in the course of the formation of the Kojiki and Nihon Shoki mythology under the influence of the Chinese thought of the Lord of Heaven.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered that this kami is a conceptual god created in the course of the formation of the Kojiki and Nihon Shoki mythology under the influence of the Chinese thought of the Lord of Heaven.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered that this kami is a conceptual god created in the course of the formation of the Kojiki and Nihonshoki mythology under the influence of the Chinese thought of the Lord of Heaven.</e>
<cmt>Nihonshoki としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="17">
<j>平田篤胤は禁書であったキリスト教関係の書籍を読み、その万物の創造神という観念の影響を強く受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taneatsu HIRATA (a scholar of Japanese classical literature in the late Edo period) read a number of proscribed books concerning Christianity and was strongly influenced by its idea of the god as the creator of all nature.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taneatsu HIRATA (a scholar of Japanese classical literature in the late Edo period) read a number of proscribed books concerning Christianity and was strongly influenced by its idea of god as the creator of all nature.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taneatsu HIRATA (a scholar of Japanese classical literature in the late Edo period) read a number of proscribed books concerning Christianity and was strongly influenced by its idea of god as the creator of all nature.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>そして『霊之御柱』において、この世界の姿が確定する天孫降臨以前の万物の創造を天御中主神・高皇産霊神・神皇産霊神の造化三神によるものとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He states in his book &quot;Tama-no-mihashira&quot; (the True Pillar of Spirit) that it was Zoka-sanshin including Ame no Minakanushi no Kami, Takamimusubi no Kami and Kamimusubi no Kami that created all nature prior to tenson-korin (the descent to earth of the grandson of the sun goddess) at which time this world took on its shape.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He states in his book &quot;Tama-no-mihashira&quot; (the True Pillar of Spirit) that it was Zoka-sanshin including Ame no Minakanushi no Kami, Takamimusubi no Kami and Kamimusubi no Kami that created all nature prior to tenson-korin (the descent to earth of the grandson of the sun goddess) at which time this world took on its shape.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He states in his book &quot;Tama-no-mihashira&quot; (the True Pillar of Spirit) that it was Zoka-sanshin including Ame no Minakanushi no Kami, Takamimusubi no Kami and Kamimusubi no Kami that created all nature prior to tensonkorin (the descent to earth of the grandson of the sun goddess) at which time this world took on its shape.</e>
<cmt>ハイフンを削除し、tensonkorinとして統一しています。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>この三神は復古神道においては窮極神とされ、なかでも天御中主神は最高位に位置づけられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These three kami are regarded as the ultimate gods in &quot;Fukko Shinto&quot; (revived Shinto), and in particular Ame no Minakanushi no Kami is ranked first.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These three kami are regarded as the ultimate gods in &quot;Fukko Shinto&quot; (revived Shinto), and in particular Ame no Minakanushi no Kami is ranked first.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These three kami are regarded as the ultimate gods in &quot;Fukko Shinto&quot; (revived Shinto), and in particular Ame no Minakanushi no Kami is ranked first.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="20">
<j>神社</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shrines</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shrines</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shrines</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>神話に殆ど記述がなく、生活に直接かかわる神ではないため、長らく信仰の対象とはされてこなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This kami had not been the object of worship for long since the Japanese mythology hardly contains any description of it and as this kami is not directly related to people&apos;s daily lives.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This kami had not been the object of worship for long since the Japanese mythology hardly contains any description of it and as this kami is not directly related to people&apos;s daily lives.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This kami had not been the object of worship for long since the Japanese mythology hardly contains any description of it and as this kami is not directly related to people&apos;s daily lives.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>中世以降になって、寺院や陰陽道などで祭られるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Only after the medieval period it began to be worshipped in temples and Onmyodo (way of Yin and Yang; occult divination system based on the Taoist theory of the five elements).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Only after the medieval period did it begin to be worshipped in temples and Onmyodo (way of Yin and Yang; occult divination system based on the Taoist theory of the five elements).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Only after the medieval period did it begin to be worshipped in temples and Onmyodo (way of Yin and Yang; occult divination system based on the Taoist theory of the five elements).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>現在、この神を祭る神社には、妙見社系と水天宮系の二系統がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At present there are two groups of shrines sacred to this kami, namely the group of Myoken-sha Shrine (originally, some still currently, sacred to Myoken; the bodhisattva Myoken who is the deification of the North Star) and the group of Suiten-gu Shrine (originally sacred to Suiten; the god of waters derived from the Hindu god of waters Varuna).</e>
<cmt>「水天宮」「妙見社」の追加表記について水天宮用語集に「初出の場合Suiten-gu Shrine (a temple sacred to the guardian deity of mariners)とする」とあります。現在では、総本宮である久留米の水天宮のサイトにおいて御祭神の一番手に天之御中主神が謳ってあり、水天の名はありません。用語集で引用された研究社和英大辞典の説明は、明治初期の神仏分離以前のことを指しています。また同サイトに「国内・ハワイ等各地に鎮座する水天宮はすべて当社を本宮とする御分霊社である」とあるので水天宮グループを一つと見て問題ないと思われます。妙見社一方、妙見社の場合は、統一されておらず、例えば三大妙見の一つである能勢妙見など天之御中主神を祭神としない妙見社（寺）もあるようなのでその意味を含めました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At present there are two groups of shrines sacred to this kami, namely the group of Myoken-sha Shrine (originally, some still currently, sacred to Myoken; the bodhisattva Myoken who is the deification of the North Star) and the group of Suiten-gu Shrine (originally sacred to Suiten; the god of waters derived from the Hindu god of waters Varuna).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At present there are two groups of shrines sacred to this kami, namely the group of Myoken-sha Shrine (originally, some still currently, sacred to Myoken; the bodhisattva Myoken who is the deification of the North Star) and the group of Suiten-gu Shrine (originally sacred to Suiten; the god of waters derived from the Hindu god of waters Varuna).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="24">
<j>妙見社系の端緒は、道教における天の中央の至高神（天皇大帝）信仰にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Myoken-sha Shrine group has its origin in the belief in Taoism&apos;s supreme god residing in the heaven&apos;s center (Tien-Huang-ta-ti).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Myoken-sha Shrine group has its origin in the belief in Taoism&apos;s supreme god residing in the heaven&apos;s center (Tien-Huang-ta-ti).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Myoken-sha Shrine group has its origin in the belief in Taoism&apos;s supreme god residing in the heaven&apos;s center (Tien-Huang-ta-ti).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>北極星・北斗七星信仰、さらに仏教の妙見信仰（妙見菩薩・妙見さん）と習合され、平田篤胤が北斗七星の神とする教学を確立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The worship of Ame no Minakanushi no Kami was amalgamated with the North Star worship and the Big Dipper worship, and further with Buddhism&apos;s Myoken worship (worship of the bodhisattva Myoken, alias Myoken-san), forming the base for Atsutane HIRATA to establish a teaching theory which regards this kami as the god of the Big Dipper.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The worship of Ame no Minakanushi no Kami was amalgamated with the North Star worship and the Big Dipper worship, and further with Buddhism&apos;s Myoken worship (worship of the bodhisattva Myoken, alias Myoken-san), forming the base for Atsutane HIRATA to establish a teaching theory which regards this kami as the god of the Big Dipper.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The worship of Ame no Minakanushi no Kami was amalgamated with the North Star worship and the Big Dipper worship, and further with Buddhism&apos;s Myoken worship (worship of the bodhisattva Myoken, alias Myoken-san), forming the base for Atsutane HIRATA to establish a teaching theory which regards this kami as the god of the Big Dipper.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>さらに、明治初期に大教院の祭神とされ、いくつかの神社が祭神を天之御中主神に改めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, Ame no Minakanushi no Kami was worshipped in Daikyoin (Great Teaching Institute) early in the Meiji period, and several shrines altered their enshrined deity to this kami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, Ame no Minakanushi no Kami was worshipped in Daikyoin (Great Teaching Institute) early in the Meiji period, and several shrines altered their enshrined deity to this kami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, Ame no Minakanushi no Kami was worshipped in Daikyoin (Great Teaching Institute) early in the Meiji period, and several shrines altered their enshrined deity to this kami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>千葉氏ゆかりの千葉神社、九戸氏ゆかりの九戸神社、埼玉県の秩父神社などは妙見信仰のつながりで天之御中主神を祀る妙見社である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such shrines as Chiba-jinja Shrine which has strong connection with Chiba clan, Kunohe-jinja shrine with Kunohe clan and Chichibu-jinja Shrine in Saitama Prefecture all enshrine Ame no Minakanushi no Kami through the Myoken worship link.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such shrines as Chiba-jinja Shrine which has strong connection with Chiba clan, Kunohe-jinja shrine with Kunohe clan and Chichibu-jinja Shrine in Saitama Prefecture all enshrine Ame no Minakanushi no Kami through the Myoken worship link.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such shrines as Chiba-jinja Shrine which has strong connection with Chiba clan, Kunohe-jinja shrine with Kunohe clan and Chichibu-jinja Shrine in Saitama Prefecture all enshrine Ame no Minakanushi no Kami through the Myoken worship link.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>妙見社は千葉県では宗教法人登録をしているものだけでも50社以上もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are over 50 Myoken-sha shrines in Chiba Prefecture, counting only those which have registered as a religious corporation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are over 50 Myoken-sha shrines in Chiba Prefecture, counting only those which have registered as a religious corporation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are over 50 Myoken-sha shrines in Chiba Prefecture, counting only those which have registered as a religious corporation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>全国の小祠は数知れない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An innumerable number of small Myoken-sha shrines are located all over Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An innumerable number of small Myoken-sha shrines are located all over Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An innumerable number of small Myoken-sha shrines are located all over Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="30">
<j>水天宮は、元は仏教の神・水天を祀るものであるが、神仏分離の際、水天の元となったヴァルナ (神)の神格が始源神であることから、記紀神話における始源神・天之御中主神に置き換えられたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Suiten-gu Shrine was originally a temple sacred to Buddhism&apos;s god Suiten, but Suiten was replaced with Ame no Minakanushi no Kami at the time of the separation of Buddhism and Shintoism, based on the notion that the divinity of Varuna (a god from whom Suiten derived) was the primordial god and so was that of Ame no Minakanushi no Kami in the Kojiki and Nihon Shoki mythology.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Suiten-gu Shrine was originally a temple sacred to Buddhism&apos;s god Suiten, but Suiten was replaced with Ame no Minakanushi no Kami at the time of the separation of Buddhism and Shintoism, based on the notion that the divinity of Varuna (a god from whom Suiten derived) was the primordial god and so was that of Ame no Minakanushi no Kami in the Kojiki and Nihon Shoki mythology.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Suiten-gu Shrine was originally a temple sacred to Buddhism&apos;s god Suiten, but Suiten was replaced with Ame no Minakanushi no Kami at the time of the separation of Buddhism and Shintoism, based on the notion that the divinity of Varuna (a god from whom Suiten derived) was the primordial god and so was that of Ame no Minakanushi no Kami in the Kojiki and Nihonshoki mythology.</e>
<cmt>Nihonshoki としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Toroia(id:31889), Nnh(id:474), アイザール(id:133157), 水野白楓(id:22811), STBot(id:137943), 表現等規制委員会(id:61918), 三竹修二郎(id:88082), Charon(id:9162), 無苦斎(id:179040), Memosa(id:131221), 守羅(id:193155), 波定(id:111126), Kafuka1964(id:105407), Murasagi(id:79122), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), ラッパ食堂(id:255123), Peccafly(id:54812), Auxgllot(id:110551), FlaBot(id:30804), ウィキ豊(id:82961), 弥(id:61590), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>