<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>天忍日命</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amenooshihi-no-mikoto</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amenooshihi-no-mikoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amenooshihi-no-mikoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>天忍日命（アメノオシヒノミコト）は、日本神話の神 (神道)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amenooshihi-no-mikoto is one of kami (god) in Japanese Mythology (shinto).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amenooshihi-no-mikoto is one a kami (god) in Japanese Mythology (shinto).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amenooshihi no Mikoto is a god (Shinto) which appears in Japanese mythology.</e>
<cmt>表現を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>大伴氏の祖神とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amenooshihi-no-mikoto is said to be the soshin (ancestor honored as god) of the Otomo clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amenooshihi-no-mikoto is said to be the soshin (ancestor honored as god) of the Otomo clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amenooshihi no Mikoto is said to be the soshin (ancestor honored as god) of the Otomo clan.</e>
<cmt>神名表現を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>日本神話では、『古事記』の天孫降臨の場面にのみ登場する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Japanese Methodology, Amenooshihi-no-mikoto only appears in the scene of tensonkorin (the descent to earth of the grandson of the sun goddess) in the &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Japanese Methodology, Amenooshihi-no-mikoto only appears in the scene of tensonkorin (the descent to earth of the grandson of the sun goddess) in the &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Japanese mythology, Amenooshihi no Mikoto only appears in the scene of tensonkorin (the descent to earth of the grandson of the sun goddess) in the &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters).</e>
<cmt>mythology に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>『日本書紀』には現れない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amenooshihi-no-mikoto does not appear in the &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amenooshihi-no-mikoto does not appear in the &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It does not appear in the &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan).</e>
<cmt>文頭を一部変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>久米氏の祖神とされる天久米命と共に武装してニニギノミコトの先導をした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amenooshihi-no-mikoto armed along with Amatsukume-no-mikoto, who is said to be the soshin of the Kume clan, and led Ninigi-no-mikoto.</e>
<cmt>原文と用語集に基づいて訳すとこのような訳文になりますが、これでは全く意味が通じないと思います。「ニニギノミコトの先導をした」は、「天孫降臨においてニニギノミコトを先導した」という意味だと推測します。その場合、訳文の最後に at the time of tenshokorin などと付け加えたほうがいいかと思います。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amenooshihi-no-mikoto armed along with Amatsukume-no-mikoto, who is said to be the soshin of the Kume clan, and led Ninigi-no-mikoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amenooshihi no Mikoto armed along with Amatsukume no Mikoto, who is said to be the soshin of the Kume clan, and led Ninigi no Mikoto.</e>
<cmt>神名表現を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>『古事記』には出自が記載されていないが、大伴氏の系図などでは天忍日命（アメノオシヒノミコト）はタカミムスビノミコトの子とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the &quot;Kojiki&quot; does not describe the origin of Amenooshihi-no-mikoto, according to the family trees of the Otomo clan and other materials, Amenooshihi-no-mikoto is said to be the child of Katamimusubi-no-mikoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the &quot;Kojiki&quot; does not describe the origin of Amenooshihi-no-mikoto, according to the family trees of the Otomo clan and other materials, Amenooshihi-no-mikoto is said to be the child of Katamimusubi-no-mikoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the &quot;Kojiki&quot; does not describe the origin of Amenooshihi no Mikoto, according to the family trees of the Otomo clan and other materials, Amenooshihi no Mikoto is said to be the child of Takamimusubi no Mikoto.</e>
<cmt>神名を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>神武東征の際に随伴し、大伴氏の祖となった道臣命は、その天忍日命（アメノオシヒノミコト）の曾孫とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Michinoomi-no-mikoto, who accompanied Jinmu tosei (Eastern expedition of the Emperor Jinmu) and later became the founder of the Otomo ckan, is said to be the great-grand child of Amenooshihi-no-mikoto.</e>
<cmt>用語集には神武東征の訳にJinmu tosei (story in Japanese myth about the first generation of the Imperial family)とするものもありましたが、これでは「東征」の意味が含まれませんので、もう一方の訳語(Eastern expedition of the Emperor Jinmu)を採用しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Michinoomi-no-mikoto, who accompanied Jinmu tosei (Eastern expedition of the Emperor Jinmu) and later became the founder of the Otomo ckan, is said to be the great-grand child of Amenooshihi-no-mikoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Michinoomi no Mikoto, who accompanied Jinmu tosei (Eastern expedition of the Emperor Jinmu) and later became the founder of the Otomo clan, is said to be the great-grand child of Amenooshihi no Mikoto.</e>
<cmt>神名表現を統一しました。スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>天忍日命を祭神とする神社は少ない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are not many shrines that have Amenooshihi-no-mikoto as its enshrined deity.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are not many shrines that have Amenooshihi-no-mikoto as its enshrined deity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are not many shrines that have Amenooshihi no Mikoto as its enshrined deity.</e>
<cmt>神名表現を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>降幡神社（大阪府南河内郡河南町）、油日神社（滋賀県甲賀市）、矢保佐神社（長崎県壱岐市）などに祀られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furuhata-jinja Shrine (Kanan-cho, Minamikawachi-gun, Osaka Prefecture), Aburahi-jinja Shrine (Koga City, Shiga Prefecture), and Yahosa-jinja Shrine (Iki City, Nagasaki Prefecture) enshrine Amenooshihi-no-mikoto.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furuhata-jinja Shrine (Kanan-cho, Minamikawachi-gun, Osaka Prefecture), Aburahi-jinja Shrine (Koga City, Shiga Prefecture), and Yahosa-jinja Shrine (Iki City, Nagasaki Prefecture) enshrine Amenooshihi-no-mikoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furuhata-jinja Shrine (Kanan-cho, Minamikawachi-gun, Osaka Prefecture), Aburahi-jinja Shrine (Koga City, Shiga Prefecture), and Yahosa-jinja Shrine (Iki City, Nagasaki Prefecture) enshrine Amenooshihi no Mikoto.</e>
<cmt>神名表現を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="10">
<j>降幡神社のある場所は、大伴氏の支族が住んでいた地域である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furuhata-jinja Shrine is located in a place where the branch family of the Otomo clan used to live.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furuhata-jinja Shrine is located in a place where the branch family of the Otomo clan used to live.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furuhata-jinja Shrine is located in a place where the branch family of the Otomo clan used to live.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 PieceBlue(id:183974), Knua(id:66861), Himazin(id:22034), 竹麦魚(id:11012), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), Nnh(id:474), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>