<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>八乙女</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yaotome</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yaotome</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yaotome</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>八乙女（やおとめ）とは、主に神楽や舞（いわゆる巫女神楽・巫女舞）をもって奉仕する8人の巫女のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yaotome refers to 8 female shrine media called miko who serve to gods mainly by performing sacred music and dancing called kagura (also known as Miko kagura (dances by shrine maidens) and mikomai (female Shinto dance that the young girls each carry a small baton with bells)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yaotome refers to 8 female shrine media called miko who serve gods mainly by performing sacred music and performing a dance called kagura (also known as Miko kagura - dances by shrine maidens) and mikomai (female Shinto dance where the young girls each carry a small baton with bells).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yaotome refers to 8 female shrine media called miko who serve gods mainly by performing sacred music and performing a dance called kagura (also known as Miko kagura - dances by shrine maidens) and mikomai (female Shinto dance where the young girls each carry a small baton with bells).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>八社女・八少女・八乎止女とも書く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Beside &quot;八乙女,&quot; in kanji, Yaotome is given the following:八社女, 八少女, and 八乎止女.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Beside &quot;八乙女,&quot; in kanji, Yaotome is given the following:八社女, 八少女, and 八乎止女.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Beside &quot;八乙女,&quot; in kanji, Yaotome is given the following:八社女, 八少女, and 八乎止女.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>また、略して八女（やめ）とも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also the term of Yaotome is shortened to &quot;Yame.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also the term of Yaotome is shortened to &quot;Yame.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also the term of Yaotome is shortened to &quot;Yame.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>ただし、人数が8人と定まったのは後世の事であり、古くは「八」の字は複数あるいは多くという意味で使われていたものであると考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However the number of performers was not originally set as eight; the word of &quot;eight&quot; is considered to have meant multiple or large numbers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However the number of performers was not originally set as eight; the word &quot;eight&quot; is considered to have meant multiple or large numbers.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However the number of performers was not originally set as eight; the word &apos;eight&apos; is considered to have meant multiple or large numbers.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>古代の景行天皇の大嘗祭の際に天皇と神々に食事を奉仕した巫女に由来するとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that the Yaotome originates from shrine maidens who served food to Emperor Keiko and gods in the ancient Daijo-sai festival (a festival to celebrate the succession of an emperor) held by the Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that the Yaotome originates from shrine maidens who served food to Emperor Keiko and the gods in the ancient Daijo-sai festival (a festival to celebrate the succession of an emperor) held by the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that the Yaotome originates from shrine maidens who served food to Emperor Keiko and the gods in the ancient Daijo-sai Festival (a festival to celebrate the succession of an emperor) held by the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>festivalの頭文字を大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>後には神祇官において卜定められた采女がこうした任務にあたった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In later years Jingikan (department of worship) selected court ladies from provinces to have them perform such services.</e>
<cmt>「卜定められた」は、選ばれたと訳してあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In later years Jingikan (department of worship) selected court ladies from provinces to have them perform such services.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In later years Jingikan (department of worship) selected court ladies from provinces to have them perform such services.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>この影響を受けて他の神社においても同様の役目の巫女が置かれ、更には神事にも関わるようになったとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This had an influenced on other shrines, which set up the post of miko who originally did the similar services and later were involved in Shinto rituals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This had an influenced on other shrines, that set up the post of miko who originally performed similar services and who were later involved in Shinto rituals.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This had an influenced on other shrines, that set up the post of miko who originally performed similar services and who were later involved in Shinto rituals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>古くは春日大社や厳島神社の八乙女がよく知られていたが、今日では美保神社や金刀比羅宮、豊国神社の八乙女舞も有名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Yaotome of Kasuga Taisha Shrine and Itsukushima-jinja Shrine was renowned in old days and today yaotome mai (dance by yaotome (miko (female shrine medium) to serve by dancing and kagura (ancient Shinto music and dance))) performed in Miho-jinja Shrine, Kotohira-gu Shrine, and Toyokuni-jinja Shrine are also well known.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Yaotome of Kasuga Taisha Shrine and Itsukushima-jinja Shrine was renowned in the old days and today yaotome mai (dance by yaotome - miko female shrine mediums) to serve by dancing and kagura (ancient Shinto music and dancing) performed at Miho-jinja Shrine, Kotohira-gu Shrine, and Toyokuni-jinja Shrine are also well known.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Yaotome of Kasuga-taisha Shrine and Itsukushima-jinja Shrine was renowned in the old days and today Yaotome mai (dance by Yaotome) performed at Miho-jinja Shrine, Kotohira-gu Shrine, and Toyokuni-jinja Shrine are also well known.</e>
<cmt>Kasuga-taisha Shrineとしました。他の表記と合わせ&quot;yaotome&quot;の頭文字を大文字に、原文の内容に沿うよう文章を一部修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>また、明治時代に政府の方針で巫女舞そのものが危機に瀕した際に春日大社の八乙女舞を元にして、巫女舞そのものがより芸術性の高い舞へと変革されていったともいわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that in the Meiji Period, the yaotome mai was reformed into a dance of higher artistry quality because it was about to be prohibited according to the government policy,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that in the Meiji Period, the yaotome mai was reformed into a dance of higher artistic quality because it was about to be prohibited according to government policy,</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that in the Meiji period, the Yaotome mai was reformed into a dance of higher artistic quality because it was about to be prohibited according to government policy,</e>
<cmt>Periodの頭文字を小文字に、yaotomeの頭文字を大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="10">
<j>地名</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Geographic Name</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Geographical Name</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Geographical Name</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>八乙女浦（山形県鶴岡市由良）：蜂子皇子を、舞を踊って出迎えた八人の美しい乙女に由来する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yaotome-ura (Yura, Tsuruoka City, Yamagata Prefecture): it was named after beautiful ladies who welcomed Prince Hachinoko by performing a dance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yaotome-ura (Yura, Tsuruoka City, Yamagata Prefecture): it was named after beautiful ladies who welcomed Prince Hachinoko by performing a dance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yaotome-ura (Yura, Tsuruoka City, Yamagata Prefecture): it was named after the eight beautiful ladies who welcomed Prince Hachinoko by performing a dance.</e>
<cmt>「八人の」の訳を加えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="12">
<j>八乙女洞窟（山形県鶴岡市由良）：明治時代の酒田地震により、崩れた岩で入口が塞がっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yaotome-dokutsu cave (Yura, Tsuruoka City, Yamagata Prefecture): its entrance was covered by rocks destroyed in Sakata earthquake that occurred in the Meiji Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yaotome-dokutsu cave (Yura, Tsuruoka City, Yamagata Prefecture): its entrance was covered by rocks destroyed in Sakata earthquake that occurred in the Meiji Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yaotome-dokutsu cave (Yura, Tsuruoka City, Yamagata Prefecture): its entrance was covered by rocks destroyed in Sakata earthquake that occurred in the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>Periodの頭文字を小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="13">
<j>八乙女公園（秋田県大仙市）：八乙女城に由来する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yaotome-koen Park (Daisen City, Akita Prefecture): It was named after Yaotome-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yaotome-koen Park (Daisen City, Akita Prefecture): It was named after Yaotome-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yaotome-koen Park (Daisen City, Akita Prefecture): It was named after Yaotome-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="14">
<j>八乙女 (仙台市)（宮城県仙台市泉区 (仙台市)）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yaotome (Sendai City) (Izumi Ward, Sendai City, Miyagi Prefecture))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yaotome (Sendai City) (Izumi Ward, Sendai City, Miyagi Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yaotome (Izumi Ward, Sendai City, Miyagi Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>Sendai Cityが重複するため、前のSendai Cityを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="15">
<j>八乙女山（富山県南砺市）：平成の大合併で新市の名称を八乙女市にする案もあったが市議会で多数決により南砺市に決定した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mt. Yaotome (Nanto City, Toyama Prefecture): some proposed &quot;Yaotome City&quot; for the name of the new city formed through a municipal merger known as &quot;the Great Merger of the Heisei Era,&quot; but the municipal assembly adopted Nanto City by a majority vote.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mt. Yaotome (Nanto City, Toyama Prefecture): some proposed &quot;Yaotome City&quot; for the name of the new city formed through a municipal merger known as &quot;the Great Merger of the Heisei Era,&quot; but the municipal assembly adopted Nanto City by a majority vote.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mt. Yaotome (Nanto City, Toyama Prefecture): some proposed &quot;Yaotome City&quot; for the name of the new city formed through a municipal merger known as &quot;the Great Merger of the Heisei Era,&quot; but the municipal assembly adopted Nanto City by a majority vote.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>また京都の五山送り火に似た八文字焼きという行事が毎年行われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An event called Hachimonji-yaki, which resembles Gozan Okuribi (Mountain Bon Fire) in Kyoto, is held every year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An event called Hachimonji-yaki, which resembles Gozan Okuribi (Mountain Bon Fire) in Kyoto, is held every year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An event called Hachimonji-yaki, which resembles Gozan Okuribi (Mountain Bon Fire) in Kyoto, is held every year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Yanahan(id:2437), Nnh(id:474), U3002(id:66126), Nekomiminarikin(id:199247), Greenland4(id:114494), Comyu(id:58135), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>