<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>古事記伝</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kojikiden</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kojikiden</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kojikiden</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>『古事記伝』（こじきでん、ふることふみのつたえ）は、江戸時代の国学者・本居宣長の『古事記』全編にわたる全44巻の註釈書である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kojikiden&quot; or &quot;Furukotofumi no tsutae&quot; is forty-four volumes of commentaries on &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters) by Norinaga MOTOORI, a scholar of Japanese classical literature in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kojikiden&quot; or &quot;Furukotofumi no tsutae&quot; is forty-four volumes of commentaries on &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters) by Norinaga MOTOORI, a scholar of Japanese classical literature in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Kojikiden&quot; or &quot;Furukotofumi no tsutae&quot; is forty-four volumes of commentaries on &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters) by Norinaga MOTOORI, a scholar of Japanese classical literature in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>『記伝』と略される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This book is casually referred to as &quot;Kiden&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This book is casually referred to as &quot;Kiden&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This book is casually referred to as &quot;Kiden.&quot;</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを&quot;内に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>沿革</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its history</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its history</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its history</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>1764年（明和元年）の起稿から1798年（寛政10年）の脱稿まで、完成には約35年もの歳月が費やされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Norinaga started writing the book in 1764 and finished it in 1798, spending as many as thirty-five years completing it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Norinaga started writing the book in 1764 and finished it in 1798, spending as many as thirty-five years completing it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Norinaga started writing the book in 1764 and finished it in 1798, spending as many as thirty-five years completing it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>版本としての刊行は1790年（寛政2年）から宣長没後の1822年（文政5年）にかけてである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This book was published in print from 1790 to 1882, during which Norinaga died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This book was published in print from 1790 to 1882, during which Norinaga died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This book was published in print from 1790 to 1882, during which Norinaga died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>医学の修行のために上洛していた宣長は、1756年（宝暦6年）、27歳の時に店頭で『先代旧事本紀』とともに『古事記』の巻を購入した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1756, Norinaga, aged 27, who had studied medicine in Kyoto, bought &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters) and &quot;Sendai Kujihongi (Ancient Japanese History): Lineage of the Mononobe and Soga Clans&quot; at a book store.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1756, Norinaga, aged 27, who had studied medicine in Kyoto, bought &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters) and &quot;Sendai Kujihongi (Ancient Japanese History): Lineage of the Mononobe and Soga Clans&quot; at a book store.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1756, Norinaga, aged 27, who had studied medicine in Kyoto, bought &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters) and &quot;Sendai Kujihongi (Ancient Japanese History): Lineage of the Mononobe and Soga Clans&quot; at a book store.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>この頃、宣長は『日本書紀』に目を通しており、賀茂真淵の論考に出会って日本の古道に触れるようになっていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In these days, Norinaga had already read &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan) and became more acquainted with Japanese Kodo (ancient method, ancient moral teachings, the way of learning) after he came across the writings of Kamo no MABUCHI (a scholar of Japanese classical literature) and was intrigued with his way of discussion and reasoning.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In these days, Norinaga had already read &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan) and became more acquainted with Japanese Kodo (ancient method, ancient moral teachings, the way of learning) after he came across the writings of Kamo no MABUCHI (a scholar of Japanese classical literature) and was intrigued with his way of discussion and reasoning.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In these days, Norinaga had already read &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan) and became more acquainted with Japanese Kodo (ancient method, ancient moral teachings, the way of learning) after he came across the writings of KAMO no Mabuchi (a scholar of Japanese classical literature) and was intrigued with his way of discussion and reasoning.</e>
<cmt>名前表記</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>宣長が本格的に『古事記』研究に進むことを決意したのは、1763年（宝暦13年）の、いわゆる「松坂の一夜」ではじめて私淑する真淵との出会いを果たした頃である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1763, Norinaga finally met Mabuchi whom he had secretly admired and modeled after, and this encounter, known as &quot;the night in Matsuzaka&quot;, made him decide to carry out extensive research into &quot;Kojiki&quot; throughout his life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1763, Norinaga finally met Mabuchi whom he had secretly admired and modeled after, and this encounter, known as &quot;the night in Matsuzaka&quot;, made him decide to carry out extensive research into &quot;Kojiki&quot; throughout his life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1763, Norinaga finally met Mabuchi whom he had secretly admired and modeled after, and this encounter, known as &apos;the night in Matsuzaka,&apos; made him decide to carry out extensive research into &quot;Kojiki&quot; throughout his life.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;にカンマを&apos;内に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>その翌年、1764年（宝暦14年）から『古事記伝』を起筆した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1764, the following year, Norinaga set out to work on &quot;Kojikiden&quot;.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1764, the following year, Norinaga set out to work on &quot;Kojikiden&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1764, the following year, Norinaga set out to work on &quot;Kojikiden.&quot;</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを&quot;内に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>間に『玉勝間』や『うひ山ぶみ』などの執筆も挟んで1798年（寛政10年）まで35年かけて成立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it took him as many as thirty-five years before it was completed in 1798, during which he wrote other books, including Tamakatsuma&quot; (a collection of essays) and Uiyamabumi&quot; (First Steps into the Mountain).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it took him as many as thirty-five years before it was completed in 1798, during which he wrote other books, including Tamakatsuma&quot; (a collection of essays) and Uiyamabumi&quot; (First Steps into the Mountain).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it took him as many as thirty-five years before it was completed in 1798, during which he wrote other books, including &quot;Tamakatsuma&quot; (a collection of essays) and &quot;Uiyamabumi&quot; (First Steps into the Mountain).</e>
<cmt>&quot;補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>内容</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its content</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its content</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its content</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>『古事記伝』は、まず多数の写本を校合し、諸写本の異同を厳密に校訂した上で本文を構築した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before giving commentaries on &quot;Kojiki&quot;, Norinaga had to determine its body of text by collating a large number of copies and carefully comparing, examining and revising differences among them.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before giving commentaries on &quot;Kojiki&quot;, Norinaga had to determine its body of text by collating a large number of copies and carefully comparing, examining and revising differences among them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before giving commentaries on Kojiki, Norinaga had to determine its body of text by collating a large number of copies and carefully comparing, examining, and revising differences among them.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>古語の訓を附し、その後に詳細な註釈を加えるという構成になっている（この形式は、のちの倉野憲司『古事記全註釈』にも引き継がれている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, he provided ancient words with Japanese reading and detailed commentaries. (This style was taken over by Kenji KURANO, who later wrote &quot;Kojiki zenchushaku&quot; (a comprehensive commentary on the Kojiki&quot;).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, he provided ancient words with Japanese reading and detailed commentaries. (This style was taken over by Kenji KURANO, who later wrote &quot;Kojiki zenchushaku&quot; (a comprehensive commentary on the Kojiki&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, he provided ancient words with Japanese reading and detailed commentaries. (This style was taken over by Kenji KURANO, who later wrote &quot;Kojiki zenchushaku&quot; (a comprehensive commentary on the Kojiki).</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>『記伝』全44巻のうち、巻一は「直毘霊」（ナホビノミタマ）を含む総論となっており、巻二では序文の注釈や神統譜、巻三から巻四十四までは本文の註釈に分かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Out of 44 volumes of &quot;Kiden&quot;, Volume 1 provides general remarks (an outline), including &quot;Naobinomitama&quot; (a book of Shinto), Volume 2 commentaries on the preface and the genealogy of gods, and the rest, Volume 3 to 44, commentaries on the text.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Out of 44 volumes of &quot;Kiden&quot;, Volume 1 provides general remarks (an outline), including &quot;Naobinomitama&quot; (a book of Shinto), Volume 2 commentaries on the preface and the genealogy of gods, and the rest, Volume 3 to 44, commentaries on the text.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Out of 44 volumes of &quot;Kiden,&quot; Volume 1 provides general remarks (an outline), including &apos;Naobinomitama&apos; (a book of Shinto), Volume 2 commentaries on the preface and the genealogy of gods, and the rest, Volume 3 to 44, commentaries on the text.</e>
<cmt>コンマを&quot;内に原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>なお、一時期『古事記』本文の定本視されていた『訂正古訓古事記』は、宣長の死後、1803年（享和3年）に弟子たちが『古事記伝』の本文と訓のみを一部訂正して出版したテキストである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, &quot;Teisei Kokun Kojiki&quot;, which was once regarded as the &quot;Kojiki&quot;&apos;s authentic manuscript, is actually a book published by Norinaga&apos;s pupils in 1803 after he died; in this book, small corrections were made only to the text and reading &quot;Kojikiden&quot; provides.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, &quot;Teisei Kokun Kojiki&quot;, which was once regarded as the &quot;Kojiki&quot;&apos;s authentic manuscript, is actually a book published by Norinaga&apos;s pupils in 1803 after he died; in this book, small corrections were made only to the text and reading &quot;Kojikiden&quot; provides.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, &quot;Teisei Kokun Kojiki&quot;, which was once regarded as the &quot;Kojiki&quot;&apos;s authentic manuscript, is actually a book published by Norinaga&apos;s pupils in 1803 after he died; in this book, small corrections were made only to the text and pronuciations &quot;Kojikiden&quot; provides.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="14">
<j>宣長の『古事記伝』は、近世における古事記研究の頂点をなし、最初の実証主義的かつ文献学的な研究として評価されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Norinaga&apos;s &quot;Kojikiden&quot; is regarded as a top-level study of &quot;Kojiki&quot; in the pre-modern period, and appreciated as the first positivist, philological work.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Norinaga&apos;s &quot;Kojikiden&quot; is regarded as a top-level study of &quot;Kojiki&quot; in the pre-modern period, and appreciated as the first positivist, philological work.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Norinaga&apos;s &quot;Kojikiden&quot; is regarded as a top-level study of Kojiki in the pre-modern period and appreciated as the first positivist, philological work.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>国語学上の定説となっている上代特殊仮名遣も、宣長によって発見された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ancient special Kana usage, which is now widely accepted by Japanese language scholars, was also discovered by Norinaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ancient special Kana usage, which is now widely accepted by Japanese language scholars, was also discovered by Norinaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ancient special Kana usage, which is now widely accepted by Japanese language scholars, was also discovered by Norinaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>宣長は『古事記伝』の註釈の中で日本の神代を尊びぶ国学を確立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In providing commentaries on &quot;Kojiki&quot; in &quot;Kojikiden&quot;, he established Kokugaku (the study of Japanese classical literature), which worships the age of Japanese deities.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In providing commentaries on &quot;Kojiki&quot; in &quot;Kojikiden&quot;, he established Kokugaku (the study of Japanese classical literature), which worships the age of Japanese deities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In providing commentaries on Kojiki in &quot;Kojikiden,&quot; he established Kokugaku (the study of Japanese classical literature), which worships the age of Japanese deities.</e>
<cmt>原文に『』のない&quot;を削除コンマを&quot;内に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>彼が『古事記』を称揚したことから宣長以後は『古事記』に対する評価が一変し、それまでは正史である『日本書紀』と比して冷遇されていたのが、神典として祭り上げられるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Norinaga&apos;s admiration of &quot;Kojiki&quot; completely changed the way people had seen it; &quot;Kojiki&quot;, which had been regarded as inferior to &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), the official history of Japan, came to be regarded as Shinto scriptures.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Norinaga&apos;s admiration of &quot;Kojiki&quot; completely changed the way people had seen it; &quot;Kojiki&quot;, which had been regarded as inferior to &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), the official history of Japan, came to be regarded as Shinto scriptures.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Norinaga&apos;s admiration for &quot;Kojiki&quot; completely changed the way people saw it. It had been regarded as inferior to &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), the official history of Japan, but it came to be regarded as a collection of Shinto scriptures.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>宣長は、『古事記』の註釈にあたって、本文に記述された伝承はすべて真実にあったことと信じ、「やまとごころ」を重視して儒教的な「からごころ」を退けるという態度を貫いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In giving commentaries on &quot;Kojiki&quot;, he believed all the stories in it to be true, and strongly supported &quot;Yamatogokoro&quot; (literally, &quot;the heart of Japan&quot;) while denying &quot;kan gokoro&quot; (literally, &quot;the heart of Kara (an ancient Chinese dynasty)&quot;, a Confucian view, that attached too much importance to rules and morals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In giving commentaries on &quot;Kojiki&quot;, he believed all the stories in it to be true, and strongly supported &quot;Yamatogokoro&quot; (literally, &quot;the heart of Japan&quot;) while denying &quot;kan gokoro&quot; (literally, &quot;the heart of Kara (an ancient Chinese dynasty)&quot;, a Confucian view, that attached too much importance to rules and morals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In giving commentaries on &quot;Kojiki,&quot; he believed all the stories in it to be true, and strongly supported &quot;Yamatogokoro&quot; (literally, &quot;the heart of Japan&quot;) while denying &quot;kan gokoro&quot; (literally, &quot;the heart of Kara (an ancient Chinese dynasty),&quot; a Confucian view.</e>
<cmt>コンマを&quot;内にthat attached too much importance to rules and morals.は原文にはない説明で、ここでは特に必要ないと思うので削除。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="19">
<j>文学・歴史研究への影響</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its influence on studies on literature and history</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its influence on studies of literature and history</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its influence on studies of literature and history</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>『古事記伝』は、単に『古事記』一作の註釈書としてのみならず、のちの古代文学研究、あるいは古代史研究にも極めて大きな影響を及ぼしてた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kojikiden&quot; is not only comprehensive commentaries on &quot;Kojiki&quot;, but also had an immense impact on research into ancient literature and history.</e>
<cmt>「『古事記』一作」の「一作」を「全体の」の意味に解釈しています。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kojikiden&quot; is not only comprehensive commentaries on &quot;Kojiki&quot;, but also had an immense impact on research into ancient literature and history.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Kojikiden&quot; is not only comprehensive commentaries on &quot;Kojiki,&quot; but also had an immense impact on research into ancient literature and history.</e>
<cmt>コンマを&quot;内に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>21世紀にあっても、『古事記』および古代文化研究の基本書としての地位を保ち続けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even in the twenty-first century, his book continues to be referred to by the scholars of &quot;Kojiki&quot; and ancient culture as the authoritative book.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even in the twenty-first century, his book continues to be referred to by the scholars of &quot;Kojiki&quot; and ancient culture as the authoritative book.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even in the twenty-first century, his book continues to be referred to by the scholars of &quot;Kojiki&quot; and ancient culture as the authoritative book.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>今日の『古事記』註釈書は、基本的には宣長の採用した読み・解釈にその後の研究による訂正を加えたものが主流となっている、と言っても過言ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is fair to say that today&apos;s commentaries on &quot;Kojiki&quot; have mostly adopted the reading and interpretation by Norinaga although some corrections have been made to them by later researchers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is fair to say that today&apos;s commentaries on &quot;Kojiki&quot; have mostly adopted the reading and interpretation by Norinaga although some corrections have been made to them by later researchers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is fair to say that today&apos;s commentaries on &quot;Kojiki&quot; have mostly adopted the reading and interpretation by Norinaga although some corrections have been made to them by later researchers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>一方で、そうした宣長流の註釈・解釈に異論を唱える立場からも様々な批判がなされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, there are various criticisms from people who oppose to his commentaries and interpretations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, there are various criticisms from people who oppose his commentaries and interpretations.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, there are various criticisms from people who oppose his commentaries and interpretations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="24">
<j>邪馬台国論争に関しては、宣長は尊王攘夷の立場に立っていた『三国志演義』に基づき『魏志倭人伝』を解釈して、卑弥呼女酋説・邪馬台国九州説を提唱した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Norinaga interpreted &quot;Gishi wajinden&quot; (Records of the Wa people, Chronicle of Wei) based on &quot;Romance of the Three Kingdoms&quot;, which supported the view of Sonno Joi, (a view that advocates reverence for the Emperor and the expulsion of foreigners), and came up with the theory that Himiko was the female head of the Yamataikoku kingdom and the kingdom was located in Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Norinaga interpreted &quot;Gishi wajinden&quot; (Records of the Wa people, Chronicle of Wei) based on &quot;Romance of the Three Kingdoms&quot;, which supported the view of Sonno Joi, (a view that advocates reverence for the Emperor and the expulsion of foreigners), and came up with the theory that Himiko was the female head of the Yamataikoku kingdom and the kingdom was located in Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Norinaga interpreted &quot;Gishi wajinden&quot; (Records of the Wa people, Chronicle of Wei) based on &quot;Romance of the Three Kingdoms,&quot; which supported the view of Sonno Joi, (a view that advocates reverence for the Emperor and the expulsion of foreigners), and came up with the theory that Himiko was the female head of the Yamataikoku kingdom and the kingdom was located in Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>コンマを&quot;内に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>新井白石とともにその後の耶馬台国論争の火種とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His theory and that of Hakuseki ARAI (1657-1725), who insisted that the kingdom was in Yamato (the Kinki region), have become the source of controversy called &quot;Controversy over Yamataikoku&quot;.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His theory and that of Hakuseki ARAI (1657-1725), who insisted that the kingdom was in Yamato (the Kinki region), have become the source of controversy called &quot;Controversy over Yamataikoku&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His theory and that of Hakuseki ARAI, who insisted that the kingdom was in Yamato (the Kinki region), have become the source of controversy called Controversy over Yamataikoku.</e>
<cmt>他ファイルに合わせ(1657-1725)を削除原文に『』のない&quot;を削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="26">
<j>その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>『古事記伝』の題字は宣長を召抱えた紀州藩10代藩主徳川治寶から下賜されたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The cover title of &quot;Kojikiden&quot; (&quot;古事記伝&quot;) was written by Harutomi TOKUNAGA, the tenth lord of the Kishu domain, who employed Norinaga, as a token of his appreciation.</e>
<cmt>「下賜」の訳をですが、あえて「grant」を使いませんでした。徳川治寶が実際に書いていますので、その意味を出して訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The cover title of &quot;Kojikiden&quot; (&quot;古事記伝&quot;) was written by Harutomi TOKUNAGA, the tenth lord of the Kishu domain, who employed Norinaga, as a token of his appreciation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The cover title of &quot;Kojikiden&quot; (&quot;古事記伝&quot;) was written by Harutomi TOKUNAGA, the tenth lord of the Kishu domain, who employed Norinaga, as a token of his appreciation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kurz(id:1601), Samacat(id:133386), 目白梅(id:141468), Mooko(id:36162), Nnh(id:474), MCHC(id:208548), Stanislaus(id:1806), Mochi(id:9489), Charenji(id:7908), ラッパ食堂(id:255123), Charon(id:9162), Shimoxx(id:9332), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>