<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>神木</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinboku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinboku</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinboku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>神木（しんぼく）とは、古神道における神籬（ひもろぎ）としての木や森をさし、神体のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinboku refers to a tree or a forest as Himorogi (a shrine surrounded by trees or forests) and an object of worship.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinboku refers to a tree or a forest as Himorogi (a shrine surrounded by trees or forests) and an object of worship.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinboku refers to a tree or a forest as Himorogi (a temporarily erected sacred space or &quot;altar&quot; used as a locus of worship) in Koshinto (ancient Shinto) and an object of worship.</e>
<cmt>神籬→Himorogi (a temporarily erected sacred space or &quot;altar&quot; used as a locus of worship) としました。古神道→Koshinto (ancient Shinto) としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>また依り代・神域・結界の意味も同時に内包する木々。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Otherwise, shinboku refers to trees that involves roles as yorishiro (an object to spiritually rely on instead of a god), shiniki (shrine precincts or a holy area), or kekkai (the border of a spiritually limited area or prevention of invasion of spiritually evil existences).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Otherwise, shinboku refers to trees that involves roles as yorishiro (an object to spiritually rely on instead of a god), shiniki (shrine precincts or a holy area), or kekkai (the border of a spiritually limited area or prevention of invasion of spiritually evil existences).</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Otherwise, shinboku refers to trees that involves roles as yorishiro (an object to spiritually rely on instead of a god), shiniki (shrine precincts or a holy area), or kekkai (the border of a spiritually limited area or prevention of invasion of spiritually evil existences).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>一般的に神社神道の神社、神宮の境内にある神体としての木や神聖視される木、その周りを囲む鎮守の森や、伐採をしないとされる木を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In general, shinboku refers to a tree as an object of worship or a tree considered to be holy, in the precincts of a shrine or a high-class shrine of Jinja-Shinto; a forest surrounding a shrine to protect the shrine; or a tree that is not cut down.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In general, shinboku refers to a tree as an object of worship or a tree considered to be holy, in the precincts of a shrine or a high-class shrine of Jinja-Shinto; a forest surrounding a shrine to protect the shrine; or a tree that is not cut down.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In general, shinboku refers to a tree as an object of worship or a tree considered to be holy, in the precincts of a shrine or a high-class shrine of Jinja-Shinto; a forest surrounding a shrine to protect the shrine; or a tree that is not cut down.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>この他、神社の所有地、民間の所有地であて民間伝承などの特別な謂われのある木を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, shinboku refers to a tree which is in a site owned by a shrine or a private land and which has a special history such as a oral tradition.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, shinboku refers to a tree which is in a site owned by a shrine or a private land and which has a special history such as an oral tradition.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, shinboku refers to a tree which is in a site owned by a shrine or a private land and which has a special history such as an oral tradition.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>神社の造営に当たってその木材となる植林または自生する特別に伐採された木を指す場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinboku sometimes refers to trees which are grown by forestation, have naturally grown and which are specially cut down to be used for building a shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinboku sometimes refers to trees which are grown by forestation, have naturally grown and which are specially cut down to be used for building a shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinboku sometimes refers to trees which are grown by forestation, have naturally grown and which are specially cut down to be used for building a shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>神籬・磐座信仰（いわくらしんこう）という自然崇拝も古神道の一部であり、神や命や自然に対する感謝や畏怖・畏敬から、環境が変わる場所にある象徴的なものを、木に限らず神体とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The nature worship such as himorogi and iwakura-shinko (large rock worship) is a part of the old shinto and not only trees but also any symbolic object which is located at a border between environments is treated as an object of worship because of gratitude, fear, and reverence to gods, life, and nature.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The nature worship such as himorogi and iwakura-shinko (large rock worship) is a part of the old shinto and includes not only trees but also any symbolic object which is located at a border between environments and is treated as an object of worship because of gratitude, fear, and reverence towards gods, life, and nature.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The nature worship such as himorogi and iwakura-shinko (large rock worship) is a part of the Koshinto and includes not only trees but also any symbolic object which is located at a border between environments and is treated as an object of worship because of gratitude, fear, and reverence towards gods, life, and nature.</e>
<cmt>古神道→Koshinto としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>この古神道から数千年を経る中で、形式や様式が器としての神社や内面としての祭礼が、外来の宗教の影響または独自に確立され、神社神道などになっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Through the history of several thousand years of old shinto, forms and styles for shrines as containers and for festival rites as the inner substance have established independently or under the influence of foreign religions, and these are further established as jinja (shrine) shinto, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Throughout the several thousand year history of old shinto, forms and styles for shrines as containers and for festival rites were established independently or under the influence of foreign religions, and these were further established as jinja (shrine) shinto, etc.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Throughout the several thousand year history of Koshinto, forms and styles for shrines as containers and for festival rites as inner substance were established independently or under the influence of foreign religions, and these were further established as jinja (shrine) shinto, etc.</e>
<cmt>一部翻訳を追加しました。古神道→Koshinto　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>神の居る場所は、社（やしろ）といわれる神道の神殿に移っていったが、日本に数万ある神社は、もともとは、この古神道における神籬のある場所に建立されたものがほとんどであり、そのことから境内に神籬としての神木や磐座としての霊石（岩）やあるいは碑や塚が存在し祀られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though the place where a god stays has been changed to a sanctuary of shinto called yashiro, most of several ten thousand shrines in Japan were each originally constructed at a place where there was himorogi and, therefore, each of those shrines has shinboku as himorogi or a spiritual stone (rock) as iwakura in its precincts and it is deified.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though the place where a god stays has been changed to a sanctuary of shinto called yashiro, most of several ten thousand shrines in Japan were each originally constructed at a place where there was himorogi and, therefore, each of those shrines has shinboku as himorogi or a spiritual stone (rock) as iwakura in its precincts and it is deified.</e>
<cmt>This translation makes almost no sense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the place where a god stays has been changed to a sanctuary of shinto called yashiro, most of several ten thousand shrines in Japan were each originally constructed at a place where there was himorogi in Koshinto and, therefore, each of those shrines has shinboku as himorogi or a spiritual stone (rock) as iwakura in its precincts and it is deified.</e>
<cmt>though →although としました。「古神道における」を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>また古神道と神社神道は、ある部分では共存し不可分でもあるため、神社によっては社を持たず、神木をそのまま神体として祀っているところもあり、また、神社はなくとも自然そのままにある神木が多くの信仰を集めている場所もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Old shinto and jinja shinto coexist and are inseparable in some aspects and, therefore, some shrines have no buildings and feify shinboku as their objects of worship, and some places are worshiped because of their shinboku which have naturally grown even though there are no shrines in such places.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Old shinto and jinja shinto coexist and are inseparable in some aspects and, therefore, some shrines have no buildings and deify shinboku as objects of worship, and some places are worshiped because of shinboku which have naturally grown even though there are no shrines in such places.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koshinto and jinja shinto coexist and are inseparable in some aspects and, therefore, some shrines have no buildings and deify shinboku as objects of worship, and some places are worshiped because of shinboku which have naturally grown even though there are no shrines in such places.</e>
<cmt>古神道→Koshinto　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>依代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yorishiro</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yorishiro</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yorishiro</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>神依木（かみよりぎ）、勧進木（かんじんぼく）等は神の依り代とされ、しめ縄などで特別扱いされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kamiyorigi, kanijnboku, etc., are specially treated as yorishiro of a god and are decorated with shimenawa (a holy straw rope).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kamiyorigi, kanijnboku, etc., are specially treated as yorishiro of a god and are decorated with shimenawa (a holy straw rope).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kamiyorigi, kanijnboku, etc., are specially treated as yorishiro of a god and are decorated with shimenawa (a holy straw rope).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>社殿の無い神域などでは御神体として扱われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinboku is treated as the object of worship in shinnki where there is no shrine buildings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinboku is treated as an object of worship in shinnki where there are no shrine buildings.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinboku is treated as an object of worship in shiniki where there are no shrine buildings.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>ナギやモチノキ、スギなどが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagi trees, mochinoki tree and cedars are often treated as shinboku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagi trees, mochinoki tree and cedars are often treated as shinboku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagi trees, mochinoki tree and cedars are often treated as shinboku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>この他、伊勢神宮の神宮スギなど景観維持や、荘厳さを醸し出すために依り代とは別に特別視された木などを神木扱いにしている場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, in some cases, trees which are considered special in addition to yorishiro in order to maintain the scenery or make an solemn atmosphere such as jingu cedars in the Ise-jingu shrine are treated as shinboku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, in some cases, trees which are considered special in addition to yorishiro in order to maintain the scenery or make an solemn atmosphere such as jingu cedars in the Ise-jingu shrine are treated as shinboku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, in some cases, trees which are considered special in addition to yorishiro in order to maintain the scenery or make an solemn atmosphere such as jingu cedars in the Ise-jingu Shrine are treated as shinboku.</e>
<cmt>Ise-jingu Shrine としまｓｈた。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>山などで仕事をする物にとって、山の神の依り代として目立つ木を一時的に神木とし、祀る場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For those who work in mountains, conspicuous trees are temporarily treated as shinboku and deified as yorishiro of mountain gods.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For those who work in mountains, conspicuous trees are temporarily treated as shinboku and deified as yorishiro of mountain gods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For those who work in mountains, conspicuous trees are temporarily treated as shinboku and deified as yorishiro of mountain gods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="15">
<j>神社神道における儀式で使われ、サカキやナギによって作られる御幣も神籬というが、もともとは、古神道における自然にある神木の代用としての、簡易の依り代である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though gohei which is used in rites of jinjs-shinto and which is made of sakaki tree branches or nagi tree branches is also called himorogi, gohei is originally a simplified yorishiro as a substitute of naturally-grown shinboku in old shinto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though gohei which is used in rites of jinja-shinto and which is made of sakaki tree branches or nagi tree branches is also called himorogi, gohei is originally a simplified yorishiro as a substitute of naturally-grown shinboku in old shinto.</e>
<cmt>Spelling, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although gohei which is used in rites of jinja shinto and which is made of sakaki tree branches or nagi tree branches is also called himorogi, gohei is originally a simplified yorishiro as a substitute of naturally-grown shinboku in Koshinto.</e>
<cmt>though →although としました。古神道→Koshinto　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>神域・結界</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shiniki and kekkai</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shiniki and kekkai</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shiniki and kekkai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="16">
<j>古神道において神籬は、神の宿る場所としての神域、または常世（とこよ）と現世（うつしよ）の端境と考えれ、恐れ敬った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Himorogi in old shinto is considered as shiniki as a place for a god to stay, or the border of the other world and this world, and is feared and respected.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Himorogi in old shinto considered shiniki as a place for a god to stay, or a border to the other world and this world, and was feared and respected.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Himorogi in Koshinto considered shiniki as a place for a god to stay, or a border to the other world and this world, and was feared and respected.</e>
<cmt>古神道→Koshinto　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>そして人や現世にあるものや、常世に存在する神やまたは、現世にとって禍や厄災を招くものが、簡単に行き来できないように、結界として注連縄をはり、禁足地とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shimenawa (a decorated straw rope) is put around himorogi as kekkai to prevent people or things in this world, gods in the other world, or those that invite misfortunes and mishaps for this world from easily come and go across and, thereby, himorogi is an off-limits place.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shimenawa (a decorated straw rope) is put around himorogi as kekkai to prevent people or things in this world, gods in the other world, or those that invite misfortunes and mishaps for this world from easily coming over and go across, making himorogi off-limits.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shimenawa (a decorated straw rope) is put around himorogi as kekkai to prevent people or things in this world, gods in the other world, or those that invite misfortunes and mishaps for this world from easily coming over and go across, making himorogi off-limits.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>現在でも沖ノ島など社や神木や鎮守の森だけでなく島全体が禁足地になっているところも多くある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At present, in many places, not only shrines, shinboku, and shrine forests but also the whole island is an off-limits place such as Okinoshima Island.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At present, in many places, not only shrines, shinboku, and shrine forests but entire islands are considered to be off-limits, such as Okinoshima Island.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At present, in many places, not only shrines, shinboku, and shrine forests but entire islands are considered to be off-limits, such as Okino-shima Island.</e>
<cmt>Okino-shima Island としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>招福したい時を一定の期間だけ設けて、神木などの結界を解き神を招くという儀式や祭礼を行うところもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In some places, a specific time period to invite happiness is provided and rites and festivals to cancel kekkai of shinboku and to invite gods are held.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In some places, a specific time period to invite happiness is provided and rites and festivals to cancel kekkai of shinboku and to invite gods are held.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In some places, a specific time period to invite happiness is provided and rites and festivals to cancel kekkai of shinboku and to invite gods are held.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>伝承</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oral tradition</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oral tradition</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oral tradition</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="20">
<j>昔話など、特別な謂われのある木を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinboku refers to a tree which has a special episode such as an old tale.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinboku refer to a tree which has a special episode such as an old tale.</e>
<cmt>Doesn&apos;t make sense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinboku refers to a tree which has a special episode such as an old tale.</e>
<cmt>翻訳者の方の翻訳のとおりに、refers としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>この他、有名な歌人が歌に詠んだ木などが神木として扱われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, a tree such as one which is featured in tanka poem by a famous tanka poet is treated as shinboku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, a tree such as one which is featured in a tanka poem by a famous tanka poet is treated as shinboku.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, a tree such as one which is featured in a waka poem by a famous tanka poet is treated as shinboku.</e>
<cmt>短歌よりもより一般的に「和歌」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>太宰府天満宮の梅など歌人が歌にした木などが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many trees are treated as shinboku that are featured in tanka poems by tanka poet such as a Japanese plum tree in Dazaifu-Tenmangu shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many trees are treated as shinboku that are featured in tanka poems by tanka poet such as the Japanese plum tree in Dazaifu-Tenmangu shrine.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many trees are treated as shinboku that are featured in waka poems by tanka poet such as the Japanese plum tree in Dazaifu-Tenmangu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>Shrine 大文字にしました。短歌よりもより一般的に「和歌」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>記念樹</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Memorial Tree</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Memorial Tree</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Memorial tree</e>
<cmt>小タイトルのため、小文字にしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="23">
<j>神社等に何らかの関係のある人物が寄進した木などを神聖視し神木として扱われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A tree which was donated by a person who is related to a shrine, etc., for some reason has been considered holy and treated as shinboku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A tree which was donated by a person who is related to a shrine, etc., for some reason has been considered holy and treated as shinboku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A tree which was donated by a person who is related to a shrine, etc., for some reason has been considered holy and treated as shinboku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>造営木</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Trees for Construction Material</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Trees for Construction Material</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Trees for construction material</e>
<cmt>小タイトルのため、小文字にしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="24">
<j>神社を造営するにあたりその材木となる木を神木扱いする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The trees to be used as lumbers for constructing a shrine are treated as shinboku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The trees to be used as lumber for constructing a shrine are treated as shinboku.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The trees to be used as lumber for constructing a shrine are treated as shinboku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Æskja(id:125536), みゅり(id:266571), くっちゃめ(id:86793), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>