<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>盟神探湯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kugatachi (a way of decision putting one&apos;s hand in hot water)</e>
<cmt>Googleのヒットが一番多かった「くがたち」を読みに採用しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kugatachi</e>
<cmt>Deleted explanation as it&apos;s included later</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kugatachi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>盟神探湯（くかたち、くかだち、くがたち）は、古代日本で行われていた神明裁判のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kugatachi&quot; (also called kukatachi and kukadachi) refer to shinmeisaiban (trials by ordeals) which were held in ancient Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kugatachi&quot; (also known as kukatachi and kukadachi) refers to trials by ordeal held in ancient Japan.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Kugatachi&quot; (also known as kukatachi and kukadachi) refers to trials by ordeal held in ancient Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>ある人の是非・正邪を判断するための呪術的な裁判法（神判）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a way of spiritual trials (by ordeals) to judge if a person is right or wrong.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was a spiritual trial (by ordeal) used to judge if a person was right or wrong.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was a spiritual trial (by ordeal) used to judge if a person was right or wrong.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>探湯・誓湯とも書く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also written as 探湯 and 誓湯.</e>
<cmt>訳文に漢字を使用しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It can be written 盟神探湯, 探湯 and 誓湯.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity - though not sure this is relevant for most English speakers</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It can be written 盟神探湯, 探湯 and 誓湯.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>対象となる者に、神に潔白などを誓わせた後、釜で沸かした熱湯の中に手を入れさせる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A target person is ordered to swear his innocence under god, then put his hand into boiling water in an iron pot.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The accused was ordered to swear his innocence before the gods, and then made to put his hand into a pot of boiling water.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The accused was ordered to swear his innocence before the gods, and then made to put his hand into a pot of boiling water.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>正しい者は火傷せず、罪のある者は大火傷を負うとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that an innocent person won&apos;t get burned but a guilty person terribly will.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was said that an innocent person would be unharmed but a guilty person would be badly scalded.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was said that an innocent person would be unharmed but a guilty person would be badly scalded.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>毒蛇を入れた壷に手を入れさせ、正しい者は無事である、という様式もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is another way that a target person is ordered to put his hand into a pot which a poisonous snake is inside, and an innocent person won&apos;t get hurt.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A similar trial has the accused putting his hand into a pot containing a poisonous snake, with an innocent person remaining unharmed.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A similar trial has the accused putting his hand into a pot containing a poisonous snake, with an innocent person remaining unharmed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>あらかじめ結果を神に示した上で行為を行い、その結果によって判断するということで、うけいの一種である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They show an expected result to god in advance, then do the act.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was a kind of divination with the expected result being shown to the gods in advance and</e>
<cmt>Revised to rejoin to cell F14</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was a kind of divination with the expected result being shown to the gods in advance and then the judgment was based on the actual result.</e>
<cmt>NCでセル14と一文になったため原文と訳文を移動スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>類似の方法は日本に限らず、ヨーロッパなどの神明裁判でも行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Similar ways of shinmeisaiban were held not only in Japan but in Europe.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Similar trials by ordeal were also held in Europe.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Similar trials by ordeal were also held in Europe.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>日本書紀の記録</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Records in Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Records in Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Records in Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="9">
<j>応神天皇9年4月条に、武内宿禰が弟の甘見内宿禰の讒言を受けて殺されそうになり、武内宿禰が潔白を主張したので、天皇は2人に礒城川で盟神探湯をさせたとの記事がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a passage for April in 278, it is recorded that TAKENOUCHI no Sukune was about to be killed because of his brother, UMASHIUCHI no sukune&apos;s calumny, but he insisted on his innocence, therefore the Emperor held a kugatachi for them at Shiki-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>年は西暦を採用しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The entry for April, 278, records that TAKENOUCHI no Sukune, who was about to be killed after being falsely charged by his brother, UMASHIUCHI no Sukune, insisted on his innocence, and therefore the Emperor held a kugatachi for them at Shiki-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The entry for April, 278, records that TAKENOUCHI no Sukune, who was about to be killed after being falsely charged by his brother, UMASHIUCHI no Sukune, insisted on his innocence, and therefore the Emperor held a kugatachi for them at Shiki-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>允恭天皇4年9月条には、上下の秩序が乱れて、むかしの姓（かばね）を失ったり、わざと高い氏（うじ）を名乗る者も出てきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a passage for September in 415, it is recorded that as the pecking order got broken down, some people lost their old kabane (hereditary title) or intentionally announced themselves with uji (family names) of higher ranks.</e>
<cmt>日本語が不適切であったため、語尾を「名乗る者も出てきたという記事がある。」と変更し訳出しました。また前行と同様に、年は西暦を採用しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the entry for September, 415, it is recorded that as the social order broke down, some people lost their old kabane (hereditary title) or intentionally adopted uji (family names) of higher ranks.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the entry for September, 415, it is recorded that as the social order broke down, some people lost their old kabane (hereditary title) or intentionally adopted uji (family names) of higher ranks.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>それを正すために甘樫丘で盟神探湯を行ったという記事がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To straighten that out, a kugatachi was held at Amakashi no oka Hill.</e>
<cmt>前文の語尾を変更したことに伴い、こちらの原文は語尾を「行ったという。」に変更し訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to amend the situation, a kugatachi was held at Amakashi no oka Hill.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to amend the situation, a kugatachi was held at Amakashi no oka Hill.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>各自が沐浴斎戒し、木綿の襷をつけて探湯を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After having balneum bath and purification, each one had a kugatachi wearing a cotton tasuki (a cord to tuck up the sleeves of a kimono).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After bathing for purification, each person tied up the sleeves of their kimonos and underwent kugatachi.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After bathing for purification, each person tied up the sleeves of their kimonos and underwent kugatachi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>正しく姓を名乗っている者は何ともなく、詐りの姓を名乗っている者は皆火傷をしたので、後に続く者の中で詐っている者は恐れて先に進めなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because people with right kabane didn&apos;t get burned but all people with false kabane did, those who were lying and hadn&apos;t had their turn yet were too afraid to go forward.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because people with the right kabane didn&apos;t get scalded but all people with false kabane did, those who were lying and hadn&apos;t had their turn yet were too afraid to go forward.</e>
<cmt>Article&quot;burned&quot;→&quot;scalded&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because people with the right kabane didn&apos;t get scalded but all people with false kabane did, those who were lying and hadn&apos;t had their turn yet were too afraid to go forward.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>そのため正邪がすぐにわかったとある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore it was immediately known if they were right or wrong.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore it was immediately known who was innocent and who was guilty.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore it was immediately known who was innocent and who was guilty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>この条の註記には、「泥を釜に入れて煮沸し、手を入れて泥を探る」という具体的な手順が書かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A specific procedure &apos;put mud into an iron pot and boil it, then put your hand into the pot and search the mud&apos; is written in the note of this passage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A note on the entry records that thespecific procedure is to &apos;put mud into an iron pot and boil it, then put your hand into the pot and search the mud.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A note on the entry records that the specific procedure is to &apos;put mud into an iron pot and boil it, then put your hand into the pot and search the mud.&apos;</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="16">
<j>継体天皇24年9月条には、任那人と日本人との訴訟を決することができなかったので、誓湯を行ったとある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a passage for September in 530, it is recorded that suits between people from Mimana and Japanese couldn&apos;t be brought therefore a kugatachi was held.</e>
<cmt>年は西暦を採用しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the entry for September, 530, it is recorded that lawsuits between people from Mimana (on the Korean peninsula) and Japan that could not be decided were settled by kugatachi.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the entry for September, 530, it is recorded that lawsuits between people from Mimana (on the Korean peninsula) and Japan that could not be decided were settled by kugatachi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>中世の記録</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Medieval records</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Medieval records</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Medieval records</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="17">
<j>盟神探湯の記録はこれから900年の間存在しない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are no records about kugatachi for next 900 years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are no records about kugatachi for the next 900 years.</e>
<cmt>Article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are no records about kugatachi for the next 900 years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>記録に見えなかった時期に、盟神探湯による裁判は行われなかったのか、それとも水面下で続いていたかどうかははっきりしない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is unknown if trials by kugatachi were not held or were continuously held in secret during this period without records.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is unknown if trials by kugatachi were not held or were continuously held in secret during this period.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;without records&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is unknown if trials by kugatachi were not held or were continuously held in secret during this period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="19">
<j>しかし、室町時代の応永年間になると再び記録に表れるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However they came on records again during Oei era in Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However they reappear in records during the Oei era in the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However they reappear in records during the Oei era in the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>この時代には「湯起請」という名で呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were called yugisho (testimony by boiling water) in this period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During this period, the practice was known as yugisho (testimony by boiling water).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During this period, the practice was known as yugisho (testimony by boiling water).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>特に足利義教は政治的裁判にしばしば盟神探湯を用いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA often used kugatachi for political trials.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In particular, Shogun Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA often used kugatachi for political trials.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In particular, Shogun Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA often used kugatachi for political trials.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>しかし、その後再び記録から消滅する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But they disappeared from the records again after that.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But they disappeared from the records again after that.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But they disappeared from the records again after that.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>意義</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meaning</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Effectiveness</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity - not an exact translation but better describes the following paragraph</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Effectiveness</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="23">
<j>科学的・合理的に見れば全く無意味な方法であるが、古代社会において、容疑者に恐怖感を与えて犯罪行為を自白させるための手段としてはある程度有効であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a totally meaningless way in scientific and rational sense, but it was effective to some extent as a method to give suspects feelings of terror and make them confess to their criminal acts in an ancient society.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was completely without scientific and rational basis but, for people in earlier times, it was effective to some extent, instilling fear in suspects and making them confess their crimes.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was completely without scientific and rational basis but, for people in earlier times, it was effective to some extent, instilling fear in suspects and making them confess their crimes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other</e>
<cmt>Deleted &apos;s&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="24">
<j>神判としての盟神探湯の歴史が終わると、この言葉は神前に拝する時に身を清めるために沸かす湯の意味となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the history of kugatachi as ordeals was over, this term became the meaning of hot water to be used for purifying our bodies when we worship before the gods.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the end of the use of kugatachi as a trial by ordeal, the term came to signify the hot water used to purify the body when worshipping before the gods.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the end of the use of kugatachi as a trial by ordeal, the term came to signify the hot water used to purify the body when worshipping before the gods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>釜で沸かした熱湯を笹の葉などで参拝者にかける湯立、湯起請などの神事は、この意味の盟神探湯に由来するものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinto rituals such as yudate (a rite to apply boiling water in an iron pot to worshipers using bamboo leaves) and yugisho (a testimony by boiling water) originated kugatachi in this sense.</e>
<cmt>訳文を読みやすくするために、湯立の説明部分に括弧を補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinto rituals such as yudate (a rite where water boiled in an iron pot is applied to worshipers using bamboo leaves) and yugisho (testimony by boiling water) originated from this sense of kugatachi.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinto rituals such as yudate (a rite where water boiled in an iron pot is applied to worshipers using bamboo leaves) and yugisho (testimony by boiling water) originated from this sense of kugatachi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Zorac(id:28001), 新茶(id:157775), Sat666(id:127263), Godaigo(id:133481), Nnh(id:474), BBG(id:124711), MUSASHI(id:11881), 鈴木早智子(id:120713), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>