<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>陰陽道</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ommyodo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ommyodo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ommyodo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>陰陽道（おんみょうどう）は、古代の中国で生まれた自然哲学思想、陰陽五行思想を起源として日本で独自の発展を遂げた自然科学と呪術の体系。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ommyodo, which owes its origin in the ancient Chinese natural philosophy theory and Inyo-gogyo-shiso theory (the way of Yin and Yang, combined with the Taoist theory of five elements), is the system of natural science and the art of spell-casting that uniquely developed in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ommyodo, which owes its origin to ancient Chinese natural philosophical theory and Inyo-gogyo-shiso theory (the way of Yin and Yang, combined with the Taoist theory of the five elements), is a system of natural science and the art of spell-casting that uniquely developed in Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar corrected, Note: philosophy is not a science, Perhaps &quot;nature worship&quot; would be a better term to substitute for &quot;natural science&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ommyodo, which owes its origin to ancient Chinese natural philosophical theory and Inyo-gogyo-shiso theory (the way of Yin and Yang, combined with the Taoist theory of the five elements), is a system of natural science and the art of spell-casting that uniquely developed in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>「いんようどう」とも読む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Chinese characters for Ommyodo can be read &quot;Inyodo&quot; as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Chinese characters for Ommyodo can be read &quot;Inyodo&quot; as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Chinese characters for Ommyodo can be read &quot;Inyodo&quot; as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>陰陽道に携わる者を陰陽師といい、陰陽師集団のことも陰陽道と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">People who practise Ommyodo are called Ommyo-ji (diviners or sorcerers) and a group of Ommyo-ji is again called Ommyodo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">People who practise Ommyodo are called Ommyo-ji (diviners or sorcerers) and a group of Ommyo-ji is again called Ommyodo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">People who practise Ommyodo are called Ommyo-ji (diviners or sorcerers) and a group of Ommyo-ji is again called Ommyodo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>かつては専門の研究者によっても、陰陽家の思想が日本に伝わったものが陰陽道である、と説明されてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At one time, the researchers thought that the philosophy of the Yin and Yang that had been introduced to Japan developed into Ommyodo.</e>
<cmt>「陰陽家の思想」を忠実に訳そうとしましたが、陰陽家の部分で説明が複雑になりすぎるため、「陰陽思想」と読み替えました。内容的には変わらないと思われます。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At one time, researchers thought that the philosophy of the Yin and Yang introduced into Japan developed into Ommyodo.</e>
<cmt>sentence streamlined and simplified for clarity and readability</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At one time, researchers thought that the philosophy of the Yin and Yang introduced into Japan developed into Ommyodo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>しかし、近年では、陰陽五行説が、自然界の万物は陰と陽の二気から生ずるとする陰陽と、万物は木・火・土・金・水の五行からなるとする五行思想を組み合わせ、自然界の陰陽と五行の変化を観察して瑞祥・災厄を判断し、人間界の吉凶を占う実用的技術として日本で受容され、神道、道教、仏教などからも様々な影響を受け取って日本特異の発展を遂げた結果誕生したものと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In recent years, however, people think that Ommyodo reached its system as follows; the Ommyo-gogyo-setsu theory, which had combined the theory of Ommyo (the Yin and Yang), which considers that the universe has been derived from the Yin and Yang, and the theory of Gogyo-shiso, which considers that the universe consists of the five elements of wood, fire, earth, metal, and water, developed uniquely in Japan into practical fortune telling techniques that could serve human needs based on the auspicious and inauspicious signs obtained by observing the Yin and Yang in Nature and changes in the five elements, while being affected by Shinto, Taiosm, and Buddhism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In recent years, however, it is thought that Ommyodo developed as follows; the Ommyo-gogyo-setsu theory, that combined the theory of Ommyo (the Yin and Yang), which considers that the universe has been derived from the Yin and Yang, and the theory of Gogyo-shiso, which considers that the universe consists of the five elements of wood, fire, earth, metal, and water, developed uniquely in Japan into a practical fortune telling technique that could serve human needs based upon the auspicious and inauspicious signs obtained by observing the Yin and Yang in Nature and changes in the five elements, while being affected by Shinto, Taiosm, and Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>sentence streamlined and simplified for clarity and readability</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In recent years, however, it is thought that Ommyodo developed as follows; the Ommyo-gogyo-setsu theory, that combined the theory of Ommyo (the Yin and Yang), which considers that the universe has been derived from the Yin and Yang, and the theory of Gogyo-shiso, which considers that the universe consists of the five elements of wood, fire, earth, metal, and water, developed uniquely in Japan into a practical fortune telling technique that could serve human needs based upon the auspicious and inauspicious signs obtained by observing the Yin and Yang in Nature and changes in the five elements, while being affected by Shinto, Taoism, and Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>Taiosm→Taoism</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>5世紀から6世紀頃、陰陽五行説が仏教や儒教とともに日本に伝わったとき、陰陽五行説と密接な関係をもつ天文、暦数、時刻、易経といった自然の観察に関わる学問、占術とあわさって、自然界の瑞祥・災厄を判断し、人間界の吉凶を占う技術として日本社会に受け入れられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Ommyo-gogyo-setsu theory was introduced to Japan together with Buddhism and Confucianism during the 5th and 6th centuries, it combined with the studies and art of divination that involve the observation of Nature, including astronomy, Rekisu (a study to establish a calendar by calculating the solar and lunar movements), time science, Iching (Book of Changes), and became adopted in the Japanese society as fortune telling techniques that could serve the human needs based on the auspicious and inauspicious signs identified in Nature.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Ommyo-gogyo-setsu theory was introduced to Japan together with Buddhism and Confucianism during the 5th and 6th centuries, it combined the studies and art of divination that involve the observations of Nature, including astronomy, Rekisu (a study to establish a calendar by calculating the solar and lunar movements), time science, Iching (Book of Changes), and became adopted in Japanese society as fortune telling techniques that could serve human needs based on the auspicious and inauspicious signs identified in Nature.</e>
<cmt>grammar corrected</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Ommyo-gogyo-setsu theory was introduced to Japan together with Buddhism and Confucianism during the 5th and 6th centuries, it combined the studies and art of divination that involve the observations of Nature, including astronomy, Rekisu (a study to establish a calendar by calculating the solar and lunar movements), time science, Iching (Book of Changes), and became adopted in Japanese society as fortune telling techniques that could serve human needs based on the auspicious and inauspicious signs identified in Nature.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>このような技術は、当初はおもに漢文の読み書きに通じた渡来人の僧によって担われていたが、やがて朝廷に奉仕する必要から俗人が行うことが必要となり、7世紀後半頃から陰陽師があらわれ始めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although initially, these techniques were practised by priests from overseas, especially from China and Korea, who had settled in Japan and were proficient at reading and writing Kanbun (Chinese classical literature), the later 7th century saw the appearance of Ommyo-ji as there was a need for laymen with the techniques, not priests, to serve the Imperial court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although initially, these techniques were practised by priests from overseas, especially from China and Korea, who had settled in Japan and were proficient at reading and writing Kanbun (Chinese classical literature), the later 7th century saw the appearance of Ommyo-ji as there was a need for laymen with the techniques, not priests, to serve the Imperial court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although initially, these techniques were practised by priests from overseas, especially from China and Korea, who had settled in Japan and were proficient at reading and writing Kanbun (Chinese classical literature), the later 7th century saw the appearance of Ommyo-ji as there was a need for laymen with the techniques, not priests, to serve the Imperial court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>7世紀後半から8世紀はじめに律令制がひかれると、陰陽の技術は中務省の下に設置された陰陽寮へと組織化された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the later 7th century to the early 8th century, during which the Retsuryo system (legal codes of the Nara and Heian eras based on Chinese models) was put in place, the divination techniques of Ommyo (the Yin and Yang) were transferred to Bureau of Divination placed under Ministry of Central Affairs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the later 7th century to the early 8th century, when the Retsuryo system (legal codes of the Nara and Heian eras based on Chinese models) were put into place, the divination techniques of Ommyo (the Yin and Yang) were transferred to the Bureau of Divination under Ministry of Central Affairs.</e>
<cmt>grammar corrected, wordiness reduced</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the later 7th century to the early 8th century, when the Ritsuryo system (legal codes of the Nara and Heian eras based on Chinese models) were put into place, the divination techniques of Ommyo (the Yin and Yang) were transferred to the Bureau of Divination under Ministry of Central Affairs.</e>
<cmt>Retsuryo→Ritsuryo</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>陰陽寮は配下に陰陽道、天文道、暦道を置き、それぞれに吉凶の判断、天文の観察、暦の作成の管理を行わせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bureau of Divination had the divisions of Ommyodo, Tenmondo (the art of divination by observing the movements of the sun, moon, starts, and planets and the weather), and Rekido (masters of the almanac) under it; the three divisions performed divination, observed the movement of the sun, moon, and stars, and established the calendar, respectively.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Bureau of Divination was made up of divisions dealing with Ommyodo, Tenmondo (the art of divination by observing the movements of the sun, moon, stars and planets, and the weather), and Rekido (masters of the almanac) these three divisions performed divination, observed the movement of the sun, moon, and stars, and created a calendar.</e>
<cmt>edited and revised for clarity and readability</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Bureau of Divination was made up of divisions dealing with Ommyodo, Tenmondo (the art of divination by observing the movements of the sun, moon, stars and planets, and the weather), and Rekido (masters of the almanac) these three divisions performed divination, observed the movement of the sun, moon, and stars, and created a calendar.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>また、令では僧侶が天文や災異瑞祥を説くことを禁じ、陰陽師の国家管理への独占がはかられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ritsuryo system, which had prohibited priests from practising divination and observing the movements of the sun, moon, and planets, gave opportunities for Ommyou-ji to exclusively conduct state affairs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ritsuryo system, while prohibiting priests from practising divination and observing the movements of the sun, moon, and planets, provided opportunities for Ommyou-ji to exclusively conduct state affairs.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity and readability</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ritsuryo system, while prohibiting priests from practicing divination and observing the movements of the sun, moon, and planets, provided opportunities for Ommyo-ji to exclusively conduct state affairs.</e>
<cmt>practising→practicing, Ommyou-ji→Ommyo-ji</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>平安時代以降は、律令制の弛緩と藤原氏の台頭につれて、形式化が進んだ宮廷社会で高まりつつあった怨霊に対する御霊信仰などに対し、陰陽道は占術と呪術をもって災異を回避する方法を示し、天皇や公家の私的生活に影響を与える指針となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the Heian period onwards, where the Ritsuryo system went slack and the Fujiwara clan gained power, Ommodo, which showed people how to avoid natural disasters through the art of divination and spell-casting, came to serve as guidelines that could affect the private life of the Emperor and court nobles, in contrast to Goryo-shinko (an off-shoot of Shintoism whose purpose it is to quell the angry spirits of individuals who have been done injustices), which had become increasingly popular and more ritual in the imperial court.</e>
<cmt>「平安時代以降は」となっていますが、この表現では、鎌倉時代なども含む印象をあたえ、藤原氏の台頭した平安時代であり、矛盾するように思えますが、原文どおりに訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the Heian period onwards, when the Ritsuryo system declined and the Fujiwara clan gained power, Ommodo, showed people how to avoid natural disasters through the art of divination and spell-casting and became guidelines that could affect the private life of the Emperor and court nobles, in contrast to Goryo-shinko (an off-shoot of Shintoism, its purpose to quell angry spirits of individuals who have been done injustices), which had become increasingly popular and more ritual in the imperial court.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity and readability</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the Heian period onwards, when the Ritsuryo system declined and the Fujiwara clan gained power, Ommyodo, showed people how to avoid natural disasters through the art of divination and spell-casting and became guidelines that could affect the private life of the Emperor and court nobles, in contrast to Goryo-shinko (an off-shoot of Shintoism, its purpose to quell angry spirits of individuals who have been done injustices), which had become increasingly popular and more ritual in the imperial court.</e>
<cmt>Ommodo→Ommyodo</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>これにともなって陰陽道は宮廷社会から日本社会全体へと広がりつつ一般化し、法師陰陽師などの手を通じて民間へと浸透して、日本独自の展開を強めていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Along with this move, Ommyodo spread from the palace to the Japanese society in general while becoming more generalized; thanks to the efforts by bonze Ommyo-ji, priests who practised Ommyodo, it became permeated deeply among the populace and developed more uniquely in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ommyodo spread from the palace into Japanese society while becoming more generalized; thanks to the efforts by bonze Ommyo-ji, priests who practised Ommyodo, it permeated deeply into the populace and developed more uniquely in Japan.</e>
<cmt>revised grammar, deleted unecessary words</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ommyodo spread from the palace into Japanese society while becoming more generalized; thanks to the efforts by bonze Ommyo-ji, priests who practiced Ommyodo, it permeated deeply into the populace and developed more uniquely in Japan.</e>
<cmt>practised→practiced</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>日本の陰陽道は、陰陽道と同時に伝わってきた道教の方術に由来する方違え、物忌、反閇などの呪術や、泰山府君祭などの道教的な神に対する祭礼、さらに土地の吉凶に関する風水説や、医術の一種であった呪禁道なども取り入れ、日本の神道と相互に影響を受けあいながら独自の発展を遂げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Japanese Ommyodo developed in a unique way under the reciprocal influence of Shinto while adopting the various arts and skills from Taoism, which had been introduced to Japan together with Ommyodo; they include Katatagae (a practice of reaching a destination in a different direction than going directly from one&apos;s house by putting up somewhere the night before), Monoimi (fasting, abstinence, and confinement to one&apos;s house on an unlucky day), Henbai (special footsteps in the art of Japanese public entertainment, believed to have magical power), Taizanfukunnsai (a spirit exchange ritual), Fusuisetu, and Jukondo (an art of medicine).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese Ommyodo developed in a unique way under the reciprocal influence of Shinto while adopting the various arts and skills from Taoism, introduced into Japan together with Ommyodo; they include Katatagae (practice of reaching a destination taking a different direction than going directly from one&apos;s house by putting up somewhere the night before), Monoimi (fasting, abstinence, and confinement to one&apos;s house on an unlucky day), Henbai (special footsteps in the art of Japanese public entertainment, believed to have magical powers), Taizanfukunnsai (a spirit exchange ritual), Fusuisetu, and Jukondo (an art of medicine).</e>
<cmt>removed unnecessary words</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese Ommyodo developed in a unique way under the reciprocal influence of Shinto while adopting the various arts and skills from Taoism, introduced into Japan together with Ommyodo; they include Katatagae (practice of reaching a destination taking a different direction than going directly from one&apos;s house by putting up somewhere the night before), Monoimi (fasting, abstinence, and confinement to one&apos;s house on an unlucky day), Henbai (special footsteps in the art of Japanese public entertainment, believed to have magical powers), Taizanfukunnsai (a spirit exchange ritual), Fusuisetu, and Jukondo (an art of medicine).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>8世紀末からは密教の呪法や密教とともに新しく伝わった占星術（宿曜道）や占術の影響を受ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the end of the 8th century, Ommyodo came under the influence of Juho (a way of discipline by uttering mantras) of esoteric Buddhism, Sukuyo-do (astrology) and other arts of divination, which had been introduced to Japan together with esoteric Buddhism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the end of the 8th century, Ommyodo came under the influence of Juho (a way of practicing self discipline by uttering mantras) from esoteric Buddhism, Sukuyo-do (astrology) and other arts of divination, which had been introduced into Japan together with esoteric Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the end of the 8th century, Ommyodo came under the influence of Juho (a way of practicing self discipline by uttering mantras) from esoteric Buddhism, Sukuyo-do (astrology) and other arts of divination, which had been introduced into Japan together with esoteric Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>10世紀には陰陽道・天文道・暦道いずれも究めた賀茂忠行・賀茂保憲父子が現れ、その弟子から陰陽道の占術に卓越した才能を示し、宮廷社会から非常に信頼を受けた安倍晴明が出た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The 10th century saw the appearance of Tadayuki KAMO and Yasunori KAMO, a father and a son who mastered all of Ommydo, Tenmondo, and Rekido, and ABE no Seimei, one of their disciples and a superb Ommyodo diviner, who was fully trusted by the imperial court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The 10th century saw the appearance of Tadayuki KAMO and Yasunori KAMO, a father and a son who mastered all Ommydo, Tenmondo, and Rekido, and ABE no Seimei, one of their disciples and a superb Ommyodo diviner, who was fully trusted by the imperial court.</e>
<cmt>deleted &quot;of&quot;before Ommydo,</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The 10th century saw the appearance of Tadayuki KAMO and Yasunori KAMO, a father and a son who mastered all Ommydo, Tenmondo, and Rekido, and ABE no Seimei, one of their disciples and a superb Ommyodo diviner, who was fully trusted by the imperial court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>忠行・保憲は晴明に天文道、保憲の子光栄に暦道を伝え、平安末期から中世の陰陽道は天文道・暦道を完全に取り込むとともに、天文道の阿倍氏と暦道の賀茂氏が二大宗家として独占的に支配するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadayuki and Yasunori taught Seimei Tenmondo and Koei, Yasunori&apos;s son, Rekido, which led Ommyodo to completely encompass Tenmondo and Rekido from the end of the Heian period through the Middle Ages, allowing the Abe and Kamo clans to dominate the world of Ommyodo as the two Soke (originators).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadayuki and Yasunori taught Seimei Tenmondo and Koei, Yasunori&apos;s son, Rekido, which led Ommyodo to completely encompass Tenmondo and Rekido from the end of the Heian period through the Middle Ages, allowing the Abe and Kamo clans to dominate the world of Ommyodo as the two Soke (originators).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadayuki and Yasunori taught Seimei Tenmondo and Koei, Yasunori&apos;s son, Rekido, which led Ommyodo to completely encompass Tenmondo and Rekido from the end of the Heian period through the Middle Ages, allowing the Abe and Kamo clans to dominate the world of Ommyodo as the two Soke (originators).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="17">
<j>平安時代末期以降、安倍氏から陰陽道の達人が立て続けに輩出され、下級貴族だった安倍氏は公卿に列することのできる家柄へと昇格していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the end of the Heian period onwards, the Abe clan produced the masters of Ommyodo one after another, helping the clan, who had been low-ranking nobles, be promoted to the level of court nobles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the end of the Heian period onwards, the Abe clan produced the masters of Ommyodo, one after another, helping the clan, who had been low-ranking nobles, get promoted to the level of court nobles.</e>
<cmt>comma inserted, grammar corrected</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the end of the Heian period onwards, the Abe clan produced the masters of Ommyodo, one after another, helping the clan, who had been low-ranking nobles, get promoted to the level of court nobles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>中世には安倍氏が陰陽寮の長官である陰陽頭を世襲し、賀茂氏は次官の陰陽助としてその下風に立った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Middle Ages, the Abe clan transferred the post of Ommyo-no kami (the head of the Ommyoryo (Bureau of Yin and Yang)) by succession while the Kamo clan, who took the post of Ommyo-no suke (deputy minister of Ommyoryo), played a subservient role.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Middle Ages, the Abe clan transferred the post of Ommyo-no kami (the head of the Ommyoryo (Bureau of Yin and Yang)) by succession while the Kamo clan, who held the post of Ommyo-no suke (deputy minister of Ommyoryo), played a subservient role.</e>
<cmt>&quot;took&quot; replaced by &quot;held&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Middle Ages, the Abe clan transferred the post of Ommyo-no kami (the head of the Ommyoryo (Bureau of Yin and Yang)) by succession while the Kamo clan, who held the post of Ommyo-no suke (deputy minister of Ommyoryo), played a subservient role.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>戦国時代 (日本)には、賀茂氏の本家であった勘解由小路家が断絶、暦道の支配権も安倍氏に移るが、安倍氏の宗家土御門家も戦乱の続くなか衰退していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Sengoku period, the Kadenokoji family, the head family of the Kamo clan, ceased to exit, causing their dominance over Rekido to transfer to the Abe clan, while the Tsuchimikado family, the head of the Abe clan, gradually declined as wars continued.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Sengoku period, the Kadenokoji family, the head family of the Kamo clan, ceased to exist, causing their dominance over Rekido to be transferred to the Abe clan, while the Tsuchimikado family, the head of the Abe clan, gradually declined as wars continued.</e>
<cmt>spelling corrected</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Sengoku period, the Kadenokoji family, the head family of the Kamo clan, ceased to exist, causing their dominance over Rekido to be transferred to the Abe clan, while the Tsuchimikado family, the head of the Abe clan, gradually declined as wars continued.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>一方、民間では室町時代頃から陰陽道の浸透がより進展し、占い師、祈祷師として民間陰陽師が活躍した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, during the Muromachi period, Ommyodo became permeated more deeply among common people, causing private Ommyo-ji to flourish as fortune-tellers and shamans.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, during the Muromachi period, Ommyodo permeated more deeply among common people, causing private Ommyo-ji to flourish as fortune-tellers and shamans.</e>
<cmt>deleted unnecessary word</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, during the Muromachi period, Ommyodo permeated more deeply among common people, causing private Ommyo-ji to flourish as fortune-tellers and shamans.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="21">
<j>幕藩体制が確立すると、江戸幕府は陰陽師の活動を統制するため、土御門家と賀茂氏の分家幸徳井家を再興させて諸国陰陽師を支配させようとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Baku-han system (the feudal system characteristic of the Shogunate) was put in place, the Edo bakufu (the Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) tried to control Ommyo-ji across the country by rebuilding the Tsuchimikado family and the Koutokui family, a branch family of the Kamo clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Baku-han system (the feudal system characteristic of the Shogunate) was put in place, the Edo bakufu (the Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) tried to control Ommyo-ji across the country by rebuilding the Tsuchimikado family and the Koutokui family, branch families of the Kamo clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Baku-han system (the feudal system characteristic of the Shogunate) was put in place, the Edo bakufu (the Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) tried to control Ommyo-ji across the country by rebuilding the Tsuchimikado family and the Koutokui family, branch families of the Kamo clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>やがて土御門家が幸徳井家を圧し、17世紀末に土御門家は民間の陰陽師に免状を与える権利を獲得して全国の陰陽道の支配権を確立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Over the time, the Tsuchimikado family outstripped the Koutokui family, and by the end of the 17th century, the Tsuchimikado family achieved a dominant position in Ommyodo across Japan by obtaining the right to grant Ommyo-ji licenses.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Over time, the Tsuchimikado family outstripped the Koutokui family, and by the end of the 17th century, they achieved a dominant position in Ommyodo across Japan by obtaining the right to grant Ommyo-ji licenses.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Over time, the Tsuchimikado family outstripped the Koutokui family, and by the end of the 17th century, they achieved a dominant position in Ommyodo across Japan by obtaining the right to grant Ommyo-ji licenses.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>江戸時代には、陰陽道はもはや政治に影響を及ぼすことはなくなったが、民間で暦や方角の吉凶を占う民間信仰として広く日本社会へと定着していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Ommyodo had lost its political clout by the Edo period, it became widespread and permeated deeply in the Japanese society as folk beliefs; people sought for an auspicious date or direction for special occasions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Ommyodo had lost its political clout by the beginning of the Edo period, it became widespread and permeated deeply into Japanese society as folk beliefs; that people used to seek for an auspicious date or direction for special occasions.</e>
<cmt>revised, grammar, words</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Ommyodo had lost its political clout by the beginning of the Edo period, it became widespread and permeated deeply into Japanese society as folk beliefs; that people used to seek for an auspicious date or direction for special occasions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="24">
<j>明治維新後の1872年（明治5年）に至り、新政府は陰陽道を迷信として廃止させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1872 after Meiji Restoration took place, the Meiji government abolished Ommyodo as superstition.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1872 after Meiji Restoration, the Meiji government abolished Ommyodo as superstition.</e>
<cmt>deleted unnecessary wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1872 after Meiji Restoration, the Meiji government abolished Ommyodo as superstition.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>現代には土御門家の開いた天社土御門神道と、高知県物部村（現　香美市）に伝わるいざなぎ流を除けば、暦などに名残をとどめるのみであるが、神道や新宗教などに取り入れられた陰陽道の影響は宗教として存続している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Except for Tensha Tsuchimikado Shinto Honcho (a school of Shinto and Ommyodo, based in Fukui Prefecture) started by the Tsuchimikado family, and the Izanagi ryu school, which has been handed down in Mononobe Village (the current Kami City), Kochi Prefecture, Ommyodo leaves its traces only in the calendar, but its impact on Shinto and new religions still lives on.</e>
<cmt>「神道や新宗教などに取り入れられた陰陽道の影響は宗教として存続している」とありますが、言葉がダブっているように感じます。従って、あえて、言葉を減らして訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Except for Tensha Tsuchimikado Shinto Honcho (a school of Shinto and Ommyodo, based in Fukui Prefecture) started by the Tsuchimikado family, and the Izanagi ryu school, which has been handed down through the generations in Mononobe Village (the current Kami City), Kochi Prefecture, Ommyodo left its traces only in a calendar, but its impact on Shinto and new religions still lives on.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Except for Tensha Tsuchimikado Shinto Honcho (a school of Shinto and Ommyodo, based in Fukui Prefecture) started by the Tsuchimikado family, and the Izanagi ryu school, which has been handed down through the generations in Mononobe Village (the current Kami City), Kochi Prefecture, Ommyodo left its traces only in a calendar, but its impact on Shinto and new religions still lives on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 AlleborgoBot(id:119729), Straysheep(id:42448), ととりん(id:31982), Vodoo(id:18542), MIsogi(id:20599), Hokuto-hei(id:68481), Tiyoringo(id:70026), 春野秋葉(id:36725), Wilson Tam(id:17411), GiGiGaGa(id:118308), 真人(id:17312), 莞爾帝(id:37986), 石原充士(id:87840), 松平定治(id:146386), Shouden(id:38327), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), Rei-bot(id:94097), Kaboyose-DSD(id:123658), 上(id:14148), Loveless(id:129239), 端くれの錬金術師(id:23040), カルマック(id:38122), 西＠東(id:32113), Kikoustra(id:112155), けんち(id:5147), Safkan(id:423), ToePeu.bot(id:157833), Ziksy(id:84091), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>