<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>祟り神</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tatari-gami</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tatari-gami</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tatari-gami</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>祟り神（たたりがみ）は、四魂であり畏怖され忌避されるものであるが、手厚く祀りあげることで強力な守護神となると信仰される神々である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tatari-gami is Shikon (four spirits) awed and avoided but believed to become a powerful guardian god if treated cordially.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tatari-gami are Shikon (four spirits) which are held in awe but avoided, and believed to become a powerful guardian god if treated cordially.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tatari-gami are Shikon (four spirits) which are held in awe but avoided, and believed to become a powerful guardian god if treated cordially.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>また、恩恵をうけるも災厄がふりかかるも信仰次第とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also believed that whether to receive a benefit or misfortune depends on the depth in faith.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also believed that whether to receive a benefit or misfortune depends on the depth of a person&apos;s faith.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also believed that whether to receive a benefit or misfortune depends on the depth of a person&apos;s faith.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>すなわち御霊信仰である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is what Goryo-shinko (a folk religious belief of avenging spirits) is about.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is what Goryo-shinko (a folk religious belief of avenging spirits) is about.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is what Goryo-shinko (a folk religious belief of avenging spirits) is about.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>その性質から、総じて信仰は手厚く大きなものとなる傾向がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The faith, in general, tends to be practiced cordially and in a large scale because of its nature of the god.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The faith, in general, tends to be practiced cordially and on a large scale because of the nature of the god.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The faith, in general, tends to be practiced cordially and on a large scale because of the nature of the god.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>創建された分社も数多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many branch shrines have been established.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many branch shrines have been established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many branch shrines have been established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>平安京、京の都で長くとりおこなわれている祇園祭は、祟り神を慰撫し鎮魂する祭りである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The purpose of Gion Festival, a long-lasting festival held in Heian-kyo, an ancient capital Kyoto, is to pacify and give repose to Tatari-gami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The purpose of Gion Festival, a long-lasting festival held in Heian-kyo, an ancient capital Kyoto, is to pacify and give repose to Tatari-gami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The purpose of Gion Festival, a long-lasting festival held in Heian-kyo, an ancient capital Kyoto, is to pacify and give repose to Tatari-gami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>主祭神である「祇園信仰」「牛頭天王」ことスサノオはまさにこの意味での祟り神の代表格である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its shusaijin (main enshrined deities) or Gion Shinko (Gion Faith) and Gozu Tenno (deity said to be the Indian god Gavagriva).is Susano (Deity in Japanese Mythology), which is the typical example of Tatari-gami.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its shusaijin (main enshrined deities) or Gion Shinko (Gion Faith) and Gozu Tenno (deity said to be the Indian god Gavagriva).is Susano (Deity in Japanese Mythology), which is the typical example of Tatari-gami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its shusaijin (main enshrined deities) or Gion Shinko (Gion Faith) and Gozu Tenno (deity said to be the Indian god Gavagriva) is Susano (Deity in Japanese mythology), which is the typical example of Tatari-gami.</e>
<cmt>of の後のスペース短縮.is→isMythology→mythology</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>疫病をもたらす厄神であると同時に、手厚く祀る者には守護神として働くとされ、全国各地に牛頭天王社が創建された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gozu-Tennosha Shrines were built across Japan, because Tatari-gami was believed to be an evil god bringing epidemic but at the same time come to work as the guardian god if cordially treated.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gozu-Tennosha Shrines were built across Japan, because Tatari-gami was believed to be an evil god bringing epidemic but at the same time come to work as the guardian god if cordially treated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gozu-Tennosha Shrines were built across Japan, because Tatari-gami was believed to be an evil god bringing epidemic but at the same time come to work as the guardian god if cordially treated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>日本書紀では征服された地祇の神々、ことにそのスサノオによって退治されたヤマタノオロチなどは代表的な祟り神である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan) describes that conquered gods on the earth, particularly Yamata no Orochi (eight forked great serpent) exterminated by Susanoo are typical Tatari-gami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan) describes that conquered gods on the earth, particularly Yamata no Orochi (eight forked great serpent) exterminated by Susanoo are typical Tatari-gami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan) describes that conquered gods on the earth, particularly Yamata no Orochi (eight forked great serpent) exterminated by Susanoo are typical Tatari-gami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>八岐大蛇から現れ出た宝剣天叢雲剣は三種の神器として神剣として祀られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The sacred sword, Ama no Murakumo no Tsurugi Sword which came out of a big snake with eight heads (Yamata-no-Orochi) has been enshrined as the Three Sacred Treasures of the Imperial Family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sacred sword, Ama no Murakumo no Tsurugi Sword which came out of a big snake with eight heads (Yamata-no-Orochi) has been enshrined as the Three Sacred Treasures of the Imperial Family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sacred sword, Ama no Murakumo no Tsurugi Sword which came out of Yamata no Orochi has been enshrined as the Three Sacred Treasures of the Imperial Family.</e>
<cmt>八岐大蛇は前のセルで出ているので Yamata no Orochi としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>出雲大社や諏訪大社ではその地にあった国津神が封印され祀られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Izumo-taisha Shrine and Suwa-taisha, Kunitsukami (gods of the land) believed to have once lived there have been sealed and enshrined.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Izumo-taisha Shrine and Suwa-taisha, Kunitsukami (gods of the land) believed to have once lived there have been sealed and enshrined.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Izumo-taisha Shrine and Suwa-taisha Shrine, Kunitsukami (gods of the land) believed to have once lived there have been sealed and enshrined.</e>
<cmt>taisha の後に Shrine 追記</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>（そのような神々を祀る神社の社格には大社などが付き、征服者である天神を祀る神社の社格は神宮となる）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(The shrine ranking of the shrines sacred to such gods is Taisha, whereas the shrine ranking of the sacred to conqueror Tenjin (heavenly gods) is Jingu.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(The shrine ranking of the shrines sacred to such gods is Taisha, whereas the shrine ranking of the sacred to conqueror Tenjin (heavenly gods) is Jingu.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(The ranking of the shrines sacred to such gods is Taisha, whereas the ranking of the sacred to conqueror Tenjin (heavenly gods) is Jingu.)</e>
<cmt>shrine ranking→ranking) の前のスペース短縮</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>しかしながら、日本書紀には天武天皇が天叢雲剣の祟りが原因で崩御、日本後紀には桓武天皇が十握剣（八岐大蛇を征服した宝剣）の祟りが原因で崩御したとある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However Nihonshoki has it that the Emperor Tenmu died from a curse of Ama no Murakumo no Tsurugi Sword, and Nihon Koki&apos; (Later Chronicle of Japan) describes that the Emperor Kanmu died from a curse of Totsuka-no-tsurugi Sword (a sacred sword with which the big snake with eight heads (Yamata-no-Orochi) were exterminated.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However Nihonshoki has it that the Emperor Tenmu died from a curse of Ama no Murakumo no Tsurugi Sword, and Nihon Koki&apos; (Later Chronicle of Japan) describes that the Emperor Kanmu died from a curse of Totsuka-no-tsurugi Sword (a sacred sword with which the big snake with eight heads (Yamata-no-Orochi) were exterminated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However Nihonshoki has it that the Emperor Tenmu died from a curse of Ama no Murakumo no Tsurugi Sword, and Nihon Koki&apos; (Later Chronicle of Japan) describes that the Emperor Kanmu died from a curse of Totsuka-no-tsurugi Sword (a sacred sword with which Yamata no Orochi was exterminated.)</e>
<cmt>八岐大蛇の表記変更were→was最後に閉じ括弧</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>神剣の祟りは相当なものと認識されていたようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The curses of the sacred sword appears to have been considered as powerful</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The curses of the sacred sword appear to have been considered to be extremely powerful</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The curses of the sacred sword appear to have been considered to be extremely powerful</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>前者は熱田神宮から盗まれた行方不明だった天叢雲剣が献上され宮中にとどめおいたため祟ったとある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the former case, Nihonshoki has it that the curse was placed because the Ama no Murakumo no Tsurugi Sword stolen from Atsuta-jingu Shrine and lost were presented to the Imperial Court but stored in it.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the former case, Nihonshoki has it that the curse was placed because the Ama no Murakumo no Tsurugi Sword stolen from Atsuta-jingu Shrine and lost were presented to the Imperial Court but stored in it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the former case, Nihonshoki has it that the curse was placed because the Ama no Murakumo no Tsurugi Sword stolen from Atsuta-jingu Shrine and lost was presented to the Imperial Court and stored there.</e>
<cmt>but の後のスペース短縮were→wasbut→andin it→there</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>後者は石上神宮から平安京へ無理矢理移動させたため祟ったとある</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the latter case, the curse was placed because the sword was forced to move from Isonokami-jingu Shrine to Heian-Kyo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the latter case, the curse was placed because the sword was forced to move from Isonokami-jingu Shrine to Heian-Kyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the latter case, the curse was placed because the sword was forced to move from Isonokami-jingu Shrine to Heian-Kyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>結局、畏れをなされた神剣は元の場所に戻されることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The sacred sword was at last awed and returned to what it had been.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sacred sword was at last held in reverence and returned to what it had been.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the end, these sacred swords were held in reverence and returned to where they had been found.</e>
<cmt>上記二つの神剣と解釈し、複数形にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="18">
<j>御霊信仰</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Goryo-shinko (a folk religious belief of avenging spirits</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Goryo-shinko (a folk religious belief of avenging spirits</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Goryo-shinko</e>
<cmt>既出のため説明削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>非業の死を遂げ畏れられたもの、たとえば菅原道真や崇徳天皇、平将門は祟り神に部類される神として祀られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tatari-gami was awed because of the unfortunate deaths, but SUGAWARA no Michizane, the Emperor Sutoku, and TAIRA no Masakado have been enshrined as a god categorized into Tatari-gami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tatari-gami was awed because of the unfortunate deaths, but SUGAWARA no Michizane, the Emperor Sutoku, and TAIRA no Masakado have been enshrined as a god categorized into Tatari-gami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Persons who were awed because of their unfortunate deaths, such as SUGAWARA no Michizane, the Emperor Sutoku, and TAIRA no Masakado have been enshrined as a god categorized into Tatari-gami.</e>
<cmt>Neilさん前半、原文と内容が違うと思い変更しました。ご確認願います。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>ことに平将門は東京を守る産土神であると同時に、平将門の首塚伝承で知られる数々の祟りをなす典型的な祟り神である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In particular, TAIRA no Masakado has been regarded as Ubusunagami (guardian deity of one&apos;s birthplace) that protects Tokyo but it is at the same time a typical Tatari-gami that placed many curses, which is known as Tradition of head tumulus of TAIRA no Masakado.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In particular, TAIRA no Masakado has been regarded as Ubusunagami (guardian deity of one&apos;s birthplace) that protects Tokyo but it is at the same time a typical Tatari-gami placed many curses, which is known as Tradition of head tumulus of TAIRA no Masakado.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In particular, TAIRA no Masakado has been regarded as an Ubusunagami (guardian deity of one&apos;s birthplace) that protects Tokyo, but it is at the same time a typical Tatari-gami that places many curses, which is known as Tradition of head tumulus of TAIRA no Masakado.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="21">
<j>八所御霊</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hassho goryo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hassho goryo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hassho goryo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>早良親王、伊予親王、藤原吉子、橘逸勢、文室宮田麻呂、菅原道真、吉備真備、井上皇后の御霊を総して八所御霊といい、各所で祟り神として祀られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The spirits of Imperial Prince Sawara, Imperial Prince Iyo, FUJIWARA no Yoshiko, TACHIBANA no Hayanari, FUNYA no Miyatamaro, SUGAWARA no Michizane, KIBI no Makibi, and Empress Inoe were collectively called Hassho goryo (the spirits of eight people who died unhappy deaths as a result of political conspiracies) and enshrined as Tatari-gami in many places in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The spirits of Imperial Prince Sawara, Imperial Prince Iyo, FUJIWARA no Yoshiko, TACHIBANA no Hayanari, FUNYA no Miyatamaro, SUGAWARA no Michizane, KIBI no Makibi, and Empress Inoe were collectively called Hassho goryo (the spirits of eight people who died unhappy deaths as a result of political conspiracies) and enshrined as Tatari-gami in many places in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The spirits of Imperial Prince Sawara, Imperial Prince Iyo, FUJIWARA no Yoshiko, TACHIBANA no Hayanari, FUNYA no Miyatamaro, SUGAWARA no Michizane, KIBI no Makibi, and Empress Inoe are collectively called Hassho goryo (the spirits of eight people who died unhappy deaths as a result of political conspiracies) and enshrined as Tatari-gami in many places in Japan.</e>
<cmt>were→are</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 うぃき野郎(id:53567), Tenko(id:102318), Kamida(id:250305), Sat666(id:127263), Mymelo(id:122034), モール(id:166047), くっちゃめ(id:86793), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>