<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>採物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Torimono (symbolic offerings)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Torimono (symbolic offerings)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Torimono</e>
<cmt>タイトルですので、カッコ内の補足は削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>採物（とりもの）は、神事や神楽において巫女や神楽などが手に取り持つ道具。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Torimono are the tool miko (a shrine maiden) and performers of Kagura, (sacred music and dancing performed at shrine) take hold of in Shito rituals and Kagura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Torimono are the tools used by miko (a shrine maiden) and performers of Kagura, (sacred music and dancing performed at shrine) in Shinto rituals and Kagura.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Torimono are the tools used by miko (a shrine maiden) and performers of Kagura, (sacred music and dancing performed at shrine) in Shinto rituals and Kagura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>『古今和歌集』の「大歌所御歌」には榊・葛・弓 (武器)・杓の4種が記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Outadokoro Onuta poetry&quot; of Kokin Wakashu&apos; (A Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry) describes four kinds: Sakaki, Kudzu, archery (a weapon), and shaku (ladle).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Outadokoro Onuta poetry&quot; of Kokin Wakashu&apos; (A Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry) describes four kinds: Sakaki, Kudzu, archery (a weapon), and shaku (ladle).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Outadokoro Onuta poetry&quot; of &quot;Kokin Wakashu&quot; (A Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry) describes four kinds: Sakaki, Kudzu, archery (a weapon), and Shaku (ladle).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>更に神楽歌の中にはこれに加えて幣・杖・弓 (武器)・剣・鉾の5種が加えられて計9種類とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, a Kagurauta song describes a total of nine tools by adding five kinds: nusa (symbols of divinity made of cloth or paper and hung on a pole), shakujo (hand bell), archery (a weapon), Ken (sword of sharpened two edges), and hoko (a pike).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, a Kagurauta song describes a total of nine tools by adding five kinds: nusa (symbols of divinity made of cloth or paper and hung on a pole), shakujo (hand bell), archery (a weapon), Ken (sword of sharpened two edges), and hoko (a pike).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, a Kagurauta song describes a total of nine tools by adding five kinds: Nusa (symbols of divinity made of cloth or paper and hung on a pole), Shakujo (hand bell), archery (a weapon), Ken (sword of sharpened two edges), and Hoko (a pike).</e>
<cmt>スペースなどを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>一説には杓と葛は元は一物（「杓葛」）であったとする説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some suggest that shaku and Kudzu were originally the same (shakukudzu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some suggest that shaku and Kudzu were originally the same (shakukudzu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some suggest that Shaku and Kudzu were originally the same (&apos;shakukudzu&apos;).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>折口信夫は手に持って振り回すことで神を鎮める「鎮魂」の意味があったという説を立てている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinobu ORIKUCHI put forward a new theory that taking hold and brandishing them were intended for &quot;a repose of souls&quot; of the Gods.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinobu ORIKUCHI put forward a new theory that taking hold and brandishing them were intended for &quot;a repose of souls&quot; of the Gods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinobu ORIKUCHI put forward a new theory that taking hold and brandishing them were intended for &apos;a repose of souls&apos; of the gods.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 赤井彗星(id:18381), Nnh(id:474), 江口磐世☆(id:168037), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>