<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>生祀</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seishi (Deification of a Living Man)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seishi (Deification of a Living Man)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seishi (Deification of a Living Man)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>生祀（せいし）とは、存命中の人間の霊を祀ること。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seishi (生祀) means to honor or worship the spirit of a living person.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seishi (生祀) means to honor or worship the spirit of a living person.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seishi (生祀) means to honor or worship the spirit of a living person.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>生祠ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seishi (生祠) means the same.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seishi (生祠) means the same.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seishi (生祠) means the same.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>功績があった存命中の他者の霊を祀る場合と、自己の霊魂を祀る場合とがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are cases where the spirit of someone else who has performed great achievements and is alive is honored and where own soul is worshipped.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are cases where the spirit of someone else who has performed great achievements and is alive is honored and where their soul is worshipped.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are cases where the spirit of someone else who has performed great achievements and is alive is honored and where one&apos;s own soul is worshipped.</e>
<cmt>their→one&apos;s own</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概略</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>自己の霊魂を祀る生祀は、長命を得るため、あるいは死後に神となるために行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seishi carried out to worship own soul was to live a long life or become Kami (god) after death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seishi carried out to worship one&apos;s own soul was to live a long life or become Kami (god) after death.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seishi carried out to worship one&apos;s own soul was to live a long life or become Kami (god) after death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>大国主が自らの奇魂・幸魂を三諸山（三輪山）に祀った故事に由来するとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is thought that this originated in the tradition that Okuninushi (chief god of Izumo in southern Honshu Island, Japan, and the central character in the important cycle of myths set in that region) worshipped his own Kushimitama (wondrous, miraculous, or salubrious) and Sakimitama (propitious) in Mt. Mimoro (Mt. Miwa.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is thought that this originated in the tradition that Okuninushi (chief god of Izumo in southern Honshu Island, Japan, and the central character in the important cycle of myths set in that region) worshipped his own Kushimitama (wondrous, miraculous, or salubrious) and Sakimitama (propitious) in Mt. Mimoro (Mt. Miwa.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is thought that this originated in the tradition that Okuninushi (chief god of Izumo in southern Honshu Island, Japan, and the central character in the important cycle of myths set in that region) worshipped his own Kushimitama (the wondrous, miraculous, or salubrious) and Sakimitama (the propitious) in Mt. Mimoro (Mt. Miwa.)</e>
<cmt>that の後のスペース短縮奇魂・幸魂の括弧内に the 追記。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>自己の霊魂を祀った生祀の文献上で最も古い事例は、平安時代の923年、伊勢神宮の外宮の神官であった松木春彦（824年 - 924年）が、伊勢度会郡尾部で、石に自己の霊魂を鎮め、祀ったことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The oldest case of worshipping own soul in materials was related to Haruhiko MATSUKI in the Heian period and when he was Shinto priest of Geku (outer shrine) in Ise-jingu Shrine, he worshipped his soul included in stones or rocks in Obe, Watarai-gun, Ise in 923.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The oldest case of someone worshipping their own soul was related to Haruhiko MATSUKI in the Heian period when he was a Shinto priest of Geku (outer shrine) in Ise-jingu Shrine, he worshipped his soul included in stones or rocks in Obe, Watarai-gun, Ise in 923.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The oldest case of someone worshipping their own soul was related to Haruhiko MATSUKI (824 - 924)in the Heian period when he was a Shinto priest of Geku (outer shrine) in Ise-jingu Shrine, he worshipped his soul included in stones or rocks in Obe, Watarai-gun, Ise in 923.</e>
<cmt>sou, periodl の後のスペース短縮（824年 - 924年） 追記</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>江戸時代、松平定信が1797年、奥州白河城に自分の生祀を成立した例がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a case that Sadanobu MATSUDAIRA carried out Seishi for himself at Oshu Shiraka Castle in 1797 in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>”奥州白河城の中で、生祀を実行した”と英訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a case where Sadanobu MATSUDAIRA carried out Seishi for himself at Oshu Shiraka Castle in 1797 in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a case where Sadanobu MATSUDAIRA carried out Seishi for himself at Oshu Shirakawa-jo Castle in 1797 in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>Shiraka→Shirakawa-jo</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>生祀は江戸時代に増えたが、それは中国思想の影響であろうという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The number of Seishi increased in the Edo period, and it is probably because it was influenced by the Chinese thoughts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The number of Seishi increased in the Edo period, and was probably due to influence by the Chinese.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The number of Seishi increased in the Edo period, and this was probably due to the influence of Chinese thought.</e>
<cmt>中国思想なので Chinese thought に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="9">
<j>江戸時代に、山崎闇斎が儒教の礼式を参考に祭式を考案し、自らの霊魂を祀った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Edo period, Ansai YAMAZAKI established rules for ritual procedures based on a ceremony style for Confucianism and worshipped his soul.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Edo period, Ansai YAMAZAKI established rules for ritual procedures based on a ceremony style for Confucianism and worshipped his soul.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Edo period, Ansai YAMAZAKI established rules for ritual procedures based on a ceremony style for Confucianism and worshipped his soul.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>その生祀は1671年、京都の自邸の垂加霊社に成立したものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Seishi was carried out in his residence, Suika (Shidemasu)-Reisha in Kyoto in 1671.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Seishi was carried out in his residence, Suika (Shidemasu)-Reisha in Kyoto in 1671.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Seishi was carried out in his residence, Suika (Shidemasu)-Reisha Shrine in Kyoto in 1671.</e>
<cmt>Shrine 追記</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>これ以後も、神道家や平田派の国学者によって、それぞれ独自の祭式で自己の霊魂を祀った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, Shintoists and scholars of Japanese classical literature in Hirata-ha school worshipped their own souls in accordance with their established ritual procedures.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, Shintoists and scholars of Japanese classical literature in Hirata-ha school worshipped their own souls in accordance with their established ritual procedures.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, Shintoists and scholars of Japanese classical literature in Hirata-ha school worshipped their own souls in accordance with their established ritual procedures.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="12">
<j>生祀の研究は加藤玄智（1873年 - 1965年）が有名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Genchi KATO (1873-1965) is well-known for the research of Seishi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Genchi KATO (1873-1965) is well-known for his research on Seishi.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genchi KATO (1873-1965) is well-known for his research on Seishi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>加藤によれば判明している生祀は六七十あり、新しい生祀は1931年8月、北海道日高国浦河町に祀られた西忠義氏のものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Kato, sixty to seventy Seishi were identified and the latest Seishi is the one for Chugi NISHI which was enshrined in August 1931 in Urakawa-cho, Hidaka Province, Hokkaido Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Kato, sixty to seventy Seishi were identified and the latest Seishi is the one for Chugi NISHI which was enshrined in August 1931 in Urakawa-cho, Hidaka Province, Hokkaido Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Kato, 60 to 70 Seishi were identified and the latest Seishi is the one for Chugi NISHI which was enshrined in August 1931 in Urakawa-cho, Hidaka Province, Hokkaido Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>数字表記変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="14">
<j>明治天皇の生祀は明治9年宮城県石巻港に、明治26年上伊那郡小野村の矢彦神社境内に、建立された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Meiji&apos;s Seishi was built in Port of Ishinomaki in Miyagi Prefecture in 1876, and also in the site of Yahiko-jinja Shrine in Ono-mura, Kamiina-gun in 1893.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Meiji&apos;s Seishi was built in Port of Ishinomaki in Miyagi Prefecture in 1876, and also in the site of Yahiko-jinja Shrine in Ono-mura, Kamiina-gun in 1893.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Meiji&apos;s Seishi was built in Port of Ishinomaki in Miyagi Prefecture in 1876, and also in the site of Yahiko-jinja Shrine in Ono-mura, Kamiina-gun in 1893.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>明治天皇、昭憲皇太后の生祀は明治20年および明治37年に2箇所に、大正天皇の生祀は明治44年北海道日高国門別村に、貞明皇后の生祀は大正2年広島県広瀬町に、秩父宮殿下、高松宮殿下の生祀は大正13年姫路市同心町に成立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seishi of Emperor Meiji Seishi and Empress Dowager Shoken was each built in two locations in 1887 and 1904, Seishi of Emperor Taisho was built in Monbetsu-mura, Hidaka Province, Hokkaido Prefecture in 1911, Seishi of Empress Teimei was built in Hirose-machi, Hiroshima Prefecture in 1913, and Seishi of Prince Chichibu no miya and Prince Takamatsunomiya was each built in Doshin-machi, Himeji City in 1924.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Seishi of Emperor Meiji Seishi and Empress Dowager Shoken was each built in two locations in 1887 and 1904, the Seishi of Emperor Taisho was built in Monbetsu-mura, Hidaka Province, Hokkaido Prefecture in 1911, the Seishi of Empress Teimei was built in Hirose-machi, Hiroshima Prefecture in 1913, and the Seishi of Prince Chichibu no miya and Prince Takamatsunomiya was each built in Doshin-machi, Himeji City in 1924.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Seishi of Emperor Meiji and Empress Dowager Shoken was each built in two locations in 1887 and 1904, the Seishi of Emperor Taisho was built in Monbetsu-mura, Hidaka Province, Hokkaido Prefecture in 1911, the Seishi of Empress Teimei was built in Hirose-machi, Hiroshima Prefecture in 1913, and the Seishi of Prince Chichibunomiya and Prince Takamatsunomiya was each built in Doshin-machi, Himeji City in 1924.</e>
<cmt>Chichibu no miya→ChichibunomiyaMeiji の後の Seishi 削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>昭和天皇の生祀は大正12年北海道十勝国本別村義経山上に、昭和天皇、香淳皇后の生祀は昭和3年広島市広瀬町に成立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seishi of Emperor Showa was built on Mt. Yoshitsune, Honbetsu-cho, Tokachi Province, Hokkaido Prefecture in 1879, and Seishi of Emperor Showa and Empress Kojun was each built in Hirose-machi, Hiroshima City in 1928.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Seishi of Emperor Showa was built on Mt. Yoshitsune, Honbetsu-cho, Tokachi Province, Hokkaido Prefecture in 1879, and the Seishi of Emperor Showa and Empress Kojun was each built in Hirose-machi, Hiroshima City in 1928.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Seishi of Emperor Showa was built on Mt. Yoshitsune, Honbetsu-cho, Tokachi Province, Hokkaido Prefecture in 1879, and the Seishi of Emperor Showa and Empress Kojun was each built in Hirose-machi, Hiroshima City in 1928.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 663highland(id:18755), Himazin(id:22034), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>