<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>クシナダヒメ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kushinadahime</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kushinadahime</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kushinadahime</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>クシナダヒメは、日本神話に登場する神 (神道)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kushinadahime is a goddess that appears in Japanese Mythology (Shinto religion).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kushinadahime is a goddess that appears in Japanese Mythology (Shinto religion).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kushinadahime is a goddess that appears in Japanese Mythology (Shinto religion).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>『古事記』では櫛名田比売、『日本書紀』では奇稲田姫と表記する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kojiki &quot;(Records of Ancient Matters) gives her name &quot;櫛名田比売&quot; in Chinese character and &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan) gives &quot;奇稲田姫.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kojiki &quot;(Records of Ancient Matters) gives her name as &quot;櫛名田比売&quot; in Chinese characters and &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan) gives it as &quot;奇稲田姫.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Kojiki &quot;(Records of Ancient Matters) gives her name as &quot;櫛名田比売&quot; in Chinese characters and &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan) gives it as &quot;奇稲田姫.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>神話での記述</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mythological Description</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mythological Description</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mythological Description</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>ヤマタノオロチの説話で登場する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She appears in a setsuwa (anecdotes) about Yamatanoorochi(eight-forked-snake).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She appears in a setsuwa (anecdotes) about Yamatanoorochi(eight-forked-snake).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She appears in a setsuwa (anecdotes) about Yamatanoorochi (eight-forked-snake).</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>アシナヅチ・テナヅチの8人の娘の中で最後に残った娘で、スサノオの妻となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among eight daughters of Ashinazuchi and Tenazuchi, she was the last to leave them for marriage and became the wife of Susano (Deity in Japanese Mythology).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among eight daughters of Ashinazuchi and Tenazuchi, she was the last to leave them for marriage and became the wife of Susano (Deity in Japanese Mythology).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among eight daughters of Ashinazuchi and Tenazuchi, she was the last to leave them for marriage and became the wife of Susano (Deity in Japanese Mythology).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>古事記ではヤシマジヌミ（この子孫に大国主がいる）、日本書紀では大己貴命（大国主）を生んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She gave birth to Yashimajinumi (whose decedent is Okuninushi (chief god of Izumo in southern Honshu Island, Japan, and the central character in the important cycle of myths set in that region)) according to Kojiki and Onamuchi no mikoto (Okuninushi) according to nihonshoki.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She gave birth to Yashimajinumi (whose decendent is Okuninushi - the chief god of Izumo in southern Honshu Island, Japan, and the central character in the important cycle of myths set in that region) according to Kojiki and Onamuchi no mikoto (Okuninushi) according to nihonshoki.</e>
<cmt>spelling, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the Kojiki, she gave birth to Yashimajinumi (whose descendent is Okuninushi - the chief god of Izumo in southern Honshu Island, Japan, and the central character in the important myths set in that region) and according to Nihonshoki she gave birth to Onamuchi no mikoto (Okuninushi).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。重複部分を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>高天原を追放されて出雲に降り立ったスサノオは、ヤマタノオロチという怪物に毎年娘を食われているアシナヅチ・テナヅチの夫婦に出会った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Having exiled from Takamanohara and landed on Izumo, Susano met a couple of Ashinazuchi and Tenazuchi, whose daughters had been eaten by a beast called Yamatanoorochi (eight-forked-snake) every year.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Having been exiled from Takamanohara and the landing in Izumo, Susano met the couple Ashinazuchi and Tenazuchi, whose daughters had been eaten by a beast called Yamatanoorochi (eight-forked-snake) every year.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Having been exiled from Takamanohara and arriving in Izumo, Susano met the couple Ashinazuchi and Tenazuchi, who each year had daughters who were taken and eaten by a beast called Yamatanoorochi (eight-forked-snake).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>クシナダヒメを妻として貰い受けることでヤマタノオロチの退治を請け負った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He promised to kill the Yamatanoorochi in return for being given Kushinadahime.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He promised to kill the Yamatanoorochi in return for being given Kushinadahime.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He promised to kill the Yamatanoorochi in return for being given Kushinadahime.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>ヤマタノオロチを退治した後、スサノオはクシナダヒメと共に住む場所を探し、須賀の地に宮殿を建てた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After killing the Yamatanoorochi, Susno searched a place to live with Kushinadahime and built a palace in Suga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After killing the Yamatanoorochi, Susno searched for a place to live in with Kushinadahime and built a palace in Suga.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After killing the Yamatanoorochi, Susano searched for a place to live in with Kushinadahime and built a palace in Suga.</e>
<cmt>Susno→Susano</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>また、スサノオが追放されたのは日の国の外である（いわゆる朝鮮半島）との説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some suggest that Susano was exiled from a country outside Hinokuni (or Korean Peninsula).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some suggest that Susano was exiled from a country outside Hinokuni (or Korean Peninsula).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some suggest that Susano was exiled from a country outside Hinokuni (or Korean Peninsula).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="11">
<j>解説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Explnation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Explanation</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Explanation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>名前は通常、日本書紀の記述のように「奇し稲田（くしいなだ）姫」すなわち霊妙な稲田の女神と解釈される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her name is generally interpreted as &quot;奇し稲田姫,&quot; which means a mysterious goddess of rice field as Nihonshoki describes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her name is generally interpreted as &quot;奇し稲田姫,&quot; which means a mysterious goddess of rice fields as Nihonshoki describes.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her name is generally interpreted as &quot;奇し稲田姫,&quot; which means a mysterious goddess of rice fields as Nihonshoki describes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>他に串蛇（くしなだ）とする説などもあるが、否定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although some give different Chinese characters &quot;串蛇,&quot; but this interpretation is believed to be incorrect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although some give different Chinese characters like &quot;串蛇,&quot; this interpretation is believed to be incorrect.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although some give different Chinese characters like &quot;串蛇,&quot; this interpretation is believed to be incorrect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>また、櫛の字を宛てることからクシナダヒメは櫛を挿した巫女であると解釈し、ヤマタノオロチを川の神として、元々は川の神に仕える巫女であったとする説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Others suggest that Yamatanoorochi was a god of a river and that she was originally a shrine maiden serving the god by giving her name a Chinese character with a meaning of comb and interpreting her as a shrine maiden wearing a comb.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Others suggest that Yamatanoorochi was the god of a river and that she was originally a shrine maiden serving the god by giving her name a Chinese character meaning comb and depicting her as a shrine maiden wearing a comb.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Others suggest that Yamatanoorochi was the god of a river and that she was originally a shrine maiden serving the god by giving her name a Chinese character meaning comb and depicting her as a shrine maiden wearing a comb.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="15">
<j>『出雲国風土記』の飯石郡の項では久志伊奈太美等与麻奴良比売命（くしいなだみとよまぬらひめ）という名前で登場する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She appears on Chapter &quot;Iishi-gun&quot; of &quot;Izumo no kuni fudoki&quot; (Fudoki of Izumo no kuni) in the name of Kushiinadamitoyomanura-hime.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She appears on Chapter &quot;Iishi-gun&quot; of &quot;Izumo no kuni fudoki&quot; (Fudoki of Izumo no kuni) in the name of Kushiinadamitoyomanura-hime.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She is mentioned in Chapter Iishi-gun of &quot;Izumo no kuni fudoki&quot; (the topography of Izumo Province) under the name of Kushiinadamitoyomanura-hime.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。補足を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>また、能登国の久志伊奈太伎比咩神社（石川県七尾市）では久志伊奈太伎比咩（くしいなだきひめ）を祀神としたという記述が延喜式神名帳にあり、同一神と考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, Engishiki jinmyocho (List of shrines, Engishiki) of Kushiinadaki-hime-jinja Shrine (Nanao City, Ishikawa Prefecture) describes that it was erected to the spirit of Kushiinadaki-hime, who is beloved to the identical goddess.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, Engishiki jinmyocho (List of shrines, Engishiki) of Kushiinadaki-hime-jinja Shrine (Nanao City, Ishikawa Prefecture) describes that it was erected and dedicated to the spirit of Kushiinadaki-hime, who as beloved to the identical goddess.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, Engishiki jinmyocho (List of shrines, Engishiki) of Kushiinadaki-hime-jinja Shrine (Nanao City, Ishikawa Prefecture) describes that it was erected and dedicated to the spirit of Kushiinadaki-hime, who was believed to be the same goddess.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="17">
<j>稲田の神として信仰されており、廣峯神社（兵庫県姫路市）、氷川神社（さいたま市大宮区）、須佐神社 (出雲市)（島根県出雲市）、八重垣神社(島根県松江市)、須我神社（島根県雲南市）、八坂神社（京都市東山区）、櫛田神社 (射水市)（富山県射水市）、櫛田宮（佐賀県神埼市）のほか、各地の氷川神社で祀られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Worshiped as a goddess of a paddy field, she is enshrined in Hiromine-jinja Shrine (Himeji City, Hyogo Prefecture), Hikawa-jinja Shrine (Omiya Ward, Saitama City), Susa-jinja Shrine (Izumo City, Shimane Prefecture), Yaegaki-jinja Shrine (Matsue City, Shimane Prefecture), Suga-jinja Shrine (Unnan City, Shimane Prefecture), Yasaka-jinja Shrine (Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City), Kushida-jinja Shrine (Imizu City, Toyama Prefecture), Kushida-gu Shrine (Kanzaki City, Saga Prefecture) and shines named Hikawa-jinja Shrine all over the country.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Worshiped as a goddess of paddy fields, she is enshrined in Hiromine-jinja Shrine (Himeji City, Hyogo Prefecture), Hikawa-jinja Shrine (Omiya Ward, Saitama City), Susa-jinja Shrine (Izumo City, Shimane Prefecture), Yaegaki-jinja Shrine (Matsue City, Shimane Prefecture), Suga-jinja Shrine (Unnan City, Shimane Prefecture), Yasaka-jinja Shrine (Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City), Kushida-jinja Shrine (Imizu City, Toyama Prefecture), Kushida-gu Shrine (Kanzaki City, Saga Prefecture) and shines named Hikawa-jinja Shrine all over the country.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Worshiped as a goddess of paddy fields, she is enshrined in Hiromine-jinja Shrine (Himeji City, Hyogo Prefecture), Hikawa-jinja Shrine (Omiya Ward, Saitama City), Susa-jinja Shrine (Izumo City, Shimane Prefecture), Yaegaki-jinja Shrine (Matsue City, Shimane Prefecture), Suga-jinja Shrine (Unnan City, Shimane Prefecture), Yasaka-jinja Shrine (Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City), Kushida-jinja Shrine (Imizu City, Toyama Prefecture), Kushida-gu Shrine (Kanzaki City, Saga Prefecture) and shines named Hikawa-jinja Shrine all over the country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>多くの神社では、夫のスサノオや子孫（又は子）の大国主などと共に祀られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many of these shrines are dedicated to her along with her husband, Susano and descent (or son), Okuninushi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many of these shrines are dedicated to her along with her husband, Susano and descent (or son), Okuninushi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many of these shrines are dedicated to her along with her husband, Susano and descent (or son), Okuninushi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="19">
<j>福岡県福岡市にも櫛田神社 (福岡市)があるが、ここの祭神は大幡主大神・天照大神・素戔嗚大神である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fukuoka City, Fukuoka Prefecture has Kushida-jinja Shrine but it is dedicated to Ohatanushi-no-okami, Amaterasu Omikami (the Sun Goddess), and Susanoo-no-omikami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fukuoka City, Fukuoka Prefecture has Kushida-jinja Shrine but it is dedicated to Ohatanushi-no-okami, Amaterasu Omikami (the Sun Goddess), and Susanoo-no-omikami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fukuoka City, Fukuoka Prefecture has Kushida-jinja Shrine but it is dedicated to Ohatanushi no okami, Amaterasu Omikami (the Sun Goddess), and Susano no omikami.</e>
<cmt>ハイフン削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>ただし、元々はクシナダヒメを祀っていたとする説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However some suggest that Kushinadahime was originally enshrined in it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However some suggest that Kushinadahime was originally enshrined in it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However some suggest that Kushinadahime was originally enshrined in it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 おはぐろ蜻蛉(id:8405), Avxz(id:123412), Nnh(id:474), 暗黒な方(id:44101), Jade0416(id:104181), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>