<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>大将軍八神社</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daishogunhachi-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daishogunhachi-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daishogunhachi-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>大将軍八神社（だいしょうぐんはちじんじゃ）は京都府京都市上京区にある神社。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Daishogunhachi-jinja Shrine&quot; is a shrine in Jokyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Daishogunhachi-jinja Shrine&quot; is a shrine in Jokyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Daishogunhachi-jinja Shrine&quot; is a shrine in Kamigyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>上京区（かみぎょうく)の読みの誤りを訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>素盞嗚命を祭神とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Susano no mikoto is the enshrined deity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Susano no mikoto is the enshrined deity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Susanoo no mikoto is the enshrined deity.</e>
<cmt>Susano→Susanooとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>平安京建設時、都の方除け守護として造営され、当初は大将軍堂と呼ばれたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Heian kyo was built, it was built as protection for the capital for removing calamities related to direction, and was originally called Taishogun-do.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Heian kyo was built, it was built as protection for the capital to remove calamities related to direction, and was originally called Taishogun-do.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Heian kyo was built, it was built as protection for the capital to remove calamities related to direction, and was originally called Taishogun-do.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>江戸時代に入り大将軍社と改称、明治時代に現名称へと変更された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Edo period, it was renamed to Taishogun-sha, and in the Meiji period, it was changed to the current name.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Edo period, it was renamed Taishogun-sha, and in the Meiji period, it was changed to the current name.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Edo period, it was renamed Taishogun-sha, and in the Meiji period, it was changed to the current name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>本来の祭神は大将軍という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The original enshrined deity was Taishogun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The original enshrined deity was Taishogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The original enshrined deity was Taishogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>大将軍は陰陽道の方位神であり、とくに建築や転居、旅行などにおいて方角の吉凶を司る神であるため、長きにわたり民間の崇敬を集めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taishogun is a hoi-jin of Onmyodo (way of Yin and Yang; occult divination system based on the Taoist theory of the five elements), and since it is a god ruling the fortune of directions for construction, moving, and travel, it was worshipped for a long time by the people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taishogun is a hoi-jin of Onmyodo (way of Yin and Yang; occult divination system based on the Taoist theory of the five elements), and since it is a god ruling the fortune of directions for construction, moving, and travel, it was worshipped for a long time by the people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taishogun is a hoi-jin (the directional deity) of Onmyodo (way of Yin and Yang; occult divination system based on the Taoist theory of the five elements), and since it is a god ruling the fortune of directions for construction, moving, and travel, it was worshipped for a long time by the people.</e>
<cmt>方位神の補足を入れ、余分なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>明治の神仏分離令にて祭神は素盞鳴尊と改められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under the order for the separation of Buddhism and Shintoism in Meiji, the enshrined deity was changed to Susano no mikoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the order for the separation of Buddhism and Shintoism in Meiji, the enshrined deity was changed to Susano no mikoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the order for the separation of Buddhism and Shintoism in the Meiji period, the enshrined deity was changed to Susanoo no mikoto.</e>
<cmt>the Meiji period, Susanoo no mikotoとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>文化財</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cultural properties</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cultural properties</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cultural properties</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>木造大将軍神像 80躯（重要文化財）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wooden Taishogun shinzo (sculpture of god), 80 bodies (important cultural property)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wooden Taishogun shinzo (sculpture of god), 80 figures (important cultural property)</e>
<cmt>terminology</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wooden Taishogun shinzo (sculpture of god), 80 figures (important cultural property)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>これらの神像群は平安時代中期から末期の制作といわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These groups of shinzos are said to be created in mid- to late-Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These groups of shinzos are said to have been created in the mid- to late-Heian period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These groups of shinzos are said to have been created in the mid- to late-Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>すべて男神像で、甲冑を着用した武装形の像、束帯姿の像、童子形の像（1体のみ）など計80体を数える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Totaling 80 bodies, they are all male shinzos, with armed sculptures wearing armor and helmet, sculptures in old ceremonial court dresses, sculptures of a child (only one), etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Totaling 80 figures, they are all male shinzos, armed sculptures wearing armor, and helmets, sculptures in old ceremonial court dresses, sculptures of a child (only one), etc.</e>
<cmt>terminology, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Totaling 80 figures, they are all male shinzos, armed sculptures wearing armor, and helmets, sculptures in old ceremonial court dresses, sculptures of a child (only one), etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>破損の多い像も多いが、これだけ多数の古神像が一神社にまとまって伝来する例は日本でも他になく、貴重なものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many are heavily damaged, but this is the only case in Japan where so many old shinzos are handed down in one shrine, and is precious.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many are heavily damaged, but this is the only case in Japan where so many old shinzos have been handed down in one shrine, and they are precious.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many are heavily damaged, but this is the only case in Japan where so many old shinzos have been handed down in one shrine, and they are precious.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>武装形像は作風に仏教の天部像との共通性もみられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Armed sculptures have a style common with that of Buddhist Tenbu zo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Armed sculptures have a style in common with that of Buddhist Tenbu zo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Armed sculptures have a style in common with that of Buddhist Tenbu zo (sculptures of the Buddhist guardians).</e>
<cmt>天部像の補足を入れました。(参考:http://www.pref.nara.jp/nara_e/dd_aspx_itemid-1385.htm)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>1972年、国の重要文化財に指定された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1972, it was designated as an important cultural property of Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1972, it was designated as an important cultural property of Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1972, it was designated as an important cultural property of Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="14">
<j>古天文暦道資料（京都府指定文化財）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kotenbunreki do shiryo (designated cultural property of Kyoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kotenbunreki do shiryo (designated cultural property of Kyoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kotenmonreki do shiryo (designated cultural property of Kyoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>Kotenbunreki→Kotenmonrekiに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="15">
<j>境内にはこれらの文化財を収めた方徳殿という建物があり、毎年5月1日～5月5日と11月1日～11月5日には一般に公開されている（その他の日は予約制）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the compound, there is a building called Hotoku-den (important cultural properties), where these cultural properties are stored, and is open to the public during May 1 to May 5 and November 1 to November 5 every year (reservation necessary on other days)..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the compound, there is a building called Hotoku-den (important cultural properties), where these cultural properties are stored, and it is open to the public from May 1 to May 5 and November 1 to November 5 every year (reservation necessary on other days)..</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the compound, there is a building called Hotoku-den, where these cultural properties are stored, and it is open to the public from May 1 to May 5 and November 1 to November 5 every year (reservation necessary on other days)..</e>
<cmt>Hotoku-denの後の&quot;(important cultural properties)&quot;は原文になく不要と思われますので削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 うぃき野郎(id:53567), Urania(id:7213), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>