<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>天之常立神</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amenotokotachinokami</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amenotokotachinokami</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amenotokotachi no Kami</e>
<cmt>神名表現を統一しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>天之常立神（あめのとこたちのかみ）は、日本神話に登場する神 (神道)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amenotokotachinokami was a Shinto deity appearing in the Japanese Mythology.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amenotokotachinokami was a Shinto deity appearing in the Japanese Mythology.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amenotokotachi no Kami is a god (Shinto) appearing in the Japanese mythology.</e>
<cmt>他ファイルと表現を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>天地開闢 (日本神話)の際、別天津神五柱の最後に現れた神である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the creation of heaven and earth (the Japanese Mythology), Amenotokotachinokami was the last one to come into being as the five Kotoamatsukami (separate heavenly deities).</e>
<cmt>「別天津神柱」の用語集の用語を一部変更しています</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the creation of heaven and earth (the Japanese Mythology), Amenotokotachinokami was the last one to come into being as the five Kotoamatsukami (separate heavenly deities).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the creation of heaven and earth (the Japanese mythology), Amenotokotachi no Kami was the last one to come into being as the five Kotoamatsu Kami (separate heavenly deities).</e>
<cmt>mythology を小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>独神であり、現れてすぐに身を隠した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was regarded as Hitorigami (a solitary deity), and hid himself away just after coming into being.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was regarded as Hitorigami (a solitary deity), and hid himself away just after coming into being.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was regarded as Hitorigami (god without gender), and hid himself away just after coming into being.</e>
<cmt>独神→god without gender としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>日本書紀本文には現れず、古事記および日本書紀の一書にのみ登場する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He does not appear in the main text of Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan), but appears in only Kojiki (Records of Ancient Matters) and Arufumi (supplement volumes of explanatory notes in Nihonshoki).</e>
<cmt>「一書」は「あるふみ」という日本書紀本文に対する別伝ですので、左記のように訳出しました</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He does not appear in the main text of Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan), but appears in only Kojiki (Records of Ancient Matters) and Arufumi (supplement volumes of explanatory notes in Nihonshoki).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He does not appear in the main text of Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan), but appears in only Kojiki (Records of Ancient Matters) and Arufumi (supplement volumes of explanatory notes in Nihonshoki) of Nihonshoki.</e>
<cmt>日本書紀　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>日本書紀では天常立尊と表記される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nihonshoki describes him as &quot;Amenotokotachinomikoto 天常立尊.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nihonshoki describes him as &quot;Amenotokotachinomikoto 天常立尊.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nihonshoki describes him as 天常立尊 (Amenotokotachi no Mikoto).</e>
<cmt>一部表現を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>天（高天原）そのものを神格化し、天の恒常性を表した神である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Heaven or Takamanohara (plain of high heaven) itself is deified as this deity symbolizing Heaven&apos;s eternity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Heaven or Takamanohara (plain of high heaven) itself is deified as this deity symbolizes Heaven&apos;s eternity.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Heaven or Takamanohara (plain of high heaven) itself is deified as this deity symbolizes Heaven&apos;s eternity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>先代旧事本紀では天之御中主神と同一の神であるとしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Sendai Kujihongi (Ancient Japanese History), he is identical to Amenominakanushinokami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Sendai Kujihongi (Ancient Japanese History), he is identical to Amenominakanushinokami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Sendai Kujihongi (Ancient Japanese History), he is identical to Amenominakanushi no Kami.</e>
<cmt>神名表現を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>その後に現れる国之常立神の方が古くから信仰されてきた神であり、国之常立神の対になる神として創造された神と考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Kunitokotachinokami, who came into being after him, has been worshiped longer than he, he is probably created to form a pair with Kunitokotachinokami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Kunitokotachinokami, who came into being after him, has been worshiped longer than he, he is probably created to form a pair with Kunitokotachinokami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Kunitokotachi no Kami, who came into being after him, has been worshiped longer than he, he is probably created to form a pair with Kunitokotachi no Kami.</e>
<cmt>神名表現を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>抽象的な神であり、神話に事績が全く出ないことから、祀る神社は少ない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Few shrines are dedicated to him because he is a metaphysical deity, and no description about his achievements can be found in mythology.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Few shrines are dedicated to him because he is a metaphysical deity, and no description about his achievements can be found in mythology.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Few shrines are dedicated to him because he is a metaphysical deity, and no description about his achievements can be found in mythology.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>出雲大社（出雲市）に客座神として祀られているほか、駒形神社（岩手県奥州市）、金持神社（鳥取県日野郡日野町 (鳥取県)）などに祀られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is enshrined in the Izumo Taisha Shrine (Izumo City) as a guest deity; he is also enshrined in the Komagata-jinja Shrine (Oshu City, Iwate Prefecture) and the Kanemochi-jinja Shrine (Hino-cho, Hino-gun, Tottori Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is enshrined in the Izumo Taisha Shrine (Izumo City) as a guest deity; he is also enshrined in the Komagata-jinja Shrine (Oshu City, Iwate Prefecture) and the Kanemochi-jinja Shrine (Hino-cho, Hino-gun, Tottori Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is enshrined in the Izumo Taisha Shrine (Izumo City) as a guest deity; he is also enshrined in the Komagata-jinja Shrine (Oshu City, Iwate Prefecture), Kanemochi-jinja Shrine (Hino-cho, Hino-gun, Tottori Prefecture), etc.</e>
<cmt>etc. を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 三竹修二郎(id:88082), Yanahan(id:2437), Rusk(id:9895), Gpserist(id:84885), Nnh(id:474), Hatsune(id:26654), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>