<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>穢れ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kegare</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kegare</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kegare</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>穢れ（けがれ）とは、仏教、神道における観念の一つで、不潔・不浄等、清浄ではない汚れて悪しき状態のことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kegare is a notion in Buddhism and Shinto and means an unclean (清浄ではない,) dirty and bad state other than unclean or impure state (不潔,) (不浄,) etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kegare is a notion in Buddhism and Shinto and means an unclean (清浄ではない,) dirty or bad state separate from being in an unclean or impure state (不潔,) (不浄,) etc.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kegare is a notion in Buddhism and Shinto and means a dirty, bad, not clean state, such as being unclean, impure etc.</e>
<cmt>原文と意味が違うと思います。書き直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>元来は現代語の「怪我」が万葉仮名で書かれるように、単に負傷する事を示した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally, it simply meant to get injured as a modern term &apos;Kega (怪我) (injury)&apos; was written in Manyo-gana (a form of syllable used in the Manyo-shu or Collection of Myriad Leaves.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally, it simply referred to becoming injured as a modern term &apos;Kega (怪我) (injury)&apos; was written in Manyo-gana (a form of syllable used in the Manyo-shu or Collection of Myriad Leaves.)</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally, it simply referred to becoming injured as a modern term &apos;Kega (怪我) (injury)&apos; was written in Manyo-gana (a form of syllable used in the Manyo-shu or Collection of Myriad Leaves.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>「けがる」と「よごる」の違いは下記のとおりである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A difference between &apos;Kegaru&apos; and &apos;Yogoru&apos; is</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A difference between &apos;Kegaru&apos; and &apos;Yogoru&apos; is</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A difference between &apos;Kegaru&apos; and &apos;Yogoru&apos; is as follows:</e>
<cmt>原文、訳文ともに言葉を補って文を完結させました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>「よごる」が一時的・表面的な汚れであり洗浄等の行為で除去できるのに対し、「けがる」は永続的・内面的汚れであり「清め」等の儀式執行により除去されるとされる汚れである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yogoru&apos; is a short-time and surface dirtiness and can be removed by acts of cleaning, but &apos;Kegaru&apos; is continuous and inner dirtiness and a type of dirtiness which seems to be removed by ritual ceremonies such as &apos;Kiyome,&apos; etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yogoru&apos; is a temporary and shallow impurity that can be removed by acts of cleaning, but &apos;Kegaru&apos; is a continuous and inner impurity and a type of impurity which seems to be removed by ritual ceremonies such as &apos;Kiyome,&apos; etc.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yogoru is a temporary and shallow impurity that can be removed by acts of cleaning, but &apos;Kegaru&apos; is a continuous and inner impurity and a type of impurity which seems to be removed by ritual ceremonies such as &apos;Kiyome,&apos; etc.</e>
<cmt>文頭の &apos; &apos; 削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>主観的不潔感。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Subjective feeling of uncleanness</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subjective feeling of impurity</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subjective feeling of impurity</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>罪と併せて「罪穢れ」と総称されることが多いが、罪が人為的に発生するものであるのに対し、穢れは自然に発生するものであるとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kegare and sin are often collectively called as &apos;Tsumi Kegare&apos; and while Tsumi is man-caused, Kegare is thought to arise naturally.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kegare and sin are often collectively called as &apos;Tsumi Kegare&apos; and while Tsumi is caused by man, Kegare is thought to arise naturally.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kegare and sin are often collectively called as &apos;Tsumi Kegare&apos; and while Tsumi is caused by man, Kegare is thought to arise naturally.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>穢れが身体につくと、個人だけでなくその人が属する共同体の秩序を乱し災いをもたらすと考えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Upon attachment of Kegare on someone&apos;s body, it was believed that the Kegare would cause to disturb the order of both the person and the community the person belonged to and generate troubles to the both.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Upon attachment of Kegare to someone&apos;s body, it was believed that Kegare would disturb the order of both the person and the community the person belonged to and generate troubles for both.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Upon attachment of Kegare to someone&apos;s body, it was believed that Kegare would disturb the order of both the person and the community the person belonged to and generate troubles for both.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>穢れは普通に生活しているだけでも蓄積されていくが、死・疫病・出産・月経、また犯罪によって身体につくとされ、穢れた状態の人は祭事に携ることや、宮廷においては朝参、狩猟者・炭焼などでは山に入ることなど、共同体への参加が禁じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Kegare increased even in ordinary daily lives, Kegare was thought to attach to people&apos;s body from death, plagues, child birth, period and crimes, and persons with Kegare were prohibited to be involved in ritual ceremonies, conduct Chosan (a visit of a government official to the imperial court) and enter mountains to hunt, char-grill lumbers, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While Kegare increased even in ordinary daily lives, Kegare was thought to attach to people&apos;s body from death, plagues, child birth, period and crimes, and persons with Kegare were prohibited to be involved in ritual ceremonies, conduct Chosan (a visit of a government official to the imperial court) and enter mountains to hunt, char-grill lumbers, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While Kegare increased even in ordinary daily lives, Kegare was thought to attach to people&apos;s body from death, plagues, child birth, period and crimes, and persons with Kegare were prohibited to be involved in ritual ceremonies, conduct Chosan (a visit of a government official to the imperial court) and enter mountains to hunt, char-grill lumbers, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>穢れは禊（みそぎ）や祓（はらえ）によって浄化できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kegare can be removed by Misogi or Harae (form of Shinto purification.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kegare can be removed by Misogi or Harae (form of Shinto purification.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kegare can be removed by Misogi or Harae (form of Shinto purification.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>「罪」は「恙み（ツツガミ）」から、精神的な負傷や憂いを意味する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsumi (sin)&apos; is the same as &apos;Tsutsugami (harm)&apos; and means mental injury or trouble and sadness or sorrow from it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsumi (sin)&apos; is the same as &apos;Tsutsugami (harm)&apos; and means mental injury or trouble and sadness or sorrow from it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsumi (sin) is the same as &apos;Tsutsugami (harm)&apos; and means mental injury or trouble and sadness or sorrow from it.</e>
<cmt>文頭の&apos; &apos; 削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>近年の民俗学では、「ケガレ」を「気枯れ」すなわちケとハレがカレた状態とし、祭などのハレの儀式でケを回復する（ケガレをはらう、「気を良める」→清める）という考え方も示されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ethnic studies in recent years show an idea that &apos;Kegare (ケガレ)&apos; is &apos;気枯れ,&apos; that is the state that Ke and Hare (noticeably cheerful and formal situations or such places) disappeared, and Ke has to be recovered (remove Kegare, &apos;Ki o yomeru (気を良める)&apos;=&gt;Kiyomeru (clean)) by holding Hare ceremonies such as a festival.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ethnic studies in recent years show an idea that &apos;Kegare (ケガレ)&apos; is &apos;気枯れ,&apos; which is the state in whicht Ke and Hare (noticeably cheerful and formal situations or such places) disappeared, and Ke has to be recovered (remove Kegare, &apos;Ki o yomeru (気を良める)&apos;=&gt;Kiyomeru (clean)) by holding Hare ceremonies such as a festival.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ethnic studies in recent years show an idea that &apos;Kegare (ケガレ)&apos; is &apos;気枯れ,&apos; which is the state in whicht Ke and Hare (noticeably cheerful and formal situations or such places) disappeared, and Ke has to be recovered (remove Kegare, &apos;Ki o yomeru (気を良める)&apos;=&gt;Kiyomeru (clean)) by holding Hare ceremonies such as a festival.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="12">
<j>この点については「ハレとケ」の項目も参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Refer to the &apos;Hare and Ke&apos; section for more details.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Refer to the &apos;Hare and Ke&apos; section for more details.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Refer to the &apos;Hare and Ke&apos; section for more details.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="13">
<j>類似の観念は他の宗教や民間信仰にもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are similar notions in other religions or folk beliefs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are similar notions in other religions or folk beliefs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are similar notions in other religions or folk beliefs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>これらについては一般の穢れ観念の項を参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Refer to the general notions of Kegare on this respect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Refer to the general notions of Kegare on this respect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Refer to the general notions of Kegare on this respect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>日本神話における穢れ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kegare in Japanese myths</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kegare in Japanese myths</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kegare in Japanese myths</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="15">
<j>黄泉の国から戻ったイザナギは禊をしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Izanagi went through Misogi after he was back from Yominokuni (hades, realm of the dead, the next world.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Izanagi went through Misogi after he was back from Yominokuni (hades, realm of the dead, the next world.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Izanagi went through Misogi after he was back from Yominokuni (hades, realm of the dead, the next world.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>これは、黄泉の穢れを払う行為であり、その最中に何柱もの神々が誕生した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was an act to remove Kegare which had attached to him in Yominokuni, and gave birth to a lot of Kami (god) during the course of Misogi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was an act to remove Kegare which had attached to him in Yominokuni, and gave birth to a lot of Kami (god) during the course of Misogi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was an act to remove Kegare which had attached to him in Yominokuni, and gave birth to a lot of Kami (god) during the course of Misogi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>三貴子など。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mihashira no uzuno miko (three noble children) was one of them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mihashira no uzuno miko (three noble children) was one of them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mihashira no uzuno miko (three noble children) were among them.</e>
<cmt>three children なので複数にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>また、祓われた穢れそのものからも神が誕生した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kami was also born from removed Kegare.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kami was also born from removed Kegare.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kami was also born from removed Kegare.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="19">
<j>スサノオがアマテラスの屋敷に天斑駒を乱入させた故事に於いて従女の死である「死の穢れ」が初出である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first appearance of Kegare was &apos;Kegare of death&apos; which was related to the death of Tomomewarawa (servant) appearing in a tradition that Susano directed Ama no fuchigoma Horse to break into Amaterasu&apos;s residence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first appearance of Kegare was &apos;Kegare of death&apos; which was related to the death of Tomomewarawa (servant) appearing in a tradition where Susano directed Ama no fuchigoma Horse to break into Amaterasu&apos;s residence.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first appearance of Kegare was &apos;Kegare of death&apos; which was related to the death of Tomomewarawa (servant) appearing in a tradition where Susano directed Ama no fuchigoma Horse to break into Amaterasu&apos;s residence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>神道と仏教</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinto and Buddhism</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinto and Buddhism</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinto and Buddhism</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="20">
<j>両者とも穢れに対する意識はあるがもっとも異なるのは、死そのものに対する考えで、神道では死や血を穢れとするが仏教では神道のようには死を穢れとみなさない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Both Shinto and Buddhism are conscious of Kegare, but the biggest difference between the both is a notion of death, and while Shinto considers death and blood as Kegare, Buddhism does not regard death as Kegare like Shinto does.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Both Shinto and Buddhism are conscious of Kegare, but the biggest difference between the both is the notion of death, and while Shinto considers death and blood as Kegare, Buddhism does not regard death as Kegare like Shinto does.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Both Shinto and Buddhism are conscious of Kegare, but the biggest difference between the both is the notion of death, and while Shinto considers death and blood as Kegare, Buddhism does not regard death as Kegare like Shinto does.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>葬式などは、仏教では寺で行うこともあるが、神道では神域たる神社ではなく各家で行う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A Buddhism funeral may be held at a temple, and a Shinto funeral is held at a place other than a shrine which is regarded as the holly precincts of a shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A Buddhism funeral may be held at a temple, and a Shinto funeral is held at a place other than a shrine which is regarded as the holy precincts of a shrine.</e>
<cmt>Spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A Buddhism funeral may be held at a temple, and a Shinto funeral is held at a place other than a shrine which is regarded as the holy precincts.</e>
<cmt>最後の of a shrine は不要と判断しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>これは神聖なものがなんであるかの違いであり、また、清めの塩は穢れを清めているものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is depending on what the holly thing is, and salt for purification is intended to remove Kegare.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This depends on what the holy thing is, and salt for purification is intended to remove Kegare.</e>
<cmt>Grammar and Spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This depends on what the holy thing is, and salt for purification is intended to remove Kegare.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>この穢れは死者ではなく、死という事象が穢れていると感じた精神的な物である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This Kegare does not mean a dead person but means mental aspect that an incident of death feels Kegare.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This Kegare does not mean a dead person but refers to a mental aspect that an incident of death feels Kegare.</e>
<cmt>Robert: Translation doesn’t make sense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This Kegare refers to death itself rather than a dead person.</e>
<cmt>NCのコメントを読み、書き換えました。原文に忠実に訳すとコメントのようになってしまうと思い意訳しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>仏教では、死は次へ転生する輪廻という世界の有り様であり、これを否定するような概念は存在しない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Buddhism, death designates the situation of Rinne (the wheel of life) world in which death reincarnates to the next stage, and there is no concept to deny this.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Buddhism, death represents the Rinne (the wheel of life) world in reincarnation takes place, and there is no concept to deny this.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Buddhism, death represents the Rinne (the wheel of life) world in reincarnation takes place, and there is no concept to deny this.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>その現象から自ら抜け出そうとする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It means to try to get out of such phenomenon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It means trying to escape from such a phenomenon.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It means trying to escape from such a phenomenon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>仏教での穢れは、業として蓄積されることを嫌うものであり、こちらは論理的根拠に基づく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Buddhism dislikes that Kegare is accumulated in a form of karma, that is based on the logical basis.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Buddhism dislikes that Kegare is accumulated in a form of karma, that is based on login.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Buddhism dislikes that Kegare is accumulated in a form of karma, that is based on logic.</e>
<cmt>login→logic</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>他にも宗教では、すべて穢れなど嫌う物に対しなんらかの論理的根拠を持っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In other religions, there is some logical basis for all disliked things such as Kegare.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In other religions, there is some logical basis for all things that are disliked such as Kegare.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In other religions, there is some logical basis for all things that are disliked such as Kegare.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="28">
<j>他にも日本古来の土着的な穢れ(何を嫌っているか)の概念は、普段の生活に垣間みることができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other notions of Kegare (a sense of discomfort) which have been established since the ancient times in Japan can be seen in people&apos;s ordinary life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other notions of Kegare (a sense of discomfort) which have been established since ancient times in Japan can be seen in people&apos;s ordinary life.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other notions of Kegare (a sense of discomfort) which have been established since ancient times in Japan can be seen in people&apos;s ordinary life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>そのひとつに食事の作法があるだろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Manner for eating meals will be one of them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Manners in eating meals is one.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Manners in eating meals is one.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>また、このような概念は古代のシャーマニズムとして世界中に土着し存在していたと考えられるが、それは世界的な様々な宗教の流布や民族の流れによってうやむやになってしまっているところも多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such notions are thought to have been ancient shamanism which have indigenously existed all over the world, but they, in many ways, have become vague or ambiguous as a result of the spread of religions and people&apos;s relocations in the world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such notions are thought to have been ancient shamanism which indigenously existed all over the world, but they, in many ways, have become vague or ambiguous as a result of the spread of religions and people&apos;s relocations in the world.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such notions are thought to have been ancient shamanism which indigenously existed all over the world, but they, in many ways, have become vague or ambiguous as a result of the spread of religions and people&apos;s relocations in the world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="31">
<j>日本人にとって神は超自然的な物であり、畏れられると共に敬われもした(御霊信仰など)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kami (god) was mythical and venerable for Japanese people (Goryo-shinko (a folk religious belief of avenging spirits.))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kami (god) was mythical and venerable for Japanese people (Goryo-shinko (a folk religious belief of avenging spirits.))</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kami (god) was mythical and venerable for Japanese people (Goryo-shinko (a folk religious belief of avenging spirits.))</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>神を斎き祀るとは、恐怖としての神を信仰し御霊とすることで鎮めることにある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To enshrine and worship Kami is aimed to believe in Kami considered awful and cool down Kami by making Kami a spirit of a deceased person.</e>
<cmt>理解しづらい日本語文章です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To enshrine and worship Kami is aimed to believe in Kami considered awful and cool down Kami by making Kami a spirit of a deceased person.</e>
<cmt>Robret: Translation doesn’t make sense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">People appeased Kami, who inspired a sense of fear in them, by enshrining and worshipping them as holy spirits.</e>
<cmt>Ｅ欄にあるように、原文がわかりにくいのですが、ＮＣコメントに従って書き換えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>天皇は皇祖神である天照大神の血を引いているとされ、神々と同じく尊い方であるとされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor was believed to be from Amaterasu Omikami (the Sun Goddess) regarded as Kososhin (Imperial ancestor) and a respectful person as well as Kami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emperor was believed to be from Amaterasu Omikami (the Sun Goddess) regarded as Kososhin (Imperial ancestor) and a respectful person as well as Kami.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emperor was believed to be from Amaterasu Omikami (the Sun Goddess) regarded as Kososhin (Imperial ancestor) and a respectful person as well as Kami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>それら神々を祀る神社は、神を磐座や禁足地より降臨させ祭り事を執り行う臨時のものであったが、次第に禁足地に対して拝殿が、そして神そのものが常駐するという本殿が造営されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shrines to enshrine such Kami were a temporary place where Kami was descended from Iwakura (dwelling place of a god, usually in reference to a large rock) or Kinsokuchi (tabooed land,) and ritual ceremonies were performed, but gradually, Haiden (a hall of worship) was built for a substitute of Kinsokuchi and Honden (a main shrine) was built to let Kami reside there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shrines to enshrine such Kami were a temporary place where Kami descended from Iwakura (dwelling place of a god, usually in reference to a large rock) or Kinsokuchi (tabooed land,) and ritual ceremonies were performed, but gradually, Haiden (a hall of worship) was built as a substitute for Kinsokuchi and Honden (a main shrine) was built to let Kami reside there.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shrines to enshrine such Kami were a temporary place where Kami descended from Iwakura (dwelling place of a god, usually in reference to a large rock) or Kinsokuchi (tabooed land,) and ritual ceremonies were performed, but gradually, Haiden (a hall of worship) was built as a substitute for Kinsokuchi and Honden (a main shrine) was built to let Kami reside there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>これらの神と穢れは相成り得ないものであり、神社での手水舎は、外界での穢れを祓うために設置されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such Kami and Kegare are not compatible, and that is why Chozusha (purification trough) is placed at a shrine to remove outside Kegare from visitors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such Kami and Kegare are not compatible, and that is why Chozusha (purification trough) is placed at a shrine to remove outside Kegare from visitors.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such Kami and Kegare are not compatible, and that is why Chozusha (purification trough) is placed at a shrine to remove outside Kegare from visitors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="36">
<j>日本での仏教は神道との習合がいたるところで存在し、両者での考えが入り乱れていることもある(寺院における鳥居、建築様式など)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Syncretization of Shinto with Buddhism exists in many places in Japan and the ideas and concepts of the both are somewhat mixed up or confusing (Torii (an archway to a Shinto shrine) and construction style at a shrine.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Syncretization of Shinto with Buddhism exists in many places in Japan and the ideas and concepts of both are somewhat mixed up or confused (Torii (an archway to a Shinto shrine) and construction style at a shrine.)</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Syncretization of Shinto with Buddhism exists in many places in Japan and the ideas and concepts of both are somewhat mixed up or confused (Torii (an archway to a Shinto shrine) and construction style at a shrine.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>穢れも同様である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are the same mix-up and confusions in Kegare.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The same mix-up and confusions also apply in Kegare.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The same mix-up and confusions also apply in Kegare.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>穢れ観念の起源</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Origin of a notion of Kegare</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Origin of Kegare</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Origin of Kegare</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="38">
<j>穢れという観念が日本に流入したのは、平安時代だと言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is thought that the time when a notion of Kegare was imported in Japan was the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is thought that the notion of Kegare was imported in Japan during the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is thought that the notion of Kegare was imported in Japan during the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>死、出産、血液などが穢れているとする観念は元々ヒンドゥー教のもので、同じくインドで生まれた仏教にもこの思想が流入した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The notion that death, child birth and blood were Kegare originated in Hinduism, and flowed into Buddhism which had arisen in India too.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The notion that death, child birth and blood were Kegare originated in Hinduism, and flowed into Buddhism which had arisen in India as well.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The notion that death, child birth and blood were Kegare originated in Hinduism, and flowed into Buddhism which had arisen in India as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>特に、平安時代に日本に多く伝わった平安仏教は、この思想を持つものが多かったため、穢れ観念は京都を中心に日本全国へと広がっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Particularly, many of Heian Buddhism which were imported to Japan in the Heian period had this thought, and the notion of Kegare spread from Kyoto to all other places in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Particularly, most Buddhism imported to Japan in the Heian period had this thought, and the notion of Kegare spread from Kyoto to all other places in Japan.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Particularly, most Buddhism imported to Japan in the Heian period had this thought, and the notion of Kegare spread from Kyoto to all other places in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>賤視から不浄視へ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From looking down to seeing unclean</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From looking down to seeing the unclean</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From looking down to seeing the unclean</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="41">
<j>これ以前の日本にも、邪馬台国の奴婢制や奈良時代の五色の賤など、身分差別は存在したが、それは賤視（下へ見下す見方）であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before that time, there also was a caste system in Japan such as Nuhi system in Yamatai-Koku kingdom and Goshiki no sen (Ryoko, Kanko, Kenin, Kunuhi, Shinuhi) in the Nara period, and that was a disdain (a way of looking down.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before that time, there also was a caste system in Japan such as Nuhi system in Yamatai-Koku kingdom and Goshiki no sen (Ryoko, Kanko, Kenin, Kunuhi, Shinuhi) in the Nara period, and was a way of exhibiting disdain (a way of looking down.)</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before that time, there also was a caste system in Japan such as Nuhi system in Yamatai-Koku kingdom and Goshiki no sen (Ryoko, Kanko, Kenin, Kunuhi, Shinuhi) in the Nara period, and was a way of exhibiting disdain (a way of looking down.)</e>
<cmt>disdain の前のスペース短縮</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>これに対し、穢れ観流入後の被差別民に対する差別は、不浄視（穢れ視する見方）へと変化した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other side, after the arrival of Kegare notion, discrimination against discriminated people changed to the way of seeing them unclean (to see them Kegare.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other side, after the arrival of the notion of Kegare, discrimination against discriminated people changed, in that they were seen as unclean (to see them Kegare.)</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other side, after the arrival of the notion of Kegare, discrimination against discriminated people changed, in that they were seen as unclean (to see them Kegare.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>江戸時代の最も代表的な賤民が穢多（穢れが多いと言う意味）と呼称されたのは、その象徴である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is represented by the fact that the most typical humble people in the Edo period were called Eta (meaning much Kegare.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is represented by the fact that the most typical humble people in the Edo period were called Eta (meaning much Kegare.)</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is represented by the fact that the most typical humble people in the Edo period were called Eta (meaning much Kegare.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>神道との関連</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Relation to Shinto</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Relation to Shinto</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Relation to Shinto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="44">
<j>上記のように、穢れは元々仏教により日本にもたらされた観念であるが、次第に天皇を神聖視する神道の考えと結びつき、被差別民は神聖な天皇の対極に位置する穢れた民と見なされるようになったという説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As explained above, though Kegare was a notion which had been originally brought into Japan with Buddhism, it gradually tied up to the concept of Shinto in which the Emperor was seen holly, and as a result, discriminated people were thought to be Kegare people who was a negation of the Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As explained above, though Kegare was a notion which had been originally brought into Japan with Buddhism, it gradually tied up to the concept of Shinto in which the Emperor was seen as holy, and as a result, discriminated people were thought to be Kegare people who was a negation of the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>Robert: Translation doesn’t make sense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a theory that though Kegare was a notion which had been originally brought into Japan with Buddhism as mentioned above, it was gradually syncretized with the concept of Shinto in which the Emperor was seen as holy, and as a result, the discriminated were thought to be Kegare people who were at the opposite end of the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>ＮＣコメントに従って書き換えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>だが、朝鮮半島においても、牛馬の解体・皮革産業に従事する被差別民「白丁」が存在し、中世ドイツでも焚書を牛馬の解体場で行うなどの例があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were discriminated people called &apos;Hakucho&apos; (inferior servants) in Korean Peninsula who were engaged in slaughtering cows and horses and leather industry, and in medieval Germany, there were cases in which books were burnt in a slaughterhouse of cows and horses.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were discriminated people called &apos;Hakucho&apos; (inferior servants) in Korean Peninsula who were engaged in slaughtering cows and horses and leather industry, and in medieval Germany, there were cases in which books were burnt in a slaughterhouse of cows and horses.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were discriminated people called &apos;Hakucho&apos; (inferior servants) in Korean Peninsula who were engaged in slaughtering cows and horses and leather industry, and in medieval Germany, there were cases in which books were burnt in a slaughterhouse of cows and horses.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>この種の差別を神道と直結する説には反対意見もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there are objections about the thought that this type of discrimination is directly connected with Shinto.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there are objections towards the thought that this type of discrimination is directly connected with Shinto.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there are objections towards the thought that this type of discrimination is directly connected with Shinto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>また、学者の網野善彦などの研究により、被差別民と天皇との密接な結びつきが明らかとなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Close relations between discriminated people and the Emperor were clarified through the research of a scholar Yoshihiko AMINO, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Close relations between discriminated people and the Emperor were clarified through research by scholars such as Yoshihiko AMINO, etc.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Close relations between discriminated people and the Emperor were clarified through research by scholars such as Yoshihiko AMINO, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>天皇を「清め」（不浄なものの浄化）の職能の最高者とみる説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a view that the Emperor is an awesome person who has a function of &apos;Kiyome&apos; (cleaning of unclean things.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a view that the Emperor is an awesome person who has a function of &apos;Kiyome&apos; (cleaning of unclean things.)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a view that the Emperor is an awesome person who has a function of &apos;Kiyome&apos; (cleaning of unclean things.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>高取正男は仏教の不浄観によって「ケガレ」の観念が変容したと見ている（『神道の成立』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masao TAKATORI thinks that the notion of &apos;Kegare&apos; changed because of the notion of uncleanness in Buddhism (&quot;Shinto no seiritsu&quot; (Formation of Shinto.))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masao TAKATORI thinks that the notion of &apos;Kegare&apos; changed because of the notion of uncleanness in Buddhism (&quot;Shinto no seiritsu&quot; (Formation of Shinto.))</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masao TAKATORI thinks that the notion of &apos;Kegare&apos; changed because of the notion of uncleanness in Buddhism (&quot;Shinto no seiritsu&quot; (Formation of Shinto.))</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="50">
<j>一般の穢れ観念</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">General notion of Kegare</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">General notion of Kegare</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">General notion of Kegare</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>穢れまたは不浄に相当する観念は世界的に見られ、質・程度の差こそあれ多くの文化に存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A notion corresponding to Kegare or uncleanness is observed in the world, and exists in many cultures on one nature and level or another.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A notion corresponding to Kegare or uncleanness exists in many cultures on one nature and level or another.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A notion corresponding to Kegare or uncleanness exists in many cultures on one nature and level or another.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>特に現代のような科学知識のない近代以前や未開の人々からみれば重要な概念である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was an important view for people living before the modern period or in uncivilized areas in which there was no scientific knowledge as we have now.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was an important view for people living before the modern period or in uncivilized areas in which there was no scientific knowledge as we have now.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was an important view for people living before the modern period or in uncivilized areas in which there was no scientific knowledge as we have now.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>穢れたものは、それに物理的または精神的に触れることによって穢れが「伝染」すると見なされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was thought that upon physical or mental contact to a thing with Kegare, the Kegare was infected.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was thought that upon physical or mental contact to a thing with Kegare, the Kegare was infected.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was thought that upon physical or mental contact to a thing with Kegare, the Kegare was infected.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>また現代人にとっては、手や体を水で洗うことは病原体を洗い流すためと説明できるが、古代人にとってはそのような意味はなく、目に見えるよごれを落とすと同時に、穢れをはらうことでもあると考えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It can be explained to modern people that cleaning hands and body aims to wash away viruses, but it did not mean so for ancient people, and rather, the purpose was both to take off visible dirt and remove Kegare.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It can be explained to modern people that cleaning one&apos;s hands and body aims to wash away viruses, but it did not mean so for ancient people, and rather, the purpose was both to take off visible dirt and remove Kegare.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It can be explained to modern people that cleaning one&apos;s hands and body aims to wash away viruses, but it did not mean so for ancient people, and rather, the purpose was both to take off visible dirt and remove Kegare.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>これは現代でも禊、潅頂や洗礼を始め様々な宗教儀式に名残を留めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This remains in various religious ceremonies such as purification ceremony, Kanjo (the esoteric Buddhist ritual of pouring water on the top of a monk&apos;s head) and being christened.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This remains in various religious ceremonies such as purification ceremony, Kanjo (the esoteric Buddhist ritual of pouring water on the top of a monk&apos;s head) and being christened.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This remains in various religious ceremonies such as purification ceremony, Kanjo (the esoteric Buddhist ritual of pouring water on the top of a monk&apos;s head) and being christened.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>神道の「罪穢れ」のように罪と穢れを同列に扱う考え方も、古代には特殊なものではなかったと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that a conception of treating sin and Kegare in the same way like &apos;sin and Kegare&apos; in Shinto was not a special one in ancient periods.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that a conception of treating sin and Kegare in the same way like &apos;sin and Kegare&apos; in Shinto was not a special one in ancient periods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that a conception of treating sin and Kegare in the same way like &apos;sin and Kegare&apos; in Shinto was not a special one in ancient periods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="57">
<j>穢れているとされる対象としては、死・病気・怪我・女性ならびにこれらに関するものが代表的である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Typical things with Kegare are death, disease, injury, women and all things related to the four mentioned above.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Typical things with Kegare are death, disease, injury, women and all things related to the four mentioned above.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Typical things with Kegare are death, disease, injury, women and all things related to the four mentioned above.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="58">
<j>具体例を挙げると、文化・宗教によって大きく異なるが、排泄物・腐敗物、血・体液・月経・出産、特定または一般の動物・食物、女性・男女間のあらゆる接触ならびに行為（ごくまれに男性、同性間の性関係ならびに行為）・自らの共同体以外の人（他県人・外国人・異民族）やその文化・特定の血筋または身分の人（不可触賎民など）・特定の職業（芸能、金融業、精肉業等）・体の一部（左手を食事に使ってはならない等）などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though they may differ depending on the culture and religion, some concrete examples are egested things, rotten things, blood, body fluid, period, child birth, particular animals and foods, all contacts and acts between women and between men and women (very rarely, sexual relations and acts between men and people of the same sex,) people outside own community (people of other prefectures, foreigners and different races,) culture, people of particular blood line or rank (scheduled castes,) particular occupations (entertainment, financial and meat industries) and particular parts of a human body (a left had can not be used for eating, etc.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though they may differ depending on the culture and religion, some concrete examples are egested things, rotten things, blood, body fluid, period, child birth, particular animals and foods, all contacts and acts between women and between men and women (very rarely, sexual relations and acts between men and people of the same sex,) people outside own community (people of other prefectures, foreigners and different races,) culture, people of particular blood line or rank (scheduled castes,) particular occupations (entertainment, financial and meat industries) and particular parts of a human body (a left had can not be used for eating, etc.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though they may differ depending on the culture and religion, some concrete examples are egested things, rotten things, blood, body fluid, period, child birth, particular or general animals and foods, all contacts and acts between women and between men and women (very rarely, sexual relations and acts between men and people of the same sex,) people outside own community (people of other prefectures, foreigners and different races,) culture, people of particular blood line or rank (scheduled castes,) particular occupations (entertainment, financial and meat industries) and particular parts of a human body (a left had can not be used for eating, etc.)</e>
<cmt>「一般の」 追記</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>これらは必ずしも絶対的な穢れのみというわけではなく、行為などによって異なることが多い（例えば、ある動物に触れるのは構わないが食べてはいけない、など）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These are not necessarily absolute Kegare, and differ in many cases depending on acts (e.g. it is alright to touch a certain animal, but eating it is prohibited, etc.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These are not necessarily absolute Kegare, and differ in many cases depending on acts (e.g. it is alright to touch a certain animal, but eating it is prohibited, etc.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These are not necessarily absolute Kegare, and differ in many cases depending on acts (e.g. it is alright to touch a certain animal, but eating it is prohibited, etc.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="60">
<j>穢れの観念は民間信仰はもとより、多数の有力宗教にも見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The notion of Kegare is recognized not only in folk religions but also in many primary religions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The notion of Kegare is recognized not only in folk religions but also in many primary religions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The notion of Kegare is recognized not only in folk religions but also in many primary religions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>ユダヤ教では古くから様々な穢れの観念が事細かに規定され、これは食タブーなどに関してイスラム教にも影響を与え、現代でも多くの人々の生活様式に影響を残している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Judaism, various notions of Kegare have been determined in detail for a long time, and this affected Islam in regard to the food taboo and also have left imprints on many people&apos;s life styles even in modern times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Judaism, various notions of Kegare have been determined in detail for a long time, and this affected Islam in regard to the food taboo and also have left imprints on many people&apos;s life styles even in modern times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Judaism, various notions of Kegare have been determined in detail for a long time, and this affected Islam in regard to the food taboo and also have left imprints on many people&apos;s life styles even in modern times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>バラモン教の穢れ観念は現代のヒンドゥー教に受け継がれ、また仏教にも影響を残した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A notion of Kegare in Brahmanism was succeeded by modern Hindu and also left imprints on Buddhism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A notion of Kegare in Brahmanism was succeeded by modern Hindu and also left imprints on Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A notion of Kegare in Brahmanism was succeeded by modern Hindu and also left imprints on Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="63">
<j>「穢れ」に対立する概念は「清浄」または「神聖」であるが、穢れと神聖はどちらもタブーとして遠ざけられる対象であり、タブーであることだけが強調されて、必ずしも厳密に区別できないこともある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Opposite concept for &apos;Kegare&apos; is &apos;purity&apos; or &apos;sacredness,&apos; but both Kegare and sacredness are often the subject to be avoided as taboo things and it is only emphasized that both are taboo and it is not always possible to distinguish one from another strictly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Opposite concept for &apos;Kegare&apos; is &apos;purity&apos; or &apos;sacredness,&apos; but both Kegare and sacredness are often the subject to be avoided as taboo things and it is only emphasized that both are taboo and it is not always possible to distinguish one from another strictly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Opposite concept for &apos;Kegare&apos; is &apos;purity&apos; or &apos;sacredness,&apos; but both Kegare and sacredness are often the subject to be avoided as taboo things and it is only emphasized that both are taboo and it is not always possible to distinguish one from another strictly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>例えばユダヤ教では動物の血は食に関する限り「不浄な生き物」と同様に忌まれるものであるが、これはユダヤ教において「血は命であるから食べてはならない」（申命記）と説明される神聖なものであることに起因するものであり、決して穢れたものであるからではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taking Judaism as an example, animal&apos;s blood is hated as much as &apos;unclean living thing&apos; only for eating, but this is because animal&apos;s blood is a holly thing which is described as &apos;blood is life, so it can not be eaten&apos; (Shinmeiki) in Judaism and not because animal&apos;s blood is a thing with Kegare.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taking Judaism as an example, animal&apos;s blood is hated as much as &apos;unclean living thing&apos; only for eating, but this is because animal&apos;s blood is a holly thing which is described as &apos;blood is life, so it can not be eaten&apos; (Shinmeiki) in Judaism and not because animal&apos;s blood is a thing with Kegare.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taking Judaism as an example, animal&apos;s blood is hated as much as &apos;unclean living thing&apos; only for eating, but this is because animal&apos;s blood is a holy thing which is described as &apos;blood is life, so it can not be eaten&apos; (Deuteronomy) in Judaism and not because animal&apos;s blood is a thing with Kegare.</e>
<cmt>holly→holyas の前のスペース短縮申命記を英語に変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Toroia(id:31889), Nnh(id:474), 杉原からの手紙(id:69849), Kstigarbha(id:13376), Syatihoko(id:51625), Memosa(id:131221), 横浜大塚(id:107010), Tribot(id:186681), Hokahoka(id:37244), Neo chemistry(id:143489), Lyijykyyneleet(id:13506), ABnormal(id:254617), 白鉢巻(id:250052), Tenko(id:102318), ぬめりけ(id:124504), KASAGI(id:24405), Suisui(id:69), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>