<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>神域</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shin-iki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shin-iki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shiniki</e>
<cmt>ハイフンを削除し、Shinikiとして統一しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>神域（しんいき）とは、神社の境内または神が宿る場所（依り代）のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shin-iki is precincts of a shrine or a place where gods dwell (yorishiro).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shin-iki is precincts of a shrine or a place where gods dwell (yorishiro).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shiniki is precincts of a shrine or a place where gods dwell (yorishiro).</e>
<cmt>ハイフンを削除し、Shinikiとして統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>あるいは、それから派生して重要な場所という意味でも使われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Or deriving from it, the term Shin-iki is also used in referring to an important place.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Or deriving from it, the term Shin-iki is also used in referring to an important place.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Or deriving from it, the term Shiniki is also used in referring to an important place.</e>
<cmt>ハイフンを削除し、Shinikiとして統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summery</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summery</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summery</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>古神道である神籬（ひもろぎ）や磐座（いわくら）信仰は、神の依り代である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Koshinto (the ancient Shinto), himorogi (a temporarily erected sacred space or &quot;altar&quot; used as a locus of worship) and iwakura (dwelling place of a god, usually in reference to a large rock) are yorishiro of gods.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Koshinto (the ancient Shinto), himorogi (a temporarily erected sacred space or &quot;altar&quot; used as a locus of worship) and iwakura (dwelling place of a god, usually in reference to a large rock) are yorishiro of gods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Koshinto (the ancient Shinto), himorogi (a temporarily erected sacred space or &quot;altar&quot; used as a locus of worship) and iwakura (dwelling place of a god, usually in reference to a large rock) are yorishiro of gods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>とともに、神籬の「籬」は、垣（かき）の意味であり、磐座は磐境（いわさか）ともいい神域との境界を意味する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time &quot;rogi &quot;(籬) from himorogi (神籬) meaning &quot;a fence&quot;and iwakura, also called iwa-saka (saka means a border) both signify borders of Shin-iki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the same time &quot;rogi &quot;(籬) from himorogi (神籬) meaning &quot;a fence&quot;and iwakura, also called iwa-saka (saka means a border) both signify borders of Shin-iki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the same time &apos;rogi &apos;(籬) from himorogi (神籬) meaning &apos;a fence&apos; and iwakura, also called iwa-saka (saka means a border) both signify borders of Shiniki.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。ハイフンを削除し、Shinikiとして統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>そして、その「鎮守の森」や神籬や磐座としての森林や山・海・川や岩・木などは、神域である常世（「とこよ」と読み、神の国や理想郷のこと）と現世（うつしよと読み現実世界のこと）の端境を示し、結界としての役割も果たしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Chinju-no-Mori&quot; (Sacred Shrine Forest), other forests, mountaines, seas, rivers, rocks and trees as himorogi or iwakura represent the boundary zone and they also function as Kekkai (barrier) between Tokoyo that is to say Shin-iki (the kingdom of gods or the ideal world) and Utsusiyo (the actual world).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処原文「端境」は「端境期」など時間の流れに使用する言葉なので誤用かと思います。「境界域」という意味にとらえ、boundary zone　としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Chinju-no-Mori&quot; (Sacred Shrine Forest), other forests, mountaines, seas, rivers, rocks and trees as himorogi or iwakura represent the boundary zone and they also function as Kekkai (barrier) between Tokoyo that is to say Shin-iki (the kingdom of gods or the ideal world) and Utsusiyo (the actual world).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, &apos;Chinju-no-Mori&apos; (Sacred Shrine Forest), other forests, mountains, seas, rivers, rocks and trees as himorogi or iwakura represent the boundary zone and they also function as Kekkai (barrier) between Tokoyo that is to say Shiniki (the kingdom of gods or the ideal world) and Utsushiyo (the actual world).</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。スペルを修正しました。ハイフンを削除し、Shinikiとして統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>禁足地である場所も多くある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Quite a few places are Kinsokuchi (tabooed land).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Quite a few places are Kinsokuchi (tabooed land).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Quite a few places are Kinsokuchi (tabooed land).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>沖ノ島などは社（やしろ）や森だけでなく島全体が神域となっていて禁足地になっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for Okinoshima Island, not only the shrine and the forest but also the whole island is Shin-iki, furthermore Kinsokuchi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for Okinoshima Island, this refers to not only the shrine and the forest but also the whole island is Shin-iki, furthermore Kinsokuchi.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for Okino-shima Island, not only the shrine and the forest but also the whole island is Shiniki, furthermore Kinsokuchi.</e>
<cmt>一部翻訳を修正しました。ハイフンを削除し、Shinikiとして統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>また古来より郊外の集落につながる道の辻などに配置された道祖神、庚申塔、祠、地蔵などの石仏は、神域との結界の役割をしていたともいわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also said that since ancient time, Doso-shin (traveler&apos;s guardian deity), Koshin-to Tower (stone tower from Taoism), Hokora (small shrine) or stone Buddhist images such as Jizo (guardian deity of children) placed at the crossroads leading to villages in suburbs functioned as barriers to Shin-iki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also said that since ancient times, Doso-shin (traveler&apos;s guardian deity), Koshin-to Tower (stone tower from Taoism), Hokora (small shrine) or stone Buddhist images such as Jizo (guardian deity of children) placed at the crossroads leading to villages in suburbs functioned as barriers to Shin-iki.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also said that since ancient times, Doso-shin (traveler&apos;s guardian deity), Koshin-to Tower (stone tower from Taoism), Hokora (small shrine) or stone Buddhist images such as Jizo (guardian deity of children) placed at the crossroads leading to villages in suburbs functioned as barriers to Shiniki.</e>
<cmt>ハイフンを削除し、Shinikiとして統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>神社神道においても、神域を示す結界が用いられ、たとえば境界線を示すために、境内や社では意図的に段差を設けたり、扉や柵、鳥居や注連縄などを用いる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also in Jinja Shinto (Shrine Shinto, all the rites and other activities performed by a local community or a kin community mainly in a building called Jinja or Shrine) the barriers are used to define Shin-iki, for example, designed steps, doors, bars, Torii (Shrine gates) or Shime-nawa (sacred rice-straw ropes) are provided to signify the border.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also in Jinja Shinto (Shrine Shinto, all the rites and other activities performed by a local community or a kin community are performed mainly in a building called Jinja or Shrine) the barriers are used to define Shin-iki, for example, designed steps, doors, bars, Torii (Shrine gates) or Shime-nawa (sacred rice-straw ropes) are provided to signify the border.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also in Jinja Shinto (Shrine Shinto, all the rites and other activities performed by a local community or a kin community are performed mainly in a building called Jinja or Shrine) the barriers are used to define Shiniki, for example, designed steps, doors, bars, Torii (Shrine gates) or Shimenawa (sacred rice-straw ropes) are provided to signify the border.</e>
<cmt>ハイフンを削除し、Shinikiとして統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>例として一般的にはあまり知られていないが、参道は、本来、神が降り社に住まうための神の道である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although it is little known to the general public, basically Sando (the approach to Shinto shrine) is an approach for gods who descend and live in shrines.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although it is little known to the general public, basically Sando (the approach to Shinto shrine) is an approach for gods who descend and live in shrines.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it is little known to the general public, basically Sando (the approach to Shinto shrine) is an approach for gods who descend and live in shrines.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>その中央は神域とされ禁足となっているので、参拝者は端を歩かなければならないことが挙げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the center of Sando is Shin-iki and tabooed, visitors must walk along the side of Sando.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the center of Sando is Shin-iki and tabooed, visitors must walk along the side of Sando.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the center of Sando is Shiniki and tabooed, visitors must walk along the side of Sando.</e>
<cmt>ハイフンを削除し、Shinikiとして統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>結界は古神道や神道において、一定範囲の空間に設定されたタブー（禁足）を視覚化したものとも言える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Koshinto and Shinto, Kekkai can be considered visualization of taboo in a certain space.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Koshinto and Shinto, Kekkai can be considered to be a representation of taboo in a certain space.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Koshinto and Shinto, Kekkai can be considered to be a representation of taboo in a certain space.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>それは神域という聖なる領域（常世）と俗なる領域（現世）という二つの世「界」を「結」びつける役割をも持つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kekkai (結界) also functions to connect (結) two worlds (界) that are a sacred area (Tokoyo) and a profane area (Ustushiyo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kekkai (結界) also functions to connect (結) two worlds (界) that are a sacred area (Tokoyo) and a profane area (Ustushiyo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kekkai (結界) also functions to connect (結) two worlds (界) that are a sacred area (Tokoyo) and a profane area (Ustushiyo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>神道においての神域の重要性</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The importance of Shin-iki in Shinto</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The importance of Shin-iki in Shinto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The importance of Shiniki in Shinto</e>
<cmt>ハイフンを削除し、Shinikiとして統一しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="14">
<j>神道において、神域とはどのような性質をもっているのか。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">What kind of characteristic Shin-iki has in Shito ?</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">What kind of characteristic does Shin-iki have in Shito ?</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">What kind of characteristic does Shiniki have in Shinto ?</e>
<cmt>Shinto に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>それは神をもてなしたり、神を祀るために絶対に必要な領域である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is the most essential area to enshrine and serve deities.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is the most essential area to enshrine and serve deities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is the most essential area to enshrine and serve deities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>神苑を作ったり、神器を祀ったりするなど、そこに神を祀る土地として必要である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shin-iki is necessary as the land where Shin-en (shrine garden) is made or jingi (the sacred treasures) are enshrined.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shin-iki is necessary as the land where Shin-en (shrine garden) is made or jingi (the sacred treasures) are enshrined.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shiniki is necessary as the land where Shinen (shrine garden) is made or jingi (the sacred treasures) are enshrined.</e>
<cmt>ハイフンを削除し、Shinikiとして統一しました。Shinen としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>また、手水舎を用意したりするのにも、神域が必要なのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shin-iki is also required when Chozusha (purification trough) is provided.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shin-iki is also required when Chozusha (purification trough) is provided.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shiniki is also required when Chozusha (purification trough) is provided.</e>
<cmt>ハイフンを削除し、Shinikiとして統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>神苑を作るのは、社に祀られている神を樹木、草苔、花実でもてなすからである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Making Shin-en is to please the enshrined deities with trees, mosses, flowers and fruits.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Making Shin-en is to please the enshrined deities with trees, mosses, flowers and fruits.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Making Shin-en is to please the enshrined deities with trees, mosses, flowers and fruits.</e>
<cmt>Shinen としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>神域の現状</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Present status of Shin-iki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Present status of Shin-iki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Present status of Shiniki</e>
<cmt>ハイフンを削除し、Shinikiとして統一しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="19">
<j>現在、神社の神域は、単なるイベント会場と意識されることがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today Shin-iki can be regarded just as an event site.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today Shin-iki can be regarded just as an event site.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today Shiniki can be regarded just as an event site.</e>
<cmt>ハイフンを削除し、Shinikiとして統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>日常でも、的屋や屋台が出る場所として意識されているのが神域である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In our daily life, Shin-iki is considered as a place for stalls.</e>
<cmt>一般的に「的屋」は人、「屋台」はモノですが、同一の概念なのでstall一語にしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In our daily life, Shin-iki is considered as a place for stalls.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In our daily life, Shiniki is considered as a place for stalls.</e>
<cmt>ハイフンを削除し、Shinikiとして統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>また、あまり気にされなかったり、神をもてなすというよりも、人間の活動場所として使用されていることがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Without much concerning, it is sometimes used for human activities rather than serving the deities.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is sometimes used for human activities rather than serving the deities.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is sometimes used for human activities rather than serving the deities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="22">
<j>実際に、京都府の平安神宮などで東京スカパラダイスオーケストラなどのライブが行われたりするなど、開けた場所ということで、催し物が行われることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In fact, entertainments, such as Tokyo Ska Paradise Orchestra live in Heian-jingu Shrine, are occasionally held due to its open space.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In fact, entertainment, such as Tokyo Ska Paradise Orchestra concert in Heian-jingu Shrine, are occasionally held due to its open space.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact, entertainment, such as Tokyo Ska Paradise Orchestra concert in Heian-jingu Shrine, are occasionally held due to its open space.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="23">
<j>また、神域というのはもともと神事などの催し物をするための場所として、開けた場所として作ったために、そのようなことに利用される傾向にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shin-iki tends to be used for such entertainments since it was originally established as open space for Shinto rituals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shin-iki tends to be used for such enteratinment since it was originally established as open space for Shinto rituals.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shiniki tends to be used for such entertainment since it was originally established as open space for Shinto rituals.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>現代的な語彙としての使用</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Contemporary usage of the term.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Contemporary usage of the term.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Contemporary usage of the term</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="24">
<j>現代では、主に物事において重要な場所を示す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today Shin-iki mainly signifies an important place.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today Shin-iki mainly signifies an important place.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today Shin-iki mainly signifies an important place.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>たとえば「登山家にとってエベレストは神域」、「映画関係者にとってハリウッドは神域」といった使い方がされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, it is used such as &quot;Mt.Everest is Shin-iki for mountain climbers&quot;, &quot;Hollywood is Shin-iki for cineasts&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, it is used such as &quot;Mt.Everest is Shin-iki for mountain climbers&quot;, &quot;Hollywood is Shin-iki for cineasts&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, it is used such as &apos;Mt.Everest is Shiniki for mountain climbers,&apos; &apos;Hollywood is Shiniki for cineast.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>これらは、その主体となっているものにおいて、始まりの場所であったり、最終目標の場所を指す場合に使われることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These often indicate a starting point or a finishing goal to the person in question.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These often indicate a starting point or a finishing goal to the person in question.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These often indicate a starting point or a finishing goal to the person in question.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="27">
<j>また、場所だけでなく重要な部署にも使用したりする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is used not only as a place but also as an important part.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is used not only as a place but also as an important part.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is used not only as a place but also as an important part.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>たとえば、「原動機は原動力学の神域」、「リーマン予想は数学の神域」という対象物を重んじるときに使用する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is applied to emphasize objects, for example, &quot;a mortar is Shin-iki of driving power mechanics&quot;, &quot;Riemann&apos;s hypothesis is Shin-iki of mathematics&quot;.</e>
<cmt>「原動力学」の意味が不明です。英語をそのまま訳しdriving power mechanics としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is applied to emphasize objects, for example, &quot;a mortar is Shin-iki of driving power mechanics&quot;, &quot;Riemann&apos;s hypothesis is Shin-iki of mathematics&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is applied to emphasize objects, for example, &apos;a mortar is Shiniki of driving power mechanics,&apos; &apos;Riemann&apos;s hypothesis is Shiniki of mathematics.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>用途的には『メッカ』と類似する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its usage is similar to that of &quot;Mecca&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its usage is similar to that of &quot;Mecca&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its usage is similar to that of &quot;Mecca.&quot;</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 蒼海牧菜(id:78923), NISYAN(id:169936), ぽえこ(id:88711), Pica(id:9502), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>