<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>勅祭</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chokusai</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chokusai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chokusai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>勅祭（ちょくさい）とは、天皇の使者（勅使）が派遣されて執行される神社の祭祀のことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Chokusai&quot; is a religious service of a shrine where imperial messengers are sent by the Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Chokusai&quot; is a religious service at a shrine whereby imperial messengers are sent by the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>word revision</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chokusai is a religious service at a shrine where imperial messengers are sent by the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>意味を正確にするため変更。 “whereby”=&gt;“where”</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>特に近現代の用語で、勅使派遣が定例になっている神社を勅祭社という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Particularly in the modern ages, the term &quot;chokusai-sha shrine&quot; is used for shrines where imperial messengers are sent regularly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Particularly in the modern ages, the term &quot;chokusai-sha shrine&quot; is used for shrines where imperial messengers are regularly sent.</e>
<cmt>word order revision</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Particularly in the modern ages, the term &quot;chokusai-sha shrine&quot; is used for shrines where imperial messengers are regularly sent.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>多くは各神社の例祭となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In many cases, it is the regular festival of the shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In many cases, it is the regular festival of the shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In many cases, it is the regular festival of the shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>また勅使は原則として宮中祭祀に当たる掌典をあてる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The imperial messengers assigned are in principle, the Shoten, who attend to religious services in the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The imperial messengers assigned are in principle, the Shoten, who attend to religious services in the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The imperial messengers assigned are in principle, the Shoten, who attend to religious services in the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>勅祭の内、旧儀保存の目的で古式を参照した特殊な内容を持つものを特に「三勅祭」という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chokusai with a special content referring to old styles for preserving traditional ceremonies, are called &apos;san chokusai.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chokusai with special content that refer to old styles that preserve traditional ceremonies, are called &apos;san chokusai.&apos;</e>
<cmt>word revision</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chokusai with special content that refer to old styles that preserve traditional ceremonies, are called &apos;san chokusai.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>三勅祭とは賀茂神社の賀茂祭（葵祭）、石清水八幡宮の石清水祭、春日大社の春日祭の3つである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">San chokusai are the Kamo-matsuri Festival (Aoi-matsuri Festival) of Kamo-jinja Shrine, Iwashimizu-sai Festival of Iwashimizu Hachiman-gu Shrine, and Kasuga-matsuri Festival of Kasuga-taisha Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Examples of san chokusai are; the Kamo-matsuri Festival (Aoi-matsuri Festival) of the Kamo-jinja Shrine, Iwashimizu-sai Festival of the Iwashimizu Hachiman-gu Shrine, and Kasuga-matsuri Festival of the Kasuga-taisha Shrine.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Examples of san chokusai are; the Kamo-matsuri Festival (Aoi-matsuri Festival) of the Kamo-jinja Shrine, Iwashimizu-sai Festival of the Iwashimizu Hachiman-gu Shrine, and Kasuga-matsuri Festival of the Kasuga-taisha Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>これらは江戸時代以前の慣例による束帯を着た勅使が派遣され、随行の官人である弁官その他の「代」として、やはり古い故実に則った姿をした人々が奉仕する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial messengers wearing old ceremonial court dresses following a custom from pre-Edo period are sent, and people also dressed according to ancient practices attend as &apos;representations&apos; of accompanying government officials of the Oversight Department and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial messengers, wearing old ceremonial court dress, following customs from the pre-Edo period are sent, and people who also dress according to ancient fashion attend as &apos;representations&apos; of accompanying government officials of the Overseeing Department, and others.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity and correctness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial messengers, wearing old ceremonial court dress, following customs from the pre-Edo period are sent, and people who also dress according to ancient fashion attend as &apos;representations&apos; of accompanying government officials of the Overseeing Department, and others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>これらの人々と神社の神職が儀式次第にしたがい執行するものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These people along with the priests of the shrine perform the service according to the program of the ceremony.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These people, along with the priests of the shrine, perform the service according to the ceremony program.</e>
<cmt>punctuation and words reordered</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These people, along with the priests of the shrine, perform the service according to the ceremony program.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>ただし石清水祭は神仏習合色の強い石清水放生会を継承しつつ、神道色を強めているなど、さまざまな変更は行われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, various changes are taking place, such as in the Iwashimizu-sai Festival, where Iwashimizu hojoe with strong characteristics of syncretism of Shinto and Buddhism is being inherited, and is increasingly leaning towards Shinto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, various changes are taking place, such as in the Iwashimizu-sai Festival, where Iwashimizu hojoe with strong characteristics of syncretism of Shinto and Buddhism is being inherited, and is increasingly leaning towards Shinto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, various changes are taking place, such as in the Iwashimizu-sai Festival, where Iwashimizu hojoe with strong characteristics of syncretism of Shinto and Buddhism is being inherited, and is increasingly leaning towards Shinto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>また装束も新調が重ねられる過程で次第に故実に合わないものになりつつある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The costumes are also gradually separating from ancient practices as they are repeatedly renewed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The costumes are also gradually differing from ancient fashion as they are repeatedly renewed.</e>
<cmt>terminology changed for accuracy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The costumes are also gradually differing from ancient fashion as they are repeatedly renewed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>このほか、首都のある武蔵国一ノ宮の氷川神社、国家の保護の篤い橿原神宮・明治神宮・平安神宮・靖国神社などの例祭も勅使が派遣される勅祭である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, regular festivals at Hikawa-jinja Shrine in Ichinomiya, Musashi Province, where the capital is, and Kashihara-jingu Shrine, Meiji-jingu Shrine, Heian-jingu Shrine, Yasukuni-jinja Shrine, etc. which are heavily protected by the country, are also chokusai to which imperial messengers are sent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, regular festivals at the Hikawa-jinja Shrine in Ichinomiya, Musashi Province, where the capital is, and Kashihara-jingu Shrine, Meiji-jingu Shrine, Heian-jingu Shrine, Yasukuni-jinja Shrine, etc. which are heavily protected by the country, are also chokusai to which imperial messengers are sent.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the&quot; inserted before the first mentioned shrine, not necessary for the following ones because of the context</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, regular festivals at the Hikawa-jinja Shrine in Ichinomiya, Musashi Province, where the capital is, and Kashihara-jingu Shrine, Meiji-jingu Shrine, Heian-jingu Shrine, Yasukuni-jinja Shrine, etc. which are heavily protected by the country, are also chokusai to which imperial messengers are sent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>これらでは勅使は衣冠（神社本庁の定める「正服」に同じ）を使用し、所作などはほぼ定型化している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At these chokusai, imperial messengers use kimono and ancient head-dress (similar to the &apos;formal dress&apos; defined by Jinja Honcho (The Association of Shinto Shrines)), and their conducts are mostly fixed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At these chokusai, imperial messengers use kimono and ancient head-dress (similar to the &apos;formal dress&apos; defined by Jinja Honcho (The Association of Shinto Shrines)), and their conduct is mostly fixed.</e>
<cmt>&quot;s&quot; deleted from &quot;conduct&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At these chokusai, imperial messengers use kimono and ancient head-dress (similar to the &apos;formal dress&apos; defined by Jinja Honcho (The Association of Shinto Shrines)), and their conduct is mostly fixed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Nnh(id:474), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>