<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>霊光殿天満宮</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reikoden-tenmangu Shrine</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reikoden-tenmangu Shrine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reikoden-tenmangu Shrine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>霊光殿天満宮（れいこうでんてんまんぐう）は、京都市上京区にある神社である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reikoden-tenmangu Shrine is a shrine in Kamigyo Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reikoden-tenmangu Shrine is a shrine in Kamigyo Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reikoden-tenmangu Shrine is a shrine in Kamigyo Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>天神信仰（菅原道真）と徳川家康を祀る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It enshrines the Tenjin-shinko Faith (SUGAWARA no Michizane) and Ieyasu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It enshrines the Tenjin-shinko Faith (SUGAWARA no Michizane) and Ieyasu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It enshrines the Tenjin-shinko Faith (Sugawara no Michizane) and Ieyasu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>SUGAWARA→Sugawara</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>寛仁2年（1018年）、菅原道真の6代後の菅原義郷が勅命により河内国若江郡に神殿を建てたのが始まりである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Initially, Yoshisato SUGAWARA, who was six generations after SUGAWARA no Michizane, built a sacred place in Wakae District, Kawachi Province, under imperial command in 1018.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Initially, Yoshisato SUGAWARA, who was six generations after SUGAWARA no Michizane, built a sacred place in the Wakae District, Kawachi Province, under imperial command in 1018.</e>
<cmt>inserted &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Initially, Yoshisato SUGAWARA, who was six generations after Sugawara no Michizane, built a sacred place in the Wakae District, Kawachi Province, under imperial command in 1018.</e>
<cmt>SUGAWARA→Sugawara</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>社名は、道真の左遷の際、天から一条の光とともに天一神・帝釈天が降臨したとの伝説によるものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name of the shrine comes from a legend that the Tenichi jin (god worshipped in Onmyodo ((way of Yin and Yang)), Taishaku Ten, descended from the sky with a streak of light, when Michizane was degraded.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name of the shrine comes from a legend that says the Tenichi jin (god worshipped in Onmyodo ((way of Yin and Yang)), Taishaku Ten, descended from the sky with a streak of light, when Michizane was degraded.</e>
<cmt>&quot;say&quot; inserted</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name of the shrine comes from a legend that says the Tenichi jin (god worshipped in Onmyodo ((way of Yin and Yang)), Taishaku Ten, descended from the sky with a streak of light, when Michizane was degraded.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>元寇の時には後宇多天皇が当社にて夷賊退治の祈祷を行わせたところ元の船がことごとく沈んでしまったので『天下無敵必勝利運』の額を天皇より賜った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Mongol Invasion, when Emperor Gouda ordered the shrine to pray to fight off the izoku (barbarians), all of the ships of Yuan sank, and the Emperor presented a frame saying &quot;Tenka muteki hisshori un.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Mongol Invasion, when Emperor Gouda ordered the shrine to pray to fight off the izoku (barbarians), all of the ships of Yuan sank, and the Emperor presented a plaque to the shrine that says &quot;Tenka muteki hisshori un.&quot;</e>
<cmt>words revised</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Mongol Invasion, when Emperor Gouda ordered the shrine to pray to fight off the izoku (barbarians), all of the ships of Yuan sank, and the Emperor presented a plaque to the shrine that says &quot;Tenka muteki hisshori un.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>応仁の乱の際に社領を失い、東寺境内に遷された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It lost its territory in the Onin Rebellion, and was transferred to the premises of To-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shrine lost its land in the Onin Rebellion, and was transferred to the premises of To-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>words added for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The shrine lost its land in the Onin Rebellion, and was transferred to the premises of To-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>江戸時代に社家の若江家が再興され、塔之段に社殿を再建、宝暦11年（1761年）に現在地に鎮座した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Edo period, the Wakae family, the family of Shinto priests serving the shrine on a hereditary basis was revived, the main building of the shrine was rebuilt in Tonodan, and was enshrined in its current location in 1761.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Edo period, the Wakae family, the family of Shinto priests serving the shrine on a hereditary basis was revived, the main building of the shrine was rebuilt in Tonodan, and was enshrined in its current location in 1761.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Edo period, the Wakae family, the family of Shinto priests serving the shrine on a hereditary basis was revived, the main building of the shrine was rebuilt in Tonodan, and was enshrined in its current location in 1761.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>徳川家康は当社を深く崇敬し、元亀元年（1570年）に天下太平の祈願をし、また、若江家の再興に尽力した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ieyasu TOKUGAWA deeply revered the shrine, prayed for halcyon times of peace in 1570, and made efforts to revive the Wakae family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ieyasu TOKUGAWA deeply revered the shrine, prayed for halcyon times of peace in 1570, and made efforts to revive the Wakae family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ieyasu TOKUGAWA deeply revered the shrine, prayed for halcyon times of peace in 1570, and made efforts to revive the Wakae family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>家康の死後の寛永13年（1636年）、徳川家光が仙洞御所にあった家康の像を当社に移し、祭神とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1636, after the death of Ieyasu, Iemitsu TOKUGAWA moved the statue of Ieyasu from Sento-gosho Imperial Palace to this shrine as the enshrined deity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1636, after the death of Ieyasu, Iemitsu TOKUGAWA moved the statue of Ieyasu from the Sento-gosho Imperial Palace to this shrine to be the enshrined deity.</e>
<cmt>wording revised</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1636, after the death of Ieyasu, Iemitsu TOKUGAWA moved the statue of Ieyasu from the Sento-gosho Imperial Palace to this shrine to be the enshrined deity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="11">
<j>現在の社殿は、明治5年に近衛家の旧鎮守社を移築したものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The current main building of the shrine was transferred and reconstructed in 1872 after dismantling the old chinju-sha shrine (Shinto shrine on Buddhist temple grounds dedicated to the tutelary deity of the area) of the house of Konoe.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The current main building of the shrine was transferred and reconstructed in 1872 after dismantling the old chinju-sha shrine (the Shinto shrine on Buddhist temple grounds dedicated to the tutelary deity of the area) of the house of Konoe.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the&quot; added</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The current main building of the shrine was transferred and reconstructed in 1872 after dismantling the old chinju-sha shrine (the Shinto shrine on Buddhist temple grounds dedicated to the tutelary deity of the area) of the Konoe family.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the house of Konoe&quot; -&gt; &quot;the Konoe family&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Nnh(id:474), ととりん(id:31982), Ignis(id:28979), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>