<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>例祭</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reisai (regular festival)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reisai (regular festival)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reisai (regular festival)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>例祭（れいさい）とは、神社で毎年行われる祭祀のうちの一つである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reisai is one of saishi, which is the religious service that is performed annually at shinto shrines.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reisai is a term used to to describe one kind of saishi, religious services that are performed annually at shinto shrines.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reisai is a term used to to describe one kind of saishi, religious services that are performed annually at shinto shrines.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>そのうち、最も重要とされるもののことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among saishi, reisai is regarded as the most important.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among saishi, reisai is regarded as the most important.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among saishi, reisai is regarded as the most important.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="3">
<j>例祭は年一回、多くは祭神や神社に特別の由緒のある日に行われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reisai is held once a year, and in many cases on the day specially associated with the enshrined deity or the shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reisai are held once a year, and in many cases on a day specially associated with the enshrined deity or the shrine.</e>
<cmt>VerbArticle</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reisai is held once a year, and in many cases on a day specially associated with the enshrined deity or the shrine.</e>
<cmt>are→is例祭は1つの神社に１つだけなので単数形でいいと思います。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>例えば人物神を祀る神社ではその人物の誕生日や命日としていることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, in the shrines sacred to man-gods, it is often performed on the birthday or the death day of the sacred person.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, in shrines dedicated to human gods, it is often performed on the birthday or the death day of the sacred person.</e>
<cmt>ArticleRevised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, in shrines dedicated to human gods, it is often performed on the birthday or the death day of the sacred person.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>特に由緒のある日のない場合は、春祭りや秋祭りをもって例祭としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If there is no such a commemorative day, a spring festival or an autumn festival is regarded as reisai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If there is no such commemorative day, a spring festival or an autumn festival is regarded as reisai.</e>
<cmt>Article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If there is no such commemorative day, a spring festival or an autumn festival is regarded as reisai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>例祭が行われる日は毎年一定で、みだりに変えることはできないものとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reisai is held on a given date every year and no one is allowed to change the date without permission.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reisai are held on a given date every year and no one is allowed to change the date without permission.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reisai is held on a given date every year and no one is allowed to change the date in vain.</e>
<cmt>are→iswithout permission→in vain</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>第二次大戦以降も、神社本庁被包括の神社については、例祭日を変更する場合は神社本庁の承認を受ける必要がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even after World War II, as for the shrines under the administration of Jinja-Honcho (The Association of Shinto Shrines), an amendment to the date of reisai requires approval from the Jinja-Honcho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even after World War II, shrines administered by Jinja-Honcho (The Association of Shinto Shrines) require approval from the Jinja-Honcho to change the date of reisai.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even after World War II, shrines administered by Jinja-Honcho (The Association of Shinto Shrines) need to require approval from the Jinja-Honcho to change the date of reisai.</e>
<cmt>need toを追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>「例祭」という名称が使われ出したのは近世のことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is only in recent times that the name &apos;reisai&apos; has come into use.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is only in recent times that the name &apos;reisai&apos; has come into use.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is only in recent times that the name &apos;reisai&apos; has come into use.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>それ以前には「大祭（おおまつり）」「御祭（おんまつり）」などと呼んだり、社名に祭をつけて「春日祭」「石清水祭」などと呼んだりしていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Until that time, people called it &apos;oomatsuri&apos;, &apos;onmatsuri&apos; or the host shrine&apos;s name with the suffix meaning a festival, such as Kasuga-Matsuri Festival or Iwashimizu-Sai Festival.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before then, it was known as &apos;oomatsuri&apos;, &apos;onmatsuri&apos; or the host shrine&apos;s name with the suffix meaning a festival, such as Kasuga-Matsuri Festival or Iwashimizu-Sai Festival, was used.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before then, it was known as &apos;oomatsuri&apos;, &apos;onmatsuri&apos; or the host shrine&apos;s name with the suffix meaning a festival, such as &apos;Kasuga-Matsuri&apos; Festival or &apos;Iwashimizu-Sai&apos; Festival, was used.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォートを追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>近世には、各地の名所図絵などに「○○神社例祭○月○日」と記載されているのが見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the recent times, such description as &apos;The xxxx shrine reisai, xxth day of xxxx&apos; can be found in some kind of a pictorial description of noted places in various regions.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Recently, the phrase &apos;The xxxx shrine reisai, xxth day of xxxx&apos; can be found on posters for noted places in various regions.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In recent times, the phrase &apos;The xxxx shrine reisai, xxth day of xxxx&apos; can be found on posters for noted places in various regions.</e>
<cmt>Recently→In recent times</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>これにより、その神社を代表する重要な祭を「例祭」と呼ぶことが定着していたことがわかる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This indicates that the custom of calling the most important festival representing the shrine as &apos;reisai&apos; has come to stay.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This indicates that the custom of using &apos;reisei&apos; to describe a shrine&apos;s most important festival is firmly established.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This indicates that the custom of using &apos;reisei&apos; to describe a shrine&apos;s most important festival is firmly established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="13">
<j>明治の神社制度においては、例祭は祈年祭・新嘗祭などとともに「大祭（たいさい）」に定められていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the shinto shrine system in the Meiji period, reisai, as well as Kinensai (prayer service for a good crop), Niiname-sai festival (ceremonial offering by the Emperor of newly-harvested rice to the deities) and so on, was designated as &apos;taisai&apos;(grand festival).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the shinto shrine system of the Meiji period, reisai, together with festivals such as the Kinensai festival (to pray for a good crop) and the Niiname-sai festival (ceremonial offering by the Emperor of newly-harvested rice to the deities), were designated &apos;taisai&apos; (grand festivals).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the shinto shrine system of the Meiji period, reisai, together with festivals such as the Kinensai festival (to pray for a good crop) and the Niiname-sai festival (ceremonial offering by the Emperor of newly-harvested rice to the deities), were designated &apos;taisai&apos; (grand festivals).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>そのため、官国幣社・府県社・郷社および一部の村社（神饌幣帛料供進指定神社）には勅使あるいは幣帛供進使が参向して国・皇室から幣帛が供進された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, the reisai at Kankoku Heisha (general term for Kanpeisha and Kokuheisha that were high rank shrines), Fukensha (prefectural shrines), Gosha (village shrine) and certain village shrines (shrines designated as beneficiary of offerings of food, alcohol and heihaku), was attended by imperial envoy or hakukyoshinshi (an imperial messenger to a Shinto shrine) who carried heihaku (paper or silk cuttings or red and white cloth presented to deities) presented by the state or the Imperial house.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処神『饌幣帛料供進指定神社』の定訳不明です</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, the reisai at national and Imperial shrines, prefectural shrines, village shrines and certain town shrines (those appointed to accept offerings of food, alcohol and gifts of monery wrapped in paper called heihakuryo), were attended by imperial envoys or heihaku kyoshinshi (special imperial messengers) who carried came to offer heihaku (paper or silk cuttings or red and white cloth presented to deities) presented by the state or the Imperial house.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, the reisai at national and Imperial shrines, prefectural shrines, village shrines and certain town shrines (those appointed to accept offerings of food, alcohol and gifts of monery wrapped in paper called heihakuryo), were attended by imperial envoys or heihaku kyoshinshi (special imperial messengers) who carried came to offer heihaku (paper or silk cuttings or red and white cloth presented to deities) presented by the state or the Imperial house.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="15">
<j>第二次大戦以降は、国からの幣帛供進制度は廃止された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The system of haihaku presentation by the state was abolished after World War II.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処『幣帛供進制度』の定訳不明です</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The system of heihaku presentation by the state was abolished after World War II.</e>
<cmt>Spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The system of heihaku presentation by the state was abolished after World War II.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>しかし、勅祭社については例祭に際し勅使が参向する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, imperial envoy is still attending to the reisai at shrines called Chokusai-sha (shrine attended by imperial envoy).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, imperial envoys (chokushi) still attend reisai at shrines designated as Chokusai-sha.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, imperial envoys (chokushi) still attend reisai at shrines designated as Chokusai-sha (shrine attended by imperial envoy).</e>
<cmt>(shrine attended by imperial envoy)を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>それ以外の神社では、公的な幣帛供進制度に代わって神社本庁から「本庁幣」として献幣が行われている（ただし神社本庁被包括の神社に限る）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For other shrines, the offering is still ongoing as &quot;honcho-hei&apos;, which took the place of the official heihaku presentation system. (However, this is true of only the shrines under the administration of the Jinja-Honcho.)</e>
<cmt>『幣帛供進制度』の定訳不明です</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For other shrines, the official heihaku presentation system was replaced with &quot;honcho-hei&apos; offerings from Jinja-Honcho. (However, this is true only of shrines administered by Jinja-Honcho.)</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For other shrines, the official heihaku presentation system was replaced with &quot;honcho-hei&apos; offerings from Jinja-Honcho. (However, this is true only of shrines administered by Jinja-Honcho.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="18">
<j>名称</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Name</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Name</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Name</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>例祭は祭祀の分類の中で「大祭（たいさい）」に分類される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under the classification of religious services, reisai is classified as &apos;taisai&apos;.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the classification of religious services, reisai are classified as &apos;taisai&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the classification of religious services, reisai are classified as &apos;taisai&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>このことから、例祭のことを例大祭（れいたいさい）と呼ぶことがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For that reason, reisai is sometimes called rei-taisai (regular grand festival).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For that reason, reisai are sometimes called rei-taisai (regular grand festival).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For that reason, reisai are sometimes called rei-taisai (regular grand festival).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>ただし、これは俗称であり、正式なものではない（例祭の名称として「○○神社例大祭」としていることはある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, this is the familiar name and not the formal one (although some reisai are referred to such as &apos;xxxx Shrine Rei-taisai Festival&apos; by its popular name).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, this is a colloquial name, not the formal one (although some reisai are popularly referred to as &apos;xxxx Shrine Rei-taisai Festival&apos;).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, this is a colloquial name, not the formal one (although some reisai are popularly referred to as &apos;xxxx Shrine Rei-taisai Festival&apos;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="22">
<j>正式には、大祭式例祭（たいさいしきれいさい）とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its formal name is Taisaishikireisai (regular festival in the form of grand festival).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The formal name is Taisaishikireisai (regular festival in the form of grand festival).</e>
<cmt>Pronoun</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The formal name is Taisaishikireisai (regular festival in the form of grand festival).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="23">
<j>本来の「例祭」以外の祭祀についても、祭の名称に「例祭」を含んでいる場合（例えば「春季例祭」）があるが、一つの神社について例祭は一つだけである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other religious services than the formal &apos;reisai&apos; sometimes include the word &apos;reisai&apos; in its name (e.g. &apos;Spring Reisai Festival&apos;), but there is only one reisai in one shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Religious services other than the formal &apos;reisai&apos; sometimes include the word &apos;reisai&apos; in their name (e.g. &apos;Spring Reisai Festival&apos;), but there is only one reisai in one shrine.</e>
<cmt>Word orderPronoun</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Religious services other than the formal &apos;reisai&apos; sometimes include the word &apos;reisai&apos; in their name (e.g. &apos;Spring Reisai Festival&apos;), but there is only one reisai in one shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="24">
<j>主な神社の例祭日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Date of reisai of main shrine</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Date of head shrine&apos;s reisai</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Date of head shrine&apos;s reisai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="25">
<j>伊勢神宮においては「例祭」という概念はない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is no concept of &apos;reisai&apos; in Ise-jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is no concept of &apos;reisai&apos; at Ise-jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>Preposition</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is no concept of &apos;reisai&apos; at Ise-jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>最も重要な祭祀である神嘗祭（10月17日）が一般の神社の例祭に相当する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Kannamesai (held on Oct.17), which is the most important religious service in the shrine, is equivalent to reisai performed by other shrines in general.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Kannamesai (held on Oct.17), which is the shrine&apos;s most important religious service, is equivalent to the reisai performed at ordinary shrines.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Kannamesai (held on Oct.17), which is the shrine&apos;s most important religious service, is equivalent to the reisai performed at ordinary shrines.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 ととりん(id:31982), Nnh(id:474), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>