<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>言霊</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kotodama</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kotodama</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kotodama</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>言霊（ことだま）とは、一般的には日本において言葉に宿ると信じられた霊的な力のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kotodama was usually the spiritual power believed to be contained within words in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kotodama was usually the spiritual power believed to be contained within words in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kotodama was usually the spiritual power believed to be contained within words in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>言魂とも書く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was also called as Kotodama (言魂).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was also called Kotodama (言魂).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was also called Kotodama (言魂).</e>
<cmt>スペル削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>清音の言霊（ことたま）は、森羅万象がそれによって成り立っているとされる五十音のコトタマの法則のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The seion (an unvoiced consonant) of kotodama was the law of fifty Japanese syllables of kototama forming Shinrabansho (everything in nature).</e>
<cmt>清音→seion (an unvoiced consonant)[http://ejje.weblio.jp/content/清音]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The seion (a silent consonant) of kotodama was the law of fifty Japanese syllables of kototama forming Shinrabansho (everything in nature).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The seion (a silent consonant) of kotodama was the law of fifty Japanese syllables of kototama forming Shinrabansho (everything in nature).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>その法則についての学問を言霊学という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The academic field concerning that law is called as Kotodamagaku (the study of Kotodama).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The academic field concerning that law is called Kotodamagaku (the study of Kotodama).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The academic field devoted to studying kototama is called Kototamagaku.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>声に出した言葉が現実の事象に対して何らかの影響を与えると信じられ、良い言葉を発すると良い事が起こり、概要な言葉を発すると凶事が起こるとされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was believed that the spoken words had some kind of influence on actual phenomena, and good things happened when good words were spoken while ominous things happened with unlucky words.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was believed that spoken words had some kind of influence on actual phenomena, and good things happened when good words were spoken while ominous things happened with unlucky words.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was believed that spoken words had some kind of influence on actual phenomena; that is, good things happened when good words were spoken, while ominous things happened when unlucky words were spoken.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>そのため、祝詞を奏上する時には絶対に誤読がないように注意された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, it was made sure that there would be no mistake in reading during the Shokushi (reciting a Shinto prayer) to the emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of this, all steps were taken to be sure that there would be no mistake in reading during the Shokushi (reciting a Shinto prayer) to the emperor.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of this, all steps were taken to be sure that there would be no mistake in reading during the Shokushi (reciting a Shinto prayer) to the emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>今日にも残る結婚式などでの忌み言葉も言霊の思想に基づくものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The taboo words at weddings that still remain today originated from the kotodama ideology.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Words that are taboo at weddings, that still remain today, originated from the kotodama ideology.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even today there are taboo words that should never be used at weddings or other such occasions, and these words have their origins in the concept of kotodama.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>日本は言魂の力によって幸せがもたらされる国「言霊の幸ふ国」とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan was considered to be the nation filled with well-being from the power of kotodama, &apos;happy kotodama nation.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan was considered to be a nation filled with well-being from the power of kotodama, &apos;happy kotodama nation.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan was thought to have become a fortunate land through the power of kotodama, a so-called &quot;land of happy kotodama.&quot;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>『万葉集』（『萬葉集』）に「志貴島の日本（やまと）の国は事靈の佑（さき）はふ國ぞ福（さき）くありとぞ」（「志貴嶋 倭國者 事霊之 所佐國叙 真福在与具」 - 柿本人麻呂 3254）「…そらみつ大和の國は 皇神（すめかみ）の嚴くしき國 言靈の幸ふ國と 語り繼ぎ言ひ繼がひけり…」（「…虚見通 倭國者 皇神能 伊都久志吉國 言霊能 佐吉播布國等 加多利継 伊比都賀比計理…」 - 山上憶良 894）との歌がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were poems in &quot;Manyoshu&quot; (written as 万葉集 or 萬葉集), &apos;Souls reside within words of Yamato nation (Japan) of Shikishima (another name for Japan), and it will be filled with luck due to the power they contain&apos; (&apos;志貴嶋 倭國者 事霊之 所佐國叙 真福在与具&apos;) by Kakinomoto no Hitomaro 3254) and &apos;... and as it has been told since the time of gods, the solemn souls reside in words of this country even from eyes of gods, and the nation will be filled with well-being from that power so the current people should use words while being wary of this fact... (... 虚見通 倭國者 皇神能 伊都久志吉國 言霊能 佐吉播布國等 加多利継 伊比都賀比計理...) &apos; by YAMANOUE no Okura 894.</e>
<cmt>「志貴島の日本（やまと）の国は事靈の佑（さき）はふ國ぞ福（さき）くありとぞ」（「志貴嶋 倭國者 事霊之 所佐國叙 真福在与具」→&apos;Souls reside within words of Yamato nation (Japan) of Shikishima (another name for Japan) and it will be filled with luck due to the power it contains&apos; (&apos;志貴嶋 倭國者 事霊之 所佐國叙 真福在与具&apos;)、「…そらみつ大和の國は 皇神（すめかみ）の嚴くしき國 言靈の幸ふ國と 語り繼ぎ言ひ繼がひけり…」（「…虚見通 倭國者 皇神能 伊都久志吉國 言霊能 佐吉播布國等 加多利継 伊比都賀比計理…」 → &apos;... and as it has been told since the time of gods, the solemn souls reside in the words of this country even from eyes of gods and the nation will be filled with happiness from that power so the current people should use words while being aware of this fact... (... 虚見通 倭國者 皇神能 伊都久志吉國 言霊能 佐吉播布國等 加多利継 伊比都賀比計理...)[http://namuamidabutsu.blog.so-net.ne.jp/2009-08-08]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were poems in &quot;Manyoshu&quot; (written as 万葉集 or 萬葉集), &apos;Souls reside within words of the Yamato nation (Japan) of Shikishima (another name for Japan), and it will be filled with good luck due to the power they contain&apos; (&apos;志貴嶋 倭國者 事霊之 所佐國叙 真福在与具&apos;) by Kakinomoto no Hitomaro 3254) and &apos;... and as told since the time of gods, the solemn souls reside in words of this country even in the eyes of the gods, and the nation will be filled with well-being from that power so the current population should use words while being wary of this fact... (... 虚見通 倭國者 皇神能 伊都久志吉國 言霊能 佐吉播布國等 加多利継 伊比都賀比計理...) &apos; by YAMANOUE no Okura 894.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were poems in &quot;Manyoshu&quot; (Collection of Ten Thousand Leaves) (written as 万葉集 or 萬葉集), &apos;Souls reside within words of the Yamato nation (Japan) of Shikishima (another name for Japan), and it will be filled with good luck due to the power they contain&apos; (&apos;志貴嶋 倭國者 事霊之 所佐國叙 真福在与具&apos;) by Kakinomoto no Hitomaro 3254 and &apos;... and as told since the time of gods, the solemn souls reside in words of this country even in the eyes of the gods, and the nation will be filled with well-being from that power so the current population should use words while being wary of this fact...&apos; (&apos;... 虚見通 倭國者 皇神能 伊都久志吉國 言霊能 佐吉播布國等 加多利継 伊比都賀比計理..&apos;.) by YAMANOUE no Okura 894.</e>
<cmt>(Collection of Ten Thousand Leaves)補足&apos;補足)削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>これは、古代において「言」と「事」が同一の概念だったことによるものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was from a general notion that &quot;koto&quot; (言) and &quot;koto&quot; (事) were same from the ancient times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was from a general notion that &quot;koto&quot; (言) and &quot;koto&quot; (事) were same from ancient times.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was from a general notion that &apos;koto&apos; (言) and &apos;koto&apos; (事) were the same from ancient times.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>漢字が導入された当初も言と事は区別せずに用いられており、例えば事代主が『古事記』では「言代主神」と書かれている箇所がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The koto (言) and koto (事) were used without distinguishing each other at the beginning of incorporation of kanji, and Kotoshironushi (事代主)(the god that appears in Japanese mythology) was also written as Kotoshironushi (言代主神) in &quot;Kojiki&quot; (the Record of Ancient Matters).</e>
<cmt>『古事記』→&quot;Kojiki&quot; (the Record of Ancient Matters)[http://www.amazon.co.jp/古事記-英文版―-KOJIKI-Records-Ancient/dp/4805307943]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The koto (言) and koto (事) were used without distinguishing them at the beginning of incorporation of kanji, and Kotoshironushi (事代主)(the god that appears in Japanese mythology) was also written as Kotoshironushi (言代主神) in the &quot;Kojiki&quot; (the Record of Ancient Matters).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Two different characters for koto, 言 (word, speech) and 事 (thing, matter) were used without distinction when kanji were first incorporated into Japanese, and Kotoshironushi (事代主, a god who appears in Japanese mythology) was also written as Kotoshironushi (言代主神) in the &quot;Kojiki&quot; (the Record of Ancient Matters).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>自分の意志をはっきりと声に出して言うことを「言挙げ」と言い、それが自分の慢心によるものであった場合には悪い結果がもたらされると信じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The act of speaking out one&apos;s own will was called as &apos;kotoage&apos; (言挙げ (literally, speak out the word)) and the bad ending would be brought if it was based on one&apos;s pride.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The act of speaking out one&apos;s own will was called &apos;kotoage&apos; (言挙げ - literally, to speak out the word) and a bad result would be brought about if it was based on one&apos;s pride.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The act of speaking out one&apos;s own will was called &apos;kotoage&apos; (literally to speak out the word) and a bad result would be brought about if it was based on one&apos;s pride.</e>
<cmt>言挙げ - 削除　ここでは特に漢字表記は必要ないと思います。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>例えば『古事記』においてヤマトタケルが伊吹山に登ったとき山の神の化身に出合ったが、倭建命はこれは神の使いだから帰りに退治しようと言挙げした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For an example, Yamatotakeru climbed up the Ibuki Mountain and met with the incarnation of a mountain god in &quot;Kojiki,&quot; but Yamatotakeru said kotoage that he will defeat it on the way back home since this was the messenger of god.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For an example, Yamatotakeru climbed Ibuki Mountain and met with the incarnation of a mountain god in the &quot;Kojiki,&quot; but on the way back home Yamatotakeru said that he will defeat it (kotoage) since this was a messenger of god.</e>
<cmt>grammar, revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, according to the &quot;Kojiki&quot; when Yamato Takeru climbed Mt. Ibuki he encountered an avatar of the god of the mountain, only to announce that since it was merely a messenger of the god, he would destroy it on his way back home.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>それが命の慢心によるものであったため、命は神の祟りに遭い亡くなってしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since it was from the pride of Yamatotakeru, he was cursed by the god and passed away.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since what Yamatotakeru spoke was from his pride, he was cursed by the god and he passed away.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since he had spoken out of pride, Takeru was cursed by the god and died.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>すなわち、言霊思想は、万物に神が宿るとする単なるアニミズム的な思想というだけではなく、心の存り様をも示すものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In another words, the ideology of kotodama was not the simple animismistic ideology that god resided in everything but represented existence of the mind.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In another words, the ideology of kotodama was not the simple animismistic ideology that god resided in everything, rather it represented the existence of the mind.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In another words, the ideology of kotodama was not the simple animistic ideology that god resided in everything, rather it represented the existence of the mind.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>他の文化圏の言霊</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kodama of Other Cultural Regions</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kodama of Other Cultural Regions</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The kotodama of other cultural regions</e>
<cmt>文頭以外の語頭を小文字にスペル</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="16">
<j>他の文化圏でも、言霊と共通する思想が見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were similar ideologies seen in other cultural regions similar to kodama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were deologies seen in other cultural regions similar to kodama.</e>
<cmt>redundancy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were ideologies seen in other cultural regions similar to kotodama.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>『旧約聖書』の「ヘブライ語：רוח הקודש」（ルーアハ）、『新約聖書』では「希: Πνεύμα」（プネウマ。動詞「吹く」（希: πνεω）を語源とし、息、大いなるものの息、といった意が込められる）というものがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were holy spirits &apos;Hebrew: רוח הקודש&apos; (Ruwach) in &quot;The Old Testament&quot; and &apos;Greek: Πνεύμα&apos; (Spiritus) in &quot;The New Testament&quot; that was derived from the verb, &apos;blowing&apos; (Greek: πνεω) and held the meaning of the breath of the great presence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were holy spirits &apos;Hebrew: רוח הקודש&apos; (Ruwach) in &quot;The Old Testament&quot; and &apos;Greek: Πνεύμα&apos; (Spiritus) in &quot;The New Testament&quot; that were derived from the verb, &apos;blowing&apos; (Greek: πνεω) and held the meaning of the breath of a great presence.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Old Testament mentions holy spirits (called &quot;???&quot; in Hebrew), while in the New Testament such spirits are referred to as &quot;Pneuma&quot; in Greek. The word &quot;pneuma&quot; derives from the verb &quot;pneo&quot; (to blow), and refers to the breath of a powerful being.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>「風はいずこより来たりいずこに行くかを知らず。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;It is not known where the wind came from or where it goes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;It is not known where the wind came from or where it goes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is not known where the wind came from or where it goes.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>風の吹くところいのちが生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A life is born where the wind blows.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A life is born where the wind blows.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A life is born when the wind blows.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>」この「風」と表記されているものが「プネウマ」である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The thing that was referred as &quot;wind&quot; here was &quot;Spiritus.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reference to &quot;wind&quot; here was &quot;Spiritus.&quot;</e>
<cmt>wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reference to &apos;wind&apos; here was &apos;Spiritus.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="21">
<j>一般に、音や言葉は、禍々しき魂や霊を追い払い、場を清める働きがあるとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In general, the sound or words were believed to have the effect where it shooed away evil souls or spirits.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In general, sound or words were believed to have the effect to chase away evil souls or spirits.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In general, sound or words were believed to have the effect to chase away evil souls or spirits.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>これは洋の東西を問わず、祭礼や祝い、悪霊払いで行われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is performed in festivals, celebrations, or to get rid of evil spirits everywhere around the world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was performed in festivals, celebrations, or to get rid of evil spirits everywhere all around the world.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was performed in festivals, celebrations, or to get rid of evil spirits everywhere all around the world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>神事での太鼓、謝肉祭での笛や鐘、太鼓などはその例である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The drum used during religious services, flutes, bells, and drums used during carnivals were such examples.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The drum used during religious services, flutes, bells, and drums used during carnivals were such examples.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Examples of the power of sound include the drums used during Shinto rituals and the flutes, bells, and drums used during carnivals.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="24">
<j>言葉も、呪文や詔としてその霊的な力が利用される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even the spiritual power of words were used as incantations or the command of the emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even the spiritual power of words were used as incantations or the command of the emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even the spiritual power of words were used as incantations or the command of the emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>ただし、その大本になる「こと」（事）が何であるかということには、さまざまな見解がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there are different interpretations of what the main &quot;koto&quot; (事) (event) was.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there are different interpretations of what the main &quot;koto&quot; (事) (event) was.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there are different interpretations of what the main &apos;koto&apos; (事) (event) was.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>たとえば「真理とは巌（いわお）のようなものであり、その上に教会を築くことができる」と考えたり、あるいは「真実を知りたければ鏡に汝自身を映してみよ、それですべてが明らかになる」といい、それは知りうるものであり、また実感として捉えられるものであるとみる意見や、「こと」自体はわれわれでは知りえないものであるという主張もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For an example, there were different thoughts and opinions that &apos;the truth is like a big rock, and one could build a church on top of it,&apos; &apos;if one wants to know the truth, reflect thyself on a mirror and everything shalt be revealed,&apos; these were something that could be comprehended, understood, or &quot;koto&quot; itself cannot be understood.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For an example, there were different ideas and opinions that &apos;truth is like a big rock, and one could build a church on top of it,&apos; &apos;if one wants to know the truth, reflect thyself in a mirror and everything shall be revealed,&apos; this was something that could be comprehended, understood, but &quot;koto&quot; itself cannot be understood.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, some believed that &quot;truth is a great rock upon which the church can be built,&quot; while others held that &quot;if you seek the truth, gaze at your reflection in a mirror, and all shall be revealed,&quot; according to which truth was something that could be comprehended or grasped; yet both suggest that the &quot;koto&quot; (essence of the matter) itself is not something we human beings can ever know.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>これらはさまざまな文化により、時代により、また個人により大きく異なっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These were greatly different depending on cultures, time periods, and individuals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This differed greatly depending upon culture, era, and individuals.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This differed greatly depending upon culture, era, and individuals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Pentagon999(id:278678), Okc(id:17021), Izayohi(id:13095), JYOQ2(id:7240), いろはにほへと(id:89648), Nnh(id:474), Kotodama(id:85498), Eskimbot(id:29676), PixelBot(id:166734), Aphaia(id:3132), YODAFON(id:161109), Mishika(id:276), Greenland4(id:114494), Azu(id:1328), Michey.M(id:906), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), ＮｉＫｅ(id:7512), Point136(id:211299), Fievarsty(id:201483), Corwin(id:973), Dump(id:26383), FlaBot(id:30804), Mosad999(id:285131), 七草みけ(id:93327), Louperibot(id:128971), Nito(id:83007), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>