<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>ウガヤフキアエズ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ugayafukiaezu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ugayafukiaezu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ugayafukiaezu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>ウガヤフキアエズは、日本神話の神。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ugayafukiaezu is a deity in Japanese mythology.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ugayafukiaezu is a deity in Japanese mythology.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ugayafukiaezu is a deity in Japanese mythology.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>古事記では天津日高日子波限建鵜草葺不合命（あまつひこひこなぎさたけうがやふきあえずのみこと）、日本書紀では彦波瀲武草葺不合尊（ひこなぎさたけうがやふきあえずのみこと）と表記する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This deity is referred to as &quot;Amatsuhiko hikonagisatake ugayafukiagezu no mikoto&quot; in &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters), and &quot;Hikonagisatake ugayafukiaezu no mikoto&quot; in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan).</e>
<cmt>漢字表記は、欧米の読者には無意味と思われましたので、音のみの記述としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This deity is referred to as &quot;Amatsuhiko hikonagisatake ugayafukiagezu no mikoto&quot; in &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters), and &quot;Hikonagisatake ugayafukiaezu no mikoto&quot; in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This deity is referred to as 天津日高日子波限建鵜草葺不合命 (Amatsuhiko hikonagisatake ugayafukiaezu no mikoto) in the Kojiki (The Records of Ancient Matters), and 彦波瀲武草葺不合尊(Hikonagisatake ugayafukiaezu no mikoto) in Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>神話の記述</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His descriptions in mythology</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His descriptions in mythology</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Myths</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>ホオリ（山幸彦）と、海神の娘であるトヨタマビメ（豊玉毘売）の子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a son of Hoori (Yamasachihiko), his father, and Toyotamabime, his mother who was a daughter of Watatsumi no kami (the sea god)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the son of Hoori (Yamasachihiko), his father, and Toyotamabime, his mother who was the daughter of Watatsumi no kami (the sea god).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the son of Hoori (Yamasachihiko), his father, and Toyotamabime, his mother who was the daughter of Watatsumi no kami (the sea god).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>ニニギ・ホオリ・ウガヤフキアエズの三代は日向三代（ひむかさんだいまたはひゅうがさんだい）と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Three generations of deities, made up of Ninigi, Hoori, and Ugayafukiaezu, are called &quot;Himuka sandai&quot; or &quot;Hyuga sandai&quot; (literally, three generations of deities in Hyuga (an area that covered today&apos;s Miyazaki Prefecture and part of Kagoshima Prefecture)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Three generations of deities, made up of Ninigi, Hoori, and Ugayafukiaezu, are called &quot;Himuka sandai&quot; or &quot;Hyuga sandai&quot; (literally, three generations of deities in Hyuga - an area that covers today&apos;s Miyazaki Prefecture and part of Kagoshima Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Three generations of deities, including Ninigi, Hoori, and Ugayafukiaezu, are called Himuka sandai or Hyuga sandai.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>トヨタマビメは龍宮で懐妊したが、天神の子を海の中で生むわけにはいかないとして、陸に上がってきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Toyotamabime, a daughter of the sea god, became pregnant at Ryugu (the palace of the dragon king believed to exist at the bottom of the ocean), she went up on the land as she thought it inappropriate to give birth to a child of Tenjin (the heavenly god) in the sea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Toyotamabime, the daughter of the sea god, became pregnant at Ryugu (the palace of the dragon king believed to exist at the bottom of the ocean), she went up on the land as she thought it was inappropriate to give birth to a child of Tenjin (the heavenly god) in the sea.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Toyotamabime, the daughter of the sea god, became pregnant at Ryugu (the palace of the dragon king believed to exist at the bottom of the ocean), she went up on the land as she thought it was inappropriate to give birth to a child of Tenjin (the heavenly god) in the sea.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>浜辺に産屋を作ろうとしたが、茅草がわりの鵜の羽を葺き終らないうちにトヨタマビメが産気づいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although she attempted to make a maternity room, actually a hut, on the beach, she went into labor before finishing thatching the roof with waterfowl feathers, not with grass normally used.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although she attempted to make a maternity room, actually a hut, on the beach, she went into labor before thatching the roof with waterfowl feathers was completed, instead of with grass that is normally used.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although she tried to make a shelter on the beach, she went into labor before she could completely thatch the roof with waterfowl feathers which she used instead of the usual grass.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>「ウガヤフキアエズ（鵜茅葺き合えず）」と名付けられることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That&apos;s why the newborn baby was named &quot;Ugaya fuki aezu&quot;, which literally means &quot;being unable to finish thatching the roof with waterfowl feathers&quot;.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That&apos;s why the newborn baby was named &quot;Ugaya fuki aezu,&quot; which literally means &quot;being unable to finish thatching the roof with waterfowl feathers.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hence the newborn baby was named &apos;Ugaya fuki aezu,&apos; which literally means being unable to &apos;finish thatching the roof with waterfowl feathers&apos;.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>トヨタマビメは、「他国の者は子を産む時には本来の姿になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toyotamabime said to Hoori, her husband, that when a woman from a different country delivered her baby, she would turn herself into what she really was.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toyotamabime said to Hoori, her husband, that when a woman from a different country delivered her baby, she would turn herself into what she really was.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toyotamabime said to Hoori, her husband, that women from different countries turned into their real selves when giving birth.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>私も本来の姿で産もうと思うので、絶対に産屋の中を見ないように」とホオリに言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And she asked her husband not to look into her maternity room for all the world as she also wanted to deliver her baby by turning herself into her real self.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And she asked her husband not to look into her maternity room for all the world as she also wanted to deliver her baby by turning herself into her real self.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She told her husband not to look into her maternity room as she wanted to assume her real self to deliver her baby.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>しかし、ホオリは産屋の中を覗いてしまい、そこにトヨタマビメが姿を変えた八尋和邇が這い回っているのを見た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Despite her plea, Hoori peeked in her room only to see a giant alligator, her true self, crawling around.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Despite her plea, Hoori peeked in her room only to see a giant alligator, her true self, crawling around.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Despite her plea, Hoori peeked in her room only to see a giant alligator, her true self, crawling around.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>ホオリは逃げ出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He ran away.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He ran away.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He ran away.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>トヨタマビメはホオリに覗かれたことを恥ずかしく思って、産まれた子を置いて海に帰ってしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ashamed of having her true self looked at by her husband, Toyotamabime went back to the sea, leaving her newborn baby behind.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ashamed of having her true self looked at by her husband, Toyotamabime went back to the sea, leaving her newborn baby behind.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ashamed of being seen by her husband Toyotamabime went back to the sea, leaving her newborn baby behind.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>代わりに妹のタマヨリビメ（玉依毘売）を遣わした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, she sent her younger sister, Tamayoribime, to her husband.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, she sent her younger sister, Tamayoribime, to her husband.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, she sent her younger sister, Tamayoribime, in her place.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>トヨタマビメは、ホオリが覗いたことを恨みはしたが、やはり恋しかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Toyotamabime was angry with Hoori for having peeked in her delivery room, she still loved him and missed him a lot.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Toyotamabime was angry with Hoori for having peeked into her delivery room, she still loved him and missed him a lot.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Toyotamabime was angry with Hoori for having peeked into her delivery room, she still felt great affection for him.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>タマヨリビメを通してホオリと歌を詠み交わした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">So, she exchanged poems with him through Tamayoribime.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">So, she exchanged poems with him through Tamayoribime.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She exchanged poems with him through Tamayoribime.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="17">
<j>ウガヤフキアエズは、育ての親であるタマヨリビメと結婚し、タマヨリビメとの間に五瀬命（五瀬命）・稲飯命（稲氷命）・御毛沼命（御毛沼命）・ワカミケヌ（若御毛沼命）の四子をもうけた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ugayafukiaezu, when he grew up, got married to Tamayoribime, his fostering mother, and had four children with her: Itsuse no mikoto, Inahi no Mikoto, Mikenu no Mikoto, and Wakamikenu no Mikoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ugayafukiaezu, when he grew up, got married to Tamayoribime, his fostering mother, and had four children with her: Itsuse no mikoto, Inahi no Mikoto, Mikenu no Mikoto, and Wakamikenu no Mikoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ugayafukiaezu, when he grew up, got married to Tamayoribime, his fostering mother, and had four children with her: Itsuse no mikoto, Inahi no mikoto, Mikenu no mikoto, and Wakamikenu no mikoto.</e>
<cmt>Mikoto→mikoto</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>ミケヌは常世へ渡り、イナヒは母のいる海原へ行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Inahi went over to Tokoyo (the perpetual country) while Inahi went to the ocean where his mother resided.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Inahi went over to Tokoyo (the perpetual country) while Inahi went to the ocean where his mother resided.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mikenu went over to Tokoyo (lit. &quot;the normal world,&quot; though some texts hint that it is the afterworld), while Inahi went to the ocean where his mother resided.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。カンマの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>末子のワカミケヌが、後にカムヤマトイハレビコ、神武天皇となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His youngest child, Wakamikenu, who later became Kamu yamato ihare biko, was Emperor Jinmu, the first Emperor of Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His youngest child, Wakamikenu, who later became Kamu yamato ihare biko, was Emperor Jinmu, the first Emperor of Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His youngest child, Wakamikenu, who later became Kamu yamato ihare biko, was Emperor Jinmu, the first Emperor of Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="20">
<j>解説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Comments on this story</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Comments on this story</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Comments on this story</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>異類の者と結婚し、何かをするのを見るなとタブーを課し、そのタブーを破られて本来の姿を見られて分かれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One gets married to someone of a different kind and is given a taboo by the partner, but the taboo is broken and the true self of the partner is revealed.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One gets married to someone of a different kind and is given a taboo by the partner, but the taboo is broken and the true self of the partner is revealed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One gets married to someone of a different species and is told that a particular action is taboo, but the taboo is broken and the true self of the partner is revealed.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>分かれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, the couple breaks up.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, the couple breaks up.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The couple are forced to separate.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>こういう話は世界各地に見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Stories of this type are common across the world.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Stories of this type are common all over the world.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Stories of this type are common all over the world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>日本神話でも同様の説話が何度か登場する（神産みの黄泉訪問説話など）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are occasionally found in Japanese mythology as well, (as seen in a tale of visiting Yomi (a world after death) to give birth to a deity).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are occasionally found in Japanese mythology as well, (as seen in tales of visiting Yomi - a world after death - to give birth to a deity).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are often found in Japanese mythology as well, (as seen in tales of visiting Yomi, a world after death, to give birth to a deity).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。ハイフンをカンマにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>民話でも鶴の恩返しなどがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;The Grateful Crane&quot;, a folktale, also has a similar plot.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;The Grateful Crane,&quot; a folktale, also has a similar plot.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Grateful Crane, a folktale, also has a similar plot.</e>
<cmt>原文に『』のない&quot;を削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>また、そういう説話では、異類の者との間に生まれた子の子孫が王朝・氏族の始祖とされていることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In them, the offspring of children who were born from the parents of different kinds are often described as the earliest ancestors of the imperial family and noble clans.</e>
<cmt>「氏族」がどんな氏族を意味しているのかはっきりしませんが、前に王朝となりますので、貴族の意味に訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amongst them, the offspring of children who were born from the parents of different kinds are often described as the earliest ancestors of the imperial family and noble clans.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amongst them, the offspring of children who were born from the parents of different species are often described as the earliest ancestors of the imperial family and noble clans.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="27">
<j>天皇につながる神が皆「稲」に関係のある名前である中で、ウガヤフキアエズだけが稲穂と無関係になっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">All the deities that are connected to Emperors, except for Ugayafukiaezu, have names related to the &quot;rice plant&quot; or &quot;rice ear&quot;.</e>
<cmt>ここでは、「稲」と「稲穂」がほぼ同義に用いられています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">All the deities that are connected to Emperors, except for Ugayafukiaezu, have names related to the &quot;rice plant&quot; or &quot;rice ear.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">All the deities that are connected to Emperors, except for the deity Ugayafukiaezu, have names related to the &apos;rice plant.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。ピリオドの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>この理由については様々な説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many scholars explain why Ugayafukiaezu is an exception in different ways:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many scholars explain why Ugayafukiaezu is an exception in different ways:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many scholars hold different theories on the reason for this.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>ウガヤフキアエズには事績の記述がほとんどないことから、後から作られた神ではないかとする説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some say that Ugayafukiaezu might have been a deity created at a later time as there have been few descriptions of his deeds and achievement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some say that Ugayafukiaezu might have been a deity created at a later time as there have been few descriptions of his deeds and achievements.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some say that Ugayafukiaezu might have been a deity created at a later time as there have been few descriptions of his deeds and achievements.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>その理由は、山と海の力が合わさったこの神によって、天皇が山から海まで支配するその支配力を表すためとしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They consider that Ugayafukiaezu, a deity that combines the power of mountains and the sea, might have served as a symbol of the Emperor who ruled everything, from mountains to the ocean.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They consider that Ugayafukiaezu, a deity that combines the power of mountains and the sea, might have served as a symbol of the Emperor who ruled everything, from mountains to the ocean.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They consider that Ugayafukiaezu, a deity who combines the power of mountains and the sea, might have served as a symbol of the Emperor who ruled everything, from mountains to the ocean.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="31">
<j>なお、『上記』『竹内文書』など一部の古史古伝では、ウガヤフキアエズは一柱の神ではなく、数十代に渡る王朝であったと記述している（ウガヤフキアエズ王朝）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also note that according to some ancient history records and legend, including &quot;Uetsufumi&quot; (Ancient Japanese Literature) and &quot;Takeuchi-monjo&quot; (an ancient text which recorded the lineage of ancient kami and a dynasty preceding Emperor Jinmu), Ugayafukiaezu is depicted as a dynasty (the Ugayafukiaezu dynasty) that lasted tens of generations, not as a deity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also note that according to some ancient historical records and legends, including &quot;Uetsufumi&quot; (Ancient Japanese Literature) and &quot;Takeuchi-monjo&quot; (an ancient text that recorded the lineage of ancient kami and a dynasty preceding Emperor Jinmu), Ugayafukiaezu is depicted as a dynasty (the Ugayafukiaezu dynasty) that lasted tens of generations, not as a deity.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, according to some ancient historical records and legends, including &quot;Uetsufumi&quot; (Ancient Japanese Literature) and &quot;Takeuchi-monjo&quot; (an ancient text that recorded the lineage of ancient deities and a dynasty preceding Emperor Jinmu), Ugayafukiaezu is depicted as a dynasty (the Ugayafukiaezu dynasty) that lasted tens of generations, not as a deity.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>また、出雲国風土記の屋代郷(島根県安来市)の地名説話に出てくる天津子がウガヤフキアエズともいう説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some say that Ugayafukiaezu is Tentsushi, who appeared in a tale of Yashiro-go (Yasugi City, Shimane Prefecture) in &quot;Izumo no kuni fudoki&quot; (descriptions of the climate and culture of Izumo no kuni (Izumo Province)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some say that Ugayafukiaezu is Tentsushi, who appeared in a tale of Yashiro-go (Yasugi City, Shimane Prefecture) in &quot;Izumo no kuni fudoki&quot; (descriptions of the climate and culture of Izumo no kuni or Izumo Province).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some say that Ugayafukiaezu is the same as Tentsushi, who appeared in a tale of Yashiro-go (Yasugi City, Shimane Prefecture) in Izumo no kuni fudoki (the topography of Izumo Province).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。用語集の補足に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>信仰</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Faith</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Faith</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Faith</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="33">
<j>ウガヤフキアエズは、他の天皇につながる神と同様に農業の神として信仰される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Like other deities connected to emperors, Ugayafukiaezu has been worshipped as a deity of agriculture.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Like other deities connected to emperors, Ugayafukiaezu has been worshipped as a deity of agriculture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Like other deities connected to emperors, Ugayafukiaezu is worshipped as a deity of agriculture.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>その他に、上記の説話から夫婦の和合、安産などの神徳もあるとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of the tale mentioned earlier, Ugayafukiaezu has also been adorned as a deity to whom people pray for matrimonial harmony and safe childbirth.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of the tale mentioned earlier, Ugayafukiaezu has also been adorned as a deity to whom people pray for matrimonial harmony and safe childbirth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of the tale mentioned earlier, Ugayafukiaezu has also been prayed to as a deity to whom people pray for matrimonial harmony and safe childbirth.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>鵜戸神宮（宮崎県日南市）、宮崎神宮（宮崎市）などに祀られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ugayafukiaezu is enshrined in Udo-jingu Shrine (Nichinan City, Miyazaki Prefecture) and Miyazaki-jingu Shrine (Miyiazaki City).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ugayafukiaezu is enshrined in Udo-jingu Shrine (Nichinan City, Miyazaki Prefecture) and Miyazaki-jingu Shrine (Miyiazaki City).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ugayafukiaezu is enshrined in Udo-jingu Shrine (Nichinan City, Miyazaki Prefecture) and Miyazaki-jingu Shrine (Miyazaki City).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="36">
<j>埋葬地は、日本書紀に「吾平山上陵」と記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Nihonshoki, Ugayafukiaezu was buried in a placed called &quot;Aira no Yamanoue no Misasagi&quot; (literally, &quot;Imperial Tomb at the Top of Mt. Aira&quot;).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the Nihonshoki, Ugayafukiaezu was buried in a placed called &quot;Aira no Yamanoue no Misasagi&quot; (literally, &quot;Imperial Tomb at the Top of Mt. Aira&quot;).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the Nihonshoki, Ugayafukiaezu was buried in a placed called &apos;Aira no Yamanoue no Misasagi&apos; (literally, Imperial Tomb at the Top of Mt. Aira).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>その伝承地は南九州各地にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there are many places in South Kyushu that have been believed to be the burial place of Ugayafukiaezu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there are many places in Southern Kyushu that have been believed to be the burial place of Ugayafukiaezu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there are many places in Southern Kyushu that have been believed to be the burial place of Ugayafukiaezu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>明治7年、明治政府はそれらの中から、旧薩摩藩の学者の意見を参考にして鹿児島県鹿屋市（旧 肝属郡吾平町）を「吾平山上陵」に治定した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1874, the Meiji government determined based on the opinions of the scholars of defunct Satsuma Domain that Kanoya City, Kagoshima Prefecture (old Aira-cho, Kimotsuki-gun) is where his tomb, &quot;Aira no Yamanoue no Misasagi&quot;, is located.</e>
<cmt>「明治７年」を西暦に直しています。一原文一訳文例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1874, the Meiji government determined based upon the opinions of the scholars of the defunct Satsuma Domain that Kanoya City, Kagoshima Prefecture (old Aira-cho, Kimotsuki-gun) is where his tomb, &quot;Aira no Yamanoue no Misasagi,&quot; is located.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1874, the Meiji government determined that his tomb is located in Kanoya City Kagoshima Prefecture (formerly Aira-cho, Kimotsuki-gun), based on the opinions of the scholars of the defunct Satsuma Domain.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。重複するinを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>（他の日向三代の神陵も鹿児島県内に治定している）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(The government also identified tombs in Kagoshima Prefecture as those of the other Himuka sandai deities.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(The government also identified tombs in Kagoshima Prefecture as those of the other Himuka sandai deities.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(The government also identified tombs in Kagoshima Prefecture as those of the other Himuka sandai deities.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>しかし、日向の人々からの反論があり、国学者や宮内庁の調査を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as opposition came from people in Hyga (today&apos;s Miyazaki Prefecture) to this decision, a survey was conducted by the scholars of ancient Japanese literature and culture and Imperial Household Agency.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as opposition came from people in Hyga (today&apos;s Miyazaki Prefecture) to this decision, a survey was conducted by the scholars of ancient Japanese literature and culture and the Imperial Household Agency.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as opposition to this decision came from people in Hyuga a survey was conducted by the scholars of ancient Japanese literature and culture and the Imperial Household Agency.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>明治29年、鵜戸神宮背後の速日峯山上が「御陵墓伝説地 吾平山上陵」と定められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1896, a decision was finally made on this issue that the top of Mt. Hayahi-no-Mine, which is located behind Udo-jingu Shrine, is the legendary place of &quot;Aira no Yamanoue no Misasagi&quot;, the tomb of Ugayafukiaezu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外処理明治２９年を西暦で表現しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1896, a decision was finally made on this issue that the top of Mt. Hayahi-no-Mine, which is located behind Udo-jingu Shrine, is the legendary place of &quot;Aira no Yamanoue no Misasagi,&quot; the tomb of Ugayafukiaezu.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1896, a decision was finally made on this issue that the top of Mt. Hayahi-no-Mine, which is located behind Udo-jingu Shrine, is the legendary place of &apos;Aira no Yamanoue no Misasagi,&apos; the tomb of Ugayafukiaezu.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>他に、宮崎県西臼杵郡高千穂町の「吾平山陵」とする説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are some scholars who still insist that &quot;Aria no Yamane no Misusage&quot; in Takachiho Town, Nishi usuki County, Miyazaki Prefecture is where his tomb is located.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are some scholars who still insist that &quot;Aria no Yamane no Misusage&quot; in Takachiho Town, Nishi usuki County, Miyazaki Prefecture is where his tomb is located.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are some scholars who still insist that the tomb is located in &apos;Aria no Yamane no Misusage&apos; in Takachiho Town, Nishi usuki County, Miyazaki Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Izayohi(id:13095), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), Nnh(id:474), 暗黒な方(id:44101), YurikBot(id:18605), 代言人(id:33675), MlolM(id:24777), Sanjo(id:83413), Huemat(id:19503), NDR(id:5500), Escarbot(id:59151), Bbt888s(id:8239), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>