<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>拍手 (神道)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hakushu (clapping [Shinto])</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hakushu</e>
<cmt>Moved explanation tocell F4</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hakushu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>拍手（はくしゅ、かしわで）とは、神道の祭祀や、神社・神棚など神 (神道)に拝する際に行う行為である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term &quot;hakushu&quot; or &quot;Kashiwade&quot;(clapping) refers to a gesture people make when they offer prayers to gods (of Shinto religion) at Shinto religious services or before Shinto shrines or household altars.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term &quot;hakushu&quot; or &quot;kashiwade&quot; (both of which mean clapping) refers to a gesture people make when they offer prayers to kami (deities, spirits) at Shinto religious services or before Shinto shrines or household altars.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term &quot;hakushu&quot; or &quot;kashiwade&quot; (both of which mean clapping) refers to a gesture people make when they offer prayers to gods (deities, spirits) at Shinto religious services or before Shinto shrines or household altars.</e>
<cmt>kami→gods</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>柏手と書かれることもあり、また、開手（ひらて）ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hakushu (拍手) is alternatively written as &quot;kashiwade&quot; (柏手), and is also called as &quot;hirate&quot;.</e>
<cmt>以下必要と認めたところに漢字表記を併記しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hakushu is written with the Chinese characters for &apos;beat&apos; and &apos;hand&apos; (拍手) or &apos;oak hand&apos; (柏手) and it is also known as &quot;hirate&quot; (開手 - &apos;open hand&apos;).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hakushu is written with the Chinese characters for &apos;beat&apos; and &apos;hand&apos; (拍手) or &apos;oak hand&apos; (柏手) and it is also known as &quot;hirate&quot; (開手 - &apos;open hand&apos;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>作法</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Manners</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ｅtiｑuette</e>
<cmt>Ｉ ｔｈｉｎｋ &apos;ｅｔｉｑｕｅｔｔｅ&apos; ｉｓ ａ ｂｉｔ ｍｏｒｅ ｎａｔｕｒａｌ</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ｅtiｑuette</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>両手を合わせ、左右に開いた後に再び合わせる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Join your palms, and after opening your hands sideways, join them again.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Join your palms, and after spreading your hands to the sides, join them again.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Join your palms, and after spreading your hands to the sides, join them again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>通常、手を再び合わせる際に音を出す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Generally, clap your hands when rejoining your palms to make a sound.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Generally, clap your hands when rejoining your palms to make a sound.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Generally, clap your hands when rejoining your palms to make a sound.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>音を出す理由は、感謝や喜びを表す為、凶事や悲しみを表す行事においては音を出さない作法（後述）もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the purpose in making clapping sounds is to express gratitude or joy, there is another manner in which hakushu is made silently in depressing events or expressing sorrows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the purpose of making clapping sounds is to express gratitude or joy, the etiquette is different at solemn events and when expressing sorrows (see below).</e>
<cmt>PrepositionRevised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the purpose of making clapping sounds is to express gratitude or joy, the etiquette is different at solemn events and when expressing sorrows (see below).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>その他に、願いをかなえるために神を呼び出す、または邪気を祓うためともいわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also said that the clapping sounds are made to invoke gods to make your wish come true or to ward off evil spirits.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also said that the clapping sounds are made to invoke kami to make your wish come true or to ward off evil spirits.</e>
<cmt>&quot;gods&quot;→&quot;kami&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also said that the clapping sounds are made to invoke gods to make your wish come true or to ward off evil spirits.</e>
<cmt>kami→gods</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>この場合、音を出さないのは故人の霊まで祓ってしまわない為と解釈される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this sense, making silent hakush can be construed as avoiding warding off spirits of the dead.</e>
<cmt>「この場合（in this case)」は文脈的に不適当と思われましたので、In this senseとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this sense, making silent hakushu can be construed as avoiding warding off spirits of the dead.</e>
<cmt>Spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this sense, making silent hakushu can be construed as avoiding warding off spirits of the dead.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>種類</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Types</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Types</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Types</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>拍手にはいくつか種類がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are several types of hakush.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are several types of hakushu.</e>
<cmt>Spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are several types of hakushu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>現代の参拝で行われる「二拝二拍手一拝」など、3回以下のものは「短拍手（みじかて）」と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The types including three or less hand claps such as &quot;nihai-nihakushu-ippai&quot; (two bows, two hand claps and a final bow) generally employed when people visit shrines today are called &quot;mijikate&quot; (short claps).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One type is the &quot;mijikate&quot; (short claps) of three or less hand claps, such as the &quot;nihai-nihakushu-ippai&quot; (two bows, two hand claps and a final bow) generally employed when people visit shrines today.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One type is the &apos;mijikate&apos; (short claps) of three or less hand claps, such as the &apos;nihai-nihakushu-ippai&apos; (The greeting of Shintoism which performs a bow twice first, then applauds twice, and finally bows once) generally employed when people visit shrines today.</e>
<cmt>用語集に統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>出雲大社、宇佐神宮の4回、伊勢神宮の8回など、4回以上手を打つものは「長拍手（ながて）」と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those including four or more hand claps employed in shrines such as Izumo Taisha Shrine (four claps), Usa Jingu Shrine (four claps) and Ise Jingu Shrine (eight claps) are called &quot;nagate&quot;(long claps).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Four or more hand claps, such as those used at Izumo Taisha Shrine (four claps), Usa Jingu Shrine (four claps) and Ise Jingu Shrine (eight claps) are known as &quot;nagate&quot;(long claps).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Four or more hand claps, such as those used at Izumo-taisha Shrine (four claps), Usa-jingu Shrine (four claps) and Ise-jingu Shrine (eight claps) are known as &apos;nagate&apos; (long claps).</e>
<cmt>用語集に統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>他に、8回打った後に再度短拍手を1回打つ「八開手（やひらて）」もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is another type called &quot;yahirate&quot; including eight claps followed by a final short one.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is another type called &quot;yahirate&quot;, which is eight claps followed by a final short one.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is another type called &apos;yahirate&apos;, which is eight claps followed by a final short one.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>神葬祭で音を出さずに打つ「偲手・忍手（しのびて）」や、直会で盃を受けるときに一回打つ「礼手（らいしゅ）」などもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among other types are &quot;shinobite&quot; (soundless clapping) in which hands are clapped silently at Shinto funerals and &quot;raishu&quot; including one clap made when receiving a cup of sake at naorai (feast).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among other types are &quot;shinobite&quot; (soundless clapping), in which hands are clapped silently at Shinto funerals, and &quot;raishu&quot;, one clap made when receiving a cup of sake at naorai (banquets held at the end of festivals).</e>
<cmt>PunctuationRevised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among other types are &apos;shinobite&apos; (soundless clapping), in which hands are clapped silently at Shinto funerals, and &apos;raishu&apos;, one clap made when receiving a cup of sake at naorai (banquets held at the end of festivals).</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>細かい所では、両手を合わせる際に、指先まで合わせる作法と、意図的にずらす作法がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">More specifically, examples of hakush manners include one in which the palms are joined exactly so that the tips of the fingers (including the thumb) can meet the tips of the same fingers of the other hand and another in which intentionally the palms are not joined so exactly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">More specific examples of hakushu etiquette include occasions when the palms are joined exactly so that the tips of the fingers (including the thumb) meet the tips of the same fingers of the other hand and occasions when the palms are intentionally not joined so exactly.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">More specific examples of hakushu etiquette include occasions when the palms are joined exactly so that the tips of the fingers (including the thumb) meet the tips of the same fingers of the other hand and occasions when the palms are intentionally not joined so exactly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>ずらす作法にも、途中からずらす作法と、最初から最後までずらしたままの作法がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The latter is further divided into two manners: one in which the palms are joined exactly at first and then slided in midstream; and the other in which the palms are not joined exactly from the beginning to the end.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The latter case is further divided between times when the palms are joined exactly at first and then slid half way through; and another time when the palms are not precisely joined from beginning to end.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarityArticles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The latter case is further divided between times when the palms are joined exactly at first and then slid half way through; and another time when the palms are not precisely joined from beginning to end.</e>
<cmt>スペース調整</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="15">
<j>ずらす理由としては、「音を良くする」他に「不浄の手と合わせない」「（神道と仏教or公家と武家などの）教派の違い」がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reasons for joining the palms not in exact conformation with each other include &quot;to make a clearer sound&quot; and &quot;to avoid contact between the clean hand and the unclean hand&quot;, and also depend on religions and sects (e.g. Shintoism or Buddhism, court nobles or warrior households).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reasons for not aligning the palms exactly include &quot;to make a clearer sound&quot; and &quot;to avoid contact between the clean hand and the unclean hand&quot;, and also depend on religions and sects (e.g. Shintoism or Buddhism, court nobles or warrior households).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, brevity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reasons for not aligning the palms exactly include &apos;to make a clearer sound&apos; and &apos;to avoid contact between the clean hand and the unclean hand&apos;, and also depend on religions and sects (e.g. Shintoism or Buddhism, court nobles or warrior households).</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="16">
<j>音を良くする場合、左手指股に右手指先をあてる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In case of making clearer sounds, hand claps are made such that the tips of the fingers of the right hand can go between the fingers of the left hands.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For a clearer sound, claps are made such that the tips of the fingers of the right hand go between the fingers of the left hand.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, brevity, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For a clearer sound, claps are made such that the tips of the fingers of the right hand go between the fingers of the left hand.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>由来</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Origin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Origin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Origin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="17">
<j>魏志倭人伝には、倭人（後の日本人）の邪馬台国などの風習として、「見大人所敬 但搏手以當脆拝」と記され、貴人に対し手を打ち跪いて拝礼をしていたとされており、当時は人に対しても拍手を行っていたことがわかる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gishi-wajinden (Records of the Wa people, Chronicle of Wei) describes handclapping as &quot;People clapping their hands to show respect to others&quot;, a greeting custom of wajin (ancestors of Japanese people) which was used in veneration to noble people in countries such as Yamatai-koku Kingdom and accordingly, it is understood that hakush was also made toward humans in those days.</e>
<cmt>「見大人所敬 但搏手以當脆拝」の訳は仮訳です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the description in the Gishi-wajinden (Records of the Wa people, Chronicle of Wei) of handclapping as the customary greeting of the people of Wa (the Japanese) in the Yamatai-koku Kingdom, used in veneration of nobles, it is understood that hakushu was also made toward people in those days.</e>
<cmt>I presume there is a phrase missing from between the inverted commas, so deleted them.Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the description of &quot;People clapping their hands to show respect to others&quot;in the Gishi-wajin-den (the first written record of Japan&apos;s commerce) of handclapping as the customary greeting of the people of Wa (the Japanese) in the Yamatai-koku Kingdom, used in veneration of nobles, it is understood that hakushu was also made toward people in those days.</e>
<cmt>用語集に統一。訳漏れの箇所を追記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>古代には、人でも神でも貴いものに対して拍手をしていたのが、人に対しては行われなくなり、神に対するものだけが残ったということになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It means that hakush was made toward gods and noble people in ancient times and the custom of hakush toward humans was gradually extinct while only hakushu toward gods has survived.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This shows that hakushu were made toward both kami and nobles in ancient times but the custom of hakushu toward humans gradually died out, leaving only the practice of hakushu toward kami.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This shows that hakushu were made toward both gods and nobles in ancient times but the custom of hakushu toward humans gradually died out, leaving only the practice of hakushu toward gods.</e>
<cmt>kami→gods</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>なお古代人は、相手に対して挨拶する時、手の中に武器を持っていない事を示すために、パンパンと拍手を打って、敵意の無いことを示すことで、相手への敬意をあらわしたという説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another study suggests that ancient people clapped hands in greeting others for the purpose of expressing their respects and showing that they neither had weapons in their hands nor felt hostility,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another study suggests that ancient people clapped hands in greeting others for the purpose of expressing their respects and showing that they neither had weapons in their hands nor felt hostility,</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another study suggests that ancient people clapped hands in greeting others for the purpose of expressing their respects and showing that they neither had weapons in their hands nor felt hostility,</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="20">
<j>「かしわで」という呼称は、「拍」の字を「柏」と見誤ったため、あるいは混同されて用いられたためというのが通説となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to a popular theory, the name &quot;kashiwade&quot; comes from mistaking &quot;拍&quot; (pronounced as &quot;haku&quot;) for &quot;柏&quot; (pronounced as &quot;haku&quot; or &quot;kashiwa&quot;) or from confusion between the two similar kanji letters.</e>
<cmt>漢字の読みの説明を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to a popular theory, the name &quot;kashiwade&quot; comes from mistaking &quot;拍&quot; (pronounced as &quot;haku&quot;) for &quot;柏&quot; (pronounced as &quot;haku&quot; or &quot;kashiwa&quot;) or from confusion between the two similar characters.</e>
<cmt>&quot;kanji letters&quot;→&quot;characters&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to a popular theory, the name &apos;kashiwade&apos; comes from mistaking &apos;拍&apos; (pronounced as &apos;haku&apos;) for &apos;柏&apos; (pronounced as &apos;haku&apos; or &apos;kashiwa&apos;) or from confusion between the two similar characters.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>他に、宮中の料理人のことである「膳夫（かしわで）」と関連があるとする説。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another theory relates it to &quot;kashiwade&quot; which means a court cook.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another theory relates it to &quot;kashiwade&quot;, which means a court cook.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another theory relates it to &apos;kashiwade&apos;, which means a court cook.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>や、手を合わせた時の形を柏の葉に見立てたためとする説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is still another theory that the shape of the joined hands was likened to an oak leaf, since &quot;kashiwa&quot; can mean oak.</e>
<cmt>最後の節は分かり易くするため付け加えました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is still another theory that the shape of the joined hands was likened to an oak (&quot;kashiwa&quot; in Japanese) leaf.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is still another theory that the shape of the joined hands was likened to an oak (&quot;kashiwa&quot; in Japanese) leaf.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Lonicera(id:20638), Izayohi(id:13095), クロウ(id:21337), Nnh(id:474), ABnormal(id:254617), Greenland4(id:114494), Kaz2008(id:196880), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>