<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>火須勢理命</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hosuseri no Mikoto</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hosuseri no Mikoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hosuseri no Mikoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>火須勢理命（ほすせりのみこと）は、日本神話に登場する神 (神道)である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hosuseri no Mikoto, written as 火須勢理命 in Japanese, is a god (in Shinto) appearing in Japanese mythology.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hosuseri no Mikoto, written as 火須勢理命 in Japanese, is a Shinto god in Japanese mythology.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hosuseri no Mikoto is a Shinto god in Japanese mythology.</e>
<cmt>written as 火須勢理命 in Japanese→削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>古事記にのみ登場する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He appears only in the Kojiki (the Records of Ancient Matters).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He appears only in the Kojiki (the Records of Ancient Matters).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He appears only in the Kojiki (the Records of Ancient Matters).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>火須勢理命は、ニニギとコノハナノサクヤビメの子である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hosuseri no Mikoto is a child of Ninigi (a god in Japanese mythology) and Konohanasakuyabime (a goddess in Japanese mythology).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hosuseri no Mikoto was a child of the god Ninigi and the goddess Konohanasakuyabime.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hosuseri no Mikoto was a child of the god Ninigi and the goddess Konohanasakuyabime.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>天孫降臨の段において、一夜で身蘢ったためにニニギに国津神の子ではないかと疑われ、コノハナノサクヤビメがその疑いを晴らすために火中で生んだ三神の第二子である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the section of the tenson-korin (the descent of the Sun-Goddess&apos;s grandson), Konohanasakuyabime became pregnant after spending only one night with Ninigi and he thought the father of the babies should be a kunitsukami (a god of the land), and Hosuseri no Mikoto was a second child out of the three gods, who were born in the fire because she wanted to eliminate Ninigi&apos;s suspicion.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the section on the tenson-korin (the descent to earth of the Sun-Goddess&apos;s grandson), Konohanasakuyabime became pregnant after spending only one night with Ninigi, who thought the father of the babies was a kunitsukami (Earthly God), and Hosuseri no Mikoto was a second child out of the three gods, who were born in a fire to eliminate Ninigi&apos;s suspicion.</e>
<cmt>PrepositionAdded &quot;to earth&quot;Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the section on the tenson-korin (the descent to earth of the Sun-Goddess&apos;s grandson), Konohanasakuyabime became pregnant after spending only one night with Ninigi, who thought the father of the babies was a kunitsukami (Earthly God), and Hosuseri no Mikoto was a second child out of the three gods, who were born in a fire to eliminate Ninigi&apos;s suspicion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>火が盛んに燃え立つときに生まれたので「ホスセリ」と名附けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was named &apos;Hosuseri&apos; because he was born while the fire was blazing very much (the Chinese character &quot;火&quot; included in his name means &quot;fire,&quot; and another character &quot;勢&quot; in his name means &quot;force&quot;).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処英文のみではなぜ「火が盛んに燃え立つときに生まれた」ことが「ホスセリ」という名に結びつくかがわかりにくいため、カッコ内に「ホスセリ」に使用されている漢字の説明を追加いたしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was named &apos;Hosuseri&apos; because he was born while the fire was raging (one of the Chinese characters in his name means &quot;fire,&quot; and another means &quot;force&quot;).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was named &apos;Hosuseri&apos; because he was born while the fire was raging (one of the Chinese characters in his name means &quot;fire,&quot; and another means &quot;force&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>兄がホデリ、弟がホオリである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His elder brother is called Hoderi and his younger brother is called Hoori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His elder brother is called Hoderi and his younger brother is called Hoori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His elder brother is called Hoderi and his younger brother is called Hoori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>神名は、他の二柱と同様に本来は「穂」に因むものと考えられ、誕生時の説話に因んで「火」の字が宛てられたか、逆に「火」の字が宛てられたことから誕生時の説話が生まれたと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that his name was originally derived from the Chinese character &apos;穂&apos; (an ear of a grain) as well as his two brother gods, and then the character &apos;火&apos; (fire) was assigned to his name according to this birth story, or on the contrary, the birth story was created after people started to use the character &apos;火&apos; for his name.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Like his two brothers, it is believed that his name was originally derived from the Chinese character for an ear of a grain, and the character for fire was assigned later in accordance to his birth story, or conversely, the birth story was created after people started to use the character for fire for his name.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity - deleted kanji since they probably mean nothing to most English speakers</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Like his two brothers, it is believed that his name was originally derived from the Chinese character for an ear of a grain, and the character for fire was assigned later in accordance to his birth story, or conversely, the birth story was created after people started to use the character for fire for his name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>「スセリ」はスセリビメなどと同様「進む」という意味で、「ホスセリ」は稲穂の成熟が進むという意味である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Suseri&apos; means &apos;susumu&apos; (proceed), as well as the name Suseribime (a goddess in Japanese mythology) is derived from the same word, and the name &apos;Hosuseri&apos; means the progress of rice ear growth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Suseri,&apos; which is part of the name of other gods such as Suseribime, means &apos;proceed,&apos; and so the name &apos;Hosuseri&apos; means &apos;progress of the growth of an ear of rice.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Suseri, which is also part of the name of other gods such as Suseribime, means &apos;proceed,&apos; and so the name &apos;Hosuseri&apos; means &apos;progress of the growth of an ear of rice.&apos;</e>
<cmt>also を part の前に加えました。これがないと他の神の「スセリ」のみ言及している印象を受けたためです。文頭の &apos; &apos; 削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>火須勢理命は、その誕生の時に名前が登場するだけで、その後は一切出てこない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hosuseri no Mikoto just appears in his birth scene and he never appears in the story after that.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hosuseri no Mikoto appears in his birth scene only and then is not mentioned again.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hosuseri no Mikoto appears in his birth scene only and then is not mentioned again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>海幸彦（火照命）と山幸彦（火遠理命）という対称的な神の間に何もしない神を置くことで、バランスをとっているとする説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some people think that having a god who does nothing keeps the balance of power between two gods who have opposite characteristics, Umisachihiko (Hoderi no Mikoto) and Yamasachihiko (Hoori no Mikoto).</e>
<cmt>原文中「対称的」は誤字でここでは「対照的」の意と思われます。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some people think that having a god who does nothing keeps the balance of power between two gods who have opposite characteristics, Umisachihiko (Hoderi no Mikoto) and Yamasachihiko (Hoori no Mikoto).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some people think that having a god who does nothing keeps the balance of power between two gods who have opposite characteristics, Umisachihiko (Hoderi no Mikoto) and Yamasachihiko (Hoori no Mikoto).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>同様の構造は天御中主神、ツクヨミにも見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The story about Amenominakanushi no Kami (a god ruling the center of heaven) and the story about Tsukuyomi (a god of the moon) have the same structure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The story about Amenominakanushi no Kami (a god ruling the center of heaven) and the story about Tsukuyomi (a god of the moon) have the same structure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The story about Amenominakanushi no Kami (a god ruling the center of heaven) and the story about Tsukuyomi (a god of the moon) have the same structure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="12">
<j>日本書紀では、火闌降命（ほすそりのみこと。本文・第八の一書）または火酢芹命（ほすせりのみこと。第二・第三・第六の一書）が登場する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Nihonshoki (the Chronicles of Japan), Hosusori no Mikoto (written as 火闌降命 in Japanese) appears in the main account and the eighth issho (a variant version), and Hosuseri no Mikoto (written as 火酢芹命 in Japanese) appears in the second, the third, and the sixth issho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (the Chronicles of Japan), Hosusori no Mikoto (written as 火闌降命 in Japanese) appears in the main account and the eighth issho (addendum), and Hosuseri no Mikoto (written as 火酢芹命 in Japanese) appears in the second, the third, and the sixth issho.</e>
<cmt>&quot;a variant version&quot;→&quot;addendum&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (the Chronicles of Japan), Hosusori no Mikoto (written as 火闌降命 in Japanese) appears in the main account and the eighth issho (addendum), and Hosuseri no Mikoto (written as 火酢芹命 in Japanese) appears in the second, the third, and the sixth issho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>火闌降命は、本文では隼人の祖としており、第八の一書では、古事記で火照命の事績とされていることが火闌降命の事績として書かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The main account explains that Hosusori no Mikoto is the ancestor of Hayato (an ancient tribe in Kyushu region), and the eighth issho describes his achievement that is regarded as Hoderi no Mikoto&apos;s achievement in the Kojiki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The main account explains that Hosusori no Mikoto is the ancestor of the Hayato (an ancient tribe in Kyushu), and the eighth issho describes the exploits that are regarded as Hoderi no Mikoto&apos;s in the &quot;Kojiki&quot;.</e>
<cmt>ArticleRevised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The main account explains that Hosusori no Mikoto is the ancestor of the Hayato (an ancient tribe in Kyushu), and the eighth issho describes the exploits that are regarded as Hoderi no Mikoto&apos;s in the &quot;Kojiki&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>また、第二・第六の一書では、火酢芹命が長子としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, the second and the sixth issho say that Hosuseri no Mikoto is the eldest child.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, the second and the sixth issho say that Hosuseri no Mikoto is the eldest child.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, the second and the sixth issho say that Hosuseri no Mikoto is the eldest child.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>よって古事記における火照命の記述は本来は火闌降命（火酢芹命）についての伝承であり、古事記の編纂者が火照命という神を創作して火闌降命の事績をそちらに移したものと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus it is considered that the story of Hoderi no Mikoto in the Kojiki had been originally a tradition about Hosusori no Mikoto (or Hosuseri no Mikoto), and compilers of the Kojiki created a god named Hoderi no Mikoto and transferred the achievement made by Hosusori no Mikoto to Hoderi no Mikoto&apos;s story.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus it is considered that the story of Hoderi no Mikoto in the &quot;Kojiki&quot; was originally a legend concerning Hosusori no Mikoto (or Hosuseri no Mikoto), with the compilers of the &quot;Kojiki&quot; creating a god named Hoderi no Mikoto and transferring Hosusori no Mikoto&apos;s exploits over to Hoderi no Mikoto.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus it is considered that the story of Hoderi no Mikoto in the &quot;Kojiki&quot; was originally a legend concerning Hosusori no Mikoto (or Hosuseri no Mikoto), with the compilers of the &quot;Kojiki&quot; creating a god named Hoderi no Mikoto and transferring Hosusori no Mikoto&apos;s exploits over to Hoderi no Mikoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Izayohi(id:13095), Nnh(id:474), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>