<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>三種の神器</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Three Sacred Treasures of the Imperial Family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanshu no Jingi or Mikusa no Kamudakara (The Three Sacred Treasures of the Imperial Family)</e>
<cmt>added Japanese reading since there is a description in the article about &quot;Jingi&quot;; added &quot;The&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanshu no Jingi or Mikusa no Kamudakara (The Three Sacred Treasures of the Imperial Family)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>三種の神器（みくさのかむだから、さんしゅのじんぎ）とは、天孫降臨の時に、天照大神から授けられたとする鏡・剣・玉を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Three Sacred Treasures of the Imperial Family refers to a mirror, a sward, and a jewel that are believed to have been granted by Amaterasu omikami (Tensho daijin) in the event of tensonkorin (the descent to earth of the grandson of the sun goddess).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Three Sacred Treasures of the Imperial Family refer to a mirror, a sword and a jewel that are believed to have been granted by Amaterasu Omikami (also known as Tensho daijin or the &apos;Sun Goddess&apos;) to her grandson Ninigi during &apos;Tensonkorin&apos; when he descended from heaven to rule over the country.</e>
<cmt>refers→refer; sward→sword; eliminated comma after &quot;sword&quot;; changed &quot;omikami&quot; to &quot;Omikami&quot;; added &quot;also known as&quot; before &quot;Tensho daijin&quot;; added &quot;or the the &apos;Sun Goddess&apos;&quot;; changed &quot;in the event of&quot; to &quot;during&quot;; capitalized &quot;Tensonkorin&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Three Sacred Treasures of the Imperial Family refer to a mirror, a sword and a jewel that are believed to have been granted by Amaterasu Omikami (also known as Tensho daijin or the &apos;Sun Goddess&apos;) to her grandson Ninigi during &apos;Tensonkorin&apos; when he descended from heaven to rule over the country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>日本の歴代天皇が継承してきた三種の宝物である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These are three treasures handed down by successive emperors of Japan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These three treaures have been handed down by the emperors of Japan.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These three treasures have been handed down by the emperors of Japan.</e>
<cmt>treaures→treasures</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Outline</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Outline</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>統一用語より</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>神器とは神の依代（よりしろ）を意味する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The jingi (the sacred treasures) means &quot;deities&apos; yorishiro&quot;--objects or places where god are dwelling.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term Jingi (sacred treasures) means &quot;yorishiro of the gods&quot; (objects representative of a divine spirit).</e>
<cmt>god→gods; changed double hyphen to a description in parenthesis; changed &quot;deities&apos; yorishiro&quot; to &quot;yorishiro of the gods&quot;; changed description in parenthesis</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term Jingi (sacred treasures) means &quot;yorishiro of the gods&quot; (objects representative of a divine spirit).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>天皇の即位に際し、この神器の内、鏡と剣のレプリカ及び勾玉を所持することが日本の正統なる帝として皇位継承の際に代々伝えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Possessing the mirror, the sword replicas, and magadama, a comma-shaped bead among these treasures. has been recogniｚed as symbols to demonstrate authentic succession to the imperial throne when the emperor ascends the throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Possession of the mirror, the sword replica and the jewel is a recognized symbol, demonstrating authentic succession to the imperial throne by the emperor.</e>
<cmt>eliminated &quot;a comma-shaped bead&quot; since a better description comes shorty after describing it as a &quot;comma shaped jewel&quot;; fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Possession of the mirror, the sword replica and the jewel is a recognized symbol, demonstrating authentic succession to the imperial throne by the emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>但し過去には後鳥羽天皇など神器がない状態で即位したケースもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, some emperors such as Emperor Gotoba ascended the throne without the Three Sacred Treasures.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, since a number of emperors, such as Emperor Gotoba ascended the throne without the three sacred treasures, they are not necessarily essential for enthronement.</e>
<cmt>These two sentences seem to flow better as one, so I combined them;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, A number of emperors, such as Emperor Gotoba ascended the throne without the three sacred treasures.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>このように、必ずしも即位の絶対条件ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus the Three Sacred Treasures are not necessarily essential for enthronement.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus the Three Sacred Treasures are not necessarily essential for enthronement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, they are not necessarily essential for enthronement.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>三種の宝物とは、「八咫鏡」・「八尺瓊勾玉」・「天叢雲剣」（「草薙剣」）のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Three Treasures refer to &quot;Yata no Kagami&quot; (the eight-span mirror; one of the Imperial regalia), Yasakani no magatama (comma-shaped jewel, and theory of submerging Ama no Murakumo no Tsurugi Sword (Kusanagi no tsurugi).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Three Treasures refer to the &apos;Yata no Kagami&apos; (the eight-span mirror), the &apos;Yasakani no magatama&apos; (a comma-shaped jewel), and the &apos;Ama no Murakumo no Tsurugi&apos; (&apos;Kusanagi no tsurugi&apos;) (the sacred sword).</e>
<cmt>added closing parenthesis after &quot;jewel&quot;; eliminated &quot;one of the Imperial regalia&quot;; eliminated &quot;and theory of submerging&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Three Treasures refer to the &apos;Yata no Kagami&apos; (the eight-span mirror), the &apos;Yasakani no magatama&apos; (a comma-shaped jewel), and the &apos;Ama no Murakumo no Tsurugi&apos; (&apos;Kusanagi no tsurugi&apos;) (the sacred sword).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>神器という言い方が一般化したのは南北朝時代 (日本)ごろからと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the word &quot;jingi&quot; (the sacred treasures) became common around in the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the term &apos;Jingi&apos; became common around the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan).</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;in the Northern&quot; to &quot;in the period of the Northern&quot; to match the word list; eliminated (the sacred treasures);</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the term &apos;Jingi&apos; became common around the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>『古事記』では、天照大御神（あまてらすおおみかみ）が日子番能邇邇藝命（ひこほのににぎのみこと）に「八尺の勾璁（やさかのまがたま）、鏡、また草薙（くさなぎの）剣」を授ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Kojiki&quot; (the Records of Ancient Matters), Amaterasu Oomikami granted &quot;Yasaka no Magatama (sacred jade accessory),&quot; a mirror, and Kusanagi no Tsurugi (alternate name for Ama-no-Murakumo no Tsurugi, the sword of the Imperial regalia) to Hikoho no ninigi no mikoto.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the &quot;Kojiki&quot; (Records of Ancient Matters), Amaterasu Omikami (the Sun Goddess) granted the Yasaka no Magatama (the sacred jewel), the mirror and the Kusanagi no Tsurugi (another name for the Ama no Murakumo no Tsurugi) to Hikoho no Ninigi no mikoto.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;the&quot; before &quot;Kojiki&quot;; eliminated &quot;the&quot; before &quot;Records&quot;; added (the Sun Goddess) after Amaterasu Omikami; changed (sacred jade accessory) to (the sacred jewel); changed &quot;alternate name for&quot; to &quot;another name for&quot;; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the &quot;Kojiki&quot; (Records of Ancient Matters), Amaterasu Omikami (the Sun Goddess) granted the Yasaka no Magatama (the sacred jewel), the mirror and the Kusanagi no Tsurugi (another name for the Ama no Murakumo no Tsurugi) to Hikoho no Ninigi no mikoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>『日本書紀』本文には三種の神宝（神器）を授けた記事が無い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The main text of &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan) does not describe the grant of the Three Sacred Treasures.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the main text of &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), there is no article describing this grant of the Three Sacred Treasures.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;does not describe&quot; to &quot;there is no article describing&quot;; changed &quot;the grant&quot; to &quot;this grant&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the main text of &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), there is no article describing this grant of the Three Sacred Treasures.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>第一の一書に「天照大神、乃ち天津彦彦火瓊瓊杵尊（あまつひこひこほのににぎのみこと）に、八尺瓊の曲玉及び八咫鏡・草薙剣、三種（みくさ）の宝物（たから）を賜（たま）ふ」と記している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first &quot;alternate writing&quot; of Nihonshoki says, the Three Treasures--Yasakani no magatama (comma-shaped jewel), Yata no Kagami (the eight-span mirror; one of the Imperial regalia), Kusanagi no tsurugi--were granted by &quot;Amaterasu Omikami (the Sun Goddess), i.e. Amatsuhiko hikoho no ninigi no mikoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the first &quot;alternate writing&quot; of the Nihonshoki, it describes that the Mikusa no Takara (the Three Treasures)--the Yasakani no magatama (the sacred jewel), the Yata no Kagami (the eight-span mirror) and the Kusanagi no Tsurugi--were granted by Amaterasu Omikami, namely Amatsuhiko hikoho no ninigi no mikoto.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;In&quot;; added &quot;it describes that&quot; before &quot;the Three Treasures&quot;; changed &quot;i.e.&quot; to &quot;namely&quot;; fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the first &quot;alternate writing&quot; of the Nihonshoki, it describes that the Mikusa no Takara (the Three Treasures)--the Yasakani no magatama (the sacred jewel), the Yata no Kagami (the eight-span mirror) and the Kusanagi no Tsurugi--were granted by Amaterasu Omikami, namely Amatsuhiko hikoho no ninigi no mikoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="12">
<j>古代において、鏡、玉、剣の三種の組み合わせは天皇家だけに特有のものではなく、一般に支配者の象徴であったと考えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The combination of three items--a mirror, a sward, and a jewe--was not unique only to the Imperial family but regarded as the symbol of common rulers.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A combination of the three items--a mirror, a sword, and a jewel--was not unique only to the Imperial family but regarded as symbols common to all rulers.</e>
<cmt>sward→sword; jewe→jewel; changed &quot;symbol of common rulers&quot; to &quot;symbol common to all rulers&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A combination of the three items--a mirror, a sword, and a jewel--was not unique only to the Imperial family but regarded as symbols common to all rulers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>仲哀天皇の熊襲征伐の途次、岡県主の熊鰐、伊都県主の五十迹手らは、それぞれ白銅鏡、八尺瓊、十握剣を差し出して恭順の意を表している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Emperor Chuai expedited to conquer Kumaso (a tribe living in the ancient Kyushu district) led by Oka no Agatanushi (the ruler of Tsukushi area) and Itote led by Ito no Agatanushi (the ruler of Ito area) showed their allegiances by offering their Maso kagami (bronze mirror), Yasakani no magatama (comma-shaped jewel), and Totsuka-no-tsurugi Sword.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Emperor Chuai made an expedition to conquer the Kumaso (a tribe living in the ancient Kyushu district) led by the Oka no Agatanushi (ruler of the Tsukushi area) and Itote led by the Ito no Agatanushi (ruler of the Ito area), these leaders showed their allegiance by offering their Maso kagami (bronze mirror), Yasakani no magatama (comma-shaped jewel) and Totsuka no Tsurugi Sword.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;expedited&quot; to &quot;made an expedition&quot;; added &quot;the&quot; before &quot;Kumaso&quot;; fixed grammar; I am unclear on the meaning of &quot;五十迹手&quot; so it is difficult for me to properly fixed the part about &quot;Itote let by Ito no Agatanushi&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Emperor Chuai made an expedition to conquer the Kumaso (a tribe living in the ancient Kyushu district) led by the Oka no Agatanushi (ruler of the Tsukushi area) and Itote led by the Ito no Agatanushi (ruler of the Ito area), these leaders showed their allegiance by offering their Maso kagami (bronze mirror), Yasakani no magatama (comma-shaped jewel) and Totsuka no Tsurugi Sword.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>また景行天皇に服属した周防国娑麼の神夏磯媛も、八握剣、八咫鏡、八尺瓊を差し出している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kamunatsusohime in Suo Province&apos;s saba (the land under direct control of an emperor) that subjected to the Emperor Keiko offered his Yatsuka no Tsurugi (Yatsuka Sword), Yata no Kagami, and Yasakani.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Princess Kamunatsuso of the Suo Province&apos;s saba (land under direct control of the emperor) that showed allegiance to Emperor Keiko, also offered a Yatsuka no Tsurugi (Yatsuka Sword), Yata no Kagami (mirror) and Yasakani (jewel).</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;Kamunatsusohime&quot; to &quot;Princess Kamunatsuso&quot;; changed &quot;that subject to the Emperor Keiko&quot; to &quot;that showed allegiance to Emperor Keiko&quot;; added &quot;also&quot; to carry the meaning of &quot;も&quot;; added description for &quot;Kagami&quot; and &quot;Yasakani&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Princess Kamunatsuso of the Suo Province&apos;s saba (land under direct control of the emperor) that showed allegiance to Emperor Keiko, also offered a Yatsuka no Tsurugi (Yatsuka Sword), Yata no Kagami (mirror) and Yasakani (jewel).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>また壱岐市の原の辻遺跡では最古の鏡、玉、剣の組み合わせが出土されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Harunotsuji Ruins in Iki City yielded a combination of the oldest mirror, sward, and jewel.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Harunotsuji Ruins in Iki City, a combination of the oldest mirror, sword and jewel were excavated.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;In the&quot;; changed &quot;yielded&quot; to &quot;excavated&quot;; sward→sword; eliminated comma after &quot;sword&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Harunotsuji Ruins in Iki City, a combination of the oldest mirror, sword and jewel were excavated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="16">
<j>現在では八咫鏡は伊勢神宮の皇大神宮に、天叢雲剣は熱田神宮に神体として奉斎されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yata no Kagami and Ama no Murakumo no Tsurugi Sword are now dedicated as shintai (an object of worship housed in a Shinto shrine and believed to contain the spirit of a deity) to Kotai-jingu Shrine of Ise Jingu Shrine and Atsuta-jingu Shrine, respectively.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, the Yata no Kagami (mirror) is dedicated to the Kotai-jingu Shrine of Ise Jingu Shrine, and the Murakumo no Tsurugi Sword is dedicated to the Atsuta-jingu Shrine as a shintai (object of worship housed in a Shinto shrine and believed to contain the spirit of a deity).</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;now&quot; to &quot;Today&quot; and place at the beginning of the sentence; rearranged sentence to read more understandably</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, the Yata no Kagami (mirror) is dedicated to the Kotai-jingu Shrine of Ise Jingu Shrine, and the Murakumo no Tsurugi Sword is dedicated to the Atsuta-jingu Shrine as a shintai (object of worship housed in a Shinto shrine and believed to contain the spirit of a deity).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>八尺瓊勾玉は皇居の御所に安置されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasakani no magatama is stored in the residence of Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Yasakani no magatama (jewel) is stored in the residence of the Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;The&quot;; eliminated extra period; added &quot;the&quot; before &quot;Imperial Palace&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Yasakani no magatama (jewel) is stored in the residence of the Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="18">
<j>また皇居には八咫鏡と天叢雲剣の形代があると考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition it is believed that katashiro (representation of a sacred object) of Yata no Kagami and Ama no Murakumo no Tsurugi Sword are enshrined to the Imperial Palace; katashiro of Yata no Kagami is in kashikodokoro (a palace sanctuary) of the Three Shrines of the Imperial Court, and katashiro of Ama no Murakumo no Tsurugi Sword is in Kenji no Ma (hall of sacred sword and jewels) with Yasakani no magatama.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, it is believed that replicas of the Yata no Kagami (mirror) and the Ama no Murakumo no Tsurugi (sword) are in the Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処; changed &quot;katashiro (representation of a sacred object)&quot; to &quot;replica&quot; for easier understanding; split the sentence since the same objects are mentioned more than once in one, making it confusing;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, it is believed that replicas of the Yata no Kagami (mirror) and the Ama no Murakumo no Tsurugi (sword) are in the Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>八咫鏡の型代は宮中三殿の賢所に、天叢雲剣の形代は八尺瓊勾玉とともに御所の剣璽の間に安置されているとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The replica of the Yata no Kagami (mirror) is believed to be in the Kashikodokoro (a palace sanctuary) of the Three Shrines of the Imperial Court, and the replica of the Ama no Murakumo no Tsurugi (sword) is in the Kenji no Ma (hall of the sacred sword and jewels) along with the Yasakani no magatama (jewel).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処; changed &quot;katashiro&quot; to &quot;replica&quot; in both cases; added English equivalent to each item in parenthesis;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The replica of the Yata no Kagami (mirror) is believed to be in the Kashikodokoro (a palace sanctuary) of the Three Shrines of the Imperial Court, and the replica of the Ama no Murakumo no Tsurugi (sword) is in the Kenji no Ma (hall of the sacred sword and jewels) along with the Yasakani no magatama (jewel).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="20">
<j>儒学伝来以後、鏡は「知」、勾玉は「仁」、剣は「勇」というように、三種の神器は三徳を表わすという解釈もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Confucianism was introduced into Japan, some have interpreted that the Three Sacred Treasures of the Imperial Family represent santoku (three primary virtues): the mirror, sward, and jewel were symbols of a &quot;valor,&quot; &quot;wisdom,&quot; and &quot;benevolence,&quot; respectively.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the introduction of Confucianism to Japan, some have interpreted the Three Sacred Treasures as representations of santoku (the three primary virtues): the mirror representing &quot;wisdom,&quot; the jewel representing &quot;benevolence,&quot; and the sword representing &quot;valor.&quot;</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;Since&quot; to &quot;After&quot; for &quot;以後&quot;; changed &quot;Confucianism was introduced&quot; to &quot;the introduction of Confucianism&quot;; changed &quot;into Japan&quot; to &quot;to Japan&quot;; fixed spacing; added &quot;the&quot; before &quot;three&quot;; sward→sword; changed word order to read more smoothly and understandably</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the introduction of Confucianism to Japan, some have interpreted the Three Sacred Treasures as representations of santoku (the three primary virtues): the mirror representing &quot;wisdom,&quot; the jewel representing &quot;benevolence,&quot; and the sword representing &quot;valor.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="21">
<j>なお、これら3器を「三種の神器」と総称する用例は、『平家物語』、『神皇正統記』などに見える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The way of referring to these three items as &quot;Three Sacred Treasures of the Imperial Family&quot; is found in books such as &quot;The Tale of the Heike&quot; and &quot;Jinno Shotoki&quot; (A Chronicle of Gods and Sovereigns).</e>
<cmt>「なお」は特に意味がないので訳し出ししていません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The way of referring to these three items as &quot;Sanshu no Jingi&quot; (Three Sacred Treasures of the Imperial Family) is found in books such as &quot;The Tale of the Heike&quot; and &quot;Jinno Shotoki&quot; (A Chronicle of Gods and Sovereigns).</e>
<cmt>fixed spacing; added &quot;Sanshu no Jingi&quot; and moved the English equivalent into parenthesis to work as a description;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The way of referring to these three items as &quot;Sanshu no Jingi&quot; (Three Sacred Treasures of the Imperial Family) is found in books such as &quot;The Tale of the Heike&quot; and &quot;Jinno Shotoki&quot; (A Chronicle of Gods and Sovereigns).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>また『神皇正統記』では、「三種の神宝（さんしゅのしんぽう・みくさのかむだから）」とも称される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Jinno Shotoki&quot; also names these items &quot;Sanshuno Shinbo or Mikusa No kamudakara.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Jinno Shotoki&quot; also names these items &quot;Sanshuno Shinbo&quot; and &quot;Mikusa no Kamudakara.&quot;</e>
<cmt>added &quot;The&quot;; changed quotation marks to be two separate terms rather than one; made &quot;no&quot; lowercase; capitalized &quot;Kamudakara&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &quot;Jinno Shotoki&quot; also names these items &quot;Sanshuno Shinbo&quot; and &quot;Mikusa no Kamudakara.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>各神器と伝承</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Each Sacred Treasures and Legend</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The legend behind each of the Jingi (the Three Sacred Treasures)</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;Sacred Treasures&quot; to &quot;Jingi&quot; and added description; fixed to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The legend behind each of the Jingi (the Three Sacred Treasures)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="23">
<j>記紀の伝承では、三種の神器はアマテラスの神代（よりしろ）として天孫降臨の際に天照大神よりニニギに授けられたとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiki (the Kojiki and Nihonshoki) legends say that Amaterasu Omikami granted Ninigi the Three Sacred Treasures of the Imperial Family as yorishiro in the event of tensonkorin (the descent to earth of the grandson of the sun goddess).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The legends described in the Kojiki and the Nihonshoki say that Amaterasu Omikami (the Sun Goddess) granted the &apos;Sanshu no Jingi&apos; (three sacred objects) to her grandson Ninigi as yorishiro (objects representative of a divine spirit) during &apos;Tensonkorin&apos; where he descended to earth in order to rule over the country.</e>
<cmt>eliminated &quot;Kiki&quot; and moved &quot;Kojiki and Nihonshoki&quot; outside of parenthesis; added description for &quot;Amaterasu Omikami&quot;; changed &quot;the Three Sacred Treasures of the Imperial Family&quot; to &quot;the Sanshu no Jingi&quot; and added description;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The legends described in the Kojiki and the Nihonshoki say that Amaterasu Omikami (the Sun Goddess) granted the &apos;Sanshu no Jingi&apos; (three sacred objects) to her grandson Ninigi as yorishiro (objects representative of a divine spirit) during &apos;Tensonkorin&apos; where he descended to earth in order to rule over the country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>八咫鏡（やたのかがみ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yata no Kagami</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yata no Kagami (mirror)</e>
<cmt>added (mirror)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yata no Kagami (mirror)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="24">
<j>詳細は八咫鏡を参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Refer to Yata no Kagami Section for details.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Refer to the section on Yata no Kagami for details.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Refer to the section on Yata no Kagami for details.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="25">
<j>日本神話では、天照大神が天岩戸に隠れた岩戸隠れの際、イシコリドメが作ったという鏡。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Japanese Mythology, the mirror was made by Ishikoridome in the event of Iwato-gakure in which Amaterasu Omikami, the sun goddess, hid herself in Ama no iwato (Cave of heaven).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Japanese mythology, the mirror was created by the god named Ishikoridome during the event of Iwato-gakure (literally &quot;hiding in Iwato) in which Amaterasu Omikami hid herself in the Ama no Iwato (literally &quot;the cave of the sun god&quot; or &quot;heavenly rock cave&quot;).</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;made&quot; to &quot;created&quot;; added &quot;the god&quot; before &quot;Ishikoridome&quot;; changed &quot;in&quot; to &quot;during&quot; before &quot;the event&quot;; added description for &quot;Iwato-gakure&quot;; added &quot;the&quot; before &quot;Ama no Iwato&quot;; changed description for &quot;Ama no Iwato&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Japanese mythology, the mirror was created by the god named Ishikoridome during the event of Iwato-gakure (literally &quot;hiding in Iwato) in which Amaterasu Omikami hid herself in the Ama no Iwato (literally &quot;the cave of the sun god&quot; or &quot;heavenly rock cave&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>天照大神が岩戸を細めに開けた時、この鏡で天照大神自身を映し、興味を持たせて外に引き出し、そして再び世は明るくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Amaterasu Omikami opened the rock a little, this mirror reflected her face to draw her attention, successfully making her come out.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Amaterasu made a small opening in the rock, the mirror reflected her face, drawing her attention and successfully making her come out of the cave, thus bringing light back to the world.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;opened the rock a little&quot; to &quot;made a small opening in the rock&quot;; added &quot;of the cave&quot;; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Amaterasu made a small opening in the rock, the mirror reflected her face, drawing her attention and successfully making her come out of the cave, thus bringing light back to the world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>のち鏡は天照大神が瓊瓊杵尊に授けたといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amaterasu Omikami is said to have later granted the mirror to Ninigi-no-mikoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Amaterasu Omikami later granted the mirror to her grandson Ninigi-no-mikoto.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;her grandson&quot; before &quot;Ninigi&quot;; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Amaterasu Omikami later granted the mirror to her grandson Ninigi-no-mikoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>現在は伊勢神宮の皇大神宮に奉斎されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is now dedicate to Kotai-jingu Shrine of Ise Jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Currently the mirror is an offering at the Kotai Jingu Shrine of Ise Jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;It is now&quot; to &quot;Currently&quot;; changed &quot;Kotai-jingu&quot; to &quot;Kotai Jingu&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Currently the mirror is an offering at the Kotai Jingu Shrine of Ise Jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>八尺瓊勾玉（やさかにのまがたま）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasakani no magatama</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasakani no magatama (jewel)</e>
<cmt>added (jewel)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasakani no magatama (jewel)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="29">
<j>詳細は八尺瓊勾玉を参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Refer to Yasakani no magatama Section for details.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Refer to the section on Yasakani no magatama for details.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Refer to the section on Yasakani no magatama for details.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="30">
<j>八坂瓊曲玉とも書く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also written as &quot;八坂瓊曲玉.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasakani no magatama &apos;八尺瓊勾玉&apos; is also sometimes written as &apos;八坂瓊曲玉.&apos;</e>
<cmt>added kanji characters of the first reading so that a comparison can be made with the second way to write the term</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasakani no magatama &apos;八尺瓊勾玉&apos; is also sometimes written as &apos;八坂瓊曲玉.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>大きな玉で作った勾玉である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a magadama made of a large bead.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The magatama was made in the shape of a large bead.</e>
<cmt>magadama→magatama; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The magatama was made in the shape of a large bead.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>一説に、八尺の緒に繋いだ勾玉ともされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some suggest that the magadama is connected to an eight-shaku long strap.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has been suggested that the magatama is connected to a strap with a length of eight aka (&apos;aka&apos; is a unit of measurement that was used in ancient times; eight aka is about 1.4 meters long).</e>
<cmt>magadama→magatama; changed &quot;eight-shaku&quot; to &quot;eight aka&quot; and added description for &quot;aka&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has been suggested that the magatama is connected to a strap with a length of eight saka (&apos;saka&apos; is a unit of measurement that was used in ancient times; eight aka is about 1.4 meters long).</e>
<cmt>aka→saka</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>岩戸隠れの際に玉祖命が作り、八咫鏡とともにサカキの木に掛けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was made by Tamanooya no Mikoto and hung on a branch of persimmon tree in the event of Iwato-gakure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The jewel was created by the god Tama-no-oya-no-Mikoto and hung on a sakaki tree (a species of evergreen sacred to Shinto) along with the Yata no Kagami (mirror) when Amaterasu hid in the Ama no Iwato (cave of the sun god).</e>
<cmt>fixed spacing; changed &quot;It&quot; to &quot;The jewel&quot;; changed &quot;made&quot; to &quot;created&quot;; added &quot;the god&quot; before &quot;Tamanooya&quot;; added hyphens in &quot;Tama-no-oya&quot;; changed &quot;persimmon tree&quot; to &quot;sakaki tree&quot; for &quot;サカキの木&quot;; added &quot;along with the Yata no Kagami (mirror) for &quot;八咫鏡とともに&quot;; since there is no article at all with the title of &quot;Iwato-gakure&quot; I thought it would be better to just explain it this time, so I changed it to &quot;when Amaterasu...&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The jewel was created by the god Tama-no-oya-no-Mikoto and hung on a sakaki tree (a species of evergreen sacred to Shinto) along with the Yata no Kagami (mirror) when Amaterasu hid in the Ama no Iwato (cave of the sun god).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>天叢雲剣（あめのむらくものつるぎ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ama no Murakumo no Tsurugi Sword</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ama no Murakumo no Tsurugi (sword)</e>
<cmt>moved &quot;Sword&quot; into parenthesis and made lowercase</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ama no Murakumo no Tsurugi (sword)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="34">
<j>詳細は天叢雲剣を参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Refer to Ama no Murakumo no Tsurugi Sword Section for details.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Refer to the section on Ama no Murakumo no Tsurugi Sword for details.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Refer to the section on Ama no Murakumo no Tsurugi Sword for details.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="35">
<j>草薙剣（くさなぎのつるぎ）とも称される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called Kusanagi no tsurugi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sword is also called Kusanagi no Tsurugi.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;It&quot; to &quot;The sword&quot;; capitalized &quot;Tsurugi&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sword is also called Kusanagi no Tsurugi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>記紀神話ではスサノオが出雲・簸川上（ひのかわかみ）で倒した八岐大蛇の尾から出てきたとし、その時の名前は都牟刈の太刀（偉大な力を持つ太刀）であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiki-shinwa (the Kojiki, Nihonshoki and mythology) say that it came out of the tail of the big snake having eight heads (Yamata-no-Orochi) killed by Susano (Deity in Japanese Mythology) and that it was named Tsumukari no Tachi (Tsumukari Sword) (a sward having a great power) at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the &apos;Kojiki&apos;, the &apos;Nihonshoki&apos; and Japanese mythology (&apos;Kiki-shinwa&apos; for short), it is said that the sword came out of the tail of a giant, eight-headed snake (Yamata-no-Orochi) that was killed by the god Susanoo and it was then that it was named Tsumukari no Tachi (Tsumukari Sword) (a sword having great power).</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;Kiki-shinwa&quot; to &quot;the Kojiki, the Nihonshoki and Japanese mythology&quot; and used &apos;Kiki-shinwa&apos; as a description in parenthesis; changed &quot;Susano&quot; to &quot;Susanoo&quot; for consistency; sward→sword; fixed grammar to read more naturally;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the &apos;Kojiki,&apos; the &apos;Nihonshoki&apos; and Japanese mythology (&apos;Kiki-shinwa&apos; for short), it is said that the sword came out of the tail of a giant, eight-headed snake (Yamata-no-Orochi) that was killed by the god Susanoo and it was then that it was named Tsumukari no Tachi (Tsumukari Sword) (a sword having great power).</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>出雲国風土記では、出雲国意宇郡母里郷（現；島根県安来市）にてオロチ退治が行われたともされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Izumo no kuni fudoki (the topography of Izumo Province) describes that Orochi (eight forked great serpent) was exterminated in Mori-go, Ou-gun, Izumo Province (now Yasugi City, Shimane Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the Izumo no kuni fudoki (topography of Izumo Province), Orochi (the eight forked great serpent) was vanquished in Mori-go, Ou-gun, Izumo Province (now Yasugi City, Shimane Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;exterminated&quot; to &quot;vanquished&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the Izumo no kuni fudoki (topography of Izumo Province), Orochi (the eight forked great serpent) was vanquished in Mori-go, Ou-gun, Izumo Province (now Yasugi City, Shimane Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>剣は須佐之男命から天照大神に奉納され、天皇家に天照大神の神体として八咫鏡とともに手渡された事になっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that the sword was offered by Susanoo no mikoto to Amaterasu Omikami (the Sun Goddess) and then handed down to the Imperial family along with Yata no Kagami as the shintai (an object of worship housed in a Shinto shrine and believed to contain the spirit of a deity) of Amaterasu Omikami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that the sword was offered by Susanoo no mikoto to Amaterasu Omikami and then handed down to the Imperial family along with the Yata no Kagami (mirror) as shintai (objects of worship housed in a Shinto shrine and believed to contain the spirit of a deity) of Amaterasu.</e>
<cmt>added (mirror) after &quot;Kagami&quot;; eliminated &quot;the&quot; before &quot;shintai&quot;; eliminated &quot;Omikami&quot; at the end of the sentence to reduce redundancy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that the sword was offered by Susanoo no mikoto to Amaterasu Omikami and then handed down to the Imperial family along with the Yata no Kagami (mirror) as shintai (objects of worship housed in a Shinto shrine and believed to contain the spirit of a deity) of Amaterasu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>一説には鍛冶の神である天目一箇命（アメノマヒトツノミコト）が作ったと言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some suggest that Amenomahitotsu no mikoto, the blacksmith god, made it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are some who suggest that the blacksmith god Ame-no-mahitotsu no mikoto made the sword.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally; added hyphens in &quot;Ame-no-mahitotsu&quot; for easier reading;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are some who suggest that the blacksmith god Ame-no-mahitotsu no mikoto made the sword.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="40">
<j>皇居内に天照大神の御神体として八咫鏡とともに祭られていたが、崇神天皇（伝紀元前148年-紀元前30年）の時代に皇女豊鋤入姫命により八咫鏡とともに皇居の外に祀るようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although once enshrined in the Imperial Palace as the shintai of Amaterasu Omikami, the sword started to be enshrined outside the Imperial Palace along with Yata no Kagami by order of Princess Toyosukiirihime no mikoto.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although it was once enshrined in the Imperial Palace as the shintai of Amaterasu Omikami, the sword was enshrined outside of the Imperial Palace along with the Yata no Kagami (mirror) by order of Princess Toyosukiirihime no mikoto.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;the sword started to be&quot; to &quot;the sword was&quot;; added (mirror) after &quot;Kagami&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it was once enshrined in the Imperial Palace as the shintai of Amaterasu Omikami, during the reign of Emperor Sujin (reported 148 B.C.-30 B.C.), the sword was enshrined outside of the Imperial Palace along with the Yata no Kagami (mirror) by order of Princess Toyosukiirihime no mikoto.</e>
<cmt>「崇神天皇（伝紀元前148年-紀元前30年）の時代に」を補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>途中で垂仁天皇（伝紀元前69年-70年）の皇女倭姫命に引き継がれ、あわせて約60年をかけて現在の伊勢神宮の皇大神宮（内宮）に落ち着いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It took a total of sixty years that it was handed to Yamatohime no mikoto, a princess of Emperor Suinin (reported 69B.C. to 70B.C.) and finally enshrined in the current Kotai-jingu Shrine (Naiku) of Ise Jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It took a total of sixty years before it was handed down to Yamatohime no mikoto, a princess of Emperor Suinin (reported 69B.C. to 70B.C.) and finally enshrined in the current Kotai-jingu Shrine (Naiku) of Ise Jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;that&quot; to &quot;before&quot; after &quot;sixty years&quot;; added &quot;down&quot; after &quot;handed&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It took a total of sixty years before it was handed down to Yamatohime no mikoto, a princess of Emperor Suinin (reported 69B.C. to 70B.C.) and finally enshrined in the current Kotai-jingu Shrine (Naiku) of Ise Jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>その後、倭姫命から、蛮族の討伐に東へ向かうヤマトタケルに渡された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamatohime no mikoto later handed it to Yamato Takeru (no mikoto) who set off for the east to suppress barbarian tribes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Princess Yamatohime no mikoto later handed it to Yamato Takeru no mikoto, who set off for the east to suppress barbarian tribes.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;Princess&quot;; moved &quot;no mikoto&quot; outside of parenthesis; added comma after &quot;mikoto&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Princess Yamatohime no mikoto later handed it to Yamato Takeru no mikoto, who set off for the east to suppress barbarian tribes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>この時、倭建命が野火攻めから脱出する為に、この太刀で草を薙いだ事が草薙剣の名前の由来とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some suggest that, at that time, Kusanagi no tsurugi named after the sword with which Yamato Takeru no mikoto cut down grasses when he escaped from burning attack in the fields.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has been suggested that because Yamato Takeru used the sword at that time to cut down grass in order to escape from an attack of burning fields, the sword was given the name Kusanagi no Tsurugi (literally &quot;grass-mowing sword&quot;).</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;Some suggest that&quot; to &quot;It has been suggested that&quot;; added literal translation for &quot;Kusanagi no Tsurugi&quot;; fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has been suggested that because Yamato Takeru used the sword at that time to cut down grass in order to escape from an attack of burning fields, the sword was given the name Kusanagi no Tsurugi (literally &quot;grass-mowing sword&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>しかし、クサは臭、ナギは蛇の意で、原義は「蛇の剣」の説が有力。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, a more convincing suggestion is that &quot;kusa&quot; comes from &quot;smell,&quot; and &quot;nagi&quot; from a snake, thus originally meaning &quot;a snake&apos;s sword.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A more convincing theory, however, is that &quot;kusa&quot; stands for &quot;smell&quot; (or &quot;having the aura of&quot;), and &quot;nagi&quot; stands for &quot;snake,&quot; therefore the original meaning is &quot;the sword of a snake.&quot;</e>
<cmt>moved &quot;however&quot; to the middle of the sentence; added an extra description for &quot;kusa&quot; for a clearer understanding; fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A more convincing theory, however, is that &quot;kusa&quot; stands for &quot;smell&quot; (or &quot;having the aura of&quot;), and &quot;nagi&quot; stands for &quot;snake,&quot; therefore the original meaning is &quot;the sword of a snake.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>倭建命が病死したのち熱田神宮に祀られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Yamato Takeru no mikoto died of illness, the sword was dedicated to Atsuta-jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Yamato Takeru no mikoto died of illness, the sword was dedicated to Atsuta-jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Yamato Takeru no mikoto died of illness, the sword was dedicated to Atsuta-jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="46">
<j>天皇の即位儀礼の際に三種の神宝（神器）を奉る儀礼が行われていたのはいつ頃からか。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">About when was it that the enthronement ceremony to grant three kinds of sacred treasures (jingi) or items equivalent to the treasures started ?</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At what point did they start having the ritual of presenting the Three Sacred Treasures (Jingi) to the Emperor during the enthronement ceremony?</e>
<cmt>eliminated &quot;or items equivalent to the treasures&quot; since I do not see corresponding Japanese for this part; capitalized &quot;Jingi&quot;; rearranged sentence and fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At what point did they start having the ritual of presenting the Three Sacred Treasures (Jingi) to the Emperor during the enthronement ceremony?</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>『古事記』には即位に際して神宝（神器）またはそれに類する品の宝剣に関する記事はない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">No description is found in &quot;Kojiki&quot; regarding sacred treasures (jingi) or the equivalent hoken (treasured sword) for enthronement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">No description is found in &quot;Kojiki&quot; regarding sacred treasures (Jingi) or the equivalent hoken (treasured sword) for enthronement.</e>
<cmt>capitalized &quot;Jingi&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">No description is found in &quot;Kojiki&quot; regarding sacred treasures (Jingi) or the equivalent hoken (treasured sword) for enthronement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>『日本書紀』には以下のように見える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Chronicles of Japan&quot; describes as follows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following can be see in the &quot;Nihon Shoki&quot; (&quot;Chronicles of Japan&quot;).</e>
<cmt>fixed to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following can be see in the &quot;Nihon Shoki&quot; (&quot;Chronicles of Japan&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="49">
<j>允恭天皇元年十二月の条、「是に、群臣、大きに喜びて、即日に、天皇の璽付（みしるし）を捧げて、再拝みてうえる」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The article of December of the first year of Emperor Ingyo states, &apos;at this moment, people felt great happiness and immediately they presented the Emperor&apos;s treasures and admired them.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An article from December of the first year of Emperor Ingyo states, &apos;At this moment, the crowd of retainers felt great happiness, immediately presenting the Emperor&apos;s treasures and admiring them.&apos;</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;people&quot; to &quot;crowd of retainers&quot; for &quot;群臣&quot;; fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An article from December of the first year of Emperor Ingyo states, &apos;At this moment, the crowd of retainers felt great happiness, immediately presenting the Emperor&apos;s treasures and admiring them.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="50">
<j>清寧天皇前記十二月の条、「大伴室屋大連、臣・連等を率て、璽（しるし）を皇太子に奉る」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The article of December of Emperor Seinei states, &apos;OTOMO no Muroya no omuraji led omi, muraji, etc. and presented the treasures to Imperial prince.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「前記」は定訳不明ですので訳出しておりません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An article from December of Emperor Seinei states, &apos;The Omuraji (the highest administrator of the ancient Japanese Imperial Court) OTOMO no Muroya led the Omi (retainers with one of the two highest hereditary titles), the Muraji (retainers with one of the two higheest hereditary titles) etc., and presented the treasures to the Imperial prince.&apos;</e>
<cmt>found definition for 大連 at: &lt;http://dictionary.goo.ne.jp/leaf/jn/23808/m1u/%E5%A4%A7%E9%80%A3/&gt;; added description for &quot;Omi&quot; and &quot;Muraji&quot;; changed &quot;etc&quot; to &quot;and others&quot;; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An article from December of Emperor Seinei states, &apos;The Omuraji (the highest administrator of the ancient Japanese Imperial Court) OTOMO no Muroya led the Omi (retainers with one of the two highest hereditary titles), the Muraji (retainers with one of the two highest hereditary titles) etc., and presented the treasures to the Imperial prince.&apos;</e>
<cmt>higheest →highest</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="51">
<j>顕宗天皇前記十二月野上、「百官、大きに会へり。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The article of December of Emperor Kenzo states, &apos;The vassals met an emperor and the Imperial Prince Oke took the sacred treasures and placed them on the emperor&apos;s throne.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「大きに会へり」を天皇にあったと解釈しています。「前記」は定訳不明ですので訳出しておりません。 一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An article from December of Emperor Kenzo states, &apos;The vassals met with the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処; fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An article from December of Emperor Kenzo states, &apos;The vassals met with the Emperor.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&apos;を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>「皇太子億計（おけ）、天子の璽（みしるし）を取りて、天皇の坐に置きたまふ」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Prince Oke took the sacred treasures and placed them on the emperor&apos;s throne.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Prince Oke took the sacred treasures and placed them on the emperor&apos;s throne.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&apos;を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="53">
<j>継体天皇元年二月の条、「大伴金村大連、乃ち跪きて天子の鏡（みかがみ）剣（みはかし）の璽符（みしるし）を上りてまつる」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The article of February of the first year of Emperor Keitai states, &apos;OTOMO no Kanamura no omuraji knelt down and presented the sacred treasures of the mirror and the sword.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An article from February of the first year of Emperor Keitai states, &quot;The Omuraji OTOMO no Kanamura knelt down and presented the sacred treasures of the mirror and the sword.&apos;</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;OTOMO no Kanamura no omuraji&quot; to &quot;The Omuraji OTOMO no Kanamura&quot;; fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An article from February of the first year of Emperor Keitai states, &quot;The Omuraji OTOMO no Kanamura knelt down and presented the sacred treasures of the mirror and the sword.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="54">
<j>宣化天皇前記十二月の条、「群臣、奏して、剣（みはかし）鏡（みかがみ）を武小広国押す盾尊に上りて、即天皇之位さしむ」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The article of December of Emperor Senka states, &apos;The vassals presented the sword and the mirror to Takeohirokuni Oshitatenomikoto which immediately made him an emperor.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「前記」は定訳不明ですので訳出しておりません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An article from December of Emperor Senka states, &apos;The vassals presented the sword and the mirror to Takeohirokuni Oshitate no mikoto which immediately made him an emperor.&apos;</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;Oshitatenomikoto&quot; to &quot;Oshitate no mikoto&quot; for easier reading; fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An article from December of Emperor Senka states, &apos;The vassals presented the sword and the mirror to Takeohirokuni Oshitate no mikoto which immediately made him an emperor.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="55">
<j>推古天皇前記十一月の条、「百寮、表を上りて勧進る。三に至りて乃ち従ひたまふ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The article of November of Emperor Suiko state, &apos;Many vassals went out to ask for donation for a temple; 三に至りて乃ち従ひたまふ.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処；　「前記」は定訳不明ですので訳出しておりません。「三に至りて乃ち従ひたまふ」の解釈が困難なため訳出できず。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An article from November of Emperor Suiko states, &apos;Many vassals went out to ask for donations for a temple. 三に至りて乃ち従ひたまふ.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処; split the cells in accordance with the Japanese sentences; fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An article from November of Emperor Suiko states, &apos;Many vassals went out to ask for donations for a temple. 三に至りて乃ち従ひたまふ.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&apos;を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>「因りて天皇の璽印（みしるし）を奉る」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are presented the sacred treasures of the emperor.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As such, they are presented the sacred treasures of the emperor.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処; added &quot;As such&quot; for &quot;因りて&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As such, they are presented the sacred treasures of the emperor.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&apos;を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="57">
<j>舒明天皇元年正月の条、「大臣及び郡卿、共に天皇の璽印（みしるし）を以て、田村皇子に奉る」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The article of January of the first year of Emperor Jomei states, &apos;Ministers and vassals presented the sacred treasures to Imperial prince Tamura.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An article from January of the first year of Emperor Jomei states, &apos;Ministers and vassals presented the sacred treasures to Imperial Prince Tamura.&apos;</e>
<cmt>capitalized &quot;Prince&quot;; fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An article from January of the first year of Emperor Jomei states, &apos;Ministers and vassals presented the sacred treasures to Imperial Prince Tamura.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="58">
<j>つぎは、即位儀礼の時ではないが、関連記事がみえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following are descriptions not on the enthronement ceremony but related articles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following are descriptions that are not on the enthronement ceremony but are related articles.</e>
<cmt>fixed to read more grammatically</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following are descriptions that are not on the enthronement ceremony but are related articles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="59">
<j>孝徳天皇前記六月、「天豊財重日足姫天皇、璽綬（みしるし）を授けたまひて、位を禅りたまふ」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The article of June of Emperor Kotoku states, &apos;Ametoyotakaraikashihitarashihime was presented the sacred treasures and conferred an emperess.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An article from June of Emperor Kotoku states, &apos;Princess Ametoyotakaraikashihitarashihime was presented with the sacred treasures and conferred an empress.&apos;</e>
<cmt>added &quot;Princess&quot;; emperess→empress; fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An article from June of Emperor Kotoku states, &apos;Princess Ametoyotakaraikashihitarashihime was presented with the sacred treasures and conferred an empress.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="60">
<j>封建の品を璽・璽符・璽印という漠然とし書き方をしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The feudal items are vaguely defined as &quot;璽,&quot; &quot;璽符,&quot; and &quot;璽印.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The feudal items are vaguely defined as &quot;emperor&apos;s seal&quot; &apos;璽&apos; (read as &quot;ji&quot;), &quot;imperial seal&quot; &apos;璽符&apos; (read as &quot;jifu&quot;), and &quot;imperial seal&quot; &apos;璽印&apos; (read as &quot;inji&quot;).</e>
<cmt>added English equivalents and their readings to the characters;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The feudal items are vaguely defined as &quot;emperor&apos;s seal&quot; &apos;璽&apos; (read as &quot;ji&quot;), &quot;imperial seal&quot; &apos;璽符&apos; (read as &quot;jifu&quot;), and &quot;imperial seal&quot; &apos;璽印&apos; (read as &quot;inji&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>鏡と剣との名をあげているのは、継体紀と宣化紀の二つのみである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Only two sections, the Keitai section and the Senka section, specifically define them as a mirror and a sword.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Keitai section and the Senka section are the only two sections that specifically define the items as a mirror and a sword.</e>
<cmt>rearranged sentence to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Keitai section and the Senka section are the only two sections that specifically define the items as a mirror and a sword.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>宝物は元は二つであったのではないかという疑問が出てくる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A doubt arises that the treasures may have been of two kinds.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This raises the question about whether or not the treasures might be of different origins.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;kinds&quot; to &quot;origins&quot; for &quot;元&quot;; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This raises the question about whether or not the treasures might be of different origins.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="63">
<j>690年の持統天皇の即位の際に臣下の忌部氏が剣と鏡の2種を献上している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 690, the Inbe clan, Empress Jito&apos;s subject, offered two kinds--a sword and a mirror--when Empress Jito ascended the throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 690 when Empress Jito ascended the throne, the Inbe clan as retainers presented two forms of treasure: a sword and a mirror.</e>
<cmt>fixed to read more grammatically</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 690 when Empress Jito ascended the throne, the Inbe clan as retainers presented two forms of treasure: a sword and a mirror.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>『日本書紀』持統天皇四年（690）正月の条に、「物部麿朝臣大盾を樹て、神祇伯（じんぎのかみ）中臣大嶋朝臣天神の寿詞（よごと）を読み、畢（おわ）りて忌部宿禰色夫知神璽の剣鏡を皇后に奉上り、皇后天皇の位に即く」とある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The article of January of the fourth year of Empress Jito (690) in the &quot;Nihon shoki&quot; states, &apos;MONONOBE no Maro Ason held up the large sheild; NAKATOMI no Oshima no Ason who was Jinginokami read the shinto prayers; and after that INBE no Sukune no Shikobuchi presented the sacred treasures of the sword and the mirror to the Imperial princess and she was conferred an empress.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An article from January of the fourth year of Empress Jito (690) in the &quot;Nihon Shoki&quot; states, &apos;MONONOBE no Maro Ason held up the large shield; NAKATOMI no Oshima no Ason, who was Jinginokami, read the Shinto prayers; afterwards INBE no Sukune no Shikobuchi presented the sacred treasures of the sword and the mirror to the Imperial princess and she was conferred an empress.&apos;</e>
<cmt>sheild→shield; changed &quot;and after that&quot; to &quot;afterwards&quot;; fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An article from January of the fourth year of Empress Jito (690) in the &quot;Nihon Shoki&quot; states, &apos;MONONOBE no Maro Ason held up the large shield; NAKATOMI no Oshima no Ason, who was Jinginokami, read the Shinto prayers; afterwards INBE no Sukune no Shikobuchi presented the sacred treasures of the sword and the mirror to the Imperial princess and she was conferred an empress.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>後に中臣氏が3種説を主張して勾玉が加わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The magadama was added to the treasures when Nakatomi clan claims three kinds.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The magatama was added to the treasures when the Nakatomi clan claimed there were three kinds.</e>
<cmt>magadama→magatama; added &quot;the&quot; before &quot;Nakatomi&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The magatama was added to the treasures when the Nakatomi clan claimed there were three kinds.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="66">
<j>尚、以下の説は神器が宮中にあったという説を元にしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following is based on the belief that the jingi were in the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>「尚」は、特に意味がないので訳し出ししていません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following is based on the theory that the Jingi were in the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;belief&quot; to &quot;theory&quot; for &quot;説&quot;; capitalized &quot;Jingi&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following is based on the theory that the Jingi were in the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>伊勢神宮などでは神器が持ち出されたという記録はない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is no record on any of the jingi that was carried away from Ise Jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is no record of any of the Jingi being carried away from Ise Jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>fixed to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is no record of any of the Jingi being carried away from Ise Jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="68">
<j>1185年（元暦2年）の壇ノ浦の戦いで平氏と源義経率いる源氏が戦った際に、安徳天皇が入水し草薙剣も赤間関（関門海峡）に水没したとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the naval battle of Danno-ura in 1185 between the Taira clan and the Minamoto clan led by MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune, the Kusanagi no tsurugi is said to have been submerged in Akamagaseki (Kanmon-kaikyo Strait) when Emperor Antoku sank in the sea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the naval battle of Dan-no-ura in 1185 between the Taira clan and the Minamoto clan, it is said that the Kusanagi no Tsurugi (sword) sank into the sea with Emperor Antoku in Akamagaseki (Kanmon-kaikyo Strait).</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;Danno-ura&quot; to &quot;Dan-no-ura&quot;; capitalized &quot;Tsurugi&quot;; added (sword) after &quot;Tsurugi&quot;; fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the naval battle of Dan-no-ura in 1185 between the Taira clan and the Minamoto clan, it is said that the Kusanagi no Tsurugi (sword) sank into the sea with Emperor Antoku in Akamagaseki (Kanmon-kaikyo Strait).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>またこの時後鳥羽天皇は三種の神器が無い状態にも関わらず後白河法皇の院宣を根拠として即位している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also the Emperor Gotoba ascended the throne despite the absence of the Three Sacred Treasures of the Imperial Family, giving a ground based on the inzen (a decree from the retired Emperor) of the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also during this time, despite the absence of the Three Sacred Treasures, Emperor Gotoba ascended the throne based on the inzen (imperial decree) of the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;during this time&quot; after &quot;Also&quot;; eliminated &quot;the&quot; before &quot;Emperor Gotoba&quot;; eliminated &quot;of the Imperial Family&quot;; eliminated &quot;giving a ground&quot; since it did not make any sense to me; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also during this time, despite the absence of the Three Sacred Treasures, Emperor Gotoba ascended the throne based on the inzen (imperial decree) of the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="70">
<j>足利尊氏が後醍醐天皇の建武の新政に離反し、1336年（延元元年/建武 (日本)3年）に光明天皇の北朝 (日本)を立てて京都に室町幕府を開く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1336, Takauji ASHIKAGA defected Kenmu Restoration by the Emperor Godaigo and established the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) in Kyoto by putting the Emperor Komyo on the throne of Northern Court (Japan).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1336, Takauji ASHIKAGA defected from the Kenmu Restoration of Emperor Godaigo and established the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) in Kyoto by putting Emperor Komyo on the throne of the Northern Court (Japan).</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;Takauji ASHIKAGA defected Kenmu Restoration&quot; to &quot;Takauji ASHIKAGA defected from the Kenmu Restoration&quot; as the former&apos;s meaning was not clear and did not make sense;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1336, Takauji ASHIKAGA defected from the Kenmu Restoration of Emperor Godaigo and established the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) in Kyoto by putting Emperor Komyo on the throne of the Northern Court (Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>しかし、後醍醐は、自分が北朝に渡した神器は贋物であり自己の皇位が正統であると主張して吉野（奈良県吉野郡吉野町）に南朝 (日本)を開く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the Emperor Godaigo said that he had a fake jingi to the Northern Court with a claim that he had the legitimate right to succeed the Imperial throne, and then established the Southern Court (Japan) in Yoshino (Yoshino-cho, Yoshino-gun, Nara Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Emperor Godaigo claimed that the Jingi he had given to the Northern Court was a fake, that he had the legitimate right to succeed the Imperial throne and established the Sourthern Court (Japan) in Yoshino (Yoshino-cho, Yoshino-gun, Nara Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>capitalized &quot;Jingi&quot;; fixed grammar to read more understandably;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Emperor Godaigo claimed that the Jingi he had given to the Northern Court was a fake, that he had the legitimate right to succeed the Imperial throne and established the Sourthern Court (Japan) in Yoshino (Yoshino-cho, Yoshino-gun, Nara Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>こうして南北朝時代 (日本)が始まる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With this establishment, the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan) started.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These events led to the beginning of the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan).</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;With this establishment&quot; to &quot;These events led to the beginning&quot;; eliminated &quot;started&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These events led to the beginning of the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>正平一統の後に南朝が一時京都を奪還して北朝の三上皇を拉致する際に神器も接収した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Southern court seized the jingi, when it temporarily recaptured Kyoto and kidnapped three retired emperors of the Northern Court after Shohei itto (temporal unification of the Northern and Southern Courts).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Shohei Itto (temporary unification of the Northern and Southern Courts), when the Southern Court temporarily recaptured Kyoto and kidnapped three retired emperors of the Northern Court, they also confiscated the Jingi.</e>
<cmt>rearranged sentence; capitalized &quot;Itto&quot;; changed &quot;temporal&quot; to &quot;temporary&quot;; capitalized &quot;Court&quot; after &quot;Southern&quot;; capitalized &quot;Jingi&quot;; changed &quot;seized&quot; to &quot;confiscated&quot; for &quot;接収した&quot;; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Shohei Itto (temporary unification of the Northern and Southern Courts), when the Southern Court temporarily recaptured Kyoto and kidnapped three retired emperors of the Northern Court, they also confiscated the Jingi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>そのため後光厳天皇はじめ北朝の天皇は後鳥羽天皇の先例にならい神器無しで即位している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the result, Emperors of the Northern Court including the Emperor Kogen ascended the throne without jingi, following a precedent of the Emperor Gotoba.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, Emperors of the Northern Court, including Emperor Kogen, ascended the throne without the Jingi following a precendent of Emperor Gotoba.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;As the result&quot; to &quot;As a result&quot;; added commas after &quot;Northern Court&quot; and &quot;Kogen&quot;; capitalized &quot;Jingi&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, Emperors of the Northern Court, including Emperor Kogen, ascended the throne without the Jingi following a precedent of Emperor Gotoba.</e>
<cmt>precendent→precedent</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>南朝の北畠親房は「北畠親房神皇正統記」で、君主の条件として血統のほかに君徳や神器の重要性を強調する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chikafusa KITABATAKE of the Southern court emphasized, in his &quot;Chikafusa KITABATAKE Jinno Shotoki&quot; (A Chronicle of Gods and Sovereigns), the importance of the blood line as well as virtues and jingi as the conditions for a monarch.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;Kitabatake Chikafusa no Jinno Shotoki&quot; (Chikafusa KITABAKAKE&apos;s Chronicle of Gods and Sovereigns), Chikafusa KITABAKE of the Southern Court emphasized the importance of the blood line, virtue and the Jingi as conditions for a monarch.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;Chikafusa KITABATAKE Jinno Shotoki&quot; to &quot;Kitabatake Chikafusa no Jinno Shotoki&quot;; changed description to include the name; capitalized &quot;Jingi&quot; and added description; fixed spacing; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;Kitabatake Chikafusa no Jinno Shotoki&quot; (Chikafusa KITABAKAKE&apos;s Chronicle of Gods and Sovereigns), Chikafusa KITABAKE of the Southern Court emphasized the importance of the blood line, virtue and the Jingi as conditions for a monarch.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>しかし神器無しでの即位は後鳥羽天皇が後白河法皇の院宣により即位したという先例があり、三種の神器は即位の絶対条件ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the three sacred imperial treasures are not necessarily essential for enthronement, as there was a precedents that Emperor Gotoba ascended to the throne under inzen (a decree from the retired Emperor) of the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Jingi are not necessarily essential for enthronement, however, as there was the precedent of Emperor Gotoba ascending to the throne under the inzen (decree from the retired Emperor) of the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;the three sacred imperial treasures&quot; to &quot;Jingi&quot;; moved &quot;however&quot; to the middle of the sentence; fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Jingi are not necessarily essential for enthronement, however, as there was the precedent of Emperor Gotoba ascending to the throne under the inzen (decree from the retired Emperor) of the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="77">
<j>南朝が保有し続けた神器は、1392年（元中9年/明徳3年）に足利義満の斡旋により南北朝が合一された際に南朝の後亀山天皇から北朝の後小松天皇に渡った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The jingi that the Southern Court had kept was handed from the Emperor Gokameyama of the Southern Court to the Emperor Gokomatsu of the Northern court when the Northern and Southern Courts joined through the mediation of Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA in 1392.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1392, the Jingi retained by the Southern Court were handed from Emperor Gokameyama of the Southern Court to the Emperor Gokomatsu of the Northern Court when the Northern and Southern Courts joined through the mediation of Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>capitalized &quot;Jingi&quot;; changed &quot;had kept&quot; to &quot;retained by&quot; for &quot;保有し続けた&quot;; eliminated &quot;the&quot; before &quot;Emperor Gokameyama&quot;; capitalized &quot;Court&quot; after &quot;Northern&quot;; moved &quot;In 1392&quot; to the beginning of the sentence;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1392, the Jingi retained by the Southern Court were handed from Emperor Gokameyama of the Southern Court to the Emperor Gokomatsu of the Northern Court when the Northern and Southern Courts joined through the mediation of Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="78">
<j>室町時代の1443年（嘉吉3年）に、南朝の遺臣が御所へ乱入し神器を奪う「禁闕の変」が起こった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1443, &quot;Conspiracy of Kinketsu &quot; occurred in which vassals of the extinct Southern Court forced in gosho (Imperial Palace) to steal the jingi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1443, the &quot;Conspiracy of Kinketsu&quot; occurred in which surviving retainers of the Southern Court forced their way into the Gosho (Imperial Palace) to steal the Jingi.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;vassals of the extinct Southern Court&quot; to &quot;surviving retainers of the Southern Court&quot; for &quot;遺臣&quot;; capitalized &quot;Jingi&quot;; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1443, the &quot;Conspiracy of Kinketsu&quot; occurred in which surviving retainers of the Southern Court forced their way into the Gosho (Imperial Palace) to steal the Jingi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>勾玉が後南朝に持ち去られたままになるが、その後1458年（長禄2年）までに奪還されたと伝えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The magadama was kept under the control of Gonancho (Second Southern Court) but reportedly recaptured by 1458</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The magatama was kept under the control of Gonancho (Second Southern Court) but reportedly recovered before 1458.</e>
<cmt>magadama→magatama; changed &quot;recaptured&quot; to &quot;recovered&quot; for &quot;奪還&quot;; changed &quot;by&quot; to &quot;before&quot;; added period</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The magatama was kept under the control of Gonancho (Second Southern Court) but reportedly recovered before 1458.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="80">
<j>明治時代には、南北両朝の皇統の正統性をめぐる南北朝正閏論と呼ばれる論争が起こった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Meiji Period, a controversy called Nanbokucho-Seijunron (argument on legitimacy of either Northern or Southern Dynasty over the legitimacy of imperial enthronement occurred.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Meiji Period, a dispute called &apos;Nanbokucho-Seijunron&apos; occurred where both the Northern and Southern dynasties argued over the legitimacy of the imperial line.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;controversy&quot; to &quot;dispute&quot;; added single quotation marks around &apos;Nanbokucho-Seijunron&apos;; changed &quot;imperial enthronement&quot; to &quot;imperial line&quot; for &quot;皇統&quot;; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Meiji Period, a dispute called &apos;Nanbokucho-Seijunron&apos; occurred where both the Northern and Southern dynasties argued over the legitimacy of the imperial line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>最終的には明治天皇が、南朝が三種の神器を保有していた事を根拠に南朝が正統であると決定する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emperor Meiji finally determined that the Southern court as legitimate for the ground that it owned the three sacred imperial treasures.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the end, Emperor Meiji determined that the Southern Court held legitimacy on the grounds that they owned the three sacred imperial treasures.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the end, Emperor Meiji determined that the Southern Court held legitimacy on the grounds that they owned the three sacred imperial treasures.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="82">
<j>明仁は1989年1月7日に宮殿松の間で行われた「剣璽剣璽渡御の儀（剣璽等承継の儀）」において神器を継承した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Emperor) Akihito succeeded the jingi in &quot;ceremony called &quot;ceremony to transfer Kenji (the Sacred Sword and the Sacred Jewel)&quot; held in Matsu no Ma (State Room) of the Imperial Palace on January 7, 1989.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 7, 1989, Emperor Akihito inherited the Jingi in the &quot;Inheritance Ceremony of Kenji and others&quot; that was held in the Matsu no Ma (State Room) of the Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt>moved date to the beginning of the sentence; capitalized &quot;Jingi&quot;; fixed to read more understandably;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 7, 1989, Emperor Akihito inherited the Jingi in the &quot;Inheritance Ceremony of Kenji and others&quot; that was held in the Matsu no Ma (State Room) of the Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="83">
<j>現存・消失論議</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Controversy over the existence or disappearance</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Controversy over the existence or disappearance of the treasures</e>
<cmt>added &quot;of the treasures&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Controversy over the existence or disappearance of the treasures</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>神器が現存、消失しているか様々な説が飛び交っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are various opinions over the existence or disappearance of the jingi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are various opinions over the existence or disappearance of the Jingi.</e>
<cmt>capitalized &quot;Jingi&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are various opinions over the existence or disappearance of the Jingi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>いずれにしろ、三種の神器は、「天皇家が所有しているとされていること」に意味があるともいえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Whatever happened, the importance of the three sacred imperial treasures may lie in &quot;the belief that the imperial family own them.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Whatever happened, the importance of the three sacred imperial treasures may lie in &quot;the belief that the imperial family own them.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Whatever happened, the importance of the three sacred imperial treasures may lie in &quot;the belief that the imperial family own them.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>つまり、「天皇家が三種の神器を所有している」というより、「天皇家が所有しているもの」こそが、三種の神器なのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In other words, what is important is not whether &quot;the Imperial family owns the three sacred imperial treasures,&quot; but that the three sacred imperial treasures are &quot;what the Imperial family owns.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In other words, what is important is not whether &quot;the Imperial family owns the three sacred imperial treasures,&quot; but that the three sacred imperial treasures are &quot;what the Imperial family owns.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In other words, what is important is not whether &quot;the Imperial family owns the three sacred imperial treasures,&quot; but that the three sacred imperial treasures are &quot;what the Imperial family owns.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="87">
<j>そもそも実際の儀式に使われるのは三種の神器の「形代」（分身つまりレプリカ）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After all, what are actually used in the ceremony are the &quot;katashiro&quot; (incarnation or replica).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the first place, what are actually used in the ceremony are &apos;katashiro&apos; (incarnations or replicas).</e>
<cmt>changed &quot; to &apos;; changed &quot;After all&quot; to &quot;In the first place&quot;; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the first place, what are actually used in the ceremony are &apos;katashiro&apos; (incarnations or replicas).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>実物については祭主たる天皇自身でさえ実見を許されていないという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that even an emperor, chief priest, is not allowed to see the real objects.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that even the emperor, the head priest of the Ise Shrine, is not allowed to see the real objects.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;chief priest&quot; to &quot;the head priest of the Ise Shrine&quot; for &quot;祭主たる&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that even the emperor, the head priest of the Ise Shrine, is not allowed to see the real objects.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>このことからも、実物が現存しているかどうかは確かめようもない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">So there is no way of determining whether the real objects are present or not.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This means that there is no way of determining whether the real objects are present or not.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;So there is no way&quot; to &quot;This means there is no way&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This means that there is no way of determining whether the real objects are present or not.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="90">
<j>伊勢神宮の神体として祀られている八咫鏡は古来のものが現存しているといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Yata no Kagami dedicated to Ise Jingu Shrine as shintai is the mirror that has been existed since the ancient times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the Yata no Kagami (mirror) dedicated to Ise Jingu Shine as a shintai (object of worship housed in a Shinto shrine and believed to contain the spirit of a deity) is the mirror that has existed since ancient times.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;the&quot; before &quot;Yata&quot;; added (mirror) after &quot;Kagami&quot;; added description for &quot;shintai&quot;; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the Yata no Kagami (mirror) dedicated to Ise Jingu Shine as a shintai (object of worship housed in a Shinto shrine and believed to contain the spirit of a deity) is the mirror that has existed since ancient times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>御桶代と呼ばれる入れ物に入って祀られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The mirror contained in a container called mihishiro is enshrined.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The mirror is enshrined in a container called a mihishiro.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The mirror is enshrined in a container called a mihishiro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>式年遷宮の際には、夜間、人目に触れぬよう白布で覆った神体を移御するための行列が組まれて新しい本殿に移される（一説に、伊勢の八咫鏡は式年遷宮と同時に壊され代替わりを行っているというが、この説は論拠不明）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In transferring a deity to a new shrine building once in a prescribed number of years, it was transferred to a new Honden (main shrine) during night by forming a procession for the transfer of the shintai covered with a white cloth not to avoid being seen.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After a prescribed number of years in a ceremony called &apos;Shikinen Sengu&apos;, at night, a shintai is covered with a white cloth to keep it from being seen and transferred to a new Honden (main shrine) by forming a procession.</e>
<cmt>rearranged sentence to read more naturally;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After a prescribed number of years in a ceremony called &apos;Shikinen Sengu&apos;, at night, a shintai is covered with a white cloth to keep it from being seen and transferred to a new Honden (main shrine) by forming a procession.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>（一説に、伊勢の八咫鏡は式年遷宮と同時に壊され代替わりを行っているというが、この説は論拠不明）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Some suggest that Yata no Kagami in Ise is destroyed every transfer of a deity to a new shrine building once in a prescribed number of years time to be replaced by new one, but it is not known where this comes from.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(One theory suggests that the Yata no Kagami in Ise is destroyed during every Shikinen Sengu and replaced by a new one, but it is not known where this theory comes from.)</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;every transfer of a deity to a new shrine building once in a prescribed number of years time&quot; to &quot;every Shikinen Sengu&quot;; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(One theory suggests that the Yata no Kagami in Ise is destroyed during every Shikinen Sengu and replaced by a new one, but it is not known where this theory comes from.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="94">
<j>宮中三殿の賢所に八咫鏡の形代としての神体の鏡が祀られているが、これは火災等により焼けた記録がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The mirror of shintai is now enshrined in Kashikodokoro in the Imperial Palace as katashiro of Yata no Kagami but there is a record that it was once burnt in a fire</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The mirror shintai is enshrined in Kashikodokoro in the Imperial Palace as a katashiro (replica) of the Yata no Kagami, but there is a record that it was once burnt in a fire.</e>
<cmt>added period; changed &quot;mirror of shintai&quot; to &quot;mirror shintai&quot;; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The mirror shintai is enshrined in Kashikodokoro in the Imperial Palace as a katashiro (replica) of the Yata no Kagami, but there is a record that it was once burnt in a fire.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>現在皇居の賢所には、2個の神体の御桶代があり、ひとつは火災等で焼けたものをそのまま御桶代を新造して安置している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kashikodokoro in the Imperial Palace, mihishiro of two pieces of shintai are enshrined; one is in a mihishiro newly made for what was burnt in a fire.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Kashikodokoro in the Imperial Palace, there are mihishiro (containers) for two pieces of shintai, one of which is a newly made mihishiro that contains the remains of an item burnt in a fire.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Kashikodokoro in the Imperial Palace, there are mihishiro (containers) for two pieces of shintai, one of which is a newly made mihishiro that contains the remains of an item burnt in a fire.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>もうひとつは火災で焼けた後で用意された代用品の鏡が入っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The other contained is the mirror that replaced what was burnt in a fire.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The other contains a substitute mirror that was prepared after the fire.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The other contains a substitute mirror that was prepared after the fire.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>これらは源平の壇ノ浦の戦いにおいては回収された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These were collected after the Battle of Dan no ura between the Minamoto and Taira clans.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These were collected after the Battle of Dan-no-ura between the Minamoto and Taira clans.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;Dan no ura&quot; to &quot;Dan-no-ura&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These were collected after the Battle of Dan-no-ura between the Minamoto and Taira clans.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="98">
<j>熱田神宮に祀られている天叢雲剣は古来のものが現存しているとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ama no Murakumo no Tsurugi Sword enshrined in Atsuta-jingu Shrine is believed to the sword that has been existed since the ancient times.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ama no Murakumo no Tsurugi (sword) enshrined in the Atsuta-jingu Shrine is believed to be the sword that has existed since ancient times.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;Sword&quot; to a description in parenthesis as (sword); fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ama no Murakumo no Tsurugi (sword) enshrined in the Atsuta-jingu Shrine is believed to be the sword that has existed since ancient times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>しかし、一説には、平氏滅亡に際し海に没したとされていることから、三種の神器の中で現存しない物であるとも言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However some suggest that, among the three sacred imperial treasures, it has not existed, because it was sunk in the sea the fall of the Heike family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, one theory suggests that among the three sacred treasures, the sword does not exist because it had sunk into the sea with the fall of the Heike family (the Taira clan).</e>
<cmt>added (the Taira clan) after &quot;Heike family&quot; for clarity; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, one theory suggests that among the three sacred treasures, the sword does not exist because it had sunk into the sea with the fall of the Heike family (the Taira clan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="25">
<sen id="100">
<j>皇居の神剣（天叢雲剣の形代）は、源平の壇ノ浦の戦いにおいて、二位の尼が安徳天皇を抱き腰に神器の剣を差して入水したため一緒に水没した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Divine Sword was sunk in the sea with Emperor Antoku in the Battle of Dan no ura between the Minamoto and Taira clans. Because Nii no ama who held the emperor with the sword on his waist committed suicide by drowning but the sword was not the real but a katashiro.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Battle of Dan-no-ura, the divine sword sunk in the sea along with Nii no Ama when he committed suicide by drowning while holding Emperor Antoku and wearing the sword on his side.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処; changed &quot;Dan no ura&quot; to &quot;Dan-no-ura&quot;; eliminated &quot;between the Minamoto and Taira clans&quot; since this information is already written above; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Battle of Dan-no-ura, the divine sword sunk in the sea along with Nii no Ama when he committed suicide by drowning while holding Emperor Antoku and wearing the sword on his side.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>しかし、この剣は神剣そのものではなく形代であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, this was not the real sword, but a katashiro (replica).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, this was not the real sword, but a katashiro (replica).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>そのため後に改めて形代としての剣を伊勢神宮の神庫から選び出し、それが現在皇居に存在している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later another sword as a katashiro was selected among those stored in the sacred warehouse of Ise Jingu Shrine and has been existed since the ancient times.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later on another sword as a katashiro was selected among swords stored in the sacred warehouse of the Ise Jingu Shrine and has existed since ancient times.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later on another sword as a katashiro was selected among swords stored in the sacred warehouse of the Ise Jingu Shrine and has existed since ancient times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="26">
<sen id="103">
<j>勾玉は、源平の壇ノ浦の戦いにおいて、二位の尼が安徳天皇を抱き勾玉の箱を奉じて入水した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The magadama was sunk in the sea with Emperor Antoku in the Battle of Dan no ura between the Minamoto and Taira clans. When Nii no ama who held the emperor and the box for the magadama committed suicide by drowning.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Battle of Dan-no-ura between the Minamoto clan and Taira clan, the magatama (jewel) sunk in the sea with Emperor Antoku when Nii no Ama, who held the emperor and the box containing the magatama, committed suicide by drowning.</e>
<cmt>magadama→magatama; changed &quot;Dan no ura&quot; to &quot;Dan-no-ura&quot;; added (jewel) after the first &quot;magatama&quot;; fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Battle of Dan-no-ura between the Minamoto clan and Taira clan, the magatama (jewel) sunk in the sea with Emperor Antoku when Nii no Ama, who held the emperor and the box containing the magatama, committed suicide by drowning.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>その際に箱ごと浮かび上がり、入水を目撃し急ぎ漕ぎ寄せた源氏方によって回収された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The magadama then rose to the surface and was collected by soldiers of the Minamoto clan who saw them sink in the sea and hastily rowed toward them.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The magatama rose to the surface in its box and was collected by soldiers of the Minamoto clan who hastily rowed to the spot after watching them sink in the sea.</e>
<cmt>magadama→magatama; fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The magatama rose to the surface in its box and was collected by soldiers of the Minamoto clan who hastily rowed to the spot after watching them sink in the sea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>この勾玉は古代のものがいまも皇居に現存しているとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The magadama is believed to have been existed and stored in the Imperial Palace since the ancient times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that this magatama exists and has been stored in the Imperial Palace since ancient times.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;The&quot; to &quot;This&quot;; magadama→magatama; fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that this magatama exists and has been stored in the Imperial Palace since ancient times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Los688(id:12316), BOTarate(id:185620), Nnh(id:474), MIsogi(id:20599), 経済準学士(id:22656), Charenji(id:7908), Eskimbot(id:29676), Faso(id:11300), Lupinoid(id:68), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), Sutou(id:32), Bue(id:237847), Gombe(id:27), EruS(id:164306), 暗黒な方(id:44101), 代言人(id:33675), Rekishi(id:13885), Kone(id:377), ASAMA501(id:91947), Nopira(id:29335), 翰林硯士(id:99377), Izumisawa(id:4148), Lonicera(id:20638), Izayohi(id:13095), Toroia(id:31889), Fujikko(id:62756), Sakura-no-kuni(id:115977), Blue-comet(id:192801), いろはにほへと(id:89648), たんじゅんそぼく(id:61057), Ceridwen(id:36889), Stanislaus(id:1806), Sei(id:590), 水野白楓(id:22811), ZZZ(id:9462), Sat.K(id:3751), Himazin(id:22034), Tyanken(id:129245), Goncyan(id:92158), Vina-iwbot(id:56449), Ef3(id:84901), Michey.M-test(id:3537), Interregnum(id:25269), 伊勢山(id:188062), Murasagi(id:79122), Carkuni(id:79281), RoboDick(id:34097), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), YurikBot(id:18605), N yotarou(id:60870), ＮｉＫｅ(id:7512), Shikai shaw(id:14306), K-kazumasa(id:9265), Alexbot(id:157199), 小太刀(id:18154), Dojo(id:32472), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>