<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>吉田神道</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshida Shinto</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshida Shinto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshida Shinto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>吉田神道（よしだしんとう）とは、室町時代京都吉田神社の神官吉田兼倶によって大成された神道の一流派。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Yoshida Shinto&quot; is a school of Shinto which was perfected in the Muromachi period by Kanetomo YOSHIDA, a Shinto priest from Kyoto Shida-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Yoshida Shinto&quot; is a school of Shinto perfected during the Muromachi period by Kanetomo YOSHIDA, a Shinto priest from the Kyoto Shida-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>removed and revised wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Yoshida Shinto&quot; is a school of Shinto perfected during the Muromachi period by Kanetomo YOSHIDA, a Shinto priest from the Kyoto Shida-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>唯一神道、宗源神道とも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also referred to as Yuiitsu Shinto (One-and-Only Shinto), Sogen Shinto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also referred to as Yuiitsu Shinto (One-and-Only Shinto), Sogen Shinto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also referred to as Yuiitsu Shinto (One-and-Only Shinto), Sogen Shinto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>『唯一神道名法要集』によれば、神道は本迹縁起神道、または社例縁起神道、両部習合神道、元本宗源神道の三種に分けられ、このうち第三の元本宗源神道は吉田家の祖先神であるアメノコヤネノミコトによって伝えられた正統的神道であるとする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Yuiitsu shinto myobo yoshu,&quot; Shinto is categorized into three types - Honjaku engi Shinto or Sharei engi Shinto, Ryobu Shugo Shinto, and Gempon Sogen Shinto, and the third Gempon Sogen Shinto is considered the orthodox Shinto, passed on by Amenokoyane no mikoto, the sosen shin (ancestral god) of the Yoshida family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Yuiitsu shinto myobo yoshu,&quot; Shinto is categorized into three types - Honjaku engi Shinto or Sharei engi Shinto, Ryobu Shugo Shinto, and Gempon Sogen Shinto, and the third Gempon Sogen Shinto is considered the orthodox Shinto, passed on by Amenokoyane no mikoto, the sosen shin (ancestral god) of the Yoshida family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Yuiitsu shinto myobo yoshu,&quot; Shinto is categorized into three types - Honjaku engi Shinto or Sharei engi Shinto, Ryobu Shugo Shinto, and Gempon Sogen Shinto, and the third Gempon Sogen Shinto is considered the orthodox Shinto, passed on by Amenokoyane no mikoto, the sosen shin (ancestral god) of the Yoshida family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>同書によれば元本宗源神道とは「元とは陰陽不測の元元を明す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the book, in Gempon Sogen Shinto, &apos;&quot;Gen&quot; illustrates the gen gen of unforeseen ying and yang.</e>
<cmt>「」内は調査の結果解釈が困難だったため仮訳です。参考サイト：http://imakumanojinja.or.jp/media/myweb1014007.pdf</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the book, in Gempon Sogen Shinto, &apos;&quot;Gen&quot; illustrates the gen gen of unforeseen ying and yang.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the book, in Gempon Sogen Shinto, &apos;&quot;Gen&quot; illustrates the gen gen of unforeseen ying and yang.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>本とは一念未生の本本を明す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Hon&quot; illustrates the honbon of ichinen misho (thoughts are yet to be met).</e>
<cmt>調査の結果解釈が困難だったため仮訳です。参考サイト：http://ameblo.jp/akas-onmyouji/entry-10268732421.html#main</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Hon&quot; illustrates the honbon of ichinen misho (thoughts yet to be met).</e>
<cmt>removed &quot;are&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Hon&quot; illustrates the honbon of ichinen misho (thoughts yet to be met).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>（中略）宗とは一気未分の元神を明す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(An omission) &quot;So&quot; illustrates god as the origin in Ikki mibun.</e>
<cmt>調査の結果解釈が困難だったため仮訳です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(An omission) &quot;So&quot; defines god as the origin in Ikki mibun.</e>
<cmt>replaced &quot;illustrates&quot; which refers to a drawing or photo, etc.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(An omission) &quot;So&quot; defines god as the origin in Ikki mibun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>源とは和光同塵の神化を明す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Gen&quot; illustrates god as a form of wako dojin (mingling with the world by hiding one&apos;s true talent or knowledge).&apos;</e>
<cmt>調査の結果解釈が困難だったため仮訳です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Gen&quot; defines god as a form of wako dojin (mingling with the world by hiding one&apos;s true talent or knowledge).&apos;</e>
<cmt>replaced &quot;illustrates&quot; which refers to a drawing or photo, etc.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Gen&quot; defines god as a form of wako dojin (mingling with the world by hiding one&apos;s true talent or knowledge).&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>」ものであり、即ち「吾国開闢以来唯一神道是也」とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, &apos;this is the one and only shinto since the beginning of the nation.&apos;</e>
<cmt>調査の結果解釈が困難だったため仮訳です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, &apos;this is the one and only true shinto since the beginning of the nation.&apos;</e>
<cmt>revised and added wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, &apos;this is the one and only true shinto since the beginning of the nation.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>顕隠二教を以って一体となすのが特徴で、顕露教の教説を語るものとしては『古事記』『日本書紀』『先代旧事記』（三部本書）、隠幽教の教説は『天元神変神妙経』『地元神通神妙経』『人元神力神妙経』（三部神経）に基づくとするが、兼倶独自のものとは言い難く、その教理や儀礼は密教や道教、陰陽道等の教理や儀礼を取り入れている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is characterized by being composed of two religions, Kenro kyo and Inyu kyo, and while &quot;Kojiki (Records of Ancient Matters),&quot; &quot;Nihon Shoki (Chronicles of Japan),&quot; and &quot;Sendai kujiki&quot; (Sanbu honsho (three books on ancient Japan)) describe the lessons of Kenro kyo, and the lessons of Inyu kyo are said to be based on &quot;Tengenshimpen shimmyokyo,&quot; &quot;Chiggenshintsu shimmyokyo,&quot; and &quot;Jingenshinryoku shimmyokyo&quot; (Sanbu shinkyo), it is not likely to be uniquely Kanetomo&apos;s, and includes principles and rituals from Esoteric Buddhism, Taoism, Onmyodo (way of Yin and Yang; occult divination system based on the Taoist theory of the five elements), etc.</e>
<cmt>原文の誤記：「その教理や儀礼は密教や道教、陰陽道等の教理や儀礼を取り入れている」で、「教理や儀礼」が重複しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is characterized by being composed of two religions, Kenro kyo and Inyu kyo, and while &quot;The Kojiki (Records of Ancient Matters),&quot; &quot;The Nihon Shoki (Chronicles of Japan),&quot; and the &quot;The Sendai kujiki&quot; (Sanbu honsho (three books on ancient Japan)) describe the lessons of Kenro kyo, and Inyu kyo are said to be based upon &quot;Tengenshimpen shimmyokyo,&quot; &quot;Chiggenshintsu shimmyokyo,&quot; and &quot;Jingenshinryoku shimmyokyo&quot; (Sanbu shinkyo), it is not likely to be uniquely Kanetomo&apos;s, and includes principles and rituals from Esoteric Buddhism, Taoism, Onmyodo (way of Yin and Yang; an occult divination system based upon the Taoist theory of the five elements), etc.</e>
<cmt>removed redundant words, added necessary words</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is characterized by being composed of two religions, Kenro kyo and Inyu kyo, and while &quot;The Kojiki (Records of Ancient Matters),&quot; &quot;The Nihon Shoki (Chronicles of Japan),&quot; and the &quot;The Sendai kujiki&quot; (Sanbu honsho (three books on ancient Japan)) describe the lessons of Kenro kyo, and Inyu kyo are said to be based upon &quot;Tengenshimpen shimmyokyo,&quot; &quot;Chiggenshintsu shimmyokyo,&quot; and &quot;Jingenshinryoku shimmyokyo&quot; (Sanbu shinkyo), it is not likely to be uniquely Kanetomo&apos;s, and includes principles and rituals from Esoteric Buddhism, Taoism, Onmyodo (way of Yin and Yang; an occult divination system based upon the Taoist theory of the five elements), etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>兼倶は神祇伯白川家に対抗して朝廷・幕府に取り入って神祇管領長上という称を用いて、「宗源宣旨」を以って地方の神社に神位を授け、また神職の位階を授ける権限を与えられて、神道界に大きな力を有した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanetomo countered with Jingihaku, Shirakawa family by ingratiating with the Imperial Court and shogunate to use the title, Jingikanryochojo, to create deities for local shrines with &apos;sogen senji&apos; (decrees of foundations and origins), as well as received authority to create ranks for Shinto priests, and gained strong power in the world of Shinto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With Jingihaku, Kanetomo countered the Shirakawa family by ingratiating the Imperial Court and shogunate to use the title, Jingikanryochojo, in order to create deities for local shrines with &apos;sogen senji&apos; (decrees of foundations and origins), and received authority to create ranks for Shinto priests, and subsequently gained a powerful influence in the world of Shinto.</e>
<cmt>restructured, grammar improved</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With Jingihaku, Kanetomo countered the Shirakawa family by ingratiating the Imperial Court and shogunate to use the title, Jingikanryochojo, in order to create deities for local shrines with &apos;sogen senji&apos; (decrees of foundations and origins), and received authority to create ranks for Shinto priests, and subsequently gained a powerful influence in the world of Shinto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>一時衰退した時期もあったが、江戸期には神道本所として全国の神社・神職をその支配下に置いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although it declined at one point, it ruled the shrines and Shinto priests nationwide in the Edo period as Shinto honjo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although it eventually declined, it ruled the shrines and Shinto priests nationwide during the Edo period as Shinto honjo.</e>
<cmt>edited out unnecessary words, added others</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it eventually declined, it ruled the shrines and Shinto priests nationwide during the Edo period as Shinto honjo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 うぃき野郎(id:53567), Nnh(id:474), Hatsune(id:26654), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>