<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>地鎮祭</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jichin-sai</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jichin-sai (ground-breaking ceremony)</e>
<cmt>説明を追加</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jichin-sai (ground-breaking ceremony)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>地鎮祭（じちんさい・とこ しずめ の まつり）は、土木工事や建築などで工事を始める前に行う、その土地の神 (神道)（氏神）を鎮め、土地を利用させてもらうことの許しを得る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A Jichin-sai (a ground-breaking ceremony) (tokoshizume no matsuri) is performed prior to the construction of architecture and civil engineering work to appease the god or spirit of the land (Shinto) (Ujigami (the guardian god of the family or the community)) to receive permission to use it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jichin-sai (also pronounced &quot;tokoshizume no matsuri&quot;) is a Japanese word used to describe the ground-breaking ceremony that is performed prior to the construction of an architectural structure or civil engineering work in order to appease the Shinto god or spirit of the land (known in Japanese as the Ujigami, the guardian god or spirit of the family or the community) and receive permission to use the land.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jichin-sai (also pronounced &quot;tokoshizume no matsuri&quot;) is a Japanese word used to describe the ground-breaking ceremony that is performed prior to the construction of an architectural structure or civil engineering work in order to appease the Shinto god or spirit of the land (known in Japanese as the Ujigami, the guardian god or spirit of the family or the community) and receive permission to use the land.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>これには神道と仏教がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has Shinto and Buddhist styles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Shinto ceremony differs from the Buddhist one.</e>
<cmt>This may be a little 意訳 but it reads more naturally this way.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Shinto ceremony differs from the Buddhist one.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>一般には、神を祀って工事の無事を祈る儀式と認識されており、安全祈願祭と呼ばれることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Generally, it is recognized as a ceremony that seeks the blessing of the god for the safety of the construction work, and it is sometimes called Anzen-kigan-sai (a ceremony to pray for safety).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Generally, it is recognized as a ceremony that seeks the blessing of the god in order to ensure the safety of the construction work, and it is sometimes called Anzen-kigan-sai (a ceremony performed to pray for safety).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Generally, it is recognized as a ceremony that seeks the blessing of the god in order to ensure the safety of the construction work, and it is sometimes called Anzen-kigan-sai (a ceremony performed to pray for safety).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>鎮地祭、土祭り、地祭り、地祝いとも言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also referred to as Chinji-sai, Tsuchi-matsuri, Chi-matsuri, and Ji-iwai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also referred to as Chinji-sai, Tsuchi-matsuri, Chi-matsuri, and Ji-iwai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also referred to as Chinji-sai, Tsuchi-matsuri, Chi-matsuri, and Ji-iwai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>一般には、土地の四隅に青竹を立て、その間を注連縄で囲って祭場となし、斎主たる神職のもと、建築業者・施主の参列の上で執り行う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Usually, the site demarcated with green bamboo logs that are placed at the four corners and shimenawa (sacred rice straw ropes) connecting them is turned into a ceremonial site, in which the ceremony is held by a Shinto priest, who plays a role of the spiritual conduit and administrator, in the presence of the builder and the client.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Usually, green bamboo logs are placed at each of the four corners of the construction site with shimenawa (sacred rice straw ropes) hung between them to form a ceremonial site, after which the ceremony is conducted by a Shinto priest, who plays the role of master of religious ceremonies, in the presence of the builder and the client.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Usually, green bamboo logs are placed at each of the four corners of the construction site with shimenawa (sacred rice straw ropes) hung between them to form a ceremonial site, after which the ceremony is conducted by a Shinto priest, who plays the role of master of religious ceremonies, in the presence of the builder and the client.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>祭場の中には木の台（八脚台という）を並べ、その中央に神籬（ひもろぎ、大榊に御幣・木綿を付けた物で、これに神を呼ぶ）を立てて祭壇となす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the ceremonial site, an eight-legged wooden stand (called hakkyaku-dai) is placed as an altar, in the center of which a himorogi (a branch of the evergreen sacred osakaki tree adorned with a gohei (a wooden wand with zigzag paper strips) and yu (wood fiber used to make washi paper), into which the god is invited to descend) is erected.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the ceremonial site, an eight-legged wooden stand (called hakkyaku-dai) is placed, representing an altar, in the center of which a himorogi (a branch of the evergreen sacred osakaki tree adorned with a gohei (a wooden wand with zigzag paper strips) and yu (wood fiber used to make washi paper), into which the god is invited to descend) is erected.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the ceremonial site, an eight-legged wooden stand (called hakkyaku-dai) is placed, representing an altar, in the center of which a himorogi (a branch of the evergreen sacred osakaki tree adorned with a gohei (a wooden wand with zigzag paper strips) and yu (wood fiber used to make washi paper), into which the god is invited to descend) is erected.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>そして、酒・水・米・塩・野菜・魚等の供物を供える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Offerings such as sake, water, rice, salt, vegetables, and fish are placed on the altar.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Offerings such as sake, water, rice, salt, vegetables, and fish are placed on the altar.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Offerings such as sake, water, rice, salt, vegetables, and fish are placed on the altar.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>また、関西などの特定の地方によっては伊勢神宮近隣の浜から砂または塩を取り寄せ、四隅に置く場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In certain areas like Kansai, sand or salt is sometimes brought from the beach near Ise-jingu (the Grand Shrine of Ise) and put in the four corners.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In certain areas like Kansai, sand or salt is sometimes brought from the beach near Ise-jingu (the Grand Shrine of Ise) and put in the four corners of the stand.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In certain areas like Kansai, sand or salt is sometimes brought from the beach near Ise-jingu Shrine and put in the four corners of the stand.</e>
<cmt>Ise-jingu (the Grand Shrine of Ise)→Ise-jingu Shrine</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>祭壇の左右に、緑・黄・赤・白・青の五色絹の幟に榊をつけた「真榊」を立てる場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In some cases, a &quot;masakaki&quot; which is a sakaki (a branch of the evergreen sacred sakaki tree) decorated with a silk flag that has five colors -- green, yellow, red, white, and blue -- is erected in the left and right sides of the altar.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In some cases, a &quot;masakaki&quot; which is a sakaki (a branch of the evergreen sacred sakaki tree) decorated with a silk flag that has five colors -- green, yellow, red, white, and blue -- is erected in the left and right sides of the altar.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In some cases, a &apos;masakaki&apos; which is a sakaki (a branch of the evergreen sacred sakaki tree) decorated with a silk flag that has five colors -- green, yellow, red, white, and blue -- is erected in the left and right sides of the altar.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>この五色絹は五行説における天地万物を組成している5つの要素、つまり木・火・土・金・水を表している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This five-colored silk represents the five elements that form all things in the universe in the Gogyo-setsu (the Theory of the Five Elements), that is, tree, fire, soil, metal, and water.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This five-colored silk represents the five elements that form all things in the universe in the Gogyo-setsu (the Theory of the Five Elements), that is, tree, fire, soil, metal, and water.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This five-colored silk represents the five elements that form all things in the universe in the Gogyo-setsu (the Theory of the Five Elements), that is, tree, fire, soil, metal, and water.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>仏教における地鎮祭</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jichin-sai in Buddhism</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jichin-sai in Buddhism</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jichin-sai in Buddhism</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>仏教では、地鎮法、鎮宅法（じちん、ちんたく・ほう）、安鎮法（あんちんほう、安鎮国家不動法の略）、地天供（じてんく）、あるいは俗に地祭り、地堅めの法などともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Buddhism, Jichin-sai is called Jichin-ho, Chintaku-ho, Anchin-ho which is an abbreviation of Anchin-kokka-fudo-ho, and Jitenku, or popularly Ji-matsuri, Jigatame no ho, and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Buddhism, Jichin-sai is called Jichin-ho, Chintaku-ho, Anchin-ho which is an abbreviation of Anchin-kokka-fudo-ho, and Jitenku, or popularly Ji-matsuri, Jigatame no ho, and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Buddhism, Jichin-sai is called Jichin-ho, Chintaku-ho, Anchin-ho which is an abbreviation of Anchin-kokka-fudo-ho, and Jitenku, or popularly Ji-matsuri, Jigatame no ho, and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>密教の場合は不動明王を本尊として行う鎮宅不動法という儀式がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the case of Mikkyo (esoteric Buddhism), there is a rite called Chintaku-fudo-ho which is carried out with Fudo Myoo (the god of fire) as the principal image. It is performed in the demarcated sacred space, in which a temple, a pagoda, or a tombstone will be built, to appease the souls, including those of the gods of various heavenly worlds and the spirits who died violent deaths, by holding a service for them centering around Jiten (the earth god) and using him as the principal image, and avert obstacles and hardships forever.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the case of Mikkyo (esoteric Buddhism), there is a rite called Chintaku-fudo-ho which is carried out with Fudo Myoo (the god of fire) as the principal image. It is performed in the demarcated sacred space, in which a temple, a pagoda, or a tombstone will be built, to appease the souls, including those of the gods of various heavenly worlds and the spirits who died violent deaths, by holding a service for them centering around Jiten (the earth god) and using him as the principal image, to forever avert obstacles and hardship.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the case of Mikkyo (esoteric Buddhism), there is a rite called Chintaku-fudo-ho which is carried out with Fudo Myoo (the god of fire) as the principal image.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処二文に分かれているので原文ともにセルを分けました。「あり、」→「ある。」</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>堂宇や仏塔、墓碑を建立する前にその土地を結界して、地天を本尊・中心として諸天の天神や、横死した霊魂なども含めて、それらを供養し鎮霊して、永久に障難が及ばないように修する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is performed in the demarcated sacred space, in which a temple, a pagoda, or a tombstone will be built, to appease the souls, including those of the gods of various heavenly worlds and the spirits who died violent deaths, by holding a service for them centering around Jiten (the earth god) and using him as the principal image, to forever avert obstacles and hardship.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="14">
<j>堂宇などの場合、まだ板敷きを敷かずに土壇を鎮める修法を鎮壇法といい、地鎮と鎮壇を個別に修する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the case of buildings like a temple, there is a rite named Chindan-ho, which is held to calm the dirt mound before laying a wooden floor, and Jichin (calming the land) and Chindan (calming the mound) are performed separately.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the case of buildings like a temple, there is a rite named Chindan-ho, which is held to calm the dirt mound before laying a wooden floor, and Jichin (calming the land) and Chindan (calming the mound) are performed separately.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the case of buildings like a temple, there is a rite named Chindan-ho, which is held to calm the dirt mound before laying a wooden floor, and Jichin (calming the land) and Chindan (calming the mound) are performed separately.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>なお略式で同時に修する場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Informally, however, they are sometimes carried out together.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Informally, however, they are sometimes carried out together.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Informally, however, they are sometimes carried out together.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>壇の中央に五宝や七宝をなどを入れた賢瓶を埋める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A kenbyo (a wise jar) containing goho (five treasures, or gems), shichiho (seven treasures, or gems), etc. is buried in the center of the mound.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A kenbyo (a wise jar) containing goho (five treasures, or gems), shichiho (seven treasures, or gems), etc. is buried in the center of the mound.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A kenbyo (a wise jar) containing goho (five treasures, or gems), shichiho (seven treasures, or gems), etc. is buried in the center of the mound.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>鎮石と呼ばれる平らな石を置き、再建する場合も決して動かさない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A flat stone called Chinseki is placed on top, and it is never moved even when reconstruction is undertaken.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A flat stone called Chinseki is placed on top, and it is never moved even when reconstruction is undertaken.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A flat stone called Chinseki is placed on top, and it is never moved even when reconstruction is undertaken.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>八方に輪や橛（くい）、五玉を埋める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rings, piles, and five crystal balls are buried in all directions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rings, piles, and five crystal balls are buried in all directions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rings, piles, and five crystal balls are buried in all directions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="19">
<j>日蓮正宗でも「起工式」という形で行われ、本尊の力で土地を清め、工事の安全を祈願する意味合いがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The rite is also performed in Nichiren Soshu (a school of Nichiren Buddhism based on the teachings of the 13th century Japanese monk, Nichiren Daishonin) in the form of a &quot;kiko-shiki&quot; (a ground-breaking ceremony), which implies praying for safety in the construction through the purification of the land with the power of the principal image.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The rite is also performed in Nichiren Soshu (a school of Nichiren Buddhism based on the teachings of the 13th century Japanese monk, Nichiren Daishonin) in the form of a &quot;kiko-shiki&quot; (a ground-breaking ceremony), which implies praying for safety in the construction through the purification of the land with the power of the principal image.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The rite is also performed in Nichiren Shoshu Sect (a school of Nichiren Buddhism based on the teachings of the 13th century Japanese monk, Nichiren Daishonin) in the form of a &apos;kiko-shiki&apos; (a ground-breaking ceremony), which implies praying for safety in the construction through the purification of the land with the power of the principal image.</e>
<cmt>Nichiren Soshu→Nichiren Shoshu Sect&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>敷地中央に祭壇を組み、寺院の常住本尊を掲げて住職の導師により読経・唱題の上、鍬入れの儀式が行われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An altar is built in the center of the site, and following the posting of the joju-honzen (the principal image drawn by a past high priest) of the temple and sutra-chanting by the chief priest, the kuwaire no gishiki (a ground-breaking ritual) is carried out.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An altar is built in the center of the site, and following the posting of the joju-honzen (the principal image drawn by a past high priest) of the temple and sutra-chanting by the chief priest, the kuwaire no gishiki (a ground-breaking ritual) is carried out.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An altar is built in the center of the site, and following the posting of the joju-honzen (the principal image drawn by a past high priest) of the temple and sutra-chanting by the chief priest, the kuwaire no gishiki (a ground-breaking ritual) is carried out.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>地鎮祭の流れ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Flow of a Jichin-sai</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Flow of a Jichin-sai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Flow of a Jichin-sai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="21">
<j>一般的な地鎮祭の流れは次の通りである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The general flow of a Jichin-sai is as follows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The general flow of a Jichin-sai is as follows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The general flow of a Jichin-sai is as follows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="22">
<j>修祓（しゅばつ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shubatsu (purification)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shubatsu (purification)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shubatsu (purification)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>祭に先立ち、参列者・お供え物を祓い清める儀式。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A ritual whereby the attendants and the offerings are purified in advance of the ceremony.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A ritual whereby the attendants and the offerings are purified in advance of the ceremony.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A ritual whereby the attendants and the offerings are purified in advance of the ceremony.</e>
<cmt>ritual の後のスペース短縮</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="24">
<j>降神（こうしん）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koshin (calling down the god)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koshin (calling down the god)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koshin (calling down the god)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>祭壇に立てた神籬に、その土地の神・地域の氏神を迎える儀式。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A ritual to summon the god of the land and the guardian god of the community to a himorogi that is erected on the altar.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A ritual to summon the god of the land and the guardian god of the community to a himorogi that is erected on the altar.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A ritual to summon the god of the land and the guardian god of the community to a himorogi that is erected on the altar.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>神職が「オオ～」と声を発して降臨を告げる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Shinto priest announces the descent of the god by voicing the sound, &quot;Ohhh&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Shinto priest announces the descent of the god by voicing the sound, &quot;Ohhh&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Shinto priest announces the descent of the god by voicing the sound, &apos;Ohhh&apos;.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="27">
<j>献饌（けんせん）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kensen (food offering)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kensen (food offering)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kensen (food offering)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="28">
<j>神に祭壇のお供え物を食べていただく儀式。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A ritual whereby food and drink on the altar are offered to the god.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A ritual whereby food and drink on the altar are offered to the god.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A ritual whereby food and drink on the altar are offered to the god.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>酒と水の蓋を取る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The caps of the sake and water bottles are removed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The caps of the sake and water bottles are removed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The caps of the sake and water bottles are removed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="30">
<j>祝詞奏上（のりとそうじょう）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Norito-sojo (the recital of Shinto prayers)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Norito-sojo (the recital of Shinto prayers)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Norito-sojo (the recital of Shinto prayers)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>その土地に建物を建てることを神に告げ、以後の工事の安全を祈る旨の祝詞を奏上する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The god is informed that a building will be constructed on the land, and Shinto prayers are recited asking him for the safety of the construction to follow.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The god is informed that a building will be constructed on the land, and Shinto prayers are recited asking him for the safety of the construction to follow.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The god is informed that a building will be constructed on the land, and Shinto prayers are recited asking him for the safety of the construction to follow.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="32">
<j>四方祓（しほうはらい）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shiho-harai (the purification of the four directions)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shiho-harai (the purification of the four directions)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shiho-harai (the purification of the four directions)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>土地の四隅をお祓いをし、清める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oharai (purification) is performed to purify the four corners of the land.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oharai (purification) is performed to purify the four corners of the land.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oharai (purification) is performed to purify the four corners of the land.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="34">
<j>地鎮（じちん）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jichin (appeasing the god of the land)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jichin (appeasing the god of the land)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jichin (appeasing the god of the land)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>刈初(かりそめ)、穿初(うがちぞめ)、鍬入(くわいれ)等が行われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Karisome (the act of mowing the grass), Ugachizome (the act of leveling the land), Kuwaire (the act of plowing the land), and the like are performed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Karisome (the act of mowing the grass), Ugachizome (the act of leveling the land), Kuwaire (the act of plowing the land), and the like are performed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Karisome (the act of mowing the grass), Ugachizome (the act of leveling the land), Kuwaire (the act of plowing the land), and the like are performed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>設計・施工・建主に振り分ける事が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are often divided among the architect, the builder, and the client.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are often divided among the architect, the builder, and the client.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are often divided among the architect, the builder, and the client.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="37">
<j>玉串奉奠（たまぐしほうてん）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tamagushi-hoten (the offering of a tamagushi)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tamagushi-hoten (the offering of a tamagushi)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tamagushi-hoten (the offering of a tamagushi)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>神前に玉串を奉り拝礼する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A tamagushi is put on the altar and worship the god.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A tamagushi is put on the altar and worship the god.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A tamagushi is put on the altar and worship the god.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>玉串とは、榊に紙垂を付けたもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Tamagushi&quot; is a sprig of the sakaki tree that is decorated with shide (zigzag paper streamers).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Tamagushi&quot; is a sprig of the sakaki tree that is decorated with shide (zigzag paper streamers).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Tamagushi&quot; is a sprig of the sakaki tree that is decorated with shide (zigzag paper streamers).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="40">
<j>撤饌（てっせん）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tessen (the removal of the offerings)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tessen (the removal of the offerings)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tessen (the removal of the offerings)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>酒と水の蓋を閉じお供え物を下げる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The caps of the sake and water bottles are closed, and the offerings that were made to the god are removed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The caps of the sake and water bottles are closed, and the offerings that were made to the god are removed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The caps of the sake and water bottles are closed, and the offerings that were made to the god are removed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="42">
<j>昇神（しょうしん）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shoshin (the ascent of the god)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoshin (the ascent of the god)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoshin (the ascent of the god)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>神籬に降りていた神をもとの御座所に送る儀式。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A ritual to send the god who descended to the himorogi to his original residence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A ritual to send the god who descended to the himorogi to his original residence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A ritual to send the god who descended to the himorogi to his original residence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>直会</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naorai (feast)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naorai (feast)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naorai (feast)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="44">
<j>地鎮祭の式次第が終了したら直会（なおらい）を行う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A Naorai (a feast) is held at the end of the Jichin-sai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A Naorai (a feast) is held at the end of the Jichin-sai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A Naorai (a feast) is held at the end of the Jichin-sai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="45">
<j>当地でお神酒で乾杯し、お供え物の御下がりを食する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the ceremonial site, the attendants of the ceremony have a toast with omiki (sacred sake) and eat the offerings that were withdrawn.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the ceremonial site, the attendants of the ceremony have a toast with omiki (sacred sake) and eat the offerings that were withdrawn.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the ceremonial site, the attendants of the ceremony have a toast with omiki (sacred sake) and eat the offerings that were withdrawn.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Opponent(id:720), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), Nnh(id:474), Boca samba(id:137526), ABnormal(id:254617), Tpjapan(id:150462), Stanislaus(id:1806), 勝美(id:158611), 竹麦魚(id:11012), Ietateyou(id:107390), 地鎮祭(id:196358), Yatobi(id:9686), DorganBot(id:149946), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>