<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>小忌衣</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omigoromo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omigoromo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omigoromo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>小忌衣（おみごろも）とは、古代から伝わる、神事などに使用される上衣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omigoromo is an outer garment used in Shinto rituals that has been handed down since ancient times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omigoromo is an outer garment used in Shinto rituals that has been handed down since ancient times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omigoromo is an outer garment used in Shinto rituals that has been handed down since ancient times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>『古事記』などに見える青摺衣の系統を引く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is descended from aozuri no koromo (blue rubbed dyed robes) described in &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters) and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is descended from aozuri no koromo (blue rubbed dyed robes) described in &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters) and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is descended from aozuri no koromo (blue rubbed dyed robes) described in &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters) and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>平安時代には新嘗祭および天皇の代始めの新嘗祭である大嘗祭と、六月十二月の神今食(これらはいずれも天皇が自ら祭祀を行う「親祭」)に供奉する貴族以下の官人が使用した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Heian period, it was worn by the government officials ranked lower than the nobles when they were in attendance on Niiname-sai festival (ceremonial offering by the Emperor of newly-harvested rice to the deities) and Daijo-sai festival, which is one of the Niiname-sai festival to celebrate the succession of an emperor, and jingonjiki ritual held in June and December (the both festivals are &quot;Shinsai festival,&quot; which means a Saishi (religious services) hosted by the Emperor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Heian period, it was worn by the government officials ranked lower than the nobles when they attended the Niiname-sai festival (ceremonial offering by the Emperor of newly-harvested rice to the deities) and Daijo-sai festival, which are one of the Niiname-sai festivals to celebrate the succession of an emperor, and jingonjiki ritual held in June and December (the both festivals are &quot;Shinsai festival,&quot; which means a Saishi (religious services) hosted by the Emperor).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Heian period, it was worn by the government officials ranked lower than the nobles when they attended the Niiname-sai festival (ceremonial offering by the Emperor of newly-harvested rice to the deities) and Daijo-sai festival, which are one of the Niiname-sai festivals to celebrate the succession of an emperor, and jingonjiki ritual held in June and December (the both festivals are &quot;Shinsai festival,&quot; which means a Saishi (religious services) hosted by the Emperor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>なお神今食のときは冠に心葉や日陰鬘をつけない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When it is worn in the jingonjiki ritual, kokoroba (a kind of artificial flowers) or hikagenokazura (a specie of club moss which formal name is Lycopodium clavatum) is not attached to the crown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When it was worn in the jingonjiki ritual, kokoroba (a kind of artificial flowers) or hikagenokazura (a specie of club moss which formal name is Lycopodium clavatum) it was not attached to the crown.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When it was worn in the jingonjiki ritual, kokoroba (a kind of artificial flowers) or hikagenokazura (a specie of club moss whose formal name is Lycopodium clavatum) it was not attached to the crown.</e>
<cmt>which →whose としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>(『西宮記』ほか)これらの親祭では、占食といって亀占により選ばれた者が「小忌(小斎)」と呼ばれて神祭に奉仕した(これに選ばれない者は「大忌」－「大」は「凡」と同じで「一般の」の意味－と呼ばれ、祭の枢要に携わることはできなかった)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(According to the records such as &quot;Saikyuki &quot;), a person called &apos;omi&apos; or &apos;kosai&apos; that was chosen by kameura (tortoise-shell divination) in the process called senjiki (占食), served in Shinto festivals. (Anyone not chosen by the senjiki (占食), was called ohomi (大忌) (&apos;oh&quot;(大) means &apos;mediocrity&apos;(凡)) and was not allowed to hold an important position in the festivals.</e>
<cmt>(『西宮記』ほか)がどの文にかかるか不明でしたが、本文にかかるものとして訳しました。占食-定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(According to the records such as &quot;Saikyuki &quot;), a person called &apos;omi&apos; or &apos;kosai&apos; that was chosen by kameura (tortoise-shell divination) in the process called senjiki (占食), served in Shinto festivals. (Anyone not chosen by the senjiki (占食), was called ohomi (大忌) (&apos;oh&quot;(大) means &apos;mediocrity&apos;(凡)) and was not allowed to hold an important position in the festivals.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(According to the records such as &quot;Saikyuki &quot;), a person called &apos;omi&apos; or &apos;kosai&apos; that was chosen by kameura (tortoise-shell divination) in the process called senjiki (占食), served in Shinto festivals (anyone not chosen by the senjiki (占食), was called ohomi (大忌) (&apos;oh&quot;(大) means &apos;mediocrity&apos;(凡)) and was not allowed to hold an important position in the festivals).</e>
<cmt>文末に閉じ括弧を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>小忌衣とは主に小忌の者が用いることからきたことばである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is called Omigoromo because it is mainly worn by omi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is called Omigoromo because it was mainly worn by omi.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is called Omigoromo because it was mainly worn by omi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>『忌』は神聖なことを表現しているとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The word &quot;mi&quot;(忌) of omi(小忌) said to be representing divine things.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The word &quot;mi&quot; (忌) of omi (小忌) is said to represent divine things.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The word &quot;mi&quot; (忌) of omi (小忌) is said to represent divine things.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>男女共に平安装束の上に羽織り、右肩から赤紐（赤黒紐の場合もある）を垂らす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Regardless of gender, it is put on over costume of Heian period, and scarlet strings (occasionally mixed with black strings) are hung down from the right shoulder.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regardless of gender, it is over Heian period costumes, and scarlet strings (occasionally mixed with black strings) were hung down from the right shoulder.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regardless of gender, it is worn over Heian period costumes, and scarlet strings (occasionally mixed with black strings) were hung down from the right shoulder.</e>
<cmt>worn を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>神楽などの舞人は、邪魔になる為か、紐を左肩から垂らす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Maibito (dancer) of performances, such as kagura (sacred music and dancing performed at shrines), has the strings down from the left shoulder probably because it is less obstructive than from the right shoulder.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Maibito (dancer) of performances, such as kagura (sacred music and dancing performed at shrines), had the strings down from the left shoulder, most likely because it was less obstructive than from the right shoulder.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Maibito (dancer) of performances, such as kagura (sacred music and dancing performed at shrines), had the strings down from the left shoulder, most likely because it was less obstructive than from the right shoulder.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>模様としては、白絹及び白麻地に青摺（あおずり）と呼ばれる山藍の葉の汁で、花鳥風月等の素朴な文様を書くのが一般的。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its common pattern is naïve painting of kacho-fugetsu (the traditional themes of natural beauty in Japanese aesthetics) and the like that is drawn on white silk and white linen with the leaf juice of mercury (Mercurialis leiocarpa) called aozuri (things dyed deep blue).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its common pattern was the naïve painting of kacho-fugetsu (the traditional themes of natural beauty in Japanese aesthetics) and the like which were drawn on white silk and white linen with the leaf juice of mercury (Mercurialis leiocarpa) called aozuri (things dyed deep blue).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its common pattern was the naïve painting of kacho-fugetsu (the traditional themes of natural beauty in Japanese aesthetics) and the like which were drawn on white silk and white linen with the leaf juice of mercury (Mercurialis leiocarpa) called aozuri (things dyed deep blue).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>袖が付いていないものと、袖付きのものがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some have set-in sleeves, others don&apos;t.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some have set-in sleeves, others don&apos;t.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some have set-in sleeves, others don&apos;t.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>各種の小忌衣について、院政期以降の規定に基づき説明する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following is the classification of Omigoromo under the provisions valid since the cloister government period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following is the classification of Omigoromo under provisions valid since the cloister government period.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following is the classification of Omigoromo under provisions valid since the cloister government period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="13">
<j>１・諸司小忌</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1. Shoshi no omi Shoshi no omi has tarikubi (wrapped front with V-shaped neckline) without a gusset, and the width of mi (torso) is double (approx 30 inches) and each of left and right sleeves has a single width (approx. 15 inches) and the total width is quadruple width (approx 60 inches).</e>
<cmt>身-定訳不明1幅を37.8cm(約15インチ)として換算しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1. Shoshi no omi Shoshi no omi has tarikubi (wrapped front with V-shaped neckline) without a gusset, and the width of mi (torso) is double (approx 30 inches) and each of left and right sleeves has a single width (approx. 15 inches) and the total width is quadruple width (approx 60 inches).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1. Shoshi no omi</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>身が二幅、袖が左右各一幅、計四幅のおくみのない垂領である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoshi no omi has tarikubi (wrapped front with V-shaped neckline) without a gusset, and the width of mi (torso) is double (approx 30 inches) and each of left and right sleeves has a single width (approx. 15 inches) and the total width is quadruple width (approx 60 inches).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>右肩に赤紐をつける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Scarlet strings are attached to the right shoulder.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Scarlet strings are attached to the right shoulder.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Scarlet strings are attached to the right shoulder.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>親祭当日に小忌の官人が下賜されて着用することからこの名称がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is called shoshi no omi (omigoromo for officials) because it is granted as an Imperial gift and worn by officials assigned as omi in the day of Shinsai festival.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is called shoshi no omi (omigoromo for officials) because it is granted as an Imperial gift and worn by officials assigned as omi on the day of the Shinsai festival.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is called shoshi no omi (omigoromo for officials) because it is granted as an Imperial gift and worn by officials assigned as omi on the day of the Shinsai festival.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>参内後に下賜されると束帯の上に着て、裾まわりは石帯にはさみこむ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The omi, having been granted it after the arrival of the Imperial Palace, put it on over sokutai (traditional ceremonial court dress) and insert the bottom hems below sekitai (leather belt).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The omi, having been granted after the arrival of the Imperial Palace, wore it over sokutai (traditional ceremonial court dress) and inserted them into the bottom hems below sekitai (leather belt).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The omi, having been granted after the arrival of the Imperial Palace, wore it over sokutai (traditional ceremonial court dress) and inserted them into the bottom hems below sekitai (leather belt).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>生地は、近世では麻を粉張(こばり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In recent times, the fabric is the linen processed with kobari (thick coating of whitewash).</e>
<cmt>訳文の区切りが原文と異なります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In recent times, the fabric is the linen processed with kobari (thick coating of whitewash).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In recent times, the fabric is the linen processed with kobari (thick coating of whitewash).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>胡粉という白い絵の具を厚く引く)にして、「竜胆と尾長鳥」「梅と柳」などの摺文を施している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Surimon (pattern printed with woodblock) of &apos;Rindo (gentian) and long-tailed fowl&apos; or &apos;plum trees and willows&apos;, etc. is printed on the fabric.</e>
<cmt>訳文の区切りが原文と異なります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Surimon (pattern printed with woodblock) of &apos;Rindo (gentian) and long-tailed fowl&apos; or &apos;plum trees and willows&apos;, etc. are printed on the fabric.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Surimon (pattern printed with woodblock) of &apos;Rindo (gentian) and long-tailed fowl&apos; or &apos;plum trees and willows&apos;, etc. are printed on the fabric.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="20">
<j>２・私小忌</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">2. Watakushi no omiWatakushi no omi has agekubi (round collar), and the width of mi (torso) is a single width (approx. 15 inches), and each of left and right sleeves has double width (approx. 30 inches).</e>
<cmt>身-定訳不明1幅を37.8cm(約15インチ)として換算しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">2. Watakushi no omiWatakushi no omi has agekubi (round collar), and the width of mi is single width (approx. 15 inches), while each of the left and right sleeves have double width (approx. 30 inches).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">2. Watakushi no omi</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>身が一幅の盤領で、袖は左右各二幅。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Watakushi no omi has agekubi (round collar), and the width of mi is single width (approx. 15 inches), while each of the left and right sleeves have double width (approx. 30 inches).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処既出単語の補足は削除しました（「身」など）。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>狩衣の裾の長いような形であるが、袖括はない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its shape is like kariginu (informal clothes worn by Court nobles) with the longer bottom, but there is no sodekukuri (straps to turn up one&apos;s cuffs).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is shaped like kariginu (informal clothes worn by Court nobles) with a longer bottom, but there is no sodekukuri (straps to turn up one&apos;s cuffs).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is shaped like kariginu (informal clothes worn by court nobles) with a longer bottom, but there is no sodekukuri (straps to turn up one&apos;s cuffs).</e>
<cmt>court nobles としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>右肩に赤紐をつける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Scarlet strings are attached to the right shoulder.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Scarlet strings are attached to the right shoulder.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Scarlet strings are attached to the right shoulder.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>束帯の袍を着ずに、下襲・半臂の上に袍のかわりに着用する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As an alternative to ho (outer robe/vestment) which is part of sokutai (traditional ceremonial court dress), it is worn over shitagasane (long inner robe) and hanpi (sleeveless body wear).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As an alternative to ho (outer robe/vestment) which is part of sokutai (traditional ceremonial court dress), it is worn over shitagasane (long inner robe) and hanpi (sleeveless body wear).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As an alternative to ho (outer robe/vestment) which is part of sokutai, it is worn over shitagasane (long inner robe) and hanpi (sleeveless body wear).</e>
<cmt>既出単語の補足は削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>神祇官人や大嘗祭の悠紀・主基国司などの、早くから神事に奉仕することが確定している者は親祭当日にも着用する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also worn on the very day of Shinsai festival by those who are determined to serve the Shinto rituals from early on, such as officer of Jingikan (the traditional office for public Shinto affairs) and governors of Yuki and Suki (the east and the west provinces designated for production of the rice offered during the course of the festival) in the Daijo-sai festival.</e>
<cmt>「悠紀・主基」には説明を加えました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also worn on the very day of Shinsai festival by those who are determined to serve the Shinto rituals from early on, such as officer of Jingikan (the traditional office for public Shinto affairs) and governors of Yuki and Suki (the east and the west provinces designated for production of the rice offered during the course of the festival) in the Daijo-sai festival.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also worn on the very day of Shinsai festival by those who are determined to serve the Shinto rituals from early on, such as officer of Jingikan (the traditional office for public Shinto affairs) and governors of Yuki and Suki (the east and the west provinces designated for production of the rice offered during the course of the festival) in the Daijo-sai festival.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>親祭で諸司小忌を下賜された者は、新嘗祭や大嘗祭の直会(祭後の宴会)にあたる節会に使用する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those who are granted shosi no omi in the Shinsai festival wear it in Sechi-e (seasonal court banquets) which is naorai (feast after festival) of the Niiname-sai festival or the Daijo-sai festival.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those who are granted shosi no omi in the Shinsai festival wear it in Sechi-e (seasonal court banquets) which is naorai (feast after festival) of the Niiname-sai festival or the Daijo-sai festival.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those who are granted shoshi no omi in the Shinsai festival wear it in sechie (seasonal court banquets) which is naorai (feast after festival) of the Niiname-sai festival or the Daijo-sai festival.</e>
<cmt>shoshi, sechie としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>下賜品である諸司小忌に対して私弁であるために私小忌の名称を持つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is called watakushi no omi (privately owned omigoromo) because it is prepared at personal expense while shoshi no omi is an Imperial grant.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is called watakushi no omi (privately owned omigoromo) because it is prepared at personal expense while shoshi no omi is an Imperial grant.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is called watakushi no omi (privately owned omigoromo) because it is prepared at personal expense while shoshi no omi is an Imperial grant.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>生地は、近世では麻を粉張にして、様々な文様を青摺にする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In recent times, the fabric is the linen processed with kobari, and various patterns are printed with aozuri on the fabric.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In recent times, the fabric is the linen processed with kobari, and various patterns are printed with aozuri on the fabric.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In recent times, the fabric is the linen processed with kobari, and various patterns are printed with aozuri on the fabric.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="29">
<j>以下は、中世の記録には明確でないが、近世には制度的に確立していたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following classification is obscure in the records of the Medieval Period, but it had been institutionally established in the early modern times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following classification is unclear according to records from the Medieval Period, but it has been institutionally established in early modern times.</e>
<cmt>&quot;institutionally established&quot; doesn’t make sense.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following classification is unclear according to records from the Medieval Period, but it has been institutionally established in early modern times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="30">
<j>３・如形小忌</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">3. Nyogyo no omi (如形小忌)</e>
<cmt>如形小忌-定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">3. Nyogyo no omi (如形小忌)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">3. Nyogyo no omi (如形小忌)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>諸司小忌の袖を略した形式。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nyogyo no omi (如形小忌) is a sleeveless version of the shoshi no omi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nyogyo no omi (如形小忌) is a sleeveless version of the shoshi no omi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nyogyo no omi (如形小忌) is a sleeveless version of the shoshi no omi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>裃のようなもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It looks like kamishimo (an Edo-period ceremonial dress of the warrior class).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Resembles the kamishimo (an Edo-period ceremonial dress of the warrior class).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Resembles the kamishimo (an Edo-period ceremonial dress of the warrior class).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>身が二幅の垂領で、右肩に赤紐をつける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its mi (torso) is double width (approx 30 inches) and has tarikubi (wrapped front with V-shaped neckline) and scarlet strings are attached to the right shoulder.</e>
<cmt>身-定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its mi (torso) is double width (approx 30 inches) and has tarikubi (wrapped front with V-shaped neckline) and scarlet strings attached to the right shoulder.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its mi is double width (approx 30 inches) and has tarikubi and scarlet strings attached to the right shoulder.</e>
<cmt>既出単語の補足は削除しました（「身」など）。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>主に祭祀にたずさわる地下官人が使用。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was worn mainly by jigekanjin (lower ranking groups of officials serving the imperial court) who served in religious services.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was worn mainly by jigekanjin (lower ranking groups of officials serving the imperial court) who served in religious services.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was worn mainly by jigekanjin (lower ranking groups of officials serving the Imperial Court) who served in religious services.</e>
<cmt>Imperial Court としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>束帯では裾を石帯にはさみ、その他では裾をはさまずただうちかけた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When it was worn as sokutai (traditional ceremonial court dress) the bottom hems were inserted below sekitai (leather belt), and in other cases, the hems were just hung down without the insertion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When it was worn as sokutai (traditional ceremonial court dress) the bottom hems were inserted below sekitai (leather belt), and in other cases, the hems were just hung down without the insertion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When it was worn as sokutai, the bottom hems were inserted below sekitai, and in other cases, the hems were just hung down without the insertion.</e>
<cmt>既出単語の補足は削除しました（「束帯」など）。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>生地は麻に粉張とし、青摺で主に梅と柳の文様をあらわした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fabric is the linen processed with kobari, and patterns are mainly plum trees and willows printed with aozuri on the fabric.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fabric is comprised of linen processed with kobari, and patterns consist of mainly plum trees and willows printed with aozuri on the fabric.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fabric is comprised of linen processed with kobari, and patterns consist of mainly plum trees and willows printed with aozuri on the fabric.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="37">
<j>４・別勅小忌</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">4. Becchoku no omi</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">4. Becchoku no omi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">4. Becchoku no omi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>天皇の神事服(御斎服)着装に奉仕する衣紋者の公家が使用した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Becchoku no omi was worn by court nobles called emonja who engaged in dressing the Emperor with the imperial costume for Shinto rituals (Gosaifuku).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Becchoku no omi was worn by court nobles called emonja who engaged in dressing the Emperor with the imperial costume for Shinto rituals (Gosaifuku).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Becchoku no omi was worn by court nobles called emonja who engaged in dressing the Emperor with the imperial costume for Shinto rituals (Gosaifuku).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>また、側近で世話をする議奏の公卿が使用した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was also worn by kugyo (the top court officials) who looked after the Emperor as close aides called giso (a position conveying what the congress decides to the emperor).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was also worn by kugyo (the top court officials) who looked after the Emperor as close aides called giso (a position conveying what the congress decides to the emperor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was also worn by kugyo (the top court officials) who looked after the Emperor as close aides called giso (a position conveying what the congress decides to the emperor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>重要な任務ゆえに占食と無関係に着用したのでこの名がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was called becchoku (special imperial ordinance) no omi because the wearers were not chosen by senjiki (占食) due to the importance of their role.</e>
<cmt>占食-定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was called becchoku (special imperial ordinance) no omi because the wearers were not chosen by senjiki (占食) due to the importance of their role.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was called becchoku (special imperial ordinance) no omi because the wearers were not chosen by senjiki (占食) due to the importance of their role.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>衣冠の上に着ることが多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In many cases, it was worn over ikan (traditional formal court dress).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In many cases, it was worn over ikan (traditional formal court dress).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In many cases, it was worn over ikan (traditional formal court dress).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>その場合前は懐の「かいこみ」にはさみこみ、後ろはうちかけて着た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In such case, the front hems were inserted into the area between the chest and kimono called &quot;kaikomi&quot; and the back hem was hung down.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処かいこみ-定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In such case, the front hems were inserted into the area between the chest and kimono called &quot;kaikomi&quot; and the back hem was hung down.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In such case, the front hems were inserted into the area between the chest and kimono called &apos;kaikomi&apos; and the back hem was hung down.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>生地は麻の粉張とし、青摺で主に流水とわらびをあらわした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fabric is the linen processed with kobari, and patterns of mainly running water and bracken are printed with aozuri on the fabric.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fabric is comprised of linen processed with kobari, and patterns consist mainly of running water with bracken printed together with aozuri on the fabric.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fabric is comprised of linen processed with kobari, and patterns consist mainly of running water with bracken printed together with aozuri on the fabric.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>衣冠の上に着るものは普通赤紐をつけない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When it is worn over ikan, scarlet strings are usually not attached.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When it is worn over ikan, scarlet strings are usually not attached.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When it is worn over ikan, scarlet strings are usually not attached.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>名称と衣紋者等の使用は『延慶大嘗会記』(後伏見上皇が弟花園天皇の大嘗祭を記録した日記)に基づく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name and the wearers, such as emonja, are based on the description in &quot;Engyo Daijoe-ki&quot; (the diary of the retired Emperor Gofushimi which recorded the Daijo-sai festival of his younger brother, Emperor Hanazono).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name and the wearers, such as emonja, are based on the description in &quot;Engyo Daijoe-ki&quot; (the diary of the retired Emperor Gofushimi which recorded the Daijo-sai festival of his younger brother, Emperor Hanazono).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name and the wearers, such as emonja, are based on the description in &quot;Engyo Daijoe-ki&quot; (the diary of the Retired Emperor Gofushimi which recorded the Daijo-sai festival of his younger brother, Emperor Hanazono).</e>
<cmt>Retired Emperor としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>しかし、詳細な仕様は貞享四年の大嘗祭復興に際して新たに決められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the details of the style were determined at the time of revival of Daijo-sai festival in 1687.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the details of the style were determined at the time of revival of Daijo-sai festival in 1687.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the details of the style were determined at the time of revival of Daijo-sai festival in 1687.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="47">
<j>※なお『代始和抄』(一条兼良)などに「出納小忌」の名称があるが、実態は不明で、近世では別勅小忌の(一説では如形小忌の)別名とされていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omigoromo called &apos;suinou no omi&apos; appears in documentary records, such as &quot;Daihajimewa-sho&quot;(written by Kanera ICHIJO), but the actual state has remained unclear. In recent times, it has been said to be another name for Becchoku no omi (or Nyogyo no omi (如形小忌), according to another account).</e>
<cmt>如形小忌-定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omigoromo called &apos;suinou no omi&apos; appears in documentary records, such as &quot;Daihajimewa-sho&quot;(written by Kanera ICHIJO), but the actual state has remained unclear. In recent times, it has been said to be another name for Becchoku no omi (or Nyogyo no omi (如形小忌), according to another account).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omigoromo called &apos;suinou no omi&apos; appears in documentary records, such as &quot;Daihajime-washo&quot; (written by Kanera ICHIJO), but the actual state has remained unclear; in recent times, it has been said to be another name for Becchoku no omi (or Nyogyo no omi (如形小忌), according to another account).</e>
<cmt>Daihajime-washo としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="48">
<j>なお、采女のちはやは如形小忌であるが、生絹に蝶を青摺し、赤紐はない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chihaya (Japanese coat for female priests) of uneme (a maid-in-waiting at the court) is the Nyogyo no omi (如形小忌), but the fabric is suzushi (raw silk products) on which Cho (butterfly) is printed with aozuri, and no scarlet strings are attached.</e>
<cmt>如形小忌-定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chihaya (Japanese coat for female priests) of uneme (a maid-in-waiting at the court) is the Nyogyo no omi (如形小忌), but the fabric is suzushi (raw silk products) on which Cho (butterfly) is printed with aozuri, and no scarlet strings are attached.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chihaya (Japanese coat for female priests) of uneme (a maid-in-waiting at the court) is the Nyogyo no omi (如形小忌), but the fabric is suzushi (raw silk products) on which Cho (butterfly) is printed with aozuri, and no scarlet strings are attached.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>東遊などの日本古来の古代歌謡を伴う舞楽に用いるものは私小忌と同型で、ただ赤紐が左肩につく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A type worn in performance of bugaku (traditional Japanese court music accompanied by dancing) which is accompanied by Japanese ancient songs and ballads such as Azuma-asobi is the same as watakushi no omi but the scarlet strings are not attached to the left shoulder.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A type worn in performance of bugaku (traditional Japanese court music accompanied by dancing) which is accompanied by Japanese ancient songs and ballads such as Azuma-asobi is the same as watakushi no omi but the scarlet strings are not attached to the left shoulder.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A type worn in performance of bugaku (traditional Japanese court music accompanied by dancing) which is accompanied by Japanese ancient songs and ballads such as Azuma-asobi is the same as watakushi no omi but the scarlet strings are attached to the left shoulder.</e>
<cmt>not を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>これは占食で選ばれるものではないので普通は小忌衣とはいわず、「青摺」と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as the wearer is not chosen by senjiki (占食), it is normally not called omigoromo but &apos;aozuri&apos;.</e>
<cmt>占食-定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as the wearer is not chosen by senjiki (占食), it is normally not called omigoromo but &apos;aozuri&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as the wearer is not chosen by senjiki (占食), it is normally not called omigoromo but &apos;aozuri.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>五節舞姫も羅の青摺の唐衣を用いるが、これも普通は小忌衣とはよばれない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gosechi no Maihime/Maihime at Gosechi-festival also wears karaginu (a waist length Chinese style jacket) but it is also not called omigoromo normally.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gosechi no Maihime/Maihime at Gosechi-festival also wears karaginu (a waist length Chinese style jacket) but it is also not called omigoromo normally.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gosechi no Maihime/Maihime at Gosechi-festival also wears karaginu (a waist length Chinese style jacket) but it is also not called omigoromo normally.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>ただし青摺の神事服である点では小忌衣と同じ性格を持つといえるものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, its characteristics could be regarded as the same as those of omigoromo in the respect that both are the Shinto ritual costumes with printing of aozuri.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, its characteristics could be regarded as the same as those of omigoromo in the respect that both are Shinto ritual costumes that have aozuri printings.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, its characteristics could be regarded as the same as those of omigoromo in the respect that both are Shinto ritual costumes that have aozuri printings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="53">
<j>近代には諸司小忌を男女の供奉員が着用する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the recent period, shoshi no omi is worn by gubukan (a special monk who holds a position in the Imperial court) regardless of gender.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the recent times, shoshi no omi is worn by gubukan (a special monk who holds a position in the Imperial court) regardless of gender.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the recent times, shoshi no omi is worn by gubukan (a special monk who holds a position in the Imperial Court) regardless of gender.</e>
<cmt>Imperial Court としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>占食のしきたりはないので「小忌」に選ばれる者はないが、名前は従来のままであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this case, although the wearer is not chosen to be &apos;omi&apos; because there is no practice of senjiki (占食), but the original name has been retained.</e>
<cmt>占食-定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this case, although the wearer is not chosen to be &apos;omi&apos; because there is no practice of senjiki (占食), but the original name has been retained.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this case, although the wearer is not chosen to be &apos;omi&apos; because there is no practice of senjiki (占食), but the original name has been retained.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="55">
<j>新嘗祭や豊明節会等の宮廷での諸神事の宮人が使用した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was worn by kunin (female servants in residence at Miya) at the Imperial court in the Niiname-sai festival and the Toyoakari no sechie and so on.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was worn by kunin (female servants in residence at Miya) at the Imperial court in the Niiname-sai festival and the Toyoakari no sechie and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was worn by kunin (female servants in residence at Miya) at the Imperial Court in the Niiname-sai festival and the Toyoakari no sechie and so on.</e>
<cmt>Imperial Court としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>また、大嘗祭の五節舞姫、神楽の舞人、大喪の八瀬童子、神職、巫女等が使用した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was also worn by Gosechi no Maihime in the Daijo-sai festival, maibito (dancer) in kagura, Yasedoji in taiso (Imperial mourning), Shinto priest and miko (a shrine maiden).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was also worn by Gosechi no Maihime in the Daijo-sai festival, maibito (dancer) in kagura, Yasedoji in taiso (Imperial mourning), Shinto priest and miko (a shrine maiden).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was also worn by Gosechi no Maihime in the Daijo-sai festival, maibito in kagura, Yasedoji in taiso (Imperial mourning), Shinto priest and miko (a shrine maiden).</e>
<cmt>既出単語の補足は削除しました（「まいびと」など）。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="57">
<j>◎八瀬童子の使用の証拠を示してください。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Please provide evidence for the use of shoshi no omi by Yasedoji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Please provide evidence for the use of shoshi no omi by Yasedoji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">* Please provide evidence for the use of shoshi no omi by Yasedoji.</e>
<cmt>◎　の部分を * に置き換えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="58">
<j>天照大神が岩戸隠れから再び姿を現した時、身に付けていたとの伝承がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a tradition that Amaterasu Omikami (the Sun Goddess) was wearing it when she reappeared from her Iwadokakure (a story of ancient Japanese myth in which Amaterasu hid from anger in a stone cave).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a tradition that Amaterasu Omikami (the Sun Goddess) was wearing it when she reappeared from her Iwadokakure (a story of ancient Japanese myth in which Amaterasu hid from anger in a stone cave).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a tradition that Amaterasu Omikami (the Sun Goddess) was wearing it when she reappeared from her Iwadokakure (a story of ancient Japanese myth in which Amaterasu hid from anger in a stone cave).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>伝承だが、これが起源とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said to have its origin in this story although it is only a tradition.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said to have its origin in this story although this is only a tradition.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said to have its origin in this story although this is only a tradition.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="60">
<j>特に豊明節会にも使われることから、崇神天皇が笠縫邑で天照大神を祀った時代からあったことも考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It could be considered that it dates back to the time when Emperor Sujin enshrined Amaterasu Omikami in Kasanui no Mura especially because it is worn in the Toyoakari no sechie.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It may date back to the time when Emperor Sujin enshrined Amaterasu Omikami in Kasanui no Mura especially because it is worn in the Toyoakari no sechie.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It may date back to the time when Emperor Sujin enshrined Amaterasu Omikami in Kasanui no Mura especially because it is worn in the Toyoakari no sechie.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="61">
<j>雄略天皇が葛城山に登った時、天皇と一言主神の従者が青摺に紅紐を付けた装束を共に着ていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Emperor Yuryaku climbed Mt. Katsuragi, the followers of both of the Emperor and Hitokotonushi-no-kami was wearing the same costume that was printed with aozuri with scarlet strings attached.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Emperor Yuryaku climbed Mt. Katsuragi, the followers of both the Emperor and Hitokotonushi-no-kami wore the same costume that was printed with aozuri with scarlet strings attached.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Emperor Yuryaku climbed Mt. Katsuragi, the followers of both the Emperor and Hitokotonushi no Kami wore the same costume that was printed with aozuri with scarlet strings attached.</e>
<cmt>神名表現を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>その装束は小忌衣と比較して興味深い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is intriguing to compare this costume with omigoromo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is intriguing to compare this costume with omigoromo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is intriguing to compare this costume with omigoromo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="63">
<j>巫女装束にも、同じように、青摺を使用している例が一般的である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Likewise, the aozuri is typically used in shrine maiden costume.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Likewise, the aozuri is typically used in shrine maiden costume.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Likewise, the aozuri is typically used in shrine maiden costume.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>近年の巫女神楽の装束にも小忌衣が使用されている（例：浦安の舞）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omigoromo is also used as the costume for Miko kagura in recent times (ex. Urayasu no Mai Dance).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omigoromo is also used as the costume for Miko kagura in recent times (ex. Urayasu no Mai Dance).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omigoromo is also used as the costume for Miko kagura in recent times (ex. Urayasu no Mai Dance).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="65">
<j>また、千早や比礼（ひれ：女性が、首に掛けて、結ばずに、左右から同じ長さで前に垂らすスカーフ様のもの）との関係が注目される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, its correlation with chihaya (Japanese coat for female priests) or hire (scarf-like cloth draped around woman&apos;s neck, both ends of which are hung down frontwards at the same length) is also worthy to note.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, its correlation with chihaya (Japanese coat for female priests) or hire (scarf-like cloth draped around woman&apos;s neck, both ends of which are hung down frontwards at the same length) is also interesting to note.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, its correlation with chihaya or hire (scarf-like cloth draped around woman&apos;s neck, both ends of which are hung down frontwards at the same length) is also interesting to note.</e>
<cmt>既出単語の補足は削除しました（「ちはや」など）。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="66">
<j>歌舞伎に同名の小忌衣があり、貴人の普段着の使われ方をしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omigoromo with the same name appears in Kabuki (traditional drama performed by male actors) as everyday cloth of the nobility.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omigoromo with the same name appears in Kabuki (traditional drama performed by male actors) as an everyday cloth of the nobility.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omigoromo with the same name appears in Kabuki (traditional drama performed by male actors) as an everyday cloth of the nobility.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>だが、豪華な絹衣装で、エリマキトカゲの様に襟が長い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it is luxurious dress of silk with a large neckband like that of a frilled lizard.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is a luxurious dress of silk with a large neckband like that of a frilled lizard.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is a luxurious dress of silk with a large neckband like that of a frilled lizard.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>よって、本来の小忌衣とは全く異なるもので起源は不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, as it is completely different from the original omigoromo, its origin is uncertain.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, as it is completely different from the original omigoromo, its origin is uncertain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, as it is completely different from the original omigoromo, its origin is uncertain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), Doorurban(id:132333), Nnh(id:474), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>