<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>日月神示</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hitsuki Shinji</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hitsuki Shinji</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hitsuki Shinji</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>日月神示（ひつきしんじ）は神典研究家で画家でもあった岡本天明、1897年（明治30年）明治30年–1963年（昭和38年）昭和38年に「国常立尊」（別名、国之常立神）と呼ばれている高級神霊より自動書記によって降ろされたとされる神示、神典である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hitsuki Shinji is the Divine Revelation that Tenmei OKAMOTO (1897-1963), a painter and a Shintoist claimed to have received from a holy spirit called &apos;Kuninotoko Tachinokami 国常立尊 or 国之常立神&apos; by automatic writing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hitsuki Shinji is the Divine Revelation that Tenmei OKAMOTO (1897-1963), a painter and a Shintoist, claimed to have received from a holy spirit called &apos;Kuninotoko Tachinokami&apos; (国常立尊 or 国之常立神) by automatic writing.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hitsuki Shinji is the Divine Revelation that Tenmei OKAMOTO (1897-1963), a painter and a Shintoist, claimed to have received from a holy spirit called &apos;Kuninotoko Tachinokami&apos; (国常立尊 or 国之常立神) by automatic writing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>原文はほとんどが漢数字、かな文字、記号の混じった文体で構成され抽象的な絵のみで書記されている「巻」も有る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The original was written mostly in mixed sentences of Chinese numerals, kana characters and symbols, and included volumes which were written only in symbolic drawings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The original was written mostly in mixed sentences of Chinese numerals, kana characters and symbols, and included volumes which were written only in symbolic drawings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The original was written mostly in mixed sentences of Chinese numerals, kana characters and symbols, and included volumes which were written only in symbolic drawings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>その難解さから当初は書記した天明自身もほとんど読むことが出来なかったが、仲間の神典研究家の協力などで少しずつ解読が進み天明亡き後も妻である岡本三典の努力により、今では一部を除きかなりの部分が解読されたと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the beginning it was too difficult even for Tenmei himself to read, but it has been decoded little by little to significant portion except a part, with cooperation of his fellow Shintoists and efforts of his wife Minori OKAMOTO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the beginning it was too difficult even for Tenmei himself to read, but most of it has been decoded little by little, with cooperation of his fellow Shintoists and efforts of his wife Minori OKAMOTO.</e>
<cmt>except a part-&gt;most of it</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the beginning it was too difficult even for Tenmei himself to read, but most of it has been decoded little by little, with cooperation of his fellow Shintoists and efforts of his wife Minori OKAMOTO after his death.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>しかし、一方では神示の中に「この筆示は8通りに読めるのであるぞ」と書かれている箇所もあり解読法の一つに成功したという認識が関係者の間では一般的で、その為に仮訳と言う副題を添えての発表も有った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it includes a part written as &apos;this written revelation has 8 different interpretations&apos;, therefore the people concerned generally consider that only one of those were decoded and it was released with subtitle as tentative translation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it includes a part written as &apos;this written revelation has 8 different interpretations&apos;, therefore the people concerned generally consider that only one of those were decoded and it was released with subtitle as tentative translation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it includes a part written as &apos;this written revelation has 8 different interpretations,&apos; therefore the people concerned generally consider that only one of those were decoded and it was released with subtitle as tentative translation.</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>なお、日月神示の構成は本巻38巻と補巻1巻の計39巻から成る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hitsuki Shinji consists of total 39 volumes including 38 main volumes and 1supplementary volume.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hitsuki Shinji consists of total 39 volumes including 38 main volumes and 1 supplementary volume.</e>
<cmt>spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hitsuki Shinji consists of total 39 volumes including 38 main volumes and 1 supplementary volume.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>別名「ひふみ神示」または、「一二三神示」とも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called &apos;Hifumi Shinji ひふみ神示 or 一二三神示&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called &apos;Hifumi Shinji&apos; (ひふみ神示 or 一二三神示).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called &apos;Hifumi Shinji&apos; (ひふみ神示 or 一二三神示).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>また、上記の他にも神霊より発表を禁じられている「巻」が13巻有り、天明は「これら未発表のものは、或る時期が来れば発表を許されるものか、許されないのか、現在の所では不明であります。」と昭和36年に語っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also other than above mentioned volumes there are 13 volumes that has been prohibited to be released by the spirit and Tenmei said about it in 1961, &apos;So far I&apos;m not sure if those unpublished volumes will be allowed to be released at some time or not&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also other than above mentioned volumes there are 13 volumes that have been prohibited to be released by the spirit and Tenmei said about it in 1961, &apos;So far I&apos;m not sure if those unpublished volumes will be allowed to be released at some time or not&apos;.</e>
<cmt>has-&gt;have</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also other than above mentioned volumes there are 13 volumes that have been prohibited to be released by the spirit and Tenmei said about it in 1961, &apos;So far I&apos;m not sure if those unpublished volumes will be allowed to be released at some time or not.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオド位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>日月神示はその登場以来、関係者や一部専門家を除きほとんど知られていなかったが、1990年代の初め頃より神典研究家で翻訳家の中矢伸一の著作等により広く一般にも知られるようになって来たと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the appearance, almost no one had known about Hitsuki Shinji except the people concerned and some experts, but since around the early 1990&apos;s it has come to be known commonly due to the books written by Shinichi NAKAYA, a Shintoist and translator.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the appearance, almost no one knew about Hitsuki Shinji except the people concerned and some experts, but since around the early 1990&apos;s it has come to be known commonly due to the books written by Shinichi NAKAYA, a Shintoist and translator.</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the appearance, almost no one knew about Hitsuki Shinji except the people concerned and some experts, but since around the early 1990&apos;s it has come to be known commonly due to the books written by Shinichi NAKAYA, a Shintoist and translator.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>日月神示の降ろされた時代背景</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The historical backdrop of Hitsuki Shinji</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The historical backdrop of Hitsuki Shinji</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The historical backdrop of Hitsuki Shinji</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>写真は若かい頃のもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The photo was taken when he was young.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The photo was taken when he was young.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The photo was taken when he was young.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>近衛は第34、38、39代と3期にわたって内閣総理大臣をつとめた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Konoe served as the Prime Minister of 3 periods of the 34th, 38th and 39th.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Konoe served as the Prime Minister for 3 terms, the 34th, 38th, and 39th.</e>
<cmt>periods-&gt;terms</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Konoe served as the Prime Minister for 3 terms, the 34th, 38th, and 39th.</e>
<cmt>上付き文字削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>近衛は敗戦後にGHQよりA級戦犯者のひとりとして指名されるが、その出頭命令日前日に服毒により自ら命を絶った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was called by GHQ as one of the class-A war criminals, but one day before the day of appearance order, he took poison and committed suicide.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">GHQ named him as a class-A war criminal, but one day before the date of his summons, he took poison and committed suicide.</e>
<cmt>phrasing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">GHQ named him as a class-A war criminal, but one day before the date of his summons, he took poison and committed suicide.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>第二次世界大戦も終盤に差し掛かった昭和19年（1944年）4月18日に今後の戦局を占う意味や日本の古代史の事を聞く目的もあって東京の原宿で扶乩（フーチ）実験が行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 18 in 1944 at the end of World War II, an experimental test of Fuchi was conducted in Harajuku, Tokyo to tell the future war situation and to ask about the ancient history of Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 18, 1944, at the end of World War II, an experimental test of Fuchi was conducted in Harajuku, Tokyo, to tell the future war situation and to ask about the ancient history of Japan.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On April 18, 1944, at the end of World War II, an experimental test of Fuchi was conducted in Harajuku, Tokyo, to tell the future war situation and to ask about the ancient history of Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>扶乩とは中国に昔から伝わる神霊の御神意をうかがう占い方法で、一種の自動書記現象である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fuchi, a fortune-telling to ask sprits about God&apos;s will, is a kind of automatic writing.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fuchi, a fortune-telling to ask spirits about God&apos;s will, is a kind of automatic writing.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fuchi, a Chinese traditional fortune-telling to ask spirits about God&apos;s will, is a kind of automatic writing.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>この時の参加者は日本の古代史を研究していた修史協翼会のメンバーや、陸軍少将の小川喜一等であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The members of Shushi Kyoyokukai, who studied the ancient history of Japan and Kiichi OGAWA, an Army Major General and others participated in it.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The members of Shushi Kyoyokukai, who studied the ancient history of Japan and Kiichi OGAWA, an Army Major General and others participated in it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The members of Shushi Kyoyokukai, who studied the ancient history of Japan and Kiichi OGAWA, an Army Major General and others participated in it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>その場において審神者（サ二ワ）兼司会進行役をつとめたのが岡本天明であった。（天明はこの頃、東京の千駄ヶ谷に在る八幡神社（鳩森八幡宮）で正神主が出征中の為、留守神主をしていた）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tenmei OKAMOTO who was looking after Hachiman-jinja Shrine (Hatomori Hachiman-jinja Shrine) in Sendagaya, Tokyo as a temporary Shinto priest while the regular one was in the field, served as saniwa (person who receives and tells the revelation) and master of ceremony in it.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tenmei OKAMOTO who was looking after Hachiman-jinja Shrine (Hatomori Hachiman-jinja Shrine) in Sendagaya, Tokyo, as a temporary Shinto priest while the regular one was in the field, served as saniwa (person who receives and tells the revelation) and master of ceremony in it.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tenmei OKAMOTO who was looking after Hachiman-jinja Shrine (Hatomori Hachiman-jinja Shrine) in Sendagaya, Tokyo, as a temporary Shinto priest while the regular one was in the field, served as saniwa (person who receives and tells the revelation) and master of ceremony in it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>この時に降臨した神霊がその後に日月神示を天明に書記させていく「国常立尊」で、これがその後に続く機縁の始まりだと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The spirit, Kuninotoko Tachinokami who would have him received Hitsuki Shinji later, appeared at that time, which seemed how it all started.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The spirit Kuninotoko Tachinokami, who would later possess Hitsuki Shinji, appeared at that time, and that was the start of it all.</e>
<cmt>this sentence made no sense as it was</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The spirit Kuninotoko Tachinokami, who would later possess Hitsuki Shinji, appeared at that time, and that was the start of it all.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>ただこの時には「日月のかみ」や「天之日月神」と名乗り国常立尊とは名乗っていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, at that time, the spirit introduced himself as &apos;Hitsuku no Kami&apos; or &apos;Ame no Hitsuku no Kami&apos;, not Kuninotoko Tachinokami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, at that time, the spirit introduced himself as &apos;Hitsuku no Kami&apos; or &apos;Ame no Hitsuku no Kami&apos;, not Kuninotoko Tachinokami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, at that time, the spirit introduced himself as &apos;Hitsuku no Kami&apos; or &apos;Ame no Hitsuku no Kami,&apos; not Kuninotoko Tachinokami.</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>この扶乩実験の後、終戦直前の昭和20年の夏のある日に軍関係者（青年将校達数名）が天明のもとを訪れたのは、それまでに都合3度の内閣を組閣しその後も隠然とした力と、軍部の考えとは正反対に独自の終戦工作を画策していたらしい元内閣総理大臣経験者である「近衛文麿」に関してであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the experimental test of Fuchi, in the summer of 1945 just before the end of the war, some young military officers visited Tenmei to tell about the former Prime Minister &apos;Fumimaro KONOE&apos; who had formed his government three times and been maneuvering for termination of war with his latent power, which was the exact opposite of the military intention.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the experimental test of Fuchi, in the summer of 1945 just before the end of the war, some young military officers visited Tenmei to tell about the former Prime Minister &apos;Fumimaro KONOE&apos; who had formed his government three times and been maneuvering for termination of war with his latent power, which was the exact opposite of the military&apos;s intention.</e>
<cmt>military&apos;s</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the experimental test of Fuchi, in the summer of 1945 just before the end of the war, some young military officers visited Tenmei to tell about the former Prime Minister &apos;Fumimaro KONOE&apos; who had formed his government three times and been maneuvering for termination of war with his latent power, which was the exact opposite of the military&apos;s intention.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>将校達は「近衛は弱腰で役に立たない。｣と述べた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They said &apos;Konoe is weak-kneed and useless.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They said &apos;Konoe is weak-kneed and useless.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They said &apos;Konoe is weak-kneed and useless.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>さらに、｢このままでは日本は滅びるだけだ。｣と続けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They continued &apos;this could just destroy Japan.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They continued &apos;this could just destroy Japan.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They continued &apos;this could just destroy Japan.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>また、｢そこで、御神霊の意見を是非うかがって、その返答によっては近衛の殺害も厭わない」と述べ、かなり殺気だった雰囲気に包まれたと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They also said in a stormy atmosphere &apos;we would like to ask the spirit about God&apos;s will and depending on the answer, we are willing to kill Konoe.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They also said in a stormy atmosphere &apos;we would like to ask the spirit about God&apos;s will and depending on the answer, we are willing to kill Konoe.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They also said in a stormy atmosphere &apos;we would like to ask the spirit about God&apos;s will and depending on the answer, we are willing to kill Konoe.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>しかし、それは天明の賢断によって無事に回避されたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However it was avoided without any incident by Tenmei&apos;s wise judgment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However it was avoided without any incident by Tenmei&apos;s wise judgment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However it was avoided without any incident by Tenmei&apos;s wise judgment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>その判断とは「軍関係者の望んでいる答えと御神霊の答えが違っている場合はどうするのか？それを聞かなければお伺いは立てられない」と天明が言った事に対して、軍関係者達に神霊の言葉に従うという内容の約束をさせた事であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He said &apos;what are you going to do if the answer of spirit is different from the will of the military? I can&apos;t ask it to him before you answer it.&apos; and have them agreed to follow the answer of the spirit.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He said &apos;what are you going to do if the answer of spirit is different from the will of the military? I can&apos;t ask it to him before you answer it.&apos; and they agreed to follow the answer of the spirit.</e>
<cmt>have them-&gt;they</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He said &apos;what are you going to do if the answer of spirit is different from the will of the military? I can&apos;t ask it to him before you answer it.&apos; and they agreed to follow the answer of the spirit.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>神霊の回答は「それはならぬ」だったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The spirit answered &apos;don&apos;t do that.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The spirit answered &apos;don&apos;t do that.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The spirit answered &apos;don&apos;t do that.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>この頃はまだ日月神示の解読は十分されてはなかった筈だが、軍人の一部にはすでにこれを信頼し神聖視していた者もいたらしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though Hitsuki Shinji was not decoded enough at that time, some of the military officials seemed to believe and sacralise it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though Hitsuki Shinji was not decoded enough at that time, some of the military officials seemed to believe and sanctify it.</e>
<cmt>sanctify</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though Hitsuki Shinji was not decoded enough at that time, some of the military officials seemed to believe and sanctify it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>神示にはその後の日本の敗戦を明らかに書記されている部分があり、希望を失っていた軍人の中でも、前もってそれを知っていた為に終戦時に自殺を思いとどまった者も多く居たという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because it was written the future defeat of Japan clearly in the revelation, it helped prevent many of hopeless soldiers from committed suicide.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because Japan&apos;s future defeat was written clearly the revelation, it helped prevent many hopeless soldiers from committing suicide.</e>
<cmt>all kinds of problems here</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because Japan&apos;s future defeat was written clearly the revelation, it helped prevent many hopeless soldiers from committing suicide.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="28">
<j>日月神示が遂に降ろされる</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hitsuki Shinji finally came down</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hitsuki Shinji finally came down</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hitsuki Shinji finally came down</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="29">
<j>前述の扶乩実験の約2ヶ月後の6月10日に天明は知人であった高田集蔵の誘いで千葉県印旛郡公津村台方（現・成田市台方）を訪れるが、そこに実験の時に現れた天之日月神を祀る延喜式内社で麻賀多神社の末社である「天之日津久神社」があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On June 10, after two months from the Fuchi experiment, Tenmei was invited to Daikata, Kozu village, Inba Country, Chiba Prefecture (presently Daikata in Narita City) by his acquaintance Shuzo TAKADA, where was &apos;Ame no Hitsuku-jinja Shrine&apos; of Ame no Hitsuku no Kami,a subordinate shrine of Makata-jinja Shrine listed in the Kangi-shiki shrine list.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On June 10, two months after the Fuchi experiment, Tenmei was invited to Daikata, Kozu village, Inba County, Chiba Prefecture (presently Daikata in Narita City) by his acquaintance Shuzo TAKADA, where was &apos;Ame no Hitsuku-jinja Shrine&apos; of Ame no Hitsuku no Kami was located, which is a subordinate shrine of Makata-jinja Shrine listed in the Kangi-shiki shrine list.</e>
<cmt>spelling; punctuation; spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On June 10, two months after the Fuchi experiment, Tenmei was invited to Daikata, Kozu village, Inba County, Chiba Prefecture (presently Daikata in Narita City) by his acquaintance Shuzo TAKADA, where was &apos;Ame no Hitsuku-jinja Shrine&apos; of Ame no Hitsuku no Kami was located, which is a subordinate shrine of Makata-jinja Shrine listed in the Engishikinaisha shrine list.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="30">
<j>神典研究家であった天明でも天之日月神がいかなる神なのか、また、どこに鎮座され祀られている神なのかが扶乩実験後もしばらくは分らなかったと後に述懐している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tenmei recalled later that even he as a Shintoist hadn&apos;t known for a while after the Fuchi experiment what God Ame no Hitsuku no Kami was and which shrine was dedicated to him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tenmei recalled later that even he as a Shintoist hadn&apos;t known for a while after the Fuchi experiment what God Ame no Hitsuku no Kami was and which shrine was dedicated to him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tenmei recalled later that even he as a Shintoist hadn&apos;t known for a while after the Fuchi experiment what God Ame no Hitsuku no Kami was and which shrine was dedicated to him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="31">
<j>天明によると天之日津久神社を参拝し厚く御礼を申し上げ、社務所で一息ついている時に予期しない自動書記現象が起こったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Tenmei, when he was taking a rest after giving his appreciation at Ame no Hituku-jinja Shrine, he got the automatic writing phenomenon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Tenmei, when he was taking a rest after giving his appreciation at Ame no Hituku-jinja Shrine, he experienced the automatic writing phenomenon.</e>
<cmt>got-&gt;experienced</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Tenmei, when he was taking a rest after giving his appreciation at Ame no Hitsuku-jinja Shrine, he experienced the automatic writing phenomenon.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>画家でもあった天明は画仙紙や矢立を常に持ち歩く習慣がありこの時も例外では無かったが、突然、額のあたりに「ピリッ」とした強い衝動と右手に非常な激痛を感じ（天明の言葉によれば、右腕に焼火箸を突っ込まれたような激痛だったという）、矢立と紙を取り出したところ自分の意思に反して猛烈な勢いで筆が走り意味不明の殴り書きをした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tenmei was usually bringing drawing papers and a portable brush-and-ink case as a painter and when he felt a strong shock on his forehead and an acute pain in his right arm (he expressed it as if burned metal chop stick was stuck in his right arm) and he took out his brush and a paper, the brush moved very fast automatically and scribbled unknown terms.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tenmei usually brought drawing papers and a portable brush-and-ink case as a painter and when he felt a strong shock on his forehead and an acute pain in his right arm (he expressed it as if a burned metal chop stick was stuck in his right arm) and he took out his brush and a paper, the brush moved very fast automatically and scribbled unknown terms.</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tenmei usually brought drawing papers and a portable brush-and-ink case as a painter and when he felt a strong shock on his forehead and an acute pain in his right arm (he expressed it as if a burned metal chop stick was stuck in his right arm) and he took out his brush and a paper, the brush moved very fast automatically and scribbled unknown terms.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>以前から霊的体験が豊富で自らも霊媒役等を務めた経験がある天明は、右腕の激痛時にこれらは自動書記の前触れかもしれないと瞬間的に思ったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because he had a lot of spiritual and spirit medium experiences, he thought instantaneously that it would be sign of coming automatic writing when he had an acute pain in his right arm.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because he had a lot of spiritual and spirit medium experiences, he thought instantaneously that it was a sign of automatic writing when he had an acute pain in his right arm.</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because he had a lot of spiritual and spirit medium experiences, he thought instantaneously that it was a sign of automatic writing when he had an acute pain in his right arm.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>従来の自動書記では天明自身が中止しようと思えば中止出来たが、今回の場合は中止しようとすれば更に右腕の激痛が耐えられぬほどになり全く自由にならなかったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Normally he had been able to stop automatic writing by his will, but at that time, the more he tried to stop, the more pain he got in his right arm and couldn&apos;t stop that.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Normally he had been able to stop automatic writing by his will, but at that time, the more he tried to stop, the more pain he got in his right arm and he couldn&apos;t stop.</e>
<cmt>deleted “that”</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Normally he had been able to stop automatic writing by his will, but at that time, the more he tried to stop, the more pain he got in his right arm and he couldn&apos;t stop.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="35">
<j>これが後に日月神示と呼ばれる神示、神典でこの日が発現の重要な日となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is the Divine Revelation that is called Hitsuki Shinji later and it was the important day of the appearance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was the Divine Revelation that was later called Hitsuki Shinji and it was the important day of the appearance.</e>
<cmt>phrasing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was the Divine Revelation that was later called Hitsuki Shinji and it was the important day of the appearance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>なお、書記を終えた時には先程までの右腕の激痛は嘘のように消えていたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the writing was finished, the pain in his right arm was gone magically.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the writing was finished, the pain in his right arm was gone magically.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the writing was finished, the pain in his right arm was gone magically.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>その後も神示が降りてくる時には右腕が痛くなり、書記が終われば治まるということの繰り返しが続いたと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since then, every time the revelation was received, he had pain in his right arm and after finished writing the pain was gone.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since then, every time the revelation was received, he had pain in his right arm and after finished writing the pain was gone.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since then, every time the revelation was received, he had pain in his right arm and after finished writing the pain was gone.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="38">
<j>なお、この時に書記されたものが日月神示の第一巻である「上つ巻」（うえつ巻）の第一帖及び第二帖であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">What were written at that time are the first and second chapters of &apos;volume Uetsu&apos;, the first volume of Hitsuki Shinji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">What were written at that time are the first and second chapters of volume &apos;Uetsu&apos;, the first volume of Hitsuki Shinji.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">What were written at that time are the first and second chapters of volume &apos;Uetsu,&apos; the first volume of Hitsuki Shinji.</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="39">
<j>日月神示原文と解釈</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The original text and interpretation of Hitsuki Shinji</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The original text and interpretation of Hitsuki Shinji</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The original text and interpretation of Hitsuki Shinji</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>麻賀多神社の社務所で天明が最初に自動書記で書かされた原文は右のようなものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The original text that Tenmei was made to write automatically first at the shrine office of Makata-jinja Shrine was as follows:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The original text that Tenmei was made to write automatically first at the shrine office of Makata-jinja Shrine was as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The original text that Tenmei was made to write automatically first at the shrine office of Makata-jinja Shrine was as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>「二二八八れ十二ほん八れ　㋹の九二のま九十の㋹のちからをあら八す四十七れる」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">2288re12hon8re ㋹-no 92-no ma90-no ㋹-no chikara wo ara8su 47reru&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">2288re12hon8re ㋹-no 92-no ma90-no ㋹-no chikara wo ara8su 47reru&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">2288re12hon8re ㋹-no 92-no ma90-no ㋹-no chikara wo ara8su 47reru&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>これは次の通りに読めると言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered to be interpreted as follows:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered to be interpreted as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered to be interpreted as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>「富士は晴れたり日本晴れ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&apos;Fuji was haretari nihonbare. Kami no kuni no makoto no chikara wo arawasu yo to nareru. (Fuji is perfect. The weather is perfect. The world will show the true God&apos;s power of the God&apos;s county)&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fuji was haretari nihonbare. Kami no kuni no makoto no chikara wo arawasu yo to nareru.&apos; (Fuji is perfect. The weather is perfect. The world will show the true God&apos;s power of the God&apos;s county)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fuji was haretari nihonbare.&apos; (Fuji is perfect and the weather is perfect.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>「神の国のまことの神の力を現す世となれる。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kami no kuni no makoto no chikara wo arawasu yo to nareru.&apos; (The world will show the true God&apos;s power of the God&apos;s county.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>続いて「卍も十も九も八きりたすけて七六かしい五くろうのない四かくるから　三たまを二たんにみかいて一すしのま九十を十四て九れ四　いま一十九十六あるか　九の九六八三たまを三かいておらぬ十こせぬ　九の四八まって二十十七一九六てある」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It continues &apos;卍-mo 10-mo 9-mo 8kiri tasukete 76kashii 5kuro-no nai 4ka kurukara 3tama-wo 2tan-ni mikaite 1sushi-no ma90-wo 14te9re4 ima1-10-96 aruka 9-no 9683tama-wo 3kaiteoranu 10kosenu 9-no 48matte 2-10- 10- 71 96tearu.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It continues &apos;卍-mo 10-mo 9-mo 8kiri tasukete 76kashii 5kuro-no nai 4ka kurukara 3tama-wo 2tan-ni mikaite 1sushi-no ma90-wo 14te9re4 ima1-10-96 aruka 9-no 9683tama-wo 3kaiteoranu 10kosenu 9-no 48matte 2-10- 10- 71 96tearu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It continues &apos;卍-mo 10-mo 9-mo 8kiri tasukete 76kashii 5kuro-no nai 4ka kurukara 3tama-wo 2tan-ni mikaite 1sushi-no ma90-wo 14te9re4 ima1-10-96 aruka 9-no 9683tama-wo 3kaiteoranu 10kosenu 9-no 48matte 2-10- 10- 71 96tearu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>これについても、読み方は「仏もキリストも何もかも、ハッキリ助けてシチ難しい御苦労の無い世がくるからミタマを不断に磨いて一筋のマコトを通して呉れよ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is read as &apos;Hotoke mo Kirisuto mo nanimokamo hakkiri tasukete shichi muzukashi gokuro no nai yo ga kurukara mitama wo hudan ni migaite hitosuji no makoto wo toshite kureyo. (Everything including Buddha and Christ will help clearly to make the world without any difficult troubles, so please improve your spirit constantly and keep being honest)&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is read as &apos;Hotoke mo Kirisuto mo nanimokamo hakkiri tasukete shichi muzukashi gokuro no nai yo ga kurukara mitama wo hudan ni migaite hitosuji no makoto wo toshite kureyo.&apos; (Everything including Buddha and Christ will help clearly to make the world without any difficult troubles, so please improve your spirit constantly and keep being honest)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is read as &apos;Hotoke mo Kirisuto mo nanimokamo hakkiri tasukete shichi muzukashi gokuro no nai yo ga kurukara mitama wo fudan ni migaite hitosuji no makoto wo toshite kureyo.&apos; (Everything including Buddha and Christ will help clearly to make the world without any difficult troubles, so please improve your spirit constantly and keep being honest)</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>「今一苦労あるが、この苦労はミタマを磨いておらぬと越せぬ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hitokuro aruga kono kuro wa mitama wo migaite oranuto kosenu konoyo hajimatte nido to nai kuro dearu. (You will have one more hardship which you cannot go over without improving your spirit. It is the biggest hardship that the world ever has)&apos;</e>
<cmt>　</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hitokuro aruga kono kuro wa mitama wo migaite oranuto kosenu konoyo hajimatte nido to nai kuro dearu.&apos; (You will have one more hardship which you cannot go over without improving your spirit. It is the biggest hardship that the world ever has)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hitokuro aruga kono kuro wa mitama wo migaite oranuto kosenu.&apos; (You will have one more hardship which you cannot go over without improving your spirit.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>「この世始まって二度とない苦労である。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Konoyo hajimatte nido to nai kuro dearu.&apos; (It is the biggest hardship that the world ever has.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処&apos;konoyo →&apos;Konoyo</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="49">
<j>これは次のように解釈されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is interpreted as follows:</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is interpreted as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is interpreted as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>｢マコトの神が世に出現して神の力を現して、すべてを助け何の苦労もない理想的な世界に立て直していくが、その前には人類は未だかつてなかった程の大災厄や大試練を迎えなければならない。｣</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A true God will appear in the world and show his power and help everyone to make the world ideal without any hardship, but before that people must have the biggest disaster and trial.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A true God will appear in the world and show his power and help everyone to make the world ideal without any hardship, but before that people must have the biggest disaster and trial.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A true God will appear in the world and show his power and help everyone to make the world ideal without any hardship, but before that people must have the biggest disaster and trial.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>｢助かる為には身魂（心、精神、身体）を絶え間なく磨きつつ備えよ。｣</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prepare for it by improving your mind, spirit and body constantly to survive.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prepare for it by improving your mind, spirit and body constantly to survive.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prepare for it by improving your mind, spirit and body constantly to survive.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>｢磨いていなければ助かることが出来ない。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">You will not survive without improving yourself.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">You will not survive without improving yourself.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">You will not survive without improving yourself.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>これらの帖を手始めに昭和19年から天明が亡くなる2年前の昭和36年まで17年間にわたり神示は書記されていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Beginning with those chapters, the Revelation had been written for 17 years from 1944 until 1961, two years before Tenmei&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Beginning with those chapters, the Revelation had been written for 17 years from 1944 until 1961, two years before Tenmei&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Beginning with those chapters, the Revelation had been written for 17 years from 1944 until 1961, two years before Tenmei&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>日月神示は「人間の生き方」、「正しい食生活について」、「夫婦のありかた」、更には「霊界」の実相についても書記されているなど非常に広範囲にわたっての記述が見られるが、未来に関するいわゆる「予言書」的な記述部分も見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hitsuki Shinji includes very broad area such as &apos;a way of life&apos; &apos;proper diet&apos; &apos;marital relationship&apos;, the real state of &apos;the spiritual world&apos;, and also descriptions about the future like so-called &apos;prophets&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hitsuki Shinji covers very broad areas such as &apos;way of life,&apos; &apos;proper diet,&apos; &apos;marital relationships,&apos;, the real state of &apos;the spiritual world&apos;, and also descriptions about the future like so-called &apos;prophets&apos;.</e>
<cmt>includes-&gt;covers; punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hitsuki Shinji covers very broad areas such as &apos;way of life,&apos; &apos;proper diet,&apos; &apos;marital relationships,&apos;, the real state of &apos;the spiritual world&apos;, and also descriptions about the future like so-called &apos;prophets.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオド位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>日月神示はそのほとんどが数字や記号で書記されているが、その理由を神霊自らが神示の中で次のように述べている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reason why Hitsuki Shinji is mostly written in numbers and symbols is told by the spirit himself in the Revelation as follows:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reason why Hitsuki Shinji is mostly written in numbers and symbols is told by the spirit himself in the Revelation as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reason why Hitsuki Shinji is mostly written in numbers and symbols is told by the spirit himself in the Revelation as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="56">
<j>「高度の霊人の文字として、殆ど数字のみが使用されている場合もある。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Numbers are often used as the scripts by holly spirits.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Numbers are often used as scripts by holy spirits.&apos;</e>
<cmt>articles; spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Numbers are often used as scripts by holy spirits.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>「数字は、他の文字に比して多くの密意を蔵しているからである」（二日んの巻第十三帖）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is because that numbers have more hidden true meanings than other scripts.&apos; (the chapter 13 of volume Jishin)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is because numbers have more hidden true meanings than other scripts.&apos; (chapter 13 of volume Jishin)</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is because numbers have more hidden true meanings than other scripts.&apos; (chapter 13 of volume Jishin)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>「天人同志の文字は数字が多いぞ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In heaven we often use numbers to communicate with each other.&apos; &apos;In heaven our words are true, so we can tell tens of thousands words in only one word.&apos; (the chapter 18 and 19 of &apos;volume Seiza&apos; [constellation])</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In heaven we often use numbers to communicate with each other.&apos; &apos;In heaven our words are true, so we can tell tens of thousands of words in only one word.&apos; (chapter 18 and 19 of volume &apos;constellations&apos;)</e>
<cmt>prepositions; articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In heaven we often use numbers to communicate with each other.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>「天人の言葉はマコトであるから、只一言で万語を伝え得るぞ。」（「星座之巻」第十八帖、第十九帖）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In heaven our words are true, so we can tell tens of thousands of words in only one word.&apos; (chapter 18 and 19 of volume &apos;constellations&apos;)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>同様な事は霊能者で有名なスェーデンのE.スウェデンボルグも天界探訪の事を記した自著で「天人の文字は数字ばかりであった。」と書いていて興味深いものが有る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">What is interesting is that Swedish famous psychic E. Swedenborg wrote the same thing in his book about touring heaven as &apos;in heaven people always use numbers.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">What is interesting is that famous Swedish psychic E. Swedenborg wrote the same thing in his book about touring heaven as &apos;in heaven people always use numbers.&apos;</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">What is interesting is that famous Swedish psychic E. Swedenborg wrote the same thing in his book about touring heaven as &apos;in heaven people always use numbers.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>日月神示より以前に他で出された物ではこのような事は見られず、神霊が「今まで他に出て居たのは皆、神示先（ふでさき）ぢゃ。ここは神示（ふで）ぢゃ。キの神示ぢゃ」（カゼの巻第六帖）と書記させている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before Hitsuki Shinji, such description hadn&apos;t been seen in any publication and the sprit have him written &apos;all before this were predictions and this is the revelation of Ki&apos; (the chapter 6 of volume Kaze)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before Hitsuki Shinji, such description hadn&apos;t been seen in any publication and the spirit made him write &apos;all before this were predictions and this is the revelation of Ki&apos; (chapter 6 of volume Kaze).</e>
<cmt>spelling; verb conjugation; punctuation; articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before Hitsuki Shinji, such description hadn&apos;t been seen in any publication and the spirit made him write &apos;all before this were predictions and this is the revelation of Ki&apos; (chapter 6 of volume Kaze).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>また、「アメの巻」第十三帖でも次のように語っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also in the chapter 13 of &apos;volume Ame&apos; it is written as follows: &apos;This is the only revelation that shows fundamental Ki. I&apos;ll tell everything about the Three Thousand World.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also in chapter 13 of volume &apos;Ame&apos; it is written as follows: &apos;This is the only revelation that shows fundamental Ki. I&apos;ll tell everything about the Three Thousand World.&apos;</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also in chapter 13 of volume &apos;Ame&apos; it is written as follows:</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>「外で判らん根本のキのこと知らす此の方の神示ぢゃ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is the only revelation that shows fundamental Ki.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>「三千世界のこと一切の事説いて聞かして得心させて上げますぞや。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">I&apos;ll tell everything about the Three Thousand World.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>「落ち着いて聞き落としのない様になされよ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Listen calm not to miss.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Listen calmly so as not to miss.&apos;</e>
<cmt>expressions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Listen calmly so as not to miss.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="66">
<j>また、一方ではこの神示は単に現界に生きる人間のみならず、天界や霊界、また、その他多くの世界に住んでいる存在（神、竜神、天人、天使、霊人達）にも等しく与えられているらしい次のような記述も見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, this Revelation seems to be given not only people in this world but also in heaven and spiritual world and gods, the Dragon King, celestial beings, angels, spirits in the other worlds equally.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, this Revelation seems to be given not only to people in this world but also in heaven and spiritual worlds and to gods, the Dragon King, celestial beings, angels, spirits in the other worlds equally.</e>
<cmt>prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, this Revelation seems to be given not only to people in this world but also in heaven and spiritual worlds and to gods, the Dragon King, celestial beings, angels, spirits in the other worlds equally.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>「この神示は、神と竜神と天人天使と人民たちに与えてあるのぢゃ」と「極め之巻」第十八帖で述べている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the chapter 18 of &apos;volume Kiwame&apos; it is written &apos;this revelation is being given to gods, the Dragon King, inhabitants of heaven, celestial beings, spirits and people.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the chapter 18 of volume &apos;Kiwame&apos; it is written &apos;this revelation is being given to gods, the Dragon King, inhabitants of heaven, celestial beings, spirits and people.&apos;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the chapter 18 of volume &apos;Kiwame&apos; it is written &apos;this revelation is being given to gods, the Dragon King, inhabitants of heaven, celestial beings, spirits and people.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="68">
<j>三千世界の大道</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Three Thousand World principle</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Three Thousand World principle</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Three Thousand World principle</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="69">
<j>日月神示の内容は極めて広範囲にわたり、そのそれぞれに多くの記述が見られるが最も大きな特徴は神霊自身が「黄金の巻」第二帖で次のように述べている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hitsuki Shinji covering very broad and many descriptions features a description in chapter 2 of volume &apos;Ogon&apos; (gold) as follows:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hitsuki Shinji covering very broad and many descriptions features a description in chapter 2 of volume &apos;Ogon&apos; (gold) as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hitsuki Shinji covering very broad and many descriptions features a description in chapter 2 of volume &apos;Ogon&apos; (gold) as follows:</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>「今迄の日本の宗教は日本だけの宗教。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The existing religions in Japan are only for Japan. But the Three Thousand World principle is the basic of the whole world and not just a teaching.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The existing religions in Japan are only for Japan. But the Three Thousand World principle is the basis of the whole world and not just a teaching.&apos;</e>
<cmt>basis</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The existing religions in Japan are only for Japan.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>「この度は世界のもとの、三千世界の大道ぞ、教えでないぞ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But the Three Thousand World principle is the basis of the whole world and not just a teaching.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>このように神示を宗教でもなく教えでもないと語っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">So, it is described the Revelation as neither religion nor teaching.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">So, it described the Revelation as neither religion nor teaching.</e>
<cmt>deleted “is”</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">So, it described the Revelation as neither religion nor teaching.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>その為に既成宗教の信仰のあり方や教えとは大きく異なるものが多く、それらを否定している記述も随所に見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore it often differs from the faiths and teachings of existing religions and also often denies them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore it often differs from the faiths and teachings of existing religions and also often denies them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore it often differs from the faiths and teachings of existing religions and also often denies them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>例えば既成宗教では有名な教えのひとつとされる「右の頬を打たれたら、左の頬も出しなさい」と言う教えについてでは日月神示を書記させたこの神霊は次のように述べている。（極め之巻第十五帖）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, the spirit of Hitsuki Shinji describes one of the famous teachings of an existing religion, &apos;Whoever hits you on the cheek, offer him the other also&apos; in chapter 15 of volume Kiwame as follows:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, the spirit of Hitsuki Shinji describes one of the famous teachings of an existing religion, &apos;Whoever hits you on the cheek, offer him the other also&apos; in chapter 15 of volume Kiwame as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, the spirit of Hitsuki Shinji describes one of the famous teachings of an existing religion, &apos;Whoever hits you on the cheek, offer him the other also&apos; in chapter 15 of volume Kiwame as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="75">
<j>「右の頬をうたれたら左の頬を出せよ、それが無抵抗で平和の元ぢゃと申しているが、その心根をよく洗って見つめよ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It says that whoever hits you on the cheek, offer him the other also for peace, but clean your mind and look carefully. It is not nonresistance. You will be hit if you have something to be hit in your mind.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It says that whoever hits you on the cheek, offer him the other also for peace, but clean your mind and look carefully. It is not nonresistance. You will be hit if you have something to be hit in your mind.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It says that whoever hits you on the cheek, offer him the other also for peace, but clean your mind and look carefully.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>「それは無抵抗ではないぞ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is not nonresistance.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>「打たれるようなものを心の中にもっているから打たれるのぞ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">You will be hit if you have something to be hit in your mind.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>「マコトに居れば相手が手をふり上げても打つことは出来ん。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If you are sincere, a raised hand will be put down. Listen carefully and understand.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If you are sincere, a raised hand will be put down. Listen carefully and understand.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If you are sincere, a raised hand will be put down.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>「よくききわけてくだされよ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Listen carefully and understand.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>「笑って来る赤子の無邪気は打たれんであろう。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">You will never hit infants smiling and approaching you. That is nonresistance.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">You will never hit infants smiling and approaching you. That is nonresistance.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">You will never hit infants smiling and approaching you.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>「これが無抵抗ぞ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That is nonresistance.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>「世界一家天下太平ぢゃ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The world is one family and at peace. Don&apos;t be silly to offer your left cheek.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The world is one family and at peace. Don&apos;t be silly to offer your left cheek.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The world is one family and at peace.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>「左の頬を出すおろかさをやめて下されよ」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Don&apos;t be silly to offer your left cheek.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="84">
<j>この帖に関しては、幼児虐待や幼児殺しをしてしまう親が度々ニュースになるなど、説得力のない文章だと考える人や意見もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some people consider this chapter as unconvincing, because there are some parents in the news who abuse and kill their children.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some people consider this chapter unconvincing, because there are some parents in the news who abuse and kill their children.</e>
<cmt>prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some people consider this chapter unconvincing, because there are some parents in the news who abuse and kill their children.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="85">
<j>同様に既成宗教では神の「しるし」や「証し」として重要視される奇跡であるが、これについても完全に否定、いくつかの帖で言及し、奇跡やこれらを求め信じる人に警鐘を鳴らしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also it completely denies miracles which existing religions regard as important &apos;sign&apos; and &apos;proof&apos; of God and refers to them in some chapters sounding an alarm to people who want such miracles and believe them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also it completely denies miracles which existing religions regard as important &apos;sign&apos; and &apos;proof&apos; of God and refers to them in some chapters sounding an alarm to people who want such miracles and believe them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also it completely denies miracles which existing religions regard as important &apos;sign&apos; and &apos;proof&apos; of God and refers to them in some chapters sounding an alarm to people who want such miracles and believe them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>また、他の多くの宗教が修行の一環として断食の必要性やその意義を説いているが日月神示では「正しい食生活について」で、次のように、断食すること自体を厳しく戒めているのも注目される。（春の巻第五帖）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also while many religions preach the necessity and meaning of fast as a part of the practice, it is striking that Hitsuki Shinji warns against fast itself strictly in &apos;proper eating habits&apos; as follows (chapter 5 of volume spring):</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also while many religions preach the necessity and meaning of fasting as a part of the practice, it is striking that Hitsuki Shinji warns against fasting itself strictly in &apos;proper eating habits&apos; as follows (chapter 5 of volume spring):</e>
<cmt>fasting</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also while many religions preach the necessity and meaning of fasting as a part of the practice, it is striking that Hitsuki Shinji warns against fasting itself strictly in &apos;proper eating habits&apos; as follows (chapter 5 of volume spring):</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>「食物を食べるのも喜びであるぞ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eating is also a joy.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eating is also a joy.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eating is also a joy.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>「正しき食物正しく食べよ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eat right foods.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eat right foods.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eat right foods.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>「更に喜びふへて弥栄へるのぢゃ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">You&apos;ll have more pleasures and will flourish.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">You&apos;ll have more pleasures and will flourish.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">You&apos;ll have more pleasures and will flourish.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>「悪い食物悪く食べるから悪くなるのぢゃ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eating bad foods badly will make you worse.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eating bad foods badly will make you worse.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eating bad foods badly will make you worse.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>「何も彼も同様ぞ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is same for everything.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is the same for everything.&apos;</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is the same for everything.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>「人民は喜びの子と申してあろう。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">People are children of joy.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">People are children of joy.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">People are children of joy.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>「罪の子でないぞ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Not children of sin.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Not children of sin.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Not children of sin.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>「うれしうれしの道あるに、何故歩まんのぢゃ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Why don&apos;t you take the joyful way?&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Why don&apos;t you take the joyful way?&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Why don&apos;t you take the joyful way?&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="95">
<j>しかし、一方で多食や肉食についてはこれを戒めている。（冬の巻捕帖）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, it warns against eating much and eating meat as follows (complementary chapter of volume winter) :</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, it warns against eating much and eating meat as follows (complementary chapter of volume winter):</e>
<cmt>spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, it warns against eating much and eating meat as follows (complementary chapter of volume winter):</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>「食物節してこそ、ささげてこそ、運ひらけるのぢゃ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">You will have better luck by controlling your eating and by devoting.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">You will have better luck by controlling your eating and by devoting.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">You will have better luck by controlling your eating and by devoting.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>「病治るのぢゃ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also you&apos;ll recover from illness.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also you&apos;ll recover from illness.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also you&apos;ll recover from illness.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>「食物、今の半分で足りると申してあらうが。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">I&apos;m telling you, the half of the amount that you currently eat is enough.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">I&apos;m telling you, half of the amount that you currently eat is enough.&apos;</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">I&apos;m telling you, half of the amount that you currently eat is enough.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>「遠くて近いものヒフミの食べ方して見なされよ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Try Hifumi way of eating, which is far and near.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Try the Hifumi way of eating, which is far and near.&apos;</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Try the Hifumi way of eating, which is far and near.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>「運ひらけ、病治ってうれしうれしと輝くぞ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">You will have better luck and recover from illness and beam with happiness.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">You will have better luck and recover from illness and beam with happiness.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">You will have better luck and recover from illness and beam with happiness.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>「そんなこと位で、病治ったり、運開ける位なら、人民はこんなに苦しまんと申すが、それが理窟と申すもの。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">You may say that if such a way cured illness and brought good-luck, no one would be suffered, but it is just logic.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">You may say that if such a way cured illness and brought good luck, no one would suffer, but it is just logic.&apos;</e>
<cmt>deleted hyphen; changed “suffer” to active voice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">You may say that if such a way cured illness and brought good luck, no one would suffer, but it is just logic.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>「理窟悪と申してあるもの。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is not good that you are all talk.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is not good that you are all talk.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is not good that you are all talk.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>「低い学に囚われたメクラ、ツンボと申すものぞ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">You are like a blind and deaf with no education, when you are all talk.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">You are like a blind and deaf person with no education, when you are all talk.&apos;</e>
<cmt>added “person”</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">You are like a blind and deaf person with no education, when you are all talk.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>「四ツ足を食ってはならん。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Don&apos;t eat four-footed animals. It will be cannibalization. I&apos;m telling you, animals are born to plants. People should eat grains and vegetables.&apos; (chapter 8 of volume Hekigyoku)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Don&apos;t eat four-footed animals. It will be cannibalization. I&apos;m telling you, animals are born to plants. People should eat grains and vegetables.&apos; (chapter 8 of volume Hekigyoku)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Don&apos;t eat four-footed animals.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>「共喰となるぞ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It will be cannibalization.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>「草木から動物生まれると申してあろう。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">I&apos;m telling you, animals are born to plants.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>「臣民の食物は五穀野菜の類であるぞ。」（碧玉の巻第八帖）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">People should eat grains and vegetables.&apos; (chapter 8 of volume Hekigyoku)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>なお肉食についてはそれを戒めつつも、次のようにも書記させている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While it warns against eating meat, it also says &apos;when you eat meat, offer it to God once first and receive it from him. By doing that, they become God&apos;s foods. This way you can eat anything.&apos; (chapter 5 of volume Amatsu)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While it warns against eating meat, it also says &apos;when you eat meat, offer it to God once first and receive it from him. By doing that, they become God&apos;s foods. This way you can eat anything.&apos; (chapter 5 of volume Amatsu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While it warns against eating meat, it also says as follows.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="109">
<j>「獣の喰ひ物くふ時には一度神に献げてからにせよ、神から頂けよ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When you eat meat, offer it to God once first and receive it from him.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>「さうすれば神の喰べ物となる。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By doing that, they become God&apos;s foods.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>「何たべても大じょうぶになるのぞ」（天つ巻第五帖）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This way you can eat anything.&apos; (chapter 5 of volume Amatsu)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="112">
<j>「人間の生き方」に関しては次の記述が代表的なものであろう。（富士の巻第十四帖）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The representative of &apos;a way of life&apos; is the following description. (chapter 14 of volume Fuji)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The representative of &apos;a way of life&apos; is the following description. (chapter 14 of volume Fuji)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The representative of &apos;a way of life&apos; is the following description. (chapter 14 of volume Fuji)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="113">
<j>「臣民にわかる様にいうなれば、身も心も神のものである。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Making it clear for people, both your body and soul belong to God. You can consider it as something given from God. This way you will know how to keep your body. It will become clear when you consider it as when you are sleeping at night, you are returning your body.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Making it clear for people, both your body and soul belong to God. You can consider it something given from God. This way you will know how to keep your body. It will become clear when you consider that when you are sleeping at night, you are returning your body.&apos;</e>
<cmt>prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Making it clear for people, both your body and soul belong to God.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="114">
<j>「毎日毎日神から頂いたものと思えばよいのであるぞ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">You can consider it something given from God.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>「それでその身体をどんなにしたらよいかと云ふこと分かるであろう。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This way you will know how to keep your body.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="116">
<j>「夜になれば眠ったときはお返ししてゐるのざと思へ、それでよく分かるであろうが。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It will become clear when you consider that when you are sleeping at night, you are returning your body.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="117">
<j>「身魂みがくと申すことは、神の入れものとして神からお預りしてゐる、神の最も尊いとことしてお扱いすることぞ」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Improving your body and soul means treating them as God&apos;s most precious things and God&apos;s container which you are keeping for him&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Improving your body and soul means treating them as God&apos;s most precious things and God&apos;s container which you are keeping for him&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Improving your body and soul means treating them as God&apos;s most precious things and God&apos;s container which you are keeping for him&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="118">
<j>また、次のようにも語っている。（日月の巻第十五帖）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also says as follows (chapter 5 of volume Hitsuki):</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also says as follows (chapter 5 of volume Hitsuki):</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also says as follows (chapter 5 of volume Hitsuki):</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="119">
<j>「目覚めたら其の日の生命お預りした事を神に感謝し、其の生命を神の御心のままに弥栄に仕へまつる事に祈れよ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When you wake up, give thanks to God that you have the life for the day and pray to flourish by the will of God.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When you wake up, give thanks to God that you have the life for the day and pray to flourish by the will of God.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When you wake up, give thanks to God that you have the life for the day and pray to flourish by the will of God.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="120">
<j>「神は其の日其の時に何すべきかに就いて教へるぞ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">God will tell you what to do one day at a time.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">God will tell you what to do one day at a time.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">God will tell you what to do one day at a time.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="121">
<j>「明日の事に心使ふなよ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Don&apos;t worry about tomorrow.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Don&apos;t worry about tomorrow.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Don&apos;t worry about tomorrow.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="122">
<j>「心は配れよ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Just be mindful.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Just be mindful.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Just be mindful.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="123">
<j>「取越苦労するなよ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Don&apos;t worry unnecessarily.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Don&apos;t worry unnecessarily.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Don&apos;t worry unnecessarily.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="124">
<j>更に夫婦のありかたについては次のように述べている。（春の巻第二十六帖）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also describes about marital relationship as follows (chapter 26 of volume spring):</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also talks about marital relationship as follows (chapter 26 of volume spring):</e>
<cmt>describes-&gt;talks</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also talks about marital relationship as follows (chapter 26 of volume spring):</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="125">
<j>「愛は養はねばならん。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Love is to be cultivated.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Love is to be cultivated.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Love is to be cultivated.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="126">
<j>「夫婦はいのちがけで、お互にきづき合はねばならんぞ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Husband and wife must take care of each other at the risk of their lives.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Husband and wife must take care of each other at the risk of their lives.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Husband and wife must take care of each other at the risk of their lives.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="127">
<j>「夫婦愛はあるのではない。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Conjugal love doesn&apos;t exist simply.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Conjugal love doesn&apos;t exist simply.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Conjugal love doesn&apos;t exist simply.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="128">
<j>「築き上げねばならんぞ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is something to be built by yourselves&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is something to be built by yourselves&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is something to be built by yourselves&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="129">
<j>「つくり出すのぢゃ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is to create by yourselves.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is to create by yourselves.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is to create by yourselves.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="130">
<j>「そこに尊さあるぞ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">You will see the preciousness in it.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">You will see the preciousness in it.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">You will see the preciousness in it.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="131">
<j>「喜びあるぞ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">You&apos;ll see the joy in it.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">You&apos;ll see the joy in it.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">You&apos;ll see the joy in it.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="132">
<j>また次のように語っている。（黄金の巻第七十二帖）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also says as follows (chapter 72 of volume gold):</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also says as follows (chapter 72 of volume gold):</e>
<cmt>leading space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also says as follows (chapter 72 of volume gold):</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="133">
<j>「家の治まらんのは女が出るからぞ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If your home is not at peace, it is because your wife is overstepping her position.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If your home is not at peace, it is because your wife is overstepping her position.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If your home is not at peace, it is because your wife is overstepping her position.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="134">
<j>「夫立てると果報は女に来るぞ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If a wife pays due respect to her husband, she will have every luck.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If a wife pays due respect to her husband, she will have every luck.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If a wife pays due respect to her husband, she will have every luck.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="135">
<j>さらに次のように語っている。（黄金の巻第九十九帖）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He says further as follows (chapter 99 of volume gold):</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He says further as follows (chapter 99 of volume gold):</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He says further as follows (chapter 99 of volume gold):</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="136">
<j>「妻にまかせきった夫、夫にまかせきった妻の姿となれよ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rely on your wife. Rely on your husband.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rely on your wife. Rely on your husband.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rely on your wife and rely on your husband.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="137">
<j>「信仰の真の道ひらけるぞ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then you will find your religious way.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then you will find your religious way.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then you will find your religious way.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="138">
<j>「一皮むけるぞ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">You&apos;ll be matured.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">You will mature.&apos;</e>
<cmt>passive voice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">You will mature.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="139">
<j>「岩戸ひらけるぞ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The cave will open.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The cave will open.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The cave will open.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="140">
<j>「不二（富士）晴れるぞ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">You will see clear Fuji.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">You will see clear Fuji.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">You will see clear Fuji.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="141">
<j>また、お互いに信頼しきった夫婦関係が大切で信仰の礎であると次のように語っている。（月光の巻第九帖）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He says that a committed relationship of husband and wife is important as the foundation of religion as follows (chapter 9 of volume moonlight):</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He says that a committed relationship of husband and wife is important as the foundation of religion as follows (chapter 9 of volume moonlight):</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He says that a committed relationship of husband and wife is important as the foundation of religion as follows (chapter 9 of volume moonlight):</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="142">
<j>「夫婦けんかするでない。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Don&apos;t have your marital quarrel.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Don&apos;t have marital quarrels.&apos;</e>
<cmt>deleted “your”</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Don&apos;t have marital quarrels.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="143">
<j>「夫のみいかんのでない。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is caused not only by your husband.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is caused not only by your husband.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is caused not only by your husband.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="144">
<j>「妻のみ悪いのでないぞ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is caused not only by your wife.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is caused not only by your wife.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is caused not only by your wife.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="145">
<j>「お互に己の姿を出し合ってゐるのぞ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Both of you are seeing yourself in each other.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Both of you are seeing yourself in each other.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Both of you are seeing yourself in each other.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="146">
<j>「よく会得せよ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Understand well.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Understand well.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Understand well.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>霊界と現界との関係</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The relationship between the spiritual world and this world</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The relationship between the spiritual world and this world</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The relationship between the spiritual world and this world</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="147">
<j>日月神示には霊界についての記述も多く見られるが、特に「二日んの巻」（ジシンの巻）や「龍音之巻」は、ほとんどがこれらについての記述である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hitsuki Shinji includes many descriptions about the spiritual world especially in volume &apos;Jishin&apos; and volume &apos;Ryuon&apos; which describe almost all about it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hitsuki Shinji includes many descriptions about the spiritual world especially in volume &apos;Jishin&apos; and volume &apos;Ryuon&apos; which are mostly about it.</e>
<cmt>almost all-&gt;mostly</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hitsuki Shinji includes many descriptions about the spiritual world especially in volume &apos;Jishin&apos; and volume &apos;Ryuon&apos; which are mostly about it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="148">
<j>そのなかでも、我々が住んでいる現界と関係が深いと思われるもので主なものを以下に箇条書きで記す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among those, here we show a run of the items of descriptions which are related with this world of us.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among those, here we show a run of the items of descriptions which are related with this world of us.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among those, here we show a run of the items of descriptions which are related with this world of us.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="149">
<j>広く霊界といっても神界と幽界に大別され、神界は天国と霊国に分けられ、幽界はそれぞれ、陽界と陰界に分けられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The spiritual world in a broad sense is divided roughly into the spirit world which is divided into heaven and the spirit land and the astral world which is divided into the positive world and the negative world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The spiritual world in a broad sense is divided roughly into the spirit world, which is divided into heaven and the spirit land, and the astral world which is divided into the positive world and the negative world.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The spiritual world in a broad sense is divided roughly into the spirit world, which is divided into heaven and the spirit land, and the astral world which is divided into the positive world and the negative world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="150">
<j>天国には天人が、霊国には天使が住み、幽界は陽界には陽霊人が、陰界には陰霊人が住んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In heaven celestial beings are living, in the spirit land angels are living, in the positive world positive spirits are living and in the negative world negative spirits are living.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In heaven celestial beings are living, in the spirit land angels are living, in the positive world positive spirits are living and in the negative world negative spirits are living.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In heaven celestial beings are living, in the spirit land angels are living, in the positive world positive spirits are living and in the negative world negative spirits are living.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="151">
<j>幽界は人間界と最も深い関係にあり、初期の神懸かりの殆んどはこの幽界からの感応によるものであるから注意が必要である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most of supernatural events are caused by responding to the astral world which is linked most deeply to the human world, so you have to be careful.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most supernatural events are caused by responding to the astral world which is linked most deeply to the human world, so you have to be careful.</e>
<cmt>prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most supernatural events are caused by responding to the astral world which is linked most deeply to the human world, so you have to be careful.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="152">
<j>目に見えぬ所からの通信は高度のものほど肉体的には感応が弱くなり、暗示的なものになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In communication with an invisible place, the more advanced communication causes the weaker and more suggestive physical response.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In communication with an invisible place, the more advanced communication causes the weaker and more suggestive physical response.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In communication with an invisible place, the more advanced communication causes the weaker and more suggestive physical response.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="153">
<j>下級霊は現実界と紙一重の所に住んでいる為、その感応は極めて強く人間の目にはいかにも、もっともらしく映るので注意が必要である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The lower-grade spirits are living in the nearest place from this world, therefore humans respond to them strongly and can see them as plausible, so you have to be careful.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The lower-grade spirits are living in the nearest place from this world, therefore humans respond to them strongly and can see them as plausible, so you have to be careful.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The lower-grade spirits are living in the nearest place from this world, therefore humans respond to them strongly and can see them as plausible, so you have to be careful.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="154">
<j>高度の霊がただちに肉体人に感応する事はなく、それぞれの段階を経て感応するものであることを忘れてはならない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Don&apos;t forget that human body does not respond to higher-grade spirits immediately and only responds through different stages.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Don&apos;t forget that human body does not respond to higher-grade spirits immediately and only responds through different stages.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Don&apos;t forget that human body does not respond to higher-grade spirits immediately and only responds through different stages.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="155">
<j>高度なものはその人間の精神（心）に応じてそれと同一波長の神霊に伝達され、その神霊の感応によって表現される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Higher ones are transmitted to spirits on the same wavelength of each person&apos;s mind and expressed through the sympathies of those spirits.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Higher ones are transmitted to spirits on the same wavelength of each person&apos;s mind and expressed through the sympathies of those spirits.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Higher ones are transmitted to spirits on the same wavelength of each person&apos;s mind and expressed through the sympathies of those spirits.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="156">
<j>下級霊が懸かった霊媒の所作や動作、言動は高ぶったり、威張ったり、命令したり、断言したり、高度の神名を名乗ったりするものであるがこれらは良く見極めれば判る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">You will find it by observing carefully that a medium possessed by a lower-grade spirit acts patronizingly, behaves and says domineeringly, orders, asserts and calls oneself a holy God&apos;s name.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">You will find it by observing carefully that a medium possessed by a lower-grade spirit acts patronizingly, behaves and speaks domineeringly, orders, asserts and calls himself a holy God&apos;s name.</e>
<cmt>say-&gt;speak; oneself-&gt;himself</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">You will find it by observing carefully that a medium possessed by a lower-grade spirit acts patronizingly, behaves and speaks domineeringly, orders, asserts and calls himself a holy God&apos;s name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="157">
<j>特別の使命を持つ天使は、最下級の霊界まで降って来て人間に特別な通信をしたり、指示したりする事がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Engels who have special missions sometimes come down to the lowest spiritual world to communicate with humans specially and give instructions to humans.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Angels who have special missions sometimes come down to the lowest spiritual world to communicate with humans specially and give instructions to humans.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Angels who have special missions sometimes come down to the lowest spiritual world to communicate with humans specially and give instructions to humans.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="158">
<j>また天使の霊が母体に宿り人間として生まれて来ることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also sometimes a spirit of angel comes to a mother body to be born as a human.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also sometimes a spirit of an angel comes to a mother body to be born as a human.</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also sometimes a spirit of an angel comes to a mother body to be born as a human.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="159">
<j>末世にはこの種の降誕人が沢山ある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In degenerated age, a lot of angels are born in such a way.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In a degenerate age, a lot of angels are born in such a way.</e>
<cmt>degenerate</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In a degenerate age, a lot of angels are born in such a way.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="160">
<j>特別の使命を持つ天使は別として、人霊以外の霊で人間に憑依するのは、日本を例にとれば天狗、仙人、キツネ、タヌキ、ネコなどが大部分である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Apart from angels with special missions and human spirits, taking Japan as an example, mainly spirits of long-nosed goblins, hermits, foxes, raccoon dogs, cats and others can possess human.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Apart from angels with special missions and human spirits, taking Japan as an example, mainly spirits of long-nosed goblins, hermits, foxes, raccoon dogs, cats and others can possess humans.</e>
<cmt>plural humans</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Apart from angels with special missions and human spirits, taking Japan as an example, mainly spirits of long-nosed goblins, hermits, foxes, raccoon dogs, cats and others can possess humans.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="161">
<j>先祖霊に化けて何かを企てる動物霊が多いから注意を要する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">You have to be careful that many animal spirits change themselves into spirits of human ancestors and attempt something.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">You have to be careful because many animal spirits change themselves into spirits of human ancestors and attempt something.</e>
<cmt>that-&gt;because</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">You have to be careful because many animal spirits change themselves into spirits of human ancestors and attempt something.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="162">
<j>動物霊が祖先のことを知っているのは、その憑依の対象となる人間の肉体霊の知ってることを、直ちに知り得るからである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Animal spirits can know about human ancestors, because they can learn immediately what a spirit of their target human body knows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Animal spirits can know about human ancestors, because they can learn immediately what the spirit of their target human body knows.</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Animal spirits can know about human ancestors, because they can learn immediately what the spirit of their target human body knows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="163">
<j>動物霊が人間の言葉を使うのは不可解にも思えるが、それは例えれば、他人の家に入り込んで其処に有る道具類をそのまま使うのと同じ道理である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It may be incomprehensible that animal spirits use human words, but it is, for example, just like that they enter someone&apos;s home and just use the household belongings there around.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It may be incomprehensible that animal spirits use human words, but it is, for example, just like they enter someone&apos;s home and just use the household belongings there.</e>
<cmt>prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It may be incomprehensible that animal spirits use human words, but it is, for example, just like they enter someone&apos;s home and just use the household belongings there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="164">
<j>動物霊でも他の霊でも人間に感応したならば、ある程度その人間の持つ言葉を使いこなせる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even animal spirits and other spirits can use human words to some extent when they are responding to a human.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even animal spirits and other spirits can use human words to some extent when they are responding to a human.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even animal spirits and other spirits can use human words to some extent when they are responding to a human.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="165">
<j>日本人に感応すれば日本語を、アメリカ合衆国人ならば英語を語ることが出来る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They can speak Japanese when they are responding to a Japanese and speak English responding to an American.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They can speak Japanese when they are responding to a Japanese and speak English responding to an American.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They can speak Japanese when they are responding to a Japanese and speak English responding to an American.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="166">
<j>基本的に下級霊や動物霊は人間に感応はするが肉体の内部までは入り込めない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Basically lower-grade spirits and animal spirits can respond to a human, but cannot enter inside the body.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Basically lower-grade spirits and animal spirits can respond to a human, but cannot enter inside the body.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Basically lower-grade spirits and animal spirits can respond to a human, but cannot enter inside the body.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="167">
<j>しかし、感応の度が強ければ入ったと同様に見える場合が有る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, if the response is strong, it sometimes looks as if they enter inside a human body.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, if the response is strong, it sometimes looks as if they enter inside a human body.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, if the response is strong, it sometimes looks as if they enter inside a human body.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="168">
<j>例外として人間の魂と動物の魂が入れ替わっている事も有る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Exceptionally, human spirit and animal spirit replace each other.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Exceptionally, human spirit and animal spirit replace each other.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Exceptionally, human spirit and animal spirit replace each other.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="169">
<j>こうした場合は肉体に入り込んだと考えて良い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If that is the case, it can be considered as entering inside a body.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If that is the case, it can be considered as entering inside a body.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If that is the case, it can be considered as entering inside a body.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="170">
<j>例えばそれが狐なら狐の様相を露呈するから、すぐ判るが悪行を積んだ霊などの場合は、その時代時代に合わせて化けているので見破る事が中々難しい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, a fox spirit that just looks like a fox is easy to be identified, but spirits who have ever committed wrong acts change themselves into other appearances in line with each time, so it is difficult to find out.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, a fox spirit that just looks like a fox is easy to identify, but spirits who have ever committed wrong acts change themselves into other appearances in line with each time, so it is difficult to find out.</e>
<cmt>passive voice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, a fox spirit that just looks like a fox is easy to identify, but spirits who have ever committed wrong acts change themselves into other appearances in line with each time, so it is difficult to find out.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="171">
<j>少しでも、怪しいと思った場合はそれが神の言葉でも裏表の見境もなく闇雲に信じてはならない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Don&apos;t believe it blindly even something what you hear as God&apos;s words, when you feel it suspicious.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Don&apos;t believe it blindly even something that you hear as God&apos;s words, when you feel it suspicious.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Don&apos;t believe it blindly even something that you hear as God&apos;s words, when you feel it suspicious.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="172">
<j>例え神の言葉でも自分で一応考えて、審神する事が重要である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even if you receive it as God&apos;s words, you have to judge about it by yourself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even if you receive it as God&apos;s words, you have to judge it by yourself.</e>
<cmt>prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even if you receive it as God&apos;s words, you have to judge it by yourself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="173">
<j>人間霊の場合でも或種の霊は、自分自身が高度な神界に住んでいると誤信しているものがいるが、こうした霊が感応した場合は自信を以って断言する場合が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also some human spirits who misunderstand that they are living in a higher-grade spirit world, often say with confidence when they respond to a human.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also some human spirits who misunderstand that they are living in a higher-grade spirit world, often speak with confidence when they respond to a human.</e>
<cmt>say-&gt;speak</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also some human spirits who misunderstand that they are living in a higher-grade spirit world, often speak with confidence when they respond to a human.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="174">
<j>人間の知らぬ世界の事を自信を以って強く告げてくるので、判別は困難で多くの場合、審神者は参ってしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When they tell receivers about a world which humans don&apos;t know with confidence, it is often difficult to judge if it is true and makes receivers embarrassed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When they tell receivers about a world which humans don&apos;t know with confidence, it is often difficult to judge if it is true and makes receivers embarrassed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When they tell receivers about a world which humans don&apos;t know with confidence, it is often difficult to judge if it is true and makes receivers embarrassed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="175">
<j>仙人というのはどんなに高度に見えるものでも、幽界に属す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hermits belong to the astral world, no matter how higher-grade he looks like to have.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hermits belong to the astral world, no matter how higher-grade he looks.</e>
<cmt>deleted “like to have”</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hermits belong to the astral world, no matter how higher-grade he looks.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="176">
<j>なぜなら、仙人界には戒律があるからである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because they have their religious law in the hermit world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because they have their religious law in the hermit world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because they have their religious law in the hermit world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="177">
<j>神界には戒律はない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is no religious law in the spirit world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is no religious law in the spirit world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is no religious law in the spirit world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="178">
<j>真の宗教に戒律はないのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">True religion has no law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">True religion has no law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">True religion has no law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="179">
<j>戒律がある宗教は亡びる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Religion with law is going to die down.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Religion with law is going to die.</e>
<cmt>deleted “down”</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Religion with law is going to die.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="180">
<j>しかし、神界にも仙人的な存在はある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However there are existences like hermits also in the spirit world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However there are beings like hermits also in the spirit world.</e>
<cmt>beings</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However there are beings like hermits also in the spirit world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="181">
<j>竜体（竜神の事か？）を持つ霊は神界にも幽界にもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are spirits with dragon body (does it mean Dragon King?) both in the spirit world and the astral world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are spirits with dragon body (does it mean Dragon King?) both in the spirit world and the astral world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are spirits with dragon body (does it mean Dragon King?) both in the spirit world and the astral world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="182">
<j>竜体だからといってそれらが全て神界に属すると思うのは誤りである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is wrong that dragon body always belongs to the spirit world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is wrong that dragon body always belongs to the spirit world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is wrong that dragon body always belongs to the spirit world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="183">
<j>先祖霊が出る場合は、何か頼みたい事が有る場合が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When a spirit of ancestor appears, he/she probably has a favor to ask.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When a spirit of an ancestor appears, he/she probably has a favor to ask.</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When a spirit of an ancestor appears, he/she probably has a favor to ask.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="184">
<j>浄化した高級霊ともなれば、人間の肉体に判るような感応はほとんどない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Human body seldom responds to higher-grade spirits who have already purified.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Human body seldom responds to higher-grade spirits who have already purified.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Human body seldom responds to higher-grade spirits who have already purified.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="185">
<j>先祖は現界に住んでいる肉体人を土台として修業するものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Spirits of ancestors practice using human bodies in this world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Spirits of ancestors practice using human bodies in this world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Spirits of ancestors practice using human bodies in this world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="186">
<j>また、同様に霊界に於ける自分は先祖との交流や交渉は深いものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also people have deep interchanges and connections with their ancestors in the spiritual world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also people have deep interchanges and connections with their ancestors in the spiritual world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also people have deep interchanges and connections with their ancestors in the spiritual world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="187">
<j>下級霊や動物霊の場合は「酔いどれ」のように箸にも棒にもかからない事を言ってくる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Lower-grade spirits and animal spirits tell you something for nothing like &apos;drunkards&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Lower-grade spirits and animal spirits tell you something for nothing like &apos;drunkards&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Lower-grade spirits and animal spirits tell you something for nothing like &apos;drunkards&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="188">
<j>霊の要求だからといって、そのまま受け入れるのではなく、よく判断した上で処理しなければならない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">You have to handle their demands judging carefully without accepting for what it is.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">You have to handle their demands judging carefully without accepting it at face value.</e>
<cmt>for what it is-&gt;at face value</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">You have to handle their demands judging carefully without accepting it at face value.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="189">
<j>霊眼で見たり霊耳で聞いたりすることは間違いが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seeing and Hearing spiritually often cause mistakes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seeing and Hearing spiritually often cause mistakes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seeing and hearing spiritually often cause mistakes.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="190">
<j>霊耳は耳をふさいでも内から聞こえてくる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With hearing spiritually you can hear even if you cover your ears.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With hearing spiritually you can hear even if you cover your ears.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With hearing spiritually you can hear even if you cover your ears.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="191">
<j>物を見るのは額で見ることが重要である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seeing in forehead is important.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seeing with the forehead is important.</e>
<cmt>prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seeing with the forehead is important.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="192">
<j>額の目に見の誤りは無く、額の判断に間違いは無い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seeing in forehead doesn&apos;t cause any mistakes and makes a good judgment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seeing in the forehead doesn&apos;t cause any mistakes and makes a good judgment.</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seeing in the forehead doesn&apos;t cause any mistakes and makes a good judgment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="193">
<j>また、悪の霊が懸かった場合は肉体の背後や首すじなどから感応し、人間の「みぞおち」あたりに集まり、そこで頑張るものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also body responds to evil spirits in the back and neck first and feels concentration and energy around &apos;the pit of the stomach&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also body responds to evil spirits in the back and neck first and feels concentration and energy around &apos;the pit of the stomach&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also body responds to evil spirits in the back and neck first and feels concentration and energy around &apos;the pit of the stomach.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオド位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="194">
<j>霊覚者や行者の中には奇跡的な事や非常識な行動をする者がよくいて、一般人はそれに騙される事がよくある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because some of mediums and ascetics perform miracles and act insanely, common people are often deceived.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because some mediums and ascetics perform miracles and act insanely, common people are often deceived.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because some mediums and ascetics perform miracles and act insanely, common people are often deceived.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="195">
<j>これらは、いずれも下級霊の仕業である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those are all acts of Lower-grade spirits.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those are all acts of lower-grade spirits.</e>
<cmt>capitalization</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those are all acts of lower-grade spirits.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="25">
<sen id="196">
<j>正神には奇跡はない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Holy spirits perform no miracles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Holy spirits perform no miracles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Holy spirits perform no miracles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="197">
<j>高級霊は態度が立派である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Higher-grade spirits have a good attitude.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Higher-grade spirits have a good attitude.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Higher-grade spirits have a good attitude.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="26">
<sen id="198">
<j>どんな下級霊であっても、その霊を馬鹿にしてはならない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Don&apos;t look down on any spirit, even if the spirit is a lower-grade one.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Don&apos;t look down on any spirit, even if the spirit is a lower-grade one.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Don&apos;t look down on any spirit, even if the spirit is a lower-grade one.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="199">
<j>馬鹿にすると反射的に審神者を馬鹿にして始末に負えないことになるので思慮が必要である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If a receiver looks down on a spirit, the receiver will be looked down reflexively by the spirit, so receivers need careful consideration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If a receiver looks down on a spirit, the receiver will be looked down on reflexively by the spirit, so receivers need careful consideration.</e>
<cmt>prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If a receiver looks down on a spirit, the receiver will be looked down on reflexively by the spirit, so receivers need careful consideration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="200">
<j>特にその霊が病気に関連をもっている場合は微妙である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially it is a delicate case when the spirit is related to illness.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Especially it is a delicate case when the spirit is related to illness.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Especially it is a delicate case when the spirit is related to illness.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="201">
<j>霊には常に愛を持って接し、良い方向に導いて行こうとする努力が大切である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is important to treat any spirit with love at all times and try to lead any spirit to a better way.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is important to treat any spirit with love at all times and try to lead any spirit to a better way.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is important to treat any spirit with love at all times and try to lead any spirit to a better way.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="202">
<j>霊の邪道的要求を受けて一時的に病気を治すと、それに倍になってぶり返すものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If you accept a wrong demand of a spirit to recover from your illness, you will have a double setback after a temporally cure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If you accept a wrong demand of a spirit to recover from your illness, you will have a double setback after a temporary cure.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If you accept a wrong demand of a spirit to recover from your illness, you will have a double setback after a temporary cure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="27">
<sen id="203">
<j>悪霊自身は自身を悪だとは思っていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Evil spirits do not consider themselves as evil.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Evil spirits do not consider themselves evil.</e>
<cmt>prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Evil spirits do not consider themselves evil.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="28">
<sen id="204">
<j>霊的良識は神示や神典類によって、また体験によって養われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Spiritual common sense is developed by revelations, sacred books and experiences.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Spiritual common sense is developed by revelations, sacred books and experiences.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Spiritual common sense is developed by revelations, sacred books and experiences.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="205">
<j>更には高度の科学書も参考になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also advanced scientific books serve as a reference.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also advanced scientific books serve as a reference.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also advanced scientific books serve as a reference.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="29">
<sen id="206">
<j>神界より真っ直ぐに感応する想念が正流である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An idea which comes straight from the spirit world is the mainstream.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An idea which comes straight from the spirit world is the mainstream.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An idea which comes straight from the spirit world is the mainstream.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="207">
<j>幽界からや幽界を経て流れてくる想念が外流である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An idea from or through the astral world is outer stream.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An idea from or through the astral world is outer stream.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An idea from or through the astral world is outer stream.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="30">
<sen id="208">
<j>人間界のことを良く知っている霊は人間界を去って間もない霊か地上世界に長く住んでいた動物霊か、人間に憑依していた霊である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Spirits who know well about the human world are those who left this world recently or animal spirits which have lived on earth for a long time or those who have ever possessed a human.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Spirits who know well about the human world are those who left this world recently or animal spirits which have lived on earth for a long time or those who have ever possessed a human.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Spirits who know well about the human world are those who left this world recently or animal spirits which have lived on earth for a long time or those who have ever possessed a human.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="31">
<sen id="209">
<j>神の守護というのは人間からは全然判らないものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Devine protection is unrecognizable for humans.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Divine protection is unrecognizable for humans.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Divine protection is unrecognizable for humans.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="210">
<j>判る様な守護は低い神や悪神の守護である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Recognizable protections are those of lower-grade spirits or evil gods.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Recognizable protections are those of lower-grade spirits or evil gods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Recognizable protections are those of lower-grade spirits or evil gods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="211">
<j>悪神でも大将ともなればその守護は人間には判らない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even in case of evil gods, a protection of their head is unrecognizable for humans.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even in case of evil gods, a protection of their head is unrecognizable for humans.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even in case of evil gods, a protection of their head is unrecognizable for humans.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="32">
<sen id="212">
<j>日本には日本の守護の神、中国には中国の、外国には外国のそれぞれの守護の神がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan has a Japanese guardian god, China has a Chinese guardian god, other countries have each country&apos;s guardian gods.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan has a Japanese guardian god, China has a Chinese guardian god, other countries have each country&apos;s guardian gods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan has a Japanese guardian god, China has a Chinese guardian god, other countries have each country&apos;s guardian gods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="33">
<sen id="213">
<j>今の人間は9分9厘は幽界との繋がりを持つから、よくよく自分自身を審神し反省する必要がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">99% of the people today have a connection with the astral world, so you need to observe yourself carefully and reconsider it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">99% of the people today have a connection with the astral world, so you need to observe yourself carefully and reconsider it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">99% of the people today have a connection with the astral world, so you need to observe yourself carefully and reconsider it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="34">
<sen id="214">
<j>霊媒を通じてこの世に呼びかける霊の9分9厘は邪霊である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">99% of spirits who appeal to this world through mediums are evil.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">99% of spirits who appeal to this world through mediums are evil.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">99% of spirits who appeal to this world through mediums are evil.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="215">
<j>今後は更に激しくなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It will be more in the future.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It will be more in the future.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It will be more in the future.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="35">
<sen id="216">
<j>我は「天照大御神」などと名乗る霊にろくなものはいない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">None of those spirits who call themselves a major god&apos;s name like &apos;Amaterasu Omikami&apos; (a sun goddess) can be any good.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">None of those spirits who call themselves a major god&apos;s name like &apos;Amaterasu Omikami&apos; (a sun goddess) can be any good.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">None of those spirits who call themselves a major god&apos;s name like &apos;Amaterasu Omikami&apos; (a sun goddess) can be any good.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="217">
<j>こうした霊に憑かれた人間は例外なく大言壮語するものであり、眉唾ものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those who are being possessed by such spirits are all boasters and suspicious.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those who are being possessed by such spirits are all boasters and suspicious.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those who are being possessed by such spirits are all boasters and suspicious.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="36">
<sen id="218">
<j>幽界霊も時によっては正しく善なる事を言うが、それはただ言うだけである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sometimes spirits from the astral world say something right and good, but it is just saying.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sometimes spirits from the astral world say something right and good, but it is just saying.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sometimes spirits from the astral world say something right and good, but it is just saying.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="219">
<j>例えるなら悪人が口先だけで善を語るようなものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is like a bad person who is just saying goodness.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is like a bad person who is just saying goodness.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is like a bad person who is just saying goodness.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="37">
<sen id="220">
<j>良い言葉ならば、たとえ悪神が語ってもいいのでは？とも思えるが、それは理屈である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">You may think that if it is good words, even evil god can tell those, but that is just twisted logic.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">You may think that if it is good words, even evil gods can tell those, but that is just twisted logic.</e>
<cmt>gods</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">You may think that if it is good words, even evil gods can tell those, but that is just twisted logic.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="221">
<j>真の善言や真言は心、言葉、行ないが一致しているから直ちに力を持つが、それらが一致していないと力は出ないのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">True valuable words take a power immediately when a mind, words and acts are consistent with each other, but when those are not consistent, any words take no power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">True valuable words take on power immediately when mind, words and acts are consistent with each other, but when those are not consistent, no words have power.</e>
<cmt>articles; prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">True valuable words take on power immediately when mind, words and acts are consistent with each other, but when those are not consistent, no words have power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="222">
<j>言葉の上のみ同一であっても例えば、同じ「はい」という返事でも喜びの時と不満の時とでは違うように、偽りの言葉は落ち着いて聞けば判るものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As &apos;Yes&apos; sounds differently when it is said happily or unhappily, you will find if it is false words by listening calmly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As &apos;Yes&apos; sounds differently when it is said happily or unhappily, you will find if it is false words by listening calmly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As &apos;Yes&apos; sounds differently when it is said happily or unhappily, you will find if it is false words by listening calmly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="38">
<sen id="223">
<j>その人間の心に相応した神しか拝めない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Every human only can pray a god who is suitable to his/her own mind.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Every human only can pray to a god who is suitable to his/her own mind.</e>
<cmt>prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Every human only can pray to a god who is suitable to his/her own mind.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="224">
<j>悪い心で拝めば、どんなに立派な神前でも悪神が感応する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To your evil mind, only an evil god will respond, even when you pray to a fine god.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To your evil mind, only an evil god will respond, even when you pray to a fine god.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To your evil mind, only an evil god will respond, even when you pray to a fine god.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="225">
<j>逆に悪神を拝んでも正しい愛や喜びがあり、善い念が通じるならば悪神は引っ込んでそれぞれの善い神が現れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In contract, even if you pray to an evil god, proper love, joy and good will in your mind can make a good god appeared and evil god left.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In contract, even if you pray to an evil god, proper love, joy and good will in your mind can make a good god appear and evil god leave.</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In contract, even if you pray to an evil god, proper love, joy and good will in your mind can make a good god appear and evil god leave.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="39">
<sen id="226">
<j>悪神が懸かった時は自分では偉い神様が乗り移ったと信じ込む場合が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When people are possessed by an evil god, they often think that they are possessed by a great god.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When people are possessed by an evil god, they often think that they are possessed by a great god.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When people are possessed by an evil god, they often think that they are possessed by a great god.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="227">
<j>それは自分の天狗のような高慢な心が原因である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is because of their superior feelings like a long-nosed goblin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is because of their superior feelings like a long-nosed goblin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is because of their superior feelings like a long-nosed goblin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="40">
<sen id="228">
<j>2重3重人格というのは2重3重の憑き物の転換によるものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Split personality is caused by some different possessions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Split personality is caused by some different possessions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Split personality is caused by some different possessions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="229">
<j>また、群衆心理とはその時の一時的な憑依霊の仕業である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also crowd psychology is caused by temporally spirit possession at the time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also crowd psychology is caused by temporary spirit possession at the time.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also crowd psychology is caused by temporary spirit possession at the time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="41">
<sen id="230">
<j>霊人には何でも判ってると思うのは大きな間違いである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is completely wrong that spirits know everything.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is completely wrong that spirits know everything.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is completely wrong that spirits know everything.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="42">
<sen id="231">
<j>人は死ぬ時の想念がそのまま続くので、その想念に応じた世界に住むことになるのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">People continue to have the thoughts of when they die and each person will live in a suitable world to each thought.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">People continue to have the thoughts of when they die and each person will live in a suitable world to each thought.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">People continue to have the thoughts of when they die and each person will live in a suitable world to each thought.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="232">
<j>この世を天国として暮らしていた人は天国へ、地獄と感じて生きていた人は自ら地獄的な想念を作り出してそのような世界に住むことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those who are considering this world as a heaven will go to heaven and those who are considering this world as a hell will go to hell which they create by themselves in their thoughts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those who see this world as heaven will go to heaven and those who see this world as hell will go to hell which they create by themselves in their thoughts.</e>
<cmt>consider-&gt;see; prepositions; articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those who see this world as heaven will go to heaven and those who see this world as hell will go to hell which they create by themselves in their thoughts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="43">
<sen id="233">
<j>神的自分が本守護神であり、霊的自分が正守護神である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Divine self is your original guardian deity and spiritual self is your spiritual guardian deity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Divine self is your original guardian deity and spiritual self is your spiritual guardian deity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Divine self is your original guardian deity and spiritual self is your spiritual guardian deity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="234">
<j>また、幽界的自分が副守護神である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also astral self is your spiritual guardian deity with vice spirit.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also astral self is your spiritual guardian deity with vice spirit.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also astral self is your spiritual guardian deity with vice spirit.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="235">
<j>本守護神は大神の歓喜である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Original guardian deity is a joy of God.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Original guardian deity is a joy of God.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Original guardian deity is a joy of God.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="44">
<sen id="236">
<j>人間の肉体は最底部をなすものであるから、肉体的動きの以前において必ず霊的動きが有る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because human body is a component of the most bottom part, a physical movement always occurs after a spiritual movement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because human body is a component of the most bottom part, a physical movement always occurs after a spiritual movement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because human body is a component of the most bottom part, a physical movement always occurs after a spiritual movement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="45">
<sen id="237">
<j>天界で起こった出来事は必ず現界にも起こる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">What happened in heaven also happens in this world certainly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">What happened in heaven also happens in this world certainly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">What happened in heaven also happens in this world certainly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="238">
<j>しかし、その時の現界の状況により、ある程度左右され早くなったり、遅くなったりする場合がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, depending of the situation of this world at the time, it happens earlier or later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, depending of the situation of this world at the time, it happens earlier or later.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, depending of the situation of this world at the time, it happens earlier or later.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="239">
<j>また、時によっては順序が違う場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sometimes it happens in a different order.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sometimes it happens in a different order.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sometimes it happens in a different order.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="46">
<sen id="240">
<j>天人や天使の行為が人間にうつるのであるが、逆に人間の自由や能力の如何によっての行為も天界や霊界に反映する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Acts of celestial beings and angels are reflected in acts of humans and in contrast how humans show their freedoms and abilities is also reflected in heaven and the spiritual world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Acts of celestial beings and angels are reflected in acts of humans and in contrast how humans show their freedoms and abilities is also reflected in heaven and the spiritual world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Acts of celestial beings and angels are reflected in acts of humans and in contrast how humans show their freedoms and abilities is also reflected in heaven and the spiritual world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="241">
<j>日本や外国では土地が違うように天界へのうつり方も違うのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Japan and the other country are different, the reflections of each country in heaven are also different.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Japan and other countries are different, the reflections of each country in heaven are also different.</e>
<cmt>plural countries</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Japan and other countries are different, the reflections of each country in heaven are also different.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="47">
<sen id="242">
<j>悪い事（天災や不幸等）を待つ心は魔の心である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Waiting badness (natural disaster and unhappiness etc.) is an evil mind.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Waiting for badness (natural disaster and unhappiness etc.) is an evil mind.</e>
<cmt>prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Waiting for badness (natural disaster and unhappiness etc.) is an evil mind.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="243">
<j>いつどこにそれらが来るのかと待ち望んでいるような心は悪魔に使われているのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When you are expecting when and where those happen, you are being manipulated by a devil.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When you are expecting when and where those happen, you are being manipulated by a devil.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When you are expecting when and where those happen, you are being manipulated by a devil.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="48">
<sen id="244">
<j>神の知らせと終戦</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A notice from God and the end of the war</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A notice from God and the end of the war</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A notice from God and the end of the war</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="49">
<sen id="245">
<j>天明に日月神示が降り始めてから、まだ1年も経たない昭和20年のある日に（天明はこの頃は上記した東京、千駄ヶ谷の八幡神社で留守神主をしていた）、神前に座ると神霊の「天明、此所をやめい」と言うお告げが有り、これはそれから3日間にわたって連日続いたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One day in 1945, in less than one year since Tenmei received Hitsuki Shinji for the first time (Tenmei was looking after Hachiman-jinja Shrine in Sendagaya, Tokyo, as a temporary Shinto priest as mentioned above), when he was sitting down in front of the altar, he heard the notice of the holy spirit &apos;Tenmei, leave here&apos; everyday over a three-day period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One day in 1945, less than one year after Tenmei received Hitsuki Shinji for the first time (Tenmei was looking after Hachiman-jinja Shrine in Sendagaya, Tokyo, as a temporary Shinto priest as mentioned above), when he was sitting down in front of the altar, he heard the notice of the holy spirit &apos;Tenmei, leave here&apos; everyday over a three-day period.</e>
<cmt>prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One day in 1945, less than one year after Tenmei received Hitsuki Shinji for the first time (Tenmei was looking after Hachiman-jinja Shrine in Sendagaya, Tokyo, as a temporary Shinto priest as mentioned above), when he was sitting down in front of the altar, he heard the notice of the holy spirit &apos;Tenmei, leave here&apos; everyday over a three-day period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="246">
<j>その後、天明が留守神主を辞職した直後の昭和20年に米国軍の焼夷弾が本殿に落下し、危ういところで天明は一命を救われたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1945, it was just after his resignation as the temporary Shinto priest when US military fire bomb hit the main shrine and his life was saved.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1945, it was just after his resignation as the temporary Shinto priest when US military fire bomb hit the main shrine and his life was saved.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1945, it was just after his resignation as the temporary Shinto priest when US military fire bomb hit the main shrine and his life was saved.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="247">
<j>左記の事実は岡本三典が天明から直接に聞いた話として三典の著書（『日月神示はなぜ岡本天明に降りたか』）に記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fact was written by Minori OKAMOTO as what she heard directly from Tenmei in her book &quot;Why did Hitsuki Shinji come down to Tenmei Okamoto&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fact was written by Minori OKAMOTO as what she heard directly from Tenmei in her book &quot;Why did Hitsuki Shinji come down to Tenmei Okamoto&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fact was written by Minori OKAMOTO as what she heard directly from Tenmei in her book &quot;Why did Hitsuki Shinji come down to Tenmei Okamoto.&quot;</e>
<cmt>ピリオド位置移動“→&quot;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="50">
<sen id="248">
<j>前述のように日月神示の書記が始まったのは、第二次世界大戦が終結する約1年2ヶ月前の昭和19年からであるが、この数日後に早くも枢軸国側と日本の敗戦を告げているらしい記述が見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As previously mentioned, Hitsuki Shinji started to be received in 1944, one year and two months before the end of the war, but after a few days from the first receipt, it already mentioned about the defeat of the Axis including Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As previously mentioned, Hitsuki Shinji started to be received in 1944, one year and two months before the end of the war, but after a few days from the first receipt, it already mentioned about the defeat of the Axis including Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As previously mentioned, Hitsuki Shinji started to be received in 1944, one year and two months before the end of the war, but after a few days from the first receipt, it already mentioned about the defeat of the Axis including Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="249">
<j>「上つ巻」第四帖（書記日、昭和19年）では以下のように記述されている。（原文ではドイツは卍、イタリアは一十と書記されている）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In chapter 4 of volume &apos;Uetsu&apos; (written in 1944), it is written as follows (in the original, Germany is written as 卍 and Italy is written as 一十):</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In chapter 4 of volume &apos;Uetsu&apos; (written in 1944), it is written as follows (in the original, Germany is written as 卍 and Italy is written as 一十):</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In chapter 4 of volume &apos;Uetsu&apos; (written in 1944), it is written as follows (in the original, Germany is written as 卍 and Italy is written as 一十):</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="250">
<j>「ドイツもイタリアもあてにならぬ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&apos;Don&apos;t expect Germany as well as Italy. All the unified countries in the world will come together on to the country ㋹.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&apos;Don&apos;t expect Germany as well as Italy. All the unified countries in the world will come together on to the country ㋹.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&apos;Don&apos;t expect Germany as well as Italy.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="251">
<j>「世界中一つになりて㋹の国に寄せて来るぞ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">All the unified countries in the world will come together on to the country ㋹.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="252">
<j>「それなのに今のやり方でよいと思うてゐるのか。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Do you still think that the current way is right?&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Do you still think that the current way is right?&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Do you still think that the current way is right?&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="253">
<j>更には日本が国家としての存続が危ぶまれるほどの大打撃を受け、東京もあたり一帯が焦土と化し焼け野原になってしまうらしい事が書記されている。（同巻第十一帖、書記日、昭和19年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also mentioned that Japan will suffer a major blow and be endangered and Tokyo will be burned down and scorched all around. (written in 1944 in chapter 9 of the same volume)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also mentioned that Japan will suffer a major blow and be endangered and Tokyo will be burned down and scorched all around. (written in 1944 in chapter 9 of the same volume)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also mentioned that Japan will suffer a major blow and be endangered and Tokyo will be burned down and scorched all around. (written in 1944 in chapter 11 of the same volume)</e>
<cmt>数字修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="254">
<j>「日本の国は一度つぶれた様になるのざぞ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan will almost collapse once. Everyone will think once that there is neither God nor Buddha in the world.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan will almost collapse once. Everyone will think once that there is neither God nor Buddha in the world.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan will almost collapse once.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="255">
<j>「一度は神も仏もないものと皆が思う世が来るのぞ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Everyone will think once that there is neither God nor Buddha in the world.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="256">
<j>「東京も元の土に一ときはかえる。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokyo also will return to the original soil once. Be prepared.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokyo also will return to the original soil once. Be prepared.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokyo also will return to the original soil once.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="257">
<j>「だから、その積りでゐて呉れよ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Be prepared.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="258">
<j>「神の申したこと違はんぞ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">What God says happens definitely.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">What God says happens definitely.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">What God says happens definitely.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="51">
<sen id="259">
<j>更に終戦の約2カ月前に書記された「松の巻」第七帖（書記日、昭和20年）では次のように記述されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also in chapter 7 of volume &apos;Matsu&apos; (pine) written in 1945, it says as follows:</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also in chapter 7 of volume &apos;Matsu&apos; (pine) written in 1945, it says as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also in chapter 7 of volume &apos;Matsu&apos; (pine) written in 1945 about two months before the end of the War, it says as follows:</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="260">
<j>「偉い人皆俘虜（とりこ）となるぞ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">People in high positions will be all prisoners of war.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">People in high positions will be all prisoners of war.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">People in high positions will be all prisoners of war.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="261">
<j>「夜明け近くなったぞ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is almost before the down.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is almost dawn.&apos;</e>
<cmt>prepositions; spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is almost dawn.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="262">
<j>「夜明けたらなにもかもはっきりするぞ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the break of dawn, everything will be clear.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the break of dawn, everything will be clear.&apos;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the break of dawn, everything will be clear.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="263">
<j>「夜明前は闇より暗いぞ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is darkest before the down. Don&apos;t panic.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is darkest before the dawn. Don&apos;t panic.&apos;</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is darkest before the dawn.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="264">
<j>「慌てるでないぞ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Don&apos;t panic.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="265">
<j>間もなく戦争が終わるらしい事と指導者達（政治家高官や軍事関係者上層部）が戦犯として逮捕、収監されるらしい事がこの時点ではっきりと述べられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this way, it is mentioned clearly at this point that the war will end and the leaders (politicians in high office and military officials at the head) will be arrested as war criminals and be taken into custody.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this way, it is mentioned clearly at this point that the war will end and the leaders (politicians in high office and military officials at the head) will be arrested as war criminals and be taken into custody.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this way, it is mentioned clearly at this point that the war will end and the leaders (politicians in high office and military officials at the head) will be arrested as war criminals and be taken into custody.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="266">
<j>なお、上記した終戦時に自殺を思いとどまった軍人達の中にはこの記述を知っていた者もかなりの人数がいたと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As mentioned above, it is said that many soldiers of those who stopped themselves from committing suicide, knew about the description.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As mentioned above, it is said that many soldiers of those who stopped themselves from committing suicide, knew about the description.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As mentioned above, it is said that many soldiers of those who stopped themselves from committing suicide, knew about the description.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="267">
<j>神示にはまた、敗戦後の復興や経済的な発展、そして日本人の精神的な凋落ぶりを指摘していると思われる帖も有るという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The revelation also includes chapters that point out of the recovery after defeated in the war, the development of the economy, mental decline of Japanese people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The revelation also includes chapters that point out the recovery after defeat in the war, the development of the economy and mental decline of Japanese people.</e>
<cmt>added “and”</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The revelation also includes chapters that point out the recovery after defeat in the war, the development of the economy and mental decline of Japanese people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="268">
<j>「アメの巻」第十四帖（書記日、昭和20年昭和20年）では以下のようにある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In chapter 14 of volume &apos;Ame&apos; written in 1945, it says &apos;Those prisoners of war are not finished yet. They will be back, regain and repeat it again.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In chapter 14 of volume &apos;Ame&apos; written in 1945, it says &apos;Those prisoners of war are not finished yet. They will be back, regain and repeat it again.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In chapter 14 of volume &apos;Ame&apos; written in 1945, it says as follows.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="269">
<j>「今度の俘虜（とりこ）まだまだぞ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those prisoners of war are not finished yet.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="270">
<j>「何れ元に帰って来るから、元に帰って又盛り返して来るなれど、またまた繰り返へすぞ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They will be back, regain and repeat it again.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="271">
<j>「｜三の巻」（うみの巻）第四帖（書記日、昭和22年でも以下説明が続くので、英語説明を削除しました。のようにある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In chapter 4 of volume &apos;Umi&apos; written in 1947, it also says &apos;After they come out, they will do the same thing, but they will be already empty and only able to make a crooked work. Don&apos;t be bothered by such a thing.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In chapter 4 of volume &apos;Umi&apos; written in 1947, it also says &apos;After they come out, they will do the same thing, but they will be already empty and only able to make a crooked work. Don&apos;t be bothered by such a thing.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In chapter 4 of volume &apos;Umi&apos; written in 1947, it also says as follows.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="272">
<j>「出てきてから、又同じ様なこと繰り返すぞ、今度は魂抜けてゐるからグニャグニャぞ、グニャグニャ細工しか出来んぞ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After they come out, they will do the same thing, but they will be already empty and only able to make a crooked work.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="273">
<j>「それに迷ふでないぞ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Don&apos;t be bothered by such a thing.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="274">
<j>これらは逮捕、収監されていた者も釈放、解放される事であると言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that it refers to the release of the prisoners.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that it refers to the release of the prisoners.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that it refers to the release of the prisoners.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="275">
<j>また、敗戦後の復興の反面、精神的に退廃する社会や無気力な人間が多く現われて来る様子を書記させたものだと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also it is said that it refers to the mentally collapsing society with many feckless people while recovering after the war.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also it is said that it refers to the mentally collapsing society with many feckless people while recovering after the war.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also it is said that it refers to the mentally collapsing society with many feckless people while recovering after the war.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="276">
<j>また、「黄金の巻」第五十九帖（書記日、昭和24年昭和24年）では「金で世を治めて、金で潰して、地固めしてみろくの世と致すのぢゃ。」と語られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also in chapter 59 of volume &apos;Ogon&apos; written in 1949, he says &apos;This world will be ruled and collapsed by money and then will pave the way to Miroku no yo (heaven on earth).&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also in chapter 59 of volume &apos;Ogon&apos; written in 1949, he says &apos;This world will be ruled and collapsed by money and then will pave the way to Miroku no yo (heaven on earth).&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also in chapter 59 of volume &apos;Ogon&apos; written in 1949, he says &apos;This world will be ruled and collapsed by money and then will pave the way to Miroku no yo (heaven on earth).&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="277">
<j>これは近年興った「バブル景気」とその崩壊を指しているのではないかと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered that it refers to the recent &apos;bubble economy&apos; and the collapse.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered that it refers to the recent &apos;bubble economy&apos; and the collapse.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered that it refers to the recent &apos;bubble economy&apos; and the collapse.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="278">
<j>また、2007年～2008年頃に米国より起ったリーマンブラザーズによるサブプライムローン問題に端を発する100年に一度あるかないかと言われる全世界的な大不況を指しているとも考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It may also refer to the world wide depression which comes only once or less in a century, caused by the subprime mortgage crisis of Lehman Brothers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It may also refer to the world wide depression which comes only once or less in a century, caused by the subprime mortgage crisis of Lehman Brothers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It may also refer to the world wide depression which comes only once or less in a century, caused by the subprime mortgage crisis of Lehman Brothers in the US around 2007 and 2008.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="52">
<sen id="279">
<j>未来に関しての記述</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The descriptions about the future</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The descriptions about the future</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The descriptions about the future</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="53">
<sen id="280">
<j>国常立尊と過去の予言者達</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kuninotoko Tachinokami and the previous prophets</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kuninotoko Tachinokami and the previous prophets</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kuninotoko Tachinokami and the previous prophets</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="281">
<j>日月神示には未来に関しての記述も多く、上記の軍人達がこの神示を拠りどころにしていたのも戦争の行く末やその勝敗を知りたかった事も大きな理由のひとつだったと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It seems that the above mentioned soldiers relied on the revelation, because they wanted to know the future of the war and the victory or defeat by Hitsuki Shinji including many of descriptions of the future.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It seems that the above mentioned soldiers relied on the revelation, because they wanted to know the future of the war and the victory or defeat by Hitsuki Shinji including many descriptions of the future.</e>
<cmt>prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It seems that the above mentioned soldiers relied on the revelation, because they wanted to know the future of the war and the victory or defeat by Hitsuki Shinji including many descriptions of the future.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="282">
<j>神示の中ではこれから起こるらしい大災厄や戦乱を「大峠」や「三千世界の大洗濯」と呼び、それらは現界に生きている人間のみならず霊界等も含めた全ての世界に等しく起こるとされ、神霊の言葉によれば「三千世界すべての大建替」になるという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Revelation, the future catastrophe and maelstrom of war are called &apos;Big Mountain Pass&apos; and &apos;Large-scale Washing of the Three Thousand World&apos; which will occur equally in whole world including the human and spiritual worlds and the spirit called it as &apos;Massive Reconstruction of all the Three Thousand World&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Revelation, the future catastrophe and maelstrom of war are called &apos;Big Mountain Pass&apos; and &apos;Large-scale Washing of the Three Thousand World&apos; which will occur equally in whole world including the human and spiritual worlds and the spirit called it as &apos;Massive Reconstruction of all the Three Thousand World&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Revelation, the future catastrophe and maelstrom of war are called &apos;Big Mountain Pass&apos; and &apos;Large-scale Washing of the Three Thousand World&apos; which will occur equally in whole world including the human and spiritual worlds and the spirit called it as &apos;Massive Reconstruction of all the Three Thousand World.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオド位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="283">
<j>また、洋の東西を問わず、予言者と称される人間が過去に幾人か現れて世界の終末とその後に「理想世界」の到来する事を説いているが、それらも「国常立尊」と呼ばれるこの神霊の仕組みであったと神霊自身は語っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also the spirit says that &apos;Kuninotoko Tachinokami&apos; arranged that those people called prophets in all countries appeared and explained about the end of the world and coming &apos;perfect world&apos; subsequently.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also the spirit says that &apos;Kuninotoko Tachinokami&apos; arranged that those people called prophets in all countries appeared and explained about the end of the world and coming &apos;perfect world&apos; subsequently.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also the spirit says that &apos;Kuninotoko Tachinokami&apos; arranged that those people called prophets in all countries appeared and explained about the end of the world and coming &apos;perfect world&apos; subsequently.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="284">
<j>「一火リの巻」（ヒカリの巻）第四帖では以下説明が続くので、英語説明を削除しました。のようにある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In chapter 4 of volume &apos;Hikari&apos;, he says &apos;Here and there in the world, gods appeared inform people of the large-scale washing of the world as I had arranged. Help each other, everyone.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In chapter 4 of volume &apos;Hikari&apos;, he says &apos;Here and there in the world, gods appeared inform people of the large-scale washing of the world as I had arranged. Help each other, everyone.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In chapter 4 of volume &apos;Hikari,&apos; he says as follows.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="285">
<j>「世界国々所々に世の大洗濯知らす神柱現はしてあろが、これは皆この方の仕組ぢゃ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Here and there in the world, gods appeared inform people of the large-scale washing of the world as I had arranged.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="286">
<j>「だから皆仲良う手引き合ってやって呉れよ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Help each other, everyone.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="287">
<j>これは時代を超えて古くからこの神霊の仕組みや働きがあったものと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered therefore that there were the arrangements and approaches of this spirit throughout the ages.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered therefore that there were arrangements and approaches of this spirit throughout the ages.</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered therefore that there were arrangements and approaches of this spirit throughout the ages.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="288">
<j>なお、この先に起こるらしい未来の出来事やその対処について、神霊は次のように語っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for coming future events and how to deal with them, the spirit says as follows:</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for coming future events and how to deal with them, the spirit says as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for coming future events and how to deal with them, the spirit says as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="289">
<j>「この先どうしたらよいかと云ふ事は、世界中金の草鞋（わらじ）で捜しても九九（ここ）より他分からんのじゃ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">You won&apos;t find what to do nowhere except here, even if you search around the world with gold sandals. So reform yourself and call on me.&apos; (chapter 5 of volume Matsu)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">You won&apos;t find what to do anywhere except here, even if you search around the world with gold sandals. So reform yourself and call on me.&apos; (chapter 5 of volume Matsu)</e>
<cmt>nowhere-&gt;anywhere</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">You won&apos;t find what to do anywhere except here, even if you search around the world with gold sandals.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="290">
<j>「だから、改心して訪ねて御座れ。」（松の巻第五帖）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">So reform yourself and call on me.&apos; (chapter 5 of volume Matsu)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="291">
<j>「世が引繰り返って元の神世に返るといふことは、神神様には分って居る。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The gods know that the world will turn over and return to the world like mythological age. Here and there in the world gods exist to inform of that. But the last thing is known only by me, this god.&apos; (chapter 23 of volume Shimotsu)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The gods know that the world will turn over and return to the world of mythological ages. Here and there in the world gods exist to inform of that. But the last thing is known only by me, this god.&apos; (chapter 23 of volume Shimotsu)</e>
<cmt>prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The gods know that the world will turn over and return to the world of mythological ages.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="292">
<j>「世界ところどころにその事知らし告げる神柱ある。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Here and there in the world gods exist to inform of that.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="293">
<j>「されど、最後のことは九（こ）の神でないと分らんぞ。」（下つ巻第二十三帖）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But the last thing is known only by me, this god.&apos; (chapter 23 of volume Shimotsu)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="294">
<j>また、次のように語っている。（天つ巻第四帖）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also he says as as follows (chapter 4 of Amatsu):</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also he says as as follows (chapter 4 of Amatsu):</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also he says as follows (chapter 4 of Amatsu):</e>
<cmt>重複削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="295">
<j>「あちこちに臣民の肉体かりて予言する神が沢山出てゐるなれど、九分九厘は分りて居れども、とどめの最后（最期）分らんから、この方に従ひて御用せよと申してゐるのぞ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are a lot of gods in human bodies to predict it here and there, but they know only 99% and don&apos;t know the last thing, so follow and serve me.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are a lot of gods in human bodies to predict it here and there, but they know only 99% and don&apos;t know the last thing, so follow and serve me.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are a lot of gods in human bodies to predict it here and there, but they know only 99% and don&apos;t know the last thing, so follow and serve me.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="296">
<j>「砂糖にたかる蟻となるなよ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Don&apos;t be ants on sugar.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Don&apos;t be ants on sugar.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Don&apos;t be ants on sugar.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="297">
<j>高級神霊でもその全てが、今後に起こる未来の出来事を知っている訳ではないらしいという記述が見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is described that not all holy spirits know all about the coming events in the future.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It says that not all holy spirits know all about the coming events in the future.</e>
<cmt>described-&gt;says</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It says that not all holy spirits know all about the coming events in the future.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="298">
<j>また、「みろくの世」と神霊が呼ぶ理想世界が来る前には現界でもこうした、何もわからない霊に憑かれた、いかがわしい予言者や神懸りした宗教家などが多く現れて、世の人を惑わすらしいと記されている次のような帖もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also it is described as follows that before the perfect world called &apos;Miroku no yo&apos; comes, people are deceived by a lot of questionable prophets and fanatic religionists who are possessed by spirits who don&apos;t know anything.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also it is described as follows that before the perfect world called &apos;Miroku no yo&apos; comes, people are deceived by a lot of questionable prophets and fanatic religionists who are possessed by spirits who don&apos;t know anything.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also it is described as follows that before the perfect world called &apos;Miroku no yo&apos; comes, people are deceived by a lot of questionable prophets and fanatic religionists who are possessed by spirits who don&apos;t know anything.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="299">
<j>「夜明け前になると霊がかりがウヨウヨ、勝手放題にまぜくり返すなれど、それもしばらくの狂言。」（星座之巻第十八帖）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before the dawn, possessed people throw the world into confusion without control, but it is just a play for a little while.&apos; (chapter 18 of volume constellation)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before the dawn, possessed people throw the world into confusion without control, but it is just a play for a little while.&apos; (chapter 18 of volume constellation)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before the dawn, possessed people throw the world into confusion without control, but it is just a play for a little while.&apos; (chapter 18 of volume constellation)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="300">
<j>こうした混乱も一時的で束の間のものでしかないと語られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is described that such confusion will be only temporally in a passing moment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is described that such confusion will be only temporary in a passing moment.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is described that such confusion will be only temporary in a passing moment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="54">
<sen id="301">
<j>三千世界の大洗濯と大峠</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Large-scale Washing of the Three Thousand World and Big Mountain Pass</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Large-scale Washing of the Three Thousand World and Big Mountain Pass</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Large-scale Washing of the Three Thousand World and Big Mountain Pass</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="302">
<j>神示には過去にも世の建替は6度あったとあり、今後に起こるとされる大建替で7度目だという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Revelation says that the world was reconstructed 6 times already in the past and the coming reconstruction will be the 7th.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Revelation says that the world was reconstructed 6 times already in the past and the coming reconstruction will be the 7th.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Revelation says that the world was reconstructed 6 times already in the past and the coming reconstruction will be the 7th.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="303">
<j>そして、これが最後なのだとも書記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It also says that this will be the last time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It also says that this will be the last time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It also says that this will be the last time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="304">
<j>過去6度のそれぞれについては全て現界のみの建替であった為に、すぐに元に戻り根本的な大建替にはならなかったのだという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because those past 6 reconstructions were all done only in this world, it hasn&apos;t been reconstructed fundamentally and turned back.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because those past 6 reconstructions were all done only in this world, it hasn&apos;t been reconstructed fundamentally and turned back.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because those past 6 reconstructions were all done only in this world, it hasn&apos;t been reconstructed fundamentally and turned back.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="305">
<j>そして、今後に起こるとされる大建替では過去にあったそれらとは全く異なり、現界はもちろんの事、神界、霊界、幽界等も含めた全ての世界に起こり、天明が最初に麻賀多神社で書記させられたように、文字通り「この世始まって二度とない苦労」になるのだとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The coming reconstruction will be totally different that it occurs not only in this world but also in the whole world including the spirit world and the astral world, which will be literally &apos;the biggest hardship that the world ever has&apos; just as Tenmei was made to write first in Makata-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The coming reconstruction will be totally different in that it occurs not only in this world but also in the whole world including the spirit world and the astral world, which will be literally &apos;the biggest hardship that the world ever has&apos; just as Tenmei was made to write first in Makata-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The coming reconstruction will be totally different in that it occurs not only in this world but also in the whole world including the spirit world and the astral world, which will be literally &apos;the biggest hardship that the world ever has&apos; just as Tenmei was made to write first in Makata-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="306">
<j>「松の巻」第十二帖では以下のように述べている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is written in chapter 12 of volume &apos;Matsu&apos;, &apos;It has been reconstructed already before, but those were not the reconstruction of the Three Thousand World. Therefore clouds remained in each world, which grew up to evil to spoil people and even gods have been ignorant about that.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is written in chapter 12 of volume &apos;Matsu&apos;, &apos;It has been reconstructed already before, but those were not the reconstruction of the Three Thousand World. Therefore clouds remained in each world, which grew up to evil to spoils people and even gods have been ignorant about that.&apos;</e>
<cmt>verb conjugation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is written in chapter 12 of volume &apos;Matsu&apos; as follows.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="307">
<j>「前にも建替はあったのざが、三千世界の建替ではなかった。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has been reconstructed already before, but those were not the reconstruction of the Three Thousand World.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="308">
<j>「そのため、どの世界にでも少しでも曇りあったら、それが大きくなって悪は走れば、苦労に甘いから、神々様でも、悪に知らず知らずなって来るのざぞ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore clouds remained in each world, which grew up to evil to spoils people and even gods have been ignorant about that.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="309">
<j>「天つ巻」第二帖でも次のように述べている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also in chapter 2 of volume &apos;Amatsu&apos; it says as follows:</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also in chapter 2 of volume &apos;Amatsu&apos; it says as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also in chapter 2 of volume &apos;Amatsu&apos; it says as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="310">
<j>「これまでの改造は膏薬（こうやく）張りざから、すぐ元にかへるのぞ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The previous reconstructions were just a plaster which turns back soon.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The previous reconstructions were just a plaster which turns back soon.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The previous reconstructions were just a plaster which turns back soon.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="311">
<j>「今度は今までにない、文（ふみ）にも口にも伝えてない改造じゃ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This time it will be an unprecedented reconstruction which haven&apos;t been informed yet either in writing or orally. It will be reconstructed not only this world but also the spirit world, therefore any other spirits but us don&apos;t know about that.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This time it will be an unprecedented reconstruction which hasn&apos;t been told yet either in writing or orally. It will be reconstructed not only this world but also the spirit world, therefore no other spirits but us don&apos;t know about that.&apos;</e>
<cmt>informed-&gt;told; verb conjugation; any-&gt;no</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This time it will be an unprecedented reconstruction which hasn&apos;t been told yet either in writing or orally.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="312">
<j>「だから、臣民界のみでなく神界も引っくるめて改造するのざから、この方らでないと、そこらに御座る守護神さまには分らんのぞ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It will be reconstructed not only this world but also the spirit world, therefore no other spirits but us don&apos;t know about that.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="313">
<j>今までの建替とは違い三千世界すべてに渡って起こる大災厄になる事と一部の高級神霊しか、それらの仕組みが分らないらしい事がここでも述べられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">So it is described here again that the biggest disaster will occur all over the Three Thousand World, which only some holy spirits know.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">So it is described here again that the biggest disaster will occur all over the Three Thousand World, which only some holy spirits know.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">So it is described here again that the biggest disaster will occur all over the Three Thousand World, which only some holy spirits know.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="55">
<sen id="314">
<j>また、建替については次のように述べている帖もある。」（水の巻第十二帖）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also it is described about the reconstruction as follows (chapter 12 of volume water):</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also it is described about the reconstruction as follows (chapter 12 of volume water):</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also it is described about the reconstruction as follows (chapter 12 of volume water):</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="315">
<j>「建替と申すのは、神界、幽界、顕界にある今までの事をきれいに塵一つ残らぬ様に洗濯することざぞ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reconstruction means to wash everything in the spirit world, the astral world and this world immaculately.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reconstruction means to wash everything in the spirit world, the astral world and this world immaculately.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reconstruction means to wash everything in the spirit world, the astral world and this world immaculately.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="316">
<j>「今度と云ふ今度は何処までもきれいさっぱりと建替するのざぞ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It will be reconstructed perfectly this time for sure.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It will be reconstructed perfectly this time for sure.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It will be reconstructed perfectly this time for sure.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="317">
<j>「建直と申すのは、世の元の大神様の御心のままにする事ぞ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It will be reconstructed by the will of God.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It will be reconstructed by the will of God.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It will be reconstructed by the will of God.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="318">
<j>「御光の世にすることぞ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It will make the world in the light of God.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It will make the world in the light of God.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It will make the world in the light of God.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="319">
<j>多くの帖で、今度の大建替があらゆる世界に及ぶ事とその後に想像を絶するような光の世界が到来することが書記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In many chapters it is written that the coming reconstruction will make the world in the light of God beyond imagination.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In many chapters it is written that the coming reconstruction will make the world in the light of God beyond imagination.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In many chapters it is written that the coming reconstruction will make the world in the light of God beyond imagination.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="56">
<sen id="320">
<j>予兆</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The sign</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sign</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sign</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="321">
<j>上記の三千世界の大洗濯や大峠が来る直前にはいくつかの兆候があるのだと神示には書記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Revelation it is written that there will be some signs before Large-scale Washing of the Three Thousand World and Big Mountain Pass.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Revelation it is written that there will be some signs before Large-scale Washing of the Three Thousand World and Big Mountain Pass.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Revelation it is written that there will be some signs before Large-scale Washing of the Three Thousand World and Big Mountain Pass.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="322">
<j>まず、天空に異常が現れ本来ひとつのはずの「太陽」が複数個見られる様になるという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">First it will be found an abnormal phenomenon in the sky that some &apos;suns&apos; appear which should be one normally.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">First will be found an abnormal phenomenon in the sky that multiple &apos;suns&apos; appear which should be one normally.</e>
<cmt>some-&gt;multiple</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">First will be found an abnormal phenomenon in the sky that multiple &apos;suns&apos; appear which should be one normally.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="323">
<j>また「月」にも異常が現れ太陽はその色が「黒く」月は「赤く」なり、空も赤く染まるのだという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also the &apos;moon&apos; will be abnormal that the color will turn &apos;red&apos; and the sun will turn &apos;black&apos; and the sky will also turn red.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also the &apos;moon&apos; will be abnormal and the color will turn &apos;red&apos; and the sun will turn &apos;black&apos; and the sky will also turn red.</e>
<cmt>that-&gt;and</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also the &apos;moon&apos; will be abnormal and the color will turn &apos;red&apos; and the sun will turn &apos;black&apos; and the sky will also turn red.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="324">
<j>また、北から軍事攻撃されるのが、その始まりになるとも書記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also it will start with a military attack from the north.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also it will start with a military attack from the north.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also it will start with a military attack from the north.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="325">
<j>これらは次のように述べられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is described as follows:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is described as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is described as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="326">
<j>「北から攻めて来るときが、この世の終り始めなり。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When you will be attacked from the north, it will start the end of this world. There will be not only a sun anymore but two, three, four suns. It will be the end. Folks, the end of this world will be the beginning of the God world. I also inform gods of this.&apos; (chapter 16 of volume Fuji)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When you will be attacked from the north, it will start the end of this world. There will be not only a sun anymore but two, three, four suns. It will be the end. Folks, the end of this world will be the beginning of the God world. I also inform gods of this.&apos; (chapter 16 of volume Fuji)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When you will be attacked from the north, it will start the end of this world.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="327">
<j>「天にお日様一つでないぞ、二つ三つ四つ出て来くる。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There will be not only a sun anymore but two, three, four suns.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="328">
<j>「そしたら、この世の終りと思へかし。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It will be the end.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="329">
<j>「この世の終りは神国の始めと思へ臣民よ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Folks, the end of this world will be the beginning of the God world.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="330">
<j>「神々様にも知らすぞよ。」（富士の巻第十六帖）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">I also inform gods of this.&apos; (chapter 16 of volume Fuji)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="331">
<j>「月は赤くなるぞ、日は黒くなるぞ、空はち（血）の色となるぞ、流れもちぢゃ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The moon will turn red, the sun will turn black and the sky will turn the color of blood as well as the rivers. People will get down on all fours or stand on hands or writhe for some time.&apos; (chapter 5 of volume Shikin)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The moon will turn red, the sun will turn black and the sky will turn the color of blood as well as the rivers. People will get down on all fours or stand on hands or writhe for some time.&apos; (chapter 5 of volume Shikin)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The moon will turn red, the sun will turn black and the sky will turn the color of blood as well as the rivers.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="332">
<j>「人民四つん這ひやら、逆立ちやら、ノタウチに、一時はなるのであるぞ。」（紫金之巻第五帖）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">People will get down on all fours or stand on hands or writhe for some time.&apos; (chapter 5 of volume Shikin)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="333">
<j>天空の異変については、上記以外にもう次のように書記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other than above, it is written about an abnormal change of the sky as follows:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other than above, it describes an abnormal change of the sky as follows:</e>
<cmt>passive voice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other than above, it describes an abnormal change of the sky as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="334">
<j>「宵の明星が東へ廻ってゐたら、愈々（いよいよ）だぞ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the evening star comes to the east, it will start finally. Be aware of abnormal changes in the sky as I&apos;m telling you over and over&apos; (chapter 19 of volume Matsu)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the evening star comes to the east, it will start finally. Be aware of abnormal changes in the sky as I&apos;m telling you over and over&apos; (chapter 19 of volume Matsu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the evening star comes to the east, it will start finally.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="335">
<j>「天の異変気付けと、くどう申してあろがな。」（松の巻第十九帖）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Be aware of abnormal changes in the sky as I&apos;m telling you over and over&apos; (chapter 19 of volume Matsu)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="336">
<j>更には次のように書記されている。（夜明けの巻第三帖）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also it is written as follows (chapter 3 of volume dawn):</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also it is written as follows (chapter 3 of volume dawn):</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also it is written as follows (chapter 3 of volume dawn):</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="337">
<j>「天の異変気付と申してあろう。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Be aware of abnormal changes in the sky. I&apos;m telling you it is not always true that spring comes after winter.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Be aware of abnormal changes in the sky. I&apos;m telling you it is not always true that spring comes after winter.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Be aware of abnormal changes in the sky.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="338">
<j>「冬の次が春とは限らんと申してあろが。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">I&apos;m telling you it is not always true that spring comes after winter.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="339">
<j>「夏雪降ることもあるのざぞ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It can be snow in summer.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It can snow in summer.&apos;</e>
<cmt>deleted “be”</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It can snow in summer.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="340">
<j>「人民の邪気が凝りて、天にも地にも、わけの判らん虫わくぞ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">People&apos;s evil will gather, by which unknown insects and worms appear in the sky as well as on the ground.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">People&apos;s evil will gather, by which unknown insects and worms appear in the sky as well as on the ground.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">People&apos;s evil will gather, by which unknown insects and worms appear in the sky as well as on the ground.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="341">
<j>同様に「空に変りたこと現はれたならば地に変りたことがあると心得よ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also written &apos;When you see an abnormal change in the sky, be aware that something abnormal will follow also on the ground. It will be coming finally.&apos; (chapter 13 of volume Amatsu)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also written &apos;When you see an abnormal change in the sky, be aware that something abnormal will follow also on the ground. It will be coming finally.&apos; (chapter 13 of volume Amatsu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also written &apos;When you see an abnormal change in the sky, be aware that something abnormal will follow also on the ground.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="342">
<j>「いよいよとなりて来てゐるのざぞ。」とある。（天つ巻第十三帖）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It will be coming finally.&apos; (chapter 13 of volume Amatsu)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="343">
<j>天や空の異変が見られるのだと神示には幾つかの帖で書記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">So it is described in some chapters of the Revelation that it will be seen abnormal changes in the sky and on the ground.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">So it is described in some chapters of the Revelation that it abnormal changes will be seen in the sky and on the ground.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">So it is described in some chapters of the Revelation that it abnormal changes will be seen in the sky and on the ground.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="344">
<j>また、次のように書かれている。（下つ巻第三十帖）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also it is written as follows (chapter 30 of volume Shimotsu):</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also it is written as follows (chapter 30 of volume Shimotsu):</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also it is written as follows (chapter 30 of volume Shimotsu):</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="345">
<j>「八のつく日に気つけて呉れよ、だんだん近づいたから。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Be aware of the dates of 8, because it is approaching. The day and month of Kanototori (the 58th of the sexagenary cycle) will be good.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Be aware of the dates of 8, because it is approaching. The day and month of Kanototori (the 58th of the sexagenary cycle) will be good.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Be aware of the dates of 8, because it is approaching.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="346">
<j>「辛酉（かのととり）はよき日、よき年ぞ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The day and month of Kanototori (the 58th of the sexagenary cycle) will be good.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="347">
<j>「冬に桜咲いたら気つけて呉れよ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Be careful if cherry blossoms bloom in a winter.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Be careful if cherry blossoms bloom in winter.&apos;</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Be careful if cherry blossoms bloom in winter.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="348">
<j>冬に桜が咲いたり夏に雪が降ったりといった季節の異常なども大きな予兆になるのだという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It says that abnormal phenomenon of season like cherry blossoms in winter and snow in summer will be also strong signs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It says that abnormal phenomenon of season like cherry blossoms in winter and snow in summer will be also strong signs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It says that abnormal phenomenon of season like cherry blossoms in winter and snow in summer will be also strong signs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="57">
<sen id="349">
<j>大峠</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Big Mountain Pass</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Big Mountain Pass</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Big Mountain Pass</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="350">
<j>上記した予兆の後に起こるとされる大戦乱や天変地異についての記述は神示の中に多く見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As mentioned above, in the Revelation it is described that a major war and natural disasters will occur after the signs.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As mentioned above, in the Revelation it is described that a major war and natural disasters will occur after the signs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As mentioned above, in the Revelation it is described that a major war and natural disasters will occur after the signs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="351">
<j>戦乱については多くの国がひとつになって日本に攻めて来るのだという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for the war, it is described that allied forces consisted of many countries will come against Japan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for the war, it is described that allied forces consisting of many countries will come against Japan.</e>
<cmt>consisted-&gt;consisting</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for the war, it is described that allied forces consisting of many countries will come against Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="352">
<j>また、時を同じくして天変地異なども起こると神示には書記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also it is written in the Revelation that natural disasters will occur simultaneously.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also it is written in the Revelation that natural disasters will occur simultaneously.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also it is written in the Revelation that natural disasters will occur simultaneously.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="353">
<j>「富士の巻」第三帖では次のように書記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In chapter 3 of volume &apos;Fuji&apos; it is written as follows:</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In chapter 3 of volume &apos;Fuji&apos; it is written as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In chapter 3 of volume &apos;Fuji&apos; it is written as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="354">
<j>「メリカもギリスは更なり、ドイツもイタリもオロシヤも外国はみな一つになりて㋹の国に攻め寄せて来る。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Allied forces consisted of the US, England, Germany, Italy and Russia will come against the country ㋹. Be prepared.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Allied forces consisting of the US, England, Germany, Italy and Russia will come against the country ㋹. Be prepared.&apos;</e>
<cmt>consisted-&gt;consisting</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Allied forces consisting of the US, England, Germany, Italy and Russia will come against the country ㋹.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="355">
<j>「その覚悟で用意しておけよ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Be prepared.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="356">
<j>「どこから何んなこと出来るか、臣民には分かるまいがな。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However you won&apos;t know what to do first and then.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However you won&apos;t know what to do first and then.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However you won&apos;t know what to do first and then.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="357">
<j>アメリカ合衆国、イギリス、ドイツ、イタリア、ロシアなどの国の軍隊が日本に攻めて来るらしい事が述べられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is described that the military forces such as the US, England, Germany, Italy and Russia will attack Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is described that the military forces such as the US, England, Germany, Italy and Russia will attack Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is described that the military forces such as the US, England, Germany, Italy and Russia will attack Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="358">
<j>また、天変地異については「下つ巻」第二十八帖で以下のようにある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for natural disasters, it is written in chapter 28 of volume &apos;Shimotsu&apos; as &apos;The world will be thrown into utter confusion in a blink of an eye as if heaven and earth turn each other upside down. So I&apos;m telling you again and again. It will be too late to prepare after it comes. Prepare now.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for natural disasters, it is written in chapter 28 of volume &apos;Shimotsu&apos; that &apos;The world will be thrown into utter confusion in a blink of an eye as if heaven and earth turn each other upside down. So I&apos;m telling you again and again. It will be too late to prepare after it comes. Prepare now.&apos;</e>
<cmt>as-&gt;that</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for natural disasters, it is written in chapter 28 of volume &apos;Shimotsu&apos; as follow.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="359">
<j>「またたきの間に天地引繰り返る様な大騒動が出来る。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The world will be thrown into utter confusion in a blink of an eye as if heaven and earth turn each other upside down.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="360">
<j>「だから、くどう気つけてゐるのざ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">So I&apos;m telling you again and again.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="361">
<j>「さあといふ時になりてからでは間に合はんぞ、用意なされよ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It will be too late to prepare after it comes. Prepare now.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="362">
<j>更にはそれだけにとどまらず次のように続く。（磐戸（一八十）の巻第七帖）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It continues further as follows (chapter 7 of volume Iwato):</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It continues further as follows (chapter 7 of volume Iwato):</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It continues further as follows (chapter 7 of volume Iwato):</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="363">
<j>「人民のイクサや天災ばかりで、今度の岩戸ひらくと思ふてゐたら大きな間違ひざぞ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is wrong that you think this cave will open only after wars and natural disasters. It will not so easy as wars and natural disasters. You&apos;ll be too surprised to say a word, so improve your spirit soon not to fear anything. It is the fear not for your bodies, but for your spirits. You won&apos;t be able to imagine the war and maelstrom of spirits, so you need to ask God. Therefore you have to improve your spirit to be able to be possessed by God.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is wrong for you to think that this cave will open only after wars and natural disasters. It will not be so easy as wars and natural disasters. You&apos;ll be too surprised to say a word, so improve your spirit soon not to fear anything. It is the fear not for your bodies, but for your spirits. You won&apos;t be able to imagine the war and maelstrom of spirits, so you need to ask God. Therefore you have to improve your spirit to be able to be possessed by God.&apos;</e>
<cmt>prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is wrong for you to think that this cave will open only after wars and natural disasters.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="364">
<j>「戦や天災でラチあく様なチョロコイことでないぞ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It will not be so easy as wars and natural disasters.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="365">
<j>「あいた口ふさがらんことになりて来るのざから、早うミタマ磨いてこわいもの無いやうになっておりてくれよ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">You&apos;ll be too surprised to say a word, so improve your spirit soon not to fear anything.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="366">
<j>「肉体のこわさではないぞ、タマのこわさざぞ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is the fear not for your bodies, but for your spirits.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="367">
<j>「タマの戦や禍は見当とれまいがな、神のミコトにきけよ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">You won&apos;t be able to imagine the war and maelstrom of spirits, so you need to ask God.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="368">
<j>「それにはどうしてもミタマ磨いて神かかれる様にならねばならんのざ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore you have to improve your spirit to be able to be possessed by God.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="369">
<j>「神かかりと申しても其処らに御座る天狗や狐や狸つきではないぞ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is not a possession of long-nosed goblins, foxes and raccoon dogs around here.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is not a possession of long-nosed goblins, foxes and raccoon dogs around here.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is not a possession of long-nosed goblins, foxes and raccoon dogs around here.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="370">
<j>「まことの神かかりであるぞ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a possession of God.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a possession of God.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a possession of God.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="371">
<j>本当の怖さは人間の戦争や天災、また、肉体などではなくタマ（魂）の災禍の怖さなのだという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It means that what to fear is not a war and natural disaster or physical fear but a spiritual disaster.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It means that what to fear is not a war and natural disaster or physical fear but a spiritual disaster.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It means that what to fear is not a war and natural disaster or physical fear but a spiritual disaster.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="372">
<j>同様に次のように書記されている帖もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also in other chapter it is described as follows:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also in another chapter it is described as follows:</e>
<cmt>other-&gt;another</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also in another chapter it is described as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="373">
<j>「戦恐れてゐるが臣民の戦位。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">People are afraid of war which is just a human war. What are you afraid of? What is more fearful is evil spirit in your mind.&apos; (chapter 7 of volume Fuji)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">People are afraid of war which is just a human war. What are you afraid of? What is more fearful is evil spirit in your mind.&apos; (chapter 7 of volume Fuji)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">People are afraid of war which is just a human war.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="374">
<j>「何が怖いのぞ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">What are you afraid of?&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="375">
<j>「それより己の心に巣くうてる悪のみたまが怖いぞ。」（富士の巻第七帖））</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">What is more fearful is evil spirit in your mind.&apos; (chapter 7 of volume Fuji)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="376">
<j>本当の怖さは魂のそれだとここでも述べられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is written here again that what is to fear is actually that of spirit.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is written here again that what is to fear is actually that of spirit.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is written here again that what is to fear is actually that of spirit.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="377">
<j>なお、神示の中で書記されている天変地異については次のような災いが起こるとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the revelation it is described about the coming natural disasters as follows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the revelation it is described about the coming natural disasters as follows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the revelation it is described about the coming natural disasters as follows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="58">
<sen id="378">
<j>世界中が唸り、陸が海となるところや、海が陸になるところもあるという。（上つ巻第三帖）、（地つ巻第十六帖）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The world will roar and in some places the land will become sea and the sea will become land. (the chapter 3 in volume Uetsu) (chapter 16 of volume Kunitsu)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The world will roar and in some places the land will become sea and the sea will become land. (chapter 3 in volume Uetsu) (chapter 16 of volume Kunitsu)</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The world will roar and in some places the land will become sea and the sea will become land. (chapter 3 in volume Uetsu) (chapter 16 of volume Kunitsu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="59">
<sen id="379">
<j>大地震、火の雨降らしての大洗濯になるという。（紫金之巻第五帖）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It will be a large-scale washing with major earthquake and fire rain. (chapter 5 of volume Shikin)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It will be a large-scale washing with major earthquake and fire rain. (chapter 5 of volume Shikin)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It will be a large-scale washing with major earthquake and fire rain. (chapter 5 of volume Shikin)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="60">
<sen id="380">
<j>火と水の災難がいかに恐ろしいかを大なり小なり知らされる事になるという。（富士の巻第十九帖）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It will show more or less how fearful fire and flood disaster will be. (chapter 19 of volume Fuji)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It will show more or less how fearful fire and flood disaster will be. (chapter 19 of volume Fuji)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It will show more or less how fearful fire and flood disaster will be. (chapter 19 of volume Fuji)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="61">
<sen id="381">
<j>一時は天も地も一つにまぜまぜになるという。（富士の巻第十九帖）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Heaven and earth will be mixed for a time. (chapter 19 of volume Fuji)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Heaven and earth will be mixed for a time. (chapter 19 of volume Fuji)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Heaven and earth will be mixed for a time. (chapter 19 of volume Fuji)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="62">
<sen id="382">
<j>天地がうなり、上下引っくり返るという。（上つ巻第二十七帖））</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Heaven and earth will roar and turn each other upside down. (chapter 27 of volume Uetsu)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Heaven and earth will roar and turn each other upside down. (chapter 27 of volume Uetsu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Heaven and earth will roar and turn each other upside down. (chapter 27 of volume Uetsu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="63">
<sen id="383">
<j>大風が起こり、大海原には竜巻が発生し、やがて火の雨と地震が、山は火を噴きどよめくという。（富士の巻第二十四帖）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gales will blow, tornadoes will break out from the ocean, fire rain will fall, earthquakes will occur and rumbling mountains will breathe fire. (chapter 24 of volume Fuji)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gales will blow, tornadoes will break out from the ocean, fire rain will fall, earthquakes will occur and rumbling mountains will breathe fire. (chapter 24 of volume Fuji)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gales will blow, tornadoes will break out from the ocean, fire rain will fall, earthquakes will occur and rumbling mountains will breathe fire. (chapter 24 of volume Fuji)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="64">
<sen id="384">
<j>富士山がいよいよ動くのだという。（上つ巻第二十一帖）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And finally Mt. Fuji will start to move. (chapter 21 of volume Uetsu)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And finally Mt. Fuji will start to move. (chapter 21 of volume Uetsu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And finally Mt. Fuji will start to move. (chapter 21 of volume Uetsu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="65">
<sen id="385">
<j>大地も転位、天も転位するという。（五葉之巻第十五帖）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Earth will turn as well as heaven. (chapter 15 of volume Goyo)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Earth will turn as well as heaven. (chapter 15 of volume Goyo)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Earth will turn as well as heaven. (chapter 15 of volume Goyo)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>その他エピソード等</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other episodes</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other episodes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other episodes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="386">
<j>天明が知人である高田集蔵の誘いで、昭和19年6月10日に千葉県印旛郡公津村台方（現・成田市台方）を訪れたのはその近くに「どぶろく」を造っている家が在り、そこに行けば「どぶろく」を飲めると言う事が最初の理由だったらしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On June 10, 1944, it seems that Tenmei was invited to Daikata, Kozu village, Inba-gun, Chiba Prefecture, (presently Daikata in Narita City) by his acquaintance Shuzo TAKADA originally to visit a family brewing &apos;doburoku&apos; (raw rice wine) to drink it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On June 10, 1944, it seems that Tenmei was invited to Daikata, Kozu village, Inba-gun, Chiba Prefecture, (presently Daikata in Narita City) by his acquaintance Shuzo TAKADA originally to visit a family brewing &apos;doburoku&apos; (raw rice wine) to drink it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On June 10, 1944, it seems that Tenmei was invited to Daikata, Kozu village, Inba-gun, Chiba Prefecture, (presently Daikata in Narita City) by his acquaintance Shuzo TAKADA originally to visit a family brewing &apos;doburoku&apos; (raw rice wine) to drink it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="387">
<j>当時は戦時中でもあり酒には不自由していた時代であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because it was during the war at that time, it was hard to obtain alcohol.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because it was during the war at that time, it was hard to obtain alcohol.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because it was during the war at that time, it was hard to obtain alcohol.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="388">
<j>天明自身は酒がかなり好きだったといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Tenmei liked alcohol very much.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Tenmei liked alcohol very much.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Tenmei liked alcohol very much.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="389">
<j>しかし、先方の都合で結局、酒は飲めなかったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However it seems that they were unable to drink due to the family&apos;s reason at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However it seems that they were unable to drink due to the family&apos;s reason at that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However it seems that they were unable to drink due to the family&apos;s reason at that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="390">
<j>天之日津久神社に参拝し、自動書記も終えて無人の社務所で休んでいた時に籠を背負った農家風の老婆が現れ天明と親しくなり、社務所にあった御神酒を2人で平らげてしまったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Tenmei visited Ame no Hitsuku-jinja Shrine and took a rest at the shrine office after the automatic writing, he met an old woman carrying a basket on her back and became friends with her and drank up sacred rice wine together with her there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Tenmei visited Ame no Hitsuku-jinja Shrine and took a rest at the shrine office after the automatic writing, he met an old woman carrying a basket on her back and became friends with her and drank up sacred rice wine together with her there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Tenmei visited Ame no Hitsuku-jinja Shrine and took a rest at the shrine office after the automatic writing, he met an old woman carrying a basket on her back and became friends with her and drank up sacred rice wine together with her there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="391">
<j>老婆はまるでここの主でもあるかのように、遠慮もなく酒瓶を持ち出して来て、天明に酒を飲むように勧めたらしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It seems that she brought out a bottle of rice wine without any permission as if she was the owner and offered it to Tenmei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It seems that she brought out a bottle of rice wine without any permission as if she was the owner and offered it to Tenmei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It seems that she brought out a bottle of rice wine without any permission as if she was the owner and offered it to Tenmei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="392">
<j>その雰囲気は天明に勧めつつ、そしてまた自分も共に飲むといった感じで、自然で上手だったと天明は後に語っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tenmei said later that she had encouraged him to drink while she had also been drinking in a natural and nice manner.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tenmei said later that she had encouraged him to drink while she had also been drinking in a natural and nice manner.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tenmei said later that she had encouraged him to drink while she had also been drinking in a natural and nice manner.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="393">
<j>その後も神社近くの老婆の裕福そうな家でたらふく御馳走になったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that he was treated a lot of food in her luxury looking house.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that he was treated a lot of food in her luxurious house.</e>
<cmt>luxurious</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that he was treated a lot of food in her luxurious house.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="394">
<j>この2年後に天之日津久神社近くに天明は住むことになるが、この老婆にまず、挨拶しようと老婆の家を探したが家もなく老婆もおらず（天明の後の述懐によれば、そこに家があったと思われる痕跡すら無かったという）、近所の人に聞いても分からず、浦島太郎になったような釈然としない不思議な気持ち（天明の言葉によれば、今浦島のような気持ち）だったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Two years later, when Tenmei moved near Ame no Hitsuku-jinja Shrine, he looked for her house to see the old woman, but she wasn&apos;t there (according to Tenmei, there was even no trace of ant house) and nobody knew about her there and he felt unsatisfied like Urashima Taro (a Japanese legend) (in Tenmei&apos;s word, he felt like Ima Urashima [someone who is surprised by the change when he/she comes back to home after a long time just like Urashima Taro]).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Two years later, when Tenmei moved near Ame no Hitsuku-jinja Shrine, he looked for her house to see the old woman, but she wasn&apos;t there (according to Tenmei, there was even no trace of the house) and nobody knew about her there and he felt unsatisfied like Urashima Taro (a Japanese legend) (in Tenmei&apos;s word, he felt like Ima Urashima [someone who is surprised by the change when he/she comes back to home after a long time just like Urashima Taro]).</e>
<cmt>typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Two years later, when Tenmei moved near Ame no Hitsuku-jinja Shrine, he looked for her house to see the old woman, but she wasn&apos;t there (according to Tenmei, there was even no trace of the house) and nobody knew about her there and he felt unsatisfied like Urashima Taro (a Japanese legend) (in Tenmei&apos;s word, he felt like Ima Urashima [someone who is surprised by the change when he/she comes back to home after a long time just like Urashima Taro]).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="395">
<j>岡本三典によると天明は神示が降ろされてからも、しばらくの間はそれを全くと言っていいほど読む事も出来ず内容も解らなかった為、下級霊の仕業に依るものだと思っていたらしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Minori OKAMOTO, Tenmei couldn&apos;t understand almost all the contents of the Revelation for some time, so he considered what he had received as something from a lower-grade spirit.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Minori OKAMOTO, Tenmei couldn&apos;t understand much of the Revelation for some time, so he considered what he had received as something from a lower-grade spirit.</e>
<cmt>almost all the contents-&gt;much</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Minori OKAMOTO, Tenmei couldn&apos;t read or understand much of the Revelation for some time, so he considered what he had received as something from a lower-grade spirit.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="396">
<j>その為に書記された原文も放って置いたり、中には捨ててしまったものさえあったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore he left the original text and even threw away a part of them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore he left the original text and even threw away a part of it.</e>
<cmt>them-&gt;it</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore he left the original text and even threw away a part of it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="397">
<j>神示の重要性を最初に気付き天明に知らせたのは、「大本」時代からの知り合いである「矢野新」（陸軍大佐の矢野祐太郎の妻）だったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was his acquaintance in Omoto (a religious community) &apos;Shin YANO&apos; (the wife of Yutaro YANO, an army colonel), who found the importance of the revelation first and let Tenmei know it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was his acquaintance in Omoto (a religious community) &apos;Shin YANO&apos; (the wife of Yutaro YANO, an army colonel), who found the importance of the revelation first and let Tenmei know it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was his acquaintance in Omoto (a religious community) &apos;Shin YANO&apos; (the wife of Yutaro YANO, an army colonel), who found the importance of the revelation first and let Tenmei know it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="398">
<j>この矢野新は優れた霊能者であり天明からはじめて原文を見せられた時に、即座にその重大性を直感し「これは正真正銘の太神様の御真筆ですよ」と顔色を変えて答えたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shin YANO who was a good psychic, intuitively found the importance at once and said turning pale &apos;this is a true autograph document of a holy spirit&apos; when she was shown the original texts by Tenmei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shin YANO who was a good psychic, intuitively found the importance at once and said turning pale &apos;this is a true autograph document of a holy spirit&apos; when she was shown the original texts by Tenmei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shin YANO who was a good psychic, intuitively found the importance at once and said turning pale &apos;this is a true autograph document of a holy spirit&apos; when she was shown the original texts by Tenmei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="399">
<j>その後、この矢野が呼びかけ指揮を執る形で幾人かの霊能者や神典研究家が集まり神示を解読する研究会が誕生。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, Yano encouraged and led some psychics and Shintoists to establish a study group to decode the Revelation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, Yano encouraged and led some psychics and Shintoists to establish a study group to decode the Revelation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, Yano encouraged and led some psychics and Shintoists to establish a study group to decode the Revelation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="400">
<j>神示は少しずつ解読されていったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Revelation was decoded gradually.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Revelation was decoded gradually.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Revelation was decoded gradually.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="401">
<j>上記の矢野以外に神示の重要性に気付いた、もう一人の人物が天明と同じく八幡神社で留守神主を務めていた「法元」だったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Except Yano, another person who found the importance of the Revelation was &apos;Hogen&apos;, a temporary Shinto priest of Hachiman-jinja Shrine at that time just like Tenmei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Aside from Yano, another person who found the importance of the Revelation was &apos;Hogen&apos;, a temporary Shinto priest of Hachiman-jinja Shrine at that time just like Tenmei.</e>
<cmt>prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Aside from Yano, another person who found the importance of the Revelation was &apos;Hogen,&apos; a temporary Shinto priest of Hachiman-jinja Shrine at that time just like Tenmei.</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="402">
<j>法元も陸軍大佐であり、軍人達の中（特に陸軍内）に日月神示を知っている者が多かったのはこれが理由のひとつだったと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hogen was also an army colonel, therefore many of soldiers (especially those of the army) knew about Hitsuki Shinji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hogen was also an army colonel, therefore many soldiers (especially those of the army) knew about Hitsuki Shinji.</e>
<cmt>prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hogen was also an army colonel, therefore many soldiers (especially those of the army) knew about Hitsuki Shinji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="403">
<j>おそらく法元は八幡神社で勤務していた時に、天明が自動書記で神示を書かされる場面を垣間見た事があり、その状況や雰囲気に大きく感銘を受けたものと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is assumed that when Hogen worked for Hachiman-jinja Shrine, he probably saw the moment Tenmei was made to write the revelation automatically and was impressed by the situation and the atmosphere.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is assumed that when Hogen worked for Hachiman-jinja Shrine, he probably saw the moment Tenmei was made to write the revelation automatically and was impressed by the situation and the atmosphere.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is assumed that when Hogen worked for Hachiman-jinja Shrine, he probably saw the moment Tenmei was made to write the revelation automatically and was impressed by the situation and the atmosphere.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="404">
<j>軍人でありながら留守神主の一人に任命されている事から法元自身がかなりの神道知識と素養を持っていたと考えられ、この「法元」という名前自体もそれに基づく「神号」か「雅号」だと推測される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As he was appointed as one of the temporary priests though he was a soldier, it is assumed that Hogen had considerable knowledge and background of Shinto and the name &apos;Hogen&apos; would be also a Shinto name classified under &apos;Shingo&apos; or &apos;Gago&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As he was appointed as one of the temporary priests though he was a soldier, it is assumed that Hogen had considerable knowledge and background of Shinto and the name &apos;Hogen&apos; would be also a Shinto name classified under &apos;Shingo&apos; or &apos;Gago&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As he was appointed as one of the temporary priests though he was a soldier, it is assumed that Hogen had considerable knowledge and background of Shinto and the name &apos;Hogen&apos; would be also a Shinto name classified under &apos;Shingo&apos; or &apos;Gago.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオド位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="405">
<j>しかも、陸軍大佐という高位の立場にあった為、陸軍内における発言力や影響力は非常に大きく、上層部や仲間の軍人達に報告し、承認されたであろう事も容易に推測される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because he was in a high position as army colonel with powerful influence, it is easily assumed that he would report it to the military leader ship and army comrades and they approved it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because he was in a high position as army colonel with powerful influence, it is easily assumed that he would report it to the military leadership and army comrades and they approved it.</e>
<cmt>leadership</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because he was in a high position as army colonel with powerful influence, it is easily assumed that he would report it to the military leadership and army comrades and they approved it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="406">
<j>また、神示が散逸せずに無事に残ったのもこの法元のおかげであったと三典は自著で記している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also Minori wrote in her book that the Revelation wasn&apos;t scattered and lost, thanks to Hogen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also Minori wrote in her book that the Revelation wasn&apos;t scattered and lost, thanks to Hogen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also Minori wrote in her book that the Revelation wasn&apos;t scattered and lost, thanks to Hogen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="407">
<j>その後に天明自身も神示の重要性に気付き書記されたものを清書したりしていたが、清書した神示のいくつかは、神前に供えていたところ霊化して消えて無くなってしまったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later Tenmei also recognized the importance and tried to make a fair copy of the Revelation written by automatic writing, but some parts of the fair copy offered on the altar were spiritualized and disappeared.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later Tenmei also recognized the importance and tried to make a fair copy of the Revelation written by automatic writing, but some parts of the fair copy offered on the altar were spiritualized and disappeared.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later Tenmei also recognized the importance and tried to make a fair copy of the Revelation written by automatic writing, but some parts of the fair copy offered on the altar were spiritualized and disappeared.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="408">
<j>（清書したものが消えて、原文は残っていたと思われる。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(It is assumed that the original text remained after the fair copy disappeared)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(It is assumed that the original text remained after the fair copy disappeared)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(It is assumed that the original text remained after the fair copy disappeared)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="409">
<j>天明自身はもともと、かなりの小食家だったが神示が降りる前には更に少なくなり、1日に餅1個やリンゴ1個しか食べない日が続いたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tenmei who was basically a very small eater, ate less - only a rice cake or an apple in a day - for several days before the Revelation came down.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tenmei who was basically a very small eater, ate less - only a rice cake or an apple in a day - for several days before the Revelation came down.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tenmei who was basically a very small eater, ate less - only a rice cake or an apple in a day - for several days before the Revelation came down.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="410">
<j>それでも本人は元気で気分は至って爽快だったらしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However he was fine and felt very good.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However he was fine and felt very good.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However he was fine and felt very good.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="411">
<j>神示の中で「天明は神示うつす役、書かす御役」（極め之巻第十帖）や「天明は神示書かす御役ぞ、陰の役ぞ」（地つ巻第二十九帖）などと書記されている部分があるが、神霊も天明に懸かるのが難しい時や苦労した場合もあったらしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the revelation it is written some indications that the spirit sometimes had difficulties to possess Tenmei &apos;Tenmei&apos;s task is to transcribe the Revelation, to write it down&apos; (chapter 10 of volume Kiwame) and &apos;Tenmei&apos;s role is to write the Revelation down. It is a behind-the-scenes role.&apos; (chapter 29 of volume Kunitsu)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the revelation are written some indications that the spirit sometimes had difficulties possessing Tenmei &apos;Tenmei&apos;s task is to transcribe the Revelation, to write it down&apos; (chapter 10 of volume Kiwame) and &apos;Tenmei&apos;s role is to write the Revelation down. It is a behind-the-scenes role.&apos; (chapter 29 of volume Kunitsu)</e>
<cmt>it is-&gt;are</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the revelation are written some indications that the spirit sometimes had difficulties possessing Tenmei &apos;Tenmei&apos;s task is to transcribe the Revelation, to write it down&apos; (chapter 10 of volume Kiwame) and &apos;Tenmei&apos;s role is to write the Revelation down which is a behind-the-scenes role.&apos; (chapter 29 of volume Kunitsu)</e>
<cmt>一文にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="412">
<j>それに関して次のように神霊が述べている帖がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The spirit says about it as follows:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The spirit says about it as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The spirit says about it as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="413">
<j>「天明阿房になりて呉れよ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Be empty, Tenmei. Drop your sense of self. It is hard for me to possess you.&apos; (chapter 12 of volume Kunitsu)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Be empty, Tenmei. Drop your sense of self. It is hard for me to possess you.&apos; (chapter 12 of volume Kunitsu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Be empty, Tenmei.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="414">
<j>「我すてて呉れよ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Drop your sense of self.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="415">
<j>「神かかるのに苦しいぞ。」（地つ巻第十二帖）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is hard for me to possess you.&apos; (chapter 12 of volume Kunitsu)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="416">
<j>「テンメイかいしん（改心）まだまだのまだであるぞ。」（黄金の巻第二十五帖）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tenmei, clean up yourself more and more and more.&apos; (chapter 25 of volume Ogon)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tenmei, clean up yourself more and more and more.&apos; (chapter 25 of volume Ogon)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tenmei, clean up yourself more and more and more.&apos; (chapter 25 of volume Ogon)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="417">
<j>国常立尊の姿については、「下つ巻」第三帖で以下のように書記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In chapter 3 of volume &apos;Shimotsu&apos; it is described about the appearance of Kuninotoko Tachinokami &apos;I was going to show you myself, but you may be frightened out of your senses, so I showed myself engraved in a stone, but you didn&apos;t notice it, so I gave you a wood carving. That is an appearance of the spirit at an activity. Don&apos;t make a show of it.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In chapter 3 of volume &apos;Shimotsu&apos; is described the appearance of Kuninotoko Tachinokami &apos;I was going to show you myself, but you may be frightened out of your senses, so I showed myself engraved in a stone, but you didn&apos;t notice it, so I gave you a wood carving. That is an appearance of the spirit at an activity. Don&apos;t make a show of it.&apos;</e>
<cmt>prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In chapter 3 of volume &apos;Shimotsu&apos; is described the appearance of Kuninotoko Tachinokami as follows.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="418">
<j>「この神のまことの姿見せてやる積りでありたが、人に見せると、びっくりして気を失ふもしれんから、石にほらせて見せておいたのにまだ気づかんから木の型をやったであろうがな。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">I was going to show you myself, but you may be frightened out of your senses, so I showed myself engraved in a stone, but you didn&apos;t notice it, so I gave you a wood carving.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="419">
<j>「それが神の或る活動の時の姿であるぞ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That is an appearance of the spirit at an activity.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="420">
<j>「神の見せ物にしてはならんぞ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Don&apos;t make a show of it.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="421">
<j>「天つ巻」第四帖でも「この方は元の肉体のままに生き通しであるから、天明にも見せなんだのぞ。」と書記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also in chapter 4 of volume &apos;Amatsu&apos; it is written &apos;I have been living through in an original body, so I don&apos;t show it even to Tenmei.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also in chapter 4 of volume &apos;Amatsu&apos; it is written &apos;I have been living in an original body, so I don&apos;t show it even to Tenmei.&apos;</e>
<cmt>prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also in chapter 4 of volume &apos;Amatsu&apos; it is written &apos;I have been living in an original body, so I don&apos;t show it even to Tenmei.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="422">
<j>天明自身も若い頃に所属していた「大本」の「出口王仁三郎」によると、その姿は光明に輝き、深いまなじりに光をたたえた、「八握の神剣」を腰に帯した白髪の老神だったという。（出口和明『大地の母3巻　地獄の釜』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &apos;Onisaburo DEGUCHI&apos; from &apos;Omoto&apos; to which Tenmei also belonged when he was young, the appearance was a glittering old spirit with thoughtful twinkling eyes and white hair, belting &apos;the sacred Yatsuka sword&apos; on. (&quot;the Cauldron of Hell of the volume 3 of Great Mother&quot; written by Yasuaki DEGUCHI)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &apos;Onisaburo DEGUCHI&apos; from &apos;Omoto&apos; to which Tenmei also belonged when he was young, the appearance was a glittering old spirit with thoughtful twinkling eyes and white hair, belting &apos;the sacred Yatsuka sword&apos; on. (&quot;the Cauldron of Hell of the volume 3 of Great Mother&quot; written by Yasuaki DEGUCHI)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &apos;Onisaburo DEGUCHI&apos; from &apos;Omoto&apos; to which Tenmei also belonged when he was young, the appearance was a glittering old spirit with thoughtful twinkling eyes and white hair, belting &apos;the sacred Yatsuka sword&apos; on. (&quot;the Cauldron of Hell of the volume 3 of Great Mother&quot; written by Yasuaki DEGUCHI)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="423">
<j>また、同じ「大本」の「出口なお」も霊夢で見た国常立尊の姿は純白の衣冠束帯で剣も白金の光芒を射放つ、眩いばかりの神だったという。（出口和明『大地の母4巻　立春の光』）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nao DEGUCHI&apos; also from &apos;Omoto&apos; said that Kuninotoko Tachinokami whom she saw in a spiritual dream was a sparkling spirit in a white Ikan Sokutai (noble formal dress) wearing a sword which was radiating platinum light. (&quot;Light in the beginning of spring of the volume 4 of Great Mother&quot; written by Yasuaki DEGUCHI)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nao DEGUCHI&apos; also from &apos;Omoto&apos; said that Kuninotoko Tachinokami whom she saw in a spiritual dream was a sparkling spirit in a white Ikan Sokutai (noble formal dress) wearing a sword which was radiating platinum light. (&quot;Light in the beginning of spring of the volume 4 of Great Mother&quot; written by Yasuaki DEGUCHI)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nao DEGUCHI&apos; also from &apos;Omoto&apos; said that Kuninotoko Tachinokami whom she saw in a spiritual dream was a sparkling spirit in a white Ikan Sokutai (noble formal dress) wearing a sword which was radiating platinum light. (&quot;Light in the beginning of spring of the volume 4 of Great Mother&quot; written by Yasuaki DEGUCHI)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="424">
<j>神示によると世の中が乱れたのは人間界からではなく、神界からなのだという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the Revelation, social unrest has started in the spirit world first, not in the human world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the Revelation, social unrest has started in the spirit world first, not in the human world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the Revelation, social unrest has started in the spirit world first, not in the human world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="425">
<j>「んめの巻（梅の巻？運命？の巻）」第十帖で以下のように述べている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In chapter 10 of volume &apos;Nme&apos; (volume Ume [plum]? or Unmei [fate]?) it is described &apos;It has been confused first in the spirit world. The human world needs to have a determination to set the world aright and to open the cave by yourselves, which will make a continuing perfect world and open the cave.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In chapter 10 of volume &apos;Nme&apos; (volume Ume [plum]? or Unmei [fate]?) it is described &apos;It has been confused first in the spirit world. The human world needs to have a determination to set the world aright and to open the cave by yourselves, which will make a continuing perfect world and open the cave.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In chapter 10 of volume &apos;Nme&apos; (volume Ume [plum]? or Unmei [fate]?) it is described as follows.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="426">
<j>「世は神界から乱れたのであるぞ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has been confused first in the spirit world.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="427">
<j>「人間界から世建直して地の岩戸人間が開いて見せると云ふ程の気魄（きはく）なくてならんのざぞ、その気魄幸はふのざぞ、岩戸ひらけるぞ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The human world needs to have a determination to set the world aright and to open the cave by yourselves, which will make a continuing perfect world and open the cave.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="428">
<j>人間界側からの努力が大切なのであると語られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It says that the efforts from the human world are important.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It says that the efforts from the human world are important.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It says that the efforts from the human world are important.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="429">
<j>また、同巻の第二十四帖でも以下のように書記させている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also in chapter 24 of the same volume it is described &apos;depending on the efforts, also human can reach a certain level of spirit which can be offered advices by God. It is best to improve yourself.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also in chapter 24 of the same volume it says &apos;depending on the efforts, also human cans reach a certain level of spirit which can be offered advice by God. It is best to improve yourself.&apos;</e>
<cmt>is described-&gt;says</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also in chapter 24 of the same volume it says as follows.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="430">
<j>「人民も磨けば神に御意見される程に身魂に依ってはなれるのであるぞ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Depending on the efforts, also human can reach a certain level of spirit which can be offered advice by God.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="431">
<j>「何より身魂磨き結構。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is best to improve yourself.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 北越6号(id:141986), BoB774(id:148281), Kinori(id:443), 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>