<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>絵馬</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ema</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ema</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ema</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>絵馬（えま）は、神社や寺院に祈願するとき、および祈願した願いが叶ってその謝礼をするときに寺社に奉納する、絵が描かれた木の板である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Ema&quot; is a wooden board with a picture of a horse, which is dedicated to a temple or a shrine when making a wish, or when showing gratitude for the granted wish.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Ema&quot; is a wooden board with a picture of a horse, which is dedicated to a temple or a shrine when making a wish, or when showing gratitude for the granted wish.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Ema&quot; is a wooden board with a picture of a horse, which is dedicated to a temple or a shrine when making a wish, or when showing gratitude for the granted wish.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>個人で奉納する絵馬は小型でウマなどの絵が描かれていて、余白や裏面に祈願の内容や氏名などを書くようになっているものが寺社で販売されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ema sold at temples and shrines for personal dedication are small with a picture of a horse, and have space in the margin or on the back to write the wish and name.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ema sold at temples and shrines for personal dedication are small with a picture of a horse, and have space in the margin or on the back to write the wish and a person&apos;s name.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ema sold at temples and shrines for personal dedication are small with a picture of a horse, and have space in the margin or on the back to write the wish and a person&apos;s name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>大人数で奉納するものは大型で、画家に描かせるなどして奉納者が用意する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those dedicated by a large group of people are large, and are prepared by the dedicator, sometimes with pictures drawn by artists.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those dedicated by a large group of people are large, and are prepared by the dedicator, sometimes with pictures drawn by artists.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those dedicated by a large group of people are large, and are prepared by the dedicator, sometimes with pictures drawn by artists.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>通常は五角形（家型）をしているが、これはかつて、板の上に屋根をつけていた名残である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It normally has a pentagon shape (shape of a house), which can be traced back to the fact that, in the past, they were made with a roof attached to a piece of board.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It normally has a pentagon shape (shape of a house), which can be traced back to the fact that, in the past, they were made with a roof attached to a piece of the board.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It normally has a pentagon shape (shape of a house), which can be traced back to the fact that, in the past, they were made with a roof attached to a piece of the board.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="6">
<j>奈良時代の『続日本紀』には、神の乗り物としての馬、神馬（しんめ、じんめ）を奉納していたことが記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the &quot;Shoku-Nihongi &quot; (the second in a series of chronicles about Japan) from Nara period, a sacred horse for the god to ride was dedicated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the &quot;Shoku-Nihongi &quot; (the second in a series of chronicles about Japan) from the Nara period, a sacred horse for the god to ride was dedicated.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the &quot;Shoku-Nihongi&quot; (the second in a series of chronicles about Japan) from the Nara period, a sacred horse for the god to ride was dedicated.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>しかし、馬は高価でなかなか献納できず、また、献納された寺社の側でも馬の世話をするのが大変である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, horses were high-priced and could not be dedicated easily, and the temples and shrines receiving the horses had a hard time taking care of them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, horses were high-priced and could not be dedicated easily, and the temples and shrines receiving the horses had a hard time taking care of them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, horses were high-priced and could not be dedicated easily, and the temples and shrines receiving the horses had a hard time taking care of them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>そのため、馬を奉納できない者は次第に木や紙、土で作った馬の像で代用するようになり、平安時代から板に描いた馬の絵で代えられるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, those who could not dedicate a horse began substituting with statues of horses made from wood, paper, or soil, and from Heian period, it was substituted with a picture of a horse drawn on a board.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, those who could not dedicate a horse began substituting with statues of horses made from wood, paper, or clay, and from the Heian period, it was substituted with a picture of a horse drawn on a board.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, those who could not dedicate a horse began substituting with statues of horses made from wood, paper, or clay, and from the Heian period, it was substituted with a picture of a horse drawn on a board.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="9">
<j>さらに、室町時代になると馬だけでなく様々な絵が描かれるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, in Muromachi period, pictures other than horses were drawn.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, in the Muromachi period, pictures other than horses were drawn.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, in the Muromachi period, pictures other than horses were drawn.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>例えばキツネを使いとする稲荷神社では狐の絵が描かれている所もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, in Inari-jinja Shrine, where fox is the messenger, some have pictures of foxes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, in Inari-jinja Shrine, where a fox is the messenger, some have pictures of foxes.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, in Inari-jinja Shrine, where a fox is the messenger, some have pictures of foxes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>眼病予防に「め」および左右逆の「め」を書いた絵馬や、夫の浮気防止に「心」の字に鍵をかけた絵を描いた絵馬もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are ema with the character &apos;め&apos; (eye) and a mirror image of &apos;め&apos; for prevention of eye disease, and ema with the character &apos;心&apos; (heart) with a lock for prevention of extramarital affairs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are ema with the character &apos;め&apos; (eye) and a mirror image of &apos;め&apos; for the prevention of eye disease, and ema with the character &apos;心&apos; (heart) with a lock for the prevention of extramarital affairs.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are ema with the character &apos;め&apos; (eye) and a mirror image of &apos;め&apos; for the prevention of eye disease, and ema with the character &apos;心&apos; (heart) with a lock for the prevention of extramarital affairs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>和算家は、自分が解いた問題の解法を書いた算額という絵馬を奉納し、日本武術では剣術、柔術などで薙刀など木刀や棒術の棒を門人の一覧に付した絵馬を奉納した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Practitioners of Japanese mathematics dedicated ema called sangaku, with the solution of the problem they solved written, while in Japanese martial arts such as kenjutsu (fencing) and jujutsu (classical Japanese martial art, usually referring to fighting without a weapon), ema with wooden swords such as halberd or sticks for bojutsu (art of using a stick as a weapon) attached to a list of pupils were dedicated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Practitioners of Japanese mathematics dedicated ema called sangaku, with the solution of the problem they solved written, while in Japanese martial arts such as kenjutsu (fencing) and jujutsu (classical Japanese martial art, usually referring to fighting without a weapon), ema with wooden swords such as halberd or sticks for bojutsu (art of using a stick as a weapon) attached to a list of pupils were dedicated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Practitioners of Japanese mathematics dedicated ema called sangaku, with the solution of the problem they solved written, while in Japanese martial arts such as kenjutsu (fencing) and jujutsu (classical Japanese martial art, usually referring to fighting without a weapon), ema with wooden swords such as halberd or sticks for bojutsu (art of using a stick as a weapon) attached to a list of pupils were dedicated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>安土桃山時代になると著名な画家による絵馬が持て囃されそれらを展示する絵馬堂も建てられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Azuchi-Momoyama period, ema by distinguished artists were lionized and emado (shrine building where ema were hanged) were built to exhibit them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Azuchi-Momoyama period, ema by distinguished artists were lionized and emado (shrine building where ema were hanged) were built to exhibit them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Azuchi-Momoyama period, ema by distinguished artists were lionized and emado (shrine building where ema were hanged) were built to exhibit them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="14">
<j>江戸時代になると、家内安全や商売繁盛といった実利的な願いをかける風習が庶民にも広まり、今日のように個人が小さな絵馬を奉納する形は江戸時代から始まったものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Edo period, praying for practical benefits such as the well-being of the family or prosperity of business became widespread among common people, and it is in the Edo period that people began dedicating small ema as we do today.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Edo period, praying for practical benefits such as the well-being of the family or prosperity of business became widespread among common people, and it is in the Edo period that people began dedicating small ema as we do today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Edo period, praying for practical benefits such as the well-being of the family or prosperity of business became widespread among common people, and it is in the Edo period that people began dedicating small ema as we do today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>昭和時代からは、学問の神様である天神として菅原道真を祀った天満宮に受験生が合格祈願の絵馬を奉納することが盛んになっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the Showa period, students preparing for examinations often dedicate ema for passing the exam at the Tenmangu Shrine where SUGAWARA no Michizane is honored as Tenjin (heavenly gods), the god of learning.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the Showa period, students preparing for examinations often dedicate ema to pass exams at the Tenmangu Shrine where SUGAWARA no Michizane is honored as Tenjin (heavenly gods), the god of learning.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the Showa period, students preparing for examinations often dedicate ema to pass exams at the Tenmangu Shrine where SUGAWARA no Michizane is honored as Tenjin (heavenly gods), the god of learning.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="16">
<j>近年では、白蛇などの縁起物の動物や、祭りの風景など馬とは関係ない絵馬が多く作られ、神社、寺院毎の縁起物として珍重され、これは神社、寺院巡りをした際のお守りとしても持て囃される様になっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In recent years, many ema unrelated to horses, such as those of good-luck animals like albino Japanese rat snakes and festival scenery are made and valued highly as good-luck charm of shrines and temples, and are lionized as charms when visiting the shrines and temples.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In recent years, many ema unrelated to horses, such as those of good-luck animals like albino Japanese rat snakes and festival scenery are made and valued highly as good-luck charm of shrines and temples, and are lionized as charms when visiting the shrines and temples.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In recent years, many ema unrelated to horses, such as those of good-luck animals like albino Japanese rat snakes and festival scenery are made and valued highly as good-luck charm of shrines and temples, and are lionized as charms when visiting the shrines and temples.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>さらに、2005年放送のアニメ『かみちゅ!』や、2007年放送のアニメ『らき☆すた』を見たファンが、ロケ地となった神社（前者は広島県尾道市の御袖天満宮、後者は埼玉県鷲宮町の鷲宮神社）を訪れた際に、登場人物を絵馬に描いて奉納するという現象が起きている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, fans watching the animation &quot;Kamichu!&quot; aired in 2005 and the animation &quot;Lucky☆Star&quot; aired in 2007, are drawing the characters on ema and dedicating them when they visit the shrines where the animations took place (former at the Misode-tenmangu Shrine in Onomichi City, Hiroshima Prefecture, and the latter at the Washinomiya-jinja Shrine in Washimiya-cho, Saitama Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, fans watching the animation &quot;Kamichu!&quot; aired in 2005 and the animation &quot;Lucky☆Star&quot; aired in 2007, are drawing the characters on ema and dedicating them when they visit shrines where animations took place (formerly at the Misode-tenmangu Shrine in Onomichi City, Hiroshima Prefecture, and the latter at the Washinomiya-jinja Shrine in Washimiya-cho, Saitama Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, fans watching the animation &quot;Kamichu!&quot; aired in 2005 and the animation &quot;Lucky☆Star&quot; aired in 2007, are drawing the characters on ema and dedicating them when they visit shrines where animations took place (the former at the Misode-tenmangu Shrine in Onomichi City, Hiroshima Prefecture, and the latter at the Washinomiya-jinja Shrine in Washimiya-cho, Saitama Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>&quot;formely&quot;は「前者」の意味から外れるように思われますので、「後者」の&quot;the latter&quot;に合わせ、&quot;the former&quot;としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="18">
<j>また2006年頃から、個人情報保護法の観点から、絵馬に書かれた願い事や住所・氏名の部分にステッカーが貼れるようになっている絵馬も用意される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since around 2006, from a Private Information Protection Law perspective, some ema come with stickers to place on the wish, address, and name written on the ema.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since around 2006, from a Private Information Protection Law perspective, some ema come with stickers to place over the wish, address, and names written on the ema.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since around 2006, from a Private Information Protection Law perspective, some ema come with stickers to place over the wish, address, and names written on the ema.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Izayohi(id:13095), ととりん(id:31982), 田無稲子(id:63575), Ceridwen(id:36889), Immanuel Giel(id:20517), Nnh(id:474), Sina(id:10021), STBot(id:137943), Robbot(id:3063), Birdie(id:36320), Greenland4(id:114494), Toto-tarou(id:16648), VolkovBot(id:105371), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), Nnn(id:26535), YurikBot(id:18605), Miya(id:1881), けんち(id:5147), Louperibot(id:128971), KASAGI(id:24405), Chac(id:21208), Tmatsu(id:10583), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>