<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>カミムスビ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kamimusubi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kamimusubi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kamimusubi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>カミムスビ（カミムスヒ、カムムスビ）は、日本神話の神 (神道)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kamimusubi (or Kamimusuhi, Kamumusubi) is one of kami (god) in Japanese Methodology (shinto).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kamimusubi (or Kamimusuhi, Kamumusubi) is a kami (god) in Japanese Methodology (shinto).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kamimusubi (or Kamimusuhi, Kamumusubi) is a god (Shinto) in Japanese mythology.</e>
<cmt>mythology としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>『古事記』では神産巣日神、『日本書紀』では神皇産霊尊、『出雲国風土記』では神魂命と書かれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kamimusubi is referred to as Kamimusubi no kami (神産巣日神) in the &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters), Kamimusuhi-no-mikoto (神皇産霊尊) in the &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), and Kamimusubi (神魂命) in the &quot;Izumo no kuni fudoki&quot; (the topography of Izumo Province).</e>
<cmt>読み方がそれぞれ似ているのに異なる漢字を当てていたことを示すのがこの文章の趣旨であると解釈し、漢字も併記しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kamimusubi is referred to as Kamimusubi no kami (神産巣日神) in the &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters), Kamimusuhi-no-mikoto (神皇産霊尊) in the &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), and Kamimusubi (神魂命) in the &quot;Izumo no kuni fudoki&quot; (the topography of Izumo Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kamimusubi is referred to as Kamimusubi no kami (神産巣日神) in the &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters), Kamimusuhi no Mikoto (神皇産霊尊) in the &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), and Kamimusubi (神魂命) in the &quot;Izumo no kuni fudoki&quot; (the topography of Izumo Province).</e>
<cmt>神名表現を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>天地開闢 (日本神話)の時、天之御中主神・タカミムスビの次に高天原に出現した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the time of creation of heaven and earth (in Japanese Methodology), Kamimusubi appreared at the Takamanohara (plain of high heaven) following Takamimusubi, who was Ame no Minakanushi no Kami (one of the gods in Japanese mythology).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the time of creation of heaven and earth (in Japanese Methodology), Kamimusubi appreared at the Takamanohara (plain of high heaven) following Takamimusubi, who was Ame no Minakanushi no Kami (one of the gods in Japanese mythology).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the time of creation of heaven and earth (Japanese mythology), Kamimusubi appeared at the Takamanohara (the Plain of High Heaven) following Ame no Minakanushi no Kami and Takamimusubi.</e>
<cmt>mythology としました。天之御中主神とタカミムスビの後に出現した、　という表現にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>別天津神の一とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kamimusubi is supposed to be one of Kotoamatsukami (literally, separate heavenly kami).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kamimusubi is supposed to be one of Kotoamatsukami (literally, separate heavenly kami).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kamimusubi is supposed to be one of Kotoamatsukami (literally, separate heavenly kami).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>本来は性のない独神であるが、造化三神の中でこの神だけが女神であるともされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally Kamimusubi is a hitorigami (kami which came into being alone), being neither man or woman; however, Kamimusubi is sometimes said to be the only goddess among the Zokasanshin (three gods of creation).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally Kamimusubi is a hitorigami (kami which came into being alone), being neither man or woman; however, Kamimusubi is sometimes said to be the only goddess among the Zokasanshin (three gods of creation).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally Kamimusubi is a hitorigami (god without gender), being neither man or woman; however, Kamimusubi is sometimes said to be the only goddess among the Zoka-sanshin (three gods of creation).</e>
<cmt>独神→hitorigami (god without gender) としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>また、先代旧事本紀においては、高皇産霊神の子であるとも言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also in Sendai Kujihongi (Ancient Japanese History), Kamimusubi is said to be the child of Takamimusubi-no-kami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also in Sendai Kujihongi (Ancient Japanese History), Kamimusubi is said to be the child of Takamimusubi-no-kami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also in Sendai Kujihongi (Ancient Japanese History), Kamimusubi is said to be the child of Takamimusubi no Kami.</e>
<cmt>神名表現を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>大国主が兄神らによって殺されたとき、大国主の母が神産巣日神に願い出た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Okuninushi (chief god of Izumo in southern Honshu Island, Japan, and the central character in the important cycle of myths set in that region) was killed by other senior kami, the mother of Okuninushi pleaded Kamimusubi no kami to revive Okuninushi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処訳文では「（大国主の命を蘇らせるように）願い出た」のようにカッコ内を補足しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Okuninushi (chief god of Izumo in southern Honshu Island, Japan, and the central character in the important cycle of myths set in that region) was killed by other senior kami, the mother of Okuninushi pleaded Kamimusubi no kami to revive Okuninushi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Okuninushi (chief god of Izumo in southern Honshu Island, Japan, and the central character in the important cycle of myths set in that region) was killed by other senior kami, the mother of Okuninushi pleaded Kamimusubi no Kami to revive Okuninushi.</e>
<cmt>神名表現を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>神皇産霊尊に遣わされたキサガイヒメ・ウムギヒメの治療によって大己貴命は蘇生する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thanks to the treatment by Kisagai-hime and Umugihime who were sent by Kamimusuhi-no-mikoto (a.k.a. Kamimusubi no kami), Onamuchi no mikoto (a.k.a. Okuninushi) was brought back to his life.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処大己貴命は大国主の別称と考えられます。原文通りの訳では、大国主と大己貴命が別人のように解釈される可能性がありますので、（　）で言葉を補いました。http://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E5%A4%A7%E5%9B%BD%E4%B8%BB</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thanks to the treatment by Kisagai-hime and Umugihime who were sent by Kamimusuhi-no-mikoto (a.k.a. Kamimusubi no kami), Onamuchi no mikoto (a.k.a. Okuninushi) was brought back to his life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thanks to the treatment by Kisagai-hime and Umugi-hime who were sent by Kamimusuhi no Mikoto (a.k.a. Kamimusubi no Kami), Onamuchi no Mikoto (a.k.a. Okuninushi) was brought back to his life.</e>
<cmt>神名表現を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>『古事記』では、スクナビコナは神産巣日神の子である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the &quot;Kojiki,&quot; Sukunabikona is the child of Kamimusubi no kami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the &quot;Kojiki,&quot; Sukunabikona is the child of Kamimusubi no kami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the &quot;Kojiki,&quot; Sukunabikona is the child of Kamimusubi no Kami.</e>
<cmt>神名表現を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="10">
<j>「むすひ」は生産・生成を意味する言葉である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Musuhi&apos; means production and generation.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Musuhi&apos; means production and generation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The word &apos;Musuhi&apos; means production and generation.</e>
<cmt>翻訳を文頭に追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>高皇産霊神とともに「創造」を神格化した神である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kamimusubi is a kami of &apos;creation&apos; along with Takamimusubi-no-kami.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kamimusubi is a kami of &apos;creation&apos; along with Takamimusubi-no-kami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kamimusubi is a kami of &apos;creation&apos; along with Takamimusubi no Kami.</e>
<cmt>神名表現を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>高皇産霊神と対になって男女の「むすび」を象徴する神でもあると考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also Kamimusubi is thought to be a symbol of &apos;ties&apos; between men and women in pairs with Takamimusubi-no-kami.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also Kamimusubi is thought to be a symbol of &apos;ties&apos; between men and women in pairs with Takamimusubi-no-kami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also Kamimusubi is thought to be a symbol of &apos;ties&apos; between men and women in pairs with Takamimusubi no Kami.</e>
<cmt>神名表現を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 三竹修二郎(id:88082), Charon(id:9162), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), Nnh(id:474), 暗黒な方(id:44101), BOT-Superzerocool(id:65015), Hatsune(id:26654), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>