<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>霜月神楽</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shimotsuki kagura (November kagura)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shimotsuki kagura (November kagura)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shimotsuki kagura</e>
<cmt>説明削除</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>霜月神楽（しもつきかぐら）とは、11月_(旧暦)（グレゴリオ暦の12月から翌年1月）に行われる神楽のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shimotsuki kagura is kagura (sacred music and dance performed at shrines) performed in November (on the old lunar calendar) (December through the following year&apos;s January on the Gregorian calendar).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shimotsuki kagura is kagura (sacred music and dance performed at shrines) that is performed in November (according to the old lunar calendar; December through to January of the following year according to the Gregorian calendar).</e>
<cmt>The explanations of Japanese provided by the translator are very helpful.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shimotsuki kagura is kagura (sacred music and dance performed at shrines) that is performed in November (according to the old lunar calendar; December through to January of the following year according to the Gregorian calendar).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>湯立と組み合わせて行われていたことから湯立神楽（ゆだてかぐら）とも呼ばれ、また伊勢神宮外宮の神楽を祖型としていることから、伊勢流神楽（いせりゅうかぐら）とも呼ばれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Having been performed in combination with yudate (a rite in which a large pot of hot water before the gods is splashed by bamboo leaves), it is also called Yudate kagura, and again, based on kagura performed at Ise-jingu Shrine geku (outer shrine), it is also called Ise-ryu kagura (Ise style kagura).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As it was performed in combination with yudate (a ceremony in which Shinto priests sprinkle hot water over worshippers using bamboo leaves that they have dipped in a large pot of hot water before the gods), it is sometimes called Yudate kagura, and because it is performed at the geku (outer shrine) of Ise-jingu Shrine, it is also sometimes called Ise-ryu kagura (Ise-style kagura).</e>
<cmt>Again, the explanations are very helpful but I have had to tweak the explanation of yudate.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As it was performed in combination with yudate (a ceremony in which Shinto priests sprinkle hot water over worshippers using bamboo leaves that they have dipped in a large pot of hot water before the gods), it is sometimes called Yudate kagura, and because it is performed at the geku (outer shrine) of Ise-jingu Shrine, it is also sometimes called Ise-ryu kagura (Ise-style kagura).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>神楽は本来は旧暦の11月に行われる行事と考えられていたとみられ、古代・中世の宮中に鎮座していた園韓神社の神楽は11月に行われ、また毎年11月13日_(旧暦)に伊勢神宮外宮の御師が一口頭大夫邸にて神楽（寄合神楽・奉納神楽）も11月に行われていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kagura is believed to have been originally considered as occasion performed in November, so kagura held at Sonokarakamino-yashiro Shrine enshrined in the ancient and medieval Court was performed in November, and kagura (Yoriai (meeting) kagura and Hono (dedication) kagura) by Ise-jingu Shrine geku onshi (low-ranking Shinto priest) at the residence of 一口頭大夫 on every November 13 (on the old lunar calendar) was also performed in November.</e>
<cmt>原文後半の「御師が一口頭大夫邸にて神楽も11月に行われていた」は、「御師が一口頭大夫邸にて行った神楽も11月に行われていた」の意で訳しました。「一口頭大夫」読み方不明。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kagura is believed to have originally been considered an event to be held in November, with kagura held at Sonokarakamino-yashiro Shrine, which was enshrined in the imperial court in ancient and medieval Japan, performed in November, and kagura (which included a Yoriai [meeting] kagura and Hono [dedication] kagura) conducted by geku onshi (low-ranking Shinto priests) of Ise-jingu Shrine every November 13 (according to the old lunar calendar) at the residence of the priest that led the kagura also performed in November.</e>
<cmt>According to information on the Internet (ref:http://www.akita-life.jp/03densyo/a10_01.html), 一口頭大夫 is the person that leads the kagura.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kagura is believed to have originally been considered an event to be held in November of old lunar calendar, with kagura held at Sonokarakamino-yashiro Shrine, which was enshrined in the imperial court in ancient and medieval Japan, performed in November, and kagura (which included a Yoriai [meeting] kagura and Hono [dedication] kagura) conducted by geku onshi (low-ranking Shinto priests) of Ise-jingu Shrine every November 13 (according to the old lunar calendar) at the residence of the priest that led the kagura also performed in November.</e>
<cmt>of old lunar calendar補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>伊勢御師の神楽は明治期に衰退したが、それ以前の段階において熊野信仰や修験道・陰陽道・修正会などの要素と組み合わさった形で日本各地に広まったと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though kagura by Ise onshi went into decline in Meiji period, it is thought to have spread to various places in Japan before that phase, having combined with elements of Kumano belief, Shugendo (mountaineering asceticism), Onmyodo (yin-yang philosophy) and Shushoe (new year&apos;s service).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though kagura performed by Ise priests went into decline in the Meiji period, it is thought to have spread to various places in Japan before then, having combined with elements of the Kumano Shinko cult, Shugendo (mountain asceticism), Onmyodo (yin-yang cosmology) and Shushoe (New Year&apos;s festival).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity - revised definitions of Japanese terms</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though kagura performed by Ise priests went into decline in the Meiji period, it is thought to have spread to various places in Japan before then, having combined with elements of the Kumano Shinko cult, Shugendo (mountain asceticism), Onmyodo (yin-yang cosmology) and Shushoe (New Year&apos;s festival).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>旧暦の11月は神や自然が衰弱する時期であり、魂振の儀式などを行って魂の再生・更新を行って新年に備えるために神楽が行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">November on the old lunar calendar was a period when gods and Nature become week, so kagura was performed to prepare for the new year, recovering and restoring souls in rites such as Tamafuri (shaking of souls).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The eleventh month of the old lunar calendar was a period when gods and Nature became weak, so kagura was performed to prepare for the new year, refreshing and restoring souls in rites such as Tamafuri (shaking of souls).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The eleventh month of the old lunar calendar was a period when gods and Nature became weak, so kagura was performed to prepare for the new year, refreshing and restoring souls in rites such as Tamafuri (shaking of souls).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>その際に熊野の再生儀式であった湯の清まりと忌籠の呪法が取り入れられてそれが湯立として残ったとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said to have been handed down as yudate on that occasion, having introduced Yu no kiyomari (purification by hot water) and Igomori no juho (incantation of confining), both of which were rites of spiritual rebirth in Kumano belief.</e>
<cmt>「湯の清まり」「忌籠の呪法」定訳不明。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yudate, a mixture of the Kumano cult rebirth rites Yu no kiyomari (purification by hot water) and Igomori no juho (incantation of confining), is said to have been handed down from that time.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yudate, a mixture of the Kumano cult rebirth rites Yu no kiyomari (purification by hot water) and Igomori no juho (incantation of confining), is said to have been handed down from that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>祭場となる舞台の庭には神座として御幣などによる神籬が飾られ、舞台の中央には湯釜が設置され、その天井には白蓋、大乗、雲などの天蓋が下げられ、周囲には注連縄や切紙飾が巡らされて神々を迎える準備がなされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In preparation for receiving gods, himorogi (a piece of sacred land) with gohei (ritual wand with pleated paper) as the place of gods is arranged on the garden stage of the ceremony site, a large pot is placed in the middle of the stage, a canopy such as white canopy, great vehicle and cloud is hung from the ceiling, and the area is surrounded with sacred straw ropes and pieces of decorative paper.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In preparation for welcoming the gods, in the garden where the kagura will be held, a himorogi (sacred space) where the deities will stay is decorated with gohei (ritual wands with paper streamers attached), a large pot is placed in the middle of the stage, a white canopy decorated with &apos;great vehicles&apos; and clouds is hung from the ceiling, and the area is surrounded with sacred shimenawa ropes and pieces of decorative paper.</e>
<cmt>*Unsure of some of the terms in this sentence, especially &quot;大乗&quot; - I asume it doesn&apos;t refer to the branch of Buddhism, so not sure how best to rework it</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In preparation for welcoming the gods, in the garden where the kagura will be held, a himorogi (sacred space) where the deities will stay is decorated with gohei (ritual wands with paper streamers attached), a large pot is placed in the middle of the stage, a white canopy decorated with &apos;great vehicles&apos; and clouds is hung from the ceiling, and the area is surrounded with sacred shimenawa ropes and pieces of decorative paper.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>湯釜を中心として夜を徹して各種の祈祷・祝詞・神人らによる神楽などの舞が行われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around the pot, various prayers, norito (ritual prayers), and dances such as kagura by jinin (shrine associates) are performed through the night.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around the pot, various prayers, norito (ritual prayers), and dances such as kagura by jinin (shrine associates) are performed through the night.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around the pot, various prayers, norito (ritual prayers), and dances such as kagura by jinin (shrine associates) are performed through the night.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>霜月神楽の方法はそれぞれの地域・神社によって差異はあるものの基本的には儀式に先立って特定の川や滝から汲んだ水を釜で沸かした湯を神前に供えて、祈祷の湯立を行った後に参加者に振り掛けることで祓禊となし、招待神の名前が書かれた神名帳を読上げるところから始まり、前夜の素面による採物舞の神招き、神讃めの願上、夜半の招待神の神送り、直会（なおらい）、後夜の鬼や翁などの面形舞の神遊び、祝福の式の順序で行われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though the manner of Shimotsuki kagura varies from one region or shrine to another, it is basically conducted in the following order; prior to the ceremony to bring a large pot of water drawn from a specific river or fall to the boil and offer it before the gods, to perform misogiharae (Shinto purification) by splashing the hot water on participants after the prayer of yudate, to read out Jinmyocho (the list of deities) with the names of invited gods written on it as the beginning, to invite gods by Torimonomai (dance of symbolic offerings) with sumen (no mask) the night before, to praise gods making a wish, to see invited gods off at midnight, to hold naorai (feast), to perform Kamiasobi (kagura) of Mengatamai (dance with mask) of Oni (demon) or Okina (old man) after midnight, and to hold a ceremony of blessings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though the style of Shimotsuki kagura varies from one region or shrine to another, it is basically conducted in the following order: prior to the ceremony, water drawn from a specific river or waterfall is boiled in a large pot and offered before the gods; after the yudate prayer, participants are splashed with hot water purify them; the kagura then begins with the reading of a list of invited deities; before midnight, the unmasked Torimonomai (dance of symbolic offerings) is performed; prayers are offered in praise of the deities; the invited gods are seen off at midnight; a naorai (feast) is held; after midnight is the Kamiasobi (kagura), with the dancers wearing Oni (demon) or Okina (old man) masks; a blessing ceremony is held.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though the style of Shimotsuki kagura varies from one region or shrine to another, it is basically conducted in the following order: prior to the ceremony, water drawn from a specific river or waterfall is boiled in a large pot and offered before the gods; after the yudate prayer, participants are splashed with hot water purify them; the kagura then begins with the reading of a list of invited deities; before midnight, the unmasked Torimonomai (dance of symbolic offerings) is performed; prayers are offered in praise of the deities; the invited gods are seen off at midnight; a naorai (feast) is held; after midnight is the Kamiasobi (kagura), with the dancers wearing Oni (demon) or Okina (old man) masks; a blessing ceremony is held.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>特に神位は低いものの地元とのつながりが密接な神に対しては厚礼をもって接した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gods being low in rank of deity but having close relation to the local were especially received cordially.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In particular, deities low in rank but having a close connection to the local area were warmly received.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In particular, deities low in rank but having a close connection to the local area were warmly received.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>代表的な霜月神楽</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Representative Shimotsuki kagura</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Typical Shimotsuki kagura</e>
<cmt>&quot;Representative&quot;→&quot;Typical&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Typical Shimotsuki kagura</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>以下は代表的な霜月神楽を掲げる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following are representative Shimotsuki kagura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following are typical Shimotsuki kagura.</e>
<cmt>&quot;representative&quot;→&quot;typical&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following are typical Shimotsuki kagura.</e>
<cmt>全角削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>この他にも伝統的な霜月神楽の全てあるいは一部を継承した神楽は全国各地に存在している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kagura to which a whole of or a part of traditional Shimotsuki kagura have been handed down exist across the nation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other kagura continue to practice either the whole or part of traditional Shimotsuki kagura but are not mentioned here.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other kagura continue to practice either the whole or part of traditional Shimotsuki kagura but are not mentioned here.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>秋田県横手市大森町八沢木に伝わる重要無形民俗文化財の民俗芸能。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The traditional folk entertainment designated as important intangible folk cultural property handed down in Yasawagi, Omori-machi, Yokote City, Akita Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The traditional folk entertainment designated an important intangible folk cultural property handed down in Yasawagi, Omori-machi, Yokote City, Akita Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>&quot;as&quot;→&quot;an&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The traditional folk entertainment designated an important intangible folk cultural property handed down in Yasawagi, Omori-machi, Yokote City, Akita Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>保呂羽山の霜月神楽を参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">See Horowasan no Shimotsuki kagura (Shimotsuki kagura in Mt. Horowa).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">See Horowasan no Shimotsuki kagura (Mt. Horowa Shimotsuki kagura).</e>
<cmt>Word orderDeleted preposition</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">See Horowasan no Shimotsuki kagura (Mt. Horowa Shimotsuki kagura).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="15">
<j>長野県下伊那郡天龍村に伝わる重要無形民俗文化財の民俗芸能。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The traditional folk entertainment designated as important intangible folk cultural property handed down in Tenryu-mura, Shimoina-gun, Nagano Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The traditional folk entertainment designated an important intangible folk cultural property handed down in Tenryu-mura, Shimoina-gun, Nagano Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>&quot;as&quot;→&quot;an&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The traditional folk entertainment designated an important intangible folk cultural property handed down in Tenryu-mura, Shimoina-gun, Nagano Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>天龍村の霜月神楽を参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">See Tenryumura no Shimotsuki kagura (Shimotsuki kagura in Tenryu-mura Village).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">See Tenryumura no Shimotsuki kagura (Tenryu-mura Village Shimotsuki kagura).</e>
<cmt>Word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">See Tenryumura no Shimotsuki kagura (Tenryu-mura Village Shimotsuki kagura).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="17">
<j>長野県飯田市の旧・南信濃村・上村 (長野県)に伝わる重要無形民俗文化財の民俗芸能。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The traditional folk entertainment designated as important intangible folk cultural property handed down in former Minamishinano-mura and Kami-mura, Iida City, Nagano Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The traditional folk entertainment designated an important intangible folk cultural property handed down in former Minamishinano-mura and Kami-mura, Iida City, Nagano Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>&quot;as&quot;→&quot;an&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The traditional folk entertainment designated an important intangible folk cultural property handed down in former Minamishinano-mura and Kami-mura, Iida City, Nagano Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>遠山郷霜月まつりを参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">See Toyamago Shimotsuki matsuri (November festival in Toyama-go Village).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">See Toyamago Shimotsuki matsuri (November festival in Toyama-go Village).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">See Toyamago Shimotsuki matsuri (November festival in Toyama-go Village).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="19">
<j>愛知県の奥三河地方に伝わる重要無形民俗文化財の民俗芸能。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The traditional folk entertainment designated as important intangible folk cultural property handed down in Okumikawa region, Aichi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The traditional folk entertainment designated an important intangible folk cultural property handed down in the Okumikawa region of Aichi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>&quot;as&quot;→&quot;an&quot;ArticlePreposition</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The traditional folk entertainment designated an important intangible folk cultural property handed down in the Okumikawa region of Aichi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>花祭りを参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">See Hanamatsuri (flower festival).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">See Hanamatsuri (flower festival).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">See Hanamatsuri (flower festival).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Muyo(id:14948), P.Tonnies(id:163233), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>