<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>菊理媛神</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kukurihimenokami</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kukurihimenokami</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kukurihimenokami</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>菊理媛神（くくりひめのかみ）は、日本の神。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kukurihimenokami is a Japanese deity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kukurihimenokami is a Japanese deity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kukurihimenokami is a Japanese deity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>加賀の白山や全国の白山神社に祀られる白山比咩神（しらやまひめのかみ）と同一神とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She is identified with Shirayamhimenokami, who is enshrined at Hakusan in Kaga and other Hakusan-jinja Shrines throughout the nation.</e>
<cmt>「白山」は白山比咩神　ならびに白山比咩神社を除き、&quot;Hakusan&quot;としております。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She is identified with Shirayamahimenokami, who is enshrined at Hakusan in Kaga and other Hakusan-jinja shrines throughout the nation.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。スペルミスを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She is identified with Shirayamahimenokami, who is enshrined at Hakusan in Kaga and other Hakusan-jinja shrines throughout the nation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>日本神話においては、古事記や日本書紀本文には登場せず、日本書紀の一書に一度だけ出てくるのみである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japanese Mythology, she appears neither in Kojiki (The record of Ancient Matters) nor in the text of Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan) and appears only once in the Issho (a book cited in Nihonshoki) of Nihonshoki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japanese Mythology, she appears neither in Kojiki (The record of Ancient Matters) nor in the text of Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan) and appears only once in the Issho (a book cited in Nihonshoki) of Nihonshoki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japanese Mythology, she appears neither in Kojiki (The record of Ancient Matters) nor in the text of Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan) and appears only once in the Issho (a book cited in Nihonshoki) of Nihonshoki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>神産みでイザナミに逢いに黄泉を訪問したイザナギは、イザナミの変わり果てた姿を見て逃げ出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to this document, Izanagi visited yomi (world after death) to see Izanami during the process of the birth of deities, but he run away after seeing Izanami who was dead and cold.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to this document, Izanagi visited yomi (the world after death) to see Izanami during the process of the birth of deities, but he run away after seeing Izanami who was dead and cold.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to this document, Izanagi visited yomi (the world after death) to see Izanami during the process of the birth of deities, but he run away after seeing Izanami who was dead and cold.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>しかし泉津平坂（黄泉比良坂）で追いつかれ、そこでイザナミと口論になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he was caught up at Yomotsuhirasaka (Yomotsuhirasaka) and squabbled with Izanami there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Izanami caught up with him at Yomotsuhirasaka and they squabbled there.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。括弧にあった部分ですが、日本語だと漢字は異なりますが、英語で意味がないので削除しました（綴りは同じなので）。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Izanami caught up with him at Yomotsuhirasaka and they squabbled there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>そこに泉守道者が現れ、イザナミの言葉を取継いで「一緒に帰ることはできない」と言った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, Yomotsuchimoribito appeared there and conveyed Izanami&apos;s message saying &quot;I cannot follow you&quot;.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, Yomotsuchimoribito appeared there and conveyed Izanami&apos;s message saying &quot;I cannot follow you&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, Yomotsuchimoribito appeared there and conveyed Izanami&apos;s message saying &apos;I cannot follow you.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;にピリオドの位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>菊理媛神が何かを言うと、イザナギはそれを褒め、帰って行った、とある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Kukurihimenokami said something, Izanagi praised it and left.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Kukurihimenokami said something, Izanagi praised it and left.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Kukurihimenokami said something, Izanagi offered praise and went home.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>菊理媛神が何を言ったかは書かれておらず、また、出自なども書かれていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nothing is written about what Kukurihimenokami said and there is no description of her place of birth etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nothing is written about what Kukurihimenokami said and there is no description of her place of birth, etc.</e>
<cmt>カンマを追加しまました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nothing is written about what Kukurihimenokami said and there is no description of her place of birth, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>この説話から、菊理媛神はイザナギとイザナミを仲直しさせたとして、縁結びの神とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Based on this anecdote, Kukurihimenokami is regarded as a deity of match-making since she reconciled Izanagi and Izanami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based on this anecdote, Kukurihimenokami is regarded as a deity of match-making since she reconciled Izanagi and Izanami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based on this anecdote, Kukurihimenokami is regarded as a deity of match-making since she reconciled Izanagi and Izanami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>また、死者（イザナミ）と生者（イザナギ）の間を取り持ったことからシャーマン（巫女）の女神ではないかとも言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, she is also said to be a goddess of shaman (miko (a shrine maiden)) because she reconciled the deceased (Izanami) and the living (Izanami).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further, she is also said to be a goddess of shaman (a miko (shrine maiden)) because she reconciled the deceased (Izanami) and the living (Izanagi).</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。スペルミスを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further, she is also said to be a goddess of shaman (a miko (shrine maiden)) because she reconciled the deceased (Izanami) and the living (Izanagi).</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>ケガレを払う神格ともされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She is also regarded as a deity who takes away impurities.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She is also regarded as a deity who takes away impurities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She is also regarded as a deity who takes away impurities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="12">
<j>神名の「ククリ」は「括り」の意で、イザナギとイザナミの仲を取り持ったことからの神名と考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her deity name &quot;Kukuri&quot; means &quot;bind&quot; and this deity name is contemplated to have derived from the anecdote that she reconciled Izanagi and Izanami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her deity name &quot;Kukuri&quot; means &quot;bind&quot; and this deity name is believed to have been derived from the anecdote in which she reconciled Izanagi and Izanami.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her deity name &apos;Kukuri&apos; means &apos;bind&apos; and this deity name is believed to have been derived from the anecdote in which she reconciled Izanagi and Izanami.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>他に、糸を紡ぐ（括る）ことに関係があるとする説、「潜り」の意で水神であるとする説、「聞き入れる」が転じたものとする説などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other than the above, there are several views on her name such as the one that assers it relates to spinning thread (&quot;kukuru&quot; also means &quot;bind strings&quot;), the one that asserts it means &quot;kuguri (pass under water)&quot; and she is a deity of water and the one that asserts it is a transferred meaning of &quot;kikiireru (accept a person&apos;s request)&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other than the above, there are several views on the origins of her name, such as the one that asserts it relates to spinning thread (&quot;kukuru&quot; also means &quot;bind strings&quot;), the one that asserts it relates to &quot;kuguri (pass under water)&quot; and she is a deity of water, and the one that asserts it is derived from &quot;kikiireru (accept a person&apos;s request)&quot;.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other than the above, there are several views on the origins of her name, such as the one that asserts it relates to spinning thread (&apos;kukuru&apos; also means &apos;bind strings&apos;), the one that asserts it relates to &apos;kuguri (pass under water)&apos; and she is a deity of water, and the one that asserts it is derived from &apos;kikiireru (accept a person&apos;s request).&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;にピリオドの位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>白山比咩神と同一視されるようになった経緯は不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The details concerning the reason why she came to be identified with Shirayamahimenokami is not clear.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The details concerning the reason why she came to be identified with Shirayamahimenokami are not clear.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The details concerning the reason why she came to be identified with Shirayamahimenokami are not clear.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>白山神社の総本社である白山比め神社（石川県白山市）の祭神について、中世までの書物ではイザナギ・イザナミとしか書かれていなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Concerning the enshrined deity of Shirayamahime-jinja Shrine (Hakusan City, Ishikawa Prefecture), the head shrine of Hakusa-jinja Shrines, only Izanagi and Izanami were referred to in the books written up to the medieval Period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Concerning the enshrined deity of Shirayamahime-jinja Shrine (Hakusan City, Ishikawa Prefecture), the head shrine of the Hakusa-jinja shrines, only Izanagi and Izanami were referred to in books written up to the medieval Period.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Concerning the enshrined deity of Shirayamahime-jinja Shrine (Hakusan City, Ishikawa Prefecture), the head shrine of the Hakusa-jinja shrines, only Izanagi and Izanami were referred to in books written up to the medieval Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>しかしながら、室町時代吉田兼倶によって書かれた『大日本一宮記』内には菊理媛が白山比咩神社の上社祭神として書かれており、江戸時代の書物において白山比咩神と菊理媛が同一神と明記されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Dainihon Ichinomiya Ki (List of prominent shrines in Japan)&quot; written by Kanetomo YOSHIDA during the Muromachi Period, however, Kukurihimenokami was referred to as the enshrined deity of the Kamisha of Shirayamahime-jinja Shrine and in the books written in the Edo Period, it is clearly put down that Shirayamahimenokami and Kukurihimenokami are the same deities.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in &quot;Dainihon Ichinomiya Ki (List of prominent shrines in Japan)&quot; written by Kanetomo YOSHIDA during the Muromachi Period, Kukurihimenokami was referred to as the enshrined deity of the Kamisha of Shirayamahime-jinja Shrine and in the books written in the Edo Period, it is clearly stated that Shirayamahimenokami and Kukurihimenokami are the same deity.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in &quot;Dainihon Ichinomiya Ki (List of prominent shrines in Japan)&quot; written by Kanetomo YOSHIDA during the Muromachi period, Kukurihimenokami was referred to as the enshrined deity of the Kamisha of Shirayamahime-jinja Shrine and in the books written in the Edo period, it is clearly stated that Shirayamahimenokami and Kukurihimenokami are the same deity.</e>
<cmt>Period→period</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="17">
<j>なお、神仏習合のなかでは白山比咩神は白山大権現、白山妙理権現、または白山妙理菩薩とされ、本地仏は十一面観音とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the era of syncretism, Shirayamahimenokami was called either Hakusan-Daigongen, Hakusan-Myori- Gongen or Hakusan-Myori-Bosatsu and honji-butsu (Original Buddhist divinity) was Eleven-faced Kannon (Goddess of Mercy).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the era of syncretism, Shirayamahimenokami was called either Hakusan-Daigongen, Hakusan-Myori-Gongen, or Hakusan-Myori-Bosatsu, and the honji-butsu (the original buddhist divinity) was Eleven-faced Kannon (the Goddess of Mercy).</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the era of synthesis of Shinto and Buddhism, Shirayamahimenokami was called either Hakusan-Daigongen, Hakusan-Myori-Gongen, or Hakusan-Myori-Bosatsu, and the honji-butsu (the original Buddhist divinity) was called the 11-faced Kannon (the Goddess of Mercy).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。スペースを削除し、表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="18">
<j>現在の白山比咩神社は、菊理媛神（白山比咩神）を主祭神とし、イザナギ・イザナミも共に祀られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Current Shirayamahime-jinja Shrine enshrines, together with Izanagi and Izanami, Kukurihimenokami (Shirayamahimenokami) as its principal deity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Currently Shirayamahime-jinja Shrine enshrines, together with Izanagi and Izanami, Kukurihimenokami (Shirayamahimenokami) as its principal deities.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Currently Shirayamahime-jinja Shrine enshrines, together with Izanagi and Izanami, Kukurihimenokami (Shirayamahimenokami) as its principal deities.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>フィクション上の菊理媛</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kukurihime depicted in fiction</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kukurihime depicted in fiction</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kukurihime depicted in fiction</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="19">
<j>菊理媛には不明な点が多いため、フィクション上では神秘的な存在として描かれることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In fiction, Kukurihime is often depicted as a mysterious being because much is unknown about her.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In fiction, Kukurihime is often depicted as a mysterious being because little is known about her.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fiction, Kukurihime is often depicted as a mysterious being because little is known about her.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="20">
<j>また名前を一部に使用して菊理媛神のイメージが投影された人物を登場させる作品もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, there are some works in which a character reflects the image of Kukurihimenokami by using a portion of her name.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further, there are some works in which a character reflects the image of Kukurihimenokami by using a portion of her name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further, there are some works in which a character reflects the image of Kukurihimenokami by using a portion of her name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Rusk(id:9895), Memosa(id:131221), Nnh(id:474), Tribot(id:186681), Khhy(id:13490), Mare*i(id:220586), Iokseng(id:92490), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>