<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>御子神</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mikogami</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mikogami</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mikogami</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>神社において、親子関係にある神 (神道)が祀られる場合、子に当たる神のことを御子神（みこがみ）または苗裔神（びょうえいしん）という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a shrine where parent-child gods (Shito religion) are enshrined, the child god is called Mikogami or byoe-shin (descendant deity).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In a shrine where parent-child gods (Shito religion) are enshrined, the child god is called Mikogami or byoe-shin (descendant deity).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In a shrine where parent-child gods (Shito religion) are enshrined, the child god is called Mikogami or byoei-shin (descendant deity).</e>
<cmt>byoe-shin→byoei-shinに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>「御子神」という言い方をする場合は、親子ともに主神である場合や、親神が主神でその子も共に祀る場合である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The word of &quot;Mikogami&quot; is used when both parent and child gods are chief gods and when the parent as the chief god and its child are enshrined together.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The word &quot;Mikogami&quot; is used when both parent and child gods are chief gods and when the parent as the chief god and its child are enshrined together.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The word &apos;Mikogami&apos; is used when both parent and child gods are chief gods and when the parent as the chief god and its child are enshrined together.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>特に、母子関係にある場合は、母子神信仰との関連もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In particular when mother-child gods are enshrined, there is something to do with the Bashi-gami shinko, belief of mother-child gods.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In particular when mother-child gods are enshrined, it has something to do with the Bashi-gami shinko, belief in mother-child gods.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In particular when mother-child gods are enshrined, it has something to do with the Boshi-jin shinko, belief in mother-child gods.</e>
<cmt>Bashi-gami→Boshi-jinに修正しました。(参照:http://eos.kokugakuin.ac.jp/Alphabet/alphabet.html)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>例えば、八坂神社は主神としてスサノオを中央に祀り、東に妃神のクシナダヒメ、西に「八柱御子神」を祀っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, Yasaka-jinja Shrine is dedicated to Susano (Deity in Japanese Mythology) in the center as the chief god, Kushinadahime as God Empress, Kisakigami on its east and &quot;Yahashira-mikogami&quot; on its west.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, Yasaka-jinja Shrine is dedicated to Susano (Deity in Japanese Mythology) in the center as the chief god, Kushinadahime as God Empress, Kisakigami on its east side and &quot;Yahashira-mikogami&quot; on its west side.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, Yasaka-jinja Shrine is dedicated to Susanoo (Deity in Japanese Mythology) in the center as the chief god, Kushinadahime as God Empress, Kisakigami on its east side and &apos;Yahashira-mikogami&apos; on its west side.</e>
<cmt>Susanooとしました。シングルクォーテーションに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>春日大社には摂社の「若宮社」があり、主神の天児屋命の御子神である天押雲根命を祀っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kasugataisha Shrine has its &quot;Wakamiya-sha shrine&quot; sessha (auxiliary shrine (dedicated to a deity close-related to that of a main shrine)), which is dedicated to Ameno-oshikumone-no-mikoto, the Mikogami of its chief god, Amenokoyane no Mikoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kasugataisha Shrine has its &quot;Wakamiya-sha shrine&quot; sessha (auxiliary shrine - dedicated to a deity close-related to that of a main shrine), which is dedicated to Ameno-oshikumone-no-mikoto, the Mikogami of its chief god, Amenokoyane no Mikoto.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kasuga-taisha Shrine has its &apos;Wakamiya-sha shrine&apos; sessha (auxiliary shrine - dedicated to a deity close-related to that of a main shrine), which is dedicated to Amenooshikumone no mikoto, the Mikogami of its chief god, Amenokoyane no mikoto.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更、Kasuga-taisha Shrine, Amenooshikumone no mikoto, Amenokoyane no mikotoとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="6">
<j>この「若宮」は、多くの場合主神の御子神を祀る神社であるが、祀られる神ではなく社が若いという意味である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This &quot;Wakamiya,&quot; which is often a shine dedicated to the Mikogami of its chief god, means that not the dedicated god but the shrine itself is young.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This &quot;Wakamiya,&quot; which is often a shine dedicated to the Mikogami of its chief god, means that not the dedicated god, but the shrine itself is young.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This &apos;Wakamiya,&apos; which is often a shrine dedicated to the Mikogami of its chief god, means that not the dedicated god, but the shrine itself is young.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更、shrineのスペルミスを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>後からできた社に「若宮」と名附ける場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A shrine developed later is also called &quot;Wakamiya.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shrines developed later are also called &quot;Wakamiya.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shrines developed later are also called &apos;Wakamiya.&apos;</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>その場合は、主神の親神や祖先神が祀られていることや、主神の御旅所、主神を勧請した神社を若宮と呼んでいる例もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this case, some shrines are dedicated to the parent god as the chief god, or sosen shin (ancestral god), whereas others call otabisho (place where the sacred palanquin is lodged during a festival) or branch shrines Wakamiya.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this case, some shrines are dedicated to the parent god as the chief god, or sosen shin (ancestral god), whereas others call otabisho (place where the sacred palanquin is lodged during a festival) or branch shrines Wakamiya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this case, some shrines are dedicated to the parent god as the chief god, or sosen shin (ancestral god), whereas others call otabisho (place where the sacred palanquin is lodged during a festival) or branch shrines Wakamiya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>よって、必ずしも若宮に御子神が祀られているとは限らない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore all Wakamiya are not dedicated to Mikogami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore all Wakamiya are not dedicated to Mikogami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore all Wakamiya are not dedicated to Mikogami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Nnh(id:474), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>