<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>アメノウズメ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amenouzume</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amenouzume</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amenouzume</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>アメノウズメ（アマノウズメ）は、日本神話に登場する神 (神道)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amenouzume (Amanouzume) is a deity who appears in Japanese mithlogy (Shinto)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amenouzume (Amanouzume) is a deity who appears in Japanese Shinto mythology</e>
<cmt>grammar, spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amenouzume (Amanouzume) is a deity who appears in Japanese Shinto mythology.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>「岩戸隠れ」のくだりなどに登場する芸能の女神であり、日本最古の踊り子と言える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She is a goddess of entertainment who appears in the story of &quot;Iwatokakure&quot; and can be said as the oldest dancer in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She is the goddess of entertainment who appears in the story of &quot;Iwatokakure&quot; and can be said to be the oldest dancer in Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She is the goddess of entertainment who appears in the story of &apos;Iwatokakure&apos; and can be said to be the oldest dancer in Japan.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>古事記では天宇受賣命、日本書紀では天鈿女命と表記する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Chinese character, her name is written as 天宇受賣命 in &quot;Kojiki&quot; and 天鈿女命 in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Chinese characters, her name is written as 天宇受賣命 in &quot;Kojiki&quot; and 天鈿女命 in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot;.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Chinese characters, her name is written as 天宇受賣命 in Kojiki (The Records of Ancient Matters) and 天鈿女命 in Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan).</e>
<cmt>原文に『』がないので&quot;　&quot;を削除古事記、日本書紀に英語の説明を補足。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>神話での記述</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Story described in the mithology</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Story described in the mythology</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Story described in the mythology</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>天岩戸で天照大神が天岩戸に隠れて世界が暗闇になったとき、神々は大いに困り、天の安河に集まって会議をした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Amaterasu Omikami hid herself in the Ama no iwato (cave of heaven) and the world became dark, deities were so embarrassed that they gathered at Ama no Yasukawa and held a conference.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Amaterasu Omikami hid herself in the Ama no iwato (cave of heaven) and the world became dark, deities were so embarrassed that they gathered at Ama no Yasukawa and held a conference.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Amaterasu Omikami hid herself in the Ama no iwato (cave of heaven), the world became dark. Embarrassed by this, the deities gathered at Ama no Yasukawa to hold a conference.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>オモイカネの発案により、岩戸の前で様々な儀式を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the proposal made by Omoikane, they conducted various rituals in front of the iwato.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the proposal made by Omoikane, they conducted various rituals in front of the iwato.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They conducted various rituals in front of the iwato according to the proposal made by Omoikane.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>そして、アメノウズメがうつぶせにした桶の上に乗り、背をそり胸乳をあらわにし、裳の紐を股に押したれて、低く腰を落して足を踏みとどろかし、力強くエロティックな動作で踊って、神々は大笑いした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, as Amenouzume mounted on a bowl which was turned over and danced powerfully and erotically with her back straitened, breasts exposed, strings of clothes hung down in the crotch, waist lowered and feet stamping, deities burst into laughter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, as Amenouzume mounted on a bowl which was turned over and danced powerfully and erotically with her back straightened, breasts exposed, shredded clothes hanging down in front of her crotch, waist lowered and feet stamping, the deities burst into laughter.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But when Amenouzume climbed up onto an overturned bowl and began a powerful sensual dance, straightening her back, exposing her breasts, letting the cord to her skirt dangle in front of her crotch, lowering her waist and stamping with her feet, the deities burst out laughing.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>「あなたより尊い神が生まれた」とウズメが言って、沸き起こった哄笑にさそわれて天照大神が覗き見をしようとして戸を少しあけた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Amenouzume said &quot;A nobler deity than you was born&quot;and deities burst into laughter, Amaterasu Omikami was enticed to peep out and opened the iwato slightly.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Amenouzume said &quot;A nobler deity than you was born&quot;and the deities burst into laughter, Amaterasu Omikami was enticed to peep out and opened the iwato slightly.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Amenouzume declared, &quot;A deity nobler than you has been born,&quot; the resulting laughter enticed Amaterasu Omikami to open the iwato a little in order to take a peek.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>その時、天照大神はアメノタヂカラオにひっぱり出され、再び世界に光が戻った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that moment, Amaterasu Omikami was pulled out by Amenotajikarao and the world became bright again.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that moment, Amaterasu Omikami was pulled out by Amenotajikarao and the world became bright again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that moment, Amaterasu Omikami was pulled out by Amenotajikarao and the world became bright again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>天孫降臨の際、ニニギが天降ろうとすると、高天原から葦原中国までを照らす神がいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Ninigi was to descend on the occasion of tensonkorin (the descent to earth of the grandson of the sun goddess), he found a deity who shine from Takamagahara to Ashihara no nakatsukuni.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Ninigi was to descend on the occasion of tensonkorin (the descent to earth of the grandson of the sun goddess), he found a deity who shone from Takamagahara to Ashihara no nakatsukuni.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Just as Ninigi was descending from heaven during tensonkorin (the ceremonial descent to earth of the grandson of the sun goddess), along came a deity who was illuminating the entire area from Takamagahara all the way to Ashihara no nakatsukuni.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>アマテラスとタカミムスビに、「手弱女だが顔を合わせても気後れしない（面勝つ）からあなたが問いなさい」と言われたアメノウズメが名を問い質すた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Urged by Amaterasu and Takamimusubi as &quot;Although you are a week woman, you ask him because you don&apos;t become diffident (face wins) when you meet with others&quot;, Amenouzume asked the name of the deity in question.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Urged by Amaterasu and Takamimusubi &quot;Although you are a weak woman, you asked him because you don&apos;t hessitate when you meet with others,&quot; Amenouzume asked the name of the deity in question.</e>
<cmt>wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amaterasu and Takamimusubi urged Amenouzume on, saying &quot;You should ask him who he is, because even though you may be a weak woman, you never grow timid when meeting others,&quot; so she asked him his name.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>その神は天津神・国津神のサルタヒコであり、道案内をするために迎えに来たのであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name of the deity was Sarutahiko and he came there to guide.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name of the deity was Sarutahiko and he came there to act as a guide.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The deity&apos;s name was Sarutahiko, who was both an Amatsu kami (god of heaven) and a Kunitsukami (god of the earth), and it turned out he had come to meet them in order to serve as their guide.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>アメノウズメは天児屋命、フトダマ、玉祖命、イシコリドメと共に五伴緒の一人としてニニギに随伴して天降りした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Along with Amenokoyama no Mikoto (a legendary ancestor deity), Futodama, Tamanooya no Mikoto and Ishikoridome, Amenouzume descended, following after Ninigi, as a member of itsutomonoo (chiefs of the five clans).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Along with Amenokoyama no Mikoto (a legendary ancestor deity), Futodama, Tamanooya no Mikoto and Ishikoridome, Amenouzume descended, following after Ninigi, as a member of itsutomonoo (chiefs of the five clans).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">So Amenouzume followed Ninigi and descended from heaven as one of the itsutomonoo (the five clan chiefs), together with the other four, Amenokoyama no Mikoto (a legendary ancestor deity), Futodama, Tamanooya no Mikoto and Ishikoridome.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>アメノウズメはサルタヒコの名を明かしたことからその名を負って仕えることになり、猿女君の祖神となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Amenouzume revealed the name of Sarutahiko, she started to serve under this name and became the soshin (ancestor honored as deity) of Sarumenokimi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Amenouzume revealed the name of Sarutahiko, she started to serve under this name and became the soshin (ancestor honored as deity) of Sarumenokimi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Amenouzume revealed the name of Sarutahiko, she started to serve under this name and became the soshin (ancestor honored as deity) of Sarumenokimi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>一説にはサルタヒコの妻となったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also said that she became Sarutahiko&apos;s wife.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also said that she became Sarutahiko&apos;s wife.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also said that she became Sarutahiko&apos;s wife.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="16">
<j>アメノウズメは大小の魚を集めて天孫（ニニギ）に仕えるかどうか尋ねた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Collecting many kinds of fish, regardless of big or small, she asked them whether they were willing to serve for tenson (Ninigi).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Collecting many kinds of fish, regardless of their size, she asked them whether they were willing to serve for tenson (Ninigi).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amenouzume gathered together many fish, both large and small, and asked them whether they would be willing to work for Tenson (Ninigi).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>みな「仕える」と答えた中でナマコだけが何も答えなかったので、アメノウズメはその口を小刀で裂いてしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As only a sea cucumber said nothing while all of others replied &quot;Yes, I do&quot;, Amenouzume tore its mouth with a knife.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As only the sea cucumber said nothing while all of others replied &quot;Yes, I am,&quot; Amenouzume tore its mouth with a knife.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">All answered &quot;We will serve&quot; except the sea cucumber, who remained silent, so Amenouzume slashed open its mouth with a knife.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>それでナマコの口は裂けているのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The above is the reason why a sea cucumber&apos;s mouth is split.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is the reason why a sea cucumber&apos;s mouth is split.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is the reason why a sea cucumber&apos;s mouth is split.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="19">
<j>アメノウズメの原形</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Origin of Amenouzume</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Origin of Amenouzume</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Origin of Amenouzume</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>神々を笑わせたことからそのような芸事を生業とする女神である（すなわち芸人、コメディアンである）という理解が関西では先行しがちである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kansai region, people tend to believe that she is the goddess whose occupation is such entertainment (namely, public entertainers or comedians) because she let deities laugh.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Kansai region, people tend to believe that she is a goddess whose occupation is entertainment (namely, public entertainers or comedians) because she makes deities laugh.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The theory that, because she often made the gods laugh, she was the patron goddess of the entertainment professions (like performers and comedians), tends in the Kansai region to take priority over other interpretations.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>事実大和国の賣太神社に祀られるアメノウズメは芸能の始祖神として信仰を集めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">I fact, Amenouzume who are being enshrined at Meta-jinja Shrine in Yamato Province are widely worshipped as the Shiso Shin of entertainment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amenouzume who are enshrined at Meta-jinja Shrine in Yamato Province are widely worshipped as the Shiso Shin of entertainment.</e>
<cmt>wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact, the Amenouzume enshrined at Meta-jinja Shrine in Yamato Province has historically been widely worshipped as the Shiso Shin of entertainment.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>だが、記紀の記述からは「神懸かって舞った」と読めるため、笑いをとることが彼女の踊りの目的ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the above description can be interpreted as &quot;she danced while being possessed by the supernatural&quot; and therefore, letting someone laugh was not the purpose of her dance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the above description can be interpreted as &quot;she danced while being possessed by the supernatural&quot; and therefore, making someone laugh was not the purpose of her dance.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the description recorded of her dance can also be interpreted &quot;She danced while possessed&quot; and thus, she was not dancing in order to provoke laughter.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>むしろ手弱女であるが、恥じらいをかなぐり捨て乳房を出して半裸となり、踵を股の内側に、つま先を外側にひねって地を踵で強く踏む申楽のステップをする動作が重要である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">What is important is the fact that she, though being a week woman, performed dance steps of Sarugaku with casting off shyness, becoming half-naked with her breasts exposed, twisting heels inside while toes outside and stomping heels on the ground strongly.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">What is important is the fact that she, though being a weak woman, performed Sarugaku dance steps, while forgetting her shyness, becoming half-naked, her breasts exposed, twisting heels inside while toes outside and strongly stomping her heels on the ground.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Indeed, what is important how she moved during the dance--that despite being a weak woman, she forgot her shyness and threw herself into the Sarugaku dance, half-naked, breasts exposed, using her heels to pound out the steps onto the ground while bending her heels towards her inner thighs and twisting her toes to face out.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>これは、下半身の力強さを演舞で表現したとみられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It seems that she expressed her powerful lower half of the body by dancing.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It seems that she expressed the powerful lower half of her body by dancing.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It seems that her dancing gave expression to the powerful lower half of her body.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>その女相撲めいた武道的力（強女＝オズメ）のエロティシズムに対して喝采が贈られ、乱闘的祭り（宴会？）の喧噪に天照大神の心が動いたと見る方が自然である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is more natural to understand that deities applauded such eroticism of the military art (strong woman=ozume), which was something like female Sumo wrestling, and Amaterasu Omikami was enticed by the bustle caused by a brawl-like festival (party?).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is more natural to understand that the deities applauded such eroticism of military art (strong woman = ozume), which was something like female Sumo wrestling, and Amaterasu Omikami was enticed by the bustle caused by a brawl-like party.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is more natural to think that the gods applauded the eroticism of the martial arts display, which somewhat resembled female Sumo wrestling (and indeed, the term &quot;strong woman&quot; can be pronounced &quot;ozume&quot;), and that Amaterasu Omikami&apos;s emotions were affected by the ruckus resulting from the boisterous celebration.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="26">
<j>天岩戸の前におけるこのような彼女の行為は、神への祭礼、特に古代のシャーマン（巫）が行ったとされる神託の祭事にその原形を見ることができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The original form of such performance conducted in front of Amanoiwato is seen in the divine festival, especially in the oracle festival conducted in ancient times by Shaman (kannagi).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The original form of such performance conducted in front of Amanoiwato is seen in the divine festival, especially in the oracle festival conducted in ancient times by Shaman (kannagi).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The original form of just such dances as the one Amenouzume gave in front of Amanoiwato could also be seen during festivals to the gods, and in particular during the ancient oracle festivals that are thought to have been conducted by shamans (kannagi).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>いわばアメノウズメの逸話は古代の神に仕える巫女たちの姿を今に伝えるものであると考えることができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a nutshell, the episode of Amenouzume is a legend that passes down the figure of miko (a shrine maiden) who served for ancient deities.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The episode of Amenouzume is a legend that tells the story of miko (a shrine maiden) who served ancient deities.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity, wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The episode of Amenouzume is a legend that tells the story of a Miko (shrine maiden) who served the ancient deities.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>この場合の神とはアマテラスという神格が与えられるより以前の古い太陽神信仰であり、後に太陽神の神格がアマテラスへと置き換わった後にもアメノウズメの立場までは置き換わらなかったために現在のような神話として伝わっている、と思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The deity in this case was, however, the old sun god before it was given the divinity of Amaterasu and even after the divinity of the sun god was replaced by Amaterasu, the above mythology has been passed down until now because Amenouzume&apos;s position was not replaced.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The deity in this case was the sun god before it was given the divinity of Amaterasu and even after the the sun god became Amaterasu, the above myth has been passed down to the present because Amenouzume&apos;s position was not replaced.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity, wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The deity in this case was the sun god at a time before being granted the divine aspect of Amaterasu, and it is thought that it is because Amenouzume&apos;s role was left unchanged that the myth continued to be passed down even after the sun god was given Amaterasu&apos;s aspect.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="29">
<j>このことを顕著に示す事例が、岩戸神楽の原型と伝えられる宮崎県西臼杵郡高千穂町の「高千穂の夜神楽」である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A typical example which indicates the above is &quot;Takachiho Night Kagura&quot; conducted in Takachiho-cho, Nishiusuki-gun, Miyazaki Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A typical example which illustrates the above is &quot;Takachiho Night Kagura&quot; conducted in Takachiho-cho, Nishiusuki-gun, Miyazaki Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>vocabulary</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A typical example which illustrates the above is &apos;Takachiho Night Kagura&apos; conducted in Takachiho-cho, Nishiusuki-gun, Miyazaki Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>この神楽では、始めに素面で男性の舞手が日本刀の剣舞をした後、後半の舞で登場するアメノウズメは、左手に笹葉を模した木の枝を、右手に幣をつけた五十鈴を持って、中国の剣舞の「刺剣」の動作をしてスピン回転をしながら舞う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the beginning of this Kagura, a male dancer dances, without putting on a mask, a sword dance using Japanese sword and Amenouzume, who appears in the later half, dances by making spin rotation of &quot;shiken&quot;, a Chinese sword dance, with a tree branch that imitated bamboo leaves held in her left hand and isuzu (literally 50 bells) with nusu (symbols of divinity made of cloth or paper) held in her right hand.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the beginning of this Kagura, a male dancer dances, without wearing a mask, a sword dance using a Japanese sword and Amenouzume, who appears in the later half, dances with a spin or &quot;shiken&lt;,&quot; a Chinese sword dance, with a tree branch that imitated bamboo leaves held in her left hand and isuzu (literally 50 bells) with nusu (symbols of divinity made of cloth or paper) held in her right hand.</e>
<cmt>wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the beginning of this Kagura, after a maskless male dancer dances a sword dance using a Japanese sword, Amenouzume, who appears in the second half, dances a spinning Chinese sword dance called a &quot;shiken,&quot; holding a tree branch designed to imitate bamboo leaves in her left hand and an isuzu (literally &quot;50 bells&quot;) adorned with nusu (symbols of divinity made of cloth or paper) in her right hand.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>アマテラスは33番の最後に夜明けに高木（外注連）に降誕する神霊（タカギムスヒノカミ）と考えられていて、舞い手の神としては最後まで登場しない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amaterasu, who is considered as a deity (Takagimusuwho hi no Kami) who descends in Takagi (sotojime (place like the heavens)) lastly, 33th, at dawn, never appears as a dancer until the end of Kagura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amaterasu, who was considered a deity (Takagimusuwho hi no Kami) who descends to Takagi (sotojime - place like the heavens) lastly, the 33th, at dawn, doesn&apos;t appear as a dancer until the end of Kagura.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amaterasu is given the role of the deity (Takagimusu hi no Kami) who descends to Takagi (considered a &quot;sotojime&quot; or heaven-like realm) at dawn, and appears last of the 33, nor does she come on stage as a dancing deity until the very end of the performance.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>そこで大神とされるのは、大わだつみの神である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Okami in this Kagura is Owadatsumi no Kami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Okami in this Kagura is Owadatsumi no Kami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Okami in this Kagura is Owadatsumi no Kami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="33">
<j>こうした踊りは、神を慰撫し、力を回復させるための踊り（巫＝神凪／かんなぎ、神座／神楽＝かみくら／かぐら／かみあそび）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such dance was performed for the purpose of consoling deities and recovering their power (kannagi, kamikura/kagura/kamiasobi).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such dance was performed for the purpose of consoling the deities and recovering their power (kannagi, kamikura/kagura/kamiasobi).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such a dance (which was danced by a medium known as a kannagi to sacred music called kamikura, kagura, or kamiasobi) was performed to consol the deities and restore their power.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>一方日本書紀においては「巧みに俳優(わざおぎ)をなし」とあり、これは神の業をその身に招いて観衆を楽しませる姿を表している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the meantime, the description of &quot;by acting (wazaogi) skillfully&quot; appears in the Nihonshoki and it means a performer entertaining audiences with deities&apos; skill that was invited into him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the meantime, the description of &quot;by acting (wazaogi) skillfully&quot; appears in the Nihonshoki and it means a performer entertaining audiences with deities&apos; skill that was given to him.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A description of &apos;takumini wazaogi o nashi&apos; appears in the Nihonshoki, and it means a performer entertaining an audience with the skills bestowed upon him/her by the deities.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>このことが「俳優」の語源になっているように、神楽舞に連なるこれらの祭事は、日本の芸能の出発点となったことが確かである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As shown by the fact that the above is the origin of the word of &quot;actor&quot;, it is certain that these festivals of Kaguramai (dance for Kagura) were the starting point of Japanese public entertainment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As shown by the fact that the above is the origin of the word &quot;actor,&quot; it is certain that these festivals of Kaguramai (dance for Kagura) were the starting point of Japanese public entertainment.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As shown by the fact that the above is the origin of the word &apos;actor,&apos; it is certain that these festivals of Kaguramai (dance for Kagura) were the starting point of Japanese public entertainment.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="36">
<j>なお、ヤマト王権のヤマト大王（天皇家の祖）が行った古代の大嘗祭においても、大王家の祖神を祀る巫女たちが同様の神懸かりした激しい踊りを踊っていたということがわかっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also known that in the ancient Daijosai Festival (a festival to celebrate the succession of an emperor) held by Yamato Daio (the ancestor of the Emperors&apos; family) of Yamato dynasty, miko who were possessed by the supernatural furiously performed a dance in order to worship Daio family&apos;s soshin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also known that in the ancient Daijosai Festival (festival to celebrate the succession of an emperor) held by Yamato Daio (the ancestors of the Emperors&apos; family) of Yamato dynasty, miko who were possessed by the supernatural furiously performed a dance in order to worship Daio family&apos;s soshin.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also known that in the ancient Daijosai Festival (which celebrated the accession of a new emperor) held by the Yamato Daio (the ancestors of the Emperors&apos; family) of the Yamato dynasty, Miko were possessed by the spirits and performed a fast and furious dance in worship of the Daio family&apos;s soshin.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>これは上記のような太陽神への祭事が変化したものであると考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is considered as the one which evolved from the festivals for the sun god mentioned above.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is considered as the one which evolved from the festivals for the sun god mentioned above.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is considered as the one which evolved from the festivals for the sun god mentioned above.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>その背景は、大和王権が太陽神＝アマテラスを祀りかつその子孫を標榜していたことに着目すると理解しやすい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It can be easily understood by directing attention to the background fact that Yamato dynasty worshipped the sun god=Amaterasu and professed itself as her descendant.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It can be easily understood by directing attention to the background that the Yamato dynasty worshipped the sun god=Amaterasu and professed that the dynasty decended from her.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It can be easily understood by directing attention to the background that the Yamato dynasty worshipped the sun god = Amaterasu and professed that the dynasty descended from her.</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="39">
<j>また天孫降臨の際にサルタヒコと応対し、その後、その名を負って猿女君を名乗ったという逸話も、サルタヒコが元々伊勢国地方で崇められていた太陽神であったとされることから、アメノウズメが太陽神に使える巫女たちを神格化したものであることの証拠とも言える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The above anecdote concerning Amenouzume, in which she is said to have addressed to Sarutahiko during tensonkorin and named herself Sarumenokimi after him, can be pointed out as an evidence to prove that Amenouzume was the deified figure of miko who served for the sun god because Sarutahiko was originally the sun god admired in Ise province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The above anecdote concerning Amenouzume, in which she is said to have addressed Sarutahiko during tensonkorin and named herself Sarumenokimi after him, and this can be pointed out as evidence that Amenouzume was the deified figure of miko who served the sun god because Sarutahiko was originally the sun god admired in Ise province.</e>
<cmt>revised grammar for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The above anecdote concerning Amenouzume, in which she is said to have addressed Sarutahiko during tensonkorin and named herself Sarumenokimi after him, and this can be pointed out as evidence that Amenouzume The anecdote concerning Amenouzume recounted above, in which she is said to have addressed Sarutahiko during tensonkorin and named herself Sarumenokimi after him, can also be marshalled as evidence that Amenouzume was a deified figure of a Miko who served the sun god, because Sarutahiko was originally the sun god worshipped in Ise Province.was the deified figure of miko who served the sun god because Sarutahiko was originally the sun god admired in Ise Province.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>猿女一族は古くから朝廷の祭祀と深く結びついていた一族であり、また猿女君は宮廷祭祀において神楽を舞うことを担当した神祇官の役職名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Sarume clan was traditionally involved in the festivals held by the Imperial Court and Sarumenokimi was a position of Jingikan (department of worship) of which role was dancing Kagura on the occasion of court festivals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sarume clan was traditionally involved in festivals held by the Imperial Court and Sarumenokimi was in the position of Jingikan (department of worship) of which role was dancing Kagura at court festivals.</e>
<cmt>wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sarume clan was traditionally involved in festivals held by the Imperial Court, and Sarumenokimi was an official position in the Jingikan (department of worship) whose duty was to dance the Kagura at court festivals.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="41">
<j>神名の「ウズメ」の解釈には諸説あり、「強女」の意とする説や、中国風に髪を頭の上にあげ、蔦をかざし（髪をとめるピンやはちまき）にしてとめた「髻（ウズ）」を結った女性の意とする説などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Concerning the interpretation of her deity name &quot;Uzume&quot;, there are several views such as it means &quot;strong woman&quot; or it means a woman who does her hair in &quot;uzu&quot; style with hair tied on head, in Chinese style, by tsuta (devices to tie hair such as a hair pin or a headband)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Concerning the interpretation of her deity name &quot;Uzume,&quot; there are several views such as it means &quot;strong woman&quot; or it means a woman who does her hair in &quot;uzu&quot; style with hair tied up, in Chinese style, by tsuta (devices to tie hair such as a hair pins or a headband)</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are several theories as to the origins of her divine name, &quot;Uzume,&quot; including that it means &quot;strong woman&quot; or that it refers to a woman who arranges her hair in the &quot;uzu&quot; style, a hairstyle where the hair is bound high in Chinese fashion by tsuta (hair-binding ornaments like pins or headbands).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="42">
<j>信仰</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Faith</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Faith</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Faith</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="43">
<j>猿女君・稗田氏の祖とされ、稗田氏の氏神である賣太神社では、芸能の始祖神、福の神、おたふく、おかめ、等と称すると伝わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She is believed to be the ancestor of Sarumenokimi・the Hieda clan and at Meta-jinja Shrine, a private deity of the Hieda clan, she is called Shiso Shin of entertainment, Fuku no Kami, Otafuku, Okame etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She is believed to be the ancestor of Sarumenokimi・the Hieda clan and at Meta-jinja Shrine, a private deity of the Hieda clan, she is called Shiso Shin of entertainment, Fuku no Kami, Otafuku, Okame etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She is held to be the ancestor both of Sarumenokimi and of the Hieda clan, and at Meta-jinja Shrine, where the private deity of the Hieda clan is enshrined, she is called by a variety of other names, including the Shiso Shin of entertainment, Fuku no Kami, Otafuku, and Okame.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>芸能・技芸全般の神として信仰されており、芸能神社（京都市右京区）、椿大神社（三重県鈴鹿市）、鈿女神社（長野県北安曇郡松川村）などで祀られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She is widely worshipped as the deity of entertainment・gigei in general and is enshrined at Geino-jinja Shrine (Ukyo Ward, Kyoto City), Tsubaki Okamiyashiro Grand Shrine (Suzuka City, Mie Prefecture) and Uzume-jinja Shrine (Matsukawa-mura, Kitaazumi-gun, Nagano Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She is widely worshipped as the deity of entertainment・gigei in general and is enshrined at Geino-jinja Shrine (Ukyo Ward, Kyoto City), Tsubaki Okamiyashiro Grand Shrine (Suzuka City, Mie Prefecture) and Uzume-jinja Shrine (Matsukawa-mura, Kitaazumi-gun, Nagano Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She is widely worshipped as the deity of entertainment, gigei in general and is enshrined at Geino-jinja Shrine (Ukyo Ward, Kyoto City), Tsubaki Okamiyashiro Grand Shrine (Suzuka City, Mie Prefecture) and Uzume-jinja Shrine (Matsukawa-mura, Kitaazumi-gun, Nagano Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>・→,</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>鈿女神社は地元で「おかめ様」として崇められており、最寄駅の大糸線北細野駅は信濃鉄道の駅として開業した際「おかめ前駅」と呼ばれていた（国営化に当たって改称）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Local people admire Uzume-jinja Shrine as &quot;Okame sama&quot; and the nearest railway station to it, Kitahosono Station of the Oito Line, was initially called &quot;Okame-mae Station&quot; when it commenced operation as the station of Shinano Railway Company (the station was renamed when the line was nationalized).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Local people admire Uzume-jinja Shrine as &quot;Okame sama&quot; and the nearest railway station to it, Kitahosono Station of the Oito Line, was initially called &quot;Okame-mae Station&quot; when it commenced operation as the station of Shinano Railway Company (the station was renamed when the line was nationalized).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Uzume-jinja Shrine is reverentially referred to locally as &quot;Okame-sama&quot; and Kitahosono Station on the Oito Line, which is the closest train station to the shrine, was initially named &quot;Okame-mae Station&quot; back when it began operations as a station of the Shinano Railway Company (it was renamed &quot;Kitahosono Station&quot; when the rail line was nationalized).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="46">
<j>宮崎県西臼杵郡の高千穂町には、アメノウズメがサルタヒコと結婚した場、荒立宮の後と伝わる荒立神社が存在し、国際結婚・安産の神として、ウズメとサルタヒコが神体となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Takachiho-cho, Nishiusuki-gun, Miyazaki Prefecture, there exists Aratate-jinja Shrine, which is believed to be the old site of Aratate-gu where Amenouzume married with Sarutahiko, and Uzume and Sarutahiko are enshrined there as the deity of international marriage・safe delivery.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Takachiho-cho, Nishiusuki-gun, Miyazaki Prefecture, there exists Aratate-jinja Shrine, which is believed to be the old site of Aratate-gu where Amenouzume married with Sarutahiko, and Uzume and Sarutahiko are enshrined there as the deity of international marriage・safe delivery.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Takachiho-cho, Nishiusuki-gun, Miyazaki Prefecture, there exists Aratate-jinja Shrine, located in Takachiho-cho, Nishiusuki-gun, Miyazaki Prefecture, is believed to be the old site of Aratate-gu where Amenouzume married Sarutahiko, and Uzume and Sarutahiko are enshrined there as the deities of international marriage and safe delivery.Aratate-jinja Shrine, which is believed to be the old site of Aratate-gu where Amenouzume married with Sarutahiko, and Uzume and Sarutahiko are enshrined there as the deity of international marriage and safe delivery.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="47">
<j>村境や道路の分岐点などに立てられる道祖神は、サルタヒコとアメノウズメであるともされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Doso-shin (travelers&apos; guardian deity) which are set at the boundary of villages and/or junctions of roads are said to be Sarutahiko and Amenouzume.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Doso-shin (travelers&apos; guardian deity) which are set at the boundary of villages and/or junctions of roads are said to be Sarutahiko and Amenouzume.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Doso-shin (guardian deities of travelers), granite sculptures of which are set at village boundaries and/or road junctions, are said to be Sarutahiko and Amenouzume.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 AlleborgoBot(id:119729), Darkicebot(id:272877), Bakkai(id:7233), Nnh(id:474), Newtype(id:185412), Nallimbot(id:230812), Sutou(id:32), Robbot(id:3063), Gombe(id:27), ＋－(id:17104), Ef3(id:84901), Uenokami(id:179211), Tanuki Z(id:612), Thijs!bot(id:69644), Alecs.bot(id:194707), AlnoktaBOT(id:135808), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), SuisuiBot(id:10165), Loveless(id:129239), SassoBot(id:285258), Shimoxx(id:9332), Alexbot(id:157199), Tinecici(id:192914), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>