<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>梓弓</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Azusayumi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Azusayumi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Azusayumi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>梓弓（あずさゆみ、あづさゆみ）は、神事などに使用されるアズサの木で作られた弓 (武器)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Aazusayumi is a bow made of Japanese cherry birch and used for Shinto rituals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Aazusayumi is a bow made of Japanese cherry birch used for Shinto rituals.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Aazusayumi is a bow made of Japanese cherry birch used for Shinto rituals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>材質に関わらず弓のことを梓弓と呼ぶこともある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Any bow can be called an Azusayumi, regardless of the material it is made from.</e>
<cmt>I think the indefinite article should be used before &quot;Azusayumi&quot; if it is being used as a singular.</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>または枕詞の一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Or it is a Makura word (Poetic epithet convention)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Or it is a Makura word (Poetic epithet convention)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Or it is a Makura word (Poetic epithet convention)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Outline</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Outline</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>&quot;Outline&quot; -&gt; &quot;Summary&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>古くは神事や出産などの際､魔除けに鳴らす弓（鳴弦）として使用された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In old days it was used as a bow (meigen (resounding bowstrings)) that makes sound for amulet in Shinto rituals and childbirth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the old days it was used as a bow (meigen - resounding bowstrings) that makes a sound for the amulet used in Shinto rituals and childbirth.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the old days it was used as a bow (meigen - resounding bowstrings) that makes a sound for the amulet used in Shinto rituals and childbirth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>甲斐国や信濃国から都に献上され、現在でも遺品として残されている例がいくつかある（正倉院中倉の3張など）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bow was presented to shrines in Kyoto from Kai Province and Shinano Province, and some examples have been left today (three bows in Shoso-in chuso storage).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bow was presented to shrines in Kyoto from Kai and Shinano Provinces, and some examples are still in existence today (three bows in Shoso-in chuso storage).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bow was presented to shrines in Kyoto from Kai and Shinano Provinces, and some examples are still in existence today (three bows in Shoso-in chuso storage).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>梓弓という固定された様式が有るわけではなく、伏見稲荷大社の奉射祭ではアズサの木の枝にそのまま弦を張っただけの弓が使用され、また式年遷宮に奉納される弓は京弓師柴田勘十郎に代々伝わる製法で作られるなど、使われる場ごとにその様相を異にする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Azusayumi does not have a fixed shape and how it is shaped depends on where it is used; the bow used in Hosha-sai Festival of Fushimi Inari Taisha Shrine is simply a branch of cherry birch with a bowstring; the bow used in the transfer of a deity to a new shrine building once in a prescribed number of years is made by kyo-yumi bow maker Kanjuro SHIBATA with a technique handed down from previous generations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Azusayumi does not have a fixed shape and how it is shaped depends on where it is used; the bow used in Hosha-sai Festival of Fushimi Inari Taisha Shrine is simply a branch of cherry birch with a bowstring; the bow used in the transfer of a deity to a new shrine building once in a prescribed number of years was made by kyo-yumi bow maker Kanjuro SHIBATA using a technique handed down from previous generations.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Azusayumi does not have a fixed shape and how it is shaped depends on where it is used; the bow used in Hosha-sai Festival (an archery ceremony that drives evil away) of Fushimi Inari-taisha Shrine is simply a branch of cherry birch with a bowstring; the bow used in the transfer of a deity to a new shrine building once in a prescribed number of years was made by kyo-yumi bow maker Kanjuro SHIBATA using a technique handed down from previous generations.</e>
<cmt>Fushimi Inari-taisha Shrineとし、奉射祭の補足を入れました。(参照:http://books.google.co.jp/books?id=b7KbLLjzuRgC&amp;pg=PA235&amp;dq=hosha-sai&amp;as_brr=3#)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>枕詞としての梓弓</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Azusayumi as a Makura word</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Azusayumi as a Makura word</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Azusayumi as a Makura word</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>万葉集などにおいては、春（張る）、引くなどを導く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It preceded spring (a homonym of putting up string) and pulls in Manyoshu (Collection of Ten Thousand Leaves).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This word preceded spring (a homonym of setting up the string) and pulls in Manyoshu (Collection of Ten Thousand Leaves).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This word preceded spring (a homonym of setting up the string) and pulls in Manyoshu (Collection of Ten Thousand Leaves).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 福太郎(id:132415), Shimotsuke(id:19741), 赤井彗星(id:18381), Totti(id:35433), Libertas(id:40611), Nighthawks(id:36125), 寒漁夫(id:99134), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>