<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>神饌</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinsen (Food and Alcohol Offering to the Gods)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinsen (Food and Alcohol Offering to the Gods)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinsen (Food and Alcohol Offering to the gods)</e>
<cmt>&quot;Gods&quot; -&gt; &quot;gods&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>神饌（しんせん）とは、日本の神社や神棚に供える供物の事である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinsen is an offering to shrines and household Shinto altar in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinsen is an offering to shrines and household Shinto altars in Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinsen is an offering to shrines and household Shinto altars in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>御饌（みけ）あるいは御贄（みにえ）とも言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called Mike or Minie.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called Mike or Minie.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called Mike or Minie.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>神饌には、調理して供える熟饌（じゅくせん）と、生のまま供える生饌（せいせん）とがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Mike includes the cooked type called Jukusen and the raw type called Seisen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mike includes the cooked type called Jukusen and the raw type called Seisen.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinsen includes the cooked type called Jukusen and the raw type called Seisen.</e>
<cmt>Mike→Shinsenに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>熟饌の調理には、本来は燧石、舞錐式などで起こした神聖な炎（忌火・いみび）のみを使う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To cook the Jukusen, in principle, only flames (secret fire (imibi)) produced by firestones or maigirishiki is used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To cook the Jukusen, in principle, only flames (secret fire or imibi) produced by firestones or maigirishiki is used.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To cook the Jukusen, in principle, only flames (secret fire (imibi)) produced by firestones or maigiri-shiki (style using gimlets (maigiri), ancient tools for making fire) is used.</e>
<cmt>舞錐式の表現を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>神社などでは、米、塩、水、野菜、鯛、鰹節（干鰹）、海藻、果物、清酒などを供える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In shrines, offerings include rice, salt, water, vegetables, bonitos, dried bonito, see feed, fruits, and seishu or refined sake.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In shrines, offerings include rice, salt, water, vegetables, bonitos, dried bonito, see feed, fruits, and seishu or refined sake.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In shrines, offerings include rice, salt, water, vegetables, bonitos, dried bonito, seaweed, fruits, and seishu or refined sake.</e>
<cmt>see feed→seaweedに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>基本的には、かわらけと呼ばれる素焼きの焼き物を器にするが、地域によってはアワビの貝殻を代用する場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Shinsen is usually offered in a unglazed vessel called Kawarake (earthen cup), an abalone shell may be used in some regions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Shinsen is usually offered in a unglazed vessel called Kawarake (earthenware cup), an abalone shell may be used in some regions.</e>
<cmt>vocabulary</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Shinsen is usually offered in a unglazed vessel called Kawarake (earthenware cup), an abalone shell may be used in some regions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>本来、朝夕の2回供えるが、地域によって異なっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is, in principle, served twice a day--morning and evening--but how often it is served a day may vary from region to region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is, in principle, served twice a day--morning and evening--but how often it is served a day may vary from region to region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is, in principle, served twice a day--morning and evening--but how often it is served a day may vary from region to region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="8">
<j>祭儀の後に供えた神饌を食べる宴のことを直会（なおらい）という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nnaorai refers to the Shinsen eaten in a feast after a ceremony.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nnaorai refers to Shinsen eaten in a feast after a ceremony.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naorai refers to Shinsen eaten in a feast after a ceremony.</e>
<cmt>Nnaorai→Naoraiに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>直会には、神の供物を食べることで神に近づくという意味もあるが、人が食べることのできないものは供えてはいなかったという証明でもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eating the Nnaorai not only means getting closer to a god by eating what has been offered but also proves that things unfit to eat have not offered.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eating the Nnaorai not only means getting closer to a god by eating what has been offered, but also proves that things unfit to eat have not been offered.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eating the Naorai not only means getting closer to a god by eating what has been offered, but also proves that things unfit to eat have not been offered.</e>
<cmt>Nnaorai→Naoraiに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="10">
<j>ただ、厳密に言うならば、献饌された神饌が必ず直会にあがるという訳ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Strictly speaking, however, the Shinsen offered on the altars is not necessarily served as a Naorai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Strictly speaking, however, the Shinsen offered on the altars is not necessarily served as a Naorai.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Strictly speaking, however, the Shinsen offered on the altars is not necessarily served as a Naorai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>献饌し終わった神饌を神体山へ投げる、土中に埋めるなどの行為が今現在でも一部見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In some regions, the Shinsen offered on the altars are thrown in Shintaizan (a mountain where the spirit of deity is traditionally believed to dwell) or buried underground even today.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In some regions, the Shinsen offered on the altars are thrown in Shintaizan (a mountain where the spirit of deity is traditionally believed to dwell) or buried underground even today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In some regions, the Shinsen offered on the altars is thrown in Shintaizan (a mountain where the spirit of deity is traditionally believed to dwell) or buried underground even today.</e>
<cmt>前出の表記に合わせShinsenに続く動詞を&quot;are&quot;→&quot;is&quot;に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>各々神饌に対しての礼儀作法、考え方が異なっていたこと、それらが今でも継承されてきたことが伺える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This indicates that there were different courtesies or stances toward Shinsen, which have been passed down to the present day.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This indicates that there were different courtesies or stances toward Shinsen, which have been passed down to the present day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This indicates that there were different courtesies or stances toward Shinsen, which have been passed down to the present day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>特殊神饌</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Special Shinsen</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Special Shinsen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Special Shinsen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="13">
<j>現在、多くの神社における神饌は生饌が多く扱われているが、有名古社や古い神事を継承し続けている神社においてはきわめて珍しい形式の神饌を献饌していることがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Shisen offered in many shrines is Seisen today but quite a rare style of Seisen has been offered in some well known and old shrines or other shrines that have carried on traditional Shinto rituals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Shisen offered in many shrines is Seisen today but quite a rare style of Seisen has been offered in some well known and old shrines or other shrines that have carried on traditional Shinto rituals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Shinsen offered in many shrines is Seisen (raw type) today but quite a rare style of Shinsen has been offered in some well known and old shrines or other shrines that have carried on traditional Shinto rituals.</e>
<cmt>Shinsen, Seisenの誤表記を訂正し、生饌の意味を明確にするため補足を入れました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>便宜上、それらは特殊神饌と呼ばれ、熟饌を中心とした、調理されたものが献饌されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such a rare Seisen is called Special Seisen, for convenience, and Seisen, a cooked type, is mainly offered..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such a rare Seisen is called Special Seisen, for convenience, and Seisen, a cooked type, is mainly offered..</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such a rare Shinsen is called Special Shinsen, for convenience, and Jukusen, a cooked type, is mainly offered..</e>
<cmt>神饌の表記をSeisen→Shinsenに訂正、および熟饌の表記をSeisen→Jukusenに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>（神社祭式に規定されたものを基準として考えているので、それまで存在していた古式の神饌は「特殊」という括りで称されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Because the standard Seisen is considered as what is defined in the Rules for Ritual Procedure at Shrines, the traditional Seisen has been seen as &quot;Special,&quot; and called so.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Because standard Seisen is considered to be what is defined in the Rules for Ritual Procedures at Shrines, the traditional Seisen has been seen as &quot;Special,&quot; and called so.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Because standard Shinsen is considered to be what is defined in the Rules for Ritual Procedures at Shrines, the traditional Shinsen has been seen as &quot;Special,&quot; and called so.</e>
<cmt>神饌の表記をSeisen→Shinsenに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>明治維新を境にした神社祭式の刷新と神社の在り方・神道のあり方が大きく影響を及ぼしている）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is greatly influenced by a reform of the Rules for Ritual Procedure at Shrines as well as a changed meaning of shrines and Shinto after Maiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is greatly influenced by the reform of the Rules for Ritual Procedures at Shrines as well as the change in meaning of shrines and Shinto after Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is greatly influenced by the reform of the Rules for Ritual Procedures at Shrines as well as the change in meaning of shrines and Shinto after Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="17">
<j>一例を挙げるならば、以下のようなものがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Examples of Special Shinsen are:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Examples of Special Shinsen are:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Examples of Special Shinsen are:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="18">
<j>奈良県奈良市 春日大社 春日若宮おん祭り　『御染御供』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Osome goku&quot; in Kasuga Wakamiya Onmatsuri Festival of Kasuga Taisha Shrine, Nara City, Nara Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Osome goku&quot; in the Kasuga Wakamiya Onmatsuri Festival of Kasuga Taisha Shrine, Nara City, Nara Prefecture</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Osome Goku&quot; in the Kasuga Wakamiya Onmatsuri Festival of Kasuga-taisha Shrine, Nara City, Nara Prefecture</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション内の頭文字を大文字に、およびKasuga-taisha Shrineとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>奈良県奈良市 春日大社 春日祭　『御戸開八種神饌』『御棚神饌』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Mitobiraki yakusano shinsen&quot; and &quot;Mitana shinsen&quot; in Kasuga Wakamiya Onmatsuri Festival of Kasuga Taisha Shrine, Nara City, Nara Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Mitobiraki yakusano shinsen&quot; and &quot;Mitana shinsen&quot; in Kasuga Wakamiya Onmatsuri Festival of Kasuga Taisha Shrine, Nara City, Nara Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Mitobiraki Yakusa no Shinsen&quot; and &quot;Mitana Shinsen&quot; in Kasuga Matsuri Festival of Kasuga-taisha Shrine, Nara City, Nara Prefecture</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション内の頭文字を大文字に、および&quot;Yakusa no&quot;としました。&quot;Kasuga Wakamiya Onmatsuri Festival&quot;→&quot;Kasuga Matsuri Festival&quot;に訂正しました。&quot;Kasuga-taisha Shrine&quot;としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>奈良県奈良市 率川神社 率川祭　『率川祭神饌』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Isagawa matsuri shinsen&quot; in Isagawa Matsuri Festival of Isagawa Shrine, Nara City, Nara Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Isagawa matsuri shinsen&quot; in Isagawa Matsuri Festival of Isagawa Shrine, Nara City, Nara Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Isagawa Matsuri Shinsen&quot; in Isagawa Matsuri Festival of Isagawa-jinja Shrine, Nara City, Nara Prefecture</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション内の頭文字を大文字に、およびIsagawa-jinja Shrineとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>奈良県桜井市 多武峰 談山神社 嘉吉祭 『百味御食』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Hyakumi onjiki&quot; in Kakissai Festival of Tanzan Shrine, Tonomine, Sakurai City, Nara Prefecture</e>
<cmt>http://www.tanzan.or.jp/maturi.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Hyakumi onjiki&quot; in Kakissai Festival of Tanzan Shrine, Tonomine, Sakurai City, Nara Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Hyakumi Onjiki&quot; in Kakissai Festival of Tanzan-jinja Shrine, Tonomine, Sakurai City, Nara Prefecture</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション内の頭文字を大文字に、およびTanzan-jinja Shrineとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>京都府京都市 賀茂御祖神社・賀茂別雷神社 葵祭 『内陣神饌』『外陣神饌』『庭積神饌』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Naijin shinsen,&quot; &quot;gaijin shinsen,&quot; and &quot;niwazumi shinsen&quot; in Aoi-Matsuri Festival of Kamomioya-jinja Shrine/Kamowake-Ikazuchi-jinja Shrine, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt>http://www.kamigamojinja.jp/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Naijin shinsen,&quot; &quot;gaijin shinsen,&quot; and &quot;niwazumi shinsen&quot; in Aoi-Matsuri Festival of Kamomioya-jinja Shrine/Kamowake-Ikazuchi-jinja Shrine, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Naijin Shinsen,&quot; &quot;Gaijin Shinsen,&quot; and &quot;Niwazumi Shinsen&quot; in Aoi-Matsuri Festival of Kamomioya-jinja Shrine/Kamowake-Ikazuchi-jinja Shrine, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション内の頭文字を大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>三重県伊勢市 伊勢神宮 『由貴大御饌』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Yuki omike&quot; of Ise Jingu shrine, Ise City, Mie Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Yuki omike&quot; of Ise Jingu shrine, Ise City, Mie Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Yuki Omike&quot; of Ise-jingu Shrine, Ise City, Mie Prefecture</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション内の頭文字を大文字に、Ise-jingu Shrineとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>滋賀県大津市 日吉大社 山王祭 『粟津御供』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Awazu no goku&quot; in Sanno Matsuri Festival of Hiyoshi Taisha Shrine, Otsu City, Shiga Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Awazu no goku&quot; in Sanno Matsuri Festival of Hiyoshi Taisha Shrine, Otsu City, Shiga Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Awazu no Goku&quot; in Sanno Matsuri Festival of Hiyoshi-taisha Shrine, Otsu City, Shiga Prefecture</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション内の頭文字を大文字に、およびHiyoshi-taisha Shrineとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>島根県松江市 美保神社 青柴垣神事 『青柴垣神事神饌』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Aofushigaki shinji shinsen&quot; in Aofushigaki shinji of Miho-jinja Shrine, Matsue City, Shimane Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Aofushigaki shinji shinsen&quot; in Aofushigaki shinji of Miho-jinja Shrine, Matsue City, Shimane Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Aofushigaki Shinji Shinsen&quot; in Aofushigaki shinji of Miho-jinja Shrine, Matsue City, Shimane Prefecture</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション内の頭文字を大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>新潟県弥彦村 彌彦神社 灯篭神事 『大御膳』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Ogozen&quot; in Toro shinji of Iyahiko-jinja Shrine, Yahiko Mura, Nigata Prefecture</e>
<cmt>http://genbu.net/data/etigo/iyahiko_title.htm</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Ogozen&quot; in Toro shinji of Iyahiko-jinja Shrine, Yahiko Mura, Nigata Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Ogozen&quot; in Toro shinji of Iyahiko-jinja Shrine, Yahiko-mura, Nigata Prefecture</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション内の頭文字を大文字に、およびYahiko-muraとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>長野県諏訪市 諏訪大社 御頭祭 『御頭祭神饌』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Ontosai shinsen&quot; in Ontosai Festival of Suwa Taisha shrine, Suwa City, Nagano Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Ontosai shinsen&quot; in Ontosai Festival of Suwa Taisha shrine, Suwa City, Nagano Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Ontosai Shinsen&quot; in Ontosai Festival of Suwa-taisha Shrine, Suwa City, Nagano Prefecture</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション内の頭文字を大文字に、Suwa-taisha Shrineとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>千葉県香取市 香取神宮 大饗祭 『大饗祭神饌』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Daikyosai shinsen&quot; in Daikyosai of Katori-jingu Shrine, Katori city, Chiba Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Daikyosai shinsen&quot; in Daikyosai of Katori-jingu Shrine, Katori city, Chiba Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Daikyosai Shinsen&quot; in Daikyosai Festival of Katori-jingu Shrine, Katori city, Chiba Prefecture</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション内の頭文字を大文字に、およびDaikyosai Festivalとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>近畿地方などでは小さな社でも特殊神饌を献饌する神事・祭祀儀礼を伝承・継続しているところがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some small shrines in Kinki region have handed down and carried on traditional Shinto rituals and services in which Special Shinsen is offered on the altar.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some small shrines in the Kinki region have been handed down and carried on traditional Shinto rituals and services in which Special Shinsen is offered on the altar.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some small shrines in the Kinki region have been handed down and carried on traditional Shinto rituals and services in which Special Shinsen is offered on the altar.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>神道学・民俗学・食文化研究などの研究対象になることも多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Special Shinsen in those shrines are often the subject of researches in the studies of Shinto, folklore, and food culture.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Special Shinsen in those shrines are often the subject of research into the studies of Shinto, folklore, and food culture.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Special Shinsen in those shrines are often the subject of research into the studies of Shinto, folklore, and food culture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>各々の特殊神饌は、各社の地域産業や神社経済、信仰の在り様、祭祀儀礼の意義など複雑な要素が見え隠れしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Various factors such as the regional industry, finance of shrines, the way of practicing a faith, and purposes of Shinto services and rituals can be glimpsed in each Special Shinsen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Various factors such as the regional industry, financing of shrines, the way of practicing faith, and purposes of Shinto services and rituals can be glimpsed at in each Special Shinsen.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Various factors such as the regional industry, financing of shrines, the way of practicing faith, and purposes of Shinto services and rituals can be glimpsed at in each Special Shinsen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>日本人が生み出した食文化の一つとして着目すべき宗教現象だと言えると思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Special Shinsen can be regarded as a remarkable religious phenomenon as a food culture developed by the Japanese.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Special Shinsen can be regarded as a remarkable religious phenomenon as a food culture developed by the Japanese.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Special Shinsen can be regarded as a remarkable religious phenomenon as a food culture developed by the Japanese.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 翰林硯士(id:99377), 千葉県民(id:24321), Ypacaraí(id:11031), Nnh(id:474), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), N yotarou(id:60870), Nekosuki600(id:21263), Bit(id:2197), Im224(id:57113), Yosemite(id:5808), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>