<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>国家神道</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">State Shinto</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">State Shinto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">State Shinto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>国家神道（こっかしんとう）とは明治から太平洋戦争の終戦までの間に大日本帝国の政策により成立していた国教、あるいは祭祀の形態の歴史学的呼称である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">State Shinto was a historical name of a state religion or a form of a religious service that was established under a policy of the Empire of Japan from the Meiji period to the end of the Pacific War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">State Shinto is the name given by historians to the state religion, as well as the religious services, that were established as a policy of the Empire of Japan from the Meiji period (1868-1912) to the end of the Pacific War.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">State Shinto is the name given by historians to the state religion, as well as the religious services, that were established under a policy of the Empire of Japan from the Meiji period (1868-1912) to the end of the Pacific War.</e>
<cmt>as→under</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>「国体神道」・「神社神道」とも、また、単に「神社」とも称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was also called &apos;Kokutai Shinto (National Structure Shinto)&apos;, &apos;Jinja Shinto (Shrine Shinto)&apos; or simply &apos;jinja (shrine)&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was also called &apos;Kokutai Shinto&apos; (National Structure Shinto), &apos;Jinja Shinto&apos; (Shrine Shinto) or simply &apos;jinja&apos; (shrine).</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was also called &apos;Kokutai Shinto&apos; (National Structure Shinto), &apos;Jinja Shinto&apos; (Shrine Shinto) or simply &apos;jinja&apos; (shrine).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Outline</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Outline</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>他のファイルとあわせました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>「国家神道」は広義には神道的な実践を国民統合の支柱とするもの、狭義には「宗教」とされた「教派神道」に対して内務省 (日本)神社局によって統制されたものをいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">State Shinto&apos; is the Shinto that used Shinto practice as a support for integration of people in a broad sense, or the Shinto that was controlled by the Bureau of Shinto shrines of the prewar Ministry of Home Affairs (Japan) in a narrow sense in contrast to the &apos;Sect Shinto&apos; that was regarded as &apos;religion&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Broadly speaking, &apos;State Shinto&apos; was the use of Shinto practices to shore up public unity, while in a narrow sense it was Shinto that was controlled by the Bureau of Shinto Shrines of the prewar Ministry of Home Affairs, as opposed to &apos;Sect Shinto&apos;, which was regarded as a &apos;religion&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Broadly speaking, &apos;State Shinto&apos; was the use of Shinto practices to shore up public unity, while in a narrow sense it was Shinto that was controlled by the Bureau of Shinto Shrines of the prewar Ministry of Home Affairs, as opposed to &apos;Sect Shinto,&apos; which was regarded as a &apos;religion.&apos;</e>
<cmt>カンマ、ピリオドの位置</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>国家神道の定義によっては、内務省が神社を管掌する以前の神祇官、教部省による神社行政も含まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to definition of State Shinto, it includes shrine administration by the previous Jingikan (Department of Divinities) and Kyobusho (Ministry of Religion) before the prewar Ministry of Home Affairs took charge of shrines.</e>
<cmt>「神社行政」はshrine administrationと訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The definition of State Shinto also includes shrine administration, which was carried out by the earlier Jingikan (Department of Divinities) and Kyobusho (Ministry of Religion) before the Ministry of Home Affairs took charge of shrines.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The definition of State Shinto also includes shrine administration, which was carried out by the earlier Jingikan (Department of Divinities) and Kyobusho (Ministry of Religion) before the Ministry of Home Affairs took charge of shrines.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>大日本帝国憲法では文面上は信教の自由が明記されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Constitution of the Empire of Japan stipulated freedom of religion on its face.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Constitution of the Empire of Japan ostensibly stipulated freedom of religion.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Constitution of the Empire of Japan ostensibly stipulated freedom of religion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>しかし、政府は「神道は宗教ではない」(神社非宗教論)という公権法解釈に立脚し、憲法の信教の自由とは矛盾しないという「強弁」をして、これを公式見解としていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the government was based on an official interpretation or construction that &apos;Shinto was not a religion&apos; (Jinjahishukyoron (theory that Shinto is not a religion), &apos;insisted&apos; that it did not contradict the freedom of religion stipulated in the constitution and made this its official position.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the government was based on an official interpretation that &apos;Shinto was not a religion&apos; (&apos;Jinjahishukyoron&apos; in Japanese), &apos;insisting&apos; that it did not contradict the freedom of religion stipulated in the constitution and making this its official position.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the government was based on an official interpretation that &apos;Shinto was not a religion&apos; (&apos;Jinjahishukyoron&apos; in Japanese), &apos;insisting&apos; that it did not contradict the freedom of religion stipulated in the constitution and making this its official position.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>政府による「神社崇拝」の国民への強制の度合いは時代によって異なったが、1930年代初頭から太平洋戦争にかけての時期には、国家神道は戦争遂行の精神的支柱として重視された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The degree of forcing of &apos;worship of shrines&apos; to people by the government was different from age to age, but State Shinto was emphasized as an emotional prop for prosecution of war in the period from the beginning of the 1930&apos;s to the Pacific War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The extent to which people were forced by the government to participate in the &apos;worship of shrines&apos; varied with the times but, from the beginning of the 1930&apos;s to the Pacific War, State Shinto was emphasized as an emotional prop for the prosecution of war.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The extent to which people were forced by the government to participate in the &apos;worship of shrines&apos; varied with the times but, from the beginning of the 1930&apos;s to the Pacific War, State Shinto was emphasized as an emotional prop for the prosecution of war.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>官国幣社を内務省 (日本)神社局が所管し、新たな官国幣社の造営には公金が投入された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Bureau of Shinto shrines of the prewar Ministry of Home Affairs (Japan) took charge of Kankoku Heisha (general term for Kanpeisha and Kokuheisha that were high rank shrines) and built new Kankoku Heisha using public money.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ministry of Home Affairs&apos; Bureau of Shinto Shrines took charge of the &apos;kankoku heisha&apos; shrines (a general term for Imperial shrines [kanpeisha] and national shrines [kokuheisha]) and built new kankoku heisha shrines using public money.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ministry of Home Affairs&apos; Bureau of Shinto Shrines took charge of the &apos;kankoku heisha&apos; shrines (a general term for Imperial shrines (kanpeisha) and national shrines (kokuheisha)) and built new kankoku heisha shrines using public money.</e>
<cmt>カッコの表記</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>村社以上の社格の神社の例祭には地方官の奉幣が行われ、一種の国教的な制度であったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Local officials offered a wand with hemp and paper streamers to a Shinto god in reisai (regular festivals) of shrines with ranks of sonsha (village shrines) or higher, and it was said to be a kind of state religion system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Local officials offered wands made of hemp and paper streamers to the gods at the festivals of shrines with the rank of sonsha (village shrine) or higher, and it is considered to have been a kind of state religion system.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Local officials offered wands made of hemp and paper streamers to the gods at the festivals of shrines with the rank of sonsha (village shrine) or higher, and it is considered to have been a kind of state religion system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>第二次世界大戦後、GHQにより「神道指令」（国家神道の終焉）が出され、国家神道は解体へ向かったが、国家と神道を巡る政教関係については今日に至るまで議論の的となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After World War II, the GHQ issued the &apos;Shinto Directive&apos; (termination of State Shinto), and State Shinto was demised, but the relationship between the country and Shinto has been a topic of debate until now.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After World War II, GHQ issued the &apos;Shinto Directive&apos; (termination of State Shinto), and State Shinto was abolished, but debate over the relationship between the state and Shinto has continued up until today.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After World War II, GHQ issued the &apos;Shinto Directive&apos; (termination of State Shinto), and State Shinto was abolished, but debate over the relationship between the state and Shinto has continued up until today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>（日本国憲法第20条、信教の自由、政教分離原則、津地鎮祭訴訟参照）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Refer to Article 20 of the Constitution of Japan, freedom of religion, the principle of separation of government and religion, and the lawsuit over &quot;Jichinsai&quot; (a ceremony of purifying a building site, which was carried out by the Tsu Municipal Authority).)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Refer to &apos;Article 20 of the Constitution of Japan&apos;, &apos;freedom of religion&apos;, &apos;the principle of separation of government and religion&apos;, and &apos;the Tsu &quot;Jichinsai&quot; lawsuit&apos; [where Tsu Municipal Authority was sued for using public funds to hold a purification ceremony at a building site])</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Refer to &apos;Article 20 of the Constitution of Japan,&apos; &apos;freedom of religion,&apos; &apos;the principle of separation of government and religion,&apos; and &apos;the Tsu &quot;Jichinsai&quot; lawsuit&apos; (where Tsu Municipal Authority was sued for using public funds to hold a purification ceremony at a building site))</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置、カッコ</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>靖国神社は国家神道の象徴的存在とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasukuni-jinja Shrine is considered to be a symbol of State Shinto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasukuni-jinja Shrine is considered to be a symbol of State Shinto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasukuni-jinja Shrine is considered to be a symbol of State Shinto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>靖国神社は御霊信仰を基盤とし、初めは主に鎮魂を目的としたが、やがて慰霊、さらに顕彰へと展開した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasukuni-jinja Shrine is based on Goryo-shinko (a folk religious belief of avenging spirits) and it was mainly intended for repose of souls at first, but it was then aimed at memorial service and honouring.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasukuni-jinja Shrine was founded based on Goryo-shinko (a folk religious belief in avenging spirits) and was at first mainly intended for the repose of souls, but later evolved into a memorial and place to honor the dead.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasukuni-jinja Shrine was founded based on Goryo-shinko (a folk religious belief in avenging spirits) and was at first mainly intended for the repose of souls, but later evolved into a memorial and place to honor the dead.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>靖国神社は国民統合の精神的中核であり、戦死者を「神」とすることによって戦死を国民に肯定的に受け入れさせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasukuni-jinja Shrine is a spiritual core for integration of people, and made people accept death in battle by making the deceased &apos;gods&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasukuni-jinja Shrine was the spiritual core for the unification of the people, and made them accept death in battle by deifying the war dead.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasukuni-jinja Shrine was the spiritual core for the unification of the people, and made them accept death in battle by deifying the war dead.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>しかもこれに対する批判は禁止されており、天皇を神格化する国家体制形成を大きく支えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, criticism against this was prohibited and Yasukuni-jinja Shrine strongly supported the formation of the national polity that deified the Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, criticism against this was prohibited and Yasukuni-jinja Shrine strongly supported the formation of the national polity that deified the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, criticism against this was prohibited and Yasukuni-jinja Shrine strongly supported the formation of the national polity that deified the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="16">
<j>『古事記』『日本書紀』等の古典を根拠として万世一系の天皇が日本を統治すること、国家の中心に存在する天皇と国民との間に伝統的な強い紐帯があることを前提に、全国の神社は神祇官の元に組織化され、諸制度が整備された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the assumption that the Emperor of the unbroken imperial line governed Japan based on classics, such as &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters) and &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), and that there were traditional strong connections between the Emperor that existed at the center of the nation and people, shrines all over the country were organized under control of Jingikan (Department of Divinities) and various institutions were established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the premise that, based on ancient classics such as &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters) and &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), the Emperor ruled Japan as part of an unbroken imperial line, and that there were traditional strong connections between the Emperor at the center of the nation and the people, shrines all over the country were organized under the control of the Jingikan (Department of Divinities) and various institutions were established.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the premise that, based on ancient classics such as &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters) and &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), the Emperor ruled Japan as part of an unbroken imperial line, and that there were traditional strong connections between the Emperor at the center of the nation and the people, shrines all over the country were organized under the control of the Jingikan (Department of Divinities) and various institutions were established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>当初、全国の神社は全て官有となり、全神職は官吏待遇（神官）となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the beginning, all shrines in the country were brought under government ownership and all Shinto priests were treated as government officials (Shinto priests).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the beginning, all shrines in the country were brought under government ownership and all Shinto priests were treated as government officials (shinkan).</e>
<cmt>&quot;Shinto priests&quot;→&quot;shinkan&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the beginning, all shrines in the country were brought under government ownership and all Shinto priests were treated as government officials (shinkan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>だが、制度面として未成熟な部分があり、神官と呼ばれる官吏としての神職は伊勢神宮に奉仕する者のみとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But it was an immature institution and only the Shinto priests who served Ise-jingu Shrine were called government officials.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, some of the institutions remained undeveloped and only the priests who served at Ise-jingu Shrine became shinkan government officials.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, some of the institutions remained undeveloped and only the priests who served at Ise-jingu Shrine became shinkan government officials.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>官国幣社の神職には官等を配し、位階、勲等を付与した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Shinto priests of Kankoku Heisha (general term for Kanpeisha and Kokuheisha that were high rank shrines) were assigned official ranks, and given ikai (Court ranks), medals for merit and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The priests of kankoku heisha shrines were assigned official ranks and given ikai (Court ranks), medals for merit and so on.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The priests of kankoku heisha shrines were assigned official ranks and given ikai (Court ranks), medals for merit and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>その多くは判任待遇としたが、一部は奏任官待遇（高等官）とし、叙位の恩典も与え、退職後の恩給制度も整備した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most of them were treated as junior officials, but some were treated as the offices originally selected as candidates by the Prime Minister, and given a special dispensation of conferment of a court rank, and a pension system after retirement was established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most of them were treated as junior officials, but some were treated as high-level bureaucrats, received a court rank as a special privilege, and a pension system for after retirement was also established.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most of them were treated as junior officials, but some were treated as high-level bureaucrats, received a court rank as a special privilege, and a pension system after retirement was also established.</e>
<cmt>forを削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="21">
<j>信教の自由は近代国家を樹立する上で必要とされたため、1889年発布の大日本帝国憲法下でも認められていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since freedom of religion was necessary to build a modern state, it was also accepted in the Constitution of the Empire of Japan promulgated in 1889.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since freedom of religion was necessary to build a modern state, it was included in the Constitution of the Empire of Japan promulgated in 1889.</e>
<cmt>&quot;also accepted&quot;→&quot;included&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since freedom of religion was necessary to build a modern state, it was included in the Constitution of the Empire of Japan promulgated in 1889.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>大日本帝国憲法第28条の条文では「日本臣民ハ安寧秩序ヲ妨ケス及臣民タルノ義務ニ背カサル限ニ於テ信教ノ自由ヲ有ス」となっていたが、この「臣民タルノ義務」の範囲は立法段階で議論の的となっており、起草者である伊藤博文・井上毅は神社への崇敬は臣民の義務に含まれないという見解を持っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Article 28 of the Constitution of the Empire of Japan stipulated that &apos;Japanese subjects had freedom of religion unless they disturbed peace and order or evaded their duties of people&apos;, but the scope of the &quot;duties of people&apos; was a topic of debate at the stage of lawmaking, Hirobumi ITO and Kowashi INOUE who drafted the constitution had an opinion that the worship of shrines was not included in the duties of subjects.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Article 28 of the Constitution of the Empire of Japan stipulated that &quot;Japanese subjects shall, within limits not prejudicial to peace and order, and not antagonistic to their duties as subjects, enjoy freedom of religious belief&quot;, but the scope of their &apos;duties as subjects&apos; was a topic of debate at the lawmaking stage, with Hirobumi ITO and Kowashi INOUE, who helped draft the constitution, of the opinion that the veneration of shrines was not included in the duties of subjects.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, changed translation of Article 28 to Miyoji Ito&apos;s translation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Article 28 of the Constitution of the Empire of Japan stipulated that &quot;Japanese subjects shall, within limits not prejudicial to peace and order, and not antagonistic to their duties as subjects, enjoy freedom of religious belief,&quot; but the scope of their &apos;duties as subjects&apos; was a topic of debate at the lawmaking stage, with Hirobumi ITO and Kowashi INOUE, who helped draft the constitution, of the opinion that the veneration of shrines was not included in the duties of subjects.</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>昭和に入ってから美濃部達吉や神社局 には神社崇敬を憲法上の臣民の義務ととらえる姿勢があったが、内務省の公式の憲法解釈として発せられることはなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Showa period, Tatsukichi MINOBE and the Bureau of Shinto shrines considered that the worship of shrines was one of the constitutional duties of subjects, but it was not issued as a formal constitutional interpretation by the prewar Ministry of Home Affairs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Showa period, Tatsukichi MINOBE and the Bureau of Shinto shrines considered that shrine veneration was one of the constitutional duties of subjects, but it was not issued as a formal constitutional interpretation by the prewar Ministry of Home Affairs.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the worship of shrines&quot;→&quot;shrine veneration&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Showa period, Tatsukichi MINOBE and the Bureau of Shinto shrines considered that shrine veneration was one of the constitutional duties of subjects, but it was not issued as a formal constitutional interpretation by the prewar Ministry of Home Affairs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="24">
<j>宗教的な信仰と、神社と神社で行われる祭祀への敬礼は区分されたが、他宗教への礼拝を一切否定した完全一神教の視点を持つキリスト教徒や、厳格な政教分離を主張した浄土真宗との間に軋轢を生んだ面もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Religious belief was differentiated from salutation in shrines or in rituals performed in the shrines, but it caused discord with Christians who had a perfect monotheistic belief that denied the worship of other religions or Jodo Shinshu (the True Pure Land Sect of Buddhism) that insisted on strict separation of government and religion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Religious belief was differentiated from paying reverence in shrines or in shrine rituals, but it caused discord among Christians, who were totally monotheistic and repudiated the worship of other religions, or followers of Jodo Shinshu (the True Pure Land Sect of Buddhism), which insisted on the strict separation of government and religion.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Religious belief was differentiated from paying reverence in shrines or in shrine rituals, but it caused discord among Christians, who were totally monotheistic and repudiated the worship of other religions, or followers of Jodo Shinshu (the True Pure Land Sect of Buddhism), which insisted on the strict separation of government and religion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>また1889年の勅令第12号によって官立・私立の全ての学校での宗教教育が禁止され、「宗教ではない」とされた国家神道は宗教を超越した教育の基礎とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Education of religions in all public and private schools was prohibited by imperial edict 12 in 1889, and State Shinto which was said to be &apos;not a religion&apos; was used as a basis for education that transcended religions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Religious education in all public and private schools was prohibited by Imperial Edict 12 in 1889, and State Shinto, which was said to be &apos;not a religion&apos;, was used as the basis for education that transcended religion.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Religious education in all public and private schools was prohibited by Imperial Edict 12 in 1889, and State Shinto, which was said to be &apos;not a religion,&apos; was used as the basis for education that transcended religion.</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>翌1890年には教育勅語が発布され、国民道徳の基本が示され、国家神道は宗教・政治・教育を一体のものとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Imperial Rescript on Education was issued the next year (in 1890), the basics of national morality were shown and State Shinto integrated religions, politics and education.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following year, 1890, the Imperial Rescript on Education was issued, pointing out the basics of national morality and State Shinto integrated religion, politics and education.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following year, 1890, the Imperial Rescript on Education was issued, pointing out the basics of national morality and State Shinto integrated religion, politics and education.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>近世との関係</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Relationship with modern times</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Relationship with the post-feudal era</e>
<cmt>Since State Shinto was from the late 19th century to the end of World War 2, I don&apos;t think modern is appropriate</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Relationship with the post-feudal era</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="27">
<j>応仁の乱の際に、律令制のもとで神社を管掌した神祇官の庁舎が焼失してしまい、以来吉田家・白川伯王家が私邸を神祇官代として祭祀と神社管掌を継続していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The building of the Jingikan (Department of Divinities) that managed shrines under the Ritsuryo system was burned in the Onin War and the Yoshida family and the Shirakawahakuo family continued to manage religious services and shrines with their private houses as Jingikandai.</e>
<cmt>「神祇官代」は、神祇官と同じような名称のようですが、内容が不明なためJingikandaiとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The building that housed the Jingikan, which managed shrines under the Ritsuryo system, was burned down in the Onin War and the Yoshida family and the Shirakawahakuo family continued to manage religious services and shrines with their private houses as Jingikandai.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The building that housed the Jingikan, which managed shrines under the Ritsuryo system, was burned down in the Onin War and the Yoshida family and the Shirakawahakuo family continued to manage religious services and shrines with their private houses as Jingikandai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>特に吉田家は寺社法度の制定によって江戸幕府より神社管掌を公認されていたため、これを一手に引き受けていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In particular, the Yoshida family was approved by the Edo bakufu to manage shrines by establishing Jisha Hatto (Acts governing temples and shrines) and assumed all the responsibilities.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In particular, the Yoshida family, by the enactment of Jisha Hatto (Acts governing temples and shrines) which gave it authorization from the Edo bakufu to manage shrines, assumed all the responsibilities.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In particular, the Yoshida family, by the enactment of Jisha Hatto (Acts governing temples and shrines) which gave it authorization from the Edo bakufu to manage shrines, assumed all the responsibilities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="29">
<j>幕末になると黒船来航を初めとする外交問題が発生した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Diplomatic issues, such as the arrival of the Black Ships, occurred at the end of the Edo period, the Imperial Court and the Edo bakufu prayed for expulsion of the foreigners in main temples and shrines throughout the country, and revival of Jingikan (Department of Divinities) was called for by the public due to flourishing of the study of Japanese classical literature to save the nation in a great crisis.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The end of the Edo period saw diplomatic issues caused by the arrival of the Black Ships, the Imperial Court and the Edo bakufu praying in main temples and shrines throughout the country for the expulsion of the foreigners, and the public, due to a flourishing of the study of Japanese classical literature, calling for the revival of the Jingikan to save the nation in a time of crisis.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Starting with the arrival of the Black Ships, the end of the Edo period encountered diplomatic issues.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>朝廷と江戸幕府は全国の有力社寺に攘夷の祈願をおこなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Imperial Court and the Edo bakufu offered a prayer in main temples and shrines throughout the country for the expulsion of the foreigners.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>また、民間では国学の隆盛から国難打開のために神祇官再興論が浮上していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also the public, due to a flourishing of the study of Japanese classical literature, called for the revival of the Jingikan to save the nation in a time of crisis.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>特にペリーの来航について幕府は直に朝廷に奏聞し、以後、幕府は外交問題について朝廷の判断を仰ぐようになったことから朝廷の権威にふたたび日が差すようになり、尊王攘夷思想・討幕運動と相まって王政復古 (日本)の実現へと繋がった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In particular, the bakufu reported the arrival of Perry to the Emperor immediately, and then came to seek a judgment of the Imperial Court concerning diplomatic issues, and the authority of the Imperial Court revived, leading to realization of the restoration of imperial rule (Japan) with antiforeign imperialism and anti-shogunate movement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In particular, the bakufu reported the arrival of Perry to the Emperor immediately, and thereafter came to seek Imperial Court&apos;s decisions concerning diplomatic issues, which revived the Imperial Court&apos;s authority and, together with the Sonno Joi (Revere the Emperor, Expel the Barbarians) and anti-shogunate movements, led to the realization of the restoration of imperial rule.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In particular, the bakufu reported the arrival of Perry to the Emperor immediately, and thereafter came to seek Imperial Court&apos;s decisions concerning diplomatic issues, which revived the Imperial Court&apos;s authority and, together with the Sonno Joi (Revere the Emperor, Expel the Barbarians) and anti-shogunate movements, led to the realization of the restoration of imperial rule.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="33">
<j>かくなる上で、幕府の大政奉還の後、明治維新は慶応三年十二月九日の王政復古の大号令によってその幕を開いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, after the Taisei Hokan (transfer of power back to the Emperor) by the bakufu, the Meiji Restoration began with a declaration of the restoration of imperial rule on December 9, 1867.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, after the bakufu transferred power back to the Emperor, the Meiji Restoration began with a declaration of the restoration of imperial rule on December 9, 1867.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, after the bakufu transferred power back to the Emperor, the Meiji Restoration began with a declaration of the restoration of imperial rule on December 9, 1867.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>平田篤胤の思想に共鳴した平田派の神道家たち、また津和野藩出身の国学者たちは明治維新の精神を神武天皇の精神に基くものとし、近代日本を王政復古による祭政一致の国家とすることを提唱していたが、王政復古の大号令には王政復古と神武天皇の語が見え、従来理想として唱えられていた王政復古と「諸事神武創業ノ始ニ原」くことが、実際の国家創生に際して現実性を帯び、「万機御一新」のスローガンとして公的な意義を持つようになったのであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shintoists of Hirata-ha school who sympathized with the way of thinking of Atsutane HIRATA and scholars of Japanese classical literature from the Tsuwano Domain proposed that the spirit of the Meiji Restoration should be based on the spirit of Emperor Jammu and modern Japan should be a country of saisei icchi (unity of church and state, theocracy) by the restoration of imperial rule, and there are such words as the restoration of imperial rule and Emperor Jammu in the declaration of the restoration of imperial rule, and the restoration of imperial rule that was advocated as an ideal before and &apos;doing everything as in the time of Emperor Jammu&apos; became reality when building an actual country and had a public significance as a slogan of &apos;renewal o everything&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shintoists of the Hirata-ha school, who sympathized with Atsutane HIRATA&apos;s way of thinking, and scholars of Japanese classical literature from Tsuwano Domain proposed that the spirit of the Meiji Restoration should be based on the spirit of Emperor Jimmu and the restoration of imperial rule should make modern Japan a country of &apos;saisei icchi&apos; (unity of religion and state) and the declaration of the restoration of imperial rule contains the phrases &quot;restoration of imperial rule&quot; and &quot;Emperor Jimmu&quot;; the restoration of imperial rule and &apos;doing everything as in the time of Emperor Jimmu&apos;, which until then had been advocated as ideals, became reality when building an actual country and took on public significance with the slogan of &apos;renewal of everything&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity but I think this needs splitting into 2 or 3 parts</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shintoists of the Hirata-ha school, who sympathized with Atsutane HIRATA&apos;s way of thinking, and scholars of Japanese classical literature from Tsuwano Domain proposed that the spirit of the Meiji Restoration should be based on the spirit of Emperor Jimmu and the restoration of imperial rule should make modern Japan a country of &apos;saisei icchi&apos; (unity of religion and state) and the declaration of the restoration of imperial rule contains the phrases &quot;restoration of imperial rule&quot; and &quot;Emperor Jimmu&quot;; the restoration of imperial rule and &apos;doing everything as in the time of Emperor Jimmu,&apos; which until then had been advocated as ideals, became reality when building an actual country and took on public significance with the slogan of &apos;renewal of everything.&apos;</e>
<cmt>カンマ、ピリオドの位置</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="35">
<j>明治政府は新政府樹立の基本精神である祭政一致の実現と、開国以来の治安問題(浦上四番崩れなど)に発展していたキリスト教流入の防御のため、律令制の崩壊以降衰えていた神祇官を復興させ、中世以来混沌とした様相を見せていた神道の組織整備をおこなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Meiji Government restored the Jingikan (Department of Divinities) that had been declining since the collapse of the Ritsuryo system and reorganized Shinto that sank to a state of chaos in and after the Medieval Period to realize saisei icchi (unity of church and state, theocracy) which was a basic spirit for building the new government and to prevent inflow of Christianity that caused problems of public order (Urakamiyobankuzure (oppression for Christians in Nagasaki)) since the opening of a country.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to realize &apos;saisei icchi&apos;, which was the basic spirit of the Meiji Government, and to prevent an influx of Christianity which, since the opening up of the country, had created public order problems (such as the Urakami Yoban Kuzure crackdown on Christians), the new government restored the Jingikan, which had been in decline since the collapse of the Ritsuryo system and reorganized Shinto, which had been in a state of chaos since the Medieval Period.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to realize &apos;saisei icchi,&apos; which was the basic spirit of the Meiji Government, and to prevent an influx of Christianity which, since the opening up of the country, had created public order problems (such as the Urakami Yoban Kuzure crackdown on Christians), the new government restored the Jingikan, which had been in decline since the collapse of the Ritsuryo system and reorganized Shinto, which had been in a state of chaos since the Medieval Period.</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>「国家神道」の語の用例</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Examples of use of term &apos;State Shinto&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Examples of use of the term &apos;State Shinto&apos;</e>
<cmt>Article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Examples of use of the term &apos;State Shinto&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="36">
<j>「国家神道」の語彙は第二次世界大戦前より存在し、議会や神道学、内務省、陸軍省などでは「国家神道」およびその同義語を用いている例がみられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term &apos;State Shinto&apos; existed before the World War II and there were some examples in which the term &apos;State Shinto&apos; or its synonyms were used in assemblies, Shinto studies, the prewar Ministry of Home Affairs, and the Department of War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term &apos;State Shinto&apos; existed before World War II and there are some examples of the term or its synonyms being used in assemblies, Shinto studies, the prewar Ministry of Home Affairs, and the Department of War.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term &apos;State Shinto&apos; existed before World War II and there are some examples of the term or its synonyms being used in assemblies, Shinto studies, the prewar Ministry of Home Affairs, and the Department of War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="37">
<j>1911年（明治44年）2月、小田貫一衆議院議員「国家神道ト云フモノハ明カニ分ツテ居タ」「神社局ニ於テハ国家神道ナルモノヲ扱ヒ、宗教局ニ於テハ耶蘇、仏法及神道ノ各派ニ属スルトコロノ、即チ宗教神道ヲ支配スル」（帝国議会における発言）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In February 1911, House of Representatives member Kanichi ODA said &apos;What was called State Shinto was clearly known&apos;, &apos;the Bureau of Shinto shrines treats State Shinto, the Bureau of Religions manages Christianity, Buddhism and religion Shinto that includes various schools of Shinto&apos; (speech in the imperial Diet).</e>
<cmt>「宗教神道」はreligion Shintoとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In February 1911, House of Representatives member Kanichi ODA said in a speech to the Imperial Diet, &quot;It was clearly understood what was meant by State Shinto...the Bureau of Shinto Shrines treats State Shinto and the Bureau of Religions manages Christianity, Buddhism and the various sects of Shinto, that is, religious Shinto&quot;.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In February 1911, House of Representatives member Kanichi ODA said in a speech to the Imperial Diet, &quot;It was clearly understood what was meant by State Shinto...the Bureau of Shinto Shrines treats State Shinto and the Bureau of Religions manages Christianity, Buddhism and the various sects of Shinto, that is, religious Shinto.&quot;</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>1924年（大正13年）、加藤玄知（陸軍士官学校教授・東京帝国大学神道講座助教授）は「神道」を「宗派的神道」と「国家的神道」とに分け、さらに「国家的神道」を「神社神道」と「国体神道」とに区分する説を立てた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1924, Genchi KATO (professor of Army War College, military academy, associate professor of the Shinto course, Tokyo Imperial University) advocated a theory that divided &apos;Shinto&apos; into &apos;religious Shinto&apos; and &apos;national Shinto&apos; and further divided &apos;national Shinto&apos; into &apos;Jinja Shinto (Shrine Shinto)&apos; and &apos;Kokutai Shinto (National Structure Shinto)&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1924, Genchi KATO (a professor at the Imperial Japanese Army Academy and associate professor of Shinto at Tokyo Imperial University) advocated a theory that divided &apos;Shinto&apos; into &apos;religious Shinto&apos; and &apos;national Shinto&apos; and further divided &apos;national Shinto&apos; into &apos;Jinja (or Shrine) Shinto&apos; and &apos;Kokutai (or national structure) Shinto&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1924, Genchi KATO (a professor at the Imperial Japanese Army Academy and associate professor of Shinto at Tokyo Imperial University) advocated a theory that divided &apos;Shinto&apos; into &apos;religious Shinto&apos; and &apos;national Shinto&apos; and further divided &apos;national Shinto&apos; into &apos;Jinja (or Shrine) Shinto&apos; and &apos;Kokutai (or national structure) Shinto.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="39">
<j>1941年（昭和16年）、宮地直一（内務省 (日本)神社局考証課課長、東京帝国大学教授など）は「大化改新は、祭祀に始まり、惟神の道によりて樹立せられし国家中興の大業にして、此時に振起せられし国家神道の精神は、此後久しきに亘り持続せられて」 などと、「国家神道」の語を頻繁に用いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1941, Anoka MIYAJI (manager of Kahoka ((historical) investigation section) of the Bureau of Shinto shrines of the prewar Ministry of Home Affairs (Japan), professor of Tokyo Imperial University) used the term &apos;State Shinto&apos; frequently by saying &apos;the Taka Reforms was a great achievement of restoration/rejuvenate of the country in accordance with kannagara no micho (Shinto, the Way of the Gods) beginning with religious service and the spirit of State Shinto cultivated at this time will last perpetually&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1941, Anoka MIYAJI (head of the historical research section at the Ministry of Home Affairs&apos; Bureau of Shinto Shrines and a professor at Tokyo Imperial University) used the term &apos;State Shinto&apos; on several occasions, such as &quot;beginning with religious services, the Taika Reform accomplished the great achievement of reviving the country in accordance with &apos;kannagara no michi&apos; (the Way of the Gods), and the spirit of State Shinto cultivated at this time will last perpetually&quot;.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1941, Naoichi MIYAJI (head of the historical research section at the Ministry of Home Affairs&apos; Bureau of Shinto Shrines and a professor at Tokyo Imperial University) used the term &apos;State Shinto&apos; on several occasions, such as &quot;beginning with religious services, the Taika Reform accomplished the great achievement of reviving the country in accordance with &apos;kannagara no michi&apos; (the Way of the Gods), and the spirit of State Shinto cultivated at this time will last perpetually.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Anoka→Naoichi, ピリオドの位置</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="40">
<j>ただし、教派神道の「『神道各派』から区別された神ながらの道は特に国家神道とも呼ばれるが、法律家や行政実務家は以前からそれを神社と呼ぶのが例」であり、「国家神道」の語は政治家や内務省 (日本)、その神社局、陸軍上層部、神道学などの場での専門用語であって、一般民衆に流通した語彙ではなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, &apos;the Way of the Gods (Shintoism) that was differentiated from &quot;each school of Shinto&quot; of Sect Shinto was also especially called State Shinto, but was customarily called shrines by lawyers and administration practitioners&apos;, the term &apos;State Shinto&apos; was a technical term used in the Bureau of Shinto shrines, the top military brass of the army, Shinto studies, and so on and was not used by the general public.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, &quot;though it was the &apos;Way of the Gods&apos;, distinct from &apos;each Shinto sect&apos; of Sect Shinto, in particular that was called State Shinto, it was customarily known as &apos;shrines&apos; (jinja) by lawyers and administrators&quot;, the term &apos;State Shinto&apos; being a technical term used by the Bureau of Shinto Shrines, the top brass in the army, Shinto scholars and so on, and not by the general public.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, &quot;though it was the &apos;Way of the Gods,&apos; distinct from &apos;each Shinto sect&apos; of Sect Shinto, in particular that was called State Shinto, it was customarily known as &apos;shrines&apos; (jinja) by lawyers and administrators,&quot; the term &apos;State Shinto&apos; being a technical term used by the Bureau of Shinto Shrines, the top brass in the army, Shinto scholars and so on, and not by the general public.</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>現在では「神社」の語義が変化しているため、「神社」ではなく「国家神道」の語をもちいるのが通例である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the meaning of the term &apos;jinja&apos; changes currently, it is usually the case that the term &apos;State Shinto&apos; is used rather than &apos;jinja&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the meaning of &apos;jinja&apos; is currently changing,, it is usually the case that the term &apos;State Shinto&apos; is used rather than &apos;jinja&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the meaning of &apos;jinja&apos; is currently changing,, it is usually the case that the term &apos;State Shinto&apos; is used rather than &apos;jinja.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>非宗教説・宗教説と教義</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Non-religion theory/religion theory and creeds</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Non-religion/religion theories and creeds</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Non-religion/religion theories and creeds</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="42">
<j>「国家神道」を宗教ではないとする説と宗教であるとする説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a theory that states that &apos;State Shinto&apos; is not a religion and another theory that states that it is.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a theory that states that &apos;State Shinto&apos; is not a religion and another theory that states that it is.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a theory that states that &apos;State Shinto&apos; is not a religion and another theory that states that it is.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>非宗教説は、敬神を国民の義務とし、この義務は道徳の範疇にあるので、神社・軍隊・学校・官公庁などにおける敬神は宗教ではないとする説である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The non-religion theory says that reverence is a duty of people but since this duty falls into a category of morality, reverence in shrines, army, schools and public offices is not a religion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The non-religion theory says that piety is a duty of the people and this duty is one category of morality, therefore piety towards shrines, the army, schools and public offices is not a religion.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The non-religion theory says that piety is a duty of the people and this duty is one category of morality, therefore piety towards shrines, the army, schools and public offices is not a religion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>宗教説はこれを詭弁とするものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The religion theory regards it a paradox.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The religion theory says this is just sophistry.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The religion theory says this is just sophistry.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="45">
<j>菱木政晴は世界には言語による教義表現を軽視する宗教もあり、宗教学や文化人類学の成果をもちいることによって困難なく抽出可能であるとして以下のようにまとめている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masaharu HISHIKI said that there were some religions that disregard representation of creeds by language in the world and it can be extracted easily by using results of science of religion and cultural anthropology and summarized as follows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masaharu HISHIKI said that some religions in the world place little value on expressing doctrine in words, but using the results of religious studies and cultural anthropology, State Shinto doctrines can be extracted without difficulty, and summarizes them as follows:</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masaharu HISHIKI said that some religions in the world place little value on expressing doctrine in words, but using the results of religious studies and cultural anthropology, State Shinto doctrines can be extracted without difficulty, and summarizes them as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="46">
<j>聖戦</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Crusade</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Holy War</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Holy War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>- 自国の戦闘行為は常に正しく、それに参加することは崇高な義務である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">- Military actions of your own country are always correct and participation in them is a lofty duty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">- hostile acts by one&apos;s own country are always right and participation in them is a noble duty.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">- hostile acts by one&apos;s own country are always right and participation in them is a noble duty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="48">
<j>英霊</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eirei (spirits of the war dead)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eirei (spirits of the war dead)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eirei (spirits of the war dead)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>- そうした戦闘に従事して死ねば神になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">- If you die in such a battle, you become a god.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">- those who die in such battles become gods.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">- those who die in such battles become gods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>そのために死んだ者をまつる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those who died for that purpose are enshrined.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore the dead are enshrined</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore the dead are enshrined.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="51">
<j>顕彰</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Honouring</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Honoring</e>
<cmt>Changed to US spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Honoring</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>- それ（英霊）を模範とし、それに見習って後につづけ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">- Model after them (the spirits of the war dead) and follow them by learning from them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">- make them (the spirits of the war dead) a model and follow them by learning from them.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">- make them (the spirits of the war dead) a model and follow them by learning from them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="53">
<j>そして、「顕彰教義に埋め込まれた侵略への動員という政治目的を、聖戦教義・英霊教義の宗教的トリックで粉飾するもの」と指摘している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He pointed out that &apos;the political purpose of mobilizing people for invasion which was included in honouring creeds was embellished with a religious trick of creeds of crusade and Eirei (spirits of the war dead)&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He pointed out that &apos;the political purpose of mobilizing people for invasion, which was embedded in the doctrine of honoring, was embellished with the religious tricks of the crusade and Eirei doctrines&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He pointed out that &apos;the political purpose of mobilizing people for invasion, which was embedded in the doctrine of honoring, was embellished with the religious tricks of the crusade and Eirei doctrines.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>また、国家神道の教義の中心を「天皇現人神思想」や「万世一系思想」とする意見もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some say that the core of the creeds of State Shinto is an &apos;idea of Emperor Arahitogami (kami who appears in this world in human form)&apos; and an &apos;idea of unbroken imperial line&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some say that the core of State Shinto doctrine is the &apos;idea of the Emperor Arahitogami (kami who appears in this world in human form)&apos; and the &apos;idea of an unbroken imperial line&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some say that the core of State Shinto doctrine is the &apos;idea of the Emperor Arahitogami (kami who appears in this world in human form)&apos; and the &apos;idea of an unbroken imperial line.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="55">
<j>柳川啓一は「国家神道は明確な教義を有していた」として以下の4点を挙げている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keiichi YANAGAWA said that &apos;State Shinto had clear creeds&apos; and showed the following four points.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keiichi YANAGAWA said that &apos;State Shinto had clear doctrines&apos; and offered the following four.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keiichi YANAGAWA said that &apos;State Shinto had clear doctrines&apos; and offered the following four.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="56">
<j>天皇は、神話的祖先である天照大神から万世一系の血統をつぐ神の子孫であり、自ら現人神である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emperor is a descendent of a god that ran in the unbroken imperial line from Amaterasu Omikami (the Sun Goddess) which was a mythical ancestor and he himself is an arahitogami (kami who appears in this world in human form).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emperor is descended from the gods in an unbroken imperial line going back to the mythical ancestor, Amaterasu Omikami (the Sun Goddess), and he himself is an arahitogami.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emperor is descended from the gods in an unbroken imperial line going back to the mythical ancestor, Amaterasu Omikami (the Sun Goddess), and he himself is an arahitogami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="57">
<j>『古事記』、『日本書紀』の神話の国土の形成、天壌無窮の神勅にみえるように、日本は特別に神の保護を受けた神国である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As shown in the tale of creation of a country and tenjomukyu (as eternal as heaven and earth) no shinchoku (oracle) in the myths of &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters) and &quot;&quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), Japan is a land of the gods, which is specially protected by them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As shown in the Tenjumukyu oracle and the creation myths in &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters) and &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), Japan is a land of the gods and is specially protected by them.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As shown in the Tenjumukyu oracle and the creation myths in &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters) and &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), Japan is a land of the gods and is specially protected by them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="58">
<j>日本は世界を救済する使命がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan takes up a mission to save the world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan has a mission to save the world.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan has a mission to save the world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>他国への進出は聖戦として意味づけられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Invasion into other countries was considered as a crusade.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Invading other countries was considered a holy war.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Invading other countries was considered a holy war.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="60">
<j>道徳の面においては、天皇は親であり、臣民は子であるから、天皇への忠は孝ともなるという忠孝一本説。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to a theory that loyalty to your lord is the same as filial piety, loyalty to the Emperor is filial piety since the Emperor is a parent and subjects are children from the aspect of morality.</e>
<cmt>「忠孝一本説」は、a theory that loyalty to your lord is the same as filial pietyと解釈しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From a moral aspect, the Emperor is a parent and his subjects are children so following the theory that loyalty to your lord is the same as filial piety, loyalty to the Emperor is filial piety.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From a moral aspect, the Emperor is a parent and his subjects are children so following the theory that loyalty to your lord is the same as filial piety, loyalty to the Emperor is filial piety.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>主な国家神道政策</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Main State Shinto policies</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Main State Shinto policies</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Main State Shinto policies</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>神仏分離</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Separation of Buddhism and Shintoism</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Separation of Buddhism and Shintoism</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Separation of Buddhism and Shintoism</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>社格制度</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shrine Ranking System</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shrine Ranking System</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shrine Ranking System</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>宣教</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Missionary work</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Missionary work</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Missionary work</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>人物の顕彰のための神社造営</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Construction of shrines for honouring people</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Construction of shrines for honouring people</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Construction of shrines for honouring people</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="61">
<j>橿原神宮、平安神宮、明治神宮などの天皇や皇族を祀る神社や湊川神社、四條畷神社などの功績のある人物をまつる神社（建武中興十五社など）が数多く造営された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A lot of shrines that enshrine emperors and imperial families, such as Kashihara-jingu Shrine, Heian Jingu Shrine and Meiji-jingu Shrine, and shrines (the fifteen Shinto shrines enshrining the royalty and military commanders in the Southern Court side who contributed to the Kenmu Restoration and so on) that enshrine meritorious people, such as Minatogawa-jinja Shrine and Shijonawate-jinja Shrine, were built.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A lot of shrines were built to enshrine emperors and the imperial family, such as Kashihara-jingu Shrine, Heian-jingu Shrine and Meiji-jingu Shrine, and to enshrine meritorious people, such as Minatogawa-jinja Shrine and Shijonawate-jinja Shrine (as well as the fifteen &apos;Kenmu Chuko&apos; shrines that enshrine royalty and military commanders from the Southern Court side who contributed to the Kenmu Restoration).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A lot of shrines were built to enshrine emperors and the imperial family, such as Kashihara-jingu Shrine, Heian-jingu Shrine and Meiji-jingu Shrine, and to enshrine meritorious people, such as Minatogawa-jinja Shrine and Shijonawate-jinja Shrine (as well as the fifteen &apos;Kenmu Chuko&apos; shrines that enshrine royalty and military commanders from the Southern Court side who contributed to the Kenmu Restoration).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>靖國神社・護国神社</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasukuni-jinja Shrine and Gokoku-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasukuni-jinja Shrine and Gokoku-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasukuni-jinja Shrine and Gokoku-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="62">
<j>靖國神社は国家からの免税、祭祀料の支給、毎年の「寄付金」の交付、天皇家よりの下賜金など、特別な優遇を与えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasukuni-jinja Shrine was given special benefits, such as tax exemption, supply of a grant of money for religious service, delivery of annual &apos;donations&apos; and imperial donation from the imperial family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasukuni-jinja Shrine was given special benefits, such as tax exemption, a grant of money for religious services, delivery of annual &apos;donations&apos; and an imperial donation from the imperial family.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasukuni-jinja Shrine was given special benefits, such as tax exemption, a grant of money for religious services, delivery of annual &apos;donations&apos; and an imperial donation from the imperial family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>神社合祀政策</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shrine merger policy</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shrine merger policy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shrine merger policy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="63">
<j>江戸時代、会津藩や岡山藩、水戸藩、長州藩、津和野藩では、批判論が出るなどの議論が続く中で、小祠や淫祠の廃止・統合がおこなわれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Edo period, discussions took place and criticism was aroused, but the Aizu, Okayama, Choshu and Tsuwano clans abolished or integrated shoshi (small shrines) and shrines of evil deity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Edo period, amidst discussion and criticism, Aizu, Okayama, Mito, Choshu and Tsuwano domains abolished or integrated shoshi (small shrines) and shrines to evil deities.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Edo period, amidst discussion and criticism, Aizu, Okayama, Mito, Choshu and Tsuwano domains abolished or integrated shoshi (small shrines) and shrines to evil deities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>このうち、水戸藩の神社合祀政策を特に「八幡改め」と称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The shrine merger policy of the Mito clan was specially called &apos;Hachiman aratame (Hachiman-jinja Shrine reformation)&apos;.</e>
<cmt>「八幡改め」はHachiman aratame (Hachiman-jinja Shrine reformation)としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In particular, Mito domain&apos;s shrine merger policy was called &apos;Hachiman aratame&apos; (Hachiman-jinja Shrine reformation).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In particular, Mito domain&apos;s shrine merger policy was called &apos;Hachiman aratame&apos; (Hachiman-jinja Shrine reformation).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>これは旧支配者佐竹氏が尊崇した八幡神社を破壊し、みずから崇拝する鹿島神宮に置き換える運動である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This movement destroyed Hachiman-jinja Shrine that was worshipped by the former governor, the Satake clan, and replaced it with Kashima-jingu Shrine that was revered by the Mito clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This movement destroyed Hachiman-jinja Shrine, which was worshipped by the former governors, the Satake Clan, and replaced it with Kashima-jingu Shrine, which was revered by the Mito Clan.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This movement destroyed Hachiman-jinja Shrine, which was worshipped by the former governors, the Satake Clan, and replaced it with Kashima-jingu Shrine, which was revered by the Mito Clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="66">
<j>明治になると、神祇官は神社の調査が済むまで神社の整理をおこなわない方針をとった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Meiji period, Jingikan (Department of Divinities) determined a policy that it did not reorganize shrines until their investigation finished.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Meiji period, the Jingikan adopted a policy of not reorganizing shrines until its investigations were finished.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Meiji period, the Jingikan adopted a policy of not reorganizing shrines until its investigations were finished.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="67">
<j>1876年以降、教部省はこの方針を変更して近代社格制度や仏堂の整理を開始した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1876, Kyobusho (Ministry of Religion) changed this policy and started to streamline the modern Shrine Ranking System and butsu-do (Buddha statue halls).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1876, the Kyobusho (Ministry of Religion) changed this policy and started to reorganize the modern Shrine Ranking System and butsu-do (Buddha statue halls).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1876, the Kyobusho (Ministry of Religion) changed this policy and started to reorganize the modern Shrine Ranking System and butsu-do (Buddha statue halls).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="68">
<j>1906年(明治39年)12月、一町村一社を原則に統廃合をおこなうとする「神社合祀令」が出された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In December 1906, a &apos;Shrine Merger order&apos; was issued to integrate or abolish shrines so that there was a shrine in each town or village in principle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In December 1906, a &apos;Shrine Merger order&apos; was issued to integrate or abolish shrines so that there was, in principle, one shrine in each town or village.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In December 1906, a &apos;Shrine Merger order&apos; was issued to integrate or abolish shrines so that there was, in principle, one shrine in each town or village.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>同年以来、内務省 (日本)は数年間かけて神社の整理事業をおこなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since then, the prewar Ministry of Home Affairs (Japan) carried out a shrine reorganization project for several years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That same year, the prewar Ministry of Home Affairs carried out a shrine reorganization project that lasted several years.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That same year, the prewar Ministry of Home Affairs carried out a shrine reorganization project that lasted several years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>神社整理というと一般にはこの頃の事業を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reorganization of shrines generally refers to the project that was done at this time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reorganization of shrines generally refers to the project that was carried out at this time.</e>
<cmt>&quot;done&quot;→&quot;carried out&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reorganization of shrines generally refers to the project that was carried out at this time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>合祀が著しかったのが三重県と和歌山県で、三重県の6500社の神社が7分の一以下に、和歌山県の3700社の神社が6分の1以下に合祀された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shrine merger was performed significantly in Mie Prefecture and Wakayama Prefecture; 6500 shrines in Mie Prefecture decreased to 1/7 or less and 3700 shrines in Wakayama Prefecture decreased to 1/6 or less.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shrine mergers were performed significantly in Mie and Wakayama Prefectures; 6500 shrines in Mie Prefecture decreased by at least 6/7 and 3700 shrines in Wakayama Prefecture decreased by at least 5/6.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shrine mergers were performed significantly in Mie and Wakayama Prefectures; 6500 shrines in Mie Prefecture decreased by at least 6/7 and 3700 shrines in Wakayama Prefecture decreased by at least 5/6.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>最初の3年間で全国の4万社が取り壊された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">400,000 shrines throughout the country were destroyed for the first three years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">400,000 shrines throughout the country were destroyed in the first three years.</e>
<cmt>Preposition</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">40,000 shrines throughout the country were destroyed in the first three years.</e>
<cmt>400,000→40,000</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>1913年頃に事業はほぼ完了し、社数は19万社から12万社に激減した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The project was almost finished in about 1913, and the number of shrines was reduced greatly from 190,000 to 120,000.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The project was almost finished by about 1913, with the number of shrines greatly reduced from 190,000 to 120,000.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The project was almost finished by about 1913, with the number of shrines greatly reduced from 190,000 to 120,000.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="74">
<j>事業の目的は荒廃した小祠や淫祠を廃止・統合して国家の祭祀として神社の尊厳を高めることにあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The purpose of the project was to restore dignity of the shrines as religious service of the nation by abolishing or integrating ruined shoshi (small shrines) and shrines of evil deity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The purpose of the project was to restore the sanctity of shrines as national religious services by abolishing or integrating ruined shoshi and shrines to evil deities.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The purpose of the project was to restore the sanctity of shrines as national religious services by abolishing or integrating ruined shoshi and shrines to evil deities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>また、地方行政の合理化という側面もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has another purpose of streamlining local administration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It also had the effect of streamlining local administration.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It also had the effect of streamlining local administration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="76">
<j>一方で、地域の氏神信仰に大きな打撃を与えるなどの理由で反対意見も多く出された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, many objections were presented because it had a large influence on local guard gods.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, as it greatly affected belief in local guardian gods, many objections were raised.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, as it greatly affected belief in local guardian gods, many objections were raised.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>民俗学者・博物学者の南方熊楠は『日本及び日本人』などで10年間にわたって反対運動をおこなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kumagusu MINAKATA (biologist and naturalist in the early Showa period) wrote &quot;Nippon oyobi Nipponjin&quot; (Japan and The Japanese) and carried on a campaign against it for ten years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The folklorist and naturalist, Kumagusu MINAKATA, carried on a campaign against it for ten years in works such as &quot;Nippon oyobi Nipponjin&quot; (Japan and The Japanese).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The folklorist and naturalist, Kumagusu MINAKATA, carried on a campaign against it for ten years in works such as &quot;Nippon oyobi Nipponjin&quot; (Japan and The Japanese).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="78">
<j>広大な面積の鎮守の森を失ったことも弊害の一つだったといえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The loss of vast Chinju-no-Mori (Sacred Shrine Forests) is said to be one of its bad effects.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The loss of vast Chinju-no-Mori sacred forests surrounding shrines is said to have been one of its bad effects.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The loss of vast Chinju-no-Mori sacred forests surrounding shrines is said to have been one of its bad effects.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>そのため、神社が保有する森林を材木とし財源とすることが一つの狙いであったといわれるようにもなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, some say that one of its purposes was to tap a new source of revenue by selling trees in the woods owned by shrines.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some say that one of the aims of this destruction was to tap a new source of revenue by selling trees in the woods owned by shrines.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some say that one of the aims of this destruction was to tap a new source of revenue by selling trees in the woods owned by shrines.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>海外統治領下の神社造営</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Construction of shrines in overseas territories</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Construction of shrines in overseas territories</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Construction of shrines in overseas territories</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="80">
<j>台湾、朝鮮、南洋諸島などの統治領には神社が建てられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shrines were built in territories, such as Taiwan, Korea and the South Sea Islands.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shrines were built in Taiwan, Korea, the South Sea Islands and other territories.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shrines were built in Taiwan, Korea, the South Sea Islands and other territories.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>これはもともとは統治領に在留する日本人が自分たちのために建てたものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were originally built by the Japanese who stayed in the territories for themselves.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were originally built by Japanese living in the territories for themselves.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were originally built by Japanese living in the territories for themselves.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="82">
<j>統治領下の神社建立にあたり、多くの神道家らは現地の神々をまつるべきだと主張したが、政府は同意せず、欧米列強の植民地へのキリスト教伝道、土着信仰の残滓の払拭といった発想と同様に多く明治天皇、天照大神を祭神とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many Shintoists insisted that local gods should be revered when building shrines in the territories, but the government did not agree with them and enshrined Emperor Meiji and Amaterasu Omikami (the Sun Goddess) like the allied western powers that preached Christianity in their colonies to dispel indigenous beliefs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many Shintoists insisted that local gods should be revered when building shrines in the territories, but the government did not agree and, like the western powers that preached Christianity in their colonies to erase indigenous beliefs, enshrined Emperor Meiji and Amaterasu Omikami.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many Shintoists insisted that local gods should be revered when building shrines in the territories, but the government did not agree and, like the western powers that preached Christianity in their colonies to erase indigenous beliefs, enshrined Emperor Meiji and Amaterasu Omikami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>これは明治政府が宗教勢力を完全に国家の従属化に置き、宗教勢力の意向を政策立案過程から排除することに成功した先進国の中でも稀有な世俗政権だったことも示しているが同時にこれら時期を逆説的に「神道の暗黒時代」とする意見の根拠ともなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This indicates that the Meiji government was a rare secular government among developed countries, which succeeded in subordinating and holding religious groups completely under control of the nation and eliminating their intentions from the policy making process, but it is also a basis of an opinion that this period was a &apos;dark age of Shinto&apos; paradoxically.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This indicates that the Meiji government was, even among developed countries, a rare secular government, which succeeded in subordinating religious groups, bringing them completely under control of the nation and eliminating their intentions from the policy making process, but it is also a basis of the opinion that this period was, paradoxically, a &apos;dark age of Shinto&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This indicates that the Meiji government was, even among developed countries, a rare secular government, which succeeded in subordinating religious groups, bringing them completely under control of the nation and eliminating their intentions from the policy making process, but it is also a basis of the opinion that this period was, paradoxically, a &apos;dark age of Shinto.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="84">
<j>外地に建立されたおもな神社としては朝鮮神宮、台湾神社、南洋神社、関東神宮、樺太神社（樺太は後に1943年内地編入）などが挙げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Main shrines built in overseas territories include Chosen-jingu Shrine, Taiwan-jinja Shrine, Nanyo-jinja Shrine, Kanto-jingu Shrine, and Karafuto-jinja Shrine (Karafuto (Sakhalin) later came under the mainland in 1943).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Major shrines built in overseas territories include Chosen-jingu Shrine, Taiwan-jinja Shrine, Nanyo-jinja Shrine, Kanto-jingu Shrine, and Karafuto-jinja Shrine (Karafuto, the Japanese name for Sakhalin, was later incorporated into the mainland in 1943).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Major shrines built in overseas territories include Chosen-jingu Shrine, Taiwan-jinja Shrine, Nanyo-jinja Shrine, Kanto-jingu Shrine, and Karafuto-jinja Shrine (Karafuto, the Japanese name for Sakhalin, was later incorporated into the mainland in 1943).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>台湾については台湾の神社を参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Refer to the shrines in Taiwan for details on Taiwan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Refer to the shrines in Taiwan for details on Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Refer to the shrines in Taiwan for details on Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>民間信仰禁止政策</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Folk beliefs/religion prohibition policy</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Folk beliefs prohibition policy</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Folk beliefs prohibition policy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="86">
<j>明治初期において、神霊の憑依やそれによって託宣を得る行為、性神信仰などが低俗なものや迷信として否定され、多くの民俗行事が禁止された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the early Meiji period, possessing of divine spirits and acts that deliver oracles by it, believing in sex gods and so on were denied as vulgar or superstitious and many folk events were prohibited.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the early Meiji period, possession by divine spirits and acts to obtain oracles from that possession, belief in sex gods and so on were rejected as vulgar or superstitious and many folk customs were prohibited.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the early Meiji period, possession by divine spirits and acts to obtain oracles from that possession, belief in sex gods and so on were rejected as vulgar or superstitious and many folk customs were prohibited.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>そのため、出雲神道系などの信仰が偏狭な解釈により大きく後退した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this reason, the religious beliefs of Izumo Shinto were receded greatly by an intolerant interpretation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This meant that, due to intolerant interpretation, religious beliefs such as those of Izumo Shinto went into decline.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This meant that, due to intolerant interpretation, religious beliefs such as those of Izumo Shinto went into decline.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>また、神社の祭神も、その土地で古来からまつられていた神々ではなく、『古事記』、『日本書紀』などの皇統譜につながる神々に変更されたものが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The enshrined deities of shrines were changed from the gods worshipped locally from old times to the gods that derived from Kotofu (the genealogy of the Imperial Family), such as &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters) and &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Enshrined deities were changed from gods worshipped locally since old times to gods that connected with the imperial genealogies of the &quot;Kojiki&quot; and &quot;Nihonshoki&quot;.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Enshrined deities were changed from gods worshipped locally since old times to gods that connected with the imperial genealogies of the &quot;Kojiki&quot; and &quot;Nihonshoki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>そのため、地域での伝承が途絶えた場合にはその神社の古来の祭神が不明になってしまっている場合がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, if a local tradition ceased, ancient deities of the local shrines often became unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, if a local tradition ceased, ancient deities of the local shrines often became unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, if a local tradition ceased, ancient deities of the local shrines often became unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="14">
<tit>
<j>天皇の神格性と「現人神」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Divinity of Emperors and &apos;Arahitogami&apos; (kami who appears in this world in human form)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Divinity of Emperors and &apos;Arahitogami&apos;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Divinity of Emperors and &apos;Arahitogami&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="90">
<j>古来より天皇の神格性は多岐に渡って主張されるところであったが、明治維新以前の尊皇攘夷・倒幕運動と相まって、古事記・日本書紀等の記述を根拠とする天皇の神格性は、現人神（あらひとがみ）として言説化された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The divinity of the Emperor was discussed from various aspects from ancient times, but the divinity of the Emperor was based on descriptions of &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters) and &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan) was stated as &apos;Arahitogami&apos; (kami who appears in this world in human form) according to a movement to reverence for the emperor and the overthrow of the shogunate before the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Various aspects of the Emperor&apos;s divinity had been discussed from ancient times but, influenced by the pre-Meiji Sonno Joi and anti-Shogunate movements and based on descriptions in the &quot;Kojiki&quot; and &quot;Nihonshoki&quot;, the Emperor began to be described as &apos;Arahitogami&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Various aspects of the Emperor&apos;s divinity had been discussed from ancient times but, influenced by the pre-Meiji Sonno Joi and anti-Shogunate movements and based on descriptions in the &quot;Kojiki&quot; and &quot;Nihonshoki,&quot; the Emperor began to be described as &apos;Arahitogami.&apos;</e>
<cmt>カンマ、ピリオドの位置</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>また、福羽美静ら津和野派国学者が構想していた祭政一致の具現化の過程では、天皇が「神道を司る一種の教主的な存在」としても位置づけられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emperor was positioned as &apos;a kind of founder of a religion who takes charge of Shinto&apos; in the process of realization of saisei icchi (unity of church and state, theocracy) that was considered by scholars of (ancient) Japanese literature and culture of Tsuwano school, such as Bisei FUKUBA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the process of realizing &apos;saisei icchi&apos; as conceived by scholars of ancient Japanese literature and culture from the Tsuwano school, such as Bisei FUKUBA, the Emperor was positioned as &apos;a kind of religious founder in charge of Shinto&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the process of realizing &apos;saisei icchi&apos; as conceived by scholars of ancient Japanese literature and culture from the Tsuwano school, such as Bisei FUKUBA, the Emperor was positioned as &apos;a kind of religious founder in charge of Shinto.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>幕府と朝廷の両立体制は近代国家としての日本を創成していくには不都合であったが故の倒幕運動であり、天皇を中心とする強力な君主国家を築いていきたい明治新政府の意向とも一致したため、万世一系の天皇を祭政の両面でこれの頂点とする思想が形成されていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A movement to overthrow the Shogunate was conducted because the system in which the bakufu and the Imperial Court coexisted was not appropriate for creating Japan as a modern nation, and it agreed with the intention of the Meiji new government to build a powerful monarchy centered around the Emperor and an idea in which the Emperor of the unbroken imperial line came out on top from the aspects of saisei icchi (unity of church and state, theocracy) was created.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The movement to overthrow the Shogunate arose because the system of coexistence between the bakufu and the Imperial Court was not appropriate for creating Japan as a modern nation, and it agreed with the new Meiji government&apos;s intentions to build a powerful monarchy centered around the Emperor, therefore giving rise to the idea of the Emperor, coming from an unbroken imperial line, being the head of both Shinto and the state.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The movement to overthrow the Shogunate arose because the system of coexistence between the bakufu and the Imperial Court was not appropriate for creating Japan as a modern nation, and it agreed with the new Meiji government&apos;s intentions to build a powerful monarchy centered around the Emperor, therefore giving rise to the idea of the Emperor, coming from an unbroken imperial line, being the head of both Shinto and the state.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="93">
<j>具体的な国民教導に失敗した宣教使が廃止された後、神仏儒合同でおこなわれた教部省による国民教導では「三条ノ教則」が設定された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After senkyoshi (Shinto Missionaries) that failed specific teaching of people were abolished, &apos;Sanjo no kyosoku (Three Fundamental Articles on Creed)&apos; were set in the teaching of people by the Kyobusho (Ministry of Religion) which was carried out by Shinto, Buddhism and Confucianism together.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the system of senkyoshi (Shinto missionaries), which had failed to teach the specifics to the people, was abolished, the &apos;sanjo no kyosoku&apos; (Three Teachings) was established for the public&apos;s education, which was carried out by the Ministry of Religion and involved Shinto, Buddhism and Confucianism.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the system of senkyoshi (Shinto missionaries), which had failed to teach the specifics to the people, was abolished, the &apos;sanjo no kyosoku&apos; (Three Teachings) was established for the public&apos;s education, which was carried out by the Ministry of Religion and involved Shinto, Buddhism and Confucianism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>その内容は、「敬神愛国の旨を体すべきこと」、「天地人道を明らかにすべきこと」、「皇上を奉戴し朝旨（ちょうし）を遵守（じゅんしゅ）せしむべきこと」であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its contents are &apos;worshipping gods and patriotism should be realized&apos;, &apos;ways of heaven and earth and man should be made clear&apos;, and &apos;the Emperor should be respected and the intention of the Imperial court should be observed&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its contents were &apos;piety and patriotism should be realized&apos;, &apos;the ways of heaven, earth and man should be made clear&apos;, and &apos;the Emperor should be respected and the intention of the Imperial court should be observed&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its contents were &apos;piety and patriotism should be realized,&apos; &apos;the ways of heaven, earth and man should be made clear,&apos; and &apos;the Emperor should be respected and the intention of the Imperial court should be observed.&apos;</e>
<cmt>カンマ、ピリオドの位置</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>この「三条ノ教則」を巡る解説書は仮名垣魯文『三則教の棲道』（1873年）など多数が出された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A lot of commentaries regarding this &apos;Sanjo no kyosoku&apos;, such as &quot;Sansoku-oshie no chikamichi (shortcut to teachings)&quot; (1973) written by Robun KANAGAKI, were published.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many commentaries on &apos;sanjo no kyosoku&apos;, such as &quot;Sansoku-oshie no chikamichi&quot; (Shortcut to Teachings, 1873) written by Robun KANAGAKI, were published.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many commentaries on &apos;sanjo no kyosoku,&apos; such as &quot;Sansoku-oshie no chikamichi&quot; (Shortcut to Teachings, 1873) written by Robun KANAGAKI, were published.</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>これらのなかには「神孫だから現人神と称し奉る」とする例が複数存在した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were several examples in which &apos;descendents of the god are called Arahitogami (kami who appears in this world in human form)&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amongst these, there are several instances of &apos;descendents of the gods are called Arahitogami&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amongst these, there are several instances of &apos;descendents of the gods are called Arahitogami.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="97">
<j>また、教部省廃止以降もその思想的展開として、東京大学で宗教学を講じた加藤玄智は『我が国体の本義』（1912年）で「現人神とも申し上げてをるのでありまして、神より一段低い神の子ではなくして、神それ自身である」と述べている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Genchi KATO who lectured philosophy of religion in the Tokyo University said that &apos;he was an arahitogami (kami who appears in this world in human form), and was a god himself, not a child of a god, which was a being one level lower than the god&apos; as ideological development even after the abolition of the Kyobusho (Ministry of Religion).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even after the abolition of the Ministry of Religion, this ideological development continued, with Genchi KATO, who lectured in philosophy of religion at Tokyo University, said that the Emperor &apos;was an arahitogami and therefore a god himself, not a child of a god, which was a being one level lower than the god&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even after the abolition of the Ministry of Religion, this ideological development continued, with Genchi KATO, who lectured in philosophy of religion at Tokyo University, said that the Emperor &apos;was an arahitogami and therefore a god himself, not a child of a god, which was a being one level lower than the god&apos; in &quot;Waga Kokutai no Hongi&quot; (Meaning of Our National Polity) in 1912.</e>
<cmt>in &quot;Waga Kokutai no Hongi&quot; (Meaning of Our National Polity)を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>憲法学者で東京大学教授の上杉慎吉の「皇道概説」（1913年「国家学会雑誌」27巻1号）は「概念上神とすべきは唯一天皇」などと述べ、これは昭和初期には陸軍における正統憲法学説となっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kodo gaisetsu&apos; (overview of the imperial way) (&apos;Kokkagakkai-zasshi&apos; Volume 27, Number 1, 1913) written by Shinkichi UESUGI, a constitutional scholar and professor of the Tokyo University, said that &apos;only the Emperor should be called a god conceptually&apos; and this was used as an orthodox constitutional theory in the army in the early Showa period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &apos;Kodo gaisetsu&apos; (Overview of the Imperial Way) which appeared in &apos;Kokkagakkai-zasshi&apos; Volume 27, Number 1, (1913), Shinkichi UESUGI, a constitutional scholar and professor at Tokyo University, said that &apos;conceptually, only the Emperor ought to be called a god&apos; and this was used as orthodox constitutional theory by the army in the early Showa period.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &apos;Kodo gaisetsu&apos; (Overview of the Imperial Way) which appeared in &apos;Kokkagakkai-zasshi&apos; Volume 27, Number 1, (1913), Shinkichi UESUGI, a constitutional scholar and professor at Tokyo University, said that &apos;conceptually, only the Emperor ought to be called a god&apos; and this was used as orthodox constitutional theory by the army in the early Showa period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>陸軍中将石原莞爾は『』（原型は1929年7月の中国の長春での「講話要領」）のなかで人類が心から現人神（あらひとがみ）の信仰に悟入したところに、王道文明は初めてその真価を発揮する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;??&quot; (the prototype was &quot;lecture outline&quot; in Changchun, China in July, 1929), lieutenant general (army) Kanji ISHIWARA went far as to say that when human beings believed in arahitogami from the bottom of their heart, royal road civilization proves its merits.</e>
<cmt>『』は、かっこの中が抜けています。&quot;&quot;としました。「講話要領」はlecture outlineと訳しました。「王道文明」はroyal road civilizationと訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;??&quot; (which was based on the &quot;lecture outline&quot; in Changchun, China in July, 1929), Lieutenant General Kanji ISHIWARA went as far as to say that when human beings believe in arahitogami from the bottom of their hearts, then the true value of a civilization of the righteous monarch will be seen.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity - left missing tile of book blankI presume &quot;王道&quot; refers to the Confucian ideal of a virtuous ruler rather than an easy way to achieve something so retranslated.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;Saishu Sensoron, Sensoshi Taikan&quot; (On the Final War and a General Outline History of War) (which was based on the &quot;lecture outline&quot; in Changchun, China in July, 1929), Lieutenant General Kanji ISHIWARA went as far as to say that when human beings believe in arahitogami from the bottom of their hearts, then the true value of a civilization of the righteous monarch will be seen.</e>
<cmt>Webで『』の部分を確認して『最終戦争論・戦争史大観』＝Saishu Sensoron, Sensoshi Taikan (On the Final War and a General Outline History of War)を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>最終戦争即ち王道・覇道の決勝戦は結局、天皇を信仰するものと然らざるものの決勝戦であり、具体的には天皇が世界の天皇とならせられるか、西洋の大統領が世界の指導者となるかを決定するところの、人類歴史の中で空前絶後の大事件である。と極論を展開するなど、昭和維新運動以後の軍国主義の台頭によって、天皇の威を借りた軍部による政治介入が頻発した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The final battle, that is, the final war of the royal road and the rule by military power and plots was the final battle between those who worshipped the Emperor and those who did not, especially, it was the most serious incident in the history of mankind that determined whether the Emperor became the Emperor of the world or the president of the Western countries became the leader of the world and as militarism emerged after a Showa restoration movement, military authorities that exercised the authority of the Emperor intervened in politics.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The final battle, that is, the decisive war between righteous monarchy and military rule, is the final battle between those who worship the Emperor and those who do not; specifically, it will be the most important incident in the history of mankind, determining whether the Emperor will be the Emperor of the world or whether Western presidents will lead the world&quot; and with the rise of militarism after the Showa Restoration movement, the military appropriated the authority of the Emperor to intervene in politics.</e>
<cmt>I presume the &quot;。&quot; in the Japanese is supposed to be a quote mark but I&apos;m not sure where the quote starts</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The final battle, that is, the decisive war between righteous monarchy and military rule, is the final battle between those who worship the Emperor and those who do not; specifically, it will be the most important incident in the history of mankind, determining whether the Emperor will be the Emperor of the world or whether Western presidents will lead the world&quot; and with the rise of militarism after the Showa Restoration movement, the military appropriated the authority of the Emperor to intervene in politics.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>満州事変はこの石原の最終戦争論にもとづいて始められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Manchurian Incident was provoked based on the final battle theory of Ishihara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Manchurian Incident was provoked based on Ishiwara&apos;s final battle theory.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Manchurian Incident was provoked based on Ishiwara&apos;s final battle theory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="102">
<j>連合国軍最高司令官総司令部による神道への危険視は、神国・現人神・聖戦などの思想が対象となっており、天皇の人間宣言もこのような背景で出されたものと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The General Headquarters (GHQ) regarded Shinto as dangerous due to its ideas, such as Shinkoku (land of the gods), arahitogami and crusade, and it is considered that Humanity declaration of the Emperor was made on such a background.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">General Headquarters (GHQ) regarded Shinto as dangerous due to ideas such as Shinkoku (land of the gods), arahitogami and holy war, and it is considered that the Emperor&apos;s Humanity declaration was made against such a background.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity.Left &quot;GHQ&quot; as is, though I&apos;m not sure how common this is in English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">General Headquarters (GHQ) regarded Shinto as dangerous due to ideas such as Shinkoku (land of the gods), arahitogami and holy war, and it is considered that the Emperor&apos;s Humanity declaration was made against such a background.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="15">
<tit>
<j>出来事</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Incidents</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Incidents</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Incidents</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="16">
<tit>
<j>神道事務局 祭神論争</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Argument over enshrined deities of Shinto Jimukyoku (secretariat of Shinto)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Argument over enshrined deities of the Shinto Jimukyoku (Office of Shinto Affairs)</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Argument over enshrined deities of the Shinto Jimukyoku (Office of Shinto Affairs)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="103">
<j>1880-1881年の論争。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Arguments in 1880 to 1881</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Arguments from 1880 to 1881</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Arguments from 1880 to 1881</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>東京の日比谷に設けられた神道事務局神殿の祭神をめぐって神道界に激しい教理論争が起こった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A raging debate arose in Shinto circles over the deities of the Shrine of Shinto Jimukyoku (bureau) which was built in Hibiya, Tokyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A raging debate arose in Shinto circles over the deities of the Shinto Jimukyoku&apos;s shrine in Hibiya, Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A raging debate arose in Shinto circles over the deities of the Shinto Jimukyoku&apos;s shrine in Hibiya, Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>神道事務局は事務局の神殿における祭神として造化三神（天之御中主神、高御産巣日神、神産巣日神）と天照大神の四柱を祀ることとしたが、その中心を担っていたのは伊勢神宮大宮司の田中頼庸ら「伊勢派」の神官であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Shinto Jimukyoku enshrined four gods, Zokasanshin (Three gods of creation) (Ame no Minakanushi no Kami, Takamimusubi no kami, Kamimusubi no kami) and Amaterasu Omikami (the Sun Goddess), but Shinto priests of &apos;Ise school&apos;, including the chief priest of Ise-jingu Shrine, Yoritsune TANAKA, played a central role.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Priests of the &apos;Ise-ha school&apos;, including the chief priest of Ise-jingu Shrine, Yoritsune TANAKA, played a central role in choosing the four gods, the Zokasanshin, or Three Gods of Creation (Ame no Minakanushi no Kami, Takamimusubi no kami, Kamimusubi no kami) and Amaterasu Omikami, enshrined at the Shinto Jimukyoku&apos;s shrine.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Priests of the &apos;Ise-ha school,&apos; including the chief priest of Ise-jingu Shrine, Yoritsune TANAKA, played a central role in choosing the four gods, the Zokasanshin, or Three Gods of Creation (Ame no Minakanushi no Kami, Takamimusubi no kami, Kamimusubi no kami) and Amaterasu Omikami, enshrined at the Shinto Jimukyoku&apos;s shrine.</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>これに対して千家尊福を中心とする「出雲派」は「幽顕一如」を掲げ、祭神を大国主大神を加えた五柱にすべきとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The &apos;Izumo-ha&apos; school centered on SENGE Takatomi advocated &apos;Yuken ichinyo&apos; and insisted that the deities of shrines should be five gods, including Okuni nushi no okami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the &apos;Izumo-ha&apos; school centered on SENGE Takatomi advocated &apos;Yuken ichinyo&apos; and insisted that Okuni nushi no okami should be added, making five deities.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the &apos;Izumo-ha&apos; school centered on Takatomi SENGE advocated &apos;Yuken ichinyo&apos; and insisted that Okuni nushi no okami should be added, making five deities.</e>
<cmt>SENGE Takatomi →Takatomi SENGE</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="107">
<j>伊勢派のなかにも出雲派支持者が多く出たが、伊勢派の幹部はこれを危惧し、明治天皇の勅裁により収拾（宮中三殿の遙拝殿と決定、事実上の出雲派敗北）した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since many priests of the Ise school supported the Izumo-ha school, some leaders of the Ise school felt apprehensions about this situation and solved the problem by the imperial decision of Emperor Meiji (Yohaiden (worshiping Kami from afar of the Three Shrines in the Imperial Court was determined and in fact, the Izumo-ha school defeated).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since many priests of the Ise-ha school supported the Izumo-ha school, some leaders of the Ise-ha school had misgivings about the situation and solved the problem with an imperial decision by Emperor Meiji (it was decided to practice &apos;yohaiden&apos;, or worship from afar, at the Three Palace Shrines, which was in reality a defeat for the Izumo-ha school).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since many priests of the Ise-ha school supported the Izumo-ha school, some leaders of the Ise-ha school had misgivings about the situation and solved the problem with an imperial decision by Emperor Meiji (it was decided to practice &apos;yohaiden&apos;, or worship from afar, at the Three Palace Shrines, which was in reality a defeat for the Izumo-ha school).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>政府は、神道に共通する教義体系の創造の不可能性と、近代国家が復古神道的な教説によって直接に民衆を統制することの不可能性を認識したといわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the government considered it impossible to create a system of creeds common to Shinto or control people directly with creeds of the ancient Shinto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the government considered it impossible to create a system of common creeds for Shinto or to control people directly with creeds of the ancient Shinto.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the government considered it impossible to create a system of common creeds for Shinto or to control people directly with creeds of the ancient Shinto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="17">
<tit>
<j>朝鮮神宮 祭神論争</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Argument over deities of Chosen-jingu Shrine</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Argument over deities of Chosen-jingu Shrine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Argument over deities of Chosen-jingu Shrine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="109">
<j>1919年、朝鮮神宮(京城)の造営に際して政府は明治天皇と天照大神とを祭神とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1919, the government determined Emperor Meiji and Amaterasu Omikami (the Sun Goddess) as enshrined deities when building the Chosen-jingu Shrine (Keijo (old name of Seoul City in the period of Japan&apos;s rule)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1919, the government decided that Emperor Meiji and Amaterasu Omikami should be the enshrined deities when building Chosen-jingu Shrine in Keijo (Japan&apos;s colonial name for Seoul).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1919, the government decided that Emperor Meiji and Amaterasu Omikami should be the enshrined deities when building Chosen-jingu Shrine in Keijo (Japan&apos;s colonial name for Seoul).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>これに対して靖国神社の三代目宮司の賀茂百樹は「朝鮮民族の祖神」の「檀君」もまつるべきであると主張した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The third Guji (chief priest who serves a Shinto shrine, controls festivals and general affairs), Momoki KAMO, insisted that &apos;Dangun&apos; that was an &apos;ancestor of Korean people&apos; should also be enshrined.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the third head priest, Momoki KAMO, insisted that &apos;Dangun&apos;, the &apos;ancestor of the Korean people&apos; should also be enshrined.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the third head priest, Momoki KAMO, insisted that &apos;Dangun&apos;, the &apos;ancestor of the Korean people&apos; should also be enshrined.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="18">
<tit>
<j>国家神道の終焉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">End of State Shinto</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">End of State Shinto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">End of State Shinto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="111">
<j>1945年8月15日、太平洋戦争の敗戦以後、神道周辺の状況は一変した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 15, 1945, the situation around Shinto changed drastically after the defeat of the Pacific War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 15, 1945, the situation around Shinto changed drastically after the defeat of the Pacific War.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 15, 1945, the situation around Shinto changed drastically after the defeat of the Pacific War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>連合国最高司令部から、同年10月に政治的、社会的及宗教的自由に対する制限除去の件が通達された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The General Headquarters (GHQ) notified the Japanese government of separation of shrines from the state in the form of memorandums, &apos;elimination of restrictions on political, social and religious freedom&apos; in October of the same year, and &apos;abolition of the guarantee, support, maintenance, supervision and publication of State Shinto and Jinja Shinto&apos;, i.e., &apos;the Shinto Directive&apos;, on December 15, putting an end to the period of State Shinto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In October of the same year, it had been announced that all restrictions on political, social and religious freedoms would be removed but on December 15, General Headquarters (GHQ) notified the Japanese government of the separation of shrines from the state in the form of a memorandum, known as the Shinto Directive, which &apos;abolished the guarantee, support, maintenance, supervision and promulgation of State Shinto and Jinja Shinto&apos;, putting an end to the period of State Shinto.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">General Headquarters (GHQ) notified the Japanese government that all restrictions on political, social and religious freedoms would be removed in October of the same year.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="113">
<j>12月15日には「国家神道、神社神道に対する政府の保証、支援、保全、監督並に公布の廃止に関する件」、いわゆる「神道指令」により、神社は国家から分離することが日本政府に覚書の形で通達され、国家神道の時代が終わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December 15, GHQ also notified of the separation of shrines from the state in the form of a memorandum, known as the Shinto Directive, which &apos;abolished the guarantee, support, maintenance, supervision and promulgation of State Shinto and Jinja Shinto,&apos; putting an end to the period of State Shinto.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="114">
<j>1946年2月2日には神祇院が解散し、皇典講究所・大日本神祇会・神宮奉斎会が合同して翌日3日に神社本庁を設立、宗教法人としての神社神道が再出発した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 2, 1946, the Jingiin (Institute of Divinities) dissolved, Koten Kokyusho (a research institute for Shinto sect), Dainihon-jingikai and Jingu-hosaikai merged to establish Jinja-Honcho on March 3, and Jinja Shinto restarted as a religious corporation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 2, 1946, the Jingiin (Institute of Divinities) was dissolved, the Koten Kokyusho (Institute for Research of the Imperial Classics), Dainihon-jingikai (Shinto Association of Great Japan) and Jingu-hosaikai (Shrine Reverence Society) were merged into the Jinja-Honcho (The Association of Shinto Shrines) on March 3, and Jinja Shinto restarted as a religious entity.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 2, 1946, the Jingiin (Institute of Divinities) was dissolved, the Koten Kokyusho (Institute for Research of the Imperial Classics), Dainihon-jingikai (Shinto Association of Great Japan) and Jingu-hosaikai (Shrine Reverence Society) were merged into the Jinja-Honcho (The Association of Shinto Shrines) on February 3, and Jinja Shinto restarted as a religious entity.</e>
<cmt>March→February</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="19">
<tit>
<j>国家神道に関する年表</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Timeline on State Shinto</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Timeline of State Shinto</e>
<cmt>Preposition</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Timeline of State Shinto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="115">
<j>慶応3年(1868年)、王政復古 (日本)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Restoration of Imperial Rule (Japan) in 1868</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1868 - Restoration of Imperial Rule</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1868 - Restoration of Imperial Rule</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="116">
<j>慶応4年 (1868年)、神祇事務科の設置。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1868, Shingi jimuka was established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1868 - Shingi jimuka (Shinto Section) established.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1868 - Shingi jimuka (Shinto Section) established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="117">
<j>すぐに神祇事務局に改称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was renamed to Jingi Jimukyoku (Shinto Worship Bureau) soon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soon renamed Jingi Jimukyoku (Shinto Worship Bureau).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soon renamed Jingi Jimukyoku (Shinto Worship Bureau).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="118">
<j>慶応4年 (1868年)、神仏分離令。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1868, the Edict of Separation of Shinto and Buddhism was issued.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1868 - Edict on the Separation of Shinto and Buddhism issued.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1868 - Edict on the Separation of Shinto and Buddhism issued.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="119">
<j>同年、神祇事務局を改め、古代の律令制にならって神祇官とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same year, Jingi Jimukyoku (Shinto Worship Bureau) was renamed to Jingikan (Department of Divinities) according to the ancient Ritsuryo system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same year, Jingi Jimukyoku renamed Jingikan (Department of Divinities) in accordance with the ancient Ritsuryo system.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same year, Jingi Jimukyoku renamed Jingikan (Department of Divinities) in accordance with the ancient Ritsuryo system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="120">
<j>祭政一致の制度を復活し、諸神社神主等を神祇官に附属するものとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The system of saisei icchi (unity of church and state, theocracy) was restored and Shinto priests were affiliated to the Jingikan (Department of Divinities).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">System of saisei icchi (unity of church and state, theocracy) restored and Shinto priests were affiliated to the Jingikan.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">System of saisei icchi (unity of church and state, theocracy) restored and Shinto priests were affiliated to the Jingikan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="121">
<j>明治2年 (1869年)、東京招魂社（後の靖国神社）、楠木社（後の湊川神社）を創設。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1869, Tokyo Shokonsha Shrine (later Yasukuni-jinja Shrine) and Kusunoki-sha Shrine (later Minatogawa-jinja Shrine) were established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1869 - Tokyo Shokonsha Shrine (later Yasukuni-jinja Shrine) and Kusunoki-sha Shrine (later Minatogawa-jinja Shrine) established.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1869 - Tokyo Shokonsha Shrine (later Yasukuni-jinja Shrine) and Kusunoki-sha Shrine (later Minatogawa-jinja Shrine) established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="122">
<j>明治天皇は東京招魂社（後の靖国神社）に実質5千石（名目は1万石）の社領を「永代祭粢料」として与え、毎年の収入源とさせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Meiji gave Tokyo Shokonsha Shrine (later Yasukuni-jinja Shrine) an estate of actual 5000 koku (nominally 10,000 koku) as &apos;eitai saishiryo (permanent grant of money for funeral expenses)&apos; which became a source of annual income of the shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Meiji gave Tokyo Shokonsha Shrine an estate worth 5000 koku (nominally 10,000 koku) as &apos;eitai saishiryo&apos; (permanent grant of money for funeral expenses) which became a source of annual income of the shrine.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Meiji gave Tokyo Shokonsha Shrine an estate worth 5000 koku (nominally 10,000 koku) as &apos;eitai saishiryo&apos; (permanent grant of money for funeral expenses) which became a source of annual income of the shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="123">
<j>同年、宣教使を置く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Senkyoshi (Shinto Missionaries) were established in the same year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Senkyoshi (Shinto Missionaries) were established the same year.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Senkyoshi (Shinto Missionaries) were established the same year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="124">
<j>天長節、神武天皇祭などを定め、全国的に遥拝式を実施。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tencho setsu (The birthday of the reigning emperor) and Jinmu Tenno Sai (The Emperor Jinmu Festival) were determined and yohai-shiki (service of worshipping from afar) was performed nationally.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tencho setsu (birthday of the reigning emperor) and Jimmu Tenno Sai (Emperor Jimmu Festival) were set and yohai-shiki (services of worshipping from afar) were performed nationwide.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tencho setsu (birthday of the reigning emperor) and Jimmu Tenno Sai (Emperor Jimmu Festival) were set and yohai-shiki (services of worshipping from afar) were performed nationwide.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="125">
<j>明治3年 (1870年)、大教宣布の詔。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1870, the Imperial Edict for Establishment of Shinto was issued.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1870 - Imperial Edict on the Establishment of Shinto issued.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1870 - Imperial Edict on the Establishment of Shinto issued.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="126">
<j>明治4年 (1871年)、伊勢神宮以下、すべての神官社家の世襲を廃し、神祇官および地方庁に神職の任免権を与えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1871, the heredity of all families of Shinto priests of shrines, including Ise-jingu Shrine, was abolished and the Jingikan (Department of Divinities) and intendance were given the power of appointing and removing Shinto priests.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1871 - system of priests serving on a heredity basis abolished, including at Ise-jingu Shrine, and Jingikan and local governments given power to appoint and dismiss priests.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1871 - system of priests serving on a heredity basis abolished, including at Ise-jingu Shrine, and Jingikan and local governments given power to appoint and dismiss priests.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="127">
<j>「官社以下定額及神官職員規則等」（明治4年5月14日太政官布告）により、伊勢神宮を頂点として官国幣社、府藩県社、郷社の位階を定め、官国幣社長官は華族・士族から選任、国幣社長官は府藩県の参事の兼任とし、世襲神職のすべてを「改補新任」することとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &apos;Rules on jogaku and Shinto priest of official shrines or lower&apos; (edict of Daijokan (The Grand Council of State), May 14, 1871)), the ranks of Kankoku Heisha (general term for Kanpeisha and Kokuheisha that were high rank shrines), fuhanken-sha (prefectural shrine (of prefectures other than Kyoto and Osaka)), and gosha (village shrine) with Ise-jingu Shrine as the top were specified, the chief of Kankoku Heisha was selected from among the peerage and warrior class, the chief of the Kokuheisha (shrines under the control of provincial governors) was served concurrently by the secretary of fu-han-ken, and all hereditary Shinto priests were &apos;newly appointed&apos;.</e>
<cmt>「官社以下定額及神官職員規則等」は、 Rules on jogaku and Shinto priests of official shrines or lowerと訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In accordance with &apos;Rules on shrine ranks and priests of official shrines or lower&apos; (edict of Daijokan [The Grand Council of State], May 14, 1871), the ranks of &apos;kankoku heisha&apos;, &apos;fuhanken-sha&apos; (prefectural shrines other than those in Kyoto and Osaka), and &apos;gosha&apos; (municipal shrines) were specified, with Ise-jingu Shrine at the top, the head of the &apos;kankoku heisha&apos; was selected from among the peerage and warrior class, the position of head of the &apos;kokuheisha&apos; (shrines under the control of provincial governors) was filled by the secretary fu-han-ken (prefectures and domains), and all hereditary Shinto priests were &apos;newly appointed&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In accordance with &apos;Rules on shrine ranks and priests of official shrines or lower&apos; (edict of Daijokan [The Grand Council of State], May 14, 1871), the ranks of &apos;kankoku heisha,&apos; &apos;fuhanken-sha&apos; (prefectural shrines other than those in Kyoto and Osaka), and &apos;gosha&apos; (municipal shrines) were specified, with Ise-jingu Shrine at the top, the head of the &apos;kankoku heisha&apos; was selected from among the peerage and warrior class, the position of head of the &apos;kokuheisha&apos; (shrines under the control of provincial governors) was filled by the secretary fu-han-ken (prefectures and domains), and all hereditary Shinto priests were &apos;newly appointed.&apos;</e>
<cmt>カンマ、ピリオドの位置</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="128">
<j>明治4年 (1871年)、「郷社定則」（明治4年7月4日太政官）により全国の神社と神職を序列化した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1871, the shrines and Shinto priests all over the country were graded by &apos;gosha (village shrine) precepts&apos; (1871 Daijokan (The Grand Council of State)).</e>
<cmt>「郷社定則」はgosha (village shrine) preceptsとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1871 - shrines and priests nationwide graded in accordance with &apos;gosha precepts&apos; (Daijokan, July 4, 1871).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1871 - shrines and priests nationwide graded in accordance with &apos;gosha precepts&apos; (Daijokan, July 4, 1871).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="129">
<j>また1戸籍区に1郷社を置き、他の氏神は村社として郷社に付属するものとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A gosha was established in each family register district and other ujigami (guardian gods or spirits of a particular place in the Shinto religion) were affiliated to the gosha as village shrines.</e>
<cmt>「戸籍区」はfamily register districtと訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One gosha was established in each family register district and other ujigami (guardian gods or spirits of a particular place) were affiliated with the gosha as village shrines.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One gosha was established in each family register district and other ujigami (guardian gods or spirits of a particular place) were affiliated with the gosha as village shrines.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="130">
<j>明治4年 (1871年)、神祇官廃止、神祇省設置。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1871, the Jingikan (Department of Divinities) was abolished and the Jingisho (Ministry of Divinities) was established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1871- Jingikan abolished and Jingisho (Ministry of Divinities) established.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1871- Jingikan abolished and Jingisho (Ministry of Divinities) established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="131">
<j>明治4年 (1871年)、伊勢神宮の神宮大麻を地方官を通して全国700万戸に1個2銭で強制配布することに決め、翌年から実施。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1871, it was decided to distribute Jingu taima (Shrine amulets) forcibly to 7,000,000 households throughout the country through chihokan (local officials) with a price of 2 sen per piece and it was carried out from the next year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1871 - decision to distribute Jingu taima (Shrine amulets) forcibly to 7,000,000 households throughout the country through chihokan (local officials) at a price of 2 sen per piece; carried out from the following year.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1871 - decision to distribute Jingu taima (Shrine amulets) forcibly to 7,000,000 households throughout the country through chihokan (local officials) at a price of 2 sen per piece; carried out from the following year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="132">
<j>1878年以後は受不受は自由となったが、地方官が関与してトラブルを生ずることもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amulets could be received freely since 1878, but trouble often occurred with local officials.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From 1878, people could decide whether to accept amulets, but trouble often occurred with local officials.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From 1878, people could decide whether to accept amulets, but trouble often occurred with local officials.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="133">
<j>明治5年 (1872年)、官社以下の神官の給録を制定（明治5年2月25日太政官第58号「神官給禄定額ヲ定ム」）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1872, the amount of the stipend of Shinto priests of official shrines or shrines with lower ranks was established (February 25, 1872, Daijokan (The Grand Council of State) 58; &apos;The amount of the stipend of Shinto priests was specified.&apos;).</e>
<cmt>「給録」は、the amount of the stipendとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1872 - amount of stipend for priests of official shrines and lower-ranked shrines established (February 25, 1872, Daijokan, No. 58; &apos;Specifying the amount of stipend for priests&apos;).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1872 - amount of stipend for priests of official shrines and lower-ranked shrines established (February 25, 1872, Daijokan, No. 58; &apos;Specifying the amount of stipend for priests&apos;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="134">
<j>明治5年 (1872年)、神祇省廃止、教部省設置。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1872, the Jingisho (Ministry of Divinities) was abolished and the Kyobusho (Ministry of Religion) was established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1872 - Jingisho abolished and Kyobusho (Ministry of Religion) established.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1872 - Jingisho abolished and Kyobusho (Ministry of Religion) established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="135">
<j>大教院設置。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Daikyoin (Great Teaching Institute) was established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Daikyoin (Great Teaching Institute) established.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Daikyoin (Great Teaching Institute) established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="136">
<j>宣教使を廃し、教導職の制度を定めて宣教体制を確立。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Senkyoshi (Shinto missionaries) were abolished and the kyodoshoku (evangelist) system was formulated to establish a senkyo (Shinto mission) framework.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Senkyoshi abolished and kyodoshoku (evangelist) system formulated to establish a senkyo (missionary) framework.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Senkyoshi abolished and kyodoshoku (evangelist) system formulated to establish a senkyo (missionary) framework.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="137">
<j>天皇を「奉戴」することを命じた「三条ノ教則」を国民教導の中心とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanjo no kyosoku&apos; which ordered &apos;respect&apos; for the Emperor was used as a basis of teaching of people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanjo no kyosoku&apos;, which ordered &apos;respect&apos; for the Emperor, was used as a basis of teaching of people.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanjo no kyosoku,&apos; which ordered &apos;respect&apos; for the Emperor, was used as a basis of teaching of people.</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="138">
<j>教義に関する著書出版免許願は教部省に提出させることとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Requests for license to publish books regarding creeds were required to be submitted to the Kyobusho (Ministry of Religion).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Requests for licenses to publish books on creeds were required to be submitted to the Kyobusho.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Requests for licenses to publish books on creeds were required to be submitted to the Kyobusho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="139">
<j>明治6年 (1873年)、大教院神殿が放火により全焼。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1873, the shrine of the Daikyoin (Great Teaching Institute) was burned down due to arson.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1873 - Daikyoin shrine burned down due to arson.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1873 - Daikyoin shrine burned down due to arson.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="140">
<j>神体は芝東照宮に仮遷座。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The object of worship was temporarily moved to Shiba-toshogu Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The object of worship temporarily moved to Shiba-toshogu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The object of worship temporarily moved to Shiba-toshogu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="141">
<j>明治6年 (1873年)、府県社の神官の月給を廃止。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1873, the monthly salaries of Shinto priests of Fukensha (Prefectural shrines) were abolished.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1873 - monthly salaries of priests of &apos;fukensha&apos; (Prefectural shrines) abolished.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1873 - monthly salaries of priests of &apos;fukensha&apos; (Prefectural shrines) abolished.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="142">
<j>明治6年 (1873年)、政府は全国の招魂場の社地を免税とし、祭祀費用・招魂墳墓の修繕費の国家予算支出を定めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1873, the government exempted the shrine&apos;s land of shokonjo (a shrine made around Meiji Restoration for enshrining soldiers died for the nation) all over the country from taxation and specified expenditure of religious service costs and repair costs of tombs for memorial service from the national budget.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1873 - government exempted land owned by shokonjo (shrines established to enshrine soldiers who died for the nation) nationwide from taxation and specified amount of national budget to be used for religious service costs and repair costs of memorials.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1873 - government exempted land owned by shokonjo (shrines established to enshrine soldiers who died for the nation) nationwide from taxation and specified amount of national budget to be used for religious service costs and repair costs of memorials.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="143">
<j>明治8年 (1875年)、真宗四派が神道側との対立、政教分離の必要性を理由に大教院を離脱。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1875, four Shinshu sects seceded the Daikyoin (Great Teaching Institute) due to conflict with the Shinto group and necessity of separation of government and religion.</e>
<cmt>「真宗四派」はfour Shinshu sectsと訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1875 - the four Buddhist Shinshu sects seceded Daikyoin due to conflict with Shinto camp and necessity of separation of government and religion.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1875 - the four Buddhist Shinshu sects seceded Daikyoin due to conflict with Shinto camp and necessity of separation of government and religion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="144">
<j>神道側は神道事務局設立。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Shinto group established a Shinto Jimukyoku (secretariat of Shinto).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinto camp established Shinto Jimukyoku (Office of Shinto Affairs).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinto camp established Shinto Jimukyoku (Office of Shinto Affairs).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="145">
<j>明治8年 (1875年)、太政官は神道と仏教との合同布教中止の通達を教部省に出す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1875, the Daijokan (The Grand Council of State) issued a circular notice to discontinue joint propagation of Shintoism and Buddhism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1875 - Daijokan issued circular notice to discontinue joint propagation of Shintoism and Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1875 - Daijokan issued circular notice to discontinue joint propagation of Shintoism and Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="146">
<j>また太政官は神宮以下の神社祭式を定める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Daijokan established the rules for ritual procedure in jingu (shrines) or shrines with lower ranks.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daijokan established rules for ritual procedure in jingu (shrines dedicated to ancestors of the imperial family) or shrines with lower ranks.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daijokan established rules for ritual procedure in jingu (shrines dedicated to ancestors of the imperial family) or shrines with lower ranks.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="147">
<j>明治9年 (1876年)、政府は靖国神社の社領を年7550円の現金に改め、「寄付金」へと改称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1876, the government abolished the estate of Yasukuni-jinja Shrine, and instead paid cash of 7550 yen a year as &apos;donation&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1876 - government abolished Yasukuni-jinja Shrine&apos;s estate, and instead &apos;donated&apos; cash of 7550 yen a year.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1876 - government abolished Yasukuni-jinja Shrine&apos;s estate, and instead &apos;donated&apos; cash of 7550 yen a year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="148">
<j>明治10年 (1877年)、教部省廃止。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1877, the Kyobusho (Ministry of Religion) was abolished.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1877 - Kyobusho abolished.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1877 - Kyobusho abolished.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="149">
<j>機能は内務省 (日本)社寺局へ移される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its functions were transferred to the Bureau of shrines and temples of the prewar Ministry of Home Affairs (Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its functions were transferred to the Ministry of Home Affairs&apos; Bureau of Shrines and Temples.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its functions were transferred to the Ministry of Home Affairs&apos; Bureau of Shrines and Temples.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="150">
<j>明治10年 (1877年)、神宮・官国幣社の神官を廃して祭主以下の職員の官等・月俸を定めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1877, the Shinto priests of jingu shrines and Kankoku Heisha (general term for Kanpeisha and Kokuheisha that were high-ranking shrines) were abolished and official ranks and monthly salaries of chief priests and lower-ranking priests were specified.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1877 - priests of jingu shrines and kankoku heisha were abolished and official ranks and monthly salaries of chief priests and lower-ranking priests were specified.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1877 - priests of jingu shrines and kankoku heisha were abolished and official ranks and monthly salaries of chief priests and lower-ranking priests were specified.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="151">
<j>明治12年 (1879年)、東京招魂社を靖国神社に改称し、内務省 (日本)・陸軍省・海軍省の管理とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1879, Tokyo Shokonsha Shrine was renamed to Yasukuni-jinja Shrine under control of the prewar Ministry of Home Affairs (Japan), the Department of War and the Ministry of the Navy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1879 - Tokyo Shokonsha Shrine renamed Yasukuni-jinja Shrine and put under control of the Ministry of Home Affairs, the Department of War and the Ministry of the Navy.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1879 - Tokyo Shokonsha Shrine renamed Yasukuni-jinja Shrine and put under control of the Ministry of Home Affairs, the Department of War and the Ministry of the Navy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="152">
<j>明治13年 (1880年)-明治14年 (1881年)、芝東照宮から神道事務局神殿へ祭神を遷す際、祭神をめぐり神道界に激しい教理論争。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1880 to 1881, a fierce controversy over the enshrined deities arose in Shinto circles when moving the enshrined deities from Shiba-toshogu Shrine to the Shrine of Shinto Jimukyoku (bureau).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1880-1881 - fierce controversy over enshrined deities arose in Shinto circles when moving enshrined deities from Shiba-toshogu Shrine to the Shinto Jimukyoku&apos;s shrine.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1880-1881 - fierce controversy over enshrined deities arose in Shinto circles when moving enshrined deities from Shiba-toshogu Shrine to the Shinto Jimukyoku&apos;s shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="153">
<j>明治天皇の裁定により収拾。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The controversy was ended by a ruling of Emperor Meiji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The controversy was ended by a ruling of Emperor Meiji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The controversy was ended by a ruling of Emperor Meiji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="154">
<j>後述の国家神道出来事参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Refer to the incidents of State Shinto described later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Refer to the Incidents of State Shinto described later.</e>
<cmt>Capital letter</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Refer to the Incidents of State Shinto described later.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="155">
<j>明治15年 (1882年、官国幣社の神職が教導職を兼補することを廃止。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1882, Shinto priests of the Bureau of Shinto shrines doubled as kyodoshoku (evangelists).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1882 - dual role of kankoku heisha priests as kyodoshoku (evangelists) abolished.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1882 - dual role of kankoku heisha priests as kyodoshoku (evangelists) abolished.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="156">
<j>また内務省 (日本)は神宮・官国幣社の神官が葬儀に関与してはならないことを定めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The prewar Ministry of Home Affairs (Japan) stipulated that the Shinto priests of jingu shrines and Kankoku Heisha (general term for Kanpeisha and Kokuheisha that were high rank shrines) must not be engaged in funeral service.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ministry of Home Affairs stipulated that priests of jingu and kankoku heisha shrines must not participate in funeral services.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ministry of Home Affairs stipulated that priests of jingu and kankoku heisha shrines must not participate in funeral services.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="157">
<j>神社は祭祀儀礼を中心とし、独自の教説を有する教団は教派神道として独立。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shrines mainly performed Shinto services and rituals and religious communities with their own creeds became independent as Sect Shinto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shrines mainly performed Shinto services and rituals and religious communities with their own creeds became independent as Sect Shinto.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shrines mainly performed Shinto services and rituals and religious communities with their own creeds became independent as Sect Shinto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="158">
<j>神官層は神職と教導職の完全分離と神祇官の再興運動（1896年参照）を起こした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Shinto priests made a campaign to separate Shinto priests from evangelists completely and restore the Jingikan (Department of Divinities) (refer to year 1896.).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinto priests campaigned to separate priests from evangelists completely and to restore the Jingikan (refer to year 1896).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinto priests campaigned to separate priests from evangelists completely and to restore the Jingikan (refer to year 1896).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="159">
<j>明治20年 (1887年)、官国幣社に対して1902年までの「保存金」の支給を定め、従前の経費・官費営繕を廃止した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1887, supply of &apos;preservation money&apos; to Kankoku Heisha (general term for Kanpeisha and Kokuheisha that were high rank shrines) until 1902 was stipulated and the conventional public expenses of repair were abolished.</e>
<cmt>「保存金」はpreservation moneyと訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1887 - supply of &apos;preservation money&apos; to kankoku heisha shrines until 1902 stipulated, expenses and government expenses for upkeep abolished.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1887 - supply of &apos;preservation money&apos; to kankoku heisha shrines until 1902 stipulated, expenses and government expenses for upkeep abolished.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="160">
<j>「保存金」は後に1917年までに延長された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The supply of &apos;preservation money&apos; was later extended to 1917.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The supply of &apos;preservation money&apos; was later extended to 1917.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The supply of &apos;preservation money&apos; was later extended to 1917.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="161">
<j>明治21年 (1888年)、官国幣社の神官を廃止し、宮司・禰宜・主典の神職を置いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1888, the Shinto priests of the Kankoku Heisha (general term for Kanpeisha and Kokuheisha that were high rank shrines) were abolished and Shinto priests of Guji (chief priests who serve shrine, control festivals and general affairs), negi (ritualists) and sakan (shrine officials ranking below a negi) were established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1888 - priests of kankoku heisha shrines were abolished and positions of &apos;guji&apos; (chief priest), negi (senior priest) and sakan (shrine official) were established.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1888 - priests of kankoku heisha shrines were abolished and positions of &apos;guji&apos; (chief priest), negi (senior priest) and sakan (shrine official) were established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="162">
<j>宮司は奏任官、禰宜・主典は判任官の待遇とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Guji was treated as an official of sonin rank, and negi and sakan, as junior officials.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Guji were treated as officials of sonin rank, and negi and sakan as junior officials.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Guji were treated as officials of sonin rank, and negi and sakan as junior officials.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="25">
<sen id="163">
<j>明治22年 (1889年)、大日本帝国憲法発布。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1889, the Constitution of the Empire of Japan was issued.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1889 - Constitution of the Empire of Japan promulgated.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1889 - Constitution of the Empire of Japan promulgated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="164">
<j>近代国家として信教の自由（但し&quot;法の定める範囲内&quot;での）が条文に記載される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Freedom of religion as a modern nation (however, in the &quot;range specified by the law&quot;) was stipulated in its articles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a modern nation, freedom of religion (although in the &quot;range specified by the law&quot;) was stipulated in its articles.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a modern nation, freedom of religion (although in the &quot;range specified by the law&quot;) was stipulated in its articles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="165">
<j>神社崇敬義務の範囲が議論の対象となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The scope of duties of worship of shrines became the subject of discussion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The scope of duties of shrine worship became the subject of discussion.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The scope of duties of shrine worship became the subject of discussion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="26">
<sen id="166">
<j>明治23年 (1890年)、教育勅語を発布。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1890, the Imperial Rescript on Education was issued.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1890 - Imperial Rescript on Education issued.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1890 - Imperial Rescript on Education issued.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="167">
<j>内村鑑三による教育勅語拝礼拒否（不敬事件）により、教育勅語重視の訓令を追加した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Kanzo UCHIMURA rejected the worship specified in the Imperial Rescript on Education (incidence of lese majesty), a directive to follow the Imperial Rescript on Education was issued additionally.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Kanzo UCHIMURA rejected the worship specified in the Imperial Rescript on Education (known as the Lese Majesty Incident), a directive to follow the Imperial Rescript on Education was also issued.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Kanzo UCHIMURA rejected the worship specified in the Imperial Rescript on Education (known as the Lese Majesty Incident), a directive to follow the Imperial Rescript on Education was also issued.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="168">
<j>昭和期には児童・生徒に暗唱を強いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Children and students were forced to recite the Imperial Rescript on Education in the Showa Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Children and students were forced to recite the Imperial Rescript on Education during the Showa period.</e>
<cmt>PrepositionLower case letter</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Children and students were forced to recite the Imperial Rescript on Education during the Showa period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="27">
<sen id="169">
<j>明治25年 (1892年)、久米邦武の学術論文「神道は祭天の古俗」を巡って激しい論争久米邦武筆禍事件。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1892, a raging debate arose over the treatise by Kunitake KUME, &apos;Shinto is a remnant of the ancient custom of worshiping heaven&apos; (Kunitake KUME incident occasioned by a serious slip of the pen).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1892 - raging debate arose over Kunitake KUME&apos;s treatise, &apos;Shinto is an outmoded remnant of heaven worship&apos; (known as the Kunitake KUME incident).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1892 - raging debate arose over Kunitake KUME&apos;s treatise, &apos;Shinto is an outmoded remnant of heaven worship&apos; (known as the Kunitake KUME incident).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="170">
<j>久米邦武は帝国大学教授職非職となり、『史学雑誌』『史海』の論文が掲載された該当号は内務大臣 (日本)品川弥二郎により発禁処分。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kunitake KUME was dismissed from professor of the Tokyo Imperial University and the volumes of &apos;Shigaku zasshi&apos; (Journal of Historical Studies) and &apos;Shikai&apos; which carried his treatises were suppressed by the Minister of Home Affairs (Japan), Yajiro SHINAGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kunitake KUME was dismissed as a professor at Tokyo Imperial University and the volumes of &apos;Shigaku zasshi&apos; (Journal of Historical Studies) and &apos;Shikai&apos; which carried his treatises were suppressed by the Minister of Home Affairs, Yajiro SHINAGAWA.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kunitake KUME was dismissed as a professor at Tokyo Imperial University and the volumes of &apos;Shigaku zasshi&apos; (Journal of Historical Studies) and &apos;Shikai&apos; which carried his treatises were suppressed by the Minister of Home Affairs, Yajiro SHINAGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="28">
<sen id="171">
<j>明治26年 (1893年)、太平記の南朝 (日本)の忠臣などの諸事跡や実在を疑問視した重野安繹が帝国大学史誌編纂掛委員を罷免。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1893, Yasutsugu SHIGENO who questioned the credibility and presence of the loyal subjects of the Southern Dynasty written in Record of Great Peace was dismissed from the post of a member of the history editing committee of the Tokyo Imperial University.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1893 - Yasutsugu SHIGENO, who questioned the credibility and existence of retainers of the Southern Dynasty who appeared in &quot;Taiheiki&quot; (a 14th century historical epic), dismissed from his post as a member of the history editing committee of Tokyo Imperial University.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1893 - Yasutsugu SHIGENO, who questioned the credibility and existence of retainers of the Southern Dynasty who appeared in &quot;Taiheiki&quot; (a 14th century historical epic), dismissed from his post as a member of the history editing committee of Tokyo Imperial University.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="29">
<sen id="172">
<j>明治26年 (1893年)、学校行事の「陛下の御真影への最敬礼」、「両陛下の万歳奉祝」、「教育勅語の奉読」、「校長の訓話」などの基本形式を整える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1983, basic procedures of school events, such as &apos;making a deep bow to an imperial portrait&apos;, &apos;congratulations and celebrations of the Emperor and Empress&apos;, &apos;respectful reading of the Imperial Rescript on Education&apos;, and &apos;moral discourses of school masters&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1893 - basic procedures of school events, such as &apos;bowing deeply to an imperial portrait&apos;, &apos;celebrating the Emperor and Empress with cries of &apos;banzai&apos;, &apos;respectful reading of the Imperial Rescript on Education&apos;, and &apos;moral discourses by school principals&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1893 - basic procedures of school events, such as &apos;bowing deeply to an imperial portrait,&apos; &apos;celebrating the Emperor and Empress with cries of &apos;banzai,&apos; &apos;respectful reading of the Imperial Rescript on Education,&apos; and &apos;moral discourses by school principals.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオド、カンマの位置</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="30">
<sen id="173">
<j>明治27年 (1894年)-明治28年 (1895年)、日清戦争。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1894 to 1895, the Sino-Japanese war broke out.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1894-1895 - Sino-Japanese War.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1894-1895 - Sino-Japanese War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="174">
<j>戦後、忠魂碑の建造が盛んになるなど、国家と神社との結びつきが強まる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many monuments to soldiers killed in battle were built after the war and the relationship between the state and shrines deepened.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many monuments to soldiers killed in battle were built after the war and the relationship between the state and shrines deepened.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many monuments to soldiers killed in battle were built after the war and the relationship between the state and shrines deepened.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="31">
<sen id="175">
<j>明治28年 (1895年)、平安遷都1100年記念に平安神宮創建。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1895, Heian-jingu Shrine was built in commemoration of 1100 years after the transfer of national capital to the city of Heian-kyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1895 - Heian-jingu Shrine built to commemorate 1100th anniversary of the transfer of national capital to Heian-kyo (Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1895 - Heian-jingu Shrine built to commemorate 1100th anniversary of the transfer of national capital to Heian-kyo (Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="176">
<j>祭神は桓武天皇。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The enshrined deity was Emperor Kanmu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The enshrined deity was Emperor Kanmu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The enshrined deity was Emperor Kanmu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="32">
<sen id="177">
<j>明治29年 (1896年)、「神祇官興復決議」が衆貴両院をはじめて通過したが、不平等条約の条約改正を前にして実現しなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1896, a &apos;Jingikan restoration resolution&apos; passed through both the House of Representatives and the House of Peers for the first time, but was abandoned before revision of unequal treaties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1896 - &apos;Jingikan restoration resolution&apos; passed through both the Houses of Parliament the first time, but was abandoned when revision of the unequal treaties took precedence.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1896 - &apos;Jingikan restoration resolution&apos; passed through both the Houses of Parliament the first time, but was abandoned when revision of the unequal treaties took precedence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="33">
<sen id="178">
<j>明治32年 (1899年)、不平等条約の条約改正が実現し、欧米列強の意向を顧慮する必要が薄れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1899, the unequal treaties were revised, and the intentions of the allied western powers did not need to be considered.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1899 - unequal treaties revised, and the need to take into account western powers decreased.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1899 - unequal treaties revised, and the need to take into account western powers decreased.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="34">
<sen id="179">
<j>明治32年 (1899年)、歴史教科書に天照大神、三種の神器、天孫降臨を加える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1899, Amaterasu Omikami (the Sun Goddess), Sanshu no Jingi (Three Imperial Regalia), and tensonkorin (the descent to earth of the grandson of the sun goddess) were added to history textbooks.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1899 - Amaterasu Omikami (the Sun Goddess), Sanshu no Jingi (Three Imperial Regalia), and tensonkorin (the descent to earth of the grandson of the sun goddess) added to history textbooks.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1899 - Amaterasu Omikami (the Sun Goddess), Sanshu no Jingi (Three Imperial Regalia), and tensonkorin (the descent to earth of the grandson of the sun goddess) added to history textbooks.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="35">
<sen id="180">
<j>明治33年 (1900年)、内務省 (日本)社寺局を神社局と宗教局に分離された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1900, the Bureau of shrines and temples of the prewar Ministry of Home Affairs (Japan) was separated to the Bureau of Shinto shrines and the Bureau of Religions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1900 - Ministry of Home Affairs&apos; Bureau of Shrines and Temples split into Bureau of Shrines and Bureau of Religions.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1900 - Ministry of Home Affairs&apos; Bureau of Shrines and Temples split into Bureau of Shrines and Bureau of Religions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="181">
<j>神社局は地方局や警保局を抜いて最高位の局とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Bureau of Religions was regarded as the top bureau that was above the Bureau of Areas and Keihokyoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Bureau of Religions was regarded as the highest bureau, above the Bureau of Regions and Police Bureau.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Bureau of Shrines was regarded as the highest bureau, above the Bureau of Regions and Police Bureau.</e>
<cmt>Bureau of Religions→Bureau of Shrines</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="182">
<j>出雲大社教や黒住教などの教派神道は一般宗教政策として宗教局の担当とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sect Shinto, such as Izumo Oyashiro-kyo (sect of Shinto) and Kurozumikyo sect, was in charge of the Bureau of Religions according to a general religion policy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the general policy on religion, Sect Shinto, such as the Izumo Oyashiro-kyo and Kurozumikyo sects, was placed under the Bureau of Religions.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the general policy on religion, Sect Shinto, such as the Izumo Oyashiro-kyo and Kurozumikyo sects, was placed under the Bureau of Religions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="183">
<j>（宗教局はさらに1913年には文部省に移管され、格落ちした。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(The Bureau of Religions was transferred to the Ministry of Education and its position was lowered in 1913.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(In 1913, the Bureau of Religions was transferred to the Ministry of Education and its position lowered.)</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(In 1913, the Bureau of Religions was transferred to the Ministry of Education and its position lowered.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="36">
<sen id="184">
<j>明治33年 (1900年)、植民地の台湾の台北に台湾神宮（官幣大社）を創建した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1900, Taiwan-jinja Shrine (Kanpei-taisha (large-scale state shrine)) was built in Taipei, Taiwan, which was a colony.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1900 - Taiwan-jinja Shrine (a kanpei-taisha, or major Imperial shrine) built in Taipei, Taiwan, which was then a Japanese colony.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1900 - Taiwan-jingu Shrine (a kanpei-taisha, or major Imperial shrine) built in Taipei, Taiwan, which was then a Japanese colony.</e>
<cmt>Taiwan-jinja→Taiwan-jingu</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="185">
<j>以後、台湾には官国幣社5、県社9、以下81社が造られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, five Kankoku Heisha (general term for Kanpeisha and Kokuheisha that were high rank shrines), nine prefectural shrines and 81 others were built in Taiwan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, five kankoku heisha shrines, nine prefectural shrines and 81 others were built in Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, five kankoku heisha shrines, nine prefectural shrines and 81 others were built in Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="37">
<sen id="186">
<j>明治34年 (1901年)、国費で維持する官祭招魂社の105社が定められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1901, 105 Kansai Shokonsha Shrines were specified and were maintained with national expenditure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1901 - 105 Kansai Shokonsha shrines established and maintained with national expenditure.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1901 - 105 Kansai Shokonsha shrines established and maintained with national expenditure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="38">
<sen id="187">
<j>明治39年 (1906年)、内務省 (日本)神社局は神社合祀を開始し、1914年までに全国約20万社のうち7万社を取り壊して一村一社を推進した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1906, the Bureau of Shinto shrines of the prewar Ministry of Home Affairs (Japan) started to merge shrines, destroyed 70,000 of about 200,000 shrines so that there was one shrine in each village until 1914.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1906 - Ministry of Home Affairs&apos; Bureau of Shinto Shrines started to merge shrines, abolishing 70,000 of about 200,000 shrines so that, until 1914, there was one shrine in each village.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1906 - Ministry of Home Affairs&apos; Bureau of Shinto Shrines started to merge shrines, abolishing 70,000 of about 200,000 shrines so that, until 1914, there was one shrine in each village.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="39">
<sen id="188">
<j>大正2年 (1913年)、内務省宗教局は文部省へ移管。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1913, the Bureau of Religions of the prewar Ministry of Home Affairs (Japan) was transferred to the Ministry of Education.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1913 - Ministry of Home Affairs&apos; Bureau of Shinto Shrines transferred to Ministry of Education.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1913 - Ministry of Home Affairs&apos; Bureau of Shinto Shrines transferred to Ministry of Education.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="189">
<j>憲法学者で東京大学教授の上杉慎吉の「皇道概説」が出され、昭和初期には陸軍の正統憲法学説となっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kodo gaisetsu&apos; (overview of the imperial way) written by Shinkichi UESUGI, a constitutional scholar and professor of the Tokyo University, was published and this was used as an orthodox constitutional theory in the army in the early Showa period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kodo gaisetsu&apos; (Overview of the Imperial Way), written by Shinkichi UESUGI, a constitutional scholar and professor at Tokyo University, was published and used as an orthodox constitutional theory by the army in the early Showa period.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kodo gaisetsu&apos; (Overview of the Imperial Way), written by Shinkichi UESUGI, a constitutional scholar and professor at Tokyo University, was published and used as an orthodox constitutional theory by the army in the early Showa period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="40">
<sen id="190">
<j>大正8年 (1919年)、植民地の朝鮮に朝鮮神宮（官幣大社）を創建した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1919, Chosen-jingu Shrine (Kanpei-taisha (large-scale state shrine)) was built in Korea which was a colony.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1919 - Chosen-jingu Shrine (a kanpei-taisha) was built in Korea, which was then a Japanese colony.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1919 - Chosen-jingu Shrine (a kanpei-taisha) was built in Korea, which was then a Japanese colony.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="191">
<j>祭神を天照大神と明治天皇にした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amaterasu Omikami (the Sun Goddess) and Emperor Meiji were enshrined as deities.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amaterasu Omikami (the Sun Goddess) and Emperor Meiji were enshrined as deities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amaterasu Omikami (the Sun Goddess) and Emperor Meiji were enshrined as deities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="192">
<j>官国幣社9、以下60余社が造られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nine Kanpei-taisha (large-scale state shrines) and 60 others were built.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nine Kanpei-taisha and 60 others were built.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nine Kanpei-taisha and 60 others were built.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="41">
<sen id="193">
<j>昭和10年 (1935年)頃から、八紘一宇などのスローガンが掲げられるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Slogans, such as hakkoichiu (universal brotherhood, all eight corners of the world under one roof), were created in about 1935.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Circa 1935 - slogans, such as hakkoichiu (eight corners of the world under one roof), created.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Circa 1935 - slogans, such as hakkoichiu (eight corners of the world under one roof), created.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="42">
<sen id="194">
<j>昭和12年 (1937年)、文部省思想局が「国体の本義」を発行する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1937, shisokyoku (thought bureau), the Education Ministry, issued a &apos;primordial doctrine of the national polity&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1937 - Education Ministry&apos;s Bureau of Thought Control issued &apos;underlying principle of national polity&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1937 - Education Ministry&apos;s Bureau of Thought Control issued &apos;underlying principle of national polity.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="195">
<j>政府の刊行物に公式用語として現人神が記載され、天皇の神格性について言説化（言挙げ）された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Arahitogami (kami who appears in this world in human form) was used as an official term in the government&apos;s publications, and divinity of the Emperor was remarked (mentioned).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Arahitogami was used as an official term in the government&apos;s publications, and the Emperor&apos;s divinity began to be mentioned.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Arahitogami was used as an official term in the government&apos;s publications, and the Emperor&apos;s divinity began to be mentioned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="196">
<j>「国体の本義」は必須の教材であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The &apos;primordial doctrine of the national polity&apos; was an essential teaching material.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &apos;underlying principle of national polity&apos; was required teaching material.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &apos;underlying principle of national polity&apos; was required teaching material.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="43">
<sen id="197">
<j>昭和14年 (1939年)、大日本帝国陸軍は従軍神職制度を定め、各師団に3名、兵站監に2名、独立旅団に1名を配した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1939, the Imperial Japanese Army established a military Shinto priest system and assigned three Shinto priests to each division and two Shinto priests to quarter master general&apos;s office and one Shinto priest to an independent brigade.</e>
<cmt>「従軍神職制度」は、military Shinto priest systemと訳しました。「兵站監」は、quarter master general&apos;s officeと訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1939 - Imperial Japanese Army established military priest system, assigning three priests to each division, two to quartermaster offices and one to independent brigades</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1939 - Imperial Japanese Army established military priest system, assigning three priests to each division, two to quartermaster offices and one to independent brigades</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="44">
<sen id="198">
<j>昭和15年 (1940年)、紀元二千六百年記念行事。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1940, a commemorative ceremony for the 2,600th year of the founding of Japan was held.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1940 - commemorative ceremony for the 2,600th anniversary of the founding of Japan.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1940 - commemorative ceremony for the 2,600th anniversary of the founding of Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="199">
<j>全国の神社で奉祝臨時祭が行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shrines all over the country held Hoshuku Rinji Matsuri.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shrines all over the country held special festivals.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shrines all over the country held special festivals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="200">
<j>新たに浦安の舞が創作された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Urayasu no Mai Dance was created newly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Urayasu no Mai Dance was created.</e>
<cmt>Rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Urayasu no Mai Dance was created.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="201">
<j>神祇院設置。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Jingiin (Institute of Divinities) was established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Jingiin (Institute of Divinities) was established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Jingiin (Institute of Divinities) was established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="45">
<sen id="202">
<j>昭和20年 (1945年)、米軍の空襲により明治神宮、熱田神宮、湊川神社等が炎上した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1945, Meiji-jingu Shrine, Atsuta-jingu Shrine, Minatogawa-jinja Shrine and so on were burned due to the air raid of the United States Forces.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1945 - shrines including Meiji-jingu Shrine, Atsuta-jingu Shrine, Minatogawa-jinja Shrine burned down in US air raid.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1945 - shrines including Meiji-jingu Shrine, Atsuta-jingu Shrine, Minatogawa-jinja Shrine burned down in US air raid.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="46">
<sen id="203">
<j>昭和20年 (1945年)、終戦。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1945, the World War II ended.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1945 - end of World War II.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1945 - end of World War II.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="47">
<sen id="204">
<j>昭和20年 (1945年)、神道指令（国家神道、神社神道ニ対スル政府ノ保証、支援、保全、監督並ニ弘布ノ廃止ニ関スル件）により、神社と行政機関の接点が全て廃止される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1945, all the contact points between shrines and administrative agencies were abolished by the Shinto Directive (abolition of the government&apos;s guarantee, support, maintenance, supervision and publication of State Shinto and Jinja Shinto).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1945 - all contact points between shrines and administrative agencies abolished by the Shinto Directive (the government&apos;s guarantee, support, maintenance, supervision and promulgation of State Shinto and Jinja Shinto to be abolished).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1945 - all contact points between shrines and administrative agencies abolished by the Shinto Directive (the government&apos;s guarantee, support, maintenance, supervision and promulgation of State Shinto and Jinja Shinto to be abolished).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="48">
<sen id="205">
<j>昭和21年 (1946年)、昭和天皇は人間宣言を発布。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1946, Emperor Showa issued humanity declaration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1946 - Emperor Showa issued humanity declaration.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1946 - Emperor Showa issued humanity declaration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="206">
<j>いわゆる天皇の「神格否定」として解釈された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was interpreted as &apos;denial of the divinity&apos; of the Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was interpreted as a &apos;denial of the divinity&apos; of the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was interpreted as a &apos;denial of the divinity&apos; of the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="49">
<sen id="207">
<j>昭和21年 (1946年)、神祇院官制など、すべての神社関係法令が廃止された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1946, all laws and ordinances associated with shrines, such as Jingiin kan sei (Institute of Divinities), were abolished.</e>
<cmt>「神祇院官制」は、Jingiin kan sei (Institute of Divinities)としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1946 - all laws and ordinances associated with shrines, such as Jingiinkansei (Institute of Divinities), abolished.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1946 - all laws and ordinances associated with shrines, such as Jingiinkansei (Institute of Divinities), abolished.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="208">
<j>皇室令も全廃され、宮中祭祀は天皇の私的行為となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The koshitsu-rei (the Imperial Families&apos; Act) was abolished and court rituals became private acts of the Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Imperial Families&apos; Act was abolished and court rituals became private acts of the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Imperial Families&apos; Act was abolished and court rituals became private acts of the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="50">
<sen id="209">
<j>昭和28年 (1953年)、敗戦により中止された伊勢神宮の「神宮式年遷宮」が行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1953, &apos;Jingu Shikinen Sengu&apos; of the Ise-jingu Shrine, which was suspended due to the defeat in war, was carried out.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1953 - Ise-jingu Shrine&apos;s Shikinen Sengu (reconstruction) Ceremony, suspended due to the defeat in war, was performed.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1953 - Ise-jingu Shrine&apos;s Shikinen Sengu (reconstruction) Ceremony, suspended due to the defeat in war, was performed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="210">
<j>これを機に国家神道の復活が神社本庁の指導層などによって公然と要求されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The leaders of the Jinja-Honcho took this occasion to make public requests to restore State Shinto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The leaders of the Jinja-Honcho took this occasion to make public requests to restore State Shinto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The leaders of the Jinja-Honcho took this occasion to make public requests to restore State Shinto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="51">
<sen id="211">
<j>昭和32年 (1957年)、神社本庁、生長の家、修養団などが合同で紀元節復活運動のための統一団体、「紀元節奉祝会」を結成。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1957, Jinja-Honcho, Seicho-No-Ie, Shuyo-dan, and so on organized an integrated group, &apos;Kigensetsu-hoshuku-kai&apos;, to launch a campaign to restore Kigensetsu (the National Foundation Day) (the day commemorating the ascension to the throne of the first emperor, Jinmu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1957 - groups such as Jinja-Honcho, Seicho-No-Ie, Shuyo-dan, joined forces to form &apos;Kigensetsu-hoshuku-kai&apos;, launching a campaign to restore Kigensetsu (National Foundation Day), which commemorated the ascension to the throne of the first emperor, Jimmu).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1957 - groups such as Jinja-Honcho, Seicho-No-Ie, Shuyo-dan, joined forces to form &apos;Kigensetsu-hoshuku-kai,&apos; launching a campaign to restore Kigensetsu (National Foundation Day), which commemorated the ascension to the throne of the first emperor, Jimmu).</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="52">
<sen id="212">
<j>昭和34年 (1959年)、政府は皇太子の結婚式に際して神道儀礼である「賢所大前の儀」を国事行為とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1959, the government regarded &apos;Kashikodokoro-omae-no-gi&apos; which was a Shinto ceremony as one of the emperor&apos;s constitutional functions when the crown prince married.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1959 - the government regarded the Shinto ceremony of &apos;Kashikodokoro-omae-no-gi&apos; as one of the emperor&apos;s constitutional functions when the crown prince married.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1959 - the government regarded the Shinto ceremony of &apos;Kashikodokoro-omae-no-gi&apos; as one of the emperor&apos;s constitutional functions when the crown prince married.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="53">
<sen id="213">
<j>昭和42年 (1967年)、「建国記念日」の名称で紀元節が国民の祝日として復活した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1967, Kigensetsu was revived as a national holiday under the name of &apos;National Foundation Day&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1967 - Kigensetsu revived as a national holiday under the name &apos;National Foundation Day&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1967 - Kigensetsu revived as a national holiday under the name &apos;National Foundation Day.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="214">
<j>靖国神社の再国営化運動が活発化した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A movement for renationalization of the Yasukuni-jinja Shrine became active.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A movement for the renationalization of Yasukuni-jinja Shrine gained momentum.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A movement for the renationalization of Yasukuni-jinja Shrine gained momentum.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="54">
<sen id="215">
<j>昭和44年 (1969年)、靖国神社から宗教的要素を除き、国営化する「靖国神社法案」が出されたが、審議未了廃案となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1969, a &apos;Yasukuni-jinja Shrine draft law&apos; for nationalization of the Yasukuni-jinja Shrine except its religious elements was presented in a Diet session, but was abandoned because of incomplete deliberations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1969 - &apos;Yasukuni-jinja Shrine Bill&apos; for nationalization of Yasukuni-jinja Shrine, excepting its religious elements, presented in a Diet session, but abandoned because of incomplete deliberations.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1969 - &apos;Yasukuni-jinja Shrine Bill&apos; for nationalization of Yasukuni-jinja Shrine, excepting its religious elements, presented in a Diet session, but abandoned because of incomplete deliberations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="55">
<sen id="216">
<j>昭和49年 (1974年)、自由民主党 (日本)が靖国神社法案を衆議院本会議で単独可決（参議院で廃案）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1974, the Liberal Democratic Party (Japan) got through the Yasukuni-jinja Shrine draft law in the House of Representatives plenary session (abandoned in the House of Councilors) independently.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1974 - Liberal Democratic Party independently pushed through Yasukuni-jinja Shrine Bill in a House of Representatives plenary session (rejected in the House of Councilors).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1974 - Liberal Democratic Party independently pushed through Yasukuni-jinja Shrine Bill in a House of Representatives plenary session (rejected in the House of Councilors).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="56">
<sen id="217">
<j>昭和51年 (1976年)、「靖国神社国家護持貫徹国民協議会」が「英霊にこたえる会」へと改称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1976, &apos;Yasukuni-jinja (shrine) Kokkagoji (defend and maintain the national polity) kantetsu (persistence) Kokuminkyogikai (national council)&apos; was renamed to &apos;Eirei ni kotaeru kai&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1976 - &apos;Yasukuni-jinja Kokkagoji Kantetsu Kokuminkyogikai&apos; (National Convention for Realizing State Support for Yasukuni-Jinja Shrine) renamed &apos;Eirei ni kotaeru kai&apos; (Society for Honoring the Glorious War Dead).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1976 - &apos;Yasukuni-jinja Kokkagoji Kantetsu Kokuminkyogikai&apos; (National Convention for Realizing State Support for Yasukuni-Jinja Shrine) renamed &apos;Eirei ni kotaeru kai&apos; (Society for Honoring the Glorious War Dead).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="57">
<sen id="218">
<j>昭和53年 (1978年)、靖国神社はA級戦犯の14人を合祀。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1978, the Yasukuni-jinja Shrine enshrined 14 class-A war criminals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1978 - Yasukuni-jinja Shrine enshrined 14 class-A war criminals.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1978 - Yasukuni-jinja Shrine enshrined 14 class-A war criminals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="58">
<sen id="219">
<j>昭和61年 (1986年)、中曽根康弘首相は靖国神社参拝を見送り、「A級戦犯の合祀は相手国を刺激する」と発言。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1986, Prime Minister Yasuhiro NAKASONE refrained from a visit to the Yasukuni-jinja Shrine and said &apos;Enshrining class-A war criminals stimulated other countries&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1986 - Prime Minister Yasuhiro NAKASONE refrained from visiting Yasukuni-jinja Shrine, saying &apos;enshrining class-A war criminals provokes our neighbors&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1986 - Prime Minister Yasuhiro NAKASONE refrained from visiting Yasukuni-jinja Shrine, saying &apos;enshrining class-A war criminals provokes our neighbors.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="59">
<sen id="220">
<j>平成2年 (1990年)、大嘗祭が行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1990, a Daijo-sai festival (a festival to celebrate the succession of an emperor) was held.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1990 - a Daijo-sai festival was held to celebrate the succession of the new emperor.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1990 - a Daijo-sai festival was held to celebrate the succession of the new emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Los688(id:12316), BOTarate(id:185620), Straysheep(id:42448), Nnh(id:474), Mait(id:73947), Kaz2008(id:196880), Rikumio(id:99645), 春野秋葉(id:36725), TXiKiBoT(id:107492), Njt(id:11249), 神祇官(id:99217), 下総大納言(id:43461), カイの迷宮(id:72682), Kinori(id:443), Mercenario97(id:206084), Point136(id:211299), Shimoxx(id:9332), 竹麦魚(id:11012), Component(id:146478), Nopira(id:29335), Tinecici(id:192914), YukkeBot2(id:251491), 海猿(id:26542), 翰林硯士(id:99377), Izayohi(id:13095), HikaruFukushima(id:89838), たね(id:10372), Jmacs(id:72704), Stanislaus(id:1806), 水野白楓(id:22811), Complex01(id:10454), Mega(id:34550), 俊平太郎(id:34056), Memosa(id:131221), Interregnum(id:25269), Kafuka1964(id:105407), Tanuki Z(id:612), 上(id:14148), Mine-Kansai(id:2080), AuBot(id:179501), 伏儀(id:142093), ウミユスリカ(id:9504), Meat ball(id:19377), Chuta(id:10457), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>