<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>ニニギ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ninigi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ninigi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ninigi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>ニニギ（アメニギシ クニニギシ アマツヒコヒコホノニニギ）は、日本神話に登場する神。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ninigi (Amenigishi kuninigishi amatsuhiko hiko hononinigi) is a deity in Japanese mythology.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ninigi (Amenigishi kuninigishi amatsuhiko hiko hononinigi) is a deity in Japanese mythology.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ninigi (Amenigishi kuninigishi amatsuhiko hiko hononinigi) is a deity in Japanese mythology.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>古事記では天邇岐志国邇岐志天津日高日子番能邇邇芸命、天邇岐志、国邇岐志、天日高日子とかかれ、日本書紀では天饒石国鐃石天津日高彦火瓊瓊杵尊、天津日高彦瓊瓊杵尊、彦火瓊瓊杵、火瓊瓊杵などと表記される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters), Ninigi is referred to as &quot;Ame nigishi kuni nigishi amatsuhiko hiko hononinigi&quot; (spelled as &quot;天邇岐志国邇岐志天津日高日子番能邇邇芸命&quot;), &quot;Ame nigishi&quot; (&quot;天邇岐志&quot;), &quot;kuni nigishi&quot; (&quot;国邇岐志&quot;), or &quot;amatsuhiko&quot; (&quot;天日高日子&quot;), whereas in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), he is mentioned as &quot;Ame nigishi kuni nigishi amatsuhitaka hiko hono ninigi no mikoto&quot; (&quot;天饒石国鐃石天津日高彦火瓊瓊杵尊&quot;), &quot;Amatsuhidaka hikono hono ninigi no mikoto&quot;, (&quot;天津日高彦瓊瓊杵尊&quot;), or &quot;Hono ninigi no mikoto&quot; (&quot;彦火瓊瓊杵&quot; or &quot;火瓊瓊杵&quot;).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外処理 (1)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters), Ninigi is referred to as &quot;Ame nigishi kuni nigishi amatsuhiko hiko hononinigi&quot; (spelled as &quot;天邇岐志国邇岐志天津日高日子番能邇邇芸命&quot;), &quot;Ame nigishi&quot; (&quot;天邇岐志&quot;), &quot;kuni nigishi&quot; (&quot;国邇岐志&quot;), or &quot;amatsuhiko&quot; (&quot;天日高日子&quot;), whereas in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), he is mentioned as &quot;Ame nigishi kuni nigishi amatsuhitaka hiko hono ninigi no mikoto&quot; (&quot;天饒石国鐃石天津日高彦火瓊瓊杵尊&quot;), &quot;Amatsuhidaka hikono hono ninigi no mikoto&quot;, (&quot;天津日高彦瓊瓊杵尊&quot;), or &quot;Hono ninigi no mikoto&quot; (&quot;彦火瓊瓊杵&quot; or &quot;火瓊瓊杵&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Kojiki (The Records of Ancient Matters), Ninigi is referred to as &quot;Ame nigishi kuni nigishi amatsuhiko hiko hononinigi&quot; (spelled as &quot;天邇岐志国邇岐志天津日高日子番能邇邇芸命&quot;), &quot;Ame nigishi&quot; (&quot;天邇岐志&quot;), &quot;kuni nigishi&quot; (&quot;国邇岐志&quot;), or &quot;amatsuhiko&quot; (&quot;天日高日子&quot;), whereas in Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan), he is mentioned as &quot;Ame nigishi kuni nigishi amatsuhitaka hiko hono ninigi no mikoto&quot; (&quot;天饒石国鐃石天津日高彦火瓊瓊杵尊&quot;), &quot;Amatsuhidaka hikono hono ninigi no mikoto&quot; (&quot;天津日高彦瓊瓊杵尊&quot;), or &quot;Hono ninigi no mikoto&quot; (&quot;彦火瓊瓊杵&quot; or &quot;火瓊瓊杵&quot;).</e>
<cmt>原文に『』のない&quot;を削除名前が併記される部分は&quot;があった方が分かりやすいので削除しませんでした。コンマ削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>一般には瓊瓊杵尊や瓊々杵尊（ににぎのみこと）と書かれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Generally, he is called &quot;Ninigi no mikoto&quot; (spelled as &quot;瓊瓊杵尊&quot; or &quot;瓊々杵尊&quot;).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外処理 (2)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Generally, he is called &quot;Ninigi no mikoto&quot; (spelled as &quot;瓊瓊杵尊&quot; or &quot;瓊々杵尊&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Generally, he is called &quot;Ninigi no mikoto&quot; (spelled as &quot;瓊瓊杵尊&quot; or &quot;瓊々杵尊&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>神話における記述</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His descriptions in mythology</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His descriptions in mythology</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mythology</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>アマテラスの子であるオシホミミと、タカミムスビの娘である栲幡千千姫命（萬幡豊秋津師比売命）の子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a son of Oshihomimi, a son of Amaterasu (the Sun Goddess), and Takuhatachijihime no mikoto (also called &quot;Yorozuhatatoyoakitsushihime no mikoto&quot;), a daughter of Takamimusubi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a son of Oshihomimi, a son of Amaterasu (the Sun Goddess), and Takuhatachijihime no mikoto (also called &quot;Yorozuhatatoyoakitsushihime no mikoto&quot;), a daughter of Takamimusubi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a son of Oshihomimi, a son of Amaterasu (the Sun Goddess), and Takuhatachijihime no mikoto (also called &quot;Yorozuhatatoyoakitsushihime no mikoto&quot;), a daughter of Takamimusubi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>兄に天火明命（アメノホアカリ）がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ame no hoakari was his elder brother.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ame no hoakari was his elder brother.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ame no hoakari was his elder brother.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>日本書紀の一書では天火明命（アメノホアカリ）の子とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to a different opinion cited in Nihonshoki, Ninigi was a son of Ame no hoakari.</e>
<cmt>「日本書紀の一書」とは、日本書紀が、異説を引用する際も用いた表現といわれています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to a different opinion cited in the Nihonshoki, Ninigi was a son of Ame no hoakari.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to a different theory cited in the Nihonshoki, Ninigi was a son of the deity Ame no hoakari.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>天照大神の命により、葦原中国を統治するため高天原から地上に降りたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ninigi is believed to have descended from Takamanohara (the vast realm in the high heaven where deities resided) at the order of Amaterasu omikami, his grandmother, to rule Ashihara no nakatsukuni (literally, &quot;the central land of reed plains&quot;, which was the human world).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ninigi is believed to have descended from Takamanohara (the vast realm in heaven where deities resided) at the order of Amaterasu omikami, his grandmother, to rule Ashihara no nakatsukuni (literally, &quot;the central land of reed plains,&quot; which was the human world).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ninigi is believed to have descended from Takamanohara (the vast realm in heaven where deities resided) at the order of the Goddess Amaterasu, his grandmother, to rule Ashihara no nakatsukuni (literally, &quot;the central land of reed plains,&quot; which was the human world).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>これを（天孫降臨）と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is called Tensonkorin (the descent to earth of the grandson of the sun goddess).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is called Tensonkorin (the sun goddess&apos;s gradson&apos;s descent to earth).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is called Tensonkorin (the sun goddess&apos;s grandson&apos;s descent to earth).</e>
<cmt>gradson&apos;s→grandson&apos;s</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>古事記では、この降臨の地については「竺紫の日向の高穂の久士布流多気に天降りまさしめき」と記述している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Kojiki, Ninigi descended to Kujifurutake, Kakaho, Hyuga, Tsukushi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Kojiki, Ninigi descended to Kujifurutake, Kakaho, Hyuga, Tsukushi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the Kojiki, Ninigi &apos;descended from heaven at Kujifurutake, Kakaho in Hyuga, Tsukushi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。クォーテーションを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>日本書記では、「日向襲之高千穗峯」あるいは「筑紫日向高千穗」と記述している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Nihonshoki, he is said to have landed onto &quot;Himuka no So no Takachiho no Mine&quot; (literally, the peak of Takachiho in Himuka) or &quot;Tsukushi no Himuka no Takachiho&quot; (literally, Takachiho, Himuka, Tsukushi).</e>
<cmt>降臨の場所ですが、後にもこの解釈をめぐりいろいろな説がでてきますので、ここでは、言葉を並べる程度にしておきました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Nihonshoki, he is said to have landed on the &quot;Himuka no So no Takachiho no Mine&quot; (literally, the peak of Takachiho in Himuka) or &quot;Tsukushi no Himuka no Takachiho&quot; (literally, Takachiho, Himuka, Tsukushi).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Nihonshoki, he is said to have descended from heave at the &apos;Himuka no So no Takachiho no Mine&apos; (literally, the peak of Takachiho in Himuka) or &apos;Tsukushi no Himuka no Takachiho&apos; (literally, Takachiho, Himuka, Tsukushi).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>この降臨の経路の解釈ついては、日向国の高千穂峰に降り吾田国（現在の南さつま市）の長屋の笠狭碕に到達したとする説が有力である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many scholars agree that Ninigi, who descended to the peak of Takachiho in Hyuga Province, eventually reached Kasasa no Misaki in Nagaya in Ata no kuni (Ata Province, the current Minami-Satsuma City).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many scholars agree that Ninigi, who descended to the peak of Takachiho in Hyuga Province, eventually reached Kasasa no Misaki in Nagaya in Ata no kuni (Ata Province, the current Minami-Satsuma City).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many scholars agree that Ninigi, who descended to the peak of Takachiho in Hyuga Province, eventually reached Kasasa no Misaki in Nagaya in Ata Province (currently Minami-Satsuma City).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="13">
<j>一方、行政上、日向国が設置されたのは7世紀であり、それ以前の時代には日向国地域は熊曽国に含まれていたとして、古事記の「竺紫」＝「筑紫」、日本書紀の「筑紫」から、降臨地は「筑紫国の日向」であって後世の「日向国」ではないと解釈する異説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But some consider that Ninigi might have descended to &quot;Hyuga in Tsukushi Province&quot;, not &quot;Hyuga Province&quot; established at a later time, partly because both Kojiki and Nihonshoki mention the venue of his descent as &quot;Tsukushi&quot; (spelled as &quot;竺紫&quot; or &quot;筑紫&quot; in Kojiki and &quot;筑紫&quot; in Nihonshoki), and partly because the region included in Hyuga Province in the seventh century had been covered by Kumaso no kuni (Kumaso Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But some consider that Ninigi might have descended to &quot;Hyuga in Tsukushi Province,&quot; not &quot;Hyuga Province&quot; established at a later time, partly because both the Kojiki and Nihonshoki mention the venue of his descent as &quot;Tsukushi&quot; (spelled as &quot;竺紫&quot; or &quot;筑紫&quot; in the Kojiki and &quot;筑紫&quot; in Nihonshoki), and partly because the region included in Hyuga Province in the seventh century had been covered by Kumaso no kuni (Kumaso Province).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But some consider that Ninigi might have descended to &apos;Hyuga in Tsukushi Province,&apos; not &apos;Hyuga Province&apos; established at a later time, partly because both the Kojiki and Nihonshoki mention the location of his descent as &apos;Tsukushi&apos; (spelled as &apos;竺紫&apos; or &apos;筑紫&apos; in the Kojiki and &apos;筑紫&apos; in Nihonshoki), and partly because the region included in Hyuga Province in the seventh century had previously been part of Kumaso Province.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="14">
<j>そこでオオヤマツミの娘であるコノハナノサクヤビメを娶り、ホデリ（海幸）・ホスセリ・ホオリ（山幸）を生んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ninigi got married to Konohanano sakuya bime, a daughter of Oyamatsumi, and had three sons: Hoderi (Umisachi, literally, &quot;sea treasures&quot;), Hosuseri, and Hoori (Yamasachi, literally, &quot;mountain products&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ninigi got married Konohanano sakuya bime, the daughter of Oyamatsumi, and had three sons: Hoderi (Umisachi, literally, &quot;sea treasures&quot;), Hosuseri, and Hoori (Yamasachi, literally, &quot;mountain products&quot;).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ninigi married Konohanano sakuya bime, the daughter of the deity Oyamatsumi, and had three sons: Hoderi (Umisachi, literally, &quot;sea treasures&quot;), Hosuseri, and Hoori (Yamasachi, literally, &quot;mountain products&quot;).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>ホオリの孫が神武天皇である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The grandson of Hoori is Emperor Jinmu, the first Emperor of Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The grandson of Hoori is Emperor Jinmu, the first Emperor of Japan.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The grandson of Hoori is Emperor Jinmu, the first Emperor of Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>亡くなった後は「可愛の山陵」に葬られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When he died, he was buried in &quot;Enoyama no misasagi&quot; (literally, &quot;Imperial Tomb in Mt. Eno&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When he died, he was buried in &quot;Enoyama no misasagi&quot; (literally, &quot;Imperial Tomb in Mt. Eno&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When he died, he was buried in &apos;Enoyama no misasagi&apos; (literally, &apos;Imperial Tomb in Mt. Eno&apos;).</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="17">
<j>解説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Comments</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Comments</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Comments</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>名前の「アメニギシクニニギシ」（天にぎし国にぎし）は「天地が豊かに賑う」の意。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Part of his name, &quot;Ame nigishi kuni nigishi&quot;, means that the heaven and earth are affluent and lively.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Part of his name, &quot;Ame nigishi kuni nigishi,&quot; means that heaven and earth are affluent and lively.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Part of his name, &apos;Ame nigishi kuni nigishi,&apos; means that heaven and earth are affluent and lively.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>「アマツヒコ」（天津日高）は天津神のことで、「ヒコ」（日子）は男性のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Amatsuhiko&quot; indicates Amatsukami (heavenly deities) and &quot;hiko&quot; means a male.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Amatsuhiko&quot; indicates Amatsukami (heavenly deities) and &quot;hiko&quot; means male.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amatsuhiko&apos; means the deities Amatsukami and &apos;hiko&apos; means male.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>「ホノニニギ」は稲穂が豊かに実ることの意味である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Hono ninigi&quot; means that rice is fully ripened.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Hono ninigi&quot; means that rice has fully ripened.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hono ninigi&apos; means a good rice harvest.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>「ニニギ」は「ニギニギしい」の意で、「にぎやか」と同源語である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Ninigi&quot; means &apos;being lively&apos; and has the same root as &quot;Nigiyaka&quot;, which means &apos;being bustling or busy&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Ninigi&quot; means &apos;being lively&apos; and has the same root as &quot;Nigiyaka,&quot; which means &apos;being bustling or busy.&apos;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ninigi&apos; means &apos;lively&apos; and has the same root as &apos;Nigiyaka,&apos; which means &apos;bustling or busy.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。スペース補足、削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>神話上ニニギの一族とされている上述の天忍穂耳尊やホデリ・ホスセリ・ホオリとは名前に「ホ」がある点で共通している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Deities like &quot;Ame no Oshihomimi no Mikoto&quot;, Hoderi, Hosuseri, and Hoori mentioned earlier, who are considered to be Ninigi&apos;s relatives in mythology, commonly contain the sound of &quot;ho&quot; in their names.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外処理(1)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Deities like &quot;Ame no Oshihomimi no Mikoto,&quot; Hoderi, Hosuseri, and Hoori mentioned earlier, who are considered to be Ninigi&apos;s relatives in mythology, commonly contain the sound of &quot;ho&quot; in their names.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Deities such as Ame no Oshihomimi no Mikoto, Hoderi, Hosuseri, and Hoori mentioned earlier, who are considered to be Ninigi&apos;s relatives in mythology, commonly contain the sound of &apos;ho&apos; in their names.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>「ホ」は稲穂の「穂」である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Ho&quot; signifies rice ears.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外処理(2)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Ho&quot; signifies rice ears.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ho&apos; signifies rice.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="24">
<j>農業の神として信仰されており、霧島神宮（鹿児島県霧島市）、高千穂神社（宮崎県西臼杵郡高千穂町）、新田神社 (薩摩川内市)（鹿児島県薩摩川内市）、築土神社（東京都千代田区）などに祀られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ninigi has been worshipped as a deity of agriculture, and enshrined in many shrines, including Kirishima-jingu Shrine (Kirishima City, Kagoshima Prefecture), Takachiho-jinja Shrine (Takachiho Town, Nishi usuki County, Miyazaki Prefecture), Nitta-jinja Shrine (Satsumasendai City, Kagoshima Prefecture), and Tsukudo-jinja Shrine (Chiyoda Ward, Tokyo Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ninigi has been worshipped as a deity of agriculture, and is enshrined in many shrines, including Kirishima-jingu Shrine (Kirishima City, Kagoshima Prefecture), Takachiho-jinja Shrine (Takachiho Town, Nishi usuki County, Miyazaki Prefecture), Nitta-jinja Shrine (Satsumasendai City, Kagoshima Prefecture), and Tsukudo-jinja Shrine (Chiyoda Ward, Tokyo Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ninigi is worshipped as a deity of agriculture, and is enshrined in many shrines, including Kirishima-jingu Shrine (Kirishima City, Kagoshima Prefecture), Takachiho-jinja Shrine (Takachiho Town, Nishi usuki County, Miyazaki Prefecture), Nitta-jinja Shrine (Satsumasendai City, Kagoshima Prefecture), and Tsukudo-jinja Shrine (Chiyoda Ward, Tokyo Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。スペース削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="25">
<j>埋葬地である「日向の可愛の山陵」の伝承地は南九州各地にあるが宮内庁は薩摩川内市の新田神社と正式に決定している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although there are several sites in southern Kyushu that have been believed to be &quot;Hyugo no Enoyama no misasagi&quot;, Ninigi&apos;s burial place, Imperial Household Agency has officially proclaimed that Ninigi was buried in Nitta-jinja Shrine in Satsumasendai City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although there are several sites in southern Kyushu that have been believed to be &quot;Hyugo no Enoyama no misasagi,&quot; Ninigi&apos;s burial place, Imperial Household Agency has officially proclaimed that Ninigi was buried in Nitta-jinja Shrine in Satsumasendai City.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although there are several sites in southern Kyushu that are believed to be &apos;Hyuga no Enoyama no misasagi,&apos; Ninigi&apos;s burial place, the Imperial Household Agency has officially declared that Ninigi was buried in Nitta-jinja Shrine in Satsumasendai City.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>新田神社は大正3年に宮内省直轄となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nitta-jinja Shrine came under the direct control of Imperial Household Agency in 1914.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外処理　（１）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nitta-jinja Shrine came under the direct control of the Imperial Household Agency in 1914.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nitta-jinja Shrine came under the direct control of the Imperial Household Agency in 1914,</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>新田神社のある神亀山の5分の4が御陵の領域である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The four fifths of the Mt. Shinki where the shrine is located is the imperial tomb.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外処理　（２）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Four fifths of Mt. Shinki, where the shrine is located, is the imperial tomb.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Imperial Tomb precinct covers four fifths of Mt. Shinki, where the shrine is located.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>現在は宮内庁書陵部桃山監区可愛部事務所が置かれ、内閣府事務官が陵墓守部として管理されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Currently, the Eno division of the Momoyama regional office, Archives and Mausolea Department of the Imperial Household Agency is placed within the precinct of the shrine and served by an official of the Cabinet Office, who administers the tomb as a guardian.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外処理　（３）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Currently, the Eno division of the Momoyama regional office, Archives and Mausolea Department of the Imperial Household Agency is placed within the precinct of the shrine and served by an official of the Cabinet Office, who administers the tomb as a guardian.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Currently, the Eno division of the Momoyama regional office, Archives and Mausolea Department of the Imperial Household Agency is located within the precinct of the shrine and an official of the Cabinet Office administers the tomb as a guardian.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>御陵と神社が一体となっているのは全国でも珍しい形態である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial tombs that are part of a Shinto shrine are rare nationwide.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial tombs that are part of a Shinto shrine are rare nationwide.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial tombs that are part of a Shinto shrine are rare.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>皇族の参拝は9回にも及んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This shrine was visited by the imperial family as many as nine times.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外処理　（1）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This shrine was visited by the imperial family as many as nine times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This Imperial family have visited the shrine on nine occasions.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>大正9年3月30日・昭和天皇(当時の皇太子)参拝、昭和37年・今上天皇(当時の皇太子)及び皇后美智子(当時の皇太子妃)参拝、など皇族の参拝は9回にも及んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In March 30, 1920, Emperor Showa visited the temple when he was the imperial prince, and in 1962, Emperor Kinjyo paid a visit when he was the imperial price together with his wife, Empress Michiko, who was the crown princess.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外処理　（2）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In March 30, 1920, Emperor Showa visited the temple when he was the imperial prince, and in 1962, Emperor Kinjyo paid a visit when he was the imperial price together with his wife, Empress Michiko, who was the crown princess.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This Imperial family have visited the shrine on nine occasions, including in March 30, 1920, Emperor Showa visited the temple when he was the imperial prince, and in 1962, then Imperial Prince Kinjo (later Emperor Kinjo) visited with Crown Princess Michiko (later Empress Michiko).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。上原文と重複する部分がありますが、ウェブでは該当記述がなく確認できなかったため、原文に合わせ訳文補足しました。また、theを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Tomzo(id:16777), Andre Engels(id:202), Nnh(id:474), Reggaeman(id:6214), Law soma(id:45202), Eskimbot(id:29676), Yanahan(id:2437), OMenda(id:28632), Gombe(id:27), Gibbon(id:14169), Thijs!bot(id:69644), 嫦娥(id:81469), 御子(id:109950), SuisuiBot(id:10165), Watyo(id:160812), Tomika(id:43050), 伏儀(id:142093), Namazu-tron(id:135120), Tsunogaaruhito(id:308028), SieBot(id:126695), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>