<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>巫女</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Miko</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Miko</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Miko</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>巫女、または神子（みこ、ふじょ）とは、主として日本（大和）の神に仕える女性のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">巫女 (miko) or 神子 (fujo) are women who mainly serve the gods of Yamato (Japan).</e>
<cmt>mikoは単複同形にしています。（そのほかの日本語の音をそのまま表記した単語は単複同形にしています。）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">巫女 (miko) or 神子 (fujo) are women who mainly serve the gods of Yamato (Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">巫女 (miko) or 神子 (fujo) are women who mainly serve the gods of Yamato (Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>古来、神の言葉（神託）を得て他の者に伝えることが役割とされていたが、近代に入ってからは神社に於ける女性の奉仕区分として変容した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In ancient times, their role was to get the messages of gods (oracles) and to communicate them to other people, but in the modern age, it has changed to a role in shrines served by women.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In ancient times, their role was to get the messages of the gods (oracles) and convey them to other people, but in the modern age it has changed to a role in shrines served by women.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In ancient times, their role was to get the messages of the gods (oracles) and convey them to other people, but in the modern age it has changed to a role in shrines served by women.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>柳田国男・中山太郎の分類によると、概ね朝廷の神和（かんなぎ）系巫女と民間の口寄（くちよせ）系巫女に分けられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to YANAGIDA Kunio and NAKAYAMA Taro, miko can be classified into two groups; one is called kannagi, a group of miko who served the imperial court, and the other is called kuchiyose, a group of miko who served common people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to YANAGIDA Kunio and NAKAYAMA Taro, miko can be classified into two groups: one is called kannagi, a group of miko who served the Imperial Court, and the other is called kuchiyose, a group of miko who served common people.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Kunio YANAGIDA and Taro NAKAYAMA, miko can be classified into two groups: kannagi, a group of miko who served the Imperial Court; and kuchiyose, a group of miko who served the common people.</e>
<cmt>姓名の順番入れ替え</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>本項目では歴史上の巫女、神社・祭り・結婚式場の巫女に限定する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This section limits miko to those historically famous, serving shrines, ceremonies, and wedding parlors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This section limits miko to those who are historically famous, having served in shrines, ceremonies and wedding parlors.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This section limits miko to those who are historically famous, having served in shrines, ceremonies and wedding parlors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>巫女 (作品・趣味・サブカルチャー)も参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For more information about miko, please see &quot;Miko&apos;s work, hobbies, and subculture&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For more information about miko, please see &quot;Miko&apos;s Work, Hobbies and Subculture.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For more information about miko, please see &quot;Miko&apos;s Work, Hobbies and Subculture.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>古代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ancient times</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ancient times</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ancient times</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>古代の呪術的な宗教観の元では、その祭祀の形態から神の存在は特定の場所に常在する存在ではなく、神を呼ぶという行為が行われていたと考えられ、自らの身体に神を降ろす、いわゆる神がかり（神霊の憑依）の儀式が行われたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the religious services of ancient times where magic rituals prevailed, people who believed that gods did not reside in one particular place performed invocation by having them possess a human body in rituals so called Ritual of Possession.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the religious services of ancient times, where magic rituals prevailed, people who believed the gods did not reside in one particular place performed invocations by having them possess a human body through the so-called Ritual of Possession.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the religious services of ancient times, where magic rituals prevailed, people who believed the gods did not reside in one particular place performed invocations by having them possess a human body through the so-called Ritual of Possession.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>これを掌る女性の登場が巫女の初発と考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is thought that women capable of this gave birth to miko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is thought that women capable of this gave birth to miko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is thought that women capable of this gave birth to miko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>古語では巫と呼称された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In archaic Japanese, the miko was cited as 巫.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In archaic Japanese, the miko was cited as 巫.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In archaic Japanese, the miko was cited as 巫.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>なお、男性でその様な祭祀に仕える者は巫と称された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also note that men who offered similar religious services were referred to as 巫.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, note that men who offered similar religious services were referred to as 巫.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, note that men who offered similar religious services were referred to as 巫.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>『古事記』・『日本書紀』に記される日本神話では、天岩戸の前で舞ったとされる天鈿女命の故事にその原型が見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Japanese myths recorded in &quot;Kojiki&quot; (Records of Ancient Matters) and &quot;Nihonsyoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), Amenouzume who is said to have danced in front of Amam no iwato (Rock cave of heaven) is the archetype of miko.</e>
<cmt>二文に分割しました。『古事記』http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/321176/Kojiki 『日本書紀』http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/415106/Nihon-shoki</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Japanese myths recorded in &quot;Kojiki (Records of Ancient Matters)&quot; and &quot;Nihon Shoki (Chronicles of Japan),&quot; Amenouzume, who is said to have danced in front of Amam no iwato (the rock cave of heaven), is the archetype of miko.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Japanese myths recorded in &quot;Kojiki (Records of Ancient Matters)&quot; and &quot;Nihon Shoki (Chronicles of Japan),&quot; Amenouzume, who is said to have danced in front of Ama no iwato (the rock cave of heaven), is the archetype of miko.</e>
<cmt>Amam→Ama</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>また、『魏志倭人伝』によると、卑弥呼は鬼道で衆を惑わしていたという（卑彌呼 事鬼道 能惑衆）記述があり、この鬼道や惑の正確な意味・内容については不明ではあるものの、古代に呪術的な儀式が女性の手によって行われた事が伺える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Gishi wajinden (Records of the Wa people, Chronicle of Wei), Himiko confused her people using kido (act of calling up the devil) although the details of the kido and how she confused her people are not known, but this shows that in ancient times, magic rituals were performed by women.</e>
<cmt>『魏志倭人伝』定訳不明「鬼道」に関して説明を加えています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Gishi wajinden (Records of the Wa people, Chronicle of Wei),&quot; Himiko confused her people using kido (the act of calling up the devil), although the details of the kido and how she confused her people are not known; however, this shows that in ancient times magic rituals were performed by women.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Gishi wajinden (Records of the Wa people, Chronicle of Wei),&quot; Himiko confused her people using kido (the act of calling up the devil), although the details of the kido and how she confused her people are not known; however, this shows that in ancient times magic rituals were performed by women.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>平安時代には神祇官に「御巫（みかんなぎ）」や天鈿女命の子孫とされた猨女君（『貞観儀式』）の官職が置かれ、神楽を舞っていたと推定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Jogangishiki&quot;, the offices of &apos;mikannagi&apos; and &apos;Sarumeno kimi&apos; undertaken by the descendants of Amenouzume were set up under jingikan in the era of Heian and presumably kagura (Shinto dance and music dedicated to gods) was performed there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Jogangishiki,&quot; the offices of &quot;mikannagi&quot; and &quot;Sarumeno kimi,&quot; as undertaken by the descendants of Amenouzume, were set up under jingikan in the era of Heian, and presumably the kagura (a Shinto dance and music dedicated to the gods) was performed there.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Jogangishiki,&quot; the offices of &apos;mikannagi&apos; and &apos;Sarumeno kimi,&apos; as undertaken by the descendants of Amenouzume, were set up under jingikan in the Heian period, and presumably the kagura (a Shinto dance and music dedicated to the gods) was performed there.</e>
<cmt>the era of Heian→Heian Period&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>平安時代末期の藤原明衡の著である『新猿楽記』には、巫女に必要な4要素として「占い・神遊・寄絃・口寄」が挙げられており、彼が実際に目撃したという巫女の神遊（神楽）はまさしく神と舞い遊ぶ仙人のようだったと、記している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Shin sarugoki&quot; written by FUJIWARA no Akihira at the end of Heian Period lists four abilities required of miko: foretelling, kamiasobi (kagura), yotsura (playing Japanese harp), and kuchiyose (invocation), and the author who saw kamiasobi wrote that it was like angels dancing with gods.</e>
<cmt>神遊・寄絃・口寄に説明を加えています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Shin sarugoki,&quot; written by FUJIWARA no Akihira at the end of Heian period, lists four abilities required of miko: foretelling, kamiasobi (kagura), yotsura (playing Japanese harp) and kuchiyose (invocation); the author who saw kamiasobi wrote that it was &quot;like angels dancing with gods.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Shin sarugoki,&quot; written by FUJIWARA no Akihira at the end of the Heian period, lists four abilities required of miko: foretelling, kamiasobi (kagura), yotsura (playing Japanese harp) and kuchiyose (invocation); the author who saw kamiasobi wrote that it was &quot;like angels dancing with gods.&quot;</e>
<cmt>priod→Priod</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>中世・近世</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Middle Age and Pre-modern Age</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Middle Age and Pre-modern Age</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Middle Age and Pre-modern Age</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="14">
<j>中世以後各地の有力な神社では巫女による神楽の奉納が恒例となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Middle Age onwards, kagura (Shinto dance and music dedicated to gods) came to be performed by miko routinely at major shrines across the country.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the middle age and onward, the kagura (Shinto dance and music dedicated to the gods) came to be routinely performed by miko at major shrines throughout the country.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the middle age and onward, the kagura (Shinto dance and music dedicated to the gods) came to be routinely performed by miko at major shrines throughout the country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>神楽も変容し、旧来の神がかり的要素に加えて依頼者の現世利益の祈願を併せて目的としていたとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Over the time, the kagura had undergone a change; in addition of its traditional supernatural element, it came to be performed to pray for the earthy wishes of requestors who sought for secular benefits.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Over time, the kagura experienced a change so that, in addition to its traditional supernatural element, it came to be performed as a rite of prayer for the earthly wishes of requestors who sought secular benefits.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Over time, the kagura experienced a change so that, in addition to its traditional supernatural element, it came to be performed as a rite of prayer for the earthly wishes of requestors who sought secular benefits.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>修験者と巫女が結びついて神社に常駐せずに祈祷や鎮魂を請負った、民間習俗の色彩が濃い巫女も現れるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Associated with shugenjas (people who practice shugendo, walking around mountains and valleys), a more local and secular type of miko emerged, who performed prayer and invocation outside the shrine.</e>
<cmt>修験者：定訳不明。ただし、なぜ修験者と巫女と結びつくかの背景がわかりにくいと判断し、少し言葉を加えています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Associated with shugenjas (people who practice shugendo, walking around in the mountains and valleys), a more local and secular type of miko emerged, who performed prayers and invocations outside the shrine.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Associated with shugenjas (people who practice shugendo, walking around in the mountains and valleys), a more local and secular type of miko emerged, who performed prayers and invocations outside the shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>現在でも、祈祷・祈願自体を神楽、あるいは「神楽を上げる」と称する例があるのも、このことが基であると考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This explains why, even now, the act of invocation or prayer is sometimes referred to as kagura or &apos;performing kagura&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This explains why, even today, the act of invocation or prayer is sometimes referred to as kagura or &quot;performing kagura.&quot;</e>
<cmt>The place for the period</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This explains why, even today, the act of invocation or prayer is sometimes referred to as kagura or &quot;performing kagura.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>歌舞伎の元である「かぶきおどり」を生み出したとされる出雲阿国（いずものおくに）は出雲大社の巫女であったという説もあり、古代の呪術的な動作が神事芸能として洗練され、一般芸能として民間に広く伝播していった経過を伺い知る例として捉えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some say that Izumo no okuni who originated kabuki odori (kabuki dance), which gave birth to kabuki, was a miko of Izumo Taisha Shrine and this reveals how the magic rituals of ancient times had been refined and propagated as the art of public entertainment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some say that Izumo no okuni, who originated kabuki odori (kabuki dance), which gave birth to kabuki, was a miko of Izumo Taisha Shrine; this reveals how the magic rituals of ancient times have been refined and propagated as the art of public entertainment.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some say that Izumo no okuni, who originated kabuki odori (kabuki dance), which gave birth to kabuki, was a miko of Izumo Taisha Shrine; this reveals how the magic rituals of ancient times have been refined and propagated as the art of public entertainment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="19">
<j>梓巫女（あずさみこ）は官の免許を受け、1回50文から100文の料金での口寄を稼業としていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Officially certified, Azusa miko earned her living by performing kuchiyose (invocation), charging fifty to one hundred mon each time.</e>
<cmt>口寄の説明を加えました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Officially certified, Azusa miko earned her living by performing kuchiyose (invocations), charging 50 to 100 mon each time.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Officially certified, Azusa miko earned her living by performing kuchiyose (invocations), charging 50 to 100 mon each time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>芸妓・娼妓と同様の児買いの奴隷で、売り上げは頭領が手にした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were slaves like geigi (geisha) and shogi (prostitutes) whose revenues went to their masters.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were slaves, such as geigi (geisha) and shogi (prostitutes), whose revenues went to their masters.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were slaves, such as geigi (geisha) and shogi (prostitutes), whose revenues went to their masters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>風体は異様で、黒塗りの箱を風呂敷に包んで背負い、営業時には箱を自分の前に置いて行う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They looked bizarre, carrying a dark stained box wrapped in a furoshiki on their back, and when serving a customer, they put it in front of them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such a person would have a bizarre appearance, carrying a dark-stained box wrapped in a furoshiki on her back, and when serving a customer she would place it in front of him.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such a person would have a bizarre appearance, carrying a dark-stained box wrapped in a furoshiki on her back, and when serving a customer she would place it in front of her.</e>
<cmt>him→her 「自分の前」なので</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>口寄の対象が生者（たとえばペットの猫など）の場合は青葉を用い、死者の場合は紙縒（こより）を用いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They used green leaves for calling up the spirit of a living thing (like the customer&apos;s cat) and koyori (twist of paper) for the soul of the dead.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They used green leaves for calling up the spirit of a living thing (like the customer&apos;s cat) and koyori (twist of paper) for the soul of the dead.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They used green leaves for calling up the spirit of a living thing (like the customer&apos;s cat) and koyori (twist of paper) for the soul of the dead.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>両肘を箱につけてあごを支え、数珠を鳴らし、呪文を唱え、半眠の状態で口寄を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They put their arms on the box, supporting their chin, shook their rosary beads and chanted spells until they dropped off to half-sleep to perform kuchiyose (invocation).</e>
<cmt>念のため、口寄の説明を加えました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She would place her arms on the box, supporting her chin, shake her rosary beads and chant spells until she descended into a state of half-sleep in order to perform the kuchiyose (invocation).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She would place her arms on the box, supporting her chin, shake her rosary beads and chant spells until she descended into a state of half-sleep in order to perform the kuchiyose (invocation).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>箱のなかには土人形の天神、御幣、梓弓が安置してあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the box, a clay doll in the shape of Tenjin (the god of the heaven), gohei (long strips of paper used for Shinto ceremonies), and an azusayumi (bow used for Shinto ceremonies).</e>
<cmt>天神、御幣、梓弓の短い説明を加えました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The box held a clay doll in the shape of Tenjin (the god of the heavens), along with gohei (long strips of paper used for Shinto ceremonies) and an azusayumi (bow used for Shinto ceremonies).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The box held a clay doll in the shape of Tenjin (the god of the heavens), along with gohei (long strips of paper used for Shinto ceremonies) and an azusayumi (bow used for Shinto ceremonies).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>近代になって、人身売買に等しいものとして禁止された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The modern government banned this type of business, considering it equivalent to human trafficking.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The modern government banned this type of business, considering it equivalent to human trafficking.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The modern government banned this type of business, considering it equivalent to human trafficking.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>近代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Modern Age</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Modern Age</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Modern Age</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="26">
<j>明治維新を迎え、神社・祭祀制度の復古的な抜本的見直しが為された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Meiji Restoration, the Meiji government thoroughly revamped the Shinto shrine system and its religious services in a way to support the restoration of the imperial regime.</e>
<cmt>明治維新http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/373305/Meiji-Restoration 「復古的」という表現に解釈を加えています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Meiji Restoration the government thoroughly revamped the Shinto shrine system and its religious services in a way that would support the restoration of the imperial regime.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Meiji Restoration the government thoroughly revamped the Shinto shrine system and its religious services in a way that would support the restoration of the imperial regime.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>1871年（明治4年）には神祇省に御巫（みかんなぎ）が置かれ、宮内省の元刀自が御巫の職務に当たった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1871, Ministry of Divinities set up the post of mikannagi (post of a woman administering religious affairs) and designated a woman who used to work for Ministry of Imperial Household as a toji (a role to take care of the meals the imperial family) to it.</e>
<cmt>神祇省http://www.eudict.com/?lang=engjpk&amp;word=Ministry%20of%20Divinities%20(1871-1872) 御巫および刀自の説明を加えました。宮内省http://ext.dictionary.goo.ne.jp/srch/ej/Imperial+household/m0u/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1871, the Ministry of Divinities set up the post of mikannagi (the post of a woman who administrated religious affairs) and designated it as the post of a woman who used to work for the Ministry of the Imperial Household as a toji (a role of taking care of the meals for the Imperial Family).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1871, the Ministry of Divinities set up the post of mikannagi (the post of a woman who administrated religious affairs) and designated it as the post of a woman who used to work for the Ministry of the Imperial Household as a toji (a role of taking care of the meals for the Imperial Family).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>民間習俗の巫女に関しては、1873年（明治6年）には神霊の憑依などによって託宣を得る行為が教部省によって全面的に禁止された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1873, Ministry of Religious Education banned all the acts of getting oracles through invocation conducted by miko outside the shrine.</e>
<cmt>教部省http://www.eudict.com/?lang=engjpk&amp;word=Ministry%20of%20Divinities%20(1871-1872)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1873, the Ministry of Religious Education banned all acts requesting oracles through the invocation conducted by miko outside the shrine.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1873, the Ministry of Religious Education banned all acts requesting oracles through the invocation conducted by miko outside the shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>⇒s梓巫市子並憑祈祷孤下ケ等ノ所業禁止ノ件　これは巫女禁断令と通称される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is called Miko Ban.</e>
<cmt>梓巫市子並憑祈祷孤下ケ等ノ所業禁止ノ件は、上記と重なるため、訳出なし。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is called Miko Ban.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is called Miko Ban.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>このような禁止措置の背景として、復古的な神道観による神社制度の組織化によるものである一方、文明開化による旧来の習俗文化を否定する動きの影響も伺える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This ban was imposed partly because there had been an attempt to organize the shrine system through Shitoism, the ideological background of the restoration of the imperial regime, and partly because there had been a movement of Bunmei kaika (cultural enlightenment) that negated local, traditional, secular manners and customs.</e>
<cmt>復古的の説明が少し長かったかもしれませんが、ここでは大きな背景を小さく説明しているので、訳が長くなりました。文明開化：定訳不明でした。ただし、訳を一部変えました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This ban was imposed partly because there had been an attempt to organize the shrine system through Shintoism--the ideological background of the restoration of the imperial regime--and partly because there had been a movement of Bunmei kaika (cultural enlightenment) that negated local, traditional and secular manners and customs.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This ban was imposed partly because there had been an attempt to organize the shrine system through Shintoism--the ideological background of the restoration of the imperial regime--and partly because there had been a movement of Bunmei kaika (cultural enlightenment) that negated local, traditional and secular manners and customs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="31">
<j>禁止措置によって神社に常駐せずに民間祈祷を行っていた巫女はほぼ廃業となったが、中には神社、或いは教派神道に所属することによって姿・形を変えて活動を続ける者もいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This ban put almost all the miko who had offered invocation and prayer services outside the shrine out of job although some continued to operate by belonging to traditional shrines or new schools of Shinto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This ban put nearly all the miko who had offered invocations and prayer services outside the shrine out of work, although some continued to operate by belonging to traditional shrines or new schools of Shinto.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This ban deprived work from nearly all the miko who had offered invocations and prayer services outside the shrine, although some continued to operate in various ways through participation in traditional shrines or new schools of Shinto.</e>
<cmt>「姿・形を変えて」の訳を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>また、神職の補助的な立場で巫女を雇用する神社が出始めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some shrines started to hire miko as a role to support Shinto priests.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some shrines started to hire miko as a role to support Shinto priests.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some shrines started to hire miko as a role to support Shinto priests.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>後、春日大社の富田光美らが、巫女の神道における重要性を唱えて巫女舞の存続を訴えると同時に八乙女と呼ばれる巫女達の舞をより洗練させて芸術性を高める事によって巫女及び巫女舞の復興に尽くした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, TOMITA Mitsuyoshi of Kasuga Taisha Shrine and other miko, who stressed the importance of miko in Shinto, pleaded to preserve mikomai (dance played by miko) while committing themselves to restoring their status and their dance by refining it to the realm of art.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, TOMITA Mitsuyoshi (of Kasuga Taisha Shrine) and other miko, who stressed the importance of miko in Shinto, pleaded to preserve the mikomai (dance performed by miko) while committing themselves to restoring their status and their dance by bringing it into the realm of art.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, Mitsuyoshi TOMITA (of Kasuga Taisha Shrine) and other miko, who stressed their importance in Shinto, pleaded to preserve the mikomai (dance performed by miko) while committing themselves to restoring their status and dance by elevating it to the realm of art.</e>
<cmt>姓名の順序入れ替え</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>また、宮内省の楽師であった多忠朝は神社祭祀に於ける日本神話に基づく神楽舞の重要性を主張し、其れが認められる形で浦安の舞を制作した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, O Tadatomo, a gakushi (musician) of Ministry of Imperial Household, emphasized the importance of kaguramai (Shinto dance) in religious services, citing the Japanese mythology, and composed Urayasu no mai, which marked the acceptance of his assertion.</e>
<cmt>宮内省：http://ext.dictionary.goo.ne.jp/srch/ej/Imperial+household/m0u/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, O Tadatomo, a gakushi (musician) of the Ministry of the Imperial Household, emphasized the importance of kaguramai (Shinto dance) in religious services, citing the Japanese mythology, and composed Urayasu no mai, which marked the acceptance of his assertion.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, Tadatomo O, who was a gakushi (musician) of the Ministry of the Imperial Household, emphasized the importance of kaguramai (Shinto dance) in religious services, citing the Japanese mythology, and composed Urayasu no mai, which marked the acceptance of his assertion.</e>
<cmt>姓名の順序入れ替え</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>この舞は1940年（昭和15年）11月10日に開かれる「皇紀二千六百年奉祝会」に合わせて全国の神社で行われた奉祝臨時祭にて一斉に舞われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This dance was performed simultaneously in all the shrines across the country at Hoshuku rinjisai (occasional festival) held as part of Koki Celebration of November 10, 1940 that commemorated the imperial reign of 2600 years.</e>
<cmt>奉祝臨時祭：定訳不明。ただし、訳を少し変えました。皇紀二千六百年奉祝会：定訳不明、ただし、訳を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This dance was performed simultaneously in all the shrines across the country at Hoshuku rinjisai (occasional festivals) held as part of the Koki celebration of November 10, 1940, which commemorated 2600 years of imperial reign.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This dance was performed simultaneously in all the shrines across the country at Hoshuku rinjisai (occasional festivals) held as part of the Koki celebration of November 10, 1940, which commemorated 2600 years of imperial reign.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>事前に全国で開かれた講習会と当日の奉奏の徹底は神社における神楽舞の普及に大きく貢献した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Training sessions held across the country and instructions given to ensure perfect performance on that day helped kaguramai (Shinto dance and music) promulgate among Shinto shrines.</e>
<cmt>「当日の奉奏の徹底」に意味がわかりにくいため、ある程度の工夫を加えました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Training sessions held across the country and instructions given to ensure perfect performance on that day the promulgation of kaguramai (Shinto dance and music) among Shinto shrines.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Training sessions held throughout the country and instructions given to ensure perfect performance on that day promulgated kaguramai (Shinto dance and music) among Shinto shrines.</e>
<cmt>the promulgation of→promulated</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>臨時奉祝祭の後も浦安の舞は継続して祭儀の折に舞われるようになり、維新以降整備されてきた神社祭祀制度に於いて公式に巫女が奉仕する機会が作られたと言える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even after the ceremony, Urayasu no mai continued to be performed in ceremonies and rituals, giving miko official opportunities to serve in the Shinto system which had been renewed since Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even after the ceremony, Urayasu no mai continued to be performed in ceremonies and rituals, giving miko official opportunities to serve in the Shinto system, which had been renewed since the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even after the ceremony, Urayasu no mai continued to be performed in ceremonies and rituals, giving miko official opportunities to serve in the Shinto system, which had been renewed since the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>現代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Modern Age</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Modern Age</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Modern Age</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="38">
<j>現代日本では巫女は神社に勤務し、主に神職の補助、また神事において神楽・舞を奉仕する女性を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Modern Age, miko are women who work for shrines mainly as a role of routinely supporting priests and occasionally performing kagura (Shinto music) and mai (Shinto dance).</e>
<cmt>日本の話であることは明白なので、「日本では」の部分は訳しませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the modern age, miko are women who work for shrines mainly through the role of routinely supporting priests and occasionally performing kagura (Shinto music) and mai (Shinto dance).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the modern age, miko are women who work for shrines mainly through the role of routinely supporting priests and occasionally performing kagura (Shinto music) and mai (Shinto dance).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>舞姫 (曖昧さ回避)（まいひめ）・御神子（みかんこ）と呼称される場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are sometimes called maihime or mikannko.</e>
<cmt>「曖昧さ回避」の意味がわかりませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are sometimes called maihime or mikannko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are sometimes called maihime or mikannko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>巫女を名乗るのに免許や資格は必要ない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Miko do not need a certification or a qualification.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Miko need neither certification nor qualification.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Miko need neither certification nor qualification.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>ただし神社本庁傘下の神社に神職として奉仕する場合、男女ともに本庁の発行する神職が求められる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, if you wish to work for a shrine belonging to Association of Shinto Shrines as a priest, you must be certified by the association regardless of whether you are a man or a woman.</e>
<cmt>神社本庁:http://www.jinjahoncho.or.jp/en/index.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, if you want to work for a shrine belonging to the Association of Shinto Shrines as a priest, you must be certified by the association regardless of whether you are a man or a woman.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, if you want to work for a shrine belonging to the Association of Shinto Shrines as a priest, you must be certified by the association regardless of whether you are a man or a woman.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>なお巫女は男女雇用機会均等法の適用外なので女性を指定しての募集が認められている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also note that shrines are allowed to recruit miko by specifying &apos;female only&quot; as Equal Employment Opportunity Law does not apply to the profession.</e>
<cmt>男女雇用機会均等法:http://pol.cside4.jp/justice/11.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, note that shrines are allowed to recruit miko by specifying &quot;female only,&quot; since the Equal Employment Opportunity Law does not apply to the profession.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, note that shrines are allowed to recruit miko by specifying &quot;female only,&quot; since the Equal Employment Opportunity Law does not apply to the profession.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>本職巫女</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Professional miko</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Professional miko</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Professional miko</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="43">
<j>基本的には資格が必要とされない為、心身ともに健康な女性ならば巫女になることは可能である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As no qualification or certification is required for miko, basically, any woman can serve as a miko as long as she is mentally and physically healthy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because no qualification or certification is required for miko, basically any woman can serve as a miko as long as she is mentally and physically healthy.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because no qualification or certification is required for miko, basically any woman can serve as a miko as long as she is mentally and physically healthy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>本職巫女の多くは神職の娘・近親者など、その神社に縁がある人が奉仕することが多く、本職巫女の求人は余り多いとは言えない（本職巫女を置けるのは大規模神社に限られる場合が多い）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As professional miko are mostly the daughters of priests, their relatives, or those who have connections to the shrine, shrines do not seek many professional miko in public (and generally, only large shrines can afford to hire them).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since professional miko are mostly the daughters of priests, their relatives or those who have connections to the shrine, shrines do not publicly seek many professional miko (and generally, only large shrines can afford to hire them).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since professional miko are mostly the daughters of priests, their relatives or those who have connections to the shrine, shrines do not publicly seek many professional miko (and generally, only large shrines can afford to hire them).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>本職巫女の求人は、新聞・求人広告、ハローワーク等に掲載されることがあり、神社関係者で無い場合はそれらを探すのが本職巫女になる現実的な手段であろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As some professional miko are recruited through newspapers, classified ads, or Hello Work (job-placement office), they may be practical means to land the job if you have no connections to people in shrines.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As some professional miko are recruited through newspapers, classified ads or Hello Work (job-placement office), these may be practical means by which to land a job if you lack connections to people in shrines.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As some professional miko are recruited through newspapers, classified ads or Hello Work (job-placement office), these may be practical means by which to land a job if you lack connections to people in shrines.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>また、神職養成機関（大学や養成所等）には、神職の他に少ないながら本職巫女の求人が寄せられることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Beside priests, some miko, although a few in number, are recruited through educational institutions (like a college and a training school).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Beside priests, some miko, although few in number, are recruited through educational institutions such as colleges and training schools.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Beside priests, some miko, although few in number, are recruited through educational institutions such as colleges and training schools.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="47">
<j>女性が本職巫女として奉仕できる年数は短く、義務教育修了後（現実的には高等学校卒業）から勤務し、20代後半で定年を迎える例が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Women who landed the job do not serve as a professional miko for a long time because most of them retire in their late twenties after starting to work when compulsory schooling is over, (or more practically, after graduating from high school).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Women who landed the job did not serve as professional miko for a long time, because most of them would retire in their late twenties after starting to work when compulsory schooling was over, (or more practically, after graduating from high school).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Women who obtain the jobs do not serve as professional miko for a long time, because most of them retire in their late twenties, having started to work upon the end of compulsory schooling (or more practically, after graduating from high school).</e>
<cmt>時制修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>短大・大学を卒業してからの奉仕であれば、数年間しか在職しないことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If they start to serve as a miko after graduating from college or university, they can do so for only a few years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If one starts serving as miko after graduating from college or university, she can do so for only a few years.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If one starts serving as miko after graduating from college or university, she can do so for only a few years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>定年以降に神社に勤務する場合は、神社指定の制服や松葉色・紺色などの袴を履くなどして服装で区分され、また職掌の上でも神事に奉仕する女性職員を巫女、それ以外の事務作業などを行うのが一般女性職員と区分される事が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As shrines require people who continue to work after retired to wear a dark green or blue hakama (skirtlike trousers) or of a color specified by the shrine, many of them distinguish female employees depending on their jobs; they treat the women who offer religious services as miko and those who do desk work as general workers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because shrines require people who continue to work after retirement to wear a dark-green or blue hakama (skirt-like trousers) or of a color specified by the shrine, many of them distinguish female employees depending on their jobs; they treat the women who offer religious services as miko and those who do desk work as general workers.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because shrines require people who continue to work after retirement to wear a dark-green or blue hakama (skirt-like trousers) or of a color specified by the shrine, many of them distinguish female employees depending on their jobs; they treat the women who offer religious services as miko and those who do desk work as general workers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="50">
<j>尚、神楽を奉仕、指導する巫女については、技術継承などの問題から結婚してからも神社職員として続けている例もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also note that some miko capable of performing kagura (Shinto dance and music) and teaching other miko continue to work even after they are married due to the need for passing on their knowledge and expertise to the younger generations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, note that some miko capable of performing kagura (Shinto dance and music) and teaching other miko continue to work even after they marry due to the need to pass on their knowledge and expertise to the younger generations.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, note that some miko capable of performing kagura (Shinto dance and music) and teaching other miko continue to work even after they marry due to the need to pass on their knowledge and expertise to the younger generations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>助勤巫女</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Part-time miko</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Part-time miko</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Part-time miko</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="51">
<j>正月等の繁忙期には神社の大小に関わらず臨時のアルバイトを採用している例が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many shrines, regardless of their size, temporarily hire part-time miko during busy times like New Year&apos;s Holidays.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many shrines, regardless of their size, temporarily hire part-time miko during busy periods, such as the New Year holidays.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many shrines, regardless of their size, temporarily hire part-time miko during busy periods, such as the New Year holidays.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>一般的にアルバイトと称される臨時雇用を神社では「助勤」「助務」と呼称される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shrines that hire part-time miko call them &apos;helper&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shrines that hire part-time miko refer to them as &quot;helpers.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shrines that hire part-time miko refer to them as &quot;helpers.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>神社独自で雇用を呼びかける、或いは大学・高等学校等への求人の呼びかけ等で採用される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Part-time miko are recruited directly by shrines or through colleges or high schools.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Part-time miko are recruited directly by shrines or through colleges or high schools.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Part-time miko are recruited directly by shrines or through colleges or high schools.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>また、神職養成機関に所属する女子学生が研修生・実習生として臨時に助勤巫女として奉仕する例もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some female students studying at a priest school temporarily work for a shrine as a trainee or apprentice miko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some female students studying at schools for priests temporarily work for shrines as trainees or apprentice miko.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some female students studying at schools for priests temporarily work for shrines as trainees or apprentice miko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>神社によっては、千早の着用の有無等で本職巫女と区別される場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some shrines tell part-time miko from professional ones by requiring them, for example, to wear or not to wear chihaya (half-coats).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some shrines distinguish part-time miko from professional ones by requiring them, for example, to either wear or not wear chihaya (half-coats).</e>
<cmt>usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some shrines distinguish part-time miko from professional ones by requiring them, for example, to either wear or not wear chihaya (half-coats).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>神事・祭りの巫女</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Miko at ceremonies and festivals</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Miko at ceremonies and festivals</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Miko at ceremonies and festivals</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="56">
<j>大規模な神社においては、前述の神社に勤務する巫女が祭祀の際に浦安の舞や伝統の巫女神楽を奉納するが、主に小規模な神社では、臨時に年少者が巫女として奉仕する例も多く存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In large shrines, as discussed earlier, professional miko employed by the shrine perform Urayasu no mai (Shinto dance and music) or more traditional kagura at ceremonies and rituals whereas in many small shrines, children temporarily serve as a miko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In large shrines, as discussed earlier, professional miko employed by the shrine perform Urayasu no mai (Shinto dance and music) or more traditional kagura at ceremonies and rituals, whereas in many small shrines children temporarily serve as miko.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In large shrines, as discussed earlier, professional miko employed by the shrine perform Urayasu no mai (Shinto dance and music) or more traditional kagura at ceremonies and rituals, whereas in many small shrines children temporarily serve as miko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>その多くは神社の氏子である少女によって奉仕されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are mostly the young girls of ujikos (local residents that worship the god of the shrine).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are mostly the young girls of ujikos (local residents that worship the god of the shrine).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are mostly the young girls of ujikos (local residents that worship the god of the shrine).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>祭礼に併せて行われる稚児行列にも巫女装束の年少者が加わる例もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Young female miko sometimes join the proceeding of chigo (young boys) at Shinto feasts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Young female miko sometimes join the proceeding of chigo (young boys) at Shinto feasts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Young female miko sometimes join the proceeding of chigo (young boys) at Shinto feasts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>神楽を奉納する場合は化粧を施す事が多く、特別な場であることから厚化粧となる場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When dedicating kagura to the gods, miko often wear makeup, a lot of makeup as it is a special occasion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When dedicating kagura to the gods, miko often wear makeup, and for this special occasion it is applied heavily.</e>
<cmt>structure</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When dedicating kagura to the gods, miko often wear makeup, and for this special occasion it is applied heavily.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>巫女の装束</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Miko&apos;s costume</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Miko&apos;s costume</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Miko&apos;s costume</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="60">
<j>現在では、巫女装束は白い小袖（白衣）に緋袴を履くのが通常である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today, miko typically wear a white kosode (short-sleeved kimono) and a scarlet hakama.</e>
<cmt>小袖には、説明を加えています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, a miko typically wears a white kosode (short-sleeved kimono) and a scarlet hakama.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, a miko typically wears a white kosode (short-sleeved kimono) and a scarlet hakama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>元来、袴は襠（まち）ありであったが、明治になって教育者の下田歌子が女学生用の袴として行灯袴を発明し、好評だったことから後に同じ女性である巫女の分野にも導入されることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although traditionally, hakama worn by miko had a machi (divider that makes it look like trousers) in it, a hakama called andon hakama (one without a divider) invented by SHIMODA Utako, an educator, in the era of Meiji became so popular among women that it has been adopted as the costume for miko.</e>
<cmt>襠にも説明を加えました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the hakama worn by miko traditionally had a machi (divider that makes it look like trousers) in it, a hakama called andon hakama (one without a divider) invented by SHIMODA Utako, an educator, in the era of Meiji became so popular among women that it has been adopted as the costume for miko.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the hakama worn by a miko traditionally had a machi (divider that made it look like trousers) in it, a hakama called andon hakama (one without a divider) created by Utako SHIMODA, an educator, during the Meiji period became so popular among women that it has been adopted as the miko garment.</e>
<cmt>姓名の順序入れ替え</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>したがって、現代は行灯型の緋袴が一般的であるが、伝統的な襠有りの袴を採用している神社もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These days, scarlet hakama without a machi divider are generally worn by miko but some shrines have adopted traditional ones with a machi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These days, scarlet hakama without machi dividers are generally worn by miko, but some shrines have adopted the traditional type having a machi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These days, scarlet hakama without machi dividers are generally worn by miko, but some shrines have adopted the traditional type having a machi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>特に神楽を舞う場合は足裁きの都合上、襠有りでないと不都合が生じることがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, a hakama without a machi might be inconvenient for moving legs to the music when performing kagura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, a hakama without a machi might be inconvenient for the miko who must move her legs in time to the music when performing kagura.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, a hakama without a machi might be inconvenient for the miko who must move her legs in time to the music when performing kagura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>また、神社によっては若い女性向けの「濃」（こき、赤紫色）袴を用いるところもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, some shrines have adopted koki-colored (red purple) hakama for young ladies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, some shrines have adopted koki-colored (red purple) hakama for young ladies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, some shrines have adopted koki-colored (red purple) hakama for young ladies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="65">
<j>神事の奉仕や神楽を舞う場合など改まった場面では千早を上から羽織る場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In an official scene like holding ceremonies or rituals or performing kagura, miko sometimes wear chihaya (half-coats) on top of their costumes.</e>
<cmt>千早にも説明を加えています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In an official scene, such as when holding ceremonies or rituals or performing kagura, miko sometimes wear chihaya (half-coats) atop their costumes.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In an official scene, such as when holding ceremonies or rituals or performing kagura, miko sometimes wear chihaya (half-coats) atop their costumes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>髪型については、長い黒髪を後ろで檀紙や水引、装飾用の丈長等を組み合わせて（絵元結と呼ばれる）束ねるのを基本としているが、髪の長さを足すために髢（かもじ）を付ける場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Basically, miko tie back their dark hair using the combination of a danshi (quality Japanese paper), a mizuhiki (colored string made of paper), and a takenaga (paper for ornament) (this way of tying hair is called emotoyui), and may wear kamoji (false hair) to make her hair look longer.</e>
<cmt>檀紙・水引・丈長・髢等にも説明を加えました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Basically, miko tie back their dark hair using the combination of a danshi (quality Japanese paper)m a mizuhiki (colored string made of paper) and a takenaga (paper for ornament) (this way of tying hair is called emotoyui), and may wear kamoji (false hair) to make her hair look longer.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Basically, miko tie back their dark hair using the combination of a danshi (quality Japanese paper), mizuhiki (colored string made of paper) and a takenaga (paper for ornament) (this method of tying the hair is called emotoyui), and may wear kamoji (false hair) to make her hair look longer.</e>
<cmt>m a削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>巫女と処女性</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Virginity of miko</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Virginity of miko</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Virginity of miko</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="67">
<j>現代日本における処女性重視は近代以前の武家社会における志向（家督の正統継承）と、明治維新以後、キリスト教由来の貞操観念が普及したことに起因する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Great stress on virginity laid by the modern Japanese society comes from the ideology of the samurai society where the highest importance was attached to inheriting the family&apos;s estate properly and chastity valued by Christianity that has spread since the era of Meiji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The great stress on virginity held by modern Japanese society comes from the ideology of the samurai society, where the highest importance was attached to inheriting the family&apos;s estate properly, as well as the chastity valued by Christianity, which had spread since the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The great stress on virginity held by modern Japanese society comes from the ideology of the samurai society, where the highest importance was attached to inheriting the family&apos;s estate properly, as well as the chastity valued by Christianity, which had spread since the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>勘違いされやすいが処女性重視は古代から現代まで一貫してあった価値観ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many people may misunderstand this, but protecting virginity has not always been stressed throughout the history of this country from ancient times to modern times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many people may misunderstand this, but protecting virginity has not always been stressed throughout the country&apos;s history from ancient times to the modern day.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many people may misunderstand this, but protecting virginity has not always been stressed throughout the country&apos;s history from ancient times to the modern day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>しかし現代人は現代の価値観をもとに、巫女は古来から処女であったと思うことが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, many people today assume that miko have been virgin since ancient times, judging from the value they now have.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, many people today assume that miko have been virgin since ancient times, judging from the value they now have.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, many people today assume that miko have been virgin since ancient times, judging from the value they now have.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>だが歴史的に見て日本の巫女に処女性が求められていたと断言することは出来ない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Historically, we cannot say for sure that miko have been required to be a virgin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Historically, we cannot definitively state that miko have been required to be virgins.</e>
<cmt>syntax</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Historically, we cannot definitively state that miko have been required to be virgins.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>（処女性が全く求められなかったと断言することも出来ない）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(But we cannot say either that virginity has not been required at all.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Neither can we say that virginity has not been required at all.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Neither can we say that virginity has not been required at all.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="72">
<j>なお現代においては職業選択の自由、雇用機会均等法等の観点から、処女であることを求人要項に含めることは出来ない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today, it is impossible for a recruiting shrine to include a requirement for applicants to be virgin in terms of their freedom to choose their occupation and Equal Employment Opportunity Law.</e>
<cmt>雇用機会均等法：http://pol.cside4.jp/justice/11.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, it is impossible for a recruiting shrine to include a requirement for applicants to be virgin in terms of their freedom to choose their occupation and Equal Employment Opportunity Law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, it is impossible for a recruiting shrine to include a requirement for applicants to be virgin in terms of their freedom to choose their occupation and Equal Employment Opportunity Law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>寺院の巫女</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Miko in Buddhist temples</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Miko in Buddhist temples</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Miko in Buddhist temples</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="73">
<j>一部の仏教寺院では若い女性が白衣に緋袴という、巫女装束そのもの、又は類似の服装で奉職する場合がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some Buddhist temples hire young ladies who exactly or almost look like miko, wearing a white kimono and a scarlet hakama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some Buddhist temples hire young ladies who look exactly or nearly like miko, and in such cases they wear a white kimono and a scarlet hakama.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some Buddhist temples hire young ladies who look exactly or nearly like miko, and in such cases they wear a white kimono and a scarlet hakama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="74">
<j>年末年始</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the end of the year and the beginning of the year</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the end of the year and the beginning of the year</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the end of the year and the beginning of the year</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>成田山新勝寺（成田市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Narita-san Shinho-ji Temple (Narita City)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Narita-san Shinho-ji Temple (Narita City)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Narita-san Shinho-ji Temple (Narita City)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>惣宗寺（佐野市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soshu-ji Temple (Sano City)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soshu-ji Temple (Sano City)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soshu-ji Temple (Sano City)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>成田山横浜別院延命院（横浜市西区 (横浜市)）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naritasan Yokohama Betsuin Enmei-in Temple (Nishi-ku Yokohama City)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naritasan Yokohama Betsuin Enmei-in Temple (Nishi-ku Yokohama City)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naritasan Yokohama Betsuin Enmei-in Temple (Nishi Ward, Yokohama City)</e>
<cmt>「区」をWardに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>明王院 (福山市)（広島県福山市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Myoo-in Temple (Fukushima City, Hiroshima Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Myoo-in Temple (Fukushima City, Hiroshima Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Myoo-in Temple (Fukushima City, Hiroshima Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>常時？</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Normally?</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Normally?</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Normally?</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>輪王寺（日光市）（袴が緑色）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rinno-ji Temple (where a miko wears a green hakama.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rinno-ji Temple (where a miko wears a green hakama)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rinno-ji Temple (Nikko City) (where a miko wears a green hakama)</e>
<cmt>「日光市」を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>法要・祭事</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Buddhist memorial service and Shinto ceremonies</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Buddhist memorial service and Shinto ceremonies</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Buddhist memorial service and Shinto ceremonies</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>4月14日～16日華道祭@大覚寺（京都市右京区）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kado-sai (Japanese flower arrangement ceremony) held at Daikaku-ji Temple (Ukyo-ku, Kyoto City) from April 14 to 16 every year</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kado-sai (Japanese flower-arranging ceremony) held at Daikaku-ji Temple (Ukyo-ku, Kyoto City) from April 14 to 16 every year</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kado-sai (Japanese flower-arranging ceremony) held at Daikaku-ji Temple (Ukyo Ward, Kyoto City) from April 14 to 16 every year</e>
<cmt>「区」をWardに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>10月5日～7日観月会@大覚寺（京都市右京区）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kangetsu-sai (moon seeing party) held at Daikaku-ji Temple (Ukyo-ku, Kyoto City) from October 5 to 7 every year</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kangetsu-sai (moon viewing party) held at Daikaku-ji Temple (Ukyo-ku, Kyoto City) from October 5 to 7 every year</e>
<cmt>usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kangetsu-kai (moon viewing party) held at Daikaku-ji Temple (Ukyo Ward, Kyoto City) from October 5 to 7 every year</e>
<cmt>Kangetsu-ｓai→Kangetsu-kai「区」をWardに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>11月3日浦安の舞@正福寺（東村山市）（少女の巫女、市無形民俗文化財）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Urayasu no mai performed by girl miko at Shofuku-ji Temple (Higashimurayama City) (intangible cultural heritage designated by the city)</e>
<cmt>市無形民俗文化財：定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Urayasu no mai performed by girl miko at Shofuku-ji Temple (Higashimurayama City) (intangible cultural heritage designated by the city)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Urayasu no mai performed by girl miko at Shofuku-ji Temple (Higashimurayama City) (intangible cultural heritage designated by the city) on November 3.</e>
<cmt>日付を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>歴史上の主な巫女</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Famous miko in the history</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Famous miko in history</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Famous miko in history</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="85">
<j>卑弥呼（邪馬台国）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Himiko (Yamataikoku)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Himiko (Yamataikoku)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Himiko (Yamataikoku)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="86">
<j>台与（邪馬台国）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toyo (Yamataikoku)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toyo (Yamataikoku)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toyo (Yamataikoku)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="87">
<j>神功皇后</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Empress Jingu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Empress Jingu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Empress Jingu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="88">
<j>飯豊青皇女</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Iitoyoao no mimemiko (Princess Iitoyoao)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Iitoyoao no mimemiko (Princess Iitoyoao)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Iitoyoao no mimemiko (Princess Iitoyoao)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="89">
<j>出雲阿国</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Izumo no okuni</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Izumo no okuni</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Izumo no okuni</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>その他の巫女</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other miko</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other miko</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other miko</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="90">
<j>本項で取り上げた大和の神道における巫女以外にも、「巫女」を「女性のシャーマン」として広義に解釈し、琉球のノロや台湾における尪姨、大韓民国のムーダンの他、シベリア、アメリカ州の先住民族、アフリカなどにみられるシャーマンが巫女と呼ばれる場合がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides the miko of Yamato Shinto discussed in this section, there are people around the world who can be regarded as miko if miko are interpreted as female shamans; they include Noro in Okinawa, Ang-I in Taiwan, Mudang in Korea, indigenous people in Siberia and Americas, and Shaman in Africa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides the miko of Yamato Shinto discussed in this section, there are people around the world who can be regarded as miko if miko are interpreted as female shamans; they include Noro in Okinawa, Ang-I in Taiwan, Mudang in Korea, the indigenous peoples of Siberia and the Americas, and the shaman of Africa.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides the miko of Yamato Shinto discussed in this section, there are people around the world who can be regarded as miko if miko are interpreted as female shamans; they include Noro in Ryukyu (Okinawa), Ang-I in Taiwan, Mudang in Korea, the indigenous peoples of Siberia and the Americas, and the shaman of Africa.</e>
<cmt>Ryukyuを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>また、フィクションでは西洋宗教などにおける神職を指すこともある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In novels, miko refer to the priests of western religions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In novels, the term &quot;miko&quot; refers to the priests of Western religions.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In novels, the term &quot;miko&quot; refers to the priests of Western religions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>この場合は「神子」と表記されることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are often cited as &apos;神子&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are often cited as &apos;神子.&apos;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are often cited as &apos;神子.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="93">
<j>古代ギリシア・ローマの伝説に現れる女予言者「シビル (巫女)」（enSibyl, sibylla）なども「巫女」と訳される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sibyls, female prophets in ancient Greek and Roman legends are also translated as &apos;巫女&apos;.</e>
<cmt>ｼﾋﾞﾙのスペルには、sibylを使用しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sibyls, being female prophets in the legends of ancient Greece and Rome, are also translated as &apos;巫女.&apos;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sibyls, being female prophets in the legends of ancient Greece and Rome, are also translated as &apos;巫女.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>神懸かりとなり神託を伝えるのはシャーマンの特徴である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shamans are famous for communicating messages from gods in trance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shamans are famous for communicating messages from the gods while in a state of trance.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shamans are famous for communicating messages from the gods while in a state of trance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="95">
<j>民間伝承では救世主を待望する異教徒のシンボルであり、キリスト教美術の図像にはアトリビュート（持物）として書物を持つ姿が多く見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In folklore, shamans are a symbol of heretics who have been eagerly waiting for a messiah to come, and in Christian Art, they are often depicted as carrying a book with them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In folklore, is shaman symbolizes a heretic who has eagerly awaited the coming of the Messiah, and in Christian art a shaman would often be depicted as carrying a book.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In folklore, is shaman symbolizes a heretic who has eagerly awaited the coming of the Messiah, and in Christian art a shaman would often be depicted as carrying a book.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>他に「ペルシアの巫女」は頭にヴェール、「リビアの巫女」は灯りのともった蝋燭、「キンメリアの（イタリアの）巫女」はコルヌコピア、「エリュトレイア（リディア）の巫女」は「受胎告知」の預言者として百合、「サモスの巫女」は「キリストの降誕」の預言者として秣桶（まぐさおけ）か揺り籠、「クマエの巫女」も「キリストの降誕」の預言者として貝殻、「ヘレスポントスの巫女」は「キリストの磔刑」の預言者として釘、「アグリッパの（エジプトの）巫女」は浅黒い肌で「キリストの笞打ち」の預言者として笞、「エウロパの巫女」は「出エジプト記」の預言者として「嬰児虐殺」の剣を持つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides the above, &apos;the Sibyl of Persia&apos; wears a veil over her head, &apos;the Sibyl of Libya&apos; carries a lit candle, &apos;the Sibyl of Cimmeria&apos; holds Cornu Copiae, &apos;Herophile from Erythraea&apos;, the prophet of &apos;Annunciation&apos;, carries a lily, &apos;the Sibyl of Samos&apos;, a prophet of &apos;Nativity&apos;, carries a manger or a cradle, &apos;the Sibyl of Cumae&apos;, another prophet of &apos;Nativity&apos;, carries seashells, &apos;the Sibyl of Helespontos&quot;, the prophet of &apos;Crucifixion of Jesus Christ&apos;, carries nails, &apos;the Sibyl of Agrippa&apos;, the prophet of &apos;Caning of Christ&apos;, carries moss, showing her dark skin, and &apos;the Sibyl of Europa&apos;, the prophet of &apos;Book of Exodus&apos;, carries a sword of &apos;Massacre of the Innocents&apos;.</e>
<cmt>用語リストにのっていなかったものもあるため、インタネット上の複数のサイトから調べています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides the above, &quot;the Sibyl of Persia&quot; wears a veil over her head; &quot;the Sibyl of Libya&quot; carries a lit candle; &quot;the Sibyl of Cimmeria&quot; holds a cornucopia; &quot;Herophile, from Eritrea,&quot; the prophet of the Annunciation, carries a lily; &quot;the Sibyl of Samos,&quot; a prophet of the Nativity, carries a manger or a cradle; &quot;the Sibyl of Cumae,&quot; another prophet of the Nativity, carries seashells; &quot;the Sibyl of Helespontos,&quot; the prophet of the Crucifixion of Jesus Christ, carries nails; &quot;the Sibyl of Agrippa,&quot; the prophet of the Persecution of Christ, carries moss, showing her dark skin; and &quot;the Sibyl of Europa,&quot; the prophet of the Book of Exodus, carries a sword of &quot;Massacre of the Innocents.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides the above, &quot;the Sibyl of Persia&quot; wears a veil over her head; &quot;the Sibyl of Libya&quot; carries a lit candle; &quot;the Sibyl of Cimmeria&quot; holds a cornucopia; &quot;Herophile, from Eritrea,&quot; the prophet of the Annunciation, carries a lily; &quot;the Sibyl of Samos,&quot; a prophet of the Nativity, carries a manger or a cradle; &quot;the Sibyl of Cumae,&quot; another prophet of the Nativity, carries seashells; &quot;the Sibyl of Helespontos,&quot; the prophet of the Crucifixion of Jesus Christ, carries nails; &quot;the Sibyl of Agrippa,&quot; the prophet of the Persecution of Christ, carries moss, showing her dark skin; and &quot;the Sibyl of Europa,&quot; the prophet of the Book of Exodus, carries a sword of &quot;Massacre of the Innocents.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>「フリュギアの巫女」は「復活」の預言者として十字架を伴い、「ティブルの巫女」は片手を切り落とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Sibyl of Phrygia&apos;, the prophet of &apos;Resurrection&apos;, carries a crucifix, and &apos;The Sibyl of Tibur&apos; has had one of her hands cut off.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;The Sibyl of Phrygia,&quot; the prophet of the Resurrection, carries a crucifix, and &quot;the Sibyl of Tibur&quot; has had one of her hands cut off.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;The Sibyl of Phrygia,&quot; the prophet of the Resurrection, carries a crucifix, and &quot;the Sibyl of Tibur&quot; has had one of her hands cut off.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>巫女の単独像は少なく、多くは群像として表現される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sibyls are depicted as a group, not as individual people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sibyls are depicted as a group, not as individual people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sibyls are depicted as a group, not as individual people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Bluesky07(id:121929), Bakkai(id:7233), Suguri F(id:11127), Nnh(id:474), T.Saito(id:64009), Eskimbot(id:29676), CommonsDelinker(id:84593), 海那(id:69795), Greenland4(id:114494), Idea(id:35707), Carpkazu(id:27566), Gombe(id:27), 相川　優作(id:29754), 思兼(id:116425), 神祇官(id:99217), Bandalgom(id:31841), Snow steed(id:9428), Loveless(id:129239), Metronome(id:81545), Tsubame-ex(id:53988), Bankokuya(id:91191), Japanese Boy(id:96234), Mikomaid(id:56139), 翰林硯士(id:99377), Toroia(id:31889), Izayohi(id:13095), Kkkdc(id:32227), Keito771(id:67804), U3002(id:66126), Deepimpact(id:129352), 与左衛門(id:159462), しるふぃ(id:11247), マクガイア(id:33346), Jmacs(id:72704), 水野白楓(id:22811), Memosa(id:131221), Areare(id:119960), スーパーゴルフ(id:82367), Kafuka1964(id:105407), MegMilk(id:87329), Hhhhhhhh(id:143356), SuisuiBot(id:10165), Fromm(id:71291), MS472(id:58603), Alexbot(id:157199), Sakura2008(id:182339), 10cm(id:147838), Cpro(id:28341), 弥(id:61590), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>