<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>湯立神楽</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yudate-kagura or Yutate-kagura</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yudate-kagura or Yutate-kagura</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yudate-kagura</e>
<cmt>タイトルでは、「ゆだてかぐら」　のみ表記しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>湯立神楽（ゆだてかぐら/ゆたてかぐら）は日本の伝統的な神楽の形式のひとつ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yudate-kagura is one of Japanese traditional kagura forms.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yudate-kagura is one of Japanese traditional kagura forms.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yudate-kagura (Yutate-kagura) is one of Japanese traditional kagura forms.</e>
<cmt>Yutate-kagura を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>釜で湯を煮えたぎらせ、その湯をもちいて神事を執り行い、無病息災や五穀豊穣などを願ったり、その年の吉兆を占う神事の総称である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yudate-kagura is the general name of religious rites to wish no occurrence of diseases and disasters and rich harvest of five grain crops, etc., and to have the year&apos;s fortune told by conducting rites using boiled water which is extremely boiled in a large pot.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yudate-kagura is the general name of religious rites to wish no occurrence of diseases and disasters and rich harvest of five grain crops, etc., and to have the year&apos;s fortune told by conducting rites using boiled water which is boiled in a large pot.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yudate-kagura is the general name of religious rites to wish no occurrence of diseases and disasters and rich harvest of five grain crops, etc., and to have the year&apos;s fortune told by conducting rites using boiled water which is boiled in a large pot.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="3">
<j>別名を「湯神楽（ゆかぐら）」とも言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yudate-kagura is also called &apos;yu-kagura&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yudate-kagura is also called &apos;yu-kagura&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yudate-kagura is also called &apos;yu-kagura&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="4">
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>同じ湯立神楽でも神社によってかなり違いがあり、玉串に見立てた枝葉を浸して湯を撒くもの（神奈川県藤沢市白旗神社など）や、素手で煮え湯を払うようにして撒くもの（長野県飯田市正八幡神社(遠山郷)など）、全国的にも珍しいご神体を湯につけるもの（香川県丸亀市垂水神社など）などさまざま。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The same yudate-kagura even significantly differs by shrine and various forms exist like the ones in which a tree branch compared to tamagushi (a sacred sakaki tree branch) is dipped in hot water and the hot water is splashed (Shirahata-jinja shrine in Fujisawa City in Kanagawa Prefecture, etc.), boiled water is splashed with bear hands as if sweeping (Seihachiman-jinja shrine (Enzankyo) in Iida City in Nagano Prefecture, etc.), the object of worship is dipped in hot water, being rare throughout Japan (Tarumi-jinja shrine in Marugame City in Kagawa Prefecture, etc.), etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The same yudate-kagura even differ significantly by shrine and various forms exist like the ones in which a tree branch compared to tamagushi (a sacred sakaki tree branch) is dipped in hot water and the hot water is splashed (Shirahata-jinja shrine in Fujisawa City in Kanagawa Prefecture, etc.), boiled water is splashed with bear hands as if sweeping (Seihachiman-jinja shrine (Enzankyo) in Iida City in Nagano Prefecture, etc.), the object of worship is dipped in hot water, being rare throughout Japan (Tarumi-jinja shrine in Marugame City in Kagawa Prefecture, etc.), etc.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The same yudate-kagura even differ significantly by shrine and various forms exist like the ones in which a tree branch compared to tamagushi (a sacred sakaki tree branch) is dipped in hot water and the hot water is splashed (Shirahata-jinja Shrine in Fujisawa City, Kanagawa Prefecture, etc.), boiled water is splashed with bear hands as if sweeping (Seihachiman-jinja Shrine (Enzankyo) in Iida City, Nagano Prefecture, etc.), the object of worship is dipped in hot water, being rare throughout Japan (Tarumi-jinja Shrine in Marugame City, Kagawa Prefecture, etc.), etc.</e>
<cmt>Shrineを大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>なかには釜湯の中に米やお神酒などを入れるものもある（京都府京都市城南宮など）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among them, one form also exists in which rice and holy rice wine are put in hot water in a large pot (Jonan-gu shrine in Kyoto City in Kyoto Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among them, one form also exists in which rice and holy rice wine are put in hot water in a large pot (Jonan-gu shrine in Kyoto City in Kyoto Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>Spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among them, one form also exists in which rice and holy rice wine are put in hot water in a large pot (Jonan-gu Shrine in Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture, etc.).</e>
<cmt>Shrineを大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="7">
<j>また、海辺の神社では釜湯に海水を使うところもある（千葉県横芝光町四社神社など）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In some of the shrines along seashores, sea water is used in stead of the hot water in a large pot (Yonsha-jinja shrine in Yokoshibaikari Town in Chiba Prefecture, etc.).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In some of the shrines along seashores, sea water is used in stead of the hot water in a large pot (Yonsha-jinja shrine in Yokoshibaikari Town in Chiba Prefecture, etc.).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In some of the shrines along seashores, sea water is used instead of the hot water in a large pot (Yonsha-jinja Shrine in Yokoshibahikari-cho, Chiba Prefecture, etc.).</e>
<cmt>Shrineを大文字にしました。Yokoshibahikari-cho としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="8">
<j>いずれも撒かれた湯（その飛沫）を浴びると無病息災になるとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In any of such rites, it is believed that a person who has received the splashed hot water (or its drips) shall suffer no disease and become healthy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In any of these rites, it is believed that a person who has received the splashed hot water (or its drips) shall suffer no disease and become healthy.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In any of these rites, it is believed that a person who has received the splashed hot water (or its drips) shall suffer no disease and become healthy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="9">
<j>また、神社によっては釜湯を飲むと無病息災になるとされているところもあり、ビンなどにつめて持ち帰ることのできるところもある（長野県天龍村池大神社など）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that a person who has drunk the hot water shall suffer no disease and become healthy in some shrines and, therefore, some shrines allow visitors to bring the hot water in their bottles (Ikedai-jinja shrine in Tenryu Village in Nagano Prefecture, etc.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that a person who has drunk the hot water shall suffer no disease and become healthy in some shrines and, therefore, some shrines allow visitors to bring the hot water in their bottles (Ikedai-jinja shrine in Tenryu Village in Nagano Prefecture, etc.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that a person who has drunk the hot water shall suffer no disease and become healthy in some shrines and, therefore, some shrines allow visitors to bring the hot water in their bottles (Ikedai-jinja Shrine in Tenryu-mura, Nagano Prefecture, etc.)</e>
<cmt>Tenryu-mura　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 伏儀(id:142093), P.Tonnies(id:163233), 廬舎那憂(id:168188), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>