<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>神鳳鈔</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jinbosho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jinposho</e>
<cmt>「神鳳鈔」の読みは、「じんぼうしょう」ではなく、次文にあるように「じんぽうしょう」です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jinposho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>神鳳鈔（じんぽうしょう）とは、伊勢神宮（内宮および外宮）の領地の諸国一覧表である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jinbosho is a list of various districts of Ise Jingu Shrine(both Naiku and Geku) territory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jinposho is a list of various districts of Ise-jingu Shrine (both Naiku (the inner shrine) and Geku (the outer shrine)) territory.</e>
<cmt>「神鳳鈔」の読みは、「じんぼうしょう」ではなく、次文にあるように「じんぽうしょう」です。不要なスペースを削除し、必要なスペースを加えました。内宮と外宮の補足を加えました。Ise Jingu Shrine &gt;&gt; Ise-jingu Shrine　と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jinposho is a list of various districts of Ise-jingu Shrine (both Naiku (the inner shrine) and Geku (the outer shrine)) territory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>『群書類従』第1巻に収録されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is recorded in the first volume of &quot;Gunsho ruiju&quot;(Collection of historical documents compiled by Hokiichi HANAWA).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is recorded in the first volume of &quot;Gunsho ruiju&quot; (Collection of historical documents compiled by Hokiichi HANAWA).</e>
<cmt>全角の括弧を半角に直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is recorded in the first volume of &quot;Gunsho ruiju&quot; (Collection of historical documents compiled by Hokiichi HANAWA).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>建久四年（1193年）に、原本の書き出しを始め、その後追記がなされ、延文5年（1360年）に原本完成し注進とある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The original book was started to be written in 1193, postscripted later and is said to be completed in 1360.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the beginning of writing the original work started in 1193 and followed by addition of postscript, the original work had completed and reported in 1360.</e>
<cmt>「注進」が訳漏れです。書き直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the beginning of writing the original work started in 1193 and followed by addition of postscript, the original work had completed and reported in 1360.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>慶安3年（1650年）に、写本作成。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The manuscript was made in 1650.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The manuscript was made in 1650.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The manuscript was made in 1650.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>群書類従に収録にあたって、小野高潔本を本書とし、屋代弘賢本および武州足立郡人福島東雄本を校合したと記録されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is reported that in recording in &quot;Gunsho ruiju&quot;, Takakiyo ONO book was considered as a main part and the book by Hirotaka YASHIRO and Azumao FUKUSHIMA from Adachi Country of Bushu (Musashi Province) were refered.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is recorded that a book by Hirotaka YASHIRO and a book by Azumao FUKUSHIMA, who was from Adachi Country of Bushu (Musashi Province) were collated with a book by Takakiyo ONO as the main text when recording in &quot;Gunsho ruiju&quot;(Collection of historical documents compiled by Hokiichi HANAWA).</e>
<cmt>群書類従の補足を加えました。本書　は the main text　です。文の意味は、「屋代弘賢本と福島東雄本を、小野高潔本と照合し、校合した」ということなので、訳文の意味が間違っています。書き直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is recorded that a book by Hirotaka YASHIRO and a book by Azumao FUKUSHIMA, who was from Adachi Country of Bushu (Musashi Province) were collated with a book by Takakiyo ONO as the main text when recording in &quot;Gunsho ruiju&quot;(Collection of historical documents compiled by Hokiichi HANAWA).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>さらに、嘉永6年（1853年）にも校勘とある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also told to be revised in 1853.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also told to be revised in 1853.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also told to be revised in 1853.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>原本は現存しておらず、写本に異同があり、校正して作成されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The original book does not exist today and it was executed after correction as there were differences in the manuscript.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The original book does not exist today and it was executed after correction, as there were differences in the manuscript.</e>
<cmt>カンマを加えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The original book does not exist today and it was executed after correction, as there were differences in the manuscript.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>なお、現存する最古の写本は、伊勢神宮の所有するもので、室町時代の内宮禰宜の荒木田氏経による写本である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The oldest manuscript that exist today is the one owned by Ise Jungu Shrine written by Ujitsune ARAKIDA. Negi of Naiku in Muromachi era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The oldest manuscript that exists today is the one owned by Ise-jingu Shrine written by Ujitsune ARAKIDA, Negi (Shinto priest) of Naiku in Muromachi era.</e>
<cmt>Ise Jingu Shrine &gt;&gt; Ise-jingu Shrine　と修正しました。ピリオドをカンマに修正しました。Exist &gt;&gt; exists と修正しました。禰宜の補足を加えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The oldest manuscript that exists today is the one owned by Ise-jingu Shrine written by Ujitsune ARAKIDA, Negi (Shinto priest) of Naiku in Muromachi era.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>伊勢神宮の領地は、諸国において神戸、御厨、御薗、神田、名田などと表記されており、所在地の伊勢国に集中している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The territories of Ise Jungu Shrine are represented as Kobe, mikuriya(manors of Imperial family and powerful shrines), Misono, Kanda and Myoden and are concentrated in Ise Province which is the seat.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The territories of Ise-jingu Shrine are written as Kanbe (territories of shrines), Mikuriya (manors of Imperial family and powerful shrines), Misono (territories that cultivated vegetables offered to god), Kanda (rice fields owned by shrines) and Myoden (a rice field in a manor or Kokugaryo (territories managed by provincial government) which were named with its owner&apos;s name) and they are concentrated in Ise Province, where the Ise-jingu Shrine is located.</e>
<cmt>Ise Jingu Shrine &gt;&gt; Ise-jingu Shrine　と修正しました。不要なスペースを削除し、必要なスペースを加えました。「the seat」は「the site」の間違いであると思われます。削除します。「諸国において」が訳漏れです。必要な補足を加えました。ここでの神戸、は「かんべ/ごうどetc」と読み、「神社の土地」という意味で訳すのが適切であると思います。「御薗」は、神に供える野菜類を栽培する土地、という意味で訳しました。「名田」書き換えます。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The territories of Ise-jingu Shrine are written as Kanbe (territories of shrines), Mikuriya (manors of Imperial family and powerful shrines), Misono (territories that cultivated vegetables offered to god), Kanda (rice fields owned by shrines) and Myoden (a rice field in a manor or Kokugaryo (territories managed by provincial government) which were named with its owner&apos;s name) and they are concentrated in Ise Province, where the Ise-jingu Shrine is located.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>そのため本書では、伊勢国内に関しては、郡単位に詳細が記述されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, in the main part, the detailed descriptions are given for each state regarding Ise Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, in the main part, the detailed descriptions are given for each state regarding Ise Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, in the main part, the detailed descriptions are given for each state regarding Ise Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="11">
<j>※伊勢神宮領については、神宮雑例集、太神宮諸雑事記などにも記載がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">*Regarding Ise-Jingu territory, it is mentioned in some documents such as Jingu miscellany and Okami (God) mscellany.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">*Regarding Ise-Jingu territory, it is mentioned in some documents such as Jingu miscellany and Okami (God) miscellany.</e>
<cmt>スペルミスです。Mscellany &gt;&gt; Miscellany</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">*Regarding Ise-Jingu territory, it is mentioned in some documents such as Jingu miscellany and Okami (God) miscellany.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Showhead999(id:259332), 梁山泊智多星呉用(id:127114), Law soma(id:45202), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>