<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>御旅所</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Otabisho (place where the sacred palanquin is lodged during a festival)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Otabisho</e>
<cmt>Deleted explanation as it&apos;s long and included in cell F4</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Otabisho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>御旅所（おたびしょ）とは、神社の祭礼（神幸祭）において神（一般には神体を乗せた神輿）が巡幸の途中で休憩または宿泊する場所地をさす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Otabisho means the place where a deity (generally mikoshi or portable shirine that carries a deity) takes a rest or stays at night on the way of its tour during a shrine festival (Shinko-sai Festival).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Otabisho means the place where a deity (usually the mikoshi, or portable shirine, that carries the deity) takes a rest or stays overnight while on a ritual procession during a shrine festival (Shinko-sai Festival).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Otabisho means the place where a deity (usually the mikoshi, or portable shrine, that carries the deity) takes a rest or stays overnight while on a ritual procession during a shrine festival (Shinko-sai Festival).</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>或いは神幸の目的地をさす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Otherwise, it means the destination of such Shinko (tour carrying a deity in a potable shrine).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It can also mean the destination of such processions.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, brevity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It can also mean the destination of such processions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>巡幸の道中に複数箇所設けられることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Otabisho is sometimes set up at several points on the tour route.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are sometimes several otabisho set up along the tour route.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are sometimes several otabisho set up along the tour route.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>御旅所に神輿が着くと御旅所祭が執り行われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the arrival of mikoshi in otabisho, Otabisho-sai Ceremony is performed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the arrival of the mikoshi at the otabisho, the Otabisho-sai Ceremony is performed.</e>
<cmt>ArticlesPreposition</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the arrival of the mikoshi at the otabisho, the Otabisho-sai Ceremony is performed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>御旅所には神社や祭神にまつわる場所や氏子地域にとって重要な場所が選ばれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Otabisho is selected among the places related to the shrines or the enshrined deity, or the places important for the region of ujiko (shrine parishioners).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Otabisho are selected from among places related to the shrines or the enshrined deity, or places important to the shrine&apos;s parish district.</e>
<cmt>PrepositonRevised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Otabisho are selected from among places related to the shrines or the enshrined deity, or places important to the shrine&apos;s parish district.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>元宮、摂末社や配偶神を祀る神社などのような社殿があるものもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some otabisho, such as Motomiya (an origin of Miya), Setsumatsu sha (smaller shrine managed under the shrine) and the shrines sacred to spouses of deity, have sanctuaries.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some otabisho, such as Motomiya (original shrines), auxilliary and branch shrines, and shrines dedicated to &apos;consort deities&apos;, have actual shrine buildings.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some otabisho, such as Motomiya (original shrines), auxiliary and branch shrines, and shrines dedicated to &apos;consort deities,&apos; have actual shrine buildings.</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置移動スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>そのほか、元の鎮座地などに臨時の祭殿を設けたり、氏子の代表（頭人）の家に迎える場合などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are also other cases in which the previous enshrined place set up with temporary saiden (shrine, sanctuary) or the house of director (tonin) of ujiko also serve as otabisho.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In other cases, temporary structures set up on previously enshrined land or the house of the head (tonin) of the parishoners (ujiko) also serve as otabisho.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In other cases, temporary structures set up on previously enshrined land or the house of the head (tonin) of the parishioners (ujiko) also serve as otabisho.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Rusk(id:9895), トトト(id:235842), Nnh(id:474), くにゃこ(id:38684), 依存性だんぢり中毒(id:79907), ラッパ食堂(id:255123), 弥(id:61590), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>