<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>黄泉醜女</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yomotsu-shikome</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yomotsu-shikome</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yomotsu-shikome</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>黄泉醜女（よもつしこめ）は、日本神話に伝わる黄泉の鬼女。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yomotsu-shikome is Kijo (an ogress) of Yomi (world after death) which has been handed down by Japanese Mythology.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yomotsu-shikome is a female demon of the afterworld in Japanese Mythology.</e>
<cmt>this sentence was confusing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yomotsu-shikome is a female demon of Yomi (the world after death) in Japanese Mythology.</e>
<cmt>the afterworld を Yomi (the world after death) に修正しました。参考：http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/653592/Yomi-no-Kuni</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>予母都志許売とも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also written in another kanji characters &apos;予母都志許売&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also written with the kanji characters &apos;予母都志許売&apos;.</e>
<cmt>prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also written with the kanji characters &apos;予母都志許売&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>イザナミが自分との約束を破って逃げ出したイザナギを捕まえるため、黄泉醜女にイザナギを追わせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Izanami (The Female Who Invites) made Yomotsu-shikome chase Izanagi (The Male Who Invites) in desire to catch him because he had ran away from her breaking his promise.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Izanami (The Female Who Invites) made Yomotsu-shikome chase Izanagi (The Male Who Invites) in desire to catch him because he had run away from her, breaking his promise.</e>
<cmt>verb conjugation; punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Izanami (The Female Who Invites) made Yomotsu-shikome chase Izanagi (The Male Who Invites) in desire to catch him because he had run away from her, breaking his promise.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>イザナギは蔓草で出来た髪飾りを投げつけた所、そこから山ブドウの実が生えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Izanagi threw a hair ornamentation made of tsurukusa (vine), it bore bunches of wild grape.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Izanagi threw a hair ornamentation made of a vine, it bore bunches of wild grapes.</e>
<cmt>removed parentheses; plural grapes</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Izanagi threw a hair ornamentation made of a vine, it bore bunches of wild grapes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>黄泉醜女はそれに食いつくも、食べ終わると再びイザナギを追いかけた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yomotsu-shikome once stopped chasing him as she sank her teeth into them but she started chasing again after she finished eating.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yomotsu-shikome stopped chasing him as she sank her teeth into them but she started chasing again after she finished eating.</e>
<cmt>deleted “once”</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yomotsu-shikome stopped chasing him as she sank her teeth into them but she started chasing again after she finished eating.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>次にイザナギは右の角髪から湯津津間櫛（ゆつつなくし）を取り、その歯を折って投げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, Izanagi took his yutsutsunakushi (comb) from his right tsunogami (a style of hairdo in ancient Japan, in which the hair was twisted into knots on top of the head and held in place with pins), snapped off a tooth of the comb and threw it at her.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, Izanagi took his comb from his right tsunogami (a style of hairdo in ancient Japan, in which the hair was twisted into knots on top of the head and held in place with pins), snapped off a tooth of the comb and threw it at her.</e>
<cmt>deleted “yutsutsunakushi”</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, Izanagi took his comb from his right tsunogami (a style of hairdo in ancient Japan, in which the hair was twisted into knots on top of the head and held in place with pins), snapped off a tooth of the comb and threw it at her.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>すると今度はタケノコが生えてきて、黄泉醜女はまたそれに食いついた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Now, takenoko (bamboo shoots) sprouted from it and Yomotsu-shikome sank her teeth into it again.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then bamboo shoots sprouted from it and Yomotsu-shikome again ate them.</e>
<cmt>deleted “takenoko”</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then bamboo shoots sprouted from it and Yomotsu-shikome again ate them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>その間に、イザナギは黄泉醜女から逃げ切ったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, Izanagi got clear away from Yomotsu-shikome.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, Izanagi got clear away from Yomotsu-shikome.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, Izanagi got clear away from Yomotsu-shikome.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), BOTarate(id:185620), Fromm(id:71291), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>