<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>御田</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Onda (same meaning as Ta-asobi as play a series of processes from rice field preparation until harvest)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Onda</e>
<cmt>この文書の内容上、用語集にある「御田」の補足を使用するのは適切でないため、また、次文で「御田とは…」が説明されているため、補足は使用しません。同じ漢字で「おでん」もありwikipwdia上では「この項目では…」と注が入っていますが、ローマ字では読みが「おんだ」と違うため、タイトルでは「Onda」のみの記載とします。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Onda</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>御田(おた、みた、おみた、おんた、おんだ、おでん)とは、寺社や皇室等が所有する領田のこと、またその領田で行われる行事のことも指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Onda (ota, mita, omita, onta, onda, oden) means the territory that temples, shrines and the Imperial family own and also the rites and festivals held there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Onda (ota, mita, omita, onta, onda, oden) is the territories owned by temples, shrines and the Imperial family and also the rites and festivals held there.</e>
<cmt>means the territory that … から、 is the terrirories owned by….と変更しました。不要なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Onda (ota, mita, omita, onta, onda, oden) refers to the territories owned by temples, shrines and the Imperial family and it also refers to the rites and festivals held there.</e>
<cmt>is→refers toにしました。 also→it also refers to</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>「寺田（てらだ）」、「神田(かんだ)」「御神田」とも呼ばれるが、一般に「寺田」「神田」と呼ぶ場合は領田そのもののことを指し行事のことは指さない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called as &quot;Terada (Tenple-Rice field)&quot;, &quot;Kanda&quot; and &quot;Omita&quot;, but when we say &quot;Terada&quot; and &quot;Kanda&quot;, they no not mean the rites and festivals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called as &quot;Terada (Temple-Rice field)&quot;, &quot;Kanda&quot; and &quot;Omita&quot; but when they are called as &quot;Terada&quot; and &quot;Kanda&quot;, it generally means the territory itself, not the rites and festivals.</e>
<cmt>Tenple &gt;&gt; temple のスペルミスです。「they no not mean」ですが、「they do not」と修正しました。。「一般に」が訳漏れです。「領田そのもののことを指し」が訳漏れです。書き直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called as &quot;Terada (Temple-Rice field), &quot;&quot;Kanda&quot; and &quot;Omita,&quot; however, they genrally refer to the territory itself, not the rites and festivals.</e>
<cmt>コンマを引用符の中に入れました。 but when they are called as &quot;Terada&quot; and &quot;Kanda, &quot; it→however, they genrally refer to に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>また田楽と同義にも使われおでんと読んだ場合は一般に料理のおでんのことを指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also used for a synonym of dengaku and when we call it as &quot;oden (a Japanses dish containing al kinds of ingredients cooked in a specal broth of soy sauce), it generally means oden of dishes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also used for a synonym for dengaku and when it is read as oden, it generally means oden (a Japanse dish containing al kinds of ingredients cooked in a specal broth of soy sauce) of dishes.</e>
<cmt>&quot; が一つのみ入っていました。削除しました。また、おでんの補足ですが、「おでんと呼んだ場合は・・・」に続けるよりも、「料理のおでん」の後に続ける方が適切であると思われます。（「読んだ場合」は単に読みのことを指しているので、料理のおでんを指してはいないので。）synonym of ではなく、synonym for が正しいと思われます。when we call it as を when it is read asと書き換えました。Japaneses &gt;&gt; Japanese のスペルミスです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also used for a synonym for dengaku and when it is read as oden, it generally means oden (a Japanse dish containing al kinds of ingredients cooked in a specal broth of soy sauce) of dishes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>明治初頭の上知令で寺社の領地（寺社領）が廃止されたため、一時的に日本全国の寺社の御田が消滅した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Onda of temples and shrines disappered temporarily for the whole country of Japan as the territory of temples and shrines was abolished by Agechi-rei (confiscation command of territory) in the early period of Meiji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Onda owned by temples and shrines in the whole of Japan had disappeared temporarily, as Agechi-rei (confiscation command of territory) issued in the beginning of Meiji period abolished territories of temples and shrines (temples and shrines estate).</e>
<cmt>（寺社領）が訳漏れです。書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Onda owned by temples and shrines in the whole of Japan had disappeared temporarily, as Agechi-rei (confiscation command of territory) issued in the beginning of Meiji period abolished territories of temples and shrines (temples and shrines estate).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>その後周辺の住民の寄贈などにより御田が再興された寺社があり、伊勢神宮は2ヶ所に御田を残している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Onda was revived for some temples and shrines by the contribution of the residents of the vicinities afterwards and there are Onda in two places of Ise-Jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, some temples and shrines retrieved their Onda with donation from the neighboring residents; Ise-jingu Shrine keeps Onda in two locations.</e>
<cmt>書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, some temples and shrines retrieved their Onda with donation from the neighboring residents; Ise-jingu Shrine keeps Onda in two locations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>皇居内の御田では天皇自らが田植と稲刈りを行う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The emperor plants and cuts rice himself within Onda of Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emperor himself plants and harvests rice at Onda inside Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt>The emperor &gt;&gt; The Emperor himselfと修正しました。Cut rice &gt;&gt; harvest rice と修正しました。Within &gt;&gt; at と修正しました。Of &gt;&gt; inside「（皇居）内」が訳漏れです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emperor himself plants and harvests rice at Onda inside Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>行事</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">rites and festivals</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rites and Festivals</e>
<cmt>小文字になっていました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rites and Festivals</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>日本人と稲作の深い関わりを示すものとして、多くの御田に関する行事が日本各地に伝承されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many rites and festivals regarding Onda are handed down as factors that shows deep relationship with Japanese and rice cropping and Tawara no onda, Isobe no Omita (Dengaku performed in the shrine festival in Isobe) and Kiragawa no Onta Matsuri (the Festival of Ontamachiman-gu Shrine in Kiragawa) are listed as intangible folk-cultural property.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many rites and festivals related to Onda have been passed down in all parts of Japan, showing a close relationship between Japanese people and rice cultivation.</e>
<cmt>「日本各地に」が訳漏れです。書き換えました。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many rites and festivals related to Onda have been passed down in all parts of Japan, showing a close relationship between Japanese people and rice cultivation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>田原の御田、磯部の御神田、吉良川の御田祭は、重要無形民俗文化財に指定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tawara no onda (Ta-asobi performed as a shrine ritual in Tawara), Isobe no Omita (Dengaku performed in the shrine festival in Isobe) and Kiragawa no Onta Matsuri (the Festival of Ontamachiman-gu Shrine in Kiragawa) are designated as intangible folk-cultural property.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処listed &gt;&gt; designated　と修正しました。 田原の御田の補足を加えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tawara no onda (Ta-asobi performed as a shrine ritual in Tawara), Isobe no Omita (Dengaku performed in the shrine festival in Isobe) and Kiragawa no Onta Matsuri (the Festival of Ontamachiman-gu Shrine in Kiragawa) are designated as intangible folk-cultural property.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Miketsukunibito(id:10208), たね(id:10372), Miya(id:1881), N yotarou(id:60870), Wakkubox(id:30396), きゅーてぃーキッズ・なおちゃん(id:28547), Aomuna(id:44720), 短髄彦(id:5555), 梅澤 威志(id:17353), Shimoxx(id:9332), Nekosuki600(id:21263), Tr-909(id:25414), Greenland4(id:114494), Hatsune(id:26654), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>