<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>事代主</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kotoshiro nushi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kotoshiro nushi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kotoshiro nushi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>事代主（ことしろぬし、言代主神）は、日本神話に登場する神。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kotoshiro nushi (a Japanese ancient god) is a god that appears in Japanese Mythology (Shinto religion).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kotoshiro nushi (a Japanese ancient god) is a god that appears in Japanese Mythology (Shinto religion).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kotoshiro nushi (a Japanese ancient god) is a god that appears in Japanese Mythology (Shinto religion).</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>別名 八重言代主神、八重事代主神（ヤエコトシロヌシ）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also known as Yaekotoshironushi-no-kami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also known as Yaekotoshironushi-no-kami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also known as Yaekotoshironushi no kami.</e>
<cmt>ハイフン削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>神話の記述</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mythological Description</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mythological Description</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mythological description</e>
<cmt>文頭以外の語頭を小文字に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>大国主とカムヤタテヒメとの間に生まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born to Okuninushi and Kamuyatate-hime.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born to Okuninushi and Kamuyatate-hime.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born to Okuninushi and Kamuyatate-hime.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>葦原中国平定において、タケミカヅチらが大国主に対し国譲りを迫ると、大国主は美保ヶ崎で漁をしている息子の事代主が答えると言った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Okuninushi was requested by Takemikazuchi to give him the country at Ashihara no Nakatsukuniheitei, Okuninushi replied that his son, Kotoshiro nushi (a Japanese ancient god) is fishing in Mihogasaki Cape and would reply.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Okuninushi was requested by Takemikazuchi to give him the country at Ashihara no Nakatsukuniheitei, Okuninushi replied that his son, Kotoshiro nushi (a Japanese ancient god) is fishing at Mihogasaki Cape and would reply.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Okuninushi was requested by Takemikazuchi to hand over the land at Ashihara no Nakatsukuniheitei, Okuninushi replied that his son, Kotoshiro nushi (a Japanese ancient god) was away fishing at Mihogasaki Cape and would reply.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>そこでタケミカヅチが美保ヶ崎へ行き事代主に国譲りを迫った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then Takemikazuchi went to Mihogasaki Cape to request Kotoshiro nushi to give him the country.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then Takemikazuchi went to Mihogasaki Cape to request Kotoshiro nushi to give him the country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then Takemikazuchi went to Mihogasaki Cape to request Kotoshiro nushi to hand over control of the land.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>事代主は「承知した」と答え、船を踏み傾け、手を逆さに打って青柴垣に変えて、その中に隠れてしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kotoshiro nushi answered, &quot;I will give the country,&quot; and then tilted the boat with his foot, slapped his hands upside down to transform the boat into Aofushigaki (fresh brushwood fence), and hid himself in it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kotoshiro nushi answered, &quot;I will give the country,&quot; and then tilted the boat with his foot, slapped his hands upside down to transform the boat into Aofushigaki (fresh brushwood fence), and hid himself in it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kotoshiro nushi answered in the affirmative, then tilted the boat with his foot, slapped his hands upside down to transform the boat into a fresh brushwood fence and hid himself in it.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>タケミナカタもタケミカヅチに服従すると、大国主は国譲りを承諾し、事代主が先頭に立てば私の180人の子供たちもは事代主に従って天津神に背かないだろうと言った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hearing that Takeminakata also gave in to Takemikazuchi, Okuninushi agreed to give the country saying that his 180 children would not disobey Amatsu kami (god of heaven) following Kotoshiro nushi if Kotoshiro nushi lead them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hearing that Takeminakata also gave in to Takemikazuchi, Okuninushi agreed to give the country saying that his 180 children would not disobey Amatsu kami (god of heaven) following Kotoshiro nushi if Kotoshiro nushi lead them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Upon hearing that Takeminakata also gave in to Takemikazuchi, Okuninushi agreed to hand over the land saying that his 180 children would not disobey Amatsu kami (god of heaven) if Kotoshiro nushi was the leader.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="9">
<j>解説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Explanation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Explanation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Explanation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>名前の「コトシロ」は「言知る」の意で、託宣を司る神である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His name &quot;Kotoshiro&quot; literally means &quot;knwoing words&quot; and he is a god that took charge of takusen (oracle).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His name &quot;Kotoshiro&quot; literally means &quot;knowing words&quot; and he is a god that took charge of takusen (oracle).</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His name &apos;Kotoshiro&apos; literally means &apos;knowing words&apos; and he is a god that took charge of takusen (oracle).</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>言とも事とも書くのは、古代において言（言葉）と事（出来事）とを区別していなかったためである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Koto&quot; in his name can be written in Chinese character &quot;言&quot; (words) or &quot;事&quot; (events), because there was no difference between words and events in the ancient times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Koto&quot; in his name can be written in the Chinese character &quot;言&quot; (words) or &quot;事&quot; (events), because there are no difference between words and events in ancient times.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koto in his name can be written in the Chinese character &quot;言&quot; (words) or &quot;事&quot; (events), because there was no distinction between words and events in ancient times.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="12">
<j>大国主の子とされているが、元々は出雲ではなく大和の神とされていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Believed to be a son of Okuninushi, Kotoshiro nushi is said to have originally come from not Izumo but in Yamato.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Believed to be a son of Okuninushi, Kotoshiro nushi is said to have originally come not from Izumo, but from Yamato.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Believed to be a son of Okuninushi, Kotoshiro nushi is said to have originally come not from Izumo, but from Yamato.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>国譲り神話の中で出雲の神とされるようになったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He started to be a god in Izumo in a mythology of giving the country.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became a Mythical god in Izumo known for giving away the country.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became a Mythical god in Izumo known for giving away control of the land.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>元々は葛城の田の神で、一言主の神格の一部を引き継ぎ、託宣の神の格も持つようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was originally a god of a paddy field in Katsuragi and started to assume the status of a god of an oracle by taking over a part of the status of Hitokoto nushi (a Japanese ancient god).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was originally a god of paddy fields in Katsuragi and started to assume the status of a god of oracles by taking over part of the status of Hitokoto nushi (a Japanese ancient god).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was originally a god of paddy fields in Katsuragi and assumed the status of a god of oracles by taking over part of the status of Hitokoto nushi (a Japanese ancient god).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。スペース削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>このため、葛城王朝において事代主は重要な地位を占めており、現在でも宮中の御巫八神の一つになっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is why Kotoshiro nushi held an important position in Katsuragi Dynasty and is regarded as one of the Mikannagi Hasshin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is why Kotoshiro nushi held an important position in Katsuragi Dynasty and is regarded as one of the Mikannagi Hasshin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is why Kotoshiro nushi held an important position in Katsuragi Dynasty and is regarded as one of the Mikannagi Hasshin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>葛城には、事代主を祀る鴨都波神社（奈良県御所市）があり、賀茂神社（賀茂別雷神社・賀茂御祖神社）のような全国の鴨（賀茂・加茂など）と名の付く神社の名前の由来となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Katsuragi has Kamotsuba-jinja Shrine (,Gose City, Nara PrefectureI, which is the origin of the names of shrines having &quot;kamo&quot; in it all over the country, for exmaple Kamo-Jinja Shrine (Kamowakeikazuchi-jinja Shrine and Kamomioya-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Katsuragi has Kamotsuba-jinja Shrine (,Gose City, Nara PrefectureI, which is the origin of shrines having the names &quot;kamo&quot; in it all over the country, for example Kamo-Jinja Shrine (Kamowakeikazuchi-jinja Shrine and Kamomioya-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>spelling, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Katsuragi has Kamotsuba-jinja Shrine (Gose City, Nara Prefecture), which is the origin of shrines having the names &quot;kamo&quot; in it all over the country, for example Kamo-jinja Shrine (Kamowakeikazuchi-jinja Shrine and Kamomioya-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>文中のカンマ削除I→）Jinja→jinja</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="17">
<j>美保で青柴垣に引き籠った事代主神は、伊豆の三宅島で三島明神になったとする伝承もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a legend that Kotoshiro nushi, who shut himself up in Aofushigaki in Miho, became Mishima-myojin (the deity of Mishima-jinja Shrine) in Miyake-jima Island in Izu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a legend that Kotoshiro nushi, who shut himself up in Aofushigaki in Miho, became Mishima-myojin (the deity of Mishima-jinja Shrine) in Miyake-jima Island one of the seven islands of Izu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a legend that Kotoshiro nushi, who shut himself up in Aofushigaki in Miho, became Mishima-myojin (the deity of Mishima-jinja Shrine) in Miyake-jima Island one of the seven islands of Izu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>富士山の神とともに10の島を生み、現在の三嶋大社（静岡県三島市）に鎮座したとする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The legend also says that he was enshrined in present-day Mishima-taisha Shrinei (Mishima City, Shizuoka Prefecture) after producing 10 islands with the god of Mt. Fuji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The legend also says that he was enshrined in present-day Mishima-taisha Shrinei (Mishima City, Shizuoka Prefecture) after producing 10 islands together with the god of Mt. Fuji.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The legend also says that he was enshrined in present-day Mishima-taisha Shrine (Mishima City, Shizuoka Prefecture) after producing 10 islands together with the god of Mt. Fuji.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="19">
<j>信仰</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Worship</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Worship</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Worship</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>託宣神のほか、国譲り神話において釣りをしていたことから釣り好きとされ、海と関係の深いえびすと同一視される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is regarded not only as a god of takusen but also as a lover of fishing and identical to Ebisu (god of fishing and commerce) having a close relation with the sea because he was fishing in the story of giving the country.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is regarded not only as a god of takusen but also as a lover of fishing and is identical to Ebisu (god of fishing and commerce) having a close relationship with the sea because he was fishing during the story of giving away the country.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is regarded not only as a god of oracles but also as a lover of fishing and is identical to Ebisu (god of fishing and commerce) because he was fishing during the story of giving away control of the land.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>海の神、商業の神としても信仰されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also worshiped as the sea god and a god of commerce.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also worshiped as the sea god and a god of commerce.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also worshiped as the sea god and a god of commerce.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>七福神の中のえびすが大鯛を小脇に抱え釣竿を持っているのは、国譲り神話におけるこのエピソードによるものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ebisu of Shichifukujin (Seven Deities of Good Luck) carries a big sea bream under his arm and has a fishing rod comes from the episode of turning over the country.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ebisu of Shichifukujin (the Seven Deities of Good Luck) carries a big sea bream under his arm while holding a fishing rod, comes from the episode of turning over the country.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The deity Ebisu, one of the Seven Deities of Good Luck, carries a big sea bream under his arm while holding a fishing rod, and originates in the story of handing over control of the land.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="23">
<j>美保神社（島根県松江市）、長田神社（神戸市長田区）のほか、今宮戎神社（大阪市浪速区）などのえびすを祀る神社でも祀られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is alos enshrined in shrines that are dedicated to Ebisu such as Miho-jinja Shrine (Matsue City, Shimane Prefecture), Nagata-jinja Shrine (Nagata Ward, Kobe City) asd well as Imamiya-ebisu-jinja Shrine (Naniwa Ward Osaka Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is also enshrined in shrines that are dedicated to Ebisu such as Miho-jinja Shrine (Matsue City, Shimane Prefecture), Nagata-jinja Shrine (Nagata Ward, Kobe City) asd well as Imamiya-ebisu-jinja Shrine (Naniwa Ward Osaka Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is also enshrined in shrines that are dedicated to Ebisu such as Miho-jinja Shrine (Matsue City, Shimane Prefecture), Nagata-jinja Shrine (Nagata Ward, Kobe City) as well as Imamiya-ebisu-jinja Shrine (Naniwa Ward Osaka Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="24">
<j>ただし今宮戎神社については、その名称からして本来は「今西宮」の略であろうと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the name of Imamiya-ebisu-jinja Shrine suggests that &quot;Imamiya&quot; is an abbreviation of &quot;Ima Nishinomiya.&quot; originally</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the name of Imamiya-ebisu-jinja Shrine suggests that &quot;Imamiya&quot; is originally an abbreviation of &quot;Ima Nishinomiya.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the name of Imamiya-ebisu-jinja Shrine suggests that &apos;Imamiya&apos; is originally an abbreviation of &apos;Ima Nishinomiya.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>従って祭神は戎総本宮を名乗る西宮神社と同じくヒルコであったと考えるのが自然である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore it is natural that its enshrined deity was Hiruko like Nishinomiya-jinja Shrine, which presents itself as Ebisu Sohongu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore it is natural that its enshrined deity was Hiruko like Nishinomiya-jinja Shrine, which presents itself as the Ebisu Sohongu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore it is natural that its enshrined deity was Hiruko like Nishinomiya-jinja Shrine, which presents itself as the Ebisu Sohongu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 妙翅鳥(id:55475), Rusk(id:9895), Dreammagic(id:86847), Nnh(id:474), Greenland4(id:114494), Law soma(id:45202), Ajax(id:11202), ベッチョナイ(id:52283), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>