<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>本朝神社考</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Honcho Jinja Ko&quot; (a study of Japanese shrine)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Honcho Jinja Ko&quot; (a study of Japanese shrine)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Honcho Jinja Ko&quot; (a study of Japanese shrine)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>本朝神社考（ほんちょうじんじゃこう）は、林羅山の著。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Honcho Jinja Ko&quot; (a study of Japanese shrine) is a book authored by Razan HAYASHI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Honcho Jinja Ko&quot; (a study of Japanese shrine) is a book authored by Razan HAYASHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Honcho Jinja Ko&quot; (a study of Japanese shrine) is a book authored by Razan HAYASHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>中世以来、仏教者のために王道が衰え、神道が廃れたのに憤り筆をとった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Razan wrote the book from the indignation that the influence of the Imperial family and Shintoism plunged after the medieval period due to the emerge of Buddhists.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Razan wrote the book out of indignation that the influence of the Imperial family and Shintoism plunged after the medieval period due to the emergence of Buddhists.</e>
<cmt>prepositions; use of “emerge” as a noun</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Razan wrote the book out of indignation that the influence of the Imperial family and Shintoism plunged after the medieval period due to the emergence of Buddhists.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="3">
<j>神仏混淆を斥け、国家を上古の淳直の世に立ち返らせようとこいねがい、口碑縁起を訪ね歩き、これを『古事記』、『日本書紀』、『延喜式』、『風土記』その他に証し、日本のおもな神社の伝記その他をしるしたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wishing to eliminate the syncretism of Buddhism and Shintoism and have the nation return to simple and right world of ancient time, Razan visited many sites of folklores and origins of shrines and recorded legends of main shrines in Japan by referring to &quot;Kojiki&quot; (Records of Ancient Matters), &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), &quot;the Engishiki&quot; (an ancient book for codes and procedures on national rites and prayers), fudoki (description of regional climate, culture, etc.) and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wishing to eliminate the syncretism of Buddhism and Shintoism and have the nation return to the simple and right world of ancient times, Razan visited many sites of folklores and origins of shrines and recorded legends of the main shrines in Japan by referring to &quot;Kojiki&quot; (Records of Ancient Matters), &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), &quot;Engishiki&quot; (an ancient book for codes and procedures on national rites and prayers), &quot;fudoki&quot; (description of regional climate, culture, etc.) and others.</e>
<cmt>so on-&gt;others</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wishing to eliminate the syncretism of Buddhism and Shintoism and have the nation return to the simple and right world of ancient times, Razan visited many sites of folklores and origins of shrines and recorded legends of the main shrines in Japan by referring to &quot;Kojiki&quot; (Records of Ancient Matters), &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), &quot;Engishiki&quot; (an ancient book for codes and procedures on national rites and prayers), &quot;fudoki&quot; (description of regional climate, culture, etc.) and others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 千早スパイラル(id:180323), Nnh(id:474), 松茸(id:27535), 弥(id:61590), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>