<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>矢大臣</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yadaijin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yadaijin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yadaijin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>矢大臣（やだいじん）は、 神社の随身門の左右に安置されている、随身の装束をした2神像のうち、向かって左方の弓矢をもっている神像。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yadaijin is one of the two deity statures in Zuijin (Imperial guards during the Heian period) costumes that are placed at the both sides of Zuijin-mon gate, holding bows and arrows on the obserber&apos;s left.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yadaijin is one of the two deity statures in Zuijin (Imperial guards during the Heian period) costumes that are placed at the both sides of Zuijin-mon gate, holding bows and arrows on the observer&apos;s left.</e>
<cmt>Spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yadaijin is one of the two deity statures in Zuijin (Imperial guards during the Heian period) costumes that are placed at the both sides of Zuijin-mon gate, holding bows and arrows on the observer&apos;s left.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>概略</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summery</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>Spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>神社の門守（かどもり）の神である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is Kadomori, a guardian deity at the shrine gate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kadomori, a guardian deity at the shrine gate.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kadomori, a guardian deity at the shrine gate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>闕腋袍を着て、巻纓の冠をかむり、緌をし、剣を佩き、弓箭を帯する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is dressed in Kettekino-ho (open sleeve seams outer robe), putting on Kenei no kanmuri (headdress) with Oikake (accessaries for the headdress), wearing a sword, holding bows and arrows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is dressed in Kettekino-ho (open sleeve seams outer robe), putting on Kenei no kanmuri (headdress) with Oikake (accessaries for the headdress), wearing a sword, holding bows and arrows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is dressed in Kettekino-ho (open sleeve seams outer robe), putting on Kenei no kanmuri (headdress) with Oikake (accessories for the headdress), wearing a sword, holding bows and arrows.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="5">
<j>箭を負うことから矢大臣といい、随身門を矢大臣門ということがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is called Yadaijin (Minister with arrows) after his arrows, and Zuijin-mon gate is sometimes called Yadaijin-mon gate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is called Yadaijin (Minister with arrows) after his arrows, and Zuijin-mon gate is sometimes called Yadaijin-mon gate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is called Yadaijin (Minister with arrows) after his arrows, and Zuijin-mon gate is sometimes called Yadaijin-mon gate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="6">
<j>しかし大臣ではなく、看督長（かどのおさ）である随身である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he is not a Daijin (minister) but a Zuijin of Kadono-osa (public officer).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, he is not a Daijin (minister) but a Zuijin of Kadono-osa (public officer).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, he is not a Daijin (minister) but a Zuijin (attendant) called Kadono-osa (public officer).</e>
<cmt>隋身→attendant と補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="7">
<j>天石門別神をいうともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also he is referred as Amanoiwatowake-no-kami (one of the deities from Japanese Mythology).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also he is referred as Amanoiwatowake-no-kami (one of the deities from Japanese Mythology).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also he is referred as Amanoiwatowake no Kami (one of the deities from Japanese mythology).</e>
<cmt>神名表現を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>天孫降臨のとき天忍日命および天久米命が、天石靭をとり、頭椎の太刀を佩き、天波十弓をとりもち、天真児矢をたばさみ、先に立ったさまをうつしたともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Or it is said that the image of Yadaijin comes from Amenooshihi-no-mikoto and Amatsukume-no-mikoto in the lead, removing Amenoiwahagi (big rocks), holding Kabutsuchi-no-tachi (the ancient sword), 天波十弓 (bows), and 天真児矢 (arrows) at the time of Tensonkorin (the descent to earth of the grandson of the sun goddess).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処天波十弓、天真児矢、読み方不明です。天石靭が岩かどうかは不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Or it is said that the image of Yadaijin comes from Amenooshihi-no-mikoto and Amatsukume-no-mikoto in the lead, removing Amenoiwahagi (big rocks), holding Kabutsuchi-no-tachi (the ancient sword), 天波十弓 (bows), and 天真児矢 (arrows) at the time of Tensonkorin (the descent to earth of the grandson of the sun goddess).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Or it is said that the image of Yadaijin comes from Amenooshihi no Mikoto and Amatsukume no Mikoto in the lead, removing Amenoiwahagi (big rocks), holding Kabutsuchi-no-tachi (the ancient sword), 天波十弓 (bows), and 天真児矢 (arrows) at the time of Tensonkorin (the descent to earth of the grandson of the sun goddess).</e>
<cmt>神名表現を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>