<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>大物忌神</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omonoimi-no-kami</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omonoimi-no-kami</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omonoimi no Kami</e>
<cmt>Omonoimi-no-kami→Omonoimi no Kami　として、神名表現を統一しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>大物忌神（おおものいみのかみ）は、鳥海山に宿るとされる神 (神道)である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Omonoimi-no-kami&quot; is a god (Shinto) believed to dwell in Mt. Chokai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Omonoimi-no-kami&quot; is a god (Shinto) believed to dwell in Mt. Chokai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omonoimi no Kami is a god (Shinto) believed to dwell in Mt. Chokai.</e>
<cmt>Omonoimi-no-kami→Omonoimi no Kami　として、神名表現を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>鳥海山頂の鳥海山大物忌神社をはじめ、東北地方各地に大物忌神を祀る神社がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are shrines enshrining Omonoimi-no-kami in various locations in the Tohoku region, including Chokaisan-Omonoimi-jinja Shrine at the summit of Mt. Chokai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are shrines enshrining Omonoimi-no-kami in various locations in the Tohoku region, including Chokaisan-Omonoimi-jinja Shrine at the summit of Mt. Chokai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are shrines enshrining Omonoimi no Kami in various locations in the Tohoku region, including Chokaisan-Omonoimi-jinja Shrine at the summit of Mt. Chokai.</e>
<cmt>Omonoimi-no-kami→Omonoimi no Kami　として、神名表現を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>鳥海山は古代のヤマト王権の支配圏の北辺にあることから、大物忌神は国家を守る神とされ、また、穢れを清める神ともされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Mt. Chokai is in the northern area of the region ruled by the ancient Yamato sovereignty (the ancient Japan sovereignty), Omonoimi-no-kami was considered a god guarding the nation, and also a god purifying stains.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Mt. Chokai is in the northern area of the region ruled by the ancient Yamato sovereignty (the ancient Japan sovereignty), Omonoimi-no-kami was considered a god guarding the nation, and also a god purifying stains.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Mt. Chokai is in the northern area of the region ruled by the ancient Yamato sovereignty (the ancient Japan sovereignty), Omonoimi no Kami was considered a god guarding the nation, and also a god purifying stains.</e>
<cmt>Omonoimi-no-kami→Omonoimi no Kami　として、神名表現を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>鳥海山は火山であり、鳥海山の噴火は大物忌神の怒りであると考えられ、噴火のたびにより高い神階が授けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Mt. Chokai is a volcano and the eruption of Mt. Chokai was believed to be the anger of Omonoimi-no-kami, a higher shinkai (ranks granted to Shinto gods) was granted every time it erupted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Mt. Chokai is a volcano and the eruption of Mt. Chokai was believed to be the anger of Omonoimi-no-kami, a higher shinkai (ranks granted to Shinto gods) was granted every time it erupted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Mt. Chokai is a volcano and the eruption of Mt. Chokai was believed to be the anger of Omonoimi no Kami, a higher shinkai (ranks granted to Shinto gods) was granted every time it erupted.</e>
<cmt>Omonoimi-no-kami→Omonoimi no Kami　として、神名表現を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>大物忌神は、ウカノミタマ・トヨウケビメ・大忌神・廣瀬大社などと同神とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omonoimi-no-kami is considered the same god as Ukano-mitama, Toyokebime, Oimi-no-kami, Hirose-taisha Shrine, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omonoimi-no-kami is considered to be the same god as Ukano-mitama, Toyokebime, Oimi-no-kami, Hirose-taisha Shrine, etc.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omonoimi no Kami is considered to be the same god as Ukano mitama, Toyouke-bime, Oimi no Kami, Hirose-taisha Shrine, etc.</e>
<cmt>神名表現を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>鳥海山大物忌神社の社伝では神宮外宮の豊受大神と同神としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the biography of Chokaisan-Omonoimi-jinja Shrine, it is described as the same god as Toyouke no Okami (Grand Divine Toyouke) of the Geku (the outer shrine) of Jingu shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is described as the same god as Toyouke no Okami (Grand Divine Toyouke) of the Geku (the outer shrine) of Jingu shrine, in the biography of Chokaisan-Omonoimi-jinja Shrine,</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is described as the same god as Toyouke no Okami (Grand Divine Toyouke) of the Geku (the outer shrine) of Jingu Shrine, in the biography of Chokaisan-Omonoimi-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>カンマ→ピリオド　に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>鳥海月山両所宮では鳥海山の神として倉稲魂命を祀っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the Chokai Gassan Ryoshogu Shrine, Uganomitama no mikoto is enshrined as the god of Mt. Chokai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Uganomitama no mikoto is enshrined as the god of Mt. Chokai at the Chokai Gassan Ryoshogu Shrine</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Uganomitama no Mikoto is enshrined as the god of Mt. Chokai at the Chokai Gassan Ryosho-gu Shrine</e>
<cmt>神名表現を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Nnh(id:474), 短髄彦(id:5555), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>