<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>月次祭</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsukinami-no-matsuri</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsukinami-no-matsuri</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsukinami-no-matsuri</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>月次祭（つきなみのまつり）とは、神道における祭礼のひとつ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsukinami-no-matsuri (literally, monthly festival) is one of festivals in shinto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsukinami-no-matsuri (literally, monthly festival) is a festival in shinto.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsukinami-no-matsuri (literally, monthly festival) is a festival in shinto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>伊勢神宮では6月・12月の月次祭と神嘗祭の3つの祭礼を三節祭（さんせつさい）、三時祭（さんじさい）と称される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Ise-jingu shrine, tsukinami-no-matsuri held in June and December and Kanname-no-matsuri are called sansetsu-sai or sanji-sai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Ise-jingu shrine, tsukinami-no-matsuri held in June and December and Kanname-no-matsuri are called sansetsu-sai or sanji-sai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Ise-jingu Shrine, tsukinami-no-matsuri held in June and December and Kanname-no-matsuri (Kanname-sai festival) are called sansetsu-sai festival or sanji-sai festival.</e>
<cmt>神嘗祭→Kanname-sai festival　追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>古くは毎月行われたようであるが、『延喜式』において6月と12月の11日に行うことが規定された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the old days, tsukinami-no-matsuri seemed to be held monthly, however, it was determined in &quot;Enkishiki&quot; to hold tsukinami-no-matsuri on 11th day of June and December.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the old days, tsukinami-no-matsuri seemed to be held monthly, however, it was determined in &quot;Enkishiki&quot; to hold tsukinami-no-matsuri on 11th day of June and December.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the old days, tsukinami-no-matsuri seemed to be held monthly, however, it was determined in the &quot;Engishiki&quot; (an ancient book for codes and procedures on national rites and prayers) to hold tsukinami-no-matsuri on 11th day of June and December.</e>
<cmt>Engishiki とし、説明を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>朝廷と伊勢神宮で行われ、11日の朝には畿内に祀られている304座の神に対し朝廷（神祇官）から幣帛が分け与えられた（班幣）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsukinami-no-matsuri is held in the Imperial Court and Ise-jingu shrine and, on the morning of 11th day, heihaku (silk as a gift) was provided from the Imperial Court to 304 gods worshipped in Kinai area (hanhei).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsukinami-no-matsuri is held in the Imperial Court and Ise-jingu shrine and, on the morning of 11th day, heihaku (silk as a gift) was provided from the Imperial Court to 304 gods worshipped in Kinai area (hanhei).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsukinami-no-matsuri is held in the Imperial Court and Ise-jingu Shrine and, on the morning of 11th day, heihaku (silk as a gift) was provided from the Imperial Court to 304 gods worshipped in Kinai area (hanhei).</e>
<cmt>Shrine　と大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>その後、班幣は伊勢神宮のみとなり、室町時代に入ると応仁の乱などにより班幣は廃されるようになったが、明治以降になって復活した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later on, Ise-jingu shrine only conducted hanhei and, when Muromachi period started, hanhei was abolished due to Onin War, etc., however, hanhei revived in Meiji period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later on, Ise-jingu shrine only conducted hanhei and, when the Muromachi period started, hanhei was abolished due to Onin War, etc., however, hanhei was revived in the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later on, Ise-jingu Shrine only conducted hanhei and, when the Muromachi period started, hanhei was abolished due to Onin War, etc., however, hanhei was revived in the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>Shrine　と大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>なお現在では、全国の多くの神社でも毎月一定の日を決めて月次祭が行われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Currently, many shrines throughout Japan determines a specific day of the month and conduct tsukinami-no-matsuri on that day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Currently, many shrines throughout Japan determine a specific day of the month and conduct tsukinami-no-matsuri on that day.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Currently, many shrines throughout Japan determine a specific day of the month and conduct tsukinami-no-matsuri on that day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 与左衛門(id:159462), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>