<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>風土記</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fudoki (description of regional climate, culture, etc.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fudoki (description of regional climate, culture, etc.)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fudoki (description of regional climate, culture, etc.)</e>
<cmt>イタリック体をゴシック体に修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>中国の本の名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Titles of Chinese books</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Titles of Chinese books</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Fudoki&quot; is a title of Chinese books.</e>
<cmt>Titles に主語を補って&quot;Fudoki&quot; is a title に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>西晋の平西将軍の周処による「周処風土記」に始まり、盧植による「冀州風土記」、沈瑩による「臨海風土記」、陸恭之によるとされる風土記、「北魏風土記」などが存在するとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As well as &apos;Zhou Chu fudoki&apos; written by Zhou Chu under the General Who pacified the West in the Western Jin Dynasty, it is thought that &apos;Ji zhou fudoki&apos; written by Lu Zhi, &apos;Rinkai fudoki&apos; written by Shen Ying and &apos;Northern Wei fudoki&apos; as fudoki which is believed to have been written by Kyoshi RIKU exist.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Along with Zhou Chu fudoki written by Zhou Chu under the General Who pacified the West in the Western Jin Dynasty, it is thought that Ji zhou fudoki written by Lu Zhi, Rinkai fudoki written by Shen Ying, and Northern Wei fudoki exist as fudoki which are believed to have been written by Kyoshi RIKU.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Along with &apos;Zhou Chu fudoki&apos; written by Zhou Chu under the General Who pacified the West in the Western Jin Dynasty, it is thought that &apos;Ji zhou fudoki&apos; written by Lu Zhi, &apos;Rinkai fudoki&apos; written by Shen Ying, and &apos;Northern Wei fudoki&apos; exist as fudoki which are believed to have been written by Kyoshi RIKU.</e>
<cmt>Zhou Chu fudoki, Ji zhou fudoki, Rinkai fudoki, Northern Wei fudoki にそれぞれシングルコーテーションを追記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>辺境生活の見聞をまとめたものであろうといわれるが、詳細は不明。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These books are thought to carry the summary of what was watched and heard about people&apos;s lives in remote regions, but the details are uncertain.</e>
<cmt>　</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These books are thought to carry the summary of what was observed and heard about people&apos;s lives in remote regions, but the details are uncertain.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These books are thought to carry the summary of what was observed and heard about people&apos;s lives in remote regions, but the details are uncertain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>日本の奈良時代に地方の文化風土や地勢等を国ごとに記録編纂された物。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is an item in which the information of the culture, climate, topography, etc of each province was recorded and compiled in the Nara Period in Japan.</e>
<cmt>　</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is an item in which the information of the culture, climate, topography, etc of each province was recorded and compiled in the Nara Period in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is an item in which the information of the culture, climate, topography, etc of each province was recorded and compiled in the Nara Period in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>正式名称ではなく、ほかの風土記と区別して「古風土記」ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called &apos;Kofudoki&apos; (ancient fudoki compiled by imperial order in 713 CE) to differentiate it from other fudoki, though it is not an official name.</e>
<cmt>　</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called Kofudoki (ancient fudoki compiled by imperial order in 713 CE) to differentiate it from other fudoki, although it is not an official name.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called &apos;Kofudoki&apos; (ancient fudoki compiled by imperial order in 713 CE) to differentiate it from other fudoki, although it is not an official name.</e>
<cmt>Kofudoki にシングルコーテーションを追記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>律令制度の各国別で記されたと考えられ、幾つかが写本として残されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fudoki is thought to have been prepared for each province under the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code) and some fudoki&apos;s manuscripts are restored.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fudoki is thought to have been prepared for each province under the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code) and some fudoki&apos;s manuscripts have been restored.</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fudoki is thought to have been prepared for each province under the ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code) and some fudoki&apos;s manuscripts have been restored.</e>
<cmt>Ritsuryo を ritsuryo に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>この記事ではこれについて記す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This article is talking about this.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This article discusses this.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This article discusses this.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>2の作成後散逸の為、後の時代に再度編纂された物。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some fudoki were lost or missing, and they were compiled again in later years.</e>
<cmt>ここは何が主語なのかはっきりしません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some fudoki were lost or missing, and they were compiled again in later years.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some fudoki were lost or missing, and they were compiled again in later years.</e>
<cmt>イタリック体をゴシック体に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>または地方の歴史や文物を記した書物の一般名称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Or, it is the general name of a book in which the history and products of culture of a certain region are described.</e>
<cmt>　</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Or, it is the general name of a book in which the history and products of culture of a certain region are described.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Or, it is the general name of a book in which the history and products of culture of a certain region are described.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>三河後風土記、東北後風土記、斐太後風土記、今日の風土記など。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mikawa Go Fudoki (the Topographical Records of Mikawa Province,) Tohoku Go Fudoki (Updated Geographical Description of Tohoku region,) Hida Go Fudoki (Updated Geographical Description of Hida Province) and fudoki of nowadays.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mikawa Go Fudoki (the Topographical Records of Mikawa Province), Tohoku Go Fudoki (Updated Geographical Description of the Tohoku region), Hida Go Fudoki (Updated Geographical Description of Hida Province), and fudoki of nowadays.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mikawa Go Fudoki (the Topographical Records of Mikawa Province), Tohoku Go Fudoki (Updated Geographical Description of the Tohoku region), Hida Go Fudoki (Updated Geographical Description of Hida Province), and fudoki of nowadays.</e>
<cmt>イタリック体をゴシック体に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>古風土記</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kofudoki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kofudoki</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kofudoki</e>
<cmt>イタリック体をゴシック体に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>風土記（ふどき）とは、奈良時代初期の官撰の地誌。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fudoki is a local report which was compiled by imperial order in the early Nara Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fudoki is a local report which was compiled by imperial order in the early Nara Period.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fudoki is a local report which was compiled by imperial order in the early Nara period.</e>
<cmt>イタリック体をゴシック体に修正しました。Period を period に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>元明天皇の詔により各令制国の国庁が編纂し、主に漢文体で書かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At Emperor Genmei&apos;s order, it was compiled by Kokucho (国庁) in ryoseikoku (province) and mostly written in classical Chinese.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At Emperor Genmei&apos;s order, it was compiled by Kokucho (国庁) in ryoseikoku (province) and mostly written in classical Chinese.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At Emperor Genmei&apos;s order, it was compiled by Kokucho (local government) in ryoseikoku (province) and mostly written in classical Chinese.</e>
<cmt>(国庁）を (local government) に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="14">
<j>『続日本紀』の和銅6年5月甲子(ユリウス暦713年5月30日)の条が風土記編纂の官命であると見られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The description of Kasshi (June 3, 713) in &quot;Shoku Nihongi&apos; (Chronicle of Japan Continued) is thought to have been be an imperial order directing to compile a fudoki.</e>
<cmt>ガリレオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The description of Kasshi (June 3, 713) in Shoku Nihongi (Chronicle of Japan Continued) is thought to have been an imperial order directing compilation of a fudoki.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The description of Kasshi (June 3, 713) in &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot; (Chronicle of Japan Continued) is thought to have been an imperial order directing compilation of a fudoki.</e>
<cmt>イタリック体をゴシック体に修正しました。Shoku Nihongi にダブルコーテーションを追記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>ただし、この時点では風土記という名称は用いられていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the name &quot;fudoki&quot; was not used at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the name fudoki was not used at that time.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the name fudoki was not used at that time.</e>
<cmt>イタリック体をゴシック体に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>記すべき内容として、以下が挙げられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Items or information to be reported are</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Items or information to be reported are</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Items or information to be reported are as follows.</e>
<cmt>修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="17">
<j>郡郷の名（好字を用いて）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Name of Gun (郡) and Go (郷) (using auspicious characters)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Name of Gun (郡) and Go (郷) (using auspicious characters)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Name of Gun (county) and Go (village) (using auspicious characters)</e>
<cmt>Gun (郡) and Go (郷) をGun (county) and Go (village) に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>産物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Products</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Products</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Products</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>土地の肥沃の状態</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fertility level of the land</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fertility level of the land</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fertility level of the land</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>地名の起源</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Origin of the name of the place</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Origin of the name of the place</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Origin of the name of the place</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>伝えられている旧聞異事</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other matters which were told for a long time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other matters which were told for a long time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other matters which were told for a long time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="22">
<j>完全に現存するものはないが、出雲国風土記がほぼ完本で残り、播磨国風土記、肥前国風土記、常陸国風土記、豊後国風土記が一部欠損して残る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although a complete style of fudoki does not exist, Izumo no kuni fudoki remains almost complete, and Harima no kuni fudoki, Hizen no kuni fudoki, Hitachi no kuni fudoki and Bungo no kuni fudoki exist with some parts missing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although a complete style of fudoki does not exist, Izumo no kuni fudoki remains almost complete, and Harima no kuni fudoki, Hizen no kuni fudoki, Hitachi no kuni fudoki, and Bungo no kuni fudoki exist with some parts missing.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although a complete style of fudoki does not exist, Izumo no kuni fudoki remains almost complete, and Harima no kuni fudoki, Hizen no kuni fudoki, Hitachi no kuni fudoki, and Bungo no kuni fudoki exist with some parts missing.</e>
<cmt>イタリック体をゴシック体に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>その他の国の風土記も存在したはずだが、現在では、後世の書物に引用されている逸文からその一部がうかがわれるのみである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other provinces&apos; fudoki should have existed, but at present, some of such fudoki can be known only in the itsubun (a composition previously existed but doesn&apos;t exist now) which is referred in books of later era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other provinces&apos; fudoki should have existed, but at present, some of such fudoki can be known only in the itsubun (a composition that previously existed but doesn&apos;t exist now) referred to in books of later era.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other provinces&apos; fudoki should have existed, but at present, some of such fudoki can be known only in the itsubun (lost writings) referred to in books of later era.</e>
<cmt>イタリック体をゴシック体に修正しました。a composition that previously existed but doesn&apos;t exist now を lost writings に修正しました。参考：http://books.google.com/books?id=Kjco6W_nGAAC&amp;pg=PA455&amp;dq=itsubun+lost+writings&amp;as_brr=3&amp;hl=ja&amp;cd=1#v=onepage&amp;q=itsubun%20lost%20writings&amp;f=false</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>ただし逸文とされるものの中にも本当に奈良時代の風土記の記述であるか疑問が持たれているものも存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among so-called itsubun, there are the ones which are thought skeptical about the credibility that those descriptions were contained in fudoki in the Nara Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among so-called itsubun, there are some which are thought skeptical about the credibility that those descriptions were contained in fudoki in the Nara Period.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among so-called itsubun, there are some which are thought skeptical about the credibility that those descriptions were contained in fudoki in the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>イタリック体をゴシック体に修正しました。Period を period に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="25">
<j>各国の風土記</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fudoki of each province</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fudoki of each province</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fudoki of each province</e>
<cmt>イタリック体をゴシック体に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="26">
<j>「※印」は写本としてある程度形が残っているもの、「○印」は逸文として他の書物に残っているもの、無印は逸文であるか疑わしいものしか残っていないか、未発見のもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">*&apos; shows that the manuscripts are restored in a certain level, &apos;O&apos; shows that itsubun is restored in other books, and no mark means that it is itsubun, only skeptical itsubun exists or itsubun has not been discovered.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">*&apos; shows that the manuscripts are restored in a certain level, &apos;O&apos; shows that itsubun is restored in other books, and no mark means that it is itsubun, only skeptical itsubun exists, or itsubun has not been discovered.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">*&apos; shows that the manuscripts are restored in a certain level, &apos;O&apos; shows that itsubun is restored in other books, and no mark means that it is itsubun, only skeptical itsubun exists, or itsubun has not been discovered.</e>
<cmt>イタリック体をゴシック体に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Higashi(id:8842), Izayohi(id:13095), Straysheep(id:42448), KEI(id:82484), 月下薄氷(id:47743), Nnh(id:474), Htks(id:24185), MIsogi(id:20599), Stanislaus(id:1806), 松茸(id:27535), RekishiEJ(id:43355), BAKU(id:55205), Sh(id:2707), Askr(id:202037), Mnkeicvbnw(id:167162), Kamitani(id:30757), MDR-SK(id:192066), Xqbot(id:273540), 暗黒な方(id:44101), ヤマト(id:8425), ハイゼン(id:21182), Kanoe(id:17203), ねこぱんだ(id:35119), Kusunose(id:5719), Shimoxx(id:9332), FlaBot(id:30804), Louperibot(id:128971), 弥(id:61590), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>