<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>古語拾遺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kogo Shui</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kogo Shui</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kogo Shui</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>古語拾遺（こごしゅうい）は、平安時代の神道資料である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kogo Shui is a piece of writing about Shinto of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kogo Shui is a piece of writing about Shinto during the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>inserted during</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kogo Shui is a piece of writing about Shinto during the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>官人であった斎部広成が大同 (日本)2年（807年）に編纂した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hironari IMBE, a government official, compiled this book in 807.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hironari IMBE, a government official, compiled this book in 807.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hironari INBE, a government official, compiled this book in 807.</e>
<cmt>IMBE を INBE に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>全1巻。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is a one-volume book.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is a one-volume book.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is a one-volume book.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>成立</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">How this book came into existence</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">How this book came into existence</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">How this book came into existence</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>807年(大同2年)2月13日に書かれたとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This book is said to have written on February 13, 807.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This book is said to have been written on February 13, 807.</e>
<cmt>grammar, (written or published? Feb 13, 807 is only one day which seems too little time to write a book)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This book is said to have been written on February 13, 807.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>大同元年（806年）とする写本もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some copies say that it was written in 806.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some copies say that it was written in 806.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some copies say that it was written in 806.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>だが、跋（あとがき）に「方今、聖運初めて啓け…宝暦惟新に」とある。たった今、天子の運命初めて</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, its postface includes a description of &quot;Just now, the Emperor&apos;s luck turned for the better for the first time…….in the first year of the new era.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the postface reads; &quot;Just now, the Emperor&apos;s luck turned for the better for the first time…….in the first year of the new era.&quot;</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the postface reads; &quot;Just now, the Emperor&apos;s luck turned for the better for the first time…….in the first year of the new era.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>このことから、平城天皇即位による改元の806年(延暦25年・大同元年）5月18日以降であることが分かり、「大同元年」説は誤りということが分かる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This reveals that at least, the book was written later than May 18, 806, on which the eras changed from the 25th year of the Enryaku era to the first year of Daido, suggesting that the view that the book was written in the first year of Daido is wrong.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This reveals that the book was written at least later than May 18, 806, when the era changed from the 25th year of the Enryaku era to the first year of Daido, suggesting that the book being written in the first year of Daido is wrong.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This reveals that the book was written at least later than May 18, 806, when the era changed from the 25th year of the Enryaku era to the first year of Daido, suggesting that the book being written in the first year of Daido is wrong.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>『日本後紀』の大同元年8月10日の条に「以前から続いていた「中臣・忌部相訴」に対する勅裁があった」とある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the section of &quot;August 10, 806&quot; of &quot;Nihon Kouki&quot; (third of the six classical Japanese history texts), a ruling was made by the Emperor on the case filed and fought by the Nakatomi and Imbe clans over a long time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the &quot;August 10, 806&quot; section of &quot;Nihon Kouki&quot; (third of the six classical Japanese history texts), a ruling was made by the Emperor on a case filed and fought by the Nakatomi and Imbe clans for over a long period of time.</e>
<cmt>grammar improved, wording revised</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the &quot;August 10, 806&quot; section of &quot;Nihon Kouki&quot; (third of the six classical Japanese history texts), a ruling was made by the Emperor on a case filed and fought by the Nakatomi and Inbe clans for over a long period of time.</e>
<cmt>Imbe を Inbe に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>この条文から、「大同元年」論者は、『古語拾遺』をこの勅裁に先立つ証拠書類だと考えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those who supported the view that the book was written in the first year of Daido (806), considered that &quot;Kogo Shui&quot; served as evidence based on which the ruling was made.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those who support the view that the book was written in the first year of Daido (806), considered that &quot;Kogo Shui&quot; was evidence of this, based upon when the ruling was made.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity, grammar and tense improved</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those who support the view that the book was written in the first year of Daido (806), considered that &quot;Kogo Shui&quot; was evidence of this, based upon when the ruling was made.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>しかし、本文にはこの8月10日の出来事を前提に書かれているので矛盾することとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But, the view goes against the fact that Kogo Shui was written based on the ruling of August 10.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But, this view goes against the fact that Kogo Shui was written based upon a ruling of August 10.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But, this view goes against the fact that Kogo Shui was written based upon a ruling of August 10.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>選者</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Author</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Author</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Author</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>斎部広成の伝記は、『日本後紀』の808年(大同3年)11/17の条に「正六位上」から「従五位下」に昇ったとあるのみで、ほかの事は分からない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nothing is known about Hironari IMBE except for the fact that he was promoted from Shorokuinojo (Senior Sixth Rank, Upper Grade) to Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade), as stated in the section of &quot;November 17, 808&quot; of &quot;Nihon Kouki&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nothing is known about Hironari IMBE except that he was promoted from Shorokuinojo (Senior Sixth Rank, Upper Grade) to Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade), as stated in the &quot;November 17, 808&quot; section of the &quot;Nihon Kouki&quot;</e>
<cmt>redundancy reduced, sentence restructured grammatically</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nothing is known about Hironari INBE except that he was promoted from Shorokuinojo (Senior Sixth Rank, Upper Grade) to Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade), as stated in the &quot;November 17, 808&quot; section of the &quot;Nihon Kouki&quot;</e>
<cmt>IMBE を INBE に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>ちなみのこの昇階は、平城天皇の大嘗祭の功によるものだろうという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, his promotion is thought to be due to his excellent services at Daijo-sai (the first ceremonial offering of rice by newly-enthroned Emperor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, his promotion is thought to be due to his excellent services at Daijo-sai (the first ceremonial offering of rice by newly-enthroned Emperor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, his promotion is thought to be due to his excellent services at Daijo-sai (the first ceremonial offering of rice by a newly-enthroned Emperor).</e>
<cmt>不定冠詞必要。 - “by newly-enthroned Emperor”=&gt;”by a newly-enthroned Emperor”</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>ところが、本書の跋には「従五位下」とあり、807年(大同2年)当時は「正六位上」だったはずである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the postface of this book, however, he was ranked Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade), but in 807 (when he wrote the book), he should have been ranked Shorokuinojo (Senior Sixth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the postface of this book, however, he was ranked Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade), but in 807 (when he wrote the book), he should have been ranked Shorokuinojo (Senior Sixth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the postface of this book, however, he was ranked Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade), but in 807 (when he wrote the book), he should have been ranked Shorokuinojo (Senior Sixth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>これは後世の改変だと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The postface must have been altered at a later time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The postface must have been altered at a later time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The postface must have been altered at a later time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="17">
<j>目的</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Objective</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Objective</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Objective</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>愁訴陳情書説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To complain about his clan&apos;s state and to file a petition</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To complain about the state of his clan and to file a petition</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To complain about the state of his clan and to file a petition</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>元々、斎部氏は朝廷の祭祀を司る氏族だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Imbe was a clan who had traditionally administered religious rituals and services in the imperial court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Imbe was a clan who had traditionally administered religious rituals and services at the imperial court.</e>
<cmt>&quot;at&quot; replaces &quot;in&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Inbe was a clan who had traditionally administered religious rituals and services at the imperial court.</e>
<cmt>Imbe を Inbe に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>しかし、大化の改新以降、同様に祭祀を司っていた中臣氏（藤原氏を与えられたが、後に別流は中臣姓に戻された）が政治的な力を持ち、祭祀についても役職は中臣氏だけが就いているという状況だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the Nakatomi clan, who had conducted religious services together with the Imbe clan, gained political power and became predominantly engaged in religious services after Taika Reform; a family of the Nakatomi clan, who had been given the name of Fujiwara, had been given the name of Nakatomi, again.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the Nakatomi clan, who had conducted religious services together with the Imbe clan, gained political power and became predominantly engaged in religious services after Taika Reform; a family of the Nakatomi clan, who had been given the name of Fujiwara, had been given the name of Nakatomi, again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the Nakatomi clan, who had conducted religious services together with the Imbe clan, gained political power and became predominantly engaged in religious services after Taika Reform; a family of the Nakatomi clan, who had been given the name of Fujiwara, had been given the name of Nakatomi, again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>本書は、斎部氏の正統性を主張し、有利な立場に立つために著されたものであると考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This book is thought to have written to ensure that the Imbe clan was favorably positioned in the imperial court by claiming that it was a legitimate clan for conducting religious services.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This book is thought to have been written to ensure that the Imbe clan was favorably positioned in the imperial court by claiming that it was a legitimate clan for conducting religious services.</e>
<cmt>&quot;been&quot; inserted</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This book is thought to have been written to ensure that the Inbe clan was favorably positioned in the imperial court by claiming that it was a legitimate clan for conducting religious services.</e>
<cmt>Imbe を Inbe に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="22">
<j>調査報告書説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To submit a report to the imperial court</e>
<cmt>表題的なので短く表現しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To submit a report to the imperial court</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To submit a report to the imperial court</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>「愁訴陳情書説」が古くから唱えられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The view had been long supported that this book was written for the purpose of complaining about the state the Imbe clan had been in and filing a petition for it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The view had been long supported that this book was written for the purpose of complaining about the state the Imbe clan had been in and filing a petition about it.</e>
<cmt>&quot;about it&quot; added</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The view had been long supported that this book was written for the purpose of complaining about the state the Inbe clan had been in and filing a petition about it.</e>
<cmt>Imbe を Inbe に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>現在では、朝廷が行なった法制整備のための事前調査に対する忌部氏の報告書であるという説が有力である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nowadays, the popular view is that this book was a report submitted by the Imbe clan to the imperial court, who had been conducting investigation to put a legal system in place.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nowadays, the popular view is that this book was a report submitted by the Imbe clan to the imperial court, that had been conducting investigation to put a legal system in place.</e>
<cmt>&quot;that&quot; replaces &quot;who&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nowadays, the popular view is that this book was a report submitted by the Inbe clan to the imperial court, that had been conducting investigation to put a legal system in place.</e>
<cmt>Imbe を Inbe に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="25">
<j>伊勢神宮の奉幣使の役職をめぐって、忌部氏と中臣氏の間で、長年争われてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was a long time dispute between the Imbe and Nakaomi clans over which would take the post of Hoheishi (imperial messenger to a shrine and envoy returning courtesies) to Grand Shrine at Ise.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was a long time dispute between the Imbe and Nakaomi clans over which would take the post of Hoheishi (imperial messenger to a shrine and envoy returning courtesies) at the Grand Shrine of Ise.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was a long time dispute between the Inbe and Nakatomi clans over which would take the post of Hoheishi (imperial messenger to a shrine and envoy returning courtesies) at the Grand Shrine of Ise.</e>
<cmt>Imbe を Inbe に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>大同1年8月10日に忌部氏に対する勝訴判決が出ている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 10, 806, a ruling was made in favor of the Imbe clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 10, 806, a ruling was made in favor of the Imbe clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 10, 806, a ruling was made in favor of the Inbe clan.</e>
<cmt>Imbe を Inbe に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>本書が上程された大同2年2月13日は、この判決の後である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was after the ruling that this book was submitted to the imperial court on February 13, 807.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was after the ruling that this book was submitted to the imperial court on February 13, 807.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was after the ruling that this book was submitted to the imperial court on February 13, 807.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>「勝訴」のあとに陳情を出すのは不自然なことから、「愁訴陳情書説」は説得力を欠くことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It would be weird for the Imbe clan to file a petition after they won the suit, making the view that the book was written for the purpose of complaining and filing a petition less unconvincing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It would be strainge for the Imbe clan to file a petition after they won the suit, making the view that the book was written for the purpose of complaining and filing a petition less convincing.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It would be strange for the Inbe clan to file a petition after they won the suit, making the view that the book was written for the purpose of complaining and filing a petition less convincing.</e>
<cmt>strainge→strangeに訂正。　Imbe を Inbe に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="29">
<j>時の天皇である平城天皇は式（律令の施行規則）を制定する方針をもっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The-then Emperor Heijyo had a strategy to establish Shiki (enforcement regulations (of the ritsuryo)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Heijyo, at that time, had a plan to establish the Shiki (enforcement regulations (of the ritsuryo)).</e>
<cmt>revised, grammar and wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Heijo, at that time, had a plan to establish the Shiki (enforcement regulations (of the ritsuryo)).</e>
<cmt>&quot;Heijyo&quot; -&gt; &quot;Heijo&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>本書の跋に「造式の年」とあり、14年後の嵯峨天皇820年(弘仁11年)4月に『弘仁式』ができている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The postface of this book includes an description of &quot;Zo-shiki-no-toshi&quot; (&quot;the year in which regulations were established&quot;), according to which Konin-shiki (regulations of the Konin era) were established in April 820, the eleventh year of Konin, 14 years after the ruling.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The postface of this book includes a description of &quot;Zo-shiki-no-toshi&quot; (&quot;the year in which regulations were established&quot;), according to which Konin-shiki (regulations of the Konin era) were established in April 820, the eleventh year of Konin, 14 years after the ruling.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The postface of this book includes a description of &quot;Zo-shiki-no-toshi&quot; (&quot;the year in which regulations were established&quot;), according to which Konin-shiki (regulations of the Konin era) were established in April 820, the eleventh year of Konin, 14 years after the ruling.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>このことから、造式のための調査報告書だった可能性が指摘されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It would be safe to conclude that this book was a report submitted to the imperial court, who had been conducting investigation to establish enforcement regulations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It would be safe to conclude that this book was a report submitted to the imperial court, that had been conducting investigations to establish enforcement regulations.</e>
<cmt>workding, tense, grammar revised</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It would be safe to conclude that this book was a report submitted to the imperial court, that had been conducting investigations to establish enforcement regulations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="32">
<j>また、同時期には『延暦儀式帳』が伊勢神宮から提出されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was during this period that &quot;Enryaku gishiki cho&quot; (a list of shrines) was submitted by the Ise jingu shrine (Grand Shrine at Ise), too.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was during this period that &quot;Enryaku gishiki cho&quot; (a list of shrines) was alao submitted by the Ise jingu shrine (Grand Shrine at Ise).</e>
<cmt>grammar,</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was during this period that &quot;Enryaku gishiki cho&quot; (a list of shrines) was also submitted by the Ise jingu shrine (Grand Shrine at Ise).</e>
<cmt>alao→also</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>これも造式に備えた事前調査の一環だったといわれており、『古語拾遺』と同じ一連の流れに沿ったものだと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is also considered to have been part of preliminary investigation by the imperial court to establish Shiki and of a series of events that included &quot;Kogo Shui&quot; as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is also considered to have been part of a preliminary investigation by the imperial court to establish Shiki and of a series of events that included &quot;Kogo Shui&quot; as well.</e>
<cmt>&quot;a&quot; inserted</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is also considered to have been part of a preliminary investigation by the imperial court to establish Shiki and of a series of events that included &quot;Kogo Shui&quot; as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="34">
<j>内容</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Content</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Content</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Content</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>序</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Preface</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Preface</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Preface</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="36">
<j>本文</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Body</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Body</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Body</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>神代古伝承</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Legend of ancient times</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Legend of ancient times</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Legend of ancient times</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>神武天皇以降の古伝承</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Legend from Emperor Jimmu onwards</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Legend of Emperor Jimmu onwards</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Legend of Emperor Jimmu onwards</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>古伝承に抜けた11カ条</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eleven sections missing from the legend of ancient times</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eleven sections missing from the legend of ancient times</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eleven sections missing from the legend of ancient times</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>御歳神祭祀の古伝承</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Legend about Mitoshi gami (Shinto god enshrined, to whom beef was served)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Legend about Mitoshi gami (enshrined Shinto god, to whom beef was served)</e>
<cmt>word order revised</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Legend about Mitoshi gami (enshrined Shinto god, to whom beef was served)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>跋</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Postface</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Postface</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Postface</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="42">
<j>天地開闢 (日本神話)から天平年間（729年～749年）までが記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This records the events that occurred during the period from the creation of heaven and earth to the Tempyo era (729-749).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This records the events that occurred during the period from the creation of heaven and earth to the Tempyo era (729-749).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This records the events that occurred during the period from the creation of heaven and earth to the Tempyo era (729-749).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>古事記や日本書紀などの史書には見られない斎部氏に伝わる伝承も取り入れられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This book takes up the legend that had been handed down among the Imbe clan, but not involved in Records of Ancient Matters (Japan&apos;s oldest historical record), Nihon-shoki (the oldest chronicles of Japan), or other history books.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This book takes up the legend that had been handed down through generations among the Imbe clan, but does not involved Records of Ancient Matters (Japan&apos;s oldest historical record), Nihon-shoki (the oldest chronicles of Japan), or any other history books.</e>
<cmt>words added, grammar improved</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This book takes up the legend that had been handed down to subsequent generations among the Inbe clan, but does not involved Records of Ancient Matters (Japan&apos;s oldest historical record), Nihon-shoki (the oldest chronicles of Japan), or any other history books.</e>
<cmt>Imbe を Inbe に修正しました。&quot;handed down through generations&quot; -&gt; &quot;handed down to subsequent generations&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="44">
<j>斎部氏はアメノフトダマの子孫とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Imbe clan is considered to be the descendants of Amenohutodama, a god who served Amaterasu omikami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Imbe clan is considered to be the descendants of Amenohutodama, a god who served Amaterasu omikami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Inbe clan is considered to be the descendants of Ame no Futodama, a god who served Amaterasu omikami.</e>
<cmt>Amenohutodama→Ame no FutodamaImbe を Inbe に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>このことから、天太玉命ら斎部氏の祖神の活躍が記紀よりも多く記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That&apos;s why this book contains more of the success stories of Ame no Futotama and other Soshin (enshrined ancestors) than Kojiki and Nihonshoki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That&apos;s why this book contains more success stories of Ame no Futotama and other Soshin (enshrined ancestors) than the Kojiki and Nihonshoki.</e>
<cmt>words deleted and added</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That&apos;s why this book contains more success stories of Soshin (enshrined ancestors) of the Inbe clan such as Ame no Futotama than the Kojiki and Nihonshoki.</e>
<cmt>「斎部氏の」の部分を訳出し、原文どおりにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>例えば、岩戸隠れの場面においては、天太玉命が中心的役割を果たしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, when Amaterasu omokami hid herself in Amano iwa to (literally, &quot;the rock cave of heaven&quot;), Ame no Futotama nomikoto played a central role.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, when Amaterasu omokami hid herself in Amano iwa to (literally, &quot;the rock cave of heaven&quot;), Ame no Futotama nomikoto played a central role.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, when Amaterasu omikami hid herself in Amano iwa to (literally, &quot;the rock cave of heaven&quot;), Ame no Futotama no mikoto played a central role.</e>
<cmt>omokami→omikami</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="47">
<j>影響</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Impact</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Impact</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Impact</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>『先代旧事本紀』『本朝月令』『政事要略』『長寛勘文』『年中行事秘抄』『釈日本紀』や伊勢神道の文献などに利用・引用された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This book was cited and used in literature including Sendai Kuji Hongi, Honcho Gatsuryo, Seiji yoryaku, Chokan-kanmon, Nenju Gyoji Hisho, Syakunihongi, and the books of Ise Shinto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This book was cited and used in literature including the Sendai Kuji Hongi, Honcho Gatsuryo, Seiji yoryaku, Chokan-kanmon, Nenju Gyoji Hisho, Syakunihongi, and the books of Ise Shinto.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the&quot; inserted</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This book was cited and used in literature including the Sendai Kuji Hongi, Honcho Gatsuryo, Seiji yoryaku, Chokan-kanmon, Nenju Gyoji Hisho, Syakunihongi, and the books of Ise Shinto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>神典として重視されてきたことがわかる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This reveals that this book has been valued as a book of Shinto gods.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This reveals that this book has been valued as a book of Shinto gods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This reveals that this book has been valued as a book of Shinto gods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="50">
<j>研究</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Research</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Research</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Research</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>1773年(安永2年)に奈佐勝皋（かつたか）が『疑斎』を著している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1773, Katsutaka NASA wrote a book titled &quot;Gisai&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1773, Katsutaka NASA wrote a book titled &quot;Gisai&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1773, Katsutaka NASA wrote a book titled &quot;Gisai&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>その中で『古語拾遺』を「斎部氏の衰廃を愁訴したるに過ぎざるのみ」と批判している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In it, he criticized &quot;Koji Shui&quot; as just depicting the Imbe clan who had been complaining about their state and filing a petition.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In it, he criticized &quot;Koji Shui&quot; as just depicting the Imbe clan who had been complaining about their state and filing a petition.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In it, he criticized &quot;Koji Shui&quot; as just depicting the Inbe clan who had been complaining about their state and filing a petition.</e>
<cmt>Imbe を Inbe に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>これに対して、本居宣長は『疑斎弁』を著して、『古語拾遺』を弁護した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Norinaga MOTOORI, who opposed to this view, wrote a book titled &quot;Gisaiben&quot; to defend it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Norinaga MOTOORI, who opposed to this view, wrote a book titled &quot;Gisaiben&quot; to defend it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Norinaga MOTOORI, who opposed to this view, wrote a book titled &quot;Gisaiben&quot; to defend it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="54">
<j>近代以降では、1928年(昭和3年)に津田左右吉が『古語拾遺の研究』で執筆当時の歴史史料とはなるが、記紀以前のことを知るための史料としては価値がないと評価している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Modern Ages onwards, Sokichi TSUDA evaluated this book in his book &quot;Research on Kogo Shui&quot; in 1928 as being good enough to be treated as a history book of the time the book was written, but of little value as history records showing the times before Kojiki and Nihonshoki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Modern Ages onwards, Sokichi TSUDA evaluated this book in his book &quot;Research on Kogo Shui&quot; in 1928 as being good enough to be treated as a history book of the time the book was written, but of little value as history records showing the times before Kojiki and Nihonshoki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Modern Ages onwards, Sokichi TSUDA evaluated this book in his book &quot;Research on Kogo Shui&quot; in 1928 as being good enough to be treated as a history book of the time the book was written, but of little value as history records showing the times before Kojiki and Nihonshoki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="55">
<j>これまで記紀と比して重要性は薄いとされてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">So far, this book has been regarded as being of less importance when compared to Kojiki and Nihonsyoki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">So far, this book has been regarded as being of less importance, when compared to the Kojiki and the Nihonsyoki.</e>
<cmt>punctuation &quot;comma,&quot; grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">So far, this book has been regarded as being of less importance, when compared to the Kojiki and the Nihonsyoki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>現在では重要性が再評価されつつある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is now being re-evaluated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is now being re-evaluated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is now being re-evaluated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Amigomr(id:6515), Izayohi(id:13095), Nnh(id:474), MIsogi(id:20599), Stanislaus(id:1806), Charon(id:9162), Tcyiswalk(id:7279), 伏儀(id:142093), Kiev(id:13022), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>