<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>神体山</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shintaizan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shintai-zan Mountain</e>
<cmt>Shintai-zan Mountainに訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shintai-zan Mountain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>神体山（しんたいさん）とは主に神道において神 (神道)が宿るとされる山岳信仰や神奈備（かむなび・神々が神留まる森林を抱く山）の山をいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shintaizan is a term mainly used in Shitoism meaning a mountain believed to be where deities dwell in the concept of mountain worship and also called &quot;kannabi,&quot; a mountain where deities dwell.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shintai-zan Mountain is a term mainly used in Shitoism meaning a mountain believed to be where deities dwell in the concept of mountain worship and also called Kannabi, a mountain where deities dwell.</e>
<cmt>Shintai-zan Mountainに訂正しました。Kannabiに訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shintai-zan Mountain is a term mainly used in Shitoism meaning a mountain believed to be where deities dwell in the concept of mountain worship and also called Kannabi, a mountain where deities dwell.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>また、「霊峰」ともよばれ霊峰富士として、富士山が代表的なものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such sacred mountains are also called &quot;reiho&quot; (lit. sacred peak), and Mt. Fuji is one of the representative reiho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such sacred mountains are also called &apos;reiho&apos; (lit. sacred peak), and Mt. Fuji is one of the representative reiho.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such sacred mountains are also called &apos;reiho&apos; (lit. sacred peak), and Mt. Fuji is one of the representative reiho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>また峠や坂という小さな峰も神域や神 (神道)が宿る場所とし畏怖畏敬した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Passes, slopes and other small peaks were also considered sacred and worshiped as places where deities dwell.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Passes, slopes and other small peaks were also considered sacred and worshiped as places where deities dwell.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Passes, slopes and other small peaks were also considered sacred and worshiped as places where deities dwell.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概略</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Outline</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>文化人類学のアニミズム論によれば、人類が生と死という現象を客観的に捉え、それを自我や意識わせた観念として「命」という認識を作り出し、生き物や自然の山河や岩や木々にも命や神や霊が宿ると考えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the idea of animism in cultural anthropology, the mankind viewed the phenomena of life and death in an objective manner, created a recognition of &quot;life&quot; as a concept of ego and consciousness out of such a view, and considered life, deity or spirit dwells in living creatures as well as in natural objects such as mountains, rivers, rocks and trees.</e>
<cmt>「それを自我や意識わせた観念」ですが、これは「自我や意識を合わせた」の誤植と理解しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the idea of animism in cultural anthropology, the mankind viewed the phenomena of life and death in an objective manner, created a recognition of &apos;life&apos; as a concept of ego and consciousness out of such a view, and considered life, deity or spirit dwells in living creatures as well as in natural objects such as mountains, rivers, rocks and trees.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the idea of animism in cultural anthropology, the mankind viewed the phenomena of life and death in an objective manner, created a recognition of &apos;life&apos; as a concept of ego and consciousness out of such a view, and considered life, deity or spirit dwells in living creatures as well as in natural objects such as mountains, rivers, rocks and trees.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>これは、日本において同様であり、神道、特に縄文時代以前からある縄文神道といわれる古神道（6世紀以前の外来の習俗に影響される前の神道で、現在の日本の民間信仰でもある）においては、大きいものや長くあるものや古いものに、より位の高い神が宿ると考えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This understanding also applies to Japan, and deities of higher ranks are believed to dwell in big things or things that live long in Shintoism and particularly Ancient Shintoism that is also called Jomon Shintoism for it is believed to have existed before the beginning of the Jomon period (ancient form of Shintoism that existed before the 6th century before it was influenced by the foreign customs and forms folk beliefs in today&apos;s Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This understanding also applies to Japan, and deities of higher ranks are believed to dwell in big things or things that live long in Shintoism and particularly Ancient Shintoism that is also called Jomon Shintoism for it is believed to have existed before the beginning of the Jomon period (ancient form of Shintoism that existed before the 6th century before it was influenced by the foreign customs and forms folk beliefs in today&apos;s Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This understanding also applies to Japan, and deities of higher ranks are believed to dwell in big things or things that live long in Shintoism and particularly Ancient Shintoism that is also called Jomon Shintoism for it is believed to have existed before the beginning of the Jomon period (ancient form of Shintoism that existed before the 6th century before it was influenced by the foreign customs and forms folk beliefs in today&apos;s Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>その代表的なものが山や峰峰（連峰）であり、特に特徴的な大きな山に神が宿るとされ、これを山岳信仰という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">What typically represents such idea is mountains, and the idea that deities dwell in particularly big unique mountains is known as mountain worship.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">What typically represents such idea is mountains, and the idea that deities dwell in particularly big unique mountains is known as mountain worship.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">What typically represents such idea is mountains, and the idea that deities dwell in particularly big unique mountains is known as mountain worship.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>山岳信仰は日本に限らず世界中にあり、ケニア南部のマサイ族やキユク族はキリマンジャロを神が座する山として信仰している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mountain worship is found not only in Japan but in various parts of the world; the Masai and Kikuyu in the southern part of Kenya worship Kilimanjaro as a mountain where their God abides.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mountain worship is found not only in Japan but in various parts of the world; the Masai and Kiyuku tribes in the southern part of Kenya worship Mt. Kilimanjaro as a mountain where their god abides.</e>
<cmt>Kiyukuに訂正しました。tribes補足しました。Mt.補足しました。god 小文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mountain worship is found not only in Japan but in various parts of the world; the Masai and Kiyuku tribes in the southern part of Kenya worship Mt. Kilimanjaro as a mountain where their god abides.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>その他にはチベットのシェルパ族はエベレストを、中国雲南省のナシ族（納西族）は玉龍雪山を、オーストラリアのアボリジニ（アボリジニ）はウルル（エアーズロック）をそれぞれ神が宿る、神の山として信仰している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other examples include Mt. Everest, Jade Dragon Snow Mountain, and Uluru (Ayers Rock) are worshiped by Sherpas in Tibet, the Nakhi in Yunnan Province, China, and Australian Aborigines as their holy mountain, respectively.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other examples include Mt. Everest, Jade Dragon Snow Mountain, and Uluru (Ayers Rock) are worshiped by Sherpas in Tibet, the Nakhi in Yunnan Province, China, and Australian Aborigines as their holy mountain, respectively.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other examples include Mt. Everest, Jade Dragon Snow Mountain, and Uluru (Ayers Rock) are worshiped by Sherpas in Tibet, the Nakhi in Yunnan Province, China, and Australian Aborigines as their holy mountain, respectively.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>日本には神奈備（かんなび）といわれるものがあり、山岳信仰の一つの形でもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan, kannabi, a holy mountain where deities dwell, is another form of mountain worship.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan, kannabi, a holy mountain where deities dwell, is another form of mountain worship.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan, kannabi, a holy mountain where deities dwell, is another form of mountain worship.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>古くは神奈備は磐座（いわくら）・磐境（いわさか）とともに、普通の山だけでなく、火山や森を抱かないいわゆる裸山や禿山も信仰の対象とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Formerly mountains worshipped as kannabi include ordinary mountains and iwakura (dwelling place of a god, usually in reference to a large rock) or iwasaka (the area a deity sits) as well as volcanoes and bold mountains with no forests.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Formerly mountains worshipped as kannabi include ordinary mountains and iwakura (dwelling place of a god, usually in reference to a large rock) or iwasaka (the area a deity sits) as well as volcanoes and bold mountains with no forests.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Formerly mountains worshipped as kannabi include ordinary mountains and iwakura (dwelling place of a god, usually in reference to a large rock) or iwasaka (the area a deity sits) as well as volcanoes and bold mountains with no forests.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>その後、神奈備は木々や森林を抱く集落に隣接する山として、鎮守の森や神籬（ひもろぎ）に変わっていき、磐座は夫婦岩などとともに岩・奇岩や巨石・奇石として霊石になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name &quot;kannabi&quot; then came to be given to mountains covered with trees and forests and adjacent to human communities, and such mountains came to be called &quot;Chinju-no-Mori&quot; (sacred shrine forest) or &quot;himorogi&quot; (primitive shrine, originally a piece of sacred land surrounded by evergreens), while &quot;iwakura&quot; became sacred rocks as rocks, unique rocks, big rocks such as &quot;meoto-iwa&quot; (husband-and-wife rock).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name &quot;kannabi&quot; then came to be given to mountains covered with trees and forests and adjacent to human communities, and such mountains came to be called &quot;Chinju no mori&quot; (sacred shrine forest) or &quot;himorogi&quot; (primitive shrine, originally a piece of sacred land surrounded by evergreens), while &quot;iwakura&quot; became sacred rocks as rocks, unique rocks, big rocks such as &quot;meoto-iwa&quot; (husband-and-wife rock).</e>
<cmt>ハイフン削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name &quot;kannabi&quot; then came to be given to mountains covered with trees and forests and adjacent to human communities, and such mountains came to be called &quot;Chinju no mori&quot; (sacred shrine forest) or &quot;himorogi&quot; (primitive shrine, originally a piece of sacred land surrounded by evergreens), while &quot;iwakura&quot; became sacred rocks as rocks, unique rocks, big rocks such as &quot;meoto-iwa&quot; (husband-and-wife rock).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>現在では神籬と合わせ神社神道の玉垣の原型になったといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today kannabi is said to have become the antetype of tamagaki (fence around a shrine) for Jinja Shinto (Shrine Shinto) together with himorogi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処「かんなび」と「ひもろぎ」が、原型になったのか、「ひもろぎ」と一緒になって「玉垣」の原型となったと解釈しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today kannabi is said to have become the antetype of tamagaki (fence around a shrine) for Jinja Shinto (Shrine Shinto) together with himorogi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today kannabi is said to have become the antetype of tamagaki (fence around a shrine) for Jinja Shinto (Shrine Shinto) together with himorogi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>これらの古神道の信仰された場所に、現在の多くの神社神道の「社（やしろ）」が建立され、賽神は自然そのものから「尊」（みこと）といわれる人格神に取って代わっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today many &quot;shrines&quot; in Jinja Shinto stand at those holy places worshipped in the idea of ancient Shintoism, and sainokami (guardian deities) were changed from nature or natural elements to humanized divinity called &quot;mikoto.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today many &apos;shrines&apos; in Jinja Shinto stand at those holy places worshipped in the idea of ancient Shintoism, and sainokami (guardian deities) were changed from nature or natural elements to humanized divinity called &apos;mikoto.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today many &apos;shrines&apos; in Jinja Shinto stand at those holy places worshipped in the idea of ancient Shintoism, and sainokami (guardian deities) were changed from nature or natural elements to humanized divinity called &apos;mikoto.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>このことは古代の神社の多くが神体山信仰（神奈備）に起源がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This explains that many ancient shrines were originated from the Shintaizan (kannabi) worship.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処以下、4つの文に分けました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This explains that many ancient shrines were originated from the Shintaizan (kannabi) worship.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This explains that many ancient shrines were originated from the Shintaizan (kannabi) worship.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>その根拠として、神社の建築様式おいて基本的には「鳥居→社殿→神体山」という序列があり、参拝者の後方に神体山が存在する場合にも参道を考慮に入れるとこの序列は成立しているとする説 からも窺い知ることができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This idea is evidenced by the theory that the basic layout in Shinto building construction style, which is the order of &quot;torii&quot; =&gt; &quot;main building&quot; =&gt; &quot;Shintaizan,&quot; and that this order is established even in cases where a Shintaizan is located behind worshippers by considering the approach to the shrine.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This idea is evidenced by the theory that the basic layout in Shinto building construction style, which is the order of &apos;torii - main building - Shintaizan,&apos; and that this order is established even in cases where a Shintaizan is located behind worshippers by considering the approach to the shrine.</e>
<cmt>記号を削除し、ハイフン補足しました。原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This idea is evidenced by the theory that the basic layout in Shinto building construction style, which is the order of &apos;torii - main building - Shintaizan,&apos; and that this order is established even in cases where a Shintaizan is located behind worshippers by considering the approach to the shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>その他にも各説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This idea is explained by other theories.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This idea is explained by other theories.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This idea is explained by other theories.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>古来から大規模集落にみられた祈祷や祭礼の場所としての古神道の神殿が、仏教思想の影響により、神社の本殿に神が鎮座するとする「神常在思想」が発生したと、池辺弥はしていることなども、古神道の場所に神社が建立された、とする説明に合致する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The theory proposed by Wataru IKEBA that shrines in Ancient Shintoism traditionally built as places of incantation or festival in large communities were modified by the influence of Buddhist concept and that the &quot;idea of permanent presence of deity&quot; as presented by the enshrined deity always dwells in the main building of the shrine was born also agrees with the explanation that shrines were built at places of Ancient Shintoism.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処「古来から大規模集落にみられた・・・・が発生した」ですが、てにをはがおかしいです。適当に理解し、英語にしました。「古神道の場所」という言い方もよくわかりませんが、直訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The theory proposed by Wataru IKEBA that shrines in Ancient Shintoism traditionally built as places of incantation or festival in large communities were modified by the influence of Buddhist concept and that the &apos;idea of permanent presence of deity&apos; as presented by the enshrined deity always dwells in the main building of the shrine was born also agrees with the explanation that shrines were built at places of Ancient Shintoism.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The theory proposed by Wataru IKEBA that shrines in Ancient Shintoism traditionally built as places of incantation or festival in large communities were modified by the influence of Buddhist concept and that the &apos;idea of permanent presence of deity&apos; as presented by the enshrined deity always dwells in the main building of the shrine was born also agrees with the explanation that shrines were built at places of Ancient Shintoism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>また景山春樹は古墳や塚と同様に祖霊信仰に始まり、やがて山そのものを信仰の対象とする自然神道的な形態に変遷し、後に山中の祖霊神に農耕の神の観念が重なっていったと解釈している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Haruki KAGEYAMA interprets that it began as ancestral worship like kofun (burial mound) or tsuka (ancient tomb) and was then transformed into natural Shintoistic form that sees a mountain itself as the object of worship and that in due course of time the concept of ancestral deities in mountains was fused with the concept of agricultural deity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Haruki KAGEYAMA interprets that it began as ancestral worship like kofun (burial mound) or tsuka (ancient tomb) and was then transformed into natural Shintoistic form that sees a mountain itself as the object of worship and that in due course of time the concept of ancestral deities in mountains was fused with the concept of agricultural deity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Haruki KAGEYAMA interprets that it began as ancestral worship like kofun (burial mound) or tsuka (ancient tomb) and was then transformed into natural Shintoistic form that sees a mountain itself as the object of worship and that in due course of time the concept of ancestral deities in mountains was fused with the concept of agricultural deity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="19">
<j>後世には古神道における山岳信仰が、密教や禅宗や道教（陰陽道）と習合し、修験道における登拝も活発化した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Subsequently mountain worship in Ancient Shintoism was fused with Esoteric Buddhism, Zen Buddhism, and Taoism (Onmyodo, or Way of Yin and Yang, which is an occult divination system based on the Taoist theory of the five elements), and tohai (mountaineering for worship) under Shugendo (Japanese mountain asceticism-shamanism incorporating Shinto and Buddhist concepts) became active.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently mountain worship in Ancient Shintoism was fused with Esoteric Buddhism, Zen Buddhism, and Taoism (Onmyodo, or Way of Yin and Yang, which is an occult divination system based on the Taoist theory of the five elements), and tohai (mountaineering for worship) under Shugendo (Japanese mountain asceticism-shamanism incorporating Shinto and Buddhist concepts) became active.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently mountain worship in Ancient Shintoism was fused with Esoteric Buddhism, Zen Buddhism, and Taoism (Onmyodo, or Way of Yin and Yang, which is an occult divination system based on the Taoist theory of the five elements), and tohai (mountaineering for worship) under Shugendo (Japanese mountain asceticism-shamanism incorporating Shinto and Buddhist concepts) became active.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>霊峰富士</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Holy Mountain Fuji</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Holy Mountain Fuji</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Holy Mountain Fuji</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="20">
<j>古くは、『常陸国風土記』に富士山の神と筑波山の神の逸話が記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ancient anecdotes about the deities of Mt. Fuji and Mt. Tsukuba are recorded in &quot;Hitachi no kuni fudoki&quot; (the Topography of Hitachi Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ancient anecdotes about the deities of Mt. Fuji and Mt. Tsukuba are recorded in &quot;Hitachi no kuni fudoki&quot; (the Topography of Hitachi Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ancient anecdotes about the deities of Mt. Fuji and Mt. Tsukuba are recorded in &quot;Hitachi no kuni fudoki&quot; (the Topography of Hitachi Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>親神が富士山の神のもとを訪れ、宿を乞うたが、富士山の神は物忌み中だと言う理由で宿泊を拒否した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The parent deity visited the deity of Mt. Fuji and asked for lodging, but the mountain deity rejected the request on the grounds that the deity was during fasting.</e>
<cmt>「親神」は parent deity としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The parent deity visited the deity of Mt. Fuji and asked for lodging, but the mountain deity rejected the request on the grounds that the deity was during fasting.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The parent deity visited the deity of Mt. Fuji and asked for lodging, but the mountain deity rejected the request on the grounds that the deity was during fasting.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>親神は次に筑波山の神のもとへいき、同様に宿を乞うたところ、今度は親神は歓迎された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The parent deity then went to Mt. Tsukuba, asked the deity of Mt. Tsukuba for lodging and was welcome this time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The parent deity then went to Mt. Tsukuba, asked the deity of Mt. Tsukuba for lodging and was welcome this time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The parent deity then went to Mt. Tsukuba, asked the deity of Mt. Tsukuba for lodging and was welcome this time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>そのため、筑波山には人々が集まるようになり、反対に富士山には絶えず雪が積もり人々が来なくなったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Consequently, many people began to gather at Mt. Tsukuba; on the contrary, Mt. Fuji came to be always covered with snow, and people stopped visiting Mt. Fuji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequently, many people began to gather at Mt. Tsukuba; on the contrary, Mt. Fuji came to be always covered with snow, and people stopped visiting Mt. Fuji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently, many people began to gather at Mt. Tsukuba; on the contrary, Mt. Fuji came to be always covered with snow, and people stopped visiting Mt. Fuji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="24">
<j>『本朝世紀』によると1149年（久安5年）に末代（まつだい、富士上人）が山頂に一切経を埋納したと伝えられており、現在も富士山頂出土と伝えられる埋納経が浅間大社に伝わっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Honcho seiki&quot; (Chronicle of Imperial Reigns), Matsudai (Fuji Shonin) buried Issai-kyo (Complete Collection of Scriptures) on the top of Mt. Fuji in 1149, and the buried scriptures, believed to have been unearthed atop Mt. Fuji, are enshrined at Sengen Taisha Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Honcho seiki&quot; (Chronicle of Imperial Reigns), Matsudai (Fuji Shonin) buried Issai-kyo (Complete Collection of Scriptures) on the top of Mt. Fuji in 1149, and the buried scriptures, believed to have been unearthed atop Mt. Fuji, are enshrined at Sengen-taisha Shrine.</e>
<cmt>Sengen-taisha Shrineに訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Honcho seiki&quot; (Chronicle of Imperial Reigns), Matsudai (Fuji Shonin) buried Issai-kyo (Complete Collection of Scriptures) on the top of Mt. Fuji in 1149, and the buried scriptures, believed to have been unearthed atop Mt. Fuji, are enshrined at Sengen-taisha Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="25">
<j>平安時代の文学の『更級日記』には、富士山の神が、朝廷の次の年の除目（人事）を決めると当時の一部の人々には思われていた記録がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sarashina Nikki (Sarashina Diary), a literature work in the Heian period, wrote that some people in those days believed the personnel affairs for the following year in the Imperial court were determined by the deity of Mt. Fuji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Sarashina Nikki&quot; (Sarashina Diary), a literature work in the Heian period, wrote that some people in those days believed the personnel affairs for the following year in the Imperial court were determined by the deity of Mt. Fuji.</e>
<cmt>原文の『』に合せて&quot;を補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Sarashina Nikki&quot; (Sarashina Diary), a literature work in the Heian period, wrote that some people in those days believed the personnel affairs for the following year in the Imperial court were determined by the deity of Mt. Fuji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="26">
<j>富士山の8合目より上の部分は、登山道、富士山測候所を除き、浅間大社の境内となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The area of Mt. Fuji higher than the 8th station is the compound of Sengen Taisha Shrine except for the climbing trails and Mt. Fuji Weather Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The area of Mt. Fuji higher than the 8th station is the compound of Sengen-taisha Shrine except for the climbing trails and Mt. Fuji Weather Station.</e>
<cmt>Sengen-taisha Shrineに訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The area of Mt. Fuji higher than the 8th station is the compound of Sengen-taisha Shrine except for the climbing trails and Mt. Fuji Weather Station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>但し、静岡県、山梨県の県境が未確定のため、土地登記はしていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But no land registration is yet done because the prefectural boundary between Shizuoka and Yamanashi is still undetermined.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But no land registration is yet done because the prefectural boundary between Shizuoka and Yamanashi is still undetermined.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But no land registration is yet done because the prefectural boundary between Shizuoka and Yamanashi is still undetermined.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="28">
<j>富士山本宮浅間大社</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mt. Fuji Hongu Sengen Taisha Shrine</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mt. Fuji Hongu Sengen-taisha Shrine</e>
<cmt>Sengen-taisha Shrineに訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mt. Fuji Hongu Sengen-taisha Shrine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>富士山頂には富士山本宮浅間大社の奥宮があり、富士山の神とコノハナノサクヤビメを祭る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Atop Mt. Fuji are located Okumiya (interior shrine) of Mt. Fuji Hongu Sengen Taisha dedicated to the deity of Mt. Fuji and Konohanano sakuya bime.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A top Mt. Fuji are located Okumiya (interior shrine) of Mt. Fuji Hongu Sengen-taisha Shrine dedicated to the deity of Mt. Fuji and Konohanano sakuya bime.</e>
<cmt>Sengen-taisha Shrineに訂正しました。スペース補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A top Mt. Fuji are located Okumiya (interior shrine) of Mt. Fuji Hongu Sengen-taisha Shrine dedicated to the deity of Mt. Fuji and Konohanano sakuya bime.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>コノハナノサクヤビメは「火の神」とされることがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Konohanano sakuya bime is also known as the &quot;deity of fire.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Konohanano sakuya bime is also known as the &apos;deity of fire.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Konohanano sakuya bime is also known as the &apos;deity of fire.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>しかし、富士山本宮浅間大社の社伝では火を鎮める「水の神」とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But according to the legend handed down by Mt. Fuji Hongu Sengen Taisha Shrine, this goddess is known as the &quot;deity of water&quot; that suppresses fire.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But according to the legend handed down by Mt. Fuji Hongu Sengen-taisha Shrine, this goddess is known as the &apos;deity of water&apos; that suppresses fire.</e>
<cmt>Sengen-taisha Shrineに訂正しました。原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But according to the legend handed down by Mt. Fuji Hongu Sengen-taisha Shrine, this goddess is known as the &apos;deity of water&apos; that suppresses fire.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>富士山の神が木花開耶姫命とされるようになったかは時期・由来とも明らかではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When and how the deity of Mt. Fuji came to be identified with Konohana sakuya bime is unknown.</e>
<cmt>「富士山の神」と「コノハナサクヤヒメ」が同一視されている、ここでは言っているのに、なぜ後列では２つの神が祀られている、と言っているのか不明ですが原文どおり訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When and how the deity of Mt. Fuji came to be identified with Konohana sakuya bime is unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When and how the deity of Mt. Fuji came to be identified with Konohana sakuya bime is unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="33">
<j>富士講・富士塚</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fujiko (devotional Fuji confraternities) and Fujizuka Mounds</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fujiko (devotional Fuji confraternities) and Fujizuka Mounds</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fujiko (devotional Fuji confraternities) and Fujizuka Mounds</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>江戸時代になると、富士山の登拜が庶民の間でも広く行なわれるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Edo period, climbing Mt. Fuji for worship became widely popular among commoners.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Edo period, climbing Mt. Fuji for worship became widely popular among commoners.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Edo period, climbing Mt. Fuji for worship became widely popular among commoners.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>これは戦国時代 (日本)から江戸時代初期（16世紀後半から17世紀前半）に富士山麓の人穴で修行した角行藤仏（天文 (日本)10年(1541年）-正保3年（1646年）がおこなった富士信仰から始まるとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This practice is believed to have begun as the worship of Mt. Fuji exercised by Tobutsu KAKUGYO (1541 - 1646) who conducted ascetic practices in a cave at the foot of Mt. Fuji from the Sengoku period (period of warring states) to the beginning of the Edo period (from the latter half of the 16th century to the early half of the 17th century).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This practice is believed to have begun as the worship of Mt. Fuji exercised by Tobutsu KAKUGYO (1541 - 1646) who conducted ascetic practices in a cave at the foot of Mt. Fuji from the Sengoku period (period of warring states) to the beginning of the Edo period (from the latter half of the 16th century to the early half of the 17th century).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This practice is believed to have begun as the worship of Mt. Fuji exercised by Tobutsu KAKUGYO (1541 - 1646) who conducted ascetic practices in a cave at the foot of Mt. Fuji from the Sengoku period (period of warring states) to the beginning of the Edo period (from the latter half of the 16th century to the early half of the 17th century).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>庶民は富士山への信仰を強くし、特に江戸の各地には富士山を遥拝する富士塚が多く作られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, commoners came to strongly worship Mt Fuji, and many Fujizuka mounds for worship of Mt. Fuji from afar were built at various parts of Edo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, commoners came to strongly worship Mt Fuji, and many Fujizuka mounds for worship of Mt. Fuji from afar were built at various parts of Edo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, commoners came to strongly worship Mt Fuji, and many Fujizuka mounds for worship of Mt. Fuji from afar were built at various parts of Edo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>富士塚は土を盛って作られた人工の小さな山で、富士山がよく見えるところに作られ、山頂には浅間神社が祀られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fujizuka mounds are artificial mounds constructed by filling up earth and were built at places that can command Mt. Fuji, and Sengen Shrine was built atop those mounds.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fujizuka mounds are artificial mounds constructed by filling up earth and were built at places that can command Mt. Fuji, and Sengen-taisha Shrine was built atop those mounds.</e>
<cmt>Sengen-taisha Shrineに訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fujizuka mounds are artificial mounds constructed by filling up earth and were built at places that can command Mt. Fuji, and Sengen-taisha Shrine was built atop those mounds.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>富士塚は、富士山に行くことが出来ない人たちでも擬似的に富士山の登拜を体験することができるようにするものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those mounds were designed to allow people who couldn&apos;t visit Mt. Fuji to experience climbing Mt. Fuji and worship it on a simulated manner.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those mounds were designed to allow people who couldn&apos;t visit Mt. Fuji to experience climbing Mt. Fuji and worship it on a simulated manner.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those mounds were designed to allow people who couldn&apos;t visit Mt. Fuji to experience climbing Mt. Fuji and worship it on a simulated manner.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="39">
<j>こうした富士山信仰の高まりを受け、江戸時代には富士山信仰を基盤とした神仏混交の新宗教が多数登場した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In response to the growing popularity of Mt. Fuji worship, various new religions mixing Shintoism and Buddhist based on the Mt. Fuji worship were born in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In response to the growing popularity of Mt. Fuji worship, various new religions mixing Shintoism and Buddhist based on the Mt. Fuji worship were born in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In response to the growing popularity of Mt. Fuji worship, various new religions mixing Shintoism and Buddhist based on the Mt. Fuji worship were born in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>新宗教は江戸で布教を行い富士講を組織して、江戸幕府にとっても無視できない規模になることもあり、幕府が富士講禁制の町触を出すこともしばしばであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those new religions conducted missionary work in Edo and formed Fujiko confraternities, and some such groups became too big to be ignored by the Edo shogunate government, which eventually announced directives to prohibit formation of Fujiko confraternities repeatedly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those new religions conducted missionary work in Edo and formed Fujiko confraternities, and some such groups became too big to be ignored by the Edo shogunate government, which eventually announced directives to prohibit formation of Fujiko confraternities repeatedly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those new religions conducted missionary work in Edo and formed Fujiko confraternities, and some such groups became too big to be ignored by the Edo shogunate government, which eventually announced directives to prohibit formation of Fujiko confraternities repeatedly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>例えば、1774年から1849年に、江戸町奉行所は7回の禁制の町触を出している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, the Edo Magistrate&apos;s Office announced the directive to prohibit Fujiko seven times from 1774 to 1849.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, the Edo Magistrate&apos;s Office announced the directive to prohibit Fujiko seven times from 1774 to 1849.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, the Edo Magistrate&apos;s Office announced the directive to prohibit Fujiko seven times from 1774 to 1849.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>これらの新宗教は明治期の激動を潜り抜け、今でも実行教・丸山教・扶桑教などと脈絡を保ち続いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some of those new religions still survived the hard days of the Meiji era and are still operating, which include such groups as Jikko-kyo, Maruyama-kyo and Fuso-kyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some of those new religions still survived the hard days of the Meiji era and are still operating, which include such groups as Jikko-kyo, Maruyama-kyo and Fuso-kyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some of those new religions still survived the hard days of the Meiji era and are still operating, which include such groups as Jikko-kyo, Maruyama-kyo and Fuso-kyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Interregnum(id:25269), Memosa(id:131221), Kyube(id:9866), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>