<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>アメノオシホミミ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amenooshihomimi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amenooshihomimi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amenooshihomimi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>アメノオシホミミ（マサカツアカツカチハヤヒアメノオシホミミ）は、日本神話に登場する神 (神道)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amenooshihomimi (Masakatsuakatsu kachihayahi amenooshihomimi) is a deity (shindo, or god of heaven and earth) that appeared in Japanese Mythology.</e>
<cmt>後述の名前の説明をもとに、名前を3つに区切り表記しました。神道(しんどう)は神祇のことであると解釈しました(広辞苑を参照)。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amenooshihomimi (Masakatsuakatsu kachihayahi amenooshihomimi) is a deity (shindo, or god of heaven and earth) that appeared in Japanese Mythology.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amenooshihomimi (Masakatsuakatsu kachihayahi amenooshihomimi) is a god (Shinto) that appeared in Japanese mythology.</e>
<cmt>shindo→shinto としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>古事記では正勝吾勝勝速日天忍穂耳命、正勝吾勝勝速日天之忍穂耳命、日本書紀では天忍穂耳命、先代旧事本紀では正哉吾勝々速日天押穂耳尊と表記する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is written in kanji as 正勝吾勝勝速日天忍穂耳命 or 正勝吾勝勝速日天之忍穂耳命 in Kojiki (The Records of Ancient Matters), 天忍穂耳命 in Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan), and 正哉吾勝々速日天押穂耳尊 in Sendai Kujihongi (Ancient Japanese History).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is written in kanji as 正勝吾勝勝速日天忍穂耳命 or 正勝吾勝勝速日天之忍穂耳命 in Kojiki (The Records of Ancient Matters), 天忍穂耳命 in Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan), and 正哉吾勝々速日天押穂耳尊 in Sendai Kujihongi (Ancient Japanese History).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is written in kanji as 正勝吾勝勝速日天忍穂耳命 or 正勝吾勝勝速日天之忍穂耳命 in Kojiki (The Records of Ancient Matters), 天忍穂耳命 in Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan), and 正哉吾勝々速日天押穂耳尊 in Sendai Kujihongi (Ancient Japanese History).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>古事記では、アマテラスとスサノオとの誓約の際、スサノオがアマテラスの勾玉を譲り受けて生まれた五皇子の長男（日本書紀の一書では次男）であるとしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kojiki, it is written that he was the first boy (the second boy in a volume of Nihonshoki) of five princes who were born when Susano (a deity in Japanese mythology) was given a magadama (comma-shaped bead) by Amaterasu (the sun goddess) during their ukei (pledge).</e>
<cmt>リンク(「アマテラスとスサノオの」)が表示されていたため、ウェブサイトの通りに原文を変更しました。誓約は「うけい」と読むと解釈しました。一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Kojiki, it is written that he was the first boy (the second boy in a volume of Nihonshoki) of five princes who were born when Susano (a deity in Japanese mythology) was given a magadama (comma-shaped bead) by Amaterasu (the sun goddess) during their ukei (pledge).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Kojiki, it is written that he was the first boy (the second boy in an Arufumi [supplement volumes of explanatory notes in Nihonshoki] of Nihonshoki) of five princes who were born when Susanoo (a deity in Japanese mythology) was given a magadama (comma-shaped bead) by Amaterasu (the sun goddess) during their ukei (pledge).</e>
<cmt>Susanoo としました。日本書紀　一書　の表現を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>また、物実の持ち主であるアマテラスの子としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also written that he was a son of Amaterasu who had a monozane (medium to produce something).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also written that he was a son of Amaterasu who had a monozane (medium to produce something).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also written that he was a son of Amaterasu who had a monozane (medium to produce something).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>タカミムスビの娘である栲幡千千姫命との間にアメノホアカリとニニギをもうけた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had children, Amenohoakari and Ninigi, with Takamimusubi&apos;s daughter, Takuhatachijihime no mikoto.</e>
<cmt>用語集で「栲幡千千姫命」はTakuhatachijihime-no-mikotoと登録されていましたが、訳文ではハイフンを使用しませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had children, Amenohoakari and Ninigi, with Takamimusubi&apos;s daughter, Takuhatachijihime no mikoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had children, Amenohoakari and Ninigi, with Takamimusubi&apos;s daughter, Takuhatachijihime no Mikoto.</e>
<cmt>Mikoto として神名表現を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>葦原中国平定の際、天降って葦原中国を治めるようアマテラスから命令される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Ashihara no nakatsukuni (Literally, &quot;Central Land of Reed Plains&quot;, which refers to the human world) was pacified, he was ordered by Amaterasu to go down there from the celestial world and govern it.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Ashihara no nakatsukuni (Literally, &quot;Central Land of Reed Plains&quot;, which refers to the human world) was pacified, he was ordered by Amaterasu to come down from the celestial world and govern it.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Ashihara no Nakatsukuni (literally, &quot;Central Land of Reed Plains,&quot; which refers to the human world) was pacified, he was ordered by Amaterasu to come down from the celestial world and govern it.</e>
<cmt>Nakatsukuri と大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>しかし下界は物騒だとして途中で引き返してしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However he turned back halfway saying the human world was too dangerous.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However he turned back halfway saying the human world was too dangerous.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However he turned back halfway saying the human world was too dangerous.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>タケミカヅチらによって大国主から国譲りがされ、再びオシホミミに降臨の命が下る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the land was transferred from Okuninushi (chief god of Izumo in southern Honshu Island, Japan, and the central character in the important cycle of myths set in that region) by the order of Takemikazuchi and others, he was told to go down there again.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the land was transferred from Okuninushi (chief god of Izumo in southern Honshu Island, Japan, and the central character in the important cycle of myths set in that region) by the order of Takemikazuchi and others, he was told to go down there again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the land was transferred from Okuninushi (chief god of Izumo in southern Honshu Island, Japan, and the central character in the important cycle of myths set in that region) by the order of Takemikazuchi and others, he was told to go down there again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>しかし、オシホミミはその間に生まれた息子のニニギに行かせるようにと進言し、ニニギが天下ることとなった（天孫降臨）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But he suggested that his son, Ninigi, who was born during that time would go there, therefore Ninigi went down (this occurrence is called tensonkorin).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But he suggested that his son, Ninigi, who was born during that time would go there, therefore Ninigi went down (this occurrence is called tensonkorin).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But he suggested that his son, Ninigi, who was born during that time would go there, therefore Ninigi went down (this occurrence is called tensonkorin).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>名前の「マサカツアカツ（正勝吾勝）」は「正しく勝った、私が勝った」の意、「カチハヤヒ（勝速日）」は「勝つこと日の昇るが如く速い」の意で、誓約の勝ち名乗りと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name &apos;Masakatsuakatsu&apos; means &apos;I won properly, I did&apos; and &apos;Kachihayahi&apos; means &apos;Winning was as fast as the sun rise&apos;, and they are thought to be an announcement of winning ukei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name &apos;Masakatsuakatsu&apos; means &apos;I won properly, I did&apos; and &apos;Kachihayahi&apos; means &apos;Winning was as fast as the sun rise&apos;, and they are thought to be an announcement of winning ukei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name &apos;Masakatsuakatsu&apos; means &apos;I won properly, I did&apos; and &apos;Kachihayahi&apos; means &apos;Winning was as fast as the sun rise,&apos; and they are thought to be an announcement of winning ukei.</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置をアポストロフィーの中に移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>「オシホ（忍穂）」は多くの稲穂の意で、稲穂の神であることを示す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oshiho&apos; means many ears of rice, and this indicates he is a deity of rice ears.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oshiho&apos; means many ears of rice, and this indicates he is a deity of rice ears.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The word, &apos;Oshiho&apos; means many ears of rice, and this indicates he is a deity of rice ears.</e>
<cmt>一部翻訳を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="12">
<j>稲穂の神、農業神として信仰されており、富田八幡宮/勝日神社(島根県安来市)、太郎坊宮（阿賀神社、滋賀県東近江市）、英彦山神宮（福岡県田川郡添田町）、西寒多神社（大分県大分市）、木幡神社（京都府宇治市）、天忍穂別神社（高知県香美郡香我美町）などに祀られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is believed as a deity of rice ears and agriculture, and enshrined in Toda-hachimangu Shrine and Katsuhi-jinja Shrine (Yasugi City, Shimane Prefecture), Tarobo-no-miya Shrine (or Aga-jinja Shrine, Higashiomi City, Shiga Prefecture), Hikosan-jingu Shrine (Soeda-machi, Tagawa-gun, Fukuoka Prefecture), Sasamuta-jinja Shrine (Oita City, Oita Prefecture), Kibata-jinja Shrine (Uji City, Kyoto Prefecture), and Amenooshihowake-jinja Shrine (Kagami-cho, Kami-gun, Kochi Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is believed to be a deity of rice ears and agriculture, and enshrined in Toda-hachimangu Shrine and Katsuhi-jinja Shrine (Yasugi City, Shimane Prefecture), Tarobo-no-miya Shrine (or Aga-jinja Shrine, Higashiomi City, Shiga Prefecture), Hikosan-jingu Shrine (Soeda-machi, Tagawa-gun, Fukuoka Prefecture), Sasamuta-jinja Shrine (Oita City, Oita Prefecture), Kibata-jinja Shrine (Uji City, Kyoto Prefecture), and Amenooshihowake-jinja Shrine (Kagami-cho, Kami-gun, Kochi Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is believed to be a deity of rice ears and agriculture, and enshrined in Toda-hachimangu Shrine and Katsuhi-jinja Shrine (Yasugi City, Shimane Prefecture), Tarobo-no-miya Shrine (or Aga-jinja Shrine, Higashiomi City, Shiga Prefecture), Hikosan-jingu Shrine (Soeda-machi, Tagawa-gun, Fukuoka Prefecture), Sasamuta-jinja Shrine (Oita City, Oita Prefecture), Kibata-jinja Shrine (Uji City, Kyoto Prefecture), and Amenooshihowake-jinja Shrine (Kagami-cho, Kami-gun, Kochi Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Rusk(id:9895), Avxz(id:123412), Nnh(id:474), NDR(id:5500), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>